hello everybody welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream before we get started
today I wanna just make everyone aware
as I will for the next few streams we do
have a discord now it is very active I
think we've got over 600 people on there
already even though it's been up for
only a couple days we are trying this
out because so far you know I hat wasn't
thrilled with twitch chat it's kind of
cumbersome it's less permanent it's just
not that useful
I don't like Twitter it's a trash fire
and so I just wanted some place that we
could manage and it made it easier for
me to basically like moderate right so
we have a discord now if you want to
join it we'll be putting links up to it
soon as well but if you just go to
discord GG slash Molly Rocket that'll
take you right to the invite you can
join up we're close to 700 now nevermind
and I would HIGHLY encourage people to
check it out it's been good people have
been very civil on there and I am kind
of popping in from time to time to
enforce it being civil we have a strict
no politics rule there no twitter
outrage and no politics
soon as I see something like that I'm
gonna ban it I haven't had to yet which
has been great thank you for everyone
for being on the best behavior but I'm
sure inevitably some people won't be on
their best behavior and we will
eliminate this so unlike Twitter you can
come there and be guaranteed that you
will have a much more civil experience
and if for some reason it becomes
uncivil I will step in at my earliest
convenience to make sure that that gets
rectified alright
that's all I wanted to mention there's a
pound live channel on there for
interacting with the show so you can
just use that from now on and forget
about the Twitter chat just use that
pound live channel and I will scan it
and answer questions from it during the
stream so there's really no need for the
trish chat anymore if you don't like it
or just want something a little more
easy to use on your phone you can just
use the discord pound live channel and I
will be watching it so thanks everyone
for making that a good place already and
I will be keeping a pretty close watch
on it to make sure it remains so alright
let's get to it today we've got to do
some last little cleanup I was surprised
I was thinking about how the stream went
Friday night and I
really actually surprised at how well it
went again I'm not a GPU guy it's not
what I spend most of my time doing I do
do some GPU programming but it's more
functional and less like aggressive so
you know I'm kind of a person to come to
if you want to know like how do you do
really well optimized X on a GPU yeah I
don't really know right I don't spend my
time doing that I don't have a lot of
insight to it I just kind of know what
everyone else knows right um and so when
we were looking at the fact that our
multisample resolve was taking a long
time you know I didn't really know how
to solve that problem and I asked around
I was like is there any way for me to
find out if there's multiple samples in
a bucket or not and people were like
nope you know apparently on iOS you can
in a limited sense but that's pretty
much the only place so metals like the
only thing that actually exposes that
metal on phones is the only thing that
that actually exposes that so just to
give you some perspective on how limited
that is and so I was like oh that's a
bummer I guess we can't really speed
this up but then when we actually took a
look at it and I was like oh well what
if we just kept track of when we need to
and when we don't need a sample from
these things putting in those
optimizations like drastically reduced
the amount of time we were spending in
those multi sample resolves so we did a
great job
accidentally right I wasn't expecting
much going into it but we can all give
ourselves a pat on the back if you're
out there right now reach over and give
yourself a pat on the back for what we
were able to accomplish in the last
dream because honestly for non GPU
people I think we did pretty good I'm
sure that GPU people could do better no
question about that but I think we did a
pretty good job attacking a problem when
honestly it was a pretty esoteric and
weird thing we had to do but we we
worked around it pretty well I think
we'll probably able to do more in the
future as we learn a little bit more
about what's going on there and profile
more aggressively but I I was pretty
happy with how we were able to attack
that and we sped up our death appeals as
well so I think we've done a nice job
there we've effectively got what amounts
to now more or less a pretty good
deferred rendering pipeline for the
depth peeling stuff because we now know
in the def peel part we
really evaluate hardly anything we only
evaluate things that actually need to
get evaluated it's that as good as a
full deferred render and the reason for
that is because right now we still
inside a single def peel we left the
depth buffer tell us what should be
there and so we still do multiple
evaluations for no reason what that says
to me is that you know eventually we may
want to do a little bit more of a
deferred render since we have the Deaf
feel it probably is the right thing to
do
rather than putting colors into those
buffers just putting an ID into those
buffers it tells us what to render might
be a better idea long term because again
it would save us costly for pixel
evaluations might be something we want
to do I don't know yet
we'll see but that's just my guess
because as we start to layer lighting on
top of this the main thing that we're
gonna see is that the lighting
computations will dominate our shader
performance because we don't really do
anything else in our shader right all we
do in our shader is pulled from a
texture and put it on the screen whereas
sprite oriented game we don't have a lot
of complexity going on in those shaders
so it's very very fast for us to execute
our shaders and so what's gonna end up
being very slow in our shaders is that
lighting the lighting is gonna have to
grab from multiple sources it's gonna
have to integrate those sources and then
it's got to produce a light reflection
value even though that may not be a huge
deal it's gonna be way more of a deal
than the super simple just pull from a
texture that we're doing now and so
that's really why I think we have to be
aware of that and have to start to think
about that shader is something that
maybe needs to be deferred just the
lighting part anyway ought to be
deferred and so we might do that and the
good news is for that is that all we
would really need is a little bit of
extra data just a little tiny bit of
extra data into the def peel so we would
need you know really just one more
render target probably when we do our
resolve would probably sufficient to get
one more render in target in there I
think I don't know it might be copyable
see but tracking the lighting and doing
the lighting at the end
would probably not be too hard oh we
would really need to know is what the
normal is right because we already know
the position so we really would only
need to know what the normal is that's
the only thing we would need and then
when we do our lighting we could do it
on the depth peel itself effectively
right and so I think we're in good shape
for that I don't love the idea of having
to store the normal multi sampled and so
the the tricky thing and I think we'll
I'm pretty sure that what we will need
to do let's put this way is I'm pretty
sure what we need to do is kind of store
some information in a side buffer and
then what we multi sample would have to
be just to look up into that side buffer
I'm pretty sure that's the only way we'd
really be able to make it work and then
during that resolve we would pull out of
that buffer and right into our targets
something like that is probably what
we'll have to do I don't know but that's
my guess and so that would be a pretty
big step we'll save that to the very
last thing we do because we'll have to
see how attentive that lighting actually
is but my guess is that that's gonna be
an issue there's other ways to solve
that problem obviously we could also
attack it by doing a depth pre pass but
again because we've got the multi sample
buffer and the most embargoes really
expensive I'm not sure we wanted really
do pre passes and then have to go back
over them it's all very complicated I
know but that's that's where we're at so
we could choose to do a depth free pass
if we didn't get the free pass then
basically what we would do is do the
multi sample buffer as depth only no
lighting no color just depth we would
resolve that we would then have our
resolved buffer and we would render once
using that depth pre pass as an equals
operator to figure out what we're gonna
render we could do it that way as I say
that out loud
it kind of sounds like the right answer
actually so maybe I should take that guy
understood and said maybe that's what we
will do so that's what we want to move
towards the thing we're going to be
doing today is putting our ground cover
back in and that's basically going to be
about optimizing that output I want to
verify that if the output that's taking
the time and not the rendering of the
because the ways that we would address
those two problems are different so
that's we're gonna be doing today
is checking out what's going on with the
ground cover I'm assuming it's just
because our code that actually outputs
it is not particularly well written and
then all we need to do is improve that
part of the code if that turns out not
to be the case our method of attack it
would be different we would instead be
trying to cache that ground cover and
reuse it already on the card if it turns
out to be a transmission bottleneck so
that's really what I want you to focus
on today that difference there so again
a lot of talk just trying to set the
stage there I apologize that I had to
say so many things hopefully all those
things made good sense to you but again
we're kind of in a relatively complex
space right now so you have to keep that
in mind all right so looking at the
screen as it stands right now you can
see we're getting a very nice frame
right here that's because our graphics
pipe is actually quite well optimized at
this point and I think we're well below
any amount of time we might actually
take if we actually look here at the
total time we're taking we're actually
well below even 60 frames a second
amount time used so at 60 frames a
second we will be using 60 milliseconds
we're not even using that and and this
is without even the full optimization on
we love all of our certs in here right
and that's with debug collation if we
actually turn off debug collation we
would get several milliseconds back and
most of that time is spent in the GPU at
the moment it looks like as well so
we're really doing pretty good here so
that's the that's a pretty good number
that's a pretty good number because this
just goes away in our shipping version
we're sitting pretty here I would say
and if you take a look at our frames you
can see they're they're mostly again if
you look in here you've got the game
update which is pretty reliable you've
got the frame display in here you got
the debug collation here you can see
that we get some weird offsetting a lot
of what that is I think is the
unreliability of whether or not we hit
or miss the windows display stuff which
it's kind of out of our hands with the
weird setup we're using right now which
has to go to the HDMI as well as the
monitor and
stuff like that some point I should
probably get a splitter so we don't have
this problem but anyway that's what
we're looking at right now and that's
all fine so I think we're in good shape
but what we're gonna do now is take a
look at what happens to these timings
once we put in that ground cover so you
know we take a look at the actual have
any output right now there's kind of a
crappy routine we threw in there for
outputting ground cover you can see
right here during fill unpacked entity
we put that ground cover in but we never
actually render it and you can see that
the reason we don't render it is
actually I'm right in thinking that does
get called right yeah is because I
believe there's a separate function
there it is called jump draw again cover
which when we encounter an entity we are
spooling out to this function to take
the ground cover that's specified as
being on that entity and we're dumping
it to the graphics card by putting it
into the buffer you can see here what
happens is we look at what bitmaps are
used for any particular piece of ground
cover and we we push a sprite out for
that and what happens if we turn this on
so I'm just gonna turn it on here and
you can look at what happens in the game
when we do so is that once we turn that
on you can see that we have a 17% kit
here for render ground cover and you can
see that our timing does jump up
dramatically right so it we get a much
worse performance profile when we dump a
ton of ground cover in there which is
what I've just done so if we draw out if
we you know pull back a little bit here
what you can see is you've got all of
this ground covered that we've spammed
out there and my question the first
thing that I wanted to ask is our saying
before my question I want answered is to
what extent is the ground cover based on
the rendering right like to what extent
is it based on the GPU is that what's
causing us to be costly here or is it
the fact that we're taking too long to
actually push it out
right and so if we go back to our frames
like here I can see that here you can
see here we've got the debug collation
and the frame display I'm gonna go over
here to the game update and in game
update and render what you can see here
is we've kind of got a breakdown begin
world change lighting test right these
things are not really taking time cuz
they're you know this one doesn't do
anything and this one's not really
operational at the moment we jump in
here and there's too many things counted
in there
looks like we need bigger vertex buffers
maybe I should have out maybe I should
update how big those vertex buffers
actually are holos again of course the
problem is this is not a very fair test
because the debug collation would show
those differently but let's hold that
thought so if we were to give ourselves
more space like this is much more than
we need for actually running obviously
but if we're gonna give ourselves more
space so we can output lots of little
things to the debug system let's go
ahead and take a look here at where that
vertex buffer actually gets allocated so
we should have some render limits here
you can see let's see where that's
coming in here so here's our limits Max
quad-cam per frame that's pretty much
what's going to do it right and so I can
update that a little bit we'll see
it might be getting a bit large at this
point
but if I give ourselves a much larger
vertex buffer we should then be able to
output something larger right I would
think so again fling down to the game
update I just want to look at the
entities it looks like that
for whatever reason it looks like that's
just outputting too many things but I
don't know why are we counting way too
many things somewhere here I might be
misinterpreting that error we should
find out what it's saying that we're out
of space to submit that to the graphics
card but I'm not sure why that would be
so I'm wondering how we're ending up
with so many calls you know what we
should be able to look at we should be
able to see that pretty easily in here
right why do I keep looking at the
memory so I guess it's because of stuff
like this render ground cover is getting
called that many times maybe what we
should do is just take a look at that as
being something that doesn't get opened
and closed as many times but yeah if you
look here you've got so many of these
things opened every time I can see why
that's too many right I mean that's that
is just tens of thousands of those zones
and it would be nice to not actually do
that it would be nice if we didn't have
to open actual zones for that we just
did a summation but yeah at the moment
maybe that's a little bit hard to do so
yeah if you look in here the way that
we're timing it just not not great right
and we could time it a little bit
differently like and so on I'm gonna get
rid of things like timing each of these
individually for now and we can open
that back up again if if one of them
starts to be a particular problem right
but let's just get rid of those for now
because we're counting them for every
entity game is just not constructive
right
so if I was to actually get rid of all
of those right and we just looked at
update and render identities by itself
that should take a lot more stress off
of that debug system in terms of how
many things that ask to collate every
frame which of course would be good and
so anyway if I go in and look at the
frames now and in fact you can see that
right you can see the debug collation
got a lot cheaper right and the reason
for that is because we're not dumping
you know tens of thousands of zones and
do it every frame but it has to account
for so you look up now you can see that
mostly this this thing is the only thing
that's really getting pounded on get
best match asset from we do need to
start looking at that a bit more remove
world chunks pretty modest and so that
should make it a lot easier to drill
down here and see these things without
too much fuss I would think
Wow still not so I think this must be a
bug how is it it doesn't seem like it
would really be possible that we're
getting this error here let's take a
look and see can we look at commands at
all no we can't let me take a look at
what's going on there that just bothers
me at this point we should be I mean
with that much vertex space something's
up so I think we just got a bug or
something let's go exploring I want to
know what's going on there I don't like
that hitting that Headroom doesn't make
a lot of sense to me not sure why that
would be happening so here we are
running the debug obviously that cost a
lot more
let's take a look oops let's take a look
at the frame display you can see now if
all this stuff got a lot slower as you
would expect because it's all debug
compiled now if I hop into update and
render world here this is the place
we're getting the crash before when I
click on this so when I try to open up
update and render entities we get this
nasty error hitting us the question is
why right so let's inspect what's
actually happening maybe it's a
erroneous assumption that I'm making
about who's causing this problem maybe
we just have a bug and we could
the bug and then not have this problem
right so what you can see here is we're
getting a bug inside draw frame bar
graph and that is what we would expect
to see in the case where we would draw
too many things so I you know it's not
looking good because it looks like it is
actually something where we're just
drawing too many of these uh and I don't
know exactly how many of them we've
drawn but let's take a look inside where
we're actually erroring out and see what
the command table says right so if we
take a look at our max vertex count in
our vertex count we are actually sinking
four million vertices in this case and
that's just way too many as you might
expect right so why we're thinking that
mini is hard to say but I guess it's
because we have 256 frames to display
and in those 256 let's just do the math
right we were doing about 2,000 of these
things if you look at 512 the number of
vertices we're sinking for those is
probably gonna be like at least six but
probably more like twelve there's our
four million right there so you can see
that that frame display is just way too
costly for us unfortunately just again
because of how many it draws when you
start to have too many zones piling up
like that right and so if we take a look
inside the asset query there that was
the thing that was really hurting us
right the the thing that was saying we
got to do this is how many this right
here get best match bitmap from right
and so what we kind of need you know in
the best and the best of all possible
worlds and maybe we should do this at
some point but we kind of need a way of
timing zones that doesn't incur such a
bad overhead right and we don't really
have a way of doing that at the moment
but maybe just things that do general
sums that don't create as much work for
us in that sense you know maybe that's
the best way to do it I don't know but
you can see that basically our problem
is this right here because that's the
last thing that gets called way too many
times right but it's difficult to say
because you know it means that we don't
get much insight now so now
we're probably fine in fact I can
probably switch off of this but it looks
like there was no bug it's just really
too much data to display for how much
space we actually allocated for
ourselves I don't know how to work
around that problem I'm not sure what to
do about that you know one way is just
to make a much bigger vertex buffer in
debug mode
I don't really know it's a tough one
it's a tough call anyway if I look at
the frames now presumably the bug should
be gone but of course we also have the
problem now we don't get any visibility
right so it's kind of an issue in that
regard because what we would like to do
is we would like to be able to have our
cake and eat it too right we'd like to
be able to see inside here you know
what's taking at the time so you know
sixty one half dozen of the other
but at least now we can all sort of also
say look if we take a look at update and
render entities we can see how much time
it's taking we can take a look at the
differential of that and if we do the
ground cover and we can probably do one
better than that which is to say that
look iterating over the entities is
probably not the worst thing in the
world so if we wanted to we could
probably also do something where we
grout draw the ground cover after right
so like in theory right if you wanted to
you could do something like this where
you do like a second pass afterward and
draw the ground cover there just for
purposes of easy timing so you can know
that you're not timing like the function
call overhead or something like that
that would be a pretty easy thing to do
as well and so if we take a look in say
here and look at how the ground cover
was getting output just take a look at
how that's working draw ground cover you
can see here that there's really not
much information that it needs and so if
we wanted to we could just get rid of
that right like this and then in here to
say all right want you go ahead and
and draw that right so that is one
solution to the problem and if we want
to solve the problem that way then we
can at our discretion make the begin and
end block situation here a little more
concrete so what I could say is instead
of this update and render entity's time
function here what I could say is like
okay let's do a begin block end block
around just this part here and see how
bad it is so let's do begin block ground
cover and block with that I think that's
all we need to do right so and now it'll
only get called once and we can actually
see it without stressing the debug
system we can you know see it pretty
clearly right uh so if you take a look
now at what we're looking at and you and
you don't have the function call
overhead in there of calling it every
time then we can see a more pure
estimate of the cost of just doing drunk
around cover you can see it's bad right
so I don't know if it's the only cause
of badness but it's a significant cause
of badness right and if we were to go
look at what's happening to our frame
times strictly on the GPU side of things
we could get another clue as to whether
or not this is really an issue right let
me go ahead and load this up and render
dock I'm gonna launch here's our frame
I'm gonna capture that frame and then
I'm gonna ask it for the you know kind
of bogus timings but at least give us a
little bit of proportion and what you
can see here is that while it does cost
more to draw these things because
there's a lot more going on in them it's
not the end of the world right these
numbers are not so huge they're not even
in the thousands a lot of these which is
what we were paying before just for the
multi sample resolve so honestly and if
you look at the smallest of them
remember each of these has to process
all of that ground cover
it's still not even up to a millisecond
of time for each pass that has to
process all of them so it looks you know
it looks to me like the GPU is never
really struggling particularly hard on
this level of vertex through put down
the PCI pipe so it doesn't look to me
like I'm too stressed about it in
general right so what that suggests to
me is that this is the problem not just
how much we're drawing that's what I
thought was true and it's what I hoped
was true because it's much easier for us
to optimize this than it is to optimize
the other part of the probe the process
right right so taking a look at draw
ground cover the first thing that I want
to know is which part of it is slow
right so I want to know whether this is
causing us a problem or whether this is
causing us a problem just get bitmap
call and if you take a look at the get
bitmap call it gives us a little bit of
insight into what's happening you can
see here that what we're doing is we're
checking when we call this get asset
right let's take a look at that you can
see it just like doing a direct
reference here but you can see that
what's happening is if it's valid we do
a little bit of work on it and if it's
not we don't the question is how much
does this cost how much does this cost
how much does this cost this cost this
cost right there's a bunch of things
we're doing here and I don't know which
ones are costing us the time so what I'd
like to know is a little bit more about
that process and whether or not we
should be worried about it right so
here's the first thing I want to do I
would like to remove the I would like to
remove the calculation portion and
because that's an easy thing for me to
remove I'd like to remove the
calculation from part of the process and
enable myself to just do a simple like
block copy of the data that I actually
need so for example if I take a look at
push bright
what you'll see about push right it's
incredibly expensive all of the crap
that's going on here first we have to do
this then we have to compute this then
we have to do all of this nonsense right
it's a lot of garbage there's just a lot
of garbage going on there look at push
quad oops
here's push quad right look at all this
crap look at everything that that's
doing right there's just a phenomenal
amount of work going on in here just a
phenomenal amount of work right way way
way too much and so if you take a look
at what's going on there might my
inclination my first thought is maybe
all we really need to do is just compute
this stuff first and cache it right
because if I could do that if I could
compute this stuff first and just cache
the information then all I really need
to do is just block copy this right
these indices and these vertices these I
can write out fresh every time because
they're trivial right these which cost
everything that all the cost was in here
I just saved the values block copy those
for our vertices in that would save 90%
of the CPU work that's happening here
would that be enough to get us out of
the danger zone and into a happier space
right I don't know but again that's my
first inclination so what I would like
to do is say let's start to attack that
problem there's two ways I can attack it
one is I can try to separately profile
the cost of doing the computation versus
doing the other part of the process
right the problem is that's a little bit
difficult because it would require me to
somehow be able to time these things in
a more fine-grained manner now I can try
to do that
right if I look at get bitmap info I can
see that like it's just kind of a lookup
right in this process so don't think
that should be too bad so if I wanted to
I could basically say look let's split
this off and just say this is the
computation it's not great because now
there's overhead getting counted against
the outer routine but at least it would
give me some idea if my suspicion is
correct before I go spend time try and
solve the problem so now if we take a
look at what's going on what you can see
here is that the draw ground-cover
function itself doesn't seem to be
taking very much time right I don't know
if you can see that there it's only
hovering around 5% whereas the function
that's actually I'm sorry the part
that's actually eating all the time that
computation let me pause so it's not
flickering for you you can see here that
the 20% of the entire frame time is
spent just doing just that computation
this is probably even much less because
the overhead of getting these blocks
started 44,000 of them is counted
against ground cover in this case and so
this is probably even less when you when
you take that out of it so I do think
that computation I think it's safe for
me without going out on too much of a
limb it's safe for me to say look that
computation is really bad how do we
address it right okay so let's try to
start addressing it slowly
ok so let's suppose that I was to go
over to the way that the place we're
storing these actual entities so we go
look here and what you can see is that
our enemies kind of have a ground cover
thing here and it's this entity max
ground cover nonsense right and the
question is what's going on with that
right and so if we take a look at the
ground cover the way that that works
it's basically a bitmap a position of
color and a scale and we're using that
we're like decompressing that every time
basically
to produce you know this this
information now what I would rather do
is I would rather figure out a way of
storing the react ever in the form that
it's directly like how it's directly
used that'll take up more space in my
entity for sure but there's ways of
getting around that and we already have
a caching system that means that when we
add we can add arbitrarily large stuff
to our entities and we only pay for that
for the entities that are actually
active at any given time we don't
actually pay that cost for the
potentially millions of entities we
could have in the world because they are
not in the cache so it's not that bad to
make our enemies fat because we've
already done the work to make sure that
they stay lean in the bad case where
there's you know millions and millions
or billions of them so when we take a
look at the ground cover here what I
want to do is see what can I say what
can I you know change about this process
well looking at the render itself we get
an idea for what we actually output to
these vertices right
I remember where we've placed that there
it is so here's our textured vertex
right and you can see we've got the
information here for each vertex stored
it's a little bit large it's got a p
value and n value UV and color then it's
got a texture and a mission and a
reserved right so it's a bit large if
you look at how big it actually is it's
a bit large and if we think about how
big it is compared to one of these let's
just count it up right so it's to
effectively if we count Fitzhugh 32 with
this v4 here we've got 2 v4 s or two
four by fours right so that's 8 by 4
let's jump over to speed calc so we know
just to make that explicit we've got I
can in fact I can just write it out
regular we've got a 4 times 4 plus the 3
times 4 plus a 2 times 4 plus a 4 single
4 plus a 2 plus a 1 plus a 1 that
aren't total size so a textured vertex
is 44 we know we need four of those so
this is the entire size we would be
taking 176 we would take that per
ground-cover element now what we were
storing over here was a bitmap ID which
is four long a 3 x 4 a 3 x 4 and a 4
that's only 32 and so we will be
exacerbating the problem of the storage
by blowing it out no question about that
but we have to ask ourselves how much of
this do we actually need because to a
large extent we probably don't actually
need to store all of this a lot of it is
redundant now what we do know is the
normal probably going to be the same
texture index probably going to be the
same emission probably going to be the
same reserved probably going to be the
same or nothing right color probably
going to be the same so when we look at
what we actually had to do computation
on it's mostly P &amp; UV right so my
thinking is we can probably get this
down to / ground cover actually storing
something much more simple right we
probably don't need to store it x 4 for
all of these things we can probably get
away with our x for only being the P
plus the UV which is 6 times 4 times 4
or 96 that's a lot less of an increase
than we would have been suffering
otherwise and for all I know we don't
really need to store that completely
either because we might be able to store
a quicker way of getting that produced
so when we go to look at it we really do
have options for keeping this more under
control so I think we're gonna be okay
let's take a more worst-case approach to
it at the moment and say that this
ground cover that's getting generated in
here let's maybe say we want this to be
a little more straightforward and so
instead of storing the things exactly as
we were we're going to store them a
little bit differently first of all we
will pre-pack our color that's something
that we can do pretty easily that gets
us out of the business of having to take
this v3
you color in there and it takes less
space anyway so it's just a good idea to
begin with then we know we've got these
p-values in here that were those are the
things that are probably pretty
expensive to compute so at the very
least let's store the four key values
that we're actually going to use instead
of just some value that we use to create
them which was p+ scale that was how we
were creating them before and then we
will maybe take the normal and say the
normals gonna be constant so we're
probably not going to do anything with
that we're just gonna stuff that
normally and similarly the texture index
is something that's going to come from
the bitmap so that's probably something
we can't really work around at the
immediate moment although maybe some
things we can do to make that be a
little bit better in the future but
either way so these are sort of the
constants these are the I mean the
things that are constant across all
vertices these are the things that
change per vertex of output same thing
with things like admission that's
probably something we can also put in
there right so this emission value can
probably historic and we've read my
source some other things as well so the
only question now is what do we need to
store for UV my guess is we don't really
use store much for UV because probably
we're just gonna have a zero value for
the base of the UV so my suspicion is we
actually only need one UV value as well
which is how it stretches out along the
texture so I think we're really gonna be
able to get away with going from this so
previously let me make this a little
more explicit I think we can get away
with something like that so I think we
can go from something that was storing
this to something that was storing this
I don't think that's a huge deal let's
do the comparison just so we have a
little bit of perspective on the subject
if we take a look at how much that costs
we've got a three times four right three
floats for the v3 three floats for the
color and then one float right for the
scale so that's a twenty eight was how
much that cost we then have four bytes
for the year thirty two three times four
for the N and we weren't storing that in
with
or so I don't know but what we were kind
of generating so maybe that counts so
four plus three times four then we've
got our UV which is two times four we've
got our emission which is just one byte
and then we've got our p4 which is going
to be four times four times three right
seventy-three now this probably should
be stuck at the end I don't know if we
really need a mission because ground
cover doesn't have a mission so maybe
we'll get rid of that and just say at 72
72 times
I mean divided by 28 we're up we're
making it about two and a half times
larger that again not the end of the
world I'm not gonna lose sleep over that
certainly not in this part of the code
anyway so I think we're okay there and
this would allow us to generate the
ground cover much more quickly why would
it allow us to do that well if we now
pop back to the enemy system and look at
what was actually going on if we assume
now that we're taking a look at this
drug ground cover function and we're
looking at what we would have to do in
order to output our sprite we can pretty
much say that this is an f0 around here
now and we can do an else call this is
stuff we're going to do in the code
where we generate the ground cover which
remember is much cheaper because it only
happens when the entity comes into the
cache so we pay that cost only as
enemies come into the cache which
happens like in a slower rate right and
not only does happen in a slower rate
but we can manage it if we needed to we
could trickle charge it if we want to so
basically if too many entities entered
in one frame we could trickle them out
over a course of frames because they
tend to move in on the apron right not
all into the view at once and so we
could also you know help mitigate some
of that issue by putting in flow control
or rate control to avoid having too much
of a hiccup on any given frame so I
think we also have a lot of options
there in addition to it right so I think
it's gonna be there were you know easy
to mitigate that
problem so that's what we're trying to
do we're trying to move code from
something ask them every frame saying
that only has to happen when enemies
change their active set so here we go
if we now want to write a quat out here
essentially what we need is a like push
magical quad or something right we need
some function that allows us to push our
quads out cleanly and we don't really
have a way of doing that right now
unfortunately but that's something that
we need to be able to fix and so if I
was to go to push quad what you can see
in the push quad code here right here
anyway
right you can see it getting this sort
of quad stuff out doing a bunch of
garbage here looking at special textures
all this sort of stuff right this is
precisely the stuff that we want to
avoid we don't want to have to do any of
this stuff we want this to be a lot
simpler and that's part of the rendering
optimization is taking code that was
just written to do whatever because it's
whatever we thought of at the time and
it's just the easiest thing to do which
again you always do want to do because
you don't want to make matters
complicated for yourself and so you know
what actually cost you the time and what
actually is important so certainly not
an issue I'm not blaming past us for
doing anything wrong we did but when it
does come time to start thinking about
how you're gonna streamline that process
now is the time to start looking at that
and so what I want to do here is I want
to create a good way for me to
effectively do this right so I want I
want my code here to be able to do this
right and what I want to be able to do
is at the outset since I know how much
ground cover we have I want to
effectively be able to make a call
that's like I'm gonna push this many
vertices on so this is going to be like
indexed vertex output or something like
that right I want to be able to make a
call which is like output quads and I
want to be raw so I just say look I'm
gonna output this many quads give me
back the information that I
need to do that please right and so then
what I want to do is say okay I've got
you know this output function that
should allow me to do this very cleanly
and now I'm just gonna push vertices on
it so I'm just gonna do like a push
vertex here and I want to be able to put
put on these pieces of information right
okay so first things first we need to be
able to figure out what these p-values
are well guess what we're saying we're
computing those ahead of time so that's
gonna be easy right so our p-value is
very simple it's just whatever the
ground cover said it was right our n
value is also simple because it's stored
in there our UV is a little more
complicated because as you can see we
have like a bunch of you V's they get
pushed in here and we don't really know
what they should be right so that's a
little bit harder so we effectively have
some set of UVs that we're going to have
to work with and maybe we'll keep the
naming the same as they were inside our
quads or something like this so I don't
know what we'll do with that we'll talk
about that in one second but we're gonna
push on a UV there right and then
finally we're going to have in our we're
gonna have a color value so you see it
could be modulated we're gonna have a
color value and we've already specified
with that color value is as well
oops didn't mean to make that cover and
so we're gonna have a color value there
which specifies what the color is for
our vertex texture index we don't know
what it is yet so we're gonna have to
push that but then we're done right
that's all the things we need okay so
now we just do this for every vertex
that we have right and so you can look
here actually I guess the way this was
doing is the p3 was pushed first I don't
know that we really want this to be
doing that weird winding so maybe we'll
just do it this way right we'll start to
clean this up a little bit and not do it
the way it was being done before so
we'll do something like this right and
that will be sort of the clean way of
putting those vertices in place right
now there is something a little bit
unnecessary about this something I don't
super like and I don't
really know what looking pilers going to
do with it and so I'm just gonna mention
that we sort of have an issue here the
issue that we have is I don't know what
the compiler is going to do about
indexing off of the pointer let me just
explain to you what I mean by that I and
because it's kind of a little bit
relevant so inside your CPU right it's
got a bunch of logic in it that deals
with memory and the way that it uses
this logic is that it has
special-purpose routines hard-coded
directly into the arithmetic logic units
well they're not really into the
earth-mother if they're getting this
special unit that's made for memory but
that's not here there it has special
special circuitry that's designed just
to do things like array offsets right
and so there's two things that your CPU
can do at any given time so it wants to
access memory one is it can like you
know take a register like a pointer
right and say get memory at pointer
right it can like do that or store
memory at pointer right that's the thing
can do and that kind of a thing is just
called a mob instruction usually so
you'll see things like mob and it'll say
oh I want to take some particular
pointer so there's a register
you know register with pointer it'll
take some radish or the pointer and will
move something there and then it says
like well what did you want to move
there and it'll be like this floating
point value right so some register with
a value so you can do stuff like that
right and that's like the bread and
butter of how you move things off to
where a pointer is but you can also do
things like this and this operation is
free it costs you nothing to do it's
100% free basically that's probably an
overstatement but it's almost free
however
this is not free so if you take a look
at what these two things what the
difference is between these two things
one code set looks like this another
code set looks like this right these two
things do not cost the same this one is
cheaper than this one is and the reason
that this one is cheaper than this one
is is because the components are the
Natha compiler
these CPU can do that plus 12 for free
and so the compiler in many cases is
smart enough to look at your usage
pattern and know when it can do offsets
so if you tell it something like this if
you tell it something like this inside a
loop it's often smart enough to do this
right so I'm ignoring the values here
but point being I it's often smart
enough to say oh they're just writing
two sequential locations in this loop so
I can just use hard-coded offsets
because there are size that I know I
know what this is pointing to let's say
right and then I only need to do one add
at the end of the loop to move the
pointer up by the total number that I've
written so it's often smart enough to
aggregate those things to things for you
but this is what you wanted and this is
not right
that's the way to think of it I did want
this I did not want that right and
there's a lot of complexity here because
actually right literally this and this
it doesn't matter which one you choose
because of the way the CPU actually
executes with ports it's probably the
case that this is no more expensive than
this and there's a lot of other things
we could talk about that have to do with
that but once you start adding way more
of these mobs on there and so on you
start to get into a situation where it
does actually matter and so on and so
you want to make it easy for the
compiler to output this and not this
right and so sometimes when I'm down in
here in the nitty-gritty and I'm
thinking about how to output stuff
quickly and I want the compiler to
output the correct set of code for
something
I will intentionally make life a little
bit harder for me and write this
rather than this just because I want it
to be really easy for the compiler to
see what I'm doing
maybe that's do that alright so again
I'm just trying to give you some
perspective here on what I'm doing but I
may want our fast output maybe I'll call
it out vertex something like that or
vertex out so I may want to look more
like this where we do a bunch of these
as many as you want to do and then once
they're out you do in advance write
something like that rather than just
letting this increment the pointer so
that way it gets incremented only once
at the end of an aquatic foot rather
than something a little bit more
granular and again the reason for that
is so that you can have more control
over what's going on there that's like
the goal right and so here we would
basically say look the the index out is
just going to be you know draw these
things in order or whatever right and
I'm gonna use the basis value for that
as well just so I can make sure that in
we can also make those be striated if we
want to produce more indices than one at
a given time but that's more what I want
to see when I look at that that's like
sort of more what I'm looking that's
more what I'm looking for right so I
want to see something like this this is
what I want to make and that way I can
stream these vertices out really
aggressively and not have to worry about
how much time it takes
because I know the CPU code will be like
very
optimized in that case and the slow park
will now be this garbage here which
maybe we try to optimize in some way or
maybe we don't if it just doesn't matter
that much right okay so that's what I'd
like to do it's pretty easy for me to
write this and I will but then we need
to look at the opposite side of this
which is that this code here still needs
to happen and it needs to come from
somewhere so this texture index here I
need a way of getting that texture index
if I go look at the push blog call right
I should be able to see how we were
getting it in here you can see here we
do texture index from this texture so I
should be able to do something like that
I believe sprite values for upright is
probably the thing that's doing that
right now but if you take a look at how
this is happening right it's just doing
this downcast here and all that should
be good
so I probably want some thing that
converts this for me probably something
that looks like this I something like
this I think I probably want a like non
special effect
you know I'm looking at this why do we
even have to like shouldn't this just
return a 16-bit value hold on a second
yeah I mean I feel like this should just
return a 16-bit value the texture
special bit I feel like this should
really just be returning a 16-bit value
to begin with probably
[Music]
I mean technically if you it's really
whether or not you know so I'll just do
it this way so we're gonna go ahead and
grab out this and we're gonna make sure
that it's the 16 bitten index as we go
but that's pretty much all we needed to
do and so then we can just out with this
stuff and really now our goal is to move
this code that we have here right we're
gonna try and move this code sort of out
right and don't ask me why did that I
didn't mean to and so let's go take a
look at where that code goes and how
we're gonna adjust that code so taking a
look at this streaming out that uh looks
like finding me you can see how much
simpler that is no function calls just
really streamlined it's just a bunch of
block copies these are just gonna be
inline function that just block copy
that data in order and the only reason
I'm not doing that manually is because
that makes it easier for me to change
the vertex format and know who's using
it where right okay
so when we go fill our ground cover up
here you can see us doing it like this
when we actually produce this sort of
information and do our kind of like work
to get our best map get our best match
bitmaps basically what I want to do is
not fill in this stuff this way I want
to fill it in this way and we kind of
have some work to do because this
information is now stuff that you know
we want to kind of capture right we want
to kind of get this information out in a
different way
so we're gonna do that in a second okay
and looking at this right this can still
the cover bitmap can still be written
out that way but the other stuff needs
to be written out differently so let's
just go ahead and take a look at all of
the parts that we have here and let's
make sure that we're writing out all of
them so now we do have a color much like
we have here but we want to kind of make
this color be something
that someone could set like later on
when they're trying to do like varying
color like maybe there's a randomization
the color but they set it as a v3 then
we want to do is pack that back up right
so we want to do like a pack of the RGB
I don't remember where this is in fact
I'm not even going to try and remember
what I'm gonna do instead is just take a
look at how this was doing this here
right you can see on push bright that's
probably where we're doing it in fact
you can see it right here we have an RGB
pack four by eight and we do the Primo
on there right like this so you can see
this process here that we're doing with
the store color I don't love the way
we're doing this exactly it's a little
bit annoying when when we look at how
that's supposed to happen I kind of feel
like that should be a little bit more
straightforward and so I think what I
want to do is maybe change the way the
store color is working to be sort of an
all-in-one call
so the way store color works currently
it just does the pre mul there for us I
think what I want to do here is make our
own function that's more like finalized
color something like that and so we take
the input here and our like unfree
multiplied we pass that through store
color and then we pack it down right
and again that's what this is doing
again what I'm trying to do here is not
nothing fancy
right nothing nothing weird is going on
here I'm just trying to make a systemic
way that everyone who ever does this can
just call this function and know that no
matter what random you know crazy way
that people are using color stuff I just
want there to be a way they know they
can just call this with a normal non
premultiplied color and crap will happen
and you'll get back the right you 32
right so that way nobody on the outside
is thinking about how colors are encoded
they don't care they just need to know
that they can pass it through finalized
color and they'll get the right answer
and that's all they need to know which
is good because I don't want people to
have to know because what if I change it
later right because it's a bunch of
hairy crap that has to happen and maybe
I want it different right
so the finalized color is just going to
be done this way like that and then
anyone can call that with the color that
they generated and know that it gets
packed down properly that's all we need
to do for that for the normals we're not
really doing lighting yet so it's kind
of difficult to say what the lighting
should be but for the most part I think
these things are things that are
supposed to be sort of front-facing so I
suspect the normal for our intents for
our intentions at this point are gonna
be things probably like that but we
don't really know so I'm gonna put it to
do in here and say you know adjust this
once lighting is you know working so
we're actually lighting sprites we'll
see what that has to be right okay
so then we've got the UV and the
p-values that's really most of what we
actually have to do now is compute where
these p-values should actually go and we
know we have a point from UV W things
happening in the collision volume sure
that gives us the base P but we don't
know what to do after that right so now
we've got a bunch of crap
has to happen here you can see it
happening here and we probably still
need to do this stuff but then we we
kind of want our sprite values for up
right call to be the last thing we do we
don't want to push the sprite on so we
want to generate all the rest of the
stuff that this thing would have done we
want to generate that ourselves so that
push sprite call is kind of now
something that's a little bit suspicious
what we would like to do is take that
code and use our own computations to do
something smart there and by the way we
can make this a little bit more
optimized as well by calling finalize
color and not optimized cleaner less
work to maintain by reusing that code
that we were using before and doing this
that way we know that those are both
going through the same path now and
there's not multiple people sort of
falling over themselves doing weird
store color antics so anyway in here now
you can see this does these operations
right you can see how it's unpacking
that and what we'd like to do is make
that push sprite again I want that to be
something that now could work better
with faster flowing code now one of the
things that you'll notice is that that
it's really not doing much with the
other pieces of the code right it's
mostly just computing the P and the UV
values if you look at there if you look
in there what it's doing it's computing
P values and UV values but everything
else is a pass through the texture is a
pass through the normals are not even
mentioned the color is a pass through
it's just the P n UV values so again I
think we can take a step backwards here
and say let's make this this push bright
call be even more amenable to pre
calculation so if we take a look at that
compute what was it called compute
sprite values or write values for
upright that I don't remember this thing
right so if you take a look at one of
these things we've got these sprite
values here let's
go ahead and make there be a thing
called quad values or something like
that that's the equivalent of it and
let's get this stuff out of there so
let's get these up in here right so we
got a p4 there right and then let's get
that UV working so you can see how this
thing gets output right the min min max
right that nonsense you can see that
getting passed down here right let's
make that be something that well and you
know what now I'm looking at it just
even looking at that I think for the
most part that doesn't need to really be
there either
right it's mostly just this is the
calculation and this other stuff is just
exactly what you would have expected it
to be and so yeah let's not worry about
that at the moment so if this right here
is getting done with this quad values
thing then we know that we don't have to
compute that anymore that can must be
generated directly off the sprite values
and similarly these things for all these
movies those could be generated directly
on the sprite fires as well but those
are so wrote at that point I'm just not
sure we even want to store those because
you can see that the min and the max UV
and that ma'am UV is probably 0 most of
the time as well so that even that is
kind of absurd the way that that's
working so just again trying to step
back a little bit from how this is
happening and make this be a little bit
more systemic I'm not sure I'm gonna go
ahead and push forward a little bit on
just making this be custom so I'm gonna
do this here instead so you take a look
at at what we're actually passing down
here this is the min P value right so
that's the min P the scaled x-axis and
scaled y-axis are just the things that
came out of sprite right so these are
these
so that's fine and then the rest of this
stuff is irrelevant right so here are
the p-values we actually were you
writing so you can see us like write
those directly out this way if we want
we can just you know get rid of the
middleman here and again those p-values
there they don't actually need because
we're not using that Z bias anymore we
can really actually get rid of the Z
bias entirely from our system at this
point I don't think we actually ever
need it so we can get rid of that Z bias
now I think that means that basically
this can just be written this way
because we don't actually need to store
for element stuff we're not using it and
it'll probably just go away so we can
pretty much get rid of all the notion of
the v4 in there and leave it like this
right so that leaves us with just the UV
right that's all we actually need here
is just the UV at that point and so now
the only question I have is what's the
most efficient way to encode that UV and
so if we go into push quad remember push
quad is the thing that's actually doing
the work for the UV and you can see what
it does here is it takes the input
movies and it actually does the mapping
to figure out how those things exist
based on the texture size so I don't if
you can see that happening here right
but you can see as it goes to get this
in V inverse UV right you can see that
being calculated here and so that's
something that we want to again
similarly make systemic based on the
texture we we know that this is never
going to be a rectangular texture we're
not using rectangular textures in our
fast path they're just for cutscenes so
we know that we really don't need to do
any switches we don't need to test to
see what's going on here so what we want
to do is in here where we go in and set
this UV scale scaling value basically is
all we really want to know is what is
this we just need to
know what this is going to be versus the
war is it here versus the texture within
- three width and height which we
already have so that's really all we
need right that's really all we need and
so if we assume that the ground cover
always draws the complete thing which we
don't actually know so we may have to
adjust this later and have to UVs like a
minute of max right
if we want to pull out of chunks of a
thing for example but assuming we don't
want to do that then all we really need
here is to just say look all right we
need you to do we need to compute this
thing right so we need that value there
and we could make that be something
that's again systemic in a way that lets
us do that easily so basically get
scaled texture coordinates or something
like this or scale UV to texture right
and all you need to do there is just do
this
so I guess we don't want to call Celia
we just want to do like get UV scale or
texture it's probably the right way to
do it that's better
and so in this case you have to pass the
texture but that's all you need to pass
and and we probably want to specify like
regular texture because it doesn't work
if the texture is special so in here we
just say alright we've got our inverse
UV that's gonna be true for any time you
use this particular texture regular
texture texture okay and so we're gonna
return the result like so right so that
goes ahead and gives us back this in a
reliable way
that anyone can now use so you get UV
scale for regular texture is all we need
there that can then be called here get
UV schoo for regular texture and that's
actually all we need to store right so
for whatever this texture actually was
that we ended up using that's the thing
we need to that's the thing that we need
to store the scale for right now we
didn't actually grab the texture so we
need to grab the texture and get that
piece of information out of it so this
here if we didn't actually load it yet
we can't actually get that piece of
information the bummer dragged about
that is that we kind of need it right
but the good news is we should be able
to do this without loading the texture
right in here if we looked at what the
bitmap was that would tell us the scale
right so in theory even if we haven't
loaded it yet we should be able to do
this the other way round we should be
able to make a call but something like
this right
or maybe even that where we just say
look we got the bitmap info
compute the scale using that because
that's what you actually needed you just
need the texture width and height you
know what those are going to be once you
see the bitmap info we don't have to
actually have the thing paged into
memory to do all the work which is what
we want because when I create this I
don't care if it's loaded into memory
I'm not gonna draw it so we should let
the background loading routines have way
more time than this they shouldn't have
to be pressured in that way so what I
want here is a way to get this
information without knowing what the
actual texture is so let's implement
that as well if you have an HSA bitmap
again inside the renderer it's basically
this exact call which is get you know UV
scale for bitmap and there's a bitmap
info right and that bitmap what's it
called
HHA bitmaps are so there's the info
right and if I look at HHA bitmap
I can see that in here I've got a dim
and an org dim I have the information
that I actually want when I stored the
bitmap I know what's actually going on
right and so when I look at for example
when we submit these textures so inside
load bitmap right what we actually do is
we use that width and height to see
what's up right we see what's going on
there so if I wanted to I could do this
I don't know why we have to act past the
assets for that dream my I do not know
why that's being passed there possibly
because of this but I don't love that
because I'm not sure why you would need
the assets there so I'm gonna eliminate
that for now and in the future we can
put it back in if we really need it but
I don't
wanna do that so in here I can say look
if you needed this then we do one thing
otherwise we do the other thing but
we'll always produce the right result
for you either way right we'll always
produce the correct value no matter what
and so if we do get UV scale for bitmap
and really if you look at this we don't
even need that we just need the dim for
it right we just need you to tell us
like what this what it is right so we
really just need like that it's all we
really needed you to tell us and then we
can compute the value so in here where
we do dimensional cross special texture
we can pass the width and height if they
do then the UV scale is just nothing
right if it's just one one but I'll go
double-check that that's true and so
really we only have this case where we
need to know if this thing doesn't
require a special texture if the texture
is effectively regular then what we want
to do is compute these two values so we
want to compute the x value as being the
width divided by that texture array
dimension and then in you know same
thing here like so and off we go now
again I don't know whether or not we
want this thing probably the reason and
you know I could keep this go and it
doesn't really matter right if we wanted
to make it this way we're just
protecting ourselves effectively for
needing to make that dynamic this value
so we would look it up inside the assets
maybe we want to keep that I don't know
I'm willing to say that we might and
it's pretty easy for me to pass it
around so sure right whatever if we go
back and look in here you can see that
that is in fact what we do you can see
us doing the one at point O in there so
that's all fine so this basically gives
us the thing that we needed when we're
actually calling this in the entity
output so here where I'm doing get UV
scale for bitmap and I passed device
info I really want to do this but other
than that is exactly what I said it was
right so now when we get further through
here let's see what's going on here
rubes
and asked me why I wrote that wrong it's
not what that's supposed to be doing so
now we just need to go ahead and clean
up all of the mess we made if we look in
here about the v4 do that that was not
what I was expecting to look at let's go
look at that that's it there we go
so in dimensions require a special
texture we need that to be exposed now
we want that to be like up here
basically people can call it oh is this
done inside looks like maybe we don't
want this here if this needs to be in
here all right okay so now we're down to
basically what I thought we should be
although well let me double check some
things so this is the part that we
hadn't we haven't put that actual index
for tips output thing in there but let's
just do you bug this for a second cover
scale is wrong weird now don't store
that in the cover which is going to be
doing it only at compute time we've got
these sprite values for up right here
we're passing the render group down I
don't know why it looks like because of
this stuff right so it needs to be it
needs to know what the x and y axes are
for the camera and stuff like that and
so we kind of need some way of getting
that information passed down in here in
a more convenient way we will do that in
a second
finally we need in here we need like the
positions for the entities and stuff
like that so you can see that that's one
thing I can't quite do so this value
right here kind of has to go away and it
has to be reconstituted that's actually
fine that's not a huge deal if we go
back to our push vertex oops raw ground
cover rather where we're pushing our
Sahn that just means that it has to go
in here it's fine to do one ad in there
that's not gonna kill us that's just
moving it to wherever the entity is on
this frame so that's pretty easy right
it's just a simple little transform not
to push it forward so that's pretty
simple that gets that out of there but
we do have that one problem still where
is if we look at you know again this is
just because we haven't implemented it
yet so those aren't errors those are
fine we do have this one problem still
where we have to kind of think about
what we want to have happen here
why is that's not covered P where is
that value what's called base P
basically so I think that's all good and
so this is really our only issue where
sprite values for upright with the
render group there that's an issue it
doesn't need it for anything too subtle
it needs it for the y axis and the x
axis right and so it needs to know
what's the actual up value for the
camera right like what's the what's
pointing upward as far as the camera is
concerned and then it needs the it needs
to know what the world up axis is right
answer the problem that we have here is
again it's a little bit of like a
partial evaluation issue if we look at
where the world up is being you well
actually let's look if we look at where
the world up is being used we don't care
about that because that's a constant we
don't change the world up it's just what
it is right so really the problem we
have is with the y-axis h-here you can
see that when we look at what's going on
that y axis H that has the camera up
sort of lurked in there because it's how
we make our sprites be more
forward-facing you know I'm sad
now thankfully the y-axis is usually the
same so what we could do is just pretend
that that's not going to change now it
is going to change because if we move
the cameras like sort of focus level it
will change a little bit but we could
just say well it's not gonna change
enough right for us to care so we'll
just use it as it is we could do that
the other thing we could do is recognize
that well we could just reconstitute
just this part at runtime I'm gonna say
let's go whole hog let's pass these
values down and so in order to do that
I'm going to take this sprite values for
up right I'm gonna create a separate
version of it and I'm gonna say we're
gonna have this be a two-tiered call so
the first tier is going to be where you
pass these things in and there's no need
for the render group so the first tier
is this world up camera up x axis H
right and this year I guess I should
have put these in the opposite order and
this deer is the one that actually does
the work so I get rid of these lookups
in to render group and I just have you
passed us down directly then the second
tier is that you call this thing with
just a render group and it unpacks the
render group into the call that way
people who don't want to do that right
don't have to they don't have to pass a
render group if they don't want to so
then we end up with this world up camera
up x-axis H and then these other pushes
world dim align P X axis to Y axis to T
camera right so that's how that works
and now we can do these in two different
waves so now instead of passing a render
group here we can actually just pass
what we want to use for these other
pieces of information right world up
camera x-axis H world dim the line P or
whatever else I'm sorry
just these three world up camera app X
action stage
and so we get rid of the render group
here and we say well what's the world up
access well we know what the world up is
right before you specify that that's
always this what's the camera up access
well hard to say right that's one that
we probably want to specify a little
more carefully
what's the x-axis well that's really
simple we know we don't allow the camera
that to rotate so in this case we know
that that's actually always the y-axis
so it's really just this value that's
the one that we you know maybe want to
know and if we want to know like okay so
what's camera up what's pointing back or
rather what's pointing along the screen
y-axis if you will we know that's just a
subtly tilted version of the regular
y-axis but the question is well how
tilted right and so when we go to update
and render entities when we look and see
what those values actually are up sorry
I didn't mean that update in the render
world we know that we're doing our
rotation using the pitch of the camera
here to do a certain amount of rotation
so we know in the world mode that
there's a certain amount of camera pitch
and that camera pitch is really the
thing that determines what that tilt is
this value here is therefore sort of a
magic value for us it's a value that we
want to actually expose to people who
want to precache sprites because it's
the level of tilt that we want to most
of the time use right so that's really
the the value that we we kind of needed
to know and so at the moment you know we
kind of it's a little nasty because
we're like well what's that value really
gonna look like right and I don't know
where we really want to place that but
for now we can be cheesy and just
actually have this be something to
specify default camera pitch right is
this value here
right and then as a result we can also
do default camera up right and we can
also specify what that value actually is
and so that backwards pitch there that
we're actually getting we can
pre-compute whatever the rotation value
actually is of our camera up vector and
then once those two things match you
know we can be a happy camper right so
what I'd like to do is say all right
this thing is something right we'll
compute what it is and we'll just say
that we'll make these two things cost us
that we actually specify somewhere like
that then in here we say happy birthday
everyone's you know in a good mode and
then I think we're good to go
this has to take all of the values I
just said and then I think we're clean
all right so now oops where's my where's
that Depot camera up there's so now I
think we're good and I just need to
implement the actual output layer and
that's pretty easy to do and something
that I want to have been wanting to do
for a while so inside the renderer here
in the H file I wanted to find that that
little vertex output thing right and
what that's going to be is just a way of
outputting quads and vertices so it's
literally just going to be like a you
know face index
something like this so basically
something that says which index are we
on for vertices because that's we're
gonna have to sort of latch that forward
and see what I mean by that but then we
just need this to understand like okay
when you output vertices they go here
when your output indices they go here
and then as we advance things forward we
update this value so we know how our
indices should be adjusted to line up
with the actual vertex buffer that we're
submitting right uh and so we just need
some way of making that work and off we
go now I think that's probably it don't
quote me on that but if we now go ahead
and specify these actual functions yeah
if we now go ahead and testify these
actual functions you can see where we've
what we've got we've got one that's
called output quads like so let me get
that up behind my head there that takes
the render group and the quad count so
we then have a vertex tab and index out
and in advance like so right so now if I
want to do this I just have to say okay
the vertex output it just writes a
vertex so doesn't have to return
anything it takes an index vertex output
pointer that's like this sort of output
pram basically it has the vertex offset
here and then it has a p value and n
value a UV value a color value and a
texture value
it's going to write those out and then
we have a similar function for writing
indices like so and it's really just
taking the indices you wanted to grab
for your quad finally we have an advance
and the advance just says how far
forward did you want to go
now that you've outputted some stuff
right and that kind of wants to be that
this also wants to be that as well
probably but we're gonna leave it like
this in assert probably is what we're
gonna do as well all right so that's all
the functions we need and in theory now
we will get basically just like a
compile that doesn't actually work right
I of course we haven't computed these
yet so we should so we need to actually
figure out what we're gonna do here that
shouldn't be too hard
these UVs are just gonna be like well
okay like that maybe is zero zero right
or something
this is like the min UV right so this is
going to be like cover UV x this is
gonna be like cover UV x cover UV Y and
that's gonna be you know zero cover UV
wire you know we don't really care well
let's get that working and then if these
things are rotated around or flipped or
whatever we don't like there but we've
basically got what we want there
and now we need to actually implement
the streaming and so let's go ahead and
do that you can see we don't have any
errors anymore except for the fact that
we didn't actually write the functions
that we said we were going to also this
should not be a pointer I don't know why
I made it a pointer we want that to just
return an actual little utility that you
use and so that should really look more
like this right we don't need to
allocate any memory or you know keep
that around that can just be something
that's on the stack of the caller and so
that's really what we actually wanted
and so now the question is basically
like what do these things look like
imma stub this out because this could be
the more complicated one these are the
ones that are very simple so let's do
them we know if we're going to try and
output a vertex you can see us we've got
our information here that's very
straightforward we know we just want to
use and if we again we go look at the
index vertex output structure here you
can see what we've actually got we know
we're trying to write a vertex at vertex
at something so it's going to be this
offset that we're getting passed in here
right and then we want to write some
part of this thing right and there's a
bunch of these that's what we're doing
right so we want to write each of the
things that goes in a in a textured
vertex to make sure we've got them all
so we need a P and N a UV color texture
index and emission value and reserve
value right that's everything we're
assuming that these aren't set at the
moment because we don't know what they
are or how they work so we're not doing
them the rest of these are straight
ahead
and so that's everything that we need to
fill out for a textured vertex so that's
pretty much it right that's all we're
doing for index outs now we have to
output our indices those indices are
into the global vertex array so we want
to make sure we know what they actually
should be and so in this case we need to
say all right the index offset here
we've got an index add we're writing
this one and we're doing plus zero
equals zero right we're doing basically
this so we're just streaming out what
those indices are supposed to be but
what you can see is these are not gonna
be those indices are not going to be
correct when you stream them out they're
wrong why because whoever wrote this
right they don't know we're in the
global vertex buffer they are they just
know where they are relative to when
they started outputting so when they say
zero one two three what they actually
mean is zero plus some base value right
and that's exactly where the thing that
I added in there and said we'll talk
about that later comes in it's this
right here and so that needs to be added
in right so what we really need is
basically this so all of those indices
get you know shifted up to the base
value that the person thinks like in
terms of right the person who's calling
this is thinking in terms of some base i
they don't know what it is they don't
know where in the you know run of the
program they're executing they just know
they're starting to output some vertices
and there could have been any number of
vertices already in the stream so that's
just letting them not care that you can
just give us indices that are relative
to their starting position and have it
work so then when we advance we want to
do the same thing we want to take our
base index and we want to update that by
the count that we're advancing similarly
we need to that's in terms of a clot out
yes so that's in terms of quads now that
I think about it so we actually need
probably two yeah we need to multiply
that in two different ways I should be
more explicit so this right here is a
quad count
that's how many quads you're advancing
by so that means that the vertex at
right is going to go up by the quad
count times what
well how many vertices are there per
quad we know that there are four
vertices for quad however you know we
could make two versus this two one that
does that more so right now we're
assuming you're outputting indices and
quads adversities together if you were
reusing them we would have a second set
of these that you give two different
values how many vertices you want how
many quads you want right and the same
would be true up here and so maybe in
anticipation of wanting that what we may
want to do is actually sort of split
this out so there's one you pass a quad
count there's one where you do vertex
count index count right and so here
where we actually do that advance we
would say okay we want to make this be
something where we call our sub advance
here with Vlad count times however many
vertices we think there would be that
would be for how many indices we think
there would be that would actually be
six don't ask me why this is doing this
we need to change that in a second
because that should be six right correct
me if I'm wrong but that's the that's
the we don't have a way about putting
just quads so I'm pretty sure when we do
our our push squad call yeah right
so actually we need something like this
oops
and so here where we take that base
index right same exact code
nettles good to me I think that's really
all we need because this is just an onus
whistle pattern that we use and so I
think we can just keep it like that
right all right so I'm gonna change to
using that because I think that's a
little bit better I don't want to have
to worry too much about that so I think
that's better then in here we can just
say well we know it's four and six per
and so that's good and then when we do
our advanced here we will just say
alright we know we have a certain number
of vertices so we're gonna move four but
that many vertices we know we have a
certain number of indices and we're
gonna go that number of indices and then
finally we have a base index here and so
we know we want to update the base index
by however many vertices we move forward
right and so that's really all the
information we would need to track so it
gets us down to basically just this
function is the only function we
actually care about we do know we kind
of want both ways so we want this right
and then in here we would just say oh
yeah much like we did this other thing
we're just gonna say there's a version
you call with quad counts if that's what
you wanted but you don't have to so if
you wanted to output something that
isn't gonna just be strictly based on
unique quads all the time if you wanted
to do something like the cubes where
there are shared vertices you just can
and you would call the other version of
it so then we just need really this
where we set the result of the in the
you know the thing that we're gonna use
for outputting we need to be able to set
that effectively somehow and push quad
is our key because that's the thing that
that is doing all this kind of work so
when we look at what's gonna happen
there you can see how that works how
it's getting what it needs to get and
how it's doing what it needs to do but
you can see here where the
pase vertex index comes from it's that
right you can see it doing this
subtraction where it looks at how it's
going to offset those so we effectively
have a vert index which is where's that
here right so we have a vertex index and
an index index you can see us kind of
getting those things out here in effect
if you look at how we want to do this we
can probably just do this exactly as we
are doing it here effectively you know
we can basically just take this code and
say look this is what we're actually
doing here commands in this case needs
to come out of here right so then we're
taking a look at this we're getting this
information out we know we then need to
advance these by however much we're
saying we're going to eat up and then
we're saying we need to make sure that
we didn't overflow right and that all
seems fine as well
finally then here we're saying all right
we've got our I don't know what quad max
wad texture count is really doing
anymore
is anyone using that
yes so so quad texture count is is only
something that that people are using for
special textures right and I'll be
honest I don't really care about that at
all in here right so when we do output
clods we're just assuming that that's
not occurring because quad textures are
just not something we're managing right
we're not we're not we're not using this
for outputting like the cutscenes that's
not happening right so when we come
through here and we grab out the rest of
this stuff this is how we're finding out
where we're actually starting right like
so this puts us at the start of the
things that we actually needed to check
and then we you know we we just need to
take a look at these offsets here and
make sure those are all okay now the
other thing we need to do is the get
quads call in this case I think that's
what's called anyway where is that
there's like a thing we used to have for
checking our pushing get current quads
so if you look at how get current quads
works you can see how it kind of does
the work necessary to set us up for
outputting things as necessary and you
can see in here we say how many quads we
think we're gonna need at maximum and
that just as a probe to check to make
sure that we are going to have enough
room to output what we said that we're
going to output right so we want to
actually do that we want to the even
though we don't really use it much
because we actually end up using the
vertex arrays directly we don't really
do much of this stuff at all it's just
the quad count we use we need to make
that call now does push quad do that I
don't know
it does so it uses the get current quads
here in asserts that we have one we
don't really want to do that we want to
actually call get current quads because
when we've come in here we need to make
sure that we're going to have enough
quads covered right
okay so when we come in here we want to
say all right let's get this from get
current quads oops we want to be able to
call get current quads we want to pass
the render group the index count and the
texture that we're actually using in
this case we don't really want to supply
because again that varies per batch and
so in here we really we really would
wish that we didn't have to do this we
probably need to start simplifying this
code as well it's too complicated now
because it's doing way more than what we
actually wanted to do and so when it
does is special texture I think we want
to do is just pass in an old texture
here but again not great so back from
this code is not good and we should fix
it and then here we know we have six
four quads so we can just do this but
again we shouldn't be doing this anymore
we should simplify this to start
thinking in terms of more efficient less
for those things to do right all right
so let's keep going for firt index minus
vertex array offset this entry here
where we're getting our textured quads I
think this just needs to be safely
truncated back to a you you at 16 and
otherwise I think it's fine the output
quads call here is supposed to be
passing the render group but for some
reason I put the out in there and not
sure why that was not supposed to happen
but it did happen
and finally his base index the u16 it is
so actually that code didn't need to
look like it it was written at all
actually so we can actually change that
this is all irrelevant okay if I just
need to pop back and change a few things
here in this case we just need to do an
assertion
not sure the best way to do this but I
guess what we want to do is effectively
this assert that if you were to add
these two things together I guess like
that if that assert that that is less
than you 16 max right so assert that
that's not going to overflow
our situation then we're okay and
hopefully that'll do the right thing
the seeking power is always a little bit
Squinkie finally this is just I think it
squat index out and again that's just
gonna do those swizzles for us so I
think that's it we did a lot of code
here be nice to test it but we're pretty
much out of time so at this point we're
probably just gonna have to do some very
light debugging and then save it for
next week which is fine we've done all
the heavy lifting but now we have to
deal with the subtleties and it also may
inspire us to clean this code up a
little bit now that we kind of know
what's up there and that's good too I'm
not sure what this is complaining about
at the moment but I think that's because
I'd really it's probably just asserting
about something that we're doing I'm so
I would like to quickly switch back to
debug mode here just so I can get a
little bit perspective on what's going
wrong and see if I want to tackle it now
or wait till next time
so it looks like here we're getting some
kind of a output problem with our vertex
indices let me see what's going on so I
think that Oh
so we should probably this is sort of
separated we should probably fix that if
we go to output quads and they give us a
value of zero we should probably give
them back a value of zero as well so if
the index count or if the vertex count
equals zero and the index count equals
zero or I guess we should say in this
case then we go ahead right otherwise we
just give you back nothing because we
shouldn't ever probe there all right
let's now take a look at the next error
or well whatever they are actually good
okay so in this case in theory unless I
just screwed up that check now we should
actually be asking for some actual
indices yeah good um and so we gotta
make sure this code works properly I
kind of just like packed it together and
it's probably wrong but you can see here
we got the commands vertex count and
we're updating it I think the problem
here is that this entry
it looks kind of bogus oops it looks
like really bogus so if that's the
vertex and in x-rays offsets and there
at the base then how the heck could we
be that far in on the vertices in the in
the command stream right like that just
seems totally wrong and so that's just
suggest that something's busted here
right like it suggests that like I just
you know the way I'm thinking of this
thing is working is not correct right
because these things should be in order
for this to be true these things would
have to be quite different than they
were right because this is already
greater than it should be able to be in
that 65536 would have been a top value
before these things would have had to
advance and so the fact that those
things didn't advance doesn't really
make any sense and that's really the
part that that seems kind of strange so
given the index count was actually
passed something valid here I'm just not
sure what happened in there right if we
take a look inside that there we go if
we look inside here and see what's going
on you can see us sort of figuring out
what's going on
it doesn't look like
so I'll be honest I don't quite see how
this was supposed to work
so this is just wrong
and I guess I guess we just never hit
this case
I'm I'm not sure what's going on there
but this is actually pretty strange so
if you look at well okay mmm-hmm I guess
maybe I shouldn't say that maybe that
check is good enough I have to think
about it um no you know I don't think it
is so let's talk about that for a second
cuz I'm pretty sure that's just wrong um
so if you look at what happens during
get current clods you can see where
we're doing our check right here we're
saying look if we don't have a batch yet
start one basically right cuz that
that's happening here so if we do have a
batch take a look to see whether you
think we can fit these quads in the
batch or not but all we're looking to do
is say is the number of of quads that
we're pushing down this thing do we
think that's going to be you know higher
than then do we think it's gonna be too
high right and so if we look at how
we're computing that we're saying the
max number of quads or could be in a
batch is whatever the maximum 16-bit
value is divided by four because the
assumption is that's when the indices
would start to overflow right and I mean
I guess that's okay but it assumes that
we've never wasted any although I guess
that maybe is true so I don't know I
guess that is kind of true you shouldn't
if you didn't waste any you shouldn't be
able to exceed this but it's a little
dicey I'm gonna run it one more time and
see if I can see what's going on there
it's not really checking the thing I we
actually care about but it may be
sufficient so it's hard to say if we
take a look at output quads here that's
right on the crash you can see that
we're doing a safe truncate here and
when we look at what this value actually
is again the we're trying to compute the
base vertex value
and so how many quads do we actually
think we have sunk right the quad count
is 76 70 so the number of vertices
you know naively would be half that
right so I guess the question is well if
we then go and look at how many vertices
we've sunk it's way more than that so
the first question is why right so did
we mess something up so maybe we messed
something up and that's the answer but
let's take a look so when we're doing
vertex out and when we do our offsets
here is there something weird that's
happening where we're just recording way
too many vertices so you can see here
where we call advance we take however
many quads we think we did and we
multiply by six or by four four indices
and vertices that looks about correct
the same thing happens here we do output
quads we multiply by four and by 6 for
our vertex count and our index count and
you can see that happening here
so that again seems pretty reasonable
when we say get current quads what we
really should be doing is passing these
two values down so I guess if I say we
want to streamline this code a little
more but you can see if doing this
accent calculation we were doing here so
I really don't see that as being
particularly an issue so again I'm not
sure why we would be worried about this
so I'm not sure I'm seeing how we're
pushing that many how we're causing it
to to increase the number in such a way
this code isn't great and we should just
fix it but I still want to just see if I
can see what's wrong first before I
clean it up look I still don't see why
we're not getting a vertex or a offset
that increases it's like we're doing
something that somehow bypasses the
actual check so in draw a ground cover
right we call this once we Sam any quads
are which is correct once through each
of these we output the quad and then we
bail right
and I really don't see why that would be
causing a problem oh yes I do
so that right there is an advance on a
quad count it should have been one so
that's that's pretty much it so that was
just our our bad the implementation code
was not at fault we were all right
so still getting the same bug though so
we haven't fixed the problem that's a
bit weird how do we end up with good eye
not where you can do that not actually
rerun how do we end up with the same bug
with a different
right because that should have been
totally different should've got a very
different which should I got very
different numbers between those two so
that's a bit weird to say the least
right because correct me if I'm wrong
but that's like exactly the same values
which is ridiculous that should not be
possible between those two changes we
should have seen something something
change and the fact that we didn't is is
very perplexing so I think if we look at
what's going on in here for our advance
there although I guess all right I guess
that's not true because the advance is
only doing inside this so I guess that
makes sense
that was a bug but it's not V bug right
because this is the only thing that's
actually doing any advancing here so I
guess that makes sense and then this
code right here is the thing that
actually is doing that advance and so in
theory this should always match up with
what this thing is thinking but that's
really the only thing that we would
expect to have to check right so let's
take a look at whether that's actually
true each time through so if we take a
look at the entry it's the first time
through that we've done this right and
if we take a look at the commands here
and we look at how many indices were
actually we've actually gone you can see
that the first time we get in here we're
at 36 80 right
we're trying to add 256 vertices and 384
indices so we're gonna do that right and
we've done that and now this code
actually should work right because we're
gonna get a base index that's totally
reasonable there right so that all seems
fine and it's only gonna be the time I
guess where we come through where we
actually wrap it that this thing is not
properly producing the change you would
expect so as we come through here we
actually are streaming out vertices
possibly even correctly for quite some
time and then it's only when we actually
get to the one that would overflow right
do-do-do-do to do that we actually
trigger that that case and so it does
look like this is the problem of us and
get Garrett quads are not agreeing
because get current quads here is the
thing that needs to actually do this
work now we should merge these two
pieces of code is actually what should
be going on here but I wanted to buy it
first and then merge them next week so
the question is why is this not
triggering and oh do we just never
update that that's probably why
that's all so since it's triggering off
of the quad cap and we were just never
updating the clock out now you can see
how ugly this is because we're
constantly talking about quas we don't
actually care about quads we just care
about indices and vertices so we want to
kind of simplify that down so I keep
saying we should just fix this right
oops that's what I actually wanted right
and so yeah we just weren't updating the
quad count and the quad counts to think
that it actually cared about but we kind
of want to get away from that and so I
think we want to merge those code bases
those those code paths and just be
talking about vertices in indices from
now on because hey this thing could
render triangles just fine for the most
part and so we don't want to have it be
like requiring that okay so you can see
that we're now running correctly but we
don't actually get the output that we
expect and so there's a little more to
it than what we've got I'll take a quick
look at the debug but then we'll go to
questions because we could debug this
next week so the first thing I want to
take a look at is what are we actually
getting here for you know me you know
maybe the problem is in the actual
output but maybe the problem is that we
actually as computed complete crap
values for our ground cover and if
they're not actually in places we would
ever see and so the first thing I want
to check is just what are we sending
down right like what does that look like
so I'm gonna go ahead and take a look at
the drug ground cover and I'm just gonna
stop it right here and I'm gonna look at
what it actually sees you can see that
some of the times the texture handle
isn't valid so I'll stop on one where we
know we're actually getting a texture
handle right and then I'll stop kind of
right here so what what can we learn
from this like is the texture index
reasonable it is how are the UV values
UV values look totally fine well I mean
they look okay right I can't vouch for
them but they look like the kinds of
values we might see not sure what's
going on with the Watchmen no they're um
so that seems fine let's take a look at
the general cover struct itself we don't
really care at the normal is but it
looks right the bitmap we kind of know
was okay that's all that's just white
which is a fine you know non modulated
color so you know can't really be wrong
and then if we look at these p-values
here you know
um I don't think they're quite what I
expect them to be I'm okay I mean
they're not like obviously right they're
not
why would I expected I I might want to
take a quick look at what's going on
with those p-values so oops I want it to
feel unpacked entity I might just take a
look why is this is are these things
like upside down or something this this
should not and in fact that doesn't make
any sense that's not the way I was due
wanted these to get output so like this
is wrong it's not wrong in a way that
would cause the bug that we saw so you
know that's definitely something to keep
in mind but I actually wanted it to be
this so we're gonna do it that way now
it doesn't matter what those four points
are but you know that's what I was gonna
do so all right I don't know for a fact
that was not part of the problem but it
probably wasn't so we'll double-check
but I think that was just a minor
winding change nope that was apparently
pretty important all right so if you
look now it looks like our ground cover
is actually totally correct other than
the fact that the camera up Vector is
not right at the moment so we do need to
go set that but then I think we'll be in
good shape if we take a look at what our
clocks are now what we can see is that
well draw a ground cover is still pretty
expensive but remember this is in debug
mode so what I do want to do is just do
a quick Oh - and just see if we've
eliminated any of the problem and then
we can talk about the ground cover up
vector
okay so now you can see draw ground
cover is it's quite a bit better than it
was it's still not perfect right it's
still taking a little more time than I
would like but you can see that our
total time is actually quite a bit
better it's if we pause here you can see
that it's actually down where it used to
be and so even though this is taking
more time than I would like it to take
it's way faster than it was before it
was like quite a bit slower right so
we've sort of succeeded we got to change
the orientation of those things that
we've sort of succeeded partially we
probably could still do more than what
we've done but we're in good shape right
we're in pretty good shape alright so
we'll talk about the up Vector for now
what we can do is we'll cheese it I'll
just do this we'll run the game and
we'll just copy and whatever the up
Vector actually was right that's not a
good way to do it but we'll do that for
now
so here an update render worlds you can
see us producing our render group and
then we're gonna go down here and like
do some stuff and set the camera
transfer and then we're gonna actually
render the entities right so at some
point you know way down the line we'll
we do stuff like you know here let's say
and we would know that the camera up is
just gonna be whatever it is in here
right and so in the game X form I assume
that was this value right I don't
actually remember but you know what we
can just look so if we do get sprite
those are called sprite values for up
right yeah so if we go look at spray
graph right you can see the camera is
coming from game X from Y so really
we're just talking about game X form Y
this so it's it's this value literally
and so we can just go ahead and copy
those right so I can just copy that
value and say that you know it's that
and I can copy this value and say it's
that and now we actually have the
correct camera up vector in there right
and so now if we rebuild this in theory
when we run what we'll find is that we
should have the correct facing values
first rights although there could have
been another air in there right so we're
at least but that at least isn't the
problem anymore so presumably that's
correct now I looking at it I think it's
still a little wrong you can see it
looks a little sheared like do you see
how it looks a little sheared across the
top there so I think what's going on
there is our index output mmm it looks
like one of our quads is backwards and
so that you know we could also probably
fix fix that honestly let's take a look
at how those indices are being output
but that that's probably the only issue
there so I think we're almost there I'm
gonna set the debug out here I'm gonna
look at index out I just take a look at
it
that is not the way I set it up so it
actually should be that let's take a
look at that improves the situation
still looks wrong with those indices 0 1
2 3 4 5 that looks right that looks
right like what I would expect I do I
guess one of our P's could also be wrong
in which case that would explain the
that would explain that the problem but
yeah I'm not sure it really looks like
we're sheared there like we're missing
one of our things I wonder if one of our
p-value is wrong
[Music]
I don't immediately see it
I don't immediately see it oh yes I do
so again just the type of so yeah not
bad for a day's work I think we pretty
much got it and we kept that on the fast
path now so now our ground cover pretty
much looks the way it used to look I
don't see really any difference at the
moment and it's getting output in a nice
streamlined fashion so now like we're
not hurting for ground cover we're
getting a real nice throughput there and
if we look at our you know frame timings
they're they're really nice we're
keeping you know we're almost getting a
we could actually do a 120 Hertz at this
you know at this level so that's really
good at this stage when we haven't
pushed the optimization too hard so I'm
pretty happy about that and hopefully
that'll that'll stay one thing I'm not
happy about is it looks like our our
computation for where the word world
gets paged in isn't great it's too far
afield so we probably should adjust that
few region but that's not really
completely irrelevant
so anyway I think all that's looking
pretty good
I'm pretty happy with that let's go
ahead and go to the QA again I would
encourage you to try out the discord
instead of the twitch chat it's just
usually easier it's it's easier for
everybody and it's kind of more
permanent so you can use it offline
easier if you want to ask a question
head over to discord GG / Mali rocket if
you have a discord you can just go ahead
and join up there's a pound live Channel
and you could ask you know ask your
question there
all right so X 13 pixels actually that's
the fellow who wrote the debugger you
saw me use on Spain he's asking if
output quad should use an and rather
than an or or like what's the deal with
that and just to show you what he's
talking about um sorry it's this code
right here and uh yes so the answer
there is that I since I don't know how
this is about to be used no I wanted an
or the reason for that is what if
someone just wants to put some vertices
in the vertex stream and later they're
going to put indices that refer to those
and they just know what they're doing
right so while it's highly likely that
an and is probably something that we
could just do and it wouldn't matter I
don't really want to do that yet because
I don't feel super confident that I know
what we're gonna be doing so I just kept
it with the least intrusive one but yes
it totally would be fine right Balbus
asks so would the next step be to
instance the rendering of the ground
cover so there's a couple different
tacks you could take that depends on
what you want to do but basically yeah
if you wanted to make this even faster
because you started to run into problems
with transferring then in other words
right now we've taken a step of
optimizing just our handing this to the
graphics card right so we try to really
quickly write it into the vertex buffer
that's the dynamic for just buffer that
we render per frame but obviously
there's more information that really
needs to be there because frame to frame
we don't really change this stuff very
much right all we're really doing is
moving it based on where the entity
moves so if the enemy moves we offset it
but if that's just really one three
float value so we really could just send
just that three float value down
and so yeah if you were really concerned
about the transfer bandwidth of sending
down all the vertices for those clauses
to the graphics card the next thing you
would do is try to cache that stuff on
the graphics card so you'd create a
vertex buffer resident on the graphics
card when an entity came in and we undid
the unpack we would write the things
directly onto the graphics card and
leave them there and then when we go to
render we would just push on a thing
that says hey go render that thing and
here's the offset now there's a good
reason why don't do that right now it's
because that also does break up batches
right because at the moment we would
have to break up our batches to do that
and so if you really did want to move to
that system it's not as simple as I just
made it sound we would also have to
start moving to a system where we have a
fast indirect batch centralized dip loop
right so that you're always pushing down
like large chunks of two indices that
are like how many things to render with
what offset and it's like an indirect
rendering batch system so that we're not
hitting the API front-end too hard again
right because otherwise every every
sixty four quads we're switching our
batch for the ground cover and we don't
want that either
right so this as soon as you would
switch to the in test instance rendering
you're also then also creating a new
problem yourself that you would have to
solve right so you you kind of have to
be aware of that right and prime master
related question which is maybe it'll be
easier to do the upright sprite
calculation in the vertex shader instead
again same thing yes you can totally go
that route but you're gonna take on a
bunch of new work as well it's not as
simple as just in the vertex shader
because if you're doing in the vertex
shader that implies you've already got a
fast way of doing the dispatch that
allows you to switch those things Perce
right because that's changing Perce
right so and whether or not it even
happens is is curring per sprite so
again totally possible but not
you have to actually there's a bunch of
work involved which is why I'm not doing
it because until I know that we actually
want that it's we're inheriting a bunch
of work if we do that that we wouldn't
otherwise need right Ryan asks speaking
of getting the compiler to output the
right instructions I've been toying with
a lower level language assembly without
the friction really would love to hear
your thoughts I I really like the sound
of that
I'm not sure I can give it much thought
on spur of the moment but I could
certainly look at it offline here's
pastebin.com ml two TL e 8f
I would say it looks nice actually
I like where this is going
the only thing that came to mind when I
was looking at it was I was gonna say
don't be afraid of in fix notation right
the reason that see in fix notation
sucks is not because it's in fix
notation in fixed citation is a lot
easier to read than having to do like
all of this right
the reason see in fix notation sucks is
because it doesn't freaking define what
the assembly language is for it right so
one way you could think about it is I'd
forget C just forget I mean I'm talking
about C I'm just pointing it out it's
like a point of reference this is kind
of a little bit hard to read when does
it really need to be could you just have
a nice infix notation that cleanly maps
to these two a known set of things here
that would be easier to read so I don't
have to read like add Mull okay that's
do it right like join I'm saying so I
would encourage you to think about like
how do you make this easier to read what
it's actually doing while still
preserving an exact knowledge that it is
to mob's them all in an ad in this order
right because I think you can do that
you just have to be rigorous with the
way you specify how your operators work
in infix notation you can even have
these beading in fix notation like Mull
as opposed to x right so I'd say I like
where this is going maybe like I would
encourage you to think about can you
make it easier to read without taking
away any of the specificity because
that's where C really fell down they
made it a lot easier to read and as a
result it's much easier to type in but
you lose a lot of the guarantee because
a good pilot could do anything at once I
don't want the goodbye or anything it
wants I wanted to do what I want and we
lost that ability so the question would
be can you add a layer of readability on
top of this at you know maybe even keep
exact keep it so you can do exactly what
you've got here but is there a way to
also be able to write an infix
expression that's easier to read but
that someone who understands the
language knows exactly what it comes out
to be in
assembly that would be a really nice
addition to and somewhere that you could
add that that's a good value act right
that'd be my first thoughts I'm looking
at it that's all I've got off-the-cuff
for you but I like what you're doing I
think that's a great idea you know I
would love a better assembly language
because yeah register allocation not
really that important when we've got
sixteen registers flying around these
days right in X 32 I'm sorry in x86 x86
32 register allocation was a huge deal
and how you worked that out was a big
deal a lot of times now you've got
enough registers it's not clear how much
value there is to manually assigning
them most of the time right so should
there probably be a fallback in your
language for I want to explicitly assign
registers yes do we need them all the
time no and assembly language
unfortunately forced us to do it so what
you're the problem you're attacking here
I think is a good one let's get a little
bit of the cruft out of assembly
language but let's keep the good parts
great idea
I'm thumbs up any of their questions
do you ever feel like the veracity of
passing around and often use pointer
like game assets in hmmh is too much
hassle or do you find it's more
beneficial in the long run over a global
you know I'm I'm glad you asked that
question and I think the real answer is
that it is the answer is yes and yes the
answer is yes in general C and C++ have
a very hard time providing you the tools
that you actually need to to track how
things are used right a global variable
versus a function parameter are weak
ways of saying something about the
program and they conflate two different
things one is whether or not I want to
have to actually manually pass stuff
around in typing it in the other is
whether I want the compiler to pass it
for me right
and so C++ added only one extremely weak
version of this which is that in classes
that this pointer is automatically
passed for you why was that the only
thing that can be implicitly passed why
can't I just say that assets are
implicitly freaking passed right in my
game through functions that need them up
the call chain right and the answer is
because the people who write these specs
don't really know what they're doing
right they don't think through what is a
feature versus what is a specific use
case somewhere and so what they tend to
implement as language features are
actually specific use cases not language
features and that's why you get this
thing of like should this be a global
should it not up
written language would never have to ask
that question right you would never have
really anything be global unless you
didn't want to compute the address of it
off a pointer so it would be about
performance right not about whether it
was a hassle to type or not so really
the answer to your question is that I
tend to pass things around because I
would like to know about the chains in
which they are used it's sort of like a
functional programming style that's not
really functional programming but it's
part of it right
should the language have made that
easier yes did it no and here we are I
think you may have missed progress
question or maybe I missed the answer
you missed the answer platen 21 how
would you go about breakable surfaces
not like an evocative style that's
pretty off topic and depends quite a bit
on what you're talking about
breakable surfaces there's many many
things you can move mean by that and it
really depends on what you're trying to
do there are many many research papers
on this topic I would encourage you
probably to read them there was one
pretty recently that was pretty cool
actually I don't know if you saw it it
was cold
oh man I wish the web were good
Oh
they're my mechanical that's what I
wanted never remember the names of these
things any marks my my brain is too old
it's weird how you look I used to
remember everything and now I remember
very few things it's it's unfortunate
that's just how your brain goes here
yeah in this paper we present a material
point method for visual simulations of
baking bread cookies pancakes and
similar materials our model is capable
of capturing characteristic dynamics of
materials under baking or cooking
process such as melting rising cracking
and solidification here we show baking 3
loaves of bread with different slip
patterns or with no slit the dough
expands and the slits open up during
baking and now we tear one of them open
in this example we bake a tray of
cookies with varying amounts of
leavening agent and oven temperatures
now we pour pancake batter into a pen
cook it and then flip when the bottom of
the pancake is solidified in this
example we roast a marshmallow on the
stovetop the marshmallow is initialized
as a homogeneous material and we're able
to result the distinct textures of its
solid crust and melted Center after
roasting we model the material as a
solid water and gas mixture and keep
track of the heat transfer water
diffusion as well as chemical reaction
that take place during the baking
process the solid phase is modeled as a
thermal viscoelastic plastic material we
use a modified temperature and porosity
dependent chemical a yield condition a
more porous solid mixture it will have a
smaller cohesion limit and in the limit
of zero porosity we get a von Mises type
yield condition visco plasticity
replaces the hard constraint that the
straw
cannot be outside the yield surface to a
penalty term instead instead of
projecting the trial stresses back on to
the yield surface they are projected
along the same directions but only a
portion of the distance we demonstrate
the effect of viscosity with a dough
stretching and twisting example higher
viscosity makes the mixture more sticky
which matches the rheological properties
of dough here we demonstrate one of so
anyway you can go watch this in its
entirety but not suggesting you probably
want to do most of that in real time
because you're probably gonna have your
work cut out for you but point being
there's tons of these the research
community publishes many many many many
many papers on breakable surfaces and
the bottom line is what you need and how
complex that has to be depends a lot on
what you're trying to simulate if you
just want things to fracture in any old
random way you can just split them with
a plane and many times as you want right
carve them up and then use those chunks
it's a constructive solid geometry kind
of operation and you could do it right
if you actually want some kind of
simulation as to this is supposed to
behave like an actual material like with
brittle fracture and cracks that spread
and all that sort of stuff then you're
in the finite element methods and
there's a lot of different ways you can
do them but you need to start learning
some real physics and you know you have
to scale back the problem based on what
you can actually do in real time I was
because for games different than in a
research paper but that's the basic idea
and I think I said there's a lot of them
that was a recent one that came out that
was pretty cool but basically you know
it depends what you want
early in the series said you want to try
to make your own math up since we've
gotten around doing that yet I only sine
and cosine still remain we those are the
only two things we call and we
eventually will replace them but I just
haven't been motivated to go look at
that because we just had much bigger
things to worry about
whereas those are kind of a known
quantity it's like you can always
replace sine and cosine
I mean you can even just cut and paste
one off the web there's so many of them
so I know that won't be much of an issue
when we go to do it but we will have to
discuss it a bunch because we're gonna
have to do it from scratch right and so
I just haven't been motivated to
actually spend the time on that as
opposed to other things but those are
the only two functions that we didn't
implement ourselves everything else we
did so we're still calling the old sine
and cosine and we'll call the new sine
and cosine
once we implement them
all righty I think that's about it let's
wrap it up here thank you everyone for
joining me for this on a handmade hero
sort of pleasure coating with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with series at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with a source code so that you can
play around with it yourself and do your
own experimentation we also have a
discard now I'll be putting some links
to that up as we go but if you do want
to go to the discord
that's just discord GG slash Molly
Rocket it's got all of our stuff on
there and you can go ahead and log on to
that and chat offline as well it's a lot
better than the Twitter chat because it
kind of persists and there's also
different channels in there so if you're
trying to talk about something general
you can go to the general tab we're
going to talk about something general
technical lingo the technical tab if
you're trying to ask questions live go
to the live tab it just helps it's a lot
better than the twitch chat for
interacting with the folks and also I
pop on there to moderate it from time to
time to keep things civil which i think
is also a good thing just to make sure
that everything is it's Pleasant so I'd
highly recommend you check that out to
been working pretty well so far and we'd
like to get that to a point where it's
nice and stable and everyone's happy
with it so do pop in there and give us
our feedback as necessary I noticed
someone was mentioning that discord is
great but we can't live without in sebat
I agree it would be nice if in Cevat
became a discord bought at some point
but you know beggars can't be choosers
so we'll see what happens
that's it for today I'll be back here
next week when we're going to take a
look at putting lighting in we've
finished streamlining that process so
now we're gonna put in some lighting
evaluators into our pixel shaders we're
gonna see how much cost we incur from
doing that that'll start to go summer
perspective on what we're gonna have to
do because now unlike the previous pass
and lighting that we did this pass on
lighting is literally gonna light
everything it's gonna light all the
sprites as well as the rooms so we're
really gonna be stressing that lighting
path a lot a lot more than we were and
we're gonna have to see how that affects
our performance and we're gonna have to
take the corrective actions necessary to
make sure that everything still runs
smoothly we want this game to run around
60 frames a second on a good
gene so we need to keep our you know
within the budget for that that's about
it until next time thanks for joining us
and I will see everyone on the Internet
take it easy everybody