start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show recode
a complete game live on stream yesterday
we started work on some particle system
stuff that we want to do and we also
uncovered kind of a thing that I wanted
to do with our arena alligators so we
kind of have two things that we could do
right now
since we started the particle systems I
think I'm gonna go ahead and just
continue on since I don't anticipate the
arena stuff being really a problem for
them anymore but then it's kind of I
think we may spend next week doing some
stuff with the memory alligators just
because there's a bunch of things I'd
want to do with them and since we had
found kind of a thing that was I mean it
wasn't really a bug in the alligators it
was a bug you know about using them but
it was a bug that probably wouldn't be
there if we had you know expanded our
arena concept a little bit more and use
it in a more disciplined fashion so that
kind of begs the addition of some some
of those features now rather than later
since we know as soon as you hit a bug
in something that you think could have
been prevented that's a good indication
that you should you know consider
upgrading that system at that point or
you know improving that method of doing
things so it just kind of seemed like
the right time for it that's all so I'm
going to go ahead and continue with the
particle system stuff and then after
we're done with the particle system
stuff I'd like to switch back to the
arena's stuff and that's probably what
the way will shape up the next two weeks
or so all right so protocol welp I'm
more than two weeks is we could easily
spend more than a week on particle
systems rayne there's a lot to do there
in terms of TWiki things so yeah I know
I say two weeks that'll be our next
couple weeks that should easily be stuff
that we can kind of focus on and have a
little bit of a party on uh so yeah
today I believe is 337 am i right about
this midlow yep so today is day 337 so
you want to start with day 336 of source
code if you're gonna be coding along
with me we are gonna be doing a bunch of
programming today there's not really a
lot of concepts to talk about that we
haven't already talked about with
particle systems
so what I'm going to do is I'm gonna go
ahead and press a little bit further
past what we did yesterday so if you
take a look at what we did yesterday we
essentially added a system that can keep
particle systems around cached that are
tied to entities basically is what's
happening so if I want to what I can do
is and where is my my yeah if I want to
I can have any entity essentially have a
particle system attached to it now and
when that entity is in the active region
that particle system will itself become
active and when it is outside of that it
can get replaced in the cache by
something else and then it kind of gets
jettisoned so what we need to do here is
we need to start expanding on the
concept of what these particle systems
are and what they can do we need to
actually create for example a
specification for a particle system that
could make something that we want it to
make who knows so we kind of just have
to start thinking about like in
experimenting to sort of say let's make
some particle systems that might be of
the kind we would want to see in the
actual game you know who knows and then
sort of go from there now I don't know
if we actually have anything in our in
our in our sort of pack that has to do
with these it occurs to me that I never
really thought to make something that
inspects one of these HHA files so we
don't really even know like I don't even
remember what we put in there I I really
just don't so I know we've kind of got
some of this stuff in here that we were
using before I don't remember if we ever
did a actual particle of some kind I
felt like maybe we did but I think we
just used the hero's head for particles
in a lot of cases as well so I don't
really know and so what I probably say
is you know I might just have it create
a bitmap we can use or something like
the
because I don't really know if we've got
anything in here and I don't remember if
we put anything in the hhas that would
be related right I don't know if there's
anything in the intro or @hh aI don't
think there probably is because it was
probably just intro I don't think I put
any game assets in there anyway
so I think our hhas here don't really
have anything for us that we can use
anyway so excuse me
what I need to do now is I need to start
getting these particle systems going and
I need some kind of a bitmap to use for
the particles and that sort of stuff
right so I need to kind of get that
going all right so let's take a look at
this here let's say that I just want to
do something similar to our existing
particle system because we already raped
wrote some code right that was for an
existing particle system and that
protocol system that's not what I wanted
was just a thing that like spewed little
hero heads kind of out of like of a
known location right so I believe this
was the code that we use for our
particle system right here so what I
want to do is I want to come and
describe this particle system and say
well let's go ahead and just get this
particle system working as an example
inside our particle system here and you
know maybe that'll give us some insight
into what we would want to do so I don't
really know what we would call this but
doesn't really matter like I said I'm
just gonna start working with it a
little bit and just kind of get it to
the point where it's something that we
could run and we won't really think too
hard about anything else so I guess we
don't need that either so here's kind of
the the outlines of what we did back in
those days if you don't remember this
now would be a good time to go catch up
on those old episodes about the particle
system there were only two of them
shouldn't take very long so the particle
spawn index was just a thing that's
saying hey let's create some new
particles here and you can see what we
had for particles and you know maybe
this is a good guide for what we should
story we had a position for each
particle we had a velocity for each
particle at acceleration for each
particle and then we had a color and a
you know essentially a delta on that
color right and one of the things that
we were doing was we were spraying
nothing's I think in honor of Shawn
Barrett and his libraries at some point
this obviously is not you know no this
is relevant to this stuff but you know
we need at least that part so there's a
bitmap ID it was using the head bitmap
ID and each particle I guess had its own
bitmap ID I don't think we will probably
want to do it that way in terms of using
bitmap IDs like that because just
there's there's some kind of complexity
there I'll just quickly give you a
little bit of a sketch of why we
probably don't really want to do that
and we wanna do things slightly
differently so let's say that we want
these to be rather efficient so what
generally happens is that we want to
render all of our particles you know
when we're talking about having a large
number of things so for example we use
the number 4096 kind of arbitrarily but
you know if you think about how many
that is right now a single particle
system if it actually had 4096 particles
would have more more actual sprites in
it than anything else in the game
combined right so like on the screen
right now there aren't even 4096 things
and what that means is that when we go
to render these these are going to be
the most expensive things to render in
terms of getting Roth data throughput to
the card for like positions and stuff
like this positioning color and whatnot
so if you take a look at what this means
this 4096 number it means that we don't
want to be doing anything per particle
right we don't want to call the graphics
card one time to do something for each
of these right because if we have a fair
number of particles distance on the
screen and each one of the last 4,000
nice
particle just like that it's quickly
going to add up to way too many
interactions with the graphics driver
and way too much overhead so one of the
things that can create that overhead
depending on the circumstance and there
are cases with by endless graphics API
is and stuff like this where there are
cards that don't have these limitations
or drivers that don't have these
limitations but in a lot of cases
especially on older hardware or on
Hardware that might not be like you know
quite so gaming dedicated like maybe
mobile graphics who knows typically
changing the texture is bad so a lot of
times you don't want to have to change
what that remember we kind of like with
OpenGL we would say like GL you know
we'd have like this text image 2d and we
would say like GL buying texture right
and we would say here's the texture that
we're going to be using for drawing well
doing that bind it costs that is a cost
and so having to do that manual binding
is not really acceptable because it
creates way too much driver interaction
and potentially way too much card action
as well depending on the card and so
what we would rather do is have a way of
having all 4096 of our particles just
all in a nice big buffer right where we
can just point the graphics card at it
and say hey we're just going to set up
your state once and then we I want you
to process all of these particles right
so what that means is that we don't want
to have to change particles for each
change textures for each particle
because if we did that we would have to
talk to the driver Gannett and again
create more and more bus traffic
possibly more card operations and so on
so best-case scenario for us if we did
want to change textures like actually
change textures for protocol well what
we would do is say like okay so there's
the position you know of the texture the
particle for each particle there's like
a position and a color position color
and so on and then we'd put a texture
pointer here right an actual card
texture pointer here and that actually
is possible on some higher-end cards
right so you
is actually possible to include what
texture you're using as part of a buffer
that you hand to the graphics card and
say hey here's the position and the
color and the texture pointer of each
particle as you render and have that all
be done in one big batch that is
possible but it is not very widely
supported at least you know not if
you're talking about you know hardware
from 2-4 years ago whatever or even some
hardware from today that's not you know
high-end or whatever so instead what
there are is there are other techniques
that kind of approximate this so if you
do like you know what one solution to
this that's very simple right you just
say well you only get one texture per
part per particle system so you know if
this particle system all the things have
to be little spheres or all the things
have to be little stars or whatever
right so that's one solution we
certainly could go with is saying well
okay we just pick one texture and we
stated that texture right but there are
actually other alternatives that are
sort of similar to this that we could
use that don't involve that kind of
limitation so we could have different
particles in the same particle system
using different textures which I'm not
even saying we need that but I'm just
pointing out that it can be done and the
way that we do that is instead of trying
to switch the actual texture that we're
using what we typically do is find a way
to pack more images into the same
texture so for example one thing you
might do is say well okay if this was my
texture maybe I divided up into four
pieces and I put one particle here I put
another particle here you know I put
another particle here and I put another
particle here so here is my four
particle you know bitmaps and then what
I could do is just in here pass sort of
something that tells the gravis card
what the UV coordinates for the particle
should be and then I just pick one of
them by by picking the the region of the
texture that I want right and this is
similar to like the texture atlas
technique right for example that you
might see talked about where you're
basically just packing sprites into a
single texture so that you don't have to
tell the card to change textures every
time you want to pick a different image
out of it
okay similarly another thing you can do
is a lot of graphics cards now support
the concept of texture arrays and what a
texture array is is it's a single
texture handle that you set up so when
you do a texture handle it's a single
when you set up but then you can
actually pass an index here right
effectively which says which sheet of
like a stack at that address
right you want and so you pack these
guys in there right the square goes in
the back the track right and so then if
I pass index 0 I'm gonna get this one of
X index we want to get this one of the
mixture get that one and that has some
additional advantages over the the Atlas
technique assuming that everything is
going to be the same size like that
because obviously these things have to
all be the same size they're all like
you know one texture that's kind of has
different slices to it's like a 3d
texture almost right and there's some
benefits to that and the benefits are
that you can have better control about
what happens at the edges and during
mapping and things like this because
they think about what happens here as
this texture gets down sampled if you
were to do same it mapping or if you
look at what happens when I cross over
the boundary here well if I wanted to
like make a repeating pattern or
something like this I couldn't really do
it here because as I cross over this
texture boundary I'm gonna see the star
right but in this case I don't have
anything on the other side section right
so I'm free to use this sort of wrapping
and clamping texture modes that I would
normally use and so sometimes that and
plus the mipmapping not filtering them
down together
those things can have you know reasons
why they might be important not I don't
think they will have any relevance on
handmade here for the most part but you
know for certain higher-end applications
that you might be considering these
things have you know potential bonuses
it's a difference between them and of
course the Atlas can do something that
this can't do which is to make each of
these be different sizes right I could
choose to partition my thing quite a bit
differently impact the rectangle down a
small one and you know the circle over
here and whatever so you kind of also
have this notion that a texture Atlas is
a lot more flexible for packing the
things in but
one of these texture arrays is much more
flexible for actually using the textures
at the end of the day because they could
still take advantage of proper
mipmapping that doesn't degrade as you
get lower and then also border modes
which you wouldn't have it available in
the other one which is even that's not
entirely true texture atlases if you are
implementing your own textile fetching
and like a shader for example you can
overcome some of these limitations or
sometimes all of them depending on how
expensive you're willing to make that
texture sampling be but point being this
one is basically free like the card will
just do this right so you know it's a
way to get all of those modes back
pretty much for free without having to
do any kinds of additional math and the
shader to fix up texture coordinates and
pick things differently okay so as far
as particle efficiency is concerned
that's just something we want to be
aware of and probably what I would say
on handmade Hiro makes the most sense
okay so just do something kind of like
the Atlas where we just hoo huge where
you live here where we just want to take
a single texture and put you know the
four bitmaps or whatever ten bitmap 16
bitmaps whatever we want to do for our
product systems just pack them into one
texture I don't think we're gonna have
too many of them and then just use that
one texture by selecting out of it using
some UV coordinates and you know in the
simple case what we'll do is we'll just
actually pass full UV coordinates for
the particles full rectangles and and em
UV coordinates but if we ever get around
to playing with shaders and want to kind
of explore that a little further there's
other things we can do there where we
just pass down something much more
simplified like the center of the
particle and its size and maybe
representers orientation and then just
just an index for which one of these we
want and then we would have one of our
front-end shaders in like the the
geometry shader side of things we would
then have that do sort of this
amplification of that minimal
description of the text of the particle
into the actual UV coordinates you know
take
index implement the actually of course
and so on sort to feed the later stages
of the graphics pipeline so right now
we'll just build it explicitly on the
CPU but you can do more compressed
representations of particles and should
if you're going the shader route because
it you know if you're if you know your o
target Hardware always has stuff like
geometry shaders on it because not all
to do all right
so coming back I think we do want to
sort of leave this as a as an open issue
at the moment and say we'll deal with
that a little bit later because that's
really more on the rendering side of
things so for now what we'll say is you
know the bitmap IDs not something that's
going to be per protocol so we really
want these other things per protocol and
we don't really want to deal with the
other stuff just yet if those are the
things that are going to be per protocol
and we do want to make them be sort of
lined up this way then I think what we
want to do for the particle system is is
again kind of think of this a little bit
sim D wise so to me I kind of feel like
I would probably want to do this as a
Sindhi things where we kind of have
something like this where we kind of say
like okay however many particles we want
in our systems we'll divide them by four
and so that we can kind of keep our
particles in in a nice sim D fashion
right something like this because I do
want to be able to process these things
relatively quickly and we should process
them four at a time and we can always
know that we've got four of them at a
time because again particle systems the
count is very flexible no one's going to
care if we have exactly 63 particles in
a particle system we could always make
it 64 and be fine right so I'm going to
go ahead and actually delete these
because second I want to kind of make
them a little more specific so if I was
to do that you know you could see me
making essentially the variables that we
had in our existing particle system
pretty trivially I don't know that we
actually need them all but let's say
that we did we would have a particle
system that kind of looks like this so
we've got our color
and I guess I don't really know so I
guess what we were doing before is we
just wiped the color out when the we
just we just will respawn a particle oh
we just respond the we spawn particles
in a in a front so that seems fine to
never mind all right so yeah this is
what we had before
and it'd be pretty easy for us to
implement things this way using you know
sort of again the the sim D instructions
and all I'm doing carriage is saying
okay so let's suppose we've got those
things I'm just going to do sort of the
simple version of those so that all of
the operations that we do will operate
in four products at a time that's kind
of annoying you can see why you probably
would want Auto vectorization for these
sorts of things because you can kind of
see that what we're gonna have to do
here is just a lot of unnecessary busy
work when we're actually sort of trying
to work with these things because in
order to deal with things in the sort of
M 128 sense we forgo a lot of things
that would be nicer such as the nice
math notation that we had for the rest
of our sort of math ops and that's
purely just because you know these
languages weren't designed very well to
handle vector AI stops like this so
sometimes you can get away with just not
doing it writing it in scalar and when
you do writing and scalar then you get
the kind of this thing if well maybe the
compiler will vectorize it for me
there's actually ways in LLVM for
example and visual studio to sort of say
hey would you try to take this code that
was not you know four wide and make it
four wide as best you can
you know stuff like that it never really
can you do probably as good as you could
do by hand but somebody's probably good
and I believe that Intel one the Intel
Auto paralysing one was supposed to be
pretty good you could mark up your code
to kind of give it hints about how you
should do stuff and once you did that it
was it was pretty good at generating
what you would want to generate so you
know over time hopefully these sorts of
things will become easier and you won't
have to do them so much
by hand anyway so if that was a particle
system what is this same max oh yes all
right
so what I want to do here is I want to
just start to get this stuff into shape
where you know I'm gonna literally cut
try to just implement exactly the same
particle system that we had in the first
place
and I'll try to get that running so this
is just gonna be like a you know play
around we don't really know what its
gonna do but we do know that it's gonna
be operating on one of these particle
systems so you know we're pretty sure
it's going to be doing something like
this right so we need to do some
spawning obviously the spawning will
make you know what will be exactly what
you expect
we need something in our particle system
here I guess I don't know exactly how we
want to do this but we would want to
have something where we keep track of
this next particle thing because that is
something we want to do and presumably
we want to spawn I guess we would want
to spawn for our particles at a time
since we already had this spawning three
particles of time it seems like spawning
four particles at a time would not be
particularly problematic right but you
know I don't know that may be something
that for certain things is not tenable
because you may not want for a particle
spawned every frame you know that might
just not make very much sense so we may
have to make the spawning of particles
be something that operates individually
doesn't actually use the sim be part as
much but I don't know for now we'll just
keep it spawning it in clumps before
because that will be the most efficient
we'll just see where we get so I'm gonna
say this is like next particle four
because it's actually referencing into
here you know it's it's referencing into
clumps of four as opposed to actually
talking about an absolute particle index
so I'm just kind of sticking a little
it's not a very good convention not a
very rigorous convention but it's just
something to kind of
make me look at it twice from schoo
right that's that's a thing that's not
directly talking about it particle
indexing an absolute sense so if we do
this and say all right let's assume that
we can grab particle out this way we
have our index here and maybe I'll just
call that pi/4 short or a particle index
let's cut away index so in here we're
going to grab out one of these particle
indices and I'm gonna do that by saying
that it's whatever the next particle
four was I then need to check for
wrapping on this one so if it's greater
than max particle count four then we're
going to reset it and in here when we
look at this we don't need the four I
loop anymore potentially at least not at
the moment so I'm gonna get rid of it
because we're spartax wanting four at a
time and that's fine so in here we'll
just say all right once we do know which
one we've got we now have the ability to
sort of reference this slice here and we
just need to set all these guys up right
so I'm not sure if there's a smarter way
to really structure this I'd have to
think about that in a way that makes it
easier for us to talk about one of these
guys directly you know you can kind of
imagine we sort of want to talk about
the pxpypz and all that sort of stuff we
don't want to have to keep doing lots of
different sub addressing so it's a
little bit janky again so I apologize a
lot to think through whether or a
convention that I would like to use
that'd be better here but you know
essentially this is what we're doing so
you know before we were doing this this
sort of thing
and so I'm just gonna do that thing
again exactly what we're doing with it
there and the particle system entropy I
feel that could be also stored with the
particle I don't feel like we need to
have any kind of anything special going
on there so we could have a random
series here which is just the entropy
for this particle system and we could
coalesce that in fact you know what I
guess we could do is just say hey why
don't we just pass that in so there's a
random series that we'd get that's the
entropy for this guy and that's all good
in fact I could actually just do it this
way and then will that kind of would
advance it will do and then I just need
to do the rest of these guys a sec let's
save mine
nothing going on here particularly
interesting I literally just sort of
translating this into something that's a
little bit more sim de Sh and I'm
keeping all of the same values we had
before because why not
wait a minute he says
so this random between was actually
seven times okay that was almost a
copypasta there it's like wait a minute
what did I do
there we go that's the actual one
there's two ran in between and go see
all right so that's what we're doing
with that and so now we kind of have
this this sort of additional nastiness I
guess is that each of these is trying to
do four particles at a time and this is
only generating one piece of entropy so
we actually need to call this four times
one for each particle piece right so
these are actually like you know mm set
PS not set one yeah these are actually
sort of ones where we have to do this
right again not particularly pretty we
would rather have a way of writing this
a little cleaner so you know I think
what I would probably do at this point
is say you know maybe like mm set to
expression or something like this and
have a way of passing that expression in
there and then just replicating the
actual expression because that seems a
little bit easier than trying to keep
popping these so that way I can say like
mm you know maybe I'll you make it even
shorter so they're you know I'm gonna
say okay here's the name of expression
instead of having to reflect get that
four times I'll just say you know do
that four times for me right and the
same would be true for all of these
should probably indicate at least that
it's set
and that seems a little bit better
because then I can just sort of wrap
these and that we're already kind of
verbose here and so this way that keeps
down that sort of unnecessary
duplication which would just be a pain
in the butt to maintain because you know
I'm gonna come back through here and
decide to make changes I might have to
make it four times and that's just
annoying right
so yeah so finally we want to set that
acceleration as well and again this is
pretty straightforward not a lot going
on here
so those are the accelerations and now
we just have the colors what did I do
this this or CR a and the CIE RGB a here
is just again another randomization
and yeah these also get wrapped and they
should work I hope he says confidently
unaware of what was about to befall him
and last but not least we've got that
Delta color which looks like the
simplest of them all which is basically
all sets to zero except for the Alpha
value which decrements so in theory I
think that should do it
obviously we've got to replace these
effects entropy x' here with regular n
trapeze
yeah that's about it so yeah now we've
got sort of our Lagrangian or Larian
situations here and for these you know
again we can still have these if we want
them because since each particle system
is sort of a self-contained thing we can
definitely do sort of the the particle
to Grid situation the problem is it will
definitely be a bit of a Down shift for
us because in order to do that kind of
thing we are forced to downshift every
time on each batch of particles because
there wouldn't really be any way for us
to have the particles right into a grid
without picking out individual pieces
because their location in the grid will
depend on their XY coordinates and of
course their XY coordinates are all
going to be different in each batch so
for example this stuff right here where
we pull out the XY and we put it in the
grid like so that's really not going to
cut it in turn there's no way to do that
for Y in sse2 right you just can't do it
oh I wish you could but you can later on
this is why a VX 512 if I remember
correctly was such a big deal and I was
hoping we would get it in desktop chips
was and you know we will it's just
taking a really long time to actually
get any kind of installed based on that
because it was only in Zeon's and you
know blah blah but the avx-512 s were
really nice because that instruction set
for the first time I believe had the
parallel gather so you could basically
say like okay you know do this memory
fetch like you could go get particle
cells or whatever for for things for
wide right so that way you didn't
constantly have this thing where you had
to like downshift every time you were
going to work on something that happened
to sort of look up into you know a
texture or a grid or whatever and so and
where each Lane was going to want a
different
ocation there's no real reason why that
has to downshift right because you can
always do your memory ops for a wide
it's just the Intel circus that didn't
have four wide memory opposite or
anything like that for a wide fetch so
there again anyway uh yeah so I think I
will forego the grid for now and we may
want to support that but rather than put
the grid in at this point I don't know
that I really want to do that because I
think we want to probably send particles
maybe I'm making a huge mistake maybe we
just shouldn't send me the particles
because the number of particles will
have won't be enough to make that be
important so you know maybe that's just
dumb I don't know but anyway I'm gonna
go through here and just say alright so
then let's do the particle the actual
particle count and let's go through each
of the individual particles and then in
here we should be able to just nuke the
part that has to do with the grid right
which was that and I'm pretty sure that
the cells did not it was just the
dispersion that was all we were using so
in theory we should be able to do
everything else that we wanted to do and
we shouldn't have to worry about you
know the fact that we knew the grid
because only the grid was doing was
keeping particles from clumping together
so we should still see a viable particle
system with the grid turned off
alright so stimulating the particle
again this is pretty much just all we
really need to do now if we want to we
could implement some of these operations
on mm 128 if we want to I'm not sure to
what extent that would work okay I think
they actually might
already exist in some of the Intel
includes but I think we would be able to
do something like you know young-sam I
think we would be able to say like let's
overload an operator that will operate
on M 128 so if we want to we don't
really have to micromanage it quite so
much you know maybe we can just sort of
leave the equations roughly the way that
they are for moat for you know the most
part and then not have to worry about it
so much and so if we did something like
that you know you can imagine like the
particle situation here I don't know if
we can do plus equals without it being a
member function of the M 128 but like
these other ones we can so for example
scalar times you know if we do like a
scalar times it should be pretty easy to
make that work right so we should be
able to do that now unfortunately we
can't do the vector version of it so
it's still gonna look kind of like this
right
which is not great like it sucks to have
to blow that out in that way but I'm not
sure what the easier way to do that
would be notationally speaking one thing
we could do again is try to make some
kind of a macro that helps us with that
expansion we could also do something
that did slicing of these things and I
don't realistically know that that would
compile okay but we could try like we
could try to make like a little utility
that just does like pointers and then
rely on the compiler is optimizer to
sort of figure out what we were doing
there and not you know do a bunch of
indirection there certainly it's
certainly plausible that that could work
and if we wanted to do that you know it
would be more like Oh get a pointer to
the pxpypz
and then have a vector type that just
operated on pointers to things and then
hopefully we were smart enough to know
that it that they were not aliasing but
you know would it really know that they
were any other thing I don't know
etcetera etcetera so it's it's a little
tough to say I'm not sure how well it
would do this is again why you kind of
want these things to be more first SS in
the language so you don't have to try
and think through like how am I gonna
can I convince it to sort of deal with
these things that you know really it
should have just kind of naturally known
how to dealt with if you know in a
better situation so yeah so similarly
you know we can create one of these for
the multiply operator where there's a
scaler on one side so if we have like
something like this then I can say like
oh okay you know and set 1 PS for that a
and then you know multiply it by B and
that's the results off like that so we
can still use a certain degree of math
even if we don't try to do anything
fancy we can still at least do some of
that there and the same would be true
again for the color
so and the only thing like I said that
I'm not sure about is if there would be
any way for us to really do like the
plus equals and so on now obviously
there is one way we can do it which is
to wrap the m 128 in our own struct and
then put the plus equals on that which
maybe we should do I don't know
but I don't know that I can do a plus
equals externally right I'm pretty sure
that if I try to I would end up in a
situation I should probably finish this
one as well before I start trying to
compile I'm pretty sure that I would end
up in a situation where that would not
work but that's okay maybe we should
wrap it and you know that's fine too
anyway so if I go through here and say
here's my equation
then what I've got okay so all of these
things or these are all scalars that are
all happening here and then finally I
get to sort of my GDP which needs to be
expanded out
and now I think about it I could
probably at least save that expansion by
just making that a local pointer which I
probably should do but anyway you can
see that these are all just scalars
anyway so that's all fine we just need
that DT so there's the DT no no why we
do it why do we do a square is it a
little bit odd this equation it doesn't
look quite right to me why is it why is
it look like that it's doing a cubed
addition of the this looks like it's
doing a cube but why is it doing a cube
there's no real reason why it would do a
cube here I think that's a bug I feel
like this should just be this right that
seems like a bug why is it multiplying
because one half a T squared
we went up you know you remember we went
over the equations of motion one half ay
T Square is the equation we're looking
for here and for some reason that was
one half a T cubed which doesn't really
make a lot of sense if we're honest
about it's right you know doesn't make a
lot of sense so anyway not sure what was
going on there but you know in here we
can take a look and say okay so now
we've got the system DP
and in here we could say like okay the
system DP XYZ yeah right and so we need
to pass that DT we never really did pass
a DT here these in if this is an update
you know it's going to want one of these
and so that's all fine but like I said
these plus equals would be a problem for
us
so I'm not sure what to really do about
that now here's an interesting thing
here's a thought and this is kind of
ridiculous but I'm gonna say it anyway
because why not so here's the phrase if
you take a look at what this thing looks
like right
the pxpypz for an individual one of
these particles it's separated by some
number of intervening values but they
all happen to be like the same they're
homogeneous right they're all max
particle count for so if you think about
it if we were to to take one of these
things and say well we've got a particle
system and we've got this individual
thing you know maybe called a like
particle V 2 V 3 or be something right
so we have something called like a
particle V 3 you could imagine us saying
well okay what if there was an X for it
and then like an ignored
something like this and then a wife or
it and it ignored and then a Z for it
and ignored right like just
hypothetically speaking what would it
look like if we told the compiler that
we were pointing at one of these
particles and we actually gave it a
pointer to somewhere inside this P X
array right well in theory the X the Y
and the Z at that point would be
pointing into the right areas in their
respective arrays right because they're
just this far apart there's that many
interesting values to get to the Y right
because like if you started on the zero
with px you know there's max product
count for mm 128 before I get to the
zero with Y and if I was at the first X
I would know there was still max
particle count for mm 128 in between me
and the first Y so like 2 3 4 5 they're
always separated the way that's tried so
one way potentially right of simplifying
this down is something that would be
easier to work with potentially would be
to say well okay really I could get out
the particle here I could say that I
have a particle of III that's pointing
to the P and we just tell the compiler
that we have one of those and that we're
pointing at you know the PX of the the
system you know whichever index into the
particle systems are raised that we have
that's the one we're pointing at but
instead of treating it as just a single
px value treat it as this sliced
particle thing and then in theory we
could write the operators on that thing
right that's just something we could
operate on directly so we could do
something there we still like okay
there's our particle
and so then we could say well star P
equals you know well now I think about
it that part won't get it easier at
least do that right it's a little weird
right it's a little weird but you know
that's certainly cleaner to read right
so you know that to me seems like
probably a win in terms of constructing
this code right and we still have a
bunch of funny business to do here I
guess in some sense because if we want
to have operators on these guys then we
would need to each pull each one out but
you know not that big of a deal
right so it seems like that would work I
don't think I've ever done this
particular ridiculousness before but you
know I mean I don't see an obvious
reason why you couldn't do it this way
and since the stream is kind of winding
down here you know we can at least in
terms of time we could at least test
this out and see how it goes but like I
said it seems like something that would
work and of course I would have to make
a version of these that was actually
four wide for the colors check and doing
this
all right so something like this and so
I don't know will that work let's find
out if I also make a for wide one of
this well it's really no no different
it's exactly the same thing so it's just
RGB right okay so yeah clean that up and
so in theory I think that would work I
don't really know but I don't see any
reason why it would confuse the compiler
too much and then down for these things
here in theory we could make operators
on these and so in theory we could do
something like you know this guy plus
equals some way in which these guys get
up converted which i think isn't
difficult probably I'm guessing yeah
because at the end of the day you know
once we have one of these it's pretty
easy to also read out of one in a way
that collapses it right so I could also
say equivalently right if those are you
know if I'm operating on one of these
don't carry the particle v3 through
instead you will want to use something
like a v3 to carry the data so for
example let's do this one more time
I'm gonna maybe how do I want to do this
here so yeah I could do it this way
let's say I just instruct particle and
in here I just had these guys right and
so what I could do is say okay there's a
way of just getting a particle by just
passing whichever particle system that
is that you're talking about and then
the index that you wanted and then it
would just do exactly this operation but
return one of these right so you know
we've solved up key EP GDP CC and what I
might do in this case is rather than do
it that way I might actually have you
pass in the particle to fill out just so
our debug mode doesn't suffer too much
speed hit because you know in
optimization mode it would clean that
out nicely but in debug mode it's not
going to do something particular smart
there so I just since this is a loop
that'll get run a lot in debug mode I
don't want it to be too unwieldy so yes
I could say particle I don't know I'm
just going to call it a because I have
no real reason to call it maybe in
particular system AI
so now it's just you know and there we
go I think this is not anything we want
to preserve so I'm gonna go ahead and
move those guys down here and nuke them
temporarily probably permanently
eventually okay and that is not supposed
to happen
so let's take a look at that and see how
we feel about that I don't know it's a
little wonky but let's just take a look
so now we can do the same thing down
here and I'm gonna go a little over time
because I started pretty late eggs I'm
gonna go for a few more minutes so I'm
kind of enjoying this weird exploration
here I'm going to do the same thing down
here to get the particle out and then
I'm just gonna say like okay so we've
got these things right and I want to do
like math offs on them so I want to do a
single operation and update this
particular particle and I want to do
that using its DDP and stuff like this
so I want to say you know I want to say
a dot DDP here and I want to say a dot
DP here and I want that to just
magically work right
so I want to have that happen I believe
these are technically technically should
look like that
so yeah it's not great because I still
have to dereference it because it is a
pointer I believe yeah it is a pointer
so you know I would have preferred that
somehow it not be a pointer but I don't
know that there's really any way to do
that and still be able to write back to
them I suppose we could try making it a
reference but that would be kind of hard
to do the construction on we'll think
about that well think about that but for
the moment we'll just leave it like this
and then you know like I said this would
all presumably get simplified down into
something that looked a lot more like
the original so it would be something
more like this right yeah so I don't
know that I want to do this guy yet
because if will require some special
handling in the sim D so we'll leave
that out for now and we don't want to
deal with the rendering yet but
otherwise most of this stuff is okay you
know what like this is just one thing
here so this is again start a dot C plus
equals 2t times particle
PC right and similarly down here this
seems pretty straightforward as well
this is just clamping the color but I
don't know why we don't just clamp the
color I'm not sure what I'm not sure why
it I guess because we want to be able to
set the color to something other than so
the output color gets clamped so I guess
that that's just part of the rendering
so that's something that we don't I
guess I have to worry about just get
either okay so now if you take a look at
what we're doing here right we've kind
of got the stuff working that we want to
work but we've got some operator
overloads that we need to figure out how
to do because now we've got sort of
these particle VIII's here multiplying
my scalars and then they're getting
added to this and blah blah blah right
but that's okay because we can write
those things pretty easily if we take a
look at what we've got here if we want
to do one of those particle updates
right if we wanted to say okay let's
make a plus equals operator for our our
particle v3 right we could pretty
trivially do one where we just said okay
let's say it takes a v3 in well all we
need to do to make it take in our v3
well I guess we need us to be more
acidic we need a sliced v3 right so we
just need you know a v3 that's that's
for a wide right we just need something
that's this
I don't know something like that right
where we've got a four wide one of these
well if we had a 4y one of these that
came in we could then say okay well then
that's pretty easy the X is just plus
equaled the Y is plus equal to the Z is
plus equals right we just be adding the
pieces of these guys that we know we
already have right so hopefully you can
kind of see where I'm going with this
now so when we have this particle v3 we
can if we want to just do this up
operator on it and when we try to do a
plus equals operation on it we will
actually get exactly the operation that
we want right we'll just we'll just get
the piece of this so the question is
just well all right how do we then get
in these by the way here I guess not
super relevant so I I just said we can't
add those so this is what I actually
right so in this case I'm just saying
like alright let's do it and pretend we
have a thing that comes in here that's
got the values we want to add we'll add
them so then all we have to do is write
the opposite style of conversion right
when we see a scalar times one of our
particle VIII's well we don't want to
propagate this is a giant thing it's
like you know it's hugely it's a massive
object we don't want that whole
structure to be copied around but we
don't have to write what we can do
instead is just say well alright if you
were to see one of these guys where you
wanted to multiply a scalar by one of
these particle VIII's it just generates
just the part that it wanted to just the
part that we actually cared about right
so we could generate a result here and
that result would just be the x y&amp;z of
the scalar multiplication with the parts
of the giant slice that we actually care
about so we're kind of slicing off just
the x y&amp;z at this point and leaving
everything else right so now we can see
how this expression will start to take
shape how do we make this thing work
well okay it's gonna try to take one of
these guys which is a particle v3 right
it's going to try to multiply it by a
scalar so when it does that it will
evoke this operator put it in front of
that operator will take and slice away
just the x y&amp;z that we actually wanted
and then returned that as a v3 for it by
you know for X that will then get
multiplied by a scalar again right so
that means we're gonna need one of these
it's actually exact same code right and
then it will try to add that to
essentially an exact same kind of the
other side there right so we know that
that this side will generate the exact
same thing so then we just need a
operator plus for these guys and we're
done
right so now I think what is this type
missing type specifier oh sorry this
will just return in one of these guys
missed it typical ridiculousness and C++
no operator found for what oh yes this
is an mm well PS keep forgetting we
don't have any overloaded operators for
the EM 128 so anytime we're actually
doing them we have to use the SSE
intrinsics for it not a problem
okay and since this is a scaler I really
just need to blow this guy out so we
just need one of these like so all right
same thing here just need to write this
in Cindi friendly way which looks like
this
same thing blowout scaler and then you
want to do the mole PS and really we can
write this in a better way which we
could do tomorrow we could write this in
a slightly better way which is to just
make these guys first loft up particle B
just make a thing that translates a
particle B into a v3 for X and then we
just use that right so that's a much
easier thing than then writing that
every time so now you can see these two
guys compile just fine and now we just
need the four wide version of the same
thing right and then we're going to go
for it for the for the colors so I'll do
that tomorrow I don't want to run too
much out of time there but that's it all
right so I'll go to a QA for just a
little tiny tiny little bit
case anyone has any cue colons for me
Martin says on msec it is possible to
create a non-member inline operator plus
equals for emmerman 28 it is done in the
same way as you did for the other types
but for GCC clang you cannot do plus
equals 4mm 128 because they already have
it well you know that's not bad right
because we could if zero I could use
this zero not sure why I made it a
member that's a good question um I think
I was just thinking I had to for some
reason I used these features of Siebel
swish fairly rarely now so I don't
remember a lot of the minutiae I don't
really remember a lot of times like what
they pass does it pass a reference for
example yeah so
I assume that is roughly roughly what
they would want yeah
so says the kid instead of doing the
particle v3 struct could you accomplish
the same thing with macros and some
pointer math uh not that I can think of
I mean obviously you could create
something that just skipped that far
forwards but it wouldn't be you wouldn't
be able to do like the overloading
operator kind of stuff if that makes
sense but I'm not not sure
how much of your time would you say you
spend refactoring as compared to writing
new code well I don't really like the
word refactoring super much although
it's used so commonly that now I use it
too so I suppose there's not much I can
really do about that but part of the
problem is that refactoring is not very
specific about what you're actually
doing like basically anything can be
called refactoring at some level unless
you're like you know literally making
the very first pass of something
everything else is refactoring but it's
like well okay but what were you really
doing like there's a lot of different
things that all pass as refactoring but
they're not a lot of them aren't really
even all that similar to each other so I
guess what I would say there is I I
spend a tremendous amount of time
working on the architecture of code so I
definitely do spend a lot of time even
what I think would be traditionally
considered part of the refactoring
process but I don't know specifically
how much there is of that versus the
first pass through I would say it's very
hard to even talk about the first pass
through because the first pass through
oftentimes involves built-in sort of
thinking about times which you could say
was sort of a refactoring as well right
like for example even with what we just
did where we sort of started writing the
particle stuff and I changed it a couple
times already you know there was
refactoring in there technically but
it's the first time we ever wrote this
code it wasn't like we had working
version of the code that was working on
the 7d ones so you know playing around
with how I wanted to do the cindy was
kind of part of the initial rewrite how
much would you say that was refactoring
versus new code you know I don't know so
it's kind of hard to really talk about
those two things as if they're these
really black and white lines because I
don't really think that they are I think
that just writing code in general
is about a process like that as pretty
rare that you're doing something that
involves strictly one or the other in a
really pure sense
have you changed the way the particles
look if so push them
no we haven't gotten to anything like
that yet we were just playing around
with how we were going to make the
particle system code
Cindy friendly just generally how we're
going to write the particle system code
now in the actual particle system thing
and I kind of we're just playing with a
ways to make it so that you could
effectively write nan Cindy looking code
but still have an update for our
particles at a time
miss children often write code using
Cindy without a nonce MD implementation
in the same operation of the santur
fission yeah I do generally speaking
like Cindy isn't super hard to debug if
you're not doing something too crazy so
for something like a particle system
where it's really easy to inspect what's
going on I would not care if that made
if that makes sense i but for other
things like when we did the rasterizer
for example there's enough kind of
twitchiness and how that sort of thing
works and a lot of things to get right
that are kind of subtle and cannot
really be inspected directly visually
very easily I mean that inspected
nonvisually like just looking at the
numbers in debugger so I would take a
lot more precautions there if that makes
sense
for $2.99 if ji releases before the end
of this project and it's good enough
would you ever consider rewriting the
product in ji no I wouldn't rewrite this
product in ji because you know this was
started and see and we'll ship it and
see because it was designed to show how
to do C programming the reasons not to
rewrite it in joy or actually because
there's no point in me we writing
something enjoy on stream because I
don't know how to program Jai right like
there's no need to watch me program in
Jai because I don't know how to program
in it
so I wouldn't be showing you how to do
anything that wouldn't be what you would
normally just try to do probably if you
started doing it yourself it's the point
of handmade here us show how to program
in C by someone who's programmed a lot
in C and you know might know things that
a beginner doesn't know but I'm not
going to know things to be a gibe agin
er doesn't know because I will have been
a J I'd beginner so you know it I think
it only really makes sense to do
something like a handmade hero in ji if
you're a ji expert at which point then
you know it makes a little more sense so
you know I have a ton of experience
programming and C I have no experience
for a min ji so I feel like it makes
sense for me to stream showing how to
program C code or with a little C++
thrown in then it does too for me to
stream ji code which you know I've still
have never written a line in I don't
even have a copy of it
so is it hard to debug Cindy in Linux uh
that I don't know you know I really
don't know that's a very good question I
seem to recall there being an annoying
part of Symbian Linux where it doesn't
have the struct unions so you can't
inspect the values as different types or
something weird like that I remember
there being some a little annoyances
with it vaguely but I don't know I don't
really remember I'm sorry I don't often
do debugging in Linux because the
debugging is so bad on Linux normally
that I don't really know if Cindy is
appreciably worse in any particular way
it would be cool to see a stream or two
of a good programmer going through the
motions of learning ji I yeah that that
might be true but again that would kind
of be like a not really a handmade hero
a kind of thing right that'd be sort of
a separate stream that was unrelated but
I I agree like you know it probably
useful for John to see too like if
various programmers streamed their first
programming experiences in ji it would
definitely be the case that he could
probably learn some things about at the
very least how to document the language
well because you could see what people
weren't understanding or weren't doing
properly but he might also learn some
things about you know how to improve the
language to where a DC is like Oh
someone did some cool things here and I
didn't think about those so I didn't
really support them as well or you know
this person came up with something
that's like really hard for language to
do so let me try and prove it so you
know I could easily see yeah I could
easily see that being a good thing in
general I totally agree I just don't
like I said I don't think I has anything
do with handmade hero but it's
definitely there's definitely a lot of
good that could come of that as well so
alright
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for the episode of handmade hero so I
put our coating with you as always if
you would like to follow along with the
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero or it comes
with a source code I updated every night
so you can play around with whatever
we're doing on the stream in the comfort
of your own compiler we also have a
forum site you can go to if you want to
ask questions we have a patreon page and
go to if you want support our video
series a schedule bot the tweets
schedule you and an episode guide that
you can go to to catch up on past
episodes
I'll be back here same time same place
tomorrow night to play around a little
bit more with that soon decode until
then have fun program everyone and I
will see you guys on the Internet
take it easy