hello everybody and welcome oh god I
didn't mean to actually click that hello
everybody and welcome to handmade hero
show recode a complete-game live on
stream yesterday we did all the work of
optimizing the grid stepping so and I
did it in the actual table building code
so that I could verify it against our
table driven version and so that way I
have some reasonable confidence that it
will just work so today what I would
like to do is actually put it into the
main code so that I can do the change I
can make the change that I actually
wanted to make and so part of the thing
that I want to do here if we take a look
at what we've built so far I have a nice
way of verifying what or I shouldn't say
verifying measuring the slowdown so if I
actually go into handmade debug here and
I run h/h lightproof
like so one thing we can do that's nice
is we can look at what our total time is
right now in terms of the speed at which
things are going and we can sort of see
that we're hovering around 4.5 seconds
and there's some variability in there as
you might expect depending what the OS
is doing and so on so forth
but we kind of know how long our routine
takes to function right now and so what
I wanted to highlight there is just as I
make this switch I want to see if it
costs me anything so right now what
we're doing is we load you can see us
sort of passing it in here you can see
us loading this walk table and so the
way that this works is every time we go
through this loop and we do our array
casting we access the next we basically
look into that walk table to figure out
what grid square we're going to or I
should say grid cube we're going to xx
access next and so what I want to see is
can we now sub in
just the raw code from the walk table
routine and effectively get our walking
in line with no table lookups without
actually paying any significant
performance penalty again if you're here
yesterday you know the reason why I want
to do that the reason is just because I
want to be able to make the sizes of our
grid squares significantly larger than
the lighting voxel that's just so we can
do more iterations of the inner loop to
test and right now we're just really
under filled and again if you missed
yesterday's dream that's what this is
showing we really want to slot into
these much more cleanly we want a lot
more higher numbers in here so we want
box count you know 16 and stuff like
this and furthermore we really want to
reduce the count here and the since this
is just representing empty space the
only way to reduce that count is reduce
the size right and what you can
understand there it's like we're
traversing these grid squares as a way
of reducing the number of things we're a
cast against but when that number
reduces to small we just are wasting too
much time getting over the grid right
and it's really easy for me to just
change that size it's just a few
parameters we can just play with right
but the thing that would hold us back is
the watt table so we just need to go
make sure right that we can actually do
the walk generically without a table and
so that's what I'm going to try to do
now so if we go down to our compute walk
table fast routine in here you can kind
of see us doing the set up and so on and
we have a few tables that we need to use
that are just local access tables those
are cheap and pretty easy so I should be
able to just stick them in here and
furthermore once we actually have these
tables lined up in here we will also be
able to replace if we want to we could I
think probably do an extended version of
the best table
if we wanted to do an extended version
of the best table we could probably
change from using the min the mini pu 16
hack that I did here that I feel like
was kind of fancy and smart but
sometimes being fancy and smart just
just makes you fancy and dumb so I'm not
sure that this was really a good idea
because of the accuracy concerns and so
on so I'm not really sure we want to
leave that in there so now that we've
got a way to kind of do this and we're
already using a table to drive the tea
comparison and we know we need that one
to be accurate we can probably extend
this to this table to be 16 long and if
we I mean honestly we can change this to
eu8 as well so we extend this table we
could then use it for the other
comparison probably right so just
something to think about
it's in the back of my head whether I
want to do it or not I don't know and it
doesn't really matter right now but it's
just worth noting that we may be able to
more or less for free because we already
paid for the tables and they're already
in the cache we may be able to just
replace this with a more accurate one
and and that may be something we want to
do just something about ok so if we go
and now take a look at what's going on
in the table building loop that we
already optimized you can see the stuff
that's happening here is fairly
straightforward and then each time we
want to take a step it's just this code
at the top right it's this code here so
I believe if we just go down here and we
take a look at when it's using the table
right I should be able to do something
where I can just validate this against
the table directly in line right so what
I could do is say ok I'm gonna grab this
code here's the code that actually does
the walk right that's it right there
um and all its doing is it's just taking
the T values moving them forward by the
amount they would go in each of the
dimensions seeing which one hits first
so do we hit the x wall Y wall or Z wall
first updating the tracking of where we
are and you know outputting basically
thanks to the best table outputting
which one of the columns you know was it
X was it why was it Z so if you take a
look at what we actually need to know
here we just need grid index in T
terminate or more specifically we just
need D grid and T terminate and so we
kind of know at that point we can get
those two out by just doing these two we
can we can extract if T terminate if we
need one and we can extract a good
result if we need one just by looking at
these so the step table a determinate
table and so all I want to do here is
again I want to do the exact same stuff
I was doing so I basically want to do
this verification and basically have it
just fault on me immediately if they
don't fire if I I want to do that
verification against the these values so
I don't want to update the walk table
just yet right I want to kind of do that
afterwards just so I can see like so but
another way I could do that and maybe
I'll do it just for fun is here I'll
just do like what was the D grid value
I'll just read it out that way we're not
reacting that table so we've got the D
grid in the T terminate there and what
I'm gonna do here is just take and say I
want the T terminate and the degrade
values to line up like you can see and
that way as soon as there's a problem it
will crash right so I'll fault
immediately upon there and again the
reason for that is because sometimes we
turn asserts off when we're building in
release mode and so I just want this
default all the time right now and then
when I clean it out we'll be done so
that should do it
and now what I need is the preamble
right so you can see here we've got some
issues
like the shuffle table the shuffle table
is a little bit different right and I
have two and this one is and and one of
the things we'll probably want to do is
unify these shuffle tables right and we
may be able to do that but for now I
don't care so I'm just gonna call this
like the tea shuffle table and that one
can still be called shuffle table so
down here where we where we access it
there's really only one place right all
it does is is do that one shuffle to get
everything into the right location so
it's pretty straight forward and then
what we need is you can see all of these
four values are not actually they don't
exist right cuz we set them up to me we
set them up up here so what we want to
do is we want to bring those values into
the system and it's a little bit tricky
because the way we chose to do this as X
Y the way we chose to do this as X Y X Z
again that causes some problems for us
so it makes it not line up very well
with the other things we have to be
completely honest with you I think the
reason we did it was probably not a
fantastic reason so the reason we did it
was so that we could actually just make
this table be shorter but that looks
pretty dumb now doesn't it because if
you look at what's gonna happen when we
integrate this routine all of a sudden
we're going to need completely different
values for each of these right which is
a huge pain in the butt so actually you
know maybe we don't want to do that yet
like maybe that's actually dumb and
maybe what we actually want is to go
back to that routine and just make it
work with X Y Z X right I don't know
it's unclear to me like I want to double
check that that makes sense but I just
think it would because if you take a
look at what happens here with like Ray
ad packed and stuff we are
kind of have what we need but we just
would have to add like the ex in here
right and even if we didn't want to do
that we could even just leave that lane
as zero if we wanted to and if we did
that we still would probably just be
able to make this work we just need to
do one extra shuffle right we just need
to replicate the X before we do anything
so it's kind of it seems kind of
motivating to do that so if we take a
look at Rady pact and where that
actually gets used you can see it
getting used in a bunch of places for
initialization as well my only question
is like what are we doing with that one
lane there with that Lane being zero
like does that always get knocked out or
doesn't it right and that's pretty
tricky because I don't know like we're
optimized this code quite a bit and so
we're kind of past the point of this
being versatile code like we went we're
in the speed zone now so everything's
like very concentrated and so it's hard
for me to know like to what extent we
may have relied on that for tricks
because it's hard to you know can't
really document every little thing you
do when you try to optimize a piece of
code and so it's you know it's kind of
difficult to say but we can't kind of
take a quick look and just see like do
we think we could just stack an X in
there and again another thing we
probably want to do is eventually just
test these routines a little bit hard
because we can make constructive tests
where we make specific shapes and stuff
and make sure we hit in the way we
expect and things like that right so
like looking you know I mean just
looking at this stuff though I honestly
don't know that there's a huge issue
there
I mean you know it doesn't look like it
right because most of the time you see
it's extracting out and it just doesn't
really look like it particularly cares
you know because like things just get
knocked out all the time here so it just
it doesn't really look like the kind of
thing where it's gonna care if we used
that extra Lane so I think I'm just
going to go ahead and say like either
way I want to go to that fast routine
here and I just want to do a little bit
more work on that so let's just make
sure so if I go and launch this in the
debugger I should be able to make sure
that we're still validating correctly so
if I run it it works if I go in here and
I change this table to be like incorrect
or something like let's say these are
twos now it should just fall immediately
as not matching the results that we
expect right and again this is just for
me to make sure that our safety net is
still in place while we make these
changes so when I go down here and I
want to do this reorganization so if I
just move the X's to the end for
starters that looks like this oops
so now we're packed X Y Z X X Y Z X X Y
Z X and when we come down through and we
do any of our extractions and shuffles
these might be slightly different now
right so the first thing we'll see is
when we do this shuffle for X and we're
trying to line things up what you can
see is we're doing one three that's for
the X Y those are the same so that's
fine and then we do the T 4 we're doing
Z Z and
you know doesn't really make a lot of
sense
[Music]
hmm so you know now that I'm kind of
looking at this I'm also wondering
myself did we even really need that in
the first place so like we could have
just shuffled the X into here and done
the X Z comparison the wrong way round
so I don't actually even know if we need
this padding so maybe what I would say
there is let's do this one change then
I'll try the actual active also just
leaving this Lane zero and switching the
order the comparison because it looks
like we could get away with that too
right so all right so if we change that
comparison order here is our mask table
and the mask table you can see every
time there's an X it has this channel in
it as well we would want to change that
so now what we would be doing is we'd
say look when we are doing X masking
what we're only talking about the first
lane similarly when we're doing Z
masking now we would be we would be
talking specifically about the third
lane so you know we look like that so Z
is third lane Y is first that sorry well
0 with Lane is x1 if Lane is is y insect
that second lane is Izzy so the last
thing we have to update is the best
table and the reason we have to update
the best table is because now the best
table would actually be 16 wide and so
the X less than Y would be the same the
Y less than Z would be the same and the
X less than Z is now not in this channel
so it's actually like a there's a
phantom channel here right
and sort of what we're saying is we
don't care what this channel is right
like we don't want to care and so you
know and this is an interim step like I
said we don't really want to actually do
this right but you know that's just
where we're at so if we continue the bit
pattern here you know that's what we
would get here and it's gonna be the
same in this case and then we would do
you know a duplicate here as well right
so you just say like okay it's gonna be
same and again I don't think we actually
want to do this right but I'm just
trying to do it one step at a time so
that we can validate sort of things in
the interim because it's fairly
complicated code right I don't really
want to have to do it blind so again
same thing so now when we look at length
the shuffle table so the shuffle table
in this case is doing the same lookup
that you would be doing here and again
you know it's it's gonna be a little
cumbersome at first but that's fine so
it is zero one zero and then the
difference here is two is not this like
that's picking the final lane but we
actually want to pick the middle lane so
this is an 8 9 10 11 like so and so
that's the zero and zero two we would
duplicate that much like we duplicated
it up here just because that middle bit
we don't want to care we're just not
going to look at it ever so we're just
gonna leave it out and then we get to
the second part which is 2 1 2 2 and
again same problem these twelves is not
we actually want so we just want to
replace those like so and then we're
just duplicating that twice and so you
can see this like expands our tables
quite extensively and that's why I think
we want to just stick with doing the 3
wide version because it just keeps
everything smaller but I just want to do
this one first alright so now let's
debug it as you would expect like it's
probably going to be busted
the mask table is wrong though I just
realized that we didn't we didn't finish
this there we go
all right let's try that one more time
and I probably want to go into debug
mode for this as well I might just let
these be Auto yeah I want to go to debug
mode because I want to be able to go
through it and see what's wrong and so
on so I want to kind of just do a quick
yeah there we go all right so now what I
want to do is I want to kind of see like
what's going wrong here you could see
that I think the tables are roughly
correct if it's 0 1 0 2 0 1 0 2 right 0
1 0 2 0 1 0 - 2 1 - 2 - 1 - 2 - 1 2 -
the math table is 0 1 0 2 so 0 1 0 2 0 1
0 2 &amp; 2 1 - 2 - wait that's wrong
where'd it go alright so well I was
thinking I had it right I don't
yeah bit twiddling it's always very
finicky alright let's try that one more
time so - 1 - 2 - 1 - 2 times the bottom
right and so now I can take a look at
what we're actually getting here in the
registers and see what's going wrong so
let's take a look at at what all these
actually are first so looking at the
values we know when we doing T 4 and T 4
s essentially T 4 is XY and Z and oh
well and that's wrong - so we have not
finished updating this routine this we
moved from lane 3 to lane 2 so that's
supposed to be 2
three just has X in it and we don't
actually want X anywhere on the bottom
that was not a thing we're actually
doing so I don't know what that was
there for again we might change that
eventually but again it wasn't very
great okay so let's try that one more
time so let's take a look at what T 4
equals because T 4 in this case like we
always want everything the X Y Z X and
you can see we initialize it that way X
Y Z X X Y Z X always at the top right so
now if we take a look at what these
actually equal I can start to just
validate whether or not any of this
stuff went correctly right so our T 4
and our t 4s they never get modified so
I can watch exactly what happened to
them and you can see here so we've got
our T 4 here's our x y&amp;z stepping values
so that's like you can see here that
we're supposed to be picking like the Z
step because it's the lowest I'm gonna
get some extra T here
all right
okay so what I was trying to say there
is if you look here these are the T
values we computed and now you can see
that we've got this Z value here and so
here we're trying to rearrange these so
that we have Y Z and then just Z right
and that's what we have Y Z and Z so
that shuffle appears to work properly we
have a min comp here which will show us
if we look at what the comparison is so
here's the min comp
you can see here that the this is trying
to say like what's greater right so in
this case nine is not greater than 27 1
is not greater than sorry 27 is greater
than 1 1 is not greater than 1.4 or
whatever and so this is the only channel
that we get as you know a positive right
so then we say okay let's move the comp
mask out so that's going to basically
take and it's going to look at the high
bits of each of these so what we expect
to see here is 0 1 0 0 from the LSB out
so that's just gonna be 2 right here
which is what we get and then we're
looking up into the best table here to
see what the best dimension is so let's
see let's make sure our best in this
correct cuz maybe this is wrong like so
yeah if we look at what we actually have
here that's just wrong so let me look at
what's going on in that
so what we basically saw right is we saw
just this one bit set right and so we
basically said if X rather than Y Y is
less than Z wait a second
right there bring me back there so we
basically got our comparisons we said
accident you know we're doing a greater
than so in this case X greater than Y is
what that's doing and X is not greater
than Y right so that would mean that X
is lower than Y so we want to then know
if X is greater than Z right and so X
greater than Z should also be false
right yeah so we should have been
keeping X because X is greater than Z am
I wrong about that so we should be
keeping X because X and that goes the
wrong way around too so we changed these
partway through these should be this way
right because I mean that's that's what
we're looking at we're looking at it
this way am I wrong about this not sure
why we wrote it that way
because that's that's what the
comparison is it's it's blank greater
than blank right so in this case we're
looking to see did X compare greater
than than Y so in this case X did not
compare greater than Y so we keep X
right y&amp;z we don't really care about
what that actually is
so in this case well I guess we're up
here in this case it was here but we
don't care about that so all we now need
to know is is X greater than C right and
the weird part here is it looks like we
never did that somehow like the t4 value
here like that's supposed to be X right
X X X so how is that value why is that
value 0 that's why so this table here if
we want to keep something in that Lane
we need that two masks to work all right
that's fair so basically we forgot to
replicate the X out here right I removed
it from this column but I forgot that it
in this column looks ok all right
and now we're good okay so that works
just fine but like I said I think it's a
little bit unnecessary and so what I'd
like to do is make one more change which
is just to not use that fourth lane
because it just creates larger tables
for no real reason and there's two ways
we can do that one is we can put the
shuffle in here and the other is we can
we can be a little bit more clever about
the way we do the comparison so that we
actually just do the X Z comparison the
other way round now normally you'd start
there but because we're comparing
against a routine that doesn't do this
that means we may have a switch there so
I'm gonna do the shuffle first and then
we'll switch although I don't actually
know that that helps I think about it
you know it really doesn't so maybe we
ignore that but anyway so if you take a
look what's going on here right what I'm
saying is we don't care what this value
is particularly much right it just
doesn't matter so what we can do there
is say look just leave that as zero so
we know that this will always just be
zeros in that final column because
everything in it will be zeros so just
leave it as zero so that we never get a
true comparison it's always it's always
a zero and then what we do here is say
look let's put X in there so that we
just do the X comparison the other way
round so at that point then you could
say well now we don't need to worry
about lane four or lane three I guess I
don't want to say that we don't need to
worry about that Lane we're just gonna
leave that lane out of it and then we
can just get rid of of any of this stuff
right so we don't then care about that
final Lane like so and then all our
tables can shrink again so at that point
we can then say all right we don't need
this extra duplicate 'iv version here we
can just shrink it
down to eight and the same thing would
go for basically all of our tables so we
don't need that and we don't need this
so now it's much more condensed and up
here we can do the same thing to where
we say all right we only need these but
we also now need to kind of reverse the
idea of what's happening here so if I
delete this part that's all well and
good but we now have a different meaning
for our final column so we don't like
this is not this anymore it's actually
that right so in every place that
previously we were picking an X we would
need to pick the Z value and in each
case where we were picking the Z value
we'd need to pick the X file because we
flipped the meaning right so if we take
a look at what happens here all of these
right are like is X greater than Y it's
not so we take X is y greater than Z we
don't care then is Z greater than X and
if it's if it's not right then we would
take Z but it is so we keep the X right
same thing here in this case if X is
greater than Y then we keep Y and if Y
is not greater than Z then we continue
to keep Y right and so we don't really
care about that in this case where we've
got the 0 here again X is greater than Y
it's not so we keep X we don't care
about this value and then we go here and
say zero might it is right and then
finally this last one here where we're
like X is greater than Y is true
so we would actually keep Y Y is greater
than Z so now we keep Z Z is greater
than X is not possible at that point
right so really we don't care what this
value is at that point because that
creates like an okay you can't really
have that comparison
you know what I'm saying so then if we
come up here and we say let's see what
these do so this is X is greater than Y
so it's not so to keep X we then say Z
is greater than X a it's not so we keep
Z right X is greater than Y it is so we
keep Y Y is greater than C it's not so
we keep Y X is greater than C it's not
so we keep X Z is greater than X it's
not so we keep Z X is greater than Y it
is so we keep Y Y is greater than Z it
is so we keep Z and again this is these
are not possible I don't think right so
in theory we should be able to use that
because you know although there's the
equals case will come out differently we
don't care which one we use in the
equals case right so we may not be able
to validate this against the old routine
but I can rewrite the o routine slightly
to be the same so we should be able to
make it work if I'm not missing a case
right but I don't know so we'll see ok
so this is a problem as well so actually
we need to take care of that so hold on
one second so we need to figure out ok
so one of the problems is like in of
DeRay for there so the inverted version
we use here I kind of need that to make
sure that that's and just going to be 0
all the time so I may do that a slightly
different way because I want that to
just be easy for me to read I don't I
don't want to be seeing crazy stuff
there I want that to be 0 just so I can
you know for my own just from just for a
simplicity for my own sake
all right so let's get started looking
with this so if we take a look at what
the comp mask is here we're in the exact
same state that we were before I don't
actually wait
so something's weird about that possibly
because of the way I was masking it or
saying so T values should never be
negative
so I screwed something up there that we
need to address which is what oh it's
very simple the mask table is different
now so it's 2 1 2 2 0 1 0 2 right so 2 2
2 so there's 2 1 2 2 &amp; 0 1 0 tube so 0 1
0 2 all right I was gonna say that's
just nonsense that we're seeing in there
so let's try that again it's still bad
did I mess it up twice unsurprisingly
these things are very finicky so so I
may not have messed this up but I may
have messed up the construction that's a
table right so this one here so I think
this aligns right you know cuz - 1 - 2 -
1 - 2 0 1 0 2 0 1 0 2 so the mass table
and the best table look correct to me oh
but the shuffle table we didn't do that
one yet Dubey so in that case that's 2 2
2 right and there's the 1 so 2 1 2 - and
then here we have 0 1 0 2 so 0
1:02 I don't know that that would have
done it though so I don't think we're
out of the woods yet on that I think
we've still got an issue here okay
that's a new one so I'm going to step to
this and see where that comes from but I
think these are all in line now right 2
1 2 2 0 1 0 2 so it's 2 1 2 2 0 1 0 2
yeah okay good deal so now I just want
to see what's you know what we're
actually doing here let's step through
this one at a time I just want to see
what's happening okay so there's our T
computations probably yeah well so we're
supposed to pick the we're supposed to
pick the second thing in the comp mask
which comes out to be 2 so that's
suggesting that Z is the best value
that's correct
so that part works fine so let's take a
look at what we actually select so that
did correctly select Z so that's good
and so our app for now just gets
advanced by that much like we can look
at that as well and then what we want to
do is we want to take the because we
went one self forward in that direction
we want to subtract out that dimension
which would be 1 by 4 so this should now
get zeroed and it does so that whole
thing looked good so I guess what I
would say is we probably have a bug in
one particular part of the table so
because that also it's all working right
now that all looked exactly correct so
unless I just spaced
that's right and so what I probably did
is when I was reading the stuff I
probably just made it a mistake right
and I can check it one more time just to
see if we can catch it by inspection but
otherwise what I'll do is I'll step
through til I see it right and then
we'll just fix it there so in this case
you know once we could write this is
this is X greater than Y so this is y
less than X is this case oops
right so Y is less than X Y is less than
Z I'm sorry X is less than Y y is less
than Z right and X is greater than X is
less than Z no sorry Z is less than X
right I mean I'm just you have to flip
these so these are 0 0 0 so they're
gonna flip each time right so I guess I
could do it this way this is Z less than
X y less than Z X less than Y right
because every time is this a 0 it flips
so if we take a look at that if Z is
less than X and Y is less than Z and X
is less than Y is that one of those
that's like I mean that's that triple
right so Z can't be less than X like
that's one of those ones it just doesn't
work
like one of those two things has to be
wrong you know I'm saying so I wonder if
you can ever actually get that case like
shouldn't that case not really be the
thing I mean I guess you could say well
it's it's less than or equal to right
because you don't it's not it's actually
fat right so in that case it could be
that they're just all equal would would
be I guess one way that could be true so
I think that's what that means
so we could literally pick like anything
you know and I mean like no matter what
we pick it's right so let's take a look
at this one so this one is X greater
than Y y less than or equal to Z Z less
than or equal to X right so in that case
I guess we would say if X is greater
than Y then we know that X is kind of
out of the question so we're really just
looking at these so if Y is less than or
equal to Z and Z is less than or equal
to X we're really just talking about
that and so it's that looks right you
know that's why that's right so that's
fine here we're talking about X less
than or equal to Y y greater than Z Cu
less than or equal to X right so here we
would say if X is looking to the y&amp;z so
that's that's this right so that's
clearly Z
here we would say X greater than Y y
greater than Z and that's just this
right so that would also be Z pretty
clearly
I mean Z greater than X is false
so that means it's that which is not
possible I want to say because how could
how could X be greater than Y which is
greater than Z but then suddenly Z is
less than or equal to X like even
equivalence doesn't do that in this case
I believe because they could all be
equal like this is this one you could
pick any this one should never occur
we should probably assert that ok here
we have s less or equal to Y Z less
sorry y less than or equal to Z and Z
greater than X right so again if we
Junction these we just get that and this
says that Z is greater than X which is
what you would expect
so that just seems like X and that's
fine here we have X greater than Y y
less than or equal to Z Z greater than X
right so in that case I believe you can
just Junction these two and just say
well it's Y at that point y less than or
equal to Z is also correct
so that just seems like Y and that's
exactly what we put in this case we have
X less than or equal to Y y greater than
Z Z greater than X so that's this again
s X less than or equal to Y is exactly
what we would expect so again that
should just be X and it is and then the
last one is everything's true so X is
greater than Y y is greater than Z Z is
greater than X right that's not possible
I want to say
oh wait no that's the right okay no
that's actually fine Z less than or
equal to X is low allowed here so that's
fine it's this one that is not allowed
because Z can't be great so it's just
this one I think it's not seem right so
I think that one that one is actually
bogus oops
yeah what's happening stop no bad okay
so I think this table is is correct I
don't know it seems right to me I don't
see what I don't see where that goes
wrong it's possible that when you hit
this one case so so this case here feels
like it would differ from the so you
know what I could do though
in the case where they're all equal I
dunno what the other routine would pick
so in the case where they're all equal
this routine would pick X so I should be
able to say that right
all right um so let's see like how long
does it take this thing to fail okay so
we don't we're gonna have to see let's
see which one it fails on so we can
debug like that one specifically because
we're obviously in a case where it's a
little bit more sensitive to exactly
what we're asking it to do before we get
a problem so which which one are we
talking about okay how many of these are
there Wow
so we made it all the way to like
basically the end and then we kind of
pooped out so well you know too bad
let's take a look cost so we took three
steps into number ten twelve and then we
poop we pooped out right and so what did
we poop out on like what did we do wrong
so let's take a look here so let's look
at key terminate results and degrade
results and verify you terminate verify
so we're producing the correct key
terminate value but instead of picking
and I guess you can see why that's
happening is we actually have two values
that are the same here and I guess we're
differentiating on them differently so
this one picked X and we picked Z so why
did we do that would be the first
question right so what you can see here
is if we look at the comparison that
we're doing we basically have two
equivalents and one actual
yes so we we aren't picking X when we
should have been if that makes sense and
it's specifically this case right so
let's go over this one more time so we
know in this case that X is less than or
equal to Y we know that Y is greater
than Z and we know that Z is less than
or equal to X right so again we kind of
know this oops
so in that case if Y is greater than
wait these are so confusing let me write
that one more time because that can't be
true X is less than a go to Y y is
greater than Z and Z is less than equal
to
oops Z is less than or equal to X this
is just a typing problem at this point
so Z less than or equal to X ok so this
is not a bug this is just a preference
problem we're picking one instead of the
other but it's totally fine right so I'm
going to actually call that fine because
we don't actually like like in this case
we're just picking a different one we're
picking we're picking two out of the
equivalent ones right and so we could
have written this differently to do that
and we wouldn't have had a problem there
right so that seems fine
like I don't care about that I'm not
sure how we continue the validation
process with that happening so that's a
little tricky because I'd like to keep
it with that validator but I guess what
we could do is say if two of the Val
we could look for exactly that one case
and use Z instead so like we could say
in here
something more like
maybe like this so we just say okay
compute the T this values right and then
we'll use them down here like so but I'm
in a special case this one kind because
we want to match up so I'm just going to
say look if T this zero equals T this
two so they're the same and T this zero
is all I'll do 2 is less than 2 this 1
then we're just going to pick it the way
we know the other routine will right and
again that's just for me so that I can
make my validation work because if
that's the only case that we differ on
and it doesn't matter which one you pick
I'd like to make sure we still validate
right so now I think we've done that
complete validation and now we're using
the tables like our shuffle table and
our best table now are smaller so I'm
just going to go ahead and call these
like T best table T shuffle table and T
mask table just so we know what they're
doing because we're about to loft them
up into another routine and I don't
really want there to be a lot of
confusion about that okay so I'm pretty
pleased with that because that doesn't
cost us anything at all and now we don't
have to have extra table space or extra
lanes involved so we can literally just
reuse the exact same variables that we
have in here and everything should be
fine so now I'm going to go ahead and
plop that in the way I was going to do
at the start and then we'll go from
there so here's our T values and then
here is our preamble stuff that we'll
work on in a second
for right now I just want this part and
again we're only focusing on validation
right now so all I'm gonna do is well
I'm literally gonna do this all I'm
gonna do is just take a look at whether
I can match what comes out of the table
because that's all I want right now so
if we take a look at what we've got here
we just end up with situations where
some of these things we already have
values forward some of them we don't so
let's take a look we know that R ad and
n'ver ad might very well exist because
of the sorts of things we would be doing
in this routine anyway
so taking a look you can see it looks
like we have rady packed but not in
fraidy packed just from looking at it
right so rady packed here is select
radio R like that we have that it's rady
packed but we don't have say m4 ad for
that doesn't exist so we can make it
pretty easy it's not a huge deal right
but it's just like we would want some
way of getting this easier right like I
guess I'll just do this for now and this
is not the way we want to do this at all
right like actually me about it this way
so I just want to make a note that all
of this stuff is kind of like there's
way too much crap at the beginning like
a lot of these things are the same and
can be simplified and collapsed down so
we'll be able to do much better work
here eventually but for right now I just
want to keep it exactly the same as much
as I can right okay
so if we take a look at what else we
need we need to have the app for and the
seldom for so seldom I don't think we
have anywhere like that's just something
that we effectively just want to copy
right cuz that doesn't that doesn't
actually occur anywhere in here I don't
think so that's something that we can
grab pretty easily like we can lemon
grab that no problem and it's constant
so it's something that it doesn't change
based on the Ray at all right it's
completely the same no matter what
you're doing so let's grab that
somewhere and where was the seldom from
so I guess that seldom compute compute
walk table
so the seldom just comes from the
spatial grid here so that's just like
this right so at that point I'm not sure
what we call this I think this is just
ready packed right so it's in ready
packed yeah so it's really just at four
and then we need the step and well we
just we just need the step at that point
right
tea terminated in this case is wide as
you can see so I would need to extract
that to compare but that's fine
so in this case t terminate we actually
update that so basically this this value
right here that's coming out of the walk
table the problem that we're gonna have
is we need our own t terminate here to
track so just for validation purposes
and then they would collapse but I want
to actually do that work because I again
really care about validating this
because it's just too finicky otherwise
so we're gonna have like a tracking T
terminate here so I'm going to do
something along the lines of like this
and then I'll just slip stream that
right on in there
there we go and here we can also do well
that's fine so the T terminate verify in
this case what I'm going to do there is
just say well whatever the t terminate
was before that's what we're going to
use and i guess i can actually just do
that here okay
so one of the other interesting things
about this is since we would now be
tracking the position as it goes I guess
like we don't even really need to
terminate anymore though actually so we
probably can just get rid of it I mean
like if you look I mean I guess the
reason we wanted is well I don't even
know I don't even know if we're gonna
need that I guess we'll see yeah I mean
so like if you look at what we do so
this is gonna be this will actually
optimize this even more because
previously when we when we early doubt
we needed to keep track of T terminate
for this purpose we don't even need to
keep track of T terminate anymore
because when you leave we can just make
probe P single be the step value that's
that's currently in at X so basically
this right that value is just the sample
position right so we don't I think need
to worry about that anymore I could be
wrong about that but it seems like it's
fine so so I don't know if we even will
need to track to terminate we may be
able to just remove it because at four
which is what we would be doing anyway
we'll just be what we want so if we take
a look at the starting location here
what we know right now is we're always
starting at the center if this will
change eventually but for the moment I
it's not it's not going to right so
let's see where we're at
yep I agree that is a syntax error okay
um so now we just need our actual step
values that we look up in and what you
could sort of see here is that's gonna
have to get built based on the Ray
anyway when we start now the thing we
may want to do is to just that may want
to be in a table because since we know
that the Rays are what the Rays are we
may or may not actually want this right
so when we look up our D grid results I
don't know if we actually want to spend
the time to make this thing I mean maybe
we do maybe we don't for now I'm going
to do it but I don't know that I want to
spend this cost every time we shift rays
because it's sort of a waste of
everyone's time so we may want to try
and optimize this step production by
just saying look we already know what it
is also the way it's being done here is
not particularly good so we may actually
just be able to fix that part too right
so who knows hard set so if we come
through here and say we're gonna do this
computation and what we're gonna do here
is the raid erection that we're using oh
I guess so this is interesting
so because we sort of finicky eyes this
I guess we kind of do want to keep these
like that if that makes sense because we
are sort of doing a little bit of an
extra dance there aren't we right like
we want the absolute value of these
things you know I'm saying so we kind of
want to say like
we want the absolute value of each of
these right now what I don't know
offhand is do we really need that I mean
it flips everything so I think we don't
want that but we could I don't know
that's that one's going to be another
thing we should probably look at
okay yes so in here we actually wants
abs rady pecs and abs convert a pact
right and in here this is where we are
producing those so we don't actually
care about modifying this so we can just
do this you can just say you know that's
the thing
now voxel DIMM is again something that I
think we just get out of the spatial
grid so voxel games getting passed in
here but it's it's really just this
right so now we kind of have an inline
validation running of this thing and
what we can do is start to look at it
and see if we can get it to behave
properly so we can take a look at a
couple things there first of all um just
double check that all this looks right
yeah so let's take a look at some of our
info here so in this case you know we're
just we're just picking two right as you
would expect and to terminate Oh so
that's supposed to happen after the fact
sorry yeah okay so let's take a look one
more time so here we now have some
slightly different stuff we're looking
at so we're looking here at D grid and D
grid salt totally wrong T terminate and
T terminate purify and in this case I
just want to look at the zero with so
those two were matching presumably just
because you know we haven't gone
anywhere yet it's just the first step
through and so when we are looking at
what our deltas would be that you know
makes sense if I if I look at what we're
doing here I mean it's pretty clear that
you want to step in Z though so like are
we initializing our values wrong maybe I
mean we must be two because this doesn't
really make much sense like I don't know
maybe it does let's see what the radius
angle is no yeah that does fair enough
so I may have played it too fast and
loose with this for all I know like
maybe what we were doing there was
important in some other way that I
didn't think about like maybe absolute
valuing those things is not what you
want to do
but I'm not sure why that would be the
case right because in these you know
that the inverse version is going to be
that let me just double check that of
the routine so let me see what it does
so you can see that all this is doing is
just flipping the sign so it's just
guaranteeing that it's always positive
and then it just sets the step to be
negative if it was going in the negative
direction so I really don't see why that
would cause a problem
yep I don't know so the hell that all
looks fine I'm not seeing I'm not seeing
it
so in here we just yeah we don't do any
preconditioning to that do we we just we
set the starting location as you would
expect and that's just what gets loaded
right so there's nothing weird happening
there yeah I don't know I might step
through that real quick just to see if I
can understand what's where we're going
wrong there so when we enter that we set
up the tables here the cell dimensions
are exactly what you would expect let me
take a look at what happens when we get
in here so this is this ray goes
this ray goes yeah like 126 negative 468
which is right right I mean there's
nothing weird about that so I don't
quite get it that all seemed fine
so that all seems fine to make sure I
should probably do this shorthand so
it's easier to see so that also seems
right just failing to see the bug here
so law looks pretty good so far
starting at half a seldom which is just
the middle of the cell right seems
reasonable
again just does not seem particularly
weird so I don't know and let's take a
look at what the walk table says so the
walk table wanted to take an X step for
this ray right I mean we're XYZ right
the Z's is major isn't it I mean am I
just like totally missed remembering how
we did the voxel somehow
I mean right so how on earth can that
ray which is definitely taking Z steps
and only Z steps how on earth could that
possibly want to take an X step ever
like I mean it's zero
how is it going to move in X am I
missing something I mean yes is the
answer apparently
what the heck dude I mean this just
looks like our walk table stuff is wrong
but how is the walk table stuff wrong
like how did that get screwed up so
confused dude so confused
can you please show me something here so
let me run this in here I just want to
see if it's the same thing what the heck
dude look this just seems like garbage
I'm so confused about what's going on
here right cuz the wok table like what
was the starting index for the wok table
first four just lets tell me that right
because I'm so confused right now so
here's our initial grid index and here's
our grid index so we only went like one
forward right and so I don't actually
know how long the wok table is but I'm
curious to know so let's see so here's
the light sampling wok table actually
let's see how long it is let's see
so here we are computing the log table
and let's just see what that value
actually is so I mean the walk table is
huge man so all of those should be right
how are we getting imps
ittan in here exactly like like did I
mess this up somehow
I mean hourly see I don't really see how
that happened so let's do some other
things I want to take a look at when
we're assigning these right and I want
to see like what hour to terminate
values are
top ten things you can't do with Visual
Studio like this just doesn't you can't
do anything like this individual studio
right stepping speed is fine I don't
understand it's it's ooh what it takes
to half a second to step what would you
need more it was like this this is what
you need it for so this is just totally
like something's super bogus here did I
accidentally like overwrite part of this
table or something like what is going on
because you can see me writing here like
imps are not getting written to this
table you know I'm saying so like I
screwed something up and I don't
actually know like what I screwed up but
something got borked when and and you
know I probably should just look at the
solution walk table let me let me run it
that again to the crash point
well the validation fail let me just
take a look at what the walk table is at
right now so if I look at solution so
like if I just want to know which index
this was supposedly right I'm gonna go
ahead and say no to that
[Music]
how what on earth oh I've got it
backwards I'm like what there we go so
actually I'm way high here but what the
so is that the end of the walk table
then
so confused I'm just like truly baffled
by what's going on so it looks like we
actually were much higher than that
probably because when we access the walk
table I don't I don't really know all
right so let's take a look let's set a
breakpoint in here and walk through this
from start to finish so I understand
what the heck is happening because I
have an absolute an idea um so if I take
a look at where this is actually
breaking and we take a look here at
loading out of the walk table whatever
the sample directions walk table offset
is here so let me just like grab that
and see what it actually it says right
so that says 69 12 right so this is cool
I mean unless I'm just totally
misinterpreting what we're seeing here
from 69 112 we're now saying that
somehow the walk table - the solution
right so is like well that that's an
actual reasonable number so what how
were we getting that other number before
what was happening there totally don't
understand that like that was - that was
bizarre right so there's one
there's two so it looks like here's one
I know like that's obviously in bounds
right and yet there's the T terminate
int I just don't understand so if I look
at the light sampling table here like
it's not in right that I accidentally up
like increment the walk table twice or
something I just don't I just understand
so let's see so supposedly like this is
69 13 right so I guess if if I look
there I should see it right sampling
walk table 913 so it's that right and it
what happens if I look at the previous
one it's zero
so I guess one thing I could do is see
where that's written so I know which
index it is it's 69 13 so let's take a
look at 69 13 I guess I mean we can just
put a FRU FRU in there right and just
stop on the frou frou and then we'll get
to see it right in for some reason I
mean that's what it should do right I
could do this in hhhh light prophesy
want to but so there's my frou frou
right and so what we're saying here is T
terminate is in right so the question is
how did it get to be int and if I take a
look at yeah to this so everything is
garbage right so influence was fine but
the question is how how you know how did
you get it how did you get to do that
and remember this is not the optimizer
this is just a regular routine so what's
the Ray D that that let you do that
right so okay so we've got a Z here and
somehow and I have no idea how like did
I screw this up somehow like somehow the
T this values for that I mean how did
that ever be the case I don't understand
I mean how did you get in by multiplying
by one I'm I'm at a loss for someone to
tell me how you managed that right so
I'm assuming what you must have done is
in a previous round
somehow you picked infinity as your best
guess right so you you basically you you
picked a garbage value here right so at
one point me because of this right maybe
I've got that wrong
okay so the best image was the dim index
that were on
yes I just don't quite see it let's take
a look at if it only happens during
these cases I'm kind of curious to know
I should probably go to a judge light
prophetess there's no reason for running
the like game so we're not even going
through these cases we're going through
these cases right and because we haven't
even hit this we haven't hit this yet we
were doing this and we haven't even hit
this yet so I really don't know where
that's coming from so I guess what I'll
do is I'll say well alright so if
frou-frou happened here I'm gonna try
I'm going to try going back one so that
I can watch this roll through here
hopefully just slightly before things go
pear-shaped you know I'm saying so I can
watch them go pear-shaped
so let's see here we are we still have
reasonable values so we can now I think
hopefully watch what happens so here's
our tea this values for the next step
we've got negative imps here for some
reason
which I'm not sure why I guess because
these are negative but why are those
negative
someone want to tell me why those are
negative so I guess the reason those are
negative so that's kind of that's kind
of weird
so the reason those are negative is
because these are negative zeros but
really we wanted to abs this so really I
think this was just a bug in the
original that we just didn't know about
right because really what you want here
is to say look we need to negate this in
the case of knives but in either case
this just wants to be absolute value
because those negative zeros are causing
us a lot of problems and I think they
were just wrong in this routine and when
we got rid of we did the absolute value
part of things there I think that would
have fixed that right so here we just
want to do this right so now those two
routines are doing the absolute value
bit and I think that's more what we want
so let me just see if that helps us at
all because it seems like we would want
that right all right so let's see what
happens here - Artie this okay now it's
doing what I want right so like now we
shouldn't get into this disaster zone of
like at getting corrupted by garbage
yeah so everyone's fine now okay good so
now let's see what happens in the main
routine do we get errors there no okay
so that was actually just a bug in our
original routine right so that was just
a screw-up but everything else validated
so now we know that like the stepper is
now validating so I should be able to
now yank the original version of the
code and see what happens like this is
now running without any validation
problems in the actual lighting right
that was an interesting one so when we
go through this piece of code now I
should be able to just say alright so
this piece here where we do the D grid
values and the cost metric still wants
to do the same thing it was doing before
but now I believe this stuff here I
think we can just sort of do an if zero
around it right so I think we can do
this and I think we can do a t terminate
equals to terminate verify and a grid
index plus D grid results and can nerf
this and I think that gives you what you
need because now that's just using
values we know we're exactly the same
what we know to terminate verify and to
terminate we're equal
and the D grid was right so now we are
doing the stepping in the routine proper
it's not the optimal way to do it
because we've got a lot of extra craft
in there for no real reason that we
should be able to get rid of right but I
can now I think go take a look and just
see like how far away we are on speed
for having made that change so now we're
not doing table driving and we can see
how fast we are right so that's pretty
brutal like that's like way way slower
you know I'm saying like way slower and
so the question is is it way slower
because of something that we can fix or
is that just like no not gonna happen
because if it's really that much slower
we'd be in a ton of trouble like there's
no way we're gonna be able to deal with
that so I also would wonder like is it
if I do this
I'm just wondering so it looks like it's
literally just the fact that we are
doing these computations and here is
enough to make it cost too much right so
yeah like I don't know what we do about
that
because we're not really doing very much
you know and I'm saying and I guess one
question though is I guess that doesn't
really prove that this necessarily like
this part here is the culprit either
because when we remove this part we also
remove all of this stuff because if no
one accesses it right then you're not
going to have to put that code in there
so I guess I don't really know like you
know I'm saying like I don't actually
have I don't have a solid feel for like
to what extent the setup is expensive
so yeah one thing I can do is invade e
already is here so maybe I'll also just
do maybe I'll try to do something a
little more clever here so these divides
aren't there I don't know I I don't
think that's really going to be much but
it could I mean it's really hard to say
sometimes what that would actually look
like but
so one problem that we would have to is
that in this case the infrared deep act
we kind of want to zero out that Lane as
well and so that wouldn't actually be
good because I don't know what zero over
zero or one over zero is gonna come out
to but it's not going to be zero right
it's gonna be like undefined or
something or you know NAND and we would
probably rather not be manning around so
that's hard to say but you know I don't
remember what we did for that in the
faster team did we just set that one
yeah we did right but yeah so this is
this is bad and like I said I'm not
really sure what to do about this so we
have two choices one we can back off
this avenue of optimization and wait
that must mean I still have the yeah
when we can back off this avenue of
optimization and say look that's just
not going to cut it I mean it would be
nice if it did but it's not going to the
other is we can try to see if we can
optimize that stepping to not be so bad
right and I really don't know like I
said I really don't know how much that's
costing so another thing that I might
want to look at is like suppose we
actually did one again where we sort of
do an if one on this and an if one on
this right so we keep both of these
pieces of code in there with the
validator I'm just curious to what
extent is
is it just the dependency on that oops
that's bad I guess this doesn't validate
right now for some reason
[Music]
what did I do there that breaks that
because we just were validating moments
ago right is our abs in view ready
packed wrong now or something
would I do
show me where the problem is so what did
what happened because we were fine and
then I I poked it and we weren't fine
and I would like to know why so here we
are with what the walk table well
actually I guess it's not that anymore
but here's what our Oh
I mean that I suppose that I suppose
could could do it let me see
so is it just that I'm doing this in the
wrong order now so if we look at how
this gets initialized right like so
we're taking T terminate from the walk
table here here where we produce to
terminate verify I'm wondering if that
part is just the part that's busted
right to terminate verify so they're
both 0 in this case it loads the one
from the walk table which is whatever it
is here you would validate them before
adding and so this part let me just
there we go
nope I'm wrong so how did I bust that
what did I do wrong there like
something's weird
[Music]
is this not getting initialized somehow
or what's going on so these are both
starting out at zero we load from the
walk table what the new T terminate is
here and we use the D grid value and all
that nonsense right oh right
okay so we're still validating properly
now so that was just a slight false
alarm there um so yeah so I don't know
what to do I think this is a good place
to stop because I'm gonna need to think
about this or ruminate on this so like
over the course of the week I'll have
thoughts about it because I really do
need the grid squares to get bigger but
the question is maybe I need to do
something else to make that happen and
we still need to be able to load out of
tables right because just the speed hit
there is just really really bad and
again I don't know if something else is
we can inspect it a little bit more
carefully later but it's definitely like
that's just a really really unacceptably
large jump right and so I don't actually
know what's so horrible about it exactly
but and you know I could take a look to
it what the code looks like
this is a little annoying because it
looks like this is since this is um
since this is multi-threaded it's a
little bit harder to like watch it go
through what exactly is so here's the
move mask so that's here right and
here's the comp PS so that's here
there's the shuffle
there's the mall and I don't really know
what all this is though so like I'm
assuming some of this stuff got slip
streamed in here like maybe that's like
loop counter stuff so Dec add add add is
that just maybe for maybe for this
it's weird yeah don't know anyway
there's the move mask here's us doing
something I'm not sure why we would I'm
not sure why we would be doing this
exactly that's trying to load off the
table I guess and then we've got the pea
chef B and that yeah there's the moles
that part I mean is not part of the
optimized code so yeah I don't know I'll
have to look at this a little more
carefully we'll go to a brief Q&amp;A and
then we'll save it for tomorrow
I think the first entry of the tea
shuffle and tea masts tables haven't
changed 2x oh you are you are probably
correct thanks for that catch because we
just we just changed that that's
probably never happening because the
validation doesn't fail but you know
it'll happen someday
or maybe it won't you know I set a
breakpoint on that one before and it
never hit so that's probably why this
didn't cause a validation fail because
like we know that it never actually gets
there right but yeah like this should be
consistent that should look like this
right so X X both both times
all right
so that's what that should have looked
like
all right
could be going out of the cache if that
made it slow I mean no I mean we added
like if you look at the size of the
tables we added so the tables we added
here are two cache lines like one cache
line and we're talking about like three
cache lines or something right so I mean
there are weird things that could happen
we're like if you've got some weird
aliasing scenario by just putting a
table in and it just like creates this
weird you know that could happen but
just the cache is 32 K right so you
can't add like you know 512 bytes and
suddenly make the entire thing that work
it doesn't really work that way you'd
see you could use a little bit more
cache and see a slight degradation but
unless you hit a weird aliasing pattern
or something you know that's it's really
not realistic
I don't think it's not it's not a
concern I would have until we eliminated
like everything else as concerns if that
makes sense
think I'm out of tea yes I am plus the
other reason not to suspect that is that
when you turn off reading the walk cable
that means the walk table isn't taking
up any cash and the walk tables way
bigger than these tables so if anything
we probably saved cash space here but
the problem is just too many
computations probably you know too many
dependent computations so but yeah
we'll take a look at it next week we'll
see what happens all right I'm gonna
wrap it up
thank you very for joining me for those
sort of handmade here at Summa pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow the series at home you
can always go to handmade here org and
prayer to the game it comes the source
code so that you can follow along with
it at home and maybe you can go see what
you think about you know you can you can
sort of see like hey can you figure out
why that code got so much slower is it
just dependency chains you know we've
looked at a bunch of ways to analyze it
you can load up in vtune we've got a lot
of things we could do so it's probably
the kind of thing that that you could
have fun with this week if you wanted to
sort of learn more about optimization
and tracking things down you should be
able to figure it out right I'll be back
here next week to take a closer look at
it until then have fun partnering
everyone I'll see you in the Internet
take is everybody