hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream we are back today to try and play
around a little bit with something that
we're just we're basically just trying
to solve a last little graphics puzzler
and this puzzler comes about because I
don't really know that anyone does 2-d
game rendering the way that we're doing
it and that's because I kind of just
sort of stumbled on to a way of doing it
that was not necessarily something I'd
ever heard about before at all I you
know people do a lot of stuff in the 3d
world for how they do rendering of
transparency order independent
transparency but for 2d art it's not
really something that's commonly looked
into all that much because you know the
state of the art is always in 3d these
days you know 3d graphics is where all
the graphics folks spend their time and
so you know I don't know that many
people sit around thinking anymore how
do i render a sprite game because it's
just not you know it's not what they see
is the cutting edge for obvious reason
but what we were doing it real like hey
what if we use depth feeling to do order
independent transparency here instead of
using atomic framebuffer rights and it
worked pretty pretty well and so it's
kind of an interesting way to go and it
sort of seems like the kind of thing we
might want to do our rasterizer
and our renderer works really great with
this now and has order independent
transparency which is really nice and
does not require Tomic frame buffer
rights to do it so it can run on older
stuff as well but we do have one problem
which is that we can't turn on multi
sampling because we don't really have
any way of making the depth feeling that
we're doing work with multi sampling I
and so that's why I say like yeah I'm
not really sure what the obvious you
know there is an obvious solution to
that problem because I haven't heard of
people doing 2d games it sways so I
don't know
if someone has done a 2-d game this way
in the past I was unaware of it and so I
don't know what you know solutions they
may have already come up with for this
unfortunately in that way I'm not sure
what we would even search for her to
determine if someone had ever published
information about doing a game this way
and furthermore if someone has in the
game this way there's no guarantee they
actually published it how do you think
about it in the first place right a lot
of times you know people come up with
clever ideas and clever tricks they
don't necessarily write about them so
there may have been several games that
did things this way and then they just
never told anyone right or it just
didn't bother because they had other
things to do with their time so that's
the problem we don't really know I and
you know if like I said 3d graphics
really high-end 3d graphics where you're
like hey yeah you know if you want to
run you know battlefields one or or doom
or something then you have to have you
know the super beefy graphics card and
we're doing all kinds of crazy stuff
under the hood so you know they're
they're so far beyond what we're doing
in handmade hero in terms of
requirements or complexity you know this
problem is not a problem they would
probably ever care about it think about
would be my guess it's like you know
they're sixteen crazy trek new
techniques pass this level of complexity
already anyway and so they probably have
a lot more stuff to do or they always
have to baby do prefer tommix to solve
it or they do some other crazy stuff you
know who knows what they do but that's
the situation so what I want to try and
think about today is just is there some
cheap and easy solution to being able to
turn on multisample anti-aliasing if it
exists reasonably on the card in
question on the target platform we
detect it's there if we want to allow
the turning that on so that like edges
of our cubes and stuff will be nice and
clean
the question is just is that something
that currently existed for isn't it now
ironically very ironically there
actually is a old-school technique that
would have worked here but I'm pretty
sure it got removed from graphics card
support entirely and that was there used
to be a way to anti-alias the edges of
things automatically so let me show you
what that was here we go nope it's not
it
here it is so in fact that I might be
able to get a better version of it here
I so what you can see here is in the old
days there was a thing here where you
could say Oh polygon smooth hint which
is indicates the sampling quality of
anti-alias polygon hinting GL nicest can
result in more pixel fragments being
generated during risk rasterization if a
larger filter function is applied right
and that hint used to not refer to a
multi sampling it used to refer to
actually just anti-aliasing let me see
if I can get that see here see if I can
get documentation to talk about that a
little quick there in here
[Applause]
you have to do like maybe this one
so I guess I don't know if I can find
some documentation that actually talks
about it specifically I maybe I guess
I'll give you the rough idea back before
multi sampling was even thing if you
turned on the polygon smooth hints it
would actually just generate at the
edges of polygons it would generate out
anti-aliased pixels to smooth out the
line right so that is actually what we
would want here meaning what we would
want to do is we would want to say app
on the outer edges of our primitive you
know not the interior one for every for
every polygon we want it to just produce
anti-alias pixels if it would do that
for us we would be done that would be
all we would need because then we could
avoid multi sample anti-aliasing
altogether because all we need is just
for those lines themselves to have the
anti-aliasing on them that's all we
really need and there used to be a way
to specify that exactly which is this
which is the edge flag and what it was
was when you output a primitive like a
cube you could specify which edges were
on the outside of the cube versus which
edges were on the inside the cube so for
example you've got one edge that runs
down the middle of you know of every
face of the cube the diagonal line that
just pulls those two triangles together
into a square shape for the cube right
and what you would do is you set the
edge flag on those to be so that the
outside edges have a different edge
Flags on the inside edge and then when
it was going to do smoothing it would
only do
the smoothing on the edges that have the
edge flags set right so there used to be
a thing in in open Jill in graphics that
would do what we wanted here but we
don't have the option of using it
anymore unfortunately
because I believe at least unless I'm
really very much mistaken I believe what
happened was when they changed over to a
multi sampling approach in open jail as
the standard way to do anti-aliasing for
obvious reasons right it works better
when primitives abut each other and and
all these are the sorts of things it
went away so as far as I know that you
know that's not available anymore um so
yeah I don't really know of any way to
to get that behavior back but I think
that is what we would want and that's
why I mentioned conservative
rasterization yesterday because I was
like that's kind of all we really want
here is just conservative rasterization
for all of our primitives and then we
want to set those yet those those
partially covered pixels based on on the
coverage so I don't know I you know
maybe we should try turning it on and
see what it does maybe I should look at
the spec and see what it does because
maybe it still does do what we want to
do I really don't know if that's not I
want OpenGL specification
I mean we can certainly take a look here
polygon smooth so let's see
certain aspects of jail behavior when
there is room for variation is
controlled with hints all right
polygon sampling quality so it doesn't
really say here it just says polygon
sampling quality and polygon sampling
quality doesn't really tell us much I to
be completely honest great that is not a
particularly I wonder why polygon smooth
is believed to be on page one somewhere
like where do you see polygon smooth on
there is it in the PostScript hidden
somewhere we just can't see so I really
don't know since there's no
specification I really don't know what
that's going to do now I guess you know
since we're in a brave new world here I
guess one thing we could do is just see
what happens when we turn it on I don't
think that's a very good idea because we
have no idea what we'll do on different
graphics cards at all I mean now created
that ordinarily the case probably one
could say you never have any idea what's
going on on a graphics card you haven't
tested on anyway because they're always
all random and broken driver-wise but I
mean it guess for just in terms of our
own edification I suppose maybe it's
worth just saying hey let's just see
what happens when we turn it on on this
card let's just gain some insight right
so what I'm going to do here is I'm
going to turn multi sampling off because
we you know that's sort of like the next
step in terms of if we're going to try
and write our own result shader that
somehow will pick depth values that'll
work properly in the def billing process
then we can definitely do that
but for right now we're going to avoid
that so let's take a look at multi
sampling and put it to 12 so it's
already false
okay so if I run the program then we
should get just our standard situation
which we do and so I'm going to try
turning on the polygon smooth hand and
again I have no idea what that's going
to do because I you know you just saw me
look at the spec and the spec literally
says nothing it's just like what does
this do we don't know we don't know and
now neither do you so what we're going
to do is we're going to call GL hint all
right and we're going to say GL nicest
oops you can see here that the hint I
specified is the target in the mode so
we want nicest which is the most you
know would be the most smoothest
whatever and then we want GL polygon
smooth hint
well I'll type it in myself if the
browser does not want me to actually
select it so now if I run this
presumably nothing will happen I don't
know yeah I mean I don't see any
difference there it doesn't look like
it's producing any output values around
edges for all I could to serve those
just look exactly the same to me so I'm
pretty sure it's not doing anything with
that with that hint but I don't really
know now granted I guess one thing that
is true is that in the old days in order
to get that a polygon smooth hint to
work though you had to turn on GL blend
you know of course I don't want GL blend
but I guess I could just check real
quick this won't work properly when I do
this but just for the sake of seeing
whether those it's ever doing anything
there
I still don't see any any evidence that
anyone was producing any kind of alpha
all right so yeah I didn't have any real
hopes that that was going to help us at
all
and hey not surprising we have good so I
guess what we want to do now is say okay
all right let me go ahead and put the
multi sampling back on and if I remember
correctly right now what we should okay
I don't even think this would be working
at the moment but I guess it is uh what
is going on very slow frame rate are we
actually calling the we're not actually
calling the new result so that's just if
we are doing the frame buffer resolve
here so that's just the cost of doing
this I guess or the cost of having so
much multi sampling happening one or the
other
all right so
I'm not sure why that multisample
resolve takes as long as it does now I
guess I mean one thing we could say here
is that well you know the multi sampling
it should be eight times slower in
certain circumstances right but you know
since it's multi sample interesting it
should only be eight times slower at
edges of things
it should not be eight times slower
anytime we're just filling something
solid that's entirely covered so unless
this graphics card is really stupid
which again it's a very old graphics
card so maybe it actually is that's not
a unless that should be taken lightly
because it's again very old
none of our stuff that we're doing here
as far as I know anyway would ever cause
the graphics card to evaluate all pixels
in a sample all samples in a pixel
automatically I don't think anyway
now I could be wrong about that but that
was just what I thought anyway
um and I suppose there's really no way
for us to really determine that at this
point because you know normally the way
you would check that is you can actually
get debug information about your
like you know on modern if you're using
like n sight or something like this you
can actually ask there's usually a way
to find out will this thing be evaluated
per sample or not like will it will it
be an efficient shader for multi sample
Accor won't it be but we normally have
the ability to ask that I don't think on
this configuration it could be wrong
about that but I don't think the can
so yeah so right now since we're running
so slow now you know what I could do and
this is probably what we should do now I
think about it if I could set our
resolution down and that would let us
run into higher framerate temporarily
right let me set us at a low resolution
and by running the really low resolution
that would alleviate that problem if
that was the problem it does look like
that was part of the problem anyway
right
so it may just be that it was too much
memory for the rest or to deal with or
something like this because you can see
that if by just setting the resolution
down a bit we were in totally fine shape
all of a sudden so yeah if you look at
what's going on here you can kind of see
a tons of artifacts related to exactly
the problem that I'm talking about in
terms of turning on multi sampling so
let's take a look here I don't know if I
can turn can I turn multi sampling on
and off yeah so here is us without
running multi sampling and what you can
notice is that you know all of this
stuff can I let me let me see if I can
zoom in a little bit here so here's us
without multi sampling and you can see
like these edges are really hard and
everything right and if I turn on multi
sampling you can notice that those edges
smooth out really nicely so you can see
how multi sampling really helps us
they're a lot like we would like to have
the ability to turn that on you know I'm
saying but we end up with those
artifacts like I'm talking about and
those artifacts are coming from that
failure to pick the Z value in a
sensible way right at least I assume
that's what they're coming from meaning
that when we get to the edges of things
we end up in this problem where because
it's the edge of a primitive we you know
we end up taking multiple samples there
and when we take multiple samples there
we don't necessarily pick the right
depth value for death-dealing and
instead of peeling the next value down
we know we spend all of our depth peels
on the same you know triangle
essentially just picking successively
lower Z values of that same triangle as
it passes through the pixel at multiple
samples right so yeah that is the
problem that we have I also don't know
there's something else they also don't
know so if you have alpha discard on
which we do right we discard alpha
values that are zero does the multi
sample multi sample discard alpha if I
have multi sampling on does the discard
create a place where things will get
sampled more and I'm just curious
- today
so this is the question I'm talking
about I don't necessarily trust this
page I would trust the specification
more but this is sort of what I'm
talking about
basically what I want to know is if I
have a pixel whose alpha discard you
know triggers so the alpha value of the
pixel is zero so it triggers an alpha
discard does the graphics card then try
all the samples individually to see if
they would all have discarded or
actually sated ultimately before you
know when it evaluates this card does it
evaluate discard based on all 16
potentially at any time or is it always
going to do the 16 samples only in the
case where it thinks that the edge of a
primitive passes through it and I don't
know but I so anyway so that's the
problem that we're dealing with right
now
is that that artifact problem basically
because as you can see and I guess this
sort of gives us some information in
terms of whether this technique works
well or not is that yet you know if I
just look at the quality difference in
the game you know as I move around I
really feel like that multi sample
anti-aliasing is doing a really good job
you know making the game look better I
think it's doing its job of fussing up
those edges just you know it's not
making anything else look any more
blurry it's just luring those edges and
that's exactly what I want so I do think
it's worth pursuing a little bit more
because it does make the game look
better I don't know whether in the final
analysis it will but you know I do feel
like it will because although in the
outer you know in the outside areas so
areas that actually will look more like
this in the game will be stamping a lot
of ground cover
and stuff onto onto things probably I
guess what I would say is in the
interior areas it's highly likely that
there will be rooms that look more or
less exactly like this there'll be a
texture map on the cubes for like making
it look like a tile like a tiled you
know stone floor or something but it'll
still have this sort of look this is
what i roughly wanted and so i do think
that you would see these line effects
maybe not in a stationary version as
much but as it moves that sparkle that
you get from the ante you know from the
those hard edges so i feel like turning
that on i feel like you get a much nicer
much nicer effect almost everywhere all
the time and so it's really just a case
of could we fix those artifacts because
if we can fix those artifacts I think
it's a definite yes and we would just
want to turn that on on any card that
that we thought could do it which would
probably be most of them given how old
this card is any modern card can do
multisample antialiasing i would think
just fine
so yeah this is you know also I suppose
the case where it would be nice to be
able to drill down to a pixel and see
what was going on there being able to
like click on you know that and see
which you know you could do if you had a
graphics graphics tool but yeah it seems
pretty clear to me what's going on like
you know I feel like I can fairly
confidently say that that's just a
question of of depth picking being a
problem and it's something you know it's
something where the def peel is not
picking a V value that allows it to ever
get down to the actual to the actual
thing it's peeling off I think I guess
one thing we could do is try to draw
something that was clearer that way like
in order to figure out what the bug
actually was there we could try
something where we draw like you know
solid colors that see you know what they
what results they produce
Jonica any ways that we could easily
determine what was going on at these
pixels because I'm assuming that those
pixels are because the tree has that
shadow and it's where the shadow
overlaps the edge of the cube going
downward right
you
so I'm assuming that the reason that we
don't see any artifacts on the flat face
of the cube right is because the cube
itself always have a constant V value
right so you've got one thing drawing
the top of another thing neither of them
have primitive edges happening at this
point and so neither of them are
producing Z values that need to get
peeled away however when you get out to
here I'm guessing that's the edge the
primitive edge of the of the tree so
multi sampling would be enabled although
that's does alpha value maybe the Alpha
value isn't quite zero there for the
tree I guess that's one thing that could
check we could Jack all alpha values to
50% let's let's see if that's true
so what I'm going to do here it's just
going to go in and say well okay I can't
quite see because the Alpha values are
very subtle
let's try jackin those alpha values up
so we can see them so what I'm going to
do here is I'm going to say okay you
know if the mod color a is over the
Alpha threshold we're going to draw it
otherwise going to discard it when we
actually go to draw it I'm going to say
the mod color a equals 0.5 right so this
way you know we'll get anywhere that
there was any alpha at all
we'll always see something clear and so
that at least validates my hypothesis
that that's what that is
so back basically the edge of the tree
shadow and I'm assuming that's the
primitive edge of the try of the of the
sprite as well we can also I suppose Val
validate that assumption
and by forcing everybody to have alpha
all the time and yet you can see that's
the edge of the primitive as well so
that's what's happening there
which is good at least I'm not you know
at least I can validate that I'm not
completely out to lunch in terms of what
that might be so that's what's going on
that's the edge of this triangle that's
being used to draw the tree well the
bottom triangle is being used to draw
the tree and there is an alpha value
there at the if it's just subtle it's
low but it's there and so that's why
it's drawing it in and that's where
those artifacts are coming from is that
that process so what I assume is
happening is because the tree is getting
different Z values at those samples
obviously because of our our Z shader
right because remember our Z shader is
it's our z vias is going to give the
tree multiple samples there because of
that
so so riddle me this Batman and by
Batman I mean the viewing audience if
that's our only artifact which I don't
know that it is but it sure looks like
it is because the only place I'm seeing
those artifacts is at the edges of these
things then then actually maybe we don't
have a problem at all because if we were
to just always include the 1 pixel
transparent border then we would know
that the edges of our primitives would
never generate multi samples right
furthermore we could just turn off multi
sampling if you're drawing like we could
just make multi sampling be off for
anybody who has a Z bias shader like if
we have the Z by a shader if we
indicated to the graphics card and I
don't know if you can do this in OpenGL
3 our GL sells 1.5 or whatever if we
told the graphic card only to evaluate
this value at the centroid because right
because remember we don't care if I
could we not we don't care we actively
don't want Z buffer multi sampling right
in a sense we want the Z buffer to not
be multi sampled we just want the color
buffer to be multi sampled right so I
wonder if what we could do here is just
say okay don't evaluate multiple samples
for the Z just always evaluate the Z at
the centroid
and write the same z-value - all samples
please
do you think it's possible do you think
we can do it because I feel like that
would do it
what kind of qualifiers do we have here
show me centroid please ah let's see the
centroid based interpolation can you
give us a little more information about
that
the presence of and type of
interpolation is controlled by the
storage cloth fart center it in and
center it out and by the optional
interpolation cloth smooth and flat love
of a variable cloth as flat will not be
interpolated instead it will have the
same value for every fragment within a
triangle this value will come from a
single provoking vertex as described by
the OpenGL ES graphic system Association
bla bla bla these are from the vertex
shader this rush to help us but if
single sampling the value is
interpolated to the pixel center and the
centroid qualifier present is ignored
if multi sampling in the variables not
qualify the centroid then the value must
be interpolated to the pixel center or
anywhere within the pixel or to one of
the pixel samples if multi sampling and
the variable is qualified with centroid
then the value must be interpolated to a
point that lies in both the pixel and in
the primitive being rendered or to one
of the pixel samples that falls within
the primitive due to the less regular
piece of center editors may be less
accurate then non centroid interpolated
values that might be good enough for our
purposes
hmm so let's see let's actually take a
look at what our vertex shader is doing
so here's the Z biased vertex shader
right and what you can see here is we've
got our we've got our you know position
value coming out here and what I'm
wondering is like okay so when we come
through here and we take a look at our
fragrance e we're using GL frag cord z
so what I'm wondering is what if I just
pass the Z coordinate in a different
value and I mark that value as being
centroid in right so in other words if I
said centroid in s32
use frags V or whatever or something
like that and then I said well you know
the frag Z instead of getting it out of
GL fried chords of Z you know it's just
going to be that right now of course if
I'm do it that way I've also got to
write the frag cord Z I think
because I don't know I don't know that
there's any way that I can
I don't know that there's any way that I
can tell it I want you to treat the
fragments z-coordinate as being unique
across all as being the same across all
the samples because that's really all I
want it to do you know what I mean like
all I want it to do is I want it to just
you know I want it to do this and have
that only be evaluated one time even if
you evaluate the rest of the shader
multiple times I don't want this value
to change now the problem here is it
says depth testing since death testing
itself is being done in addition this is
not the only depth test like the one
that we wrote is not the only depth test
there's actually you know the regular
depth test happening as well
you know that basically means that since
we have to write to fret we have to
write to jail fried chord does need to
overwrite the potentially multi sampled
value of Z which would probably be a
speed hit because it can no longer do
Earl easy outs anymore which is not
great so I don't know let's just see I
mean I'll just try it and see what
happens
so basically you know here we've got min
transform W there I'm going to go ahead
and set frag Z to that and I don't
really know what to expect here like I
said I'm kind of in somewhat uncharted
territory here l value required a sign
GL fried chord can't modify GL for Ag
chord I wait you're telling me I cannot
set the Z value of the fragment how do
you change what gets written to the
depth buffer dare I ask I guess at this
point it's already been written to the
depth buffer
[Applause]
ah so they want you to write the frag
depth is that correct let's find out is
frag depth so if I want to I can say out
32 thank you frag depth well I guess I
don't have to say that pelvic it's
probably already defined right so I can
probably just say that I'm assuming oh
dear that does not appear to have worked
particularly well
hmm so we should get be able to make
this work
oh so actually when we specify this we
would actually have to do the
preparation of the frag as well right
because normally what's going to happen
there is that BEC for demon transform
this you know this this feel position
that GL positions going to get the
divides going to happen right and so we
would have to do that divided and then
also the range mapping is going to
happen so both of those things are going
to happen right so our W value that
we're passing in fact like and I
wouldn't want to pass the W diode know
what I was thinking there we want to
pass the modified V value right so we
want we would actually have to do our
own mapping of the range right so we'd
have to take the modified V value we
have to divide it by the V min transform
W and then we'd have to map it into the
1 to 1 into the 0 to 1 range I think and
I also don't know which direction that
has to get mapped into but you know it
would be something like like this right
[Music]
all right so yeah that looks like it's
working however I still see the
artifacts so I don't know if what I did
actually worked at all unfortunately
like I have no way of knowing of with
what of whether what I did won't fix the
artifact or whether what I did would fix
your artifact but I didn't do it
properly somehow right hmm um so again I
think what we could do here is we could
just have everything include the 1 pixel
transparent border let's go ahead and
remove that stuff because maybe that's
just a bad idea
it also doesn't means even if I was to
get that working we couldn't use
early-out on Z which made me nervous so
really what I wanted to do is only right
ones the always have the same sample for
Z everywhere and I just don't know how
to do that right I just don't know how
to force it to do that like what I
really want to do is just say hey just
don't don't when you're producing these
samples just always use replicate the Z
across them all and I feel like there
should be a way to do that maybe I'll
have to ask the graphics sort of person
if there's some easier way to
communicate that because that's all I
actually want to do but so if I went in
here to the place where we specify the
textures
now let's see
No where is our create texture call it's
in your somewhere let's say Gen textures
artists allocate texture so you can see
here we specify the width height from
the data and we put it in right and so
what I'm wondering is if we wanted to if
we wanted to ensure that there was
always a one pixel border around
everything could we do that right and
would that fix the problem
I suppose I also don't really know what
these actually looked like so let me see
what the bitmaps themselves look like
because I'm curious to know so if I come
in here and I because I thought we
always know I don't know I'm a little
confused right now to be completely
honest I'm not quite sure I understand
let's go ahead and open up one of these
trees here I think that's the tray we're
using at the moment
I get like some info about this windows
dockable dialogs well none of those will
help me unfortunately I just want
something that tells me pixel value of
this pixel will just tell me
- z4 yes so there so it does go right
out to the edge there is an alpha value
out there and same is true over here I
guess wellnot doesn't fit there is one
over there but there is one over there
so yeah if this you know if that does
not actually have a texture if that
doesn't actually have a pixel border
around it could we just add a pixel
border to it and I want to see let me go
ahead and take a look at what happens
where we do allocate texture
so those textures are texture ops right
this is a list of things we went through
I remember this where we had like you
would push these text drafts where you
want to allocate the textures and you
just sort of stick them in here and then
it would retire them when texture
management time came
so here's where we're adding those
texture apps in here's where we're
loading stuff
there's the add up right so I'm pretty
sure all we're doing is loading these
things directly out I don't really
remember in our test asset builder
whether we add that border at all when
we do a load BMP it does not look like
we insert any space so there's really
nothing at all in this entire thing that
does any sort of a guarantee which is
weird because I know that in the
software rasterizer we skip the outer
border of pixels do we not do that in
the OpenGL one kind of curious because
our UVs are all set to use everything so
I'm assuming that in our software astir
Iser we were just assuming that we would
pad those anyway so yes we wanted to Pat
it out so that we knew that we would
always get a one pixel border I could
just do that you know it's not going to
be particularly efficient right here to
do it this way but I could actually put
in a one pixel border there and I could
even do it with a clamp to edge sort of
thing if we wanted to save space I don't
think I care about that particularly
much although it is kind of wasteful to
do I guess let's take a look at what our
clamping options are and maybe I should
do something slightly different here
although there is kind of a nasty aspect
of it that yeah well let's take a look
so let me take a look at what our GL
clamp options are here because I'm
interested to know if I just introduced
a transparent border
and then did clamp it to border and then
made it so that I always gave it UV
coordinates that were a little bit
bigger than the actual sprite would that
maybe take care of it for me so let's
see here
so here's clamp to border right which we
could set our textures to and if we did
clamp to border then we just set a
texture border color and we'd set that
texture border color to zero right
and it would just be a text parameter to
set the texture border color so I could
do that there is a problem with even
that though so the reason that I'm
hesitant to go down this path and why I
would really like to figure out a way to
get it to just evaluate the Z only once
is because if you think about what's
going to happen if we ever shrink the
bitmap so if we size things down then
even if there is a one pixel border
around the whole sprite that's
transparent when it by linearly filters
if the pixel next to it isn't
transparent you'll still get some
transparency around the border and
you'll see the artifact so I would much
rather the depth feeling just worked you
know and I feel like it would just work
if we were able to do that sampling
restriction
so I think I want to pursue that
sampling restriction a little bit more
right doing the border does not really
feel like the right solution to me so I
really feel like there's some way I want
to be able to figure out some way to get
the multi sampling
I really want that what mother family to
only produce a single V value that's
what I want
I wonder it's so trying to think
could I is there a way to just make it
so that there's only one Z value in the
z-buffer of course I guess that doesn't
really work yeah
why are you keeping the OpenGL ES
shading language specification let's
take a look at the more modern one so
here's four point three and let's take a
look at multi sampling see where it
shows up
yeah
stalling please never has to be read
Eclair dwith in typical fire when using
the Capelli profile front color back
flower secondary color secondary color
that's not really want to know about
depth can I do anything to try and
convince you to do the depth differently
rag depth
tell me about it please
Dilton fragment shader variable frag the
theory declared using where the falling
LED qualifiers get any dip greater depth
less than changed the layout qualifier
for Jill frog got some strange
intentions the final value of Jeff are
just written by the shader invocation do
you'll implement a store a lot of for
implications assuming that the test
fails or pass trig environment of a
Lea's of Jill ah so this is an
interesting kid it doesn't help us but
it is interesting
like all the use of the frag dip there
on that page seven shooters emphasize
the pipeline some of the built-in
variables you'll fragmented your sample
mask unless the discard statement is
executed the sixth function computed
depth for a fragment may be obtained by
reading GL fried chords e described
below
yes range of GL frag depth will
establish the depth value for the frag
repeat process of depth buffering is
enabled and no shader writes GL frag
depth then the fixed function value for
the depth will be used to the fragments
depth value the shader statically
science there's an execution paths
through the shader this is not such a
far dip than the value perspective death
may be undefined textures and shaders I
take that path there is with a set of
links fragment shaders sadly in the
original practice that it responsive
we're always writing it okay it's fine
by me
as long as I can be for any occasion to
pixel or one of the fragment samples the
use of centroid does not further
restrict this value to be inside the
current primitive this value is the
result of the fixed functionality that
interpolates primitives after
registering to generate fragments Z
component is the death value that would
be used for the fragments depth if no
shader contained any rights to jail frag
depth this is useful for invariance if a
shader conditionally computes Defrag
depth otherwise want the fixed
functionality fragment depth fragment
shaders have access to the input built
in variable geo from facing you know
that doesn't help me at all
hmm
so we have two things at play here and I
guess technically I'm not sure which one
of them is actually going on what would
be really nice is if we had some way of
inspecting these pixels a little bit
more quickly so that we could do some
tests and get an idea of what was
happening so at the moment right we know
that the fragments themselves the
samples themselves we are only getting
artifacts at the places where multi
sampling is actually kicking in which is
the edges of primitives and that's what
we would expect if everything was
working properly with the multi sampling
so that's actually a good sign right
because we're not getting any artifacts
where two primitives overlap each other
and the primitives themselves are
completely you know the pixels
themselves are completely contained by
by the primitives so no multa de edge of
a primitive so the multi sampling
shouldn't you know be kicked in so
that's actually a good thing but what we
don't know is we don't actually know
specifically where the bug is coming
from necessarily you know I'm assuming
that it comes from the fact that we have
multiple Z values for the same primitive
ending up inside the samples and the
multi sample buffer but what I don't
really know is if that's the if that's
really the truth if that's the end of
the story because it could also be that
it's just the resolve it's picking a bad
Z value or doing something otherwise
weird it could be that the it's picking
like the minimum Z value or something
like that so I suppose what we should
try to do first before we go any further
down this path which may require again
like asking you know someone from Nvidia
or something be like hey you know could
you tell us a little bit more about how
this value gets gets worked
I guess maybe I should try to get our
own custom resolve working so at least
we know what value of Z is actually
getting picked because we actually care
quite a bit about which value of Z is
getting picked and I guess you know with
the regular resolve we really have no
way of knowing right you know we have we
have absolutely no idea so I feel like
that you know something we want to we
want to try and dress so maybe I will
take the you know we've got some time
left in the stream 30 minutes or
something maybe I will take this time to
just try and get our own resolve working
because if we can get our own resolve
working reliably then what would would
happen there is we could go ahead and
verify that you know the the actual
artifact we're seeing is specifically
because of the sort of the variance
values across single primitive inside of
samples because we don't actually know
that's what's happening and so it might
be nice to just have a way of
independently checking that so here was
the code we started to write and what it
says here as you can see it goes over
the samples and it fetches the sample
you know so for the current pixel that
is trying to resolve it fetches all the
samples that there are so an 8 X Mulder
sampling it would do this loop eight
times it grabs out the color it looks at
the depth and then you know it's going
to do this this combined so the tricky
part here is we don't really know what
to do with the samples that we have what
we want is we want to throw out samples
that are going to be from the next def
peel down that we would get that are you
know from a wholly different you know
level of Z
so I think what we want to do here is
basically have like a V threshold where
we would say you know if including this
depth sample in slide the current depth
sample would you know greatly increase
the Z range with you know with some kind
of threshold invaluable up near the top
and that you know in theory if we
actually picked that threshold if it
turns out that threshold is actually
something you can select reasonably
which I don't really know that it is but
if it turns out that it is then it might
be that you could actually get that yeah
so we have an even have the case where
two things are basically right on top of
each other so there is no actual
separation between them
so
I guess there's another thing we could
say here which is kind of nuts but I'll
just point it out it's yet another
option so another thing we could do is
we could actually have our depth peel
not not actually use a multi sample
buffer I mean I guess I I don't know if
there's any way to write to a non multi
sample buffer while you're doing multi
sample right so it might be that it's
just not possible
I have to think about it but one thing
we could do is say well with the depth
peeling if we just used a buffer that
stored the IDS of which primitives we
were rasterizing then when we go to
collect our samples we could just
collect them based on the primitive
right and we'd say well you know
whichever primitive we're going to pick
that's the closer primitive that's the
one we'll use here
gosh this is really tricky because again
if you do that then the problem with
that is you're now introducing again a
you know sort of a additional buffer and
so you just keep you know you keep
increasing the the demands on the
bandwidth because at some point you're
just like well you should have probably
just done something you probably should
have just done something like atomic
rights because you're just getting
absurd displaying so to you know doing I
feel like there's a certain value to
saying well let's just you know get as
far as we can with just the depth buffer
approach because that's like the
standard built-in stuff that you know is
efficient and off it goes so I guess
I'll try using a Z range
that I'm not optimistic I guess is also
alright so at the moment I guess let's
just try to get this working at all and
the way we'll try to get this working at
all is just by saying we've got combined
color value and I'm going to initialize
that to zero and then what I'm going to
do is as we do our fetching I'm going to
summit oops
[Applause]
so I'm going to take all the colors when
they add them together I'm going to
remember what the clothes depth was and
on the way out I'm just going to set the
result color equal to the combined color
divided by the sample count so I'm just
taking an average right I'm going to sum
up all the colors I'm going to divide by
the number I summed and that's it
right nothing more to it I am so yeah
that's about it I think I don't think I
need to do anything else for that we
already compiling this right I think I
think we are no really no
let's take a look here what happens when
we actually set it now so when use
program begin here we've got prog common
being called and I want to see what
happens in prog common
yeah so in prog common we don't have to
set some any of these arrays so what we
can do here yet is just keep this and
and that way and that way just the use
program begin will still work even
though we don't have any of those divert
colors or any of those things I so we
only have these two the color sampler in
the depth sampler and so what we would
do when we do use program begin on the
multi sample program which I don't think
we've done yet anything for which is
this part right here what I want to do
is basically set up the to the color
sampler and the depth sampler I want to
set up those two presumably to 0 and 1
so all that's going to do is just say
hey the prog color sampler and the prog
def sampler would be set this way and so
when we do resolve multi sample we just
have to bind the we just have to bind
the textures color first which we do and
then depth and that would just work so
this is the resolve code here we're not
calling it at the moment but we could so
we could come down here now and say okay
forget all that stuff it's not we used
to do over now you do it that way
anymore so we here we're just going to
say okay we know we've got to go in fact
what I could do to leave that here open
jail frame buffer from
- we know we want to go from this one
and we want to go to this one so that is
really all we have to do to call this
thing of course we don't really know
because we've never run it and we
probably it's kind of janky and
complicated this this is probably going
to take a while to get working would be
my guess
resolve multi sample program color
sampler ID we are and initializing
connector open jail frame buffer that is
a good point I should not have using
array access there okay um so yeah I
guess I don't have high hopes for this
running anytime soon but let's go ahead
and try and debug it I do personal
operation requires the currently active
program object GL and bailout operation
did I forget to call
[Applause]
did I do I not compile this program or
something I think I maybe never called
compile on this program yeah okay let's
see here
undeclared identifier depth L value
required assign GL frag cord can't
modify gel frag cord parse error so it
didn't like anything about about this
well excuse me mister let's see you
write a shader just complaining about
our code like we did something wrong so
that's just that the view we already
looked this up so you can't write to
frag cords be it's always going to be
frag gap that has to go out so there
that is I don't know that's the only
thing
undeclared identifier of depth conductor
parentheses so depth is an undeclared
identifier it says I agree with that I
don't know where the parentheses are
that it's being upset about necessarily
I don't see any errant parentheses
jumping out at me but let's see hmm
parse error all right let's take a look
here
[Applause]
so that all looks fine and furthermore
it got passed compiling all of this
[Applause]
right that looks fine unless it's
complaining about this cast which I
don't think it would although I suppose
we don't really know that all looks it
looks to me like I don't see an errant
parentheses anywhere is there now what I
could do here is just let's let's break
this out a little bit more specifically
so whatever the sample count is let's do
help man
after all that so I guess there's just
no way to tell for coder please please
stop reinventing my my tear duct
so let's try this
so I'm going to do here is see whether I
can create a floating error that I can
move around the line that's in that's
all things like I figure out which line
it is yeah so we do know it's this line
so this parenthesis f/32 must be a
problem for some reason I'm not sure
what that problem is but I guess we'll
find out so let's suppose I we do in
sample count and I do 1.0 F / f through
to sample camp here and then I multiply
in sample count by combined color do I
change my error at all so it really does
not like that cast to an f32
I just don't know why it doesn't like it
so presumably that's it that was really
strange doesn't like the cast it didn't
like casting to a float there but I'm
not sure why it didn't like casting to a
float there because it's in theory that
should work fine I would think but who
knows
we do have an error here where it
doesn't like the fact that I am trying
to bind a texture but I'm not sure what
it doesn't like about those because
those do seem to be reasonable texture
handles the error that it's professing
is GL invalid operation
and so I guess what I would suspect is
that is because those are multi sample
so I probably have to bind them to the
multi sample slop maybe this is me just
assuming that that's true I don't
actually know that it is this is just
pure guess again my part never actually
done that before so we are running now
but we're not doing anything on the
screen which is not a great situation
also
hmm nice eh
so when we found the frame buffer we
bind to the two frame buffer which are
writing those you know we're writing to
the color the non multi sampled color
end of buffers we grab the multi sampled
color and death buffers here that we
execute this sort of read from them so
you know I guess sample count might be
zero there right so because do we
actually set that I don't know that we
do in fact I I'm pretty sure we don't so
that's actually something I just have to
finish here so what I do want to do here
is say hey sample count has to be equal
to opengl multi sampling count i assume
we stored that but maybe we didn't so we
may have to store that
[Applause]
be honest I'm not sure max multi-sample
count is the right name for that I think
what we'd rather do is just call it
multi sample count but you know I guess
we can leave that for a different day
[Applause]
all right so all I have to do now is
actually query the location of that
thing which we'll go ahead and do now so
let's go ahead and get the sample count
ID here we don't really need ID
we'll just call it sample count and so
then when I'm actually buying when I
actually compile this program I just
need to get that uniform right so and I
don't think we input anything else right
the only thing that we implement input
here that's an actual you know piece of
data you know besides the texture
handles is just what that sample count
is all right well good news actually is
that that started working much quicker
than I would have expected unfortunately
it's not giving us particularly good
results here to say the least
but you know what are you going to do it
looks like the Alpha value is not
getting written properly there and I'm
not sure why that is
so if we look at what happens here I
don't see any mistreatment of the Alpha
you know we are summing all the values
together and we're keeping the closest
step but we're summing all of the all of
the texels but we're losing the alpha
value and I'm not exactly sure why we
don't change the mode adults here I
don't think gia blend is off and so
we're not actually we're always just
writing one sample directly one sample
and only one sample I guess one thing I
don't know is are they is being cleared
at all and we do want to disable the
depth test I guess but if that shouldn't
really be doing anything because there
shouldn't be any values in the depth
buffer yet at that point however we
wouldn't really normally have to clear
those so and we don't clear them so it I
am a little weirded out by what I'm
seeing act honestly because I feel like
the the depth test should have made that
go a bit squirrelly but alright let's
just see now so it was just a depth test
nevermind alright so some things to note
here
we now have multi sampling on and what's
very peculiar about this and I have to
say was not what I was expecting at all
full disclosure is that we don't have
the artifacts that we were seeing before
we have new artifacts so that's very
strange and I suppose good because I
guess at the end of the day
that means these artifacts do have
something to do with the death ticking
and we do have a shot at correcting them
that way because if they went away when
I switch to a different resolving
function than the default one the
graphics card was using all of a sudden
things changed so I suppose that's good
however it's what's not good is that
we've got a new artifact in here that
I'm seeing and I'm not sure what's going
on with that pretty subtle but it's
definitely annoying me everything else
is looking pretty good actually
right it's just the edges of those that
aren't so good and I have no idea why
those edges are having anything happened
to them at all if I'm being honest like
I'm talking about that right there I
guess it's just z-fighting maybe I don't
know that's going to warrant some
further study what I would like to do is
I'd like to switch back to higher
resolution see how slow this is right
now because remember we had to switch to
a lower res for rendering because it was
very slow when we have to do this I'm
assuming that's just because of the
multi sample rendering in the first
place but don't actually know why it's
slow right we don't get anything from
the graph start at the moment that would
tell us why it's slow so we're flying a
little bit blind as we generally have
been with this graphics card so you
can't even run anything on it really
that gives us insight so I'm assuming
this will be slow like our previous one
was slow but I don't actually know and
yeah you can see that's like super
SuperDuper slow right
what's particularly interesting about
this and it makes absolutely no sense to
me at all is if you think about what's
going on here there should be absolutely
no reason why this would be more than
four times slower so we increase the
resolution by four but the frame rate
tank by weighing more than four I would
argue so I don't really know if that
meant we fell out of some fast path
where we're just stressing out the
graphics cards memory subsystem in a way
that now like it blew it blew out of a
cache somehow you know I'm just not sure
what I would like and I don't know why
we don't have this in here is I'm going
to put in a 1280 P mode I mean I twelve
it that's good a 720p mode I'm assuming
any modern graphics card that isn't this
graphics card would actually have no
trouble with this so I think it's mainly
just because this card is so old that we
have to worry about it at all and
obviously we've got some weirdness
happening to here which I'm not sure I
understand why we where we aren't seeing
we are seeing our little render our
debug overlay so we've got something
weird happening there as well so you
know if we do this resolves multisample
and then we come through here where when
we're on the last one we then bind the
peel buffer the
it's that correct depth peel read buffer
so I think that's erroneous that's
actually causing us to draw to the wrong
one I think so that's going to out note
though that's actually correct
so that's going to draw to the one that
we're actually using for resolves which
is correct because we don't want to do
any month of sampling after this right
so in theory that should be fine
so I will say something else it's a
little bit weird
his multisample is off at the moment
isn't it so multisample is actually off
apparently but we are still getting all
of the multi sampling it would seem
because we never turned it back on again
when we went to death feeling when I use
a multi sample target how are we getting
the smoothing if multi sampling is
actually still technically supposed to
be off I have a feeling it is not
actually off
I mean because it looks the same whether
it's on or off so I have a feeling that
that is just a a non enable if you will
but anyway ignoring that for the moment
the question is why are we not getting
you know after we fall out of here why
are we not seeing any of the debug
information show up so after we get out
of here peel index peeling equaling
false and we come through here
we're not peeling anymore what's the
problem like why are we getting this
weird situation where we're not seeing
any of our other rendering take place
and assuming I mean I don't know but I'm
assuming that if we turn that rendering
hand I'm assuming that if we turn off
multi sampling oops it's back right
so as one thing I could do is set the
multi sampling hands
[Applause]
where did the compile go okay there's
so you can see as soon as I turn on
multi sampling you know we definitely
have the debug go away it's not like the
debug wasn't rendering because if I turn
off the multi sampling hint it's back so
something about the state that's getting
set in that multi sample resolve I guess
I is causing us you know it's cascading
through and causing us to not see any of
the stuff that we were supposed to be
seeing not sure why that would be and we
know that if we do the resolve without
that if we do the resolve the other way
right
don't know why I'm not getting compiled
anytime I picked twice to compile all
right
five-minute warning so if I come through
here and I ask it to use the old-school
path so if I if I just use the to bind
frame buffers and then use the blit that
one shows it just fine right no worries
there but this one doesn't and so that
seems to suggest to me that we don't
have a problem with the rest of the path
we have a problem with this right
something that we're setting in here for
whatever reason you know makes the makes
this leave the state in such a fashion
if it will mess up other things that
were kind of come later but I'm not sure
why them be because if we take a look at
what happens here we're setting our
textures you know these two multisample
texture is texture 0 texture 1 we clear
them both immediately thereafter so
we're not leaving any textures bound
when we bind the frame buffer we clear
it after the fact not that we even need
to because it will get set immediately
after anyway we don't change the read
frame buffer anywhere so that would be
the same as it was of course I don't
know maybe that's something we need to
change
you know what now that I think about it
I want to look it up in jail buying
frame buffer
cuz that just sets the whole frame
buffer right yeah so now that I think
about it this shouldn't have a draw
frame but this is this is actually still
reading from a different frame buffer
isn't it because I only bound the draw
frame buffer and I didn't bind the read
frame buffer which meant that the depth
reads that's why that's why the GL depth
test turned disabled was necessary and
why it wasn't producing artifacts I
thought it's because we were actually
reading from the wrong frame buffer of
course we then we would get totally
different artifacts now if we if we
found it this way but okay so that makes
a lot more sense all right
now that of course there's everything to
do with our bug but I was just noticing
that that was the case okay
so the question is what about this you
know what are we doing here that makes
it so that it's a it gets messed up on
the way in and I have no idea I don't
know you know I mean I guess one thing
we could try doing is let's just try to
verify that it is in fact something
state-based and the way I could do that
is just call both of these right so I
could just say you know what um just do
the result month example but then
actually just do the regular resolve the
way we were doing it before okay so
since we don't see it now I feel like
that's a good indication that that is in
fact a state-based problem so some
states that we're setting there is
causing the subsequent calls to fail and
we're not
setting that state here and so by not
setting that state here we don't end up
with a problem so I guess the other
thing we could do now is let's let's do
it this way let's now go into resolve
multisample and see what we can turn off
that would still make this work right so
we don't see anything and now we do I
let's go ahead and binary search I guess
so maybe let's go all the way down to
that and see can we do that much and
still have it show up yes we can can we
bind the program yes we can can we set
the active texture that's the wrong one
[Applause]
yes we can reset those after textures
yes we can so it's literally just the
draw arrays call so actually thinking of
primitive is required we have to
actually activate the pipeline itself
okay and now I have no idea what's going
on didn't we just verify that that would
cause the problem what am I missing
okay are you trying to tell me that
switching the order of these oh its
access GL active texture so we were
setting active texture one on the way
out it was leaving active texture Oh God
this is why state-based stuff it's so
bad man I wish I could send an owl shame
to the OpenGL people all right so that's
fine
whatevs alright so I'm going to go to
head and go to the Q&amp;A here but that's
now we are now in control of the def
resolve ourselves we're not doing
anything interesting in it but we are in
control of it so that's good to know
and yeah like I said really all we want
to do here is then play around and see
can we find something in here that would
help us and again maybe that's just
looking for a death range that's
reasonable right and and you know we'll
work on that next week you know it might
just work for all I know
all right let's go ahead and go to the
QA
nikola Casey you often argue that we
don't need to free memory and clean up
upon exiting the program does the same
reasoning applies to GL delete program
and others
I saw you use that and wondered what is
the reasoning behind it
so I'm guessing again I know it's the
beginning of stream you asked a question
that we already covered and this is also
a question we already covered so I'm
assuming you must have missed some
streams so I'll give a brief recap but
the answer is is in is already in the
streams we allow recompiling of shaders
on the fly and so the reason we call the
delete call on programs is because we my
tree compile them many times so when we
recompile them we call delete we
actually don't call delete on exit so if
you'll notice where we call GL delete
program it's when we change the settings
we free the programs before creating new
ones so we actually never do free them
on exit and you don't have to we only
free them when we're about to create new
ones and the reason for that is that
well you know do you really have to
probably not because how many times
you're really going to change them in
the course of a debug session but it's
just you know why not free them it's not
that much extra work to free them and
that way you tell the driver those
programs don't need to stay around so
you don't just keep building up building
up crust as you go and creating maybe a
bad situation for the driver where it
thinks you've got thousands of programs
all of a sudden but really all it is is
the same 10 programs and you just happen
to have switched the render settings you
know a hundred times while you were
talking between something
Cal Forest casting and GLSL has done f3
2 pencils value incentive princess
turkey though it's not actually true or
is that just only true because I'm using
the old version because I thought I
thought I have used that in GLSL
um let's see character set preprocessor
Commons tokens keywords and FRS
definition set accuse uniform variable
types basic types
let's see
now so I guess it looks like they don't
do that anymore or they don't allow that
and I'm just hallucinating that I think
they ever did because this is a this is
a later spec than even what we're
programming on it it doesn't seem to
suggest that you're ever allowed to cast
that way
so it's only C++ style casting it looks
like maybe creepy juice is there a sim
version of your color scheme I probably
I don't know not one that I've made but
there's probably a similar one out there
this is not an unusual color scheme this
will be something close because you try
using Mesa for debugging yeah you can I
mean it's a it's a real pain to get
everything set up but you know if you
really think that's going to be
necessary you can I would recommend
before doing that just getting a
graphics card that you can use with n
flight which is in videos like you know
a mouse thing which is probably what I
would I would like to do that for our
stream at some point at some point I
will build a new machine for handmade
hero so we're not using seven-year-old
hardware for the stream but I just have
not done that since it's always I always
hate spending money on new computers
when old computers are working okay so
at the moment we just live without it
but that's a very good way to debug as
well it's probably not as good as
something like Mesa in terms of being
able to step in but on the other hand
Mesa if you're in the mode where you
could step into stuff is slow whereas
insight is full speed until you actually
capture the frame right which can help
how often do we need to free and
allocate memory compared to the early
2000s I'm not sure I understand the
question can you can you elaborate on
that question a little bit
perhaps what video card do I use this is
a nut so this this machine is just a
weird machine so it's a pretty weird
let's see here
just firegl
something ATI fire probe v8 700
well
so with you know
I don't know what the year it was
released
so a 700 is this one I know what here's
the data sheet on the 8800 I don't see
it doesn't seem to be listed here oh
there it is
fire pro 3d 8700 oh my god dude we're
using a basically a decade old graphics
card at this point so that's good
so we're looking at this row right here
yeah so it flops wise so there's let's
just look at what this is so we have
1,200 flops on this graphics card let's
see what we have on a modern graphics
card just stated flops which you know
obviously they always kind of you know
fungible certainly but let's say we had
a 1080 just a straight 1080 we're not
even going to go titan how many flops
would we have there
alright so 257 I'm sorry 8000 280 8200
let's say flops in single precision mode
versus 1200 so you know figure seven
times more powerful roughly maybe just
in terms of flops not a not in any other
metric so you know everything else would
be much more efficient as well probably
taxol fetches memory bandwidth what is
the bandwidth actually here's the bus
bandwidth so 320 gigabytes a second
stated bandwidth let's see what the
stated bandwidth is on this one where
was my 8700 here
okay 700 is the fourth line up
so the bus bandwidth isn't that much
better right I mean it's definitely
better three times which is you know hey
that's great but it's not like
astronomically so so that's interesting
anyway
slightly off-topic I recently found out
that a VE exists for SSC there are
pretty clear mathematical applications
for it such as mate result apply do you
see the benefits of using a ve and in
whoop which contexts ah
eazy-e that doesn't ring a bell
as can you can you tell me what AV e is
do mean a VX or what is av e stand for
probably juice what is the name of your
color scheme well it doesn't have a name
it's just what I set up when I was
tuning the colors so it doesn't have a
name um alright last question okay you
met ABX yes so basically a BX is there's
a bunch of things to say about a BX
where do I start
so there are two halves to a VX the
first is just when the register size
gets extended past four floats right so
you know the normal normal operation in
sfe is 16 bytes wide right four floats
16 bytes 128 bits whatever right however
you want to think about it right so it's
16 bytes wide and even think of what
that means is it it terms in a cache
line which is 64 bytes it's like one
quarter of a cache line I and so part of
the move from sse2 AVX there's you know
a V X a B X 2 and X 512 is they are
slowly widening the register size out to
the same size of the cache line so I
think is good and so you end up in a
situation where if you go all the way to
avx-512 that is actually a 64 byte wide
register size which means you operate on
16 floats at a time
which seems like a pretty good number to
me right it's one cache line big it's a
4x4 of pixels if you were think to think
of it that way if you were you know
or 16 elements at a time for some kind
of matrix work 4 by 4 matrix happens to
be 16 elements as well it's a good
number it's the same number the cash
life that's good right so I think 16 is
probably a good number for a register
size for floats if it's cash line all
that's good
so just widening the register size is
good why do I not use it on handmade
here oh it's not important anywhere so
if you take a look at like the best case
scenario here is the steam Hardware
survey we take a look at the CPU see
here and what you can see here is you're
really even just turning on any AVX at
all
25% of your market goes away right and
you know that's that's just a little bit
too much of a hit and that's before you
even get to something like a big 512
which would be even worse
so targeting something like sse3 is just
a lot more sane in my opinion because
you know that basically nobody is
getting left out there the number of
people who are going to buy your game on
Steam and not have sse3 is pretty
negligible right so assuming these
numbers are accurate you know you look
at it you just go wow ssv for looking a
little dicey AVX looking very dicey it
means 1 in 4 people who might come to
your game can't run it right
and so if you know for sure that the
only people come in your game or beef
emic beef which kind of users who have
really advanced hardware them you know
maybe no big deal but it's just if
you're talking about an indie game and
you know so I think I don't like
handmade hero where we're not you know
trying to render some really fancy 3d
thing it just makes a little bit of
sense to say let's keep that support
headed down and and let's not target
something so you know that's the width
side of a bx and as the AVX stuff
progresses avx2 to 6fx 5:12 you get
closer to I think what is probably the
right size for those registers which is
probably you know probably 16 floats one
cache line however there's another side
nav X which is the instruction set the
instruction set for avx-512 is actually
very very very good it's very good
because it wasn't designed by Intel I
Intel is terrible at designing Cindy
instruction sets SSE is a horrific
instruction set in my opinion it's
really bad and avx-512 was the first
time they had outside help as far as I
know in fact it was the folks that read
who did a lot of the design work on that
Jeff Roberts Michael Abrash Tom Forest
life I don't know they're probably other
people I don't know if Mike's tartan
probably was involved possibly Ottman
binstock but basically what happened was
the rad people who are actually more on
the programming end that on the tougher
end and who write assembly language code
all the time we're like let's make this
instruction set more straightforward and
so I feel like having that you know
outside influence really improves the
instruction stress dramatically so
avx-512 is actually the first time the
instruction set from that collaboration
which was the Larrabee project is
actually making its way into the
mainline ship and that instruction set
is much better it has things like laying
base gather it's got mask registers and
mapping of operations built into it so
that you can trivially do stuff like do
test that goes into mass register and
then operate on both sides of a branch
so it basically turns your instruction
set into something you can actually use
rather than something where you're
constantly shuffling and duping
registers and
having to like overwrite things it's
just you know it's much much better
because it was actually designed by
people who program so I'm going like
this for a living
and we're like here's what you actually
need so so avx-512 if it ever gets here
you know taking its sweet time I think
the first desktop chips that have
avx-512 are like shipping now or
something right there was eons that
shipped with it a while back and it's
been in the Laribee part so it's been in
CompTIA original Xeon Phi and the new
Knights landing Xeon Phi or whatever the
V on flies are up to now it's been in
there forever
it was in the air since the first one
but in terms of actually getting the
mainline processor it's only going to
come to the desktop now and sadly I
don't think Rison picked it up which
sucks so I think Rison core doesn't do
avx-512 yes and I don't know yeah so you
know the AMD designed you know their new
core and P didn't design it with those
instructions in mind which was nuts
because there's the right way to do that
kind of code in my opinion now granted
you know these people are hardware
experts and I'm not so I don't know
maybe there's a really good reason why
the avx-512 instructions aren't the
right way to do it but it sure seems
like the right way to do it masks
registers I feel like are a big deal and
having them work seamlessly with all the
instructions is kind of what you need
but I don't know so made me really
nervous to see that rise and didn't pick
up avx-512 maybe there's a good reason
for that maybe there isn't being not
knowledgeable about CPU design I I can't
you know I can't even rant about it in
any constructive way all I can say is
that from a perspective of the
programmer not having the AVX
five twelve instruction set is really a
bad thing
now maybe that's not actually what's
going on maybe
Rison actually will be able to support
it a backslide fell pretty easily and
they just didn't want the first
generation of the core to have to
support that register with and that's a
little bit of a problem for avx-512 in
fact you have to get all the way out to
64 byte register with before you can
actually just use the part you actually
care about the most which is the
instructions that's being better what
you'd rather have had if the instruction
set for maybe X 512 introduced just to
four element vectors in some weird light
way right you know 6 64 byte registers
aren't the most important thing right
that's just wider registers what we
really want is the instruction of that
to be good so that's basically what I
what I would say I so I don't know why
they don't have stuff like the mast
registers and whatever I feel like
someone at AMD could probably talk
constructively at that about that point
I would love to hear what they had to
say about that they may have some really
good reasons why they didn't throw I
know there's patent problems involved
too for I have no idea
you know hardware stuff is nuts that way
they always have all these legal snafus
they have to work around so I don't know
I couldn't tell you you now know
everything I know so alright that's
about it for handmade here so I'm going
to wrap it up thanks everyone for
joining me for another episode of hand
made here it's been a pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow along with the series at home you
can always pre-order the game on
handmade hero Oregon it comes with a
source code so that you can play around
fit and experiment we also a forum site
you can go to if you want to ask
questions a patreon page where you can
go through my sports video series a
schedule bot where we tweet the schedule
at you and an episode guide which has
our past episodes if you're trying to
catch up
on old apart series that you missed
that's it for this week I'll be back
next week with more handmade hero
whoopsy everyone back to that until then
have fun programming enough to be on the
Internet
stick amuse everybody