hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show Rico to complete game live on
stream we are in in a lighting mood
today we actually have a lot of lighting
stuff done at this point but we have to
debug because we're sort of cranking
down on finishing the lighting system
and at the end of the last lighting
stream we did some changes to how we
were going to store our lighting over
time and we did not have a chance to
debug them so our lighting needs to be
sort of cleaned up and debugged that's
what we have to do today and yeah I will
go ahead and get right to it because
it's going to take a while because
lighting is complicated okay
I let me just go ahead and show you what
I'm talking about here because you may
not remember or you may have missed last
week's Sunday episode where we did this
the basic problem that we have to solve
is that lighting is difficult business
so just showing you what's so going on
here
this I believe is debug mode let me just
make sure yeah so this is a debug mode
build so it's very slow at the moment
but what's going on here is you can see
just like pure chaos happening with our
lighting it's completely bugged out it's
not supposed to be doing this weird
disco effect or anything like this
it was working just fine before but then
we changed how's the storage stuff was
working in there we've broken everything
so our goal obviously is to unbreak
things as you might imagine so we're
gonna go ahead and work on that today
now what is it that we broke and why did
we break it I'll just kind of go over
that really quickly on the blackboard
unless a whiteboard because it's clearly
a blackboard at this point let's get the
day number in here day four to six
lighting storage so
lighting is too expensive we it's not
that we don't know how to compute
lighting we do right in computer
graphics we know how to compute lighting
now we're actually pretty good at it
and if you want to spend an hour's worth
of computing time on a computer
somewhere that spins up hundreds of
cores you can do even incredibly
complicated scenes with incredibly
detailed lighting and get very very
realistic computations out the other end
so it's not a question of not knowing
how to do perfect lighting we kind of do
what we don't know how to do is do
perfect lighting quickly in fact we
don't even know if it's possible to do
perfect lighting quickly it may just not
be with today's horse power so what we
have to do is we have to figure out ways
of getting lighting that's usable and
interesting in our game and that looks
somewhat accurate so that it feels
believable and usable but that obviously
isn't really a real lighting solution
because we just kind of know ahead of
time that that's going to be far too
expensive for our purposes so what we
are doing here is we are using results
from previous frames to smooth out the
results from subsequent frames to keep
the lighting sort of continuous over
time the reason that we do this is
because if we have to compute sampled
lighting every frame the amount of noise
that we're going to get there in our
results is going to be very high simply
because we can't spend the amount of
time we would need to to take enough
samples to get a really good accurate
result for every frame starting from
scratch so we need to do is start from a
previous result and refine that result
with new information every frame and
keep that continuity so that the user
doesn't see like big flashes in the
lighting what this means is it creates a
very difficult problem for us in terms
of bookkeeping it doesn't create a
problem for us in terms of computation
the computation is getting easier when
we do this and that's why we're doing it
but it creates a problem in terms of
bookkeeping because in order to figure
out
what last frame was lighting wise we
need some way of corresponding the
solution that happened last frame the
solution that happened in this frame and
that means that we need to store our
lighting in some persistent storage so
what we were doing previously is we were
caching it based on some IDs and we
never really had a scheme for how we're
gonna do those IDs when I went to
actually put that into practice I
realized hey wait a minute I don't even
really think I need to do an ID based
lighting scheme actually what I could do
is just have entities in the entity
system store their last lighting
information why not and then they can
always throw it away when they get far
enough away from the viewer to know that
we don't need to know what their
lighting was last time because it's
irrelevant now right so we actually made
that change it wasn't too hard of a
change to make so that structural
modification has been made and the way
that it works is if you remember we sort
of have a world that's chunked up into
pieces right these are world chunks and
it's a three dimensional grid so
actually you know it's it's something
that's this sort of a thing right then
if you take a look at like one of these
chunks inside it we store all of our
entity data right and right now we
haven't done anything to compress that
entity data but in the future what we'll
probably do is take the full notion of
what an entity could be which can have
all sorts of huge stuff and maybe it's
like a 16 K giant piece of information
and we'll just take the part of it that
actually matters so if it's something
that doesn't you know it's not on fire
it won't star fire information it
doesn't have health it won't star health
information right so it'll just store
the compact version immunities what I
decided to do is say oh well if we've
already got this notion that we're going
to compact entities and put them into
storage why don't we just also have the
idea that when we compact entities into
storage we can also go ahead and put the
lighting information into that storage
as well so that's all we decided to do
was put the letting information into
here and so that's the entirety of the
change so
it's actually pretty efficient I think
and will be pretty good the problem is
nothing in particular with the scheme
it's just we've got a bugs bug or bugs
get our implementation of this game so
our job today is just to go through this
system now that the change has been made
go through it with a fine-tooth comb
make sure it's working correctly because
it obviously isn't yet and then when
we're done with that we can proceed to
do more optimization on our lighting now
that we know exactly how it will be
stored and updated every frame all right
so let's pop over to the entity and
remember exactly how this is working you
can see we have lighting Point State
here and what this is is it just stores
like I said we're not doing anything
efficient right now entities are just
these big old piggy structures that in
fact I don't even know where the pig hat
is do we still have the pig yeah we've
got the pig hat here I'll put it on
so we are not trying in any way to do
anything efficient here we're just
saying okay this is a problem for a
later date when we're going to have this
packing concept here and when we have
this packing concept we will just pack
in exactly the right number of these
things right so however many it is that
an entity has if it's got you know two
pieces and only one piece has lighting
then we would just store the one piece
worth of lighting in a compressed sort
of format and then if anybody doesn't
have any lighting in all we wouldn't
store it etc but for and right now we're
doing the maximally piggy thing of just
hey the whole big gigantic entity we're
storing them all why because it's just
not the problem we're focusing on and
introducing that extra complexity means
we will create more work for us all the
time because we have to be thinking
about that so again that's a change we
want to delay until a future time when
it actually becomes relevant to us
rather than doing it now when it would
just cost us development time through
the entire development process so it is
important to make sure that
optimizations like that happen at the
appropriate time and not earlier so in
here we've got the letting point States
these are the states of the points that
are tracking the lighting information
for this entity and what you can see if
we bop over - I don't know why I'm
saying Bop all of a sudden today all the
time if we head over to the lighting
code you can see in here what the
lighting point state actually stores the
emission which is a color value and and
the brightness thereof and then a
directional value which says the average
light direction for the light that's
incoming and this piece of information
is the piece of information that we are
tracking frame to frame because it needs
to get like sort of average to smooth
things out then we've got the lighting
solution here which is the thing we're
actually working on and what you can see
is that just has a bunch of light boxes
and those light boxes themselves have
the information that we're talking about
here in terms of what
goes with what so the lighting boxes
have all of the information about you
know an individual cube that's going to
collect light or block light and then it
has the lighting storage and lighting
indices which are basically used in that
computation to first refer to the
previous frame so this this pointer here
will refer to the entity storage there
that we're talking about that it will
get that emission from and then
furthermore we have at the by the same
token indices into the main lighting
array of where those will actually be
stored when we're processing them if
that makes sense so and you can really
think of these as just another pointer
effectively it's just pointing into
unknown array which is like these
emission things here so that's how this
system is supposed to work and we now
have to just make sure that it does
actually work because it doesn't appear
to be doing something correctly that may
be something small maybe something big
but we need to go find out so what you
can see in here is when we do excuse me
when we do push a cube on what we do is
we create the bounds for it and we see
whether or not it intersects the
lighting if it does intersect the
lighting then we figure out how many
lights is there are going to be in it
and we sort of do this in an ad hoc
fashion at the moment in the future
we've kind of tried to set up the system
so that we can adjust the number of
lighting points to suit our needs and
this may become important right when
we're generating the world we may decide
that we need to have different ways of
test lighting lighting across services
because some services want more light
points somewhat less to keep things
efficient so right now we do this in a
very ad hoc fashion where we just kind
of slam in some light points by default
across the cube without really having
any information from the user about
whether or not it should be highly
tessellated too low tessellated whatever
but that's what's happening at the
moment so we just pre compute a number
of light points that number of light
points is going to be 4 right 4 per
surface because there's 24 per chunk and
each chunk gets divided up across six
phases of the cube so the light points
for chunk will end up being 4 in this
case we take the light index and we
assign the light index to start with to
be whatever the place is in the light
index array that we've we've come up to
at this point and what you can see here
is we then advance by that many by that
by the amount that's in the chunk right
so this is basically our way of
allocating 24 light points to every cube
linearly as those cubes get pushed onto
the renderer so then inside here we
create a light box in the same fashion
and we just push one on linearly as we
get a cube and then we fill out the
light box and the light box has light
indices that correspond to every four
light indices in that block of 24 and
you can see that the last one here is
actually assigned to the twenty-fifth
light and that's because this is a
stopper it basically says here's where
the lights stop so this is face zero one
two three four and five those are all
the faces of the cube and where they're
lighting to see start inside the range
and then here's light index six which is
not an actual light you use it's just
like an end cap and again that's a very
standard way of doing arrays where you
just have indices in them and you need
to know their spans you need to know
where the last band stops you just add
one extra index so that you don't have
to store a count for every single one
since the counts always implicit by just
differencing with the next index in the
array we then push this on by taking the
light index which again has not moved
from what it was so it still records the
last one index and we just move it up
right and the light count in this case
will be zero for anything that doesn't
have lighting so if it didn't intersect
then it will get assigned light indices
but it won't get assigned light counts
so I believe that will prevent it from
participating in the lighting maybe I'm
wrong about that so we should
double-check that but
presumably if you always push zero on to
the lighting then the shader will notice
that there are no lights that it needs
to sum and it just won't bother summing
them and again where that happens just
and I can double check this for my own
purposes because I want to make sure in
the Z biased program which is there too
which is the thing that does the initial
rendering and computes the lighting you
can see in this program here that's
sorry that's the vertex shader you can
see in this program here when it goes to
some the lighting it's going to loop
over the light count to do that right so
even the case where there are no lights
we would expect in here there to be
early-out let's take a look if there
actually is where are we here where's
our some like some like not sunlight so
that's actually not right this is wrong
because it's the Frog like count that
will be equal to zero so this is
actually incorrect I believe
I guess
mmm I say so I guess I mean if we look
at what's happening here the result RGB
is it's just gonna come out as zeros
here because you're gonna hit this and
the light counts gonna be zero and so I
suspect this will make anything that
doesn't have a light index just end up
being black is what it looks like what
happened the reason that I don't Oh easy
we're fine so actually this is fine
because light count won't will still be
zero so this will be zero the entire
time - so both of these will be zero
nevermind so that's fine so that's why
it's gonna like the trees should be
black that was the case but yeah it's
fine cuz remember light count gets only
gets set in the case we actually enter
this so this is actually fun no need for
worry anyway that's how cubes get pushed
down and what you can see based on from
how they're pushed down here you can see
here that the light point state is
passed in and this value here tells you
what the storage address is for the the
individual light points that need to get
written back so we pass in a light
storage pointer here and that light
storage pointer gets written back to the
light box by saying hey when you go to
keep the results of the lighting that
you're about to compute on this frame
they go here and by the way you can also
if this looks valid to you you can grab
the lighting out of here to use in this
computation so that's what's going on
there now I want to make sure and I
guess what can do this into the bugger
little bit later I want to make sure
that this lighting this light storage
actually round-trips okay because we
have inside the sim region where these
things get copied out we need to make
sure that they're actually copying out
the light information because I don't
know if they are aren't I'm assuming the
whole structure gets
copied at this point it's been a long
time since we've done anything with this
and so I don't know if there's any
intervening factors in here that caused
that to not be the case so I believe it
would be in begin sim or begin world
change I guess
so inside begin world change you can see
here is we have this sort of entity
struct here that gets pulled out and I
believe we always just kind of write the
source to the desk yes so you can see
right here we've got decompression step
the source just gets moved into the desk
like so so since the source gets moved
into the desk like that that should mean
that all the lighting gets copied in and
then the question is an end world change
does it get copied back out and here you
can see it should be getting copied back
out as well so these are the two steps
that compression decompression steps
that are happening that you know really
don't do anything yet but will
eventually they appear to be copying the
light so we would expect it to be
persisted properly across frames inside
the lighting we now have to go take a
look and see whether we're actually
obeying any of this stuff properly in
the first place inside the lighting
routines because they've been modified a
bunch of times now as we've been playing
with stuff it's possible that we just
messed them up so when we come into
lighting test here what you can see is
we first remember how many boxes we
started with because remember we're
gonna do a spatial hierarchy we create
new boxes that basically encapsulate
different sections of the world so that
we can cut down on the number of things
we're a cast against when we're a
casting so if we take a look at what's
going on in here when we do our lighting
test when we when we go ahead and
process this information we go through
each of the original boxes that was
pushed on there and we are sort of doing
our copy out right here so this is the
part we have to look for to see whether
or not we're picking up the previous
frames lighting correctly
so we go through each of the boxes we
look at what the first light index is
for that box we go over each surface
right so we go for a particular q4a put
your luggage box we go zero to five each
of the phases we get out what surface
that is by using the radius and point
position of that light box we then take
and subdivide each face and we put
points in for that face so we start out
at that initial light index we go
through by adding the base point array
we look at each point as we go
we record the surface normal and the
actual location the point by displacing
it this is basically creating a location
of this point that's on the box right
again nothing particularly weird here
kind of straightforward and the surface
that all the surface information is the
same as we were using before we just use
this routine to create information about
the surface we create the reflected
color by pulling that out of the box
that was stored when we actually made
the box in the first place and then when
we do our admission we take whatever the
ocean has passed down we multiply it by
the max light emission and we we tracked
that value through the pipeline right
you can see in here by taking whatever
the emission values that's passed down
and we blow it out to white and then so
because you know it doesn't right now we
don't pass down RGB emissions we could
we probably should so anyway we store
that for whatever light index this is we
store that in the emission array and
again that's the absolute light index
that we got we didn't grant the light
index at the end of this we would expect
the light index in effect I should just
go ahead and assert that here that after
this is all said and done the box light
index six should be what we ended up
with and in fact I could just make that
happen here to say that whatever the
surface index plus one is right that's
what we should have ended up with at the
end of every
right because free-surface we should
output exactly four of these and they
should line up with what we think they
are in the box so that looks roughly
correct here what I would say is just
you know this doesn't copy out any
information about the light yet the
reason it doesn't is because right now
were in fact this is the to do for it
right here right now we don't reload the
emission we just blend with it after
that's probably not the best we can do
but it's what we were doing before so I
want to keep it with what we're doing
for I don't want to add any new stuff in
here while we're just debugging so we're
gonna leave it that way for now we then
come through here we do our light our
light propagation computation I don't
know whether we're supposed to zero emit
see I don't think we are because the
emits emu dust
let's think about this
the destiny should always be cleared by
the previous loop and it should start at
zero so we shouldn't have to clear that
and we could assert on that right we
could come in here and go alright
if handmade slow 4x equals zero and X is
less than point count so right here
where we're about to go into this stage
of the game what I could do is say all
right my lighting point I want to make
sure actually that's wrong it's just the
emit C so it's just this stuff here so
what I want to do is say all right
my emit C 1 equals I guess I'll just get
the actual one out equals whichever one
we're on right now and I want to assert
that this is set to zero
so that's just a check to make sure that
that always is starting off cleared
because again we expect that though he's
to start clear and always be cleared by
the previous frame but who knows maybe
we've got a bug in there so I feel like
we want to make sure that that's true
and so I'm just gonna go ahead and say
you know make sure that's true when we
do compute light propagation we're gonna
have to go check that routine in a
second but right now let's just go ahead
and focus on the final stages here so if
we assume that the light got propagated
properly because we didn't really touch
that routine so hopefully it's still
fine we then got a loop over all of the
boxes that we have again doing the exact
same procedure that we did here and for
each box now we have to copy out the
light state blend and store right so we
grab out the box we grab out where we're
storing it and then we want to look to
see whether or not this was valid the
way we're doing that is we're looking at
whatever the stored direction was and we
want to make sure that the stored
Direction is actually not all zeros
because the direction cannot be all
zeros a direction always has to point
somewhere right so the only times we
could ever have a direction of zero is
if we are starting afresh so it's just a
cleared array so it's the first lighting
solution in which case we have nothing
to blend with anyway
or we didn't collect any light for this
point we've never we just never saw
anything in which case again we can't
blend with it because it's not a valid
so there's no bid no light there right
so we wouldn't have any information
there should always be light coming in
pretty much everywhere
most of the time I would think unless we
created an area of the world that was
literally pitch-black at that point we
may have to rethink this and maybe have
an actual flag that says whether the
lighting was valid or not at the moment
though we're just going to assume that
that that's it's fine to use this now we
wouldn't actually need a flag we could
just set one of these to be some bogus
value in fact in fact you could imagine
setting one of these values to like a
thousand we know the direction has to be
normalized so we can just set the value
to a thousand
you know that can't ever be true so if
you see Direction X equal a thousand you
know this is an invalid point if you see
anything else you know it's a valid
point right all right so I can actually
put that in here to do KC
maybe we should in it directions to have
an X of a thousand or something so that
we can handle points that get no
lighting so we go through here and we
say if this was a valid point then we're
gonna have to do a loop that actually
blends and if it's not then we don't
have to worry about that so let's start
with the blended one because this is the
one that happens on most frames since on
most frames most points will have had
lighting the previous rain we go through
and we loop through the local index the
way we loop through the local index is
we take the total count for how many
there's going to be let me go ahead and
pull that out because that way in the
debugger will be easier for us to
inspect so here we're gonna take the
last light index for this box and the
first and we're gonna subtract two so we
know how many loops over we're gonna
loop over that many and the global point
index is going to be equal to whatever
that local index is plus the base index
which is the one we're sort of working
off of first one for the box we're then
going to say all right into the box
itself store back the emission also
store that into our light array because
we're gonna use that later to output the
points we could probably do that right
in here so output lighting points
actually could be welded directly into
here probably to be honest with you
that's probably what we should do but
you know I'll go ahead and say
that's what we want to do anyway we
store it back to the two places like so
and then we perform the actual lerp to
get it and the lerp is between the box
storage local index omission which is
the one from the previous frame and the
new one that we've computed right so
we're just doing that blank blend and
storing it back and the T value is how
far we're going right which at this
point is just a fixed value of 0.1 right
and right now we just know that you know
we just blend towards the new lighting
solution and we don't really have any
rhyme or reason for how we're doing that
we just know we add a little bit every
time so this probably will get better as
we start to think about how the lighting
a sample to make more intelligent
decisions here we then do the same thing
with the lighting direction so to do the
lighting direction what we do is we
store back into the box and into the
average rection to light array the
normalized version of the lerp between
the average direction to the light from
this frame and the the one that we
stored on the previous frame now you'll
notice we also normalize the one that we
computed this frame the reason is
because we don't want to lurk between
one thing that's been normalized and one
thing that hasn't because the thing that
hasn't been normalized will dominate
because it will have been it's too long
because it's the sum right so it needs
to get normalized down first so that's
how that works so if we come through
here we can see that the other version
which does not which assumes that the
the points were not the previous state
was not valid right for the the previous
boxes we're doing this per box the
particular box in question was not valid
then we're gonna do the same loop over
the same indices in fact we can pull
this out
like so
and what you can see it to I loop over
these weird exactly the same thing we
did here but the difference is now we
don't blend so we just store back the
exact results we got this time and
that's all we're doing so yeah we still
have to do the normalization but other
than that that's all that happens here
so that looks pretty sane I don't see a
lot of weirdness happening honestly
there oops sorry
output letting textures is what I meant
so if we take a look at output loading
textures here output letting textures go
through all the points and does some
let's see what is this what is this
doing here
so really all we do here is we just
store the location and the color and we
store the direction we pack that into
the W coordinate and it looks like
because we because we have to be able to
reconstruct the Z I don't know why we
negate D Z here because we're never
going to use it so that's really just
superfluous right the DZ never gets used
but what we do is we negate the red
Channel I should put a note in here
so we need to basically record what that
sign of that DZ was because we don't
know which it is it could have been
either because the only constraint on
the direction is that it be normalized
it doesn't have any implications for
which direction it has to be normalized
in so for example take the easy case
where you've got a normal that's 0 0 1
well all you're gonna get is 0 0 and
you'll have no idea whether it was 0 0 1
or 0 0 negative 1 so you need one more
bit of information to determine which of
the two square roots right there's a
plus or minus in the square root which
of the two you're gonna pick that's all
we're doing here so that's really it and
like I said this output lighting
textures is really something that can be
done directly in line with the copy out
here so we could just be doing that and
then we wouldn't have to copy the omit 0
like omit C 0 an average direction to
light don't actually need to be written
back to themselves in that way we could
just write directly to the textures at
that point which is what we would
probably want to do all right so that's
the complete that's the complete
roundtrip builds facial partition for
lighting is presumably not implicated
here because it doesn't do anything
differently this time so the only thing
that we're really talking about here is
compute light propagation compute light
propagation hopefully is working
correctly let's double check it and then
we just get down to debugging stepping
through the debugger because I don't see
anything semantically wrong so far
everything seems to be doing what I
would expect it to be doing so inside
the beaut light propagation we start
with emit C 0 and emit C 1 as you would
expect we go through the number of
iterations that we want to go through
and we assume that the light power
distributed every time is going to be
the
total number of rays but by the end the
ray like the light retention per
iteration is gonna take away from the
lighting so however we would distribute
a full amount of the light power each
time - however much we want to retain
each time and then we divide by the
total rate count to figure out what's
going on right again this is going to
get tuned quite a bit more in the future
we loop through all of the emitters and
for each emitter we go ahead and you
know also just curiouser
so in here light point index should
start out at one right and presumably
right now it's not I actually want to
catch this bug because I think like this
is a little subtle bug here so in here
where we do light index and we assign
the light index I want to assert that
the light index is not equal to zero and
I think we're not handling that case at
the moment so I feel like this should
assert on that assertion how is it not
are we actually setting light point
index here so we are actually setting
light point index here in the render
commands I feel like I want a quick look
at that I guess that is the right place
for it all right well okay so when we're
running this here we also are doing the
debug check now to to make sure that
those emit see ones are valid which they
apparently are so that's also good
alright so let's go ahead and keep going
here inside our compute light
propagation we're going to loop through
each of the points that we have sort of
packed into the lighter right here
we go through each of these and we say
okay let's let's go ahead and check to
see whether there's any emission coming
from this particular a light point
assuming that there is we're going to go
ahead and cast some rays from it we will
sample the hemisphere to figure out what
direction we're going to send the Rays
and we'll do the raycast as a result
inside our our test here if we hit
something we see which light index we
hit we grab that out this way we also
get the number by looking at the next
one and subtracting there so this is how
many of them there are in question we
then go through each of those and we say
okay for each of those light points
we're going to go ahead and take
whatever the surface point index offset
is here we're going to offset it from
that that base index we're gonna look to
see for that particular point how far
away are we from it if that's the
closest one we'll keep it we then go
ahead and do our all
our work on that particular point and
off we go right so again it looks all
pretty straightforward here I don't see
anything quickly weird or interesting
actually we just have a basic copy back
that happens afterward here so that's
all pretty straightforward yeah that
seems fine so yeah I don't know what's
wrong at the moment so we're gonna have
to dive in a little more detail I don't
I also feel like at this point we should
because we're debugging we should get
our f1 working again f1 was supposed to
draw the lighting points you can see
it's not drawing any lighting points so
let's go ahead and and get that routine
working as well because we need we're
gonna need that for debugging it's a
basic visualization that we need here so
yeah inside out put lighting points I
believe that's what happens when you hit
f1 right so what we need to do here is
we need to figure out how to make this
thing work correctly so we do a get
current quads with the point count
that's not correct actually what we're
we're going over boxes here and plus
point count it's gonna be four times the
point no I guess that's right because
there's one for every point so that
seems fine so anyway we come through
here we're gonna do get current quads
for the point count yeah we loop over
each of our boxes for each box we go
through each surface we get the surface
for each of those we take a look and we
go through the point index point indices
for that particular surface we grab at
that point we take the p value of the
point and we take the emission color we
then go ahead and and do the clamping
here I feel like this needs to get
adjusted
because the emission values here are
gonna be wrong that's alright we'll deal
with that later so yeah so then we clamp
the emissions we draw the points that
all looks pretty sane right so I think
we're getting some problems where our
light points are not getting initially
eyes properly is what it looks like it's
happening actually so it looks like
something bad is happening in here that
we're like writing to the wrong thing or
something weird is happening but I'm not
exactly sure what so let's take a look
in that routine actually assuming I
still got that breakpoint set yeah so
when we come through you're like what
are our p-value for example are they
what just happened
are we just not setting the point count
so we're setting the point count to the
commands light point index we're setting
the box count here
what's going on
so my light box count is zero
[Music]
I guess that's because in this case we
when we do output letting points we have
not actually called the lighting routine
yet so when we do update lighting here
and we do we're probably going to have
to move this down so that we actually
just do the if around the lighting
textures and we output the lights which
we can do now that the lighting runs
more in real time before we couldn't do
that so that's fine I don't mind making
that change because like I said the
lighting is supposed to run in real time
now unlike before when it was running in
non real-time so I'm okay with that so
if we want recompute lighting yeah so
all this stuff is is really we can clean
this up quite a bit now
yeah there's just a lot of garbage in
here we can clean this up and make this
a lot simpler now that we always run in
real time so what we can do here is just
have the show lighting information just
be a visualization that happens here so
really what we can do is just say
alright in here
we know we've got this sort of show
lighting debug thingy that we're doing
here so I can just go ahead and grab
that and say if we're doing show
lighting then we're gonna do that
otherwise we're gonna do this right and
the crucial thing here I guess is that
after we've done all of this and passed
all of this information down we actually
need to clear we need to take all of
that stuff that we would have drawn and
we need to not draw it right because
this will output the lighting points
like on top of what we were doing before
and we don't actually want that to
happen so what we need to do is after we
do the lighting test and we were going
to output letting points we need to do a
like we don't really want to call it
clear because that's just clearing the
screen discard all render commands we
need to discard all previous render
commands kind of thing so you know we we
did a bunch of rendering we don't want
to do it anymore because we were doing
it just for the sake of computing some
lighting and we're gonna do we're gonna
do like a test render here so just don't
do that so we need something that
discourage all of that and then we can
go ahead and do output lighting points
on that frame and that's all we really
need to do now updating lighting is
something that we still probably want
updating lighting that is something that
probably also wants to get done so in
here we would have
this like so so when we go through to do
that lighting test yeah we would need to
call that function so that the lighting
information is valid at the time how we
would get it why was the box count
getting cleared to zero I don't know so
that's a little bit confusing actually
[Music]
because the test lighting should not
have been we'll take a look at that a
second too so that kind of needs to get
that kind of needs to get addressed as
well all right we can get rid of those
so in here
I think all we really need to do is say
well no matter what happens I guess we
can just leave lighting enabled I don't
think we ever need to disable it if we
do we could just disable just that one
part so I think this becomes a little
more straightforward now so we really
just need these two things f1 and f4 and
then the iteration counts we can adjust
as well obviously we can leave that
happening I think all that is really the
only part we need and then if we take a
look in here we've got the updating
lighting and the show lighting
I think that's all we really care about
so I think that's all relatively
straight forward so far and so what we
really need now is we need a way to
actually do that render group discard so
in here what I'm going to do is I'm
going to find this thing and all this is
gonna do is when we go you know look at
what's in these render commands you can
see that we've got sort of this the set
of things we're streaming out here all
we really have to do is just reset those
right so we just have to take that that
command structure oops and clear it out
so we basically reset the push buffer
data at you know what the
we don't really want to render the
crois but we probably want to leave
everything else intact in other words we
probably just want to change the vertex
array back so honestly the only thing we
probably want to do here is just say is
just save vertex count equals zero I
think
yeah it's not that simple though because
we have the records of the push buffer
on there you know what since this is
debug why don't we just let it render
and then clear actually that actually
seems like a better idea that way we
don't have to worry about any of that
stuff there now we can actually up with
these and hopefully see something that
does not look like it cleared I think
that's because it's inside a depth feel
unfortunately
[Music]
so I think we would probably have to do
the end depth peel first now to be
honest with you I don't know why and
depth peel couldn't happen before and
sim because n stem is not rendering so
what we could do is just do it here
and I would have thought that clear
would work
so doesn't seem to though
so we should go check why our clear
doesn't work because I think it looks
like everything else is working but I
would like to be able to clear the
screen there because I don't want to
show anything else so inside the OpenGL
layer where I look at the clear is this
just because we actually don't process
clear commands
yeah I think the reason for this is it
looks like we just don't actually
process clear commands as actual
commands you can kind of see right here
what we do is we just we just take and
we clear at the beginning but we don't
actually do a clear command so we should
probably put the clear command in there
I'm not sure why we don't it might have
been historical because it seems like it
should be fine
to put the clear command in here look I
don't see any reason why we couldn't do
that let's try it
so we'll call this a full clear because
it just wipes out everything
and then inside the render group make a
full clear to go with our depth clear
the depth clear looks like it doesn't
have a struct associated with it do any
of these they've done so looks like only
textured quads actually has any data
which is fine so let's take a look
so that clear color that's in the render
commands I'm gonna get rid of it I'm
gonna put it over here
and I'm gonna leave that comment there
because it's the same thing right we're
gonna use the same value there and we're
gonna go from here so when we get it
clear now this is gonna actually change
the information I don't know I don't
know that we'll have to change the fog
part the fog part I think should be fine
yeah and all this should be fine as well
so in here where we get the header out
when we actually need to get the value
from this it should just be this right
here the same code that we were using
before where we get that full clear
and then in here we can say okay for
each of the things we're going to do now
instead of getting the clear color out
of the the render commands we're just
going to get it exactly as we would have
before and off we go
I am not sure what this wants us to do
so this is basically saying like
whatever the clear color whatever the
last clear color was but we're gonna use
it I don't know that I care about that
just yet so instead I'm just gonna say
like okay just clear it to black for now
so now we can do an actual push here
that pushes actual information onto the
render stock and yeah that should just
look like this
so now in here when we go to do a push
render elements we're going to push on
the render entry full clear like so and
so now the clear color gets stored
directly in the entry I think that will
work but I don't know so we'll find out
I so when I say I think that will work
is what I mean is it won't work at all
so it looks like inside of the open gel
they are here uh when this clear happens
[Music]
happens a couple times let's see it's
basically right here and in the cutscene
so this has to happen actually I guess
outside the deaf feels as well I think
because the Deaf peels are a special
block so the clear can't happen inside
there yeah okay so that's all it was
so now in theory we should be able to
figure out a way to make sure that this
actually works we needed to clear
everything but I thought it was gonna do
I feel like it was I thought it was
supposed to clear all of our surfaces
because we go through every depth peel
and do we clear it
so I'm not sure why that shouldn't reset
our state correctly but it definitely
doesn't so in so insofar as we do all of
our peels here
I have to think about how this actually
gets composited on the back end so you
know the composite on the back end it
does the lighting peel composite that's
what this does right here so when we do
the lighting peel composite my thinking
here was that well we can just throw in
a clear an additional clear and it
should work because it'll just clear out
the depth feel so when they get
composited they'll only get the stuff
that comes after that was my thinking
anyway because we know we can render
stuff afterwards because we have like
the debug system is rendering stuff that
just gets rendered directly to the top
theft peel right I mean it's supposed to
that's supposed to work so I'm not sure
why we would have
right here we clear out the depth layer
for our our the peel that we're on and
we don't do a begin end peel here right
there's no depth peeling I don't think
because the only place that does that is
in here so I would have thought that a
clear plus the depth peel began we would
go through and we do deaf people and so
this stuff gets rendered multiple times
to each deaf peel if we then came
through and did the clear and then did
the output letting points after that I
would have thought that would have been
fine but evidently clearing after the
depth peels doesn't actually work
apparently
unbeknownst to me or rather contrary to
what I would have logically thought
clearing in here does not seem to
actually work now the DEF peel count is
constant right and all of those depth
peels are getting cleared
so the result multisample has already
happened
all of these are getting cleared I guess
the main frame buffer I guess the only
thing is the main frame buffer isn't
getting cleared is it so we've already
done every cell method this is only the
depth peel buffers so I don't actually
know if we do want to clear those that's
a good question but zooming we do
[Music]
I'm gonna say let's clear that main
buffer as well yeah that's just pure
bizarre to me I have no idea what's
going on here I'll be honest with you
this is the way of driving since you
can't step into it I would feel like so
that what happens when I do an f1 is the
inverse of what I would think what
actually happens is it clears everything
that comes after right so everything
that comes after the clear that gets
inserted is what ends up being cleared
and the stuff that came before remains
now what I would have thought would have
happened is when this resolves oh that's
not the main frame buffer so here's the
render entry end peels I this is still
binding the last depth peel buffer which
is not actually what I wanted right what
I actually wanted is for the end peels
what I actually want here is whatever
buffer you were targeting to be cleared
right I want whatever you were going to
render to to be cleared and we need to
rebind that buffer
so yeah I'm not sure if I really want to
do it this way maybe I just want to do
this it's it's hard to say right
it depends what we want that clear to
actually mean so I guess what we want to
do is when we do the clear here we want
to say like okay whatever the render
entry end peels would have targeted if
you know if you come through here and
you're on the last one we bind this
frame buffer that's the one we're
actually using and that's what we would
have to bind if we were currently on
that one so we almost need to like save
and restore it here which is kind of
nasty
so like
I mean you can see what I'm saying here
right this is really what needs to
happen and it's just kind of ugly
it's very special case like but I feel
like basically that still don't even
work which is weird but basically what
happens is when we come in through here
we rely on the fact that we're targeting
this frame buffer when we start the
first depth field buffer and then after
we're done with the DEF peels we end up
targeting this other frame buffer right
this one here so I guess actually
technically it's this and peeling
I don't really know because peeling will
start off as false
so the first clear actually doesn't even
want to do that which is even weirder
so who sets peeling to true so the first
time through peeling is set to false
because there's nothing to check against
right and then on peel index gets set
back to zero when you're done so there's
really no way to know whether you're in
one of these are not
I mean I guess one way to do it would be
to do it this way we would have to we
would effectively have to track you know
which one of these we were on since this
is messy enough I'm gonna say let's go
ahead and do it let's go ahead and
actually try to clean this up a little
bit because it's just kind of bad so
what we could do here is say well
alright when you do begin render entry
peels maybe that's when we target a
buffer you know
because you look at these we're gonna
jump back so you know you're gonna come
through you're gonna begin the the peels
you could just do this I mean I feel
like you could do this any way where you
say all right when we begin peels we
target whatever the peel buffer is that
we're on and then at the end you know we
increment the the on peel index and we
jump back
and similarly you know where the
repealing or not is in here which is
different from whether we're on appeal
or not assuming that we don't do that
we're gonna fall out of the loop then we
bind the other frame buffer and we know
that peeling is false and on peel index
also it has to equal zero because of
what we're gonna do inside the peel
thing so that's at least a little bit
cleaner there right so that when we go
to like start appeal we know what's
going on there the thing I suppose we
could do is clear at that point so when
you do a begin peel you would clear the
peel but I don't know if we want to do
that differently where we allow multiple
peel sets that doesn't really work so I
almost say this clear should really be
here technically meaning when you bind
the peel buffer then that is actually
where you would do this
and so this entry would be a real entry
right the the the render entry begin
peals would actually be a thing that
said what the color was and in that
entry you would store what the color is
that you expected to be clear to for
your peel resolve right you know
whatever you wanted that to be then when
you were done with the peels then it
would resolve the multi sample buffer
resolve it to the main buffer and off
you would go and then you're going to be
targeting the peel buffer directly from
then on right the main buffer I don't
know whatever you want to call that
and that seems fine
so then when you do a render entry full
clear you don't do this targeted next
thing anymore you just clear whatever
buffer you're targeting and that's it
I think
so I think that's right
so we'll see so if that's the case then
what you end up with is inside render
group here where we've got clear I'm
gonna call that something else where did
that go so in here I'm going to call
this push flow clear so we're super
obvious on what gets supposed to be full
clear depth peels gonna get its own one
of these entries now which also has the
clear color in it
that seems about right to me so the end
appeal doesn't have any information in
it but the begin depth field does and
that's I think a better way of looking
at that then we would go up into here
and say that this is a real citizen now
so in here we don't actually need to do
a clear anymore I don't think I think we
just do that and then the clear
functions that we actually have this is
a push flow clear that's going to do the
real clear
I don't know that this actually needs a
flow clear to be honest I don't think
this one uses depth peeling either but
we'll have to look to see what's
happening there exactly so we'll just
leave those as full clearest for now
so when we begin our def peels we need
to know which target it is we need to
know which one we're doing and we want
to know if it equals if it's the last
one right so the first time through it's
at zero and when it gets some extra it
goes to the top so I think all we need
to do here is just say all right look
whatever whichever one were on that's
going to tell us which whether we want
to clear it to nothing because it's the
depth feel or whether we want to clear
it to the background klar so it's the
last one we're gonna do we'll fill in
the background color there right so I
think that's roughly what we want to do
but it looks like we're not quite there
yet we're close
so I think that's a little bit cleaner
about with what's going on but still
yeah okay not quite there yet so let's
go ahead and and finish this off so when
we come through with the peels
I guess the only question I have here is
exactly how these are getting bound so
if we're peeling we use the previous
depth buffer and that seems fine and
that would have been cleared because it
would have gotten bound and when you
enter into the peel it will clear that
peel both the depth and the color right
you can see those two there so my only
question is this this guy doesn't seem
to be actually happening meaning this
clear color pit here assuming we're
tracking it right that should be gray
there and is not at the moment coming
through so this right here
[Music]
perhaps not sitting on peel index
correctly so on peel index will start
out at zero the first time through it
will clear it to all nothing's and go
it'll increment when it gets here
whatever max render target indexes
shouldn't it be depth feel count I'm not
sure why we have two specifications for
that yeah because it's just a depth
field count minus one here which
which doesn't seem logical I mean
basically what we're saying is that this
is the max render target index so we're
saying if the on peel index is less than
the max render target index then we
restore it and jump but if it's not then
we bind it so what's interesting about
that is
for some reason we didn't use it here
but that this is really all we're saying
we're just saying if it's on the maximum
then we should clear to the clear color
because it's the last one we can draw I
don't know why we must just not of like
when we originally doing it we must just
not have replaced it you know so that
seems fine so the other thing I would
say is I don't know if we really want
this other global here I don't like that
that seems busted so we're gonna go
ahead and get rid of it I think and say
look on peel index is just gonna have to
tell you the information that you need
you know I'm saying so basically you
only get one piece of information and
that's on peel index and on peel index
has to give you the information that
you're looking for if you can't get it
from that you don't get it
all right
[Music]
so resolve multisample presumably reads
from all the peel buffers and puts their
results so we're gonna take the frame
buffer we're writing to and we're gonna
put the result in there by reading from
all of the color buffers you know I'm
saying to you so if we look at where
resolve multi-sample is going to when we
do end peels we resolve the multi sample
to the depth peel resolve buffer for
that peel and we do the result mother
sample there and that gives us the final
result that we're gonna composite later
right so it looks like that kind of
educates me as to what our problem was
so because we leave the depth field
buffer is sitting around then it really
does mean that the clear would have to
clear all of them right it can't only
just clear the one of them it's just a
clear depth it's always the same I'm
gonna leave that outside so that when
this gets cleared it will get cleared to
the right values believe this expanded
there
and so that means that the full clear
would actually have to discard the data
that's in all the peeling buffers
unfortunately so when you do see the
full clear yeah it's gonna have to
it's gonna have to do that targeting but
I still think that should be okay so all
right let's keep going here so again
getting a little closer as we clean this
up you can see now I can actually see my
lighting points I'm getting some weird
like flit stalls so you can tell where
it's just a little bit wonky at this
point
and you can also see that the lighting
is actually for the lighting points it
actually looks about right which is
bizarre so it seems as though our main
problem with the lighting is actually in
the correspondence of lights to polygons
at the moment because you can see that
it's not all flickery here but if we
switch back to actually drawing the the
sampling is completely wrong so that's
interesting and that gives us some more
data to work with as well all right so
moving on here when we take a look at
what's happening with our def peels so
this is close to right now but I still
think it's subtly wrong well no you know
what I think this might be fine now
we're clearing the whole thing so when
the composite happens we actually should
be okay cuz the depth buffer and the
color since it's clearing the color to a
1.0 that should not allow anything below
it to show through so I think this is
actually right now I mean right in big
ol quotes there but I'm not sure boobs
I'm not sure what's going on with our
frame rate stutter though something
weird has happened that I'm going to
have to track down it might just be it
looks like when I run it in release mode
we're getting a full frame right here
for the most part so yeah it might just
be the debug situation being ugly but it
might be something look at it in a
second so what this tells me is we're
getting some kind of an anomaly because
if I switch to this mode the lighting
does not appear to be as messed up which
is a little bit weird now I do still see
a lot of flickering out in these regions
so
I'm not sure what to make of that
but you can see the lighting is very
smooth in here and when I flip back it's
all crazy so it feels like we first have
a correspondence bug actually where
we're not corresponding the samples for
the quads with the lights uh or we're
not downloading them right so when we do
like output lighting for example in here
maybe this output lighting textures is
busted with one possibility
another possibility is the things are
writing into the actual push quad are
broken so if we looked at where the
things we're lining up they wouldn't
line up properly so I'm not sure which
of those is happening and we're gonna
have to figure it out right I if we take
a look at what happens here we're just
sending down the full size of it every
frame and we send down the light data in
the light data zero and one arrays so
there's not a lot of weirdness going on
there it's pushed lighting is literally
just doing these two copies right so you
know this is the routine where we get
the information from we get it by
sampling these pointing to cease the the
point sees for the whole set of points
and we're just grabbing it out of the
the solutions that we had there's
nothing else happening in there Jimmy so
it's very straightforward and it seems
like it corresponds with this routine
pretty directly this is just taking the
point P and the emit C and drawing them
[Music]
but you know what you know what we're
not doing here so we aren't properly
handling the Maxum mission range where
is that device program so in the Z bias
program when we do our summation for the
lighting we should be blowing it out
based on how much light is available but
we're not doing that at all
so we definitely have some issues here
in terms of clamping but we do clamp it
here hmm so we're just passing down
points with the emission baked in to
full emission so I guess there isn't a
problem because the light data gets sent
down as floats and processed as floats
so the light data is stored as actual
float values at the moment we don't
actually pack it down so I guess that's
fine so the fact that it's an emission
the emission value gets blown out by the
maxim ition value is actually totally
fine
I was a little bit nervous about that
but looks like that's actually not a
problem at least not that I can think of
at the moment I just want to get a look
at this
push cube function just real quick so
when we take our light index here I want
to make sure that these are getting
correspond properly so we have a count
the count would be for the light index
would be strided here
[Music]
I don't see anything peculiar going on
there
hmm so I'm not sure I don't know what
we're getting in terms of they go
double-check the squad know know what's
going on there
it's like cut light index and that gets
set on here exactly as we would expect
and in here I mean that looks fine to me
so so I don't see what the problem is
and why those wouldn't be corresponding
properly but we definitely know there's
something up because we can see when we
actually output them the other way that
we don't have that problem I'm going to
take a look at output lighting textures
to see what's going on in there Oh
so if I take a quick peek in here I just
want to see some things like oops what
is the solution say for how many points
there are that's the value we would
expect what kind of position does it
think it has kind of color what kind of
direction so we definitely have some
points that don't have very much light
in fact everyone has very very low light
hmm which I'm not sure exactly why that
would be because again we're looking at
them in the other oh man let this run a
little bit
it's just really tiny light values for
the colors in emit c0 and I'm wondering
so if I were to switch to this one would
I suddenly see something different so
what do those same values look like if I
look at them here so
so they definitely don't look all that
unusual I want to try one more thing
because they don't look that different
between the two and yet one
visualization looks okay and the other
one looks wonky I want to try forcing
valid to false so forcing valid to false
would make it so that I always see
exactly what this frame computed and I
never average the previous frame right
that's so weird I have no idea what's
going on here like the lighting samples
for the quads are totally disaggregated
so this has nothing to do with storage
so storage is now out of the question so
the part that we changed is in theory
not actually happening anymore right
we're never looking at what the old
values were we're never taking this
branch we're only ever using the one
where we just directly set the values so
you know whatever omits e0 was and
whatever the direction was that's what
we send out the pipe
it feels like we must not be going over
all of the actual value somehow but I'm
not sure how I let me look so I come in
here to this function I want to see
which point indexes we actually do so
you know I mean that sure does look
correct right
so those are the emission values let's
take a look at the app restriction to
light so these should all be like you
know normal values which they look to be
you know either we didn't get any light
in which case for zero or we did get
light in which case we should be a
normal you know and that looks
reasonable
Oh
so I'm gonna take one more look at this
and then I think the next tack of my
take is to construct a very simple test
case that I can walk all the way through
because I really don't I just can't
guess what the value is I don't have I
don't have a guess I also don't know why
is this gray like why is that gray it's
happening is there a reason why it's
grayed out
that's just like a bug in Visual Studio
it's very strange
I just don't have a good idea here
see this is clearing the emission array
there's our lights
you know what I should probably do
actually let me go ahead and cut this
down to the smallest possible so I just
let's have less things to look at
because this would just be easier to it
actually also increases the framerate
which is nice so we can see so
again that looks pretty correct to me
yeah all right so if I go into the
lighting here and Irene Abel
you know that lighting looks pretty
reasonable I mean it could still be
buggy but it's pretty reasonable so then
to go from that to this when you're
actually drawing the quads I'm
completely at a loss to explain why
that's happening because I can't figure
out any reason why would have that kind
of a change so I think the fact that
it's emit c0 it must be the normals
let's find out by just stuffing the
normals with valid data
that's my only thinking here so let's
suppose we set all the normals to just
be like
so assuming we stuffed these values so
that the D values are all bogus right
then what do we see yeah it's still
garbage
all right let's stuff the color values
you know thought of as well no okay so
I'm just gonna set the color values as
well so the RG and B values are now all
supposed to be the same lovely so if
that's the case I'm gonna now let the D
values let the normals be whatever
they're almost want to be so just want
to see if there's noise there so there's
a tremendous amount of noise in the
normals right that's just garbage so
even if you assume that the color values
are the same every frame the normals are
varying that much which is ridiculous
right I mean that's just absolutely
crazy I mean there's just no chances
this is even remotely correct and I just
have no idea where that complete garbage
is coming from because it feels like
weird looping over the same information
that appears stable would you loop over
it per box here um you end up getting
the exact same stuff we were getting
before but if you actually go through
and output it for a point not so and I
have no explanation for that at all I
have no idea what's going on if that's
pure mystery to me
so I guess the next thing to do is I'm
gonna take a look and see if I have the
color values and the direction values
set here I want to go ahead and set them
somewhere else so if instead of setting
them here let's suppose I set them you
know so this is actually outputting what
it's supposed to output now right it's
it's just doing the same output routine
that it used to do and instead when I go
up here when I actually go to ratify
these points I'm going to actually set
them to I'm going to cold set them here
so I'm gonna set valid to false which
forces me always into this loop and
inside this loop I'm going to set the
values so that they have to be specific
things
so here are those two values that will
be coming out as C and D respectively
and so I'm going to set them to exactly
the same thing as I set them to you
before and now running so I'm basically
just isolating parts of the pipeline
here so what we write here does actually
come out if I was to flip this around
now I should see it shift over to blue
lighting and it does right so that seems
totally fair so the noise is definitely
coming upstream somehow meaning that the
actual information we're getting out
here somehow and this doesn't make any
sense because output lighting points is
reading from the same information so I
have no idea how it's possible I mean I
guess the thing is
am i like not rendering some of the
points my only right now like a subset
of the points I don't thinks I'm think
I'm rendering all of them I should be
able to see the noise in here
you know we're not drawing D so D does
not get drawn when we push this quad on
but you know D is not the only thing
that was problematic so if I don't stuff
the colors let's see let's see if it is
only D if I let the colors come through
however they want yeah it's still
complete garbage so how is it possible
that switching to here yeah I just don't
understand
those two things quote should coincide
and they do not coincide at all right
they are completely fictitious and
furthermore if we cranked up the
smoothing on that particular like so
let's say I blur it instead of over ten
frames I've lured over a hundred frames
so it's very blurry right this change is
not at all so it appears to just again
be just random values that it's getting
this one should be much smoother well
you know it's not oh wait no that's
because I've I'm not actually doing
smoothing this one is now about test
so I guess what I would say here is that
still seems wrong so there is more to it
than I'm making it appear because if it
was really smoothing over a hundred
frames here we would have a pretty
significant difference there
I guess the possible explanation is that
because of the directionality thing I
mean one way I could do it is say let's
suppose the direction is always set to
true I'm sorry fouled right so true so
it forces the blend case does that
remove the noise yeah it does so you can
see that this is perfectly smooth here
blended over a hundred frames so it
doesn't even really change for quite
some time right the frame lag on the
lighting change is massive and all the
lighting values are very smooth I switch
to here and they're complete nonsense so
what's going on right like what is
happening here again let's do the same
thing we did before let's stuff the
values
so assuming that I stuffed the values
that we're gonna send down the lighting
pipeline like so if I just take average
direction out of the equation by saying
alright let's just look at the emit
color by itself so we're vaping the the
average direction to light is just gone
it's always set to point upward and you
can see that just even the emit colors
are garbage
right they're totally wrong so I guess
now what I want to see is I want to see
this quad I want to see those those quad
indices I like what's going on right so
I'm gonna actually take a look inside
push quad because it's the only place I
can think of now to start to figure out
how is it possible that apparently the
data that looks absolutely fine is
somehow not nonetheless ending up
completely bogus and I have no idea how
right so let's go ahead in there to the
place where we actually push it and see
what we're pushing so these vertices as
they come out
I'm just going to look at what they are
all right there's one for every quad
these should all be the same because
like I said right now in fact we even
have to do on there it's like these
don't need to be per vertex they can
actually be primitive which we can do
later to just reduce the bandwidth so if
I take a look and I step through here
the light captured Olli as before and it
is and the indices should just climb up
nice and smooth like they are
so this should this is probably just the
sprite which has no light indices on it
and I yes a push rect
there's only push cubes have this and
this saw I mean it just looks totally
fine nothing out of the ordinary is
happening so that all seems reasonable
right and if we look at I guess I should
look at a subsequent frame as well like
are those values correct through here
this is all pushed bitmap unfortunately
let's look at push cube now so here we
are in push cube
I mean again all exactly what you would
suspect nothing weird is happening here
that I can see anyway
come into the lighting group 77 boxes
1,800 points
again everything just looks totally
clean here 1 2 1 2 45 so again that just
that just seems like totally fine
nothing bizarre happening right I see
what we get to by the end here oh come
on I hate that aspect of visual studio
studio how it can't show you variables
that were in the previous scope it's so
busted
you used to do it used to be able to
want this
so you know if I run this for a while I
should see this crawl up towards the
full value
and it totally does right so that all
seems pretty good I come through here
and we have average selection to light
getting zeroed out right could double
checked if that's plausible
here's that restriction to light and it
is exactly what you expect so that all
seems totally fine then we go through
the seventy seven boxes again each one
of them should have twenty-four
that all seems fine
it's just some basic stats there and
then we go to output lighting textures
we go through all the points again
and again that all seems really
straightforward
you gotta take a look at what these
these eyes look like
those look pretty reasonable cuz they
should mirror and they appear too
and then for the for the Z values there
I'm sorry the W values there those
should always be stuffed with just the
DX value which we took out of the
equation by setting with so it should
always be stuffed to 0 right because we
we are stuffing it here so we don't even
have to pay attention to that one it's
not even it's not relevant so that that
seems like it's the right point
information light data one which should
be the color values here let me go ahead
and take a look at what the emit c0 is
we should emit c0
I mean that all looks right to me
so these are the same so we're sending
down exactly the same packed values that
we're supposed to be sending down as far
as I can tell the color is positions and
the things all get packed in there
properly so the question is just how is
it possible that this routine gets the
right values and our routine doesn't how
does this routine manage to get proper
values and the other routine doesn't I
I'm so confused right now because this
routine I mean it loops over the boxes
so it is slightly different in that
sense but I have no idea how that could
ever actually affect it I could make the
other routine loop over boxes just to
validate that fact
I mean and the other thing we do here is
we clamp and we're not clamping here so
I mean I could see if this was a
clamping oriented thing but we clamp
inside the shader
so unless we messed up the clamping
inside the shader I'm not sure how that
even that wouldn't have an effect I
don't think so if I were to do something
where I said okay C equals the clamp of
C right yeah I don't think that should
actually have any effect at all on what
we're seeing yeah it doesn't so it's not
a clamping problem right we're not
getting something where the clamping is
is the primary is the primary problem
there what we're seeing is something
else and I don't know what that's
something else even is so this doesn't
appear to be a problem
it still looks totally fine so if I was
to do this the other way round again for
absolutely no reason whatsoever if I
just purely decided if I just decided to
make this do the loop the other way
around
like so and I will say that Shh
shouldn't really be commands light box
count that's a bit of a cheating move
there but that's okay for now I suppose
so here's us out putting these in
literally the exact same loop is the one
that works so we have one that outputs
them and works in one after that it's
exactly the same loop so again
completely identical here only
you know we've changed the loop
structure okay so continuing this
absolute absurdity what if I was to just
take the other routine so this is you
know we'll just leave this this is how
it's supposed to work and as far as we
know it should work so this is probably
correct and we've got a book somewhere
else if I was to take out put lighting
points which at this point I know works
properly in terms of outputting the
colors let's just have it out put the
colors right so this is what it draws
and it is drawing it properly
if we go back and look at how that's
working you can see that the only
difference here is you know we push the
full clear on so you know if I didn't
push the full clear on and I just let it
do its thing you can see that in this
scenario right I you have to look at
both things on top of each other but it
appears to me I can even still say even
with all that noise it's correct it's
still the same thing it was drawing so
the full clear really has nothing to do
with it
it's just output lighting points works
and output lighting textures doesn't
work so what if I just go ahead and
loan output lighting points into making
it be output letting textures right so
what if I literally take this thing
right here and instead of having it do
push quads what if I just get rid of the
full Clare okay and instead of doing a
push quad I'm just going to do this
operation so we literally take exactly
the operation we were doing here exactly
the same things that we're pushing on
okay so we got this front of it here so
I'm going to take the C and I'm gonna
make that be equal to the front of it
that's what we were using I'm gonna take
the p value and use that as is I don't
care about the D value because we're
stuffing that anyway but let's go ahead
and and and use that it's fine doesn't
matter and I'm gonna actually just stuff
those values you know directly in there
because I've got them there the lighting
textures thing here so I'm gonna set
that to dest and now we are actually
outputting the lighting value from here
and then I'm going to take the call at
the end and do the actual push lighting
just like the other one did so now the
exact same routine that we were using to
get correct results with rendering I'm
gonna use so here is the version that's
running through the old one here is the
version that's running through the new
one and there's absolutely no difference
between them right so something is super
messed up with our sampling with our
pulling from these values I mean I don't
see any way I could be making a mistake
up here now because it's literally doing
the exact same operation and if I
draw these directly I know that they're
correct I can see that they're correct
values so unless I'm really nuts and I'm
just missing some really obvious thing
that's going on here
this is gotta work right because if I
flip this to an if one if I just toggle
that right then all of a sudden when I
draw this thing it's right you know when
I draw these values they're right and
yet instead like those are the values
that should be interpolated right there
instead I just get garbage like complete
nonsense happening so where is the
nonsense coming from why am I getting
just just garbage there right why am I
getting totally arbitrary interpolation
happening what did we change you know
and this has been happening the entire
time so this has nothing to do with the
clear change nothing to do with any of
those this has been happening since we
made the initial modification at all
this has been happening so inside our
sunlight call or something you know this
is just working wrong and I have no idea
why the fragment light values that come
in here where we sample them off of our
two lighting textures that we're sending
down those are busted somehow so let's
take a look at what's happening one
thing we did change is way back when
when we set the render commands up right
these things here I you know that that
was something we changed and I don't
know whether that had anything to do
with it
I don't think there's any data from
there that we actually send down but
let's make sure
so those lighting texture informations
that we send down those come from the
from these right here this lighting
textures value and that's it's coming
from right here so these test textures
it's just a buffer we use it gets sent
down to the render system it picks it up
later when it when it wants to right
that's all that happens so in the OpenGL
layer we have those pieces of letting
information and they get sent down and
transferred
you know I guess one thing that's a
little bit odd there is that actually
gets sent down after the first time we
render is that that's just a that's one
frame lagged isn't it which is kind of a
separate problem I don't think that has
anything to do with the bud we're seeing
but it's worth noting that that should
really be queued for transfer prior to
the
prior to the actual drawing that occurs
meaning this is really in the wrong
place
technically it should be pushed before
everything else happens and you know if
we were to look at that I guess the way
I'd say it is you know that that call if
we're going to be honest with ourselves
this push lighting here should really
not be happening here at all the push
lighting call should actually be
occurring like at the head end right so
when it actually goes to start working
with this stuff and we enable the
lighting it should really push the
lighting at that point right it go right
because the Stu source is right and then
we fill them in later so that's that's
actually that's actually how that should
be working in order to not have a frame
of lag
again that should not really change that
okay well I am happy that I fixed the
problem I am NOT happy because that
should not have fixed the problem
those arrays should have been stable so
when we transfer them should have just
resulted in a frame of lag it should not
have changed what we're actually seeing
so I'm not gonna consider this okay yet
that's a happy accident I guess but
something is still wrong here and we
have to go figure out why that did that
because we must that would imply that
we're actually corrupting those arrays
or something at some point in the render
process so that the lighting information
got destroyed
but why like where is that happening so
we have to go we're not done yet
unfortunately we we found a bug we fixed
that bug it's there's still another bug
in here and it just happens that the
fact that we're sending them late was
exposing this other bug and sending them
the having them push at the right time
make us so that they aren't but that's
not really sufficient so let's push
forward and find out what the bug
actually was before I do that that I'm
going to clean out the stuff that was
happening here
because we don't care about this now
so let's see if this works properly now
with everything running as it normally
does so not quite so this valid part
still seems to be problematic for us and
you know that makes a little bit of
sense because it may be that since not
everyone gets light every frame we can't
really use that fact directly but here
is the lighting as it is you know
supposed to be running obviously and if
we see that at actual frame rate
you know we're in reasonable shape here
right that looks like the lighting used
to look for the most part
so the question here is why is it that
those light values get corrupted on the
round trip what was happening there
those late values should never be
touched by anyone right
[Music]
I just don't see where that was coming
from so if
all right that is definitely an owl of
shame right there oh man that was brutal
so hopefully everyone realized it at the
same time I did now that we had the
happy accident of figuring out that it
was because of a frame of lag so now I
know exactly what's happening and that
is pretty baller so what was happening
is that originally and maybe I should
draw this out on the blackboard but I'm
just gonna assume that everyone kind of
sees it now but we'll go to the Q&amp;A and
if anyone wants me to draw it out in the
blackboard I'll draw it on that
blackboard so what happened is
originally we were just assigning IDs
persistently so that when something got
a light index assigned that light index
was assigned the same every frame so the
fact that we were sending down the light
data from this frame for use on the next
frame was fine
because all of the quads were going to
use the same light indices as they would
have had the previous frame because
remember we were persisting the light
indices when we switched from persisting
light indices to persisting light values
it means that every quad potentially
gets a different light index every frame
because it doesn't matter what index is
assigned they just get assigned linearly
in the order they're pushed so now
sending the light data from a frame
behind right so using the light data
from the previous frame is wrong because
all of the quads are looking at
different light index positions as to
what they were assigned this frame
because what they were assigned last
frame is not what they were assigned
this frame or go they pick up lighting
from some totally unrelated quad
I don't know if you guys remember this
but we've talked about this before and
occasion some time people have asked me
what are the hardest bugs
I believe you can probably go back to
the archives and find me saying
something literally that in this index
is not lining up is one of the biggest
bugs that you have it take a long time
to find because it's hard to look at
them and debug them properly well ladies
and gentleman guess what that was
literally like an hour of debugging time
trying to nail that down right if you
take out the time that I went and
decided to fix the clearing stuff
because I wanted that to be fixed and
just look at the other part of it well
there you go all right so let's go ahead
and go to the QA we still got more
lighting work to do but we're we're over
time now
on topic questions please so on the
stuff we're doing today
let's see here
perhaps the perspective the game would
make this a bit awkward to do but are
you planning to have water in the game
with reflections since waves and shaders
and all that cool stuff or sine waves
and shaders and uncle stuff no I don't
think we would be doing that I haven't
thought about it too much but I do think
that you're kind of hitting the nail on
the head there that spending a lot of
time implanting reflections would
probably be wasted because it's a lot of
work to make reflections work properly
in a game you know there's a lot of sort
of additional rendering work you have to
do to kind of get that you have to
render from different direction and map
that directional render on to services
and so on so forth I and so for a game
like this that's top-down where it would
mostly be water reflecting up at us I
just don't think it's gonna be worth it
so we probably wouldn't do that unless
there's some other thing that we
encounter along the way that makes that
more sensible Oh pith no said blackboard
please so I'm going to draw it on the
blackboard so here's what was happening
before and then I'll show you why it
broke so previously what was happening
is we've got light results okay that's
light data zero light data one that's
what gets passed down to the renderer
and used so all of the fussing that we
do with ray casting and all that stuff
obviously all of that is just to produce
a single block of data and well in our
case we keep it in two separate blocks
but it doesn't matter they could be
contiguous in just one blob of data that
says the position color and direction of
the lighting information that we're
going to use to render the scene once we
actually go to make pixels on this
right so all of that lighting result
data is the thing that we actually need
to compute and how we compute it is
largely irrelevant for purposes of the
render the render just knows somebody
figured this out and now we're going to
use it right so what we need it is quads
out in the world that need to get
rendered have light points on them that
have to map into this buffer right so
each point on the quad that we're going
to sample lighting from because remember
any point in the quad we draw from a
bunch of sample points to figure out
what its color should be so when we draw
from these sample points to figure out
what color is we're looking into these
light results and the way that we're
doing that is by an index so there's
literally a value that comes with the
CLOB that says hey I've got four points
and they start at point 37 or something
right if this is light 37 so the shader
goes in and looks and goes okay from
point 37 I got to do for life so 37 38
39 and 40 I'm gonna look at and that's
what we've got okay very straightforward
at that point not a lot of weirdness
there that's just all of it happens now
our bug comes from the fact that this
particular piece of information the
index has to get assigned from somewhere
and in the old way what was happening is
that somewhere was getting assigned
stabili so every time you did a push
cube it was having a light index storage
value right that was persisting across
those pushes that said where it was so
on frame 0 this quad got these lighting
values on frame 1 it got these lighting
values again on frame 2 it got these
lighting values again the index was the
thing that persisted now the problem is
we know this was only going to be a
temporary solution without more work
because once we start moving around the
world we knew that we would have to
assign those indices dynamic dynamically
because there's only a certain amount of
room in our light result buffer
and so if there's a million entities in
the world we can only store you know ten
thousand of them or eight thousand of
them or something I don't know how many
we're gonna end up keeping in our local
light result buffer just in terms of
processing power wise and storage wise
and all that sort of stuff right so what
has to happen is those light indices had
to get allocated dynamically so that
when Andy came out of the lighting
solution it wasn't needing to be
computed lighting wise anymore it
wouldn't take up space
in the lighting solution however what I
realized was the better way to do that
would be just to store the light results
themselves back in the entity so that
led to the new way of doing things which
was instead of preserving this light
index we would just say oh okay at the
start of the frame let's go into the
entity now and grab the block of results
out of the entity place that into
wherever we want
so as we're just rendering we just go
through in any as we encounter entities
we just sort of push them on so they
just kind of get pushed on in any order
we want as we render grab the block of
results place it in here before I'm the
lighting computation and then when we're
done we'll write it back to the entity
so now we don't have to worry about
latencies anymore the light in the sees
of a quad or just arbitrary every frame
they change and we just know that the
results themselves are mapped back into
the correct position right and we wrote
this perfectly the first time we did it
right but there was a bug the bug was
that when we were rendering frames zero
one two three four five six what was
actually happening was that on this
frame we would compute light results
we'll call those are we were cute light
results and then we would use the light
results in our actual rendering from the
previous frame that means on frame zero
the lighting was garbage we just
couldn't see it because there was
nothing on frame zero then on frame one
what we would do is we would pass by now
we would get the lighting in
from the previous frame we would compute
a new lighting information right and
then we would render with the previous
frames lighting information right
previous previous so every frame we were
rendering with the previous frames
lighting information that was because we
pushed lighting on at the end of the
frame and that means that when it would
read through the render buffer to
execute all of the commands he had
already executed all of our render
commands before ever updating the
lighting textures so the fix or I
shouldn't let me describe the exact bug
first so the bug is that hey the
lighting indices aren't stable anymore
it's the results that we're preserving
not the indices so now using the
previous frame doesn't work
none of the indices line up all of the
entities quads have moved where they're
looking in the light buffer so they're
not looking in the same place they were
in the previous frame that just led to
completely random lighting results it
was grabbing lights from all kinds of
random places that had nothing to do
with where the lighting for this entity
was actually stored on this frame so the
only thing we added to fix it was to
stop doing this actually push down the
light information we want to use on this
frame on this frame and everything's
fixed does that make sense
what time of the free scene we're not
doing a hand made here tomorrow we're
off tomorrow sorry so it would be next
week usually the pre stream starts
around 10 minutes prior to noon
something like that with all of us so we
have to call the push lighting twice for
a solution or there is another cell
no we don't to call it twice all we have
to do is we just have to push at the
beginning of the frame so remember the
the rendering command buffer is just a
buffer of things to do so we can just
push the command that says update the
lighting textures as the very first
command which is what we do now and even
though we haven't filled in the lighting
information yet that's okay because all
we're doing is pushing the pointers on
that say where to grab it from then
we're doing all of the other pushes
computing the lighting and then we're
issuing that whole render command buffer
out to the renderer so we don't have to
do anything at all to fix the bug other
than just move the push call at the
beginning that's it we don't have to
change anything
so it's just fixed now it's it's correct
there's nothing there's nothing else
that has to happen right that's just
that's just what's going on right so
yeah no other no other changes are
actually necessary there and if we go
back and look at how we have this before
really this is the only part now that we
have to fix which is the fact that
there's a lot of people who don't get
lighting on a particular frame and so
that has to be fixed because we can't
use those directional values anymore as
as indication that you don't have
lighting
the seltzer I know you said it's a
common class of bug but do you have any
thoughts on how you might avoid a bug
like this in the future
not really so the the only thing I know
of that catches bugs like this and makes
them easier to debug was a program that
I wrote at rad game tools called
mustache which is designed to figure out
complex problems like this
unfortunately no debugger that I know of
has this capability so until a program
like that becomes more standard ly
integrated into debugging I don't know
that there is another way to if I knew
of a better way to keep bugs like this
from happening I wouldn't I would have
done it but the bottom line is sometimes
when you're doing finicky stuff like
this you just have a situation where you
can't avoid having indices like this you
know and you try to keep it to a minimum
you know I don't go introducing
indirection willy-nilly in fact I try to
keep things as direct as possible for
this very reason the more indirection
you have the more places there are for
those in directions to be wrong right so
it's definitely the case that you know
in general what I'm programming I am
actively trying to eliminate the places
where you can have the kind of bugs I
don't always know of or there may not
always exist a methodology for a
particular class of problems that can
get away with you know no indices or no
no sort of frame lag no you know and so
you tend to see this kind of thing
happen in complex rendering situations
like lighting where you're doing a lot
of what's the word I'm looking for where
you're doing sort of a lot of complex
frame to frame correspondence and a lot
of things that are using you know in the
C's and that's where stuff you end up in
situations where it's not a lot you can
really do about it you're gonna have
these bugs and you just gotta grin and
bear it
or grin and bear it or whatever that
phrase is
Val Basu this frame latency is bad if we
would make this a multi thread system
nope really there's no we're not doing
frame latency weird we're doing it on
the same frame are you allowed to
elaborate more on how moustache works
exactly I don't know
so you can't use the fourth lines of
light and on the sixth line the light
stops I'm not sure and storm bus I don't
understand the question can you
elaborate on that maybe I should go in
and while we're at it fix that
there we go so now we can look at our
lighting solution which I wanted to make
sure was still possible to do okay is
that it for the questions do we have any
question on the lighting
because what are the performance on that
well the big level is still problematic
performance wise I mean we we need to do
we were in the middle of optimizing the
lighting so we we still have a lot of
work to do before we're finished with
that optimization so if we let it create
a larger level it appears like the
lighting is fast enough now but it's not
actually because if you move to
someplace where more of stuff like more
screens are kind of in that visible set
you can see that the light the framerate
gets gets bad right so you know you can
kind of see the subset of the region for
its getting computed so this this white
area here is outside the lighting
computation boundary and this stuff is
inside the lighting computation boundary
so you can see what's getting lit and
what's not and you know like I said the
lighting is getting there we have to go
in and start the world-building process
which is what we'll do right after
lighting and then when points are
distributed more evenly across these
pieces then I think we'll get a much
better quality of lighting as well
because right now we're not distributing
our lighting points in a sane way to you
know these I think we can get rid of
these seams for example in a number of
ways and so on but so you know it's it's
definitely getting there it's just we've
got to get the speed up and there's a
lot of ways we could do that and so
we're gonna we're gonna take a look at a
couple more things but that's that's
really where we're at at the moment
Irma's can you implement more light
sources later I will actually start with
will you add toe mapping at some point
probably not tone mapping I wouldn't
success expect we may put a bloom filter
in them storm blasts can you implement
more light sources later like holding a
torch or other sources like actually
right now that is already happening so
you can add as many light source as you
want in fact the little guys are all
holding lights right now that are
getting fully computed you can actually
see that they're getting their full the
full treatment you know you can see for
example over here where there's a
ceiling you can see the lighting
reflecting off the ceiling of those
little guys moving around you can see
them lighting up this red wall etc etc
right so those are low low held light
sources that's why they don't have as
much range on the ground as this guy
because this guy's up higher as you move
the light source up higher it gets a
bigger spread right so yeah we already
have as many you can throw as many
lights in as you want this solution
doesn't have a fixed number of lights
you can have arbitrary number of lights
and we'll be playing with that later
[Music]
not exactly on topic but you don't use
your attempt in the for-loop in split
box oh we didn't really get a chance to
finish debugging that or really even
that that code is pretty primitive right
now we don't even draw it so when you
say we don't use the attempt what do you
mean is it just do you mean we just
don't break out of it properly
oh I see what you're saying yeah yeah
you're right
so this dim index should actually be
cycled right and it's not because next
dim index isn't updated so I think
that's actually what should be happening
right is that what you meant
I'm not sure if that's what you meant or
not I don't think we'll really see much
in the way of results from that but you
know some kind of weird oh you know what
that is so the lighting bounds probably
should be based on the camera as well
and right now they're not so that's a
little bit of a bug too right
Jackson Bannon what's there still
between a game without OpenGL and with
OpenGL so right now we have not updated
the old render path to be the new render
style so we can't really address that
yet that'll be later all right
otherwise you useless loop yes okay so
good that is what you meant there so I
think that's all that we really need to
do to take that into account this
routine is still kind of garbage we have
to go through and actually draw our our
hierarchy so have you tried the clang
compiler on Windows the versions of the
last three months I been I use clang on
Linux and Mac I have not tried the
Windows version in quite some time the
last time I tried it it wasn't really
there yet supposedly they've got it
putting PDP's now but I don't know I I
figured there's no rush to using it so
at some point I'll probably switch but
that's probably be after my current
rounded project because I don't have any
huge problems with a visual so you can
power at the moment I still use 2012 so
next time instead of updating to a new
visual studio compiler I'll probably
update to clang assuming that no one
says it's like busted on Windows
assuming it's you know working okay and
the ppb's work and stuff so cuz yeah it
would be nice to switch to clang because
then you could always be on clang
because almost everything you ever
compiled on would be on clang at that
point Linux Mac and Windows would all be
on playing and I assume I don't remember
what PlayStation 4 was using but I'm
assuming PlayStation 4 used clang
because I'm not sure what else it would
have used could have still use canoe I
guess I'm not sure but at that point I
think the only thing you would have to
use Visual Studio for would be like Xbox
maybe because Android ops uses claying
iOS uses clang Matt Goss uses clang
Linux uses clang so Windows is the only
place you still use Visual Studio so if
you switch that to clang you could be
clang everywhere and the only place you
might have to use something other than
clang would be like Xbox because I
assume I've never done any Xbox one
development but I assume that the Xbox
one
is currently using visual Studios
toolchain but I don't know and yeah I
see your point specifically I do agree
the clang compiler gives much better
error messages especially if you're
someone who's like a doing you know sort
of more C++ heavy stuff which I don't
really like but if you're the kind of
person who uses like templates and stuff
all over the place you know the template
error messages in Visual Studio have
historically been quite bad and it makes
it pretty hard to do to debug template
code errors
whereas clang does a much better job
from what I remember anyway in code
bases that are like template happy of
actually giving you actionable error
messages instead of going okay that
really didn't tell me what I need to
know I got to kind of guess myself about
what happened wrong in the template
expansions you know clang if I remember
correctly was pretty good about saying
here is where in the template stream of
things stuff went wrong and that was
nice so all right I'm gonna go close it
down
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for the episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with the series at home you could always
pre-order the game on hand my hero org
and it comes with the source code that
you can use to play around with yourself
and experiment we also have a schedule
bot you can use if you want to know when
we're going to be live in that was a
question today the schedule bot will
tell you it opposed to schedule there is
a bit of a snafu with I'm updating the
Molly Rocket websites this month rolling
them over to all-new systems and stuff
and they're kind of going on to a CDN
which means that the place where these
tools get their information from as far
as the schedule is a little wonky so the
schedule bot is always up to date but
the information on some of the other
utilities like in sohbat i think on the
web and also this little guy here are
currently perhaps a little bit iffy so
that will be getting straightened out
but if you're wondering why there's been
some issues with that it's because
there's going to be a web migration and
some of the things cannot be done the
way that they used to be so i will be
working with people like the folks who
maintain and sohbat and so on to make
sure that they can get stuff from the
correct new locations but until then
schedule bot is the place to look if you
want to know what schedule is alright
we'll be back next week there is no
hand-made here tomorrow it's a day off
we'll be back next week when we can
resume our letting actualization and
we'll be playing around with that
spatial hierarchy and the update loop to
try and get to something nice and fast
and we'll also be probably introducing
our sky lighting into there as well so
we've got some work to do that'll be fun
and we'll be able to improve the
lighting quality but I think as well so
that'll be good that's it for this week
until next week have fun programming and
I'll see everyone on the Internet take
it easy everybody