hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream the live astons
streamis that one can possibly be when
one is live on stream look I'm not gonna
I'm not gonna lie to you we've you know
we've got we've got some serious entity
work to do we did a bunch of cool stuff
to our entity system but now's the time
to start you know start getting real in
there start start you know facing up to
it to the hard life the hard reality
reality is the harsh realities of life
is an entity and I'd like to dive right
into it so today is day 281 I think
we've got that right is that right let's
double check if today is in fact a to 81
to 79 oh well looks like the episode
guide may be missing a day let's double
check from the YouTube and made archive
you know what is it youtube.com slash
user hammer here because such great
vanity URLs from YouTube right they
nailed it but yeah day two eighty so
stay to 81 here we reset see try that's
the only reason that I'm wanted to
double-check that so day two 81 is what
we're on you want to unpack day two 80s
source code if you want to follow along
with what I'm doing that's what I'm
starting with and if I remember
correctly we ended yesterday on a slight
bug I wanted to look at I probably will
look at it now and that's just a glitch
we reimplemented basically room based
movement it would reimplemented strong
term we basically just turned it back on
again and so what I wanted to do was
take a look at exactly how this
transition was working when I come up
here there's some kind of I believe a
glitch where I see for a split second I
felt like I was seeing yeah I still am I
see a flash it's like an instant flash
of this of a different screen
and and it's like I don't know how it's
getting that but it's obvious to me or
at least it seems relatively clear to me
that the camera update takes two frames
to work properly you might not be able
to see that because of the twitch you
know it's your compress you're getting a
compressed video stream and it probably
throws that frame out entirely but
you'll just have to trust me it's there
I know that it's there and let's go
ahead and yeah come on come on mr.
potato there we go
and so I just want to take a look at
that logic it's not like it's the final
logics that's gonna be used in the game
at all but I want to make sure that
there isn't something deeper going on
because we were just sort of finishing
up how this code was going to work and
we don't want to have some stuff in
there that we don't understand right
like I don't want there to be something
weird happening and I don't understand
what it is if it's just something like
Sogo we got to write the final camera
code later and it'll be different that's
fine but I don't want there to be a
glitch that's happening for some other
reason and so I want that's why I'm
interested in investigating this
particular thing so here we go with our
camera movement you can see here when we
do NCM we do unpacks into the into the
buffer here
I'm sorry pax into the buffer where we
do a sort of all of our entity right out
and before we do anything else you can
see here we before we pack the entity
into the permanent storage we go through
and we update the camera if this happens
to be the entity that the cameras
following right now why we check every
time I don't know that's not a
particularly interesting thing to do we
could just check outside this loop and
that's probably smarter I'm gonna leave
it in there though because the whole
point is to investigate this bug so I
don't want to start touching things
until I actually know what's going on so
I'm gonna take a look inside here we're
gonna say all right we've got this
entity we know that this is the one we
are following we have not touched the
entity yet right there's been no editing
of the entity code yet so we dropped
through here and we say okay let's
process this thing you can see that
we've got this global render
camera room base that's what's actually
happening here if you turn that off you
go into scrolling mode and I guess I
should mention we haven't tested that
scrolling mode I probably want to delete
it because there's never gonna be a
scrolling mode in this game it is not
something that actually is allowed but
if I wanted to yeah so it looks like
that still works just fine it can track
the player exactly and nothing weird
happens there it's kind of kind of
nauseating I don't think we would want
it to follow the jumping like that but
it's kind of funny that it does to say
the least anyway so that's clearly
working fine so the only thing that's
not working is that update that's based
on the room location and so what I'm
guessing is that this particular this
information here is really what the
problem is so if we take a look at
what's going on we can see here that
we're testing the entity's displacement
from the sim region center right because
the sim Region center is of course with
the cameras we're testing the
displacement from the sim region center
and we're seeing whether it's more than
nine in the x-direction or more than
five in the y-direction and if it is
we're just placing it now I could pretty
much tell you what the bug is already
because I'm just looking here it's like
that's the bug right for some reason
there's still a value of x displacement
being stuck in there and what's kind of
interesting is this is sort of a
feedback based operation what's amusing
is it's self-corrected right so you can
see what happens is it displaces the
camera 18 units to the right and then 10
units upward and so effectively what was
happening when we were moving out side
there
here's day 281 effectively what was
happening is here's the camera this is
what we're looking at we hop off the
edge it detects that okay it hits this
case which is we're greater than five
units off of
the center line right so then it says
well I'd better displace this thing 18
and 10 is the de placement it uses so
it's basically putting the camera like
over here somewhere now that's the 18 is
what we would normally displace for the
whole sideways motion so it's basically
doing this I don't really know how far
we move it sideways if it's one whole
screen whatever it is that's what we're
doing effectively so the camera moves
here and then what happens is and we see
one frame with it there but then the
very next frame it goes oh hey guess
what that entity we're gonna check its
location again and it sees that it's
more than negative nine off it's it's
more than nine units this way right so
then it goes oh I'd better apply that
displacement which is this which
subtracts the 18 back off again right so
we effectively do this
to get there so just the way that we
happen to write the routine
self-corrected which i guess is good but
that's definitely a bug obviously we
only want to displace the camera in the
direction we're trying to go and not in
some other direction that's kind of
self-evident so now when I hop off I'm
expecting something cleaner and I got
something cleaner we're no longer really
locked to the size of a screen it looks
like so we should probably take some
time to get that looking a little bit
more correct and the other thing that I
would like to do is I think I would like
to have a more stable idea of what's
supposed to happen for the camera in
terms of interpolation because what we'd
probably like to do is even though I
don't want any smooth scrolling in the
game like I was saying it would be nice
to do a smooth transition between them
so even though you're locked to this
view while this little fellow is hopping
around when you go through here even the
8-bit Legend of Zelda it like that Peppa
Peppa you know it kind of like
transitioned the screen in sense we've
got plenty of horsepower it seems like
it would be nice to give the user a nice
animated transition between those and
and and so I think that's what we'll
play around with today like obviously we
fix that very simple bug but you know
maybe now's a good time look at that
camera code and actually make something
real I also think that now hopefully we
shouldn't have any bugs with
with any of the camera motion like and
so we can hit up against these and we
don't get any bugs and so that's nice
we're nice and stable here and that's
good so I'm pretty happy about that and
we're starting to things are starting to
shape up here for our actual game code
which is nice because we're gonna start
dropping a bunch of logic in there and
you know enemies and fighting and stuff
like this we don't want to be in a bad
situation oh that's interesting Wow Wow
so because our room thing happens to
just be like sort of weird and buggy
right now and just makes random stuff I
guess you can have those points occur
further away and so then you can like oh
that's great because remember I said I
wanted to make it so it's not on a fixed
grid well it happened to create a longer
hop and he hops it how cool is that
that's just great I love it ha that's
hilarious okay well um yeah so can we
just full-on abuse this system that's so
cool
I guess those we shouldn't have put
hopital squares where the trees are but
that's kind of funny right because we
don't do any collision section on the
body now remember we assume that
anywhere that there's a hobble right now
it actually lets it go through there's a
bunch of work we're gonna do on that
later so that's that's like a separate
issue but that's just kind of funny yeah
oh that's so cool
sorry this is what happens when you
start making games is you find little
things that your think are funny and you
play with them what can you do alright
enough of that sorry to waste your time
there
so anyway point being what I'd like to
do is start looking at how we could have
a more solid notion of where the cameras
should be looking and then you know I'd
like to make some sort of an idea of how
it's going to interpolate back and forth
that's that would be my preference so I
think what I'd like to do is I'd like to
introduce a more stable notion of that
size of the screen and when we're
what we're gonna do is we're gonna test
more stable e where we are in that
that's in that sort of screen boundary
and then do some interesting things with
it I think that's the best way to go so
let me pop over to the whiteboard for a
second here and just talk about you know
camera control and some things that we
want to think about when we're doing
camera controls okay so the first thing
that I want to explain or maybe the
really one of the only things that I
want to explain that's sort of a new
concept to us that we haven't talked
about very much is the concept of
hysteresis and I don't know how to spell
hysteresis any more than you do so let's
just say that it's hysteresis I don't
know like that maybe I have no idea how
to spell that word there we go we were
close we just missed the eye right
and hysteresis is kind of an important
concept especially with cameras there
are other situations where it's
important to understand what that means
and why you should care but camera
controls are probably the most important
because camera controls are the things
or rather how your game deals with a
camera especially in 3d but also in 2d
basically no matter what hysteresis sort
of is a concept that comes into play in
a lot of ways and so let's talk about
what that means and why we should care
all right so camera control is sort of
the person's perception of where they
are to a large extent right because
remember when you put VR goggles on or
something like if you're wearing an HTC
vive or something then your point of
view of the world is controlled by you
in a natural way right look I've moved
my head around and it knows where I'm
looking and all these are the sorts of
things and so there's no real disconnect
between the person and the point of view
but in a game where we're talking about
a monitor right and you're and you're
sort of presenting this view of the
world through that monitor and the
person's movement of their head and how
they look is disconnected from what's
actually going on the screen you
essentially have a perception problem
right you sort of have like a perception
almost like a perception grammar you
might even say that's going on when you
look through this monitor so I look at
the monitor you know when I see some
things around in the monitor or whatever
you know when I see them moving in
certain directions and I know because
I'm a video game player and I've been
conditioned for a long time to
understand what I've seen the screen I
know a bunch of things when handmade
hero comes up it's not like oh my god
what's going on I don't understand it's
like no I immediately see oh this looks
orthographic I can see by the way like
the trees are in the ground and even
though we don't even have the final art
in there you're still already like I
just get it right I can move my guy
around and whatever whatever right and
so what you have to remember is even
though you probably know all this stuff
and so do the gamers and everything else
just because we all take it for granted
doesn't mean it's not still there so
there's constantly this sort of thing
that's happening where you've kind of
got you let me give you a little bit of
hair just a tiny bit of hair there
you've got you and you're looking at the
screen right and then you've got your
hand on the on the mouse or the keyboard
or whatever right and you're doing stuff
this sort of arc that goes through where
you're like seeing something making
decisions going through there's a huge
amount of perception that's going on
there there's all of these sort of
things that you're doing in your brain
to allow you to be able to play this
game and the camera because it is out of
your control right it's moving around
not in the way your head moves but
rather in some sort of secondary
response to what you're doing with the
keyboard or the mouse it's moving right
your ability to do what you need to do
with the controls and your ability to
perceive the game and your ability not
to get sick and vomit all over the place
right all of that is sort of tied up in
the camera controls right and so there's
two things that are happening there one
is like your you know your ability to
sort of project right your ability to
know what you know I'm seeing what's in
the world and I'm kind of imagining what
that actually is in 3d and how it works
and then there's your ability to like
control it okay and both of these are
effectively have a transform happening
right your head is taking all these
symbols it's seeing they're very
abstract and they're not really in 3d
they're ins like pseudo 3d it's making
this sort of understanding of what it
really means and then you are sort of
formulating what you would need to do
with the controls to affect the change
that you want to see happen on the
screen and how you want to play the game
you're doing that process right so it's
like this step of like first construct
what's actually happening the world
based on what I see construct what the
controls are that I should use and like
do that right and the camera messes with
this more than anything else right
because let's say for example that I'm
looking at the screen okay and you know
I've got my guy here
and I'm like walking him forwards or
something like this and I'm trying to
understand what I'm going to go hit when
I'm here and the camera just starts
scrolling this way right now my brain
has to do this thing all of a sudden
where it's like trying to go like okay
the screens moving this way so I'm
predicting the motion of these things
and I know that I would like Kerr
slightly left or whatever right so the
camera is like drastically change that
perception let's say I wrote start to
rotate it so I'm pushing up on the thing
well now what happens does my guy keep
pushing up as he turns or does he always
move upwards in screen space even though
the cameras like spinning him around or
whatever right and if you don't believe
me or can't think of an example try to
think of the last time you played a game
that had clockwise clap counterclockwise
in it because this is the place where
you can really tell especially if you're
like me and aren't super good at doing
the mapping right there are these games
that are like oh let's say I push the a
key my guy rotates that way and I push
the like D key and my guy rotates this
way right so he's pointing this
direction
I pushed the the you know the a key and
he starts to rotate that direction
I pushed the D key and he starts to
rotate the other direction right well if
you've ever been in that situation you
know that when your guys pointing
downward oftentimes you make this make
of like I wanted to rotate this way I
push D and it doesn't like go that way
it goes this way because D is for
rotating around in the clockwise fashion
right your ability to perceive like what
the controls were will do right relies
on your brain's ability to constantly do
these mappings of what do the controls
me and so the cameras orientation its
position its motion all of those are
like affecting your brains ability to do
stuff right so yeah
in handmade hero I hate I hate this
stuff so there will be none of that ever
in handmade hero I went with a control
scheme that's like you've moved by just
pushing the direction you want to go and
you attack them by pushing the Russian
you want to attack right it's a standard
control scheme that everyone understands
and that does not involve any of those
things so there's all sorts of issues
with controls in your perception all
that sort of stuff I'm just choosing the
sidestep those and not tackle them
because I think it's way better just
have nice direct controls don't have
that problem so we don't have that but
we still have all the same problems with
the camera and let's take as an example
to introduce the concept of hysteresis
that I said it's what I want to talk
about here let's just take for example
even what I'm already looking at right
now okay now you can see when I kind of
move through there right when I when I
do that jump it's very sharp you know we
don't really have a game going on here
right we haven't made enemies that
attack you so it's not it's like it's
low stress that it's not a problem
that's jarring because I don't need to
do anything I'm not in imminent danger
anything but you can imagine if I just
hopped in here and bam hopped in here
and all of a sudden the screen comes up
and there's like lava right in front of
me I'm about to die or whatever right
that's not a good experience right so
even just what we have right now we
would start to worry about that whole
perception loop are we allowing the
player the ability like are we giving
them what they need in terms of a
pleasant experience of moving from room
to room and the answer is like kind of
already know all right so let's talk
about what hysteresis is hysteresis is a
word that essentially means you know
sort of in printer products takes into
account the previous frame might be the
way to put it but another way to say it
is that it's not time independent right
so I can make a function that does
something and it could be completely
independent of time okay and that's what
we have right now like if you take a
look at how our camera code works
effectively it's not dependent on time
really any significant degree
it's just dependent on position so
wherever the player goes we will figure
out where they're supposed to go based
on this now it's
not strictly true because since this is
a delta technically it is based on time
a little bit it's based on the order in
which you did things and you can see
that in fact if I restart the game you
can kind of see that it is that does
have a little bit of a dependence there
right which is to say I come up here I
come down here and I can get it to be
well actually no I guess that's not true
our deltas are exactly even so I guess
it isn't I was gonna say you could get
it into a different state but I guess
you can't because our deltas are always
exactly the same so even so yeah so it's
pretty much not depending on time at all
it's just wherever the person is there's
a specific camera a position that is
that is the cameras gonna look at and
when they get there I think I feel like
is even that because the 918 I don't
know that might not be true it doesn't
matter point being ignore that for a
second and let's just say this is only
dependent on position rather than trying
to figure out whether there's a way you
could get it to not be right that
doesn't take into account time it
doesn't take an account the path that
the player flowed through the world
right it just knows when the person's
here I want to show them this particular
camera angle now hysteresis is about not
doing that it's about saying let's take
into account time let's take into
account the path by which something
arrived where it's going to be and let's
make our algorithms aware of that okay
now why is that important well I'll give
you a very simple example let's say that
we had a room perhaps and you know we we
well trying to think of what the what
the easiest way to to to describe
something like this is
let's say that we have a room and we
were trying to figure out where to place
the camera in this room right and there
is a a obstacle okay that the player has
to navigate in some way
it's like somewhat difficult for them to
navigate right look maybe it's a locked
door or something like this right and so
I've got like a situation where I've got
this door here right and then I've got a
wall and and then I've got you know some
stuff down here or whatever and then
there's like an opening over here right
okay now let's say that our solution for
how we were going to do the camera was
just that it's a fixed thing in the
world and maybe this is what the the map
was going to be and so the the way that
the the partitions for the world work
out is here's where like one camera
angle is right and here's where another
camera angle is okay
and here's where another one is right
and you can imagine that if all I was
gonna do is just pick one of these based
on where I was I don't get a very
satisfying result from this right
because if I'm walking up to the room
this way right if this was the way I was
coming in and maybe I can see you know
what let me simplify this a little and
just consider the top two parts back
since that'll be a little bit easier
okay
so here's one let's let's do it this way
here's one here's the other so I'm
coming in this way I walk in through the
door at the open area in here and then
I'm in this area and I can't even see
this yeah right I walk off the side of
the screen which appears to have nothing
on it and then I'm in this little tiny
sliver of space with the door and I see
all this stuff over here right that's
what I that's what I'm getting okay
now if instead I was let's say there was
another entrance over here if instead I
walked this way and came around through
here then I'm get a much more pleasant
thing what I would expect I'd be able to
see the room I was in I'd be able to see
the door right and only a little bit of
what's on the other side of it makes
good sense right now if you take a look
at this and go I would like both
approaches I would like both of these to
work properly then what you want right
is a camera scheme that takes into
account where you came from right if I'm
approaching from this side I want to see
up to the door and end if I'm
up to the door and end right so I'm
gonna have like different views for
potentially similar locations depending
on when I came through right and that's
the nature of hysteresis not the best
example and I apologize for that I
wanted to give at least one other
example and for some reason I'm having
trouble thinking one now I will give you
the example I actually care about which
is what we need to use a foreign
handmade hero okay now I just said what
I wanted to do when we were talking
about it before is I've got a room based
camera model so this sort of thing is
not super concerning to us because we're
building our like individual play units
to be contained inside a screen anyway
right so I don't need to worry about
picking camera views the camera views
are created as part of the world
creation we know what a room is and
regardless of how big or small we make
rooms or even if there are multiple room
sizes the camera has always has very
strict information this is what you
should show show this right so we don't
have that mr. Reese's problems talked
about four but we do have a different
one and that is our standard
kind of layout right will be one that
looks sort of like this will have two
different camera views right here's
camera view a and here's camera view B
and we've got a passageway in between
them and the player will cross that
threshold at some point and we'll watch
a transition from the camera from A to B
right and what I want to do there is I
want the camera to sort of smoothly vary
from A to B and back right and so
there's a couple different ways that we
might want to do this and I'm not sure
exactly how we want to do them but I
wanted to talk to you about the
hysteresis after that so when I start
mentioning that as we sort of play with
things we may choose to use a method
that takes into the into the that into
account now a method that has no
hysteresis like I just said will always
will mean that wherever the player is
right at any time anywhere that I pick
it does not matter how they got there we
will be able to say exactly where the
camera is so if the thing is here the
camera angle is B if the things here
it's a right and we can construct a
smooth scrolling camera system right
that would work with this the way we
would do that is we would take some
region in between the two and say as the
player transits between these two
locations right we take the T value that
maps from camera A to B right we've got
sort of a camera
ATB thing happening here that outputs
some kind of interpolation between the
two okay we could say that that T value
that interpolation T value is just based
on where you are in this narrow corridor
right and that will probably be the
first thing I'll try if it's good great
but we may have a problem and what the
problem might be is what if the player
Dali's in here what if the player just
kind of hops back and forth in between
here the camera will just be going like
this like crazy right maybe that's what
we want to have happen
I don't know and like I said we'll play
with it but maybe we don't and if we
don't want that to happen that's where
we have to start thinking about
hysteresis and
but hysteresis will tell us in this
situation is we have to pay attention to
what the players actually been doing and
then we can figure out whether we want
this to happen
so for example if the player starts
hovering in here maybe we want to bring
the camera to a rest straddling the two
rooms right until they cross this side
of the threshold for more than a second
or something right and again so then
we're putting in that hysteresis that
measurement of where they've been wow I
can't even write that we're putting in
that measurement of where they've been
and we're figuring out how to sort of
change the function of the camera so
that it has state associated with it
based on what the player has been doing
okay and so I'm not sure exactly which
one we're gonna do or how we're gonna do
that but what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
do the direct mapping one first and the
way that I'm gonna do that is I'm just
gonna introduce essentially a apron
right I'm gonna say that there's there
sort of this this border region here
right where as you cross into it if you
cross into one of these areas and I
don't know what we'll do if you're in
one of these maybe both transitions I'm
not sure but if you cross into one of
these areas it will start to do the
interpolation right and and as it starts
to do that interpolation if you come
back it'll it'll it'll just use
basically your distance in there to
figure out what the you know what that
interpolation level should be okay so
what this is going to mean is we're
going to need some information like our
camera our understanding of where the
camera is needs to be a little bit
broader because right now we have this
concept that the simulation region and
the camera are coincident but that's not
actually what we want in it to be right
our simulation region should always be
the room you're in and only when it
crosses so like this I guess I'm saying
is this code is actually correct for the
camera as far as the simulation region
is concerned
that's fine and then once you cross into
another room we move the simulation
region over there right and that's fine
but we need sort of this other idea of
of displacement of the camera and so in
addition I'm gonna go into world mode in
and add a concept here that we have a
displacement now this is probably a good
thing in general not just for our smooth
scrolling and the reason that it's
probably a good thing in general right
is because we want for sure we want like
things like screen shake and stuff to be
easy to implement like if we want to
shake the screen like a big monster like
stomps on the ground or something we
might want to shake the screen or
something like this so we would we
wanted the ability to displace things
around anyway
and so that's you know just kind of a
natural thing we might want to do so
what I'm gonna do in here since we have
the concept of the camera Pete I don't
know what last camera P is for in fact
before we get started I just want to see
what what is that even used for
absolutely nothing so then I'm gonna
have a you know camera displacement and
all I'm gonna do is I'm gonna when we
actually go ahead and use the camera P
to sort of actually create the here when
we use that to create the center of the
of the sim region you can see we do this
begin sim and then we start drawing
things and that sort of stuff right what
I want to do is I want to be able to
displace this without displacing the
simulation region right and the way that
I'm going to do that is just by saying
well okay we we know that we have some
rendering that's occurring right and
effect I guess I don't know where we
actually start the render here's where
we start the render and we do this
perspective where we do we do a
perspective transport here right and
what I want to do is when we start doing
the offsets because we do entity
transforms offset P and we do this stuff
here where we do get grounded we point
that stuff I want to move the camera by
that amount right and by the way I don't
want to really displace these I don't
think because these should actually be
there well I'll actually guess they
should move hmm how do I want to do this
exactly I guess I want to set this right
off the bat right you can see default
upright and a transformed say any
transform off the oops that's no good
there we go
default upright transform and then
offset P in here what I want to do is I
want to see it can I just displace that
basically set the camera up to be
pointing in a different location because
all these guys use the entity transform
right I think everyone does yeah so if I
want to I could displace everything by
saying whatever the camera displacement
is I can just add that in here and I
could do the same thing for for these
push rect outlines as well right now
it's not the kind of thing the annoying
thing about it I don't know what we
actually do with camera P here I guess
it's behind my head
get granted any point entity - camera P
camera relative round P ah so the only
reason we were even using the camera P
is just to fade things in and out as we
went up and down yeah but anyway so our
camera P when we do this subtraction all
we would need to do is its add the
displacement in here and then we know
where the cameras placement is in the
world right so this is just our world
mode camera displacement so we know
where the camera is but then what we
have to do is when we do default flat
transfer here everything is going to be
have to beat when we do our transference
it's going to have that world transform
in it and so yeah so I'll change this
here to be camera P I guess camera P is
actually is not the camera displacement
though camera P is where the camera is
the displacements the negative of that
so we still want to do we still want to
have a thing called camera displacement
if that makes sense yeah
so camera displacement to avoid having
that be negative I guess what we would
say is maybe we'd call that Delta camera
P or something like this I just want I
need to know how to call it or camera
offset let's call it camera offset
that's easier because camera
displacement it's hard to tell which way
it's phrased is it phrased in the in
terms of I'm going I'm it is how much
the camera moves or is it the opposite
which is how much things move because of
the camera right so I'm gonna call it
camera offset so then we know that
that's true and the entity transform
right is going to be the negative of the
camera P right so let's say this here is
the
you will transform and that's just the
camera P inverted right so these guys
are going to have world transform will
transform world transform and then down
here where we do displacement again I'll
just instead do - camera feet alright
offset is not a member of what is it
then I'll set P sorry alright so I think
that's all correct let's double check by
maybe playing with that a little bit so
here I am in right in this world here
I'm gonna try just placing myself by
moving the camera I'm gonna move the
camera this way which would move
everything else in that way so I'm going
to move the camera one unit to the right
okay perfect
that's what I wanted to see and I'm
going to try the same thing in Y yeah
okay so that's what I was hoping for and
you can see what I was hoping would be
true is true which is the simulation
boundary is shown right there which is
what I wanted
okay so now we have the ability to have
a camera offset so what I'm going to do
is I'm just gonna start very lightly
playing with that so today in here where
we do our stuff for room based camera
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna say let's
add some displacement in here for the
camera and I'm just gonna make it be
based off of that apron so if I know
that when I transition is nine I'm gonna
use like everywhere from like eight
point five to nine for example to
displace the camera towards the other
screen right so what I want to start is
I want to define something here first I
wanted to find like a v3 which is the
you know room Delta or something and the
room Delta is going to be 1810 right
that's how much we move when we go you
know if we were to go the X component is
how much we go for a room horizontally
and the Y component is how much we go
for a room vertically so then when we
come in here I would know that all right
let's see like like H room Delta maybe
is half of that so now I can say like
okay if we're each room Delta X right or
negative H room Delta X H room Delta Y
negative H room Delta Y okay and then
when we do our displacement here I know
I can say well this is room Delta X
negative room Delta
room Delta Y negative room Delta Y and
the reason I want that encoded now is
because obviously I want to make sure
that I don't have to that everything is
based on a size we can change and that
could even change dynamically maybe if I
want it to right okay so one other thing
I wanted to try guests that I didn't try
is I want to be able to displace the
camera away from me as well so I'm just
gonna quickly also say what if I was to
do whatever the world is here I'm gonna
take the camera off set and I'll make
the Z equal to one so that we displace
the camera vertically does that work at
all oops world mode is spelled wrong so
no it certainly wouldn't okay good
because that's another thing I want to
be able to do is I want to make sure I
can displace the camera vertically I
mean a depth wise well to the screen all
right so now what I'm going to do is
gonna say what happens when I'm in that
apron right so what happens when because
I know what happens when I move right I
know what happens when I do the
displacement here but I also want to be
able to say once I know once I know that
I'm outside of a sort of more
conservative region what's that and so
I'm gonna do a thing that's like room
apron here and room apron I'm just gonna
say for now is like seventeen point five
eight and nine point five F I'd let me
just say like point five of the way
there okay so what I'm going to do is
gonna say if entity P dot X is greater
than H room Delta
and we'll just do one for now and then
we'll see how we can kind of generalize
that up I'm now gonna say okay instead
of atrium Delta I'm gonna use like H
room apron and I guess actually that's I
really just want that right so I guess
what I really want to say is a true
apron is just whatever the half room
Delta X is minus that 0.5 right -
whatever the the apron value is like so
right so when I do this I now want to
set the cameras displacement value
specifically right so what I want to do
is assume I'll start out by assuming
that if nothing else happened right that
the world modes camera offset is just
going to be nothing so we'll assume it's
nothing and that'll reset it right so
now we're in the normal case and I guess
I should work on the Y value for us
because we're gonna go off the top of
the screen as the test so let's do this
one first so if I want to go off the top
of the screen what I want to do is do
something interesting when I get to this
half point here and you'll note it's not
quite right it's we're it seems like
we're off by one so I feel like this
really shouldn't should be like 19 or
something I don't know what the value
should be but it feels like it's wrong
at the moment right it needs to be it
needs to go up by one screens worth and
it doesn't at the moment so I'm not sure
not sure what the deal is with that
that's much better
is 12 better 12.5 I'm not sure like I
said well after we have to go look at
what we're actually creating for room
sizes first all right so let's start it
out doing it based on Delta's like that
is probably also not a great idea and so
we should probably fix that too all
right
at least we're now a little bit cleaner
there
okay so when I am going off the top of
the screen and I see that I'm past the
apron value what I want to do is I want
to do a clamp map to range remember
we've got our sort of standard way of
taking getting a t-value from from to
sort of boundary points and a point in
between so clamp zero I think it's
called like clamp zero one map to range
yeah so I want to do one of those clamp
zero one map to range to get myself a
t-value and I know what my min is my min
is my room apron right my age room apron
and I know what my max is it's my H room
Delta so all I need now is the actual
thing to map and obviously that's the
location of the player right because I
know that player is between these two so
that gives me back a T value and I can
use that T value to control the camera
offset what I'm gonna do is make the
camera offset so that as it goes it's
gonna go about halfway to where I want
it to change
and then it'll flip and we'll go the
other half of the way right so what I'm
gonna do is say okay the camera offset
in this case is going to be equal to
whatever the whatever the room Delta
would be and I want it to go to half of
that basically so I want to take my T
value and I wanted to make the camera
offset be half of whatever that room
Delta is and we'll see what this does is
we kind of go back to code right
it seems really fast oh you know what I
mean
not I'm using the body right now which
moves it really quickly I think I want
to use the head no hold on a second
I need something slower here so let's do
an ad player
what are we tracking
yeah it's tracking the body in you
subtract the head all right that's a
thing that's at world creation time so
I'm gonna have to restart in order to
make that happen but that's okay okay so
there you can see right we're doing that
half interpolation right and then when
it gets to the halfway point it snaps
why did it snap well because we haven't
done the corresponding side yet right so
let's go ahead to the sim region and do
the corresponding side here is the exact
same code and again like we're gonna
want to generalize this out and do a
bunch more work on it so bear with me
but we're gonna do the exact same thing
here if we're less than the negative
room apron we're gonna do the exact same
mapping from negative 8 room Delta Y to
each room apron Y and you notice I
inverted those right because this is the
sorry still the same so yes so I have to
make these negative because I'm talking
about the bottom part of the screen now
instead of the top part of the screen so
I'm talking about the negative apron
right and I'm mapping between the
negative apron and the negative Delta to
figure out where we are and I'm gonna do
the exact same thing but only this time
I'm talking about moving backwards right
so I'm talking about sliding the camera
the other direction so now when we pop
the camera over we'll be on the other
side of the apron and we should get the
other part of the scroll right so
hopefully you can kind of see how that's
working right now that's like one of
those things that's one of those things
that's better to look at I think if we
can slow time down a little bit here so
what I'd like to do because there's a
couple things that we think we want to
wait and that's not what I wanted to do
where is the simulation there it is I'm
gonna I'm gonna crank the simulation
time step-down it to really slow so now
we're just moving it molasses speed so
now I'm gonna move down right and now I
move up again
and so what I'm noticing is I'm noticing
a little glitch there right when we
transition between the two I'm not sure
if you guys can see it when we change
simulation regions there's a little bit
of a glitch but I don't know what it's
from so we still have we have some kind
of a bug there with our camera change
over and again this is something that
we're gonna clean up so that's no big
deal but you know just be aware that
it's there as we as we sort of converge
on this all right mm-hmm
and that could be because - we're not
really again we take we may have not
quite written it correctly so that we're
not continuous through there's all kinds
of things we could have done wrong so
we'll get there so what I want to do now
is I want to just tune this a little bit
I'm gonna make that room that I think
this was a little bit too too small
right so I'm going to go back here and
I'm gonna make it a little bit bigger
oh whoops that's not at all that's the
wrong value
so we were talking about 1/2 meters was
a meters worth of play I'm gonna make it
to ya all right so you can see that if
we allow it to be too you can actually
stand in there right so maybe that's a
little bit too much I'll I'll drop it
down to like 7 and now you can't stand
now as you transition between the two
right but it feels pretty good to me
except for the glitch right so that's
getting better
all right so yeah we got to fix that
glitch but other than that we're getting
into better shape here what I also want
to do is I want to add a little bit of
Bounce here so what I want to do is I
want to say let's have a bounce height
or something where we displaced by like
up to a meter in Z and the reason I want
to do this is just for fun it's just
kind of silly but I think it might be
fun so I'm gonna put a bounce height in
here and the bounce height is just gonna
be like squared T so as as we like go to
that middle point we just do a parabolic
arc up to the bat site right if that
makes sense
is that right so squared T no that would
be that would be this curve so I needed
to go the other way right I needed to
actually be square root of T right I
need it to be I need to be this shape so
that it will it will play effectively
need it to be an inverse parabola so I
suppose what I actually want is well
let's see what I actually want
so what I want is I want this upside
down right so I pretty much want that
right I want negative T squared and I
want it to be displaced over so that
it's so that it starts at the origin and
goes up to the height of the parabola
and then down right inside the you know
at though at the one point right so oops
I didn't mean to undo that there we go
so essentially you know I want it so
that I actually have a displaced T so
that the height is there and I guess
that's negative T I need it to also be
so that it gets back to zero at the
start right so since rather than playing
with the graph I think it's easier to
just write it out what I want is I want
an F of T that's equal to a T squared
plus BT plus C right so nodes I want a I
want a parabolic arc
I want f of 0 to be 0 and I want F of 1
to be 1 right so I should be able to
start out by solving that and then I
guess I don't have any other information
about it I need one more piece of
information which I guess I want it to
be curved upwards not downwards probably
enough but we'll see so if I solve this
out right if f of 0 is 0 well that
doesn't really tell me anything other
than C is 0 right meaning because as I
as I which is fine I mean I need to
solve for three things but so I plug in
a 0 here I get 0 plus 0 equals C right
and that equals 0 so C is definitely 0
okay so that's simple enough
that's right right yeah and F of 1
equals 1 which means that when I have T
squared plus T that's got to be equal to
1 so I have T squared plus T equals 1
right so yeah so from that I can
determine ooh that's what am I talking
about my brain is fried today for some
reason I have a plus B equals 1
probably prep plug in for the right term
there right so I know that a plus
vehicle's equal also equals 1 so I could
just say all right a is 1 minus B or I
guess we went in alphabetical order we
could say B is 1 minus a right so all I
need to know is what my actual value for
what I'm actually gonna plug in for a
and so I don't know if there's anything
else I want to know about this value I'm
trying to think of like like I said
whether it curves up or down would be
mostly all I would need to know so if I
have if I write a thing here that's like
80 squared plus 1 minus a T right I can
take a look at the graph of that for I
can try some different values of a and
see what they look like so let's see
here if I say graph a T squared so let's
say 1 T squared plus that would be 1
minus 1 so that'd be 0 so it would just
literally be a T squared right and then
I get the shape that I didn't want so if
instead we plug in like a negative 1 for
that right
let's say I'm just gonna see if that
helps us that would be negative 1
squared which of course is oops key
squared plus negative T
and that also goes the other direction
though does it not what did I do wrong
here cuz this should always give me F of
1 equals 1 right
did I plug that in wrong oh right sorry
it's negative T squared minus T and
there's what I actually wanted of course
that but that does that goes backwards
there did I plug that in wrong again 1
minus a ah that would be 2t man plugging
in this way is tricky that's what I
wanted so I guess that is the values I
actually want that's a slow math day
here in case you couldn't tell
brain is fried this math was actually
correct but doing this took forever not
sure what the easiest way would have
done oh I know how we would have done
that I guess we could have said what we
wanted the derivative to be here well ok
anyway point thing we figured it out so
this is the equation we actually want
which is negative T squared plus 2t all
right
so let's just say it's negative T
squared plus 2t times the bounce site
to give that little parabolic flavor if
you will there we go lovely
yeah
okay so now it's again it's a little bit
too fast like I would like it to be
maybe not as fast as that cuz it's a bit
too much I feel like at this point or
maybe it just needs to be more subtle
you know maybe bounce height should be
something less
all right well that's good enough for
now but like I said tomorrow I think are
probably the first thing we should do is
figure out why we're getting a glitch
there cuz we're definitely getting a
glitch as we go across and we want to
clean up this camera code anyway as we
go forward so we should probably figure
out what that is and what cuz we're
definitely getting like a little hitch
again you might not be able to see it
because depending on like your
compression like how the video stream is
coming across you may be getting like
better or worse ability that you know to
see what's actually happening there but
on the transition we're definitely
getting a bug there it might be because
the camera offset oh you know what it is
it's that the camera offset is not
taking into account the change this
change so probably what we would need to
do is say okay this has to happen
afterwards and since weird right because
you can you can see what's happening
there right we move the camera and then
we were still using the offset from the
previous frame so it's way offset then
it gets solved properly on the next
frame and jumps back so in order to do
that right when we do a mapping here we
would have to update what the entities
position is in order to compute this so
we'd need to basically say like we
compute a new entity P after we update
to figure out what the cameras offset
should be for the next frame right which
is kind of janky but that's what we're
what we have to do so in order to do
that what we could say is like well
alright if we'd apply this offset then
we know what that is right the enemy P
that we would use is just going to have
that same offset applied right
so whatever the Delta is that we apply
here we've got to save it right
so we'd have to say like okay apply
Delta is whatever this is and what I'm
thinking probably I'm just guessing but
like I thinking the way we probably will
end up cleaning this up is just by
making the camera an enemy right so that
we don't have to deal with any of this
stuff anymore for either all right but
let's try that although if the camera
goes by the applied Delta then this
little piece of that will be subtracted
away right Hey look the glitch is gone
okay so let's actually go to the Q&amp;A
keeper Caleb are you concerned about the
player Singh outside the boundaries of
the map or seeing into other rooms in
the camera zooms out no but that's a
game design thing not an implementation
problem right that has nothing to do
with the implication if you if that's a
game design decision that someone wants
to make at some point they can just turn
it off
cast a 5 so no more sterling yeah the
game design requires there to not be
smooth scrolling it has to be room based
so when you go to a room you're in that
room until you're like done with what
you're doing in there and then you can
go to the next one
soy sauce the kid I know the rooms are
going to fit the screen but will there
be variable sized rooms with the camera
making it fit to the screen so yeah I
don't know whether I'll ever want rooms
other than the standard size room but
I'm guessing that that maybe once or
twice for interest purposes we will
allow that to happen
there's no nothing like there's nothing
in the simulation that requires us to
have rooms be this size right does this
stuff work right now - yeah
it's funny to see it so tiny like that
hmm
when thinking of enemies would you have
classifications for AI level one
approach constantly zombie what would be
the main levels you'd say for difficulty
earthling that's game design again which
I don't do and guessed a 5 I am already
39 someone probably needs to update the
the 38 in their popcorn have you seen
the work glitch from Link's Awakening
how would you avoid that mmm
what is the Warped glitch in Link's
Awakening I don't know
does anybody know what that is the work
glitch or can explain it is it simple
enough to explain there was something
complicated that I'd have to see
so this one is about it looks like 24
maybe to 23.5 I should say let us see
what we actually make our gonna need to
actually make sure that we have concepts
of how big rooms are if that makes sense
that's a weird number to guess it 24 I
don't know what was it gonna say here -
oh right so the can if we want to just
copy this out where everything's an X
just to see what looks like while I wait
for someone to tell me whether they know
what links awakenings glitch is you
press Start when before you enter a room
and the link will end up on the top of
the screen well we don't have that so
I'm guessing the reason they have that
well I can I can sort of explain why I
suspect they have that bug and we don't
have the same kind of bug we don't have
the same kind of engine I guess is what
I would say so we probably wouldn't be
able to have the same kind of bug as
that right doo-doo-doo sorry go just I
got to hop a little bit here
yeah I'm stuck I can't get back at the
world okay there we go um so the reason
that I'm assuming that they have that
bug and I don't really know anything
about Link's Awakening but I'm just
gonna say what I assume so you know we
actually have a coherent sense of world
space in a certain in a certain sense
meaning that we actually know where you
are in the world because when we pack
you into world chunks right you know
we've got a world that's divided up into
these world chunks and we know you're
like you know this far from the center
of this world chunk and then when we
simulate you we simulate you in a real
Cartesian space there and then we pack
you back in so at no time are we unaware
of where you actually really are in the
world like we have a very coherent
definition of that so I don't think we
can have that bug we're gonna have other
bugs but not that one what I assume they
did is they had something like well okay
we've just got a sprite position on the
screen so here's the screen and like
link is walking towards the top of the
screen and he gets here right so links
there and they're like we got to trigger
the scroll subroutine so you go out to
like scroll right and now what happens
is the scroll routine makes link
I don't know disappear or who knows how
they draw him right I don't I have like
I said haven't seen the game but we
scroll the background this way right but
we haven't updated links actual position
values to be anywhere other than here
and so if we can interrupt the thing
that tells it to reset its position to
down here then he'll just be at the top
right but we don't have that happening
like we're not ever unaware of where you
actually really were in the world we
don't have any screen space location for
you we have a simulation space but we
unpack into it and pack out of it during
every frame so there's no way for you to
interrupt that process if that makes
sense
sergeant Carnival if you want a good
hysteresis example a heater controller
does the job yeah I guess I mean it's
hard to explain if people don't already
know control theory but like yeah if you
have something where you're like I got a
turn heater on to heat a room or turn it
off based on a thermostat right you want
to like you don't want to constantly
turn the heater on off on off on off on
off on off all the time to try and keep
the temperature right what you want to
do is heat it up to like a bit above the
temperature let it come down a little
bit below the temperature and then turn
it back on again right so if you can
kind of keep it within a band I'm
guessing not that I've ever written a
thermostat controller but
alright sounds like we are done okay
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it has
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home you can always peer to the game
on hand made here it organic comes with
the source code so you can follow along
with what we're coding you can also go
to the forum site if you want to ask
questions you can go to our patreon page
for a support the video series you can
go to our schedule bot if you want to
know when we're live and you can go to
our episode guide to catch up on past
episodes and that is really all there is
to say about that I will be back here
tomorrow 5:00 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time
when we will do probably a little bit
more camera work but that's mostly all I
really need to do for the camera for now
we'll probably just get a better sense
of rooms and then I think it's time to
start thinking about our actual like
physics updating representations and
stuff like that so we're probably gonna
have to start getting into some multi
entity you push a block around other
things like of this nature not really
push the block around cause you don't
super do that in this game but you know
what I mean those sorts of things where
we have some entities interacting with
each other so that we can clean up that
part of the code that's about it hope
see you guys back here tomorrow until
then have fun programming and I'll see
you on the Internet take it easy