and welcome to handmade hero show we
code a complete game live on stream we
are currently today
uh doing some cleanup on the collision
code uh i we we accidentally
um yet last week we were just trying to
add some ability to step through like
diagrams so we could analyze the
collision system uh when it went wrong
we accidentally fixed the bug
uh it turned out we once we had the
ability to like scrub through things and
see what was happening it became very uh
straightforward for us to find the bug
accidentally uh so we we actually fixed
it
uh and that's great but
um
i i wasn't totally satisfied with that
because it was very strange what the bug
was
uh it turns out there's like entities in
our system that are basically having
their they're getting created and they
have sort of
uh
rectangles that don't actually have any
area for
collision
and so
that may be fine
because
we we do
want to have that occur
but the problem is we need to
think about whether or not
we need to make sure that was
intentional and i think it probably was
but we need to make sure that that's
actually smart
maybe we want a bit field for that
because it's kind of expensive to
say like is this collision
uh we have to actually compare like
floating point values and all this crap
to know that there's no collision so we
may not want to do that so we may want
to add a bit field we had one in there a
long time ago that was like does this
thing collide or not and we decided it
was necessary uh but maybe it is
actually is sort of is that
what should be happening two are these
actually things that don't have
collision or is there a bug in the world
generator that's generating things that
should have had collision volumes and
don't
two
uh and three what we would like to do is
even if we find out there's no bugs in
here
what we would like to do
uh is finish up things that need to get
finished up on the collision system such
as
re-enabling the ability to move out of
uh starting collisions so if you start
embedded in an object because the
gameplay code just like moved someone
there or whatever
we want you to be able to get out of
that so we we want that
uh and then the other thing that we want
is the spatial partitioning
to avoid having to test all the entities
in the world when we do collision so
when we
when we check for collision
we don't right now right uh we're going
to
have to sweep through all like
everything
right we have to sweep through every
entity in the entire uh active set
which is quite a few i mean i don't know
how many it is but it could be on the
order of like 10 000 entities or
something because the active set is
quite large
um
so you know it could be very large it
probably isn't that large right now it's
like a thousand or something or two
thousand
but we're sweeping through all of those
entities for every check of every
collision it which is just ridiculous uh
it's
the game should be running at an
absolute crawl but it's not just because
um processors are so fast
so what we want to do is stop that
we want to when we um unpack people into
the world we want to actually
now have some idea about where they are
so that we only check entities that are
close by to the one that is moving now
this doesn't have to be perfect it can
be a fairly loose
boundary right
um but there are some difficulties
involved and it and there are some
decisions we have to make about how we
want this system to work because
we
when we produce the spatial partition
we will have the situation where as we
then move entities they will move where
they are in the spatial partition
so
it's not static like if you remember
look we did exactly this before
with the lighting
we take the current like things that are
within the view
at that time and we build a spatial
partition before we start doing lighting
for looking up ray tracing
um
and
that was fine
but it it assumed
that you did not have to move things
around
so we knew that we could just like pile
all the stuff in there
and the system could just be optimized
for the lookup it doesn't have to be
optimized for moving things
this one will be different
in this one we have to have entities be
able to move
now there's a lot of stuff we can
consider doing here
um
and
my assumption is that because this is
running so fast already
that we don't have to be very fancy
because right now we have no spatial
partition and the code's still running
right
um so for example uh you know if we if
we open it up here
uh
so let me go ahead and just run the
program
uh and what you can see is uh even in
this circumstance where we're literally
doing ridiculous numbers of collision
checks for like the glove here
um it still runs in in a pretty
reasonable frame rate uh it's not great
i don't think like i don't know what the
frame rate is right now but it's
probably not fantastic right um
what's the quick way for that yes it's
uh it's 30 frames a second
right
um
but honestly like that's not really
significantly lower you can see though
as the collision moves around you see
how it spikes right it's spiking down to
like 15 frames a second
right
um
so you can kind of see like it has a
really negative
uh impact right so it's running fine but
it's bad and you it will get worse when
there's like several colliders like you
know there's gonna be 10 20
things on the screen at least that will
be undergoing collision right now
there's like only one or maybe there's
another one it depends i don't know if
any of those skull guys are in the
working set right now i don't think they
are
um but you can see why that's a problem
because that's horrible for just one
thing and the reason for that like i
said is that it's sweeping through
everything
so but the fact that still running at
interactive frame rates means we
probably don't have that much work to do
meaning we don't have to go crazy with
this we can probably just do something
fairly straightforward and not be in too
much trouble right
um so i'm guessing that just a simple
grid
uh like a simple voxel where we just can
move things around the voxel as
necessary is going to be all that we
really need um and so uh i probably will
just do something like that
but if we were seeing uh much like if
this were running at one frame a second
generally uh i would i would be more
worried and maybe would be trying to do
something more aggressive right
um so yeah and you can see there right
like so here's an example
i think
of these getting stuck
um
can i
look at this
here's an example you can see of these
objects getting getting stuck right
which is what we would expect to have
happen now because right now we allow
things to be placed
in ways that
will make them interpenetrate so that's
not actually strange uh but
one thing i do wonder a little bit
is why it allowed these these are two
colliding objects so i'm not quite sure
why they were allowed to do this in the
first place
but like i said we don't really right
now try to guarantee that meaning we
don't really try to guarantee that
things don't end slightly
interpenetrating after they've both
moved
um
like our refinement step is not
particularly careful about that so i
could also believe that this was fine
the point is uh
yeah you can see right here right
um
it's gotten into a situation where it's
like entirely colliding on step one
you know what i'm saying
here is the step before that let's just
take a quick look at it
so you can see that it allowed it to be
placed there it allowed this guy to be
placed there you know what the other
thing is we kind of need we need some
way to pick who we're looking at because
this guy moved second so he's the one
who was allowed to move into that
placement
right
um
so yeah
but
uh
i assume basically just what's going on
here is that we don't really require any
kind of symmetric
checking
so because these objects move
um themselves
i'm not sure there's really anything
smarter we can do let me let me try to
think about this for a second so when
two objects move
right now we do we move them in order
and we don't really do anything in
particular to try to ensure that they're
not going to interpenetrate
we could
so one thing we could do
is always check
only the lower
entity
so
i know what i'm saying it sounds pretty
weird but
collision checks are symmetric in the
sense that when we ask when two objects
collide or not
that's not a different question
semantically meaning
if i have two objects a and b and i ask
whether they collide
i don't semantically
want that to be directional i don't want
the answer to does a collide with b to
be different from does b collide with a
right
like that's not what i actually want
so what's interesting about that
is it means that maybe i should think
about the way the collider works
because right now that's not what
happens right now what happens is when
we do collision moves we are thinking
about one object and we ask if that
object could be placed at certain points
in the world
and have the collision query say that it
will not collide with a different object
right
and i'm not sure
no i can guarantee that that's not
correct
uh commutatively right
because
when you check the two collisions you're
checking the
the
corner points for one of the objects
against only this the actual position of
the other object
right
and so i think what you probably want to
do
instead
is you want to check to see whether or
not the other objects like you want to
pick one of the objects and say
uh if we were you i mean i guess you
could do it either way you could say we
want to check to see whether we collide
at the points or whether the other
object collides at the points right
um or you could always just pick the
lower object so you could say like look
whoever has a lower entity id it's just
a tiebreaker arbitrary tiebreaker
whoever has the lower entity id we check
their collision voxel
and we make sure that they are not
colliding in that case right
um
so
this is an interesting question
i feel like there's probably a smart
answer here but i've never really
thought about it before
there's a lot of ways that come to mind
so the simplest way that i can think of
actually is you don't bother doing that
um the simplest way i can think of is
actually just that you
you take
the point
where the entity is and you
snap it to the center of the voxel
before checking
that
might
be preferable
because then you're always asking the
same question
and i'm not sure that you need to be any
fancier than that
to make this work
so so i might i might
um well you know what first let me make
sure that this happens often it should
when you have two colliding objects this
should happen like all the time right
now
um
let me see
just to make sure
that this is something that can happen
often
and assuming that it is
i would like to propose a fix for that
which we can do right now again i'm the
reason i'm doing this before because the
unembed code would have just fixed that
problem but i'd rather just never have
that problem to begin with in the
collision
system first and if i fix the unembed
code
then i i won't be able to fix it because
i won't see it happen so there i think
that
is was it
right
um
that was the system detecting that fact
it's not as easy as i would like like it
does take a little while to make this
happen like i'm able to kind of like
muck around
an uncomfortably large amount of time
um
unfortunately
i don't know if that means i'll have to
create a situation where two things move
towards each other where i think it will
happen more frequently and just create
that circumstance
um because like man this takes a long
time
there we go
so like i can make it happen
but it
it's not as reliable as i would like
um so what i'm suggesting here right
is that for purposes of the collision
like everything is discrete that's what
i'm basically saying
so uh if for example i went and
let's go to move entity
and in the
uh when it calls collides at p here
if i
was to say okay
we know
when you look at this code we're passing
in an entity point here
right
and
we then test against entity points and
the entity points are
like
gonna be snapped
so
this right here would be snapped to like
the center of
a uh
of a voxel
and as i'm thinking about this i'm
wondering in my head as well
should we have done this system slightly
differently have i
have i over complicated things
if instead of choosing corners if we had
just tested the centers of voxels to
begin with
and then used
just
can i stand at the center of this voxel
as the thing
would i not be able to test like far
fewer voxels and get basically the exact
same behavior
um
and then you always consider yourself to
be at the center of the voxel that you
start yeah is that just better
i think it is
i think that's just smarter
so i feel like what we probably want to
do is just simplify this code down a
little bit so that you don't have to do
that checking that i was doing and the
grid is just now center points of the
voxels
you are
in the voxel that you would round to
towards the center of the voxel
yeah i don't know why i didn't think of
that first it seems like we can just
collapse this scheme down to that
and then everyone is just considered to
be in the center of the voxel they're
actually in
right
i don't really know why i didn't do that
like most things i think sometimes
these things are so complicated
like most things in games if you
actually want to go look at a problem
really carefully are complicated enough
that your brain doesn't really
understand it all until you've actually
gone and done it and then you see like
oh actually this is much simpler
when you
sort of
when you actually iron out all the
details it turns out that like the
complexity can be collapsed down but it
not in a way that your brain could have
understood at the time
right
so that does actually seem pretty
straightforward
and i might just say that's what we
should do it's way easier
and way less computation
i i guess i was just being kind of
blunt uh obtuse
i want to scroll down
i want to scroll down i can't see in my
head there we go
um
so yeah i mean gosh that just seems way
better
like
like that's just so much better because
then like you just say look we just have
a voxel
convention
um
there's no corner code it's just center
code
right
um
and the best part is now the center code
is actually just a boolean
because you know whether or not you
pushed it uh or tested it you don't have
to share corners it's just like if
you're gonna push something you test it
if you're not gonna push something you
don't test it
um
that's really it
so this gets way better in fact you
could just do this and say center code
and it says like pushed or not
right
and pushed open knot
yeah i think that literally just
collapses down to did we push this or
not
so we would just have have tested and
like either we've tested it or not and
if we haven't tested it we test it if we
have it and
optionally move there
if or consider it right
all right well that was embarrassing um
so yeah i mean it's not embarrassing
like like i always say like this is why
it's
i'm the type of person who always like
i think you you have like there's
there's two types of people out there
right
um
you've got like the people who give like
a lot of conference presentations who
anytime they figure out something even
remotely mundane they they think it's
amazing and want to say how great they
are
um and then there's other people like
myself who whenever they figure
something out they think they were
stupid for not figuring out earlier
they're both the same thing
uh it's just
uh probably one makes you feel a lot
smarter than you are and one makes you
feel stupider than you are but i don't
know that there's actually a bad thing
about that i think feeling stupid is
probably good
um
because it makes you try to be smarter
whereas feeling smart is probably bad
because it means that you're not trying
very hard to to not be stupid and you
probably still are stupid
anyway difference of opinion
point being
this was dumb
because now what we really need
is voxel corners can just be voxel
center uh you get back what the cell was
that you were in
whether or not uh it's like possible to
move there
the repulsion vector can still be the
same
uh and the embedded
flag can still be the same
um so all this stuff just kind of still
works fine i think
uh
and
we probably can now just simplify all
that code down to something much more
straightforward that doesn't have to
look at corners or any of that stuff so
it'll be much faster
uh and
we can always do our testing only at
voxel centers
so when we do the refinement step we
will
allow testing outside of centers
but for all actual movement stuff
um
we will always test at centers meaning
that it will now be symmetric uh which
is what we want
so i think
this is like
way better
but i guess it remains to be seen
so we'll
type in the code first
before declaring it as such
okay
so when we come into move entity uh what
you can see here is we do like um an
aligned to movement voxel and that all
is fine
uh i think that's
that code would be the same no matter
what happens because the voxel is the
voxel whether we're talking about the
center or not
uh doesn't matter right
now there is one thing that is
possibly true
which is that if we just simply don't
need that anymore
we can stop talking about the cell
entirely and just talk about the grid
point
so it may be such that we don't really
need this idea because if you think
about it if we're just stepping along
centers what the heck did we need the
cell for
so really like a line to movement voxel
a line to movement voxel can just be the
center points now
right
i mean i just don't know that any of
this stuff is necessary
so i think this
just doesn't matter
i think we still need the bounds on
movement
i mean it's really just because of stor
the the only reason we even need the
bounds on movement is because of storage
size
um we wouldn't even need that
like that's another thing to think about
whether we actually want
once you don't have to really do this
there's other options you could think of
i
i'm not going to do that right now so
i'm still going to say that look we've
got a delta p here and that's going to
give us effectively like an ending p
so we're still going to do this
right
um
but we're now talking about these
centers right
which are like we're talking about being
at the center of the voxel
so instead of a floor
uh right this is going to be more of
like a rounding operation here
in a line
so like when we align to the movement
voxel here what we're really talking
about is like that
um because we want to go to
whatever is closest
we're like snapping to a center not down
to a floor other than that i think the
rest of this code just works
and then the like voxel min corner max
corner like none of this stuff
really even matters anymore we probably
don't need the voxel grid
we probably don't need any of that stuff
um
i i think we just don't need that
anymore
so like in here where we talk about uh
the grid stuff
um
i i really just don't think any of that
matters now
we've got the voxel uh
yeah like we've got the starting p
[Music]
and the ending p
i can see why these are getting like
min chord but again i don't know that we
need any of this i think we're just
gonna like
get rid of this
um excuse me
i don't think we need any of this and
that way too like this part here like if
we want to do the expansion side of
things
um
this would just be like
these two values
starting and ending
this is still correct
the only difference is i don't think
it's two times anymore because we now
know that the movement grid is exactly
what we're looking at we want to expand
it by one on either side but it was
rounded so we don't need to expand one
side more than the other which is what
we do in a floor when you floor
something you have to expand the high
side twice and the low side once but
when you round you're just expanding
each side once because you've already
said well we're only going in the the
region that we actually cared about
so i think this becomes a simpler
uh
set of things to do here
right
um
i think that's it this stuff all works
just fine uh the span part of things i
don't know that this matters at all like
i don't know that we care about the span
anymore
we know what it is this is just for an
assertion um
so i don't think we care about the voxel
dimension anymore
like i'm pretty sure we just don't care
we can assert um
we can't assert that like the span
is less than the stack dimension
uh because we do care about that
right
um
i guess i'm not sure certain if we need
to round that first though like like
maybe we do i don't know
um
anyway
what is this about
it's like putting a weird like error oh
because i'm holding my mouse there
um so i think that's all fine
we'll see as we go
uh initial cell and target cell i are
just going to be
the indexes
um so they're just like this code
right
um but we so so really
really all we need to do is round these
with the align to movement voxel thing
so when we do a line to movement voxel
this is the thing that actually like
produces the value that we cared about
here
so when we want to get the movement
voxel index for a particular thing we
need to know what the min corner is but
other than that that's it so we would
just say like get movement voxel index
and then we subtract them
so
like this code right here is that actual
value
um
excuse me
so this code is is basically the same
and it's just like after you do the
round you're just doing a round
uh
that goes to a integer value instead of
not
right
so this code
is like that
so once we know
what the
uh rounded version is
the only question is do we want to do
deltas or not and i'm
not entirely sure
um
that part's a little bit tricky i'm not
sure
but uh we can if we want to know these
these are like supposed to be relative
to the base grid so i think what we do
is we just say like
voxel min corner
um
and we pass in here the
in the start you know
the box will start p
so these two pieces
are now like
to me
are now just based on
on that one piece of information
oh whoops i didn't mean that was dumb i
didn't mean to actually delete the voxel
stack there what i meant to do was leave
the voxel stack but get rid of the voxel
grid
my
bad so basically what we want to do here
is get rid of that
um so we do still want the voxel stack
we just don't need to initialize it with
anything
it's just empty right
so we can initialize the voxel stack
with nothing
um
and
and off it goes
we've have it all
we
don't really need to do the diagram box
thing but i'm going to
anyway
uh by saying like wrecked min max
and passing the vox will start p voxel
and p but i actually want to use the
ones where we
um
like got them into the correct positions
and then expanded them
just to be able to show the whole thing
uh so then when we do the uh voxel
corners bit we don't really need the
check corners thing anymore so
[Music]
so like
that whole thing
this is why i say i feel like this is
just way smarter and i don't know why i
was i was thinking corner i was thinking
about voxel corners a set of voxel
centers
um
there are times when you care about one
in times when you care about the other
right
also tim 775 that's like
that's the part of the personality type
though right so for me
i don't want to keep going when i feel
smart
i want to keep going when i feel stupid
right when i don't understand something
is when i'm most motivated to look into
it
so that's like the part about
personality types right
um
it's also why i have a hard time with a
lot of games is because like
once i kind of roughly understand
something i i don't really want to play
them anymore
um
so
i always
i always work harder when i feel like i
don't understand something
and then once i feel like i understand
it too much i get a lot less interested
in doing it
um because i'm just like well what am i
going to learn right like not much
so
anyway uh
so let's see here so the voxel corners
thing
again is not very
necessary anymore like this whole thing
uh doesn't have to happen
and so really all we're gonna do is
we're gonna get the current cell i and
we can just look it up directly in here
i think
right
so we can basically say like look we're
gonna look up the corner code
uh for this voxel
actually we don't even need to do that
uh because we already know that we can
stand here so the only thing we're gonna
do is like check
the directions we want to
travel in from here
right
so we already know
we already know we can stand here
because we've checked it right
and the embedded part is the only
problem that we're going to have
so when we get up here yeah so we do
want we want something like this
which is like
that checks for collision but we
wouldn't be doing it here is my point
right so
so we wouldn't be doing it here
um and embedding we'll have to kind of
we'll have to
work out
in a different way
so
looking at this part of the cell code
get closest point in box conservative
if we want to know what the cell is
it's literally just
wherever we
are so
the cell center p
and then the cell dimension
is just the cell
right
and
so knowing the position is very simple
the cell center p is just the current
cell i times the cell dim plus whatever
the voxelman corner was
right
um
all right so uh yeah so the the this 2p
part of things right that this 2p is
just i believe it's just the 2p but we
um
have like an adjustment that we're going
to do for embed code so we're going to
leave that part in
um
this part does an if not found best so
that's just to skip over the part
where it decides it doesn't need to look
for stuff anymore
so it doesn't do this part of things
so when we do this
again this part now is much more
straightforward so when we actually go
to check various sides
there's only going to be one test here
right
so each one of these is just going to be
like um
like something like should
test corner
you know what i mean
um and should test corner is gonna wanna
do
this it's gonna pass like whatever that
um
thing was that it was
building
for the next voxel eye
um and so what i might s
hey
is that like
push voxel stack
we could just roll that into that call
i'm having trouble deciding
it would be relatively free for us here
too if we wanted to to allow diagonal
movement now but i just don't know that
we want to
but we definitely could allow it now
so yeah so like when we go in here
i guess i can see why we had the voxel
grid part of things but i'm not sure we
actually
want to keep it like i said we probably
want to just remove it because it's a
little bit
misaligned for our needs now but
so when we do should test corner
uh what i'm trying to figure out is
what's the best way to structure this
part here
like
we can
do it this way
but that seems kind of redundant because
we're already calling a function whose
only job is to do literally that
you know
so it seems like maybe what we would
want to do instead is just
have that be what this code does
right
so when we call push voxel stack this
code checks to see whether we actually
want to do that now the only reason not
to do that is that push voxel stack then
would need like the condition code
which it would have to get by doing an
actual test
so
in order to call collides at p it needs
the same region the entity and the p
which it doesn't actually have right
so
maybe
what we do is something more like this
uh
so that we have like in
push voxel stack
we have like the condition code maybe
that goes on the end
right
now the reason i don't like that is
because it should check the corner code
first
so that just seems to it seems to me
that you really do want
this to be one thing
right
so effectively you come in here and you
do this
and this
is predicated right so you're like
right so you basically say all right
we're going to go
and look to see whether we can stand on
this or not and if we can or can't we're
going to like go ahead and push that on
there's got to be some more stuff in
here which is like when we push things
on the stack we have to look to see
whether or not we can be there or not
based on the embed code so there's going
to be a little bit of extra fungibility
there but
so basically what has to happen is this
uh where we say you know go ahead and
put that on there
now again maybe this is the wrong way
about it maybe these should actually be
out in the code here but i don't know
it's really hard to say
um but you could see it would now look
basically like that
the p-value for the entity is going to
be derived from i
so i'm pretty sure we don't need that
right
um
and then if we had a way
and maybe we sort of do
so like if we came in here and said
let's not phrase it that way let's
phrase it this way where we say current
cell plus like side x zero zero
you know what i mean
um then what we could do is say well
each one of these
just rolls into that call
right
so at that point this also seems a
little bit unnecessary because you
essentially have
this flip thing happen right where side
x
you can see here like
we already have the thing we actually
wanted to test which is you know you you
could just do
um
in fact you don't even need the flip
part of things you could just put this
at the bottom
like this is just um
right
because all you're doing is this
like side x equals not side x
i suppose it's maybe it's more compact
to write it that way because you'd have
to initialize the variable up here but
you know
so anyway
a little bit more compact
which is nice
um and then the min corner value i think
probably what i would do is say like the
min corner value
um
and and maybe like the better way to say
this is min center
like this is the min center point of
this voxel
so i think that's what we roughly want
and in here
we're gonna have this problem where when
you're embedded you can't push on so you
wouldn't be able to move at all right
um
and so that's okay right now um we're
just not gonna deal with that at the
moment
so we'll we'll take a look at that later
but at the moment
we just want to do the sim region
i don't actually know what that's called
here's just region not sim region
uh so basically what we're going to do
here is yeah just have push voxel stock
stack handle that
so we set up the min center p so that it
knows what that would actually be uh we
come through here and you know
this
cell center p would be maybe something
that we have a call for
so we just say like
this code for example
yeah so all of this stuff now goes away
too
right so we can basically get rid of
this voxel iterator nonsense we don't
need it anymore
i don't know where that was actually
defined
all right i guess it was all all
encompassing
um
so
i think
i think we're all good so if we have all
these already defined we should then be
able to do a thing where we say
from the voxel stack
um
we can
take the voxel min center
we can add the cell dim
and we can get
any center out that way trivially right
so that allows us to do
the operations we actually care about
um which is like this
here
can now just be like
get cell
center p
here's the stack
here's the index
and off we go
when we do push voxel stack here uh we
need to do
uh checking against
the is in bounds or is in rectangle
or whatever
i don't know if we have
one of these too many functions
too much volcano
so we really just don't have you know
there's too many
there's too much volcano
um
there's too many of these like if we you
know if this were a normal project i
would have a much cleaner math library
for it
uh because you know it'd be something
that i would spend time cleaning up
uh but on a project like handmade here
where you kind of drop in and out of it
it tends to get a little bit more
sprawling it's not as you know tidy
but
what are you gonna do so anyway uh
really all we need to check here is if
this thing is
you know not too far out of bounds we we
want effectively this
function
right
um
but we don't have it because the gen v3
is like a different thing
and and
it's it's actually not like you see the
type def here is the same
so
i'm guessing that means that actually
actually we can just use that
so i guess we can just use this we can
say is in array bounds
and then we can just say like well
it's not voxel stackdem
is it
i guess it is
i think that's all we really need
um
probably
so is in array bounds
is all we really need for that
um
now the pushed part of things the push
voxel stack part
um is just like
have tested
because we may never have pushed it
right so we're really just saying have
we ever tested this particular one
once we
go to visit it we only want to visit it
once so we say never visit it again
which is all that does
and then we call collides at p
um and we pass the sim region the entity
and then the p value here is just the
like
get min
uh uh does it get voxel center p
it's just the center p for whatever the
in whatever the index was that they
passed in
so we're just going to test it at that
point
right think that's all we need
uh the collision field that comes back
from this
uh for embedding purposes
um i guess we now need to
return
and we'll look at how this data flow
works in a little bit because we
probably want to make some modifications
but
right
so
something like this
um
this code is now gone
right um it's just not a thing
anymore
uh so all of that is
is just not necessary which is why i
said i think this is just better right
so
[Music]
all right
so the best cell thing so this code
right here
um
is probably all we really need
so i'm not sure we care about the rest
of that we could make that an actual
call i'm not sure if we want to or not
we maybe do
uh in which case
you know we would just make our own
version
so like get cell bounds and we could put
that in here as well
so in here we'd pass whatever the index
was and this would return
probably just by calling this
and we'll
assume that'll be sufficient
so we'd call rec center dim with
whatever the stack value was
the cell dim
we again need here
and then everyone can call this
when they want
the
information
about the entire rectangle
and so now we just want to kind of clean
this up a bit um before debugging it uh
because it's kind of all garbage up now
and probably isn't quite as
like properly aligned now than it as it
should be
um
and then maybe we weld these things
together because the voxel grid probably
if we just added a feature that allowed
it to be created
um we could use the voxel grid here
so we may don't want to go merge that
code so that there's just like one set
of voxel code
like in the system or whatever like
maybe we want to do that i don't
actually know
uh
it's hard to say
if we actually want that or not you know
we might we might not
um
so now like yeah you know
surprisingly that just ran the first
time
which is actually not what i was
expecting to have happen
and not only does it run but it's
like doing something but i don't think
it's actually working right you can see
like it's
it's doing the opposite of what you
would expect it to do
i think in a lot of cases maybe not
well no i guess it's actually
it's running and it's working which are
not things that i would have expected it
to do
so that worked unreasonably well uh for
something that probably shouldn't have
there you go you got it stuck there or
whatever you know
so you know it's like it's like it
shouldn't be working as well as it's
working because we literally just kind
of slapped that in there
um
i guess that's good i'm i'm not going to
complain too hard
but uh it's definitely
yeah um
yeah
anyway uh you know what i might do too
while we're at it i i'm just kind of
tired of looking at the world in
wireframe so i might turn that
off for now
so the code where we kind of nerfed the
um
we nerfed the part where we drew the
actual entities
for cubes
um
at least i think that's what we did
yeah
uh and i'm just going to put that back
in
probably something we should have a
debug switch for right
um
so yeah like again i'm kind of surprised
that that works
uh
but
you know
uh i'm sure it doesn't work very well so
like that was you know i guess that was
a good first um go at it but like yeah
as you can see it gets stuck really
easily so you know it's it's it's
incorrect what i typed in which is what
i would have expected but
um it's surprising that it works as well
as it does uh
that was unexpected
so what i'd like to do is go through now
and just clean this up a little bit more
if we look at
the move entity call uh so the first
thing i was saying is like what like
maybe we can collapse these down
uh to the voxel grid stuff uh
the stack is is quite a bit different
but it's possible that we could
change it around i i don't the reason
i'm worried about that is because the
voxel grid is not based around centers
the voxel grid is based around corners
so you know i don't know if i want
it to
i don't know if i want to try and make
those both work together
there's not that much reason why you
can't do that
but it does
my instinct says no like not for
collision code you probably want to be
working on the centers if you're working
on centers always
so that's why i'm a little hesitant to
do that
i do however think we could move the
voxel stuff out of there and into the
other piece of code
um so that part i'm not sure about like
like we could say that you know the
voxel stack goes in here because it's a
voxely kind of thing
um
and and we push that code out into this
voxel part of things because they're all
like voxely things
um so i might kind of do something like
that
hard to say
i'm i'm undecided undecided
um
so there's some pretty nice aspects of
this so when we actually call refined
voxel placement we now know like what
we're actually doing
so when we do like get closest point in
box conservative and we pass like the
front p and the 2p
here uh that was actually not necessary
right um
the from p part of things we don't
actually have to do
so this actually solves the problem we
had before which is that this code was
actually garbage
now this code doesn't have to be garbage
because we can do
um
instead one where we say clamp just the
local target
right
and then we will refine the voxel
placement based on the center point so
like that
because now we know we are starting from
the center of the voxel which we have
tested and know that we can occupy and
then we're not going to move outside of
the bounds of it because we clamped this
to the bounds of it
so uh that is actually way better so
again the center
voxel centers way better for collision
um
we are finding out rapidly
uh base everything off your voxel
centers and i think you're in better
shape
uh so anyway um i think all of that is
fine so let's take a look at now the
rest of this code a little bit more
carefully
so i don't know what dir does now
does it do anything
no
what does side do
so side only exists here
right
um so that to me
uh suggests
that
this probably could be
written directly in here
you know what i mean
now the only point of this anyway
is just to make sure we look in the
faster direction first
which is just an optimization so even
this is kind of stupid
right
um
but hopefully what you can see here is
like
this code could just be
that
probably um i mean maybe not
i'm just trying to code this a little
bit cleaner
so like if you there's just way too much
garbage in here so so let's say let's do
this differently
we now know basically what we're doing
right and we're doing this
we start out with these
um we know we want to do this loop twice
and at the end we just do
[Music]
this
negate side
each time
right so now we know that we've
pushed on the three ones that are going
in the direction we're actually trying
to go and then we flip them and we push
the other ones the second time
right
um
that's what we're doing here
and at that point one has to ask oneself
why you would not just do this
which is what the compiler is going to
do anyway and that's probably easier to
read
right
i think
that is a cleaner way to write that
um
that just that just seems like what you
want
so i'm gonna i'm gonna call that good
so i think that's all we need for that
part of the code it pretty
straightforward right so we're just
testing and we test in that order
and that's all we do
um
we don't have the embedding stuff in
here yet so we're going to do that in a
second but i want to do the first part
first
so this code is now quite simple right
um
i mean maybe what we do want to do is
sort of i don't know maybe we do want to
have the embed stuff here so like
if we were in an embedded state
um
it would be like this
so the collision field has the occupied
flag
um and we'd have to imagine that if it
came back occupied then we are embedded
to start with
right if we're embedded to start with
then what we're doing is we're searching
through embedded space for some place
that's not embedded
um
and so uh when
we when we look at a particular point
we're
going to allow ourselves to
we're going to allow ourselves to
post
so i take that back
uh i think actually
we don't even need that we just need one
we don't even need to track this
am i wrong
um you know i might be wrong
um
i think all that happens here
is that if we are
embedded we are allowed to move to
embedded
so basically that doesn't have to happen
and neither does that
this doesn't
happen so what we do here is we just do
a push voxel stack
and
we don't return anything
uh all we do
is say
uh
that if we are embedded we're allowed to
move to somebody else who was embedded
right
so in the event that we haven't tested
whoever it is
uh we do the collides at p test and we
just say that the result occupied has to
be equal to
uh
our occupied or or like um um originate
or occupied
so whoever originated this move
they just pass us in
whether they were occupied or not and we
can only move to one that's the same as
what we are
right
because we're embedded and we need to
get unembedded and so the only thing
we're allowed to do is move to
the closest
unembedded space
and that's the end of our move right
now one could argue that we're supposed
to do that and then also be able to move
but
uh
i don't know about that so i think i'm
gonna leave it at that for now
so if that's the case then really all we
do here is just say that when we re when
we pop the voxel stack here right
um
and so i guess i
i may be misspoke the first push voxel
stack
does have to be able to always work
and i suppose that's the one thing that
we're not really ex sort of doing here
meaning this one has to work no matter
what
so it's almost like a mask
in that sense
you know what i mean
um
because we don't want you to move back
to this point
so this one maybe maybe there's just
like that which is like look you have
you have to push this on
yeah
uh
something like that i don't know we'll
well
so in push voxel stack here right
this is just more
complicated unfortunately right
what we need to be able to do is we want
to be able to do this code and we want
to be able to do it either with this
condition or always
right
so you can imagine like there's an
always flag here
and so that's a little bit
jank
right
um
so it's you know it's not as good
trying to think if there's a better way
to do this part
because what we really want to be able
to do here is just say look if we were
embedded
we're just trying to find
the closest unembedded space
oh so actually maybe there's a different
way to do that
maybe what you're doing is actually
something like
is actually something like this
if the originator was occupied then you
could move to either
right
that actually makes more sense
so it's actually like if
if the result is not occupied
or the originator was occupied
that's actually what you want yeah yeah
yeah so like if the originator was
occupied or
the place that we're moving to is not
occupied
yeah
so i think the only problem we then have
there is knowing the answer to this
question which has to be stored on the
stack
meaning the cell stack
has to track whether or not that point
was occupied or not
right
which means maybe we can untangle this
code a little bit more because if that's
the case then maybe we can just say
well
no because we still have to track who
pushed us on
so you see what i'm saying i'm not the
only thing i'm not sure about here is
where i get this flag from it seems like
it has to be stored on the stack and i'm
not sure if there's a more clever way
right
um now the one thing i could do is store
it in here
so this could be a corner code
right
um
so basically it's like the zero one two
thing
so instead of have tested
this could be like you know
an occupy code
so it's like zero if you've never tested
it one if it's occupied two if it's
unoccupied or vice versa
right
and then what you would do is you'd pull
it out here
um where you would say like um
so you'd pull out the occupy code for
the one you were on you'd pass it in
and say this is the occupy code
that i'm
oops
this is the occupy code that i came from
and then
the code would be able to
do a test there to determine which one
it should use
um
that's the actual code for it
i'm going to write that in a slightly
different way it's same thing but i'm
just going to write it as equal 0
because i want to emphasize the fact
that it's now a um
like a code it's 0 1
2. so now when we go in here what we
would say is we need to do the uh test
and so what we're gonna do is set the
occupy code equal to uh the result
occupied
um that's gonna be zero or one
or like true or false so we need to do
is set it to like if it's occupied it's
one thing if it's unoccupied it's the
other right so maybe it's two in one i
don't know
so then what we want to be able to do
here is something like if
the originator code
which is this thing
if the originator code is
uh
two
so i think what we want is this way
although i guess it doesn't really
matter
i guess it doesn't really matter um so
we're going to produce a code
we're going to store the code
we know that whatever we stored
will get sent back in here when we're
trying to do a move
we want to do something like this
right
so as long as whoever the originator was
if we just want to set the code equal to
whatever would make this be true in the
case we care about
so for example if it's occupied right
um then
yeah i mean what we probably want to do
is say look if this code is greater than
the originator code
and uh that way like um
that way what we would do is say
look
in the case where the originator code
was occupied then the thing we moved to
could be occupied or unoccupied so we
just say
uh occupied is one unoccupied is two
so then when we do the move we just test
to make sure that like all right if you
are coming from an unoccupied you're a
two so you can't move into a one you can
only move into a two which would be this
right
if you are occupied you can move into an
occupied or an unoccupied so we use
again greater than or equal to right
for pushing uh on at the beginning oops
now we have a clear path here as well
which is to say that we can just pass a
1 there or a zero right which just says
that it doesn't matter what happens
you're gonna move right
um so that's kind of handy because now
like all that stuff makes reasonable
sense
right
okay
so now i
think that handles um
embed codes just fine
it wouldn't require repulsion here
meaning this will just find if there's a
way to get out it'll find it
um
the problem is only in the best distance
calculation
so i think actually this code doesn't
need to be here anymore
i think this is now just entirely
correct the search just works
everything's fine
the only problem with this code now
is we want it to pick the closest point
to the embedded
location
right
so we don't really want to allow you to
move in a direction we want you to now
have to be
searching for
the closest point to you
um
and so that's a little tougher
because it means that push voxel stack
needs like an if statement here
um
and the problem is we almost want to do
the test early
so so like we kind of want to do
this
and
in the event that we find
here
uh
we probably want to do this test and get
the repulsion vector
and actually make that be the movement
direction so we're just looking in the
direction of the repulsion for some
place to put us roughly um
so so i honestly feel like we kind of
have to do this
right so so when we do
the voxel start p
um we kind of want this
if it's occupied then 2p
uh is just going to be equal to
from p
right
and
this part here
is
the only change that we make is we only
do this code
the found best code
we only do that if we were unembedded
and so now rather than have those in
there we should be able to do like
an occupy code
thing here which is like occupy
untested
occupy
like filled and occupy open or something
something like that
um and so here you know we set these
equal to these uh so that now the code
we can just make the code more readable
like instead of two you know it's occupy
open
um instead of uh zero
it's occupy untested
and then up here uh
we just you know put those in
there um
right
and just a little bit clearer
what's happening there
um
c is just c plus plus is the worst just
freaking
deal with it dude
enum typing is like complete garbage and
see
um so i think that would work
uh for embedding as well
um and i think we're basically out of
time so i'll call it there but
next week we'll just go ahead and and uh
tighten up this this code
uh but i think this is probably much
better
than it was right um
i think this is in much better shape
way simpler um
much easier to understand
and i think it will be like
better too
because it means that for like the same
amount of testing you could use a um
a more refined grid
because you're not doing like
all of this thinking about corners which
is going to make it be less efficient
right um so yeah so i think this will be
good uh the only thing we now have to do
is actually go do the part i was talking
about before
uh where we only test uh at aligned
corners which we're not doing at the
moment right so the bug that we're
talking about originally will should
still be in there it's not showing up at
the immediate moment but
uh the reason for that is because um we
disabled the code for checking it we now
allow things to get unembedded so the
bug is there
uh but we're just not
um
seeing it right
um so yeah we got a bunch of stuff to do
and we will do it but
that's the issue so i'm gonna put it to
do in here
so when we do this collides at p
um
and and maybe we don't even maybe i
shouldn't say that maybe we just do like
an align to movement voxel
so
we always do this
so that way we know like we're always
going to test the position as if it was
at the center of its movement voxel so
that way we don't ever have like that
particular bug
um
and you know again so it shouldn't
really change anything the only thing
that you will see is now you'll notice
you notice how like where things are is
slightly offset from where they are
tested so like you could see how the
white
collision
diagrams don't exactly line up with the
blue collision volumes
that is that snapping and again that
snapping is to ensure that our numerical
accuracy is doesn't matter um and are
like we don't have to be careful about
those things we're always going to test
apples to apples even
in the most extreme scenario because
we're just forcing everyone to just be
where their voxel is right
um so more work to do definitely but
getting there rapidly um i'm starting to
really like this collision detector i
think it's going to be pretty good at
the end of the day
it just takes a while to get there
because it's a complicated problem and
you want you have to kind of think it
through and see opportunities as they
arise and so on
so yeah
obviously
again
you you definitely uh
need the spatial partition though to
make it be not too slow um so that's
something we're going to have to do
um but other than that
um
relatively optimistic about it i would
like to be able to turn off the
diagramming
but i don't have a button for that right
now
we should have had one
so like in the editor code
uh
i actually don't remember what this is
supposed to do but like this
um
so like this
i feel like we need some kind of a
global for
um
so you know something like
this
where you just disable diagrams by
pushing some button
and
it just does
something like that
i think that's probably the easiest way
to do it not sure
apparently not
because while that that doesn't seem to
actually do the reset
maybe i'm misinterpreting what that
actually does
oh that's got the yeah
that's got this garbage in there
um
we really should have a way of
controlling that part of things
i'm assuming that roughly what should
happen there is the
maybe there should be like a
a thing here where it's like
like a capture frame count something
like that
you know what i mean
uh
so like you set that
capture frame count
maybe that's the right thing to do
because then you can just set that up to
how many frames you want to capture and
that's what you have right
um and i guess the
you know one annoying thing is we would
like to be able to set the capture frame
count to something
um originally
but
this should be good enough
i don't actually remember what that is i
think it's the step
um
so anyway um so in theory now like we
could do a thing where we like capture
more frames
like so
um it's a little weird though that it
doesn't i guess because reset it's
always going to capture like one frame
because that reset gets called at the
end
right
so disabled diagrams is not really going
to do anything
but
yeah
we'll take a look at that next time
we'll have to provide better controls
for the diagramming
than what we have at the moment
you can see like how slow it gets down
here right so you can see like that the
collision detector just takes all the
time right
because this was previously running
nicely and smoothly
so the spatial partition is a must-have
and maybe we'll put that in soon
but i do just want to get this cleaned
up a little bit more first
you
i wonder what i should do about the fact
that you can go like the glove goes
underneath these guys right
because hey the collision detector
figures out that you can put it
underneath so when it tries to go under
it just rolls off
anyway
all right so we'll clean that up next
week um but otherwise i think we're good
any questions about that
chat was too quiet
be careful what you wish for technic
beam
there was 330 viewers it looks like so
it was a fairly normal
number of people watching i guess they
just didn't have much to say
or twitch chat is broken and they're all
like frantically typing but
it's like just going into devnull
or something
so you never see it
yeah so uh
just to be clear about uh mine mark 42
the problem that we have with things
moving um that i was trying to explain
earlier was just that
we are using the corners of voxels to
determine we were using the corners of
voxels and looking at them
and
we then said if you could be placed
inside this voxel because like one of
the corners was open that meant that you
could sit be somewhere in the voxel at
least then we allow you to be in that
voxel
the way we test the corners is we were
testing if you could put the entity at
those corners
against entities in their actual final
resting positions which are placed by
the refinement algorithm
which means that the refinement
algorithm
and the corner testing are completely
different so depending on whether you're
the person moving
or the person being moved against you're
using completely different tests
so it's trivial to get two objects if
they're both moving
to be placed in a way such that from
either of their perspectives they are
both colliding
right or rather from one of their
perspectives they are now embedded
because when the second person moved
they placed the object in a place that
would invalidate all of the corners of
the person against whom they're moving
because the place where the person was
actually placed doesn't happen to be one
of those corners
so what i wanted to do instead is switch
to a system where we always test voxel
centers
and everything is always considered to
be at its voxel center so the test is
always the same
and then when we do our refinement
movement we do do allow you to place
things continuously so it doesn't like
snap as it moves around
but
when we place it there it's only visual
so we we put it there visually
but where we actually do the collision
check is still where the voxel is
that's why i align it back so that way
everybody who ever does a collision test
always tests each other based on the
center of the voxel
and we know that it's the same
i don't think i do have chat set to
subscriber only because there's tons of
non-subscribers posting so i think it's
just
how much verticality is there going to
be because gameplay-wise you may end up
restricting election to a plane uh no we
don't have to restrict question to a
plane
you can just be totally free with that
don't know if we'll use it but the
engine allows you to use it so we we
don't have that restriction in the
gameplay you're allowed to
um
to
have collision work
vertically
uh won't won't that result in clipping
uh clipping
what is clipping in this case
clipping is like
a
very nebulous term
it really got corrupted because what
happened was
because quake uses a bsp
carmack used to use the term
clip
into the bsp to for collision because
you would push a point through the bsp
and you would clip it
in the way that you normally think of
clipping you clip the movement so when
you turn
when you wanted to move everywhere you
turned on no
but but that's like not the right term
right so but
ah okay so uh no i don't think it does
because we check based on the center
um
only to the extent that we uh
want to collide against something
but when something's moving we adjust
its position
uh
we do the collision checks on the
position as well
so when we we start at the center and we
say allow the thing to move inside the
voxel that it's in up to the point where
it would collide with something and no
further
right
so you can't get inside a wall because
as it tries to place the thing it won't
allow it to get any closer to the wall
than if it was colliding
so everyone's still checking for
collision it's just that when you
actually do your versus your collision
checks versus each other
we do adjust you to the center of the
voxel because we want it to always be
the same
the voxel has to be small enough that
the displacement of the wall
won't be so much
that you could
dramatically
you know like if the voxels were very
large
then you could see that allowing you to
put yourself
significantly inside a wall because it's
like well
we're gonna pretend the wall is very far
away from where it actually is
um but because the voxel is very small
relative to the size of the sprites that
really isn't a concern right
um yeah i knew you could do something
about enum types but i didn't know what
spec that was in so i never use it um
i am usually loathe to add anything
that's a new c plus feature because
usually what happens is if you use it it
sucks
um in ways that you don't know about yet
so you try to start using it thinking it
will be reasonable and then it turns out
like all your code breaks because it
actually isn't reasonable
um
so
i haven't tried that yet i'm usually
very skeptical about those sorts of
things but if that's now widely
supported
i might consider it
like uh i think what you're saying is
that it would allow me to do
that
right
um
so like ah
maybe um
i again i'm usually very very like
skeptical
uh
so i tend unless i really need a feature
in c plus i usually won't add it
because
almost every time i've ever tried to do
that it ends up being a bad idea
so
you know
do i really need that piece of code no
so i probably would just leave it out
um but you know
it may be one of the rare c plus
features that isn't totally awful um
but i don't usually like to bet on that
so since i normally don't care
like normally you don't have this
problem because normally you're not
putting things in a u8 so you're usually
okay
um
but
it is one of the things that sucks about
the original way c was defined so you
know
it's not like c did that right and c
plus did it totally wrong or something
but
i i headless course i have never uh
corpse i've never read that book
what is the reason that things like sim
region get passed around instead of
plucking it from a global variable um
the reason is because uh you might have
more than one of them
like we we even did that because we have
a thing that we don't like leave it on
right now but we have a thing that
allows you to do multi-threaded region
updates
where like you can update multiple
regions of the world at the same time
like you could imagine if you had like a
multiplayer situation where like one
player was in one place and another
player was in another place they're
completely separate and you wanted to
update both of them
so the reason i generally don't put
things in global variables is for that
reason most things
have at least a slight risk
of needing to have two or three
you know if not a hundred right
and so it's pretty rare that i don't
want to pass in
just at least one pointer that's like
here's the context that you're operating
in
and yeah it's sort of a global
but it's just not global enough that i
don't want to have to go fix all the
code
because i usually know i'm like yep once
in a while i'm going to want to have two
of these live or something right
so
it's like a global and i treat it like a
global
but i just want it passed in because i
know that sometimes i need more than one
in flight not a thousand but you know a
couple
so
all right
looks like we're
we're good here
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for the episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow the
series at home you can always pre-order
the game on handmadehero.org it comes
with the source code
um so that you can
follow along at home and if you'd like
to go
inspect the
collision stuff like i just kind of put
that stuff in there just now and next
week will really be the time we're going
over it so if you would like to go ahead
and
uh
try yourself to kind of like
iron out the the rough parts of the code
before i do
um you can give it a shot right
our kickstarter is also currently going
on right now you can actually uh just
type meow book 2 kickstarter into your
favorite search engines wherever they
may be
our kickstarter is only one week left
so
if you would like
to receive your very own copy of very
cool graphic novel series you can
actually go there and do that right now
um the campaign went very well so i
guess there was a lot of people who were
um
yeah it went very well went way better
than we were expecting
um to say the least it's almost 300
percent of the of the goals that's
pretty cool but
there's not much time left for that so
if you're interested in that please
check it out
we'd love to send you some books from a
print run uh and uh
it's a it's got all the information on
here so you can check it out
anyway
that's about it for this week
because it is still the last week of
kickstarter i will be doing um some more
stuff
um
this week that are kickstarter related
because like i just been doing a lot of
streams for publicity uh right for doing
pr
to let people know the kickstarter is
available and to check it out and all
that
and uh there will be some more of that
so
there will be at least
two more streams
on
tuesday
morning
uh there will be a stream
um that will be another lecture kind of
like the university of tuenta lecture
um for a company asked me on the east
coast if i would do
um a presentation
to to their company
um not exactly sure why but that's just
something that happens companies ask you
to give talks sometimes i don't know
normally i say no but
in this case it's during the kickstarter
so you know during the kickstarter i'm
doing pr stuff i'm happy to do talks
because
part of my job description during the
kickstarter is you know to
to do pr right
so uh
that's gonna happen tuesday morning the
topic is still not necessarily
determined i
have
a list of topics they were interested in
because i asked them uh and i don't have
to pick one from there but i probably
will because i find it's usually better
if i just like find out what the people
who are
at that company are like interested in
of the stuff that i do
so
i i don't quite know yet
but it'll probably either be about
cryptocurrency stuff
or it will be about uh
like
the 30 million line problem
kind of stuff
um
so we'll see
but that'll be tuesday morning
and yeah it'll it'll be
uh
it'll be the well dj terfel the the goal
is to allow you to pay a lot more money
for those
that's what starco galaxy is it's just
we're still in development
right so you can't have it yet
for that reason it's uh
uh it's coming right uh
i everyone's been asking for it for like
seven years now or something six years
however long i've been doing this for uh
and i'm finally doing it it's just very
very
um
it's very time intensive for me because
i wanted to do a good job
like like when it goes from being me
just sitting up in front of a blackboard
randomly saying stuff
to this is actually a course that you're
going to pay for
right
i want it to be a certain quality level
and i want to explore
certain possibilities that
you know require time
so it's just it's like anything i do
it's a long development process because
i don't just crap out the first thing i
think of so like you know
that's the thing
but uh we're working on it
handmade hero does work on linux if you
use community ports of it there are
people who have ported it to linux but i
don't maintain a linux port so that kind
of depends on you
right
um
yeah
anyway uh i was supposed to be signing
off and here i am talking about more
stuff
no point being
so yeah please check out the kickstarter
if you haven't already
uh star code galaxy which just came up
it's just starcodegalaxy.com
right um and you can sign up for the
mailing list but that's going to be the
place where you will uh
actually find
the full set of like everything
um
that uh
basically like a here's my idea of how
you learned a program
right like actually learned a program
not like the fake learn to program that
people do when they get a cs degree
and not the fake learner program that
people do when they like go watch some
crappy cpp con thing or take some
seminar by someone who doesn't really
program right
um
so starcode galaxy is like this is how i
think you actually learned a program
like if you actually want to know how to
program this is how i this is how you do
it
um and
like i said it's a very big undertaking
it's been extremely difficult
uh
i basically had to move on to it full
time because there's so much stuff to do
uh but i'm hoping that you know at least
at that point it'll just be like okay
look here it is and we're done so like
anyone who wants it it's there now i
don't have to keep saying i don't know
uh where you would go to learn it
because obviously people ask me all the
time and that's what i have to say i'm
like i don't know i i don't know how you
learned a program
currently because i there are no
resources out there that are very good
right
so this will just be like look
this is now you ask me this is my answer
i can definitively say that i think this
is how you should learn to program you
know that doesn't mean i'm right but at
least now i have an answer right and and
i can just be like this is the answer
for me is this
um
but yeah like i said it involved
creating a lot of new technology uh tons
of stuff that no one's done before or at
least i've never seen anyone do before
and when you push into that space
you end up
having a lot of work to do and a lot of
experimentation so even though the final
thing that comes out
maybe is something you could have built
in six months
you had to spend two years experimenting
to get there right um
and so
uh
yeah it's just a slow development
process and at the at this point now i'm
in in the phase of building the back end
stuff because uh that turned out to be a
big issue as well
just how do you deploy it how do you
update it how do you have other people
be able to use the tools to do things
all these sorts of things are like
actual issues
and
i was not big surprise happy with any of
the web stuff i found that i really
didn't feel like it would be any good
um i mean that's kind of obvious just
use the web you can tell it sucks
so
we're working on it
um
it'll be done when it's done
if you sign up for the mailing list
we'll do our best to notify you but our
mailing list goes to spam all the time
because google sucks and can't program
and so does hotmail
or microsoft big surprise there
um
if you know it
the people who who work on gmail could
maybe take the class and learn to
program but the problem is they'll never
receive the email that lets them know
that the class is ready because they
program so poorly that it just goes to
their spam folder right
so it's kind of a it's kind of a weird
like unfortunate situation where like
the people who should probably take the
class and learn to code are so bad at
programming that they wrote programs
that don't let them get the emails that
let them know that now they could learn
to program
you know what can you do
uh but we're working on that we switched
our email backend provider
uh and we're going to try and send the
emails more regularly so once every two
weeks or so so that we build up a
reputation
which you now need
this is my favorite part so like in
their infinitesimal wisdom
um you know they they crawled out of
their crib to program gmail
spam filter and in their infinitesimal
wisdom what happens is the more you spam
your users the more legitimate they
think you are
so if you send email every week
you're much less likely to be sent to
spam than if you send email once every
three months
so the worst
act the more you misbehave the more they
think you are a good
actor right
like you can't make this stuff up but
that's really something that they do
because they are just that bad at their
job right um
so who knows maybe you'll get the email
maybe you won't
the people who definitely need to get
the email definitely won't
uh so that's unfortunate
but you know
you can only lead a horse to water
if the water doesn't get sent to the
spam folder
right
so
all right so uh that's about it i will
uh catch you guys on tuesday uh if not
on tuesday i have another cryptocurrency
interview uh with alex gladstein or
gladstein i don't know how he pronounces
his last name yet because i haven't
talked to him yet but on friday we'll
find out um
so uh i've got another cryptocurrency
email uh
interview going uh
uh
on friday and that one should be
interesting uh it's a person who
basically
is interested in cryptocurrencies is
because uh they do like humanitarian
work
and they have a lot of like practical
problems
getting currency to
foreign places where the banking system
may not work very well on other things
like this
and so you know uh
it's not so much gonna be an interview
about whether cryptocurrency works or
not but more about like what would like
is there any possibility that there's a
technology that we could build that
would help in this situation or is it
just never gonna work right
um
and so you know off it would go
right
um
off it would go
so
we're gonna do that interview and
hopefully that'll be good uh but we'll
see
so that's about it i'll see you for
those this week and i will be back here
next week for handmade hero same time
same place obviously as well so i'll see
you in one of those until then have fun
program everyone and i'll see you on the
internet take it easy everybody