hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream and I don't I'll be
completely honest I don't super remember
what I wanted to do but I feel like I
feel like I had wanted to implement a
little snake creature and we never
really got around to that so and I think
we also were gonna make the familiar
float around too so I feel like we're
still gonna do some more brain
programming just to make sure that that
API or I shouldn't say PR but
architectural decision pans out
reasonably well and that there's no
hidden surprises there and I know we did
the monster and we've done the hero but
doing the familiar and a little snake
creature I think would just be a good
idea to make sure that that's all it's
all kosher anyway
if you were following along at home
today is day 292 so you can go ahead and
unpack day 291 source code intro
directory if you want to follow along
with today's programming and you know I
highly recommend that you do so here
comes our project we will build and we
will load here we go and run so I think
we just have a monster hopping around
yeah
and then we've got my my hero here and
he's kind of moving around too so we've
got all those guys working but if I
remember correctly we had not yet had we
don't have a currently a floating method
of movement and we do want a floating
method of movement for this little this
little fellow right here meaning me I
guess might be a good name for him so we
want mini-me to be able to kind of float
around and yeah I feel like that's that
shouldn't be too hard
to add in there and then the other thing
that we're gonna have to do as well is I
would like to make that snake creature
and so I don't know what will make the
snake creature out if maybe we'll make
the snake creature out of these little
heads as well I'm not sure anyway so
let's go ahead and and see what's going
on there and figure out if we can get
our familiar familiar ring itself around
in a nice Pleasant fashion so here is
the code for all the brains right now
and here's the code for the familiar and
you can kind of see it doing its thing
here you can see that it figures out
roughly where it thinks the closest hero
type thing is and then it it does like a
it does a little sort of what direction
would I go to get there sort of a thing
and tries to make that happen now I
don't actually know we have not stepped
through any of this code so we don't
know what any of this stuff is doing and
furthermore we don't set a movement mode
on this character so really the movement
of it I think would immediately get
negated anyway because if yeah if if
it's set I don't actually remember let's
take a look because we've got these
movement modes in here right
there's planted and hopping and I seem
to recall that planted things will snap
themselves to they're occupying location
I feel like if they have one and so we
probably need like a movement mode you
know floating kind of a thing
to make that be okay and now I'm gonna
it's gonna go through because I think
again oops it's not in there I want
world mode we haven't really sort of
nailed down the movement mode stuff
anyway and I think that maybe needs a
little bit more attention to detail so
okay so you can see there it's it's not
even doing that operation that I said
that it should do it's not doing that at
all so that's something that probably
should have been fixed anyway you can
see the move entity called here and
that's using the entity DDP so I would
have thought and I guess I don't have to
add this yet to because this I should be
able to debug this should actually be
working as it is so this guy here we
just need to figure out what is wrong
with setting his DDP so that he can move
towards the hero because he should be
getting some sort of acceleration there
or something and we're not seeing that
so the question is you know what do we
do to make that happen all right so
first things first we've got this
acceleration over square root thing here
and that term is designed to make it so
that our accelerations got a point in
the direction of the closest hero and be
the length that we specify in
acceleration now the first thing that I
noticed there is I wonder if that
acceleration is too low so before we
start debugging anything too fancy I'm
just gonna crank it up to huge and see
what happens you know just to make sure
that it's not just a low value problem
right so you can see that the heads not
moving so with that kind of a push on it
we can be fairly sure certain that it's
not that it you know that it's basically
it's being ineffectual right and I
suppose the other thing I should
double-check first and then I'm gonna go
ahead and step in because I don't want
to guess for too long I can just when I
can just step in and see what's going on
I also want to see what happens in add
familiar want to make sure that we're
actually adding the brain and it's
correct and all that it does look like
it so I'm going to take a look at that
code and see what's happening inside
that that code for the for the familiar
for the familiars brain I should say and
just want to make sure that it's setting
it to something that makes sense so you
know here's the game running there's the
familiar we should see it creating a
vector that points off towards the hero
and let's just make sure that that's
actually happening and that is not in
any way even remotely happening in fact
so why not because we did set this to
true remember right we turn that on so
we go through our entities here and
we're looking to see if they have these
slots
in fact that's getting set is oh is it
just that it's the closeness it's too
far away I guess is that the problem I
guess that must be the problem
let's find out
closest hero d-squared
is now set to 0
how is that possible so the test entity
- our head is somehow evaluating to zero
for something with a brain slot type of
hero I am very interested to know more
about this so here's I'm going to do
step out to there and now I'm gonna step
through all of these and I'm gonna see
what's going on here here's my watch
window and here's my test dsquared so
there it is at 48 there it is a thirty
five twenty five thirty nine twenty five
fifteen thirty three nineteen and you
know I'd also point out oh you yeah so
the fact that I just had that bug and
I'll tell you what it is you didn't
already notice tight brain hero is just
the default value remember I said we
don't need a default value there well
that pretty much tells me the fact that
I can have that bug right which is just
a stupid bug that we don't want to have
tells me that brain type if in case I'm
ever looking at brain type what I
probably should do is either make it so
that there actually is a null brain type
or so that when you get the brain type
it hacks that has to actually have a
brain ID and I think I do want that to
be the case meaning I think I want you
to have a brain of sign because if this
if you happen to still have a brain type
but you haven't had you don't actually
have a brain ID that doesn't really
exist per se at that point so I got to
think about how I want to do that so
instead of brain slot type I want to do
something like an is type here where I
say brain slot and I say that right
something like this and that way when we
have these brain slaps here I can just
make it so that if the if if the type it
matches the index still has to be
nonzero does that make sense
so basically there'd be like a B 32 here
that's like is type and I say here is
the slot and then what the type is that
I want and then the result of that is
just that it has an index and the type
is the same right so that that is better
because now we're not gonna it was going
to return all kinds of false positives
before so there we go and of course
we're gonna get a max entity velocity
violation there were you know our
assertion that things shouldn't be
moving too quickly because we're gonna
have to go return the ridiculous
acceleration on this guy down to
something not so ridiculous as it were
okay so yeah we're gonna have to tune
this guy's motion and the other thing
too is we probably want him to slow to a
stop like right now what he's doing is
he's kind of doing some weird stuff
he'll be doing some very strange things
we're like he'll just stop moving
entirely if we're out of range and other
stuff like that so we probably want to
clean up this code to a certain extent
right so yeah and in fact I should also
say that in in the entity code that
actually brings up a good point which is
that in the enemy code we don't call
move entity if you're if your
acceleration is not greater than zero
but we also probably want to check to
make sure that your your velocity isn't
greater than zero because otherwise you
should keep moving right and so that
that should be more like this certainly
okay so yeah if if we take a look at
what's happening here this this dude
doesn't have any drag on him right now
so he kind of this is just going to
accelerate to random places he'll he'll
orbit us basically is what he'll do
right because he has no dragon
has no he's not attempting to stop
anywhere so he'll just keep orbiting us
indefinitely I guess pretty much always
and the eccentricity of the orbit I
guess would be something related to the
entry velocity that he had uh I think
you can kind of see now he's sort of
doing a very like triangular weird thing
and that's because when he's close to us
he's not accelerating at all
but when he gets far away from us he
accelerates back toward us and again
produces that sort of orbital like
mechanic there right all right so that's
that dude and we've got a little bit
more to do with this dude right because
again we want to introduce movement
modes for all the guys that do that
transactional move stuff properly
because what you can see is we're not
updating his occupying square and so we
don't want to just shove the velocities
into things willy-nilly we want those
velocities to you know as the the head
moves we want those to be things that
sort of properly track which square the
guys on and don't let the familiar go
into squares where there isn't room for
him right so for example you shouldn't
be able to go into that square right
that I'm on but right now we can do
anything that he wants in that respect
and that's no good
furthermore of course I can't go into I
can't enter this square right you can
see I always hop over it which is also
not right so so we need that space to
update always all right
so we've got a bunch of work to do here
and I think I want to work on these
movement modes but first I'm going to
finish off my brain stuff here and I'm
gonna create this snake dude right
because I want a snake dude so I'm gonna
do like an ADD snake thing I'm you know
we got like add monster and junk like
that
I'm gonna do an ADD snake and let's see
what I want to do with that snake is I
want to be able to drop like snake
pieces so you know I mean technically I
should probably call this add snake
piece right and what I want to do is is
take exactly the stuff that was
happening before where we're placing
pieces we're getting exactly the same
thing and essentially we're just going
to add a Monstar
in fact we could even keep hip points on
there right and I'm gonna use the
instead of a torso manie's ahead and but
otherwise students are going to be the
same and it's gonna do exactly the same
stuff that that it was doing before only
it's gonna cause a brain snake to be
created for this guy and instead of
adding the brain I'm gonna have the
brain ID be passed in and the reason for
that is I want all the snakes to I want
all the pieces of one snake to have the
same brain ID so they'll get aggregated
up and can be used you know all be
attached to the same brain all right uh
so let's see here I don't remember what
I call this or even if I had one of
these yet I thought I did but it might
not so let's see you can see I've got
type brain snake here but of course my
macro is gonna require that I have an
actual thing here as well and so I'm
gonna say alright snake segment and
we've got a bunch of segments
and I don't know how many there should
be exactly but I guess there will just
be you know you know I'm wondering too
do we use this really anymore the array
16 thing I don't know if we do anyway
because week well it doesn't matter we I
guess we yeah we kind of do because we
need to pack them so it's fine
oh wait no we don't we don't even pack
we don't even pack them yeah we might be
able to just get rid of that I'm
wondering okay so so bear with me here
for a second but let's say that the
maximum number of snakes segments is 8
I'll just bear with me for one sec
because I want to know the answer to
this question rain slop for a segment
and I guess in here we'll have segment
index and so this brain slot for thing
is also going to be a little dicey right
we're probably going to need a brain
slot or like an indexed brain slot for
where we can say like it's the segment's
thing but it's actually an array so
we've got an index right something like
that right but ok so I got a couple
things I want to do now that sort of
came up as a result of this so let's go
into the brain and you can see the brain
slot for stuff the problem here that we
would have is we need that to be a
constant and if we're passing it to a
function it's not going to be constant
now we it's pretty easy for us to have
the indexed version of this it's really
trivial so if we have the you know
indexed brain slot for all we need is
the index on here we could just say like
well whenever you get this
this member whatever it is right just go
ahead and add
however many work forward you were
wanted to go right whatever the index
was just go ahead and add that in and
that should be sufficient if that makes
sense
all right so let's compile that whereas
an l-value does it where am I that's
gonna be in here
see wait what
oh sorry parenthesis it's like a lisp
it's like programming lisp on son let's
see entities star eight and entity star
star so I guess I'd probably have to ask
specifically for the I'd also have to
ask specifically for the well or I can
just get rid of the ampersand which
actually seems smarter right so I can
just make it a simpler expression so
yeah got closed closed is that right
and let's see here converting from n64
to u16 okay
so the pack value we would have to
guarantee that it's a u16 but that seems
pretty reasonable you can see what's
happening here right this index value we
now no longer before the compiler could
tell what this offset was a compile time
now it can't write because of the index
and so well you know what I could do
this is actually a lot simpler what I
could do is just say o indexed brain
slot for it just could call brain slot
for write with exact it could be the
exact same expression and when I pass
that that second value I could just add
the index as a u16 right here right
because whatever that index value is
we're just gonna increment it up from
there so I don't really know why I
didn't think of that originally that's
way easier right
so yeah that's that's the right way to
do it and I just have to take care of
the fact that you don't really need to
take the address of this guy so it's not
an address anymore all right so what's
the problem here this is the u16 I guess
I've got to tell if this is you sixteen
as well
brain slot for a function does not take
one arguments oh okay but I'm not
passing it one argument what is what is
the problem here Porter can only be
subtracted from another pointer
oh I just love trying to program in C++
all right so let's see this has to do
the subtraction first before I can add
there you go and this is a pointer so
I'm not sure why that would be a problem
right that is already a pointer so I
guess that was just my cast with being
in the wrong place there we go
man that was our address all right so
before we get to the snake part what I
wanted to say was I don't know that we
actually need the array thing anymore
like do we need this does anyone use it
I don't actually know if they do so I'm
gonna find out if they actually do a
foot down so here we go let's see brain
index is less than array count so I
guess having a size there is nice but I
don't really know if that's the assert I
want to use and so this this array right
here I think I could just call I think
what I you know like I guess what I'm
saying is what I really want to do is I
just want to say there's one entity star
that's like the you know array pointer I
should now just be able to specify that
and this way I no longer have to guess
what the maximum number is whatever the
maximum number of things is in any of my
brains will just be the size of the
brain structure and then we'll still
access off of array right that seems
like a much better idea to me so let's
go ahead and do that because I think
that's better so in here what I want to
do is is I want to just be able to map
something into the brain this is the
only place that I need that so what I
can do is say like alright give me the
address of that pointer and then I'm
going to I'm going to address the enth
version off of that right and that
should place it basically in the right
location right because I know this is
this is the start of everything and I
can just move as many forward pointers
as I want based on the index so the only
thing I can't do is assert that that
pointer is in a valid area but even
that's pretty easy to do because I can
say entity star you know
and we're gonna want to do this for
another reason as well and that is that
c++ in its infinite decimal with 'dom
and like this is like one of the worst
decisions I've ever heard anyone make
ever when you're doing pointer
arithmetic if you don't do pointer
arithmetic on you eights
C++ is allowed to just totally screw you
and do the arithmetic entirely wrong if
they don't come from the same memory
allocation meaning based off of the same
sort of pointer granularity so for
example if you were to do pointer
arithmetic on something that's 8 bytes
long and you didn't have it aligned to
an 8 byte boundary or some other thing
like this C++ is not guaranteed to do
the arithmetic correctly it's allowed to
like substitute inferior arithmetic if
it thinks you can get a speed win I
never ever want that because if I cared
about that speed win I would do that
addressing manually but that's just the
the the rules of it in this case I don't
think we'd ever get hit because since
these things are 8 bytes long that's a
really trivial one and it would never do
any weird arithmetic because 8 bytes is
very basic but if you had something that
would say 18 bytes long that's where you
might get into trouble so anyway what I
want to do here is say okay I've got a
you 8 pointer and I'm just going to take
the address of this pointer that I've
got here right I'm then gonna say ok I
want that pointer to be advanced by
however big one of these entity pointers
is times however much the brain however
many brain slots forward I'm trying to
go then what I can do is I can just say
well ok the the the pointer to right to
right is just whatever that pointer is
cast to and E star star dereferenced
right so I'll just here I will go ahead
and do my dereferencing and I'll write
to that enemy star with the enemy star
that I have now what this allows me to
do after I have the pointer is I can
also assert that this pointer is inside
the brain structure that I started with
right so I can assert that this pointer
is less than or equal to the the pointer
of the brain and furthermore I can
subtract off the size of one entity star
to make sure that it's it's not pointing
sort of a little bit like that the eight
extra bytes for the pointer isn't
pointing off the end either right and so
I should be able to do that entity there
we go and replace all that code with
something that now no longer cares how
big it is what did I do
pointer brain oh wait what is it talking
what's the problem
pointer pointer you eight star brain -
size of entity let me take a look at
what's going on here brain
if X is zero so my pointer is pointing
to the same thing as the brain is right
so not quite I guess but let me see here
ah duh when I said I wanted to point to
the end I have to obviously add the size
of the brain duh so I need to start
where the brain begins go to the end of
the brain and then subtract off one
entity and that's the furthest forward I
should ever be and so I can make my
assertion back into what it used to be
all right so that's more pleasant to me
now so I'm gonna leave it that way
oops so by the way like just to
underscore kind of you know I'm always
complaining about C++ and so I like to
kind of point out the reasons why I
think it's such it's so ridiculous what
they do none of that code should ever
have to be written by a programmer you
should just be able to say that these
things are overlays and they're you know
different mappings of the same thing
that I want to then access by an index
that's what you want your programming
language to be able to do right you want
to be able to have your programming
language understand the concept that you
may be packing multiple things in one
place and you want to be able to like
figure out what the biggest one of those
things was and then create an array of
entity stars that's the one that you use
to map those automatically this is super
super like so basic it's like one of the
most basic things you might ever do in a
meta programming environment it's
trivial to implement very very simple
but you know C++ is mentality and that
like the mentality of the people who
upgrade it is always to like make these
systems that allow you to program in
some way that they think is a good way
to program or whatever it doesn't even
really make sense to me most of time
what they're really trying to do but
it's something like this and in so
instead of allowing programmers to just
write the code
that they want and make that systemic
they want to enforce a system so this is
the kind of code for example I don't
ever have to write that Molly rocket
because when you are using meta
programming as your basis you've built
stuff that allows you to just make this
stuff happen correctly automatically
right but when you're forced to program
in a language that's about people
specifying policy and especially when
those people aren't very good at
programming to begin with they make bad
policy and then the only tools you're
left with in the language are ones that
enforce bad policy and so it's really
hard to do basic simple operations like
this like you saw all the weird stuff I
have to do here this is a very
semantically straightforward very basic
programming operation barely above what
you would do in assembly language right
and yet C++ makes it impossible to
actually write the thing that you want
which is just how many is the most
number of
entity stars in the set that I have that
I want an array of that right in this
union sorry we have no idea how we could
ever write a program realize it would
let you do that right and it's that sort
of thing that I am always up against I
find if you don't have meta programming
you're constantly doing these really
basic things that are just about simply
looking at what you've already defined
in a very very straightforward fashion
that really doesn't even involve much
code you know very very simple code and
it can't do any of them it's just like
and then of course you get the single
source was like oh well you know you
just make a it into a template and you
template eyes it on the number of things
there are and then you pass that
template to the other time you're just
like what no it's three lines of code
for me to write it directly the thing
that actually does it should be you know
at least that simple anyway all right so
enough about that let's go ahead and
make our snake because that's what I
want to do when I started so but I just
want to clean up that part first so if I
go over to the snake piece thing
I should be able to call the snake adder
so when I add the Monstar which I'm
doing here as you can see I'm gonna go
ahead and add the snake and in order to
add the snake I'm gonna add like the I
might cost stripe two pieces across the
top or something
so I'll just say piece index equals zero
and piece index you know is less than
one plus plus piece index so you know
start out with coops but to start out
with we'll just have one snake piece and
then when we get that working will add
more snake pieces right pretty pretty
singing approach I would think and I'll
need a brain for this so you know before
I do anything I'll have to make a brain
ID here but that's pretty easy just that
and then the segment index so I guess
it's segment index sorry why I called it
a piece and snake segment so that's the
snake now all I have to do is decide
where it's gonna be
I'll put it vertically down the far side
maybe so let's say it's Sun twelve I you
know why round twelve Y and we'll just
make y equal to 4 plus segment index
okay and so if I create one of those
oops let's see here I create one of
those that's a snake wow that is a very
large snake head that was not really the
size that I had in mind
so I'm gonna go ahead and and make those
snake segments a little bit smaller
that's that's just way too big way way
way too big so let's make that tinier
okay that's much better
all right so now that I have those snake
segments I need something to move them
around and what I'll probably do is the
exact same I'll use the exact same
system that I used for the familiar I'm
sorry the Monstar
so the Monstar code here where it kind
of searches in I'm gonna go ahead and
and copy that out but we're gonna daisy
chain the movements so what I'm going to
do is I'll say you know I've got
obviously a head on this guy so a brain
snake parts equals brain snake right and
then what I'll do here is say well hmm
there's sort of the notion of the head
of the snake is the first segment and if
I don't have one of those then there's
effectively no snake
let's say just that's purely whimsy but
that's what I'm gonna say
and so in here I don't know what is this
okay so yeah this will try to pick a
direction to go like you know as as it
does and I'll see if they can find a
place that's unoccupied and if it will
and if it can find one then it will do
this transactional occupy all right then
what I want to do is I want to basically
have a for loop here which if the
transactional occupy succeeds I just
want to go through and make everyone do
exactly that same thing right that they
were doing so I want to say okay you
know the head will move one square and
then each segment behind will do the
same thing so we're going to start with
segment index one we're gonna go until
however many there are in the
oops in parts segments and then we're
gonna go ahead and take each segment of
the snake and if we have one of those
we'll do the same
transactional occupy and we really don't
get care if it succeeds or fails it
should always succeed because we know
we'll be putting the snake into a place
we just evicted another snake piece out
of and if for some reason it failed well
that just leaves the snake piece in a
different location than we thought it
would be but that's not really a problem
so I think that's fine alright so when
we do transactional occupy we want the
segment to go from its occupying to you
know the last occupy kind of a thing and
I want to save that traversable
reference here right so that's the one
we were in we go to this one and I
basically set I record whichever place
we came from so the next person can go
there right similarly and here we do oh
well you know what body came from is
what that is already well I guess it
doesn't matter so we're just gonna say
here that last occupying equals wherever
the body is right now so and yeah this
transactional occupy I guess we can
excuse me do the same thing here where
we just say like okay whatever the t
movement whatever we were doing we'll do
the same thing to the segment here
so if body came from I guess we can
literally just do this and this looks
like very shareable code so I think I'll
probably end up
making some of these into utility
functions sorry I just got to clean this
up there we go so that transactional
occupy and then we'll launch the sky
which is movement right I and I don't
know by the occupying body Occupy
movement mode segment index segments
blah blah blah blah blah so I think
that's all fine so all of this stuff
just has to be switched from body to
head okay oops
and ya need to actually set that in here
alright so that is exactly what we
expect right because it's gonna behave
just like a Monstar if it doesn't have
any additional information so now let's
see what happens though if I create when
I do an ADD snake piece oops we don't
you know we the interesting case is when
I add more of them than just one so we
want to see if we can get it so that
they are properly following each other
along right and that actually does seem
to be working just fine
okay so let's try adding a lot more of
them eight might be too many cuz I guess
Y in the Y direction that would leave us
with some that are embedded in somebody
somebody's current standing place so
maybe I should do this as an X thing
instead so maybe just to make it easier
on myself so you know it's like an X X
is two plus seven index and that way I
can do like twelve of them or whatever
right oh except I don't allow snakes
that big said so right in my thing well
alright maybe we do allow up to sixteen
segment snakes or something
yeah so that seems to work just fine
I might argue that that you know people
probably shouldn't be moving diagonally
right and so when I owe our snake like
locked up its head its own head that was
funny that was pretty funny it liked it
there's no way it would ever get out of
that that's so funny
right cuz here's this is the head and in
fact you know what let me just
demonstrate this again cuz that was kind
of funny and if you can't tell which
one's the head it may be hard to know
what's going on there so I'm gonna do
add snake P segment there so here's the
color information so what I'm gonna do
is I'm just going to take this segment
index and I'm gonna make the the front
of the snake be like colored differently
then you know as a snake goes further
basically so I you know I'll do
something like oh actually you know what
I'll do I'll do this if the segment
index is is not the first then I'll make
a torso otherwise it's a head right
that's a lot more straightforward right
so there's the snake like sneaking
around or whatever and if it can get
into a situation where it's wrapped
around itself tightly enough then the
head cannot jump to any other location
and it will that will be it
that snake like like here it can still
eventually jump out because there was
one square but at some point it will
curl around itself enough that it can't
jump out and then here we go so there
you go
so you can see here right this is the
head of the snake there's no empty
squares and it's just that's it for our
for our mr. snake which is kind of cool
that's pretty funny
all right so yeah so that all seems to
be working great actually that was
really easy which is what I want and you
can see I can still not sort of access
any of this all right so I feel like
that is a pretty good testament to the
fact that the brain stuff seems to work
really well like that was super easy to
do like you know and it it doesn't
require any statefulness there was no
like persistence stuff you know no
reference counting no life time
management you just add a bunch of crap
and say it's a snake and you get a snake
which is what I wanted and when you
delete if you were to kill one of these
guys I think it would be pretty trivial
as well you just remember the snake like
an array deletion basically and I think
that would be it right or don't for that
matter so I think that's pretty cool so
I think it should be okay so I think
it's really the movement mode stuff to
concentrate on now I should also look to
see what happens if this if everything
scales up okay I assuming it does wheat
we have a lot of N squared e things in
there right now that we need to because
we don't have a spatial query yet so we
can't create a lot of stuff without
having problems because of the spatial
query so that's something we're gonna
have to take a look at to just be warned
about that but actually I see if I
create some additional screens what
happens here just want to make sure that
it's all good yeah I want to make sure
that you know there's stuff happening
and you know no nothing weird is going
on uh yeah so that's all fine that seems
reasonable I should probably get that
row of trees out of here because I can't
move through there at the moment
why is that road chooser I think we were
testing something about hopping over the
walls or something like this yeah tile x
equals 14 that looks like yeah and so
you can also see that you know having
all of these people do all these queries
like we should see that in our profile
that our simulation time is just really
bad right and I mean this is a debug
build so yeah we could get around that
by just compiling in release mode but
you know I mean it should for this few
things we should have no trouble
handling it and the fact that we are
spending that much time is just a good
indication and I guess I shouldn't be
premature and say that I know exactly
what it is but doing that many N squared
spatial queries is just going to be
unacceptable I assume that is the thing
that is unacceptable already but you
know if it wasn't it it would be
eventually soon enough so that's
something that we also want to take a
look at relatively soon and yeah so you
can see where we're missing our we're
not 60 frames a second were 30 frames a
second at the moment in fact right well
even without that on you can see that it
doesn't quite hit it's about but we're
up around 18 because it's simulating the
snake in the next room over and all that
stuff and that's just doing tons and
tons of spatial queries for no reason so
what I might suggest as well is what you
know maybe we want to look at that let's
see it's six o'clock so we've got about
15 minutes what do I want to tackle I
think I want to do movement mode because
I think we should probably save the
spatial query stuff for a little bit
later but that's definitely a good thing
to do because we're gonna want to we're
gonna have a lot of spatial query enough
that we want to do and we're gonna want
to put something in place there that's
nice and zippy so I'm gonna leave this
I'm gonna crank it up to fact a little
bit more although I don't know maybe we
can't really crank it up much more
because we don't simulate stuff that's
that's far enough away so like we can't
arbitrate arbitrarily much work because
we only simulate the things that are
near
so you know at some level we're not
actually sinning I'm gonna just drop out
here the camera I'm gonna use the debug
camera so you can see that it's not
simulating the stuff outside the sim
region here's the simulation apron I
think well actually no that's that's
correct
because this guy it instantly in this
guy it and it would be something those
two but it won't simulate these right
and so as I move closer and these come
into that that cyan region they start
simulating now these aren't simulating
because their head is not in the region
yet and the head is the thing that makes
the decisions right so there you can see
now these guys are no longer moving
right and you can see that we kind of
have a bug there too that we have to
figure out how we want to handle
or do we well I think we would have a
bug I'll put it to you that way I think
we would have a bug and the bug is that
we would not when we move people in if
you have a multi-piece entity like a
snake you might get a situation where if
the head could move and the body was not
in the simulation region so I'm not sure
how we want to deal with that but you
can see why that would be a problem
right so that's something that we should
probably address as well let me see
let's let's watch I should be able to
get those bugs to occur but that's a
good thing I hadn't thought of that and
that seems like a good thing to get
right all right so let's start moving
out of here and see what happens
so this guy has unfortunately locked up
right at the entrance it's okay because
we're not blocked by him yet since our
head can float over
I really need a case where the head can
move but the body can't which I'm not
super able to do okay there we go
you saw that happen right yeah if it's
not quite enough I just need that guy to
like go the other way yeah
he's not going to do it well point being
we have a bug I'm pretty certain of it
it's just it's a bug that's a little bit
hard to make happen right but yeah when
you have entities that are spatially
fairly large there's sort of a notion
there of like how we would handle that
that apron region hmm and I don't know I
do not know one way to do it is to
always pack entities into the location
of their head right so you could sort of
you could sort of do some sort of you
could do some kind of packing scheme
where you always put things into the
room where the head was even if they
were outside that room so that you knew
that they always got picked up together
that's one thing
I don't know since things in this game
are room based I don't know that we
really care all that much but it's
something that I just would like to
think through because you know like I
said I kind of wanted to try some
interesting weird things with this
entity system so I don't just want to
ignore something that might lead to an
interesting concept if that makes sense
so I have to think that one through a
little bit more I'm out to put that in
the to-do list because otherwise I might
forget what that problem is exactly but
you know while it's fresh in my head I'm
gonna write it out
I do think one thing that's kind of cool
that I guess I would say we want to we
want to encourage is while I'm standing
here in theory the snake from the room
above us can come down into our room
because we are simulating it and so that
is neat and the kind of thing that I
would like to have happen in the game so
that things in nearby rooms aren't
turned off entirely
you know like yeah okay so our snake
just left for example and the monster
Wow everyone left alright I guess we're
just not that popular anymore so the
snake leaving
I assume it's simulating up there and
could come down if it wanted to right
the fact that it hasn't I don't know if
I should be concerned about let's see
one of them's locked up that's why he
didn't come down here oh man that snake
is just leaving all the time and of
course now that snake has run into the
other snake and deadlocked right so it
can't go anywhere now that's pretty
funny
that's hilarious
so yeah all right well anyway point
being I think that's all good the only
thing that I'm concerned about is I just
don't know what to do about that sort of
that notion of how we do the gather one
thing we can do is if we know the
spatial the maximum spatial extent of an
entity we know whatever that ends up
being I suppose one thing we could do
there is just say well if we know the
maximum spatial extent of an entity we
can make sure that if we see a
particular entity of a given type we
expand the search for entities of that
type to a region that's wider than the
region we're gathering right so that
seems like a reasonable a reasonable
solution in fact I think that maybe the
brightest solution yeah
stop stop attacking me snake
yeah so here's what I think we should do
what I think we should do is when we're
doing our chunk searches let's see here
so when we're pulling out the chunks I
guess what I'm thinking is when we
stream well yeah see that's not that
great either mmm I don't know this is a
doozy I was gonna say because I think
it's very efficient to be able to cut a
stream at chunks stream and chunks and
stream them back out and you know if I
do something where I expand the search
region I have to start looking into
chunks that I don't necessarily want to
stream out the entire contents so that
just seems problematic I guess what we
could do is say that any entity with a
certain radius like here's how many grid
squares it could be away from itself you
know we we don't want to let them
separate so we're going to only simulate
it if it's at least that far in from the
simulation boundary it's still not great
so I don't know that that's kind of
annoying it's a thing we only have a
problem with where we have
geographically like dispersive entities
but it still kind of seems like a bad
situation so I'm gonna put that in the
to do list
let's see yeah I guess we did the
rudimentary behavior examples and stuff
like that but we still want to do
pathfinding and AI storage I don't know
how much we're gonna have of that but we
should do like with these these are the
same thing basically well maybe not so I
don't know what AI storage would
necessarily with how much state we'd
store for a is and where they would
necessarily be stored so I suppose
that's something that we should still
keep in there
and yeah this we did we know what the
entity system is now but the rest of
this stuff seems pretty reasonable swerd
collisions are not going to be a thing
yeah and these a lot of this stuff
really this is probably not gonna be
yeah a lot of this stuff is not really
gonna be the way I'll leave them in
there for now but ah that's not going to
be the way that we talked about it so
yeah anyway we've got on the to-do list
I'm gonna put an envy system thing here
which is basically just that what to do
about geographically disparate entities
that might only partially get streamed
into a simmer ijen but which need to
move together as a unit because that I
don't know we could just say we don't
handle that right and it's fine every
system has limitation so you know that's
okay
but maybe we want to try and see if
there's a good way to solve that problem
all right I'm gonna end it there and I
think maybe we'll do spatial queries
tomorrow because I think that's a good
idea
and maybe movement mode stuff we'll see
but I'm gonna go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
for now
bad flight uh wasn't today an off day I
don't think so
June 1st 5 p.m. right so it was it was
enough day can the compiler really mess
up the point arithmetic I mean it is
just integer ops can't be that hard to
mess up well it's it's not that it
messes it up it's not like it produces
erroneous code in the sense of the spec
but the problem is the spec says it's
undefined what happens if you do that
that's the problem
and when compiler writers we're gonna
pilar vendors see the word undefined
they take that to mean do whatever you
want so that you can have the fastest
benchmark scores rather than seeing obey
the principle of least surprise which is
what I think it should mean right and so
you get a lot of these situations where
Pilar writers will decide that because
the spec says something is undefined or
unspecified behavior or whatever they
can just do whatever they want and you
know I don't really necessarily blinkin
fire vendors I wish they wouldn't do it
but I really blame the spec writers
because what the spec writers should
have written is they should have written
something that's specified in all cases
and in any case where they can't specify
what needs to happen they should say
something explicit like this will you
know in you like in the case of doing
signed arithmetic the result will be
whatever the processor would do if it
was going to subtract these two values
you know they it should say whatever the
programmer would expect the processor to
do on the target platform or something
right so rather than say it's undefined
do whatever you want it should be more
like no it's specified as much as
humanly possible and anywhere that we
can't specify it we specify you must
obey the principle of least surprise you
can't just not work or generate bogus
code in those cases you have to generate
code that would do what the programmer
might expect the the CPU to have done
rather than expecting you know something
that no one would ever expect it to do
unless you were a compiler vendor
long billion is the way to fix the snake
from getting stuck to just allow it to
run over itself or to make the snake AI
smart enough to not trap itself so I
would say first of all snakes probably
won't generally be that long so the
problem is is probably exacerbated a bit
in the current thing where we were just
testing it hmm excuse me but
a the AI would generally probably not be
randomly picking so it'd be less likely
to get into that state but B if it could
get stuck on itself
I'd say that's actually fine that just
means hey you can kill it really easily
I just go up and wail on it or whatever
right so I wouldn't even necessarily has
a problem like I said the AI is in this
game are supposed to be about being
predictable and interesting not about
being really smart because I don't think
that really adds anything to a game like
this so I would rather it be like the oh
if the snake occasionally gets caught
like awesome that means I can kill this
snake really easily whereas normally
they're much harder or something right
I've recently watched a video on the gjk
algorithm it's great thanks for that
you're welcome did you also do a video
on the EPA algorithm what is the EPA
Ogham the Environmental Protection
Agency I don't think they have an
algorithm sir Kane will the snake head
be able to move to the position of its
last segment so it can go in a circle or
loop we could allow that certainly but I
don't know that I care about that enough
to implement that but you certainly
could right you just transactionally D
occupy before you did your search and
then reoccupy after right
Shawn McGrath is expressing surprise
that I did a video on gjk yes I did a
video geunji decay what other
explanation videos have you done well
you knew I did a quaternion double cover
one right para Jane and are you going to
implement every I thing and bring entity
when does path funding and rest of a guy
coming on schedule also can you say some
good reference book for AI I cannot say
that I know any good reference books for
AI so I can help you there
as for if I'm going to implement every
AI thing in the brain yeah basically
like brain dot CPP will probably have
all of the control logic in there and
what we'll do is like right now you can
already see it starting to happen and so
will you know we'll make this a reality
soon enough like these sorts of pieces
of code are very self similar so we'll
be breaking these out into utility
functions so that you know this isn't so
it's not so complicated to write one of
these right so instead of having to do
something like Oh find the closest hero
manually they'll just be like a simple
call that's like get closest of type
blah and then hop towards blah right and
the brains will just be built out of
those utility functions basically so
those are pretty straightforward and
that's how this this thing will go after
when they're on the schedule we don't
have a schedule that you know game
development rarely operates in a like a
rigid fashion in that way you have to
work on what makes sense to work on at
the time so I have no idea when we'll do
various AI things when they come up when
it is most logical to do them for from
the architecture standpoint of the
program is when we'll do them
Shawn McGrath said yes and and I am
gooey but what else so I don't think
there's many others I think there's
there's one on in on Bezier splines and
how you can understand how they're
actually constructed and how you for
example don't have to look up the
formula in a book you can just always
derive it yourself really trivially by
just remembering that it's all linear
blends all the way down so I did one on
that but I don't remember there's many
others expanding polytope algorithm okay
no I've never done an explanation of the
expanding poly tip algorithm as you can
imagine if you apply the same logic that
I applied in the gjk video to the
expanding poly tope algorithm you should
sort of pretty readily see how there
it's a very geometric algorithm but I if
I remember correctly expanding polytope
is a little messier gjk is very very
simple and I seen remember EPA being
slightly less simple but yeah if you're
looking for those old old videos they're
really old but you can go to youtube.com
can you do senior Torre probably not
that is not me all right YouTube Casey
and mera Torre okay so it's Casey Mira
Tori so here's the videos so these three
here are the ones that were old videos
this one's a newer one and I think those
are the only ones so this one this one
this one in this one
yeah and these used to be up on my other
site that were directly but I uploaded
them to YouTube now so you can get them
directly off of here
could you briefly explain how a snake
segment knows which node to jump to a
non habe segment that is so hmm
oh if someone just said don't forget the
API segment you're right that's a good
point there is one other one this one
designing and evaluating reusable
components so there was one other one
that I forgot to mention sorry about
that
all right anyway so the way that that
snake code works is really pretty simple
all all it does is it uses the monster
code like you saw where is it uses the
monster code to just figure out where
the closest traversable is to the head
that's not occupied right it then says
okay jump there then all it says as well
all right I've got some number of
segments that follow me so just loop
through every segment and tell that
segment to jump to whichever place I was
just at and that continues down the line
so the head is leaving a square right
this is the square the head was
occupying its gonna leave that square so
that goes into last occupying then we
just loop through every segment and say
ok this segment goes to that right it
goes to that place where the head was
then we say well replace that last
occupied variable with wherever we were
so every time someone leaves it
remembers where it left and tells the
next person down the line to hop to that
so it's just like a bucket brigade it's
like every segment of the snake leaves
the place and tells the next segment to
hop to that place so that just hops each
one hops into its own position
boozy beaver well I've got gjk an EPA
implant in 2d and gjk in 3d but I'm a
bit struggling at EPA in 3d yeah well
yeah that that's reasonable right it's a
lot more complicated in 3d just like gjk
that the conceptualising the cases in 3d
for those algorithms is just way harder
in 3d because there's way more different
types of constructs right so
alright it looks like we're done with
the queues I don't see any more coming
up so I'm gonna wrap it up close alright
thank you everyone for joining me for
the episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always pre-order the game at
handmade hero or gonna come to the
source codes for your educational
pleasures we also form site you go to
one ask questions a patreon page you can
go to if you would like to support our
fine video series a schedule about that
tells you when we are live and of course
an episode guide if you would like to
catch up on past episodes that is it I
will be back here tomorrow at 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time when we will
probably do the spatial query or
movement mode stuff I'm not sure which
of those two will do you know what
movement mode will do movement mode
tomorrow because we gotta make a
floating movement mode and we want to
solidify the other movement mode so
we'll kind of we'll try to make movement
mode a more specific thing and you know
maybe we'll try adding one more type of
movement like maybe burrowing through
the ground for example so someone who
doesn't really collide with stuff at all
but can move from place to place would
be another one or ghosts like that kind
of thing so we can try to make different
movement modes that make sense or
something like that
and kind of solidify that down because
you know that that's or something we
want to get right so that's about it
hope see you there until then have fun
programming I'll see you guys on the
Internet