hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we are well we added
yesterday the ability to do sort of per
element sorting and we did that in kind
of an interesting way I thought which
you know we that's something different
we had sort of had this plan to do
something a little more complicated then
right in the middle of implementing I
realized there was a much simpler way to
do it and so we ended up doing it in a
much simpler way and it seems to work
quite well and at the end of yesterday's
stream we actually used the cycle
detection that we put in there to
determine that we didn't actually have a
bug in the comparison as well so the
cycle detection ended up being kind of
useful too so it's a pretty good day all
around I think and I'm relatively happy
with it however at this point it does
mean that I think we've moved into the
firmly into the territory of now we've
got to go back and finish up our Z
layering stuff because we've got sorting
working inside a layer properly we don't
currently have our layering stuff
working and so what that means is of
course if we go into the game at the
moment because we sort of left it in in
a sort of as I often say zygote estate
so if we kind of go in here and we run
it you can see that we've got sort of
this one thing this this one room if you
will that's doing what we expected to do
now and that's good but we've got this
stairwell here that we had made and it's
it's not well it's already still using
the old sort of perspective transform
that we said we didn't want for things
inside a room like we just want these
these should just be up higher in Y but
they shouldn't be going to the side or
getting larger like they are so that
obviously we need to fix and then
similarly if we go and actually start
allowing more than one room to be added
instead of loops that's not where I want
to be at all so if we allow two rooms to
be added stacked on top of each
we can quickly see that also our sorting
won't work properly because our sorting
is designed to only sort inside a single
room given the rules of a single room
and that's just because it's a two and a
half day sort so it has to make some
concessions but you can see right now
that this is totally wrong right and the
reason for that is our sorting rule
doesn't really handle the idea of layers
of Z slices on top of each other and you
know we could try to make that work or
whatever but the goal is not to make the
sort handle everything that was never
the goal the idea is we actually want to
just slice the world into these slices
and then have them sort separately which
we know works that was always the plan
and so now we need to make that happen
and as you can see right now you know
it's totally unworkable as it is because
these things are just randomly sorting
and you can't make any sense of it
whatsoever so what we need to do is we
need to take a step back and we need to
go finish that slicing so that we can
see whether our sort rule actually does
work if we give the renderer slices to
work with now this is going to be a
pretty difficult excursion for us it's
gonna be a little difficult for me in
the sense that this is the kind of work
that normally I do over probably the
course of one or two days in a really
concentrated like for our for our pair
block or something like this where I
really get in there and get everything
right it's gonna be really hard as a
thing to do on the stream because
breaking things up into our chunks and
talking while you're doing it is kind of
difficult so it is gonna be a little
difficult for me because it's a it's an
architectural like reorg kind of thing
which can be difficult but it's also
gonna be kind of difficult for everyone
else to follow too because I'm probably
gonna be you know I'm moving things
around and sort of talking about like
the feel of things and how they go so I
apologize for that but that's just
something that you have to do
periodically like I've always said I'm
really into exploratory architecture
which means you kind of have to feel
your way out to like okay now I see how
this works that's the only way that
really good architecture ever happens
and certainly the architecture that is
going to be best for handmade hero which
I think we're slowly annealing into is
not one that we ever could have
conceptualized at the start of the
project so if we had you know
tried to write out some some UML class
diagram of how this game was going to
work we would have been so far away from
the actual correct architecture it would
have been hilarious and so like just to
sort of give some encouragement when you
find this sort of thing happening you
want to embrace it don't discourage it
right you want to embrace the idea that
the architecture gets better over time
and that you're exploring towards a good
architecture and if you believe that
what good architecture is is thinking
about everything upfront and getting
this design and then plowing you know
forwards on it after you finalize it
like this is a design that's where bad
software architecture comes from so you
know always embrace the the sort of
forward flow of the architecture and a
lot of what you do when you're
programming is absolutely about trying
to make sure that you have a code base
that's fluid enough that you can make
those decisions and move forwards and
get to better places rather than
something that's really been rigidly
codified and Kant has no flexibility to
get to where it needs to go to be well
working and fluid and fast and efficient
and all that so so that's what we need
to start working on now and so that is
what I'm going to start looking at now
if you recall we actually sort of
started looking at this and that's what
made us decide we needed to do the sort
and so we went and did the sort but if
you recall before we finish doing the
sort we had actually sort of started
this conceptualization of layering and
you can see here where we've got this
relative layer convert to relative layer
and it does a temp Z thing right and you
can see what ended up happening curious
I just patched it really quickly so what
was supposed to happen or what was
happening in here is when we call
convert to layer relative what would
happen is it would return a relative
layer value which is basically saying
like oh you know here is which slice of
the world this particular sprite is on
or whatever but then the other thing for
the the value pass in it would modify
the value passed in to make it be now
just an offset based on that layer and
so what I did to sort of patch it out so
that we could have two
still on top of each other just while we
were testing other stuff is I pass a
temp value there that never then gets
used so if we want to return to the
previous way you know the previous state
of the program before we put the sword
in and when we were just working on the
layers it would look like this and at
that point what happens is everything's
flattened down into one plane so now you
can see we actually have two rooms here
okay but instead of drawing those two
rooms on top of each other we've
actually truncated them out so they're
actually drawn in the same place and you
can see that flip happen here so no
matter whether I go up or down either
way like here I go up doo doo doo and
you can see the flicker happened to
where it's like the two tiles are being
rendered on top of each other and
they're fighting for who gets thrown
first and all that right so this is
basically just drawing two rooms on top
of each other but that's actually what
we want right we want to flatten all of
the rooms down into the same space
essentially and then we just want the
renderer to know that each one is
rendered at a different offset in terms
of perspective now just to refresh your
memory since it's been a while let me
just reiterate why we are doing that
here on day two 3:13 oh I forgot to say
today is 3:13 so if you want to start if
you want follow along day three twelve
source code is the right code to start
with what's going on my my Milton seems
to think I'm a mouse again it's weird
well reopen Milton
hello there we go much nicer yeah I
don't know why that happens but
sometimes Milton decides that's in mouse
mode there we go um okay so let's talk
about the slice again really quickly
just so everyone's on the same page so
here's what we've got we have two sort
of areas in the world right and we've
got these sort of you know trees around
here whatever and maybe this one's got
trees around it too and you know who
knows these are gonna be whatever they
are with the actual game art but point
being you've got you know two things
stacked on top of each other
so what we want to have happen is we
want to have two separate
conceptualizations of what it means to
be up in the world right you know up
goes this way it's our z-value but we
have two different things that that's
going to mean so when you're looking at
an individual slice of the world what we
want up to mean is just displacement in
Y so for example if we have a stairwell
a stairwell should actually just look
like this kind of right it should be it
should be basically the same size all
the way up okay and it should be right
in line with each other and right now as
you see we have kind of a perspective
stairwell so it kind of goes off at this
direction and the tiles get bigger as
they go so when we're looking at a
single slice of the room we want to see
all of those Z values are just converted
to Y displacements and that's it no
scaling no X displacement just Y
displacements so it's true orthographic
one sort of tilt orthographic so what
we're essentially saying is if you are
looking at a particular slice than
something that is hovering above that
slice or that is up you know from that
slice like so that thing that Z the
reason that I was saying we need to
always think about relative to the layer
is because that portion of the Z
he needs to get converted to a wide
displacement that's what we want for the
art style okay now on the other hand
this displacement here so the fact that
this floor is up above this other floor
this is a separate slice and what that
means is that everything on that slice
who by the way have their own relative Z
displacements everything on that slice
needs to actually be scaled so that it's
in perspective in the sense that it does
get bigger and it does displaced in x
and y right so fundamentally what we're
trying to do here is basically render
the world in slices and take those
slices which have Z offsets translated
as Y offsets take those slices and scale
and modulate and do whatever effects we
want to the slices as wholes and by the
way while we're at this we would like to
correct the alpha blending of these
things so that the Alpha blend away or
fog in or out or all those sorts of
things we want that to be consistent as
a layer because you remember we sort of
had this bug that's it's not very
noticeable bug but I find it looks very
unprofessional if you leave this kind of
thing and I see a lot of games that have
this actually you know if I've got a
tree and right in front of it is another
tree there's a region of overlap that's
say right here so this right gets drawn
and this right gets drawn usually what
happens is you know a gets drawn before
B and so that's why the part of a that's
not visible is not visible right that's
the way we're currently doing it as
we're drawing back to front now when we
draw back to front if the alpha level
that we're using to draw everything at
so if the opacity of these two things
happens to be 100% everything's fine
right you just see two trees and they
appear to be be in front of a just like
what we wanted however if we then set
the opacity to 50%
because say for example we're fading out
an alpha layer that's getting close to
the camera like you know when you go
down a stairwell or something and it's
supposed to kind of come up at you and
disappear
when we reduce that to 50% well this one
will become 50% translucent which is
fine but then this tree that gets stuck
on top of it well this part of it will
be 50% translucent but this part already
had a 50% layer on it and now it's
having another 50% layer put on top of
that right and so if you think about
what that ends up happening to the total
translucency of this area it is not at
50% anymore right because you can
imagine what's happening there's
something underneath this that the stuff
that's below this layer right we'll call
that a well let's not call it because
all right do that let's let's call that
what am i call that let's see here let's
call this I'm gonna say m and n okay
well no I'm gonna do that M is what's
behind and then on this layer
we've got I'm gonna talk about the
individual objects we've got the two
trees and the two trees can be a and B
like we had there so here's a here's B
okay so if you think about what happens
here right if the bottom part is M then
that's what we're starting with right
and what we end up with if we imagine
that this layer was was labeled n or
whatever what I want to see if my a
pathway level is 50% right is I want my
final pixel to be 0.5 M plus 0.5 n right
that's what I want to see I want to see
50% of the underlying and 50% of the of
the thing on top okay now the question
is will I get that with this process
well if I am to draw em first right well
we know that's just what's in the buffer
right so we start with M everything is
cool if I was then to draw just some
single object called M right then using
my linear blend I know I would have you
know 1 minus whatever the alpha value is
n plus the alpha value of M right and
that would be my pixel so if I set my
the value to 0.5 what happens I get
point five here and point five here
right because 1 minus 0.5 is 0.5 and you
know the value itself 0.5 is 0.5 so I
would get exactly what I wanted if I
just did 1 rasterizing operation but we
don't have 1 rasterizing operation in
this case we have multiple we're drawing
multiple sprites so if all we do is set
those individual sprites alpha value
then what we get is a repeated
application of this formula right so the
first time through right if I repeat
this formula 1 minus alpha a remember
that's our back tree plus alpha value M
well I'm a pretty happy camper because
then I get point 5 a plus 0.5 M right
but now I come to draw B well this is
now what's in the buffer so I end up
with 1 minus alpha times B plus alpha
times this whole thing right 0.5 a plus
0.5 M well if I multiply that out I get
point 5 of B which is all fine that's
probably you know if I was just trying B
that would be good but then I get 0.5
0.5 egg plus 0.5 M right so now let's
multiply that out 0.5 B plus 0.25 a
right plus 0.25 M do you see the problem
B and a are both part of my n layer so
if I now wanted to see what the total
contribution of the N layer is well I
could add these together I could say
that this was N and this was n right so
the total contribution from the N layer
is 0.75 n plus my point 2 5 M which is
still there well that's not 50% opacity
right not even close so you can see what
the problem is if we layer multiple
sprites at a certain opacity level on
top of each other what we end up is is
we darken the contribution you know we
increase the
chasidy everytime they overlap right and
we increase it by whatever that
proportion actually is right the less
this is the less noticeable it would be
it's in theory potentially right because
you're adding less each time but still
right it's always wrong it's always the
incorrect alpha
except that one exact point where it
would happen to be okay right which is
if you only had one sprite and as you
get more and more and more sprites it
gets more and more and more wrong repeat
this process one more time this number
will increase this number will decrease
you'll get even more opaque and off you
go so one solution to this problem and
the one that I was going to use is just
to say okay you know we could try to do
some rendering tricks to maybe work this
out maybe we use something in the
destination alpha maybe we have a
separate buffer maybe we do who knows
bla bla bla bla bla right we could do a
depth pass first and have the depth pass
then set comparison so we could figure
that out whatever there's lots of things
we could do to solve this problem the
one that I'm choosing to do and this is
not necessarily for any reason other
than I'd like to limit the degree into
which we get into crazy shader
ridiculousness is to just render the
scene in slices because if we render the
scene in slices we can choose to just do
essentially this operation P equals one
minus alpha n plus alpha M we can just
say we composite everything for the N
layer first and then just draw in one
pass so rather than changing the alpha
opacity on all of the sprites to fade
out the layer we actually draw the layer
normally with whatever the sprites
actual alpha values are which most the
time is one but if something's you know
maybe transparent than that it's less we
draw that first for the N layer and we
already have the M layer we then just do
our composite operation on top of them
and we get the right results because
we're only applying the equation once no
matter how many sprites were in the end
layer because they've already been
composited into essentially a single big
sprite that can just be composited once
okay
so that's that's the idea if that makes
sense and you know I'm not 100% certain
but we may be able to implement that in
a in a way that that might be somewhat
tricky as well I'm not sure but we can
see when we actually get to there we may
be able to do things where we don't
actually have to render separately but
worst case all we're talking about here
when we do this is just having a few
render buffers right so rather than
having just one thing we render to on
the screen we would have a number of
render buffers and the number of render
buffers is proportional to the number of
these operations we plan to do now from
what we looked at originally right we
don't have that many of these operations
we have a fog effect which actually
doesn't need this because it doesn't
have this problem right for all the
layers that are lower than the current
layer so as we go down right as we go
down from if this is the layer the hero
is standing on as we go down these get
fogged and fog doesn't have a problem
fog is not an asset II write fog is a
color effect so we're not drawing things
on top of each other multiple times so
fog we don't have to deal with in this
way so we can actually composite all of
the layers from the hero all the way
down to the lowest level can be done
into one buffer right so the only thing
we need to do to get this effect is the
single layer that's above the hero right
that one has to be done this way so
essentially what we're talking about
here is we have to do one of these that
has that that property to it and then
the rest of them will just work so you
know worst case scenario we're talking
basically to render buffers
so that's fine because you know 1920 by
1080 right if we have 1920 by 1080 by 4
bytes per pixel that is an extremely
modest amount of size right it's about 8
megabytes oops
no right and so saying that we need a
second one of these right about 16 Meg's
is really not problematic in any way and
it's not problematic from tubers to
points of view really first we are not
going to be stressing the graphics cards
memory subsystem in terms of allocation
at all to say we need to 8 Meg buffers
right most graphics cards today have at
least half a gigabyte of memory often
times have a gigabyte often times have 2
gigabytes right and by the way in that
way that it's not particularly accurate
but hey you can get some idea of what's
going on if you look at the Steam
Hardware survey there's basically break
points right around that sort of level
you can see them here so you can see
right around half a gigabyte you've got
you know a reasonable amount of people
who fall in there about 10% of the
people falling about you know somewhere
around a half a gig then you've got
another really big break point up here
at a gigabyte a lot of people falling
into that category almost a third of all
cards and then you've got a bunch of you
know about probably the other third or
so is is somewhere above there right is
probably even more than a third it looks
like yeah so even more than a third it's
up above in the in the 2 gig and so when
you talk about you know when you're
talking about the bottom number you can
even have is 256 megabytes then looking
at 16 megabytes as a number is is not
threatening right so you know if you say
I need to
render buffers for a 1080p game you're
not to you that's child's play on any PC
certainly now maybe you talk about the
Raspberry Pi or something but you know
who does maybe we don't run 1080p on you
know weak hardware right so that's
totally fine the other way that is
totally fine is the memory bandwidth
necessary to do that extra blit is
pretty minimal as well right if you're
talking about an 8 megabyte copy you
know again you can get a little bit of
idea this is again you know only very
ballpark but you can do you know list of
and video hardware or something like
this and you can go pick you know some
graphics processing unit off of here
let's pick something not necessarily top
of the line or something let's just say
a GeForce 600 series processor like a
you know hack will even do a mobile part
right so if you take a look at what the
graphics memory bandwidth here is you
can see right here it's in gigabytes a
second
right and you can see that you know even
the most modest one is fourteen point
four gigabytes per second so if you look
at how many that's gonna be for a
particular frame and that's again that's
really weak sauce because this is a
mobile part low-end mobile part super
lousy so we're talking about at 60
frames a second what is that 240
megabytes
we could do each frame of memory
bandwidth again totally random pulling
that out there but so if you're talking
about just adding 8 megabytes more of
bandwidth that we have to do to do that
wrap that alpha composite pass not a big
deal right and hopefully you understand
sort of what I'm talking about there the
idea is just that well you know
originally we drew everything to the
screen so however much bandwidth however
much memory bandwidth that took the
graphs hard to do you know pulling in
the sprites letting them on top of each
other reading the z-buffer writing the
z-buffer reading the color buffers
reading riting color buffers whatever
it's doing right all of that stuff it is
the memory bandwidth necessary
to run the game and we do you know every
60s in a second we need that much memory
memory bandwidth to make the game happen
and not missus framerate so when you say
I need to add a second composite pass
what you're talking about is using up
however big the screens memory you know
however much memory it takes to store
one screens worth of data if you're
talking about a second slice now you're
talking about well I've got to do this
alpha composite operation of that slice
is adding right because you still have
to do all the sprite blitz right all of
the sprite operations you're still doing
them you're doing them to two separate
buffers right some of them go to one
buffer something or the other you're
still doing all of that so all of that
memory bandwidth you're still taking
that hit but now you also have to pay
the cost of copying the on top buffer
onto the lower buffer and you know that
is going to take the extra eight
megabytes of memory bandwidth assuming
that there's no compression or bubble a
lot but you get the idea right so
somewhere in that ballpark and so
usually when you're doing stuff like
this you know is any of this stuff stuff
that you can really work out on paper no
because it's all super specific to
what's going on the memory subsystems
and you know okay what kind of shader
operations are happening here and is it
compressed and is the Z compressed and
can it early-out and blah blah blah so
there's so many different things in
there that are involved I don't want to
give the impression that it's like oh
that's how much more memory bandwidth it
is that's not true but it always helps
when you're in this situations when
you're working on code that has to do
with performance it always helps to just
have in the back of your mind
what am I doing here like like is this a
reasonable thing to even go or is it a
disaster so if this number had come back
and it was like oh it's 300 megabytes
right or something like this you would
go wait hold hold on a second right
first of all I don't know if I have the
memory bandwidth to do 300 megabytes
extra up copying like certain cards are
now off the table certainly I mean
that's 300 megabytes would be more
bandwidth at 60 frames a second then
then that mobile part we just looked at
even had at all right so never mind
rendering the game just doing the alpha
compositing would have would have killed
it but you'd also go well 300 mega
might is too much memory potentially to
because of all I have is 512 Meg
graphics card let's say well if 300
megabytes of that graphics is just
storing frame buffers well all of a
sudden I'm like where the sprites gonna
go and where's you know all the where's
some Headroom for the operating system
in like I'm getting nervous right
already so it just helps to know to turn
of be aware of what these values are I
think Mikey brass used to call these
back of the envelope computations it's a
common industry term but it's basically
just like being aware that anytime
you're making decisions like this you
should at least have an idea of whether
of what's involved you shouldn't just be
completely oblivious to like what
actually has to happen in order to make
that be the case so that's why I just
want I always kind of sanity check
myself there and and that's you know in
negligible that's what I think that's
something that we won't have to care
about it all and and refine so yeah so
what we need to do now is we need to
start pushing forwards on two
fundamental pieces of this of this
problem I guess is what I would say the
first piece is we have to actually get
our transform straightened out because
now we've got two different meanings for
Z and we need to have some idea of how
that's going to work out right and the
second thing that we need to do is and
like I said we can also put if we want
to we can put this back temporarily if
we want to work on them separately I
don't know if we do or don't but you
know I think maybe we might want to if
we take a look at this here you know we
could start with this and say well
separate from the transform let's just
get the renderer handling the concept
that we have these two different slices
and then let's alpha blend those two
things on top of each other correctly
right and I thought we had alpha being
specified here but now I don't see it
and so I'm wondering why the Alpha isn't
set on these to begin with so maybe the
first thing I'll do is just take a look
at why that is the case so I thought
that was specified up in here
right and I don't actually know why it's
not at the moment I am Not sure it looks
like it's because oh well you know why I
guess I guess what happened
III guess I see what happened actually
now that I think about it what's going
on here is just that we had already
partitioned it and so we're not setting
the entity alpha right we're just let me
just verify that that's true so if I
wanted to set the entity alpha I think
do we still have the global alpha
concept probably not but if we wanted to
set the entity alpha what I could do is
say well what should the entity alpha be
because we're in here and we've got this
like level index concept so what I
should be able to do here is say well
this cliprect FX thing here's where I do
my push cliprect well I guess now it
looks like there's no way for me to
really get out what it what that alpha
value should have been let me just do it
this way I want to just be able to I
guess get this myself since we won't be
able to look it up any other way I'm
gonna call this test alpha I'm just
gonna do you know however many of these
there are I want to get that out so here
we'll just say well the test alpha for
our level index equals whatever the
whatever this thing said the Alpha value
was right so you can see here if we're
above the fade top see we do a tea color
two zero zero zero of this T value so I
think really all we want to do is say
the test alpha is I guess one minus
whatever that that tea color is right
so that way I've stored it and then if I
go through here and we could should be
able to link live coded at this so we
should be able to be able to you should
be able to go in through
here and actually make this work this
way so when I actually go ahead and do
the rendering of this guy when we do the
pieces and the collision volume
traversals law stuff I should be able to
say like oh well what was the Alpha
supposed to be here and I could put that
in right I can sort of just say well you
know whatever the Alpha was supposed to
be off we go and so this would be you
know before color equals peace color
color alpha x equals alpha right and so
now we need to do is actually look up
that alpha so in here where we say like
oh what's the relative layer then we
would have to say well the Alpha value
is going to be the test alpha of
whatever the relative layers right and
since we have to base that off of our
our base level we got to put that in
there all right so let's see what
happens here so as I climb up the stairs
we should see this fade in but that is
actually not at all what I'm seeing
which is weird which is good I verified
this because I want to make sure this is
correct first
yeah it looks like that just switches
immediately why am I getting this result
why I ask why so I have my level index
and I'm writing in whatever this value
is I would like to look at that value
personally and let's take a look inside
handmade entity I just want to see when
we come in here I just want to see what
this actually says so here at my test
office one one one one one zero all
right uh let's be a little bit more
forthcoming there let's see what happens
in this case okay so basically no one is
above fade tops start Z oh no there we
go
so what's my T value T value is one hmm
all right well if you say so I guess I'm
not gonna yell at you yet for being a
liar but eventually you fade in right
there so now what do you think your T
value is you think your T value is one
now as well
what am I missing here camera relative
ground Z Abe top start Z so that is
actually quite a bit higher
is there another there's only one ever
that's above right all right I'm a
little perplexed I don't mind telling
you what's fade I want to see what the
fade top NZ is as well 2.25 so it's
definitely outside but yet at the same
time right I'm looking at it so I don't
understand
Casey is confused quite confused
actually so when I'm here
then I do expect it to be faded out
completely and when I see it right and I
look that's exactly what I get my top
end is 2.25 the relative positioning of
this layer is 3.0 that's it's exactly
right right I that just looks that looks
like exactly what I would expect however
if I go up the stairs now right I don't
expect to see that at all that isn't
what I would have expected to see right
I guess is it because the world has now
shifted down
I guess I should probably look at what
the actual Z is that we're talking about
here so if I take this right and I look
at what the offset Z is from the
actually I guess that's not so much what
I want I want the chunk
so that's chunk one look were we on
chunk zero before okay so basically what
happens is it's sliding us up before the
fade actually has a chance to take
effect can't say I didn't necessarily
see that one coming but so I guess I'm
not 100% certain how we ended up in that
place but that does mean that you know
our the way that we're doing our fade
ends our fade in has to happen further
up I guess is what I would say in order
for that for it to actually come in
before it gets switched to as sort of
the new the new normal if you will but I
don't understand because if you look at
the typical floor heights here if half a
typical floor right is where it starts
fading in and two-thirds of it is where
it fades out it was where it stops
waiting in I don't know that that just
seems really weird let's try something
more like this
okay so nobody is over the fade fade top
start Z at this point take a look
I step through this actually one by one
there we go so let's see we have
negative 12 we have negative 9 negative
6 negative 3 the one we're actually on
which is 0 the one above us which is at
3 and then of course we've got our fade
top start Z is 3 so yeah
I don't know I'm a little perplexed
maybe it's just a slow day it happens
sometimes but it feels like as long as
we you know I don't really understand
why starting it here wouldn't have
worked
I mean it feels like that should be a
reasonable alpha region for doing the
transition alright so there we've at
least got it in the range but doesn't
even seem to really do the the range map
it just has its own this feels really
sloppy I feel like there's something I'm
missing
all right we're gonna have to drill down
on this because I'm not happy about this
this is obviously something I'm doing
stupid in the meantime I should probably
when we do where we're doing our sort of
when we draw a rectangle will be
outlined it which is actually pretty
good and it makes it easier to see stuff
but I do want to make sure I get the
Alpha more correct
so what I'd rather do is take the Primo
colors alpha here and make sure that
that gets respected that way at least
everything fades out together so you
know it doesn't we don't have the lot
the rectangles lie and staying around
right but you can see that they just the
things things basically are popping out
of that range and we've got kind of a
nasty I think this is kind of busted so
I think what's happening is this
computation is not quite correct so
I feel like if it might be this idea
right here that's kind of busted in fact
I'm not really sure why I did it this
way at all because it seems like the
camera relative ground Zee this should
have been subtracted right it feels like
this should have been like this that's
not what we wrote so I'm gonna go work
this out on the blackboard and figure
out if I'm just on crack or if we were
just doing something stupid there right
but yeah either way it doesn't work so
I'm not sure why we wrote that and I'm
not really sure why this isn't working
more correctly
it's a tricky it's very tricky don't get
me wrong but I just kind of want to know
what's going on so here is the situation
as we have it we have some number of
stacks here and somewhere in here is the
actual simulation origin now most of the
time it's going to actually probably
coincide with one of these slices so
it's going to actually be like right on
one of these slices so then our question
is well you know the oh wait
that might be that that might be it
right there what's the actual camera
part of this because this is the origin
of the simulation region but the camera
is actually in a different place right
the camera does this nonsense so right
this is the camera situation where we
say like okay you know world mode camera
offset so I think that's the problem is
the simulation region moves in steps so
if we actually want to know you know
this is fine but if we actually want to
know where it is relative the camera
we've got to subtract away the world
mode camera offset Z right and we
weren't doing that so that we just kind
of left ourselves some bad code there
when we were working on that to begin
with
I don't know why or how that was working
in the first place
but there we go so now now we're flying
again right now everything's happy so
now we can kind of see like alright now
we get our fade back that's all nice
right and when we get down here we're
good to go again so so that's all much
much more fancy and happy alright let's
just double check start to fade start to
fade all looks good alright and maybe we
can make this a little bit wider again
just I don't know we'll tweak those
values later on but yeah that's not
that's not good
so let's see if this makes things a
little more gradual still not not great
well we'll have plenty of time to play
with that anyway alright so yeah so
that's that's basically what we're
looking at here and like I said what we
want to do now is we want to kind of get
these things to be in layers more
properly and we kind of already have a
little bit of a problem in my opinion
which is that our layer selection
doesn't seem to be quite correct
because if you look at what's going on
here these stairs should all be part of
my layer right because we're supposed to
be flooring pun intended
I think our what layer were on and so
when we do reckon annika lies coordinate
here like this I I feel like that's a
mistake
because that's not what we actually want
essentially what we're doing at the
moment is we're rounding and so what I
think we need to do is re canonicalize
coordinate unfortunately is is just kind
of wrong for Z because if you remember
the way that we decided to do this and
maybe this was a mistake but this is how
we were doing it is if you remember we
had sort of tiles in the world right and
we stored things relative to the tile
the center of the tile and we had
switched because we were in the in the
previous time we were doing it relative
to the corner that's how we were working
things out right and we don't really
have there's really no rhyme or reason
for why you would have to do it one way
or the other but now we sort of do have
a little bit of a rhyme or a reason
right because once we extend this to 3d
which we now have
we now do have a reason to decide right
if our goal is to make everything
contained here in be part of this level
and then everything that's on this plane
and up be part of this level right then
we we want more of a truncate right we
want a operation that's more truncation
based than centroid based now it doesn't
really matter because we can just decide
how we want to layer these things
together but what it does mean is if we
want to continue with a centroid based
scheme where we put the floor the floor
needs to be placed down a bit right or
up a bit depending on how we want that
box to work out so for example what I'm
currently conceptualizing pretend these
are the two floors we actually have here
is this well know
so here are a bunch of people with Z
displacements and the problem is right
now we've got a rule which basically
says well everything between here and
here is on this floor and everything
between here and here is on this floor
right and so what happens is these guys
they get kind of picked up and if I drew
this from the side which I probably is
what I should've done begin with if I
drew it like this right here's that
stairwell curious those displacements
okay and if I'm looking at this and
going well you know I've got this
problem where this is what's my
definition of who falls into which
brackets well the problem now is these
guys fall into the correct bracket but
these guys who I actually want to be
down here are falling into this bracket
so what I need to do is push the floors
downward so the floor should actually be
at negative something relative to their
centroid right in order to make it so
that everything that might be offset
from them all of the ground layers are
always up and that's fine right we can
just say that that's how that works
that's not a problem at all
we could just go into world mode or
something right and we can take a look
at when we do ad standard room you can
see how we're adding things you know and
when we come in here we've got the like
P offset Z value right and so when we
call chunk position from tile position
it's implicit in there that what it's
doing is it's giving us that sort of
floor level right and so you can see
that that's happening here and it just
kind of does it's it's it's mapping
right but what we really want to do in
that case is we want to say that the
offsets Z value is actually going to be
down a little from the size of a tile so
we want it to be like the tile depth in
meters we want it to be some you know
whatever our floor region there would be
we want would want it to be some ways
down
okay so now when we actually do that in
theory well I don't actually know I
should double-check to see that this is
actually what we call all the time I
think it is yeah so now when we actually
do this in theory we should get we
should have all of the things move down
relative to yeah relative to where we
should have all entities moved downwards
so that they aren't sorting up into the
thing now unfortunately I look just then
and saw that that's not actually what
happened right because we're still
missing these two guys here so that's a
little odd to see them not there right
Oh
No that's what I would expect so I'm
gonna have to go take a look at this
down and just see what I actually see
why that is now the other thing is this
is getting kind of sloppy here so these
tile side and meters and tile depth and
metres things I think we we had our kind
of world concept here we have the chunk
chunk diamond meters so really I feel
like this should you know I feel like we
should be getting this this way right
and because I think that's what we
decided for the chunk stuff but anyway
so yeah if the if that's the size of one
of these things and we're talking about
zero zero being sort of a centroid point
then if we displace it downwards by you
know almost half then we're close to
that floor level that's what I would
have expected so I want to take a a
second to just go and find out why
that's not right before we exit all
right so let's step into the world
creation I want to see what's going on
with that chunk position from top
position fit there we go scroll up here
so I just want to look and see what
we've got
you can kind of see that we have a Z
displacement of negative 1.2 that's what
we would expect cuz that's gonna be this
divided you know there are times 0.4 so
when we do our map into chunk space I
just want to look and see what the
result is up being so yeah that's like
exactly what I would have expected it to
be so it's operating the way I would
have thought let me take a look at the a
standard room code I just want to see
what else is doing here
so offset y plus 2 so that's this is the
part that's actually displacing
everything upwards here so I'm not sure
I really understand I mean that looks
like it should do exactly what I'm
asking it to do and it feels like it
should never be able to quite get high
enough there now maybe that's not true
maybe what's happening is offset Y is
actually too large when we come in here
so if it's 3 I'm sorry if it's between
negative 2 and 2 that's gonna be 0
through 4 so what that means it's going
to add up to 2 units that should not put
us over the boundary right that should
our P offset Z should always still be
okay at that point I should think but
I'm gonna go ahead and take a look here
and let's go to the highest possible one
so 0 1 2 so there we go and let's take a
look at what our p offset z is now so
looking at our p offset we've got
negative 1.5 1.2 rather which is you
know what we wanted the fluoride to be
we're now going to add to it the
displacement for the highest level of
the stairwell and we can see that we get
0.8 all right now to me that seems
exactly right because 0.8 is still going
to sort onto the same layer it's still
going to gonna snap when those cook
those coordinates are reckon analyzed so
I think I did what I wanted to do here
and that all of these people are going
to still be in that same chunk right but
obviously you know that's not true
because that's not what we're getting
here so I'm interested to know if if we
do step into here and just take a look
at what some of the Z values are what
are the Z values that we're actually
looking at here so I'm getting a Z value
of 0 and I'm getting that a lot and I'm
I'm wondering how am I getting a z value
of 0 right and I'm guessing that
probably what's happening there is the
camera is getting set to the location of
something specific which is undoing the
displacement that I did right so things
are sorting into the right chunk area
but we're not actually getting that same
sorting on the way out now mind you what
we should be doing is just using the
chunk in the first place for how we do
the rendering but that's sort of a
separate issue we'll get to that well as
we kind of collapse things down as we go
further so if I take a look here at the
entity transform with the default
upright transform bit and then we do
sort of the get ground to point entity
minus the camera P so what we can see
happening there
is I'm not really like this is not
really correct
right we're not actually using absolute
coordinates here which is what we should
actually be using what we should
actually be doing here is saying well
where is the entity in absolute
coordinates which is get enemy ground
point I guess well actually I don't even
know any ground point is relative this
sim region right and so what I need to
do is I want to know specifically what
the the difference is in chunk Z between
these two things
I want to know the difference in chunk
see between the the entity that I'm
rendering and the the sim origin so
really this is all noise at some level
and not really what we want to be doing
but that's okay right
like we just sort of we just sort of pop
back over here so it's you know we're
getting our bearings we're not expected
to know everything right away so yeah
what we wanted to do here is say okay
really what's going on here is I want to
know for purposes of the relative layer
alpha lookup right what I would actually
want to know for the alpha lookup is I
want to know or rather what I want to
know to figure out which layer I'm in is
really just saying well where is this
entity's actual location in the world
right so you know who knows where that
is exactly but I want to I want a base
to build like world locate you know
world position and I want to do the
chunk Z of that minus V whatever the the
simulation origin is or whatever the the
you know the fundamental point around
which I'm looking so I want the the sim
regions origin chunk see that is the
actual location I care about right now
fortunately I'm out of time but that is
what we will do tomorrow and then we
will take a look at what we want to do
for the rest of this stuff I think we
don't I think we don't care about this
anymore
right because this is computing the
distance from the camera in Z which we
don't care about because it's only the
layers themselves that we'll have that
be relevant so we have plenty of work to
do but now we know what we're actually
doing I'm gonna put it to do in here to
do
KC it's the chunk z difference that
tells us what the relative layer is I
already sent this bug to Allen so
hopefully next version of our critter
will have there's a bug that got
introduced regarding multi line double
slash comments but so roll areas and we
no longer care about the camera Z Delta
because things inside a layer aren't
transformed proportionately respectively
anymore all right so we'll go ahead and
tackle that tomorrow and I'll go to the
Q&amp;A now which I'm gonna have to teach
this machine to not blank the screen so
while I wait for the Q&amp;A I will see here
why tell this little fellow
system settings yeah
time and date hardware detection
appearance window manager desktop
behavior so I can shut down hardware
power management maybe on AC power don't
dim the screen don't do that
no no no apply like no okay so so maybe
that'll work
I don't really know we'll see okay
alright now we're good to go
and so that does do a great job of
asking questions it's true
no questions
what keyboard do I have well thanks to
mid low and fiery Drake I have a Razer
BlackWidow stealth tournament edition
actually which was sent to me as a gift
by those two fine gentlemen and I am
absolutely delighted to be typing on it
because it's so much better than the Das
Keyboard it's not even funny I have one
of these at work it's what I type on at
work and it's awesome and they sent me
one for typing on handmade here it's
been it's been extremely put it's been
very very pleasurable typing is like I
really enjoy the act of typing which is
probably why I'm a programmer in the
first place to be honest because I feel
like if you don't enjoy the act of
typing it's got to be pretty hard to
want to work on a computer all day but
it just feels great to type on these
things they just they feel fantastic I
really like their switches the Cherry MX
switches we're always just too hard in
my opinion I don't I like almost no
activation force like I want the key to
just like bottom like just like like
putting your finger in a cloud and the
these I think they're called orange
razor orange switches or are lighter
touch than Cherry MX browns which is
what I was looking and and that lighter
touch makes a big difference for me best
of luck to expect that the final game
will contain enough sprites to warrant
using a texture Atlas to reduce the
number of texture binds per frame well I
mean it depends on the circumstances
probably not it'd be pretty unlikely but
in either case it's that's really only
an AMD Hardware question I think wait is
it even it no I guess there really isn't
there there I don't think there's
anybody who has texture change overhead
anymore is there I don't even think
Intel does
so basically if you're trying to work on
really old hardware because nowadays
there's no penalty for changing the
texture handle right you don't you don't
it's just like changing the constant
store right so it's it's just like
trivial you could even put it in the
vertex if you wanted to so really that's
a hard that's a very specific hardware
question it's like you know on an Nvidia
card absolutely not like Nvidia any
Nvidia card would it won't matter at all
because you can just use bind lists on
your textures and be done right and then
you have note you never have a texture
bind right but on other hardware that's
not as true so depending on the hardware
that you target you would then be able
to answer that question but it's
certainly not something I would care
about well till we end up going to ship
the game right because it doesn't matter
right it's something we could go put in
a texture Atlas after the games done or
after it shipped even and it's not gonna
affect the architecture it just means we
have to write a better asset manager
than the one we wrote because now it has
to think about how it's gonna page
things in and out in a in a much more
specific way
and understand why Basie value of each
floor would be negative it seems really
contrived it seems very logical to me to
have zero as the bottom maybe it has to
do with rendering I have not follow the
latest shows well it's really it's just
it's a it's a very very straightforward
decision you can make and you can make
it any way you want
so saying contrived I guess I would
object because your it sort of makes it
sound like there's a right answer but
there isn't you have a cube right in
hand made here oh we call these chunks
but it's basically a spatial partition
where we clearly I did not do a good
enough job telling it not to blank my
screen stop thanking my screen options
how do I tell it sorry I gotta tell the
singer stopping my circa I can't see the
chat when it does that so let's see
screen saver screen locking screen
locking is in desktop behavior
okay screen locking lock screen
automatically don't do that there you go
apply okay hopefully now we're good so
you have two choices right we are
essentially a 3d world in handmade hero
right we you can move things around in
3ds we're so although we're 2d sprites
and stuff we don't have a 2d world
representation our representation is 3d
so the question is for this chunk where
would you like the sort of you know
canonical point inside a chunk to be
would you like it to be at one of the
corners say for example here would you
like it to be in the middle would you
like it to be in the middle in X&amp;Y but
at the bottom in Z all right you can
pick any one of those that you want but
which one you pick determines what your
base value is for a relative location so
if you were to pick the corner or the
center but bottom right then your Z
value for the floor would be you know
maybe zero you probably still wouldn't
get 0 for a floor value because then
it's right on the edge which seems like
it's gonna cause you some sorting head
like some rounding headaches so you
would probably still want it to be it
like you know point one or something
just to you know save yourself some
trouble but you know whatever you want
to do if on the other hand you pick the
center of the cube as the canonical
point then the floor relative that
canonical point is gonna be at negative
something which is however far down you
want the floor to be you know 0.5 point
whatever right so you can choose however
you want to do that but there isn't a
right answer like it's no more right to
say that the floor is that point 1 that
it is to say that the floor is at point
7 or something right it's completely
arbitrary it's just whatever your
reference point happened to be but I
would argue that if one was going to be
sort of persnickety about it
actually it's floor at 0 that makes the
least sense if you're not going to pick
a corner for everything so if you pick
the center bottom that's weird cuz now
your coordinates are handled very
non-homogeneous li inside all of your
computations because now everything is
about the center if you're in X&amp;Y
but it's about the minimum if you're in
Z so you've drawn this weird distinction
so now all your routines have to be
bifurcated every time you're leaving Z
you do one thing in X and ye to the
other now that's fine if you actually
had to write because you know obviously
in the renderer we're already doing some
things where we have to treat Z
separately but we're not treating Z
separately just because we like treating
Z separately I would love to treat Z
exactly the same but we have to because
we have certain effects that are based
entirely on Z well in the spatial
partition on the other hand there's no
difference between these three why would
we introduce an artificial difference so
I would argue that ok if you decided
let's say you decided that you really
want the floor at zero that's just what
you you really have to have it
ok fine your decision but I would argue
that at that point x and y should now be
also based on the minimum corner of the
cube not the center right now we're a
center right and so I wouldn't want to
move everything to min so its min X min
Y min Z at that point and hopefully you
can see why I think that
is true
all right I am going to wrap it up
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for an episode handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along with
the series at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org and it
comes to the source code so you can play
around with it and do your own
experiments for example if you wanted Z
to be at zero you could very easily go
do that we have a forum site you can go
if you want to ask questions we have a
patreon page you want support the video
series a schedule about you can use to
see when the studio's gonna be live and
an episode guide you can go to catch up
on past episodes and I highly recommend
using this good little bot because a lot
of times on the stream in fact I did it
yesterday or two days ago rather I'll
say we'll be back here tomorrow at blah
when the schedule is not for us to be
back here by I tend to be absent mind
about it so the schedule bot is almost
always accurate I am NOT so always check
the schedule bot if you want to know
when we're gonna be live it's the surest
thing to do that's about it I believe if
I'm not mistaken but I just said don't
trust me that I'll be back here too
tomorrow at 8 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time
until then have fun programming and I
will see you guys on the Internet
take it easy everyone