okay oh dear I've started the recording
for once with a with a shell window open
how unprofessional hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero show recode a
complete game live on stream we are well
you know it's gonna be interesting
day-to-day because essentially what
we've got is we have we've have it all
as Lemongrab would say but we'll fat
Lemongrab but we wrote a ton of code
over the past week weekend to use a
single text file input - well as many
text files as wanted technically but to
take a text file input and use that to
sort of specify a packing set and markup
for all of our assets and we got all of
that done it didn't take very long was
good and we kind of I think did a
reasonable job of it but we never ran
any of it
so we have no idea how much stuff we may
have screwed up we don't have any idea
how buggy it might be and so really what
we want to do this weekend today and
tomorrow is get all that code working
you know get the bugs out of it get the
like other parts of the system that
haven't been brought up to speed with
this integrated with it for example now
we have an open question that we want to
go address this will probably be what we
do right after we get everything working
here which is we now have an obvious
place and the clean path ready for us to
save changes
so basically when we do I don't know
folks who maybe don't catch the stream
every time might not know if we actually
go on here and we run the game there's
still owe and let me go ahead and put us
in release mode so we're running
reasonably quickly you'll have to bear
with me here we have some for code of
stuff I have to talk about as well
because we're still in the old for coder
and we're gonna switch to the new for a
coder shortly is as another thing
yeah so many things in here to talk
about so let's hand made here oh let me
switch to our build file here and
switches to an optimized build anyway as
I was saying inside handmade here we
made some tools that were designed to
allow us to quickly change how we were
like aligning art assets and stuff like
that
and so the F keys across the top you can
kind of see if I like click on those
right there's a bunch of jump that goes
on here and some of it we haven't really
done anything with you know there's some
stuff happening in here that really
probably needs to get updated a little
bit but then we've got you know some
stuff in here you can see there's like a
camera thing that we were using for
camera debugging that like shows us
stuff right and we can adjust things
like the fogging distances and that's
how we like tweaked those right it was
very handy for that and then we've also
got this other thing we can do here on I
guess f3 where at any time if I like
click somewhere right I can I can
highlight and you know we bring it low
so you can see it you can see there's a
little like wire highlight that kind of
goes around stuff and if I click on
those things then I can actually edit
you know the stuff that's that that I
selected so if I if I you know click on
one of these things here like you know
the glove or whatever right I can look
at what is in the glove and I can I can
sort of get some different information
points about it one of them is just like
you know what was in the file for it so
you know do have any like import errors
or anything like that and like what it
was who made it did it have a name or
description we never had a way of set
those before we do now and so those will
actually come up as being set to
something let me actually run our new
system too which is pretty cool but so
you know we've got this our stuff and
then the other one was this alignment
point saying the alignment points thing
is actually for editing in the game
right because you know we can change so
like for here you can see the default
alignment point I can change that and it
takes whatever the game thinks the
location of that thing is and it offsets
it right because we don't know you know
maybe the artist wanted to like base the
thing around the base of the glove or
maybe they wanted it around the
Fist of the Glover you know maybe we
want it around there who knows and so
that idea of be able to create these
like attachment points is something that
we need in it and we did a bunch of that
if I look at like the the sprite for the
the character that's being drawn right
now right which is just one of our
random orphans that we picked if you
look at how her textures are set up what
you can see is that actually the hot
points have already been set to like
attach her body to her head right and
you can see that here where you've got
these different attachment points here's
the one that goes to its child this is
the body this is one that goes to the
child this is the one that goes to the
world right you can see that base point
there is one that goes to the world and
then this one here that goes the base of
neck is like up there right and yeah if
you look at this this one has it's two
body one right where that is so these
two points like snap together and that's
what puts the head on top of the body
right now the problem that we had before
and it wasn't really a problem it was
more of like to do because we're like we
knew what we wanted to do with it but we
didn't have any way to actually do it
what we have there was once you did
those edits they got saved baked back
into the HHH egg so they are permanent
and like you know I run the game again
it's always there right so it's being
saved properly back into the game as as
such right so it works the way that we
want it to work and that's all good but
what we couldn't have done and never did
do is rebuild that HHA that data pack
file because if we rebuilt it we would
have lost all of that information right
all of that information would disappear
and so as we go forward and we're going
to be expecting a lot of these things
right I'm gonna go into that mode right
like if I was doing editing here and I
edit this one we're gonna edit a bunch
of these things and and we want to be
able to save them in a permanent way
that makes it easy for us to deal with
and so when we're going to be doing all
that we want those to go out into the
text file
that we can then check in to source code
control and version and all that stuff
and cut and paste between them if we
need to you know fix something all that
sort of stuff we're just tying in to the
the fact that there's a lot of text
editing tools out there right it doesn't
matter if it's text or binary in the
abstract but in terms of actually being
able to work with it having a text file
format for things that are small tends
to be pretty useful because it means you
can leverage all these other tools like
binary diff doesn't work particularly
well for example right but text ifs are
pretty good so all that stuff just means
that when we actually do one of these
edits what we'd like to do is be able to
generate the hht that corresponds to
that HHA file sort of from wool cloth so
that we can write out all those changes
and edit them that way right like that's
something we'd really like to be able to
do and so I need to put that back in as
well or not back in I need to put it in
in the first place because now we have a
clear way that we could do that and we'd
like to have that be operational okay
so let's take a look at how we're gonna
accomplish some of these things so the
first thing that we want to do is kind
of take a step backwards and say well
alright let's suppose first of all that
I mean maybe let's just try that one
step that part of it first
what if we wanted to be able to save an
hht file out from our HHA edits right so
for example if I was going to go in here
like I said before we already have this
idea that in here we have like an import
and save this save feature is grayed out
because we haven't made any changes but
that's the only reason it's grayed out
so you know we could even re-enable it
to make it so that it can do a resave in
the case where it wants to so if I did
go in here for example and said oh you
know maybe I just touched this thing you
can see that that will create an undo
record which will then mean that we
could save our HHA again if we did that
we could make it so that it saved the
hht alongside it and then it could be
our discretion whether we want to merge
that hht in or not or
whatever else we might want to do with
it and so that's that's thing number one
right and there's a couple different
ways that we could choose to do that and
I'm not sure exactly how we want to do
that just yet but we'll talk about it as
we go so if we wanted to do that how
would we how would we start off with
something like that right like how would
we make something that allowed us to
write out one of these files now if you
remember correctly what they look like
is you know is this so a tags file for
handmade hero is really pretty
straightforward it's just got you know
here's the type of thing that it's
looking at here's what the the file name
was that it came from and here are the
tags are associated with it there's also
some additional things such as the
author description and the HHA those are
set by default up here and we don't
really specify them anywhere else
because we don't have to write we don't
care about that part so what we'd like
to do now is have a way of writing out
these hht files that basically produces
something that looks exactly like this
so we can save changes that we make
inside the game and eventually for all
we know we might just make a tag editor
in there as well so that we never maybe
we never really touched these hhc files
very often anyway they're just our
archival format and we know that we can
go in here and edit them in text if we
need to if we screw something up or if
we want to be able to inspect the change
that we've made cuz something broke or
whatever we'd be able to do a diff on
them so it's a good thing to have in
there but for all we know we might never
really touch these by hand very often if
we actually put in something edit the
tags because obviously the rest of this
stuff is stuff that you know doesn't
really need to get edited much so that's
one way to think of it now there's a
couple of subtleties here which is that
in here we've got like block and body
and stuff like that I don't think we
saved this information so one of the
problems that we'll have is we'll have
to start preserving that information if
we want to be able to
to rebuild hht files so in here for
example inside where we've got the asset
source file right this thing right here
so when we talk about asset source file
we don't actually have you can see in
here we don't actually have the type of
asset import that we actually used now
we have a thing that says where the
assets went that we imported right so
that we could import them again into the
same place but we don't actually have
anything that's more specific than that
right we don't actually have anything
that that tells us any information about
what this source file was actually set
up to do and that's gonna be the hardest
thing I think for us to deal with as
long as we don't care about vaporizing
our current HHA edits which I don't
think we do cuz we only did a little bit
of edits on them basically just to test
the editor I think it's probably ok
because every time here for word that we
actually are going to be doing this we
can just store in this asset source file
what it was that we use for import and
because we can always read this file
itself in first we probably are fine and
to that end we may also be able to
actually have this overwrite the current
state of things so we probably could
even make it work now although I'm not
entirely sure so let's see about that
if I look and we talk about a you know
inside the asset importer if you
remember correctly what happens in here
is we do this note we have this notion
of like a parse pieces call right and
inside parse pieces actually can use
some of these new features you got here
just jump right to it inside parse
pieces what we have is this checking
where it says like oh you know is it a
block is it a head is it a body is it a
character right so effectively what we
do is we store that type token in
right and we we sort of remember from
that string what is the layout that we
should be using and because of that what
kind of happens here is once this piece
import occurs we sort of lose the
ability to we don't have any way to
recall what this actually is
Oh although you know I just had an
interesting idea though so I just had an
interesting idea and I'm not sure how I
feel about it
I don't think I like it so I think I'm
gonna skip it what I was gonna say let
me just put it out there what I was
gonna say is there is another way we
could do this that wouldn't require the
change that I'm about to make which is
that if you always rewrote the file by
first reading the file in and writing it
out as you go there's two really
interesting things that would happen
there and it's kind of tempting
let me fully describe what I'm talking
about because I don't want it to just be
happening in my head I don't want the
battle about which to do to only happen
to my head you know I try to avoid that
a hammer here wherever possible so
everyone could kind of hear my thought
process so here's what's going to happen
in the abstract and then let me tell you
about why the thought I had was a little
bit interesting to me and I haven't
really considered this before so let's
suppose that what we did is the most
straightforward way of augmenting the
current system to do what it is that I
wanted to do right so the way that I
thought up first because the way you
would normally do this right so let's
say that's what I wanted I wanted to
just say let's take this let's take the
system and just I want to be able to
output that this thing is a block or
whatever I have the final name in here
right and I know the assets themselves
so I can get you know the the rest of
the information out of it like what
their tags were and stuff like that but
if you look at what hat is happening
there I do have well actually and now I
think about there's actually more issues
to that I might have first right is I
don't know which one of these it is
because I not storing that in here so
what I need to do is I need to add that
information back second I would need to
write out which tags are common to this
thing that are not in the template so
I'd have to actually do a diff
of-the-art asset tags themselves and see
which tags are on the assets that aren't
in the template for that thing or store
the extra tags here my
self-right so that's a little bit of
extra work to that I hadn't included so
I need to do those two things but then
once I did those things you could prompt
presumably all see how I would like
rewrite out say block block orphanage or
one dot PNG right it's pretty
straightforward to see how we would do
that but the thing about that is if you
actually consider what's happening there
a lot of other information when I write
this out will also get lost let's just
talk about something very basic this
comment right where's that comment gonna
come from the comments not stored
anywhere we have no idea why that
comment was in there worse yet what
about this even worse what about that
right those are things that maybe I
wanted to re-enable later and so the
more I think about the more I'm thinking
that my weird idea is maybe not so weird
and it might actually be the right thing
so what if instead of doing it that way
what if we do it a completely different
way what if we instead make a system
that just reads the files that all of
the tag files as if it was going to do
an import but instead of importing it
just rewrites a new file for that tag
file and it just looks at whatever
you've added and inserts that in there
right so every time it reads one of
these lines it just mean it just copies
the line into the text file unless it
sees that you've modified what it says
on that line and then it puts it in
there right it's a little more work but
then it kind of all allows the code to
actually function properly and all the
things in there like the comments or the
defaults right we wouldn't have any idea
that there was a default block we would
just see that all of these assets had
these names we could sort of try to
reproduce that but we wouldn't even
necessarily know where the default
blocks got changed and when or why right
and more importantly we wouldn't
necessarily know the difference between
something that looked you know like
author and a rep burg here and then off
something else for the rest of these and
one that just had author specified on
this one and then a default for an
irreverent
here or something right because all we
would see is what the author actually
was on each of the assets that's all we
would know so I'm really leaning towards
that I think I'm just gonna do it I've
never done anything like that before but
it really seems like the right solution
and I don't have an argument against it
the only thing I was gonna say is that
it makes it a little weird to do edits
for things that don't exist in here at
all but I guess those are things we
could just handle specially so if you
add a new thing to the system in its
entirety using the UI we have to store
that separately but I think that's okay
I don't mind just storing that
separately I don't think so we'll see so
I think I'm actually gonna do that as
strange as it sounds
let's just do that I mean you know go
big or go home
right I mean that's that's the thing I
mean this is we're Pro we're
professionals we're professionals twitch
streamers here we're we're twitch
partners okay this is not this is this
is not some rinky-dink programming
stream right this is this is a full deal
we have custom emoticons we have custom
emoticons on here does anyone even know
that we've got we just set these up I
don't even know
check this out does this work I don't
know if this works or not I think it
might work but you know I couldn't
really tell you because I'm not 100%
sure but I think I think we have custom
emoticons in tells me here for a second
people let's let's go and eat let's go
into the emotes thing here and panel
okay try doing any mode of H a and D ma
to which is the thing they assigned us
hand ma to do hand ma to capital G
lowercase l.o.v.e yeah Oh someone's got
them right there right there yeah and
then there's Hemi there's Molly there's
Hiro and there's glove we've got are
those coming through let me take a look
let me see if we got that
let's see here oh yeah check that out
check that out look at that
crushing it alright so so we've got all
kinds of custom emotes here there's even
ones for like special subscribers like
we went all out like everything is up
there I don't know what let's see we're
the ones for the special subscribers are
there's there's two other ones that we
put up there
hand them out to baby and hand mop -
Krampus are also in there for special
subscribers which I don't I'll be honest
with you I don't really know how that
works I said I was a pro streamer I'm
not a pro streamer let's admit that up
front I do the best I can but I don't
really understand twitch super well so
you know alls I'm saying is there's
emojis in there and I don't know how
they work but they're in there and I
think that counts for something
the fact that I don't really know how to
use the UI that sets up the twitch
emotes notwithstanding I did Anna did
draw them and I did upload them so you
know that's so pro streamer right I in
and you know it's not my fault I don't
have one of those weird chairs that luck
comes up to here for some reason
but we're still pro streamers so alright
let's just do it I talked about this the
other day actually so one of the
questions was what's the difference
between like this tokenizer and maybe
one that's a little more investor
strength there are some things certainly
but the biggest change that I usually
make structurally and I'm gonna make
that change right now
is that there's two stages to
tokenization roll and unroll
and so I'll show you what that looks
like because we're gonna want it now to
preserve our comments and so I'll show
you why
so in a tokenizer typically what you do
is you have this function called get
token or something similar to it you've
seen the way ours works ours is pretty
basic right we're not trying to break
any land-speed records here we're not
trying to anything too fancy we just
want basic tokenization and that's what
we're doing but when we call this get
token what you can see is there some
filtering that is occurring on the token
all right and let's talk about what that
filtering is
so first and most important eat all
white space right and what eat all white
space is gonna do up here you can see is
it's gonna skip right over those
comments right those comments are just
gone munch you know there they go
and so that's one big thing that we're
losing when we call get token is any
comments that are in stream are gone now
normally mmm-hmm that's what you want
when you're parsing because you don't
want to think about token you don't want
to think about comments in your token
stream you don't want to check and let
me just again for those of you who don't
work with parsers very often it might be
a little non-obvious how all this stuff
works and that's okay this stuff is kind
of complicated once you work with
compilers a little bit you get used to
it but at first it's a little bit
strange certainly um but you know take a
look at what how this code works right
you can see in here we do stuff like oh
I just saw the token default so now I
know that the next thing is going to be
this open brace right because it's a
default so this is backwards by the way
nice job guys no one caught that
so is default is gonna say look I've got
one of these I don't need to look for
the string because it's the default not
a normal one so what I'm gonna do
instead is do require token open race
because I know that I get the default
token they get an open brace right and
you can see that happening in here right
defaults open brace so that's we're
looking for but the problem is the user
can stick any number of comments in here
right and so what I would have to do in
the parser if I if I actually made a
comment be its own token right is every
time we got a token like right here
every time we did token equals default
doesn't like that I would have to do a
while loop while it's a comment eat all
the comments right you seen I'm saying
and so that's a problem because it makes
all of this code more complicated and
weird but what we can do like I said is
have the parser just handle those and
that's the way we wrote it every time
you get a token it returns the neck
actual meaningful token and it throws
away anything that's just incidental to
the co stream such as a return or the
comment or whatever right but what if we
want all that stuff back right what if
we want all of that stuff back because I
want to reproduce the input to the
output
I want the comments I want the new lines
where they were
I want it laid out exactly as the user
had intended
I don't want right to put this sort of
other stuff I don't want it to throw
away all of what they did and only have
the bear the bear structure of it come
out the other end I want their comments
preserved so if we're gonna do that
again it's actually not that hard this
is something I don't know if other
people do this this is just something I
made up at some point but I would
suspect that other people probably do
similarly because it's just it's the
design that you would do right is you
turn your get token into a get token raw
so instead of having get token be the
thing that actually processes the token
you have a thing called get token raw
which is actually the thing that now
processes your tokens and then you
introduce the get token call as
something that operates on top of that
so everyone who was calling it token
before it can still call it oops put
that one to low
everyone who was calling get tokens
still calls get token but anyone who
wants to reproduce the stream can call
get token draw and that way you can get
those individual pieces back much more
easily okay and what gets who can draw
does is it actually preserves all of
that stuff right so all of the
whitespace
all of the comments all of that stuff
can actually just be handled in here and
so now what we do is we take this
routine for eat all whitespace right
and we grab that and we we kind of shove
it into here right so we say look this
is actually where we're going to be
processing the whitespace not what you
were getting before right and so in here
what we'll do is we'll say all right
let's get this whitespace
and process that properly so here is
what we'll be looking for right these
are our whitespace characters that we
know of right so these are the
whitespace characters that we know of
and you know we also have these comment
ones right so forward slash and star and
that sort of stuff those are things that
we have to care about right so we've
also gotten this so here's our white
space and here is our our slashes and so
let's go ahead and process the slashes
first okay and if I want to if I look up
here I notice we're not using slash for
anything maybe I might do this a
slightly different way because we happen
to not use these for anything else what
I could do is actually move these into
my default clause and that would work as
well right so I could put those in here
as something more like this right and so
the way that would look is like this and
so these become welded together so what
I'm doing now is saying all right let's
take a look when we do our default thing
like we were doing before we're going to
scan for things like identifiers in here
but we're also going to scan for the
other things that we were scanning for
us such as if there was a piece of white
space here right if there was comment
you know C style CSS style comment if
there was a C style comment and then if
it isn't any of those things then we
will continue processing it the way that
we were processing before as you know
something else so what we want to do
here is if we see a whitespace character
then we will do a while loop to get all
of the white space out right and we'll
just consider that one big chunk of
white space if we don't right so if
instead we see one of these comments
we'll get out the comment the only thing
we then have to do is again like you can
look at what's happening in here right
at the end of all of these
we're doing a token text count equals
the input data minus the data right this
sort of thing here this is always going
to be true for all of these cases we're
always going to suck up as much of the
token as we could there right and so all
I really have to do to support these
comments as proper tokens is to just say
hey every time you grab one of these
just now set it to comment right off you
go and I could differentiate between
these if I wanted to I could say that
this was a CPP comment right or I could
say that this is a si comment I don't
know that we're ever gonna care which
kind of comment was which I think we
just don't need to know so for now I'm
not going to differentiate between those
I'm just going to say that there is such
a thing as a token comment right now
let's go a little bit further let's keep
pushing our advantage here in to the
extent that we have one and say all
right so in that case let's say we've
also got token white space and let's say
we've also got a token let's say newline
right and this way we can sort of do
some processing of a few other things as
well so if I wanted to do that now we
know that we've got token comment in
both of these cases that should just
work because we're already have the code
for sucking up what's ever inside the
comment
let's also process these other things so
let's stop thinking about is whitespace
maybe that's the wrong thing to think
about and let's do something a little
bit different which is let's think about
whitespace let's think about is
whitespace a little bit more broadly
interesting enough look so we have two
is white spaces why is that so we have
is white space with ab32 X and is
whitespace oops that's a in line why is
it coming here that's weird it's like
some kind of weird bug
well I'm not sure what's going on there
hmm wonder if that parsers busted or
something this is sort of not the full
version of it's not even the it's it's
quite old of the new for coder stuff
that I was doing in here so I wonder if
there's some kind of I'm not sure what's
going on there where there's it's
listing two of these but one of them it
doesn't seem to know where it actually
is like there it is but this one it
doesn't seem to know and I wonder if
there's some kind of a weird bug in
there there's only one is whitespace
routine here but I'm just not sure where
it's getting that one from so who knows
anyway I won't belabor the point for now
so we here what I'd like to do is take a
look at these and say oh and you know
what actually looking at this it looks
like the is whitespace here doesn't
actually have end-of-line included so
actually this would have not really
worked properly I wonder how that was
working before if it's because I think
it must have been oh no it does it does
it has is end of line there so I think
what we want to do is something like is
spacing right and then we can basically
duplicate this out into here so we can
check for these things individually and
so this will just call is spacing or is
end of line but then you can you can
call is spacing as something that's a
little bit more specific so you know the
difference between those two so I'm
going to do an is spacing here and this
will eat up all spacing characters and
we'll call that token spacing versus
token newline right so if we have token
is spacing will suck all of those up
into one thing that's the spacing token
and then if you have a new line
is end of line then what we want to do
is remember that that's the case and it
looks like I should call that end of
line so when we get that there's an
important thing to remember here which
is that end of line processing is kind
of delicate right
and so when we actually suck up this
token we want to do this in kind of a in
a bit of a meticulous way if you look at
end of line here you can see we're
checking for either of these two things
but there's a number of ways that line
endings can occur let me show you what I
mean by that there's Linux there's Mac
and there's Windows it was hoping this
would be here we go
so you can see on here a little table of
how line endings have gone right and
what you can see is that there's a lot
of nasty variance between what these
were now let me give you a little bit of
background on how it got this way cuz
you're probably looking at this
especially if you're fairly young and
never lived through the terminal years
you probably are wondering why you could
get messed up this badly although you
know if you've ever seen
CSS you're probably not wondering that
but you're probably like wow this is
relatively clean so if you think about
how these escape sequences are working
these are special ASCII codes write a
backslash n actually translates to it -
oh X a as a hex value right and back
says R is o x OD right or just o XD as a
hex code right and so those are
non-printing characters and they
represent when you're trying to go to
the next line and if you look at what
happens here backslash R + backslash
and you might be like well why is there
some that are just back session why are
there some that are back sis are back
session why are there some that are just
back such are why are there some that
are backslash-n back so sorry how did
that happen and the answer is because
these date all the way back to the years
when you actually weren't talking about
like raster displays on a micro computer
or something like that right you were
actually talking about things like I
have a mainframe and it's connected via
some kind of cabling or even over a
phone wire to like a vt100 terminal or
something that's just a dumb terminal
that all it is is a screen and a
keyboard and a little chip that's smart
only smart enough a load ship there's
still a big board that's only smart
enough to like send things off the wire
when they're pressed and receive things
back from the wire when they are
received and all it had from memory was
just the buffer of this what was on the
screen
that's all it remembered right so what
these things correspond to were actually
two different operations sometimes one
is go back to the beginning of the line
and I believe that's backslash or right
so in the old days if you if the
terminal got o x OD what it meant was
wherever you were on the line because
remember it's keeping track as as
letters are coming down the pipe
it's stacking them one right after each
other across the screen right then if
you do backslash R right which was Oh X
OD right if that came if you've got that
oh XD down the pipe what it meant was
wherever the cursor is go all the way
back to the beginning of the line go go
down just go back to the beginning of
the line right backslash n on the other
hand or Oh X a if that came down the
pipe it meant move down one line right
but it didn't necessarily mean go back
to the beginning of the
and so the protocol for these terminals
and the protocol for these transmitted
formats and however else you want to
look at it because there was no real
standard it was fairly flexible some
people decided well you know what
generally when we go back we want to go
down the line and back to the beginning
so let's just send o X a and that'll
mean like go down and back right other
people were like no let's have two codes
one that is the thing that go back to
being aligned and one that is to go down
the line right let's do that
other people were like well you know
what I agree we should only send one but
instead of sending Oh X a let's just
send o XD that's the thing they need to
go back to the beginning of the line
that's that that's the one we would
probably want to automatically go down
not the one that goes down that one we
might want to use just to like stay
where we are or whatever right etc etc
etc etc so it's just it's just
historical accident that we ended up
with this nowadays you would never do
this you just have one way of encoding
end of line but that is not the way
organic systems evolve right so what
that means for us is if we want to
generally not care what kind of text
editor produced this thing because we
don't know what you know this text
editor could have done anything who
knows what it's stuck at at the end of
the line maybe it's doing mac format or
UNIX format or Windows format or who
knows what or any of these other things
we have up here like Linux Mac cost
FreeBSD ax xenix biasa MIGA and RIS cos
for example or maybe it's Atari windows
das deck tops-10 right like or baby it's
the Commodore
maybe it's the the c64 I don't know
right so who knows where this came from
or Mac offs but maybe it coming
someone's using an old Mac one of those
ones that has a little smiley face when
you boot all right so if we're doing
that then what we want to do is when we
get an end-of-line we want to look to
see if it matches any of these possible
sequences and if it does we want to
generally assume that the largest
sequence we could match is the end of
line so that if it inserted this or this
we will suck that up as a single
end of line character instead of
treating it as - end of lines which
would be incorrect right so what I want
to do is say all right this is an end of
line token and then I want to look and
see if tokenizer at zero equals
something and scoops and tokenizer at 1
equals something then we'll consider
advancing I'm sorry right this covers
you in fact I could I could do it this
way as well so what I could do is do two
of these checks like that right and so
all I want to do here is say look when I
get an end of line character if it's
just a backslash R by itself or just a
backslash n by itself we'll assume that
that is what the text editor is using
for and of line but if we see a
backslash R followed by a backslash N or
we see a backslash n followed by a
backslash R we can assume that we need
to move one more character forward right
because we've sucked up one of the
characters but we haven't sucked up the
other character right so we want to skip
that so that we don't treat it as two
end of lines this will handle all four
variants of the end of line that we
could see no matter which crazy type
type of text editing line ending we got
it should still work because this way if
it's back to star boxes an or back stem
boxers are will eat them both if it's
just a bare black R or a bare back end
we will just consider one of them if
it's - backslash ends or - backslash
ours that obviously means there actually
are two end of lines because there was
nothing there are no end of line formats
that have two backslash ends meaning one
carriage return that's not a valid line
ending that I mean your text Center to
ever use so we don't have to worry about
that one right so now we have all of the
ways we can get whitespace and comments
and stuff into the system and now we can
call get token raw and get token raw
will then give us what we actually
needed to use right
okay so now we can sort of imagine what
you would do if you did want get token
we probably won't really use get token
very much because we're going to have to
sort of do a little bit of a porting
style shim here probably I mean it
depends on how we want to do it you'll
see there's probably some fancy-pants
stuff we can do here so maybe we will
actually call get token well we'll see
how we want to make it work at the end
but so you can now see how get token
would be implemented so that you can get
either one what you're going to do here
is you're going to say hey let's get the
actual token from get token wrong and
we'll see what it is right and I
probably want this to happen up up top
right and so what I'll do is I'll go
into my loop
I'll get token raw and I just won't exit
the loop when it's a token that I don't
care about right so if I want to write I
can just do an if you know token dot
type equals blah else break and in the
equals block Clause I can just put the
types that I actually care about right
these ones here I'm sorry that I
actually don't care about I can just do
those so if it's a spacing
if it's a spacing if it's an end of the
line or if it's comment I'm just gonna
ignore it right so that'll allow me to
kind of eat forward through the stream
and then the other thing I want to do
here we'll talk about one second but
what that means is when I call get token
now I'm only gonna get things that were
actually valid to the code stream and
that actually have meaning anything that
was just whitespace end of line four
comments will still get filtered out so
now it's it has not changed the behavior
of the parser at all the part still
works exactly as it used to but we now
have the ability at any time to really
talk about the token stream at a lower
level if we want to which is exactly
what we want to do for doing this sort
of throughput processing sort of you
know what's the word I'm looking for
unmolested copying basically we don't
want to change in any way the input into
the output if no changes have occurred
and we want to preserve all of that sort
of connective tissue that was in there
originally okay so there's one other
thing I want to do here because since we
ended up doing a slightly more hardcore
parser I also want to talk about one
other thing which is there is a string
kind of type right there is token string
and what I want to talk about here is
just that if you look at what happens
with token string so in here you can see
we get this right you can see what
happens here we go in and we say look if
we had a quote then what we're gonna do
is we're gonna actually skip that
initial quote care write that initial
quote card is gonna get skipped and you
can see us right here not actually
touching that end quote either so we're
leaving that the actual value of the
token okay is is what's inside the
double quotes and that means that it's
again it's modifying the input
in a sense right we can't just copy the
token value to the output and expect it
to work right we don't want that to
happen we want this to be preserved and
so if we do that what we can do is
recognize the fact that actually let's
leave that in there right let's just
leave that in there don't update this
right don't update that at all
and don't do this right let it actually
advance over that this has two really
interesting benefits the first is the
fact that here well there's one there's
I guess there is one thing that has to
sort lightly get a little bit more
complicated well actually no it doesn't
have to do that now that I think about
it so actually this is kind of cool so
let me show you what happens here if we
do this if everybody always uses the
actual input that they're given as their
token value and that gets modified later
as we'll talk about in a second then
what you can see here is this part of
the process actually gets simpler
instead of everybody having to think
about how they're gonna set it now
literally nobody does so this is always
the code oops
this right here is now always the code
every time so no matter what happens
when we come in through here right no
matter what happens we always set the
size of the text to just be wherever we
ended up right so what however far we
advanced from the time that we started
right which is here we always end up
setting our count to be that much nice
and uniform really kind of cool right
and then what we do is in here when we
actually get the tokens and we go to say
let's produce sort of the processed
version of the token this is the point
at which we can do something about it
so in here when we get this string what
I can say is let's trim the quotes off
of the string so pretty simple right all
I have to do is say look if the token
and let me just flip back here so if the
token text has anything in it right so
if token texts count is great well it's
just
right you know if it's if it's not zero
right if there's something in the token
and the the very first thing in it
happens to be a quote care skip it
right make sense that trims the the
leading quote here is the trailing quote
same thing if token texts count still
has something in it then if the last
character is a quote skip it
right and so what this allows us to do
is this allows us to make a really
simple tokenizer two-stage process that
means that now there's no special
handling everybody just goes through
sees what's in their particular chunk
that they want to figure out how big it
is however much they ingested is how big
the token is always and then there's a
second stage that just goes through and
says look I'm gonna go through this and
I'm gonna go ahead and in fact I could
do this a little bit differently we will
always break here but we can make that
in the second stage
I will eat any token that's just white
space cuz I don't want that right and
then when I get an actual token I'll
return it and by the way if I look and
see that this thing is a token that
needs some kind of further processing I
will process it right and off you go so
that's this really nice two-stage design
for a tokenizer it pays some extra
dividends to I'll show you those right
here let's suppose that we wanted to
start doing error line number tracking
so you can see that we kind of set
ourselves up for this we have this
notion of a line number in there we have
this notion of tokenized
inside here we sort of say hey yeah
let's set that line number to one
because we're on the first line let's
set that filename to something because
we need to actually
know what the file name is actually
gonna be um and I might say I don't know
about the file name but probably let's
let's make the file name a string
probably right I think we want that to
be the case so we'd say something like
this so this is the file name that that
were parsing in terms of you know for
air reporting so when we tokenize the
input we would do it this way and I
don't know exactly how we want to do
that per se if we want to initialize
that or force people to do it but you
know it looks something like this
so in here we'd say all right there's
the file name that we're parsing we're
starting on line number one now if we
want to report those errors it becomes
really good we can actually be super
hardcore here and even say column number
right so if we if we really want to be
mr. fancy pants this is a parser that
people are actually now using in the
real world and in life and it produces
good error messages or something like
that we can even have column number Y
well take a look at what happens inside
here we say advanced cares every time we
do advanced cares count well guess what
that's the line number count not
particularly confusing also as far as I
know does advanced cares ever do
anything other than advanced cares one
there's a two here so it does
occasionally do too well that's fine all
right so anyway in advanced Kerris we
know that we're always advanced by
certain count that means that the
tokenize our column number right that we
we've got here is always gonna be
advanced by that much so it's pretty
easy to find out what the column number
is and furthermore every time we
generate a token we know that the line
number is always the tokenizer
line number it's actually than that and
the column number is just the tokenizer
column number right so we know the
column number always advances here all
we need to do now is know what the line
number is guess what we're parsing end
of lines now that makes it really really
really simple to do that because now all
we do is every time we see a new line we
reset the line number I'm sorry we
advanced the line number and we reset
the column number right now all of a
sudden we can actually do really robust
error messages where we actually say
exactly where the error message
came from which is pretty baller and so
on here for example where we do this out
F and we've got all this nonsense have
it happening in here by the way I'm not
sure why that's being passed it out F so
why is out F getting the file name in
the line number does anybody know why
that's happening I think this is not
correct I mean it should be error F if
it's getting those things is the thing
that seems bad because why would you be
pet well you know what I don't know I'm
not gonna criticize myself we'll just
leave it the way it is for now that's
fine but it's stupid and so what I'd
like to do is figure out why we were
doing that and do we actually use that
and if we do actually use that how so
let me take a look at where that's
actually happening so if I list
locations for out F I want to see like
who who's doing that and why
so when here we got our error messages
those are fine if you look at look on
here for example so that's that's doing
an error message but it's actually got
the source grid like that's that does
yeah that's not what we actually want
there so yeah I'm just looking at this
so I don't really know it looks to me
like a deaf shouldn't really have that
probably I mean I mean you could there's
ways in which I could see that being the
case but just I'm really torn okay so
let's let's say this let's let's let's
do this because these chunks say the
file and line number here we have to
imagine what would you be doing with
that file on line number right and do we
want that file on line number to
correspond to like the text file input
in the case where you're processing a
text file input or do we want that to
correspond to the piece of code that's
issuing the error message right and I
don't really know the answer to that
question I'm not sure and that's why
it's just a little bit Squinkie in this
case right I think what I'm gonna say is
that should just the out F should be
like a separate thing right the out F
should be doing it should be talking
about code errors so that you can jump
to the piece of the code that issued the
error in case you wanted to do that or
something I'm gonna say that that's more
what it is maybe I don't know sort of
kind of don't quote me on this
I'm really torn here as opposed
destroying the what the actual file was
that got loaded and that was generating
the error I'm just thinking that's
probably what you want but I really
don't know let's say that that was the
case and we can always change it later
if it turns out that it's stupid right
so I'm not gonna do this because that is
not what I want to do what I'm gonna do
instead is I'm going to call out F in
both cases right like so and I'm going
to actually put the error information
into here right so I'm going to say here
that this is the error in question and
then here comes the the rest of the
information oh and also we should put
print out what that token was in the
case where there is a token as a
separate issue right okay so in here
what I want to do is say well there's
some token in here that's the token that
we want to record as being the error as
well and I'll quote that so you can you
know see what it was and then there's
the error message that you actually have
and that'll go in there I don't know to
what extent this does carriage turns or
anything like that so we'll have to kind
of talk about that a little bit later
and I guess that's because it's
streaming I guess this would probably
need that as well I want to say I'm not
100% sure about that but you know we'll
just say that that's true so this would
be how we would have to make that
formatting work right in order for
everything to work okay and so we here
we would pass the token eyes sorry the
on token file name the on token line
number and the on token column number
right so that would give us those three
pieces of information so we would just
be able to print those out that's
necessary and then finally for the
actual content of the token we would
just pass in its text field so that
gives us error reporting pretty cleanly
in here where we don't actually have the
you know a specific token we still could
print out a token if we wanted to
and I'll show you how that is the case
so let's suppose instead here we were to
you know want to print out something
similar to this so we want to print out
something that looks like that but now
we don't have the on token that's okay
because we could make our own on token
right that if we wanted to we could
pretty easily do that and the way that
we would do that is we'd say well look
we know that the token neither can still
get us a token right so what we could do
is just actually like peek the token
like get whatever the next token would
have been if we wanted to do that and
use that so for example if we wanted to
in here in a handmade tokenizer
you can kind of see how we've got
everything stored here if we wanted to
we can pretty trivially do a thing where
we get the next token without actually
pulling it off of the input stream and
there's a lot of ways we can do that the
easiest way by far to do it if we want
to have a peek token call or a peek
token raw either way it's really pretty
straightforward all you would do is say
look I want to do keep token raw hey
save the state store the state
right pretty straightforward
so all you have to do there say hey
let's get that token now there's a
reason why you might not want to do this
and it's worth noting we don't have the
problem currently but it's really worth
knowing that this could be bad so if you
were actually to call peak token wrong
like this and I'll support this call
because I mind as well but I don't know
that I'm actually gonna use it and I'll
say why in a second so if we wanted to
we could call peak token wrong so I
could just say look give me whatever the
next token is off of this tokenizer
and then I'll display that as the on
token there are some reasons why you
probably don't want to do that
and the reason why you probably don't
want to do it is just because look if
you do that you're definitely in danger
of re-entering your own code so let's
say that we have something in here that
generates an error message the peak
token call could generate an error
message which then causes this code to
loop infinitely as it keeps calling peak
token and keeps getting an error message
right so there's something to be said
for not really doing peak token that way
but for our particular purposes it's
really not a big deal so I'm just gonna
say screw it it's fine right so off we
go and it's just it's just worth noting
that there's other ways you might want
to do that that it depends on what
you're doing obviously but off you go so
this also means that we probably just
want to make one of these just to make
it a little bit clearer what's going on
here we probably want to do one of these
where we just pass the arg whisk right
so something like this and then this is
really just the same call in all cases
oops so there's the you know the actual
call that we're talking about and then
in these cases it's just a question of
how do you actually fulfill the
parameters in question do you get them
from the caller like in this case
or do you generate one of them
yourselves like in this case but this
way we're now being more uniform about
the way it's being called and so that
way if we modify the way that this works
in the future both of our errors will
automatically inherit the the changes
without having to be sort of kept in
sync or anything like that so that's
just a little bit more pleasant in that
regard all right so if we look at what
happens here we can see that we've got
just a one slight error where we didn't
copy the change that we made in the CPP
file up to the H file gotta love that C
nonsense there so anyway just put it in
here you can see it's the same thing it
just takes a filename now so everywhere
that we were tokenizing we can now pass
an optional filename and so we should go
ahead and do that pretty much everywhere
because we like the error reporting to
be good there oops I would I do what did
I do
it's got semicolon
so here where we've got like file buffer
what we need to do is is get the actual
file name in there and so if we take a
look back at our platform layer I
believe we've got the what does that
called
platform file info so inside platform
file info you can see here we've got
this base name pointer here so I believe
that's all we need to pass for like what
the name of the file is so it doesn't
include a path or extension it's kind of
a little bit weird that we're doing that
at the moment but guess that was just
our convention because we were kind of
using that as a thing before probably
want to put the extension back in there
honestly I yeah that's not great but
anyway at the moment anyway you know
that's fine so that's going to be wrap
base name off of that file foe
and then presumably there was some other
places that were tokenizing
as well was that the only tokenizer
maybe that's the only one all right
that's the only one so now we'll get
those error messages will actually tell
us exactly where we're getting the error
and that's a lot better right because
that way if we look at you know problems
that we get when we're done with the
export that'll allow us to know what the
heck happened right which is kind of
something that we want to be able to do
all right so now let's move forward from
there and we also kind of need some ways
of maybe printing those out and showing
those a little bit more clearly right
now we can look at them on any given
asset if it had an error when it was
imported we can see that but that's
really the only way we can't say after
we do an import show me all the errors I
don't think that's currently something
that works and so we kind of want that
to be the case so like in here you know
we would like to be able to ask at the
end of things say show me all the errors
that happened during this import so
that's probably something we want to put
in here as well into some kind of buffer
that we could just view the errors so
that's just another thing that would be
nice to be able to do something to think
about
so that's pretty much it now we need to
do is talk about how we're gonna
actually do that you know writing
process alongside or reading process so
when we call parse hht here and we're
reading through it right this is the
function that would actually need to do
that sort of you know copy and what you
can see is as this is is plying through
here parse top-level block is one gonna
want to do its own copying is necessary
but any other token that we're getting
here we want to kind of copy it to the
the output right so what we'd rather do
is say anytime we get a top-level token
we want to be able to put sort of
incidentals and move them from the input
to the output and we don't really want
to fuss with them at all and so we
should probably not quite do that piece
of code yet and the reason I said is cuz
it's just not very complicated like all
it would be is it get token raw check to
see which type it was if it's one of the
we process if it's one of the things
that we want to just copy like comment
or whitespace we do so and then we
process the rest exact same way we may
not want to quite do the input to output
copy exactly that way and because of
that is why I sing I kind of want to
look up at something more complicated
first to see how we might want to do
that so if we come through here and we
look at parse top level block and pretty
much that's that does like all of the
parsing right this pretty much does
everything if you look at how this is
grabbing the you know it's just kind of
lemon grabbing off of the data they're
just pulling things off one at a time we
probably just looking at it right we
probably want to do a thing that just
says look at certain points in the input
stream just copy everything that you saw
because it's all fine right and so we
just want to put a thing in here that
says yeah just get all of that stuff
that you've got like get all of that
stuff you've seen so far it's all fine
so copy it right that's probably more
like what we want to do and so I don't
think we really want to do something
where we're doing a token by token copy
that way
and so what I'd rather do here is say
all right look when we actually get down
into here by the time we've gotten to
this I guess I want to say something
like I think I think I just want to say
like okay if you got the open brace just
like
this you know I'm saying like take
everything up to and maybe you know I
don't even need that I could just be
like this and so I could just say or you
know up to and including maybe so like
do this whole thing right so this would
just basically say look everything just
copy everything up to the open brace so
far is all good we haven't had to make
any changes to it so just copy all that
right and then we can look at the
parsing here and say okay we're gonna
get all of this stuff out right and
we're gonna have there's gonna be like a
new set of stuff that we need to sort of
output here and we should try to figure
out whether that stuff needs to come in
probably like line by line right and so
the way I want to do that is say alright
there's one thing that we haven't put in
here that we need to put in here and
that's these markup points so let's
let's try to put those in so that we
have the full picture pretty sure that's
the only thing that we edit right is
alignment points I mean we got tags so
we can look at week and if there's
potentially but
so here you go with haja line point type
rent and HSA line point if I look at a
bitmap that's all there is like dim and
Orick dim are processing based things so
it's really just these two I would say
this this array and so if that's all
we're doing then we really all we have
to do is is output these right each of
those just has to kind of be specified
and the size and the P percent probably
we want to just represent them as their
16-bit versions we could represent them
as f/32 I don't know I think I kind of
just leaned towards just keeping them as
whole numbers cuz I don't see us ever
editing these in text really because
we're always gonna use the editor so we
just replicate the 16-bit value about
seems fine maybe possibly probably I'm
not sure we can think about that later
but for now I think I'm gonna say that's
how that goes yeah probably should so
what I want to do is say look if the
token is a line then that's going to be
in a line point statement and the align
point statements will probably just go
like 0 through whatever and I don't know
how we want to specify that but we get
to say like this particular line point
like a line point 0 is this now an open
question is do we care about preserving
the actual indices themselves meaning is
there any reason to say like a line
point zero stays aligned point zero and
a line point three is a line point three
or should we just condense them down as
we remove things I'm gonna say let's
just leave them sparse because I don't
know how we might want to do that in the
future you know I don't I don't know
what we want to do there so I'm gonna go
ahead and say that like a line can
actually have like a bracket syntax or
something maybe on it that allows us to
specify
what it is right and you know again
don't know maybe we should just use a
parenthesis but we're using parents or
different values so I might say let's
not do that and let's actually say that
we'll do do it this way so we'll say
that there's gonna be an open bracket
poops and a closed brackets and then
we'll actually get you know an index out
of it
so we'll also require a number to come
out of there
right so we'll get all those will
require an equal sign because you're
gonna have to assign this particular
line point to something right and then
we will look at how we want this to be
structured and again I think we just
want this to be 100% rigid I don't think
there should be any way to really modify
it so it's gonna be these three things
P percent size and then there's gonna be
the like name of the thing and whether
it goes to the parent or not right so I
don't really know what I want the syntax
is that to be let's think about it so
inside the hht file it would look
something like this so we'd say align
point 0 is supposed to have a P percent
so you know P percent a size you know
and I mean if we really wanted it to
look like C it would be the P percent
would look like this the size would look
like that and then the the type would be
here so you know like like that right
and if it was HH align to parent it
would look like that
and in here for the pay percent we would
specify I don't know the two values
right so that would be sort of the way
that it would look if it were maximally
expanded to look exactly like it would
in C++ right now the braces are not
necessary right so we could just do this
certainly if we wanted to and the HHA
line is also not necessary because we
know that that's the only thing that be
read and the only reason we have to do
that sort of stuff and C++ C++ you know
is is divine designed by three frogs and
they just let as many tree frogs jump
all over a keyboard as possible and then
they call that the new specification so
you know in a real language you wouldn't
have to use the prefix because it would
know that inside an assignment
expression it was the thing that you
were signing it to and off you we go to
be fair they tried to do some of that
with namespaces but of course they
screwed it up anyway uh let's go ahead
and look at how this looks you know we
could do something like that and then
it's pretty close to C so it looks
basically the same as it would look if
you were writing it and see but it's a
little less verbose doesn't have as many
you know sort of arbitrary constructs in
it that are you know sitting around
so if we were going to do this what we
would say is okay there's a tokenizer
requirement that we get a number of
comma a number comma a number of comma
and then after that we are going to get
an identifier now after the identifier
we don't necessarily know if we're going
to get a semicolon or not right we don't
know what the next thing is going to be
so what we need to do is we need to test
to see whether or not that would be the
case
before going any further and here's
where this sort of thing becomes a
little bit more Squinkie there because
it means that we would have to use a
peak token here in order to see whether
or not the next thing was a semicolon
because if it was then we would need to
not parse it and let the the code down
here below parse it right and to be
honest I don't know how the tags list is
actually doing that so if you go up to
the tag list and you look at how the tag
list is parsing itself right it looks
like I see how that works so well no I
don't so it's not really working
properly in here right this this really
does need to be a peak token right
because if it wasn't a peak token then
it wouldn't leave the tokenizer in state
that would actually work so I'm pretty
sure that this actually should probably
you know have been written that way in
the first place so so I might go ahead
and say all right let's say we're going
to use peak token
so here I'll peak token and I'll just
say all right you know if the token
that's coming next and you know here's
another question how did optional token
work
so optional tokens totally busted right
because it didn't it actually always
grabs the token is anyone calling that
yeah so this is we kind of broke this
right cuz it's yeah so that's good
actually that we did that so we want to
do a peek token and then what we want to
do is say look only get the thing if it
was the right type right
oops now this is a little inefficient
here because as you can kind of see
we're doing the same work twice which is
kind of dumb and if we really cared
about this via the parser we wouldn't
want to do that but we don't really have
to care in this case which is kind of
nice because we're processing so little
text that it will never see it
so that's kind of nice we don't have to
be too worried about the way that codes
working um so then yeah we can just do
hey look if optional token token I guess
what do you want to call that or I guess
then we want to require the other
identifiers and that's it because you
can only have one other one right so
we're just gonna grab that you'll just
let me grab that out and then we're good
to go and then we can change this code
up here to do the same so this can do a
peak token and that way to leave the
semicolon in the input stream if it
actually gets the identifier here then
I'll just say like oh okay
actually retire it and off you go
now there's some pretty easy ways that
you cannot do this work twice and we
should feel pretty stupid for not doing
them but we are just going to not do
them you know I can it's just it's dumb
to waste the time on that so anyway here
in peak token we've got
sort of what's the problem
did I not oh you know what I only put
Pete token raw in there some reason
there we go
don't ask me what I was doing with that
because we won both of those we wanted
Pete token and Pete token raw I only put
Pete token in and I never put Pete token
and I called it P token wrong I don't
know yeah
out to lunch I guess anyway so I think
that's all good let's go ahead and jump
down here so that we have to implement
require token let's see this should be
tokenizer that was just a autocomplete
bug there and then optional token or is
undefined so we're pretty much good to
go we just have to add that or we don't
have that operator and so we just have
to add that in again it's super simple
it's just a one line in our switch
statement here so it's really easy for
us to add operators if we want them
right it's trivial so I think that's
everything
and let's see last but not least this
here is supposed to be required to
anumber s3 too so that'll get us that
number out as well this also is
something we can lemongrab we want that
to be a P percent
and the size this token identifier is
like we're gonna have up to two
potential things that combine for the
type so this is like type zero and I
think that's everything
that should parse the entire line point
thing out and now we know what it is
right and so really all we have to do
now is say well okay so as we're part as
we're doing our import on this thing and
you know we're reading in the file we
just have to kind aside like what are we
going to do with the information that
we've received so there's two things
that we can do with the information that
we get when we process an art asset one
is we can go update the art the version
of the art asset that we have and update
it with the information that we now have
in it right the other thing that we can
do is we can take the information that
we have and write it back out to the
text stream now in these cases we sort
of have probably differing ways in which
we're going to do this we can make this
more flexible if we want to but the most
like rigid and you know single path
version of this is any time we do it
since we know that a line points are
things that come from the HHA and get
edited in the HHA you know the align
points would get updated from there
probably I don't know the other way we
could do it is look at which one was
modified later
so I suppose that's also one way to do
it and I'm not sure again which one of
those two we want to do it's pretty
tough to say because again in both cases
we're not sure so I what I would
recommend that we do here is we actually
have in our context something that says
which of this is going to be right so
when we actually do an update we can
basically say look are we trying to
write out a new hht so we should be like
copying forward the information that
we've edited or is what we're actually
trying to do just do the import so the
hht should actually like overwrite
what's going on in the hij right and so
what I want to do there is just say okay
which one of these two things are we
doing so you know is this a is this a
hht rewrite or not and so we'll just say
you know if true we are writing a new
hht from the existing one not importing
its values right um and you can imagine
getting arbitrarily complicated with
this sort of stuff but you know it's in
order to keep things simple I'm just
gonna say we'll just have two buttons on
the UI
there's import in which case it's just
reading everything in and then there's
like save and that's gonna write stuff
out and we're not gonna we're not going
to conflate those two right we're gonna
do those two things as sort of we're
gonna do those two things in ways that
the user is manually saying which one
they're doing we're not gonna try and
guess based on looking at what the like
file modification times are something
who's trying to overwrite who because
that seems dicey to me and I don't think
I want to go down that route I think
it's gonna be too hard to always do it
the right way and I'd rather just have
it be exact
um so in each of these fields right when
we're doing these parses what you can
see happening here is right we grab the
author in the description the name the
HHA the tags the align and so on and
what I'd like to do is after each one of
those I'd like to see which one of these
two things we're doing
um in the case for the rewrite if we
actually do want to rewrite it and so on
here's a required semi oh oh that's
after the Wilder okay so I misspoke
there these things actually do suck up
the semicolon themselves so that was
that was less good I guess I was wrong
you don't actually need to do a peak
token here we actually wrote this to
work this way I guess that's fine I
guess there's no reason not to do that
the less peak tokens I guess the simpler
things are so I suppose that's fine
and if we want to do that we can just
say well you know this here is just a
this is just a get token and we can see
if this if you want to get something
call you can see why that's kind of ugly
right it's it's just not great and
everyone's doing requests on so you know
we made the peak token we might as well
use it and make the code simpler that's
just it just seems better to me right so
you know let's leave that as a peak
token we won't actually suck up the
semicolon will leave the semicolon in
place and then we'll just delete all
these and make our lives easier right
forget it
right and that way nobody has to look
for that it's you only parse the parts
that are actually relevant to you and
then you can let the semicolon be
handled by the end of the clause and
everyone's happy right alright so if in
here we do you know one of these line of
port parses or any of these things where
we like you know get the author parse or
whatever so when we do these what we
kind of want to do is we want to say
whether or not this thing is getting
copied the output or not in some kind of
clean way probably right so when we read
an author a description or a name field
those are just not things that we edit
in the game so I feel like
all of these can just sort of have a by
default pass-through level where we just
say like at any time that is just
something that's going to get passed
through so when we do like the require
token at the end then we'll just do the
copy all input right but but when you
have something like this alignment point
that's the part where we may want to
override it so in one of these things
what we'll say is look which one of
these are we actually doing let's
remember where things started and we'll
do a sort of a back up to there as
necessary right where we can say we
don't actually want you to copy this
alignment thing in we want to cut to
ignore it and you know you know skip
basically the stuff that was coming so
we'll do an if here and we'll basically
you know well I guess we'll just do all
this and then we'll do the if right so
we suck up all of that input and then
we'll say if the context says we're
doing an hht rewrite then what we
actually want to do is we want to write
back to the output our own version of
what this thing should actually look
like so rather than using what we got as
the input here we're instead going to
discard it and then in the other case
where we do actually want to use it
that's where we're going to stuff it
back into the alignment point for the
assets in question all right now this is
gonna get a little more complicated and
I'm not sure how we actually want to do
it because if you actually look at what
goes on in here these alignment points
can be more specific
so inside like handmade or well base
came by a ship to you for example this
would work just fine for something like
a block where we aren't really talking
about Lion points for more than just the
whole thing in fact blocks don't only
have
alignment points so it's not really
relevant but let's take something simple
like this plate in the intro cutscene if
we wanted to set an alignment for this
plate it's pretty easy because we can
just use exactly the line we've
specified because in that particular
case where we've got something like this
you know if we want to specify an
alignment point we can just say well
there's the alignment point and we're
done
and we don't really have to look at it
any more closely but the problem that
we're gonna have is alignment points
actually are much more complicated than
that because a single import directive
can actually import a lot more than one
alignment point set right the reason for
that is if you look at what happens in
like the bass game for example one of
these things like you know the body hero
for example that's got in addition to
possibly wanting multiple of these which
we supported with this array statement
there's actually also the grid right so
not only do you have to specify which
one of the which one of the alignment
points you're talking about you also
have to specify which grid location
right so it's really more expanded than
even that
so inside our bracket syntax I think
we're gonna need something harder quark
here which really is this right so
there's grid X grid Y and then the index
of the alignment point and that's really
the more fully expanded version of this
thing that we need to support and like I
said it's a little complicated
if you were entering these by hand the
whole reason we have an editor in the
game is so that we don't edit them by
hand so I don't know that we care that
it's you know fairly Squinkie because
we're never got to touch it so as long
as it's legible and we can let go
inspect it me like okay I see what that
means we don't really have to care what
the other right all right so if we come
back here to the alignment side of
things we grab all this information and
then what we're gonna do here is say
well inside here we're gonna talk about
that a little bit more cynically I'm
going to say in here that we've got
token type 1 and I'm gonna go ahead and
have that fall through properly so that
way we do the full parse and then we can
look at the rewrite here if we're going
to do the rewrite then this is where we
actually output all of our stuff and
what we can also probably say is we
probably don't actually need to do it
here we could just instead do it a
little further out so you know we'd
actually be doing it more like out here
here and I'm saying that sort of thing
so like when we get to the end of this
thing in fact you know we could even do
it where do we get the final semicolon
or the close breaks right so in here we
could say look if we're gonna rewrite it
now is the time is to you know output
the alignment points and do it that way
otherwise you know let's just preserve
everything that was written in here as
it was written in here and there's other
ways we could do that if we want to but
I think that's the way that we would
want do it so in here we would do it or
if we're gonna rewrite it we do it there
if we're not gonna rewrite it here's
where we would set it right and that's
how we do it now we can be fancier Jimmy
if we want to reproduce the input
exactly in all cases we could be fancier
what we could do is rewrite only the
ones that we saw when we saw them and
then remember which ones we rewrote and
go through and see if there are any ones
that are specified that we didn't
rewrite and we would do that by keeping
a flags array right well you do that by
keeping a thing that said look let's
let's set each of these things based on
whether or not we've seen it we will you
know process the output either at the
time we saw it so that we keep the order
the same or we
we won't now again at some point you get
into a case of diminishing returns there
do you care do you not about reproducing
the input exactly and you get into a
point where if you did care about
reproducing input exactly you may want
to start doing more of an AST style
approach where you actually produce the
parse for the thing and just modify it
in place so that you don't have to be
having so much tracking of what you did
and didn't see so you know it's hard to
say how you want to go about doing that
there's a lot of different ways you
could do it and which one is the most
efficient to implement largely depends
on exactly what you want as it always
does everything's a trade-off everything
costs more code or takes less code or is
better or is worse and also so if we
don't want to do a rewrite though then
what we do want to do is set the
alignment point for this particular grid
index and so what we're going to be
doing there right is we're going to be
doing the the zooming setting that
alignment up onto whatever the actual
import is that we do so in here where we
do the parse top of a block right you
know we've we're sort of processing this
and then we're looking at this you know
parse pieces sort of thing that happens
and what you can see here is this is a
little bit too late to the party right
we actually want to know what we're
reading from a lot earlier than this so
what we'd like to do is be able to
access at least this part of the
information like way earlier than that
right like we want it we want to
actually start this process potentially
a lot earlier than that if that makes
sense because what we want to have at
this point is we want to have this asset
source file the reason we want to have
that asset source file is if you look at
what we're actually storing for the
asset source file in here it is the
thing that actually gives us that
translation table right so the thing in
here
are you sir the asset index array this
right here this thing here is the thing
that actually tells us where we would go
to get those alignment points right
because here's the asset indices and the
asset is the thing that has the
alignment points stored in it so if we
don't have this piece of information yet
we wouldn't actually know whether there
are any of these things to set or not
right we would have no idea where to put
that particular piece of information one
way or the other and so what that boils
down to is we sort of want to do the
parse and get the data set up first and
then we want to call this actual
function which again means we sort of
want to reverse the order in which we're
doing these things now it requires us
having process the tag arrays to do that
and the alignment points here as you can
see is now something that it kind of
creates an order dependency here that
that you know we have to figure out a
way that we want to resolve because we
would like to ideally parse these things
first and then when we when we load this
stuff they'll just get stamped on as we
process those in place but again maybe
we don't really want to do that at that
time maybe we want to do that in a
slightly different way such as for
example having the process multi tile
import side of things do the tag welding
or who knows what else right there's
ways we could imagine doing this so that
we actually call this stuff first and
then at the end afterwards do this sort
of stamping kind of onto the onto the
assets in arrears right and yeah so
again it's really kind of hard to think
about exactly how these things
want to be ordered and how they want to
be processed in that sense but what I
can say is that if we just want to
cheese out for now it's actually pretty
easy for us to do so and the reason for
that is we can just parse this and
remember it right that's really easy for
us to do because you know if we want to
there's no reason that in here we can't
just store up these alignment points
ahead of time
right again really really simple for us
to do cost us almost nothing and so when
we're in here what we can do is say look
make a temporary structure we know that
we've got this many things to remember
so what we can say is like align points
and we know inside the final format that
there's only a certain number of those
that you can have and so we can store
all the ones we read pretty easily right
we initialize it to nothing so we know
that there's none of them got the outset
and then when we read them in we just
store them into this array right at the
location implied by the by the indices
here so when we get all of this
information we can then say well you
know just go to and I don't know how
these are indexed at the moment whether
we do grid X or grid Y but I can look
here so it's Y X right so grid X grid Y
and then whichever one it is here that's
going to be our line point so we can
just say like HS a a line point point
equals that one and then the point
itself can be set in specifically these
ways so I can say look I want to fill
out all of the parts of that so here's
the p % 0 oops
here's the p % 1 here's the size and
here's the type and we can fill all of
those fields out now we want to put some
error checking in here because anyone
they can put anything they want in here
so we want to first before we set one of
these alignment points what we'd like to
do is check everything for errors and
issue ears where they occur now if you
imagined this doing this piece
you can imagine we need to do if this
thing is in range then you then do the
thing otherwise air out if it's in range
air out and we want to have all this air
through cynic that says a lot of typing
we don't really want to do that so we'd
much rather do something like look only
put this in if we know all of our values
are correct so if we know all these
things fell within the tolerances that
we expect them to then actually proceed
otherwise bail and then what we want to
do is in here sort of upgrade this
concept so instead of required token and
just having anything come back here we
want to have require number and we want
to actually have a range right so we
want to do here is say look we want to
require and furthermore we wanna cry an
integer range right so what we're gonna
do is say I want you to give me a number
back and I want you to give me back that
number because they'll return the token
I suppose I want that number four grid X
to be from here to here right like I
want it to fall between these two right
and so this is going to be again
coincident with this so each one of
these instead of doing a car token is
always going to be required integer
range and in here we'll just say all
right that's what those two have to be
this one same thing require integer
range it's gonna be between zero and HHA
get map align point count so we've again
like now we can issue proper errors to
anyone who like put something wrong in
there and then finally like these for
size and P percent it's still exactly
the same thing it's just the energy
range is much larger this time but you
know it's still still again exactly the
same thing so each one of these where
you've got one of these requirements
here it's just going to be between zero
and the maximum for a u16 right so again
we can read each of those in and then we
can go from there
we of these ones we do how we do each of
these we kind of need to be a little bit
more specific about we
haven't quite handled type yet right but
now each of these can be done with just
this one simple function kind of makes
it sound like one of those around the
web things this one simple function will
get you all of yeah I won't go down that
route anyway so what I can do there is
to do that what I can do there is just
you know sort of duplicate my require
token idea here and just add a second
level to it right so I know that I'm
going to get an Esther D to you know
here where we get like one past Max and
min as a way of specifying our range
maybe that and so in here I can do the
same thing I was doing before where I
say all right let's get a token by
calling require token and I will say
that it has to be a number but then I'm
gonna do is going to check the range of
the number and so I'm going to say look
we'll issue an additional error if this
doesn't fall within the range that I
expected so first of all if it does
equal the number because it might not
right it could be that there was already
an error with require token and we don't
really need to issue a second error
right
so assuming it was actually a token
number then what I'm gonna do is check
to see if it's within range and if it is
good if it's not we will just issue the
ear and maybe even clamp the the value
that's coming out of it but I don't
think we'll do that so we'll just say
like look if it's a number then let's
check so we'll then say okay if token s
32 is greater than equal to the min
value in token s 32 is less than one
pass the max value and I could have done
where you actually pass the range in for
the name we won't have to minus one
because you almost always want to pass
other thing in there oh well know what
you know what no I'm wrong because
here's the thing we do actually want to
allow that max value in the u 16 max
case so maybe it's fine to just do this
right and so you pass in a range here
and then what that means is that each of
these just has to do like okay you know
the range is that range minus one
because I don't actually want you to
pass in the highest value because that
would be out of bounds okay so you know
this is valid and this is invalid that
allows us to print out a pretty handy
error message right we're basically
saying look we expect you to give us a
number being here in here you didn't so
go back to that place the source rod to
figure out why you were trying to
specify something out of the range of
the possible things that we allow you to
do here and then we're good to go so
like I said the only thing we don't have
now is that type I'm out of time so I
really shouldn't be doing any more so
will wind down pretty soon here but
there's a char token range so in here if
I just kind of jump to the other ears
don't ask me why we pass the token
they're possible loss of data for the
sr22 oh that's fine we know they're in
range so these are all castable so
that's all good
and I think I'll probably leave the rest
for next time there is a few things we
can do here we've wanted to maybe I'll
do them really quickly let's just look
so if you're looking here there's this
sort of a line point name from type and
a line point type from name and you can
see that that would do the translation
for us here and so if you use any of
these align point names which are in
here somewhere
okay so here none default top of head
and base of neck right if you actually
do those we can actually translate them
for you and so that's probably what we
would do there so in here we can do that
checking what I might do is say require
type 0 to be that thing so we might say
something like this type 0 text
haja line point type and we would say
this is the base type right and we'd say
if base type equals HHA align nun or i
should say it's not equal to that that
we know it was ok otherwise it's not ok
and similarly we need to do type 1 here
and see what that would do so in here
you know I can actually do it like this
I guess so in here oops
so in here we'd say like get that thing
you know get that get the get the type
there and see if it's valid if it's not
that we would error out and say yeah I
know that's not going to work right so
this type 0 here
unrecognized alignment point type and
then the only other thing we have to do
here is if we get this optional token we
may want to align you know I'm gonna
actually do it like this we're gonna or
in here you know the two parent so we
would in here say or into parent if it's
if it's appropriate and so we're gonna
want to grab that let me just let me
grab that out
here and so we want to Orion that to
parent in the case where this is valid
and if it's not valid we want to issue
an error again right so we want to do
something like this where if type 1 and
I guess do we have require identifier we
don't um so what I want to do here is
say look I requiring an Edifier and if
the token in this case equals this to
parent value which I think we should
just use to parent then we'll order this
in if it's not then it's an error
because we don't allow any other
modifiers to alignment points at the
moment and then we could so we could
just say like expected to parent and get
it right so I think that's really all we
need to do there
and I think then then we're done right
so we've got all of that and we build
the type properly and all that stuff is
saved and so that produces the complete
list which we can then do this
processing here and then we can you know
at tomorrow decide what we're going to
do at the end of all that now I don't
want to leave it in a non compelling
state so all I'm going to do is just
stub this out at the moment and leave
that as it to do so this is a not
implemented right here and we will pick
it up tomorrow
when we return from now oops we will go
to the Q and a and we'll address that
later on looks like we've got one more
air in here yeah well you know what we
could just make this a u16 up here right
in theory
okay so even though this is returning
something that has to be au 16 it
doesn't think I guess it's integral
promoting it up or what what's the
what's the deal there it's probably
because it's it it probably because it
assumes that enums are signed and so
it's looking and seeing that it's eight
zero zero zero is the maximum value
that's defined in the enum and that
means it can't store it in a 16-bit
signed value so then it goes in stores
it is 32 I don't know integral promotion
rules and see I never studied them so I
never know what they are they're always
bad it seems like I don't like them but
you know they are what they are
alright let's go ahead and go to the Q &amp;
A does anyone know by the way I can't
inside the twitch chat if I do like QA
it doesn't work why do I have to go over
to the handmade here oh the handmade
Network IRC to enter QA does anyone know
why that is like I have no idea why that
is
how would you print an enum tag as a
string in C well you I mean you can't
that's why we have these ridiculous
translation tables right C and C++ again
despite C++ having been developed for 30
years now still can't tell you what the
name of an enum is they were like I
don't know how you could possibly do
that that's like technology so far
beyond the C++ standard committee
they're like we got nothing we don't
know we don't know how we would give you
back the name of a strength of an enum
that's that's like I mean Elon Musk can
put a man on Mars maybe right that might
happen but getting the name of an enum
that I mean what do you expect from us
here right I mean we're only the C++
standards committee that's not the kind
of thing we're ever gonna be capable of
doing like we're still trying to learn
how to use the sippy cup and ride a
tricycle right so the answer is anytime
you actually want to print one of these
out you have to make your own table so
you're constantly copying and making
your own table so if you look at
something like how we do it right in
handmade hero we have to do it this way
were you going here and have a little
translation table that says what the
names are from the various things that
you've got and it's it's terrible right
now I showed on on a hand made here a
bonus stream we don't do this in
handmade hirabai showed how to do it you
can write your own language augmentation
where you write your own preprocessor
that goes through your code first and
turns ministry every industrial-strength
C programming house or C++ program house
has this so like you know I'm sure like
the people who write like the frostbite
engine or whatever they probably have a
pre pass it does something like that
right or the Unreal Engine probably has
a pre pass that does something like that
and that's basically because the
language is so decrepit you know it
can't do it
and is there a reason you don't write
bailout style functions to avoid too
much nesting of if-else blocks
yes so there is a reason I like to have
only one return point in my functions as
much as possible and the reason for that
is because it makes it a lot easier for
me to think about what is always
happening and at the start and ends of
routines so it gives me an easy way to
say oh you know what any time I go
through this routine like whether it
airs or not or whether this happens or
not I know it's gonna go down here and
do something right and each of my blocks
shows me a new level of certainty that
I've gotten to that I can also say
here's what would happen if I was
unwinding out of there right and so I
tend to just like things to be laid out
that way that's why I don't use there's
several things I don't use as a result I
don't use exception handling I don't use
go-to to jump out of blocks like that
and I don't use if return if return if
return style I don't have a problem with
any of those things well exception
handling is typically not very good for
reasons that don't really have much to
do with exception handling as a core
concept but so I might cost against that
but in general I would say I don't have
a problem with if return subprogram I
just don't care for it
would you be willing to use
metaprogramming tempest through that job
just because you absolutely have to I'd
be willing to use metaprogramming for it
with an with an actual pre pass that I
write myself I wouldn't be willing to
use templates for it
templates are so broken I just I just
don't I if I if I'm thinking to myself I
need templates I just write a medical
pilot prepass I'm always happier that
way because templates just they're just
awful Synthesia scan the difference
between the pointers have undefined
behavior I guess we use it for the count
variable so it depends differences
between pointers don't have undefined
behavior if they come from the same
allocation and ours do so meaning if you
allocate a block of memory where you
said I'm gonna have 10,000 carry stars
care characters in this stream then you
can difference that's actually
guaranteed by the spec if you allocate
to separate blocks of memory and then do
a difference I think actually
technically if it if they are byte
pointers which a care start is I think
that may still be required to work but
if they were anything else it wouldn't
have right so if it was like if they
were integer pointers then that would be
undefined
because the compiler is allowed to do
any kind of short cutting of the
difference there and while anything
that's a power of two would probably
still work anything that's not a power
of two might not work because the
compiler made you shortcut math tricks
assuming that they're both aligned to
the same value since there if they were
in the same allocation they would be
right
I'm probably not explained as well let
me say it a little bit more clearly so
let's suppose that we allocate a block
of memory and we have two pointers into
the block of memory if we ask the
compiler to generate a difference
between those two pointers then it may
want to take advantage of the fact that
the pointers because remember difference
we need pointers in C it's supposed to
give you the difference in the pointers
divided by the size they're pointing to
right so if the things they're pointing
to our 12 bytes long let's say it's a
struct with three integers in it right
then it can do you know B minus a
divided by three that's right different
divided by 12 right and give you back
that result the problem is integer
divided might be slow so it might want
to do it faster by recognizing the fact
that if both of these things are known
to be array indices off the base value
so if I know I need to allocated block
and I made an int pointer to the
beginning of the block and I have an int
pointer to the third integer and the
16th integer so they're both aligned to
four byte boundaries right I'm sorry we
were talking about 12 bytes structures
so each one is aligned to a 12 bite down
Dury because they're each you know
brackets blah they've advanced that far
from the front the compiler may choose
to output a sequence that generates a
synthetic divided by 12 that only works
if the values were all aligned to the
original 12 white values so if instead
you just have allocations randomly in
space and they're not both aligned to
the same 12 byte offset from the
beginning the compiler is allowed to
generate code that just doesn't work not
the way I would expect the language but
that's the way they spec the language
how do you feel about guidelines
encouraging coupling enums with guards
and label arrays static assertions on
min and Max of enum values and macros to
establish enums creating corresponding
label arrays um I don't think I know
what you mean by label arrays I don't
think I know what you mean by a label
arrays sorry I can't really comment on
that one it may be just a term I'm not
familiar with maybe look if I understand
right it's about only really echo stuff
from handmade Network IRC to twitch RC
however the map a goofy a Mahiro and
twitches i believe hard coded so they
okay map the other way alright
well that's too bad but there you go
regarding enum strings would you be
happy if you could write procedural
macros to solve this problem no I want
to just have it know what the number
it's it's obvious like it should you
should just be able to say what's the
string for one of these things like I
mean that's a choral introspection it's
like a core language feature it's not it
shouldn't be something that you have to
add to the language it's like the most
important language feature I mean I'm a
meta programming central kind of person
in my mind that's like day one it should
be able to do that like before it can
even add two numbers together to be able
to tell you what the name of an enum is
in medico like that's more important
than math as a student who's being
taught see this lesson College can
explain to me why you think it is a
terrible language yeah I mean I've
talked about it lots of times on stream
but basically C++ if you look at what I
would consider kind of the core metric
of a programming language which is
programming express ability versus
language complexity it's a horrible
language right it's absolutely massive
C++ is one of the largest languages in
existence I guess I don't want to say
it's the largest language in existence
because I don't know if that's true but
it might be the largest language is
instance if if someone out there is a
language
a computer languages person could you
tell me is C++ the largest language
because it might be right if it's not
it's up there right you know if you'd
listed the top 10 largest specs so that
makes them hard to implement it makes it
harder to learn it makes it difficult to
really know all the rules because even
people who really think they know the
real see us often don't right it's huge
right um so it's up there somewhere you
know it's in the top five top ten
largest languages
it hardly is able to do anything it has
almost no features like we were just
saying it can't even tell you like
here's the thing it can't tell you what
are the members of this structure you're
talking about one of the largest
languages in existence it can't even
iterate over the members of a structure
like they have added every single random
thing that came into their heads to C++
and almost none of them are useful right
and so it's just I think it's an
incredible it's almost like an exercise
it's remarkable really if you think
about it C++ has gone 30 years adding
stuff all the time having huge amounts
of stuff and it's gained almost no
actual useful features like most of the
features are critically broken or worse
than the version that you would have
just written in C it's crazy I just
don't know how they ended up being so
bad at it so what you end up with is a
language that has some good beginnings
because C was a good language at the
time but that every high-level language
feature that you actually wanted got
added in a totally broken way or not
added in a halt which is even worse
right and so it's just a terrible
language it's impressively bad and it's
impressively bad from the standpoint of
it's not that it's new it's not that
it's young it's not that it hasn't had
plenty of examples of how it could be
made better or use cases out there
there's tons of code that was flowing
around and C to look at they just
absolutely missed it every single time
every single time off topic what is your
stance a compile-time cogeneration like
Indy do you mean like like the feet the
meta pregnancies in like ji I am 100%
for them
I don't program indeed though so I
couldn't tell you about label arrays
arrays the same size of the enum with
strings correspond to the label of each
enum item four contiguous enums or
couples of labels and offset for sparse
all your emails oh okay
so going back to the original question
then sorry i'm i will reread the
original question with that how do you
feel about guidelines encouraging
coupling enums with guards and label
arrays static assertions on min and Max
values and macros to establish enums
creating the corresponding label arrays
um I do them sometimes if I have lots
and lots of enums and I edit them a lot
I I will use a pound include with the
enums in the even INL file to generate
both if I don't have them at a program
available so I I do though I do do that
sometimes it's a little cumbersome but
it works
so all right I'm gonna wrap it up here
let's go ahead and get ready to stop
recording
all right let's thank you everyone for
joining me for those sent a handmade
hero sort of pleasure recording with you
as always if you would like to follow
along the series at home you can always
peer to the game on handmade hero 2 org
come to the source code so you're
welcome to play around with it do your
own experimentation and try out stuff
inside the code base which is a great
way to learn in addition to watching
series we'll be back here tomorrow when
we'll try to get that translation
process working and that'll start our
kind of debugging of the new sort of hht
based import/export process it's pretty
complicated stuff you know it's kind of
a more proper art pipeline now but you
know we did a good job keeping it pretty
contained I think and so hopefully we
should have something tomorrow by the
end of tomorrow that's you know somewhat
reasonable and then we can kind of look
at cleaning it up so PU back here for
that till then have fun for everyone and
I will see you on the Internet
take it easy everybody