start recording hello everyone and
welcome back to handmade hero the show
recode a complete game live on stream we
are coming back up
alpha a long and distinguished break
it's been a couple weeks here without a
handmade hero good to see everyone again
and it's good to be back programming
with you guys
now here is question we stopped in the
middle of doing our printf routine and I
believe we had pretty much suppressed
surprisingly but surprisingly quickly we
were able to reproduce like all of
printf formatting and everything else in
just a really short period of time which
is great but I think we may have gotten
ourselves down to the point where the
only thing we actually have left to do
at the moment is floating-point printout
so I think we have kind of gotten
ourselves into a bit of a a bit of a
bind because if we want to finish this
part section of the code and move on I
think we have no choice but to
essentially tackle the floating point
printout problem which is a pretty nasty
problem it's not great it is not great
so let's let's double check to make sure
that that's the case but I think it is
and so I think we're just gonna have to
deal with it now we're here on day 328
which of course if you are line follow
along with me day 327 source code is
that is the source code you're going to
want to start with I believe let's just
double let's let's double check to make
sure that that's correct since we've
been away for a while
I want to make sure we're we're on the
right day day 328 oh no that's not good
it says day 328 we need to be on day 329
right because already is the day 328 I
don't know why that got set wrong okay
all right so day 328 is the source code
then if you're so sweet starting with
here on day 329 and let's go ahead and
just jump into the code because it's
been a long time and we'll probably just
need to sort of reef Emilio's ourselves
a little bit with what's going on so
here we go back into handmade do our
little build everything's building okay
so that's great we can you know what I
wonder
so a fresh build is one point five seven
four seconds right
what's a warm build one point three oh
nine so not that much different between
a warm build and a and they and a cold
build they're about 0.2 seconds anyway
so let's take a look at what's going on
here I think like I said that we have
just everything kind of working except
for the floating point printout and you
know you can remember sort of what was
happening here here's our an example of
some code that should have had you know
some numbers in there right but they're
not getting printed out so I think
everything is currently getting printed
except for those percentages so you can
kind of see here for example we're
printing out integer numbers just fine
in these places but after these
percentages there should be information
there same with this millisecond count
same with that millisecond count up
there so right now I think we're at a
point where everything's moving along
okay but we do have to add
floating-point print if we want to
restore our previously existing
functionality but everything else is
fine right so I think that's all we got
that's what we've I think that's where
we are at okay so if we go back to our
code I think someone else is sent in a
bug I don't remember if they put it into
the if they put it into the github or
not I think someone also sent me in a
bug or posted bug on the forums that we
had done we there was a mistake in the
array count see I don't remember the
citizen shared yeah somewhere I
accidentally took the array account of a
pointer yeah you can see I did it here
right this was supposed to be a
of the buffer but instead I did a rate
count of the pointer it'd be nice if
that's the kind of thing we could get
warned about but of course you know it's
not quite meta programmable enough in C
to really do that but anyway that was a
little bit of a bug there so it meant
that we would never have as we would
only have eight characters worth of
space because it was taking the length
of a pointer like how big is the pointer
and a pointer is 8 bytes in 64 a bit so
it was saying that the maximum we could
fit was 8 characters but we really want
to be able to fit a lot more than that
in case the number was long so we wanted
to fit 64 so now this will correctly
give 64 instead of you know of what it
was before so that's I think is really
all there is to that I don't know is
this tempting even used anywhere is this
actually do we even need this yeah okay
so I guess we do so I can't get rid of
it to avoid said mistake but that's okay
all right so I think like I said that
we're in good shape for everything else
so the only real thing that we've got
that's a problem here is all of these
guys you know F eg and a they all read
their floating-point argument off of the
stack like we want but then they just
throw it away right so what we want to
do is we want to have something that's
similar to the way the thing was working
before in the other cases right so we've
got this used 64 to ASCII and then we're
sort of doing some you know nonsense
with it after but what we really want to
do here is we want to basically have a
an F 64 to ASCII write we want something
like this and I don't know why we've got
the basis here I guess that was because
so we could have hack something like
that so we don't really need that
because the basis is always known we'll
probably have to pass some other things
to this piece of code later but for
right now I'm gonna ignore most of the
formatting things here at the eff like
what the difference is between all of
these guys I'm gonna ignore that for now
and just stuff all these guys with the
thing we
says hey let's just get printout working
at all and and off we go now a I don't
remember what a is but I guess it must
be some other formatting thing all right
so we've got a 64 to ASCII right let's
go ahead and put this in here and that's
sort of the the basic piece of
information that we need and we know
we're going to print out a
floating-point number here oh and this
should take an actual float right so we
have a couple problems first of all we
need to know some more information than
just this because if I recall correctly
precision we have not really been using
yet because we haven't really had to but
we're going to want to pass a precision
value here because floating-point values
unlike integer values have this sort of
additional concept of a format that says
how many things after the decimal point
could we print out maximally right so in
addition to the normal stuff that's
going to happen with our number like the
width of it you know keeping the width
correct and all that sort of stuff which
is about the total printout size we also
have another piece of information which
is that after the decimal point we may
want to restrict how many there are so
for example a lot of cases will do
something like percent 0.02 or something
which says hey we want there to be two
things past the decimal point so you
know keep that in mind right or whatever
and so that's going to be important
because it does affect how much stuff we
print out when we're doing the f60 for
it to ASCII now actually I don't know
that it's that hard to print out when
you know what the precision actually is
I mean there's probably some cases that
we would care about that we wouldn't
handle quite properly and maybe the
accuracy you know there might be some
accuracy problems there are other things
like that
but I think in general the real
trickiness is figuring out what the
minimum number of digits we would have
to print out would be to represent the
value correctly and let me just say
really quickly why that is so you have
some idea of it I'm not a floating-point
guru
so you know take it with a grain of salt
but I'm just gonna try to give you a
little bit of why this is kind of a
nasty problem all right so day three 29
float printing and baby will say like
not very good float printing so curious
fundamentally the problem right when we
were talking before about decimal
numbers what we have is remember we have
a binary representation of a number for
our decimals right so maybe our binary
representation is like something like
this right one zero zero one one and
then we have a decimal representation of
that number that's what we want to print
out because we don't want to print it
out in binary or at least we usually
don't want to print out my nuri we want
to print it out in decimal because
decimal is what humans are used to
reading sometimes we want hex with
decimal other things like that but
usually the point is the base is not
base to its base something else like
base ten right so this is base two this
is base 10 well we want to print out a
binary number in base 10 we then have to
sort of think about how we converted it
and we were using dividing by ten as a
way to do that right so what's this you
know binary number in decimal well I've
got a 1 plus a 2 we don't add a 4 we
don't add in an 8 we do add a 16 right
so we add these together and we get 19
right and so that's like what we want to
print out there right 1 plus 2 plus 16
and so this print out process this is
relatively easy for us to do because all
we actually had to do is go alright why
don't we just divide this thing by 10
periodically using an integer divide
find the remainders and print out the
the remainders right and you remember
how we did that here we you know we kind
of came through this is are you 64 to
ASCII routine we would just say all
right whatever the current remainder is
base 10 that is
we're going to print and of course those
got printed out in reverse order because
you know if you took we had this 19 here
we divided by we look at the remainder
when you divide by 10 we're getting at
the 9 first and then we kind of actually
do that divided and then we look at the
next digit which is a 1 so as we went
through the number we were going in this
direction right because we were dividing
by 10 sequentially as we went okay so
the problem that happens in float and
let me let me just go ahead and label
this side integer here the problem that
happens in float is we have a very
different circumstance going on right in
floating point what we actually have is
we have some concept of where a decimal
point is relative to the number but that
decimal point doesn't have to be at the
end so right here we always knew that
the decimal point was going to be after
this thing so we could just divide by 10
and just pick it off as we go right and
we knew that we were not really
suffering any accuracy loss there right
we weren't there was no real concern
that we would get like incorrect answers
by doing the divide by 10 it's just you
know it's it's a perfectly safe thing
for us to do looking at the remainder
mod 10 now in floating point we have a
different circumstance in floating point
you know we may still have a thing that
looks like this but we may be told that
the decimal point is effectively here on
it
right because remember how floating
point numbers are encoded they have a
thing like this it kind of looks like
this we've got a sign bit right so we've
got a bit that says whether it's
positive or negative we've got an
exponent right and the exponent says
what 2 to the what power this number is
going to be and then here we've got a
mantissa which is the actual thing that
will be multiplied by that exponent
right that will be essentially shifted
right by that exponent so it's entirely
possible for this exponent to be
negative right so it can be a fractional
value right it's entirely possible that
this exponent won't be negative but
won't be enough to make the mantissa be
entirely on one side of the decimal on
this other decimal point so we can often
have a case where the number that's
encoded right if this is if this is
encoded in here if this exponent isn't
enough to push the decimal place all the
way to the side then we're in a
decidedly different scenario in terms of
what the number means and the reason for
that is because although the part on
this side of the decimal point
could still be printed out in exactly
the same way the number on this side of
the decimal point works kind of in a
much more squirrelly fashion right this
you know is 1 over 2 this is 1 over 4
right this is going to be 1 over 8 right
so as these things go they some smaller
and smaller values kind of going out you
know as they go right so what we kind of
need to know there is how many decimal
places would we need to print out in
order to actually capture this value
whatever it is write in decimal is
something that's a little bit tricky so
if you think about what's going to
happen here first we could we could try
to break this problem down right we
could try to say well it's pretty easy
for us to remove the part of this number
that is fractional temporarily so it's
probably free if I want to just
architect again not trying to do a
particularly good job here I'm just
trying to walk through the problem so
you can kind of see me like try to fuss
with it and maybe get a better idea
about why it's kind of tricky but I can
remove this part of the problem if I
wanted to right I could probably find a
pretty simple way of just taking in a
fractional part of this number and in
fact there's actually library routine
already to do it but we would probably
want to write it ourselves but I believe
there's a like a fracked is there fact
these days in in C or is there not let's
take a look
yeah here you go so if we want to
fracked I think is the one from the
shader of languages that's that's what
I'm thinking of there but so if you want
to for example write we can make a we
can make call to see you runtime IRA we
could also imagine ways of us doing this
ourselves right where we can split a
number into its fractional and and non
fractional parts its whole number parts
so if we want to we could call mod F for
example and mod F would would do that
split for us and then we would be able
to print out the integer part separately
and know that we were left only with the
part that we actually wanted and you can
also see how we would probably do that
in terms of in terms of doing this
directly ourselves since we know the
what a floating-point number looks like
we can certainly do work with the
exponent ourselves right so we could
certainly say well whatever the exponent
value is if that exponent value is not
is if that exponent value is you know
zero or negative then we know that all
the bits are fractional right if that
number is greater than the number of
bits in the mantissa right if it's going
to push it further out then the mantissa
then we know that the entire thing is
going to be the non fractional part and
we just have to shift it up by however
many places we would need to based on
the exponent right and so the only thing
we really have to handle is the case
where it's right in the middle right
where it's something right in the middle
even so it'd be pretty trivial for us to
do this just didn't see by actually
casting it to an integer right like
removing the floating-point part of it
cassadee sure and doing like a
subtraction to remove the integer part
and then we're left with just the
fractional part which we can then
subtract from the whole thing to give us
just the integer part also in a float so
you can even see like ways we could do
that pretty trivially so if we wanted to
we could probably remove that part we
could probably make things simpler by
getting rid of this thing but we would
still be left with something like this
right where we have to figure out a way
to print this out now if you look at
what happens here
you know we've got 1/2 1/4 1/8 if we
want to send these together it's kind of
a pain in the butt still but you know we
can do it right we would want to
multiply this guy by 4 over 4 right so
we would have 4 eighths we would want to
multiply this guy by 2 over 4 right
I believe so we'd kind of go right and
then we would want to multiply I'm sorry
2 over 8 and then we would not multiply
this guy by anything so basically just
making a common denominator for this
guy's we would add them up and we get
exactly what you expect right 7/8 so you
can kind of almost see how that process
works it's it's sort of just the exact
same process that we were going through
up here you know each each bit is
contributing a number to the top and
then the divisor is just whatever the
furthest out bit was right it's pretty
straight forward anyway so I if you take
a look at what happens here we ended up
with something like 7/8 so the number
that we would want to print out here are
7/8 good to do looks like that right so
we want to print out 0.875 but the
question is how do we get there from the
floating point representation right
well we could in theory again if we're
trying to do and not very good one so we
don't care about all of the destruction
that will happen to our number and you
know for handmade here oh it's probably
fine right because this isn't a project
about printing out floating-point
numbers accurately and like I said
that's really difficult but for our
purposes what we could do is say well
alright if we know how to print out
things when we have them in the whole
number what we could do is just multiply
this number by 10 right that would shift
the fractional part over 1 and now we
could look at the integer part and print
out that integer part and then after
we're done with that we can print out by
10 again and look at the next it right
because we know how to pronounce that
for a city it's just mod 10 it's just
the number
ten right so if we just keep shifting
digits periodically over until we don't
feel like there's any digits left that
would be one way to do it now the
question of when there's no digits left
is kind of a little bit of an open-ended
thing still but you can see how that
would work right so let's start by just
trying to approach the problem in that
way right let's start by removing the
fractional part of the I'm sorry
biron taking the integer part and
printing that out the way we already
know how to do it and then printing out
the fractional part by just shifting it
up by multiple do multiplies by ten just
shift it up into the integer part so
that we can just print those out
sequentially as well right that seems
like a relative shape word before we do
it now again not the best way to do it
probably because as we're doing those
multiplies we are losing floating-point
precision percentual e there and we may
destroy bits that we actually need this
is why printing out floating-point
numbers is tricky but if we just want
something that basically prints out
floats without a lot of fuss then it's
probably not a huge deal right okay so
let's let's see what we can do now first
of all it looks like we're not handling
negatives here as far as I could tell so
I assume we're handling negatives kind
of more at the front end now I don't
know where that's actually getting
handled so I'm a little confused about
that let's take a look so that's
actually here that's getting handled
here where we do the prefix negative
positive or this now I don't really know
where we want to handle that but I think
I'm gonna put it up in here for now so
what I'm gonna do first is I'm just
gonna say alright if the value is less
than zero I'm gonna want to out care a
negative and we'll sort of work on the
formatting parts of that later if we
want to write out put a negative in that
case and then I'm gonna take the value
and I'm gonna make it positive so now we
know we don't have to deal with negative
numbers anymore cuz we printed out the
negative if there was one and then we
flipped the sign to clear the sign bit
so now we don't think about the sign bit
anymore right
okay so now we do have a slight problem
which is that we know this number is
going to be reversed so really I suppose
if this whole string is going to get
reversed we need to sort of do a thing
like we did before where we remember
whether the thing was negative or not so
is it negative is it not negative and
only at the end would we do the actual
print out so we'd still want to do the
negation but we don't want to print out
the minus to the end because remember we
put this out and then they get reversed
I believe let me double check maybe they
don't always get reversed here I think
we had the ability to do either but I
think we want to keep that ability yeah
I think we do want to keep that we want
to keep that ability for this because
we're going to print out the integers in
the wrong order so I think we want that
right although the ones after the
decimal place will be printed in that
order right because as we multiply by
ten we're printing them individually so
this is kind of a bummer right because
it means we we have some that come in
the reverse order and some that come in
the forward order which is a real pain
right that's not fun at all but I guess
we'll do we'll do what we can so if
that's the case let me take a look here
at how we were doing that because I
think we do like when we do strings we
had to do reverse equals together we get
reverse equals false so what we could do
is we could say for these guys we don't
want reversal because since you know in
fact how many people have reverse equals
false I guess
I guess all of these guys do so that's
fine at this point it's probably easier
to just put reverse folding the cases
that we actually care about so since in
this case we're gonna have to do the
reversal ourselves that also kind of
suggests that maybe the you 64 to a ski
should be the thing that does the
reversal I'm gonna put to do here to do
put reversal here instead seems like it
makes more sense to just go through and
flip them anyway f/64 to a ski here we
go in this case I can revert to doing it
sort of the cleaner way if we know that
we don't have to worry about the
reversal case if it's negative then I
can just print out the negative first
and put the value in there as a positive
so then what we want to do is we
basically want to just do a you 64 to a
ski right and it's gonna be backwards
for now but we'll deal with that in a
second so if we do au 64 to a ski we're
gonna want to do the same stuff here
we're gonna want to pass the desk we're
gonna want to paste the value we're
gonna want to print the base is we know
is 10 and the digits I don't know where
our digits are I assume they're in here
somewhere but I don't really know where
my digits at where my digit well they're
gonna look like that right there they
are
so I guess I should kind of come out
here and just say okay yeah here's our
cares
we want our duck Karras here cares and
that should be it so we'll put that in
base ten that will advance us to the
point where that well I guess I should
say we first have to actually produce
that number so I'm gonna say let's get
the the value integer part and in order
to do that I think all I really have to
do is say well give me whatever the
value would be in an integer right
because that's gonna truncate the value
which is exactly what I want it's just
gonna give me the integer portion so I
think that's enough
and then in theory I should be able to
say well now let's subtract away let's
get rid of that part of it right so I
should be able to subtract the integer
part back off
so here I am getting whatever the
integer part was without the fractional
part then I'm stalking it off so now the
value is just the fractional part and I
can print out the integer part so that's
fine so now I've got this fractional
part I need to output the decimal point
at this point and then I need to start
printing out characters in terms of the
divide now what am I do first is I'm
just gonna pass the precision because
maybe we'll just only support passed
precision I don't know but what that
means is I'm just gonna say okay I'm
just gonna say for however much
precision we have we're going to print
out things after the decimal place and
this is again pretty straightforward for
us to do there's not a lot of mystery
here all we have to do is keep
multiplying the number by 10 so
basically we just take the number we
multiply it by 10 to move whatever would
be 1 after the decimal point to 1 before
the decimal point then we can just print
that number out right we can just say
all right give me the integer part in
this case it's just you know a number
from 0 to 10 so just get that one
integer part take the value and subtract
away the integer part so it clears that
out right and then we just want to print
out whatever that integer says in the
integer table you know so then we just
need to actually pass the precision here
which I believe we should already have
right so here's the precision right here
and we'll have to do something about
when the precision isn't specified but
maybe what I'll do for that is I will
just set it to a default precision like
6 and we'll call it a day right okay
so let's come through here and actually
pass our precision precision precision
precision precision precision precision
and precision okay
so need that anymore what we should be
able to do now is take a look at this
now our numbers are going to be
backwards because remember we did not
flip them right so to start with we're
gonna be a little bit janky although
this looks especially janky I don't know
exactly why so yeah not great not off to
a good start but that's okay you know we
can't always be off to a good start and
this actually looks not totally wrong
you can see that the numbers are flipped
but otherwise it's not you know the
worst possible thing that happened
however our precision looks looks messed
up I think that's just because again
we're not actually specifying it
properly or maybe we are I think for
some of those numbers we should have
been specifying it so it seems like our
precision should have been set to
something valid but on the other hand
doesn't really seem like perhaps that it
was so I'm not sure what's going on
there we'll have to take a look I'm
gonna put this though
oh I gotta upgrade my for coder Allen
already fixed that bug I think you did I
don't remember that happening at work
right now were two doesn't allow now
specified Precision's so we just set
non-specified decisions to raise
specified value so in this case we'll
just do well precision is going to equal
eight or something let's say or maybe
six
if precision specified is false then
we'll set it so then we know our
precision is always something okay
so let's take a look at the reverse
thing that's been going on here and
maybe we can just get rid of that
entirely cuz here's what's happening
with reverse right and I don't really
like it I think what we could do is just
say let's just always print out the
number as it is without the reversal and
then what we'll do is we'll just
actually bake the reversal into
everything that needed the reversal in
the first place right so like these
things for example none of these things
needed reversal at all right oops so
that's not reversing not reversing not
reverse saying that reversing and then
when we get up to the things that are
reversing you know you can see the you
64 to ASCII is is in every single one of
them right here's all the people who
were reversing they're all you 64 to
ASCII right you 6040 ASCII you 64 to
ASCII you 64 to ASCII so it seems to me
like the smartest thing to do there
rather than being fancy like we were
before you should just do the reversal
here so we know at this point we can
track the range so let's just bake the
reversal into this routine and save
ourselves some trouble here we can
let's see there is no shared CPP oh no
for coder where have you gone
yeah I got up I clearly effed up to it I
must be using it what version of forked
or am i meeting using I haven't had a
crash in ages for a coder tell me your
version 4.0 point 10 I don't know what
I'm on but I don't think it's that I
don't know what for coder I'm on not to
look I will but just not right now
because I'm in the middle of something
here okay so let's get back to where I
was shared all right so let's take a
look at what I was doing there reverse
equals false so let's go back to what I
was about to do I think all the rest of
this stuff is right so I'm just gonna
bake the the reversal stuff into here so
I'm gonna take reverse and I guess I
forgot to do this on the last pasture
I'm gonna remove that entirely and I
guess I can just use that to ensure that
I've gotten rid of all of them
okay so I think that is all we need to
do for that and then in here when I'm
going to do my you 64 to a ski all I
need to do is remember where I was
can't remember what the desk thing is
here what is that structure there's a
structure that we're using format dest
for coder tell me where that is okay
there we go all right so all I should
have to do if I want to just reverse
this thing is say well I've got this
format desk construct right and I know
where it would start so I could say like
the start of this thing is here right
then when I get to the end I know the
end of the thing is wherever it stopped
so if I want to reverse that if I want
to reverse the order of the things that
I printed out there remember this is one
past the end yeah but I know how many
there were total right I know that the
care count is just gonna be n - start
right that's how many there are
so once I know how many of them there
are it's pretty easy for me to just walk
through half and switch them with the
other half right all I have to do is say
well swap index you know equals zero
swap index is less than care count / -
because I just have to go through half
the buffer and swap it with the other
half right and then I can just say all
right I need you I need to take you know
whatever the end is and I guess I need
to pre I need to sort of pre step the
end back one so I kinda have to do like
you know please step the end back one so
that's in a legal slot I have to say
whatever you know the the in fact you
know what I don't even really need the
care count do I
I don't even really need the care count
now think about it all I have to do is
say while start is not equal to end or
rather yet
well the start is less than the end
right I don't need the care count at all
because I have the end and I have the
start all I have to do is just move the
end back into a valid position right
read it set it to whatever the start is
and then set the start to whatever the
end was and then move the start forward
that should just right it should be two
pointers that just kind of move swapping
the values that they had I think that
would just work to be completely honest
yeah so I think let's double check that
I'm right about that
but I think that's really all we would
need to do I'm going to just I kind of
want to take a look at the oh and hey
probably I should put it in the right
routine it's just just thinking maybe we
should put it in the right routine just
seems like a good idea instead of
putting it in the wrong routine where
it's not gonna do what we wanted to do
because not even working on the right
code maybe we'll put it in the right
routine so yeah that goes alright so
there we still have to start at the end
in the middle of our loop that prints
out values then we've kind of described
this relatively simple situation here
that we can use okay so let's take a
look at what that does just to make sure
that I wrote it even remotely correctly
because you know it's been a long day
could make some mistakes make some
mistakes up in there
all right so let's see what we've got
first time through the loop or first
time through the code so we've got start
and ends not particularly interesting
word we're literally just printing out
the values 0 here apparently but that's
good we can test the case of only
printing out a single digit which we
want to make sure we get correct
certainly so here we go we look to see
if the start and the end are different
of course they are because end is
pointing to one past where the start is
pointing so we back it up and now
they're both pointing the same value we
read out
into temp we assigns End and starts for
basically overwrite itself and then we
assign start to every red we then move
the start pointer forwards now the start
pointer is pointing past the end pointer
so we exit the loop we have
quote-unquote reversed it and and off we
go let's hope that we get something a
little bit more complicated here
we didn't unfortunately so oh well
come on man give me something all right
fine I'm a cheat because I can I want to
see this printout something longer I'm
gonna say that the value I'm just gonna
use the debugger to set the actual value
and memory of value to be something else
so let's say that it's going to be one
two three four five six seven eight nine
right so now when I run this hopefully
if that debugger actually set that value
properly hopefully when we get the
string we'll get that backwards right
nine eight seven six five four three two
one
which is what we wanted to see so that's
good so now let's see if it reverses it
properly I'm gonna snap a pointer to
that right I'm just gonna say here's the
beginning of the string so as these
things move we can actually watch it
work
I'm gonna set that as a character and so
here we can see the string that we
started with and now I'm just gonna go
ahead and let it do its thing so I can
verify that it's actually doing the swap
incorrectly and hey there you can see in
the painfully slowly updating watch
window of visual studio that they're
actually swapping those values which is
what we want to have happen right so now
it's 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 and that's what
we want so I think that's a reasonable
way to bake that in there that seems
fine so now we can go back to our other
problem which is figuring out why the
precision part of our thing was not
working properly like with the dots and
so on right ok so let's move on from
there now we've got our numbers
reversing properly it looks like they're
printing out the correct numbers we're
just not printing out anything past the
decimal point on these particular cases
here it looks like we're maybe doing
things a little bit more correctly that
looks like a more plausible printout so
it looks like when we're specifying our
Precision's like these are ones with
prespecified Precision's we're only
getting two things printed out I have an
inkling of why that might be if I don't
know for sure but anyway it looks like
we're you know we're within striking
distance this is not a good printout I
would like to stress that again because
like I said we're just doing the really
the stupidest possible thing here to
print out these floating-point numbers
but at least we're printing out
something that's resembling the correct
value to some extent right okay so let's
figure out what's going on with our
precision there and try to make that
work a little bit better also how much
time do we have here at 858 okay so
we've got about 15 minutes left before
the QA I guess that won't tell me but I
I think we've got until they started at
8:15 so we got till 9:15 all right so
there's our s 64 to ASCII we've got this
precision index and we want to be less
than precision as we print things out so
it and this does appear to be working
nominally again I don't think it's
pickly accurate but and I could put it
to do here to note that this is not an
accurate way to do this so what we have
at this point is a problem with whatever
is happening printout wise here so the
first thing I want to do is I want to
look at the debug code to see what I'm
actually passing as a precision
specifier there I assume that I'm
passing like yeah so I'm passing Oh 2.0
to F right that's what I'm actually
passing and so my question is just how
is the point O two point O two gettin
interpreted and it's it would it would
seem to me and I guess I don't know but
it would seem to me that the width
specifier of
point o2 in the floating-point case is
actually doesn't work the same way it
works in the decimal case like it's not
the total width that this thing should
be it's just the width of the thing
before the decimal point right so I want
to go take a quick peek at the printf
formatting specifiers documentation so
that I know what even it's supposed to
be in that case because I guess I don't
really know what the spec oh dear oh
dear
Chrome hello chrome Chrome you can do it
all right
maybe you can't do it chrome what is the
problem all right there we go
so here are my width and precision
specifiers and yeah minimum number of
characters to be printed is the width if
the value is pretty short in this number
of the result of spatter the exercise
desires not truncated sauce is larger so
I guess the problem is we were
truncating the value if it was larger so
I guess I was not really doing what the
spec told me to do there right am i
right about this why am I looking at
that it's not really right so I think
that's not what we were doing in this
case we have width and in here we were
saying well I think we truncate we
truncate the value if it can't fit in
width
yeah so I think we're kind of I think
we're kind of following the specific
we're following the wrong specification
here right we did we did not do what the
width was actually supposed to be
because you can see here that you know
okay if the width wasn't specified use
the precision plus the prefix like this
etc these were supposed to be minimum
values that came through but then we're
doing loops that sort of stopped if the
width is not right
like if the width is not sufficient to
print them we stopped and that's wrong I
guess we should have kept going
regardless of whether or not we have any
width left all we really wanted to do
was pad if we needed to right yeah
yeah that seems to be the case so we use
precision is going to be whatever the
size of the thing is so when we say
pointer to that precision also usually
is in for floating-point values it means
something different so we probably will
even have to sort of adjust this
condition here because because that's
not really what the precision means in
the floating-point case does that mean
there's no real way in the Profoto point
case to do the equivalent thing I don't
know printf is crazy the way they do
their format specification is kind of
not so it's it's really hard to
understand exactly how all the things
are supposed to interact with each other
but you know what do you know anyway so
if we take a look at this what that
would mean if we wanted to relax that
restriction I think what that would mean
is that this use width stuff really
would allow they use with the only thing
we really need to do is just make it so
that they use with itself is always
expanding that we can even leave the
code the way it is we could just make
sure that they use with itself is always
expanded to include the entire size of
the thing if it's less right so I think
all we really need to do there is say
well you know if we need like a computed
width
you know we need to say
instead of doing if not with specified I
think what we want to do is say if they
use width is less than the computed with
the use with equals computed with so I
think that's probably a little more
correct now I don't think that should
affect anything you know I think that
should leave our printouts pretty much
untouched if I'm not mistaken so
everything should be fine here and it
does seem to be so that's good so now
what we need to do is make it so that
this precision here is actually computed
differently if it's a floating-point
value right because floating-point
values need to have their precision
specified in a different way or rather
the precision specifier for them does
not mean that you are trying to box how
big the value is it's talking about the
part after the decimal point right so
that's what precision means in this case
for these it's the number of dishes
written after the decimal point
which by default is 6 right so hey we
set it to the right value there right
that's what we said it - if it's not
specified ok so we will need to record
whether or not it's float unfortunately
I believe and then we'll have to set
that to true of these cases because we
have to handle the precision differently
depending on which one it is we're
talking about
okay and so in this case what we would
need to do is say okay if we are going
to use if we were using a floating point
number so the precision was used for
that purpose then what this means is we
would always use this value meaning we
would not so we'd say like you know if
it is a float or the presenter was not
specified then we will use the total
size of the thing being printed as the
amount to print instead okay
so that's looking better but we still
have the problem of that's not looking
like it's padding properly and that
makes sense because the width value that
we specified I don't know what that
width value is really even talking about
at this point should it have put a space
in front I don't know I don't really
know if it should ever shouldn't have I
think it should have but then again if
you read that spec it kind of makes it
sound like it shouldn't minimum number
of characters be printed if the value to
be printed is shorter than this number
the result is padded with blank spaces
the value is not truncated oh sorry that
doesn't say before the decimal point
right so it kind of sounds like actually
that's the correct behavior
honestly right I mean if you actually
read the spec it makes it sound like
that's doing the correct thing and it
sounds like you know if you actually if
that spec was actually correct then
really the part that's like doing this
stuff these should really be 5.02 right
because you you're want to print out
five total characters which is what the
wit specifier is supposed to be saying
so percent o 2 O 2 is not actually
correct even though I think that's what
I normally use it makes me feel like
maybe that spec is wrong or the
normalization of printf is wrong I don't
know but you understand my dilemma there
because you know this makes it look like
it would be the part before the decimal
point and you're specifying how wide
that should be but that's not really
what the spec suggests the spec does not
suggest that at all I shouldn't say spec
it's not the spec it's some stupid help
page so maybe that's totally wrong but
you can see what I mean like that feels
like what I should actually have done to
make the correct printout and and I
don't know who's right in this case
right and hey there you go now it's now
it's correct uh so I don't know I don't
know what to make of that is there a
better specification is there a better
specification for this somewhere right I
don't know
the width field specifies a minimum
number of curse output and is typically
okay is typically used to pad fix with
fields and tabulated output where the
fields would otherwise be smaller
although it does not cause truncation of
oversized fields the width field may be
omitted or a numeric integer value or
dynamic value and passed as other
argument when indicated by an asterisk
for example and it prints that out
though not part of the width field a
leading zero is interpreted as the zero
padding flag mentioned above and
negative values tree is the positive
value in conjunction with the left
alignment flag I don't know I don't know
what to make it as folks I mean I guess
I don't care that's some level it's our
printout now we can make the
specification be whatever we want but I
was just following the printf format
specifiers for kind of a principle of
least surprise sort of thing so that it
was just you know it's what you would
expect
unfortunately when I'm reading this I
really don't know what it's supposed to
be but I mean you can see right here
what the expected output is that three
would mean three characters total if we
were to believe what these width aspire
say and if you look that is four
characters right so clearly you know
much much as my intuition and having
used printf my whole life
would have expected that's not what that
value means yet if you look at what
these things are saying they're
suggesting something completely
different and I don't know what I really
don't know what to make of that that's
very confusing is all this documentation
just wrong
are they like not stating it properly
and I don't know let's see what
Microsoft has to say
optional decimal number that specifies
the minimum of the kerrick's that our
output for more information see printf
with specification oh well you know what
know though since it's the minimum
number I should I spoke a little bit too
soon there since the minimum number that
that could be allowed it would only be
if yeah so that that's fine because it
is allowed to print out for if you
specify three right three positions
before the decimal point called width
see even there but they're saying it
that way they're saying it that way and
that's not what they mean or that's not
what this what the spec seems suggests
although here they say it the right way
or they say it the way the spec
suggested is I don't know I'm gonna call
it four here I'm gonna say it's time to
go to the QA because I feel like I feel
like this is something where maybe
people should have an opinion about this
separately and we can maybe take a look
at the we could take a look at what what
people on the internet feel in terms of
how we do that because I don't know what
to make of that
I don't know what to make of that I feel
like it's really confusing because it
looks like people sort of think both
things I'm not sure who to believe but
but there you go
all right so any q and A's at the moment
any q and A's at the moment I'm tired
looks like the Q and a bot is not
working does the float printout account
for left or right alignment yeah I think
it does because it's still just using
the same code path so I think I believe
it would do the alignment for us
properly I let's see if we could verify
that so if I was to do this if to
construct a case where that actually
happens so if I'm to do this you can see
that this is right aligning the number
so I assume if we wanted to we could
left align that number how does it do
it's it's negative is that right this
requires me to actually remember how you
left a line which I never do yeah so so
it does appear that the float obeys that
properly because again we're just
piggybacking on the same code path which
is you know it's you'll note I did not
write this printf for like being super
performant because we don't care about
the speed of our printf right it's a
debugging tool and so I wrote the code
so that everything kind of goes to the
same path even if that's slower because
that allows us to implement all these
finicky things and without a ton of code
right you could imagine if you your
mandate was like okay print us an actual
serious thing we're really concerned
about how many print tests we're going
to be doing then you probably don't have
that luxury you might have to do things
so that you're actually smarter about
handling a lot of special case
and like oh this is the one for printing
out a floating-point number
with left alignment and it's like
specific you know or whatever
sure luck 93 are we stuck on what
something percent 3d means I was away
not really so we're very clear on what
percent 3d means because nobody seems to
be confused about that the width
specifier on integers is just obviously
the minimum space that it could take up
so it'll be padded if it's if it's less
than that so we get that the thing that
was confusing is some references on the
internet seem to believe or act like
when used with a floating-point number
it meant how many things before the
decimal point as opposed to how many
things total and so we were trying to
get confirmation that that was in fact
not true and that % 3f for example or %
3.3 F means three characters minimum not
three characters minimum before the
decimal point Culver fly sorry if it
sounds rude but why do you even care
about the specs why don't you just print
whatever you want to be I mean it's your
code yeah well like I said I kind of
just was obeying the principle of least
surprise there I mean we basically
cloned printf so it seemed like it might
be worth you know copying what their
format stuff was but no we don't have to
care right we are not trying to be a
drop-in replacement we did not for
example and probably won't do scientific
notation right so like technically if we
wanted to be complete right we have to
actually now go and differentiate
between these cases like G and E and F
instead of calling them all the same and
you know I might even say we could
probably just do
this for now
is that right these already exactly the
same thing right yeah
Sherlock 93 as far as I know percent 3.3
F means three numbers before the decimal
and precisely three decimal numbers that
is not what any of the documentation
suggests right I was sort of thinking
the same as you were thinking that that
was my intuition going to it as well and
that is why I was confused when the
documentation very clearly did not say
that
right and Martin's is posting that you
know CVB reference state citizen it's a
minimum width and that's what I was
seeing yeah so it you know it seems like
I am you know my intuition about what
that meant is not correct so I think the
way we have it implemented now is more
correct per the documentation forever
whatever that's worth
so I think we'll keep it like that I
think we will keep it like that
and Sherlock 93 you are not alone I
think that's what I thought it was too
so you know you can program a long time
still be wrong about stuff that you use
it's not not uncommon happens to me all
the time
insofar as can you say something
quotable for test purposes well I feel
like it's hard to say something quotable
on demand right
and three why gun yes I agree minimum
width makes it more consistent across
all types of printf which is why I'm
leaning towards assuming that the
documentation is actually correct
program gamer so wait is it a behavior
problem or a bad spec problem
it's neither we just wanted to know
because we can do either right it's it's
easy for us to support either one and
the way I had originally written the
code I was doing it kind of the way we
assumed but now that I read the spec I
changed it to do the other way so that
we'd go along with the spec and I think
that's probably just where we should you
know the way we should leave it
Elven do you think it's worth
implementing a custom string class that
uses a custom heap or allocation and
disposition of memory instead of dealing
directly with military FC strings
talking mostly for tools programming I
feel like that's really a question about
dependent about the context and it has I
don't feel like it has a generic answer
right
Sherlock 93 thanks to the stream have a
good evening going to work are you gonna
stream at this time from now on yes I
believe we will probably be back at the
8 p.m. timeslot because that was my
original time slot it's the one that's
baked into the trailer for example and
it was only because of you know personal
schedule situations which I no longer
have to worry about that it was ever
moved to 5:00 so I much prefer it at 8
it allows me to have a more relaxed day
and so it will probably stay there for
the foreseeable future but you know it
doesn't mean we won't occasionally have
streams at other times it just means
that they'll probably be at 8 again like
they were when it first started as Zelda
is text printing speed interfering with
your profiling accuracy in a significant
way
so not the printf part of it but the
sort is and so what we would like to do
is turn this that's sorting off at some
point because we don't really need
sorting to be happening on the on our
debug output in that way so we that
that's you know that's definitely the
case
toreador what advantages advantages does
this version of printf have over the
standard library printf none it is not
meant to be an advantage it is simply
that our mandate for handmade hero as
you know you you know if you've watched
show for a while is to write everything
so we're trying to show for example how
printf works just like we wrote a
software rasterizer is there an
advantage to our software rasterizer
overusing opengl no opengl is in fact
better right because it leverages the
hardware and it can be faster than we
can be because it uses the GPU which we
don't have access to if we're just
writing in x86 code so we don't have
access to a bunch of the computer but
the point of a made hero is not that
we're only writing code when we can
write code that's better than some
existing code that's not the point at
all the point of handmade hero is to
show how all of the code is written and
so our goal by the end of the project is
to have literally no libraries at all
we've never used like we've never
actually gone and used a library
explicitly we've always written
everything ourselves but just the fact
that we started up compiling in see on a
C compiler meant we had the C runtime
library being linked to us and
eventually we'd like to get rid of that
because we can't actually go do some
fiddling with the compiler switches and
some other things to actually tell it to
stop by you know default including that
library that we've had and so there's a
few things we need to do to make that
happen and printf was a big one because
we were using printf so the nice thing
now is we can get that off the list and
say okay now we're not using any library
code and so we're getting close to not
really having any library code at all
any C runtime library code at all which
would be pretty great because then we
would be literally library free we've
always like I said we've never gone and
used the library explicitly but just the
fact that we started up in cement our
code was being linked with the C runtime
library and that's still a library and
I'd like to make sure that handmade hero
doesn't use any libraries when it ships
that was part of the idea behind the
behind the program
long boolean right now you are padding
with zero is the spec at least in one
example except as it faces actually we
pad with both it's it's edible so if you
put a zero in front of it it uses pad
with zeros and if you don't it uses
power spaces which is exactly what the
spec says to do in my is my
understanding elven when is the next
handmade con it is November 19th and you
can get tickets right now if you would
like you can just go to handmade Kong
org you missed the early bird special so
you have to pay full price unfortunately
I tweeted about it multiple times so you
don't say you weren't warned but you
have to go to handmade con dot org you
can buy tickets to handmade con 2016 if
that is going to be on your schedule I
am in fact going to be announcing some
things about that soon one thing I will
say is we're having a job fair this year
which will be pretty awesome it looks
like we're gonna be able to have members
of the Engine teams from almost every
major triple-a engine that currently
exists and maybe even some not you know
some smaller engine teams as well
available for we're gonna have her like
a reception where you know you can go up
and talk to them and learn about what
it's like to program on their teams and
maybe make some contacts if you you know
so who did send your resume to who to
you know hit up for a job when you think
you're ready so that's a pretty cool
thing that's coming to handmade con this
year that's gonna be a big a big
addition that we didn't have Hamid Khan
2015 so that's gonna be pretty pretty
great I think I'm really I think that'd
be really great for a lot of people who
were wondering
music guru what else is left other than
printf that would need to remove there's
a cup it's just a couple math functions
I think like like cosine and cosine
there there actually is no processor
command for sine and cosine that there
was actually in the x87 so so originally
intel chips the floating-point
coprocessor did actually have a function
called F sin cos which actually did
compute a sine and cosine but those are
those no longer exists in the x64
architecture so if you want sine and
cosine or a tan to another common math
function we will need sine cosine a tan
- those are actually you have to
essentially write your own code that
computes them by using like series
expansion or you know you base it that
construct a numerical technique that
will solve the sine and cosine that you
want that will compute the sine cosine
that you want in in a few Cindy
instructions and so we have to write
those that's about it look we don't we
tried very hard to never really use
anything in the sea run teller so like I
said it's not like we have been leaning
on it as a crutch or anything printf was
definitely the biggest one in terms of
amount of code but there still are a
couple tiny ones such that if we were to
remove the standard library we would
definitely get a couple linking errors
against a tan and that sort of stuff now
in fact I I would suspect that since
this is our only pound include now that
I know of that includes something from
the C runtime library I think just doing
that compile you can see what we need so
squirt is trivial because that's in the
processor round is pretty trivial floor
and sealed pretty trivial F abs really
trivial so those wouldn't take too long
trivial is probably the wrong word first
floor and seal they're not trivial but
they're easy a sine cosine in a tan or a
little
more numerical in terms of you have to
understand a bunch of stuff to be able
to do them so and round F floor F and C
left actually if you're if you're
willing to require SSC for their
actually they are built into the
processor now they weren't built in the
processor before which is actually even
that's not true they actually have
always been built in the processor it's
just it was too hard to access them you
had to set the rounding mode first to
get to them and it's too expensive to
like set the rounding mode do the
operation of set the running mode back
what I mean to say is in SSC 4.1 or
something I don't remember what they
added a rounding function that allows
you to specify the rounding mode so that
you can floor or seal with one
instruction to say here's what I wanted
to do seal the value or floor the value
right
could you explain briefly why the simple
approach of printing floats can lead to
precision errors yes it's because
dividing by 10 is not a power of 2 right
so what happens is what you would want
to do is you know if we were printing
this out in binary it'd be really easy
you just shift 8 over 1 each time and
print out whatever the binary digit was
well you divide by 10 that doesn't shift
the number over by an even number of
binary digits so what happens is the
whole number changes and so when you do
that divide by 10 you're changing the
whole number and you're gonna lose bits
at the end when you do that right so if
you really want to print out a
floating-point number
precisely I don't think you can divide
but I don't think whatever issue an
actual divide by 10 so I think that's
why you need to go use one of the real
techniques like that one that I
referenced back before break and
actually read up on how to be more
intelligent about how you're printing it
out like I said I'm handmade here oh we
probably all need to care about that
it's not the sort of thing that we care
about here but it's definitely the case
that if you're trying to print out
floating-point numbers accurately this
is not good enough it's not good enough
and you need to have a more specific
approach
will everything be recorded at hand-made
Khan considering what nearly happened
last year I'm a little worried again
recording and streaming we make no
promises we try to record streaming we
probably just won't try I don't think
we'll try to get it streamed this year
but we will try to get it recorded as
best we can the only way to guarantee
that you get to see what happens at
handmade con obviously is to go to
handmade con I mean it's a conference
that's the point
but obviously we're trying as hard as we
can to record because I think that's
valuable for archival purposes so people
can go see what was said and have access
to it so we will be trying to record it
I probably won't bother trying to stream
it this year because it's just too much
of a hassle so we'll probably just try
to record but we will try very hard to
make sure we'd record it you know
correctly for multiple cameras so we
have some redundancy
that's here think we're done with
questions
I think we are done I'm gonna wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it has
been a pleasure coding with you as
always I'm going to remove that
so what we're still compiling there okay
thanks for coming back after the break
it's been good seeing everyone again and
coding with you if you would like to
follow along at home as always the
source code you can pre-order the game
on handmade hero or it comes with a
source code I updated every night so you
can play around with the latest build we
also have a forum site you can go to if
you want to ask questions we have a
patreon page you can go to if you want
to support the video series we have a
schedule but that tells you when the
series will be live so if you want to
keep up with that that's a great way to
do it we have an episode guide
maintained by the fabulous midlow who
keeps like chronological sort of indexes
into the episodes that are super helpful
for catching up on past episodes so I
highly recommend checking that out and
also supporting his patreon he has a
patreon that's listed up there as well
if you enjoy that service he is the one
who makes it happen
that's about it for handmade hero we'll
be back here tomorrow same time same
place 8 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time I
believe right now are we in PDT I don't
think we're in PST I think we're at PDT
I don't remember so come back and join
us for I guess we'll be done with the
printf for looking at some other
finishing stuff so we can move on to
Game Code because I think we're just
about wrapping up sort of our engine
stuff that's about it hope to see you
guys tomorrow until then have fun
programming and I will see you guys on
the Internet take it easy everyone