hello everyone and welcome back to
handmade hero we were right in the
middle of working on the renderer here
we wanted to pull it out into something
that could be used as a standalone
system and we did a bunch of that work
in the first stream of the day this is
the second stream of the day now it's
time to take a look at how to get the
for lack of a better term how to get the
integration between handmade hero and
the renderer out into something more
separable there are very few things that
the renderer actually cares about as far
as handmade here is concerned so it's
not very difficult to pull them apart
except for the one part where they do
kind of care which is the texture system
so really our job now is to make that
texture system something that is
optional and can be used through sort of
a generic access API that anybody's
asset system could play nicely with
including handmade heroes obviously but
also other people who may want to use
the renderer that is the goal so what I
did is I just started by trying to
include the renderer in here to see what
would happen if we if we build it here
you can see that if we want to start
calling the render group calls which we
do eventually want to start calling
that's how we get information to the
renderer they are not defined if I
define them then you can see this is
where we left off if I define them by
including handmade renderer dot CPP so
we can actually use those functions then
you see we start to have all these
problems accessing things that we don't
know we don't have the information
necessary to access and so on so that's
really what we need to start looking at
here and start getting into a more
refined sort of setup
all right so as you've seen me ping-pong
back and forth as we're doing this the
reason for that is very straight forward
essentially when you're working on
tuning a piece of code to get it into a
good state for rias and working out what
API should be and working out how to
what goes where there's two sides of the
problem there's the the working with the
code that exists to make changes that
allow it to be clearer better segmented
less integrated with other pieces of
code that you don't want agree with
there's that part and there's the other
part which is figuring out what the
outer API is figuring out how people
outside the code talk to it and so you
constantly want to be ping-ponging back
and forth between these and bringing
them up together that's why I have a lot
of things in flight right now I can
build the testbed I can build the game
and I can look at what habits mean those
right now I'm gonna do is I'm gonna go
back to the game where everything is
locked in like this start to pull it
apart like this and then when I feel
like I have something that's sort of
what I want to start working with on the
external API side then I'll ping pong
back to the render testbed right so I'm
working with those two things basically
as sort of a way of gradually working
the code code you know Cody is a lot
more like cooking than people would like
to admit right it's kind of like I'm
kneading the dough now now we're gonna
let it rise right there's all these
steps and things to understand it's a
very active process and I feel like
that's why streaming coding is and
watching people code is so important
because you you lose a lot of that when
you read these sort of solid books that
don't really they're like here's how you
design a piece of code no no no one's
designs piece of code that way there are
any good like this is how you do it you
have to work the code see how it goes
and then you end up with something
really nice at the end it's no doubt
that when you read these books you look
at the code that they end up with you're
like that's terrible anyway so what you
want to do is understand where the right
place is to work at any given time I'm
go ahead and say at the moment that I
want to be back in handmade here a
proper and I want to do some sort of
separation of that code and see where I
want that boundary to lie so I'm popping
back over here to win through your
handmade I can run the game like this
and see what's going on in it that's
what I want there and so what I'm going
to do here is I'm going to look at the
renderer and I want to kind of look at
what is and is not actually part of the
renderer okay because there are
definitely things in here right now that
aren't really part of the renderer so
for example all of this stuff like the
render setup and the texture quads and
the blend targets the clearing the light
transfer object transforms camera
transforms render transforms these are
all things that are generally useful
anyone who's going to use this renderer
is going to want to use them and that's
good there's a bunch of other things
that really aren't that interesting that
really don't make a lot of sense to
people who are using the render
necessarily and that's why like if we
look at something like the render group
what you could sort of start to see is
that pretty soon we probably want to
talk about the render group as something
that's two stage right we probably want
to start splitting it up so that the
render group is maybe something that's
only part of handmade here and we can
reintroduce that render group files we
want to write but such that we have
things that operate on just the renderer
part of things and then things that
happen in handmade hero that also use
the renderer
right and we kind of want to start
thinking about what those are don't ask
me why I draw a rectangle quickly is in
here I don't know is there a reason why
that had to be there no so what I want
to do is start looking at that as as
something to sort of fixate on and we're
gonna kind of we're gonna get a little
bit further down we're gonna go a little
bit further down that rabbit hole as we
go all right so we'll start with basic
things could start with really basic
things here's the handmade software
renderer right and I want to keep this
around cuz like I said I do want
updated eventually into something where
did that let's go what's going on here
what did I broke something I want oh I'm
in the wrong directory that's why
handmade blender software H okay there
we go I do want to update this
eventually so I don't want to get rid of
it but what I do want to do is make sure
that things that are related to the
software renderer are only in the
software rendered files right so for
example this tile render work stuff here
this is not something that ever gets
used in any of the other renders it's
specific to the software renderer so it
really belongs out here right and so
that's like something we want to be
aware of we want to start looking
through here and make sure that we don't
have things sitting around inside the
the render stuff that's you know acting
like it's something generic but that
really isn't right that is really
actually not generic and it's actually
something that you know that we should
should be putting exclusive to someplace
to one place or another so I'm kind of
looking at those things as we go so
looking through here you know we've got
these push buffer things push render
element we've got this get bitmap dimmed
stuff right we've got the store color
get current quads a lot of these things
do have good reason to be here certainly
and that's all fine we've got push quads
push bitmaps some of these and you can
start to see here you know we start to
get the things that maybe might be
handmade here a specific nothing in here
is specific though so far to the
software renderer or Hardware render so
that's good right that's totally fine
and we don't really need to think about
that too much right okay
this coordinate system stuff an
environment map stuff we're just not
using anymore so I'm gonna go ahead and
get rid of those as well just make sure
that those are not so taking up any
mental space there these sort of things
here this is more mathy you know this
fit camera distance and this unprojected
stuff this is kind of a little bit more
math math
and so I kind of want that to be moved
out to the math library anyway and and
so III may want to start pulling these
out and just have these pass what they
want to pass that that might start
happening if you look at these these are
already totally math math only anyway
like this stuff is all math only there's
there's no non math stuff in there
there's no accessing the render group
I'm also gonna get rid of some of these
I don't we don't really need in lines
anymore it's kind of old habits of mind
that we have in lines at all we probably
don't really need them they could all be
internal the compiler pretty much does
inlining for you and doesn't really like
to pay attention to your in lines anyway
so it's kind of one of those things that
I still do out of habit to kind of tell
myself it's an inline function but we
really don't need that to be in there a
lot of times so it's kind of
questionable in that sense all right so
anyway as we look through here we got
these sort of render calls most of these
look good they're you know depth P or
whatever there sorts of stuff that we
expect to be there get the push lighting
all of that stuff looks pretty good like
I said there's a couple math things that
I might want to pull out a little
further but for now these are the only
two that were just pure math so we got
rid of those we got rid of the one that
was only for software rendering we also
have this article here I might I
practicum move that out I want to make
sure I've got a good understanding here
of what is and is not functions in here
like these are all functions right you
can see that here and and then in here
we've got stuff that's that's structs
and so on right and so I want to make
sure that we we've got that stuff under
control so I'm gonna go ahead and kind
of take a look at these and just make
sure that we've we've got those
segregated nicely into two different
groups there there we go
and yeah that all looks fine and now
we're just left with our structural
stuff right so now if we were to move
this
into the CPP file that would all be fine
except it kind of can't quite do that
yet for some of these because they're
actually using the platform layers and
we haven't quite gotten to the point
where both of them can wear both our
test bed and our platform layer for
handmade Hiro can actually include this
file so I'm going to leave them like
this for a moment what I am going to do
here is you can see these like get
standard camera objects from stuff I'm
gonna move those into the CPP file here
as well temporarily and then I'm gonna
go ahead and compile here to make sure
that still works okay just taking a look
here so you can see here we want the the
tile render work stuff in here in the
software render the only reason it's not
seeing that is because the software
vendor here doesn't actually include its
its age file so let's make sure that's
in there right and we can put that
really wherever we want it may make more
sense to put it in the actual place
where it's used right so the the
software renderer is is only really
called no Winfrey to you platform layer
so you can see right here if I just
wanted to include it before we use it we
can I do that as well all right uh so
again just going in and continuing to
work on this code a little bit I think
these two need to stay out for the
moment if they will move down as well so
I'm gonna go now start to work on these
since these pieces are kind of I'm not
sure how I feel about having to continue
to do type toughs here I really don't
want to do that so I think I'm gonna
kind of start doing this sort of thing
where it's like look I'll go through and
see if anyone is still trying to link it
with this stuff in C I don't know that
anyone is I think there are people who
are doing like ports to Swift or
something and so I I'm gonna go with non
type deaths for the moment in these sort
of external files and we'll kind of
cross that bridge again if we come to it
that's a separate sort of thing where
you want to maintain C linkage for
certain things I don't really want to
get into that right now
so we're gonna we're going to kind of
nor that part all right so now what I
want to do is take a look and I want to
isolate the parts that are actually
talking about loaded bitmap as a thing I
want those things to sort of be a little
bit more specific here and I want to go
ahead and and make sure that we know
exactly where we're actually talking
about loaded bitmap okay
so if I wanted to get rid of loaded
bitmap in this h-file entirely for
example and move it in somewhere else
right then the police that I really am
looking that the place where we're
really hitting a little bit of a of a
snag with it right is the inside here in
the game render commands that's
someplace where we record these these
bitmaps that we're using right so what I
want to know fundamentally about those
is when we actually use them in an
actual render scenario how are they
actually getting used okay so I want to
look at how we're using loaded bitmap
here and I want to know exactly what
aspects of loaded bitmap are actually
getting used that's my my big question
okay
and what I'm hoping is that all we're
really using is like the texture handle
in the case of the opengl side and then
okay what we're using on the software
underside because I know how to make
that work so I just want to see on the
OpenGL side what we're actually using
there so I'm just gonna look quickly to
see like let's look at quad bitmaps and
white bitmap and just see so you can
look you look at where we're using that
it's so nice there's almost nowhere that
we're using those at all right it's just
it's really clean
so I think the first thing that we can
probably do you switch from having
loaded bitmaps in the stream to having
something more abstract than that in the
stream now this is a little bit more
complicated and the reason for that is
this is the place where we where we now
have
this is lace where we're starting to
earn our money right by the wealth full
disclosure I only ate part of my lunch
my lunch was three three chicken thighs
and this little gentleman right here I
don't know what it is it was a doughnut
of some kind and we're just hoping that
we get lucky that's all right it's a
supermarket doughnut so I don't go in
with high expectations but I'm alright
with that all right so we'll continue to
work on that as a crucial part of our
day now what I want to start doing now
is appreciating the fact that what we
did so so how we got here in first place
right you can understand why the render
looks like it does currently we
originally got a software vendor if the
software vendor wanted to use loaded
bitmaps so that's what we were working
with then we had a hardware renderer so
now we need texture handles which are a
graphics card thing so what we did is we
just drafted the texture handle onto our
loaded bitmap and you can see that right
here right you can see where we did that
totally reasonable thing to do I have no
problem with it but if you think about
what's going on there it's not really
what we want okay because what it does
is it assumes that you're sort of always
running the software renderer as well as
the hardware renderer right because
really a loaded bitmap is the is the
equivalent so GPU has a texture that we
upload to loaded bitmap is like the
software version of that right so really
what we want is we want to separate
texture systems here the software
renderer should
and upload to it and the graphics card
should have it upload to it and even
though the software's upload will just
be loading in the information from
loaded bitmap directly we still want to
split those out so that we're not
talking about what is effectively the
software renderers bitmap format in the
hardware renderer which cares not at all
about that particular thing ok so that's
what we're trying to work towards now is
this understanding of what is and is not
part of each renderer and how do we
unify those behind an API that makes
sense for everyone regardless of which
one they're using ok so that's where
we're going it's gonna be a big push
could take us all stream to do at least
but that's what we're doing just get
another one of these in here hmm
that's definitely working for me alright
so bring it back around
hey napkin that's here we go good
alright uh so what I want to do here is
change this to something that is
basically storing texture handles so for
example what I want to do is say we have
render commands and then I want to have
like a render texture like this and this
is basically going to be a blind piece
of information so I do want the game to
be able to work with these and be able
to push them directly on as it writes
but then I want some way of having them
work themselves out in a cleaner way
then then I don't want the game to know
what's in them right I just kind of want
to be blind now what we're gonna start
with here is we're gonna start with au
64 why am I gonna start with the U 64
I'm gonna start with au 64 because I
want to stuff pointers in there as a
temporary workaround potentially right
so I'll be able stuff pointers handles
whatever eventually we're going to make
this handle simpler it's probably gonna
go all the way down to a you 16 is my
guess so we're gonna compact compact
compact that down so this is not the end
of the story but for the temporary time
being that's what's going to look like
right and so this is just to get things
started so what I'm gonna do here is I'm
going to take this render of texture I'm
gonna say okay now we've got our
textured vertex thing that's how we
report what we want to draw then we've
got a renderer texture that's how we say
what graphical feature is slapped on to
each individual quad similarly we have
this white bitmap here I'm getting rid
of one star why because again this is
effectively going to be a pointer for
now but in the future we're really just
talking about an array of 16-bit values
or something like that that we're gonna
use okay
so again very important do you
understand all of what's going on here
we're just trying to collapse those down
okay
so at the outset we can literally do no
work and just pass it straight through
all we have to do is recognize the fact
that we can cast to this and cast out so
again I'm going to smuggle that value
through just to get things working but
then my goal is to remove the concept
that these are loaded bitmap pointers
from it entirely and go further down the
road towards making it be a separated
version for you for software render and
hardware render and any other hardware
renderer so not just not just for
separating hardware and software but
also star by Zeus d3d maybe we're
storing a texture a pointer to some
surface thing OpenGL we're storing a
handle right like we want to be able to
start talking about these things in an
opaque way where you just say I have a
texture index I don't know what it
refers to I don't know how to use it all
I say is like look draw with this and
that's all I can really understand
that's where we want the the people who
are using this renderer to be right all
right so let's get that going
let's make sure everyone follows the
rules so in here where we pull one of
these out this is actually a renderer
texture and then what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to quickly convert it to
a loaded bitmap by saying let's just
pretend that it is one right again
total nonsense not real not what we're
gonna do eventually but that this is
where we're going with this right okay
again so now we need to supply those
here's that bitmap array and we can
render texture allocate those there we
go let's look at who else is getting
stymied there oops that what's wrong
what do you complain oh the white bitmap
sure no problem
we can fix that as well this is now
going to be a renderer texture for white
bitmap we will fix that so in here now
what we know is that well this has to be
a pointer to a loaded bitmap again this
is going to go away in just a second so
I'm literally just dubbing it out this
is not code we ever want in here in any
way shape or form so just keep that in
mind but you know you'll see how it
plays out in just a second when we get a
little bit further down the line so I'm
just gonna make a dummy one there and
then I'm gonna say that we're gonna
point to that like so and then we will
just initialize this saucy gentleman
like this right and so we'll keep moving
on from here what are you complaining
about OpenGL white bitmap does not need
to have its address take it anymore so
that's good
and off we go alright so here when we're
pushing quads again just gonna smuggle
the bitmap pointer in even though we're
totally totally lying about that so what
I want to do here is say all right the
you know the handle on here is just
gonna be this then cast into a u 64
again very temporary when we're looking
at push cube here this white bitmap up
push cube this so this gets a little
harder because we want to actually
convert to pushing these sooner rather
than later this actually now in that
case wants to actually be a renderer
texture you know what I'm saying to you
so this wants to be done like that right
and that means that really this this
part where we were writing it before if
I go up to look at this here this wants
to do the same thing so when we do a
push quad I want to actually just go
ahead and have the someone have to have
done this upstream so we're always just
pushing on the actual texture that we're
using none of no more the loaded bitmap
stuff and from from here on out right
okay um so here again we can in you know
what I think I should probably do here
just to make this easier for us to find
and fix in a second when we go to sort
of change this around what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna do like render texture from
just to make it a little macro here it's
gonna take the bitmap pointer and it's
gonna do that conversion right so really
all I'm gonna do is I'm going to totally
cheese it out I'm just gonna say look I
know that if I just told you that this
actually was a renderer texture it's
just got one thing in it which is the
pointer if I just convert it to the
pointer to that and then recast down
you're gonna think it's the right thing
right so I know like this is sufficient
to turn a loaded bitmap pointer into one
of these render text temporarily then
from there we can
we can go ahead and remove that macro
and fix everything as we go forward
right so let's go ahead and get that
going mmm
let's renderer texture isn't it
so again renderer texture from here as
we keep on moving renderer texture from
this bitmap clock here is this is just
texture in all of these for this push
cube so these are just texture texture
texture all of these are just using the
texture again the push quad may need to
be extended to take that yeah so in this
case I think we probably want this to be
render a texture as well and if anyone
else needs to call that we can always
make a helper function for them all
right uh so this is renderer texture
from right here I let's see what else we
got initializing white bitmap okay
that's fine again for push volume
outline this is totally fine you could
see these line segments here
those are taking pitman points I might
just go ahead and again make those
require the person who passes them in to
actually have done that conversion
already so I'm gonna go ahead and just
say you got to do that and that way when
we come through to this call I can just
do renderer texture texture equals the
white bitmap and then in here I can just
substitute all of these
there we go so now let's just keep
looking for more opportunities for
something like that again same thing
here I'm just gonna go ahead and pass it
directly because now that will take the
texture in here where we're looking at
the white bitmap same thing so this is
just going to become ups that's gonna
become a renderer texture light texture
and now let's continue on this is again
the same thing there we go and now
you're good to go
um and so now all we have to do is
actually make sure that the rest of our
stuff is is set up correctly here in
this case it's not these are supposed to
be renderer textures so let's go ahead
and make that true like so and this
right here should be allocating the
renderer textures like so all right so
now the question is okay we just kind of
swapped out that type so but let's make
sure you make any mistakes
we could have so let's make sure we
still get textured rendering and we do
so that's good so now what we want to do
is continue to push that concept forward
further right so what we want to do now
is we want to try and and and make the
sort of the loaded bitmap stuff become
less and less and less and less relevant
to the actual renderer core so what I
want to do now is I'm going to move
loaded bitmap somewhere else and I'm
just gonna see what ends up happening to
what we include right so I'm just I'm
just trying to get sort of a more of a
feel for what's gonna happen here if I
start to move these things out so that's
all we're doing really straightforward
I know that's gonna be a problem that's
okay that's a no big deal
lift here last bit map doesn't get used
at all so that can just go it's not
super relevant at all that's just to get
the texture handle so again I don't care
about that that's totally fine
why about why can't I continue down my
error list here can I get any more
errors should be able to get some more
here's a bunch errors right here I can't
get to those some reason I can't get to
those errors I'm not sure why for a
coder why can't I jump to those errors
these are all same-same okay so here
what you can see is now when we're
looking at loaded bitmap this is all in
the software renderer you can see all of
this in a software renderer here right
just software renderer all day long
so if I were to take the loaded bitmap
now and talk and have the software
renderer have its own understanding of
what's going on with textures then it
could get the same information that it
needs here out of that so what I want to
verify and again I don't actually know
what I'm looking at here so I kind of
have to take it slowly but I want to see
to what extent we ever actually look
behind a bitmap right so what you can
see is here is one place where we use
that align percentage and the width over
height right so that's kind of an
important bitmap piece of information
and here it looks like this what is this
oh so right okay so this is just for
making sure that we're talking about the
right region of the texturing question
which is again pretty basic so it seems
like we're kind of in reasonable shape
here there's very little we actually do
with these so in terms of where we
actually pass them in right here where
we do our get bitmap dim really it's
just and that's really only happening in
one place
right so that can kind of be moved and
welded in there too one call I'm gonna
do that let me make sure first that
that's only happening in one place now
we got one more here this is for our
tech stop
so it's using XY and size just want to
see what those are so what are XY in
size size is just the height times the
width over height right so that's just
that multiply and XY is the alignment
adjustment I can't say
so the only reason we're doing that part
really is so that we can ask about these
before they're used so I think I'm
pretty happy with everything I'm seeing
here and I think what I want to do is
pull these two out into something that's
in handmade here are proper so that
everyone just goes through the case
where you've already converted it to a
texture right I think that's what I want
to do okay so I'm gonna go ahead and try
that so if we take get bitmap Tim out of
there running here skip all of this
stuff that's happening put this right
here push bitmap with a bitmap id is
what converts it to a loaded bitmap so
that's also handmade here a specific
right
so all of these are handmade here are
specific I'm just gonna drop them down
here there's our push cube there's our
push lighting push volume outline does
not require any of that stuff
push font does earth so I'm just gonna
go ahead and drop that up here push rect
does not and outline doesn't none of
these do on project doesn't
none of this stuff does none of these do
these do none of these do none of any of
these do and so what we can kind of see
here is that really with the exception
of push lighting which is a little bit
special everything below everything
below this line
is really handmade here a specific right
and everything above it doesn't need
loaded bitmap so you can see like this
is really the part that we want to put
in there for a handmade hero sake
that's just special-purpose code for
handmade hero and then we can not have
any of that in our in our renderer that
we sort of send out to the rest of the
world it's pretty good donor
now
we need to continue to we need to
continue down this road a little further
what I'm gonna do now is I'm gonna find
out kind of how loaded bitmap what I'm
gonna do now is I'm going to start by
making something that really only works
the harder render at the moment and then
we'll stub out what would need to happen
for the software renderer and then we'll
kind of tie them together alright so
looking back here
remember we kind of have this stuff that
now needs to know about loaded bitmap
we've got it in the software renderer
and we've also got it in the in in
hand-made renderer here that's you know
it needs to know about the asset system
so this handmade here a specific part of
things I want to pull out to a different
file that only gets included in handmade
hero so it's not gonna get included
anywhere else right so that way the hint
you know this renderer stuff is the part
that we want to pull out so I want to
have like something that's sort of like
handmade specific rendering or something
or like I don't know there might be a
place where I can wear that I already
have that it would make sense to put it
it could be that it would be good in the
asset system I don't because the asset
systems a thing that actually
understands these it feels a little
weird though to do that and so I really
just don't know where that should go I'm
kind of I'm not sure how I feel about it
I really just don't know what I'm gonna
do up front is I'm just gonna put this
in there for now
I don't really like that handmade asset
rendering like the sound of that
there we go
and so this is stuff that has to do
specifically with our style of assets
right our lighting our bitmaps our fonts
not someone else's right and so I'm
gonna make this our own special sauce
here right this is our own is our own
deal and so then what I'll do is now
I'll include that over in handmade
that's EPP oops and made and so after
the asset system gets included it can
just be in here handmade asset rendering
okay and we can clean that up more as we
go later it's not really a big deal one
way or the other okay so now what I want
to do is I want to make it so that we
can actually work with this directly now
we've got all these things in here like
in the software renderer that need to
know about the loaded bitmap that's
actually fine because what we can do is
look at where that software renderer is
actually being included I don't actually
know that we need to
like I'm just trying to think of how we
want to do that I I don't really want to
deal with that at the moment I guess is
what I'm saying right I want to not
really have this be happening at the
moment
and so you could yeah okay so I'm just
gonna go ahead and convert these the way
that I I'm gonna I'm just gonna go full
pull to what I think should be happening
here in the first place right okay uh so
if I take handmade renderer software and
handmade renderer hard suffered at CTP
and whatever what I want to do now is
I'm gonna make a version of this instead
of using loaded bitmap which has
literally nothing to do with that I'm
gonna take that instead and just make it
look like what it should look like right
something like this and so you know
software texture I don't know this is a
special piece of information only for
software rendering and it's specific to
the software renderer right now what I
want to do is make it so that all the
rest of this stuff instead of working
off of loaded bitmaps is actually going
to work off of software textures which
are a different thing and have nothing
to do with the loaded bitmap anymore so
then in here I want software texture for
basically everything right all of this
stuff is all gonna work over off of
software textures that's just how it
works and we're gonna go from there okay
so now I'm gonna start by like making
that stuff work okay I'm gonna skip this
part with the white texture for now and
just look at this off for a render side
of things and of course I don't know if
for coder has a some kind of weird issue
with not part if you try to jump to an
era before the buffers done it like
doesn't catch all the errors or
something this is an older version of
our coder it may already be fixed I
should probably update the one we've got
anyway so looking at these now what I
want to do is make sure that we change
all of these two software textures let's
just make sure that's the case and then
compile and I think we may be down to
just now I think we probably just work
yeah we do so that's really all I needed
and the reason I want to do that again
is because the the loaded bitmap we were
just reusing that but it wasn't really a
loaded bitmap these things were just
little back
first that the that the suffer render
was using so we want to just now
actually recognize the fact that that is
what that actually is right so moving
back to the hardware rendering side of
things what I'm gonna do now is now I'm
going to make it so that the hardware
render actually expects just the texture
handled directly okay so what that means
is now when we go into the loaded bitmap
side of things right this is not gonna
be a texture handle anymore it's going
to actually be the renderer texture
that's backing this thing right so now
we don't actually need a loaded bitmap
in there because we won't actually be
using one anywhere we can now treat
these as actual render textures directly
okay so I'm gonna grab the texture
handle here and then what I can do or I
guess just texture here and then what I
can do is use this handle directly right
alright so that's exactly what I'm gonna
do no more loaded bitmap okay that's so
that's that's where we're going with
this right Jim Sam so now our white
bitmap is not really a white bitmap
anymore our white bitmap is really just
this allocated texture right we don't we
don't need any of this anymore because
no one's ever going to actually use it
right so now we can just say hey the
white bitmaps handle oops
right is just what we allocate when we
do an OpenGL texture allocate and I'm
gonna look at that call here hold on one
second
you can see what happens we get back a
void star and you can guess what I'm
about to do here instead of a void star
what we're actually gonna be returning
from now on is a renderer texture right
so when it allocates one of these it
allocates the renderer texture by saying
here is the result the result handle is
now going to be equal to whatever we
actually generated no more pointer
fiddling okay so now when we call opengl
allocate texture instead of getting back
a void star we're actually going to get
back a renderer texture that's what we
want so that's good and in here where
we're doing our texture management stuff
you can see here we're getting the
handle out of this and whatever we don't
actually want to do that anymore either
all we really need to do is say look the
handle that we were trying to delete is
this handle it just happens to be 64
bits instead of 32 so cast it down and
have a party be my guest
all right so now when we do this
allocate result handle thing now we've
got to get into the situation where
we've got these texture ops that's again
gonna be something we're cleaning up
simplifying everything is getting better
as we do this it's good right we're
happy this stuff here now wants to be
done like this here is the place where
the renderer texture gets set here is
the renderer texture that we are
removing like so okay and so again all
I'm doing here is just making it so that
now we're streamlining this process and
just really actually pointing to what we
what we actually wanted to in the first
place the renderer texture is gonna have
to move up because now these people are
actually talking about it again totally
fine it's a core piece it's a core
component that's
really good it's all good here's that
result texture here's the deallocation
it's just textured yeah um cannot
convert from renderer textured handle
you can and there we go
okay so when we actually allocate this
white bitmap now we can just do it like
that so you want a one in one by one y
bitmap back comes the handle done deal
now no need to actually get into that
whole situation anymore
the result texture here is just going to
be the thing that we get that were you
know writing into the bitmap for and so
now what we need to do besides just
clean that up yeah now we need to do it
just make sure that these are
initialized properly here's the the
bitmap texture I just want that to end
up getting cleared so the easiest way to
do that is just to set the handle to
zero here probably the thing is since
this is arbitrary I probably want to
just do it like this just to make sure
that it's in the render itself just to
make sure that we have a known way to
clear these to zero that that in case we
end up doing something else and we need
to clear them will work if that makes
sense so this is texture handle equals
zero right and that should be fine
what what's up to that so that way just
we know when people are doing that I
don't really want them to kind of be
yeah you know you know um soon now that
we've got that texture stuff
straightened away I want to see if it
works at all right because I don't know
if it will or not so let's go ahead and
run and see if we get anything so we've
got a problem here right you can see
that we didn't we didn't do something
correctly so that's why I just wanted to
run this and debug it now we'd like to
do is see what the error was invalid
operation so presumably yeah so here we
must have just had something yeah that
texture handle was obviously bogus right
you can see it being bogus right here so
we need to start going back and now and
tracking these down make sure that when
we push these on here we're pushing them
on here in a sensible way now I think
hopefully maybe I don't know that I
actually did this kind of more sensibly
here so I'm hoping that that this part I
will now allow us to fix remember we
were just casting the corner we now
actually know what we need to do we need
to take that bitmap pointer and we need
to actually look at the texture handle
that's what we're actually trying to
write in there now right so I think
oops this has to be captured so I'm
hoping that that's like mostly the only
thing we we have to fix I don't actually
know if it is or not but we'll see yeah
so there you go okay so again what we
did there is really nice and clean
we just said look we're using textures
from now on those texture annals are
going to come back from the renderer any
time you talk to the renderer you've
talked in terms of texture handles and
here's how you do that and so we did
that and now we're good to go what we
can do now is we can also go ahead and
move forward and say we can get rid of
this entirely we don't need to have that
because now it's a very straightforward
obvious call it doesn't have any kind of
weird semantics to it or casting it's
just saying hey you use the texture
handle
the bitmap you've got very clean very
easy and we can just put that right in
line right okay so now what I want to do
again popping back I'm gonna pop back to
our win32 render test I'm gonna see if I
can start to include the whole renderer
now and we're to see where we're at okay
what it looks like to me is we're pretty
good to go everywhere except the
lighting and what you can see here is
this push cube call where we've got the
lighting and we're pushing all the
lighting on that that's really causing
us a problem right ensue
we have some decisions to make here one
of the difficult things that we have to
figure out how to do is to make our
lighting a little bit more general
anyway right and so I probably want to
pull that handmade lighting stuff out
and let that be part of the render as
well and hopefully you know eventually
get the lighting really good so that you
would just generally use it right we're
not really at that point right now but I
think I want to leave the lighting in
the renderer so I think like handmade
lighting dot CPP I really want to
probably push that into the renderer I
think that's fine and so I might just
kind of go ahead and put these in there
and let the lighting solution be part of
you know the the actual process right
and we all clean it up because we want
the lighting to be good we want to
continue down the road to good lighting
so I think that's probably what I would
prefer not only remember what lighting
surface gets used for here cuz put a
longtime look a lot of time since we've
looked at that at all I was gonna say do
we even use anymore it looks like we
don't but of course I'm not sure because
yeah we don't
so lighting surface is not a thing
anymore we're just using lighting boxes
so we can get rid of that and then we're
kind of just down to these here right so
we've just got these two pieces of
information the lighting Point State and
the lighting box there that we use for
pushing those on so what I could do is
say alright those pieces of information
because we do use those for pushing the
lighting on let's put those into the
render at the moment let's we'll think
about it a little harder as we go but
that's basically you know that stuff
would need to be in there let's put that
in there and see what happens
light points for
shunk light points per chunk needs to be
in here as well
and off we go okay um so now we can
actually start calling things inside our
win32 render tests so here I should be
able to actually put these in here and
see what happens
that's the game here's the render test
now I'm not actually seeing the clear
color that we used but I don't really
know if our clear does anything anymore
um so there is that that's one things I
would kind of like to look at is
cleaning up some of the semantics of the
renderer once we've got it like isolated
right because it's a little weird right
now because we added kind of these
things where we're doing the the begin
depth peel and n depth peel stuff so
what I kind of want to do is just go
look at world mode for how we're using
it currently do we push it clear on ever
oops it's pushed full clear
so yeah we do we push the full clear on
right before we output the lighting
points that doesn't make any sense
so we stuff we want to fix we will be
doing a bunch of nice clean up to this
which will help handmade hero as well
because it's you never really want your
stuff to be kind of to go through too
many iterations without a cleanup pass
so I think that'll be good all right so
maybe this feel clear is just maybe the
reason that have the end was to get it
ready for the debug display I don't
really know but I'm gonna go ahead and
just copy exactly what we were doing
here pretty much by the book
ah so it looks like you just need the
depth peel section to actually be there
yeah I'm saying so that's good that uh
looks fine and so now what we want to do
is kind of get a little bit more playful
with it here the full clear so curious
the full clear that was in here is for
what oh it's for the lighting test so
this doesn't really need to be here at
all so we can really just do this right
so there's our render executing
completely outside the game now and what
we can do now is do some testing with
that so what I'd like to do I'd like to
set up a camera right um you know
something a simple camera so we can see
things so let's take a look at how that
normally works right we've got here the
camera transform stuff right so I'm just
going to go ahead and grab this exact
thing that we were using and I'm
probably uh simplify it a bit because we
don't need to do all of it at the moment
but you know so just so we know what's
going on here so we've got the get width
of the draw region here I've got my
pitch my four bit Maya Dali we've got
the background color near clip plane far
clip plane
don't know what debug light P is doing
there we don't need it anymore certainly
so then we've got our camera orbit our
camera pitch delta from sim is not
relevant to this renderer camera zero we
need the camera offset in here but
really we don't I mean it's not gonna do
anything
[Music]
there's the camera dolly here's the
focal length we need to know what that
focal length is where are we getting
this camera from there it's the get
standard camera current all right so we
can do that just fine
why it's debug light P getting past a
set camera transform that's got to be
old news get rid of that just trying to
clean this up a little bit here
I suppose this is not really important
you know we can just say that's the name
for our clip playing render group
undeclared identifier that is true
get rid of the debug light pee unless
that actually is gonna use somewhere it
might be for pushing the light on later
so we'll leave that that and then I
think we are good yes okay so here we've
got in theory a camera transform setup
and now we can start drawing things
presumably we will see in a moment if
that's actually true I will push a cube
I will push a nice little tiny little
cube and we'll see how it goes
so in here we begin the depth peel in
the end the duct peel there here is our
push cube there's the group we want that
probably white texture right the cube
will be here it'll be 1 by 2 by 4 just
to make it sort of monolith esque
will set a color the color can be cyan
for now the emission will be nothing and
it will not have lighting enabled
well that's anti-climatic
that's kind of hoping to see a cube I
know about you so we got a couple things
we've got a debug now first of all we
don't really know if this is rendering
properly but similarly we don't really
know if the camera set up properly
either right we have no idea
looking at this camera dolly of zero is
not going to cut it we need to be moved
back from the camera
so that might be part of our problem
trust thing cos anything else we did
here can see us kind of rotate down that
way so let me just put ourselves ten
units back just want to take a look at
what that looks like there it is all
right um
sooo I believe when I was talking with
the person who want to use the the
renderer I believe they said they would
be a little bit steeper not fully
isometric but a little bit steeper so so
not quite handmade here oh so I'm gonna
try like one times pi and see if that is
maybe a little bit more the the angle
sort of of steepness that we're talking
about here and then I'm going to convert
this to being something that's actually
a length we might care about okay so I
think that's basically what we're
talking about our renderer is now usable
outside which is good I and I don't know
what the pull back I don't know like
what kind of parameters are gonna want
to be set here looks like that
disappeared into the fog how does the
fog level get set I don't even know we
set it when we set the indium here right
and you know we've got the fog start and
end distance I guess they're just hard
coded so we're gonna have to pull that
stuff out like we you know that needs to
be parameterised obviously you know we
can't we can't have that be something
that's that's set arbitrary like that
and the same is true of the clip alpha
start and end like all that stuff needs
to get needs to get dealt with properly
so yeah we could probably start down
rohde now I'm trying to think to myself
how do I want to proceed there's so many
things we could do now we've done the
main work so now it's all gravy from
here on out and there's like a ton of
things we could be doing and the
question of like which one of them which
you know what to prioritize so I think
what we want to do is rather than go
down to the API iteration stage of
things and start thinking about that and
going okay how do I make this easy to
use how do I make it so that you can set
up scenes easily what about the camera
like let's pull out stuff like these
hard-coded costs for the fog distance or
stuff like that
rather than go that route I think what
I'd rather do is say let's tackle
texturing texturing is an issue because
when we're creating one of these blocks
we need to be able to say you know top
sides bottom they need to be bitmapped I
think right they need to come from a
texture and so we want some easy way of
specifying that piece of information now
there's a lot of ways we can do that but
I think that's what I would want to
focus on so I think what I'll start by
doing is say let's go the texture out
because we need to increase our ability
to specify textures and like I said at
the outset we need to now have it be so
that people who are using this API who
aren't handmade hero can get their
textures into the actual system both of
those things need to happen right so
let's get textures in that's I think the
most important part
most important part after eating my
donut which is definitely more important
than either of those two things
all right
hmm
we've got another blip OBS didn't crash
that time so we're still recording so
everything should be fine
no no panic this time that's just a
twitch fun
all right
so I want to get textures in there
and we need to kind of think about that
and how we're going to do that so what
I'd like to do is get back to the just
simple yeah I'll put the camera back
someplace where the fog hasn't clipped
yet it will take care of that stuff
later if I run this now right I just got
my cube so what I want to do is I want
to go ahead and switch to a just pure
white cube no color modulation at the
moment and then what I want to do is I
want to get texture on here like that
right like I want to actually see a
texture on here thankfully for us we
have our own PNG loader lucky day okay
so we can do that and all I have to do
is just actually provide memory Reena
stuff in here for it to actually use I
don't actually need a memory arena right
so if you look at what's going on here I
can just instead say oh yeah memory
Karina's have nothing in them right and
when these actually get used like the
push size call which you aren't finding
I can actually just make that beam a
lock right
so basically push size
I could even make it be virtual walk I
guess do we already have that right
win32 allocate memory this one right
here so really if I want to I can just
make a fake thing in here for it
handling memory and off we go all right
uh so we need the H file for it I
believe although you know what I could
do I could also just let a BMP instead
that's actually you know I like that
idea much better because then I don't
have to deal with any of this stuff I
like that idea a lot better I don't
actually remember
there it is
so if I want to use this load bitmap
call I just need a way to load I just
need to like a BMP right and we can just
make one of those pretty easily that we
can use as a test so all I really need
to do is have a I need some way to do a
read entire file thankfully we have
exactly that as well so these can just
go right on in there and just work I
don't care about secure no warnings at
all what is f open s
why is f open s more secure than regular
F open
what am I missing here yet you know what
no forget you okay
so we want to be able to fill one of
these out here and and we know that we
have the loaded bitmap that I can use
here if I want to so I can just kind of
spam this in here in our test app and
again we're assuming this is not
something that anyone else has to use
this is because this is just something
that it's getting used by the test
program so this is not part of our
render poll we'd have to care if the API
is any good for this at all right so
that's totally fine
see here
we do need the bitmap header this this
right here in order to be able to load
and that has to be after we defined the
types this might be in Windows that H
already so we may be able to just get
rid of that but don't quote me on that
all right so here we can load a bitmap
in and loading in the bitmap will give
us the thing we actually need to slap on
to our texture so I'm gonna put a load
be in peak o'clock here at the outset of
you know when we're running here just so
I can get one of these in and then we'll
go from there so I'm gonna do a load
bitmap call I'm just gonna call this
like win through two renderer test BMP
or maybe I'll call this cube test dot
BMP cube and then what I'm going to do
is there's going to make one of those so
we know that inside our art directory
here right we've got sort of we've got
some of these like weird like things for
doing exactly this so what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna take this one block
orphanage PNG I'm gonna load it into
I'm gonna just size it down
[Music]
fine I'm gonna size it down to just be
like a simple you know 512 by 512 bitmap
or something like that and then I'm
going to export it to a BMP so I'm going
to do an export as I'm gonna go to
handmade data and in here I'm just gonna
put a like probably like a renderer test
directory and I'm just gonna make this
myself cube test dot BMP okay I'm gonna
make it be one of these I'm gonna export
it and then while I'm here just so we
don't have to do it later I'm also gonna
make our cell make us a sprite of some
kind right um so if I go to Krampus
maybe I'm just gonna grab the Krampus
head this right here and what I'm gonna
do is I'm just gonna grab the Krampus
head
and I'm gonna grab it as a 1024 by 1024
actually I don't even need to do that
really let me just do this where's the
crop tool Oh glad they changed all the
icons that looks like crap tool
there we go and now I'm going to scale
it down to like 512 by 512
and I'm just going to clip off that part
go so now we just have also a sprite
because I also want to test putting a
sprite in there you know just just to
make sure things working okay and so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
write that out as well same place so
it's going to be the data renderer test
directory and this is going to be like
you know head test BMP I'm assuming this
will also work yes does look like it
will and that should be all we need
I might call that sprite test instead
maybe I'll call that sprite test so now
if we look we've got a little directory
here that has the stuff in it that we
actually needed what I can do is now set
the run directory on this particular
program to be there so when it runs the
working directory will just be work will
be W handmade data renderer test and
that way now you know in theory if we
just run to that point and load the
texture it should just work right so we
run here this should grab the entire
file and in theory it'll give us you
know back the you know the file by 512
bitmap and it does right so that's all
good
done deal so now what we would like to
do now is make it so that we can submit
these bitmaps to the renderer itself and
have some way that we can
we need to start thinking about how
we're working with these textures right
so we need to think about how that's
going to work we know that the car does
not have unlimited storage we know that
there's a limited amount of texture
space on the card and so what we want to
do is kind of come up with a way of
thinking about and managing that
particular piece of the rendering puzzle
right so there's two fundamental
concerns that we're gonna have going
into this it was time do I have
I got like 30 minutes all right so what
I would like to see here is I'd like to
see us get two things out of this one
I'd like to be able to easily talk about
textures and submit them which shouldn't
be too hard because they're already kind
of doing that fairly easily with the API
as it is but the other thing I want to
do is to start to move towards something
where the size of the texture comes in
one of like three flavors or something
what I mean by that is right now we sort
of have this hodgepodge of every texture
can be whatever size it wants that's not
particularly useful because graphics
hardware wants all textures to be the
same size and when I say that I don't
really mean it
I kind of mean graphics API is want
textures to be the same science honestly
a lot of hardware now could couldn't
care less about that and like if
everything were a general-purpose GPU
like an Nvidia 1080 or whatever you just
wouldn't care because half
to have all your textures be specific
sizes and using handles the set of
pointers into GPU memory and stuff like
that all of that is just because of
old-school limitations that when GPUs
used to not have like real memory and
caches and stuff like this so to a
certain extent I don't really know that
there is that much of a win to having
textures be known sizes like it really
depends on your perspective but in terms
of running on a wide variety of machines
and like phones and
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah
there are old-school power-of-two
texture dimension limitations and want
to be able to use lots of textures of
the same dimension so you can leverage
things like texture arrays and stuff
like that these are actual concerns that
we do sort of care about sort of right
so what I would like to do is I would
like to say let's break our textures
into two types textures that are big
like fancy cutscene huge things and then
like 512 by 512 stuff that's just used
for other things like sprites and
whatever right that's kind of where I
want to see us go because then all of
the things that are rendered in that 512
by 512 block those can all be rendered
as a single batch that just uses a
texturing index to access the texture in
question right that's a huge performance
win for older cards it's even probably a
performance win even on like a fancy
card like the one that's in this machine
because they like least through OpenGL
it's pretty janky unless you use
extensions to talk about texture changes
if use extensions are good to go there's
all kinds of good ways to talk about it
but assuming you're just on the vanilla
version we're on there's really no good
way to do it and so we'll probably get a
significant speed when I would imagine
even just from this or we would if we
were drawing enough things we don't
really draw that many things at the
moment so it's unclear you know that
would be that much you win on a fast
card like this but you know you get the
point so that's kind of where I want to
see us go now what that means is we sort
of need two separate ways of talking
about what we're submitting okay so if
we look at the render commands in the
renderer what you can see is we only
have one push buffer that we put things
on where we say what we're going to be
doing there right and if you look at the
kinds of things that go in to that so if
you look at what you can actually
specify we have textured quads
we have full clear depth clear and the
beginning end peels calls right then
there's the lighting transfer what I
would like to do fundamentally is start
having like the textured quads call say
which one of it it's doing and that way
we can kind of talk about the we can
kind of talk about blocks the textured
quad blocks as being of the fast kind
which is 99% of all the rendering we're
doing or the slow kind and you can't mix
them so when you call textured quads and
you'll have to even even tune calls
right so like we could have our textured
quads here be two kinds one that takes a
render set up a quad count in a vertex
array
and reads out of the bitmap array and
one that actually just takes quads and a
single maybe piece of bitmap information
or something like this I don't know I'm
trying to think about how I want to
structure that
I'm thinking
so here's what I think I would propose I
would suggest maybe we have our render
entry textured quads just takes like a
bitmap size thing so I basically say
like we've got render edge across
there's a bitmap size category that's
for faster or drawing and they maybe we
have a render entry single quad that can
take its own special bitmap pointer for
those are for odd size things that will
go through kind of the slower way that
seems more plausible to me I think
that's what I'd like to see us go
towards I'm gonna go ahead and say let's
hold off on any of that at the moment
anyway
what I want to do here is just go in and
look at the texture op stuff first so
let's get the texture up stuff working
and it'll go from there now the way that
the texture op things work is these
texture ups get issued as a separate
thing that happens out of bands so I
want to look at that in the game proper
I want to look at where we're doing like
texture op allocate and how those are
getting sent down just in general right
so you can see kind of in terms of where
we're calling that
here's like an example of us
adding us up to the texture op queue and
that texture op Q is like is like this
special thing that the platform deals
with its Mew text right so you can push
things on you can like shove things onto
this queue and you know that like
someone will deal with them later right
um so here's where I saying you know I
might want this I won't want mutexes to
be in the shared stuff this is why I was
thinking that we might want to do that
because you may want these things to be
mutex so that background loading will
just will work so I think I'd like to go
ahead and clean me Oh pull this sort of
together now so how is this going to
work well for starters inside handmade
renderer dot cpp this add up call here
this actually can be something that's
shared right when were stood meeting one
of these textures we don't have to know
anything about which renderer we're
using we're just queuing up stuff here
like and everyone can use the same one
as far as I can tell right so I believe
this add up could easily be in here and
this platform texture op q well you know
that's really not a platform texture op
Q per se right it's really a renderer
texture op q you know what I'm saying to
you
so like the Platt the fact it's a
platform texture op Q doesn't really
make a lot of sense it's really not that
it's it's specific to the renderer
nothing to do with the platform layer
actually at all as far as I can tell
right so again if we start pulling this
out and making this into its own sort of
separate thing we then have this sort of
texture op Q thing which is just where
you can queue texture uploads to occur
and you know continue move on from there
this part here is not really where we
want this stuff to be we would rather
the texture op queue in some sense it's
I'm trying to think of how to how to
talk about the texture op queue
I mean in some sense it really just
should be I'm wondering if it may be
really just should be a blind pointer
and maybe everyone does have their own
NQ for that I'm just not sure what I
think about that
I have mixed opinions
what I would say is I almost feel like
we could make the texture up cube be
something that's passed back from the
game as well like if you think about it
you could almost say that the render
commands get the platform texture op
cube passed back in them and it's not
platform-specific
I know it sounds a little weird but I'm
just trying to think to myself so if I
were to do this could this just be
something totally separate from the
platform layer at all and then what
happens is the renderer just ends up
getting this thing later and like it
just gets specified in here you know so
you know when we when you get
like when you get game render commands
I'm just thinking like hey if you know
this could just you could just pass the
pointer to the texture op queue here
that you wanted you could even pass as
many as you wanted you could just say
here's all the cues that I was using and
you know when when the thing goes to do
its rendering it just grabs the ones out
of there that kind of seems good to me
so if we look at texture opt which is
you know which is here if we just say
look here the texture cues to be looking
at you know then they can just be
allocated on the server side I mean on
the game side not on the sort up side I
just don't know if that's right because
the other way is you know we just passed
them you just pass them in right
I'm having trouble coming up with any
argument for either of those
yeah so I really just don't know the
tricky part about it is because it's
called from a separate thread so it's
called from asset loading threads so as
the asset loads complete they're calling
into to do that and the thing that I'm
just not sure about is you know who
should allocate this thing it doesn't
really matter and like I in my head I
just can't come up with that argument
for putting it in any particular place
it seems like it doesn't matter where
you put it it could be anywhere on the
one hand we could allocate it on the
game side of things then you pass it
back in on the other hand we could
allocate in the renderer and then pass
it through to the game I just don't have
a coherent opinion I guess what I'll say
is let's go ahead and continue to
allocate on the platform side of things
I guess because that seems like the
sanest thing to do and what we're gonna
probably end up with here I'm just
guessing is we'll probably Oh
[Music]
I mean another argument would be it
shouldn't really be anywhere and it's
just in the renderer and then you just
the game itself should be the thing that
sticks things in there
that almost sounds better to me on the
other hand that doesn't support overlap
downloads if you want to start them
right away I'm gonna say I'm just
calling it because it's too much
guesswork I really don't know which one
it's going to be I'm just gonna say that
what we want to do here is we want pass
it into the game I'm just gonna say
we're gonna keep it the way it is if you
don't have a good argument for doing
something different then you know then
don't write I mean
I'm gonna call this to render or text
your cue it's gonna look like that for
right now we're gonna deal with we're
gonna deal with it we're gonna deal with
all the fallout from that I'm gonna make
ticket mutex remember I said I wasn't
sure what I want to do there I'm gonna
go ahead and make ticket mutex a part of
the base type system because ticket
mutexes are pretty darn important or at
least having some kind of a ticket mutex
is pretty darn important I guess it
doesn't matter if it's a ticket mutex
ticket mutexes are fine they're not
anything special they're just the one
that we happen to use but you need
something right so let's go ahead and
grab that out here so that we've got our
ticket mutexes and that's going to
require us to also have our Atomics
because we can't do anything without the
Atomics
cut there so let's make sure we've got
all those there's our Atomics and now we
can we can ticket all day long sex to
queue was this just called texture queue
I don't remember what it's called
all right so now we can move on platform
texture up queue texture up queue this
sort of whole situation here I just want
to make sure that this is still sort of
sane at the moment it's allocating this
sort of slightly haphazard way that's
actually probably okay but I want to
clean that up a little bit so here's the
render or texture cube and that's gonna
be done like this
go that way we've got the OP Q created
and then what we've got to do is
actually make sure all this stuff is
okay like so
all right so now let's make sure this is
working at all so let's go back to the
game real quick so for some reason we
did not actually get here's that add up
so texture up cue was set to zero there
Oh duh because we never actually set it
right so what we actually want to do is
once we get this thing we want game
memory a texture cue to equal texture op
cue
so what I want to do here again is kind
of make this be something that's a
little less janky it's pretty janky at
the moment my wheel is stuck there we go
so what I'd like to do is make it so
that anyone who wants to use a texture
queue can use its extra cute more
cleanly this requires a bunch of
special-purpose garbage going on here
which we don't actually want so what I
want to do is I want to make that part
be more sensible and make it so that
it's easier to use right so we're gonna
tackle this in a couple steps the first
thing I want to do is I want to
recognize the fact that allocating and
freeing textures is probably not
something we want to do so before I go
any further down the like how do we set
up the allocate to allocate sort of
stuff what I want to do instead is
switch this over to something which uses
a fixed number of textures so what I
want to do is I want the user at the
outset to say here's how many textures
that are going to be and I'm just going
to talk about those textures right and
then most of the time what you're gonna
do there is you're gonna say well
whatever texture like most of time
they're all going to be like 512 by 512
textures or whatever the fixed size is
for textures but then in certain
circumstances like I said if we want to
have sort of different sized textures
that's fine too right so what I want to
do is get us to a point where we're
talking about those things more sensibly
so imma start by saying let's suppose we
just have a fixed number of textures and
let's get rid of the notion that we're
ever allocating or D allocating a
texture in the first place and let's
pretend the only thing that we do is
just update the data that's in a texture
and that's it okay so what would happen
if we were going to do that
right so in order to do that what we're
gonna do now is say that well in
handmade renderer than the game renderer
commands that we're talking about here
we need one more thing as part of this
which is how many textures there are
right so there's kind of this this
implicit texture limit here that's like
how many textures do you want there to
be right and when you start up the
renderer you kind of need to tell it how
many textures you expect to have and you
know it needs to create that may
textures for you right you need to be
able to talk about that many textures
and I want those to be things where you
talk specifically about maybe how many
of each type of texture like I kinda
want to say how many 512 by 512 textures
are you gonna have how many you know
arbitrary size textures you're gonna
have something like that right
and so I don't really have much more to
say about it other than that's really
what we're talking about here is having
those sort of having those sort of
striations so I kind of need a thing
that's like renderer texture group and I
need to talk about a renderer texture
group as being something which has like
a texture count set by the user how many
of these do you want then a texture
dimension which is to say like how big
is it
width and height right and finally I
trying to think if I need anything in
here to identify I don't think so I
think I wanted to say here's the number
of texture groups there are and here
they are right
yeah I mean I think that's really all I
all I really cared about was that um
so I can't think of anything else we
really need to do there so I'm gonna go
ahead and say that's what we've got and
so in the game render settings I'm just
gonna say we've got a texture cube count
and then we've got a renderer texture
group that are the texture groups and
that's what the renderer will expect to
see meaning when you do that it will
allocate textures that follow that
pattern right and the only thing that I
don't know about is how we want to deal
with textures that are arbitrary
dimension maybe we just don't ever want
those maybe we just force it to have all
textures have to have a size and they
have to fall into one of our group sets
I'm kind of tempted to say that you have
to do that and then we just have a
texture group that's like you know for
the cutscenes it's like fine if we have
to do a 2048 by like 1024 it's only 8
megabytes a graphics card memory to
store that if we have 64 of those and
that's pretty big though
so I don't know I mean maybe what I'd
say is maybe we just forced the cutscene
to be scaled attention everywhere
attention for I'd rather just make that
clean you could actually still do them
at 2048 by 2048 or something if you want
or 1024 by 1024 or something like this
cuz hey when you page them in you page
them in and then you can page them out
when you need them again you know and
it's not the end of the world so ice
I suppose that's fine and I think it
would be nice to be able to just say
everything goes into a group
yeah I don't know it's a tough call it's
a really tough call we're down to the
five-minute warning here where are we
compiling okay so that's really the
thing that will probably pick up on
tomorrow is how we're gonna start doing
those texture groups but what I'd like
to do is I'd like to get the texture
apps down to somewhere we don't allocate
and deallocate right we just say update
this texture and it's always just a
standing store of like here's all the
texture space that you have update this
texture right so I'd like to keep it in
that way I think we're probably gonna
want to do something where this stuff
gets a little bit more explicit as well
so I'm thinking maybe we've got a thing
that's like this
I'm thinking we maybe have something
like this don't quote me on that but
seems like sort of the right thing to do
and furthermore I suspect we might even
do something like say that actually max
push buffer sizes service everything but
we might say something like this where
we actually go and say look all of the
stuff that you do it sorts into the
texture group that it's going to go to
so that we only issue one render call
protects your group so that we get it to
a you know let's say there's 64 by 64
textures 512 by 512 textures and 1024 by
1024 textures or something like that
right then we just have three draw calls
per depth peel right and we don't ever
do any of the like texture changes or
any of that stuff because we can issue
those demo on a batch I have some merit
to it he's perfect probably not I don't
know but some think about so I'm gonna
go ahead and call it for today we've
done a pretty good job I think so far
pulling that out we got it rendering and
running so now we're just got to improve
it which is not a huge deal I'll go
ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
hmm how would you approach front-to-back
rendering well if you have to render
front to back then you have to sort
right I'm not sure what you're actually
asking like do you mean how would you
approach being able how would you
approach having the game send down the
sprites in front to back order is that
the question
so the answer is we already did that on
handmade hero you can go look at it we
had a thing that would sort sprites and
you could sort them in either order
front to back or back to front and what
I found is it just is not very nice to
have to sort sprites because you can't
do any sort of complex 3d placement of
them become it be if you have a sprite
that should be like in front of one
thing but in behind another it creates
these like weird cycles and you end up
with painter algorithm badness so I
found having a z-buffer was just much
nicer so we don't do that anymore but
that's what we used to do make it to 97
is including a CPP file generally a bad
idea no it's so at the risk of stating
the obvious CPP and H are just names you
give to files
that allow you to organize them however
you want a dot CPP file in a doubt hfl
are exactly the same the compiler does
not care about the difference between
those two things at all right so
including CPP files and other cv files
is just an easier way than having a make
file that has all these things listed on
like a build line right
so rather than to having a thing that's
like link all d cv files together we
just include all our cv files and that
way you're done you don't have to have a
separate build you don't have to have
any of that stuff
it all kind of is just nice and clean
right so including cv files is great
it's definitely not a bad idea it's a
great idea it's probably one of the best
ideas in terms of how to do builds but
you don't have to do it because like I
said su v--'s and HS doesn't matter as
long as all the code gets been powered
whatever works
is it possible to make very attic
functions in C when compiling without
Lib C sure yeah what you have to do is
you have to let me show you
so if you look at VAR s it's called
varargs now I don't really remember yeah
if you look at what happens it's just
you need like you know how we have a
platform-specific switch that says so we
know which kind of atomic to call right
you need to be the same thing for your
VAR args so when you talk about like V a
start right you just need to go look and
you can see how it works it's very
straightforward
it's actually just when you finally get
down to it here yeah it's actually just
a thing that uses the address of the
thing on the stack to find out where on
the stack the first argument after it
would be and then each time you peel off
an arc
it just advances by whatever the size of
the thing would be for that type of
argument why because in size of is the
thing that says look if this thing is
smaller than integer then it's an
integer size if it's bigger than an
integer then it is bigger than the
integer size right but it's it's the
thing that says that the there are
calling convention in C is that you
never pass cares or shorts as vert arcs
you always passed integers right so if
you actually have a very odd function
that puts those things on there that are
cares or shorts you need to instead of
moving down that size in the stack to
read what to read each one you need to
move down by a full integer so that's
what in size of does and so you have to
also do that like you need your own
version of this macro but if you just
cut and pasted these into your code on
x64 you will just work because that's
the calling convention for ver args done
right
but he only works on x64
you need to have like I said a thing
that cracks out what platform you're on
and then uses the correct calling
convention now it may be that this
correct this is the correct decryption
of the stack in terms of memory it could
be that this is correct for all the
platform's you care about in which case
you're done but you may have other like
if you want to run on both x86 and x64
for example this is not the same I'm
pretty I seem to remember it's been a
long time I see remember the x86 version
was different I think don't quote me on
that but I'm pretty sure it was so yeah
Oh in fact is this the are we compiling
us in 32-bit mode or something is this
the actual execute for code and maybe
this is the x86 code and this is the x4
because this is our little test project
here let me just let me just see if I
can make that happen yeah yeah so so I'm
I'm definitely correct it's different
this is the x86 version that was why I
was a little confused I was like but
that looks like the accessory this is
the x64 version so if I change my build
configuration right you see how that
comes in so this is the version for x64
and so that again that's just because of
whatever the VAR args calling convention
is you have to do the opposite of that
to peel the things off the stack it's
stupid right it's it should have been
part of the compiler as a first-class
citizen because the compiler is the
person who knows what it decided to do
for stack layout and just because it
happens to be a standard doesn't seem
like a good reason to make the library
do it it's just it's just dumb but
that's how they did it
and so was pointing out that including
Viraj that h doesn't pull in Lipsy yeah
so if you don't mind using the C runtime
libraries headers and you just don't
want to use this here in house code you
can you don't even have to cut and paste
it you could just include it and use it
but assuming that you want to get rid of
the CRT entirely like even the include
files then you have to like make your
own versions of those macros but that's
it why would the person you are helping
not want to use a game engine if they're
not experiencing 3d programming um so
they are hmm they are somebody who has
made many game engines themselves and
knows what they are doing and probably
would not think that that game engine
was very good for all of the other
things that they do and so they don't
want a game engine
they just want a renderer and of course
things like unity and unreal are so
god-awful unwieldy gigantic unusable in
terms of like you could never just use
the renderer from them like forget it
right you'd be able to learn 3d graphics
and write your own by the time you'd
ever make that be a same process right
so that's mainly the problem right the
person just wants to have a simple 3d
renderer they can graft on to their
existing engine that already does
everything else including run the basic
game that they wanted to make in the
first place in 2d is like done so
they've got it all right they just don't
know enough 3d math to do the basic 3d
render and they're not looking for
anything special they just want like
handmade hero style I've got some cubes
I've got some sprites on the cubes kind
of thing so you know you can understand
why they don't want to take the hit of
going to some big blue
thing that's not going to work the way
they want just for that one piece of the
game engine when they've written
everything else and want it the way they
want it you know if that makes sense
Microsoft kind of knew the stream but
did you do any sort of batch rendering
like rendering once by sword storing
into a texture I'm not sure what you
mean by rendering once by storing in
texture do you mean like batch rendering
in that you know and I have no idea why
would you store it into a texture do you
mean like just batch rendering like put
instance lists into a buffer and then
queue the buffer because I'm not sure
what you mean by storing it into a
texture because that would be a weird
place to store batch information I would
think I'm not sure why you would use a
texture for batch information you know
it's just yeah I don't know why you
would need to do that is there a reason
you would need to put it in a texture
the queue 297 does the current renderer
support arbitrary meshes or shaders no
no no it this is not that kind of a
renderer right this is a renderer for a
specific purpose it so I guess it does
technically support arbitrary meshes
it's definitely not does it doesn't
support arbitrary shaders though that
make sense this is not supposed to
really have meshes at all it's supposed
to be sprites but we support a special
case of a sprite which is a cube shape
like a if that make sense
when the texture is sent to the GPU is
it a one-to-one size ratio or does it
get compressed it's one-to-one at the
moment
do you notice the stream went down for a
minute around minute 45 dream I didn't
really it didn't that might have just
been a twitch blip or an Internet thing
I'm not sure it wasn't before we had a
problem our OBS actually crashed and I
had to restart it that did not happen
this time so everything was fine on this
end which was good
thoughts on a simple handmade obs
yeah I mean I guess I have some thoughts
on it
[Music]
maybe like lock it to one particular
type of hardware and just use hardware
encoding like Nvidia chips can just do
mp4 encoding so you could just like say
look this only runs in Nvidia the main
thrust of the program is like grab the
webcam stuff off of the web off of the
USB I dump that and I let Nvidia encode
it any other thing and then I send it
out right you could do something like
that I don't know but it's gonna be
nasty whatever you do because just
dealing with hardware like that it's
always super janky like just it's just
janky
with the technosystem solve our binding
texture timing I don't know what that
means what do you mean by binding
texture timing where do you buy your
cool hats I don't really have cool hats
the pig hat was given to me as a gift I
I don't really have any other hats
stupid question but whether everybody
needed to use compute shaders in the
game are we staying away from that cell
you've had we are staying away from that
just as being out of the scope of the
series
I'm sure you could come up with reasons
to use it if you were looking for them
we don't need to do it though and we're
that's too far afield Velva says I mean
the time spent in geo bind texture yes
this will solve our texture binding
problem which I really want to fix
because that's the only like slow part
of our renderer now really like most of
the rest of the renderer stuff is fine
it's all good like it's you know it's
it's not hyper optimized or anything but
it's totally fine texture bind per quod
is totally not ok and is just always
going to be a problem for the moment and
so so I feel like that is really we want
to fix that in this pass because that's
annoying and it should be fixed and so
we should figure out a good way to do it
and I and I'm going to probably try to
do that tomorrow can we get another
Lemongrab impersonation for my
compilation yes I can you can so what I
really need is I need in addition to
Lemongrab I need to get do they have a
soft Lemongrab because I know that like
like this is regular Lemongrab not soft
Lemongrab soft Lemongrab has a white
is has a white suit and regular lemon
like original Lemongrab has the grey
suit and so it would be kind of useful
to have a soft Lemongrab because a lot
of the interesting scenes have like soft
Lemongrab and Lemongrab together so the
problem is I have to think about like
what would be a good what would be a
good scene that just has regular
Lemongrab and no soft Lemongrab that I
can quote so like I already did the one
with that's why I am royal and you are
servile I already did this codebase is
in unacceptable condition
you know I guess I'm gonna have to take
it back I don't know what other
lemongrab impersonations I can do that
don't have I guess I don't know what
other ones I can do that don't have soft
Lemongrab you know I kind of want to do
like the one where they play with little
lemonsweets a little lemonsweets some so
precious have you enjoyed sitting in
your chair what would you like to do now
go to board no he wants to dance
oh dear brother I really think either
the lemonsweets would rather go to bed
see I need the other one here I'll fetch
our sauna sleeping bonnet beautiful like
you know it just doesn't work with the
other just doesn't work without the soft
Lemongrab so I kind of need a soft
Lemongrab I think 12 years dungeon seven
years no trials come on let's go my
voice is kind of hoarse
why do you change the visual studio
editor I didn't change to the visual
studio editor I use for coder for my
editing as always they maybe had to
handle different texture when using
instancing rendering pack called
textures into array and write a custom
sampler yeah packing into a texture
raise a good plan it really depends on
what platforms are trying to support so
I if you're on like a platform that you
actually have some access to you can
also just use texture pointers and those
just work like for example if you didn't
care if you're just on nvidia you could
just use texture pointers and you can
actually just put the texture pointer
directly into the actual shader like
straight in as just as just stuff that
gets streamed in from a vertex buffer
like that's how direct it is right so
it's really just this stupid old notion
that textures are special and that
they're not just addresses that's
causing the whole thing but yeah I mean
at the moment you kinda have to deal
with it why do your function signatures
use the internal keyword that's just
static I don't like to use static
because static has two different
meanings and you can't search them so I
just redefined internal to be static so
like and I put that to make sure
everything uses it do you know if dx12
is going to be needed for making use of
the new hardware ray tracing stuff what
alternatives exist and is it going to be
worth it I that is all I I really don't
know what I can't tell you is I'm sure
that dx12 will not be the only way to
access it because hardware vendors are
going to want you to use it everywhere
because it's slow and requires a lot of
computation power and so they want you
to call it everywhere so people will
have to buy new graphics cards that it's
in their best interest to make sure
everyone can use it so I don't think it
will be DirectX 12 only
but on Windows will they back port it to
D through the 11 that I don't know
so will it only be accessible from
OpenGL and DirectX 12 maybe maybe it
won't be accessible from dx11 I'm not
sure that I couldn't tell you but I'm
sure it will be in metal I think it
already is actually and on Linux I would
assume that it will be it that it's
gonna be available on OpenGL and Vulcan
but yeah I don't know about d3 d11
they define version of a trail so ah
well but that's good so if you can't
include the stl in along with any of our
code that's good because the STL is
garbage and should never be used for any
purpose at any time so I would it would
be my very fondest hope that you can
literally never mix STL code and
handmade Hiro code because like I don't
want STL code anywhere near my code base
or anything that could even be
considered to resemble my code base or
that uses my code in it the STL is like
the worst thing
what's wrong with us Yale literally
everything I don't even know where to
start I like literally every single
thing you could do wrong they did wrong
I easier to list the things that they
did right which which would also be an
empty page probably I mean it's just a
disaster now to be fair I don't want to
keep all the blame on the people who
design the STL C++ is not a good
language for generic programming it's a
lousy language for the generic
programming so some of the things that
are wrong with the STL are because C++
is not a very good Lannister genetic
programming and some of them are because
they have C++ has added features since
the STL was architected that would have
made it potentially easier to architect
the STL to be less bad right so it's
kind of both things C++ is a bad generic
language and Eric's even the things that
it does have now for generics it didn't
always have and the STL was a bad
architecture even given that so it was
just it's like everything is wrong like
look everything I I it's totally not
what you would ever want for generic
programming at all I mean you can start
with basic things like it doesn't do
invasive lists and stuff like that like
like really basic stuff you want with
generic programming it can't do but it's
like everything like the way the new
iteration is wrong the the choices they
made with how you have to specify
iterators is wrong the way they had you
be able to set up memory allocation is
wrong
I mean it's there's nothing good about
it I can't stress that enough
look at any other generic library
instead like it's it's the STL is the
like the bottom of the barrel as far as
I'm concerned right
and I include em think like I would also
include like I don't know if standard
string is included in STL technic like I
don't know what STL is umbrella typing
clothes but standard string is also
absolutely horrible so like don't use
any STL like list map vector those are
all horrible and just the architecture
there is bad
don't use standard string that
architecture is bad like all of those
things are really bad and never use them
for any reason they're just horrible but
I don't know like I don't remember what
all other things are in the STL like
what the I'm trying to think there's
anything in the STL that's not horrible
and I can't really think of anything
yeah sorry if I call her invasive list
intrusive list that's what I meant to
say everything should sue a good way to
tell if your generic system is actually
generic is to see whether the person
who's using it can inject it inside one
of their own existing things if they
can't forget it you're done I don't I
don't ever want to hear another word
from you ever again cuz you're not
generic you're a joke at that point so
like that stuff is pretty sensitive for
me like I generate means I can target
this however I want and I can make sure
that it works the way that I want it to
work and the SDL is not that thing right
all right
I'm gonna close down shop I do think a
lot of the things so one thing that is
nice is since they added like Auto the
STL like using it now like if you can
use Auto it makes it way better than it
used to be it stills awful but using STL
without Auto is insane like it's so bad
it makes all of your iterators
completely brittle and it's it's just
horrible so Auto at least got it a
little bit better but you know back
before Auto it was like oh my god like
it's just I I don't even know how they
thought this was acceptable it's it's
just crazy to think about that they
thought this was like a good thing
anyway thank you for joining me for this
sort of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow us series at
home become a spear to the game on
handmade hero org and it comes the
source code so you can play around with
it we also have a watch page you can use
to watch it's streaming on there right
now it also has the schedule so if we're
not lied we'll tell you when we're gonna
be live it also has an episode guide you
can use to catch up on the series I
highly recommend checking that out so if
you have questions you can just search
for where I've answered them already
it's a pretty handy tool we also have
the handmade fun page that's if you're
interested in helping fund projects like
the episode guide or like the forums
that are hosted at handmade Network if
there's explanations of what it is on
there if you're feeling generous and you
want to donate to some of those projects
you can always do it I'll do the
handmade fund and finally if you want it
what else we're up trip Molly rocket you
can always check it out by clicking on
the handmade here ahead these are the
rest of our pages here you can go check
out as well as my blog and other stuff
that's it for today I'll be back here
tomorrow when we will see what we can do
about the texture situation I think
that's the last major piece that I kind
of really want to play with there once
that's done we can focus more on just
cleaning up the API and pulling things
out into useful pieces that you're
useful like helper functions
but we're pretty good so I think we're
in good shape and I'm happy with how
that went that's it for today see
everyone tomorrow take it easy and I'll
see you on the Internet