hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream we are going to do some I
guess sort of file translation and slash
testing today we want to get our game
packages building from a text file spec
that we have implemented and probably
sort of mostly at this point parsed but
we have some additional concerns we want
to address here and I'm gonna go ahead
and start addressing let me show you
what I'm talking about for those of you
who don't necessarily quite remember
okay
I don't know why I just loaded handmade
array probably because I wasn't paying
very close attention so let's go ahead
and do our compiler our compile here and
I'll show you what I'm talking about it
looks like we left it in a compiling
state although we weren't quite finished
with one of the things so let's go ahead
and jump in here so what we wanted to do
is and what we've been working on for
the past this past weekend and this
weekend is we've got these hht files
there in the handmade tags directory and
you've got bass game 2 h-e-a-t and intro
cutscene that it should see or the -
once we defined can see in here there
basis a text file format that just
describes a packing list and all of the
mark-up that we need for our files so it
says for every given file that that
artist may have provided us what the
additional information that the artist
didn't provide was and that's mainly the
thing we need them for otherwise we
could just take all the things in the
directory and just gobble them up right
so again we just really wanted some way
of cleanly saying look there's tons of
information that we're maybe gonna have
to add here the very least there's tags
but then there's also alignment points
we need somewhere to store that this is
where we're gonna store it and so we've
got this this format here what we want
to do is we want to be able to load this
produce a result from it so we want to
be able to like produce a packed game
from it but then we also want to have a
system for doing edits in the game and
reflecting them back out so re saving
those edits to the tech
file not just our binary format we want
them reflected in the binary format as
well because we want them to have be
live and like when we run we want them
to just be there and we don't want have
to rebuild our binary or something like
that every time we make a small change
so what we've got working now is good
and we don't really want to fuss with it
we just want to add this additional
layer of having a text file backing
store so that we know we can always
rebuild the whole package with just PNG
s in the text and not needing this
special-purpose binary format that we're
running with because it's just some
hacky format we designed it's not you
know the kind of thing that that's
designed to be a standard file
interchange format like PNG and text
right again that's a decision we're
making because we're a small game we're
not like a huge city or something it's
totally reasonable to do a big binary
format that you're going to like to
maintain and that's gonna be your format
going forward you can do that it's just
that's a bigger investment and it's
probably not super appropriate for our
particular scenario and like with
anything else you've got to choose the
thing that's appropriate for what you're
doing at the given time so this seemed
like the easiest way for us to get what
we need and so that's what we're going
to be working with now inside our actual
code we're sort of in the middle of it
here and we have this concept called
parsed top-level block and that's really
what we kind of need to work with now to
make sure that this actually goes well
also by the way just so you know I guess
I didn't mention Molly is with us today
hello Molly how are you doing it's a
good good kitten yes you want to look
out the window window she was sleeping
so I had the window closed but I'm gonna
go ahead and open the window in case she
likes to watch the birds outside okay so
when we go to parse top level block what
we need to do is we need to have this
code do two things that it's not doing
right now the first one is we need to
actually create that awareness that I'm
talking
about where the top level block parser
is able to you know put data back into
the text file or at least know when it
needs to do that sort of an operation
and then the other thing we need to do
is actually implement the thing that is
moving code from the text file when
we're rewriting it into a new text file
right because what we want to be able to
do like I said before is do an export
that basically rewrites the text file as
it was so it's supposed to look roughly
the same as when we you know you know in
import it could be the first time but we
want to add any changes that have been
made so if you lo the hht you do some
mucking about with the alignment points
I then want to be able to insert those
alignment points back in and so that's
really what we're trying to do here and
remember that's you know because if you
if you jump back in here and take a look
at the game running the way that we want
to do this was we want to be able to you
know have in this so you know if this is
the game that's running we want to be
able to switch to our editor here that
can edit stuff like alignment points we
want to be able to pick you know what
we're looking at and grab you know any
sort of information that we change here
put it back to the text file so if we
add like an alignment point like this
right and we want that to be saved
you know and we did pick you know what
you know what it means whatever all that
stuff we need that to be savable so then
when we go back here and have our little
Save or sit or import and save buttons
right when we click that Save button
that's when we want to write that new
hht file now we know that the overwrite
our old hht file we can make a new one
and then the user could choose whether
they want to keep it or not
right so it also gives us an extra level
of sort of like security there where we
can create a new hht file and then the
the user could like diff the two and
verify that the changes that you made
during edits actually were changes that
they wanted right and that their that
they
didn't like make some changes they
forgot about that they actually want to
revert or whatever so it also can
provide us with an extra layer of sort
of assurance there that we didn't
accidentally save an edit that we didn't
mean to or things like that so there's a
bunch of stuff we could do in that
regard even if we save it over the
existing file even that still provides
us a layer of security which is that if
we assume that we're checking these
things into source code control at least
daily then you at least can see the
changes you made relative to like
yesterday's you know hht or something
like that right so I feel like that's
you know an important thing to
understand about the way this process is
going to work okay so assuming that
we're doing that when we're in here in
parse top level block what we need to do
is start by you know thinking about this
copy all input up to an including we
need that to be implemented and what
that's gonna do is that's gonna take the
existing text so as we sort of troll
through this that's gonna take the
existing text and move it from the old
file to the new file right so it's gonna
just copy text over as we confirm each
line of text is okay we can just copy it
over right and that's you know one thing
we want to do the other thing we want to
do is then when we come in here we need
to have some understanding of when to
add things that we saw that or sorry
things that we didn't see that we have
added or things like that that's
something a place where we need to to
add into the text file new things that
maybe weren't specified in the text file
at all right okay so let's take a look
at how we might do this there's a couple
of different things we can do here but
if you take a look at the way this code
is working what we're essentially doing
is going over this parsing loop and
every time we parse something what we're
going to do is just copy it to the
output you can see us doing that there
at the moment you cannot edit tags hhas
names descriptions or authors inside the
game those are not things that we have
an editor for so at least at the moment
we don't actually have to do any work
for those
we can simply copy them that's the
beginning and end of the work that we
would have to do right however when we
get to the alignment points the
alignment points are not that way the
alignment points actually do need that
information they need to have something
in there which tells them exactly which
ones we should write and which ones we
shouldn't so when we read in these
alignment points we have two things we
can do first of all we could look and
see for any given alignment point does
it match the one that we currently have
and if it does copy that
lying in right or we could just eat all
the alignment point lines and always
rewrite them with the ones that we have
right in the case of rewriting if we're
actually doing the import then we don't
want to do that we want to overwrite our
versions with the new versions right but
assuming we're doing a save like
assuming this is a save operation and so
that's kind of difficult and the reason
we might want to do it one way or the
other way depends largely on how closely
we're trying to mimic the input if we
want to keep the exact thing that the
user typed in in the case where it
hasn't changed that's one kind of way
that we might want this to go I'm going
to try going the whole nine here you
know I mean I don't pretend that this is
necessarily a good idea but let's just
see what happens if we work I'm gonna
have a thing here called a line point
written and I'm just gonna keep a
boolean that's the exact same size as as
this array of alignment points here
right so I'm gonna I'm gonna keep that
updated right and when we're doing our
reads I'm going to remember whether or
not we wrote one of these out or not
right okay so that's one thing that we
want to do and that will help me if I if
I need to understand exactly what's
going on there but as you can kind of
see we still have a little bit more work
to do
before like reorganized routine a little
bit around one particularly nefarious
thing and what that is here in the
alignment it's the first time that
we have to actually specify a sublevel
of of specificity for an import so if we
import a body like the hero's body for
example there's multiple frames in a
single PNG it's got like you know a
Dodge left maybe or it's got you know
facing left facing up facing right you
know it's got different angles of
artwork baked into that one PNG file so
what I think we want to do here is we'd
like to sort of move past where we're at
the moment where we have to sort of do
all of that in one sort of baked pass
what I'd like to do is I'd like to get
the information about that sublevel of
of how the block will actually get
processed whether it's a body a head
plate block I'd like to get that before
we do our parsing now normally I just do
it after like I was doing before but in
this case the problem is I need to be
able to rewrite those text lines as I
see them because if I don't do that I
can't preserve all the comments and
stuff right and so that's really what's
going on here so I want to be able to
kind of do that part of it all right so
let's let's try and mutate this code a
few times and get a little further down
that path so if you look at what's going
on here you can see that a bunch of the
things that we're doing like get our
create asset source file those things
could have been done earlier and they
should be done earlier probably right
and so what I want to be able to do is I
want to be able to well I get you know
what here's the thing there is one way
that that might not be true this is
tough so one reason that might not be
true is if a particular if a particular
asset can be targeted to a specific HHA
that would would change it because then
we really don't even know where we would
look for this particular
for this particular packing order which
is not necessarily the end of the world
I mean we could always pre-process it
but here's I'm gonna say for our benefit
I'm gonna go ahead and remove this I'm
gonna say we don't have an HHA field so
we'll just say that the text file and
the HHA have to match right another way
we could do it is just say that the HHA
has to appear in some kind of
system-wide way so you know it could
have to appear at the top of this thing
that's another way to do it but I think
I'm gonna go with the simpler thing that
just says the text file and the HHA have
to be together maybe because that will
just simplify our lives a little bit
here and it will make it so that we
always know that text and Agent J are
paired and there isn't a lot of fine
grain switching that could happen so
let's just say that that's the case
and assuming that's the case then what
we can do is now pop up here and that'll
also solve this problem for us in this
case so for example what we can do is we
can grab this pretty much everything
down to here right and we can start to
move it up so when we come through this
particular part of the code where we do
like you know this open brace once we
have that open brace we can then do some
work on this this is not really super
necessary at this point so this is
probably not something we actually want
to do in fact I may want to keep that
here but you know we at least want this
right so what I probably want to do here
is is put that is default you know down
at a part where you know before we would
actually be doing any kind of actual
processing of the file so somewhere in
here probably you know we'd also have
have that so I'm gonna leave that part
right there but what I want to do here
say okay the temporary memory stuff you
know that's actually something that we
just have out here right we can do the
beginning temper
temporary memory part sort of at the
beginning of the top of a block and I'll
put the end temporary memory at the end
of the block because there's not a lot
of reason not to right so we'll just
leave it like this and then as I come
through here let's take a look at what
we want to do so if this is not the
default then what I'd like to do is acne
I don't need this parse pieces cause
actually happening in there I'd like to
keep this part happening based of the
way it is right now
I want the HHA to be in there this is
not gonna be in the fields part of
things this is actually gonna be in the
context now so this is like the HHA
filename we're talking about here this
will produce the full asset name we can
then see if that file actually exists
you know and assuming that it does we
can then create a match for it right and
if we get that match then we can do the
the additional work here of testing to
see whether it's been modified once we
have that we can actually do our check
to see if we want to do parse pieces
that can happen right here
and then we can proceed with this the
rest of it later on so I think that's
where I want to be at the start so I
want something that looks kind of like
this I probably want this to be here so
this will be like an import type and
that'll be like import none probably and
we'll get that here like so and then we
can we can kind of grab and we don't
really want that we would probably want
this right to happen outside so like
this right so again just doing the first
part of this we get all of that
information up front so now we have like
our tags array our import type and you
know all that sort of stuff and the
problem that we'll have there is the
append tags that part is happening
inside parse pieces again I'm gonna
start to pull that out because it gets
creating too much rigidity there for the
way we want to do things so then we go
through our parsing here ramp and
remember I sort of got loaded in here
this
we're gonna do the the import type check
so we're still gonna do that but anyway
we come through here we're gonna do
where we've got you know parsing of
alignment points and so on and then we
get when we get to the end here is when
we're actually going to start doing some
some more of this this work so we'll it
reinstitute this check to make sure if
we have errors so far then just don't
bother doing any imports because we know
that this was a busted text file right
and so we don't want that occurring so
here we have our import check assuming
that we actually have an import that
we're going to actually do then we can
do the work of actually you know
creating it right now this import type
equals import type none part of things I
guess what I want to say there too is
that may be something that really should
just create an error so when we come
through here you know I think maybe we
want to do and I guess one way to do
that would be you know to keep it within
this block well I guess we don't really
do that we could just do it up here we
could just say look when we create one
of these things and we look and see if
we've got the default or not right we
could just say if it's not the default
we're gonna go in here and do a parse
pieces on the import type and right
there if the import type doesn't come
back with something valid so if it's
none we will do an error so that we know
on that block token report the error
that we don't understand what this thing
is supposed to be right look we just
don't even know what it's supposed to be
furthermore these things here should
also have their errors associated with
them I don't know if we had errors here
yeah like we had unrecognized block type
and file not found so we want to keep
these errors we want to just move them
to where they are now actually occurring
so let me just grab those and bring them
up here so again what we want to do is
say in here unrecognized block type is
going to be right here right and file
info is going to be here right so we
want something
we want something looks sort of like
this we're still not quite done you can
see this file info file date stuff
that's checking to see whether we need
to re-import this I again that's sort of
a thing that just says whether we need
to re-import the PNG itself but it
doesn't really tell us much else so
that's actually something we're not
going to be doing this way anymore
it's just an out of date check and so
what we really need now is this concept
that do we need to rebuild the asset
right so we can just say like look is
this asset dirty or not you know is it
something that needs to be rebuilt
another way to say that would be like
needs are rebuild right and so we can
say here whether or not it needs to be
rebuild or not and what we can do is say
we default to the fact that it doesn't
but in the case that these things don't
match then it least needs a rebuild in
that case so if someone changes the PNG
but then we also need a way to rebuild
it if other things don't match such as
if you change the tags right now when
we're actually looking at this we
probably want to keep two states we
probably want to say is the art dirty or
just the the metadata right so we would
need like a needs full rebuild and it
needs meta rebuild in the case where the
actual PNG is changed that's a full
rebuild right we need to it reinforce
the whole thing right but if this if
it's if that's not the case right if we
just have a situation you know what I
could also can do this let's do it this
way keep this a little cleaner here
all right so now you can see this
starting to come together
the only issue we've got right now is
the append tags here it's not actually
something that we know yet and so we
kind of need to put that down here and
we need to stop passing it in so we need
something that looks a little bit more
like that and so we we kind of have to
reverse the way in which we were doing
some of that tag appending kind of work
and so we'll take a look at how we're
gonna do that a little bit later but you
get the idea so in here we do our parse
pieces this is the thing that will let
us know exactly what everything was
supposed to be and when we do get our
create asset source file we can also now
know what the tags were for any given
thing so now we have some way that we
can actually differentiate between these
two things I started to think about them
okay so now we get down to the actual
parsing you can see here we've got our
append text we'll fill that out later
and that's the thing we're gonna have to
reverse from the parse pieces because
parse pieces would weld those two things
together and that's not gonna work now
so what we want to do here is just sort
of now proof this routine so as we read
through here again most of these things
are fine because we're gonna get all of
these fields and we're gonna parts get
the tag list out and all that sort of
stuff we're gonna parse the alignment
points and any time we see an alignment
point we also now have the option of
updating it or not so we have the
information we need so we'll look at how
we're gonna do that in a minute but
after we get done with all of that stuff
and we see the final semicolon then we
can actually look and say did everything
work if it did work let's go ahead and
assign the default fields if this was a
default if not let's go ahead and
process it as an actual art asset now
this data for alignment points and
alignment points written that obviously
should go up here because that's
happening as part of this parse so we
want that up at the top there and in
here this is where we actually do our
updates now as you can see we've got
different ways that we might want to do
these updates and that's why I say we
kind of want to break these processes
apart a little bit rather than having
the tags well and in there I think we
want to do the tags as a separate kind
of a write and the process tile imports
all that stuff we need to start doing
these as a little bit more striated
right we need to kind of think about
this a little bit more specifically so
what we want to do is first say all
right we need to break this into two
parts we need to break it into one part
that actually just takes the PNG and and
get the data out and that's when we need
it if we need to do a full rebuild right
and then we need another part that says
look if all we were doing is just
updating the tags of this thing so we
don't actually need to reread the PNG
don't do that work because remember
reading the PNG can be very expensive
these are big high resolution files we
actually do pressing on the pixels
that's a lot heavier weight than just a
simple update that says add this one tag
so if we wanted to add a tag to like a
hundred things we don't want to repress
a hundred PNG s for no reason that's
just dumb because we know which one
we're doing we might as well do it
correctly so if we need to do needs full
rebuild then we're going to go through
this whole situation where we actually
do the entire update so we update the
date and the checksum this contents and
all that sort of stuff
parse the PNG do what we need to do
right and that part is the part that we
actually need in terms of of doing the
processing the multi tile import and all
that sort of stuff the problem is as you
can see that will also update things
like tags fields and so on which we
don't really actually need to do and so
we kind of want to separate these two
things out into like almost like a the
import of the PNG and then like a
stamping process which like goes through
and then like updates the tags in
anything that it would need to update
the tags for and so as hairy as that is
I think that is what we actually want to
do and so although you know we got this
HHA appended next that we stuck on the
info I think we want to do now is kind
of like say yeah sorry oops about that
not really what we wanted to do take
this info and the tags get that off of
there right so that's not going to be
on there anymore right this stuff is not
gonna get past anymore and so what we're
gonna do with the multi tile single tile
and plate imports is we're just gonna
that's just gonna import the it's
strictly going to import the the image
data and it's not gonna touch anything
else right okay we still need this part
the append HHA index the get or create
by stem indexing sort of thing right and
that getter create by stem part of
things that's actually going to want to
happen yeah in either case so if we need
to do a full rebuild or if we need to do
a partial rebuild but we're gonna want
to do that and so what we can do here we
just say look actually this info thing
that's actually part of the partial
rebuild so like if needs meto rebuild or
whatever that can go down here let me
just verify that I've got that that's
the if needs full rebuild oh hey look my
little scope thing even told me that
right you can see right here if needs
full rebuild anyway that goes into the
the meta built part and what we want to
do here is have this append HH 8 index
that's actually just going to be
something that we use to talk about as
we flow through the system so I don't
know if you want to pass the HH 8 index
or not I suspect we probably just do so
in here we're gonna replace that stuff
with when it flows down the pipe is
gonna actually just be here's the HH a
to write this to go nuts we're not gonna
talk about anything else right off we go
so that's what I want to do here and
again this is going to be the context
HHO that we're talking about and so this
is not going to be that at all
this is going to be that to do oops I
didn't cut and paste that to do there
again um and so that's part one right
part two is if we need a meta rebuild
and the meta rebuild will happen if we
do a full
build as well so basically what we want
to say is look if we need if you need a
full rebuild we're gonna stamp things
it's free - anyway you might as well and
there might have been new tiles added
because maybe someone filled in a grid
square that they didn't previous do
right the needs Metairie building needs
full rebuild those two things regardless
of which one gets set we're always going
to re stamp so it's just a PNG part
that's going to not happen in the case
where we only need to update like tags
or author information or something like
that so what I want to do now is say
okay in that case now we've got a thing
that just says look we're gonna stamp or
stemp I guess this case may be we're
gonna stamp this thing so I'm gonna do
the same thing I was doing before where
I say look give me you know one of these
indexes that I can use here and if you
can't find it that's not good and we're
gonna call that an error I'm not sure
why I'm missing one of these but
apparently I am and that's the if of is
default so that one there is fine again
check out those little scope guys I'm
glad I added those they're actually very
handy they tell me exactly what those
things were I've got a better version of
that that's coming down the pipe by the
way oh my god I forgot to announce crap
I forgot to announce next weekend his
for coder Jam that was a mistake
I regret not announcing that beginning
the stream at the end of the stream I
will talk more about that next weekend
is for coder Jam and you're gonna want
to be there for that so anyway I forgot
to announce that I'll announce at the
end of the stream because it's what's
happening next weekend okay so when we
get to here we want to stamp what we're
talking about right and so the way that
we're gonna do that is we've got the
append HHA index right and we're gonna
say we need to stamp this stuff with
like the tags and all that sort of thing
when we do our process multi tile import
right that's going to give us sort of a
set of images that are going to go into
a particular you know place as we've
sort
cycle through them right and what we
need to do is we need to in fact I guess
why why do we not have the match should
come down through here is there a reason
no I'm looking as I'm wondering the the
when we match when we do this match here
are we not oh we are we are we're
passing it good good you're a passing
they match and because that's the thing
we actually need we need that match so
this right needs to be up here as well
so that match is gonna tell us like
where this stuff goes right and so what
all we really need to pass when we're
doing the stamping is saying look this
match that we're talking about is is
what we need to do that to know where
all the assets were that we imported now
I think about it was there a reason that
itself doesn't have the HHA index in it
so that's kind of interesting cuz yeah
it doesn't so down asset source file
that asset source file should really
have its HHA found in there I want to
say so I kind of feel like this this
notion of of the asset source file kinda
needs to be upgraded because it's going
into a particular HH a and that
knowledge is you know is important right
and so I almost want to say this append
HHA index what I think we really want to
do here is say okay say that so it's
like which one of which one of the files
is this going into right you know
this thing and you don't want to dangle
a preposition so you know just make sure
you don't dangle your prepositions kids
so when we stamp it really that should
be sufficient now that I think about it
and when we acquire this match I think
what we want to do is is actually then
expand this notion a little bit more I
like the way this is shaping up again
you know when you work with code you
start to see the the correct things
emerge and it's always very satisfying
in my opinion so when we create that
match what we want to do is sort of at
the at the outset here assuming that's
not the default what we want to do is
say let's get a create the HHA that
we're going to use here and say let's
find this one now if we get one back
then we're in a good situation if we
don't we're kind of in trouble right and
so what we want to do there is say when
we create one of when we get or create
one of these hhas
that we're going to use we want to then
update the match and if we were told
like because let's say a hypothesis what
if we move what if we move one of our
assets from one HHA to another right
well when we get the asset source file
and we look at which desk file index
what which one it was coming from right
that record needs to be checked as dirty
as well because if it says it's going
into file three but we're telling you it
needs to be go into file five we need to
do a reinforce
right we have to do a full rebuild in
that case so that's very important so
actually you know I may even do that
sort of up here where I say look as part
of this process
I'm gonna do a check and I'm gonna
create this HHA here to say where this
thing is gonna go into right and that
will help me determine what I need to
know um you know what I think and I
think I may have been premature looking
at the way this code is working out it
looks like you can still specify the HHA
per thing possibly well not really
because of this so I guess that means
now that I say it you don't ever move
between two of those things you can't
really move one because since the path
is fixed the path is always supposed to
be underneath the HHA you if you moved
one you wouldn't find the original one
you wouldn't see it so we really don't
need to do what I was saying I'm gonna
leave it in here because it's an easy
enough effort to do but it's not as
necessary as I thought it was it's not
really gonna do anything
so assuming we've got an eight append HH
any index what I'm gonna do here is say
we've got a match right
so assuming we've got a Matt and you
know what I can really just check is
match because match will only get set in
the case where it's not the default so
match is really a thing that tells us
that anyway
in fact in here we could do the same
thing well you know right we can just
look and see if match is valid it is not
valid we don't need to proceed so that's
fine and all I need to do here is say
look whatever match we got look at the
desk file index right whatever that
desperatly next is if the append HHA
index
is different so if these are not the
same then we need to update that oops
that's supposed to be index not name by
the way
so in the case where desk Val index
equals the append HHA index we don't
have to do anything but in this case we
do and again just to support moving
assets which really can't happen I guess
but if for some reason we change this
pathway I want to needs full rebuild can
just get set to true here so we know
that that was a change that we now need
to record right so we need to do a
reinforce we're going to a different
target than we were before so that's
fine you know I don't see a lot of
problem with that honestly it's okay um
and so this right here will get that HHA
index for us and that tells us what's
going on with the match that means that
later on we don't need to do that
anymore and so if we just go ahead and
vaporize this part of things wreck and
that we're still doing that check up
here so we're still doing that that
means that can be eliminated from these
paths and so rather than passing an HHA
index the match actually has that in
there which is what it should have done
in the first place
and then you know off you go right now
hmm and again I could make base name
match on just the PNG name and then you
could move one thing from another and it
would would retain its data I don't want
to do that the reason I don't want to do
that is I'd like to support multiple
people making multiple hhas that have
the same named files in them because
they might have been made by two
different people have no idea what the
other person was naming their files so
as long as there are different hhas so
as long as you pick a unique name for
your distributable HHA you don't worry
about the conflict that that is the more
important part of this right so that's
that's why don't want to push it there I
want to I want to leave that you being
unique based on the hhx that I think is
important so yeah
like I said moving on if we do a stamp
of these and I want to pass down the
assets here again now's our chance to
fix this import info nonsense we've got
the hht fields and that's good I'm gonna
go ahead and put that this in here like
so and that can actually be potentially
an index as well so when we see the HSA
we could actually set the index there if
we want to because this is actually
gonna be set as the index so we can
actually pull that part out and I should
we should we should just do that um so
here in the hht fields that name off
your description that's actually what we
needed in in terms of the import source
info you can see it's exactly the same
thing so what I'm going to do there is
just call this hht fields for now and
we're gonna pass that directly so
instead of having to do this nonsense
we're just gonna pass fields down to the
stamping function we're gonna delete
this and that again really simplifies
that process so stamp asset that's gonna
go or go through all the assets in this
match and stamp them with the the values
in the fields it's also going to need
that tag array so it's gonna need the
information that's coming out of this so
this right here that tag set that's
gonna have to be in there as well and so
if you look at what's going on here we
want to pass that address once we hand
those are the stamp assets it should be
pretty straightforward for it to do that
asset stamping that'll be good and then
we've got a much cleaner import process
here right so this is the part that
actually processes the image data and
that's great this is the part that
actually does the the metadata and
that's great and so this should all flow
pretty cleanly now like that's pretty
reasonable I don't know why that's a
to-do
- completely honest if you've not sure
right that's it to do
[Music]
I got nothing
that seems like just a note if somebody
wants to go back to when we if you look
at the github it'll tell us when we do I
if there was an actual reason why that
was it knew it it doesn't have an actual
to do like that's just what you want to
do right update it first because we then
pack the assets and since we're
reloading the PNG we want to stamp the
date for and check some of the of the
PNG right I mean that's just kind of
obvious I don't know what else to say
yeah I got nothing
so yeah if we do the checksum the file
date stuff then you know we're good to
go and we've we've reprocessed
everything and that's all fine so I
think this is all reasonable and again
we just have to actually implement that
stamp assets function but that's a
pretty good learning scheme there um and
so now let's just go back and say okay
that HHA part of things let's actually
make that work a little more properly so
you know in here where we actually do
this part this can actually be done a
little even a little bit further down
which is to say now we can actually do
that right here where we update that
right at the beginning this part of
things will move into the outer code
because when we actually do a parse of
the h HT itself and we build that
context that actually is the part that's
going to want to know what the HHA is
and we could make that be like a top
line directive or something like that
and we could even make that be something
that you can actually change inside an
HT if you want to you just can't change
it inside a block right so we could if
you wanted to do is do something like
this where we say like HHA
I don't know like I don't know what we
would say exactly but you know we could
say something like
I don't know I have no idea but we could
do something like that if we wanted to
and then you know you could still feel
free to make some kind of thing that
packs two multiple of these I I just I
don't know but you know why not my
excuse for everything that we ever do is
just as an educational stream so I don't
really have to make great decisions as
long as I'm showing something useful
that you might take and use yourself off
we go right so I can if I want to just
add like what is essentially a
preprocessor directive here that says
you know there's a pounds and and if in
here we said that sometimes you know we
go going back and looking at what we
said here you know the string comes
after it so if we come through here and
say look you know if the token type that
we see on the outside is a pound it's
like a preprocessor directive of some
kind and we're gonna Jimmy we're gonna
use that right and so this is a
preprocessor directive we get the
directive that we want so we just say
here's the directive get token and we
can then look at the directive like so
and we could even you know we could even
have multiple of these directives if we
want to so for example we could even
support a pound include right and we
could support a HHA so that seems cool
right I mean I don't know
doesn't seem horrible to me I also don't
know why we have to break here because
this will break automatically so that's
kind of dumb but anyway so when we're
going through here what
could do here is like this is just an
unrecognized directive here our
directives can Molly Molly has an
automated feeder that goes off regularly
throughout the day and so that she
always like basically like she gets wet
food once a day but she also has like a
little automated feeder that will just
put out dry food for her so it's kind of
like a thing that she always knows is
reliable and you know if no Wooden's to
hear defeat her will still go off so she
can have meals at her regular times
right and so when you hear it go off
she's always a little bit early I think
she can hear like a little bit better
than we can and so as soon as the thing
starts to go off she's off to get food
so that's where Molly went I don't know
if she'll come back she might want to do
some exploring and you know walk her
route but that's where she went okay so
if we have an include directive again we
could just include a file here and you
know to do processing food and then the
HHA again is just going to set that
target and so that's really just this
thing and so anytime we see one of those
we're going to want to do this and
inside here where we've got sort of the
context HHA index we're going to set
that to zero and what we want to do is
say look you're not allowed to have a
block that doesn't have an HHA assigned
and so what we're gonna do in here is
just say if we see a top-level block
there had better be an HHA index so
we'll only actually gonna go down that
route if if we see one of those so if we
haven't seen one yet then we'll just say
hey
yeah also by the way this should be
effective here's our token type equals
in a fire that means we need to have an
HSA if we did great if we didn't I don't
know what to call this import blocks are
not allowed to appear before at least
one HHA directive how's that for a
cryptic error message all right so you
know we'll we'll just fault on that and
say yeah we're not gonna process art
assets if you don't actually specify an
HHA in the packing list we come through
here me say all right we're gonna get
that HHA we'll find out what the heck's
going on there right and so let's get
our let's get our actual one that when
we do create a by stem we'll will grab
that out and so we'll just say that's
directive text right and so that will
try to create it and assuming that it
can create it when we get it back then
we can do
this so that should allow us to set
those hhas and process going forwards
and also ensure that we actually have
one and now we've recovered the
functionality that we lost before that
way you can't start an import without
knowing where it's gonna go because that
just creates a pre parse problem so that
seems fine to me I'm gonna prom with
that if we wanted to handle includes
it's actually probably not that hard if
we won - we can just do a and get a
great asset source file probably just
using the base name although since
they're in the tags directory I don't
know maybe that's not entirely true but
I suspect it is probably true uh so yeah
we could we could just actually do the
include pretty easily right let's go
ahead and and check that out actually so
if we wanted to if you look in here all
it needs is like the platform file
handle so yeah so if we want to do that
we just could let's do that it seems
fine right so if we want to do something
like this oops I forgot to cut and paste
the actual info part of it I wanted that
so if we wanted to have an include
directive that's actually trivial right
it's just three entrant code it's
probably not the best thing in the world
because we're not storing a coherent
context here but we can fix that we can
even fix that so if we want to we can
make this work let's just grab the hht
context in fact we can even do the
include limit so that's actually not
that hard either so when we come in
through here let's just do it we can say
here's the the context the file groups
going to be this the assets we already
know but temporary nough is this and
since
the yeah I mean you look at what's going
on there with that memory arena pointer
that's actually just part of the context
now so we don't even really need that to
be done that way we could do it like
this I'm gonna leave it like that just
to make it a little easier on people so
that they don't have to do that
ampersand every time so I'm going to
leave it like that for no real reason
but that's what we'll do and so I think
that's probably all we actually need to
do I think that's fine and I think we
don't care about this because we're not
going to do space reclamation we're just
going to say that's something that you
should do on your own yeah okay so let's
keep going here so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to take that away we're
gonna leave this this is all gonna come
up into this function here and rather
than passing this stuff down this is
just going to take the hht context you
can see what I'm doing here right
hopefully it's pretty clear that
tokenizer is gonna get put in here I'm
gonna just again make it so that people
don't have to do the ampersand so if you
look at what's going on here we're now
just going to take that context and the
only thing we really need is that
platform file info so when we get that
info that's what we'll start with
because you can see in here
well actually platform file handle I
guess
well I guess really that part I guess
that part's fine so we could just pass
the info right and do this
seems good right do we have a closed
file handle yeah we do it's right there
and so really all we need is that info
so this routine now becomes much much
cleaner I think because it can now do
reentry and have everything and have a
little party with all its little friends
so there's that context file feel we've
already got so we just call parse hht in
a loop with that particular block inside
here we do parse hht we just tokenize
whatever we got if we want to do another
file info cure that comes by and include
we can we just say look the tags file is
going to be in there somewhere
so why don't you go and get that here's
the directive text so go go ahead and
load that include oh wait we need the
actual file name text so we need to get
that file name up oh hello you have
returned what an auspicious occasion why
do you always go that way you know you
can't balance on that anyway so we go
ahead and get the file name out of here
and then we try to load it either we can
or can't load it and if we can't load it
then it's an error right so if that file
name is not available we can just or we
can't load it's like unable to include
file or something right so we go ahead
and get that file this can be a required
token so we can say that this has to be
a string because it does have to be a
string we can go ahead and get it we
don't need a sub dirt here because it's
always going to be in tags so we go
ahead and get that file by path and we
see what's up we inside our file info
when we actually assuming we actually
get it
we just parse the hht and we pass it in
now you can see that this is reentrant
which means that if you include the same
file it'll just include itself over and
over and over again until it runs out of
stack station crash if we want to
prevent that
we absolutely can all we have to do is
just insert into the context right in
fact let me just go ahead and do that
here
into the context we just need a thing
that says hey what we're actually gonna
do here in the weed and loops we don't
actually need this either
that's HHA index we just need a thing
that's like include depth and every time
we do and include all you have to do is
just Inc that number and make sure that
we're not going to do that so if we do
say this we can just do an error and say
look when we got this directive maximum
include depth exceeded so that way we
won't just spiral out of control if
someone makes a stupid mistake and all
we have to do like I said to do that is
say look whenever week whatever this
context is whatever the include depth is
just increment it and if it's less than
some reasonable number like 16 let's say
I mean who could shouldn't ever be doing
much more than that right I don't even
know I would think it included the 1
would be sufficient for most of our
purposes but all right so let's say you
got something ridiculous going on if you
blow past that include depth it's an
error and we're gonna get mad and we're
gonna issue an air and we're gonna stop
so that should allow us to do and
include as well off we go so this all
should just run and be fun and happy and
everything's great
right off we go so once we've got that
that allows us to do the HHA targeting
and it allows us to do this parsing in
this order and so really all we're down
to now to finish things off is we have
to write the stamp function but then we
got to get back to this sort of touchy
aspect of how do we want to actually
sort of merge these like like do that
text transfer right and so what I'd like
to do first is say well we know that
during stamping we're gonna pass the
tags and we're also going
past let's say the append tags right so
that append tags is coming in here that
we built but we want to attack those
onto the end and so when we do the parse
pieces bit right we don't expect that to
do any appending anymore
so like in here where we do parse pieces
and we've got those append tags we're
just not going to do that so we're gonna
let this thing just produce the version
that it needs now the nice part about
doing it this way is this work could now
be amortized right we could then say to
do KC
this could now just be built one for
each type ahead of time and we don't
have to reconstruct the tags over and
over and over and over and we should do
that but we don't really need to do it
quite yet
so since we're making tons of changes
there's no sense making it harder for
ourselves in that regard right okay so
taking a look at what's going on here
this is that append operation right and
what we're going to be doing is adding
that stamping function on here and that
stamping function is really the thing
that we need to start thinking about
there so let's go ahead and do that and
that will sort of have more to do as we
get there so all of this code now that
sort of have this append tags that can
end and that even cleans up this code
path and it makes it not dependent on
who was calling it and that's really the
important part that's what will also
allow us to again cache this so we just
build those templates once at the start
of an import and we'll we won't have to
build them for everything and that would
be really nice right because it's just a
waste of everyone's time that this is
happening every single time through and
that was just us being sloppy right we
just that's just the way we happen to
write it because it was easiest but it's
not the best way to do it and so we're
improving code that way as well which is
kind of a nice fringe benefit of kind of
cleaning up that path okay so getting
rid of the impending here so that those
don't get passed through anymore now
we're pretty much good to go
all this stuff does what it needs to do
and and we're good
item tags here I don't know and and we
don't have those to find it so we're
just gonna insert those later and
that'll be fine so all of that looks
pretty clean if you look here at right
all HHA modifications this should still
just work fine so all we really need to
do now is just that stamping and then
focus on the text transfer and I think
we're good to go okay I'm gonna go ahead
and and recompile I don't know what
mommy was doing there she's you know
she's doing she's kitten she has you
know she has her ways when we do right
image shhh I remember we got rid of this
info hmm and so if we take a look at
what's going on there
actually don't know why it's complaining
about that asset index what's the
problem file isn't undeclared an affair
it's right here so I guess it just
doesn't like that part
but anyway so what I was saying is that
info struct we're not actually gonna
allow that infrastruc ture more that's
not going to be their asset source file
will be there and if I jump in here you
can see where it's getting the asset
file index that's actually now going to
come from the file right I don't think
we called it that what do we call it we
call it desk file index so that's coming
again from that file and then when we
look at where the actual info is coming
from what you can see is like these
right asset strings stuff right that's
where the info was coming from now we
don't actually want to do that again
that's the part that wants to be done
separately and what you can see from
right asset data is like this stuff is
not actually touching that this all of
this is actually the part that's that
needs to be handled sort of separately
so it's actually this part
here that's important these are this is
all the annotation data right that comes
with the asset and so what we want to do
is we want to be able to do this part as
the separate pass that will update the
asset in a different way right and
looking at how this works when looking
at how this works when we actually do
the right asset data right asset data is
the thing that's presumably rewriting
out the asset itself no I guess it's not
so these things all HHA modification
yeah so I think cuz this just sets
modified to true right
something someone sets it to show you
somewhere so that right asset data call
will set modify it equal to true I don't
really know why it's only happening
there because you would think that that
should actually happen sort of in us in
a broader context so we may move that
modify that may want to loft out a
little bit further right so that I'm not
sure about but what I can say is the
simple part that I wanted to actually do
is actually you know very
straightforward exactly what we want so
here where we set all of the asset
annotation data here what I can do is
also set the annotation data here pretty
pretty straightforward right so when we
do these asset indices you know when we
export the PNG s and stuff all that
stuff can get set that's exactly what we
want but then what we can do in addition
to that is just grab this part out that
was sort of a separate piece there in
fact we can actually even take the well
I guess the file date and file checksum
park is important as well so we'll leave
that in place that's fine where it is
we're gonna grab this out here and
inside stamp that's where this is gonna
happen so when we actually go to stamp
the assets down this is where that will
actually happen and this way we can
rewrite the all the stuff that that we
had happen on this particular
pass-through now it's an open question
what you want to do with the air stream
it may be that you want to preserve the
original air stream and so when you
update the tags you don't want to
destroy the air stream that existed
previously I'm not sure how we really
want that to happen I think that
probably we just I I think that probably
we would want to have two separate air
streams one for the PNG and one for the
metadata probably I just really don't
know
the problem so I'm not sure which should
happen in this case what I will say is I
think thinking about it a little bit
deeper I think what we may want to do is
take a different tack with the Airstream
so we'll talk about that later we'll get
those working and then play with them
all right so let me go ahead and fix the
errors that are in the upper part of the
file let me see here
you 64 to you 32 oh that didn't need to
be you 64 Beth can just be you 32
so I just want to fix the part where we
were passing through source infos those
I just don't think are necessary anymore
so what should happen is the info struct
here can get struck doesn't need to
actually occur so everywhere that we
were previously passing it will just go
away and so people who have these source
infos come along those will just get get
nerfed and that's all fine and I'll just
kind of work through that slowly because
it's just it is a case of nobody needs
it anymore because it's not actually
using any of that and these are just
errors that are you know spirits errors
from the compiler that are actually just
go away automatically so yeah none of
that matters at all right so I think
that's probably most of it well what is
it complaining about here I'm not sure
in tax doesn't take for parameters out
what does it take token Iser category so
yeah what was that original then I
didn't want that to jump but it jumped
so result is the import tag array I
don't really understand how that was how
it was so this was returning an import
grid tag temp and passing an import tag
array that didn't actually happen
so this is just code we don't care about
I think that was just old old news all
right so what you looking at Molly
what's going on you seem agitated you
doing okay you just you just got the
zoomies I don't know what's going on out
there but she's pretty attend time all
right so if we take a look at what's
going on in the lower part of the code
just to make sure that we've still got
stuff going on that's supposed to be
going on
so the append HHA index is actually
coming from the context now right so
there's an HH a index that's associated
with that context and we want to update
that every time when we actually work
through the code
lower down here so oops I don't actually
care about this right now um let me take
a look so yeah here we're saying that
there should be some kind of HH a file
name that we're loading out so we do
actually want that I eliminated it
before but right we need it for the path
so we do want an HH a base name I guess
right in HH a stem we want so I'm gonna
go ahead and put the the that back in
there and that's easy enough to get
because all that is is when we actually
grab the token here so when we go
through this code and we say parse h HT
anytime that we're going to set that HH
a in here all we need to do is say when
we actually find it we'll set that stem
so basically the oh you know what we
need this as well
so we grabbed the HHA name here we're
gonna say that stem and I'll call it
stem
we're gonna remember that stem and when
we actually do this we're gonna say
let's go ahead and get that right and I
can I can actually do it like this
that should be sufficient that root lets
us remember both things so we actually
pre get the index and we get the stem so
we can actually produce it properly here
the file name dot txt
that's this up here and remember that's
only valid in the non default case so
that's all fine looking the rest of this
it looks to me like these code paths can
be welded so all of this can move up
right and this part should be able to
just operate here I think so I believe
we can now simplify that code path as
well because we can just get the file
name we can do our file matching attempt
and you know proceed from there so I
think that code path can actually be
simplified quite a bit taking a look at
what's going on here let's see there was
previously a file name mentioned here we
don't need that one anymore so that's
good I'm gonna go ahead and make stamp
have that this basically if doubt so we
can jump right to the first error easily
and yeah let's see that needs a
semicolon we can open our file and oh
here looks like the file info in
question is not being preserved
makes sense we're getting it up here so
that's actually the thing and not the
file name that needs to be placed up
here so there's our file info and looks
reasonable we should also say the import
type gets initialized to what was it
import type none okay so here we now
need to look at what the definition of
these actually was so if we go to like
multi tile import it's got the tag array
I don't know what the tag array is
actually being used for right image two
HHA is taking the grid tags but I don't
actually know if they're used so we do
need to know the tag array looks like so
I'm going to continue passing that
because it looks like we want to know
the type when we add these things in
right so that seems good probably it
does mean that maybe we need a thing
here that says if we change the metadata
in a way that is gonna change the types
of the tags that may require a full
rebuild because that would mean that
we'd have to actually have the assets
stamped differently so this part right
here is a little confusing because
that's the only place that's used and
that's really sucky right because that
means we're passing that whole thing
down for no other reason than just the
fact that we're calling set asset type
on it which just seems real dumb so I'm
gonna actually say no even to that
I'm gonna say that goes in stamp and
then that whole thing is getting cleaned
out as well so up here we're gonna do
this you know if we detect that the
asset type previously didn't exist for
when we're doing the stamp and it looks
like the way that that has to happen
there is when we reserved a new asset
right the asset type if we didn't
already have one right so we'll have to
deal with that but otherwise that's
pretty good because this tags type ID
doesn't actually then need to happen and
with this I guess what I would say is
the part where we do sprite founded was
accredited blank tile again that part we
can actually save for later so that can
happen in here right so the stamping
process can still again be separate so
when we come through here and do all of
this asset processing now we don't need
the tags at all so right image to HHA
just doesn't need to take those and that
solves that problem for us right and
here again when we're looking at this
HHA asset and we do this assignment
again don't really need that we don't
need to update that that stuff can be
updated later so this can just be
updated in here right and these parts
that are being updated will just get
updated again so this stuff's all fine
and it can all be rewritten
but off we go so when we type my phone
my phone was on silent
I guess my phone was not on silent so
much for a professional podcaster or a
professional streamer I should say
all right so I'm here we do write image
to HSA we're removing the tags from the
list and so anywhere from the Brady much
hhj so that stuff doesn't have to happen
and now we just got that partitioned
into two parts which I like better so
the metadata can be updated separately
from the image data and we should
probably take that as far as we can go
so later on we probably want to keep
doing that let's take a look at process
multi tile import now so anywhere we
were doing this before so there's the
multi tile here's the plate I'm going to
take the tags out of there because again
they just aren't necessary okay so now
grid tag array where's that happening on
a second this is not gonna happen right
that goes away and we've got stamp
assets platform open file okay
so inside here this is context file
group because remember that's getting
passed down now that temporary nough is
happening here and you know honestly
inside this part hht bit i think yeah
everything this all seems fine we could
move that clear further down if we
wanted to we could make that something
that actually clears out the HH tees as
they're brought in I don't think we care
about that so I'm not going to bother
but we could if we needed to stamp
assets is the thing we're gonna have to
write file info here is this is getting
passed in so this is actually sort of a
sub file info or included might be this
is the included file info and so we want
that to work so we'll go ahead and have
that work there and in here if we can't
open in HHA then we're gonna do
HHA stem in this case what else we got
when we do purse top of a block that's
just a question of too many ampersands
oops
final group looks fine there
thug group star is there a reason that's
not a star oh so then actually returns
the actual file group that seems fine as
well
so that can just be stored and we're
almost down to the end tougher files
okay let's see what else we got
so that looks like that
all right so now we have come to the
part where we really got to figure out
what's going on here so if we actually
call like imagine we have this function
where we say here's the assets here's
the asset source file here's the hht
fields here's the tags right this is
what a import grid tags and this is an
import tag array something like this so
if we actually start with this now what
we have to do is figure out how to
actually make something that goes
through all of the assets that were ever
pulled in for this particular file and
rewrite all of their asset headers to
make sure that they now contain the
metadata that we've received and
furthermore what we need to do is when
we actually go in here to parse
top-level block we want to have a thing
that says whether or not we actually
need to save based on that operation we
could just not bother at some level we
don't care right
so it's a little bit tough to say
whether we actually want to be too
specific about saying we need to rewrite
these or not in other words we could
just always Reese tamp all the assets
and especially if we did a little bit of
string pooling we probably never know
the difference but I'd rather not do
that so I think I'm gonna actually try
to make it so it's a little bit more
specific just so we don't blow our files
during development so in here when we
actually do stamp assets I'm going to
get rid of the f0 and we're gonna
actually try to make this work
when we go and do the right hht part of
this from before which is all right up
here I need to follow this logic a
little bit so this part here where we
sort of specify what's going on
inside the file asset indices you can
see as we flew through this code that
down here we're gonna assign this thing
and in terms of the type that gets
assigned to it what's kind of a little
bit frustrating about that is that we
don't actually store that piece of
information anywhere right it's just
inside the tags and it's impossible for
me to actually know whether or not we
hit this path or this path and we kind
of need to know because we need to be
able to set the type ID on whatever this
thing is I think that's really not that
big a deal though because inside
handmade asset it's pretty easy for us
to just go ahead and take an asset and
when we look in here and you've got this
like next of type field it'd be pretty
trivial for us to just store the type in
there right so that doesn't really seem
that bad to me when we do that set asset
type we could just put it there so maybe
we'll do that also that stuff is kind of
irrelevant anyway because we're gonna
probably eliminate that it's sort of a
non-issue at this point but anyway so in
here
when we do set asset type we want to get
the asset we want to assert that the
asset type is zero and then we want to
set that asset type right again it's a
little fragile because like what happens
if you want to change the type of an
asset it just doesn't work and so I
think again this is something that we're
really gonna have to change the way we
were doing it we had this sort of fairly
fragile like way that we were looking
through and this is just for tag
matching so what we're really going to
want to do as we go forward is we're
just going to want to have a tag
matching index that we just rebuild
right and so I think like this is it to
do here
so I think we just want to make sure
that that that's a little bit more
robust going forwards anyway when we
come through here we're gonna want to do
set asset type on this thing and so
we're gonna have to have you know
something that actually does this check
here so we don't call this unnecessarily
and that's gonna be right
mmm modifications tha yeah no actually
that's not what I wanted what I actually
wanted was this so what I want to do
here is I want to get this piece of
information out so I want to say like
hey let's get which asset we're talking
about in this case and and actually pull
that out right and I want to make sure
that the asset index actually exists if
it doesn't exist I'm not going to do
anything to it because we don't stamp
things that aren't there right we only
stamp things that are and so we'll start
with that and that needs to be obviously
in sort of a double for because we're
going to be going over an entire tag
array
stamping anything that we see inside the
tag array so much like in the code
is in here somewhere for loop on that
that's in there somewhere
no you know so this right where we're
gonna actually look and see when they
come through the tag array we're gonna
figure out like much like this code here
we're gonna look through all of the
asset indices in the actual file so
we're gonna say look there's our counts
that we're going to go through and then
we're gonna go through these one by one
and for each of them we're going to grab
the asset that corresponds to it
and we're gonna try and stamp it if
there actually is an asset there so
assuming that there is an asset there
we're gonna take a look and see if that
asset has a particular type involved
again we need to get the tags out here
so if you take a look at the import grid
tag if I jump out to here and say import
grid tag array there right we've got the
first tag index one passed last tag
index that sort of thing so what I want
to do here is say let's grab that out so
here's the tags that go with it rid tags
like so so now we've got the tags and
the asset index I guess I can delay
actually looking for it by doing this if
we then look to see and say that hey
there is an asset and we expect to be
able to do something with it but oddly
enough there wasn't actually supposed to
be anything in this slot you know oops
so we can actually act on that here I'm
gonna say
only set this in that case and off we go
right so that's basically what we're
dealing with here
I guess previously we just did this and
that's fine too so now we start moving
through this code we set up all of our
tags and we stamp them and stuff like
that but as you can see here we want to
kind of be a little bit broader we need
to merge these tag sets together all of
this stuff is fine and so really what we
want to do here is when we do this stamp
we need a place to get the errors from
and that's fine too
so all of this stuff looks pretty clean
the stamping should be pretty basic so
the only thing we're really gonna have
to do is do a temporary tag build here
so that we can merge the two sets of
tags together the one that came from the
template and the one that's been like
merged into the file right and so what
we want to do is is probably jump down
to parse tag list use the Builder here
and just merge those two tags together
so we're gonna do that right here here's
the easiest way to do that right and
then when we do our end tags like this
that's the thing that'll give us the the
temporary there right um and so let's
see
combined tags here write them out there
and we're done right so I think that's
all we need to do to get our tag merging
and all that stuff working in and of
course asset names and source files and
errors and all that garbage will you
know just be in there and so when we
actually do this import here what we can
see is when we do our source tags like
so on we need to merge from two
different tag arrays we need to first
merge from the tag array that comes here
and then we need to merge from the tag
array that comes and effect just
duplicate that from the append tags so
first let's take this one
we've got that specified right here so
we just do tags tags we append each of
those tags on no big deal there that
should be it and then here we do the
exact same thing with the ones that
we're appending right pretty
straightforward so again we don't need
to worry about holes in the in the grid
because we're only going to import when
there's actually an asset index so
that's fine we won't like be creating
assets in places where they didn't exist
before because we're only gonna ever see
them I'm gonna go ahead and call this Y
or X&amp;Y index because we know those are
the only things we actually have here
and then I think we're good
looking through here this is just a dot
right and we should probably make this
just being a thing that comes with the
Builder by default like so that you can
just say merge and it'll merge tag sets
let me see what else we got here so tags
is not a member of import grid tag
that's true and that's that's I'm not
sure what the problem is scattered it's
that's that's all good and in here we've
got a tokenizer that's got to get passed
down there I think that's just for
reporting out of memory errors if I'm
not entirely mistaken if we want to sort
of propagate that forward we would need
to pass the tokenizer here I'm not
adverse to that because again it just
helps us report errors at the correct
location which I like so let's see HHA
assets in this case what don't we have
info in this case is just the fields and
so this is pretty easy to restore that's
just going to be this like so in here
where we write the asset file source
name that is not currently getting
passed down so we're probably going to
need to pass that down although really
it's sort of is because if you take a
look at what's going on here actually we
can just get it
here's that base name and we know what
that asset source file actually is
coming from in terms of the source file
itself so I think that's really just
that's just fine so I don't know why
that was actually flagged that may
actually not have been a problem at all
so I assume it's just asset file here
that's the problem we're we're doing it
right assets string in terms of what
actually needs to get passed down there
so if we look at what asset file expects
I think that wants to know this which we
haven't actually retrieved yet and so we
want to get that by index so we want
like get asset file or get file here and
I mean this
soin cure when we actually go to write
this out and we're calling stamp assets
we want to be able to get the file in
question that file is gonna be you know
whatever are our source says it's going
to be and from then we should should not
have a problem with that
oh and sorry that's called asset file
right it looks like we're basically done
so now we just need that HHA asset that
needs to actually get sort of stamped
that hij asset is coming from the asset
itself so we're we're actually writing
that in that actually needs to be more
like you know this so that it can
actually stamp into the asset itself I
think then we're good to go
so I think this needs to take the
tokenizer otherwise we're good
[Music]
HHA stem here these are arrows and again
we're gonna have to flow that down all
these old paths were written before that
became passed in and that's it so you
can see a lot of work a lot of
bookkeeping but it's slowly starting to
take reasonable shape and you can see if
we were writing this originally without
having sort of wrap route found to it it
wouldn't be too hard to just make one of
these from whole cloth there's not that
much code there right and so as we start
to refine it I think we're kind of
zeroing on something reasonable and so
I'm not too worried about where that's
going now we should be able to actually
do an import from the agency and it
should actually work I think that's at
the point where it's testable and so the
thing that wouldn't actually work yet is
the import that goes from one hht to a
new one and puts in edited data that
wouldn't work and the reason that it
wouldn't work is because we haven't done
the copy yet and so we'll have to do
some work there but I think we could
start to test this and see if this
actually can start to build hht files
let's just start down that debugging
path I think we've got like five minutes
left let's just see how bad a shape
we're in
or actually no I think we have more than
that I think we actually have 20 minutes
left
all right um so what I want to do here
is I want to compile in debug mode and I
would just want to kind of step through
the code oh whoops
we've got two of those open my bad those
there I want to compile in debug mode
and I want to look through this code and
just see what what's going on
right because we've done a ton of stuff
we probably made a lot of mistakes and
so we want to kind of start to look and
look through what we're doing and see
how it's going so I want to go ahead and
jump oh and you know what we never set
that asset type to zero when we
initialize an asset yet so we should do
that let's go ahead and look at set
asset type
so you can see it here when we actually
allocate these you can see us doing it
so what we want to do is say type equals
zero where is that next of type next so
what's interesting about that is we're
not initializing that next of type oh
there we go and I'm like so it should
have been initialized for us as a clear
to zero so that was because I actually
that we left it not in there but that
does remind me there's a couple other
things we did want to do here so that
deaths file index is probably not going
to get set here because when we load the
things and it's not going to say where
it came from we do want it to say where
it came from so if you look in here and
you know we go back to ham audacity age
so as we come through here and we see
this like asset source file that desk
file index when we create that asset
source file we want that to be specified
and so in here where we actually create
the source file in question
and you can see we do a getter create
what I want to do there is I want to
have that when that gets rid in I want
that to say where it came from
right and so in here the the setting
that we set like that
that desk file index wants to get set in
here so when we get that source file I
want that to be like set okay and that
because we weren't that was a new field
we added that you know wouldn't never
have gotten set would never get set all
right so moving on again like I said I
want to step through some of this code
here's the game loading these are the
old age eight days right so that's you
know nothing's going on there and so the
first thing that should happen is if we
actually try to trigger a rebuild
we should get hit here and I'm expecting
we'll get an error because we currently
don't ever create new files right and so
when we start parsing and we say this is
the HHA this should go into we should
not find that HHA and so this is what
i'm expecting to happen if we
miraculously have no bugs that's what
should happen right but we probably do
have bug so that's probably not what's
gonna happen but just so you know that's
what we're talking about so I'm going to
hit important save and I think we're
supposed to when we hit that button we
should get down to here now handmade
internal we didn't turn that off did we
it's up to one so when I push that
button we should get breakpoint here
it's making me a little nervous that
this is grayed out how does it know that
handmade internal isn't bound to find I
mean we should be able to see that code
path right yeah so just cuz it's grayed
out
that's just visual studio being its
usual bug itself so here we go
first we're gonna say let's get all the
hht files and hey look we got one let's
see what it actually is
it's intro cutscene that hht that's
great that's correct so we're gonna open
that file and we're gonna read in the
contents and then really close it right
and so what we should see now is we
should have a file buffer here if that
file buffer should have the entire thing
in it if I open up this little text
viewer here you can see like hey that's
exactly what we expect so off to a
reasonable start we're gonna start
tokenizing again tokenizer is now
supposed to have things like file and
line number information let's make sure
that's right yeah it's there that's good
the file name is intro cutscene that's
exactly what we expect so off we go
we start our parsing we get a token what
is that first token pray tell because we
don't know let's see the first token is
[Music]
an unknown so our tokenizer is busted
and we need to fix it it didn't parse
the comment which it was supposed to
parse so I'm gonna go ahead and rerun
that and do that operation a second time
so I'm just gonna click this button and
let's see what happens I'm gonna run to
here and step in the first thing we call
is get token raw that's exactly what we
should call and so now we're gonna take
a look at what the character settings
actually are so here's our C it's set to
forward slash we jump into here we look
in and check what it actually is now we
should hit one of these comment paths
should be this one right so we should
parse into there but we're not okay so
we're not actually that match didn't
work probably you know why it's because
we already sucked up that character so
actually yeah this path is is not
correct so we gotta fix that when we did
that actually
port we screwed it up totally fine so
this actually needs to be see and this
needs to actually be based on whatever
the thing we're going to advance is
right and so it really looks like this
and so that still probably should be
fine everything else think is okay
that's probably fine
[Music]
looking at the parsing of is number that
looks incorrect because as you can see
it's sort of doing a peak on C there and
it won't you want to actually have that
first digit recorded properly so this
should actually be this right so you
know looking through this probably we
shouldn't have pulled we shouldn't have
pulled the advance it probably would
have been smarter not to do that
yeah so that might not have been the
smartest way to write that but that's
okay you can see what the bug was right
so it's pretty straightforward I'm gonna
jump right to here so that we can you
know debug that more easily oops
I don't know what that did so when we
start parsing here I'm going to jump
into the get token draw and when I do
this switch now I'm expecting to be able
to flow through this comment block and
thankfully I actually do now and so we
kind of eat away you can see it slowly
eating through this string when by the
time we get to here we should have eaten
the entire comment hopefully and if we
see that we actually did get a valid
stopping point here we can advance
forward this should really check the
entire thing I'm not sure why it didn't
I guess it doesn't really matter cuz the
advance cares too should still work
either way so it's probably fine but
anyway so we now get the token it's a
comment so we should get another token
and let's see if we get the correct
token this time we got an end-of-line
token that's also correct so when we
look at that the line number should
actually advance and it did right so
that's good we'll skip that and now we
should see what's the token we got now
some
just some more notes these are the
assets for the intro cutscene is that
what should actually they let's see what
the actual files I don't remember
so what token did we actually get back
here
we got an end-of-line and there's a note
Casey but I don't understand where
that's coming from
I'm looking at the wrong file ok so no
that's right that's another comment it
should get skipped that's exactly what I
expect and now we've got to our string
right so the first thing we got was a
string that doesn't seem right because
we should have gotten identifiers first
right so that seems a still a little
broken because the first thing that we
got there unless I'm mistaken oh no it
wasn't it was token identifier alright
nevermind I just misread that branch
okay good so we look here and we've got
a token identifier and we immediately
hit an error and that's actually correct
impart blocks are not allowed to appear
so that's actually great we caught that
error and didn't do the parse and so
what we know there is this doesn't have
the HHA on it
right and so I'm tempted to say let's
leave that error in there so that we can
work on our error processing so I'm
gonna go ahead and say let's not change
that let's go to base game data hht and
watch it parse this and see how that
goes so here we are in parsing that one
let's take a look at that first token
that's going to be the the directive so
we look at that directive here's the HHA
we're gonna get that stem what's the
stem it's base game we're gonna try and
get that we should get back a zero
because
won't find it it doesn't we get the
error there and then we can move on
right so again our token thing was a
little busted other than that our error
checking actually passed with flying
colors at least for those first basic
errors it prevented two errors one
trying to start writing to a file that
it couldn't actually open and another
one that's you know just there to try
and make sure that you've specified
where you're actually gonna write things
to now what we want to do here is figure
out how we do want to handle this case
where you're specifying an HHH a that
doesn't actually exist and so if I do a
get or create this call right here it's
going to look to see whether or not it
can find the HHA in question and if it
can't we want to potentially create a
blank
HHA now we do know how to create a blank
HHA because in our HHA edit we actually
have a - create call right and so right
here that already does exist and you can
see it's pretty trivial all it does is
just write a blank header into the file
and furthermore that hutter is gonna get
rewritten like every time anyway so we
almost don't even really need to do that
if we don't want to because when we
actually go to open that file for
writing it would just rewrite the header
anyway if it actually had any data to
write in the first place but either way
let's suppose we were going to do this
we would want to do the equivalent of
that and we'd want some way of opening
an actual file handle that would create
the file for us now that's not that hard
to do we just need our platform layer to
be a little bit more understanding
because what happens at the moment is
that if we actually say platform get
file by path there's no way to tell this
thing that we actually want to make
it always exists right and so what we
could do here is say well you know we've
already got these mode flags let's just
tell it hey you know what you pass those
flags when you do this as well
so that if you asked and get a file by
path we can actually create it if it
doesn't exist and so if we jump back
down to the win32 code path there and we
look at the open file by path in here
sorry get file by path in here where we
actually get that information you can
see us getting the information here what
we can do is we can allocate file info
for something that doesn't actually
exist
and return that if you asked us to write
to it right so if you told us we want to
write to this file we can create it and
so what I'll do there is say hey let's
do a get file attributes and we'll do
the result here if we couldn't get that
let's create the file and then try again
right so I really just want to do this
so that we'll try twice makes sense and
so what I want to do is have a create
file here where we do you know
essentially this and so in the case
where we say get file attributes and it
doesn't actually return we'll do a test
here to say well if the mode says that
you would allow writing so you're trying
to actually create one of these
potentially if it doesn't exists already
then we'll just say all right if you
wanted to open it for writing then when
we do this we can you know do the full
nine yards with the permissions and the
creation and all that sort of stuff and
then if we get back a valid handle then
what we can do is you know process it
from there right and we actually have I
think yeah
we can just do a closed handle on that
and then get the file info and go from
there
so what we really need is just a way to
get generate our are you know sort of
creation operations you know generic
right open always that sort of stuff
right so we would really need something
that does that now if we want to we can
we can actually make it so that we don't
actually have to create that that data
so the win32 allocate file info where is
that in to allocate oops into to
allocate file info what you can see
there is that just uses like this sort
of synthetic stuff we could just say
let's just give it a fake one of those
right and have it have it used that so
we don't even really need to do this
part because that would happen
automatically so what we could do is say
all right let's create a fake one of
these as necessary right and and just
say yeah in fact we could just say like
zero struct out that data right and set
the relevant portions of it like the
past sixteen part and so on
that seems pretty reasonable to me now
I'm looking at this here and I'm just
wondering when we're taking a look at
this where we do win through to allocate
file data I'm not sure where it's
actually getting the name from though
where is that actually happening so this
is actually incomplete isn't it because
this past 16 is never getting set on
there so this is actually not right you
know I'm saying
because that information should have
been passed down so yeah we didn't quite
finish this code it looks like because
here's where that's getting created here
right it does a allocate file info but
then it does this operation that you
actually do need to do right where it
puts the information in for what the
platform is going to need to open the
file that's actually getting copied in
there and we're not doing that and we
need to do that right so in this routine
where we actually call win32 get filed
by path
this was actually bogus yeah we should
have done that way so what we should be
doing here is we should say look
if we can get this or we're writing to
it so even if this fails we'll still do
this and then at the end here we just
need to set those actual parameters
right because those the file name and
stuff was not getting set here so in the
when we actually get that file info back
we need to set you know base name and we
need to set platform now in here we've
already got it so it's pretty easy right
the past 16 is the platform name and
you're passing in the actual path itself
so that we could put in here and you
know maybe we should duplicate it or not
I'm not sure like to do KC like should
the base name be duplicated and maybe
the answer is yes maybe the answer is no
I really couldn't tell you but in this
case you know that that's the open
question but what would happen in here
if we wanted to get or create one of
these is we would first need to you know
get that file by path using a file group
that we you know that we create somehow
and then we'd have to open the file
handle for writing now that file group I
believe do we actually have that in the
assets itself because I should have
actually stored it let me take a look at
where we do that so when we actually do
a platform file group here we do get all
files of type again and then we come
down here yeah we do get all files of
type end and so that needs to I mean we
could keep it around I guess we don't
really have to though because what we
could do here just say like look open
the file group for these things like so
right and then we want to create one of
these things by name in the case where
where it actually wasn't already in
existence so it's a little janky I don't
know how I feel about it I feel like we
want to kind of clean up the way we're
doing the
we kind of need something a little bit
more purpose-built for the types of
operations we're actually doing but for
the most part it's still pretty good so
we here what we want to do is you know
get file by path and we want to do
something that looks sort of like this
right and so at least at the moment what
we want to do is is get that out of the
data directory actually we don't mean to
do it like that so we just need to do
like data and then the stem right and
then we have to to sort of create that
HHA and it doesn't actually exist yet
right so we need to sort of bootstrap it
if you will so if we take a look at how
this works in here we would need to take
that stem and we just need to put it in
right like so and then we would want to
get that as a path to the extent that it
is able to do so and then when we call
that function remember we need to now
say what we're actually going to be
doing with this so you know are we
reading or writing and in this case we
want to be able to do both so when we
come through here when we create the
blank
HHA this is us doing that and we just
need a way to write it and so we need to
do like a write file so in here where
we've got write data to file we need to
pass the file handle and we need to pass
the offset the size and the address
right so we do need to do this and again
it's kind of annoying because since
we're sort of retrofitting the asset
system to do these kinds of in-place
merges it's not set up the best for it
and we probably want to do a path to
clean that up once we know what
everything actually is but at the moment
that's actually okay so here's us
getting that file info by path and then
assuming that we get it we can do a
platform file handle where we open that
and actually looking at it we want to do
that as the same way that we did the
other files in the system so back in
here where we've sort of got those files
where are those files when we initially
open them you can see them happening
here right so when we go through me open
all these files the first time through
you can see us doing this where we sort
of opened them and create we sort of
create the initial stem with the asset
base and the tag base and that sort of
things for them right and since this is
a new file all of this stuff right none
of this stuff really has to happen and
so the initial settings for it don't
have to have you know they don't have to
be retracted or anything but because we
want to keep this code as simple as
possible probably what I think we want
to do is actually call this so we're
always going through the same path if
that makes sense probably that's my
guess
that just seems like the sameness thing
to do so if we actually create one of
these here what we want to do is like do
a write to it and then basically call
this code path and let it do this entire
thing even though it's somewhat
redundant just to make sure that we're
always doing the same code path right so
that there's like a init source
HHA kind of a thing that happens here
and so that in this code when we do this
we can essentially just say that and
have that work right and then we've got
a couple things here that need to kind
of get passed through this is going to
be you know on there there's file info
needs to get passed down although I
might say that this actually should be
this order
and then that stem needs to get
remembered so
oh so it's actually gonna do that from
the base name okay so that's fine so
actually the stem here in this case we
really just need the arena that's being
used the arena in this case is always
the same though it's the non restored
memory right so it I don't feel like
that actually that can just be got
enough for the assets it doesn't
actually need to be passed the file
group does want to be there like so and
that should be mostly it I think yeah
okay
um so just taking a look at this as we
move forward so what I want to do here
is I want to be able to open one of
these platform files I want to write
this thing and then I want to
essentially call initialize on it so
after we're done with that I'm gonna
call here like hey in its source HHA I
want to call it with the file index that
we're talking about so basically you
know the result effectively and I want
to pass all the rest of the data that
that actually needs to operate so that I
know it's going through the same path
even though it's going to repeat some
work I don't mind so calling that I got
to pass the file index I gotta pass the
file group which I have I have to pass
the file info which I also have right
and so as long as I just create this
piece of information for it we should be
good to go
so when I come in here I need to do a
platform file handle there's the handle
that's going to be an open file right
that has to happen on there so platform
you know open file or whatever and then
we have to close it
and so it's kind of a pain in the butt
it's not what I would prefer but you
know oh well so if all of that stuff
works so if literally all of this works
then we'll do an innate source HHA but
otherwise we won't right so all of that
stuff has to occur and has to work and
you know assuming that it all does then
we'll continue forward with it right
okay so what's the problem here that's
supposed to be sizeof not sure what the
problem is here get file by path this
needs to take in open file read so does
this
thought we passed a mode to that now
it's a mode flaps
so open file is complaining thanks
because that and I guess this isn't is
valid test how does this supposed to
work platform file handle so there's
just in no errors and so I think all we
need to do now is actually assign the
result here so what we want to do is say
end result equals zero and you know the
the number of asset files that we can
store is it's actually allowed so the
max file cap here we need to do a like
and you know plow count is less than max
file count right so we have to have room
to put this thing so assuming that's the
case then we can just say alright the
result equals the assets file count and
that can get incremented we don't
actually need to do that until
everything actually works right and so
we actually get all the way down here we
don't have to assign it an actual index
so it's kind of just like literally
right there that that ever actually
happens and I think that's all we would
really need to do I don't know if closed
file happens here we can put it here if
we want to just to make sure it always
just close in all cases so if I do this
right I think that works
and I think we're good to go so the only
thing that I might suggest is I kind of
would rather it looks more like this at
that point and I would probably also say
I would rather that it look like this so
when I do in it that HHA right that
actually happens on here so this gives
back one of those indices so I think
that's all fine and that way when we
actually do this file indexed result
right that thing is going to be set to
zero and then if we actually get one of
these
then it equals file count and we can
increment that right and that allows us
to make this be something that you know
makes more sense right
that way we're not passing file index
anymore and so this code here when it
actually does the assets file count bit
it's not going to do that it's not going
to do this what we're actually gonna do
is say hey just like everything else
assets file count actually ends up
equaling one and that's fine when we
allocate our array of asset files we're
actually gonna put on the max file count
and the Mac style count is going to
actually be based on however many of
these things there were going to be
which I believe is in the file group it
gives us a count of those right so in
here when we look at the platform file
group it's got the foul count so we're
going to take a look at that file count
and we're gonna do that if we're in
handmade internal we're gonna allow like
for a bunch of headroom like we do with
everything else right and so then we
allocate that array in leave space so if
we need to add anything
then we've got our file index here
doesn't actually need to occur anymore
so this can now just be in its source
HHA forever where it just passes the
file info and the assets and we don't
even need to know what that return value
is anymore it's just not relevant right
and so I think that's all we need to
actually do here and then when we can
look at that image source hhj code and
oh and we need to pass in addition to
the file info we just need to pass the
file group so I think that's proper and
that just kind of extends that to
allowing us to create some files it's
not as clean as I would like because
again we probably could just use
allocate on demand here and like it so
it just wasn't a particularly useful way
to structure those as an array so it
would be nice if we probably change that
there's no there's no reason for them to
be an array and so it's just kind of
holding us back right so a lot of this
stuff now that we're sort of looking at
it these could really be changed into a
more per allocation system there's
really not a reason not to and so we're
just kind of that's just like a legacy
code that's you know hampering us a
little bit unfortunately so let's just
go ahead and wrap up the stream by
verifying that that you know approach
will work we can still run the game
which is good so means we didn't break
any of that part I'm gonna run through
to here and just see if we can actually
create a file now and then we'll stop
there so if I actually click import and
save here and jump to that part of it
when we actually get to the the HHA part
of things this part is supposed to error
out right because remember we're on the
file that doesn't actually have that so
let's go ahead and parse that HHA
directive and jump into this code here
so we're not gonna find the HHA that
we're talking about cuz no one has
created that HHA again we're looking for
one that's actually called base game and
that one does not exist so let's see if
we can create one we're gonna open an
iteration on these guys we're gonna
create our own name which is this name
here right so it's it's gonna be data
slash base tha we're gonna try and get a
file by that path and see if we can
let's take a look so we get a file info
it looks like we've got it okay so then
we're gonna try and open that file and
see if we got a handle back oh yeah
that's correct so we come in here we
didn't have any errors so that's nice we
try to write the data to the file we do
it there and now we come through and try
to initialize that file we do have room
because we have plenty of extra files
here so we should now be able to process
this as a read/write file so coming
through here let's see if we can open it
we can't for some reason why is that I'm
not sure database game that HHA should
exist so for some reason
we were not actually able to read that
and I'm not sure why so you can see that
we actually created it properly and if I
dump it it's valid right so our code
actually worked great up to a point when
we actually went to open it though we
couldn't open it again for some reason
and it's unclear what that reason
actually was looking in here oh well
actually it's not I'm clear so the
problem is right here that's because we
haven't closed it yet
so in that case yeah the closed file
handle that actually needed to happen
beforehand so a better way to do this
would probably be to go like this right
so this is actually the way we should be
doing that not the way I was doing it
before but that looks fine because I
want to be able to call closed file on
this pretty much any time I want to so I
think we still did it correctly so
that's good and so I think then we're
done now we can proceed with you know
doing the rest of the the testing there
and seeing if it actually works I'm
going to call it for now and we will go
to a very brief Q&amp;A and then we'll have
a announcement about for coder Jam
situation let me go ahead and and do a
QA here which I have to do on the other
stream for some reason so there we go
done
oh we said we have one of the newline
cases is still parsing at one sorry that
was a typo there and we'll have to do
some testing of this right we didn't
really test any of this stuff
you had a note you changed it to do but
what if by with the right data indicated
the code wasn't or isn't using the right
data let me take a look
now but it is the right data yeah
any questions
looks like no questions which makes
sense I mean basis we're just doing
bookkeeping the asset importing so
we're using a KVM and that set up and do
you like it um so actually I was using a
KVM switch from I Omega and I didn't
like it and it actually was causing a
bunch of problems and then I switched to
and actually to be clear it wasn't
actually KVM switch was just keyboard
and mouse a KVM switch is technically
video as well this was not video because
I don't actually need to switch the
video I just need to switch to keyboard
mouse I upgraded to one by AV access
that's like a more substantial one
probably cost about twice as much maybe
I mean it still wasn't super expensive
buy computer equipment standards it was
like $80 or something so you know I mean
computer equipment is expensive so
that's not that expensive in the grand
scheme of things but it was more
expensive than the I Omega one was and
it's much better it actually works on
all machines which you wouldn't who used
to have a problem with it sometimes
understanding what was going on and so
it was causing problems there also it's
this one has just a button you push for
any given input so you can switch
directly the I Omega you had to like
click to get to one and I hate that so
you end up kind of so so I this AV
access one's really good it's actually a
four-way HDMI and keyboard and mouse
switcher I just I don't use the video so
you know the video could be totally
broken for all I know it I didn't have
no idea so I I really couldn't tell ya
right do you have an idea as to what the
gameplay of hammer here we're just doing
more of that design exploration um I do
have idea of what the gameplay will be
like but you know this is not really a
gameplay or this is not a game design
stream so that is not a focus right the
the gameplay will be just because we
need there to be gameplay on top of an
engine in order for it to be a game
technically and you don't really know if
all the sudden the engines working
unless you
actually play a game and it works right
so it's it's like a proof-of-concept to
in that sense but this is absolutely not
a game design stream and I will say that
repeatedly when we're doing game
development of just the play stuff as I
will I'm explicitly disavowing any
suggestion that you should be listening
to that as a game designer this is not a
game design stream and it should not be
watched by game designers because it is
not about game design and will never be
about game design there will not be a
single episode of this stream about game
design ever the stream will we will end
the handmade arrow series without ever
having talked about game design at all
because we don't do that here repeating
my question what makes asset importing
special the way you're doing it compared
to other ways in other game libs I don't
think there is something special about
it I mean every game needs to have some
you know process by which asset
importing happens I don't think we're
doing anything particularly out of the
ordinary
one thing that is a little bit different
from how some other code bases do it is
we don't spam strings into our
executable everywhere so sometimes the
way that asset importing works in game
engines is like strewn throughout the
entire code will just be strings talking
about P and G's and stuff right and we
don't do that we actually define like a
rigorous set of enums for tags and stuff
like that so that's one thing that some
asset imports do and some asset imports
don't do and so we are on that side of
that fence but that is not unique to
handmade hero there are plenty of asset
systems designed to not spam strings
everywhere so you know that's
that may be unusual compared to some
asset imports but it's certainly not
unusual across all asset imports so yeah
so I would say there's nothing special
about the way we're doing it I don't
think you know we've made some specific
choices that other asset systems
probably do slightly differently but
they're all basically doing the same
thing which is they're trying to marshal
a bunch of disparate source files and
pull them into the game in a way that
the game can recognize what they're
supposed to do right and so you know we
we sort of have a sprite sheet kind of
approach there is some things we do
differently so again depending on the
pipelining question some pipelines
don't try to actually only use the
elements of the sprite sheet that
actually it use some of them just pull
in the entire sprite sheets and ship
that right so we are a little bit better
than that right we do only keep the
parts of sprite sheets that actually
have stuff in them but again most
professional asset pipelines would be
doing that it's only kind of a janky
amateur-hour stuff that wouldn't be
doing that anyway so again I don't
really consider that to be special on
the whole we are not a particularly
advanced asset pipeline compared to a
very high-end asset pipeline so you know
yeah checksum right now is a murmur hash
I think that's what we used
when you import assets do they go into
some kind of target like a texture Atlas
on we are not using a texture Atlas
because we chose to use texture arrays
instead and so when we import our assets
actually the way that it works is we
just pack the data that we receive
directly into our source data files just
the part that's actually used and then
at runtime when we actually stream that
asset in when we detect that somebody
needs it we place it into a freeze
portion of the texture array so whatever
if there's a place in texture we haven't
used yet we use that if we don't have a
placement x-ray that hasn't been used
yet we just evict something and put it
there so we don't use a texture Atlas
that's a different method than the
method we're using
and also to give a little bit more
perspective texture atlas and
spritesheet while some people may use
them entertainment change lead
technically they are not the same thing
sprite sheet is a statement about an art
asset so if you're talking about a
sprite sheet what you're talking about
is an artist has made a single image
that has multiple different sprite
images packed into it in some way right
that is a sprite sheet a texture atlas
is just the word for any texture image
that you might use in a game or anywhere
really where you have packed in some way
some set of data into it that isn't just
one single rectangular image now it has
nothing to do with what an artist may
have made right an artists doesn't
usually make a texture Atlas directly
usually when you talk about texture
Atlas you're talking about something
that some pre-process or took a bunch of
data and you know jammed it in in a
particular way with certain borders of
certain sizes right and more
specifically texture atlases although in
the case of a 2-d game this may often be
the case for simplicity and because
you're not really usually pushing GPU
memory to its limits in the case of a 3d
game a texture analyst can often refer
to things that aren't even rectangular
lis packed right so a texture Atlas may
have things that are irregular they're
all kind of shoved together with just a
little bit of space in between them and
then you're actually pulling like shaped
regions out of them because you have to
imagine like you've got like triangle
meshes that are pulling out of these
things they don't actually have to be
rectangular right so again spritesheet
is an art term if you're using it
properly texture Atlas is a technical
rendering term and while you can make a
sprite sheet that you use directly as a
texture Atlas because you do no
processing on it when you pull it in and
you pull out of it directly from the
thing the artists actually painted you
can do that that's a
that's just a possible thing that could
happen but there is no actual
correspondence between a sprite sheet
and a texture atlas by definition there
are two very different concepts it might
help to clarify that distinction right
we are using note we are not using
texture Atlas we are sort of using
sprite sheets when the artists make
something that would go into handmade
hero they are going to be making them
based on a sprite layout we have a
number of them
so those sprite layouts look you know
like this here's an example right and
you can see that there's a bunch of
blank space so that's a very good
example of why we don't use this at
runtime another reason is because it's
much higher res than we use at runtime
we actually downsample because the
source art is higher res than the actual
one use a game but that's one of the
reasons why we go through and we
actually only extract the pieces from
the sprite sheet that we actually see
anywhere in this write sheet that's got
that doesn't have a frame of animation
for it
we just don't save right and again
that's just to make it so that we're not
just saving gobs of empty nonsense in
there right so that's all alright I
think that's it for questions so I'm
going to go ahead and wrap it up thank
you everyone for joining me for an
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure talking with you as always
if you do want to follow along the
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero org it comes
with a source code so that you can you
know sort of follow along with what I'm
doing and also play around it yourself
do some experimentation and and so on
right now I want to make an announcement
next weekend is actually not gonna be a
regular episode of hammer here I can
have a special episode of handmade hero
and that'sthe anchors write a good
stopping point actually we've kind of
done all of the work all the main
structural work and so
okay take a little bit break and come
back in after skipping a week to do the
debugging process right because that's
sort of a separate thing but what I want
to say is next weekend will be a very
special stream what we're going to be
doing is as you know I get a bunch of
upgrades to for coder I spent about
three weeks on it which was more than I
was originally planning to but I kind of
just wanted to get it all done so I did
a ton of upgrades to for coder
most of which you have not seen yet
because I've not actually updated the
for coder in two weeks time the goal
with a lot of those modifications was to
get them back into for coder proper so
that everyone can use them why I don't
know I'm just feeling generous I guess
who knows but so what I wanted to do was
get all of those modifications back to
Alan so that they could get into for
coder and be mainlined
over time so in order to do that though
I've made like so many updates to the
source base at this point it's not super
feasible to just hand it over so what we
wanted to do was have Alan and I get
together and just kind of go over all
the stuff moving into for coder as best
we can as sort of an adjunct system that
can get built alongside the four coder
source code and then once that's
happening I think Alan will then be able
to sort of move them over into for coder
over time so basically all of the mods
that I've made can get mainlined in as
sort of he gets a chance to digest those
and you know expand them a bit because
actually they're like totally specified
specific to how I wanted it to work and
so you know he's gonna want to brought
in a lot of them probably to make them
more generally applicable to the way
everyone else might want to mod it and
so on so what we're gonna do this coming
weekend is we're gonna do a for coder
Jam Alan and I will probably both stream
or we'll do some kind of hybrid stream
or something
so it'll either be on his channel or my
channel or both channels at the same
time
what we can get working and so stay
tuned for more information about that
but basically it'll should be basically
the same way you watch handmade hero the
schedule will go up it's at the set of a
normal have sort of handmade hero it'll
be the four coat of jam and we don't
know yet whether it'll be Saturday and
Sunday or just saturday we'll see how
far we get through it we may find that
we just haven't gotten far enough after
Saturday's over and then we'll do a
Sunday so that's our plan it's a little
bit tentative but you know that's what
we're playing do so stay tuned for that
and we should you know be able to post
on the watch page on the Twitter Allen's
and mine and handmade hero what's going
on so that you'll be up-to-date with
what's going on there and so that should
be pretty exciting we've got tons of new
features that that I think will be
pretty awesome and that you'll want to
see so far like basically like it's
really really far ahead of Emax now so
you know compared to what Allen
originally replaced which was Emacs you
know for coder has sort of been a like a
replacement that was way better
performance but was missing some of the
features of Emacs Allen is slowly added
basically all the features from Emacs
that I was using except for what's where
I'm before except for macro recording
Mac recording something's Allen working
on now so I haven't looked at that but
what I did is I went ahead and just
added a ton of features that basically
takes it like way past anything that
Emacs ever did by far right so now it's
got like just way better sort of feature
support than Emacs had because Emacs was
basically a giant bloated pile of list
of stuff most of which does things I
didn't care about and it really didn't
have a lot of features for things I do
care about like really fast code based
navigation things that I wanted and
stuff like that so what I've done is
I've kind of gone like all right now
that for coders up to the point where it
basically replaced Emacs what can I do
to like basically get better than Emacs
everywhere where I you know can just say
like okay
literally every operation I ever do on a
codebase this is way better than what do
you max was providing and so I've done
that and when we combine that back with
what Alan's doing with macro recording
which is the one feature that was still
missing I think by that time it'll it'll
just be like totally trancing Emacs like
it would be crazy that you'd ever bother
to use Emacs assuming that what you do
is code C++ for a living right so that's
it and and we'll be doing that next
weekend and that will include like demos
of all the new features and stuff which
I think you'll be pretty much in so
don't don't miss it until then have fun
programming everybody and I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy