hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here a power outage edition we were
supposed to start at 9:00 this morning
least that's when I originally scheduled
this particular broadcast to occur
however what we quickly found and by we
I mean what I quickly found was that the
power was not actually the the entire I
want to say six blocks Square area that
the office is in went completely dark
just was like and I had been playing
actually player unknowns battlegrounds
with some friends and I was right in the
middle of sniping someone out a window
and the screen just went and all the
lights went out and I was like all right
so I guess I won't be streaming tomorrow
so I posted on Twitter that there's
going to be some issues after that
happened when the power kick it's a long
story I posted some issues that I posted
some information on where it's like okay
we won't be able certain time but the
power did come back so I'll you know
when I get to the office we will be able
to do a stream which is gonna be later
and so here we are three hours later
from when we were supposed to be but we
are streaming so hopefully the reason I
bring all this up hopefully if the power
is back in a way that is sustainable
because if it's not we're gonna lose
this stream so yeah if you see this
stream suddenly go dead sometime in the
next two hours before I actually finish
that is what happens and I apologize but
yeah one of the sort of problems of
modern life is that without electricity
pretty much nothing we do can continue
to be done and we all have to go back to
being cavemen and foraging for food
alright let's go ahead and get back to
what we were doing last weekend I was
right in the middle of making some
fairly important changes to the lighting
specifically what
wanted to do was make it so the lighting
system would receive primarily
[Music]
rectangular elements right rectangular
prisms sort of axis aligned bounding
boxes if you will that would be used as
the lighting elements and so instead of
having it be sent down to the system as
individual faces because what we were
doing was sending them down individual
faces of cubes what I want to do instead
is have it so it sends them down
in this fashion instead where you've got
this sort of yet where you kind of have
this this understanding that the only
way that light gets transported around
is as a series of of these right
rectangular prisms and there's never a
case where you've got sort of individual
faces happening anymore so we started
that change and it's in progress what we
did is we made it so that we are
directly pushing the lighting now but
we're still directly pushing it on as a
series of faces so when we go to push a
lighting elements instead of pushing the
cube on as a cube we are pushing it on
as an individual face now what I want to
do is slowly move from there to you know
I'm going to do each successive step I
want to slowly move from there to
pushing on the actual cubes themselves
but again I'm trying to take it one step
at a time now even though we don't
actually care if this code works or not
because we're just sort of doing it to
have baby steps we just want to make
sure it's roughly working it is the case
that we made an error some folks found
it when they were working with the code
over the week it is a case that I made a
typo in the order in which the faces get
pushed on well I guess it's not the
order in which the faces get pushed on
it's actually in how I believe that
which order the faces were facing I want
to say so this routine is actually not
quite correct
I guess it's this one right here I'm not
sure I have to go look at it but point
being some folks found a bug in there
which I'm quite sure is
is going to turn out to actually be a
bug because yeah I did that really
quickly and there's a lot of sort of
fussy stuff that's that's easy to get
incorrect so if we take a look at what's
happening here here's our place where
we're pushing on the lighting
information and then if you look here
here's where we're pushing on the
lighting points and then finally we're
pushing on the actual quads right and
you can see that there's just a lot of
business involved here and this is one
of the reasons why I want to keep kind
of cutting this stuff down to it's
because it's just it's just a lot of
information traffic I mean all of this
work costs real CPU time and it's just
unnecessary because if we know we're
kind of got a good way to do the
lighting based on cubes and that's
really all we need from the thing we
don't really want to be specifying them
as individual little faces because it's
just adding complexity and tot and
wasting time in the system that doesn't
actually give us any benefit right if we
can't express something more simply and
more compactly usually it's a benefit
for us to do so and so that's exactly
what we're doing here all right so now
let's take a look at what the the the
bug was I have the report actually I can
bring it up on on the github here a hold
on a second let's take a look at the
github I'm doing this on the streaming
computer which is why you don't see it
happening so in the issues list it says
and this was reported by IROC I ruk I
don't really know how that is pronounced
but switched X surfaces positive and
negative and push group render group
function its specifying that online for
99 which is oops which is this one right
here it says we start with negative X
but the first push quad below is this
one and it has the you know separate
quad there and so the lighting surfaces
are just getting swapped on X
right it's basically what's happening
here is this is getting negative x
positive x but I guess the two phases
are actually positive X negative x for
whatever reason so in other words in
here right here P 1 P 5 P 6 P 2 let's
see what that actually is yeah so these
are positive X's so so that is correct
so this is actually supposed to be the
positive x face and if it's the positive
x face that means it's normal points
that way and the same here the negative
x face it points that way similarly once
we flip these two we've got the x axis
is going to be flipped because it's
going to be rotated around other than
that they're pretty much identical
there's nothing else that's gonna change
between them I don't suspect that makes
much of a difference basically all that
means is the lighting from one face got
assigned to another face and vice-versa
so the lighting solution should still
run pretty much identically it's just
the lighting would have been subtly
wrong all the X faces you would have
seen the lighting on the wrong side of
the cube so as you moved a light past
for X you would see it on the wrong side
of the cube now I don't know if we can
really get a look at that happening per
se but let's let's do this so this would
be the X face of the cube right here for
example so if I move the light around it
you can kind of see that it that is it
on the correct side of it at the moment
right and so if I go back here and I and
I flip these two again if I just kind of
put it back the way it was we should be
able to see that face be dark instead
because it's getting lighting from the
other side where there isn't any light
coming in right so if I kind of oops
yeah and you can actually see that's
exactly what's happening right so you
can see that
missing there and like I say it's kind
of a subtle bug because it's easy to not
notice especially in a game that happens
to have the x-axis going this way it's
it's understandable why we didn't
immediately see it because all the other
directional services are working fine so
you know that that's why that bug was
not immediately obvious to us when when
we made that error but I think that's
fixed now that seems okay let's test the
other side as well all right so that
seems reasonable and I can close this
bug here for 21 yeah
all right all good
well we're on here what else do we have
there's some handmade raised stuff but
not a whole lot in there that we need to
look at right now so we'll leave that
all right so now all we really need to
do is start looking at how we're going
to pass these down to the lighting
system more directly right so now that
we know that when we do this push right
and we do the push cube on here we're
producing all of this business right and
what we would like to do is replace all
of this business with a single thing you
know just just one call that would allow
us to represent all of this information
more concisely now it's worth noting
that we can't really do exactly some of
this stuff needs to be done explicitly
and the part that needs to be done
explicitly is the placement of the
points for light sampling on the cube so
for example all of this stuff here is
all easy to procedurally generate
meaning we can just say here is the
description of the center radius the
center and radius of the cube and that's
really all you need to know right that's
a pretty straightforward thing for us to
to figure out and to have work so this
pushing this information on is is fairly
trivial the thing that's not so trivial
is the point assignment point assignment
could easily be something that we
actually want to vary per cube that we
send down there's a couple different
reasons for this one is that the number
of points that we sample for
lighting on each cube may want to be
proportional to a number of things that
are not immediately known about the cube
for example if it is something that's a
very important element of a seam we may
want it to be sampled more densely than
things that are less important and that
we don't really care what kind of
lighting they get things off on the
periphery or back in the middle of a
forest or something right so it's
entirely possible that there's actual
game knowledge that when the world
generator is generating the the scenes
for the game and it's putting everything
down it's going to want the ability to
specify more specifically what these
points are and how they are sampled
right and so in order to accommodate
that we kind of need to be pushing the
points on very directly so that's the
part that's going to be the most
complicated here that's the part that
doesn't translate directly this part
right here will translate very directly
all we have to do is just effectively
push on the center and radius of the
cubes and I that's literally it like
there's nothing else that has to
translate but the point index which
points go with which faces of the cube
and how many there are that part is is
the part we're gonna have to sort of
rida terminally we need some way of
putting that information in and it's not
going to be straightforward there's not
an obvious right way to do that all
right so let's start with the stuff that
we can deal with right so what I'm doing
here is going to pull out the stuff
they can all just get collapsed down so
all of this information here this stuff
this is all stuff that we could specify
very succinctly okay so the way that we
would do this right is we could just say
like we were going to push on some kind
of a light cube right or it's not really
a light cube but it's a light box let's
say and we know that it's got a minimum
corner and a max corner and we have that
that information just readily available
right why is this P dot X oh no no we
want you just want this right yeah
because that's the position these are
the positives and negatives so we know
the bounds of our cube there right there
so once we have the bounds of the cube
it's trivial to just push that
information on and then from that
information all of the rest of this
could be discovered right there's
nothing else in here that we actually
need there is a transparency coefficient
which we either one specified per point
or per cube at the moment we don't have
any at all so we'll just assume that
it's per cube if the cube can pass light
through it we'll maybe put something on
there I don't know but that's kind of
ignore everything else on here is is
actually completely recoverable just
from that piece of information right
so the light box all of this work this
incredible amount of work necessary to
communicate this stuff down there that
can really all just be moved into the
lighting system and furthermore we can
even bake it into a lot of the equations
so that we probably don't even need to
explicitly expand this out anymore the
first step will do will be to expand it
out explicitly because again I'm trying
to do some baby steps very complicated
it's not complicated intellectually it's
complicated bookkeeping wise and you
typically try to take those steps slow
so you don't introduce a little bit we
already had one right like that positive
negative flip so I want to take baby
steps but right we we probably will
never even have to generate all of this
information explicitly inside the
lighting system we can probably rewrite
a lot of our equations like our ray
caster to operate directly on the box
itself and only generate this piece of
information on demand which again will
save us a lot of space a lot of cash
bandwidth all kinds of stuff right so
it's potentially very important to do
this change not even just for the fact
that we need it structurally so that we
can start attacking this problem in a
more multi-resolution sense but also
because this is just even if we were
just gonna leave the lighting algorithm
exactly it is right now and not make any
further improvements to it we would
still be in a situation where we kind of
want we kind of want this to be the case
regardless right we kind of want this
more compact representation no matter
what so the thing that we don't know how
to do is we then have this light to
point that this sorry cube face these
are the faces of the cube that we were
recording here right or box it's not a
cube it has different dimensions XY and
Z well at the moment I think moment the
only dimension that can vary is actually
Z x and y are always the same size as
each other they're always equivalent but
the Z can vary but that's not a
requirement for a lighting system anyway
so if we take a look at what's going on
here the problem that we see is that
each one of these faces of the cube was
previous is saying okay there's a
certain number of things that I record
right there's a certain number of points
that I am accounting and the problem
that here is that we don't really have
any way of specifying that in the cube
in some kind of
a concise way so what I'm going to do is
I'm just going to do it in a non concise
way first and we'll work on improving it
later because we don't really know what
we're gonna see as we sort of get a
little bit further down there so what
I'm gonna do instead is just literally
record exactly this if we just say light
box light index and say that there's
going to be six of these then I can just
pretty much specify them directly right
I can just say all right there's light
index there's light in an X plus four
you see where I'm done with this right
and furthermore we could actually have
an extra one in here and I'll show you
what why we would do that in a second
so we have 4 8 12 16 20 24 right and
there's our 24 hour 24 pieces of light
information which is exactly how many we
would expect there to be we get rid of
all this stuff entirely right well I
guess I shouldn't get rid of it entirely
because this stuff is going to be used
probably in the light system so what I
will do instead is I'll just move it
over to the lower part of render group
where the extract Hall was happening for
us we've deleted that call because we
don't actually have to extract anymore I
believe where is that
so in here we're we're actually doing
the lighting right before we make that
call you could see we set up stuff for
bike by grabbing out the information
from the lighting group which is this
stuff here so what we would want to do
here is it's just take a second to
actually expand this stuff out here
right all right so that's this going to
go there and I suppose not sure exactly
how I want to do lighting stuff so we'll
look at that probably do it pretty
similar to how we're doing it before but
there we go if we take a look at what's
going on here we now no longer after
that fussing with light index either
because it's just going to be the it's
just gonna be exactly what we think it
should be I'm not sure why okay latex is
right there I was gonna say it should be
somewhere right here so if you take a
look at what I did here is I said okay
the zeroth one is the first light index
we're supposed to use the one element is
going to be that plus four then plus
another four plus another four plus
another four plus another four that's
all the lighting sees you'll notice I
went one over so this would be if there
was a seventh face of the cube this is
or the box this is what it would be
right here now the reason I did that is
because this allows me if I have a one
extra element it allows me to just use
the concept that I can take the one
higher element and subtract the previous
element to get the count for any slot so
light blacks light index zero tells me
where I am for the first face of my cube
right but the next element also tells me
if I take what the next face starts at
if I subtract that if I subtract away
the one I'm on from the next one I get
the number of points that I am using for
my face right so what happens is when
you get to the last one which is light
index five
here if I didn't put in one extra entry
I wouldn't know how many were assigned
to the fifth face because there'd be
nothing to use as the next bound so by
adding one extra entry to the array it
allows us to use it as a set of spans
instead of just a set of indices and so
that's just basically a cap a pad on
there for that purpose okay so we can
basically pass all of the information
all of this stuff that we were passing
before it can all be passed effectively
this way and so that's what we're going
to do because you can see how much more
concise that is so what we want to do is
we want to say that there's something
called a lighting box let's say and we
just call this light box we now have
something called like a light box count
and that just gets added you know a plus
plus simple in there I'm not sure why so
this yet so this surface indexed stuff
also needs to kind of get changed a
little bit since these are packed in
order now but this stuff doesn't really
have to work this way this really just
looks like that right
so all we're doing is is getting the
next lightbox and that's all we have to
do and again we're not really super
concerned about any specificity on here
this is this is all just pretty basic
sort of test code of how we're gonna do
it we may not push it on exactly this
way in the future but we just will kind
of want to get the basic idea here so
the group light index part that's still
gonna be the same as it was so that part
this part still hasn't been sort of
fussed with at all it's really just this
part that we're talking about so now the
surface index part it's we still have to
do this loop in order to put the points
on here but it no longer has to be
talking about any particular surface
index right you can just put these
points on directly and they're all going
to come from the same light box and the
the challenge that we're gonna face here
and I don't again this is the part where
I say this this point assignment stuff
is pretty tricky the challenge that
we're going to face here is that we
don't really know for any given surface
point we don't know which part of the
cube it corresponds to so we have to
kind of see in the lighting system could
we get away with not ever having the
backwards index happen and I think it
might be possible that we could but
we're just I'm just not 100% sure right
but if we take a look here we can kind
of see a little bit more what's going on
so let's just continue down this road a
little bit i if you take a look at how
these are specified here's the lighting
point and the lighting surfaces here
you're letting point is here you could
see the piece of information we have
this surface index that's you know
recorded as part of the point
the question really is where does that
get used right and this is us just
pushing it on I assume that's behind my
head there what's going on there why can
I see that yeah alright so inside in the
surface in next thing here you can see
that really the only place that this is
getting talked about is actually in the
output function so that's kind of nice
and if we look at why that is I it's
really just to grab those those axes
those two right there so what's really
interesting about that is that means we
effectively just don't need it right
that's that's pretty fantastic so what
that means is this will be even easier
than I thought
unless we run into another situation
where we find that we're doing something
new in the lighting that does require
that back pointer but I really don't
want that like I didn't want that there
so the answer is yeah we really kind of
want something more like this where
lighting points just really do not have
any kind of back pointer back to the
surface that they're doing so we will
continue on doing exactly that
okay so if we yeah if we go back to how
we were pushing these points on is that
uh I suppose we probably don't want to
leave that in there this is when we
prefer when we were debugging um sorry
that's just funny to see that in there
so when we're pushing these points on
that's really great news that basically
means that the points just don't ever
have to know and so we can get rid of
the lighting surface stuff here all
together it's just not relevant anymore
but what we do have to do is have a way
of producing the information we actually
need to distribute the points as far as
where the points are actually supposed
to go now we can do this a little bit
more procedurally than we were doing it
before and so we can make this probably
a more compact something more compact
routine than the one that had like all
of you know all of this stuff kind of
blown out completely so let's try and
make sure that we can do that so here we
take a look at what we need for our
surface and you can kind of see all the
information that we need right and it's
the information that we had sort of
expanded out in here into individual
values so we need to be able to compute
this stuff and we need to be able to
just compute it on the fly inside the
loop for what we need so we need the
position of the face in terms of the
center position of the face although
well if you look at we really don't
necessarily need to do it that way we
could rewrite this routine as being just
in terms of the positive and negative
portions of it so we could choose to do
it either way since this isn't a
particularly important routine I'll just
leave it the way it is because this is
going to go away and these will be
specified by the world generation code I
suspect in the in the end like I was
suggesting but so what we really need to
do here is to have a way of specifying
this information in a more procedural
then we work and there's a couple
different ways we could do this I'm not
sure exactly which one is throw
one way is we can just make it be
table-based another way is we can sort
of figure out how to generate it as a
tableau where we just kind of look at
the pattern that happens in them
so I'm not sure what the most concise
way to do this would be uh bear my three
for one second we do have a way of
looking at at the yeah so if we at least
we have a nice debug view here so we can
look to see if we're generating a
sensible set of reflectors you know we
can kind of get them at a glance here as
we as we as we look at them you know and
I would also add potentially it looks
kind of like we're not really doing a
very good job distributing these things
it looks like there's a bug yeah like
these these are higher than they should
be these are offset upward compared to
where they should be so when we did that
port we had another bug right here that
nobody found which is okay like I said
this code is just mangy at the moment
anyway we're just kind of we haven't
gotten the point where we're locking it
down at all so it's fine but that
computation there is incorrect or one of
these was incorrect like for example
that maybe the width and height is
incorrect in some way or the x-axis
doesn't doesn't look like those could be
wrong that this don't look so it's
mostly this stuff that's that's looking
a bit scans here I'm not sure I'm not
sure why because it looks
yeah well yeah I mean that that does
yeah now that I look at it that doesn't
look good anyway ignore that for a
second because we will do this slightly
differently but point being when we do
this surface in next year we're gonna
have to have some way of translating
from a surface index or any other kind
of loop we could do you know more than
one loop we could do a nested for-loops
if you want to who knows but we need to
have some way of translating from the
like an index for a face of some kind
into something that gives us the
information that we need now like I said
we don't really need this surface
p-value the way that it was before it
said and we don't need the x-axis or
y-axis or any of those things actually
all we really need is the min/max
that the point needs to be distributed
in right so for example what we could
say is that X sub is going to give a
proportion of how far along the surface
we're supposed to go and then we just go
that far between the min and the max
right so for example if we were to say
that X sub you know in this case this
it's going to be 0 and 1 we divide that
by 2 and we get 0 and 0.5 if we offset
that by 0.25 we could then just do that
far in between right so we could do
something where we said all right we
want this point to be you know some kind
of alert in between the the min corner
in the max corner X and some lurk
between the min quarter and the max
corner Y
so we just have like em in corner X next
corner X in 2000 I max corner Y n oops I
did not want that to just happen and
that's really all we would need to do
right so we could just produce something
like this and then we would need the the
normal to the surface
so we need the certain we we don't need
this service index at all anymore so we
just need the surface normal and the min
and Max corner right that's really all
the information we actually need to
produce we don't need any of this stuff
at all right and so what we can do is we
could just do it this way and we know
what the X sub ratio and the Y sub ratio
are the Y sub ratio is just going to be
0.25 F plus y sub / y sub count so
that'll give us point two five and point
seven five which is I think roughly
where we wanted to place these and who
knows where we want to place them in
reality well like I said this is just
kind of you know temporary stand-in code
for at some point we're assuming we'll
figure out exactly how we want to place
points when we're generating world
geometry so that just gives us sort of a
generic placement of those points and
then we know that really all we have to
do is figure out just those three things
min corner max corner normal right so
it's min corner max corner
serves normal and I think that is
everything that we actually needed oops
all right
so once that's done then we need to and
we're gonna have to go back there and
actually do that computation we need to
specify this stuff that we're actually
storing here now and you can see we've
got our lighting box that we had started
on but we didn't quite finish and we had
already come to this conclusion
amusingly enough put this like that what
we didn't do yet is specify how these
like lighting indices and stuff works so
like I said I think I'm just going to go
with the fact that the lighting indices
will be the 0 through 6 work so we're
gonna have seven of these just like 1
extra we don't really want to have an
extra short sitting there probably that
doesn't sound particularly good so you
know we probably want eight of them for
now like I guess we could do it this way
right because we really just don't want
you know these things to be we don't
want seven shorts like so there's a 16
bit thing hanging there we need to think
about you maybe there's something we
could put in here as well or you know
we've basically got a slot to use there
we're not gonna leave that fallow anyway
so now we have to make sure that this
piece is this piece piece of information
are sent down let me just take a quick
look at this what is the question it
doesn't like
what doesn't like about that that seems
Semenko international argument list ah
here we go so right right right right I
jumped the gun on that here this is not
a component based ad so what this
actually is is we need to start at the
min corner right cuz we don't know we're
in three dimensions we are we're on some
2d surface that's embedded in three
dimensions and we want to move along its
two axes along these ratios the X sub
ratio and the y sub ratio so we need to
start at the min corner then we need to
go from the min corner the the axis that
is from the min corner to the max corner
along one way right we need to to move
along that by the X sub ratio and then
we need to move along the other one by
the Y sub ratio so it is a little more
complicated than I was making it out to
be because we don't have the information
that we need just from the min chord in
the max pointer without looking at the
individual elements to see which ones
are equal to know which one we have to
move along if that makes sense
stated alternately
so
if we assume that we want to produce
points like here here here and here
which is what we were doing we need some
way of being able to actually arrive at
these locations from the information
that we have and the MA for Asian we
have is a min corner and a max corner
but the problem is we don't actually
know where those are in space so they
could be you know such that it looks
like this
right it could be such that it looks
it's etc so the problem is just how do
we yeah how do we come up with a clean
way of doing that that doesn't just to
generate to exactly what I was doing
before and the answer is maybe we have
to do it the exact way that I was doing
it before it may be that we have to just
generate an x and y axis because we know
that this equation is going to require
those two it's not immediately obvious
to me how you generate that for them and
max that's just looking at the elements
and seeing which ones they have in
common so yeah so I think we may have to
be a little bit more a little bit more
explicit here which is unfortunate I was
hoping there would be some really nice
way to do this but I don't know that
they're really actually is
so here's the thought supposed to be
goof by acts by axis X Y Z and then for
each axis we do the positive and
negative version
Sarris I each my ankle do not ask me why
but get you ankle fleas probably so if
we go access by access and then do
positive and negative then at least one
thing we could say is we immediately
know the surface normal right because if
we assume that the surface normal starts
as just all zeros and then we just go
ahead and say well whatever element we
were whatever axis were on that element
of the normal equals either one or
negative one depending on whether we're
on the positive or negative version of
it right similarly I think we could
generate the min and Max corner that way
so like for example once we know the
surface once we know which one the
surface normal is it seems like getting
the X and y axis becomes relatively it
becomes possible at that point as well
because we can produce the other axes
related to that axis probably in a
similar way right if we assume that we
want our thing to be pointing
counterclockwise out the axis that we're
on we should be able to do something
like well just take the cross-product
with that axis or something similar
right for example if we took some other
axis we know is orthogonal to this one
so whichever direction the surface
normal is pointing in i if we want to
produce a coordinate system that is just
an X and Y axis based on that coordinate
system we should be able to do so I
think that's a little more
let's start with the min and Max corner
because I think we can use those as well
so we know that the min corner of the we
know the min corner and Max corner of
the cube are coming from these right
here and we know what they are right so
we we know just by default that that if
all we wanted was the min and Max corner
of the cube we could just get that right
that's it's just trivial so the question
then is well if we know the minimax
corner of the cube how do we know what
the min and Max corner of the face are
right because if you look they're not
the same thing
for the cube if you assume the axes look
like this then this is the max corner
and this is the min corner right of the
cube but for any given face you know
like it might be more like this like
this maybe the min corner and this may
be the max corner for this face so
whatever and I and the way that that
works right is that if it's the positive
face then you're gonna replace like the
min and Max corner are always gonna be
exactly the same on two of the axes
right it's just one of the axes gets
drawn back so basically the min in the
min corner what you're going to do is
force one of these elements to be
positive and you're gonna force the
element to be positive
that's whichever face you were doing so
for example if I'm going out the
positive x face then the min corners x
axis just has to be moved up to the
positive side right so that that's all
that's happening here
likewise the max corner is going to do
the same thing the max corner is going
to to have the same change and we can
write this more compactly actually by
just saying well if it's positive or if
it's negative we do one or the other
right so in the positive case we have to
move the min corner up in the negative
case we have to move the max corner back
right so that's that's all we're really
doing so I think that gives us the
surface and the min Max corner of the
face that we're talking about so at that
point what we need to figure out is all
right if we're going to do the the
placement of something on this face we
need some way of knowing how to apply
our to like because since we're trying
to distribute things along those surface
according to the AXI somehow we need
some way of having the x axis and the y
axis for that we would move along and in
order to do that I guess trying to think
of how this would work
so I can't think of any straightforward
way to do it there probably is one well
you know we could do let's just do this
by tableau because I was gonna say we
could do the cross this doesn't seem
like we should have to we should be able
to read this off exactly because that is
axis aligned it should be a lot simpler
than then doing something fancy like
that right while we're at it we can
simplify this part a little bit here
right so this is our fix up for the
positive a negative case so let's take a
look at what our x and y axes actually
would have been in these cases
so here's axis
here's positive right so the axis goes 0
0 1 1 2 2 and the positive is just
alternating 0 1 0 1 0 1 0 so now we just
need to know well ok for each one of
these what would the X and y axis
actually be right so here's the x axis
just the y axis
maybe I'll leave space alright so the
question is what should each of these be
for the order we're doing them in here
so I in this case we've got a surface
normal we're gonna start off with axis 0
which is the x axis and we're starting
off with positive being 0 so this can be
negative so the surface normal is going
to be negative 1 so it's pointing out
the negative x axis right which is he
which is here so we want our in that
case we want our Y axis
to be the up you know the z axis right
we did this before
so our Y axis is the z axis is just
pointing up and our x axis is going to
be the the negative Y axis right it's
going to be coming out this way does
that seem fair I hope it does we would
then do the positive x axis and that
means that we would have the opposite
thing for the Y so the y axis our x axis
is going to be positive Y instead of
negative Y so it would be like that but
our y axis would still be Z up right we
would then move on to the Y faces so
these are the Y faces so the negative Y
face is facing facing up this way so the
Z is still it's still going to be the
axis for that face that points upwards
right now mind you we may want this to
we this may this might make the tableau
harder to do this way but it doesn't
really matter how we choose to do these
so I'm just doing it that way because
that's
more human intuition when you look at
the cube but we could be more like
winding oriented about it and say that
it should be this other thing because of
the cross product or something right so
there's other ways we could decide to do
this because there's more than one X and
y axis you could use that would be
orthogonal on this plane and still
aligned with the cube right there's
several permutations you could choose
so anyway assuming that's the y axis is
this case then we need to know well what
is the x axis in this case for the
negative one it's going to be the
positive x and we get around to the
other side it's going to be the opposite
right so it looks like that and then
finally when we do the Z we're going to
end up with sort of the opposite thing
happening here so if we take a look at
what needs to happen for the y axis in
the z case the y axis could be a number
of different things but I suppose if
we're looking down from the top of it we
would expect to see for the positive z
face we would want the x axis and the y
axis to be actually themselves so for
the positive z face here we respect to
have an actual x axis an actual Y axis
be enough and then when you would flip
it around on the other side well there's
there's two different ways that we could
look at it but probably the thing we
would do is flip the x axis on it
because what we've been doing is
flipping the x axis so we'll just stick
with that as sort of the convention so
order so you can skip it the y axis
would remain the same so it just looks
like this and instead of of the x axis
pointing this way it would now point
this way down negative x right so that's
for the negative z face so if you take a
look at what we've got here this is a
pretty interesting tableau to look at
the only thing that I would point out is
so you can see what I was talking about
before in terms of how the x axis the y
axis are a little bit wonky compared to
what you might expect you could probably
make this a little bit more of a
straightforward tableau by p
a little bit smarter about how these two
things are set up because you can see
the x-axis doesn't follow a particularly
good pattern it's like negative 1 1 1
negative 1 negative 1 1 right which is
we probably could have got that to be a
negative 1 1 negative 1 1 negative 1 1
all the way down if we wanted to
by changing sort of a rule for how we
were doing those but so that y-axis is
pretty straightforward right it's just
always that and the only thing that we
really have to do is say if axis index
equals 2 y axis equals something else
right and I suppose since that's the
only place we do that I can just
represent that pretty compactly right
here so in that case you're just saying
all right we've got the axis index that
determines which one of these 2 we use
as soon as we're on Z we switch either
way and maybe we need something else
here when we do this we'll see and then
we'd have to expand that back out but it
looks like the x axis is kind of a
little bit wonky just in general so we
need two things for the x axis we need
to the sign and then which slot it goes
into right so down here we're going to
kind of do v3 x axis and we're going to
do something like I guess this if the
axis index is 0 it's going to be that
otherwise that
and the problem here is we need to know
what the sign of that is right because
it's only takes on two values those two
values but we don't know which sign it
is so we've got two cases where it's
negative 1 1 so in this case we could
say well it's positive based on the
positive value if it's 0 its negative if
it's 1 it's positive right except for
the y-axis case so we just say you know
if Y axis or sorry x axis index equals 1
and now we've got all that information
at this one I don't think we need the
max corner anymore we didn't end up
using the max corner really too much in
this so really all we need is the span
like how far it is to go between those
two so we really just need this value
but you know whatever now we've got all
the information we need could probably
ever need so in this case we just need
to go all right we're gonna go to the
min corner the X sub ratio I guess
that's not entirely true
I suppose we still want to take the
measure of the span on the x axis and
the y axis as well so we sort of want
our scaled x axis here I guess that
makes sense but anyway so we've got our
min corner we're gonna do our X sub
ratio times scaled X plus y sub ratio
times scaled Y and what we need to do is
figure out what those two things are if
those are not particularly hard once we
have our x axis and y axis we just need
to figure out how far we would go along
them to get all the way to the end and
we already know what that is
right that's just the the dot product of
the x-axis with whatever the span of the
side of the face is is going to tell us
how far along that axis we would go to
get to the end of the face right and so
now we've got a thing that will generate
this information for us in theory and we
should be good to go all right here we
go okay where are we out here here we go
just like our conversion you don't have
a surface index and I think that's it
that looks all good all right so we're
done with that part and now we have to
actually record like have a place to
record that lightbox information so now
I'm gonna switch back over to just doing
the bookkeeping here's the game render
commands we've got the surface to the
surface count we are now no longer going
to have surfaces we're just going to
have light boxes like so and everyone
who initializes one of these has to pass
one in
light Oh change the wrong one all right
uh and in theory that will have
generated a problem in win32 hand-made
where we're not actually pointing those
down there it is there's like boxes and
we're good so I think now we've got
everything done except for the part
where we actually light with these and
we'll take that again as sort of a a
slow step process so what I think we
should do here is just blow out using
the same algorithm we were using before
actually blow it out into the same the
same set of services from every lighting
box that we got recorded and we know
what those were effectively we could use
the exact same routine in fact I suppose
when I think about it if we want to we
can take this same algorithm we were
doing here which generates this stuff we
could actually just make this be a
function call that you call and it gets
you this information that seems pretty
good to me
so it would just be something like this
where you just asked for this stuff and
you get it so basically like
so you just need them in corner in max
corner to be passed into you I think
it's pretty much it
[Music]
you would pass in what the min corner
and Max corner were and the surface
index and then it would just pass you
back a result which just had all these
things in it so do light box surface
results results surface n so we could
just call that n just an y-axis whether
we need to scaled Y and scaled X I don't
know I'll leave them there for now but
but now you've got all the information
that you need to reconstruct one of
these guys and again I'm just doing that
so that way we know that they're
computed the same in both places right
because we need these two things to line
up and so we want this as much as
possible to use similar code to extract
them so that if we change it in one
place it'll still be reflected properly
in the other
all right so these light box services as
they are coming through here let me grab
this out as well because it's kind of
more appropriate to this routine now so
this kit box surface call we can just do
light box surface get box surface oh
whoops it's not surface index sorry its
axis index positive it's that and we
could just pass in a single index here I
and just generate those two from it and
maybe that's the better way to do it I
don't know so you know for example what
we could do is this suppose you were to
pass in a flat surface index so there's
just you just pass zero through six well
we know the low bit is just whether it's
positive or not right because that goes
zero one zero one zero one already so
positive is just surface index and one
right and the axis index is just a
surface in that shifted down by one
because getting rid of that bottom bit
oops right so we could just choose to do
it this way and then it's a little
cleaner as well I suppose because then
you can just say like alright I'm just
gonna go through the phases of this cube
and I don't want to have to like keep
doing all these loops and stuff because
why bother it's just more bookkeeping
let's just do it that way you know
so that's that's one way to do it seems
pretty reasonable you know who knows if
it actually is or isn't so in this case
where you see we've got the P X n X
thing here and we don't actually know
what those are anymore because they
haven't been passed in but we actually
do know this was just because they
happen to be in that routine that we did
it this way we could have easily said oh
and you know what this shouldn't be in X
and px anyway this is this was a bug
anyway these these should actually be
based off of the access index oh this
should be whatever the access index was
right it should have been this right but
anyway the plain thing is just because
we don't have the P and n values this
madam they got passed in as min corner
in Max corner anyway
so really it's just this it's just it's
really just pulling from from these
anyway so that's that doesn't matter and
hey we found a book which is even better
so we got a free bug fix out of it just
the same all right so we just need to
access these off of surface now so we'll
do that and then in here
and maybe we'll call this box surface
index like so I so all we need to do now
is we need to extract each one of these
out yeah excuse me as I stretch and we
don't really need any of this anymore
right all of this information we can get
from what we have now so really what we
just need to do is translate this sort
of systematically these lighting surface
values we just need to translate those
systematically back into from the
lighting box routine that we just wrote
into this routine and we'll be done well
modular debugging but you know what I
mean all right so anyway we've got tip
box surface here and that requires the
mid corner in the next corner we're
gonna have that because it's going to
come in as the box that we're reading
off of and then we need to create this
stuff fortunately we only have to do it
once we also do one of these these
because this loop will now take care of
all of these like so and we also need to
be able to generate that other
information that we cared about which
was if you remember inside that lighting
surface thing that we have to do light
index in the light count as well
okay so if we take a look at what's
going on here it's producing the surface
fee it's basically the same thing that
we were doing before if we were to take
box surface or rather box mid-corner
start at the box link corner and just do
box surface scaled X Box surface scaled
Y this would produce oops it's not true
we need to record one more piece of
information here that also needs to be
there right we need the min and the max
of the thing or just at least the min
right and the span that gives us the min
and the max the way that we want
actually I suppose the span we can just
go halfway along as well so we could
just say box surface min plus 0.5 X
times Box surface span that gets us
halfway across and into the center which
is what we wanted and so that's a bug in
our other routine as well let me just go
fix that so we don't forget get box
surface in here this isn't min corner
it's it's actually the min as computed
by this routine right min corner is not
supposed to be used except just to call
it right
and in fact we could avoid that being
used well we don't really want to though
I mean we want that to just be made once
and used here but you know either way I
guess we could do it this way all right
so taking a look at what we've got here
I think that's pretty much how we want
to do it and so now we just have to loop
we have to actually have a place to put
these and make sure that the light
indices line up before we do that I want
to make sure that this routine here
records the min max the min corner max
corner so result min needs to be and
corner like so and I think we're good
all right so that all seems good now
what we need to do is actually create
these arrays here in some more sensible
fashion so what we've got is the this
sort of lighting solution here where we
were pointing to surfaces before we
don't want to do we actually want this
to be a real thing now and what we're
going to do is we're going to loop over
each of those input boxes that we got
and blow them out into actual surfaces
so we know ahead of time what the
surface count is going to be the surface
count is just going to be whatever the
box count is times 6 because we're just
you know running through them and we
know that the lighting surface we should
also probably assert or I can even do it
count surfaces um so if you take a look
at what what we want to do here we need
the surface to sort of slowly go through
here so you know as we come through here
we just want to start at the first
surface record as each of these goes
through
we record one new surface and advance
the service pointer and off we go so all
we really need here is the box index and
the box count and we need to pull out
that box that were you know the source
box that was pushed on we need to pull
that out from here so where we gonna get
the box count from well it should in
theory have already been recorded right
it should have been recorded when we
push the cube on in the first place so
it should have been recorded right here
so we should have that information
available once we get here we just need
to actually fill in the rest of these
piece of information we're not really
doing transparency yet but we can pass
it through oops the width and height of
any particular face is actually now we
know that as well again it's the inner
product which we could have stored in
the Box surface piece of information
there but we kind of didn't that might
have been a mistake
but anyway box surface the inner product
of the normal and the span I'm sorry
that's x-axis and the stand and the
y-axis in the span give us our width and
height we know the X these two axes
because they already got computed so all
we really needed to know was the light
index in the light count and fortunately
for us that actually is also was
recorded in the box
information right the box has a light
index field so whichever surface were
all invested when we use and we can
actually just take whatever the next one
would have been remember I said we put
an extra into the array to figure out
how the count correspond it so that that
is again a lot of bookkeeping but that
is basically it there's there's really
not anything else to it
off we go never just get rid of that
residual their surface index what are
you talking about ah so for our debug
output where we're doing output lighting
points we have a couple of choices here
that we can how we choose to output this
information and I'm not sure exactly how
we want to do it we don't store the
surface index anymore for a lighting
point and we don't want to write we
don't want to be in the business of
having back pointers in our low-level
rendering stuff which is effectively
what that was so the more we can get rid
of stuff like that the better so the
only place that we're actually using it
is in the place where we're doing sort
of debug output right and the debug
output is not it's not essential so we'd
rather just spend a little more time in
here and generate something we can use
without having to have a back pointer
rather than compromise our whole
rendering data structure is just to put
in something that's only necessary and
debug I mean we could if debug it or
something like that but I don't really
want to if I don't have to so if we
delete the fact that we're getting a
service at all we immediately see the
two places we need it which are the two
axis values now the bonus here is that
we could just choose to use
we could do two things we could choose
to generate an axis or we could actually
just make the axis into some kind of a
temporary array by looping through the
surfaces and outputting the axes there
and I feel like that might be a more fun
way to do it because then we actually
are seeing which axis is actually being
used as a because there could be bugs in
that and it would be nice to see that
rather than generate it from the normal
which we have and us assume that the
axes were correct on the way in right so
hard to say but that's the basic idea
and I don't really know which one we
want to do it's really hard to say and
again it depends on whether we want
these to be debug things or not yeah so
I think I'm gonna do this way so here's
the way I'm gonna suggest we do this
here we were being rather literal we're
saying well we want output the letting
points let's loop over the points the
problem with doing that is that if we do
that it means that we don't actually
know what service they came from but
what we could do instead is just loop
over the surfaces right and if we loop
over the services and then loop over the
points
then we would know what the x and y-axes
work is we could get it from the surface
right so just by changing the way we
were iterating it we can get at that
information and that's all we need
what is the problem
lady Nixon like count ah those are
signed that must just be integral
promotion because they shouldn't be
signed there you 16 so it must just be
integral promotion if I was changed to
that it shouldn't complain right yeah it
was promoting this this you 16 - it s 32
I guess C's integral promotion rules or
not are not fabulous all right so let's
I think I think we have put everything
in place that we need to for this change
but we may have have buggy buggy booze
all over the place so let's go ahead and
start stepping through there let me make
sure I get a clean build on this as well
okay and start debugging these so let's
see what is the problem here so it looks
like our surface is sort of off the end
as we were looping through it
can i oh I'm like why can't expect your
thing we're in time overtime all right
yeah uh so if we take a look at our
surface you can see here that it's bogus
right it it sort of has valid memory up
to about here and then it becomes not
valid memory so first thing I want to do
is figure out what number we're on so
you can see we're we're not even
something's wrong like right off the bat
here it's just just bad so let me take a
look at is that can i define that wrong
and make sure I even defined it
correctly so we should have a ton of
these right you should have a ton of
these so let's see what's going on here
so solution surfaces so these are all
fairly valid so all of this looks ah
well that's our first problem I have no
idea what that what that was about right
there do you see it like what is
happening here I don't even understand
it's just so it's gonna stay in this
loop forever basically incrementing
surface ad infinitum until it runs out
of space so yeah that's not great you
know not a particularly good idea all
right so we are sort of part of the way
there but you can see we're messed up
right we should we should arrive back at
the same sort of lighting that we had
before but we're nowhere close right
this is not even really lighting it's
got stuff on kind of weird signs and so
on I'm
go ahead and switch to being able to
view the information that we should see
pretty clearly what's going on like it
should be completely wrong right so this
should have shown us our lighting points
we don't see any of them at all so we've
got a bunch of work to do let's get
started first things first I'm just
gonna jump into lighting test and just
get a sense of what the data looks like
like how wrong is it right does it look
sensible in here and maybe it's just
subtly wrong or is it just completely
fanciful totally stupid like there's all
kinds of problems whatever so let's
first take a look at that box surface
routine and what we can see from just
quick inspection of the box service
routine is it's not ludicrous right like
all of these things make some sense but
one thing jumps out is Mia being
obviously wrong our x-axis and wax set
to the same thing and I don't know about
you but chances are if I go to define
something with an x and y axis in there
the same I'm not gonna get a lot of
value have fat because you can't
actually make a two-dimensional surface
with only one dimensions worth of axes
so what is the problem well for starters
the problem
would appear to be wait that shouldn't
oh okay that's from I'm like that looks
right well turns out if you assign the
x-axis to both of them you don't get
very far
all right let's try that again also
let's take a quick look at what the
result is if it's any different I was
doing it's not because that that would
not have been sufficient to cause that
problem well it's a little bit different
so I guess it was it was enough
different all right
so you can see here these are the these
are the services that we're now working
with right you can you can see them
pretty plainly they actually don't look
all that wrong they're not right like
you can see we're getting some weirdness
here the positive Y services look kind
of like they're not working at all were
because this is the light right here and
we should have been seeing some light on
that it's okay that we're not seeing you
life back here but you can see that's
kind of a kind of looks bogus the other
thing is well yeah yeah yeah yeah
let me also quick take a quick spot
check out the timing how much time we
got left how much time do we have left
thirty few minutes we have a half hour
so we should be able to debug this in 30
minutes that's a lot of time hmm I did
not get much sleep last night due to the
power outage it was kind of annoying I
had to swim around for some lights and
deal with wondering about whether what
to do with the refrigerator and all
these sorts of things it doesn't matter
anyway
so running this in release mode yeah so
it's not like super slow right now or
anything so it didn't take a massive hit
or anything but so we're not too far off
but you can see like only some of our
services ever get light on them we
probably have some index mismatches or
some of the faces are not being computed
properly or various other things like
this right all right so let's slowly go
back through this and let's try to
figure out where we're at so I'm gonna
switch back to debug mode here and I'm
gonna adjust first things first we
introduced that light box service
routine and I would like to kind of go
through it and have some understanding
about whether or not I think it's
producing results that are plausible
right so I'm going to go into the push
cube function and you know kind of after
we do all of this business here and we
come down to specifying the light box
I'm gonna just take a quick look and
make sure that like all of its data is
correct and then I'm gonna look at what
we get for that that routine that
generates our various pieces of
information so our light index values 1
5 9 13 17 21 25 all look valid 0
obviously is reserved
so as for not having any lighting so it
makes sense that that starts 1 M goes up
that the way it does that's exactly what
you expect it's all good
mid-corner max corner certainly seem
fine nothing particularly odd there and
transparency is currently ignored
service index now we loop over and we're
going to go through six different zero
one two three and four and five and then
we're gonna take a look and see whether
we're getting you know sane results here
in terms of how we distribute these
points it's more or less all I really
want to know okay so let's suppose I
come in here to the box surface call and
I want to look at what the axis index is
it's zero meaning x-axis positive is
zero meaning it's the negative x-axis
that's what we'd expect I mean zero
shifted down and zero ended with a 1
both will produce zero so we're
specifically talking and why this screen
is flickering like mad like the no-good
gnome 3 or whatever it is is has all
sorts of weird bugs in it for window
compositing it's it's weird anyway so
this is the case that we're specifically
talking about here here's our normal and
we're going to compute that by using a
knockout here here is our span that is
ah that is incorrect that the span has
to be computed after this hold please we
before we go any further let me fix that
because the other values the dependent
are going
yeah because we can't take the entire
distance between the minimum and Max
quarter of the cube we want the distance
between the min corn in the max corner
of the face right yeah I think
everything else is fine all right so if
we now go ahead and try this one more
time let's take a look at what we get so
we've got our min and that should be
just the same as the min corner in this
case because it doesn't have to knock
out for the positive negative case so
it's it's all good all right so that's
these two should be equivalent and they
are the span should just be what it
takes to get to the max corner in two of
the dimensions but not the other so
since we are talking about this is the
positive x face there should be no span
along the x axis so the min corner Max
runner we should see this reflected in
the span and this reflected in the span
but not this right and that is what we
get that's exactly what we get so that's
great that that is what we want the
normal again negative x face should be
native X and it is x axis and y axis
look plausible to me and our scaled
versions also look plausible right so
that's good we now need to just just
distribute points on these surfaces
Our Lady mix is one which is the point
that we would expect to be distributing
so that's good you have an excess of
ratio and a y sub ratio so we have an X
sub ratio and a y sub ratio of 0.25
which is what we would want and we're
gonna set the surface normal for this
light thing to be whatever our radio
service normal was which we did we're
gonna take the surface man and we're
gonna add X sub ratio and scale times
scaled X and the y sub ratio times the
scaled why we should get a point that's
still within the bounds
and it should be but it should be pegged
to the minimum X which it is and we do
so that's good
we set the refere and the light index
here which is what we would expect to do
and we're off this won't change
substantively these are all the same
just with 75 now and now we come through
with another surface
so now we've moved on to the positive Y
and I guess I do still want to see white
box
corner oops
light box max corner it correctly set X
to be the positive version now so that
all looks good
normal looks correct yeah everything
looks fine to me
so now we're on Y negative that looks
right that looks right those are
plausible
yep
that so that now oops
Oh God I don't do that how do I have I
make it stop okay so that actually looks
fairly reasonable so I'm not sure why
now we're gonna have to go look at the
other side routine because I've that
looked pretty plausible to me in terms
of the surfaces that were being
generated there so I'm not sure exactly
what we're seeing as a problem there so
we're gonna have to go look at the other
side of it unless I missed something
this looks this routine looks like it's
reasonably solid now I see any obvious
problems with it
furthermore when I run this and look at
the locations where it put the points
they're actually more correct than they
were before this now looks like they're
actually in the correct locations
whereas for we actually had look like we
had a bug there so I'm fairly sure that
we're at least not you know grotesquely
wrong in some way producing those light
box functions because these now all look
like they're in pretty recent positions
what I don't know is whether the
correspondence is correct one thing that
you have to remember here is we're in a
bad position in terms of music who is
using that debug view to tell us whether
or not our lighting points correspond
with our lighting services correctly
because that the lighting services are
all regular they all go negative x
positive x negative Y positive Y
negative Z positive Z it's a threat
right right and when we're doing your
debug output we just go by surface so if
all of the services were assigned to
somehow the wrong lighting information
you would not know because the x-axis E
X axes are always the same for them all
so as long as they were only off by one
whole 24 block of light indices you'd
never know because it's not like they
all have different
AXYZ so that you would see that they
would be spun improperly or something
right so that particular view doesn't
really tell us you know we'd have to add
more information that debug view in
order to tell us stuff like whether they
were corresponding properly let's go
ahead and and take a look now at the
place where we actually pull this
information out temporarily again in the
baby steps kind of a paradigm let's just
go in here and see what we've got
so it says that we've got 77 boxes that
were processing that seems reasonable we
figured that that will generate 462
surfaces we're gonna loop over each of
the boxes one by one when we pull them
out we're gonna ask again for this this
piece of in this same box calculation to
be run and then we're gonna generate a
point by taking them in and going half
way along the span that should put us in
the center which is what the service
wants and the Box surface tells us to
normal
oops
so here's our source and here's our
destination in the sense let's take a
look at what our width and height are so
really we go we want to know the
absolute value of that - in order to get
the width to be correct because if it's
pointing along a negative axis that will
be negative
so I guess that sort of implies that
what we would prefer is that we always
were pointing along the positive
versions of our axes
see there's a couple of ways to
interpret this and it's tough to say I
guess we would want to say that the men
value is not really a min value that's
the wrong way to think about that let me
just discuss this a little bit here so a
little subtle so because this face can
be anywhere min does not really mean min
it doesn't have to be the minimum right
it's it's not necessarily minimum
anymore relative to what the x and y
axes are it's the minimum in absolute
axis XYZ world space but it's not
necessarily minimum relative to these
because it might be the x axis might be
pointing along a negative direction in
which case it's actually the maximum now
because it's you know the minimum for
the non negative version of that axis so
it's really more like a base point it's
probably the right way to think about it
it's basically saying like hey with the
base in the span you can get from the
face out to the to the you know the end
of it but it's not really telling you
anything else and the x axis and y axis
don't necessarily point out from there
in and we need to sort of fix that I
guess is the thing
yeah
so I think yeah yeah that's just that's
just a little tricky so maybe I the way
that we were doing it before was better
cuz it's a lot less it's just a lot less
room for error there I guess so maybe
we'll stick with sort of roughly the way
we were doing it before cuz that's that
is like a little clearer and I want to
avoid that error that I just made in
terms of how I was thinking about it so
yeah if we take a look at what we'd have
to do to do this this all is still fine
right we can we can produce all of this
information in terms of the min and the
max coordinates of it but now we want to
do is say all right we want to generate
a p-value and we know where that is
right we do know that the the p-value is
just going to be the min corner we don't
want this the p-values could be halfway
between the min core in the max V Max
weren't that's the center point right I
and so that gives us the the information
that we need to that gives us this
because now we have the center point now
if we want to know what the half width
is we just need to take the absolute
value of what the span would have been
and times those axes so I guess I I
still do want this and we still can do
it this way
same equation but just written slightly
differently right so we still do want
this because we do need to produce those
with the height values so the absolute
values those gives us the width and
height and we can store that half width
and that half height directly out of
that and I think that's a saner way to
do that and we just won't store this man
at all
I think I like that better
and so here yeah we can do the same
thing we were doing before
so we'll do basically the same
construction like so and what I need to
know now is I need to know I need to
make these X sub ratio and y sub ratio
things be more about going halfway in
either direction right so it's really
just it's pretty straightforward right
because of the way we happen to have
written it it's really just this it's
just you start at negative 0.5 so half
in the other direction and then we
switch to half in the other direction
when we go to the next because we just
happen to only be doing two at the
moment so it's pretty straightforward
right this becomes now incredibly simple
because it actually is the information
that we wanted and this can be used
basically directly
and off we go so yeah let me just I want
to see that debug view again all right
so this again looks roughly correct no
obvious errors here that I can see
actually don't really know what's going
on with some of these points there oh I
do they I know what's going on those are
just very tiny that's what's going on so
the size at which we're drawing the
lighting elements themselves is actually
bigger than the size of the cube the
lighting cube I think it's a that's what
I think is going on there all right so
[Music]
it looks like everything else is fine
I don't see any other issues all right
so I don't see any other issues with the
exact app there but again we're still in
that white home free because we're not
getting the lighting still doesn't look
correct can see it here if I run it at
full speed we're getting what appears to
be a reasonable lighting on some
surfaces but not others right so we're
definitely getting some weird like
assignment stuff happening possibly with
the light indices it's hard to say but
it's definitely wonky and it doesn't
look like it's properly reflected in
this view pun intended so we're almost
there but we've got a little bit more
work to do so if we want to yeah we have
to sort of figure out how to make how to
debug that correspondence a little bit
better maybe I should try to update that
view - show us the information we need
not sure exactly how we would do that at
the moment which is why I'm not doing it
if I had a good idea I would go do that
first the light index here you can see
exactly it's just getting read out of
the boxes as we would expect and we're
doing this subtraction here to determine
how many of them there are for any
particular surface and we're assuming
that they got pushed in that order now I
don't think I ever really verified that
fact so what I could do first just to
avoid any obvious stupidity is I could
go and make sure that when we do the
push we are pushing on the values we
think we're pushing on so if I step in
to push cube in here you know we go
through this index tour process we say
okay we're gonna I don't know wide light
count is
for specifically but whatever so in here
we set the light count to four because
it's for a per surface we advance the
light index so that we allocate that
many of them this again is sort of it to
do because we don't really properly do
the allocation stuff we're supposed to
do here but that's sort of a separate
issue then we have the light box that we
pull out and in there we put you know
the one the one five nine thirteen
seventeen twenty one twenty five right
and coming through here we do one to see
if we get up to here yeah twenty-five so
that's correct we then we set it back
down to one so those look like they're
getting pushed on oh but we have not
reorganized these to be in line yet so
that that makes forever since I forgot
one piece of the of the puzzle there
which is that in here as we're going
through obviously when we push these on
they have to be in the same order as our
new routine right so that's negative x
positive x yeah negative x positive x
negative Y positive Y and so on so let's
just go ahead and reorder these to be in
that order that's the first thing we
need to do so if we take a look at 0 1 2
3 here 0 1 2 3 is the positive z face so
the positive Z face is actually the last
face
miles will write these down seven six
five four is the negative Z face four
five one zero negative Y to six seven
three
positive why I like count like count
like yeah like yeah and now we've got
one five six two one five six - those
are all positive x so this must be
negative x
ah and now we're closer we still have
some issues here like I'm not seeing
light show up on there but we're
definitely getting a little closer so
that's something also let me click look
here so I can move around and just see
how the light is playing off surfaces
so it looks like we still have a face
inversion there right like maybe those
faces don't seem to be getting any at
all like there's the light and yet there
is no light on those surfaces which I
don't understand because they're being
output apparently properly I don't know
why the positive line negative wire
reversed there must be a cut-and-paste
bug I doubt that is sufficient to cause
the problem but maybe if we're lucky
that's all this I don't think said oh it
looked worse than that but no maybe it
wasn't it looked worse than that so I'm
not quite sure we're out of the weeds
yet
all right so that's seeming pretty good
now again not quite willing to say its
100% but it's looking pretty darn good
and I think we should be at the point
where tomorrow we can start first thing
on actually making the lighting
algorithm just work with the cubes
directly which I think will also give us
a speed improvement not that we
necessarily at the point where we're
trying to optimize that level of it yet
but just the fact that it won't have to
deal with as many services should
provide some additional speed and hey
we're right in time
questions
[Music]
is there any way to put a breakpoint
outside Visual Studio can you be more
specific do you mean do you mean you
want to tell Visual Studio to set a
breakpoint from another program or do
you just mean you want to issue a debug
break like just I'm not sure exactly
what you mean can you be more specific
about exactly what you want to have
happen the answer will possibly vary
this by the way it's a nice profile
right here because we can base to see
all of our time spent and compute light
propagation which is exactly what we
want because that means that as we do
the speed ups we should be in good stuff
let me see what the other question what
do you think about the blockchain future
I have no idea of questions outside of
the game are allowed generally speaking
I just answered on topic questions the
pre stream is for off-topic questions I
have already answered the blockchain
thing basically I don't really
understand the point of it it doesn't
make a lot of sense to me my short
answer is currencies aren't hard the the
the central problem of currency was
never that we didn't have a mathematical
way to do it or something like I mean
yes that's an interesting thing for
people for humans to have figured out
but that's really not the hard part the
hard part about currency is enforcement
I mean that's the hard part and
enforcement means having an army in the
police force
that's what currency is currency is
because you know we could do whatever we
wanted for currency I could I could give
you a little pieces of paper that just
said something that you know the hard
part about is enforcement what do you do
when somebody doesn't honor of a valid
version of the currency and blockchain
is just about saying there's a way to
prove who owned something too weak or a
strong sense but that's not the hard
part who cares if you can prove it is
the other person gonna pay that's the
that's the important part and so all the
only reason blockchain can exist at all
is because it exists within a system
where governments have armies and police
forces that force you to honor contracts
and that's what a currency actually is
so there is no blockchain future it's
it's that's not a thing currencies
require armies without an army you have
no currency you can be a sub currency
inside of someone else's currency regime
who does have an army in a police force
but that's all you'll ever be to me this
is like a very obvious to anyone who's
ever read any history so I don't know
why people even think there's anything
interesting about blockchains in terms
of a
future way that currency would work
because there isn't but somehow this
escapes people's understanding and I
maybe I'm missing some really obvious
way in which these things can be
enforced but math doesn't enforce itself
you know I mean you know someone can say
that two plus two equals five and
there's nothing you can do about it
right the math itself it's not like the
laws of physics where you can't break
them right i if that's not the kind of
math we're dealing with here we're just
dealing with abstract math and yes you
could all say well now we have a way to
verify I can verify that you actually
did this thing you said you did but
that's not the hard part of currency
that is a very irrelevant part of
currency the only time you would ever
care about that feature of currency is
in the case where you already had a
functional enforced currency system and
you need to create a sub currency but
who cares why don't just use the actual
currency because you're still gonna have
to obey all the laws that that sovereign
who gives you these the original
currency you're gonna have to obey all
their laws because all they have the
army they can just tell you tomorrow you
can't you can't do anything with that
sub currency and you can't game over
right so you know sorry to rant about it
but I just I don't get it I do not
understand what people are thinking it
seems like a tulip bulb craze nonsense
thing to me but shouldn't we go back to
do more stuff in December like on the
Amiga yes if we could just have the
Amiga back again and that was what we
made games on that would be awesome how
do you jump to function during debugging
usually there's a lot of functions and
not easy to find them uh I don't have a
good way of doing it I mean you've seen
how I do it I wish the debugger were
built into for coder because there are
ways to do it in here like you can do
like push quad and lists all the
location
of that that it's called and also where
it's defined so but that doesn't work in
Visual Studio like you have to have like
browse info turned on or something to do
that and you can't do that without a
project and I'm we don't have a project
frame here because it's not built using
their build system and blah blah blah
right so I don't know how you do it the
bugger but I'm just hoping that someday
we'll have it a better built into for
coder and I can get rid of that vigil
studio nonsense anyway but I don't have
a good answer for you
Johan tweeted once about how X forward
right-handed coordinate systems should
be standard do no details on why is that
important I died so I don't know why
that's important but I and I don't know
why John said that but I can hypothesize
some reasons why he might have said that
but he is a better person to ask and he
does stream programming fairly often so
hopefully you could ask him the choice
of of coordinate systems this is 100%
arbitrary I if if nothing else I I'm
signed taught us that maybe the choice
of coordinate system is completely
arbitrary frames of reference or
arbitrary so there's nothing special
about a right-handed coordinate system
and there's certainly nothing special
about an X forward coordinate system so
it's important to understand that first
and foremost and I would suspect John
would tell you exactly the same thing I
can't speak for him but if I had to
guess I would say what's exactly what I
just said the choice of courting system
is 100% arbitrary that said he is an
unnecessary complexity to pick them
arbitrarily when we all talk to each
other about routines and rewrite shared
libraries that each other want to use
and we read matrices in print that we
need to understand having an arbitrary
sense of here's a left-handed quarter
system oh this one's a right and
coordinate system oh this one has D
facing up oh this one has D facing
forward so this one sec facing right
having all of those complexities just
wastes programmers time because they are
constantly suffering from mental
overhead of remembering they have to
translate these things right so it's
kind of like saying your choice of
languages arbitrary is Chinese a better
language then you know I don't know
Indian an Indian language is better than
a European language French let's say or
something like this who knows right and
the choice of language there may be
slight pluses or minuses to some
language maybe you know this writing
system is harder
this one has more ways of expressing
tenths or whatever but largely we know
that humans can communicate many of them
so you might say well let's just write
books in all the languages and everyone
just learns to read all the languages
right but we know that that's ludicrous
because it's so much more mental
overhead to do that it would obviously
be way better if we could just
standardize on one language and then
everyone could just learn one language
and they wouldn't have to have all this
mental overhead and there wouldn't be
things that were difficult for them to
access right so that's kind of the like
extreme example but scale that back to
the coordinate systems it's it's just
like a language you start to learn all
of the ways to interpret what you're
reading quickly when you know that it's
always one coordinate system you're just
like oh yeah I know the right hand rule
always applies so when I see these two
things I just my brain just does this
right I don't have to stop and think and
so I suspect that was what John was
talking about but don't really know so
from my perspective yet if we did
standardize on a coordinate system that
might be a nice thing and the reason
that that might be a nice thing even
though the choices arbitrary is because
much like language it would be nice if
we could just eliminate that work you
know eliminate that work that people
have to do of learning and relearning
and translation in their head in order
to work with things written in these
different systems and obviously for
language it's a much worse problem than
for coordinate systems right languages
is an infinitely harder situation than
coordinate systems but it's the same
basic principle if you allow people to
start making assumptions about what is
true they can be quicker about how they
do things whereas if they constantly
have to recheck those assumptions and
always be like wait a minute
oh wait which access system we're using
oh right okay that's just a mental
overhead and a source of potential
mistakes I mean another example would be
metric system versus standard right in
that case unlike coordinate systems
there's there's some real obvious ways
where the metric system might be a
better choice right there are some ways
the English system it has some nice
things too but actually believe it or
not but either way
you know the metric system might be a
much clearer choice for what you would
want for your measurement system right
but there's still somewhat arbitrary you
can do everything you want to do in both
systems right the metric system has some
advantages so there's a good reason to
pick one over the other potentially
which is not necessary tree of
coordinate systems but still similar
problem the cost of having multiple of
them is very high so high that I think
we even had a case where a probe crashed
into a planet in outer space because
someone was using kilometers and someone
was using miles or something like this
you see if I can pull that up for you
metric mishap caused loss of nasa orbit
earth the engine fire but spacecraft
came within 60 kilometers or so miles
the planet about 100 kilometers close to
the planet and it looks like a math
mistake right here's the wiki Wikipedia
one piece of ground soars flighted by
Lucky Brand produced results in United
States customary unit contrary to its
software interface specification while
second systems lawyer nasa expected
those drills to be in SI units in
accordance with the SIS
just specifically suffer that calculate
the total impulse produced by thrust to
first reduce tilts in pounds seconds the
director calculus offered then you see
results tried to be in Newtons seconds
to update to predicted position of
spacecraft right so this is basically
the same thing right a probe crashed
into a planet not because anyone had a
bug in the actual computation but just
because one person assumed they were in
one coordinate system and one person
thought they were in another right and
and these are like really highly checked
pieces of software so you know in games
we are way less rigorous about what
we're doing because it's you know
nothing crashes into a planet when we
make a mistake and so you can understand
why reducing these sources of possible
unnecessary error are very important
everywhere
they're important even in highly
scrutinized software it still makes it
through and causes severe even in this
case catastrophic errors right where the
entire mission didn't go the way it was
supposed to because somebody didn't use
the metric system or somebody didn't use
the English system right so I suspect
that's all John's talking about but I
don't know I would say the same thing
about Indian Asst there should be no
more big endian processors for the end
period
I think anyone who dips a big-endian
processor from now on it should just be
immediately forced out of the market and
the reason is because again there's
nothing particularly difficult about
building software that works across
multiple Indian architectures it it is
not to use a pun for the priest example
rocket science that said it is
unnecessary work there is no reason to
choose big-endian or little-endian it's
arbitrary to a large extent so the fact
that we now have mostly processors that
are little endian means let's just lock
it down it's little-endian from now on
hardware people no more big endian you
don't get to do it
it's over right and so I think that
would be a crucial thing to just force
the industry to do big endian is done we
will not program for it anymore if you
ship a beginning and chip
no one will code for it we like roundly
reject this like a programmers Union or
something that goes to the bargaining
table it's like we will we will pick it
your factory if you ship a big endian
ship because it just it's hardware
companies creating work for software
companies period that is all it is
because we're done we don't need we've
proven that little-endian can be the
only platform that we need we're doing
it right now
why muck it up right
Ilyn are for UK what kind of memory
allocations do you use
are there any custom stack allocations
pools etc or are using standard math new
we are using 100% custom we don't use
any standard malloc or new and we use
stacks we don't really use pools
explicitly per se but we do sometimes
allocate from stacks and fixed chunks
which can then go back on a free list
which effectively creates a pool so we
have a in a very limited sense some pool
in in like one or two places some
pooling did you manually build all the
menus on the screen or got it from
somewhere manually well everything we
did is built by us there's no code that
wasn't built by us the only we're still
calling the C runtime libraries like
sine and cosine functions because we
haven't put in our own sine and cosine
sim D sine and cosine yet but that's
about the only thing that wasn't 100%
written on stream so far compute light
propagation 92% seems too high at the
moment does it I mean it's the only
thing really doing a lot of work
well there were nine one one nine hi
Casey would you be able to recommend
good resources to learn and practice
deficient programming habits no I I
don't know much other than what the
sorts of things we talked about
in generic and metaprogramming do
everything and solve all the world's
problems
yes obvious obviously alright I think
we're actually over time anyway so I'm
gonna go ahead and shut this stream down
let's go ahead and close this up we
accomplished exactly what I want you
today that's always good when you don't
get hung up on any sort of problematic
sort of piece of code thank you everyone
for joining you further up sort of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always pre-order the game on hand made
here at Oregon comes a little source
code so you can play around with it
yourself
tomorrow we will be doing the sort of
movement of the lighting from working
with services to working with cubes
directly so that should be interesting
if you want to try that you've got the
rest of the day today to do it shouldn't
be too hard of a thing to try although
you know it we'll see we'll see how long
it takes me to do it tomorrow it might
take more than one episode to do but
point being if you want to play around
the source code that would be a good
thing to try change the lighting to be
working on cubes directly it's a little
bit challenging so that might be a fun
thing for you to try anyway we also have
obviously an episode guide if you want
to check out the past episode of the
series it's a really nice annotated
episode I've done by Midler from the
chat it's it's fantastic I highly
recommend it
and if you want to contribute to
projects like that that people in the
community do we do have a community fund
here on the contribute button that
actually lets you contribute sort of a
recurring donation that just goes to
people who do stuff like that so it goes
to the the folks at ham braid network
who hopes the episode guide it goes to
midlow for making the episode guide and
we are constantly looking for donations
to support other projects that are hand
made here are related so yeah give that
a give that a look at well that's that's
it we'll see you back here tomorrow for
some more lighting programming until
then have fun programming on your own
and I'll see you all on the Internet
take these everybody