ten minutes over today because we're
gonna need the time all right hello
everyone and welcome to hand made here
on the show we code we code a complete
game from scratch live on Twitch no
library's no no engines this is a
essentially a serious about how to
program everything in games so we cover
everything including how you would
program an engine if you're making your
own and today we're doing a topic that
is one of those topics that is straight
to that point because it's not something
that you might do that much of if you
are just doing very sort of fluffy high
level game code and that is optimization
basically we've gotten to a point where
we finally have some code in hand made
hero that we're calling that does enough
work where it's actually causing us a
framerate problem and so what we want to
do is learn some optimization techniques
to go ahead and speed that up so that it
will not cause us a problem during
development right and so our goal right
now is not necessarily to optimize it
down to like get as fast as possible for
anything but we do need to know enough
optimization right now to be able to
optimize that piece and basically the
principles of optimization are more or
less always the same whether or not you
are trying to do the most optimal
version of something or just an optimal
enough version of something because
really they're the same process it's
just a question of when you stop
iterating on that process and so really
it's a good time to introduce
optimization and talk about how we do it
because we're going to do it at multiple
points on the stream and this is
definitely one of those points so I'm
going to go over to the blackboard and
give a really quick introduction to
optimization how to think about it and
how we are going to be thinking about it
and then we are going to sort of build a
few start building a few primitives that
we're gonna need to do our optimization
work we will probably not do any actual
optimization today because as I'm about
to talk about on the blackboard you you
never the first step to optimization
never has anything to do with actually
optimizing code it has to do with
measuring and determining a bunch of
things about your code before you start
and if you don't do that you're you're
kind of missing out on a big part of
optimizations so let's talk about that
really quickly here on day 112
alright so let's talk about optimization
what it is how you do it
everything about optimization first of
all I'd like to start with a caveat
which is I am NOT one of the world's
best optimizers you are not going to be
getting any incredible gems of wisdom
forming here I am a good-enough
optimizer I optimized code enough to get
it to the place where it needs to be for
for shipping purposes but I am NOT one
of those people who you go to when it's
like oh my god we have this thing and it
needs to be optimized within an inch of
its life that is the other guys that rad
you're talking about Jeff and Fabien
there or you know people who spend all
their time working on optimization stuff
I'm not one of those guys so I'm giving
us basically the generalist view of
optimization which is how do you make
code so that it's fairly good and fairly
performant and typically a lot of the
techniques apply but there's a certain
level beyond which I won't be able to
guide you which gets into things like
crazy stuff like cache line aliasing
issues and all these sorts of things we
won't really be getting into those other
than to mention the fact that they exist
and if you want to be one of those guys
who just spent all your time on
optimization things because there are
people who really like that that's like
what they like to do I'll sort of
mention them as we go so that you're
aware of what you need to go and learn
in order to really push optimization
like past sort of that the crazy point
if you will all right
so essentially what optimization is is
understanding ok there is the CPU right
and a GPU in your computer ok and
everything that happens every frame of
your game is going through one of these
two things and often times both ok
they are both things which look
incredibly similar both of these things
are chips that
you know either soldered on to your
motherboard or on the motherboard and on
a card and so on they are chips and what
those chips do is they decode an
instruction stream right so there's a
bunch of instructions and we've gone
over this before right there you know
we've we looked at this in the very
first streams basically there's an
encoding for that basically tells them
what to do so they go over some
instructions that are basically bytes
that are in their native format and for
each one of those things they do some
computation right they do something and
typically for the instructions that we
tend to care about the most are kind of
followed to two broad categories right
there are things that are like loads and
stores which are basically things that
modify memory right so there's some
memory somewhere and they're gonna do
these loads and stores which are
basically grabbing stuff from memory and
pulling it into the local registers or
the cache of these things operating on
them or their stores which are saying
we've got computer stuff and we push it
out right so there's those types of
instructions which time to think about
and then there's ALU style instructions
right and I guess we won't call it ALU
it's a little ambiguous we'll just say
there's basically than half operations
right there's stuff we want to do right
and typically the way that those work
nowadays and this is a very very
important thing to understand regardless
of which of these we're talking about
because I'm saying both of these things
work this way now math tends to be wide
okay
it tends to be in something called sim D
which is single instruction multiple
data and it means exactly what it sounds
like
there is one instruction but it operates
on multiple pieces of data at once and
typically in the minimal case this is
for things right this is 0 1 2 3 things
and they're all gonna have the same
thing happened to them so you know the
way that we've been looking at code
where we have stuff like float x equals
you know y plus 3 you know we have
something like this this is not at all
how modern processors ever work when
pretty much at all right this does not
happen in a CPU or a GP you ever write
we write that only because we are not
caring about whether the code is optimal
or not what will actually happen 99% of
the time the
if you write this piece of code is that
the processor will actually do this
operation on for floating-point values
right so it'll actually do four X's plus
four wise plus three replicated four
times and it will simply throw away
three of the results and keep only one
of them I'm not joking this is really
true that's what happens and the reason
for that is that most processors are
designed in this way single instruction
multiple data and four is the minimum
number that you would be throwing away
actually there's typically as many often
as many as eight in an Intel CPU soon to
go to sixteen and in the GPU it could be
as many as 64 okay again I wish I was
making this up I'm not making this up so
what that means is when you encounter a
particular instruction like I want to
add two numbers together or I want to
multiply two numbers together any math
operation you are typically talking
about something that is either slightly
wide is least four things wide or
absurdly wide like sixty-four wide
thirty-two wide that sort of thing okay
why do they do that what's the point of
that right I mean it sounds kind of
crazy right the reason is because and
again I'm not a hardware guy so you know
this is sort of the hand-wavy reason and
if you want you know a more detailed
reason you've got to ask a serious
hardware person someone who works on
chip design for a living but basically
the hand-wavy reason is because it's not
free for CPUs and GPUs to decode and
process these instruction streams right
there's a lot of work that goes on in
these instruction streams and let's
think about what one of these
instructions actually is write an
instruction might be something like say
add right and again there's registers we
talked about these before they're the
things that processors operate on and so
you might say like add a you know the
contents of our zero
well actually guess we'll say we'll put
something in our zero so add the
contents of r1 and r2 and put it in our
zero right so we want to do like r1 plus
r2 and we want to put that in our zero
right so that computes r0 equal
r1 plus r2 right this might be what's
encoded in the actual processor some
some bytes that encode the fact that we
want to you know add these things and
these registers right are just you know
some some set the working set the
smallest working set of things that the
processor works on right
maybe there's 16 of them who knows how
many there are different processor to
processor but basically everything looks
like this and if you remember back to
the beginning of handmade hero you
remember how it looked our instruction
streams typically looked like grabbed
something from memory put it into one of
these registers grab another thing from
memory put it into when these registers
operate on them and then write the
result back out from the destination
register to memory right so to give a
complete instruction stream just for
people who don't remember that stuff
very well maybe we'd say like we want to
load something into r1 so we load some
memory into some register into r1 we
load something into r2 we execute the ad
which loads r1 and r2 together right and
then we might store right that that r0
out somewhere right so we load in two
values into the registers of this
processor we add them together and then
we write them out
okay so again a really simple stupid
instruction stream but I'm just getting
you back in that feeling we haven't
talked about this in a while so I'm just
recalling back to the beginning of
things right I want you to think back
about that that's what's actually
happening inside the processor and stuff
like this okay
now what I'm trying to get into I'm
trying to point out here for the
purposes of the cindy discussion is that
this is not free this is a bunch of
circuits that actually have to do all
this work they have to select registers
for add operations they have to know
that we're you know taking this and
adding it to this and brighting it into
this that has to look to see whether or
not this gets used somewhere can it be
multi pipeline can we issue another ad
if there was another ad after this that
looked like this right could I assure
these two in parallel or not well the
answer is no because this one needs the
result of that one right but if this was
our four it could in blah blah blah
right so it's actually incredibly
expensive the work that it has to do to
decode the instruction stream that's
coming in decide how to issue it go find
free units because typically processors
have multiple adding circuits in them
right figure out which adding
rockets are free at any given time to do
this ad maybe this one goes to one and
this one goes to a different one blah
blah blah right so you can see that
there's just a ton of stuff that goes in
here we won't go into hardly any of how
that works because it's not super
relevant unless you want to again go
down the super crazy path of
optimization where you need to start
knowing about like arithmetic unit
pairing and which reservation slots of
whether this thing can issue on this
cycle or the next cycle there's all
these sorts of things that you might
want to get into you might want to know
the full details here that's true if you
want to be a super hardcore optimizer
you do need to know that we might be
won't ever really get into that on this
thing because you probably won't need to
but the point is it's incredibly
incredibly complicated and that
complexity means that if you can
leverage if you're going to typically do
operations on a bunch of data at once
right then if it can leverage all of
that thought thinking that it does here
right to go ahead and make sure that
when it figures out what it needs to do
it can do it on a lot of things at once
that's a total win in terms of circuitry
there and it means that the amount of
actual memory that has to be spun
through in order to decode the
instructions is much less - because if I
have to say if I'm gonna load here and I
can load four pieces of data at once
that's four less instructions of well
three less instructions a quarter of the
instructions to load the data as if I
had to do four instructions to load four
things right same with the ads it's
three less ads I do one add and add four
things instead of having to do four ads
right so if you know that your heavy
workloads can typically be written in
this style it saves a lot of complexity
in the processor and it saves a lot of
instruction space just the footprint
write a lot less memory band but that's
just going into the processor in terms
of like they call this an AI cache
typically it's an instruction cache it's
the place where when you read out
instruction streams and figure out what
to do with them
in terms of like what they actually mean
for the microprocessor basically that a
lot more fits in there at that point
right because you just have less
instructions so basically all processors
work this way now Cindy is everywhere
there isn't a processor you're likely to
program on at all
whether it's a CPU or a GPU that ever
doesn't look like this and so what you
need to think about obviously when
you're in here is when we are talking
about optimization the model that we're
thinking about is this model and we
essentially have three parts to it we
might say which I'll kind of codify now
that I've I've got the Cindy out of the
way hopefully you all understand what
that means when I say that the
instructions are wide means that they're
operating on many things at once right
so we have a few things to think about
right we essentially have the
instructions themselves this is what the
CPU or GPU has to actually do okay we've
got the cache we've got memory right and
what we need to think about is we need
to think about all right whenever we're
talking about optimizing something
essentially everything that we're gonna
do whether it's a CPU or GPU again
always fits this model because this is
all computers can do it's always a
question of moving things from memory
into a cache from a cache into some
instruction set basically I mean you're
not really moving them I guess you could
say there's the registers right I'm
trying to think of how to draw that but
you know if I have that say that add
here or I guess I'll do a load load are
zero something we have to move things
from memory which is where the computer
store ISM GPU our CPU they both have
memory they're gonna go into some kind
of a local cache they're going to get
loaded into registers inside the
processor right they're going to be
manipulated like those those you know
ads we were talking about before and
then they're going to be written back
right they're gonna be written back to
the cache maybe in a different place and
then eventually back out to memory okay
and whenever this is happening these
instructions are going to be wide so
basically almost everything that we do
is going to be one of those single
instruction multiple data things so it's
going to be at least four things wide
possibly more right
so the model for everything we do is we
know we have an instruction stream that
instruction stream grabs things from
memory and pulls them into the cache it
pulls them from the cache into the
registers it operates on the registers
figuring out something computing some
values and then pushing stuff back out
into the cache which then goes back out
to the memory right okay so we talked
about this a little before I'll just
mention it briefly again a cache is
basically something that is on the
processor usually sometimes it's not but
usually on the cache and they have names
like l1 l2 l3 and the number indicates
how essentially how removed they are
from the the CPU in a sense you could
think of the registers themselves the
thing that the CPU actually operates on
as an l0 in some sense right it's the
things that the CPU actually directly
addresses and it is instantaneous for
them to get them essentially right it's
not entirely true but it's like the
fastest thing for the processor to work
on is its registers then it has series
of diminishing lis small memory I'm
sorry it has series of increasingly
large memories it can access the l1
cache the l2 cache the l3 cache
sometimes might not have one and then
main memory right and the cost of
getting things from each of these gets
increasingly expensive as you go off so
whereas an l1 cache may be something
like you know 16 cycles to grab from and
an l2 cache might be more than that and
l3 cache more than that up to main
memory which may be something like 300
cycles right and one of these
instructions like an ad might be two
cycles right so if you figure like okay
looking at how this works if I want to
talk about how expensive something is I
could think about the fact that as I
sort of get further away from the
instruction stream those registers that
I'm actually a proper ating on as I get
further away from those I get more and
more expensive to - basically how long
it takes me to pull something in right
okay so let's talk about this model
over here because there's a lot of stuff
to cover but just keep this in your mind
basically this this diagram here we're
gonna refer to it a lot all right so
first let's talk about these things I
just said which are cycles right cycles
are basically the smallest thing that
the CPU enumerates work in okay so
basically when you ask the CPU to do
something typically it's going to take
some of these right it takes some of
these to do something right and what
they more or less coincide with is
processors themselves run at a certain
rate and they have internal clocking
it's far beyond my knowledge of how that
clocking works I'm sure it works very
differently now from the old days when I
sort of learned basically what it was
but this is sort of what the processor
is doing every step every cycle it can
do something right each individual cycle
it can do something so when we talk
about a processor and we talk about how
fast it is like for example this
processor in this machine right here we
can actually look at the details or I
thought we could look at the details
that's not what I want
where's the just the how do I get just
the details of this computer you know
what I'm saying
just computer there it is so you can see
this is a three point one nine gigahertz
processor it's actually got two of them
in their 3.2 gigahertz is the rated
speed so we'll use that for now all
right so a 3.2 gigahertz processor which
is what it's in this machine okay
gigahertz is an SI unit so it's actually
a thousand it's not 1024 like gigabytes
right so the gigahertz is actually a
thousand times a thousand times a
thousand right
a thousand this would be kilohertz this
would be megahertz this would be
gigahertz right so we're talking about
3.2 times 1,000 times a thousand times
thousand right that is how many cycles
per second
okay that is how many cycles per second
we expect this processor to run it right
now it could change that can change
sometimes because processors have lower
power states they have power saving
cycles in stuff like that they might
underclock themselves there's all kinds
of reasons that it might fluctuate but
at maximum when it is running full-bore
that is what it will do right so that
means we have three to zero Jimmy zero
zero zero zero zero zero zero zero right
basically 3.2 billion cycles per second
right so that is how many the processor
is actually going to issue how many
cycles it's going to go through in one
second now what's interesting about that
right I'm gonna go ahead and even though
we don't need it at the very moment I
want to open up Emacs so I can use the
little quick calc feature we were using
right right so if I do 3.2 times a
thousand times thousand times a thousand
right there is my cycles oh you know
what I don't know how to use the laughs
there it is I love B max when it does
that for you okay so there's that now we
know that that's how many cycles per
second but we know we do 30 frames per
second right our game runs 30 frames a
second which means every frame we have
that many right that's how many of poops
didn't mean for that to go away come
back that's how many we actually have
right so you can see here we've got like
a hundred and six million or like 107
million cycles per frame right so let's
just write that down 107 million cycles
per frame okay this is on the CPU so
what that means is we have a hundred and
seven million cycles to get everything
that we need to get done in a frame done
right and if we don't get everything
that we need to have done in a frame
done in that hundred and seven million
cycles our gain will not hit 30 frames a
second right it's that simple and so the
first essentially thing that I want you
to think about in terms of optimization
is you should always know what this
number is right you should always start
out by going okay given whatever it is I
have to work with right what is actually
the base amount of performance I even
have to work with what am i working with
what are those numbers right and this is
the first primary number we need to
think about 107 million cycles per frame
that's how many cycles we have on one of
the CPUs to do our work right now this
is of course not entirely that's not the
entirety of the picture because this is
essentially one core on one CPU right
now in a machine there may be multiple
processors and maybe multiple CPU cores
that sort of thing and technically each
core actually gets this many right so
really depending on the machine we're
targeting let's say we have a four core
machine or something like that then we
know we actually have more than this if
we can divide up the work among multiple
processors but we're gonna get to that
in a second for now I just want you to
focus on on one core on one CPU we have
this many cycles per frame all of our
work that has to be done on the CPU must
fit into that number okay now it's
already pretty low number 107 million
right it's not that high and why do I
say that well think about how many
pixels on the screen there would be at
1920 by 1080 right there's let's see
there is 2 million right so there's 2
million pixels on the screen at 1980 by
1980 by by 10 20 right an HD display
right 2 million so if you think about
how many cycles per pixel
there actually are to process if we were
doing you know like software rendering
like we're doing right now they're not
that many right there's like you know
something like 50 cycles of pixel right
that's it 50 cycles of pixel
not a very large number right what's
this number divided by 2 right 107
divided by 2 like 50 very very small
right it's not a very big number so just
want to sort of put that in your head
that 107 million cycles per frame is
actually not that many
this is why you know you see a lot of
stuff that doesn't run at 30 frames a
second right you open up the you know
some kind of app and it's super laggy
and weird and janky it's like it's
actually important that this number not
be exceeded and often times things will
right so anyway that's the first thing
you want to think about that Mesa cycles
per frame next thing you won't ever
actually get a hundred and seven cycles
for frame probably right because well
maybe sometimes you will but other times
there's stuff that needs to happen
that's not your cycles right so for
example there's stuff that when we call
Windows to display the frame right we
just we have stuff we have to do we call
windows to get the state of the joystick
and whatever right there's a bunch of
stuff that we don't actually control
that is using some of those cycles so
depending on which core and which CPU
were talking about we may not even be
talking about all 107 million cycles for
up being for our use right but in
today's world where there's multi-core
if you have a user whose machine has
been set up to not have tons of like
Adobe Acrobat running in the background
and like I'm sorry Acrobat Reader like
sitting there checking for updates Adobe
Creative Cloud looking to see if it's
license is valid and everything else
happening assuming that you have a user
who's got a machine set up for gaming
and it's relatively clean maybe on a
bunch of those cores you actually are
getting 100 site seven cycles per frame
but on at least one of them which is the
one where you interface with Windows you
don't so that's the next thing to be
aware of all right so let's keep that in
mind just think about that keep it in
mind the next thing what is a cycle what
actually is it right because we know
that it's running at this rate but we
don't really know what that actually
means right so it helps to have some
wonder standing what actually happens in
the CPU on something called a cycle
right and so basically what will happen
in the cycle and again this is a very
very high-level overview of what happens
in a cycle and a processor this is not a
hard-r exhalation it's just a mental
model for you to understand roughly what
is going on so please take it with with
that large grain of salt so what's
happening in the cycle first of all
right
is there is an assumption presumably
remember I told you there's that thing
called an eye cache right so basically a
processor usually has a thing that's
some kind of a cache that has the
instructions in it and these things are
actually decoded they're usually in
something called micro code okay and
what micro code is is they're not
exactly necessarily the instructions
that we see when we look at when we
start talking about optimizing things
and look at the instructions they're not
actually the ones that we see they might
be so it might be that like an ad like
something like this ad actually is just
an ad like it's just one instruction in
the micro code but there's other
instructions that might be multiple
micro code instructions so really
there's essentially two if you will this
is like the memory where our code lives
right there's two things there's
instructions here and there's
instructions here and when they get
loaded when they load here it's actually
load and decode right if that makes
sense so basically code that we write
that was compiled into instructions by
the compiler is actually getting loaded
into this I cache and decoded into a
series of micro code instructions which
are not necessarily a one-to-one
correspondence with our instructions we
see so what I'm about to say next is
true for micro code instructions not
instructions we see and sometimes you
will have the benefit of knowing what
that micro code is sometimes you won't
it depends on how documented the
processor is that you're working with
and how much the manufacturer wants to
share with you and so on okay so we pull
these things into this I cache what the
I cache is is this just like a cache for
data like we were talking about before
but all it does is cache decoded
instructions usually and then the
processor is reading out of this right
it's fetching some instruction out of
this okay so on one cycle what is
happening is it is going to go and fetch
some number of instructions right so
it's going to fetch and maybe that
number might be as many as
pay for instructions right why did I
just I don't know what just tap in there
stop drawing it could be like for
instructions it could be who knows how
many depends on the processor it's going
to fetch some instructions okay
Amos going to fetch them potentially out
of order right so depending on the
processor in the old days this was very
simple it always fetch them in order
nowadays it doesn't even necessarily
fetch them in order right so the
processor is going to have a thing it's
going to look at some window of
instructions in the microcode it's going
to fetch some instructions if things
that can do and it will issue I think up
to four is how many it typically issues
on a minor press but I'm going to say
it's gonna issue some number of them
right so it fetches some number of them
that it thinks it can issue right and
they go in here right so maybe I have
instruction 1 this is instruction 1 0
instruction 2 1 instruction 2
instruction 3 all right so I fetched
these instructions and then I'm going to
issue these instructions so on this
cycle it will look at these instructions
right and issue them so they go off to
parts of the chip they're going off to
parts of the CPU to be operated on right
so these go out to some units we don't
know what kind of units they are inside
the processor you know maybe ones an
arithmetic logic unit so it's going off
to an ALU one's a memory units going up
to some fetch some data I don't know
what but point being we're going into
this instruction Katrine inside the eye
cache we're getting back some things
we're gonna issue them now what happens
in here I said order question mark what
basically happens in here is modern
processors in order to speed things up
now issue things out of order what that
means is that if the instruction stream
said ABCDEF you know gee these are some
instructions that i want to do the the
there's actually a part of the processor
that will look at these and go okay i
can execute any now i can execute b now
see i couldn't execute because c
actually depends on a and b to have
completed right c uses like a result
from b or something with this right and
a result from a it's like adding the
result of a and b or something so i
can't issue that right now but I could
still issue another instruction because
I could issue like four instructions
this frame so I'm gonna grab D and E as
well even though C isn't there because
they don't have any
seize on see let's say and it will bring
all of those up and remember that it
hasn't executed see so that later once
when a and B complete it can grab C an
issue it right and so modern-day Intel
processors for example are heavily
heavily out of order
they work around the latency that you
can imagine here where if you have to
you know if I have to wait for these two
things to be done
I can't issue this right they work
around that by having a very large
window of instructions they look at and
grabbing maximally from that window
right so hopefully that makes some sense
okay so once it gets those and it issues
them they go out into what's generally
called a pipeline right and this is
actually the first step of that pipeline
okay and the pipeline is actually
enumerated in cycles so on a cycle
what's actually happening is this this
instruction issue is happening but also
simultaneously on that these units are
working on whatever the last instruction
was that they were given and each of
those instructions may take a certain
number of what's called pipeline stages
to complete so if I do an ADD here and
add for example might take two stages so
let's say this was an ADD here's the ALU
unit gets the assignment on the add
maybe that takes one cycle maybe on the
issuing cycle like it could be most of
the time I'd actually like to say that
this is not really a line here in fact I
probably shouldn't have drawn that line
let me remove that typically I believe
and again I'm not a hardware guy so
don't you know take this with a grain of
salt but typically on the on the cycle
that's issued it does the first the
first part of the work in the unit right
so typically this one cycle here right
and so here's another cycle that's
happening and here's that pipeline okay
I needs the stages so this is save zero
this is stage one etc so let's say this
is an add this is going into what's
called an air Matt arithmetic logic unit
an ALU which is things that do things
like adds and ORS mask bit operations
basically right it's going to go into a
unit that's free right
gonna do stage one of the ads so this is
gonna do ad Stage one okay and then on
the next processor cycle it's going to
move into the next stage of the ad which
is going to do ad Stage two okay
and then only on stage three let's say
does that actually complete and it gets
written out right and so you typically
have this concept and I don't know again
we you have to look up in the
documentation for any given processor
for any given operation what this
actually looks like for any given number
of instructions but that's what a cycle
actually means it's one tick of these
stages right so if I say to you you know
how many cycles does an ad take and you
tell me that it takes two cycles to
complete then what that means is it's
going to use this stage and this stage
and only after that will the results
actually be available right okay so
hopefully that makes some sense
everybody clear on that everybody clear
on that I don't even know are we clear
on that who knows I'm going to assume
you're clear on that you can ask
questions in the Q&amp;A all right why do
they do this what's the point of this
pipelining well the reason is because
this way it's a way of reusing parts of
units at a faster rate right it's kind
of the same reason that you have a
washer and dryer separated when you're
doing laundry right if it makes if you
think about it right let's say that I
have I'm literally I'm just gonna do it
let's say you have a washer and a dryer
in your house right let's say you have a
washer and a dryer for your clothes okay
most houses in America have this it's a
common thing for people to have not so
much in other places like in Japan
a lot of people lime dry things which is
in fact better for the environment in
America yeah people are like an
environment be damned we're gonna have a
robot wash and dry our clothes so anyway
let's say you have a washer and a dryer
right well if you think about how that
works right you typically have here's my
washer here's my dryer right I put some
clothes in right so clothes load zero
goes into the washer right and then on
the next you could actually think of
these as the stages so stage zero is I
load in the clothes to the washer right
when the washer is done we go to the
next stage right where zero clothes load
zero goes from the washer to the dryer
and if I want to I can now use the
washer again so I can load the washer
with clothes load what right well zeros
in here and then the next time around
one moves out zero goes to the laundry
basket right and it's ready you can go
somewhere can be used me war in whatever
one moves in here and to with load in
right and what you can see hopefully by
doing this right is if I was to do it
this way how many loads of laundry right
can I actually do in a fixed amount of
time let's take a look right so two
would move here nothing would go in one
comes out to the laundry basket and
finally here the last time I'm going to
take two out of the dryer and into the
laundry basket right so how many do I
need here I've got stage 1 stage 2 stage
3 stage 4 stage 5 right so you can see
essentially when I did it this way to do
two loads of sorry to do three loads of
laundry right I only needed five
operations through my washer and dryer
right now let's suppose I had some other
mystical mythical device although they
do have these which is the washer plus
dryer which takes as long as a wash plus
dry cycle so it would take two stages
right so if I do my wash plus dry a load
in zero right and it's still in
they're the next phase right and then
finally here I would get it out right if
that makes sense
in fact I guess you'd look at it like
this here I would get it out right so it
goes in here and it comes out next one
goes in comes out final one goes in
comes out right no pipelining and what
you can see is if I have this see if I
take the same amount of time right if
this takes the combined time of both of
these then I actually blow a whole stage
to do my two loads of laundry
I've wasted one whole stage because this
is six stages and this was only five
here right because I can use that first
stage I can get that extra stage in
there right and you know if I keep going
right
that gets it gets worse and worse for
this mode right so if I'm in Stage five
here let's say I go to stage six right
where's my washer washer dryer right
outcomes three if I wanted to do it here
I would have to go to eight right to get
three out and so now we're a whole two
faster and what you'll basically see is
as I crank the number up it keeps taking
one more to do this one than this one so
it just gets worse and worse and worse
and worse and worse until basically at
asymptotically it's always twice as long
to do anything through this kind of a
pipeline than it is to do it through
this one
so basically processors in order to
maximize the value of all of the
circuitry that they have they now are
all based on a pipelining model like
this right they're all based on a
pipelining model because by being based
on a pipelining model they can use the
first part of something when the second
part is completing and it gives it a way
to sort of reuse circuitry when there
are dependencies right
zoom out a little bit here hopefully
that makes some sense okay so that gets
us another part of our puzzle here right
which is in this thing actually I guess
I want to be in here right now so we've
got our code memory we've got our eye
cash reserves our micro codes in
we're grabbing things we're issuing them
right and what we have then is we have
two pieces of information that we need
to care about right we have a number
called throughput and we have a number
called latency and for every one of
these instructions we would like to know
if possible what both of these things
are going to be latency means how long
does it take for an instruction to go
from being instantiated for it for being
issued sorry to being complete right so
that's end to end and throughput is a
number that tells me how many of them I
can do if their pipeline fully right so
this is assuming issuing back-to-back
right so translating that into our
washer diet washer/dryer diagram right
the latency does not change based on the
pipelining right the latency the amount
of stages it takes for these to go or
cycles right the number of cycles it
takes to do my wash and dry right is
going to be two no matter which of these
I do it takes two cycles for me to wash
and dry something and it so that is the
latency number if I have something that
I need wash and dry right now I have to
wear it I'm going to a meeting it's the
only thing I can wear it's gonna take me
two cycles so that's latency okay on the
other hand if all I care about is I have
a ton of laundry to do it's laundry day
I want to know roughly how long it's
going to take me to do these hundred
loads of laundry throughput is your
number for that that tells you how long
it takes if you cut out the startup and
shutdown time right this is typically
called drain out which is basically to
flush the pipeline right I don't know if
there's a term I don't remember if
there's a term for startup it might just
be startup which is basically getting
the pipeline going so basically what
throughput tells you is how long does it
take for things to push through the
pipeline once we've locked off the drain
out and the the startup
and it's basically saying if I put one
in how long does it take to get one out
I don't care which one right and in this
case that's one for here and it's still
two for here so this is a this is a
latency two throughput to system
basically and this is a latency to
throughput one system which means this
is twice as fast as this guy for
operating on large sets of data but if
you're just operating on one thing
they're the same okay so basically what
that tells you is if you only ever do
one load of laundry at a time you'd be
way better off with a washer/dryer combo
because you would have to do less work
yourself but if you wash lots of loads
of laundry you want a pipelined one
that's a washer and dryer right okay
so typically when we're talking about
performance we're only ever going to
talk about this throughput number
because latency and I shouldn't say that
with respect to instructions we will use
the term latency for other things with
respect to instructions this we
typically don't care about a whole heck
of a lot because typically our goal is
to structure the code so that we're
always working on things in a pipelined
fashion so that we're not waiting around
for the latency so when we look up
things like how long it takes to do an
ad what we're going to be looking at is
what the throughput is for an ad not
what the latency is for an ad because
we're going to assume that we're always
operating a lot of things at once now
sometimes that won't be true but that's
our goal anyway okay so if we understand
that that's pretty straightforward
and so let's talk about where latency
does actually come into play and this is
again measuring essentially the same
thing but in different context let's go
up to our caches right so the place
where latency really does cause us a
huge problem and it means latency and
throughput translate exactly basically
over here unfortunately we care about
them usually in the opposite way but
sometimes not so we'll talk about this
in a little more detail what am I at
here oh man we have gone through almost
all the time all right so basically this
is gonna be entirely a blackboard
session basically that's all right this
stuff has to be covered
okay so throughput and latency actually
typically throughput for whatever reason
typically bandwidth is what's actually
used to talk about memory even though
they kind of mean the same thing they're
not exactly the same but you'll see in a
second when I tell you what they are
whereas latency is exactly the same
thing latency just means exactly the
same thing it was used in both context
alright so what happens with our memory
our cache and that sort of stuff well
again this diagram where we've got a
stages of a pipeline that are issuing so
we got instructions that issue they
retire etc etc right this this whole
this whole diagram is how we think about
what the processor does with stuff that
it has right that it has in its
registers that it can operate on now but
the question is what about stuff that
the processor does not have that it has
to go and get right and typically we've
got two things to worry about there one
is the total amount of memory that we
can move through the processor at a
maximum speed and that again is like
sort of the throughput it's called
bandwidth typically but that's like our
throughput number that means if
everything's flowing smoothly in a
perfectly pipeline fashion how much
memory could we just move in right
there's like a bus there's a thing
called a bus that takes memory off from
the motherboard it takes the kind of sub
memory from the motherboard and drives
it into the caches right that thing and
similarly there's there's it's not
really a bus but there's lines that
allow the cache to travel from the cache
memory on the chip into the register
store on the chip the register file
right and that also has a speed a
maximum thing so there's a bandwidth on
both of these right and the bandwidth is
the total maximum amount of memory that
you could move typically you don't care
that much about that for cache bandwidth
but sometimes you do and you almost
always care about that bandwidth for
your memory right because the maximum
bandwidth to and from memory just
determines the total number of stuff you
could possibly ever operate on right
it's the speed with which things can
cycle through the processor and whatever
that speed is that's the maximum you
will ever be able to operate on stuff
right because at a bare minimum even if
you did nothing but move it
one place to another it has to come into
the processor and back out again right
so the bandwidth to the memory typically
given in like gigabytes per second for
example right the bit that memory
bandwidth is what determines how much
memory we'll be able to move through the
processor at peak okay
the latency on the memory again exactly
analogous to what it was in the
instruction case the latency on the
memory talks about how long it takes
from the time we ask for a piece of
memory to when we will get that piece of
memory back and it works exactly like
instructions if we issue a load and it
let's say it takes 300 cycles to get
memory we will have to issue that load
and then 300 cycles will transpire
before we get that particular piece of
memory back right what that means is
that if we were actually going to do
that load and the load could issue at
speed right if we literally just issued
a load had to wait for it and all of our
instructions were operating on whatever
that thing that was loaded was like
where all that whatever it was getting
loaded we were gonna operate on it right
away if that's how we were working we
would literally suffer a 300 cycle delay
while all of these instructions wait for
the result of this load to come back
right pretty horrible because 300 is a
ton of cycles add like I said is like to
cycle through put right so it's just a
massive hit and that is not a made-up
number like memory often will be 200
cycles 300 cycles to access that's not
unusual
right it's certainly probably in the
hundreds even on very fast memory
systems so or I guess it could be better
if you have a very slow processor in the
old days when processors were extremely
slow memory was instantaneous it was
basically it came right to you right but
as processors get faster and faster the
memory can't so that's what happens this
cycle count keeps going up all right so
hopefully that makes some sense and
basically what that means is we that is
where this whole Cantus concept you've
probably heard write of a cache miss a
cache miss is very expensive you hear
right what a cache miss is right is it
that the
structure of this thing here where we
have these caches on the processor and
then memory that fills the caches the
cache is what we load from so on
basically these caches like I said like
16 cycles or something like that might
be I know that's that's like an l2 speed
I think right I don't know when an l1 is
maybe two cycles I'm not sure but point
being these caches are way way faster to
fetch from the memory so if you can
write algorithms that tend to work
entirely out of things that are in the
cache and do not have to go to main
memory you will not suffer a cache miss
a cache misses when you ask for
something and it's not in the cache so
it has to go to main memory to get it
right your code will run much much much
much faster because it will never have
any of these latency hits right and
what's important to understand here is
the management of how this cache is
filled is a huge part of modern
optimization basically there are
instructions we can issue will see them
as we go called prefetches and what a
prefetch is is a way of telling the
processor hey look I need to tell you
some stuff to put into the cache because
I'm gonna need it later like 300 cycles
later and I want you to get going now so
that when I can I can do a bunch of
other operations and when I come back
the thing will be in the cache right so
there's a tremendous amount of this sort
of thinking about the cache thinking
about when to fill it and how to do as
much work with the stuff that's in the
cache as you can before flushing it out
again right before it gets replaced by
something else in order to avoid these
very very expensive latency hits and to
that effect this window here this thing
I was talking about with the out of
order window that is yet another way
that the processor tries to overcome
that latency you can imagine some code
that's not particularly good that does
some loads like this and then starts
doing ads on the loads right and that
stuff's not it's never been seen by the
processor before it's not in the cache
it has to go out to main memory so it's
got 300 cycles to work with if this
window is pretty large if this window is
like 50 or 100 cycles worth of stuff it
could do it can start grabbing things
while it waits for that low
and not waste all of the 300 cycles
right another thing you may heard of is
hyper threading right you've probably
heard of that right
well what hyper threading is is just a
processor keeping two states internally
right so maybe I have state 0 and state
1 and it's exactly like a totally it's
like having two total processors so all
of the state of the processor is
represented in both of these states
right and all it does is pretty lousy to
give it two sets of code to run as if
you had two separate threads two
separate processors right but what it
will do is whenever it sees that one of
these would stall on a memory hit right
if it's like oh I'm ran out of things in
this window to execute there's no more
things for me to grab I'm waiting all of
them are waiting on memory
it'll flop over to the other state and
see if it can grab anything that thing
will then do some work and it'll
probably end up stalling on some memory
and it'll switch back to state zero
right so hyper threading is yet another
way that Intel has tried to introduce
technology basically to get around the
fact that the memory is very very slow
right so there's basically lots of
things in here that are designed to sort
of hide that thing these are called
latency bubbles right which are
basically times when the processor is
waiting on memory and Lily can't do
anything because everything it might
want to do is waiting for a very long
fetch to memory right hyper threading is
one way gets around that right and this
memory window is the other one and the
rest of them it relies on us to issue
prefetches to write cache good thing
that has cache coherent it's called
basically stuff that uses the cache
efficiently it's all up to us right
alright so now we come to finally and I
guess this is perfect we're right up at
the end here we got about eight minutes
left so now we come to the end of sort
of the introduction to thinking about
what's actually going on and the next I
guess so this will be good because
tomorrow we can literally just talk
about optimization the process so this
is optimization essentially the platform
so now you get like this is what we're
trying to think about right what we're
trying to think about is you have a CPU
and a GPU right now we're only
concentrating on the CPU but almost
all of this stuff also applies to the
GPU oddly enough but we're only think
about the CPU right now so we're
thinking about the CPU our goal is to
figure out a good set of instructions
that does not have too big of a
footprint right so it doesn't blow out
this eye cache right because where
there's a cache where the instructions
come from so we're even thinking about
not making our code too large if that
makes sense right wanna stream of
instructions that's not too large that
does the right set of operations to
maximize the amount of time it is
operating on things in this cache right
that knows what memory it's going to use
ahead of time if possible and will
pre-fill the cache with it where
possible right that can be split up
potentially along among multiple hyper
threads and perhaps even multiple
processors let's say to maximize the
number of things that can be considered
by the processor at any given time and
finally whose instruction stream as well
as possible issues the maximum number of
cycles issues the maximum number of
instructions that could on every cycle
and in so doing is keeping this pipeline
maximally filled with the things that we
want it to do right if we can do that we
can get the most out of this 107 cycles
107 million cycles per frame that we
have and turn that into a very fast high
performance piece of code right and all
of these things can come into play
depending on the type of code some type
of code it's all about the memory it's
all about managing how the memory comes
through in other types of code it can be
all about the instructions it's all
about figuring out a good way to
structure how we're doing things but in
most pieces of code it's both it's
figuring out how to make sure the memory
doesn't stall you out and then once you
have it so the memory doesn't stall you
out it's about making sure that you do
the least amount of work on it as
possible right so that is optimization
okay now I'm going to mention an adjunct
here and this is not something really
that we'll talk about too much in this
particular pass because we're going to
start at the base level of optimization
which is about how to just write the
code so that it runs quickly
but there's another kind of concept here
and we might say that this is
performance and performance is the
hardest one to think through because
there's so much domain knowledge like
you see all this stuff I had to draw out
here right all this domain logic I
didn't even talk about everything I
didn't talk about aliasing and the cache
I didn't talk about any of that stuff
right so basically like performance is
the one that has the most domain
knowledge of the processor its adjunct
is efficiency an efficiency is the
easiest to understand it will literally
take me less than the last couple of
minutes we have here to tell you what it
is efficiency means just not doing work
you don't have to do right the
efficiency is all about the algorithm
okay so when we're talking about
performance we're usually talking about
how to make a particular algorithm run
as fast as possible using all of this
nastiness and thinking through all of
this complexity right which you have to
do if you want stuff to run quickly if
you want to be really good you got to do
it right but there's a whole other side
of the coin which happens before you
even really talk about this part which
is what are you actually doing and did
you have to do it all because a very
inefficient algorithm makes it so this
performance optimization really isn't
that that interesting because a more
efficient algorithm that isn't
performance optimized might actually
beat it because let's say that I have
some algorithm whatever we want to do
right in fact we already saw this once
right do you remember when I first
showed you how to fill the triangle
right we had a triangle and we just
iterated over every pixel on the screen
and said is it inside the triangle right
because I was just trying to prove a
point right as trying to say here it's
how the algorithm works right that ran
incredibly slowly so slowly that just
that one triangle right that was a
little tiny triangle would totally tank
the frames per second we then switched
to only iterating over the things that
were inside the rectangle bounding box
of the triangle and it got much faster
right I started wasn't a triangle I
think it was actually a it's actually a
maybe a rectangle I don't know but you
get my point
that is an example of efficiency we
didn't do any performance optimization
the cost to compute any given pixel was
exactly the same right but what we did
is we checked less pixels right and so
no amount of this kind of optimization
is ever going to make up for efficiency
and so you always do want to make sure
that you've done some work to make sure
you're reasonably efficient before you
start doing this but in this case we
kind of know roughly what we're doing
we'll talk about a little bit of this
because we do have a little bit of it to
do in the software renderer but most of
our work on the software renderer will
be this kind because we kind of know at
the end of the day that we gotta do
pixel filling right okay
so that's everything really about
optimization in terms of the high-level
overview we have efficiency we have
performance efficiency means doing the
least amount of work that you can do to
get the result that you need and
performance is structuring the data and
the ins and the actual operations on
that data in such a way that they move
through the processor in the least
amount of cycles that they possibly can
right and like I said we probably won't
hit the idealized performance for
anything we do we won't spend enough
time on performance to get the absolute
best what we'll be shooting for is like
the 80 percent case or whatever like you
know a pretty well optimized algorithm
but it could easily be beaten by
somebody who wants to spend a month just
working on this algorithm right I'm not
algorithm I shouldn't say but but
basically the way of writing the
algorithm that makes sense so that's
that's basically how to think about what
we're trying to do and so tomorrow what
we'll do is we'll talk about what are
the steps that we want to do that like
how do we actually do that we we this is
how much we have how do we think through
how we're going to work with those
cycles and that sort of thing how do we
come up with an estimate for how many
cycles we think we should be taking how
do we check against that how do we
measure how much we are taking all that
stuff that's what we'll talk about
tomorrow for now we will go to the QA
since I introduced a lot of stuff on the
stream just in case anyone has any
questions I'd like to just kind of have
a brief Q&amp;A where people can ask about
them so if you do have a question please
go ahead and ask it now put Q colon in
front of it
and I will see if I can clarify things
for you
otama click would you be willing to make
more blackboard episodes this is very
informative
I always make blackboard episodes when
they come up if you have something in
particular that you think we didn't
cover in enough detail on a previous
episode please let me know and we could
do a blackboard session of it eventually
but anytime I come to a point in
handmade hero where I need to explain
something we do do a blackboard episode
and we have had multiple blackboard
episodes in the past when we have gotten
to those things so I always I never
skimp out on the blackboard when it's
time to blackboard
we blackboard grumpy giant 256 are you
going to be using anything like vtune
for measuring performance I don't know
probably not I think we'll just probably
our DTSC it but I don't know I'll ask
cuz just correct me if I'm wrong v2
still costs a lot of money if I'm not
mistaken and I'd like to keep it the
stream to things that people can
actually use themselves so we'll try to
just write our own enough of our own
stuff that we can do it and leave vtune
is an exercise for the reader with $500
unless they're giving it away for free
now I'm not sure
how our instructions written in cache
memory I have absolutely no idea to be
honest I really don't I have no idea
that would be a great question for
someone at Intel I don't know if they
document it they might but they might
not that may just be a trade secret I
have no idea so you know I programmed
for 30 years now and I have and I've
never once seen somebody talk about the
actual format of the microcode like
literally the format so I don't know but
yeah in you could I've never trot like
I've never had a case it wasn't like I
tried to go find it and couldn't find it
I just never seen it come up it might be
that if you do a search for like Intel
micro code format or something or x86
and microcurrent egg 64 micro format
maybe there's a page somewhere it talks
about it maybe Intel's got a doc on it
it could be in the system architecture
manual I don't know but yeah so I don't
know that'd be a great question for
somebody didn't tell is it public and if
so where is it do we manually issue
prefetching or is that something
inferred by the CPU by looking at how we
access memory it can actually be both
but in our case what I was talking about
on this diagram is is manual actually
when they introduced Cindy instructions
into the processor way back in the
pentium days I think was the p6 maybe
introduced them I don't know it might
have been the p5 with MMX I don't it's
too long I don't remember but way way
back when for forever ago they
introduced manual prefetching to the
processor so basically if you if you
write some code and you find that you're
getting a lot of cache misses but you
know which memory you did need and the
processor is not predicting it properly
you just put in prefetches if that's the
only problem you can just put in
prefetches that say like okay when I'm
doing this part of the loop go prefetch
the one that's like four iterations past
here or something and it goes each time
you know so that it kind of always kind
of lead
you know like a like a snipers on that
kind of leads it and the processor will
then always know oh okay I gotta bring
that in right they also have
non-temporal stores that's update
there's there's actually quite a few
probably not as much if you're a
hardcore optimizer I'm sure there's
quite a few things that it doesn't do
that you would like to be able to do
with programming the cache but they're
you know for for a lightweight optimizer
like a such as myself there's actually
plenty of instructions in there for
stuff like prefetching and non-temporal
stores like this that allow you to kind
of you know if you're just having a
basic problem with the cache you could
fix it
stuff like cache aliasing and these sort
of things which are things that I like
only vaguely understand and have never
optimized around you know they you know
a hard crafter might be like I wish they
gave me more micro control I could I
could do more with it you know whatever
and that's to give you some perspective
that's why some people really loved
optimizing further these things will be
SP use on the on the PlayStation 3 on
the Cell processor there is a single DSP
used which were basically things whose
cache was essentially fixed it was like
256 K of cache that you micro program
like you said what to move in and when
and when to move out and when and what
to move out and when and you just had
complete control and so the programmer
could do whatever they wanted and they
were able you know people who really
like that find great optimization that's
just a lot of power they don't have with
an Intel processor right I know this is
a long way off but after handmade heroes
done do you plan to continue educational
streams I can try to yeah but I probably
at some point will want to stop doing
them five days a week so maybe we'll do
like one educational stream a week after
handmade heroes done or something like
that just to make it a little easier on
me
how often do you estimate the actual
amount of work prior to implementing a
feature
versus just implementing it and
measuring it so it depends on the thing
if I'm actually going to go if I
actually have some code that I want to
be optimized I always do at least two
things one is I try to figure out how at
peak speed how fast it should go right
and two I try to I try to sort of figure
out what my target speed would be for
that right like I try to get those in
mind
so I basically say all right let's say
that everything issued exactly right and
I did the minimum number of opps for
this math that I need to and here's a
processor I'm on and I have this many
cycles per frame what you know speed
should this thing run at right I almost
always do that if I'm active trying to
optimize that said I am NOT a great
optimizer like I'm not the guy that you
want to take advice from necessarily so
that may not be such a great idea but I
always like back-of-the-envelope
computations in that way a
back-of-the-envelope computations
basically which is what I'm going to
talk about on next stream basically is
going okay just a rough estimate how
fast should this thing run and the
reason that I like that is because it
gives me something to measure against so
I can go what if it doesn't turn out to
be something within a reasonable
percentage of that I can say why what's
the thing what what was I not thinking
about that's causing me to not get what
I want right and so like for example if
you get into a situation where you're
like I should be able to do this many
loads and this many multiplies and this
many stores all pipeline properly this
should work out to this and it's not
that's a great time to go call up Intel
call up whoever and be like ask your
optimization friends what's going on
here can you give me some information
and I've seen great results from that
some optimizers who are much more
serious than I am like Mike Sartain for
example I've seen them do stuff where
they encounter they end up at places
where they're like this is running too
slowly
and I've computed everything out and I
know it is and they've gone and talked
to Intel and they've gotten Intel to run
like top secret traces of the code that
they can't even see necessarily how they
were doing them because it's like on
internal only stuff and Intel will send
them back
Oh the problem is that there's a thing
in the processor that works like this
and you're hitting it because you're
alternating these two things and it was
like okay right and so a really really
hard core optimization guy knows the
boundary that's stated in the Box sees
if they can hit it and when they don't
hit it and don't know why they ask the
processor manufacturer and find out and
that's like the hard core thing right so
I always at least try to the first part
of that process which is to let me know
where I'm at
relative to what I should be doing
because I think that's a pretty
important thing to have because
otherwise you don't really know where
you're at you're like I don't know like
is this code optimizer isn't it who
knows because I don't know how fast it
should go and if I don't know how fast
it should go I don't know whether how
fast it's running right now is pretty
fast or pretty slow you know so so if
memory takes a few hundred cycles if the
instructions have to reach out to the
hard drive what impact would that have
the answer is a lot less now because of
SSDs so it's getting better but the way
to think about the hard drive is just
adds yet another piece right so I think
we drew this diagram a long time ago and
handmade here actually but since it's a
little more relevant now imma draw it
again you could think of it this way
right register
l1 l2 l3 memory just add another box
drive right and you can even do two of
them drive and network right so cheapest
right this is like almost free this is
very expensive and everything in between
and that's why you end up with this sort
of concept that latency you know
somewhere around here latency starts
being this kind of dominating thing that
you're thinking about because it starts
getting so big you know 300 cycles up to
you know thousands of cycles or tens and
thousands of cycles or way worse
depending on what we're talking about
fetching from here what you end up doing
is somewhere you know as latency starts
to dominate as you move in this
direction
that's why everything tends to be
overlapped when you get out here in a
huge way like drive stuff you issue you
know like on the thing that I'm doing it
at work right now I issue Drive reads
two seconds in advance of where they
would be used or more right so we're
talking six billion instructions in
advance I'm issuing them at least right
and and sometimes more depending on the
circumstance right so that's just that's
just how that that is
start your pancakes two questions are
there ever any cases where we have to
worry about one of our instructions
being decoded into multiple micro
instructions without our knowledge - in
optimizing have you set up the code in
such a way that you can optimize things
function by function with this
eventualities in mind or will we have to
restructure some of the functions to
allow them to be optimized so question
one the answer is typically I never
think about micro code all that much
because the throughput and latency
numbers tend to be all you really need
to know for baseline optimization like
we're doing if you're trying to do super
hard core optimization then yes actually
that is something you need to worry
about because of this part that I was
talking about back a little earlier you
can sort of see exactly why this comes
into play this thing with the issuing
it's the it's the issuing that kills you
right so when things get too coated into
micro multiple micro code instructions
what that means is it puts more pressure
on the on your issuing count right if
something gets blown out into seven
micro instructions that means that that
thing you thought was one instruction
actually gonna take two cycles even just
to issue everything of if they're not
independent possibly more it could take
up to the seven instructions if they're
all serially dependent right and so it's
having something broken out into micro
code if they're serially dependent and
there isn't code around it that can be
executed to hide that bubble could
absolutely be a problem but again is
that common note that's not the common
case the common case is you don't have
to think about micro code will it happen
if you're a super harka code optimizer I
suspect the answer is absolutely yes
will it happen if you're just a you know
reasonable optimizer such as myself no
you don't tend to be going you don't
tend to push things to the limit of peak
performance where you're gonna have to
start thinking about things like that
question to whether I've set up the code
in such a way that we can optimize
things function by function the answer
is generally yes and generally that's a
good thing to be doing just in general
like when I try to write code I try
to write code knowing what things are
expensive and really what that boils
down to is order stuff right remember
order notation that's the thing that's
like Oh N Oh and squared right that sort
of thing basically what you want to
think about is how many iterations right
that's really like what you want to
think about so you've got four loops
sometimes you get four loops inside four
loops and so on that little piece of
code in the middle how many iterations
does it have to do right and if you
think about that in the back of your
head you're always going to kind of know
what your slow parts of the game are
going to be a lot of times right because
the things that that executes the most
frequently are the things that have that
happen and so in the case of the
software renderer pixels right is a loop
over x and y right so it's om squared in
the size of the thing on the screen
right it's it's filling in an area so I
just tend to know when I'm writing a
software renderer okay what are the
things that are gonna happen to software
renderer I know that I've got relatively
big sprites on the screen that fill up a
fair number of pixels I know that I have
a fairly low number of them by
comparison right so like I've got the
number of sprites you know maybe that's
ten thousand or something total I know
I've got the number of pixels you know I
know that's like you know millions right
and I can just tell like this is the
thing that I need to be the most
concerned about and this is less so
right and so you're already when you're
thinking about writing the code it
should be obvious to you just that
you're typing it in oh what are the
places here they're gonna have to be
optimized it's that rectangle fill right
that's the gonna be the very most
important thing optimize so everything
else is gonna be secondary to that so
you gotta make sure the code is all
about allowing me to optimize that
rectangle fill right that's at etc but
at the end of the day as long as you're
not doing totally crazy stuff for their
code and this is one of the reasons why
again I also hate object-oriented
programming is because typically I find
that if you write stuff in a
straightforward C programming style just
the
way you would normally write the code
tends to end up looking like how it will
end up being when it's optimized and the
only time that that doesn't happen is
because of the fact that C's structs
weren't designed when Cindy was the
thing and so typically you have to do a
little bit of reorganization for this
for the cindy aspect of things so that
changes things a little but I find that
typically the way people normally write
things in an OOP style it's very
different from how you would write them
if you were trying to optimize things
and so that's yet another reason I don't
like that paradigm it doesn't mean you
can't write it doesn't mean you can't
learn to program your oop in a style
that makes it okay for a play it just
means your natural instincts will often
be wrong in that domain and so that's
another reason I like the C style
because I feel like people's natural way
they might write something and C tends
to be pretty close to how it should be
laid out when you actually need to
optimize it would it be inefficient to
offload the cache to an SSD over SSD
over or with minimal RAM usage or with a
late I'm sorry I'm not sure I totally
understand the question would it be
inefficient to offload the cache to an
SSD over or with minimal RAM usage or
would the latency be too much I'm not
sure I understand the question and SSD
is basically just very slow Ram right so
it sits at again the place that I drew
it sits over here in the hierarchy right
and so you would never offload things to
an SSD you would offload them to memory
first and then to the SSD usually
because you want to overlap that right
you want to overlap that that flush but
yeah I'm not sure I totally understand
the question so sorry about that
premature optimization is the root of
all evil what's your take on that quote
my take on that quote is it's largely a
meaningless quote unfortunately because
premature is the problem right it's
obviously true just at the face of it I
mean well I don't know if the truth
face it because I don't know the root of
all evil might be a bit much right it
might be that it's a statement that
would be unequivocally true would be
premature optimization is evil or is bad
right but the problem with that
statement is saying premature
optimization doesn't really help anyone
because how do you know what's premature
right on the one hand optimizing a bunch
of things at an instruction level when
you are when your game is already
running at 30 frames a second or
something like that might obviously be
stupid and premature and yeah that was a
huge waste of everyone's time and makes
the code less harder more brittle and
because you can't change it as easily in
whatever right so obviously that's true
but that's not normally what what the
the thing that might make a mistake the
thing where you tend to make the mistake
is okay do I need to store these things
in a spatial hierarchy or not right or
do I need to do this or not right and
the problem is doing those things or not
doing those things tends to have
architectural implications for the rest
of the code and it's not as simple as
just not doing it until you absolutely
have to because doing it later might
have to change how a bunch of stuff was
architected and then that optimization
was too late so post mature optimization
that becomes a problem and so I find the
problem with that quote is is not than
anything wrong with the court itself
it's just that knowing whether
something's premature or not is actually
very difficult and is not as easy as the
quote might make it sound is there any
way to use or avoid hyper setting to
your advantage
yes and we will be doing that on the
stream we will be using both hyper
threading and regular threading in the
in the renderer and we'll talk about how
to use those on the next stream probably
what you tell someone who doesn't like
Emacs I tell them not to use Emacs I
just use Emacs because that's the editor
that I'm most comfortable with but I
think everyone should use provided they
can be provided they can be like roughly
as fast as they see me code on stream if
you can code that fast in whatever
editor you want I think you're good
if you can't
then you might want to consider either
learning how to use your editor better
or switching to another editor not so
the Emacs but just another editor that's
better so that you can be at least
roughly as fast as I am because that's
the speed that I think you want to
roughly go at if you're going
significantly slower than I'm going
that's probably a bad sign
especially because I'm coding slower on
stream than I tend to code in real life
because I'm talking and stuff so if you
can't at least hit that speed I think
you want to think about whether you're
facile enough with the editor that
you're using but it doesn't have to be
Emacs does hyper threading reduce
maximum bandwidth because it has to
switch between states or can both states
operate at the same time typically yet
if the bandwidth is is typically shared
between hyper threads so yeah the
bandwidth doesn't get any higher just
because there's thread it hyper
threading so with a reduced bandwidth is
a little bit hard to say because
bandwidth is a measure of how much stuff
is moving into the processor so that
obviously is always the same but if you
have too hyper threads they are sharing
that bandwidth obviously so you don't
get double the bandwidth just cuz
they're the two hyper threads let's see
is your in your active me in your
experience what drives the good enough
optimization and how does the notice and
how did the novice guys get a handle on
that actually it's very simple the good
enough part is actually pretty pretty
straightforward you have a game it needs
to run at 30 frames a second you have
some expensive stuff you're doing in
that game it is good enough when it runs
at 30 frames a second on your target
platform that is the end of it right and
so it's usually actually pretty easy to
know when you've hit that now hitting it
can be hard if you're trying to do too
much but you know knowing when you've
hit it is easy the game runs at 30
frames a second done all right and so
for any given piece how you know how
close that piece is to being optimal is
by doing that back-of-the-envelope
calculation that I was talking about
before it was it's basically about
having some idea of how fast the
processor could ideal
do this workload and then seeing how
fast you are doing that workload and
that's a good measure of how optimized
your performance is efficiency there's
not a lot you can do about efficiency
I'll be honest with you efficiency is is
very hard to know because how do you
know if the algorithm you're using is
very efficient sometimes you can figure
it out by going oh well I know that
somebody has proven this algorithm takes
at least this many iterations right it's
Oh n provably and I'm only doing o n so
I know I'm relatively efficient
sometimes that's true but sometimes the
thing that you're doing it's very hard
to know because it's like okay well yeah
it's proven to be O n but I'm
accelerating it with this lookup
structure that makes it a little closer
to o n most of the time if it's
distributed well but what it's not sure
well maybe I could use a different
spatial partition and then it would be
distributed better so I you know bla bla
bla bla bla and like there's all these
things where it's like really kind of
nuanced and so that part is actually
very hard to know and sometimes the
answer is just you iterate on both the
algorithm and the performance because
you just don't know until you can get
yourself down to 30 frames a second
that's just any it's any it's a grind
and there's nothing else we can do right
and that's just sometimes that's the
case right
so it looks like that's about it we're
out of time and I don't see any more
questions on optimization really
sudonym 73 you were posting a gift hub
link there for latency numbers do you
want to go ahead and post that to the
forum so we can like have it up there I
could I could tag it as a as i cap
ermine opposed or something that might
be cool but for now let's go ahead and
wrap things up tomorrow hopefully now
that we've kind of gotten all the
preliminaries out of the way I can just
talk briefly about some of the stuff
that we need to do so we can actually
get to some code because I'd like to do
a couple code things relatively soon for
us to start working with but anyway yeah
there we go that was basically a giant
blackboard session on optimization
topics hopefully that set the stage so
that when I referenced when I go through
talking about subjects and their
reference things I'm hopefully hopefully
that will be nice and easy for everyone
to understand so when I reference
something like in l3 cache or the
latency of this instruction or the
throughput or whatever will kind of all
be on that same page so if some of this
was confusing please go back and read
watch this or ask questions on the
forums so that we can kind of all be on
that page because as I go through this
I'm going to just refer to those things
like instruction throughput in that sort
so I'm gonna refer to those and and
assume that we now are clear on what
those mean all right thank you everyone
for joining me for another episode of
hand made here it's been a pleasure
talking about optimization with you know
coding today hopefully tomorrow so I was
talking about I did I hope that cleared
some things up and got us on a good sort
of on the same page for what we're about
to do for this week next week and so on
if you would like to follow along with
the code we're gonna do this week and
you want to pre-order the game that gets
you the source code so if you go to
hammer here or get Pierrot to the game
here and it comes with a source code so
you can download it every night after
we're done here
the forums are a great place to go if
you have questions that you want to ask
or you want to look up some stuff that
we've got up there like that ports to
Mac or Linux and also we've got some
coding resources anti episode guide just
stuff good stuff up there check that
site out if you're Fowler for the stream
we also have a patreon if you want to
support the video series and what we're
doing here we would love that you can
always subscribe they're very much
appreciated and we've have a tweet
but which treats the schedule so if
you're just trying to catch the stream
live on any particular day if that's the
place to go it'll always tell you the
schedule today we're 5 p.m. Pacific
Standard Time every day except Friday
when we're doing a morning stream 9 a.m.
so please check that out just so you can
check that schedule out so you can
remind yourself what the schedule is
it's a great way to do that so thanks
everyone for joining me and I will see
you guys tomorrow
take it easy everyone