hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here sure we code a complete game live
on stream we've got some parts to do
today probably I'll catch you up if you
missed yesterday's stream as to what's
going on here so we have art stuff we
want to put in the game that's what
we've been doing and we have a situation
where we've finished importing all of
our art assets and doing that sort of
thing but we now have like some assembly
that we need to do in order to like put
our stuff together right and you can
kind of see here I'm a ridiculously huge
cat now for no apparent reason but if
you take a look at like when we place
things in the world like everything's
all discombobulated like the heads and
the bodies they all just show up
centered around whatever the placement
point is we have no coherent way of like
placing these things so that the heads
go on top of bodies and stuff like that
and that expands more generally to other
types of things you might want to do for
example if you want to have heads that
go on top of bodies and then hats that
go on top of heads and so on you kind of
have this idea that there are points
inside these objects inside these
bitmaps that you know kinda have to snap
together and we need to have ways of
like selecting that sort of information
and you know basically preparing
something useful to happen there you
know we we just need something to we
need some way to make that work and so
what we're trying to do now is get that
going and what we did is we augmented
our ability to store this data I
remember you have an HSA file format
that stores game native for us we go in
here in our native directory we have
this concept of HHA files and we
augmented them yesterday to include a
bunch of information that could be used
to create exactly the thing in question
here right exactly is the ability to
snap things together using points and we
made it so that it you know
could import old ones and work the way
it used to as well but also support this
new stuff and so we have this this new
idea of alignment points and each asset
can have a set of alignment points in it
so in addition to tagging it with like
why you might want to use this resource
in a gameplay sense we also now have
alignment that says if you're using this
resource with other resources how might
it snap together and so we have two
things we need to be able to do now
and one of those things has two parts so
you might say we have three things we
have to write number one is we have to
actually use these things like supplying
the placement points doesn't really help
if we don't have any code that actually
then tries to snap things together using
those points so that's the thing we got
to do and then another thing we have to
do is get the data in there so we have
to have a way of of actually putting in
the information about where we want
these things you know where does the
head snap onto the body and stuff like
that so that's the part that has two
parts to it one is we need a way of
storing that stuff in some kind of form
that we can consider authoritative and
permanent which means probably not the
HHA files because that's supposed to be
a runtime format that we can delete and
rebuild if you want to change how the
runtime format works or stuff like that
so we probably don't want to rely on it
being stored permanently in there it's
actual work that we're doing we're
actually spending time to like place
these points you want to preserve that
work so you have to redo it every time
we want to rebuild Rho J's or something
so we need some way of storing that
perfectly I was suggesting just a simple
text file that corresponds to the PNG so
it's just you know again the simplest
possible thing nothing too complicated
so we would need some way of parsing
those text files and then taking that
information and placing it into the HHA
when we actually do our importing so
that's you know one thing the other
thing that we want to do is have a way
of seeing those results and editing them
in real time because what we'd like to
be able to do is make it really really
easy to set all of those parameters to
exactly what we want so you know one way
we could do it is just constantly tweak
the text file and then see what the
results were and tweak the text file
until it's right and that's the simplest
solution in terms of programming because
it doesn't require anything other than
the
just the text import and that's it but
if we really wanted to make it easy for
us to do large batches of these assets
without too much fuss then I think we
want something a little bit more
complete we would like some way of
having those text files be like
graphically editable right like we would
like some way we would like some way of
taking the like making a user interface
inside the game we can just at any time
say oh those two things mean like need
to line up like this and then that
information just gets saved back into
the text file for us right and that's
just a way of simplifying that process
so that it's not you know a big deal to
adjust it and doesn't take a bunch of
time and wasted energy
having that import work right so that's
all we're trying to do here it's really
pretty simple you know that right
there's not much to it but it's just
there's a bunch of grunt work involved
so we kind of got to go do that grunt
work if we want this thing to work out
okay so that's all we're talking about
that's what I want to do now and so we
just got to get started now like I said
where we're at here we kind of have to
imagine getting this stuff to work right
so I don't know where where the best
place to start is you know one way might
be to say let's go ahead and try to try
to make the Edit part well just start
with that
right so we'll start by trying to make
the thing that allows us to you know
edit those placement points and then
we'll go from there so you know if we
wanted to edit that sprite we saw you
know we see that it's wrong and we need
to be able to mark it up so we need to
be able to take this one and make a
placement point on it and we need to be
able to take this one and make a
placement point on it and then have
those things snap together in some kind
of a satisfying way that would be what
we're trying to that that's the goal
we're trying to comp
sure you know I'm saying uh so let's
think about how we would do this when we
actually have stuff that's incorrect on
on on the screen how are we going to fix
it right and one of the things that we
have here is if we were to pick one if
you know if we were to have some kind of
an editing mode we could go into where
we can pick these things here we would
then have to you know maybe show
something I don't know like using the
debug you are using something we would
have to have some way that we could show
what's going on with with one of these
entities and allow us to add or adjust
points in the entities you know what I
mean
and so that's kind of what we would want
to do here now this is a little bit
interesting because in some senses this
isn't really a debug UI it's hard to say
like one of the things I think we
probably didn't do very good on handmade
hero is respect the fact that the debug
UI maybe isn't really a debug UI or at
least a lot of the things that would be
going on View mode UI maybe shouldn't be
debug UI like maybe they should actually
just be systems that are part of the
main game and the reason that I say that
is because since a meteor is a teaching
tool it means that probably you want to
just let people play with the internals
even in the shipping version of the game
you don't want to do the same kind of
architecture you do in a normal game
where you try to actively remove all
that stuff when you ship it like you
don't want any of those things to be in
the game you want those things to be
compiled out completely and not ship at
all and so we kind of have a little bit
of a potential mistake there just in
terms of philosophical mistake in terms
of any philosophical is probably the
wrong term but maybe I'll say a mistake
regarding what the goal is of any
particular system and so we may want to
think a little bit more critically about
that and start to move it away from that
a little bit more and so when we're
talking about this you know maybe we
want this to be something that you can
just do in the game you know like if you
decide to
go into a debug mode in the actual game
proper then you maybe can just do you
know you can just get that this stuff
all the time so it's not something that
would be removed from the game in the
shipping version like we normally would
if we were making a game that was not
that did not have a teaching component
to it if that makes sense so we can keep
that in mind so if we go in here to the
enemy system for example you know we've
got a notion that we may want to you can
see here we've got like debug pick
entity right and we've got some stuff
about that and you know maybe what we
want to do I guess what I'm saying is
maybe we want to make this picking
procedure be a little bit more
integrated into the game so that you
just have a way of going into a debug
mode and if you go into the debug mode
then you can start clicking on things
you know that's just how it works or
whatever right it's just a thought so if
I want to do something like that what I
could do is when we're doing our picking
here right what I could do is have a
thing that checks to see what mode were
in in the game right you know let's
check something
what kind of mode am I in am I in a mode
where I actually be able to edit
something and then if I are if I if I
are wow that's good if I am then I would
like to do some picking perhaps maybe on
these like piece and indexes or whatever
here right and one of the things that we
know is you know we've already written
code in to do box intersection so we
kind of have ways already of picking
things in the world using Ray's because
we already have a notion of we already
have multiple notions we have things
that can intersect raisin boxes so for
example in our lighting code we already
wrote things that do this so if you look
at for example where we do our ray
casting you know we already wrote a
bunch of code that does testing of Ray's
versus boxes and in fact we have an
optimized one even the tests a bunch of
rays and boxes at the same time
stuff like that right so we have the
notion in the box intersection we also
have the understanding of how to
unprotect points so if we go into the
render itself there's actually an
unprotected here and what you can see is
what do you call this you can actually
get you know if you say here is what
clip space is you know here's what
here's where my point is on the screen
and then you can say if I was this far
away from the camera where would I be
like where you know in in the worlds
would I be right uh so we actually have
multiple ways of doing this and it seems
like at this point we could even just we
don't really even need box intersection
because if we have the ability to do a
3d reverse projection at a particular
distance we could just say look where is
this entity piece that we're talking
about let's go ahead and just do a
projection back to that Z depth and then
we'll look to see if we're inside a
rectangle that's roughly the size of the
sprite right because again this isn't
part of game play so it doesn't need to
be exact we just need an easy way of
looking at something on the screen and
selecting it right because that way we
don't have to go looking through some
we're not to make like a lister that
lists all those sprites and you know we
pick them and whatever we can just when
we see something that's off wrong we can
just fix it right there you know it's
pretty nice and handy in that sense
right so let's just do that you know
let's just see what happens if we just
did that right so we have a render group
that we know that we're drawing these
things in and we know that we have these
piece indexes and all this stuff right
and we know we can so we can know we can
do a crappy like hit test without too
much trouble if we want to and I'll just
turn this on by default we're worried
about where them worry about where the
mode switch is later so then in here you
know when we're actually looking at this
stuff I'll just pretend that
everything's a cube for now and we'll
just take a look at what that cube
information is and we'll just say like
alright so you know here's where the
thing would be right and here's how big
the thing would be and so if we have
that information we know the the world P
of the piece we know the world dim of
the piece that's not exactly right
because we interpret it somewhat
differently but we can start
regularizing that stuff a little bit
more or make this code more exact by
checking what kind were working with who
knows right um but what we could do
first you just say all right so let's
just actually with me do it this way
let's just first say okay you know if we
were going to actually put one of these
things in here and we wanted for every
sprite to just draw a little rectangle
what would it look like so I'm just
gonna start by first of all pushing a
rectangle on there to make sure we've
got some representation of the pieces at
all that's all I want to do is just get
that right to begin with right and so
here I'm gonna take a look at at where
those things are you know what I mean
and just try to figure out what's going
on so what you can see here is we've got
some weird that's kind of cool
we've got some weird placements of those
rectangles I'm not sure what exactly
that's doing this is the inner transform
offset P plus the piece offset right
not sure exactly you go to the render
here I'll be honest I don't really
remember what push rekt even does oh all
right so here's Abba transform offset
and dimension right so I'm passing the
dimension I want to draw here I'm
passing the world peak here so it does a
bunch of nonsense yes so I don't really
want to be using this I want to use
something that's more specific right so
I probably want to do not sure what you
know maybe this is a little bit better
so here it does push rect outline is
really probably what I wanted cuz the
other one's a little bit nuts right it's
it's doing totally different stuff in
terms of how it's gonna interpret the
interpret the rectangle let me see if
this is a little bit better first yeah
so that makes a little more sense there
but only a little and it kind of looks
like it looks like it's scaled out wrong
like everything is bigger than it should
be right
because if I was to push a cube I should
get exactly the same locations as I was
getting with everything else right
and again I just want to make sure that
I get this stuff correct I don't really
want a bitmap ID in there all right um
so I want to just be able to draw
something that's a non that doesn't
really have I want to be able to draw
something that doesn't really have any
weirdness to it on the you know on the
cube front here I guess the other
problem so I guess the other problems in
any transform automatically has that
baked into it so that's probably
actually what I was seeing there so that
makes some sense so probably this is
actually what what I was seeing right I
was applying the entity transform twice
because it's already gonna get applied
automatically by that routine yeah there
we go so that that was just me being
stupid so if I go look at where those
are they're kind of embedded in objects
most of the time as you can see and
that's exactly what we would expect to
see happen there to the largest and I
want to see if I can get the world dim
stuff a little bit better just see if I
can approximate the size of these things
but now we're kind of in better shape
here
kind of need a wireframe render mood I
also I need better luck debug camera
tools I need a lot of things so looking
at that it looks like it's got the why
and not the X which makes perfect sense
because the way that we did things in
the in the bitmap rendering is you just
kind of pass down a dimension in Y and
it blows the X out for you right so when
we're actually doing this in a sense you
know that that part is actually being
taken care of inside the thing that
looks up what the bitmap itself actually
would be and so you know for us it's a
little bit trickier because we don't
really know what it should be at this
point so you know hard to say how we
want to handle that going forward but
you know for the moment if we did this
we wouldn't be too far off we'd be a
little bit far off in certain
circumstances depending on the
eccentricity of the thing involved but
you know it's not the worst
approximation at the moment so again
there's the cat right and now you can
see that those rectangles would be
pickable and so we should now be able to
write something that just kind of
selects very easily can select something
so that we you know can can highlight
things by just looking at where they are
and maybe get a little bit of just get a
little bit cleaner in terms of like how
we're how we're gonna pick objects to
edit in a particular time so let me go
ahead and allow that to happen so if I
come in here and I want to do a pick
what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna
first check to see a what it would look
like if I just highlight things that are
under the mouse cursor so we can see
whether or not we can pick them properly
and if I do a none project here
like so I should be able to get back a
cursor in worlds kind of a thing so I
should be able to take like wherever the
mouse is and I should be able to do that
transfer and to figure out what's going
on yeah I mean and so in order to get
the render group transform we know this
just whatever the current transform is
right but I don't want the games
transfer I want the debug transform
because if I'm in debug camera mode I
want to be a pic from there so I'm going
to past the debug transform as the
default one because we always want to
use that rather than the game one in the
case where the game is in debug mode so
the clip space XY we need to know where
the mouse cursor is we'll do that in a
second world distance from camera Z we
know what that is because we know we
know how far this world point is from
the camera if we want to because we can
just figure out where the we can just
use the Delta between the camera and the
sprites location and we can just measure
that along the cameras z-axis right so
it's not that hard to get that right in
fact it's pretty easy so our big problem
is getting the clip space XY and to do
that right what we'd have to do is we
have to be able to look up where the
mouse actually is now fortunately we
know where the mouse probably is because
we can feed that information forwards
now the problem that we're gonna have of
course is that that doesn't come into
the update and render entities that's
okay cuz I don't know that we
necessarily even need to be in here you
know we may want this to be you know the
cut we may want this to be something
that happens outside of there anyway and
that happens in world mode or in some
kind of code that's like you know the
picking part of world mode so in here
where we do update and render world you
know we know that we
you have the camera inside the mouse
because we know that information from
the mouse pee that we generate right so
we use the user input here to get that
so we should be able to pick entities
with that as well so for example in here
where we do render entities which
happens inside I think should be like
right here I think it happens inside
does it happen inside simulate it must
which is weird
you can see it happening here inside
simulate
I wonder why it happens inside Soumya
light I guess because the sim region you
know you can't render once you've closed
the sim region but it still seems like
you could have just put that out here I
mean the fact that it's update and
render entities I guess is probably the
reason right so you know inside simulate
you're gonna do both at once so I
suppose that does make some sense so
anyway we have a couple choices here you
know one of them is we could just do the
the testing in line and the other is not
since we're rendering in line
I guess testing in line is fine too but
what we need to do is we need to pass
the mouse information down because if we
don't there's no way we can pick it
right so inside simulate here when we're
going to do up it and render em entities
we need to pass some input information
down to it which we can do this like
this and we can say you know only do
this if we actually got the input you
know only do this if someone extra so
that way they don't actually have to
pass it to us if they don't want to
which seems good right and so then all
we need to do is actually think about
how we're going to actually create that
and we have in debug mode we already
have sort of a notion that we're going
to have to map these things and do a nun
project in fact there's a nun project
here right and so inside the IMP the
input we have a clip space mouse key
which is this thing and so in theory if
we just actually asked for this we
should get back what we expect for the
clip space Mouse that should already be
correct and so then what we need to do
is just figure out what the world
distance is going to be now to figure
out what the world distance is what we
want to do is measure how far along the
cameras the access you would have to go
in order to get to the place that we're
going right now
we
that the world position of the entity we
know that the world position of the
camera which we actually have because if
you look at inside the renderer you know
we were careful to save this kind of
information so if you take a look at the
like for example the render transform
debug X X form you can see here that it
has the position from which you are
rendering baked into it right and the
projection matrix there so I assume and
you know I guess now I think about it I
don't remember exactly how the render
transform stuff is encoded so I have to
think about that but it can't be entity
based it has to be camera based I think
in fact because you know you don't have
any entity information when you're doing
this here so the the debug transform is
going to be the cameras position in
there and the cameras z-axis in here
right
that's my contention anyway so and I'll
verify that let me just go ahead and do
that so in here we say camera X Y Z P so
let's see what we do with the camera P
there it is right so we just set those
directly so what we have is inside this
the debug X forum and I can you know do
this
and that way we actually have one of
those that we can coherently access so
if I want to do the you know from camera
vector basically so if I want to
construct a vector that just goes from
the camera point which is this and I
want it to go to the you know I want to
go from the camera to the element that
I'm testing this would give me that
vector now I don't actually want that
vector now talk about why in a second
but if we want to get world distance
from camera oops
to plug into this function then you have
to ask yourself well okay if I have a
vector that goes from the camera to the
entity I want to be able to take an
inner product right to measure along the
cameras z-axis I want to be able to
measure how long that vector is along
the z axis because that's exactly what
that will be right so I take the camera
z-axis and I measure and I say using
that as the measurement if I take the
vector from where the camera is to where
the entity is how long is it that gives
me the distance in Z the problem with
this is it's going going to go the wrong
way
the z axis actually points backwards it
points like towards the viewer right so
the z axis points backwards towards the
viewer the from cameras gonna point
forward when I do the inter plug it's
gonna be negative for things that are in
front of the camera so what I really
want is the opposite right I want a to
camera vector so I want to say from the
entity to the camera that goes the same
direction as the Z so then I'm actually
measuring without having to do an
additional negation there to get the
right answer right so that gives me now
the ability to take the cursor in the
world so now I have where the cursor is
in the world and I have where the thing
is in the world right I have both of
those two things so now what I can do is
say if I want to I can actually figure
out where in this in that plane I can
figure out where the mouse cursor is in
the plane of the entity right so I can
basically say like you know entity Mouse
here or something right and the entity
Mouse PD is equally simple all I have to
do is say look I know that I've got I
know that I've got a point in the world
where the entity is and I know that I've
got where the cursor is in the world in
that same Z plane you know what I mean
so if I take a entity to cursor vector
and I basically say I have where the
entity is I so I know the world P and I
just subtract that from where the cursor
is I get a vector that goes from the
entity to the cursor and then I can just
dot part that with the X and Y axis of
the camera and I'm done right so if I
say X form X first sorry entity to
cursor X form Y entity to cursor then I
now have a location in space relative to
the entity and I can now test to see
whether it falls inside the dimension
that I've specified so if the entity
mouse piece of that that measurement
there right if the entity Mouse P X is
less than the world MX
and the absolute value y is less than
the world didn't like then I just know
that I'm inside the rectangle right and
if not then I'm outside the rectangle
and that's the end of it so it's
basically just a 2d hit test you know
what I mean
and so now we just have to debug it
right and and and then we're good to go
so the first thing I want to do so we're
not awful like you can see it sort of
works but it's not quite right you can
see we're kind of a little bit off it
looks like our Y is messed up for some
reason there why is our Y messed up I do
something strange with our Y
probably not but we'll see in a second I
would like to draw this line as well we
have a push line segment call right um
so anyway that's the fundamental
construction it's kind of just like
hacky I'm just like let's just test this
somehow and that seems like a reasonable
enough for your test so I'm just going
to bug that and we'll use that as our
way of simple picking you know just like
basic picking of the entities there um
so here's the render group here's a
texture for the line segment okay I
guess that's fine I don't remember how
to specify a texture that's just pure
white there there you go so I want to go
from the camera I'm sorry from the
entity position oh this again so yeah
this is gonna be annoying so the fact
that we're using this sort of offset
transform thing is a little annoying
because you can see I did it again I had
exactly the same bug this world P here
you know it really wants to take into
account
when we're doing that what the transform
what the entity offset would be I don't
I really don't like that transform stuff
it just it leads to all these bugs like
that and you know I don't know I kind of
feel like we shouldn't do it it should
just the renderer should just work in
world space here I think would be better
we'll have to see what we think of that
but I feel like that's just it's just
dumb and so I feel like we should
probably get rid of that because I hate
having bugs like that I want this stuff
to just always be in world space so you
know because of this the under transform
thing here we want to do just the piece
offset because it's gonna add that thing
in so you know it looks like that but
then here where we do the push line
segment right I mean let me pause this
cuz I'm like let me see if that just
works that might actually have been the
only problem because obviously that's
just gonna be offset everything's gonna
be offset incorrectly so we'll see so it
looks like our Y is wrong there
but it's pretty close right you can kind
of see that like we're it's just a Y the
Y is a little bit wrong I'm not 100%
sure why pun intended
it's like both are a little big I guess
one thing I don't know is does this
entity transform stuff have a scale in
it I assume it doesn't yeah it doesn't
look like it does and so yeah
looks roughly correct so here's a couple
things I would say also I just want do
this before I forget if the world
distance from camera Z so if that's like
less than the near clip plane basically
which I don't know if we really
articulate here anywhere not really
so what I'll basically say is if it's
less than like some some close value
there whatever we're not gonna look at
it right so you know when we when we
actually compute how far away this thing
is we're gonna we're not gonna look at
things that are behind us right and that
doesn't have anything to do with what
we're not looking at there are no things
behind us in the current setup so it's
not relevant but I just wanna put that
in there before I forget so anyway we
got our X form in here we then do our
entity cursor I want to draw that line
so I can see it and see if it's accurate
so there's the world position looks like
that's just a color
2p is going to be the entity to cursor
is just cursor in a world I guess is
where I would want to draw that and then
the thickness can just be whatever I
don't know probably too thick
it looks like current wads runs out of
and trees there but I'm not super sure
why
so here's push line segment Oh because
it doesn't actually get quads
right which is kind of annoying
yeah that's kind of annoying you want
there to be a call where it'll actually
do something for you there I don't know
why it doesn't that so it looks like
this was coming up
oops sorry say
so you know that's actually quite
accurate I mean that's pegged right to
the cursor so I'm not quite sure why
we're getting an error there I guess
so one thing that's true is this is
irrespective of the transform so
probably what I would say is because so
we're not actually getting like we don't
actually have the Delta in that we don't
actually know what the dimensions of
that rectangle are in that plane is I
guess kind of one negative aspect of how
this is being done so like for example
in here yeah we can sort of see exactly
what the problem is where you know we're
we're looking at its side on and here's
that vector it's totally it's totally
wrong in terms of how it's being
projected down so I don't know how I
want to do that I could project the
mouse cursor onto the plane
it's always hard to decide because since
these things are not real 3d shapes it's
hard to know how you should be picking
them if that makes sense look normally
you just raycast against the 3d shape
but there is no 3d shape it's just kind
of an abstract blob that's kind of stuck
on the world if I did want to do that
now if we have a wrote a ray intersects
plane
doesn't look like we did so we could
write one of those and then just take
the intersection of the camera vector
with the plane instead and do it that
way is that better and worse than
testing a box I mean I guess the nice
thing about doing a box test is the box
test would work for the cubes too so
maybe we should just do the box test and
then we just sort of make a fake box for
the entity in question and let the Box
test deal with it so if we want to do
something like that you know we can
generate the Ray ahead of time so you
know what I can do to generate the Ray
direction is actually pretty simple we
just used the same code that we have
here but we just do it in a slightly
different way so you know what I can do
is say all right take you know before we
start let's generate a picking ray and
so here I'll just say
if you gave me a render group then what
I'm going to do is take a picking ray
and the picking ray is going to go from
the camera out into the world by taking
whatever the clip space is and just
going one unit out because who cares
it's a ray right so we will do the
unprojected just say just normalize the
vector from the camera to that point and
that's our picking ray so if we have a
picking ray then what we can do is we
can just use the picking ray to
intersect with a phantom box we
construct like a made up box basically
and we just use that made up box we
don't need to do any of this really but
we do need to right oops
little box intersection code um so once
we have this information here we can
basically you know fake the dimensions
of this box and we can for actual cubes
we could make it exact but for other
things you know we can't so we you know
we have to fake it for sprites because
they don't have a real shape um so
anyway if we did that then what we could
do is just say like if ray intersects
box and then we would just pass here's
the world P here's the worlds dim and
here's the picking ring we know the
picking origin as well
because of course it's just this because
we're always starting from the camera uh
so I think that's it and that would give
us the ability to do it as if they were
boxes which seems a little better just
having play with the lives like oh yeah
right you know we don't we want to be
able to sort of still do it in pseudo-3d
even though things aren't 3d I don't
know so which argues for the Box
construction to me um and so if we did
that we just need to provide that actual
function now there are some other things
we would want to do here I'll show you
in a second so we don't really want ray
intersects box per se so we need to do a
little bit more work there but at the
moment you know it should still be okay
now the other thing I can do here is
actually draw this as well so you know I
could just make sure are picking array
is correct I can do a push line segment
that just says let's draw the quad from
the origin to the Ray or from zero zero
to the right just as a quick way of
making sure that there are picking ray
is actually correct because we don't
really know what it is
so if I said look let's draw from let's
say just the origin of the world and
then to the picking origin plus the
picking ray we should see that end at
the end of the cursor right and that
just lets us know that our picking ray
isn't garbage right it like that we
actually did that work correctly okay so
what I'll do is I'll just stub this in
here and then we'll talk a little bit
more about what we want to do so for
right now what I'll do is I'll just say
hey you know when you do put caps left
on um when you ask me to go from origin
Direction box P box radius I am just
going to tell you that the result is you
did
hit anything right and so that will just
work in the sense that it will never
actually queue the hit code and we can
run the app on its own right oh and we
still have this stupid problem I don't
know what I want that that that's so
weird do we have a way of calling that
that accounts for its own quads like why
don't we have one of those that accounts
for its own quads that just seems really
strange
we don't write like we don't have that
push line segment render group so this
will do it for us from free from CF 2 P
2 CF and fitness
um so again yeah someday polish up the
renderer
what is this saying recursive you're
correct that's what I actually wanted to
say there and so now at least we can
just call that and not have to think
about that - all right so let's try to
get this to be pegged to their correct
location it looks like it basically is
so I mean I think we're okay there all
right so if we have our picking array
doing its little picking picky poo then
what we need to do is have a way for
this box stuff to do something
reasonable and so what I want to do here
is just say look okay we've got a world
Tim we're gonna push a rect outline on
here and get that highlighting in the
case where it actually needs to get hit
what we could also do is just show those
irrespective and change the color so
that might be a little bit more fun at
the start just again as we're debugging
this so let's suppose we said that the
color was going to be black and it only
turns or yellow when you actually hit
the thing when the mouse is actually
poking through right so we'll always
draw the rectangle and we'll just draw
it by passing the right color in there
so what's the complaint here
Oh got the thickness I guess I pushed on
their group v3 neither of these are the
render transform version how did we get
how do we not have I want something that
draws the outline of a cube push volume
outline and like this whole time I'm
like being frustrated I'm like don't we
hi we do we drew cages before how can we
can't throw them now and it's like well
that's why alright good so then we can
say that we've got this rectangle
dimension here that's what I wanted to
pass the first place so that's much
happier all right good good good mystery
solved
so that's good all right cannot give her
a target three two rectangle three okay
that's fine we can create a rectangle
three let me just look really quickly so
it doesn't take a position right so it
wants you to build a rectangle three out
of these two things so we just want to
do a center radius Oh Center dimension
right like that it's not really a radius
I guess should it be left to see
I'm pretty sure we have one of these
yeah so now we should see a bunch of
little like floating black outline
things right and and that is what we see
which is good and if we were to do this
without like instead of sprites if we
were to do this like so we were assuming
sprites there but let's let's say that I
just I don't do the world dim stuff
there so let's suppose that what I
actually did is I just go like okay
let's actually create the outline sir so
it looks like those are radius calls and
this is a dim call so like I just want
this world dim it's really a world
radius here and I'm saying which is what
I was planning for anyway
and so if we do that what we want to do
is is when we create this rec center dim
we really want rec center half dim in
that sense because it's the radius not
the diameter and so now you can see we
get those thick outlines around
everything which is what we want and now
what we want to see happen and we'll nor
the sprites for a second but we want to
see happen as I want to be able to pick
those blocks right and so we have an
optimized version of Ray intersects box
that's made for patches and we're
working on the lighting but we don't
really have one it's not optimized so
what I'd like to do here is just figure
out some way to actually get this stuff
to be you know inside there like let's
just take a look at what we're doing
here and see cuz we kind of already
worked that stuff out right so if you
look at what we're doing here we have a
box P we already know what that is and
we have a box radius and we already know
what that is so if we wanted to do a box
man in a box max we could do that
exactly the same way we were doing it in
our sim decode and similarly if we want
to do
this sort of nonsense here we should be
able to do that as well if we are
looking at what's going on here the x in
brady though
that's a little bit saucy er so that's
actually doing
[Music]
that's actually doing something slightly
more competent here so that pre inverts
the Ray test right like this so it's
effectively doing that and so what it's
doing here is the same if I pre invert
and then I divide each of them axes by
the pre advert like so I'm basically
dividing each one by the Ray stepping
then I can come up with which axis I
would hit earliest
we don't really need an early out
condition here so this should be
sufficient so this is whether or not the
hip actually hit you don't care about
the T inside I don't think
yeah so I think we're really just
looking at look if the hit is between
here and the max is not on the earlier
side of it so this is basically the
thing that says what's going on so this
this is really what we're talking about
here right that's our key key valid
results so that's this is like good B
hit right
and so our Max and mins are fine this is
the part that we're gonna have a little
bit problem with so this is effectively
a Hadamard product here I think that's
correct
I'd have to read the algorithm that we
were using there which is kind of an
accelerated box test right but it's a
little swing key let me go ahead and
make this happen um so this is doing you
an inversion I don't know that we ever
actually did that in our in our routine
where you could invert by a scaler where
you're basically saying look I want to
invert each element of my my Ray and go
from there so we have like divided looks
like we did divided by a constant but
not be divided so let's let's just do it
so in order to do that all we have to do
is reverse the meaning of these two
things right so if we want to do this to
each of our individual elements then
what we want to do is say well okay B
gets divided by a X a Y and a Z and
produces the final result
um seems like I don't know that we ever
did am in here so what are you thinking
sighs we don't actually we don't
actually have a min that operates on
vectors right that does kind of seem
good though so I feel like these things
that we were taking for granted in the
sim D context you probably should have
them for our regular vectors as well I
mean it just seems good right like if we
do a min of a and B like it seems like
you would want to just be able to do
look that's min ax BX it just maps over
the vector right
is ma'am macro like if this remember how
we set that up right so is minimum of
macro yeah so that's kind of annoying
this is again just the CMAs of it all
it's kind of annoying we can't really do
what we would have wanted to do with min
and Max there but yeah oh well
so in theory that would do the
intersection I have to walk to that
routine again and make sure some it
makes clear sense and other parts of it
are a little bit they're like okay
you've done some steps with the algebra
there and so I don't necessarily want to
call that correct for an app but that's
basically what we're dealing with so it
looks like we translate it correctly
because the picking is working and so
then we just have to deal with the the
part that I was saying we we don't
exactly want rated sex box so the reason
we don't exactly want it is like if you
look at what happens if I you know pick
down the middle all the hits all get
recorded so what I really want to do is
actually provide the the T value coming
back and so in here what we really want
is something that's more like you know
f-22 result equals you know some value
that's not gonna sort properly and so
maybe what we do is we just say look the
the result would be f-22 Max and then
you know we check to see if you did hit
oops and if you did hit then we will
return you the actual hit in question
that way when you do Ray intersects box
here what we can do instead of doing it
this way is then go ahead and just just
pull this back out to its own sort of
well you know what it's really just a
render that has to change
so in here we can basically just take
the best hit and then at the end render
the volume outline in question right so
what we would do there is again just as
we run through the entities we would
just say look which entity is the actual
one that looks like the person's on top
of and which piece index as well so we
can just say look you know what's the
hit entity index and what's the kick
entity piece those the two pieces of
information we actually need and what we
can say is
when we go through we'll just track
whichever one that is so in here when
we're actually looking at the hits this
also we can roll this into the other
loop too which is kind of nice so we'll
just go ahead and do that in a second
here but what we can then do is say all
right when we do Ray intersects box
that'll give us back the T hit if the
best hit is greater than the T hit then
we'll go ahead and grab it so we'll just
say at that point grab the best hit it's
now that this is the entity we hit hello
and this is the piece that we hit so now
we know which one of those we actually
hit and now inside the render group we
can just say well I'm sorry inside the
test at the end we could just say well
alright if is a render group and the
best hit is not you know a nonsense
value then assume we hit something we'll
just pull out whatever that entity is
and draw the the piece in question right
now we may want to make that a little
easier on ourselves by just recording it
because we can hit P and hit him
that just seems nicer just to make it a
little easier on ourselves so I'm gonna
do that too so here we'll just do like
hit P equals world P get dimples radius
and then it'll just draw those so we
don't have an indeed transform and
that's fine because I don't really want
one anyway and I'm not sure how to get
just a generic transform I guess we
would just say
[Music]
you know I'm not sure which default
transform we really want to use here and
so I couldn't really tell you should
make that a rectangle too so I want to
play with that a little bit I may just
want to remove those transcripts all
together - I don't like them I don't
think they're good but anyway so now
when we're doing picking you can see
like it only picks the closest hit right
and so that's nice because that means
that we don't have to worry about that
so now let's see if we can make
ourselves pick sprites because we're
really not going to pick sprites now and
sprites are the main thing we want to
pick like it's nice to be able to pick
entities who's we probably will care
about that but I'd like to be able to
pick the sprites as well and so what I'd
like to do is roll this actually back up
into the old routine so instead of
actually doing that as a separate pass
now when we're actually going through
the piece indices here what I'd like to
do is make that happen like sort of
right in line with retiring the pieces
of cells so when we do this we can now
sort of have that happen as its own
little pass when we're actually looking
for input there and so when this part
happens what we now know is that we have
more information about what we might
want to use because these paths that
branch can now record what the world
position and stuff like that should
actually be and that's good for us right
so we know that the world P is always
that what we don't know is what the
world radius actually is and so if I was
to say look let's get the world radius
information we'll stick that in here
when we come down through here the
lights as you can see that'll just work
the cube version will just work and so
the only issue is this path here which
we don't know so in that case what I can
do is set these now to be based on the
you know sort of bogus values that we're
just slamming in for sprites so now
it'll do that testing and we'll be in
good shape don't ask me why there's a
color value of being set there we don't
need that anymore and so now in theory
we should be able to put in phantom
boxes for each sprite that can be picked
and those boxes are not going to be
exactly right but you can see now we are
picking them and so we'll probably need
to do some work to make those more
accurate for an individual sprites
probably by working with the bounds that
we know from like looking at the bitmap
and stuff like that but like let's say
we go in here now I should be able to
pick yeah and I can you know I could
pick like this sort of fakes bright for
the the cat right so there's the cat
body and there's the right and so yeah
it's not perfect but it's not horrible
and so that's that's basically allows us
to reach in and get exactly what we want
uh so that's pretty easy you know that
wasn't too bad
was a little bit of fussing but but not
too bad and that would allow us to pick
things the only issue that we're gonna
have there is again like we don't know
the right sizes these things because we
don't look at the bitmap dimensions and
we probably need to write so that's one
that's a little Squinkie and you know
probably busted there's a lot of things
that are busted about that and stuff we
can fix now because one of the things
you have to remember is the bitmap
dimension stuff we now have all the time
so there's no reason to defer the amount
of information back on the bitmap front
we should just get the bitmap and look
at what it's actual thing is because
even if it hasn't been loaded yet its
dimensions have so it's not like we
don't know where the bitmap is or how
big it is we just may not have its
pixels so there's no real reason not to
have that information directly in there
and so that's just a little stupid right
but anyway other than that I think we're
in good shape so now we can let click on
these entities
you know and we can you know do whatever
we want there and and you know who knows
what right so let's go ahead and see
about now adding something where we
could adjust information about one of
these entities so if I was to like pick
one of the cats bright ones or whatever
and by the way when we're doing this
again like I said you know it's it's a
little confusing because I don't when we
have sprites stacked up on top of each
other we need to know how big the actual
sprites are and that's something that
we're not really doing so again like
this all kind of ties in it'll get
better
as we fix and finish the placement
routines which is what we want to do
anyway so being able to pick the you
know the individual pieces will get
better - at the moment let's say even
what we could say is that even if we it
was this crappy though like even if we
never fixed it we actually do have an
easy way of making this be sufficient
because all we actually have to do to
fix it is say look when I pick one of
these then just give me like a hotkey to
cycle through the pieces right so it's
actually not we only really need to pick
entities we don't need to pick
individual pieces anyway so it's fine
like this is way good enough and it's
exact for any actual 3d stuff and it's
only a problem when we have these
individual pieces because we don't
really have tight balance on them yet
when we had type bounce we might be fine
with that too but even then you might
you know sprites layer in complex ways
and you know especially like imagine of
translucent sprites so you don't even
know which one you're picking did you
want the one that you can see through to
the back or did you want the one that
was in the front there's no real answer
for those so you know you you probably
would need something for disambiguation
in those cases anyway and so that's kind
of a separate issue too but anyway
that's you know that's it and that's
fine so let's try and make something
where we can actually adjust those
pieces of
formation and you know get it so that we
can edit it in the game and just it
won't be saved so it's like any work we
do just gets thrown away unfortunately
but let's just get that working and then
we can work on this next step after that
which is getting it through line the the
whole pipeline right so at the moment
I'm just looking it looks like we got
about thirty minutes left is that right
or did I go over time how much time do
we have
does anyone know how much time do I have
am i over time I'm out over time right I
don't know how much time is left this
thing doesn't usually tell you how much
time is left
sixteen minutes into the cute well
really
I guess I don't have time left then
never mind
[Music]
does anybody know what the actual time
is because I started I started it 1
o'clock right so now we have 30 minutes
left because I started at the beginning
of stream I was working on the hash
thing and I didn't start the timer
I moved the timer up to 1 o'clock so I
didn't start at noon in so that's
probably going on the assumption that we
actually started at the publish time but
I actually started an hour later because
we were doing other non handmade here at
programming right I feel like I'm gonna
be excited to do some more improvements
to the lighting because the lighting is
almost starting to be cool and when it
becomes a little bit cooler than it is
right now I think it's gonna be very
cool and that's all I have to say about
that
all right so yes so I guess what I want
to do now is be able to like pick one of
these things and just figure out some
convenient way to to talk about like the
various points that are involved right
so I want some way to like take a thing
and annotate it with points I guess I
don't know if I care if I can add points
or not
I'm not sure what I want to do here I
have no idea so I'm gonna start doing
something and we'll see what develops I
guess that's just how it's gonna go so
let's suppose that I want to edit a
bitmap thingy so I want to be able to
display like some information about it
and I want to be able to like like
here's what here's what I want to do so
one of the things we did in the importer
right is inside world no asset so here
so I'm gonna start with okay so inside
the asset importer one things we did is
there's a way of getting errors right so
like you can generate errors and errors
go on the file in question right and
that sort of thing and so like if
there's parse errors is the name of the
file or stuff like that like it comes
out and the bitmaps have you know errors
in them or whatever right and so one of
the things that I'm interested in is
like what if I just want to see those
errors for a particular bitmap so so
we're not even to try and edit anything
like what if I just I just wanted to
play something so I want to be able to
pick a bitmap in the world right and I
want you to tell me I want you to print
out you know what is what the errors you
recorded for that bitmap
I mean that seems reasonable right
and I mean I guess I don't necessarily
know if we have a way of telling which
file a bitmap came from but I think we
do because I seem to recall in here when
we actually have the assets themselves
right they they now store this little
u-32 pair which means that they know
which file and which asset in which file
they were so if you were to click like
well mm-hmm so we have a forward mapping
but we don't necessary have a backward
mapping so we know what hh-hey it came
from but we don't necessarily know
anything else about it we do however
have annotation for it
so if we put the errors into the
annotation then that would work and that
would work nicely which is probably more
what we would want anyway
and in fact I'm not sure why we didn't
do it that way that seems good to me
so if we look at the HHA look at the
file formats here if we look at the HHA
like so for each one of the the assets
in question we have this annotation
thing and we've got like this reserved
block here so we can actually add
additional stuff one of the things that
we should probably add I feel like is
just errors right so like were there
errors on the import of this thing
and that way you could you could do two
things one is you can ask if there's any
errors in a file and it will be like
yeah here they are and the other is you
can for any given asset you could say
where there any area any errors on this
asset or any warnings on this asset that
you know me retention that seems pretty
good right so if I cut that down and say
error offset or airstream offset and
error stream counts
right
so if I just add one more in there I can
say hey here's the Airstream I'll set
and here zero stream count I can take to
you six fours away and just like put in
one pad there and then nothing really
has to change right the file format
doesn't change at all but I can do that
and then I can actually look at errors
so I think that's good I don't really
know if it's good or not but it seems
good so if we look at like when we get
the author here right when we read in
one of these files now I can just add
another one of those like okay so here's
the Airstream and I could say era stream
asset and their stream count and in
theory that should just make a thing
right
I think so I don't know if that needs to
be so when you write an HHA this is
actually a rate h hav to write so if you
write an HH a when you write these yeah
so we'd need to do one more of these as
well but I think other than that it's
just that was it and now you can just
you can bake those in there if you want
to and so at the end when you when you
go to import these I suppose when we
dump
we should also print those out so
this is a little bit harder because if
we go to print out the Airstream we kind
of need to reformat the Airstream at
least a little bit if it has lots of
lines in it in order to like not mess up
our output here so this is like
somewhere we kinda have to take that a
little more seriously than we were now
we could I mean we could I guess just do
it like this
print out the header
and then we would have to essentially do
like a four loop here where we loop over
and try to get that data out I in some
way and so we would say something like
something like what's the say ummm so we
would say something like count left
equals you know whatever the whatever
the amount is we start with and then we
would just say looking while we've got
that remaining or I suppose another way
to do it would be this way start at zero
and just go till you find something so
you could say while it's left while it's
you know has not exceeded that size and
then I could say well you know for each
of these things in here if it equals if
it equals the line and character then
we'll print a line in the other thing I
could do is say if
yeah like if it is also the ending
then print that - yeah let's do it
so in here if I go ahead and say I'm
starting at zero I need to know where
the like I need to know where the start
of what I would print would be so the
first thing is gonna be you know the
first thing there right so I'm gonna
start with this index and I'm gonna you
know consider it going here and we got
to do smaller than 64 bit here even
though these are strings at some level
all right so what I want to do is say
let's start with the data in question
we're going to advance along it until we
see ourselves hit the end of it when we
look at each individual piece we're
going to look to see if we've hit an end
of line and if we have then we'll print
from the base through to the current
location right and I guess you know what
I could do it like this might be a
little bit better right so what we're
gonna say here is take whatever if you
do it this way so we know we want to
print out wherever we are - wherever
we're starting and we know that we need
to go from the base every time we print
so that's how we would print out one
segment and then what we would say is
okay from then on we are going to want
to go one forward right another way to
do that would be to look at it like this
right and so yeah not super confusing
seems reasonable so you say look look if
it's an end of line we print it and then
we skip the end of line character
like we don't print that particular
character otherwise we just keep going
forward and so the only problem with
this is we really need to be able to
print we want to be able to do this
print out on the last one as well so we
want to be able to say look if it was
one we also need this end criteria in
addition so if it's the last thing or if
it was a backslash n then we need to do
the print and we're done
when it is the last one we have a little
bit of an issue because we want to be
able to print the final character in the
case where it wasn't a backslash n so I
think what we want to say there is this
plus plus at can happen early so we can
say look go one more than you were but
you know print one additional character
if it is a backslash n
I think that would do it for us we'd
have to look and see at the moment it
will do nothing because there are no
errors in our HHA files so if I do you
know a dump of one of these things let
me do local and then I look at the tab
view of it so I shouldn't see any of
those because we don't save any error
streams to disk right so you can see it
doesn't really say anything and so what
I'd like to do is go ahead and see about
actually putting something in there so
inside the asset system when we actually
import one of these things let me see so
when we actually import one of the
things we have this Airstream thing
there and the errors are currently
stored not really on the actual files
themselves right so
when we like the one thing that's a
little bit mismatched II here is just
that we have the concept that errors
just happen on the import we don't
really know which asked to which assets
they would correspond right and so like
in here for example you've got errors
that apply to the whole file and you've
got errors that only apply to a
particular asset and we don't really
have a way of differentiating between
those two things specifically which we
would like to do right so in one in in
the plate and single tile export cases
the errors can all just go to the same
place and it's totally fine but in the
other cases we can't do that you know so
I'm not sure how we want to report that
because we really have to we really have
two places errors in that case like need
to go right
so I think what I would want to do there
say well you know let's
let's just say that like all of these
kind of errors right
in some sense you just want any asset
that was part of that import to have any
file errors attached to it so you know
that it's wrong it should be fixed
eventually but the only problem with
that is there are some errors that there
are some situations that produce
literally no assets so for example if
you end up in a situation where the
thing can't parse the file name at all
then you don't really have a place to
put those error messages other than to
display them at the time because there's
no other place to put them right you
have to display them on import like just
on the screen or something because
there's no way to actually capture the
fact that that error happened you can't
just bolt it onto the file somehow
because that's not actually sufficient
right so I guess what I would say is you
know in the case where we do it here we
know that the asset source files
Airstream is being built up and when we
actually go to write the image the HHA
it's pretty easy to just bolt that on
there but we probably need when we do
this we probably need to have another
source of errors in addition to the file
errors that we print I guess that's what
I'd say um so in here when we go to the
the stream stuff what I want to be able
to do here is you know this thing
creates these stream chunks right and
Scott like here's all the stuff that we
put in there so we want to be able to do
is I want to be able to do a one of
these like write a set string calls
basically but I want to be able to merge
that data in so what I want to do is is
sort of have a write asset stream almost
ensue yeah like if we look at what
happens inside write a set string
you can see what goes on so I need to be
able to do a reserve data for the entire
size of the Airstream
and then I need to be able to actually
write the asset data that is the stream
in question right and so what I want to
do here is say that the that this is
going to be equal to whatever the total
size is of both streams right now one of
those streams is fictitious because I
don't have it yet but I know that I'm
gonna have it right so I'll just make a
dummy here and that dummy stream will
have nothing right ensue
you know we'll call this the asset
specific stream or whatever like asset
specific errors or something right so
there's like asset errors and file
errors something like that so if I type
the asset errors in here so that I can
say tell me how big this actually is and
then I also know that I've got the file
errors themselves right so because
that's another stream I can see how big
is the total set of errors and it'll
just give me that and then that's good
then I can reserve that amount of space
so that I say our error stream counts
so the error stream offset is gonna be
reserved however much space I just said
that I actually needed right
and then I just need to write into it so
then I just need to like copy stream I
don't know how you want to it's it's
really a it's really a four I loop over
the stream here so that's that's how
that would work
so if I want to loop over a particular
stream I need a utility here that would
do that for me right but I know
otherwise exactly what's going on right
I know that this is the offset at which
you would start writing and furthermore
I know that the the stream is the file
era stream just the first one and I
probably need to think here too that's
the that's the size in question for
whatever this air stream is here so I
need to know the file error stream size
so right here where I get those two
things I know that I need to reserve
space for both streams that I'm going to
do so that's what I do but then I when I
go to write them I know that I need to
write both streams like so and I write
one at the offset that is how far how
much space the other one would have
already taken up right and so that's
where the the asset specific stream
would go
so this would do that writing in terms
of the the right size I don't know if
this thing ever has a way of finding out
how big the entire thing is it doesn't
look like it to me so I think we would
need both of those functions so one of
them's general-purpose is one of them is
not so the right stream part is not
right what's this called right string
where's where is that function
that's right asset data so I call this
right asset stream and I just need to
call this like multiple times right so I
need here's my file and I need my
starting data offset and then I need
whatever the actual stream is and then
it's pretty straightforward right I'm
just looping over these chunks so I'm
basically saying like all right so
whatever the first chunk is I'm gonna go
through and I'm just gonna write to the
file each individual trunk and each time
I'll just move forward by however big
the chunk actually is and that's it
and that should just write it and we
need to cast it down because it's gonna
be too big right so this these are going
to be larger than we would have lab but
we know that we're never doing buffers
that big in this particular context so
that's okay I think although actually
this in this case we're actually fine
with that because we're actually
tracking it's this good position so well
we would have to truncate the right we
could actually continue to move the
pointer correctly which is interesting
in and of itself I suppose
um so writing the asset streams pretty
easy and similarly getting the total
size is also really easy right because
again all it is is a loop over the
string to see how much space there
actually is so all you really need to do
is say look how big is this stream you
would say well the stream is however big
all the chunks are if we add them
together right so that's it I mean it's
a stupid function barely even exists and
it's just a case of of having to do a
loop over all the chunks which may not
be the most efficient thing in the world
but it's totally fine in our case
because this is only for asset importing
we don't really care about that so if we
asked for get total size here in
handmade stream let me just go ahead and
get total size of the stream we should
now be able to ask for what the total
size stream is and get it we should also
be able to produce the right stuff here
I again have that you know the problem
of not actually we don't actually handle
64 bits worth of space on any of these
things that's intentional so anyway when
we actually do the the asset data
reserves I don't really remember how
that function works so I want to make
sure I'm passing the right parameters
there just take a quick look so we need
assets asset file asset data size that's
isn't that correct
assets so that's that's its source file
so we actually need the asset
to file in this case so that's a little
bit different so we actually need to do
that and this is right asset stream so
in theory now when we do an import it
should actually put those airs into the
file now at least in theory we'll see we
can test it because right now there is
some stuff spewed to that stream for no
reason like we stuck this in there just
to see I think if anything happened so I
can force a rien port and see what
happens right if I delete the local HHA
it will rebuild oh sorry I have to
actually make one so if I tell it hey do
some reading it should do the reading
and in theory now it should dump the
errors out to each individual assets so
any asset that's in there we'll get a
error stream and in theory if I dump the
air stream I should see that now
maybe we hope right that doesn't look
like our printouts working so it looks
like we actually sort of did do that
correctly but a printout doesn't look
like it's working properly so maybe I
just screwed up that lip-lip because I
kind of threw that in there it wasn't
particularly bright so that makes it
pretty obvious obviously we don't want
those two things to both be true we need
only one of them to be true let's try
that one more time
so we're almost right still a little bit
busted but this is great because now you
can see what the errors are in a file
per per thing and I like that the this
looks like it's skipping
but I'm not sure why
Oh because now we're doing that
pre-increment
and I see yeah it's the other way around
this isn't not equal to right we're
supposed to do the pre-increment only in
the case where it's actually the final
character that's actually what we were
supposed to do there so yeah so that was
just a little bit busted so I think
we're good now the only thing is we we
need the backslash ends to be in the
actual file in the actual air as you can
see that our errors don't have backs SMS
on them which is not good so we need to
fix that but otherwise it looks like
we're in good shape now right and so one
more check we might want to do in here
if we find that there wasn't any actual
thing to print right
so if essentially what we're saying here
is like okay we got to the last
character but there wasn't anything to
print so if base is not equal to at but
we don't want to include an extra empty
line for no reason I guess it's all I'm
saying
so something more like that not the
prettiest loop in the world I'll give
you that um so now are we better off
so I'm going to use four as an example
and now I'm just gonna go in and fix
some of our errors here inside the asset
streaming stuff so I'm just gonna look
at all of our out FS and see which ones
should have had like things at the end
of them right so I may think quick spin
through and just look at like out F yeah
that should be it one there
so that looks pretty good and so if we
just get rid of the re-imported thing
because that doesn't really tell us any
information is not an error then what we
should be able to do is now see like
when we've actually got errors we should
be able to see them only on files that
actually had something go wrong and so
if I delete local daily HHA now and
create a dummy one it'll force the
re-export and now it should export our
errors correctly and we should be able
to see those errors nice and clean with
no no fussing so if I go ahead and and
re dump that file like so we can now see
probably errors where they exist right
so now we see like tile errors that had
to had stuff happen to them or whatever
and we know ones that don't it didn't
have that right so that's pretty good
and we can make a thing that just dumps
the HHA only the air is neat to say to
but I'm gonna leave it at that and then
what I want to be able to do now next
weekend what I'll do is I'm gonna make
it so I can pick an entity and show
those errors on like live and then we'll
make something that loves to edit the
points I think that's basically where I
want to be at so let's go to brief Q&amp;A
here just for a few minutes five minutes
or so
is it possible to account for sprite
opacity when selecting items physician
to be more intuitive is it useful
generate a more slim triangulation for
sprites but both of the answers is yes
so if you want to account for sprite
opacity you certainly can what you have
to do is when you actually pick a point
inside the box you have to then figure
out what texture would be on that face
and which face you're on and then you
have to go and look up into the bitmap
the way we're doing it right now you
really wouldn't want to do that because
we're making fake boxes because we're
we're actually wanted we all want to be
able to pick sprites like from a debug
view where they're not even facing the
camera so you really wouldn't want to do
that you want to just pretend there's a
selection nub and you can just draw the
selection nub if you it's too hard to
hit for a sprite and you want just pick
that like a handle because otherwise
it's gonna be totally random if you were
always picking sprites head-on then it
makes a lot more sense to look at the
opacity because then you could just say
well I'm just picking pixel based and
off you go so you know as for generating
slimmer triangulations for sprites uh it
does help if you want to minimize over
draw and you have your sprites have a
lot of empty space in them yes it can be
very handy because it prevents the
graphics card from having to iterate
over and do simple tests and like haze
or any alpha and this block of texture
no okay skip it but it doesn't have to
do that check if you just never iterate
over the first place so there's usually
a sweet spot too much triangulation can
be bad because then you're forcing too
much stuff through the vertex pipe for
no real benefit but two little triangle
a she could also be bad so we're
probably a little under triangulated by
doing quads that's probably not enough
triangulation you could probably add a
little more triangulation and get some
speed winds but you can't go too far you
have to you know pick a happy medium
because if you put too much
triangulation then you're actually just
slowing things down by forcing the
graphics card to iterate over a lot more
triangles and a lot more fractional
pixels and stuff and that's
not good either instead of fussing with
selecting the individual sprite parts
wouldn't be handier to list them in a
picked entity hood
yeah and that's sort of what I was
saying like just have a hot key that
allows me to walk through the parts
quickly and then I just don't care about
picking them exactly is the count
inclusive with strings in the words do
you really need the nested ifs in the
line printer.i yes it is well I don't
know what you mean by inclusive
inclusive of what it's in a lot of time
operas the hash function but is it worth
it most of time you calculate hashes
when doing IO which will always be
significantly slower so you'll save more
time if you calculate the hash in
parallel with IO this way now Hassen sh8
512 would have the same impact on run
time straighten me out hash being eight
times faster so I guess what I would say
there is so definitely not suggesting
that IO is the primary bound for hashing
doesn't really make any sense
io in my experience literally is never
the IO is almost never the problem ever
with hashing I can't think of a time
when I've ever been i/o bound when I was
using a hash it's just not a use case
that I can even think of actually and
the reason is because in game
development that's not what you're doing
you are in put bound on beginning your
data processing so when you have to load
say a PNG right or a PSD file which is
like typical like a 1935 let's say we
load a PSD file and that PSD files like
a hundred and sixty megabytes or
something let's say so we are in put
bound looting in the PSD because we got
a weight to get 160 megabytes right so
the best we can do is be processing some
other file while we're loading that file
so that is a given but once you start
pressing and you look at the total
amount of time it's going to take you to
process the file if you've got it in
memory and turnaround time is critically
important here remember like if an
artist wants to see an update to
something you need the credit that you
want the turnaround time to be as small
as possible
so once you've got the PSD in memory now
what you're doing is you're blowing out
those layers to individual tiles or
chunks or hovering across them you need
to hash each individual chunk and then
you need to check to see whether that
chunk is already a chunk that you've
worked with before so you're gonna look
to a memory resident hash table for a
collision right and that hash table
ain't gonna be that big right so the
number of cache misses in walking the
hash table isn't massive it's way less
than the size of the thing that you're
hashing so not only is the thing that
you're hashing in cache and it's
probably about 64 K or 32 K or something
like that not only is that Orion memory
so you're hitting the cache the entire
time so you're not waiting at all when
you're running the hash because you just
produced the thing but you're also about
to not do anything on the back end so
you're using the hash to avoid having to
actually do any IO because it's probably
a duplicate that is exactly the same as
the last time this thing was imported
but we don't know that it is yet because
we haven't looked right um so no like
literally IO time is not a bottleneck at
all in the part of the thing where the
hash is being used the things that are
bottlenecks are usually LZ compression
and hashing that's usually the
bottlenecks maybe sometimes bit entropy
encoding but not really compared to LZ
in my experience
I'm already be past the last character
history oh I see what you're saying now
yeah you could be right maybe I can make
that simpler again the loop was it was
not particularly attractive loop I will
give you that so I guess what I'd say
here is once at equals the count
I guess no I I can't see how you do it
simpler oh I see yeah yeah yeah so so
this actually is the part that we don't
need
yeah I think you're right
good catch where's my tab you at
why might not seen any errors at all
up
so I'm looking at the wrong text there
we go yeah good catch yeah that's right
we didn't really actually have to do
that all right uh I think we're good for
now and yet like yeah that there's a lot
of excuses about hashes that I don't
super understand on that sort of level
that last topic a lot of people say like
well it doesn't matter cuz it has
because it's gonna be memory bound or
this hashes memory bound anyway or
whatever almost no there's only like two
hashes I've ever profiled that are
memory bound really like almost every
hash is not memory bound at all like
they're not they're just not like they
could be going faster than they are
they're not memory bound they most of
them hash it like four four bytes per
cycle and could hash it eight bytes per
cycle or six bytes per cycle if they
remember bound so that's not usually
what it looks like to me and the other
thing is IO bound but they're never i/o
bound like you have to be doing a very
weird specific case where you literally
just read and hash and that's the only
thing you do which is like disk
utilities or something like I don't know
what I don't know what case that is I
can't even think of what it is like I'm
sure there is one like I don't mean to
suggest there isn't a case where your
i/o bound or the hashing but it's just I
can't think of it I certainly never have
that case if there is something that's
that's slowing down things that that
makes the hash not relevant it's never
IO it's usually like some other heavy
weight stream operation that's just much
slower than a hash like you know
if you wanted to optimal parse an IOC or
something and you're just like sitting
there cranking away with all these tests
or something right like I mean there's
ways you can have stream processing to
be very slow and then it doesn't matter
but it's just it's not it's one of those
excuses that hashes are slow and you
know they do slow things down it's just
it's very hand wavy to say that like
memory bandwidth is the issuer size it's
this not true so like I would much
prefer meow hash always it's just it's
not strong enough to really use always
as your hash and the problem at the
moment is I just don't know how weak it
actually is in data collision practice
so you know I don't know I would love to
just be able to use it always but I
don't know how strong it actually will
prove to be and so we would like to find
ways of potentially strengthening it to
be more cryptographic ish just because
the closer you can move towards
cryptographic the more assured you're
gonna be that you don't have spurious
collisions when used in non
cryptographic cases and so that's really
you know the thing that's that's I would
like to figure out if there's any way to
do but I haven't really found a way to
get maximum throughput without with
anything that can strengthen I just
haven't figured it out
so at the moment it's gonna have to stay
as a sort of like you know who knows one
in
you know a hundred billion case or
whatever like you know I don't know what
the actual practical collision rate is
gonna be that one again also one of the
big problems that you always have with
with hashes is you're like hey what's
the collision rate what's the expected
random collision rate on this hash
well you can't ever find it I mean if
it's sufficiently high but still not
that high like you know how are you let
let's say that meow hash was 40 bits or
something right you have to basically do
a big data run to find those collisions
if if your hash is literally only like
if your hash is literally only 40 bits
meaning it's a 40-bit hash so your
birthday rate is 20 bits no problem you
could find that immediately just by
testing right but if your hash has a
probability of random collision of forty
four bits 42 bits you're never gonna
find it right and soup going forward
knowing what that Headroom is would be
really nice but you know finding it's
really hard and especially in a case
like now hash where you know like okay
so it's gonna be this specific the kinds
of things that will collide are these
specific things that have to do with AES
one to thirty two expansions kind of
collisions how often will those happen
in practice
nobody knows right like it you just
don't know so it's kind of annoying
that's why strengthening it a little
would be nice and we could find some way
to do it because then we don't have to
wonder about whether those things would
happen in practice cuz you know then
that would be a problem with the hash
right so it's really tough it's just
it's hashes are nasty that way they're
really hard to know if it's a
cryptographic hash it's much easier
because then you just know if you found
a hole then you can't use it right but
with a non cryptographic hash it's like
I don't know I know this thing gets half
as fast if I wanted to make it stronger
is that a good decision possibly not
right ah so who knows
all right anyway I'm gonna wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me for an
episode of hand made hero its what a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always period of game on
handmade hero org and it comes to the
source code so you could follow along at
home I'll be back next weekend wait I
don't know if I will be easy
Thanksgiving weekend we'll see what's
scheduled so I don't I haven't posted
dates for that yet this was the stream
we just finished so I will post schedule
and that is when I will be back I got to
see what my schedule looks like but
we'll be back either next we could live
again after and then we can play around
with viewing entity info and and editing
the entity info in some way and when
we're done with that then I think we can
call ourselves officially done with the
art importing process and then I guess
we gotta go in to start getting
decoration stuff working plugin I have
to work on the world generator because
we're gonna have to generate one
generate more stuff ground cover and
furniture and stuff like that and so
because we'll have those in there and
we're gonna have to figure out how to
put them in the world in some meaningful
way all right that's it for day hope see
you back here next time check the
schedule for when that will be until
then have fun programming and I'll see
everyone on internet take it easy
everybody