hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream we have to sort of finish
up our code from well the past couple
weeks we've been doing a grid-based ray
tracer for our lighting transport and
I'm pretty happy about it actually I
really like sort of what we ended up
doing with it and I'm really excited
about the early termination stuff as
well I think that's gonna be super super
cool so at this point I think all I
really want to do is just kind of finish
up the the table generation code and
then today we'll just kind of take a
cruise through the code and try to get
it flowing properly and buttoned up so
that next weekend we can start the
debugging process because we we've put a
lot of code we did a lot of work and
there's going to be and it's very
delicate it's performance oriented it
has a lot of sort of stuff in it that's
that's nuanced and so I think there's
gonna be a lot of debugging that goes
along with that because you know the
more like the more performance
performance oriented you are the more
intricate the code typically becomes in
terms of how the data flows through it
how it's organized and it's much easier
to make mistakes than when you're just
when you don't care about how fast
something runs you just need it to run
you can usually architect it more
towards avoiding bugs so intricacy
usually breeds bugs at least the kinds
of bugs that I have where you have like
index mismatches and stuff like that
so I think that we're probably gonna
have our you know our hands full
debugging all next weekend would be my
guess so anyway I'm gonna go ahead and
just jump in here we've got a walk table
builder and we haven't finished that we
sketched out what it would look like and
we just need to actually enable it now
so that we can use you know we can build
walk tables and use them so if we look
at what happens with compute lock table
you can see that what you do is you say
we have a particular voxel here's a size
here's the size of each individual cell
of the voxel
and then we have some output table which
is just going to be space we're going to
use to store all of this you know
information and so when we look at this
what we see is we are going to be taking
each individual ray from our ray
Direction table and remember that's the
thing that gets built by an external
program and in fact this compute walk
table will move into that external
program once we're happy with it because
it's fixed the walk table doesn't change
based on the rays that you enter right
so if you just say here's our set of
rays you have a fixed set of walk tables
that go with them the walk tables don't
update in runtime so we can just move
this over and have the run tables that
we generate those can all go directly
into the system as a pre generated table
exactly like the rays themselves so what
we want the walk table to do is we want
it to go over all of the rays that we
have so all of the sample directions
here where we have our ad we want to
compliment that rady with the proper
walk table offset where the walk table
offset says here's where in the walk
table you would start to start walking
this particular ray direction in the
voxel so what we need here is we need
this Raider count to basically reflect
this so we know that we've got these
sample directions and you know here's
the walk tables here for example and so
what we want to do is say well let's
pass this in let's say look I want you
to generate the the walk table I want
you to generate it for sample directions
and I'm gonna say how many of those
there are because you know they're
they're gonna be proportional with this
and what you'll notice here is there's
not Ray bundles in fact this part right
here is probably wrong I don't think we
probably thought about that it's
actually going to be this because we now
trace a single Ray at a time so there's
actually going to be however many Ray's
there are purse fear that's what we're
to have so if we take a look we're gonna
want to pass in how many sample
directions we have so we're going to say
sample direction count and we're gonna
pass that in here and then what we're
gonna do is we're gonna pull the Ray
directions out of there so when we look
through our sample directions and in
fact this is not really raved your index
it's more like sampled during index but
yeah it's also array index either ones
fine
so then if we take a look at light
sample direction and here's the der we
can say sample directions plus sampled
or index and we're good
now when we pull out this ray D here
it's actually fairly straightforward now
because now that we have the sample
direction that we're talking about it's
just the radius that comes out of that I
need to turn the caps lock key off of
this keyboard whoever wants caps lock
the walk table offset is going to be
written back into here so that's
actually going to be this walk table
offset here and you can see that it's
just going to be whatever destination
we've sort of written so far we want to
assert that we never overwrite the
destination and we do that down here but
otherwise we just stream out where all
these steps are now we have the T
terminate and we're going to need the T
terminate to be something that we
actually record along the walk table
entry so you can see here that we've got
the walk table entry that we're writing
to in here so when we look back up at
this this is not going to be you 16
anymore it's actually going to be a walk
table entry and when we write to the
destination we're going to be writing to
actual like you know individual members
of this so this is not probably going to
look like this anymore it's going to
look more like this and we're going to
write two particular things out to it
the first one is going to be whatever
the step is here
and that step is just whatever the
deltas in the grid I don't think it
needs to be a 32-bit value but we'll do
a safe truncate here I don't think we
have one of these so we'll see I'm also
not sure it may actually be so that that
might actually be fine you know we may
be able to just say look what happens if
this is just a nice 16 to begin with and
then we don't have to think about it all
right so if we look at that what we need
to do is write both of these members so
we need to write the D grid value and
then we need to write the T terminate
value so and I think the good thing here
again is that these D grid values they
don't really depend on anything other
than whatever you want the size of the
voxel to be and there's two ways that we
could do this and I'm not sure which way
is the better way because when we do
this stepping we could store it's always
minus 0 minus 1 0 or plus 1 in each
direction so you only need 2 bits per
direction to encode what's going to
happen so if you take a look at what
this value is here it really doesn't
have to be an S 16 it's really just a u
8 that would encode that and the
question is how do we want it actually
encoded because when we actually use
this information we probably want the
value to have been pre computed but when
we pre compute the value its dependent
on the resolution of the voxel grid so
it would mean that the voxel grid
couldn't change over time which may be
bad right now what we could do is we
could say let's just compute it instead
of computing it here we could actually
just compute it at run time
because computing this table we could do
one set load and then we could adjust
the voxel and if we wanted to we could
actually store what the box
dimension was and create the table like
create the table anytime the voxel size
changes and that's somewhat compelling
because it seems like that's something
you might want to actually make sure
that you did properly so that you
wouldn't have to have the voxel size be
fixed and so what I'd like to do is say
maybe for now let's actually go in that
direction so if we take a look at this I
might say let's just pull this out for
now and say okay the light sampling
spheres those will generate but the walk
table will actually have be dynamic so
I'm going to move these into the
lighting solution and we'll just have
the walk table entry come out here it
still could be a global but there's
really no reason for it to be global
because people are always going to be
loading it off of the lighting solution
pretty much always they're not going to
ever need it to be global so I might
just go ahead and put it in here so I'll
put in here a walk table entry and we'll
say that the light sample walk the light
sampling walk table will go in here and
we'll always be able to know effectively
how many of those entries are going to
be because we know the maximum for any
array if we just say look we know voxel
do max plus Fox look my test box will
dim Z that's actually more than you
could ever have
I would think but you know let's say the
worst possible case you are able to
visit you know the X what's the y plus
the Z of the voxel I don't think there's
any way you could ever visit more than
that but let's say that we were going to
just take that all of that into account
and then we would then say how many
total rays do we have
and we could also add a bit of padding
in there just to make sure that if we
consider the fact that you could visit
two per line as well as you step through
it it may actually be more sensible to
take the max here where we say whatever
the maximum of these is and I'm not sure
I'd have to think about that but like
you really want to know about the
diagonal which yeah I think this is this
is overly conservative but I think we're
just going to go with it so I'm going to
call this the max desk count here and
I'm going to get rid of these two and
what I'm going to do is pass the
lighting solution in and it will just
generate on top of this it'll generate
the sampling table and I need to know
where it's going to put this I need a
memory arena where you want this table
so when we initially allocate the
lighting solution we would allocate this
piece of information as well so these
are obviously walk table entry sized and
we know we need max this count of them
that will produce that number and then
we'll just start filling them in now the
starting location for some reason I
don't know why we're not resetting this
it seems like that's something we would
need oh I guess it's because we just
computed once then we use at down here
so that's fine I think that's all we
really need to do from then on everyone
kind of needs to make sure that they
write into that table so let me just
jump back down here real quick so this
right here in terms of writing out to
the destination we need to make that
that pointer there
so I'm just gonna say alright the lock
table entry best is whatever we just
allocated and then anytime we're doing
here we have to anytime we're looking up
in that table we need to grab this
solution now when we're actually what's
the problem here
box type over there that should have
been plus not a dot um I'm not sure what
this is saying what did we do here
we've got span and we've got step
so it looks like span is just checking
for exit we see if we have gone too far
in that particular direction that we've
stepped and then we stop because we know
we can't go in further than that right
yeah
so that seems fine and I think this was
supposed to be step not negate and we
just forgot I mean looking at it that
seems right let me just see so we're
going through the dimensions here we're
looking to see if the Ray Direction is
positive in that particular dimension
and if it is you know we're basically
just conditioning these two values into
positive or negative and I guess we're
just always treating it as if it was
positive and then we just fake the step
to go in the other direction like that's
all we're doing that way we keep it
always stepping forwards and then we're
taking the dim step here which is how
much you would step and we're we're
multiplying that value by the voxel
dimension why is that yeah this is a
safe truncate because the voxel dim
should not be large enough to overflow
that
everything else seems pretty good the
span versus the voxel dim here
I guess these just want to be signed
because that's what our v2s is but I
think that's it
so that computes the entire walk table
there may be bugs in it we haven't
looked at it particularly carefully but
you know we should be good to go there
so in here where we actually initialize
the lighting we should at that point be
able to do what we need to do you can
see the voxel dim is initialized or I
guess the voxel counts aren't here
though but what we would like to do is
we'd like to initialize this table
probably anytime the voxel dimension
changed and I don't know to what extent
we really want to support anything quite
that complicated
and I don't feel like we really want to
do the the look we don't want to
generate this every frame cuz that's
another way we could do it it's like
every frame we'd regenerate the walk
tables but that just seems like way too
much work so I think what we want to do
here is probably something where we just
say all right in here where you would
knit the lighting I think that's really
the place where we'd like to allocate
and we'd like to make this be fixed so
you know maybe you have to like
uninitialized and reinitialize your
lighting if you want to change the
dimensions of your voxel right like you
have to you have to give it a the
opportunity to sort of read reinitialize
everything so we know the Vox seldom
right we know what that is so I'll be
the only thing we don't really know is
what the dimension is of the you know of
the light Maps the sample Direction
count is easier that's just baked into
here so we would know at some point what
those were when we look in here and
presumably we would just use total
raised for sphere
but I guess we have to do it for every
sphere don't we so we kind of need that
to be a double loop right because
there's some number of these spheres and
then there's the total number of raised
purse fear
so yeah I mean I think what we want to
do there is
it's a little annoying because really
there's no reason for this I mean we now
just have a big set of sample directions
and we kind of want the sample
directions to line up we we previously
did line them up properly so that they
lined up exactly with the octahedral map
so really you know this is kind of
legacy structurally it says it's
structurally old because what we more or
less want here is you know it's it's
really more like this and then we have
here like a sample direction for each of
the octahedrons
for each of the octahedral map regions
so in here we would say that the sample
Direction is the octahedral map
dimension so you know it would be
something like this
this is what we actually have and we
also don't really need them to be based
on spheres quite like that I mean we can
do it that way but it's a little bit
unnecessary you know you could also just
do this you know what I mean
so we could say here's how many
octahedrons different octahedrons we
want here's how many octahedral map
squares there are and that's how many
sample directions you get right that
just seems more like what you want and
so I kind of feel like maybe we just
switch to this it just you know so that
way we could just say hey there's a
value this is how many rays there are
just in our system forecasting that's
how many sample directions we're going
to have and when we generate our tables
we're gonna generate the tables that way
it also gets us out of this business of
generating these too disastrously
different tables for no reason which is
good so inside here where we're doing
the walk table can't believe I'm out of
water already I need a big so here's the
problem I'm really annoyed by how you
cannot get a to clean glass bottle that
holds a lot of water like I need way
more water for handmade hero than one
glass but I hate drinking out of plastic
or metal it tastes awful to me so I need
like a large plastic bottle that you can
clean there are a lot of large I'm sorry
a large glass bottle you can clean there
are a lot of large glass bottles you
can't clean and they get disgusting
but large bottles that that you can
clean easily are harder to come by large
glass bottles anyway so here's the
sample Direction table and we know that
you know we could even just use a rate
count on that so we can just say look
you know it's it's however big it is we
don't care and so really all we're
looking at is this value here and so I
want to maybe force when you initialize
the lighting I maybe want to force you
to pass the voxel in in there so that
you can initialize the lighting properly
with any information that has to do with
that rather than forcing it to wait
until it gets a render group to know so
you do that and it would compute the
walk table based on whatever you wanted
those dimensions to be and I think that
would be sufficient in the future we
could allocate this dynamically if we
wanted to and then we could just change
it and you know I mean maybe that's the
right solution it's pretty free for us
to do that maybe I'll just do that
because if we wanted to do that it's not
hard right all we would do is say like
the lighting solution you know has an
arena din it arena in it for like the
pre computed data which it like you know
and so then what we would do is in here
we would just say anytime this stuff
changes we have to recompute
you know I mean so if we have whatever
the voxel dimensions actually are here
which should in theory come from yeah so
they come from like here here and I mean
so trying to find the value out of there
I don't see that being forthcoming so it
looks like we'd have to do this right so
the light atlas is they're the things
that store the voxel Tim and
I don't see anything in particular that
that gets that value out so I'll just
load it so the specular light axis light
Atlas has the Vox lithium here so that's
going to be the of oxygen that we're
looking for and what I want to do is I
want to just remember it so in here we'd
say and this is going to ruin the layout
of this thing kind of a lot but you know
I don't really know what else to do
about that maybe this way we'll fix this
all it's just trying to have these
things overlaid gets tricky
so in here I'd just say the table of
oxygen and so when we try to start
lighting we just say like if these two
things aren't equal to each other then
we need to recompute all all of our
tables right so at that point we would
clear the table memory and we would redo
the allocations that were based on it
does that make sense so pretty
straightforward but that's what we're
talking about so if I look here at where
that's actually happening I go to the
lock table you can actually see in here
the voxel dim and the seldom and that
stuff being passed through properly in
the sample directions this will do the
allocation with the memory that we give
it and that memory is now going to be
coming from the solutions table or a
table memory right
we need to pound to find these things
reliably for the generation because the
generation needs to know them so in here
we would have what we want our
octahedral accounts to be and you know
we do want to be able to change these
and stuff but we probably don't want to
be able to we probably can't change them
at runtime
I mean there are ways we could do that
but it's probably a little too difficult
for such a performance-oriented thing
with what we're running up against to
really to make that work
can't find worse the let me see how
we're actually how are we actually
calling that though let's make light
atlas
so you can see here that this is where
we actually define this and everything
else flows through it but I don't think
that's going to be feasible like I said
because I think we kind of need to know
what that dimension is so this value
here like this value can be this value
can change right but this value really
can't and the reason that it can't is
again because we generate those things
as part of an offline process maybe at
some point we can look at using a
different pattern for the lighting that
would make it so it's not necessary for
us to pre-compute those or so that we
can pre-compute them quicker and then we
could run it online and change this
value on the fly but for the moment I
think what I'm going to do is say that
this is dependent so we're going to come
in here and we're going to say that the
octahedral map dim here and it looks
like we only support one of these at the
moment so I'm just gonna say that that's
symmetric for now even though I don't
know that we actually want that but
let's say that it is I'm going to call
that the octahedral map dim or the
lighting octahedral mapped in and then
we're going to use that value here and
that way now we'll know okay that value
is driven off a single value that's
defined when we do our pre computation
and everything else has to obey it right
so that's fine and then we know how many
of these were going to have we're going
to have 64 rays total right because it's
8 by 8 and yeah I mean that's it
so because 64 rays per per square
okay so I think that's what we want to
do again I don't really know it's it's
kind of nerve-wracking to be completely
honest with you because if you take a
look at the way this scales it's 64 and
right now I think we're doing 32 by 32
by 32 in terms of the sizes of these
things so like if I look at what the
renderer oh no it's not that's not as
bad that's not as bad
so 24 by 16 by 16 so when you look at
the number of rays that we have to cast
its really pretty terrifying that's too
op to update each octahedral map with
only one new sample you have to do that
for every frame so if you take a look at
like what speed you might think the
processor is running at that's the speed
of the process or you know give or take
it's not always going to be that high
but something like this and we have to
update it at 60 frames a second so that
means that that's rough that we're
looking at we can probably count on at
least four cores oops
you can probably count on at least four
cores so if we then say well how many
cycles do we have to to do each of those
rays it's like so tiny right
just really really bad so this is why I
say like it's it's really nerve-racking
five hundred eight cycles just isn't
very many cycles to work with
fortunately like you know more cores it
gets better it scales perfectly with
cores we don't have any interquartile
ease so that part's reassuring but it's
still scary
right it's still pretty scary so we're
definitely living on the edge here I
don't love it but you know what are you
gonna do so anyway moving along let's go
ahead and compile this here so when we
look at the sampling octahedron count
the sampling octahedron count let me let
me put this in properly here the
sampling octahedron count is just how
many of these things we want to have and
we don't really care how many we have
we'll use sixteen because that's what we
were using before but that number is not
as important this stuff will fall up the
number these things will fall out of the
cache every frame anyway so we're not
going to really get a win by having a
low number of these sampling Spears I
don't think and we only use one set of
them each frame
so I guess we could update the same
direction on each one and that would be
helpful probably I'd have to think about
that that might be a good idea actually
to increase the degree to which we can
share the cash but you know hard to say
or at least each core uses one something
like that so I'm gonna get rid of this
and then what we'll do is in here where
we're actually loading the stuff out I'm
going to change the way this looks a
little bit so when we take a look at the
dirt sample index you know that's which
sampling swear you're using and so if we
wanted to actually load out the proper
directions here what we want to do is we
want to just take the sample Direction
table and we want to probably break this
pound defined into two pound defines so
we would have the total direct sample
and the the light sample directions per
octahedron so this is how many it's this
is how many there are per octahedron and
this is how many there are
turtle so we have the sample directions
proctor hydron and the total right
yeah so in this case what we want to do
is say we don't want this to ever be
like out of bounds so let me just make
sure that that works so we've got the
light sampling octahedron count the
lights and package on mask and now
everything is lined up properly I think
so we've got the light stamp an account
and mask here and we will pick an
octahedron index we will then pick a
sample direction oops by saying the
sample Direction table plus whatever the
octahedron index is times the stride
right so we effectively want to say for
however many there are practically drawn
we're going to go that far in from there
we just pull sample ders out so we say
all right for each one of these things
that we're going to do we need to load a
direction out of this but it's really
pretty straightforward
the Rhea bundle index I don't think
really has to be they're not sure what
this is doing I think this may be old
news like why do we need all this stuff
I mean yeah this seems like it's not
really necessary so let's just take a
look at this real quick because this is
gonna collapse down so what we probably
want to do is say the light sampling
direction well actually I guess we don't
even need any of this stuff we don't
need the REA bundle index we don't need
any of that
all we're doing here is saying just do
plus plus or I should say sampled
d'oeuvre plus equals two and here we can
just say whatever the sample der zero is
or the sampled or one is that's the
radio that we wanted and here we can
just say sample der plus zero sampled er
plus one right so I think that's all and
again a lot of this stuff is cruft stuff
that can be removed actually so in this
case we're gonna have to up sample this
and that's just because again it's the
old ray caster we're still trying to be
able to run that in place to the extent
that we can this actually comes from the
solution and we want to store this here
as well so that we remember we don't
have to update it next time right so we
need a way of comparing those values
which we don't have yet we change the
name of that to this right oh wait no
it's there so I guess that's undeclared
this is probably not included in the
renderer at the moment and I'm not sure
what to do about that it depends on
where we want this to come from you know
you know what that value needs to be is
hard to say how that should flow through
the pipeline
like I said ideally you would just be
able to change it to runtime but because
we need to do so much pre-computation
I'm just not sure that's actually
feasible you know if we could produce
this at runtime we would but I'm just
not sure we can at the moment we
actually use an offline optimization
process to do it and it could be that we
should just switch to some kind of a
like fibonacci like ring we we had tried
that a little bit and yeah I don't know
so
I guess what I'd say is I don't mind
including the lighting stuff in here I
don't think that's a particularly good
decision
but at the same time I don't think it's
actually a problem for us
so we might just do that for now so
handmade sampling spheres would go in
here and I'm gonna put two doing there
that basically says because it would be
nice to not have to do that
so in our equal I just need that to be
in the math library so that we can
compare these things and I'm just gonna
make one of those and in here we're just
gonna say okay I have a v3 s and since
that's not floating-point I can actually
just do it direct comparison I don't
need to think about tolerances or any of
those sorts of things so I can just say
if x equals x
y and z huff ago so I think at that
point we're in good shape
the v3 4 X's are probably not included
in the render either those are going to
go away so I don't know that we really
want to do much about that but for now I
guess I'll just say we'll just do this
and I can elaborate on this comment a
little bit
and the reason that I was saying that is
because in theory on more powerful
machines you could get more accurate
lighting by taking more dense samples of
the octahedron so maybe it's an eight by
eight and then in on some machines it's
a sixteen by sixteen because you have
more horsepower and you can take more
Ray's right that's all so I think that's
everything I think the entire pipeline
is now running properly and mostly the
problem is we're just not actually
generating this this table when we
actually generate the sampling spheres
so hmm excuse me so I think if we went
to our light generator let's try to get
some more water I'll be right back
[Music]
[Applause]
all right
I got a recap of the price I know you
can alright so let's go ahead and
actually make this thing generate the
extra pieces of information that it's
not right now
so we have a couple things we've got the
output sphere INL thing and it's writing
out this part of it right and I think
we've got the other one I'm not sure I
guess we just always called that one
yeah so what we need to do here is we
can leave these in that we need to add
these right so we want this stuff to now
get written in there and before it
wasn't so I'm gonna put them at the top
because they're now the new thing we
actually care about and then we're gonna
get rid of all these pretty darn soon
here I'm just terrified that this whole
thing is going to still be too slow and
then it's unclear whether we want to
stick with it or not
although you know there are other things
we could do we'll see fingers crossed
so here's us printing out the light
sample direction to fine which is what
we wanted definition I should say and
then here's me outputting there you know
these additional pieces of information I
don't know if we actually have these
parameterised it looks like we sort of
do oops
again nothing nothing interesting
happening here it's just literally
making this spit out the stuff we
already typed in so that when it
generates it will generate the right
thing alright so here we've got the you
know the to the counts these are you
know the same things they're just
octahedrons now so I want this to be
printed out the same way so that's all
good the rate bundles purse fear is not
that's not really what we want
so that stuff doesn't doesn't follow
through yeah so then what we can do is
we can actually make this table here
this can actually just being equals kind
of thing and we can define it in place
and I can loop over all of the data that
we actually produced here and I can
avoid doing the bundling now the problem
here is that I I feel like this stuff
gets bundled and I really don't want it
to
I'm not sure looks like we didn't maybe
finish this or something herb this
I don't know what it means by perturb
this
I'm not sure why we would need to
perturb it I mean what we're doing is
we're looking and we're grabbing input
directions from the set of directions we
have and we're using them that's what we
should be doing I don't know why perturb
this what why so I'm not sure I
understand what the point of that is oh
so I guess I know why this is the value
that this is what's used if we don't
actually have one that matches our
direction so I guess I could I could see
why that would be the case
so maybe it just means hey make a little
bit of a random you know offset from
there so that seems fair alright so
looking through this now if we if we
assume that you know we've produced all
this stuff the interleaved directions
call is the thing that we kind of have a
problem with so we don't want our
directions interleaved anymore
you can see here like we had what we
wanted which was this and we're
effectively like screwing it up right so
we're actually like we want the original
thing we started with which was the Plus
on which was the Poisson distribution
here and so I think what we probably
want is when we call generate octahedral
lighting pattern here we probably want
to save whatever those input directions
were and we can just extend this system
to actually have that property right so
like if you look at how this works in
the sphere store we could just say like
a sample der single and this could be
sampled or multiple right and so in here
where we actually have the spheres that
were writing out we could just you know
put them in there I also don't know that
that's we actually don't want the
spheres to be repetitive like that
either so in a sense you know we could
also just do this like you can see we
produce the total set of directions here
and what we would want is just before we
interleave them we just want to return
these so if we take a look at when we do
generate octahedral lighting pattern
maybe what I'd do is I'd say like hey
give me the raw directions as well and
then in here I can just say I don't know
get my head out of the way here we go
and that would do what I need again I
really want to be able to clean all this
up but I'm just I can't do it yet I
can't make the code do what I want it to
because I'm trying to leave the other
code pass in temporarily it will be very
good if we can get it to the point where
I know that this was the right decision
and is good and we can rip them out that
would be very nice
but we are not there yet so I think now
that'll be good enough as a patchwork
thing and let's go ahead and return that
oh wait a minute it's this right no it's
what what are we passing here
okay so it's actually output directions
that we want right yeah okay so now if
we actually run HH light prof we should
be able to get an eye ml here this one
oops
no if I don't have a revert buffer in
this version of the editor unfortunately
so let me just kill this buffer and
we'll reload it so if I go in here to
build and we want to that's not what I
wanted this so if I want to take and do
a certain number of octahedrons which in
this case we're going to say is 16 we
have the Ray bundle count and I guess we
want to reap Rama tries this a little
bit because now the parameters don't
really make much sense the way we're
asking for them so really we want
instead of ray bundles purse fear we
want like directions oops per octahedron
and octahedron count right and when we
asked for it here we're gonna say like
octahedron count and rays
and then we'll just allocate these out
these are just wrong now and like I said
I really want to change this code but
I'm just very nervous because I haven't
proven to myself that it's the right
direction and pun intended and so I
think at that point you'd be really
premature to delete everything that just
be a really bad idea
right so raise for octahedron here and
we're doing sampling direction here we
want this to be times four for this and
when we do Ray bundles purse fear when
we're doing like generating letting
pattern we now want to do like rays per
octahedron as a thing and octahedron
calendar and let's just clean up this
code at least to that point and then
we'll go from there
okay so what I want to do here is
instead of ray bundles purse fear being
a thing you know I guess this is just
raised per octahedron and this will just
do the bundling operation right and
that's fine for everybody else they
wanted the total Direction count anyway
so this code doesn't have to change it's
just going to generate directions which
is what it should do
this is raised per octahedron and
octahedron count and this just gets rid
of the multiplied by four that's all
it's going to do and that way we'll do
the divide by four in here and that'll
do the interleave so at that point again
just fixing this a little bit and we'll
do another fix pass on it once we know
we can rip out the other part again the
main difference here is just we don't
have to multiply by four
and I think we're mostly there now okay
looking a little further in so this is
octahedron count this is phase four
octahedron although why is that say
bundle index and number doing times four
so this is not really a bundle index is
it it's it's array index right that's
what's actually happening and here we're
doing we're octahedra
[Music]
yeah and this just I guess loops through
and it keeps trying to pick successive
things from the octahedron so that's all
fine this is an octahedron counts here
and here the Rhea bundles purse fear is
just the Rays per octahedron divided by
four same thing here signed a biggie
there and that seems fine this actually
could be done slightly differently but
I'm not going to care because that's
code I'm going to do it anyway
all right so if we now run HH sphere we
get what we wanted which is an
octahedron count and arrays per
octahedron right which is going to be 64
now I think we could probably go one
better and say just give us what the
octahedron dimension is and so let's
just make one more pass through doing
that because we can do that too so in
here we could say look let's get the
octahedron dim out of this and then the
octahedra it's not right sorry
and then the race for octahedron is just
going to be the octahedron dim squared
and we probably want to change the way
this works a little bit you know in the
future like I said but octahedron dim
it's now what you would be passing in
there and that way we can pass in the
values we actually are thinking about
and similarly this could print out the
right value now so we could say oh okay
octahedron dim is the thing I actually
know maybe that actually goes here so
when we print out the sphere now we can
do the count the dim and the rays and
now it's intuitive because it works the
same way as it does like it's looking at
the same thing that we would expect to
see so we know if we say sixteen eight
will get what we expect right so where
do we want to put this well let's just
do a temp that I know for now because I
don't really know
and also I suppose we probably need this
to be in release mode because we're very
computationally intensive for this sort
of crappy optimization process it's
running
you
what is it Jonathan blow would like to
know your address mean on his stream you
used to know my address should I send
him my address in an email
so now we can take a look at that
always centromeres all right I will I
will do that I don't know what you
people are talking about but okay I mean
I can definitely do that I'm not sure
why I would need to do that I thought I
thought he already had my address anyway
but maybe that's not true I mean that
could that could be very that could be
very false but all right
I have sent that and now he has that so
so that's good
I think this assumes that I know my
address
which I don't always yeah
all right I have sent the address
okay wait why would you troll me to have
me send John my address that doesn't
make any sense
all right everyone is fired anyway I'm
gonna look at this and see that looks
like what I want there's my light sample
direction there's the octahedral map
dimension
there's the count and the mask
that'll looks good so I think we're good
we just now need to just spam out all of
those directions in a line so basically
like right here and we can do that with
this as well we're basically doing the
same kind of loop we're just printing
them out on interleaved that's the only
difference right so here we would say
durand x equals 0 to index lesson total
Direction count and derp index then we
would say raw directions clustered index
this is our direction
and then each of these we would just
print out now we don't have to print
them out in spans like that we can just
print out one at a time and let them
stream out right and we can print these
[Music]
this way so it's a little clearer what's
going on and I think that's all we need
the total direction count is just the
Rays per octahedron times how many out
here drums we have and off we go
yeah you guys are all fired I never look
at the chat the one time I look at the
chat while I'm programming you guys are
saying something that's totally
erroneous go on to John's dream and
explain to him what you've done that's
your penance you need to go over to
naysayer 88 stream and you need to
apologize
okay so just letting the optimizer do
its little dance here and now I'm gonna
take a look again and see if we got you
know what we expected there you go
right and the pattern looks I mean I'd
have to go through and think about
whether the pattern looks right but you
know it should be regular because it
should be octahedral samples always so
they should always go in the order that
the octahedron goes so there should be a
regular pattern of positives and
negatives throughout the entire thing it
should never change alright so let's try
compiling now that we've generated one
of these oh I got a copy it in so I'm
going to copy this temp to handmaid code
light sampling spheres or whatever it's
called handmade oops
handmade sampling spheres that and now
we can deal with any compile errors that
there are so it looks like look we're
missing a semicolon there other than
that looks pretty good so I'm gonna go
ahead and just fix this code so that
next time we run it doesn't have that
same bug and now in theory we can
actually start to debug this thing and
you know we don't have a lot of time
left in this particular stream so
probably not going to get very far but
we should be able to base to go through
the whole thing now in like one quick
pass and just clean up any obvious
problems that we have like forgetting to
initialize certain things or you know
whatever else so I think the first
problem that we're gonna have is out in
HH light prof we're gonna have the
problem that memory arena wise we don't
have an initialized arena here for the
lighting solution so what we're gonna
have to do here is probably something
where we tie them together so we could
do something like this
because we're gonna need the table
memory to have been valid outside here
where we're actually doing this we need
to actually make sure we initialize the
table memory and so I'm not 100% sure
how that should look because this never
calls begin lighting I think that means
that we would have to do it
so inside begin lighting computation you
know you look at this we're not doing
this call on the outside so we're pretty
much going to have to do this ourselves
right we have to we have to make this
call
and that's actually fine because what we
can do here is we can actually just set
this stuff directly we don't have to use
the table memory we can just pass like
the temporary no instead and that's fine
so that seems like a better solution
pretty much all around I think that's
everything we would need to do so the
voxel dim here is this the speck act
atlas voxel dim and one thing we might
want to do is make compute walk table
you mean I wonder if that should use
this value and set it here I don't know
it probably shouldn't so we'll leave it
outside okay so I think that's
everything
all right so let's start taking a look I
guess we can first see what what we
crash on would be the first stuff we can
fix and then we can move on from there
so running the light profiler we'll just
see where we get that's just a errant
breakpoint that was in the way so there
we go so this makes sense because I
don't think we ever allocate any of
these facial nodes at all so that's
something we would have to allocate
based on yeah like how how big the voxel
was I'm not sure why we're not doing
that in built spatial partition though
yeah like so these should just be
allocated and build spatial partition
and I'm not sure why they're not so you
get an arena with this and you can see
like we allocate the leaves so what we
should be doing is also allocating the
grids like that's what should actually
be happening right so in here where we
do this max grid index and we do this
initialization pass like right before
that what we should have been doing was
actually allocating the nodes that's
what actually should have been happening
now because this is just initializing to
zero we could just use a rep here and so
this particular loop seems kind of
useless and we probably don't actually
need to do it so I'm thinking probably
what we'll do instead is we'll just do a
push array here and we'll push those
nodes onto this onto that arena and let
the arena clear them so they'll just be
cleared by default right there's no real
reason to worry about it so I think what
we want here is something like that so
now we've got the spatial grid nodes and
we're good to go
so I think that will fix that problem
and then through here this all still
should work roughly the same so let me
run that and see where we go now okay
so now we ended up in compute voxel
radiance and we probably want to be in
debug mode here that's not what I want
probably want to be in debug mode here
because I'm trying to like step through
this and understand it and debug it so I
don't really want the code to be all
optimized at this point I want something
a little bit more straightforward okay
so if we pull back to grid raycast here
you can see what's going on here we're
trying to do a sample and I'm not sure
what exactly is going on here this looks
like the case where we just didn't hit
anything right we kind of exited out of
here
and I'm not sure yeah what does the grid
index is zero I'm not so I'm not really
sure what's going on here because the
initial grid index should not be zero so
one problem that we're gonna have here
is when we do the grid indexing we're
going to have the problem of needing to
offset the grid by the apron which I
don't think we did so depending on how
we want to do that we're gonna have to
actually like plan that out so this is
why I say like a lot of bugs come from
problems with how you're accessing
things because you oftentimes need to do
ridiculous crap in performance oriented
code for code for ease of development
you would never have two voxels one that
has an apron one that doesn't because
you're just asking for lots of bugs with
the indexing into that voxel that is why
performance oriented code is so
difficult is because languages just
don't provide the right tools
for making that simple this is also one
of the reasons why I pretty much always
ignore new languages like people are
always like oh you know you should check
out rust it's so cool and what you
notice is when you look at the
literature where people are saying
here's the features we added they never
try to tackle these problems they don't
even seem to know they exist you know I
don't really have a problem with memory
I don't really have a problem with
writing Constans I don't have a problem
with leaks those just aren't where I
spend a lot of my time is it nice to
have support to make certain things like
that easier sure I'm all for making
things like that easier but when you
look at what the really hard problems
are that I deal with day to day they
just have nothing to do with that and
this is the kind of thing that they do
have to deal with and I just don't get a
lot of support from the language on
things like that I don't see language
designers sitting around saying how do
we make it really easy to talk about
things like to voxels overlaid on top of
each other one with an apron one with a
knot you know how do we make that really
easy instead of having the programmer to
think it through ahead of time and make
X all these extra you know data types to
maybe try to like know which index
you're working with but then of course
those don't work because the actual
storage format has to be interleaved and
it can't be interleaved if you do it
that way right new languages especially
today seem to have no understanding of
the fact that data layout for
performance is the thing that languages
currently do poorly and new languages if
anything are doing them even more poorly
does that make sense so it's just it's
people not understanding I think because
a lot of people who design languages are
just used to dealing with very simple
code I guess like they just don't deal
with performance oriented code which
maybe is why their compilers are so
freaking slow all the time it's another
kind of logical consequence I suppose so
let's go ahead and take a look at what
we would need to do here to make that
indexing be more proper so if we take a
look at what's going to happen when we
come through here we're going to be when
we're sweeping through the you know
we're generating work orders and then
what we're going to be doing is we're
going to be trying to Ray cast off of
each slice and you can see when we do
this in full cast right we're expecting
this initial grid index to come in and
when we look at what's happening with
initial dread index that's we're just
passing it through to the right cast and
that's where it's going to start so what
we want to do here I also don't really
know why full cast needs to be here it
can just be welded into the upper
routine but probably because we had
debug stuff going on in there so if I go
take a look at where that's being called
you can see that initial grid index is
getting called by doing initial grid and
X here and we passed the voxel dim and
v3 yes again that's not correct so the
problem is this really needs to look
like this because it has the apron and
this right here is the voxel dim with
the apron included so this is wrong you
know I mean there's you know box Lib Dem
with apron so we actually want and
that's going to be you know the table of
voxel dim in this case so we're always
like using grid indices that are you
know based on that special table and
that's how we're looking up these actual
things too
and it now by the same token we have to
make sure that when we do our spatial
partition build the spatial partition
itself needs to be aware of this when
it's inserting and so we have to make
sure again that we always did that sort
of plus one version of the access or
which it looks like we did remember to
do so probably we're okay but again
that's really gonna be a thing that
we're gonna have to you know we may want
to make some specific helper functions
or even wrap the data type in a way that
tries to make it so it's very hard to
have those indexing errors because those
are errors that I think are very likely
like I'm expecting them and so we may
have to do code work here to force that
to not be an issue by taking places
where we can afford to do some
protective coating and try to eliminate
that source of error
okay so let's keep going here just
trying to get more of a feel for what's
happening here so I don't want to see
that initial code index of zero anymore
because we don't really want that to be
happening I also don't know how we're
doing this lookup exactly what's the
sample P so what what are the what are
we actually getting here entire voxel
index so that actually looks fine so
[Music]
well I guess the problem is so in this
case we are looking at the end of the
voxel but that should so
I guess the problem here is that it
seems like what's happened is when we
have exited the voxel because of the
spatial node Terminator the problem
we're getting is that the T terminate
value has already been updated so I
guess maybe what we need to do is T
terminate needs to be moved here so it's
only updated on valid maybe but that
would still do the same thing so that
should have been valid I guess it just
moves it into the incorrect location so
I think maybe just when we build the LOC
table yeah okay so the problem that
we're gonna have here is is this is
actually wrong I guess so I think what
we actually want to do is do this before
we update right so we're gonna want to
do the previous T is what we actually
want and furthermore we probably want to
go well I don't know let's put it this
way I'm gonna do this before the T
update so that we're always stopping
inside the cell that we're currently on
and the problem that we're gonna have is
that this value may still not quite be
right for picking that cell so this is a
bit of a gamble and we'll maybe have to
think about that a little harder but I
think that's what we want anyway let's
go ahead and push forward in this a
little bit okay
so if I pull out back to here a little
bit more I'm gonna just take a look at
what what the t terminate value is it
looks like that value is zero so we
never actually got in here yet
so I'm guessing that what happens is if
we leave on the on this right I guess we
never really thought about what we do
here and that's a good question
so if we were to do too much work we
would exit out here but if we also so so
the question is what kind of voxel
sample do we want to take when we get to
a place where we haven't hit anything
and we just want to kind of make sure
that that's not a problem so I guess
what we could do is just set probe piece
single to just be where we are
and since we're never gonna use that
value we're probably okay I think we'll
I might just defer looking at this
behavior until we get to the quality
pass because that's when we're gonna
have to decide how we get exterior
lighting in or if we get extra lighting
in so what I'm gonna suggest here is
let's just initialize the normal to
nothing and the probe location I'm gonna
say is going to be wherever we started
and let's see if that's a better way to
do that it looks like we had the exact
same problem so I would have thought
that would have fixed it but I guess it
doesn't hmm okay so looking at what the
coordinates are here there's the sample
P here's the voxel index and so that's
weird because that suggests the voxel
index is actually for whatever our
sample use is out of bounds so let's see
how we got there what was the actual
origin so there's the Ray origin single
and
that's the same so we should always be
able to sample the Ray origin that
suggests that our mapping here got
screwed up somehow right so we've got
some kind of a problem with our corner
value because this should not have
produced it should not have been
possible to produce such a thing right
so if we take a look at the sample p
value that we're getting which we know
is a should have been valid and we then
look at whatever the hot corner was you
know those should have been conga red
and it looks like they're not
although they are so now I'm even more
confused
so that actually looks like that should
have produced the correct answer Oh so
this right here is a subtraction for
rounding so in terms of where we're
casting from
this may have been buggy before so if we
look at what's happening when we do are
looking at where we're going to sample
if we subtract the why would we because
we're doing a floor so we would never
want to subtract the centroid of this
thing
of a cell because we're flooring the
value right so like that's just wrong I
mean if we subtract the min corner then
everything from zero to one should all
be in that corner and then only when you
get to like one point something or at
one exactly do you move to the next one
right so that just feels wrong and I'm
not sure why we did that but that's not
good so I feel like that's just an
erroneous that that should not have been
that way that was just a bug that we had
and didn't know right I don't know why
yeah so that should have been been right
so let's see what the values are now
so that's correct I don't understand why
we would get an out-of-bounds error at
that point because zero zero zero would
be a legal voxel these are supposed to
be clamped right T X and T Y could be
wrong and they are so T X and T Y in
this case the sample normal is probably
zero which we don't support yeah so we
probably need to initialize the sample
normal to something bogus and that's
fine too so in here when we do prevents
product probes sample and single I
should be able to just initialize that
to like the Ray direction or something
and we'll look at like I said we do our
lighting quality pass that's when we
want to look at what those actually
should be okay so this is good because
now we're actually running properly and
that's what we would like to see now
we're probably not actually doing
anything correct in terms of actual
computations
we're probably totally wrong here what I
mean
but at least we can get some sense of
how it's running so who knows right but
let's see so how bad is the timing would
be another question
because I have no idea and again we
can't really make to it we can't really
make too much of a judgment about that
because we haven't adjusted it or even
looked at if it's doing the right things
at all but we can see like how bad it is
at the you know initially so if we go to
handmade data and we go to build HH
light prof debug i'm just curious how
bad the time is at the outset so you
know it's hard to make a judgment call
on that yet but that you know is
significantly faster it's a full second
faster so if it turns out that we can
make this run relatively correctly that
bodes well we've got a long way to go
before we know so we really couldn't say
yet but you know at least we're not
totally screwed so we'll see I'm gonna
wrap it up here for today and we'll
start on the hard work of debugging all
this stuff next weekend so
I wish somebody had been keeping track
of all of the in sohbat quotes so
there's the thing that keeps track of
all of my quotes and there's a thing
that keeps track of all of john's quotes
but i don't think there's anything that
keeps track of all of in sohbats great
quotes and it keeps coming up with these
really great quotes
can we try the game in the current state
so I don't think we can't I mean we
could but it almost certainly won't work
right like because we've we just haven't
done enough of finishing work on the
current lighting scheme so it's I don't
think that's going to work but but we
certainly can try it I think we're just
going to get a black screen yeah
because basically like we just we have
not I mean just to give some perspective
we redid all of this code completely and
we have never even tested it right so
since this new past is just Rita
performance where do you foresee getting
speed ups after this pass so there's a
couple different things but I guess what
I would say is heavily optimizing the
current way we're doing it now and
making sure we've got that totally
correct is the first thing I want to do
the second thing we can do is now that
this pass is able to early terminate we
can actually tune this cost metric quite
a bit and probably get a fair bit of
speed up just by reducing the light and
propagation time right I'm hoping that
is what all we really need for 60 frames
second to be completely honest with you
given two points do you think there
might be way to calculate the number of
voxel cells have brezin hamlike line a
gorilla touch without walking yeah I bet
there is I'm not super motivated to
figure it out because we don't really
care because I'd rather table drive it
anyway I think but you might be able to
yeah
I just ran a church-like prov that's
that's what that is but we just we we've
got a lot of work to do to like clean
this stuff up so you know it's we've got
another weekend's worth of work before
we can run this and like have any idea
whether it's gonna be better right I'm
pretty sure we'll be though
I'm pretty sure this will eventually be
better because I think we just have a
lot more flexibility here I mean we can
even do a thing where if we had to we
could get rid of the idea of recasting
the grid at all and instead just have
people raycast 1a1 neighbourhood around
their square so it would just be like
bucket brigade
you know the whole way so we can this
scheme can be tuned down and we can read
you know the light will become laggy err
but the performance will get better
whereas the AABB scheme didn't really
have that ability very well I mean it's
sort of could do that but not to the
degree this can
it ever happened that you put so much
work into ID and it turned out not
working out oh yeah all the time
so I mean I've said this before but I'll
say it again the whole reason I wanted
handmade hero to work the way that it
works where I have to do everything on
the stream is because this is the actual
work of programming so if you are a good
programmer which admittedly takes a lot
of work to get to certainly so I'm not
suggesting that it that you just wake up
one day and you're a good program or
something but if you're a good
programmer then implementing something
that you already know how to do is like
a non-issue you just type it in and it's
done right and so it's especially
annoying the way a lot of times
programming is taught as if somehow the
hard part was like typing in the thing
you already knew how to do but it never
is right that's only if you're like a
total beginner the hard work of
programming and the part that's actually
interesting I would argue is figuring
out how to do something and so I wanted
most of handmade hero to show that that
takes a long time it takes a lot of work
and it's actually the place where
programmers add value at the moment
programming where you just already know
exactly what something is and there's
really no mystery to it that's just not
very hard not for an experienced
programmer it isn't
could we generate all these tests we do
for the lighting at box creation what
does that mean
ehh lightproof does build the spatial
partition but I just don't think it
times it it that will never be a slow
part though because you only have to do
that pass one time it doesn't have the
kind of multiplier on it the Rays do
remember the Rays multiplier is 500,000
it's on the order of a million the
number of boxes in a scene is like
10,000 right it's a hundred times less
so
and sort of a related thing to that that
I should mention it's also the case that
it's not just the fact that that's never
gonna be the slow part it's actually
more that we want it to be the slow part
it might be the way to say it so it's
less that I'm unconcerned about it and
more that my whole goal is to push more
work into the initial pre pass because
the more work that happens in the
initial pre pass the faster this thing
can be because the initial pre pass only
has to operate on a very small number of
objects whereas the raycasting has to
operate on a tremendously large number
of objects so you know I haven't even
multi-threaded the spatial partition
build I could but that's how much fat
there is in that part of the pipeline it
just does not matter yet so moving work
from the Ray caster into the spatial
partition build is actually great if we
can figure out how to do that that gives
us a lot more options because like I
said we haven't even multi-threaded that
part we could so we would much rather it
take longer and raycasting take less
time because that actually opens up
whole new avenues for us that we don't
have so I would love that I would love
it if we could make that part slower I
make and make the rate part I would love
it if we could make the raycast or
faster by making the spatial partition
build slower that would be fantastic
unfortunately other than just the grid I
don't have a lot of ideas about what we
could do there but if I had more I'd use
them
I like the idea by the way it's a June
2005 I like the idea of glass milk
bottles
there's like kind of ones with the like
a half gallon bottle maybe
yeah so I mentioned before it rad that I
made a tool for detecting indexing
errors that's true so the way that you
do it is you actually insert code into
your program that wherever you have
arrays of things you mark them so you
actually say like here's you know an
array and here's its dimensions and
where it is in memory and then the tool
is just a back-trace tool where you can
say okay when I asked about this entry
in some other array it can back-trace
through the other arrays too and tell
you which places that one had referenced
so you can see when you're indexing goes
wrong because you go you click on you
know you would look at one of the voxels
and you'd say okay this one and it would
show you like the wrong node and the
other one and you'd be like oh okay so
this person pulled from the wrong node
at some point right because you can
always add a piece of code that marks it
up where you say like you know
I don't know how to say this but like
you can do something like this right
where I say okay suppose I've got these
two voxels right and I'm going to do
something between them well I can say
like voxel a and Vox lb like this and I
just say like these two addresses like I
did you know work that went from one to
the other so now it knows like this and
it can chase those dependency trains so
it can basically say like oh I chased
all the addresses and then I reverse
computed what the index seat indices of
those addresses were and then I showed
them to you and display and then you can
quickly see when you look at this play
you're like oh sorry touch oh
whoops I have a mismatch somewhere and I
can go find that mismatch now that I
know it exists whereas up until that
time you can't see it right
so in sage in 2005's defense by the way
I would point out that glass milk
bottles are actually very popular now so
although they went out of fashion they
are coming back because milk tastes a
lot better in glass than it does in
plastic so if you go to like the fancier
places here like if you go to a really
fancy store instead of like you know the
local cheap supermarket or whatever the
really high-end milks that are like
local farm bla bla bla they're like in a
glass bottle now again it's a it's a
marketing like thing now so I think
nowadays you know I feel like glass went
away but it came back
could we look for only the farthest box
array would hit and eliminate testing
all the boxes in between I mean no
because you're trying to find the
closest hit that's how light transport
works you know like light transports
from the closest hit not the furthest
hit
no no no no hardware vendors contact me
about the 13 million line problem I mean
the whole reason I put it up on the web
is because I gave that lecture to Intel
specifically and although like some VP
called me at some point about it they
never did anything I mean to be
completely honest with you I don't
understand I feel like somebody needs to
start taking this stuff seriously
because even if you don't care about
programming and you don't care about
performance and you don't care about
like education you don't really have a
choice to not care about security in
today's worlds you know like the one
thing you absolutely can't do is not
care about security so that stuff is the
most important stuff for security to
keeping these stacks simple is the only
way to keep them secure right the more
code you have the more vulnerabilities
you have period there's really no more
direct measure for how many
vulnerabilities you probably have then
how much code you have because every
line of code is a new thing a hacker can
attack you know so all right let me wrap
it up thanks everyone for joining me for
those sort of handmade here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with a
series at home you could always
pre-order the game on handmade hero or
gonna come to the source code so you can
play around with it you could certainly
start doing the lighting debugging that
I'm going to do next weekend and that'd
be a great thing to practice on because
a very complex system but it's all laid
in now so you could go through and
follow it through and figure out what's
wrong with it that'd be a great thing to
do I'll be back here next week and we'll
all start doing that and hope to see you
back here then until then have fun
putting everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet
jig is everybody