hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero today uh i kind of wanted to do
some stuff uh we we split up the
weekends last weekend and this weekend
last weekend we uh did a bunch of
cleanup stuff on just tools like we
fixed we updated to the new four coder
and fixed any stuff that uh we had had a
problem with there and then we also uh
we you know kind of reworked the timer
app to be more in line with what we need
so it stays up and stuff and doesn't
only you know if we go long it doesn't
remove the little this little square
around my head and all that stuff we
just like long running stuff that we've
just been putting up with
um is now uh in theory fixed also we
added topics people wanted topics so the
topics exist now you can see what the
topic is for the day
um
and we can edit it and stuff so it you
know it's a little better it just just
some quality of life stuff
so you know hopefully that's good
um
what i wanted to do today was just take
a look at what we're doing engine
development wise uh and take a look
at
i want to go through and say what worked
what didn't so that we kind of have just
like okay here's the stuff we're gonna
cut
and here's the stuff we're gonna leave
for
calling the engine done
um
because there's like a bunch of stuff
that we did that like didn't work out
very well and
there's a bunch of stuff that we did
that did and it would be nice to just go
in and like
solidify things so that we don't still
have stuff hanging around that was just
like a waste of time or came out poorly
we should regress to something simpler
or just delete it entirely if it turns
out to be not something we actually want
and so i kind of wanted to make just a
list of those things uh so that we could
have some you know idea of of like of
like a checklist that we go through it's
a little bit hard because obviously
streams are difficult um it's hard to
kind of concentrate on things when you
do them in such like
in such sort of chunked like you know
you do a little bit here a little bit
there it's it's difficult to really like
um
it's difficult to make sure that you
have like a sensible uh idea of like
what you're doing at any given time it's
much harder than it is in
when you're working on stuff for all day
every day uh because it stays fresh in
your brain right um
but basically all i wanted to do was
just kind of go through here and see
what we actually have uh in terms of
stuff in handmade hero and what stuff
kind of went well and what didn't uh go
well and then maybe just put um in terms
of you know maybe we can put right above
our programmer stages of mental
development
here uh we can put like our to-do list
uh we had sort of one of these i think
at some point but i don't actually
remember
uh oh so it looks like we had like a
separate file
that's fine um you know we can keep it
in a separate file right
so a lot of these things i guess i don't
know what this to-do list was for we
made it at some point but a lot of these
things we actually already did um so
that's uh kind of uh less good
potentially in fact i don't really know
how much value this would be in general
so i think i might go with my original
plan maybe we'll you know that that's
just old stuff
maybe i'll put it up here because i find
that any time usually what i do when i'm
working normally is i use a notebook for
this process i don't actually even
keep it in files anywhere i find for
some reason having a notebook next to me
is like way better and actually also
everyone i know does it that way jeff
roberts says that way john blow does it
that way like it just seems like the way
that you keep to do lists for some
reason
not on a computer
i don't know why that is maybe because
computers are very bad at everything all
the time uh but
uh i think what we might do just delete
this this this guy uh
just get rid of it because i don't
really want it there and uh it's just
old stuff anyway uh so it's it's more
trouble than it's worth right
so
um on
you know deleting that
and
putting a to-do list here again not
great because i prefer to have like a
list next to me but you know in this
case i won't really be able to
i
what i wanted to say first of all was
like debug system sucks
like the debug system has always sucked
pretty much
uh and i think the reason that the debug
system sucks if you look at it was just
because we tried a bunch of things that
were probably just too much for what we
actually need
and they just end up creating a lot of
cruft and unreliability um so to give
some you know i said it's hard to keep
track of everything and so it's odd that
i'm probably able to come here and talk
about what i think didn't work when i
haven't touched this code in forever but
so
you know maybe take it with a grain of
salt because
it should have probably faded from my
memory quite a bit by now but
i can remember the broad strokes and in
general
what we did here is we said look we're
just going to create logs
and the logs
are going to be any thread can just
write
something to the log
and then they kind of get gathered up
afterwards and displayed as data
now there's a lot of problems with the
things that we chose to do here uh and
you know part of these are mistakes that
i think i make often meaning you keep
making the mistake and it's hard
sometimes to not make the mistake i make
it less now probably than i did when we
were doing this on handmade hero but i
still make it
it's one of the hardest mistakes not to
make
and the reason uh for this particular
mistake is when you think that you're
going to do something
to make it easy to do it somewhere and
the way that you make it easy to do it
is making the code on the other side
massively more complicated to the point
where it actually is still pretty hard
to use
uh and so one of the things we did here
like if you look at the debug interface
there's all this garbage there's all
these macros for like
timing blocks and writing out things
like event data and all this stuff
and all of these are really just they're
really just working around the fact that
c and c plus are garbage about how you
actually do meta programming you know
really all you want here is like a set
of enums like one enum
per event type you wanted to record and
then your code that's actually recording
events just says here's the you know
event
this is the one it is
and so trying to automatically generate
these things we use all sorts of tricks
you can actually see just how ridiculous
it gets up here there's like an atomic
add for the index there's this like
global table that gets updated uh it
then uses like a a
marker that it puts in that's like a
underscore counter in here as well like
like as well as like um
like let me show you what i mean it's
like
somewhere in here i don't remember there
it is um it uses like file and line
encounter to create a unique thing on a
line again all of this stuff is just
because c and c plus plus just suck at
this like like they should have solved
this problem long ago it should have
been trivial to do stuff like just put
uh things in that say hey
this thing in the code gets a unique id
and that unique id should be stable
across builds that should be a thing you
do day one if you're making a language
instead it's a thing that people never
do
and basically every language ships
without it somehow even though it's like
one of the most basic things you would
want to do in computing
um so as a result it's all just us
working around that and the result is
all of this work around just makes the
debug system a tremendous pain in the
butt to use
if instead we had just said look just
make the freaking enum anytime you want
to add
something to this code base just make
the enum man like like just make just
it's not that hard right
you know
adding one line to a file that's like
here's this new enum for this thing that
i'm
event that i want to track or whatever
would have saved so much time and so
much aggravation and as a result is
exactly the same and it's gonna probably
be more usable because you don't have
all of this craft that makes it very
confusing and requires things to be done
after the fact uh and all this other
stuff
the other thing that's ridiculous about
this and this is just probably because i
feel like you know i'm still not i
wouldn't consider myself at the point
yet where i'm really great at
multi-threaded programming i think
probably nobody these days is really
great at multi-threaded programming i'm
way better than i was though and just
looking at this code you know
thinking about how it's done it does
things that i would never do today so if
you look at how this code works for
example it does an atomic add on the
debug table so that anyone who issues a
debug event will go ahead and get a
unique slot in the table now the thing
that's so terrible about this is that
you really don't want to be doing atomic
operations in your debug system if you
are what you're doing is you're
introducing new synchronized bus traffic
for debug code which is terrible right
like you never want to do that because
anytime you do any kind of atomic
operation at the cpu level the cpu
itself has to rely on the cache logic to
actually synchronize so you don't know i
mean you might not be but you might you
don't know what kind of additional
thread synchronization you're actually
secretly introducing there lock free
isn't lock free is the good way to think
about it right any time you use an
atomic exchange atomic compare exchange
atomic add atomic increment comic
decrement any of these things
unless you've actually gone and looked
at it you don't know how much additional
synchronization you might be causing
between threads that are trying to
access this same number
right
uh so this is one of those like
uh
this is just one of those things that
once you get better at multi-threaded
programming you just avoid any kind of
atomic ads or anything like that
except in the circumstances where you
actually really wanted thread
synchronization to occur you try to
eliminate so you definitely don't want
it in a debug system because the debug
system is as much as possible trying to
be something that isn't going to
radically change the behavior of the
program that you're debugging so we
definitely don't want a situation where
we're trying to debug something and we
insert a debug event into it and all of
a sudden our threads sync at a different
point right um
so
you know what i'm saying to you right
um so it's it's just like one of those
things you just don't want to do
only one thread the way to think about
an atomic add right
is that a thread that hits the atomic
add the cpu has to then lock that cache
line as exclusive right it has to
acquire an exclusive access to that
cache line so that it can perform the ad
and know that no one else has changed
the cache at the same time if two
threads hit the atomic ad at the same
time they're both going to need to lock
the cache line as exclusive to make that
change and the one that gets it first
will stall the one that gets it second
right now sometimes it doesn't matter
and this is why i say you can just time
it
if you really care right because what's
going to happen is out-of-order cpus can
work around this fact so if this thing
about recording the event
can all be pushed onto a separate
dependency chain where the cpu is just
like leaving it in the table and going
ahead right um it's not going to be that
bad potentially because it may not
really affect anything yes you're
stalled but you're stalling one
dependency chain and you see if you can
go execute other ones
but again
you're counting on that behavior if you
use this you're counting on the fact
that the out of order window will be big
enough and there will be enough other
dependency chains blah blah blah blah
right
you're counting on all of that to occur
and like i just don't like to count on
that because unless i've actually
profiled it i don't know right it might
be fine it might not be so typically
what you want to do here if you can is
just you use thread local storage or
something and have uh things recorded
per thread and then later on at a you
know at a time when you're used to
synchronizing your threads
then you do one thing where you add them
up at that at that ending um that's
usually a better way to go now you know
you can also just decide not to do that
if you if you don't mind this this kind
of pile on um but it's just worth
understanding like that you've got these
trade-offs to make in so i probably
wouldn't want to do that either i'd
probably want to pull that out
make everyone record their own thread
local thing and then when we wish to
display the debug system
only if the debug system is actually
displaying something at that time do we
bother to actually merge those things
together so the normal run of the
program
doesn't get affected because nobody's
atomically adding anything right
so you know there's things like that we
can do and i think that would be a good
one so i would write these down in here
like uh remove the atomic add
debug table in favor of thread local
is one thing we would like to do
simplify everything
dealing
with events down to just a simple
enum table of things that you
pre-register
in the enum
uh right so all of that stuff i think
would be a much better and more usable
system because it would allow us to
record things more specifically and more
predictably
than we were doing before and we just
don't use a lot of this stuff right we
just don't use a lot of this stuff to
any great effect because it was so hard
to deal with right
and we had in the editor side of things
this in-game editor thing here which
actually has
uh us creating um some
uh you can see here like we've got begin
row end row and some button code right
um i think this is probably what we more
want to go with you can see it's very
reasonable uh it's easy to read again
the dev id from pointer kind of stuff
like we can probably simplify this stuff
down quite a bit by actually just using
an enum or something but otherwise if we
just simplify this and this is the debug
system so that you can write to it from
anywhere right um and then you can come
back here and you can just uh
just we can write little displays for
doing system that use logic to display
the things we want right
um so i would say like
transfer debug view to the editor
uh and we would probably clean up editor
uh
ui stuff
a bit
so i think that that's uh
i don't think there's that much
of substance there to fix the debug
system
it's just a lot of cruft so it'll be
like a bunch of you know
removing that craft basically and
being more diligent about keeping it
simple and not over complicating
something that we don't really need that
much of right we don't need it to do
these things because just a little bit
of code that's explicit will do whatever
it is that we needed to do and that's
usually just a better way to do it
than that sort of you know oh that's
going to do everything automatically and
let us view things dynamically it's like
no it's not because whatever you
needed to do
to create that view you should have just
created that view and code it will be
simpler faster and more powerful then
you're never going to write like a whole
ui for like constructing like debug
views and stuff right that's just a huge
waste of time so you end up in this
situation where you just have the worst
of both worlds so trying to avoid that
kind of pit but i think the debug system
fell into
um would be good
um so there's two other things i can
think of and so the other big one i
think uh that's most obvious is just
lighting um looking at lighting i think
uh
there's a couple things so i do like the
lighting like it's not actually that i
don't like the lighting and um what it
kind of ended up uh doing was very
interesting and and i'm you know i'm not
uh unhappy about it uh i should probably
turn off some of this collision
detection stuff that we were working on
um let me do that really quickly so that
we can take a look at the lighting more
specifically
um
in
move entity
um so i'm just going to go ahead and
stub move entity temporarily uh which
will get rid of you know
most of this stuff what unreachable
really
thank you so much for that piece of
information um
great uh int
didn't
don't care about that
equals one
is that better
are you happy now compiler
um so anyway uh when we look at this uh
what the lighting looks like right now
um i'm actually kind of happy with it
and i do think that it's kind of nice it
does a lot of interesting things and it
provides some kind of soft lighting and
the bounce lighting is nice and stuff
but i just think like in terms of the
complexity of the code
and the quality it's just not there and
yes like an easy way for us to i should
probably also i guess while i'm at it
turn off the um
uh in the in the entity renderer the the
collision
uh volumes being being drawn there is
not particularly relevant either um but
anyway point being uh the lighting
system is is okay but i just think bang
for the buck wise it's just not fair
right
um and we could you know one of the
reasons for that is we're doing it cpu
side
and this is really a gpu side thing we
could move it to the gpu and that would
certainly be something we could do but
we had pretty nice lighting working
before when i tried just doing circular
lights in there and they're not like
very physically correct but i think they
looked better and they were very cheap
to do
and so i think what i might want to do
is just regress one on the lighting and
use what is basically just like artistic
lighting
um so maybe i don't know exactly how to
solve the light leakage problem with
that kind of lighting like one of the
things that we get right now right
because it's actually doing some ray
casting is like the outside is dark and
the inside is light if the light can't
reach the outside right and that's
something that presumably you would want
and
so we may have to do a little bit of
package to get it to not do grotesque
things like propagate like a light too
far outside of a wall like that um
and so
but i'm okay doing some of that package
i just think the circular lights looked
really good and i think we could do
most of what we want to do with them and
it would just be way less performance
cost and better quality level and just
not as realistic but that's okay right
um so uh i think what i'd like to do is
try regressing to circular lights and
just simplify the lighting system down
to that because i think that it looked
cool and it was an interesting technique
and uh it would keep things simple right
so regress uh to circular
light source
um based lighting
so i'd like to just kind of regress to
that and say look we're gonna force it
to be artistic lighting
uh and we're gonna see what we can do
there
and the only question i have is like you
know maybe like
uh
some simple way of walls preventing
light
leakage right
and again
not having really done a system like
this before like a circular light system
uh because i haven't really done a
system like that before i don't really
know
what the hack should be like i don't
know what hack should
do it
uh but i think it shouldn't be
impossible right like after trying a few
hacks in theory we should be able to get
something
um that works okay
the
uh so that's all i would really like to
do with lighting and i think we can do
that pretty simply i also think we can
get some good quality by doing a couple
things a couple basic things in there um
again by just having a couple of
different kinds of artistic style light
that we can place uh that directly write
their values out into
uh the system should be okay and then if
we just have like occluders just take
light out of the system you know that
might just be good enough so we'll see
uh but we'll play around with it maybe
for a week or two and just like whatever
we can get out of the circular lighting
system that's what we go with because
that way it's nice and fast
and i know this one kind of seems fast
but you can see that it's not really
very good quality in order to get the
quality up higher and to not have this
being much lag it would be a lot of work
or move to the gpu
and we still don't really have a good
story for flickr right so it's just we
could do it
but it's just gonna cost a lot right uh
it's gonna cost a lot of effort and
probably also gpu time
moving it there uh and i just don't know
that that makes sense for this game
right it just seems like a bad decision
so i think maybe we get rid of it and
move to the circular lights it's it's a
shame because i do it does look cool uh
for sure uh but i'm just thinking maybe
we can make it look uh equally i don't
know as i'm saying all these words and
i'm down here like playing in the
dungeon and looking how cool the light
sources are i'm kind of having second
thoughts about that um
but you know like i said i'm not really
sure
uh how we move forward from where we are
right now that effectively uh i don't
know maybe i'm being stupid
that does look really cool though
doesn't it
um
you know you get sort of this these
these bad square effects as light
falloff happens uh maybe we can fix
those i don't know maybe i shouldn't be
so quick to dismiss this it really looks
incredibly cool
um
this is why it's so difficult um
i don't know
that really does look pretty darn cool
to be completely honest um
and you know this is on a five-year-old
machine so you know it only gets faster
with a modern machine
run this on a thread ripper and the
lighting would be quite good
um
i don't know
gosh yeah for some reason i remembered
the lighting looking a lot worse than
this
um
so so that's
part of it
you know uh
yeah i don't know i don't know what to
make of that that's a much harder
decision i thought it was going to be i
thought the lighting looked worse than
this like
really mostly what i'm seeing is like
the objectionable kind of square
artifact here and a little bit of
flickering which is really not that bad
by comparison um to where i thought we
were at
lighting-wise um
so that definitely makes it a more
difficult
decision um
yuck
well
um
i don't know
uh
maybe the answer is we actually leave it
in here and and just try to do the
square fall off try to fix fix that look
i mean the reason that the square
fall-off happens is because we're
sampling
um at you know there's light probes
basically right like placed throughout
uh the system
place throughout the world and uh those
those light probes they
they interpolate sort of along the
square
and when you get outside of where a
light is likely to be hitting ever uh
you get square falloff because
you don't have like negative light
contribution you it might be possible
um to eliminate that fall off
gosh you know
because
one of the things that happens
in that kind of a system
is that because lighting is only
strictly positive what you get is when
you drop below uh when you drop down to
zero it doesn't know how to interpolate
this is a common problem with linear
interpolation when you just have sample
points that are clamped they have to be
zero or above this is what you get
um
i guess i'm wondering now like if we
look at the lighting
uh and we go in here and uh
and
you know um
if we look at the shader i guess is
probably where we would look at it uh if
we look at the shader for this where
we're talking about how
uh we're gonna sample the lighting i'm
i'm curious to know
in here
what we do
at the moment because we haven't looked
at these particularly much like you can
see um
the the shader code in here i should
probably you know let's add to our to-do
list pull the shaders out into their own
files
unless i guess i have four coder people
on the stream here
is there any chance of four coder
probably not so is there any chance of
getting four coder to not to just
continue to do code formatting inside a
string
because like what i actually want is the
ability to just do
the code directly in here right but this
is not usable right i want it to just
indent it like in dense c code as if it
was starting like a new c program right
i'm sure that's probably not possible at
all uh but that is what i would want you
know what i mean
um so that you can keep your shaders in
the same file as your rendering code is
just kind of nice
so you don't have to have these extra
files for no reason um
so you know there's that
uh but what i was gonna say is anyway
separate from from all this maybe move
them to their own files uh unless
for coder gets you know strings indent
as code as a thing
um
but uh yeah i don't think it's possible
either uh so you know
if if somehow you could just tell
forecoder to ignore this
right like like somehow tell it that
this
this sort of thing isn't like add a
token to 4coder that we know what it is
it's like
it's like that
right
um
and and then whenever we do that just
don't
pretend it's an open bracket
just treat that as an open like like
just add that as
this as open bracket and this as close
bracket as tokens i think it would just
work right
um
it's just something to think about right
because that would be kind of cool if
you could do that um
anyway
uh
and i think it's literally just changing
the tokenizer to recognize one extra
thing as bracket right
um
like i don't think the rest of four
coders stays the same it just thinks oh
he opened a bracket here right like
right i think
anyway doesn't matter but i just think i
think it's probably easier than you
think it is i guess the only thing i was
gonna point out there
all right so anyway when we're sampling
the lighting
um what i was trying to say is that
somewhere in this disgusting mess of
code that we haven't really looked at
and don't really
care much about but when we do the
sample lighting right we do these
textile fetches and we compute lighting
uh
in this we have these octahedral light
maps this is crazy complicated for
someone who's not a graphics programmer
which is me it's ridiculous that we
don't know this stuff but you know
that's just what happens on stream we're
like let's try this and we tried it and
this is what we got
um
what i was going to say is when we do
these sums of of the light sources here
you can see it doing like a bunch of
sample lightings and then it basically
like linearly interprets between them
what happens is if you have a particular
light source like the light source that
is shining on the um character
um obviously when it no longer sees any
contributions that light source than um
and so you know just just to bring it
back to what's actually happening in
here when you look at what's happening
in the uh area right around the player
the reason that you're getting that
square fall off is you know because
and it's worth pointing out for people
who've never thought about this before
because it's it's kind of tricky and
it's it's not um intuitive
um if you look at what happens you'll
notice
you know why why isn't it square in here
right like why does it look radial right
up until the point where the light stops
right why does it look radial up till
there
um
and the reason for that is because
as long as linear interpolation has
something to interpolate it will look
radial linear interpolation actually
reconstructs radial things just fine
the problem is when you get to the point
where the light source has no
contribution so this vertex
and it's not a literal vertex i'm just
talking about this point of the lighting
that's interpolating has no contribution
from this light source basically so its
contribution is zero
when these have to interpolate to zero
what happens is the radial nature is no
longer preserved because it should have
been less than zero here technically
right
and since it should have been less than
zero it doesn't have any way to
interpolate to that because it doesn't
know how far below zero it should be it
just sees zero so it's basically like
clipping off the radial falloff and
that's what makes things appear
as a square
so there's ways we can try to work
around this uh certainly like one of
them is you just reduce the lighting
contribution
um so that actually your fall off
continues below zero if that makes sense
um you can see us doing a little bit of
that here so this this light floor value
was designed to do that right so
for example if i rebuild like this
with the light floor value of 0.2 which
basically like reduce you know it brings
it down and again i don't know if this
still
works properly here we'll see
um in a second but you can see that now
everything kind of is
that it has a lot less of that um effect
to it right
but it doesn't it it doesn't
still pres it doesn't prevent this right
because this is still above that level
and
you know obviously we don't want to do
this because we we we end up with not uh
we end up with no data out here because
we we clamp the light level down
so
previously that is how we were doing it
when we only had the one circle light
star so you can see when it falls off to
zero it works properly so the question
is just well okay
could we just do that
per light source
so when we're actually summing in our
light sources can we make it so that
they go down below zero in some other
way right
um and
you know the reason i didn't do that at
the time is because i can't really think
of it offhand exactly at work meaning
you know i can't just take each
individual light source and have those
light sources actually go below zero
because if those light sources actually
went below zero
then i would end up not
i would end up subtracting light as you
got towards the the floor of them right
now
maybe there's some way to make the
falloff
just always continue into the negative
space
yeah i i just i'm not
i'm not seeing how you take more than
one light source and you combine them in
such a way and still use that falloff
trick
right
um
like like i just don't quite see it and
maybe what we should do is spend some
time here thinking about that but that
that's what happens and that's why like
i said you know if you look at
um this stuff and it looks all very
square uh and then we but we change the
the light floor value here uh to b2
instead
um
you know
when we when we make a change like that
uh you can then see what happens in here
you can see how you get this nice
perfect circle at the zero point right
at the zero point
um and so the question is just can we do
that somehow with the summation
and
um
like
i just don't see it i
i probably should
but i don't
and so what we know we can do is we can
ensure nice radial uh smooth edges
as we go to xero
but we can't i don't think for other
things and
maybe that's
because yeah i don't know maybe if you
do it purse well per sample is not going
to help you like i said i don't think
this part i don't think you'd just do it
here because it's it's at the summation
time that it would matter
so you know
uh i'm just not sure when we have uh the
code that actually uh
writes the lighting in so when it when
it adds the samples
um
you know those samples aren't gonna pick
up you know because it's ray casting
right so those samples just aren't gonna
pick up
um
[Music]
they're not gonna pick up that
information
um it could be you know let's try it
let's try a couple things first i don't
want to give up quite yet
um so
yeah i assume that you know if you're if
you're all of these are linear
combinations so in theory uh it
shouldn't matter where we do this right
um like if we do it up here it wouldn't
it wouldn't matter um because
in theory we should be able to subtract
it at the end subtracting it to all the
values we blend versus
um
just taking it out as a constant factor
shouldn't make a difference right so
yeah i just
i mean maybe one answer is if you
somehow
blur the edges of things
so that they smooth themselves out more
[Music]
but i don't know but yeah looking at it
you know it's something to think about
i don't know like i said uh i really
don't um
i don't have an opinion about it
uh other than if i look at the lighting
right now the primary thing that i think
needs to get fixed
um is the fact that the
uh the individual lights have that kind
of square fall off to them
and
i don't see
the cheap
fix
right
um
there might well be one and i just don't
know what it is
you know what i mean
um so that's again why i say like you
know i just don't know
i agree maybe leaving the lighting in is
a good idea looks actually quite nice
so
you know i don't know what to make of
that um
but
i guess like
you you'd have to just live with the
kind of ugly
square falloff lighting or come up with
a clever solution and i don't have one
right
so i don't really have much else to say
about that we also have the problem of
kind of the lagginess of it right
um so if we take a look at how slow the
lighting is
in terms of like the the
i i guess the bring up rate because you
know it computes the lighting using kind
of you can't really do that many samples
per frame it's on the cpu
um you can kind of see here we've got a
ratio that's just like how much updating
you want to do
and so like if we allowed it to update
sort of much uh much more rapidly you
would see the flicker is way more
pronounced right
um so like that's what happens if we
update you know if we update the
the lighting at a at a fast rate so it's
it's really closely pegged
so the way we're getting uh around that
fact right the way we're getting around
uh the fact that we have a lot of
flicker is just by tuning this value
right to something that's not that bad
so here's sampling it at half that rate
um
right uh and you can see now you have
you know a lot less flicker but still
pretty noticeable let me sorry make that
full screen a lot less flicker but still
pretty noticeable
and then if you you know drop it down
maybe a little bit further
um you get less flicker still
that's probably good enough right like
in terms of amount of flicker so you
know you could hover somewhere around
there
and uh again you can also increase it
you can increase the number of rays you
cast uh on on a more powerful machine
certainly um which currently we're not
really doing um so you know we could go
in here and you can make it slower and
just more you know
more rays i don't really remember
what we use for that control
to be completely honest with you um
i don't actually remember
uh
the number of rays cast is like
i don't remember
how many uh
[Music]
somewhere in here we set this number
right
um and you can see here it you know
generates this work count
which is
uh
you know just a number we we create
um
it looks like we're we break them into
like rows right
so
yeah i don't know i don't even remember
where we set that number you can see
uh
building the space partition
doing the grid walks
here's this looping over the
voxels
so full cast presumably could
say how many it wanted
it looks like it just always does one
right
here's grid raycast
oh no it's eight
i take it back
um
although that's probably just eight
because
that is the
number it adds per row
right
yeah
so that's that's probably not it's it's
not eight rays it's the it's eight rays
because it's an octahedron right so it
does one cast out of each face of the
octahedral sampling that it's doing
that's all that is right
um you can see this it looking up the
sample direction
um
so you know
i think that's that's all that actually
does right
so you know like i said it's very
complicated code there's just a lot
happening in here and i'm just not sure
that the payoff actually is worth it i
think we can do you know if i wanted to
spend a year of my actual full time
making the best possible lighting thing
you definitely can like this is not the
best we can do by far but just in terms
of
you know cost benefit analysis i'm just
not sure uh
i'm just not sure it's there
um
let me look
why can i not search for full cast
there we go
um
so like i don't know can we for example
just do this twice
and double the number of rays cast
it looks like the answer is yes
although actually
that might not sum
because full cast
i think doesn't actually yeah so that
that's actually not quite right because
i think it just does a cold write not an
ad
so i think full cast
twice actually isn't
useful
grid raycast
um i think just writes directly i think
um
so yeah like this code would have to be
modified slightly because it needs to
call it with a different
like set of directions
right because otherwise they'll sample
the same direction twice
and you know it would have to do it
yeah it would have to like
sum the values which i don't think it
currently does or maybe it does
load yeah no it does it does a load and
then it does an add
right it does the blend
right so so it actually does
so grid raycast doing the blend it
should work if you do it twice i think
um
the only question is how do we actually
get to how do we get a separate set
of sample directions out of it right
uh because you know we
we load both of these here right
uh
so you would want to do this basically
twice where entropy index
gets updated
um
and you know we probably really should
because if you look at how long it takes
to do that
it looks like it's not really the
majority of the cost
so
probably would want to actually do this
where we in here
we would sample
the lighting twice
right
so yeah i might
i might suggest that we actually do do
that um i'd be curious to know if we
were at four frames of lag
um
which is not that bad
i would be interested to know how
limited the flicker could be by just
increasing the sampling because i think
it might be good
actually
um
that might actually be fine and just
don't update the diffuse map each time
so
i don't know i don't know this is a
really tough call i'm sorry i just don't
have the answer i don't know
um
ah that's really tough question
that's just a really tough question
so if we put in like
like full one second of lag
you can see
what the lighting looks like probably as
best it would right
um this is like the nice super smooth
version of the lighting
and i think we could get there
uh just by casting a few more arrays
because actually i think we're pretty
good so again
honestly i'm kind of worried now because
i'm like i guess i don't want to rip out
the lighting it's quite nice
maybe it just stays the way it is
the only thing i'd like to know is is
there some way
to get
less of that squariness
you know
um
because i think we could basically have
it be roughly this quality by just
casting like four times more
rays per second
uh
which i think we could easily get
is not that hard
um and then it would look like this
which is basically perfect so i don't
know i think we just cast a few more
rays and call it a day and then yeah the
the square fall off is really the bummer
[Music]
anyone
does anyone have any clever ideas about
the square fall off
yeah the other light sources are
probably less bright so you notice them
less i mean it could also just be the
height i mean that that light in
particular
that's floating above the hero
you know technically that light really
shouldn't be there because the hero is
not really lit although maybe the glove
would be
um
so that's kind of hard to say
but i think that's the debug light
actually is technically what that is i
don't i don't think that's actually
supposed to be
um
yeah that's just the entity
you know that's just off the entity so i
think it could be that maybe just it's
the the height off the ground is part of
why it looks squarier because it's kind
of more uh
in that position i don't know though uh
that's a good question
and uh
let me try moving it up more i think
it's the debug light don't quote me on
that
yeah i think that's the debug light
so yeah if the if you know if it's not
so low to the ground right or if it's
not so bright
it's not as much of a problem
right
um
so maybe it's okay i mean you can still
see the squariness right like you can
see it on the other lights too it's
always there
uh and it's just an artifact of the fact
that the interpolation is per you know
is on a square grid
and so you get that artifact as a light
ceases to contribute you get that sort
of vague fall off right
so i don't know like maybe we just leave
it this way maybe this is just what the
lighting looks like i don't know
um because i do think this is fine uh
and then we just need to cast more rays
because it's now the there's too much
lag on filling in the lighting
right um and so that's obviously
something that you want to fix
but uh i do think like because you can
see how long it takes to like actually
like light up the region right um
but i think we could fix that by just
casting a few more rays which i don't
think is that expensive in the system
um
so i think maybe we'll just do that
and that'll just be the lighting
so uh maybe get it up like maybe cast
four times as many rays that's a lot of
rays uh additional to cast but i think
we could do it because again a lot of
the time right now is actually not spent
in the raycast it's actually spent
uh in the
um
it's spent in like the dif converting
from specular to diffuse
right
so so maybe not
um
so i guess maybe we'll just do that
and i'll leave the lighting the way it
is maybe
i mean we could
um
looking at other things that i'd like to
fix
so i one question i have and i don't
know so this is kind of a broad question
and i'm not sure what the answer is so
it's it's kind of pretty tricky to think
through i don't know
um
one question i have is how much are we
actually getting out of the three
dennis of the levels
meaning
you know there's a lot of stuff in there
that would get faster if everything was
always 2d right meaning you couldn't
uh have things like these stairs where
people exist
in between because for example the
collision detection currently has to run
in 3d
it could switch to 2d
um we wouldn't need to have the lighting
would get faster because it would only
be one flat plate instead of actually a
three-dimensional
thing that has to extend downward to
lower surfaces right
so you know it's hard to say but there's
definite cost in having that
dimensionality right
so i do think that's a tough call
i don't know what the best call is there
um
but
you know we could just say that it's
just if there's only one plane of
existence right
and you know the way that that the main
difference the the thing we would see
differently uh pretty is pretty much the
only thing we would see different
differently right
is this wouldn't happen
right
we wouldn't do that
so there would just be a thing like a
square you hop on and then you suddenly
are down here
and you know when i think about it first
of all i really like this it's kind of
cool to be able to hop down but when i
think about the cost
you know what i
mean um
the cost just seems way too high for
just that
right
um
and so i think maybe a better
thing here would be regress to just a 2d
plane
for
you know what i'm saying
and so everything stays the same like it
all looks exactly the same but you just
can't do that you know what i mean
it also gets us out of the business of
trying to tune that alpha fade which is
a thing we have to manage right because
now you're just you're always drawing
everything there's no alpha fade there
it's just it is what it is you know
um
so that seems kind of compelling it just
simplifies the code a lot and and then
again yeah you get you get faster
lighting as well because you just have a
ton less probes because you only have
one flat plate
so i think maybe we'll we'll put that on
the list because i just it's not that i
don't think you could do cool things
there you obviously can
it's just that the amount of work it
would take to do the cool things there
we would save we don't have to do it and
we also get a bunch of
of free performance back in things like
the collision detector and the and the
lighting because now we only have one
plane to think about um and it just
seems like that's a win right so like i
would say remove z
um from
world construction
like optimized
lighting
optimized
collision detection that we get for that
right
because things just can't be vertical
now
um
i think that would be good and i think
that's kind of an obvious choice for
this game because we just we wouldn't be
making much use of it there's just
occasional things that you'd see down to
below you or something it's like yeah
they're cool
but they're not enough cool for what we
pay
right it's just not a good cost benefit
analysis i think
[Music]
okay
so i guess i would say
space naming just trying to stretch the
hammer yeah i know i know i know i know
the more stuff i have to do the longer
we keep this show on so
there's a natural kind of uh
thing there but at some point i would
like to stop right i can't just keep
making engines on the stream forever i
know people would prefer that because
they just like
the show and i appreciate that you like
the show i'm glad it's rare that 500
people show up every week for anything
so
you know
i appreciate it but at some point it's
just like
you know i want to move on to something
else so
you know
but anyway uh so i do think that would
be good i also think like uh simplified
arenas
so right now we are doing arenas in a
kind of a way that's not that useful uh
so just like uh base pointers and grow
um
basically is what i think we should
switch to because we don't really need
anything else for the stuff we do
uh so i think that would actually be
fine
um so i think this is most of the stuff
i guess one thing i don't know is like
uh
i probably like to to take a quick look
over at the asset builds
um i think they're still too complicated
we did simplify them a bit um but
they're still like there's just too much
right uh and i do think you know
it would be like
the asset stuff
just still seems a bit too complicated
right
um and uh
i think so maybe part of that is just
that
when we are loading these files uh when
we when we do like the build
uh i don't remember exactly what that
file was called it's like there's a
processor for the asset stuff
uh i think it's i think it's in import
um in import i feel like we've got a lot
of stuff with like grid tags you know
and all this stuff we import things when
we extract them and then we tag them
i just wonder if maybe we can switch to
a system that's like way less
complicated than this one where we
basically just treat it as like a basic
sprite sheet where we say look when you
render something you just say what the
sprite sheet is and which cell of the
sprite sheet and that's it like you
don't actually have like tags with that
are actually like picked for anything
it's like we just define that stuff in
code and off we go
um
i don't know if that makes a lot of
sense or not it could be that this is
already simple enough but i don't know
it still feels like it's a little too
complicated like when i look
um
at those tag files they just seem like
it's too much for what we get again
uh so i look at over here like the space
game stuff and it's like all these
things are are here
and like it's just too much
right it just seems like it's too much
stuff
and i don't think it should be necessary
to have quite so much stuff in quite so
much markup
you know what i mean
um
[Music]
so like i just wonder if we can simplify
the system down to something that's just
completely automated
where basically the code just puts in
the index and it just looks it up by
that directly
and i don't know
you know
i don't know how plausible that would be
the main problem that you get
pretty much all the time
is the stupid the fact that like
there's no easy way to mark up things
for sprites right like there's no easy
way in like photoshop for an artist
to say here's the like alignment point
of the sprite
for
no particular reason like they could
create those but it's kind of hard for
them to do because even if they put
something in that lets you know what it
is it's hard for them to see it because
they don't see it in the game
you know and so there's just all this
kind of nastiness there so i don't know
so maybe that's not that easy but like
right now this is just a pain in the
butt right like you have to go in here
um and you have like the hero or
something like hopping around uh and you
know you have to go into this thing
uh and you can like pick stuff
like uh i don't even remember how to do
this
i don't know why it's picking those
things is our is this broken somehow
maybe we broke it like that's not what
those are
um
oh i was on the wrong thing
so apparently there's two things here i
don't know what this one is
all right doesn't matter anyway the
point is if we look at one of these
things right it's got these alignment
points on there uh and we have to adjust
those like right to say like where
roughly the head goes relative to other
things um
i don't know like is that really the
best way to do this it just seems over
complicated like we needed this whole
editor and stuff for it
and i just don't know like i just don't
know a better way to do it uh the way
that we do it at mali for things that
are more like professional like you know
art process kinds of things is we just
do it all in photoshop right
um and then
we import the photoshop layers and stuff
like that
uh and i think that might be a bit much
for this game
so i don't know like what the simpler
solution is here where we can just
have that stuff come through any more
easily than what we've got uh so i don't
know maybe it is just as simple as it
can be
but it would be nice um
it would be nice
if we could simplify that somewhat
so like
so maybe like the code just directly
refers to grid squares in import so you
say like i'm doing this thing and this
is the grid square i want and then that
way we just get rid of the whole tagging
process which simplifies that a little
bit
um
i just there's i don't think there's any
way to get rid of the hotspot stuff so i
think that just has to stay
so i don't know
that there's much to do about that
you know it's possible that we just
require the
art to be aligned when it comes in
um
because like we could just say look the
way we're going to do it we're going to
change the way the art is and the art
just has to be aligned when it comes in
and we don't
allow any adjustment right it just comes
in stacked the way it's stacked
[Music]
and and i don't know
right
so
i don't know
so so that may be roughly it uh let me
see what else is there anything else i
think we might be mostly done i don't
think there's many other things um
the brain stuff
may be a little too complicated
um
i don't know we may want to take a look
at that and just see
like can we simplify the brain stuff
down a little bit
um
the way it works right now is like
brains gather up collections of entities
that they operate on
uh and i don't know if that's like too
complicated or not like we could see
like
and you know the way that it does that
is that an entity is itself like each of
the entities kind of like forms the
brain by
a brain like gathers up a series of
entities like you know like all the
parts of a snake or something
and then operates on them and it seems
pretty good but i don't know might be
over complicated
um
but i don't know that there's a lot of
other ways to deal with it uh because
you know entities
we could start treat i guess okay
we could start thinking of entities as
having multiple components because they
sort of already do
and so maybe we need to do this like
look at brains versus entities
uh versus what is it parts
pieces
like can we just make entities plus
pieces um and the pieces
are what uh you know
and like the entire bounding box of the
pieces is what we pack unpack right
so basically could we make it so that
entities are just they don't need to
gather anything like an entity is just a
thing that has parts to it and it can
move its parts independently if it
wishes to but in general like you know
that's considered one entity you know do
we need the brain envy pieces can we
just do entity plus pieces and call it a
day
um
i guess that'd be the one other thing i
think that's it for the things that i
wanted to think about in the engine that
i think we should probably fix
um
i don't know that there's much more here
to worry about
um
so let's talk about world gen
i think we can definitely simplify that
so i think world gen we could just go
with a much simpler layout scheme like
maybe just something that plops these
dungeons down
and then connects them right
um
would probably be a lot simpler than
what we have right now which is like
doing this kind of weird like two pass
thing
you know there's a lot of cool stuff you
could do there but realistically
speaking you know this is a game where
you're supposed to go into rooms
battle the room then go to the next room
it's unclear that we get very much from
this uh
you know like i just don't know that
there's much point to having something
more complicated happening so like uh
simplify
uh dramatically like
try to get down to single pass
uh or at least single pass
after broad layout um
so i think we could condense that down
uh
quite a bit
just just untangling that code path so i
do think that was probably probably
worth it as
well um
i think most of the other stuff is fine
i assume the cutscene stuff is still
fine
um i don't remember if there's anything
here
that we needed to do i think it all
still works pretty well uh maybe it
doesn't i don't know uh we haven't
really looked at it in a long time
um but it looks like the cutscene stuff
still works just fine
yeah
i mean this all seems like
it's all working properly right
uh and yeah i do i do do big picture
revision from time to time it's just
usually it's not as bad as handmade hero
because usually i'm doing it kind of
continuously because it's kind of in my
head all the time so it's maybe not as
bad
these days
right
um
but like you know i
i definitely do it
here's santa claus being a dick as he
always is
yes the idea is that this would have
voice over to it um
and uh
you know
i don't have voiceover yet for it but
eventually we would just have the voice
over
maybe i could record some voice over for
it
how's doing sgg informed decisions no
the other way around like i'm mostly
trying to inform starco galaxy by
handmade hero
that's not a goat monster it's krampus
don't you know who krampus is come on
man
or confus as i believe is more
properly pronounced
krampus comes
right before christmas
like the 14th or the 15th not the 25th
it comes before christmas for like the
naughty children
and like he dismembers them and puts
them in a bag
i think
um
is what happens normally so he like cuts
off their limbs and he puts them in a
bag and then they're never heard they're
just taken away
that's that's like actually what people
i think it gots i think that's what
krampus is supposedly actually does
that's what they tell children
krampus does i think
in places where they celebrate krampus
i don't know if it's german it's it's
definitely like northern european or
northeastern european that kind of area
i think
it might be german
um
but i think it's kind of more regional
than that it's not just german it's like
kind of in a lot of places
um
all right so yeah i think that's what i
would like to do
um and so this is just gonna be a
simplification pass to get everything
ready uh
and
um
like i said i probably wanna blitz it so
what i probably will do i don't know
about this week
but like maybe next week
um i might do like eight hours a day of
street well eight hours a day is
probably too much for my voice but like
you know four hours a day of streams
every day for a while
so
uh so i think that's what we'll do
and uh
you know like i said i don't exactly
when i'll start that but uh when i start
that i think i want to do it kind of
concentrated because i don't think you
can do this kind of revision work
piecemeal you kind of have to just sit
down and do it and keep it in your head
properly because if you don't
you're just going to screw it up
and that's not going to be particularly
useful so we'll probably do a fairly
dense series of streams
for that starting soon
but yeah until then
um
yeah
that's the list
all right so thanks everyone for joining
me
um
we will pick that up when we decide to
actually start as always if you do want
to follow along at home of course you
can go to handmadehero
dot org
pre-orders the game come the source code
if you want to follow along with what
i'm doing you can try to do the engine
rewrite yourself if you want to let's
not really rewrite uh cleanup i guess is
what it is
simplification
um
and uh yeah
that's about it for today i'll be back
here
probably next sunday maybe to kick
things off again i don't know exactly
what the schedule will be but
i
probably be back here next sunday to
talk about what we're going to do and
when we're going to do it or maybe just
to start doing it then and we'll just
continue through the week we'll see
until then have fun programming everyone
and i will see you on the internet take
it easy everybody