alright hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the show where we code a
complete game live on stream we found
some bugs yesterday and we fixed some of
those bugs yesterday as well as doing
some optimization work but we had a bug
that we needed to leave til today cuz I
think it's gonna be relatively involved
with math wise and so you know normally
I would say ten years ago well let's
let's say 15 years ago not 10 years ago
would've been fine ten years ago I think
this is the kind of math problem that I
wouldn't think about very long I just
feel like oh here it is
but since I've been spending my time for
the past god I don't even know how long
not doing these kinds of math problems I
am often a little bit rusty at them so I
feel like this is you know I just felt
like it was likely it was likely to take
some time to work it out
due to the rustiness of it I kind of
figure out I wonder why Milton always
loses the ability to capture the tablet
when it's been open for a while nobody
seems to know why someday I should go to
bug it we have the source code but I
don't know why and you does anybody else
so anyway point being let's take a look
here here we are on day 319 and this is
for you no skew UVs
should actually say skew UV mapping
maybe and for those of you who don't
know what I'm talking about because
maybe you didn't see yesterday's stream
we wrote a thing that looked a
quadrilateral mapping routine when we
originally wrote the renderer for this
game because remember we don't require
OpenGL at the moment we actually can
just render the game entirely in
software ourselves and so what what was
going on there was we wrote a mapping
routine where you could give it a y-axis
and an x-axis and you could rotate those
however you want it and you could scale
those so ever you wanted and it would
work the image so you know you could
look map an image on you could do
something more like this if you wanted
to and it would you know stretch the
image out right so standard texture
mapper basically that worked with a
quadrilateral the quadrilateral has to
be you know a parallelogram so not a not
a rhombus but a you know an actual it
always has two sides both sides parallel
and that'll work fine and we you know we
got that working and it was fine but we
never really supported the ability to
skew so stuff like this if you were to
actually construct using a real
parallelogram not a rectangle not a
rotated rectangle but an actual
parallelogram where this you know is not
ninety degrees this is some other angle
here that is not 90 this is not 90 we
don't really support that and the reason
that we don't support that
is because I kind of took a shortcut in
how I did the UV mapping of the
quadrilateral and so I just wanted to
take this opportunity to describe what
that shortcut was we probably described
it at the time but we probably didn't
dwell on it very much because we weren't
really thinking about the skewness of it
or at all and and so on and so forth so
maybe let's just take a minute to kind
of talk about what was going on in this
situation so first let's talk about and
I'll try to not make too many math
mistakes but you know like I said it's
I'm a bit rusty at these so you're gonna
have to bear with me on that
conceptually speaking I just want to say
here is what we're actually doing okay
so we have if you would imagine this is
our texture and on this texture we've
got you know some pixels or whatever and
essentially you could think of this you
know if you want to think of it
conceptually you could think of any
point on this thing you know
we could think of this as being defined
by all these points you know if you
didn't don't even think of it as a
texture map just think of it as a space
in where there's a bunch of colored
points right because we're talking about
transform we wanna think about the
transform so pixels we don't care about
pixels right now we're not even thinking
about pixels let's just think about
points right that are on this texture
map and the point could be anywhere it
could be over here could be in here
could be on the surface whatever any
point in this texture map right so what
we know is that we've got these basis
vectors here right that define this and
these are the X&amp;Y basis vectors of the
texture and then what we're doing when
we do a texture map conceptually
speaking even if this isn't how we're
actually computing it is we're taking
these and we're sort of specifying where
those go on the screen right so let's
take the case of when I was still using
rectangular rotated rectangles rotated
scaled rectangles you know we have a y
axis and an x axis right and those
correspond here so we're essentially
taking points and we're transforming
them over here so if we wanted to and
you know we should also point out
there's also an origin right so there's
there's some kind of a basis point here
that we're talking about and so I don't
know what we'll call that let's just
call that I don't know we'll call that a
so all right so if we have a point here
a point P what we want to know if we're
talking about the forward transform so
I'm talking about if I actually had a
bunch of points and wanted to transform
them into the space right so if I'm
talking about the forward transform
which obviously doesn't help us at all
in this particular circumstance but
trust me it matters why we want to think
about it that way for a second what
we're basically asking for is how to
create a P Prime over here that's in the
same place as the texture would be if
the whole texture was kind of warped you
know and smooth and warped over to the
location that we want the texture to be
on the screen right so you know P Prime
is our screen position and P is the
Texel space position right and so we
could talk about this transform and
maybe a was a poor choice here because I
probably would use the large a for it
but I don't know will will will sort of
creatively turn that into a B let's say
we've got an a here so I'm just gonna
describe this transform a that's gonna
take these points and do the operation
that I want to do right so assuming that
this is how I'm going to conceptualize
it what I'm saying is that if I was to
multiply you know if I was to perform
the transform a on the point P I would
get back that P Prime right and so this
is a very straightforward sort of matrix
statement I would be making I'm saying
that I have a transform that is the
transform that moves from texture space
that's where this is at zero zero that's
where this is at 1 0 and this is 0 1
right this like known space and it you
know it moves everything over to this
other space here where the origin is not
0 0 it's at B and these vectors are not
0 1 and 1 0 there are some random
vectors that are whatever they are we
they could be anything right so let's
talk about that shortcut that I took
given this matrix equation the most
simple kind of matrix equation you can
really ever have let's talk about what
this actually looked like now I know
that some people's eyes gloss over when
you see matrices and so I always like to
just remind everyone that really we're
just talking about bags of numbers here
this is a 2d transform let's take a look
at what this actually looks like if we
if we talk about it specifically right
so what's this P prime here right
well this P prime is this right here
that's just the X&amp;Y coordinates of the
point on in screen space right so that's
literally just like the screen X and the
screen Y that's all we're talking about
for this P prime vector
we then have some matrix a right and and
who knows what that matrix a is we're
going to talk about that in a second and
then we've got this vector P here and
what's the vector P well that's the U
and V coordinate right that's like
whatever the UV coordinate was to get
that point of the texture map right so I
don't know what it is here point eight
point eight something like that kind of
it looks like maybe your point nine
point nine who knows right and so the
question is just what is this a right
what is this a vector here right and so
in order to in order to actually do the
origin transform with the B we could you
know you've seen matrices where we
extend two homogeneous coordinates and
include the translation and the matrix
and all that stuff we're not going to
look at that at all so what I'm gonna
say is I'm gonna say that we just have
the B is a is a seperate origin shifting
term out here right I'm just gonna say
that you know we don't care about that
that's just you know whatever that this
screen space origin is here wherever we
wanted it is this other term because we
don't care about that at all right we
can trivially to perform the reverse
mapping which is the thing that we
actually care about or the forward
matters that matter we can always just
subtract away this origin and get just
the vector P Prime and this then becomes
the same zero zero right so translating
this back to the origin is trivial and I
don't want to complicate the matrices
for you thinking about the homogeneous
nature of them and that other stuff
because that's really graphics trickery
it's not really that important and not
something we need to concern ourselves
with for this problem at all so let's
take that out of the equation pun
intended and just focus on the actual
part we care about which is the actual
transform of the shape right so that
skewing stretching transform which is a
two by two transform on the U and V that
bends it into this shape that it's in
okay so let's think about what has to
happen there right well I've got an S X
and an S Y and what I want to do is I
want to interpret them remember s
X was interpreted this way originally
right oh I'm sorry I don't mean that I
meant UV I've got a little hell of
myself there so that you write is
interpreted this way and that V is
interpreted this way right so
essentially here is the V here is the
you okay so if I wanted to reproduce
this point over here then what I was
thinking to myself right is I was
thinking to myself well okay if I want
to go you know however far I need to
come this way for my you coordinate and
however far I need to come this way for
my V coordinate well then clearly the X
vector you know whatever this X vector
is here that is just the columnar
component of this guy so you know I've
got X X X Y whatever this if that's this
vector here right and I've got Y x y y
as you know and that's this this axis
here that's all I need now why did I
think that was true right well look at
what happens if I if I'm actually going
to if you actually multiply these out
right I taught you how to do matrix
multiplication so even if you don't know
beforehand made here you should know now
if not where were you when we covered
this we've done it multiple times now so
remember if I multiply this out you'll
see what I get
remember you you think of it this way
you take the first element in the row
and the first moment in the column you
multiply them together so it's u xx
right then you take the next element
next element and multiply those together
as a sum so V Y X right
I do the same thing here so I do you X Y
and I do v YY wish u and V were a little
more clean right and this is the result
I get right it's a vector result right
there's two elements to it this one in
this one and if you look
how these break down you can see these
terms isolate very very cleanly don't
they
right I could rewrite this very by just
cleaving it at the plus line and this is
clearly U times xx XY plus V times V y X
V Y Y ok now what are these two oops I
doubled my V there for no reason here we
go y x YY right and this is just the
x-axis this is the y-axis of my
transform up there so it's just UX + V Y
right and that's exactly what I said I
wanted I wanted to go out the x axis by
U and I wanted to go up the y-axis by Y
that's what I was trying to do right so
that is why I constructed in my head
when we were doing this that is why I
was thinking this way right so my a
matrix I know what it is it's it's
exactly what what I just said right it's
exactly this but this is not an
operation that we ever actually do right
it's just not an operation we do we
never have to in hand meet here at the
moment anyway we never have to take a
point in texture space and map it onto
the screen because remember the way we
do our texture mapping is we just loop
over the pixels and we try to figure out
where in the texture map each pixel came
from so we actually don't want a we want
the inverse of a right we want to do the
backward transform that's what we were
doing okay so how did I write that
backward transform right what did I
actually type in as the code well if you
remember what I typed in is from the SX
sy here mm-hmm and I'm gonna go ahead
and eliminate be entirely we're just not
gonna like I said we're not good at all
we're gonna pretend we already
subtracted B out so pretend that this is
the entirety of our equation it's just
SS X Y times you know
equals the matrix times a UV right so
what did I type in well I typed in two
dot products I don't know if you
remember this right but the dot products
i typed in were if we let's call this
the you know at the s vector well I
guess we called it P Prime
so that's fine the dot products I I
typed in where I wanted to take P prime
transpose X so I wanted to dot product
this end this together right that was
going to be my you coordinate and I said
I was going to take the same thing with
the y axis and that was gonna be my V
coordinate right that's what I said now
why did I say that I might have
explained at the time I don't know if I
did if I didn't but I hope I did but now
let me just explain it again because
it's crucial to understand where I got
that before you can really understand
what the bug is okay so where does this
come from where does this concept come
from well remember we have our matrix
equation P prime equals AP okay and we
know that that is s XS y equals x x XY Y
x y y x UV now I want to solve this
equation what I want to do is I want to
get the U and the V right that's what we
need to look up into the texture but I
only have the SX and the sy right so
effectively what I have to do is solve
this equation for P in order to actually
produce the UVs that I want so what that
you know involves is multiplying by the
inverse of this a matrix right if I have
P prime equals a P well if I want to
solve this equation I need to multiply
both sides on the left by a inverse a
inverse P prime equals a inverse ap and
any matrix times its inverse obviously
is going to equal the identity matrix
right so that goes away
and I get a inverse P prime equals P
okay
and so since what I'm trying to solve
for is the P means that the thing that
I'm trying to compute is a inverse P
Prime
that's what I want right so I want
moving back up to here if what I want is
a inverse P Prime well that means I've
got this X X oops XY Y x y Y matrix that
I have to invert somehow and we don't we
haven't really talked much about how to
invert a matrix right so we have to be
able to invert a matrix that's one thing
we have to do and then we have to we
have to take this and multiply it by the
input the SX X Y right that's what we
have to do so I never inverted this
matrix right that's inverting a matrix
is not in the code and I don't know if
we talked about inverting the matrix or
not or what happened but that never
happened
so how did I get from wanting to do this
equation to computing this right how did
I get there because it's kind of close
right I mean this is the this is P prime
here right and it does produce the U and
the V and the x and y-axes are there but
what you know how did I get there well
the answer is I kind of used a little
bit of a trick it just mentally without
probably going into too much detail of
it that is if you want to invert a
matrix if you know some things about the
matrix you can take a shortcut there's a
number of things that you can do what
are those shortcuts well let's start
with a very simple one let's suppose
that you have an orthonormal matrix
or rather that the vectors in the matrix
xx and YY or orthonormal what does that
mean well an orthonormal pair of vectors
is a pair of vectors that meet at 90
degrees right and are also unit length
so this is you know one long and this is
also one long okay if you know that you
have an or if you have two orthonormal
matrices I start to orthonormal vectors
so say that x and y were orthonormal to
each other then inverting your matrix is
as simple as rearranging the terms you
don't even really have to do any work to
invert the matrix if I have an
orthonormal matrix that looks like a X a
Y DX dy like this right and I want and I
know that a is a and B are orthonormal
right so I have this I know they're
orthonormal then the inverse of this
just equals the transpose and the
transfers just means flipping everything
around the diagonal right it's a X a Y B
X B Y right so you can see the ax and
the B Y stay in the same place that the
a YB x they swap right now it's a little
confusing it's like why why does that
happen right it's like it's one thing
for me to kind of sit here being mathy
about it and saying like hey guess what
guys the inverse in this case happens to
equal this so really you could say that
a inverse equals a transpose right in
the case where the vectors that make it
up happen to be orthogonal right but why
is that true you know Gibbs gives some
geometric intuition not to why that's
true or some algebraic intuition or
whatever well I can probably give you
both my linear algebra skills aren't so
rusty that I can't
probably demonstrate that in in
both ways actually so let's start with
the algebraic way and and you know I'll
show you the geometric way second so
what actually do I know about inverses
right what is an inverse of a matrix
well you know you can think about
inverses of matrices very much like
inverses of anything else right it's the
opposite operation and it's the thing
that is the unitary inverse in this case
so for example to map it back to
something that you may be more familiar
with if you're not too comfortable
matrices let's say that we just took a
you know a number like let's say we took
the number a equals five right so it's
just a symbol a it equals five if I
wanted the unitary inverse of this right
if I wanted to the the multiplicative
inverse if you will right if I wanted to
say what multiplied by a gives me one
right so I have some number I want
something that I'm going to call a
inverse I'm going to multiply it by a
and I want it to equal one right that's
what I want to have happen well you can
find out pretty trivially what this is
right you have an equation in only one
unknown a inverse right and I have a
known value for a which is five so if I
have a inverse five equals one
well then a inverse is pretty obviously
1/5 right and that's exactly what you
know intuitively you know if I give you
the number five you know that one over
five is the thing you would multiply it
by to reduce it back to one right and so
for any you know a one over a is always
the multiplicative inverse of it you can
always take anything well if that thing
is not zero you can always take anything
and you know you know invert it like
that and you get something that will
multiply out to one so the inverse of a
matrix is a very similar concept there's
just a lot more to it because there's
just so much more involved right but
it's very similar it's the thing that I
multiply a matrix by in order to produce
the identity in order to produce a value
which when multiplied when you multiply
by it it does nothing right because
that's what this was right this was a
way of producing one
which is the the value that does nothing
when multiplied right it is literally an
ineffectual multiplier right and that's
the same concept for inverting a matrix
when I do a matrix inverse times itself
you know when I do a inverse times a I
get the identity matrix the identity
matrix is just like one it's the thing
that you can multiply other matrices by
and it does not affect them
it's a pass-through right and it
actually looks you know like this right
it's just it's just a you know ones down
the diagonal the whole way right and so
anything that you multiply by it just
produces a copy on the other side it
does it does nothing so it's exactly
like one for multiplication it's just
this is for matrices so hopefully you're
comfortable enough just with
conceptually what that means a inverse a
equals the identity matrix well now I
can tell you algebraically why that
inverse transpose Y this is true for
orthonormal vectors right and so let's
say we just do out exactly what I am
suggesting we do here let's say that we
pretend that a inverse equals a
transpose and I have these vectors that
are orthonormal right so I start with a
X a Y B X B Y okay that's the matrix and
I'm going to reproduce exactly this
equation that I wrote write a inverse a
equals the identity matrix okay so if I
were to take the transpose of this
matrix which I just told you how to do
right this is this is a up here this is
gonna be a transpose right here right
which I'm saying equals the inverse I
know that my ax and my B Y stay in the
same place I know that my B X and my a Y
switch right well let's multiply these
matrices together we know we're gonna
get another 4x4 I'm sorry another 2x2
matrix of the four element matrix we
know how we do right we know how to
multiply we've done this a bunch of
times I handmade here oh so it's going
to be ax squared right ax times ax ay Y
times a y
right so it's like x squared a y squared
right that's what that's going to be
then here we're going to get ax BX + a
YB y right ax BX a YB y down here we're
going to get kind of the opposite of
that right doot-doot we're gonna get ax
BX + a YB y oops right that quickly yeah
ax BX a YB y right and you can see how
it's kind of like producing the exact
same terms all right and then the same
thing that happened up here to this this
vector which is squaring itself
essentially is going to happen to these
down here right so I get BX squared plus
B Y squared right so this looks like a
bunch of gobbledygook right it's like
what's going on here like I thought you
were gonna tell me how this equals the
identity matrix I don't understand well
if you actually look closer at what
these things are you can very quickly
see why it actually is the identity
matrix and here's why
well what is ax BX + a YB y right what
is that it's the dot product of a and B
that's a transpose B right remember a
transpose B ax times BX plus ay Y times
dy it's the dot product right same thing
up here
that's just a transpose B what's ax ax
plus ay Y a Y well that's a transpose a
and what's BX BX plus B Y B Y well
that's B transpose B so actually the
matrix that I produced is a transpose a
a transpose B B transpose B and a
transpose B again these are equivalent
terms well what are those values I would
invite you to look back here at a and B
are orthonormal and what did I say what
did I say orthonormal ment I said it
meant they had unit length and that they
met at a right angle
okay do you see it yet if not I'll keep
going a transpose a you know the dot
product I want everyone in Hamming here
are you better into the backtracked I've
said it so many times you know the dot
product of a times a it's the length of
a time's the length of a time's the
cosine of the angle between them right B
times B length of B times length of B
times the cosine of the angle between
them right a transpose B last term
length of a length of B cosine of the
angle between them well tell me now what
are all these lengths I just said
everything has a length of one right so
all of these terms go away they're gone
because they're all equal to one so all
we have left is the cosine of the angle
between them well what's the cosine of
the angle between two vectors that are
the same vector right that's an angle of
0 and a cosine of 1 which means a
transpose a and B transpose B are both
equal to 1 hey guess what 1 1 a
transpose B what's the cosine of 2
things that are 90 degrees apart what's
the cosine of that well it's 0 right the
cosine is 0 when it gets to 9 degrees 0
0 that's exactly what I wanted right 1 0
0 1 so effectively you can think of this
and when if you go down the linear
algebra path this is you know this is
real basic linear algebra stuff that I'm
doing here but if you've never done
matrices you know obviously it's it's I
think it helps to kind of ease into it
obviously but you can always think of
matrices as just a giant bag of dot
products right it's just dot product of
this you know this vector dotted with
that vector is is this entry right so
each entry you can think of a mate reply
as taking all the possible dot product
combinations that you can make from two
incoming matrices and each element of
the corresponding matrix is a
different combination of dot products
right so that is a really easy algebraic
way right of seeing why the inverse is
the transpose because when you happen to
know that these are orthonormal all the
math just comes out right when you
actually do that multiply look
everything on the diagonal happens to be
a dot product of a vector with itself
and all of them are length one and
everything on the other diagonal happens
to be a dot product of two vectors that
are 90 degrees apart right and so to put
it in sort of meta algebraic terms if
like I said if you start to think of
these as just a series of vectors right
then what you can think of is if I was
to start with some vectors up here
ABCD who knows so four vectors each for
long and I transpose them ABCD right
then you can just think of the diagonal
of the matrix just being all the dot
products of things with themselves right
B transpose B C transpose C D transpose
D all the way down however big you made
this matrix I don't care and then all
the off elements are all the dot
products of some vector with some other
vector so the reason that conceptually
speaking any matrix times its transpose
will give you the identity if you know
that all of the vectors in it are
orthonormal all of the columns of it are
all all the rows of it or NAR thermistor
everywhere you want to think of it right
is because you then know that all of the
diagonals will become one because you're
always taking the dot product of a unit
length vector with itself and that's
always one and everything off the
diagonal is always going to be the dot
part of some vector with some vector
that's 90 degrees apart from it so it
actually doesn't even matter at that
point what their lengths are they're
like to be anything but the cosine term
will always be zero so everything off
the DL becomes zero and the only thing
you get when you have ones down the
diagonal and zeros everywhere else is
the identity matrix so
conceptually algebraically I hope that
makes some clear sense as to why this is
true right so now let's look at
geometrically why it's true because some
people like to think in geometric terms
some people like to get out direct terms
somebody like to think both usually
being able to be both is usually best
because some things work well objects
some things work well geometrically it's
handy sometimes to be able to switch
back and forth between them when
something's not working but let's talk
about the geometric construction of this
right so like I said sort of previously
we could think of one of these vectors
you know when it I'm sorry one of these
matrices and I guess let me write it out
a x a y be X B Y we could think of one
of these that these matrices like a and
I'm gonna I want to you know sort of
have something a vector here than I can
multiply by it so that I can show
something algebraically right I in fact
I don't even really have to do it again
because I suppose I already did it my
Allah just rerun it again it's easy
enough to rewrite right it's a you ax
plus the b x ua y plus vby
right and so what i said was well you
know you can see very clearly that
that's u times a plus V times B right so
geometrically we've talked about this
many many many many times right all
that's doing is saying well all right if
you imagine that I had some perfect
space over here where I had you know U
and V like this to get to a point and
there's my my vector u V right if I then
take some other you know basis here
which is my ax so here's my here's my a
and here's my B I can then just
reinterpret these right I can say I want
to go this far along in you and I want
to go that far along in V and I get to
that point right and that's the forward
transform of this thing right this is
we've done this so many times you just
go you along the
vector and then V along the B vector and
you get to the point and that's how you
do a basic transform right well if you
think about what the inverse of this is
right so I want to do the inverse
operation geometrically I don't want to
go this way I want to go that way
right well what would I do instead of U
times a plus V times B I want to do the
opposite
I want to dot product right I want to
project so I want to take this and
project it onto the a so I want to take
whatever this vector is what am I going
to call this vector
I guess we'll call this vector P because
I have nothing better to call it right
so if this is my point P here I want to
dot product it with a to produce u right
I want to drop that perpendicular down
to produce the U value and then I want
to dot product it with B for the same
reason to produce that V value well how
do I produce a dot product with a and
with B right
it's exactly what I just said if these
are going you know in the column order
if I was to transpose them so it's a X a
Y B X B Y right if I take that transpose
now they're lined up such that
multiplying by the matrix does the dot
product there it is right there right so
now instead of computing the thing that
moves you out along the vectors
conceptually speaking which is this I
produce the thing that dot products with
those vectors which is the measurement
version right so again you can see
conceptually speaking if you want thing
about geometrically you can just think
about it as going the transpose if
everything's orthonormal the transpose
takes you from vectors you move along
and instead of multiplying by those
vectors your two coordinates it makes it
so that now your dot product against
against them right and that's the
difference between thinking of a matrix
in column form and thinking of it in row
form right if I have a matrix that looks
like this to me and once you're like
once you're into linear out
you just think this way usually if I
have a matrix that looks like this I
think ah this is a forward transfer
matrix because it's been labeled such
that the common terms are going down
right so I know that when I multiply by
something I'm a producing a series of
vector products whatever I put here I'm
effectively multiplying by you know that
column right and then I'm adding the
next column times something right so
when I see columns of of coherent values
going down a matrix I know this is
effectively something that when
multiplied by a vector you will
basically be producing a series of
scaled you know summed vectors right
those those column vectors these are
effectively the scales that scale each
column of the vector right but if I see
it the other way round if I see it
labeled like this now I know what we're
doing is we're measuring right we're
taking the dot product of something
against it right it's the same operation
same multiplication it's just where what
values did I put in it that determines
what I get out right same you know
matrix math is matrix math but the
values I put in and how I've arranged
them in the matrix determine what I'm
computing obviously and so you can kind
of see that if I'm thinking rows or
thinking columns not sorry thinking
columns are thinking rows that depends
on what this matrix does conceptually so
hopefully that gives you enough of
understanding of why if we go all the
way back here scroll through the
blackboard of why I wrote this because
what I did is I just transpose the
matrix conceptually speaking I wanted to
go backwards so I transpose the matrix
but all of that stuff I just explained
to you now you can see that only works
if these things are orthonormal now I
knew they wouldn't be orthonormal
because we tested scaling right
so when we tested this thing if you
remember we tried making things bigger
or you know not in your first inning but
we kept this angle at 90 degrees right
so what does that do to our matrix right
if I've got an ax ay Y B X B Y matrix
right and I know these things are scaled
right so I know that a has a scale on it
we'll call that I don't even know I hate
having to make up letter names for
things
I'm like so bad at it but anyway so
let's call that M and we'll call this
one n right so now I've taken these
vectors and instead of them being
orthonormal they're still at 90 degrees
to each other there's still orthogonal
vectors but they are not orthonormal
vectors anymore and the reason is
because a is M long and B is M long and
M is not equal to oops 1 and n is not
equal to 1 there's something else right
so now what happens to our fundamental
you by the way I hope everyone was
interested in the matrix thing today
because apparently that's all we're
gonna do I don't know sometimes I get
into it and it's just we're into it at
this point so anyway what does that do
to the fundamental operations we were
trying to do before ok now you can see
immediately why this works for the
forward case because all this m and n do
is they just multiply our U and V out
which is what we wanted right it just
makes it go further ok because what I
get is M u ax and you know plus n v bx m
you a y plus n vb y right all I've done
is just increased the distance I moved
along my vectors instead of going UA
plus VB I am now going mu A plus M VB
that's it
right so the forward transform works
great now let's see what
happens if I transpose this matrix does
it work for me again right does it just
magically work well what would I get if
I transfer this matrix well I have ma X
right but now down here I actually have
n I actually have n B X right and then
up here I have my M a Y and here I have
my n B Y right you can see that's just I
swapped these two right so now when I do
my dot product right so I'm going to dot
product this with something now when I
do my dot product I have a problem
there's a problem here we know the
length of the a vector is 1 if it's just
a but when it's been scaled by M now the
length is M so previously when I was
doing stuff like a transpose P right
which is what this was producing for me
before right
if I had my point I was trying to
measure here and I multiply this out
right now instead of a transpose P I've
got M a transpose P right this is the
value I want a unit length a transposed
with my P but there's this multiple in
there and I don't want that right so how
did I compensate for that in the code do
you remember what I did is I I baked out
the M effectively right I took and I
looked at what the length of a was ahead
of time and then I divided it by that
number right to get it down to be
orthonormal again right I basically made
it back into a unit like vector if that
makes sense so I hacked in some code it
silently hack it in but I mean I
mentally knew that I could compensate
for just the scale and still use the
same trick by effectively turning the
things into orthonormal vectors if that
makes sense so yeah so that was that was
what was going on there
and similarly I think we I'm trying to
think of exactly how we ended up doing
that but I think we yeah we used the
fact that it was squared to do a
division I don't really remember exactly
what we did but point being that is why
it was working for scaled is because I
took advantage of the fact that we could
effectively think about this where the
scale was separate and still do the same
trick now for those of you that want a
little hint of me of linear algebra like
a little bit or why you know what that
would look like if you were being more
formal what you could think of it as is
if I have an a matrix and I want this a
matrix to be orthonormal right because I
want to be able you know I've got
something like this and I want to be
able to do this right and when I do that
I want to be able to do a transpose well
if I've got a matrix that's just it
would be orthonormal except the vectors
in it happen to be scaled then what I
could do is think of that as two
separate matrices I could think of that
as s AP equals P Prime where s is a
scaling matrix and a is an orthogonal
matrix an orthonormal matrix where all
the vectors are orthonormal right so a
is our original matrix and s is just a
matrix that has the scales in it so if
we had here like we were up there we
have the M and the N right then if you
look at what happens to a matrix that
looks like this where it's a diagonal
matrix with just numbers on the diagonal
that acts as something that will scale
other matrices right or vectors that's a
scaling matrix why does it do that well
you can kind of see if I just write it
out if I've got you know my matrix here
a without the scale in it well what do I
produce here well a times M is obviously
M ax right a Y times zero is nothing so
there's no extra term right similarly B
X times M here
where is that right
that's not correct this has to be on the
other side yeah I think I've got this
backwards
in fact I do okay so like I said try not
to make too many mistakes I don't know
that I made any yet but that one was one
so si AAS - we'll explain everything
since we're here so why did I just have
to back that up all right so so far
we've mostly talked about matrices
transforming things singularly well when
you do matrix multiplication it's
actually ordered appended and you know
that's I guess one of the main things
that sort of separates it conceptually
from regular multiplication when you
think about working with it you know if
I if I have a times B and a and B are
both numbers you know it's like flat 5 +
4 whatever B times a is the same thing
right so I can commute the terms in
multiplication and it doesn't matter I
can move them all around in matrix math
sometimes that's the case sometimes it
may be that two matrices can be swapped
and their product will be the same but
in general it's not when you have two
matrices because the multiplication
happens by columns on the second it's by
columns on this guy and by and by rows
on the first guy right mean you saw me
do this multiple times right I line them
up and I do it like this
because of that it matters who's in
which slot right for diagonal matrices
it doesn't matter because you're always
gonna produce the same terms on the
diagonal they're always gonna just pick
out the exact same things but for all
the off diagonal elements it will differ
potentially depending on the structure
of the matrices right so actually these
two things are different if I scale here
or scale here I get a different result
and if you've ever worked with 3d
graphics before even if you didn't
understand matrices that well you kind
of have found this to be true of
transforms if you've looked at an
equation like this where I do ASP the
scale happens to P 4
and then the rotation of a whereas the
other way round happens here first a
first pin is rotated by a then it is
scaled right and those are two very
different geometric operations if you
think about it right if I was to take
and start with a point P right and I was
to apply a scale to that point right you
know maybe out to here or something like
this and then I was to rotate the point
around if that makes sense right
I might get a very different result
if the scale is non-uniform right if the
scale was uniform which I guess I kind
of drew so I should I should draw a
non-uniform scale so let's say I'm gonna
scale along this axis at only this axis
right so the scale is very non-uniform
if I do that and then rotate I'm gonna
get something very different than if I
rotate and then do that scale right so
if I was to have a scale that was I'm
out of time darn son all right well
anyway so that actually is captured by
the matrix map and you were about to see
it happen there so I'm gonna do it again
for you
now that I've explained what's going to
happen so it's not going to be too
confusing right so let's say I have my
scale matrix em em this time two M's and
then my my a matrix right well now I'm
okay I get em ax and BX and I get em a Y
and B Y right that was equivalent to the
thing I was about to draw there which is
like hey if I just scale everything
uniformly then the point ends up in the
same place because it doesn't matter
whether I rotate first and then scale or
scale first and then rotate because
they'll put me in the same place that is
captured by the matrix math and you can
see it since the MS will multiply
everybody the same it doesn't matter
where I was I could flip these two guys
around right do the exact same operation
in the reverse order doesn't matter
right I still just get em ax and BX ma Y
M dy right it's the exact same thing but
if I actually wanted to reproduce the
thing I was talking about with a
nonlinear scale right so when there's m
and n I can't do that anymore if I try
to do it at the head end right then I
end up with the problem I had before I
and that I you know again it's like I
said I'm pretty rusty at these sorts of
things so you can understand why I
didn't catch it till actually so it
happened I was like wait and I was like
oh right that's supposed to happen
that's the whole point of matrix math a
lot of times anyway so you can see in
this case I get ma X and then 0 a Y
right I get em B X here zero for the B Y
term I get a X drops out the N a Y and n
B Y right and that's no good that's not
what I wanted right you can see that
that scale what I wanted was mg R and
here but instead I got M's here and here
right now if I do it the other way round
now I get what I wanted right I get ma X
right 0 times BX I get NB x here right
then I get ma Y and and B Y and that's
what I actually wanted
so anyway getting back to it what I was
saying was in this case you can kind of
see that if I wanted to split these up I
could now I have to be careful and I was
sloppy before like I said getting rusty
but I can split them up I can split up a
non-uniform scaled but orthogonal so
still right angle pair of vectors I can
split them up into a scale and the unit
vectors and then I have an easier
problem so if I know
that I've got a s P equals P Prime right
and I know that this is this one happens
to be orthogonal so a inverse equals a
transpose right then I can invert this
much more straightforward and it's the
trick idea before but you can see how
it's going to work right first I
multiply both sides by a inverse so I
get a inverse a SP equals a inverse P
Prime right well what do I know about a
inverse a gets the identity matrix so
I'm just left with s P equals a inverse
P Prime
right same thing with s so I multiply
both sides by s inverse right and now I
get P equals s inverse a inverse P Prime
okay this we already know it's a
transpose we just said that was true so
the only problem we have is how do we
compute s inverse well we can use the
exact same trick I used before right if
I know that I've got some scale values M
an n right this is my S matrix right I
want some matrix I don't know what it is
right
I want something so that when I look at
the terms that are produced I get one
right I get the identity matrix ones on
the diagonal zeros everywhere else well
it's not that hard to figure this out
even by inspection right if I want this
to be one well this is a zero so that
means it doesn't matter what's in there
at least not for this term so I just
need to put something here that makes M
equal one well I just told you what that
was up there
welcome to Cove inverse right 1 over m
done okay
same difference here right zero times n
write this term falls out
what's the N well it's just gonna be 1
over n right so I know already that my
term is just it's just a really trivial
matrix it's just 1 over m 1 over N zeros
and zeros right and you can see how that
multiplies out to the 1 1 1 right so
when you have a scale matrix 2
the scale matrix you just have to invert
all the diagonal elements because
there's no cross terms right there's
nothing in anywhere else so it's set
effectively what you could say is in
order to do this I really just have to
do this and I'm done and that's exactly
what I did I just did it in my head kind
of when we were doing it I think I
explained it geometrically but this is
the actual matrix math that happened
okay so now we finally get to the thing
that I guess will now have to wait to
Monday for us to actually do because I
am out of time but we don't have a
matrix like that we don't have a matrix
that's separable into Si and the reason
is because while the scale might be
separable just fine the a is not
orthonormal right it's not so since we
don't have orthogonal vectors we don't
have cosine theta equals one or zero in
all of our terms we can't use a inverse
equals a transpose so what we're
actually going to have to do next week
to fix the bug is we're actually going
to have to invert the matrix for real we
have to take the a matrix and invert it
now thankfully it's a two-by-two matrix
that's a really easy matrix to invert we
don't have to won't even have to use
like a linear algebra assistance package
or any sort or an iterative solver or
anything like that we'll be able to just
directly do it out algebraically and
it'll be fine
but that's what we actually need to do
and when we do that I think then we will
get what we need for doing our texture
mapping properly that was a lot to drop
on you so let's go ahead and go to the
Q&amp;A and guess people have questions
because I realized we kind of got all
the way into it there
you've got some salty dogs what does
that mean
what are salty dogs
and yeah anyway I guess while I'm
waiting to see if there are any
questions which I don't know if there
are or not but that's like I said that's
really basic linear algebra stuff it
gets a lot cooler but if that sort of
thing is that all interesting to you
then you would you will love linear
algebra because there's just tons and
tons and tons of that you know really
cool it like you know especially if
you've used matrices and you haven't
learned really leage it yet so you kind
of we're using them a little above your
comfort level of really knowing what was
going on I I mean I at least speak from
my experience 20 years ago or whenever
it was at this point it's just really
rewarding to go learn how it all works
because then it's very empowering and
you don't have to they're not black
boxes anymore you can just you know
totally get what's going on and it just
really helps you know so yeah
uh I don't know if I knew or not that we
would have to do reverse mapping I
probably I mean that that we would have
to use do skew vector reverse mapping I
suspect that I probably said something
like we aren't really going to be
skewing things so we want to do is I
probably even said that on the stream
but hey we ended up skewing them so it's
not a big deal it's it's really I
probably should just have inverted the
matrix but sometimes I have mater I
avoid doing certain math things so that
we don't have to get into them at
inappropriate times because you know it
is an educational stream so if I can do
something using only tools that we've
already learned and I don't feel like
it's a good time to really attack a
particular topic then I don't do the gun
to it oh yeah my elbow is um it's it's
actually fine it's just one of the
things that happens usually when you're
rock climbing is it's really easy to
accidentally scrape you know scrape some
skin and have it be a little bloody
especially on like the elbow or other
places where there's not a lot of fat
there it's like it's not really
cushioned you know it's just like right
against the bone and so a lot of times
when you're climbing especially if you
screw up or you know or aren't paying
enough attention about what you're doing
you'll scrape something and so I had to
it was a little bloody so I had to kind
of stick um I had to just stick a gauze
on it so I didn't I didn't want to blood
stain to anything but it's not bad it's
just a little it's just a braided
so it looks like we don't have any
questions so that's good so everyone
just understands it all if I gave a
basic matrix math quiz everyone will
pass everyone will pass with flying
colors
Lord Marshal other than transpose do you
need much more from linear from linear
from linear algebra yeah I mean so I
guess what I would say is like linear
algebra and also geometric algebra if
you want to be like with the cool kids
now both of them there's I don't know
hundreds of valuable things you can
learn for game programming in them I
mean there's just linear algebra is is
almost in some sense a field created
entirely for solving things on computers
like I mean that's not really true but
it's it's kind of that way it's like
basically solving giant numerical
problems is specifically what linear
algebra was made for and so you know
when you're a computer programmer it's
hard to imagine not finding useful
things studying linear algebra like
pretty much you know I mean and I mean
everything like the people who won the
Netflix prize right the the thing for
trying to figure out what people will
rate an X flicks movie given a database
of prior ratings right is tons of linear
algebra the singular value decomposition
turned out to be a very important part
of solving the Netflix fly prize if I
remember correctly so it's not it does
not even games
it's not even graphics it's everything
like if you have problems on a computer
that involve you know more than one or
two variables linear algebra right so
compression statistics
yeah large data data mining it's all
linear algebra like it's not all the
nodules like that's all you need it's
like but if the underpinnings are all
you need the
algebra always so it's it's really hard
to it would be really hard to study too
much linear algebra like it's all really
very useful
there Marshall we had one example from
my linear algebra book class in the book
that used computers was surprised to see
it in there yeah I wish math classes
taught math with computers a little more
probably but you know I mean like
everything else linear algebra is
conceptual so you're trying to learn the
conceptual parts the solving of it is
not that interesting right it's the
understanding what this the actual steps
are that you can use and then you know
you solving matrices by hand as complete
waste of time
right and hopefully math classes have
gotten passed ever doing that because no
scientist that I know ever solves their
matrices by hand anymore right can you
know once you know how to work at all
you you know you've you've worked it out
all symbolically and then the computer
does the work
and yeah I would agree with Sean McGrath
on the fact that math papers should be
published with C source code I always
find that code is clearer than math
usually I feel like a lot of times
people have to torture stuff to put it
into math for him but have I seen
Gilbert Strang his lectures on linear
algebra I have seen some I watched like
a couple of his intro to linear nature
ones just because I learned linear
algebra from his book his intro to
linear algebra book so I just thought it
was fun to see I wanted to see what he
sounded like or whatever but I haven't
really watched any appreciable amount of
I just kind of like watched the first
one or two just to see
delicious you suggest students not
knowing how to solve linear algebra
problems by hand well let me be clear
what I mean on that because I guess that
could be taken two different ways what I
mean is I don't think you should be
numerically solving linear algebra
problems right I mean you should know
how you might do that but doing it is a
complete waste of your time right that's
what a computer is for what you do want
to know how to be able to do by hand is
the sort of stuff that I'm doing here
right you want to know how to be able to
manipulate symbolically things so that
you can solve equations that you need to
solve but once you've done it like once
you've said oh this is gonna be in a
inverse here and I know that it's not
gonna so I need a real inverse you know
blah blah blah you know don't invert the
matrix yourself because there's you can
just ask mathematic up two and four if
the matrix for you and then you know you
won't make any mistakes right so you
know I don't I don't think students
should be sitting around doing menial
math chores
if there isn't a like conceptual point
to it then it just seems wrong to me
because what are they gaining you know
Jesse Meyer would you consider using C++
templates for matrices say in 3d
programming in 3d programming it's
usually not necessary because there
aren't that many permutations of what
you want to do so typically the argument
for doing something with templates is if
you have a lot more like like if you
were doing more types of sizes so let's
say that you weren't doing 3d
programming you just had like a bunch of
major stars it was four by three ten by
ten six by nine whatever you know maybe
then it makes some sense I don't really
like templates because they're super
janky and bad so I tend not to use them
but if you don't mind the jank unis then
you know then that's what they're made
for
in fact you know so they they if you can
put up with the jank
alright looks like we are done alright
thank you everyone for joining me for
the episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always peer to the game on
handmade here org it comes with a source
code so you can play around with it and
over the weekend if you want now that
I've explained exactly what you need to
do to fix the bug
you could try fixing the bug yourself
see how you do all right
we also a forum site you can go to if
you want to ask questions you have
patreon page go to fourth video series
we have a schedule bot that you can use
to find out when we're going to be live
and we have an episode guide and that
episode guide can teach you things about
the past anything that you've missed on
handmade hero you can get there that's
about it for today I will be back
probably next week sometime I don't know
I haven't posted schedule yet take a
look that schedule about if you want to
know until then have fun programming
have a good weekend and I'll see you
guys on the Internet
take it easy everyone