okay thank you everyone for joining me
it's time for handmade here we had a
relatively long question-and-answer
session today that's just how it goes
sometimes but we're all good now I
started the timer I restarted the timer
so hopefully we'll still get roughly two
hours of programming it anyway I here's
what we're doing today last weekend we
finished our font importing and so that
we could have everything flow through
the art pipeline and we we kind of have
everything working now but we've got
like here's what I would say we finished
everything but we haven't really
polished anything in the system and so
there's still a lot of persnickety nough
stew it and there's some things that we
probably want to fine-tune and there's
stuff we want to do right it's re cetera
so I think what we want to do now is we
want to kind of like put ourselves in a
good sort of incubating situation where
we can work with the code a little bit
improve it you know get to a point where
we're happy with it and so that we can
clean out the cobwebs of what we've
created now having to do a bunch of work
with this asset importing and there's
sort of two sides to that one is that I
think we need to improve just the
handling of the assets on the game side
and so for doing that what I want to do
is just like increase the load the
cognitive load on that part of the code
now and say what if we want to add our
ground cover that we wanted to add a
ground cover back in let's add furniture
in the orphanage let's try getting the
orphans correct so which orphans are
which and all that stuff let's put a hat
on the hero these sorts of things and so
that's going to be a pretty major push
and that'll clean up I think a couple
parts of the asset system one is that we
can decide like how we're gonna like
standardize on the different grid
importing methods and stuff like this
and then another is like how the
entities query which assets they're
using and stuff like that so you know
we've got we can really like now now
that we kind of have all the pieces
working together we could really push to
make it all work right and and see how
each each thing at each decision has
effects on the parts of the pipeline so
that we can actually make intelligent
choices therefore the final you know for
the final blessed version the other
thing that I think we want to do is just
clean up some of the asset system code
so what I've seen with the way that we
did things and I meant I put some - dues
in the code about this is I really don't
like the way that we do our updating
right now because I feel like we could
consolidate it right now we're doing a
lot of individual checking so we do an
import and then we look at all these
things say like did this change did that
change right and what I'd rather do I
think is I'd rather do something more
along the lines of when we do a tag
import we build a completely new data
block for the HHA file for each hij file
and then when we are done right so when
we when we finish the entire import all
we do is compare the data block to the
old data block and if it's different we
rewrite it if it's the same we don't
write I think that's a much cleaner way
to do this because like right now if you
look at the way the code is working
we're classically having to manually do
checks to see whether we need to update
something in the HHA and not only does
that produce just a lot of code we have
to maintain but it's just it's just
error-prone right because it means that
in addition to the code that imports
things we also have the code that dips
things and both can fail whereas if we
just had it you know if we just did
something where we put here is the final
block this is exactly what it has to be
it's trivial for us to just run a mem
comp on that and the old block to know
if anything changed and it can never be
wrong right
so that
would offload a huge amount of that work
on to one centralized easy to make
correct function that doesn't have to be
maintained and then that way we only
ever have to focus on making sure that
we import correctly and that's it so I
think that's a much better way to go and
it's just like you know because of the
way the code evolved we didn't think
about that or didn't implement that way
that's a head end but there's no reason
we can't kind of extract that part out
and do it because it's not that
complicated right it's not that hard to
imagine that thing it's not like we have
to rewrite all the code we could do it
pretty straight it's more about just
removing code really and then pushing it
to the end so that's really what we want
to do here now which of those things
we're doing and why and when well who
knows but I don't really care which
order we do them in so I'm just gonna
just go and we have to let it happen I
suspect we will probably focus more on
the diffing part of things first and the
reason for that is because I think where
we left it last week was just realizing
that you know if we pull in fonts we
sometimes get in weird situations where
like you know we don't really even have
a way to delete a font right now and
stuff like that because deletion doesn't
really work in our system at the moment
we don't have things to check to see if
you never saw an asset remove it from
the HHA right right and again that's
something that would just work if we
were dipping the block because when you
imported that one would be missing so
when you dipped with the old block it'd
be like no these are different rewrite
it right it would still leave the data
in the old thing but that's okay we
don't care if we leave date extra data
in the H at J's cuz everything works
even if there's extra data right so and
then you always know that before you
ship the game you could do a rebuild
which would eliminate any text you know
extraneous data that was sitting around
in there so that would all work well and
I think it's just yeah that all seems
like good to me so I suspected that's
probably the first thing we should do
assuming that I'm remembering correctly
that we were currently having a problem
with specifically the the fact that we
couldn't delete or that the fonts
weren't being like recognized properly
or something like that I'm gonna go
ahead and make sure that I'm not wrong
about that so I'm gonna open up remedy
here and remind myself of where we
actually you know stopped because I
don't I don't remember but yet like
right we there was some kind of problem
where like the fonts you know tags we're
not working properly or stuff like this
right and so I think that that's a good
excuse to maybe make this stuff or
improve this stuff a little bit because
I've yeah I'm pretty sure that that that
the way we've got it now you know have
some issues there all right so let me go
ahead and open up the hand made here a
project I also want to open up for the
moment the there's the tags file the
tags that are in question here so we've
got two tags files there's liberation
mono this one was working just fine but
then we also had Segoe and if I remember
correctly this one wasn't so you know
they're both the same effectively they
both have the one hundred and six Tests
glyph set that we specified they're
largely the same you know one has
slightly different values here but
otherwise they're the same right I and
so you know it's different pings and one
than the other obviously but otherwise
you know no real difference between
these two and then if I go over to the
hht file sorry I load the hht file out
of the text file for the base game which
is where this this is you can see that
we have a pound include for each of
these and in one case where pound
including Segoe UI no hhd in another
case we're paddling liberation mono dot
hht if I remember correctly liberation
melody she works just fine fonts ago
thht did not work fine that we didn't
really have any explanation for this
right there was nothing like we don't
know why that didn't work and so we kind
of have to figure out like what did we
screw up here so let's go down that road
a little bit and in so doing if we feel
like the need we maybe we'll start on
some of that cleanup that I was talking
about as well
so the first thing I'd like to do is I
want to kind of see you know what was
happening in the code here I'm assuming
that we do go down this fonts to go down
hht path because if you know if I look
at the handmade source directory here up
sorry tags directory rather what we see
is that in the fonts directory there is
you know this file does exist right
Segoe UI dat hht so the fact that we're
not getting anything here I don't really
understand why that would be the case so
I kind of want to step through and find
out why obviously we know that there's
when we go in here to the watch window
[Music]
I'm assuming that the font ID just comes
back at zero right well no that's that's
odd oh well you know what this is not
debug mode though so we don't really
know to what extent those inspections
would be accurate so let me just go
ahead and do a debug build and then we
can we should be able to see more
explicitly what is happening so if I run
this here we should be able to see
what's going on inside get font info it
looks like when we pull the asset out I
don't actually know what the ID is here
but I'm guessing it's zero
yeah so the problem that we get is
exactly the problem that we expected to
get which is to say that when we call
get best match asset it cannot find the
font now I'm gonna go ahead and start
right in there and I want to verify that
the problem is that there are no fonts
or something similar right so here's us
trying to get this asset and you can see
that it basically says there's no assets
that are labeled as being a font right
so the you know the code that we use to
do that was itself busted if I go into
the import place the import and we
search for where the the font asset type
is being specified you see here here it
is this is the location where the asset
HHA type is specified right here
and if we look I mean one of the things
you could you could see about this too
is it's really indirect right if I go to
update single asset metadata right here
and take a look at it what you can see
is there's this kind of roundabout
method that this is going through as
well where the tags type ID has to have
that in it and that import grid tag is
part of things is I think the extra tags
part that's getting set here right so
we've got two separate places that are
setting these sorts of data this one's
setting the data to say this is a font
as far as the type is concerned this is
the category it's a font again not
thrilled with how any of that stuff is
working there's like multiple ways that
so you can see why this like spending
some time to clean this up I feel like
it'd be worth it anyway assuming both of
those things are set properly this this
comes in here should set the asset type
at this time question is is that tag
actually added here or not because I
don't even know the answer to that
question so let me go ahead and jump to
end tags and see so it looks like it is
which means that this extra tags should
actually now contain the tag for the
font which means that when it's actually
written out at least in theory the font
should get the tags that it's supposed
to have for that type so if I go back
and look at that we do a tag count here
to see whether the tags differ again
this is code that I would prefer not to
have had right I would like the code to
be cleaner than that certainly and this
is why I want do kind of bulk testing so
we know this sort of thing isn't a
problem but anyway when we do a thing to
see if the tags differ then we run
through and we actually like combine all
of these tags you can see us combining
the the first tag set comes from this
right second tag set comes from this so
when we do that we in theory
[Music]
we in theory would just append these it
looks
looks pretty reasonable to me I don't
see anything particularly weird right
and then we just end up with the
combined tag set I don't really know
what we pass asset and then there well I
kind of do I guess we pass asset and
done there because we don't really want
this thing to add the tag again we've
already put in the type tag right so
then we end up in here and we're like
alright we'll store these tags out off
we go
everything should get saved and then
we're done right so I'll be honest I
don't really see why that wouldn't have
worked I suppose it could be that there
was some kind of a dip that occurred and
the diff didn't end up working that's
certainly possible what I would like to
do is check because since we have the
ability to see what's going on in our
data files let's just do that if I use
HHA edit what you can see is there's a
dump here right so I can do HHA edit
dump base game HHA and I can pipe that
to base game dot txt if I then do the
tab view of that here's what I get
looking at it if I just open up the
assets you can kind of see that like
alright the first thing that's packed is
the font these are all the bitmaps they
don't have any types because they're
just looked up by name later by index
later so after all of this stuff is
ingested we should see the font itself
what's really interesting is I don't
actually see the font at all right right
like I don't see the font there
so I think that's excuse me that just
indicates a problem further up the
stream it seems like what's going on
here is this either this failed right so
we never entered in here but if that
happened we should have probably it
would have failed out entirely I think
but maybe that's not true because this
is a pound include right so it could be
that we failed out in here this is what
one excuse me sort of not particularly
great aspect is that we can't really
view the errors if we never launch the
game right like I don't have a good way
of launching the errors here so it kind
of would have been nice to be able to
see errors that were happening in the
actual dump like maybe embedded in the
file or something like that which we
sort of have per asset but not as a more
global thing right so I wonder if we
should add to our HHA just a thing
that's like here's the last error dump
that might be a nice thing but for now
let's just assume hey something happened
bad here what happened exactly in terms
of writing the asset data we don't
really know what happened here when we
did update asset update single asset
metadata I mean I don't think we really
we really couldn't get through here
without reserving an asset so it sure
seems anyway because these are
contiguous just looking at these right
there's not like an empty space either
so it just seems to me like this must
have failed and we just didn't know so
like there's a parse error like in this
file or something right and we just
don't know about it or something like
that and I'm not sure what that error
would be but that seems like the case so
I'm just gonna step into it and see if I
can figure out what that is and again
like normally we can see errors in the
little log window but since we can't the
the debug foss the one thing that can't
fail because if the debug font fails to
pack we can't
the error because it's in that window
right which is why I say maybe we need
to back up away because there is one
thing that can fail that we can't print
out the errors for if I break on par
spot block I want to look and see what
actually happens here in terms of errors
if we go through and parse stuff let's
see that was a little bit weird what was
the first thing we passed there I'm
gonna start that again I didn't see what
that actually parsed let's double check
as we go to do we get the right glyph
count and everything yep 106 so we're
gonna get a token here let's just see
what it is
it's tags so it should get parsed in
here all right that should eat it up uh
then we get our next token we got a
sender height that should eat just fine
to sender height external letting and
then we should see glyphs right all
looks good so those cliffs look like
they're parsing just fine we can we can
set a breakpoint on the horizontal
advance table make sure that all works
ok looks like it's working ok and then
we'll jump down here here's our parsing
and so we did fail right like the
parsing did fail and the question is why
did the parsing fail so let's take a
look at the tokenizer is error stream
here and just see what what was the
problem I don't know if we can jump
right to this but we'll try here's the
last thing yeah unfortunate just like
you know just gonna be like a
pretty basic error let's see what the
contents are here tags font how can I
see the rest of this ago there's a -
okay interesting so if we go we're gonna
find a negative and it looks like we did
not support that so if I search for
negative first of all those values are
complete garbage so we've got some kind
of like an a bad like overflow printout
problem which we can go to bug but
negative kearns well they're not really
legal in our system to be honest because
that would mean you're going backwards
which you can't really do negative
currents would be fine if we were
talking about the difference between the
character width and how much the current
then you would have negative all the
time but this case you shouldn't really
so I don't know what's causing that but
that that is bad right so what I'd like
to do there is go into just to just to
figure out what's happening with our hht
font like our age HT font why can I not
there is HH font sorry our HH font
program is totally crapping out on
trying to produce some floating-point
print out of these things we don't know
whether the actual value it's computing
is wrong or whether the thing that does
the printing is wrong now I think about
it h HT r HH font is used to see runtime
glabrous the chances the printouts wrong
are like zero because we didn't write it
it's something to tab times of testing
it's probably not that so that means
we're actually filling out this table
incorrectly somehow so we need to go
figure out why we're filling out the
table incorrectly so it's this
horizontal advance table is just wrong
so how is that the case if we look
how it's being filled out currently what
we could do is just search in the file
in general for we're horizontal advanced
is being being updated so you can see
here we allocate a square glyph count of
floats right and then we set the entire
thing to zero so in theory everything
should be a zero at the outset and then
we add in here information from these
pairs that we get back and I guess what
I don't really know is whether those
values can come back as some kind of
special I don't know thing like it could
be that those are coming back as
negative ones or something I'm gonna
search real quickly in Windows to make
sure there isn't anything special when
you know they're but the real thing I
wanna do is step in there and see what
they are but I want to see if there is
there anything in particular that I
should know about in terms of what gets
returned here so this says hey we need
this many of those things that's what we
expect to be doing the kerning pair
comes back as as whatever that is
there's a first a second and an amount
[Music]
so if the value is negative is there
something we're doing that would cause
that to not cast properly I don't think
so because we're taking this is an
integer we're casting it directly to a
float so it's not like it's going
through some unsigned value or some
weird thing that might munge it plus we
were seeing the negative so that
happened so I'm not really sure what
what's going on there
so I'm gonna step in here because I
really can't see what would be happening
there that would be odd and then when we
get down here and we sort of go through
this process we add the kerning change
so I suppose one other thing that could
be true is it could be that the kerning
change is wrong what I don't really know
is why do we structure the if this way
did we mess this up because if you look
at what's happening here it's like we're
gonna add the character advance minus
the kerning change but then we're just
gonna add oh it's a different place
nevermind it's a different place that'll
make sense we add the crane change in
here if the current change was wrong
that's another way we could corrupt it
so maybe we should check that out too
the scale ratio is gonna be applied to
everything so if that was wrong
everything would be wrong not just some
of the kerning values so let's take a
look at what the kerning change is there
here's how that's computed right so
what's happening there
inside kerning change we have pre step X
and MINIX I wonder if what happened is
when we use well I guess we're not using
any scaling though so that shouldn't be
a problem but anyway let's let's just
think it through so if we look at min X
and free step where are those where are
those discussed so pre step is a is an
int and min X is so you know I kind of
feel like this is one of those things
where this happened
when we're doing this doing this
subtraction in integer land is I'm sorry
in is going to happen in unsigned
integer land because integral promotion
will probably turn these into unsigned
int so this is an int and this is an
unsigned int I bet this is a problem of
things getting promoted
- from in unsigned and so I think what
we want to do instead maybe is this
let's just do this in float because we
want our float result anyway so rather
than doing these things in unsigned
integer space when we compute them let's
just compute everything in the target
space so the unsigned int regular int
problem won't rear its ugly head that's
my vote I'm gonna I'm gonna see there's
another issue with this I'm not whatever
isn't sure about pre stepping X I don't
know if that needs to be scaled
differently it may be that this value is
wrong in the scaling case because the
min X versus the pre step X I don't
think so though so anyway we'll give it
a shot
all right and now we can run our HH font
program again the HH font program was
being run on something i don't remember
what it was it's a go UI what did you do
- duze Segoe UI irregular at what font
size was it 20 I want to say anyway
let's give it a shot
I'm gonna go into base game fonts
there's all of our fonts so we're gonna
go ahead and dump this out and if I look
actually also at Segoe UI if I look at
this it's school UI regular and it's I
guess it was 2020 high right because 1
plus 19 is 20 so if I ask for a 20 - 4
Segoe UI regular here's the HH font I'm
gonna say that that's like I don't
actually know where this was but it's
probably like windows fonts Segoe UI
right so we're loading that it's Segoe
UI regular right and then we want 20 the
carrot set is test the destination hht
is going to be W handmade tags
Segoe sorry fonts Segoe UI and the DEF
PNG dirt is gonna be where I am right
now so handmade sources based game fonts
and then I'm going to let that go
now in theory that means now this if I
whoops if I revert this buffer I don't
know if I can actually do that maybe I
can't so we'll kill the buffer and load
a new so now we shouldn't see those
negatives down there I don't think
because we fixed the place where they
were getting computed it correctly and
so that all looks much nicer now right
you can see that it so I think that was
just a case of like doing it in the
wrong space we're doing an unsigned and
we needed to not convert a signed value
to an unsigned value for that
computation for obvious reasons all
right so then if I want to put the tags
in here just to say that it's a debug
font that should get me into happy land
I think let's see if that's true
so here we are in our spot block yeah
and now we can properly parse it so I
think we're good to go now hopefully
anyway I don't actually know if that's
true but yeah ok so we found the font
that time
right so that's good uh all right so
yeah now that frees us up we don't have
to do what I said we're going to do then
we don't have to start working on
cleaning that part of the code up
because it looks like it wasn't an
update problem it was just a case of our
HH font program being busted but now if
I go ahead and run we should have a
fully running system here
and I think this was in the response to
a question is when we originally did
this it was to ask how to do those
ligatures and that's how you do those
ligatures right now looking at our fonts
it looks like our fonts are not
anti-aliasing properly it would be the
other thing I would say and or in there
there's just some issues you can see
with them like I'm gonna go ahead and
zoom in just to show you I'm talking
about hopefully this works on the stream
actually I can look on me on the other
window and see if I turn the magnifier
on and I try to move around the screen
so what you can kind of see is like the
alpha blending on those is just not very
good right and part of that is they're
still going through the path of depth of
doing def peels for n alpha sorting and
stuff like that so I guess there is a
little bit of weirdness happening there
but just in terms of looking at them it
just looks it just looks a little odd to
me it might be that it's just too small
but just you know like that doesn't seem
it seems like the kerning is maybe just
too tight as well it's really hard to
say I'm not sure I could really put my
finger on it but it just looks a little
busted and
[Music]
I guess one problem is I don't know if
this thing does can I make this thing
not filter this thing might filter for
all I know to
that
okay if with that off
[Music]
so it's really hard to say but it just
it looks like the font kerning is off
sometimes I don't know I could be wrong
about that but it just looks a little
off like maybe it's just too a little
too tight like we're removing something
from the font that we shouldn't be or
something like that the other thing I
would say is we're doing currently I
don't know to what extent we're doing
when we're doing linear alpha blending
on these I don't know to what extent
we're properly doing like perceptive
alpha on the edges here but we may need
to tweak the alpha blending if we really
wanted small fonts to look correct as
well but suffice to say that's sort of
all stuff for a different time whether
we ever even care at all looking at it
in here you can you can tell regardless
that you know obviously the font stuff
is working properly now in terms of
loading and selecting and being the
right bitmaps and we even got ligatures
working just fine in there right so that
all seems good I want to undo that
change now of course because I don't
want a proportionally spaced font for my
debug display right that is not what I
want at all so I'm gonna go ahead and
kill this buffer and I'm gonna go back
to the base game and I'm gonna swap
which one of those I'm doing there and
then I'm just gonna save that and rerun
and I don't actually know because like I
said doesn't remove fonts so I'm not
sure about that but yeah it looks like
it picked the new font just fine right
and that allows us to still have our
properly because remember we were using
the the fixed width of the font to make
sure that stuff lined up properly right
[Music]
all right so we probably want to stop
the music test as well here well I don't
know maybe we don't but for the moment I
think we probably want to stop the music
test I don't really want that playing
all the times can drive me nuts so I'm
gonna go ahead and turn that guy down so
that's this code right here I'm just
gonna take that and if that out we can
if it back in if we need to test the
music some more but for now not so much
and now we can start to look at some
other aspects of things right so here's
some stuff that what I was trying to say
like the the first thing that I think we
want to look at is just be some basic
tag stuff so if I look at what's going
on in the game here you know and and the
dudes like walking around or whatever if
there's like there's two main things I
want to do right off the bat and then a
third one that we want to get to
eventually so all right I don't know
what why this room is stone when this is
in an outside room someone want to tell
me what's going on there I thought this
room was supposed to be like the garden
or something why is it a stone floor
does anyone know did we set that to a
stone floor for some unknown reason we
still have the grass in here right like
am I wrong about that all right so we've
got we have another bug here our stone
floor is our grass floor is not working
right we have stone only these this
should be grass here right some of these
rooms were supposed to be stone floor I
think like like these but the other one
says we grass so we've got some tag
problem that's happening in the base
game so that's the first thing I want to
find out because I don't know what's
going out that so here's our blocks that
are defined here we've got a forest
block so here's the stone block right
and here's the
the grass block and for some reason it
looks like we're not ever picking that
grass block right I mean that's that's
what it looks like to me so the forest
the Black Forest oh one bitmap is never
selected and I don't really know why so
so let's take a look at where that's
actually happening inside I think it's
inside the room Jen code when we want to
do like grass you can see here that we
do aspect like are we outdoors or not
this is working properly as far as you
can tell this is not so the grass tag
this thing for whatever reason is is
just not actually being selected for I
guess unless something else is going
wrong there now the block forest oh one
dot PNG block orphanage o3 like that
stuff I'm assuming that's lined up
properly because we we are like we we in
theory well here's a question for you
we didn't look at the airs we probably
should write so I don't see any errors
in there right if I saw some errors in
there then I would say maybe we're
getting a problem with the errors but
we're not seeing any problems with the
errors right uh so if we look in here
and say what is actually happening with
our tagged grass why isn't that working
first thing I want to do is look at that
dump we already have one so I might as
well make use of it right if I look at
the assets and I just ignore the font
for now and we go down here to see like
what else we've got
so here's the forest block and here's
the orphanage block I'm going to look at
what tags are in here and also on the
one that we're actually picking which is
the stone one I think that's that this
one here right yeah so you can see they
both have the same basic category so
they shouldn't be preferred and they
should they should all be checked we
have both of them have a floor tag one
of them says it's man-made stone one of
them says it's grass
right I think that's exactly what they
should say so I'm not sure why we
wouldn't pick one or the other
I'm gonna go look at the env code and
see what is actually happening there
when we go to do the selection process
did we forget something
I don't know so what's gonna happen when
we do this inside here we are inside the
render group here's where we're
rendering the pieces when we go ahead
and try to access the best matched
bitmap we use match vector weight vector
you can see the way this is working is
we go through each of the the tags that
the entity has on it we set the weight
of that thing and off we go now hmm this
code looks a little oh no it has a tag
after month so for the entire tag count
we go through setting these things here
is the tag series two tags value and we
set the weight of that thing to one that
should give us an appropriate match I
would think so I'm not sure why we're
not getting that let's go ahead and
check and see I'm gonna just to speed
things up a little here I'm gonna say
why don't we go ahead and look when we
pull out one of the tags I'm gonna see
if it's tags grass and if it is I'm
gonna make this stop right trying to
give another way to do this oh you know
what I'll do
there you go so what am I do here is I'm
just making a synthetic line of code
that I can break on but I know the
optimizer can't really optimize out
particularly effectively I mean it still
kind of could use a conditional move or
something but I'm hoping it won't so let
me go into the entity code well I guess
I'll just set a breakpoint by name is
probably faster than hunting for the
file so update and render entities run
through so here we are let's go into the
code and set a breakpoint on that code
right there
when we get down here we should now be
in a situation where the ID is grass oh
and I should build in T bug mode because
again I don't really want us to ruggle
with trying to view all of our stuff in
debugging there so off we go oh I should
have thought of that I wouldn't have to
do this extra thing I could have just
put into y equals 5 or something because
we're in debug mode all right so anyway
if I look at the ID it's a it's a grass
tag so if I look at the match vector
right here's the match vector these have
to get shrunk they're huge
right this is this is not gonna be
sustainable but anyway here's the match
vector so we've got 18 19 and 20 are all
set so one is going to be the facing
Direction one is gonna be the idle and
and those are well to be honest I'm not
sure why idle get set every time but
because it shouldn't that get onset
sometimes and that ones that's a little
confusing anyway it doesn't matter so
when we're actually matching those we've
got some here and those are fine
those'll those will do whatever their is
they're gonna do and then we're gonna
set the grass 1 the tag count here
really should just be there should only
be two tags so let's let's see it set
the grass up here it should be somewhere
there we go
[Music]
so there's the grass and so these three
things are all set in the vector that we
want to match which are what exactly
actually let's take a look so those are
[Music]
floor and idle idle is flying again
because nobody has that in floors anyway
so it doesn't matter so it's grass and
floor which exactly what should be get
set and then facing direction of course
was set so that's all fine and then here
we should presumably why don't you say
this oh you don't know what this idea is
what is this ID man-made
so this looks just like a bug in the
room generator are we setting the
man-made tag on everything because if it
ain't man-made that that's not a bug
yeah all right so we don't really want
to say that these are man-made so that's
why I was picking it is because we were
saying it had to be man-made which it
doesn't have to be and of course there
is no man-made grass at the moment so
there was nothing to pick so I think
that was the only problem we had there
and I don't know why that didn't show up
before but probably it had something to
do with the way that that we were
matching tags and had set them in order
or something weird like that
but that's just a general book generic
bug that we have in the actual room
gencode so in theory if I go back here
now I should see grass again yeah all
right so I'm glad we fixed that so our
current our current issues right like I
was saying before so if we take a look
at how all the stuff is is panning out
what we want to do here is we want
outdoor you know doesn't look like grass
right so we want to be able to put
ground cover on here so it looks more
like an outdoorsy kind of a scene we
want to put some trees in here as well
in addition we want to go ahead and in
here and add like furniture right and
then we also want to do like some
tagging of the of the orphans properly
which we can't do at the moment either
so we have a bunch of stuff we want to
do for pulling in assets and making it
easy to like place things around the
world that are based on which assets we
were trying to place there so that's
what I'd like to sort of focus on on now
and you know we sort of have like three
waves right we've got that I want to
clean up that asset system diffing of it
and then I think at that point we're
probably into lighting land where we've
got to sort of go in and simplify and
then more universalize lighting because
remember
the lighting is only sort of in there
temporarily now we can see sort of the
lighting region and it's good like I
like the look that it adds but it's just
not there yet it's too slow and we need
to start sampling on sprites as well
right now we don't sample the lighting
on sprite so it's kind of nonsensical
like you know if you look these are way
too bright right they should be dim
right now because you could see like how
that's working right so that's I think
where we're at I'll start off by sort of
looking at what we can sort of slowly
start to bring in here um you know maybe
furniture is a good start I don't know
but we've got a bunch of stuff we might
want to do so let's let's just just go
if I look at our sources and I go into
base game inside the art directory one
things that you can see here is that the
we've got like items right we've got
obstacles and I think we have covers
well in your somewhere I thought we did
anyway yeah and cover so you can see
here there's like ground cover on a
sprite sheet that we might want to
figure out how to use to like make the
grassy area that's gonna be a little
more complicated because we need to do
something that like scatters that around
and draws it and stuff a more simpler
version would be like we could add hats
right so this is a hat that can go on
some somebody same here's a Baker's hat
right and so if we wanted to put the hat
in here's a flower right similar to a
hat just the thing that can go on
someone's head so if we wanted to start
bringing like items in for that matter
that would be kind of a good thing to
start doing maybe could try putting
those on people and the other thing is
is this we've got the obstacles these
are things that could just get plopped
down sort of just like scatter around
the environment and can create like you
know you can't move on
squared not all also isn't a great term
potentially because like some of them
like this rug you know there's no it's
not an obstacle really like there's no
reason you can't hop along the rug so
it's not an obstacle it's more like
decor make sense so it's hard to say but
you know we can we can cross that bridge
when we come to it so looking at this
right and again it's windows does a
really bad job at displaying these if I
loaded up into to you can sort of
get a better feel for what we're
actually talking about here but here is
here's what we actually so you know
there's something like tables and you
know a couch or whatever right and lamps
or things like that floor lamp a table
lamp whatever right chair uh and so
those are those are things you want to
be able to place individual instances of
when we do a room Jen we want to like
scatter furniture around it right and so
this seems like an interesting problem
we have to figure out how we want to do
it with our asset system the first thing
I would say is we probably when when
these things are getting imported it's
not clear to me that we don't just want
to tag like every cell separately right
because they're looking at this there's
no like rhyme or reason to it I mean we
could try to say like chairs go in one
file or chairs or one thing and you know
sofas or another pet who cares right it
doesn't really make a lot of sense as to
how we would want these things to be
broken up and so I don't know the other
question I have is like do we want these
to just be in their own files like
should they just be split off and not be
imported as a grid worth of things and
again I don't really know we can
certainly extend our assets our assets
sort of information if you will we can
certainly
that to say let allow me to tag each
individual cell separately and maybe
that's the best way to go but I don't
have a lot of other I don't have much
else to say
yeah I don't really have a whole lot
else to say about that so I guess for
now what we'll do is we'll just make
there be you know in here in the hht
file if we look at one of these things I
don't know we've got characters and junk
like that if we were to start adding
here's you know where we would add that
so if I wanted to add like obstacles
forests and obstacles Orphanage so let's
just say that those were gonna be
something we were gonna add and what I
do is I'm gonna put them at the top of
the file in fact I'm gonna put them like
all the way at the top of the file for
now and what I want to do here is I want
to make it so well I you know what I
guess I don't really have to because I
can just set a breakpoint on that on
obstacles as a type so you know if we
look at obstacles at the moment there's
really no difference I don't think for
obstacles or cover or anything else
they're just gonna be straightforward
grid imports you know and so the
question is just if I want to do tags
equals something I'm just thinking well
you know I could do it this way where I
just like talk about individual like
places where the tags line up if I was
to open this up so I say okay you know
open this up
I can like tag each individual one of
these things based on like which grid
cell it's in you know and I don't
actually know if we've got any way of
quantifying that exactly okay I don't
see a template for that either
so if I was to drag this over here and
just do a couple of them so you know
here's one of them so I can see which
grid cell it's in right we could make a
grid that would sort of align these
things together I don't know
I'm just not feeling it
I don't think this is a good idea I
think these should be separate files so
I'm just gonna say that's what we're
gonna do so if I wanted to make these
separate files and what I'm gonna do is
say like we've got chairs or something
right or furniture sets like these
things should go together so that we
have like you know for a particular set
we know that you know this and this go
together or something like that so if
we're trying to make like a thing where
they're the same textile or something we
could do that and similarly like you
know yeah like if we had like different
styles of rug they would go together so
you could pick like a variant but I
don't really want one I don't I don't
like that these are all together because
it's just I'm not sure what advantage
that would ever give us you don't need
to edit them at the same time because
they're not really related in any
meaningful way you know what I mean so I
just I don't I'm not feeling it I don't
think we want to actually do that and
the same is probably true for the ground
cover to a certain extent like we
probably want to just have it be that
each file for something like ground
cover is just a bunch of random versions
of the same ground cover so that you
load it in and you just use that as any
one of these is interchangeable or
something right so I don't know that's
my feeling on it and I would say that
that means that if I was to open up one
of the item templates so this thing
right
we've got like floor state and warring
and stuff like that
so what I want to do is say look these
directional things are still gonna be
there and instead these are just
variants going off the side right so you
know if I want to load one of these
things in what I would do is just say
okay like give me this give me this
thing and I'm gonna paste it in here
right
and I'm gonna stick it up into there
like so and so that's the chair facing
that way and then you know maybe like
someone can read could redraw this as
well facing like all the directions so
that we would have different ways of
like placing those or whatever of course
I can't see it cuz the is sort of
there we go
let me just duplicate this layer out a
bit so if I wanted to make another one
of these I could do like transform
rotate ah wrong one right and and it's
not correct but like so then Anna could
go draw these so that there's they're
probably properly facing all the
different directions but this will at
least let us test it for now why does it
happen
alright this way
all right uh so now we have all the
different ones let turn off layer
boundaries because I don't care what the
layer boundaries are and I'm just going
to place these inside the grid cells to
which they are bound
don't really know how to even that out
yeah I do fear that these are maybe not
leaving enough empty space around them
but that's okay
we should really add that padding that
should have really been our problem not
not the artists all right
so like if you imagine that's the state
of things what I'm also gonna do is say
let's suppose there's a variance as well
so let's just pretend and actually now
that I got its merge these down right
let's pretend that we want to have a
second set of these and I'm gonna I'm
just gonna drag that over and this is
just to make the variance of these that
we again so that we can test you know
what's going on there right so let's
it seems good right and so let's test
this by saying suppose we made one of
these other variants here
what is hue chroma that's a new slider
interesting let's just change the color
of these right so you know it's it's
like hey there's there's the red chairs
and there's the green chairs and that's
just what there is so you know don't
don't play me about it and then we'll
save that off as that's like suppose I
should delete this underlying piece here
and then merge these alright so now
we've got something that's effectively a
PNG for the chair and that would allow
us to test importing that as an item and
I think we don't really want to call it
an item I think we want to call it like
a decoration or something so I think
what we want to do is is call this
something else so you know we've got
items and those are things that you can
like wear or pick up right and then so
this is not an item with this more is is
just a like a decoration so this is like
I don't know something you place in the
world that you know has potentially and
orientation to it and variant so it's
orientation invariant I would call it
maybe
as a post you know obstacle is again a
little rough because we don't know that
it's an obstacle so I don't know if it's
maybe like just scenery let's say does
that work for n does anyone care about
that I don't know so I want to call it
scenery chair I guess orphanage chair
and I don't know like this is the the
naming convention it looks like it
wouldn't start at 1:00 it starts at 1:00
that was being used so you know maybe
that's maybe that's that right so let's
export that out and we'll say that there
is no such thing as obstacles anymore
looking at this you know maybe I want to
create a couple more of these for
testing purposes right I'm gonna have
these get remade so you know we'll see
but so let's suppose that we want to do
like you know the area rug or something
or the lamp so if I wanted to do one of
those sorts of things I could say like
alright let's let's grab the lamp out
there's only one of these right it's
just the lamp there's nothing else to it
so if I if I grab this one and paste it
in here I'm gonna put it up in the
corner like so and then we'll just save
that out I'll get rid of this and say
looks for that as a ping and that can be
like a lamp
and maybe you know I don't know maybe I
should have said there was a variant but
I I don't know floor lamp versus table
lamps seems different really this should
have been two things one it should have
been like a lamp and then a table and we
can use them both so we probably want to
split those out eventually but who cares
so anyway I'm gonna say that that's
what's going on with that and then if I
load up some of this other stuff here so
let me load up like obstacles for us to
see what's up with that so if we look at
what's going on here what you can see is
it's sort of like we have some seasonal
things sort of happening here right and
there's like different kinds of trees
and I'm not sure how we want to I'm not
sure how we want to characterize that
really
we may just want this to be a generic
kind of thing that's like foliage and it
has like two parameters like
snow-covered right and snow-covered and
bear in I don't know you can kind of see
like there's different things you may
want drawn there and yeah I'm not really
sure about that so you can see here
we've got like snow covered as a
parameter right and I don't really know
exactly what this was like it's kind of
gray and weird is it dead this might be
dead death possibly I'm not sure or
burnt so we've got snow covered burnt
and we've also got like the degree of
foliage so there's a couple different
variants for trees and they seem pretty
specific to trees so it seems like we
would want a specific tree thing right
so I'm not sure about that that one
seems harder let me take a look at the
items I think they're just fine cuz
they're just already yeah this is like
worn on the ground right I'm not sure
what that was else was in that template
it's like two different on the floor
versions I'm not sure why there are two
on the floor versions
I'm not sure what I had contemplated for
that but usually most things would just
have one floor state and then a worn
state
that'd be my assumption I don't know
what floor state to is about but I guess
maybe I had something in mind so those
will just load what else we got
so let's go to ground cover and see
what's up at that
so inside ground cover and I'm just so I
can see it I'm gonna make a new layer
here and I'm gonna make it just pure
white for the moment so or I was gonna
try to there we go and I'm just gonna go
like this and so now we can look in here
and see so if you look at what's going
on here I feel like to a large extent
there's sort of two separate types of
thing in here and well three I guess
pebbles is one two so I think we just
really just need to separate these into
two categories of the grass clump and
like splotch right these are tiny and
this is bigger and then we've got sort
of a stones thing and I think those just
want to be separated out right so I
would say these are a sort of particle
ish so my guess is these want to be just
particles kind of like like we just have
one thing for particle and that's it I
don't think we need anything else
probably for that so my assumption here
is we would just do like okay take
the template like so grab us the stuff
from here so like these four that did
not work because that was on the wrong
layer ah the Photoshop layer paradigm
always never what you want so if I come
up here and line those up with the grid
and then in here I just grab like one
more of these right and I plopped that
in here nope
then what I can do is it's pretty faint
but I can position that like in here
like so uh and now I've got you know a
file that is let me go ahead and delete
these layers oops there we go I can just
export this as like particle something
like that
sink and then after we got particle
grass I can do one of the other ones
here so whatever these like smaller ones
are here like all of those look fine I
don't know what that is
it looks kind of dead so maybe that
shouldn't maybe that should not be in
there that should be like a separate
thing but I'm gonna grab like these
other ones that look like stamps more
like I'm gonna skip so I could also make
a small grass one but I don't think I
need it like I don't know that we would
need small grass ones if we have these
because they're sort of just the same so
I don't know we'll see this is something
that could be worked out with the art a
little bit later too so instead what I'm
going to do is I'm just gonna grab these
ones that look like splotches to me so
like these oops
these all look like splotches let me
come over here and paste those in
and then I'm gonna see about what else
we got so these look like splotches
and then we can
get rid of this one and then I want to
just grab like some of these other ones
that look like splotches if there are
any other ones so you know like
I guess these are flowers so they should
probably be in their own thing so I'm
going to say this is another export as
and that's gonna be particle like grass
watch or something and all these were
just made for testing so we don't really
know if they're gonna look at alright
but that's okay you know I'm saying it's
really weird that it changes the size of
these when you click on them that's just
horrible
anyway so if we now go to the flowers
these are all flowers it looks like so I
should be able to well I probably want
to do just for here paste those in
and then I'll grab the last flower here
and so I'll just drag that over here and
call it a day
all right
so that can be saved as our particle
flowers oh one and again these are ones
where nothing is differentiated it's
just a series of different things you
could use for flowers and that's it and
I guess we've got stones too so we'll do
that one
as the last one
all right so that gives us plenty of
things to import now and I'm gonna go
back and say we're gonna we're not gonna
do the trees just yet because I really
don't know what to do with them so I'm
gonna go back in here and make a slight
change to the way these are going so
we've so we've got the blocks we've got
the orphan bodies and heads and that
stuff I'm gonna take this out of the mix
now because I don't care about that we
pulled those out into different
particles and again this is gonna be
someone else's job to make these files
eventually anyway so we've got the
ground cover separated out into particle
files so I'm just gonna get rid of that
I don't care about ones that I didn't
quite grab so we're gonna get rid of
cover forests in obstacles forests we're
gonna leave that and that because we
haven't pulled necessarily everything
out that we want to try so we've got
scenery as a thing we've got particle as
a thing we've got item as a thing
obstacles and cover so cover I think we
now don't have because I deleted the
only thing that was covered right so
cover is gone so obstacles is here but
we don't want to parse it so just to
signify that I'm gonna do that for now
and put them up there just so you can
see that like these are really probably
just gonna get deleted we're not gonna
ever use those and so this is really
what we're gonna parse now is it really
this back half so items particles and
scenery let's let's do that okay so
moving in here we don't have these
anymore so these are just gone goodbye
and now we've got these item files so
we've got
them hat a 1o 2o 3 then we've got these
particles oops
and this is going to be particle flowers
a 1 PNG and these are grass large and
grass watch I think yeah and then we've
got stones right so we've got flowers
grass large glass parts and stones we're
going to tag these all with something
and then we've got the scenery so
scenery
Orphanage share and then scenery this is
just a lamp right yeah so these are
things we want to import here and again
now we need to like figure out how we
want to tag these when they come in so
when these get imported they're all
gonna have to have some tags associated
with them so we know what they are and
that's the part that I'm not sure about
yet
so off we go obviously these are easy
they're all hats so we can start with
that
at least we can also say that they're
worn might be I don't know if we need
that tag really but you know because the
hat is worn but yes we've got hats and
then the three different hats we've got
sort of like a Sun Hat and we had back
in in our tags we sort of had some ideas
of how these things go like right there
was like the sort of stuff so I think we
just want these to match so like
this is a cooking hat obviously so I
think this should just be like cook
right and this is like a gardening hat
right so it'd be like an earth hat
probably if that makes sense so that
that hat here right is that kind of hat
and then we had a hat this is it's not
really a hat it's like a flower but it's
okay
and maybe that's like spring I don't
know so then if we're on flowers here
like we've got flowers grass I don't
know what we want to do with these
exactly because it's a little bit harder
to say obviously the flowers I'm sorry
the grass should get tagged with grass
that's not hard to understand but
there's like different sort of styles
here of ways in which things are getting
sort of plunked down and so I feel like
that and probably want to be some sort
of there's gonna be some sort of
differentiation there also grass
probably there should be flowers as a
thing as well I don't know how we want
to do this or tag size so you can tag
things like with a size like how big of
a splotch type of thing or do you want
to put down maybe right so something
like that so you know this is like a
size two and you know or this is like a
size one and this is like a size 0.5 you
know what I mean just just something
like that and so here this would be like
flowers splotches right so there that's
sort of a little bit different and then
here we would have stone and these are
splotches as well that seems reasonable
I guess I don't have a lot of knowledge
of how we're gonna really do this as we
sort of moving forwards it's all just
kind of like well let's try this if I
add those here
yeah I don't think we had like any sort
of thing for tag like for a sizing tag
like something that sort of said the
largeness of something but I think we do
want that so put that in there so we've
got that and then we're down to some
stuff here like the chair and the lamp
I feel like do we have like orphan maybe
like these go with the orphanage right
it's man-made talking if there's
anything else we want you here so I
think we just need like extra tags for
these so this is chair and I feel like
this should be specified as like an
orphanage because they specifically go
in this area I don't know that seems
like a good plan but we'll see as we go
forward right so in here I'm gonna go
ahead and just grab these tags out and
we will say that we've got chair and
lamp I think that's it
that seems like everything at the moment
anyway
and so now what I really need to do is
change up how we're ingesting these
because what we want is now the
previously you know we knew about item
and previously we have like cover and
obstacles we don't want that we want
particle and scenery those are the two
things that looks like we want so in the
importer where those were stubbed out we
just gonna change what we're actually
looking for you can see that happening
right in here right you know it's item
obstacles plate blah blah blah and so
we're not actually gonna be doing this
and these are wrong so we want like for
example particle like so and then
scenery like so and we set ourselves up
for success here I think maybe in that
these just work or should just work and
so this error is just going to tell us
hey we changed what those tag types are
so maybe you should go fix them right
and let's go ahead and do that now so if
we look at where these are coming in
they're in the asset system or they're
marked up I believe yeah right here
so we want like the cover tags and like
all that stuff this needs to change now
so that's particle tags and this needs
to change the scenery tags and then we
need to actually specify them because
these were getting done when we
initialize the asset system right now I
don't think anyone actually fills out
any of those you can see right here
we've got those sort of stubbed out as
functions I don't think they do anything
at the moment so I want to be able to do
like create particle tag grid and
seorita grid and if I actually jump to
one of those things like what does it
create cover tag grid or arc cover tag
grid there uh so we look in here we just
got to do's right it's like hey you've
got to put in something into this tag
grid so this one's pretty easy I think
what we can do is just say alright if we
you know create one of these things like
so by default we're gonna do with
the with the particle tag grid is it's
just four and four right we're just
we're not doing 8x8 so we're just doing
four and four they're smaller
imports and what we want to do is just
tag them as variants so there is no
facing direction it's just a variance
right and this should be like an art
part asset particle I think I want to
look and see where where coops where
we're actually saying that so here's the
basic categories and you can see all
this stuff a lot of these we could
collapse down they don't need to be here
anymore but I'm gonna go ahead and say
there's a particle category scenerio
well and you know what I don't even have
to do that and just do this because
we're not using these so cover became
particle obstacle became scenery and so
asset particle is actually what it is
it's gonna be a tag variant the variance
just gonna be whatever the variant is
right and that's it I don't think we
actually need to do this it's just for
each one that's what it is right we
don't touch the other ones uh and I
think that just works I think you know
famous last words
oh and we'll check this particle these
could just be a nice look up later you
can sort of see that happening you know
probably not worth bothering at the
moment but eventually we could collapse
all these down and maybe we should do
that sometime soon
alright so looking through here this is
art particle tags this is art scenery
tags we now need to do the ones for the
items and for the scenery let's go ahead
and do those so if I jump back to in
pork on the scenery tag grid and so both
the scenery tag and the item tag are
both directional so we do want to keep
this sort of the thing that we were
using for hands that's the template we
want to use for both of these right
because we do want to set that facing
direction at the entire time now we
don't need to do asset import grid max
we only do a 4x4 like so and so for each
of these we also can just do this and so
the 4x4 to get set up with the facing
direction as it should and for the item
tag grid I believe we can just do asset
item here and asset scenery here and
that takes care of itself but what we
need to do now is say alright when we're
doing the facing direction we also need
to do something about the x coordinate
because each of the x coordinates is
actually a little bit different right
you know like we're gonna specify a
different tag for each of these so in
here we're gonna want to do a thing
where we say look if the X is 0 or if
it's 1 or if it's 2 or if it's 3 we're
gonna add different things now we don't
really want to use 3 because there isn't
anything in the third row yet as far as
we know so we really just want to do
something like this probably where we're
just adding a tag for these
and so in the first one this was like on
floor right you know I don't know what
we want to tag that with this one is
like worn and this one I guess we don't
really know I don't know what that
variant is but so I think I guess what
we want to do is tag this with variant
as well so you know I guess it's like
hey case 0 case 1 is the same and falls
through I guess something like this
should probably just actually do this so
this one's like worn you know I'm saying
and here we're gonna add the it's on the
floor and here this is the variant one
as opposed to the variant 0
I guess so not 100% sure like what that
was supposed to accomplish exactly so
it's something like that for the scenery
tag grid it's a little bit simpler it's
always the same stuff the facing
direction is set off the Y the variant
is set off the X so it's just like
actually should just kept this
it's literally this
right so I guess that seems good maybe
you know I don't know you know now I
think about to this variant here really
should just be it should be divided by
16 right so this should this should be
more like this because we want them to
be normalized to one just to make it
easier for us to randomly pick them we
wouldn't have to know how many there are
we can just pick things in the range of
0 to 1 and it'll always work no matter
how many there are right
so for variance I think we do want to do
something more like this right and you
know that way we always ensure that
they're they're normalized that although
that does put a slightly if you're using
rounding that's not exactly what you
want you actually want it to be divided
by the maximum you can get to if you
want to end it one so mmm you know like
man I'm not sure how you want to strike
those right you probably want to
actually bucket them so in use
truncation so I don't know we have to
sort of think about that that variant
tagging is gonna have to get thought
about harder at some point you know but
point being that is the more like bucket
oriented variant if you assumed you were
like truncating since we're taking
distances not truncating currently you
know it's not what you would actually
want to do what you actually I do is
space them out as like beacons
throughout the space that have an equal
slot thing amount on either side of them
so you know 0 the first variant
shouldn't be 0 right and so you know
just to sort of sketch out what I'm
talking about here
in terms of making variants maybe work
with distance a little bit better what
you would want to do is say well one of
them should be you know you kind of want
to divide up into thirds right and one
of them should be occupying the the
range that's like you know from 0 to 0.5
it's right in the middle of that and the
other one should be from from 0.5 to up
in the threatened mo of that right and
so yeah it's a little bit complicated
but so point being we probably would
want something looks more like this that
way when you do what's closest from 0 to
0.5 you're closest to this variant and
from 0.5 to 1 you're closest to this
variant right and we don't really care
about breaking a tie so I don't know
that seems like maybe the more correct
variant version so if I look at where we
were setting those before so in here
right same thing is going to be true
what you want to do here is say look we
need to divide the space up so that we
properly are shifted up by half of the
range and then we go up by the range
each time so instead of something that
looks like this what we really need to
do is add in half of that total range so
if 1/16 is the amount that we go up each
time we want you know like a shift that
produces that offset right so something
like this and that just shifts the range
up so that everybody has the same amount
of like ground they're covered again
just sketching this in we don't have to
do it we can look at this in more detail
later we don't have to really think it
through particularly much here I could
also just compute this off of the grid
it's not necessary to do it
right this is you can make this a
completely parallelizable loop if you
want to so anyway coming back down if
you're looking at sort of like the the
other stuff we've got we are inside the
art item tag grid looks like
everything's fine there except we
haven't defined one of these yet I don't
think there is one already for clothes
thing
so I think we need to just add that in
right where's my array there it is
all right so Warren gets thrown in there
automatically for that one it's like if
someone has put this on you know that
tag you'll get get activated for scenery
we just have facing Direction invariant
I think that's it and cover is just a
particle is just a set of variants I
don't think there's anything else to it
so I think those should now just import
all of those art assets correctly I
don't know that there's anything else we
actually need to do to make them work we
can obviously see if that's true I could
be completely wrong about that let's go
ahead and and try it and then you know
if it rolls over and dies it does that
kind of did look like it rolled over and
died because it didn't do anything yeah
so unrecognized tag name hat and then
recognized well actually that major
speakers not there so it looks like hat
was never never specified so what would
is that hat just goes I guess we just
need that here right it's just a tag
we'll see how that does probably no
better but hey we can Li see what the
era's are so if I run this
oh well that did spent some time so it
looks like it did actually update now so
hopefully now we've got those in here to
play with and you know if I do a dump
just to see if that's the case missed I
don't know I'm saying I don't think
fifteen minutes left if I do a dump just
to see what actually happened there so
here's that same dump that I ran before
I'm do it again what just happened oh
I'm in the wrong directory so if I redo
that dump and then I look at it here I
should see appended to the end of this I
should have got some new assets in here
right uh let's see I don't really know
this doesn't look promising
I'm not sure why there are these sort of
fonts sitting around in there maybe they
were just from being updated but that's
not great but looking at here these
actually do look somewhat great all of
this looks real nice so all of that
importing did seem pretty good
you know think these just kind of stack
up there unfortunately it's not great
again I think that's where we might want
to clean up some of that code so this
stuff looks fine right all that looks
fine to me
so that's all well and good no real
problem there let's go ahead and take a
look at what else you could do here that
might make some sense so let's try if we
wanted to put one of these in the world
I don't really want to try the ground
cover yet because that sort of a
separate system will have to sort of put
in there so what I'd rather do is if we
went to lava the most straightforward
thing we could do right is I guess when
you add a player you know that's gonna
construct this thing we could add a hat
on there right so that would be here
actually I just want to see if we can
load this thing up so the asset type
here is going to be an asset item we're
gonna have to fuss with this stuff a
little bit I'm not sure how we want all
that to work but when we actually create
that Hat piece we're gonna need an item
there and this actually brings up a nice
thing that we can maybe this is what we
can do tomorrow that I wanted to fix is
that the tags are uniform so like you
can't set different tags and different
little pieces I have a plan of how I
wanted to fix some of that and do it a
little bit differently than it's being
done in a way that thinks better so we
can talk about that a little bit later
but well like we first to just say okay
when we add with these players how can
we get like a hat on there right because
right now I'm not seeing one right let
me
so if you look like there's no it's just
the those two pieces right so the
question is like where what's the
problem why can't we get an asset item
for that hat pulled in here right
because we should be able to find like
something and and I don't know we could
we could put tag worn in there as well
but again we shouldn't really have to
because it should find something it
should find a hat I would think so let's
try to see why if I create some code
really quickly just to make it easy for
me to find when that happens right so
you know when we do oh wait I forgot
it's not attached so I want to attach
this to top of head right so that's
probably what I screwed up I didn't
actually connect that piece to anything
so I may not actually have to do the
test that I thought I was going to do
but we'll see yeah I still do right it's
not all right so let me go ahead and set
a breakpoint in something convenient so
we can take a look at it
I do or you know what it could be that
top of head is also just not set so I
should I should just actually set these
alignment points first just to make sure
that that's not an issue it could be
that it just can't find that alignment
point right so let me just do due
diligence here we'll pick one of these
right here and I need to
add an alignment point for that so it
would be called top-of-head okay and
look there it is
so it would be called top-of-head I
don't really know where it would go
exactly it looks like it's sort of wrong
picking the wrong facing direction
though so I don't know if maybe we've
got the facing directions a little bit
wrong on those items or something like
that let's take a look but hey it does
work taking a look at at this that needs
a default - to do alignment for it but
at the moment we don't really care if I
look at the facing directions on the
right so let me pick the other one here
there's that top of head
and finally
there we go so each of these has a top
of head now and I can save that so if I
want to save the hhd in theory
everything worked Hey look it didn't
change these two which is great because
we didn't want it to but if we did
change this one which is it should have
right and so now like again we're just
trying to figure out how well the system
works at all it looks like it kind of
does there a little bit but it looks
like the facing direction because that
should have been one that flower but it
wasn't and so I don't really know how to
investigate that further without I
probably said some very much don't look
at it but so if we look at the item
template here if I open this up and hmm
well I'll be honest I can tell it's
wrong already
yeah these just aren't right so if we
look at the way this one works if I go
to the template here you can see it's
supposed to be going that way and it so
totally definitely isn't right like it's
actually this direction that's this one
so so it's just wrong so again I think
we're fine I think it's the actual
source aren't there that's wrong I will
say one odd thing that I don't
understand is why do we not get one for
the downward Direction like what's going
on there right that makes me a little
uncomfortable I don't understand why
we're not getting a downward right I
mean we've got there isn't at the top of
there is a top of head attachment point
there you know we're looking at it and
yet for some reason that that one
doesn't actually show up and the facing
Direction there right it is the only
difference each one of these the facing
direction it does pick it out properly
right so I don't know
why we're not getting I don't know why
we're not getting why we're not getting
any any data there that's that's weird
so I want to go look and see what did it
actually say it was doing when it
imported the that particular hat I think
that one's the first one right or wait
which one is it no it's the third one so
it's it's the oh three and here are the
four things that got imported from oh
three so what's up with that if I look
at the tags well there's your answer
so three three the facing direction for
the item got imported the same in both
cases
why
[Music]
what's what's going on here
how how could it that possibly be true I
mean looking at this it looks like it's
off by one in like a weird way right
there's also like way too many of these
2 0 1 1 2 1 2 2 2 3 3 3 like where is it
getting that is there actually data in
there
okay
so I think there is some kind of a bug
in the importing too right because there
should only have been one column
recorded and these fall well within the
column right there's nothing it's not
like this is like overlapping or
something so for some reason when this
got pulled in it thinks there's a lot
more of them than there are now what's
really weird about that is it's only
this one right this one has two zero
just like this one but then it has one
one two one two two two three
it's way more imports than there should
be
these all came in right so that's
correct that that's good right but this
hat is totally borked
it's got a total of six imports so it
should have been to zero to one to two
to three
instead there is a three three and a one
one so the bottom corner had something
in it
is that actually true
but I really don't see anything down
there so it thinks the bottom corner had
something in it and it also thinks that
this had something in it right and that
explains why we're not getting one for
this facing direction because you know
we it's picking this one because they're
equivalent it thinks they're both fine
because they're both gonna be labelled
the same but they totally aren't so I
just that's really strange I don't know
how to actually ask if there are
any pixels somewhere like I don't know I
think that's a pretty clear indication
that there aren't I would assume
cuz like it's entirely pegged at zero
right so I mean I think that tells us
what we need to know famous last words
I'm gonna end it there and say that
tomorrow that'll be our debugging to
figure out what's going on with that
import cuz something's something's
busted I'm not sure what these two hat
files seem to come in just fine and this
one can't and I have no idea why if I
was to set the cook flag on us I assume
we would then be okay so for example if
in here I did this I'm assuming we
wouldn't have this problem because the
cook hat seems like it works at least
from you know cursorily looking at the
import level right of course our our
whole body changes from here oh because
we are now the cook instead of the hero
but that's okay there's our our head
piece we have to actually add the
alignment points I'll do that really
quickly just for fun profit so let's add
basis neck on there and we also want to
add a but we already have a top of head
I don't know how to really adjust this
particularly
this is two-parent right
I'm not I need to like rethink about how
I'm drawing this I don't really know how
to do these quite right and as we know
the hero head is on backwards we have to
we have to do an art drop to like clean
up all the art problems that we've had I
should make it I should be making a list
but I'm not because these have to get
done off stream right
hmm
so it's pretty straightforward yeah I
mean I think all this just works okay I
mean you know it's a lot of our tests
that clean up we have to do because of
course like all this stuff we have to
add like where they snap together and
stuff which is you know just one of the
things that creates a lot of work for
game development always that's just how
it is but
I don't even know why I'm bothering
doing this right now but
you
Oh duh so if I forgot to put it into
debug camera okay
yeah that was stupid so that's why I
couldn't see anything it's because you
have to be in debug camera mode before
those things get good I forgot to put
that there we go so yeah so it seems
like all that stuff works just fine it's
just for some reason we have an import
problem on that so I guess that's our
job for tomorrow I'm gonna go to Q&amp;A
real quick here but that's gonna be
that's gonna be our job for tomorrow is
to figure out why we don't why we don't
properly only use the ones that are
actually there
was Michael Abrash around during your
time at rad yes in fact I am one of the
people who talked him in like certain
into coming to work there copypasta
Stephanie with the variant using Y index
instead of X index in the scenery tag
grid thank you let me let me go mark
that before we forget that is what I
meant or wanted should say how about
ornaments for the oriented furniture
instead of scenery um yeah I don't love
it I'm creating an OpenGL engine in
c-sharp I really enjoy the language and
I'm enjoying the process but should I
just move go move to C++
um I don't think you have to do that
I mean c-sharp is reasonable I can't
stand garbage collection it just it
drives me insane so you know I
personally wouldn't really want to use
c-sharp but you know that that's just my
personal preference you know in how I
want to do with my code so I think
there's any particular reason you know
it's not like PHP or something where I'd
be like oh my god no right c-sharp is
reasonable I mean it's you know it's a
it's a real language it has you know
good trace compilation and stuff on it
as far as I know so it's n't it's not
it's not a complete pile it's gonna
always run really slow the garbage
collection isn't great but you know that
just means that something you'll have to
work around in the future but you know
it's not the end of the world people
have shipped games in c-sharp it's not
in common and if you want to use unity
in the future if you know obviously that
uses C sharp as the main language you
use to program it so you you know you've
got a leg up there if you
want to use unity you you know already
know how to program it well if you're
aiming more Unreal Engine man that's not
so good because I don't think people
generally use c-sharp for that but
what's your learning method when faced
with a new topic how do you juggle
figuring things out yourself versus
reading a textbook so unless it's like a
really well studied branch of something
like you know I want to learn partial
differential equations or something then
I might go to a textbook but in other
than that case I don't really read
textbooks very often but what I do is I
go surfing for papers so like let's say
I want to implement like you know screen
space lighting or something right I
generally don't just start doing it
myself unless I'm like really sure that
everyone's just an idiot in that domain
and I don't need to write but with
something like let's say screen space
lighting I know there's a lot of smart
people who've done things in that area
so what I tend to do is I just go
surfing for technical content I get a
big stack of papers in PDF form on my on
the hard drive right and then I just
read them all and I don't try to like
understand every last thing because
technical papers are usually pretty bad
at explaining technical concepts
amusingly enough but I just read them to
see like generally what are people doing
like what sorts of things have people
done what sounds good to me whatever and
then I'll focus on like one or two and
like really go in and learn like us okay
what do I think they were actually doing
here right and then I'll go and start
writing my own stuff but I really do
tend to try to read technical papers
first because typically again unless
it's just like a really really some some
areas are just nobody good ever goes
there right but other than like that
fairly rare occurrence where you
literally have a place that you know is
just devoid of talent you're gonna find
some technical papers that at least will
inform your thinking on it and give you
new ideas
and so while I don't necessarily
recommend assuming that someone else has
already solved the problem because
oftentimes when I go I do find that
there's like things I want to do that
maybe weren't addressed or there's ideas
I have that weren't tried by other
people it's rare that I don't get ideas
from tech papers at least some even if
it's just because you have an idea about
how do something better than what they
did that idea came from reading the
paper right so I really do recommend
learning to do that if you can there's a
lot of good stuff in techno papers and
even if the technical papers don't
actually have the answer you're looking
for they may inspire the answer right
they may provide context that allows you
to get to the answer quicker and that's
that's equally important to have an
official code style guide anywhere yes
my code style guide is if someone tries
to tell you to use a code style guide
fire them
hi from Hungary hello I don't know that
I've ever had anyone write in from
Hungary before that's someone from
Serbia today and now some from Hungary
these are new people places for people
for people writing in we also had
someone from France but I think I had
someone from France writing before I
took your advice you gave me last week I
started to blog to get involved gay
ministry it contains a few posts already
and some descriptions of my earlier
projects may be worth reading sometime
sandor de the home blog um oops I mean
to delete that let's take a look ah
typing
all right cool let's take a look
wait I thought there was one up here
that said something how come how does
this work so how come it just kind of
ended here but there was more I'm
confused
so these are like different ah I see
yeah that's us we have to also check
this out
what why is video unavailable
looks like these videos need to be
updated
there's my only piece of feedback so far
video needs to be updated
so this does seem like good start to me
I don't know like I've spent a little
bit more time reading through it
obviously but I would I would say you
got to fix the videos too I want to
watch this whatever it is enhanced with
my personal project yeah like I like
this is this like a is this like
substrate for scattering kind of thing
because I like this this is interesting
I would like to see more about this you
should expand this part hi from Bulgaria
wow I'm starting an internship in July
the games today I'm super excited and I
feel I owe you a lot of gratitude for
keeping me excited about game day well
I'm very glad to hear that I've seen
your name a lot on here frosty ninja
he's a frosty ninja a ninja that gets
like a frosty like the ice cream treat
and like unwraps they're like masks and
like eats it or as a frosty ninja one
that's like a snowman who's also a ninja
like Frosty the Snowman or something
Brian was asking if a distinct coding
style and though I realized he may have
evolved into it over the years so I was
wondering if there was something
specific that directed you yeah
two things really I would say one is
that I think I want to say that my dad
originally used the like some people use
the squash brace the squash tray style
where you move the brace up to here I
think my dad did it this way it may be
because I was a Pascal programmer it
could have been cuz of him I can't
remember why I use that brace style but
so I don't remember but that's one thing
the next thing is Chris hacker was the
person who I picked up the lowercase
type names uppercase functions and
variable names and that's sort of
arbitrary that's where I picked it up
from but the sort of arbitrary but I've
recently come to think that maybe it's
not so arbitrary because assuming that
you use the assuming that you use the
rule anything that is lowercase is a
type and anything that starts with
uppercase is not a type that means you
can always automatically complete the
capitalization of anything knowing only
the first letter if you do it the other
way around
you can't and the reason for that is C
by default
define its types as lowercase and even
though you can just easily avoid not
using any of C runtime libraries
functions you cannot avoid using C's
types because they are required right
you have to use int care if there's no
other way to do that right whereas you
can easily just choose to only have your
own function
which can all be capitalized right so
hard to say but you know there may be
some reasons to do it this way finally
the reason there's a there's a return
between here and here is I just like to
put the function name on a line by
itself especially when I used to program
so you close Plus these lines could get
really long like if you have like a
template and crap on here you can just
and so I like to split those out return
type versus function name just was
easier to find the function name right
are you 32x32 aliases yeah they are the
they're not the language doesn't know
what are you 32 is the language just
knows what like an unsigned is all right
we're all good
by the way I forgot to thank George if
you remember but we were having some
crashes in remedy when we used it on the
stream the other day he actually fixed
it like overnight for us that's why we
had you know we didn't have any troubles
today so I meant to thank X 13 pixels on
the chat and if he's here today but he
like he fixes bugs in this thing like
like at so fast it reminds me of just
how slow it takes Microsoft to ever fix
any bugs and their stuff it's just like
yeah it's like I had a problem on
Saturday and he fixed it by Sunday
morning we didn't end up using it on
Sunday morning I felt bad because we
went down the rat hole someone had asked
about how to draw the circle right but
it was fixed yes like last weekend on
Sunday morning it was ready for us right
so that's why I didn't crash at all this
weekend is cuz he just he fixed it look
right away and so just thought I'd say
thanks for being so fast on the bug
reports it's pretty nice to have some
confidence that when your debugger
crashes you can actually send the crash
to somebody and then it gets fixed like
I mean that's actually a feeling that I
don't have a sufferer pretty much ever
anymore
I mean like we get Photoshop crashes
every day they'll never get fixed I mean
I don't think they'll ever get fixed I
don't even know how to really report
them correctly but they never get fixed
I mean they they're bugs that a far as I
can tell I've been in there for years
right
and if they do fix them then they just
add new ones so you never really know
but it's weird but you never get them
fixed like even confirm that you fix
them right this never happens it's you
know or like web stuff I use you know
Gmail has the same bugs in it that it's
had for years the Wacom driver has the
same bugs and if that's had for years I
just you know it's just just rot really
when porting to other platforms do you
have to rewrite all your shooters in
hlsl on metal s l's are a way to
transpile GLSL yeah that's just a
shaders are a gigantic failure the fact
that the fact that they couldn't have
one stupid language is absurd especially
because they're all the same like the K
it's not like they all do the same thing
right they all compile down the same
crap on the on the different cards and
it's just it's a just a disaster just a
huge disaster I don't know of any great
thing to suggest they're all I would say
is that you know some people use trance
trance compilers or trans translators I
guess what you'd call them vagues they
do exist so there's a couple like open
source ones that are just like look this
is the thing that that compete that that
takes hlsl and dumps metal out or things
like that like they do exist I forget
the names of them but but yeah it's just
it's ridiculous that there's I don't
even know what to say it's not like
these cards do they're just computing
generic math stuff I guess I don't even
know it they don't even have branching
right they just have masking even so
it's I don't I don't I don't know I
guess they do have branching now they've
got loops so I shouldn't say that I
think they can do loops now so that's
not true they do have branching
but anyway it's just it's it's absurd
I'm gonna go ahead and and close it down
here I also should mention before we go
anywhere for the day I think this is
working now I think you don't know and
then when it came to giving a talk it's
made me think about some things that
transpired between boast of are both of
our societies some Dec so there is now a
English only version of John's talk he
gave in blocks like I said it is
somewhere in Russia but I don't actually
know where that where Russia is a big
country so that's kind of not narrowing
it dad
okay so it's in Moscow I guess so here's
the talk he gave in Moscow just like a
day or two ago and there is now a
version supposedly English only I
haven't listened the whole thing in
English yet I had to listen to the one
with the Russian simultaneous
translation which was kind of brain
bending so if you're interested in Jon's
talk which if you watch Han Mahiro you
probably are cuz you know it's it's very
much about the kinds of stuff we always
talk about in handmade hero I would
recommend giving this a watch it's on my
Twitter feed if this is annoying you can
go to Twitter / senior comma slash
territory maybe we'll get the link in
here on the on the annotations as well
but basically John just consolidated
into a talk a pretty clean set of things
it's like here's why things are pretty
bad right now with some you know
specific evidence that I call it that
you know what not i but he collected and
then like why you should care about it
it contains an important point that I
think is not it's not articulated often
and I don't think I ever really thought
about it much beyond
just a my feeling like it was a
self-evident fact to me but I never
thought to to really say it out loud and
when you say it out loud it would like
that John did and he was actually he
more steadily Elon Musk said it out loud
and John was quoting him but when you
say that you realize that people don't
ever say it out loud which is weird and
that fact is that technology left to its
own devices degrades over time and it is
only through effort that it actually
gets better and so it's really important
to point this out that people think that
science and technology improve over time
but they don't they degrade over time
and it's only through a lot of human
effort that you actually get continual
incremental improvement and that effort
is communication it's communication
between people who know how to do things
and people who don't to try and spread
that knowledge and keep it maintained so
that it so that people new people can
add to it in advance rather than having
to start over and degrade right and it's
just worth saying that because nobody
ever says that but it's 100% the case
and the institutions that are generally
responsible for preserving this
knowledge are bad at it universities are
terrible at at preserving knowledge
especially in technical fields and like
textbooks are horrible at it very very
bad so the act of actually like
preserving what we do know how to do is
tenuous and this talk should hopefully
provide you with some evidence that
that's true that you do need to do work
to prevent backslide
but also show some examples of why we
are probably in a backsliding period
right now meaning we have already
entered a time when software is
backsliding because of poor
communication and poor training and
knowledge transfer
so it's not like something that we have
to be afraid will happen in the future
it's something we should be afraid is
already happening now and something
probably should be done about it if we
can figure out what that something would
be unfortunately the talk it doesn't
have an obvious easy answer I don't
think that's the stalks fault I think
that's just the fact that there isn't an
obvious easy answer to something like
this it's it's a very complicated issue
and so it's more talked about trying to
get people to stop being so self
congratulatory and start realizing just
how dangerous the situation where you
found ourselves in and maybe try to
motivate people to try and work a little
harder to figure out how to fix this
problem that we actually have hopefully
it will do a good job of mystery of that
if it doesn't oh well but I would really
recommend giving it a listen and it will
be a lot easier for you to listen than
me because hopefully now it is it's just
English if that makes sense
so hopefully that'll work out please
check that out I will be back here
tomorrow when I want to go look at why
we're having some bugs in why that
flower hat was getting extracted as
multiple bitmap regions that though I
don't think had anything in them maybe
they did have something in them and
actually there's some noise pixels in
there either way we have a any issue if
it's extracting grid squares that don't
have anything in them that's an obvious
bug that needs fixing if it's extracting
grid squares because it grid squares
because they actually do have something
in them well we still have a problem
which is that that needs to be
articulated more clearly so that we can
see what the actual error is and fix it
in the art assets so either way we need
to do something about it we'll take a
look at that a little bit later on and
stream tomorrow for sure
so please come back for that and I'll
see you here tomorrow same time same
place until then have fun programming
and I'll see you on the air net I guess
I should also say as I say every time in
case you didn't know already if you do
want to work with source code directly
it is available if you preorder the game
it
comes in the source code so you can
follow that at home that's on hand me
here org and of course the schedule is
always under the watch tab as is the
searchable episode guide if you're
looking for something
check out that watch now it's got a lot
of good stuff on it that's it for today
until tomorrow have fun programming I'll
see everyone on the Internet
take it easy everybody