hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream I am
well I'm very allergy as you can see but
we have some relatively straightforward
stuff to do today so hopefully it won't
be a problem we can basically just start
where we left off yesterday and try to
make our lighting system use precomputed
templates for figuring out what we want
to do with our ray casting from any
individual ray cast sample point and
also ray casting seems to be in the news
a bit lately I don't know if you saw but
there's a lot of talk about pushing
future GPU development directions
towards a ray tracing future which as I
sort of mentioned yesterday I think in
the pre stream I am very much in favor
of I like ray tracing I don't have
strong opinions about whether ray
tracing or rasterization is the correct
way to do things or anything like that I
just like ray tracing better it feels
cleaner to me and easier to experiment
with and I've I've never really liked
the sort of large number of stages you
go through when you try to make a
rasterizer to try and approximate
lighting so I'm pretty happy about the
fact that people are you know trying to
start a push towards the ray tracing
world I don't know if we're gonna get
there but you know I I want us to get
there I guess is what I'd say so you
know it's kind of exciting to see people
giving it a shot and I think it's a good
direction for GPU vendors because at the
end of the day ray tracing paralyzes
pretty darn well
and so you know they're not really in a
position to be able to up their clock
rates much right and so serialized
rasterization kinds of stuff with lots
of like pre doing lighting that had and
then you have to wait for the next stage
to do something that's our stuff I feel
like just hay stamping down gigantic
sets of ray tracing cores may not be a
bad idea hardware wise you know maybe
we're
at that point where that's really what
we should be doing I don't know totally
outside of my area of expertise I have
no idea but point being I'm kind of
happy that people are looking into that
and maybe we'll see some fruits of that
down the line for now I'm just happy
that we have our own raytracer for doing
our lighting and I want to make it a
little bit better so that's exactly what
we're doing today is trying to come up
with some better sampling schemes we've
been playing around that for a week or
two the how we want to cast Rays out of
a point part of the problem and that's
what I'd like to start looking at today
so a couple things we don't know at the
moment and we got a look at them all
today so first of all just at the end of
last dream I change to using a template
for doing our sampling and it looks like
it kind of broke things a little bit so
I think we've got either some errors or
well we don't really know I I don't know
exactly what's going on all I know is I
don't think we have a completely clean
result here with that switchover now
that could be it could be that we've
implemented just fine and our pattern is
is bad because we haven't actually put
in a real pattern yet and maybe the fact
that we did a randomized pattern maybe
this isn't enough randomized patterns to
actually even out the light or who knows
but it doesn't look the same as it
looked before when we move around and it
should look roughly the same so we just
we don't really know exactly what's
going on there so we basically have a
couple things that we want to accomplish
going forwards number one is we want to
go ahead and put some real patterns in
number two is we want to introduce some
debugging so that we can verify that
these patterns are being applied the way
we think they are because obviously
there's plenty of things that can go
wrong as part of this process and we
don't know until we inspect a little bit
more cleanly and figure that out like
for example you can see right here like
why is this not getting very much light
right it just it just looks wrong and so
I'm guessing that we've got some
problems and we're going to
a look at those problems in more detail
so that's our job for today to start
looking at that stuff and yeah and there
we go so for starters the first thing
that I want to do is I want to just go
ahead and enable our debug line support
again because that will allow me to draw
where we're sampling and then what I'd
like to do is just take a look at how
those samples are working out so that we
can you know get some opinion of of
what's going on now if you remember how
this used to work and you can see that
this well you know what this this is
something we can switch back on actually
for those of you maybe missed last name
so you can kind of see here here's what
the lighting looks like when we were
generating the random samples using the
previous method which generates them in
line so just at the time that we want to
generate the random samples we generate
them and you can see that the lighting
looks pretty reasonable like it's a
pretty reasonable approximation of the
lighting to the scene it seems like to
me you know that's just my my sort of
like take on it is that this this you
know isn't so bad and we haven't run any
really rigorous testing on it or
anything but it's it seems reasonable
and then when we go in if we actually
switch that if zero you can sort of see
how the lighting changes there and it's
not obviously super wrong but it does
look you know it definitely just looks
more incorrect than the version that was
generating the randoms on the fly and
that's just why I say I think we've got
some bugs in there or at least if there
aren't bugs we've got a problem with the
way the random pattern was working and
in it's it's yeah again it's less about
knowing if the bug or not it's just
noticing that so this is suspicious
behavior and that just reinforces the
fact to me that I want to see this I
want to be able to visualize what's
going on so that I can know what I'm
looking at what is causing that
particular effect to occur because I
don't trust that it's reasonable it
could turn out to be a totally
reasonable it could turn out to just be
a straight-up bug and we need to know
which is which
right
okay so I want to re-enable this sort of
situation and what this is is the thing
that lets us draw our debug lines right
and the problem is we kind of updated
this code since we were drawing these
debug lines so I need to extract the
debug lines in a more straightforward
way
now hitbox at the moment is the only
thing here that it's complaining about
first that it's got T ray is another one
right so we've got a couple of these
things that we want to be able to access
sort of individually and we need to
figure out how to do that
so let's take a look at how we're going
to go about doing that so if I come back
here and look at how we made our stuff
for for wide you can see that we still
have a tier a it's just for wide so what
we should be able to do is access T ray
by just extracting it from the Ray
casting result and pull it loops and
pulling out the sub ray of one of those
so that's not a particularly hard one to
get hitbox is really just the thing that
was telling us whether or not this
particular thing how to hit and so again
that one is really just this so we can
just do that where we look to see
whether or not this thing got hit or not
and then that replaces what we were
doing here then finally the last thing
if you notice from the compiler is we
just don't know what direction this
thing goes in but we can know that
obviously right we can know what
direction it goes in because we made a
bundle of four directions that the thing
goes in so this is really just a case of
pulling out which whichever one of those
we're on so we can just say hey why
don't you give us out of the bundle of
four that we made we have a thing
already that extracts those when we find
that we actually need them which is this
get component call here and so that'll
pull out the sample date so at that
point then we are actually doing those
debug lines those will now get updated
which allows me to see exactly what I
want to see which is where the samples
are happening we also have the ability
to set this debug point index and so the
interesting thing about the Diego points
if you remember we have this thing that
sort of says hey where do I want to pick
who do I want to pick for
grabbing those debug it paces us to pick
a point in the world and say show us the
debug cast from this location so we can
actually move it around and look at some
different stuff right so here is the
version of this that's working I believe
this is the this is the debug lines that
happen and I move the light out of the
way these are the debug lines that
happen I believe when when we're not
when we're using the correct lighting I
think right yes so this is using the
lighting and correct as a strong murder
this is using the lighting that we
thought looked or I thought looked more
reasonable right and you can kind of see
what lines were shooting out there so
now I'm just going to go ahead and look
at what happens if I shoot out the
template lines and we can see what those
are okay so you can see those are
totally borked
right they're just not rotating I should
see it rotating through a whole set of
them but it's not so like I suspected
we're just picking slightly wrong here
totally fine we threw that into the end
of last scene I'm not upset about it at
all but it's just that's exactly what I
wanted to know and so we need to take a
look at it now the other thing I don't
know is those red lines there those are
ones that didn't hit anything I believe
I think that's okay because if I look at
where those red lines are pointing they
shouldn't probably have hit anything it
looks like they managed to escape out
the side and out the top so I don't
think there's any cause for concern
there and all these rest of these lines
are correctly Green terminated and you
can see they're terminating at the
places where they would have hit now
remember it's a little bit confusing
because we allow early termination if
you hit a bounding volume early and then
you don't gather you gather the light
that's aggregated from that bounding
volume that's by design so again nothing
particularly weird here other than the
twitchy like this should be changing
every frame it's not so we just need to
go through and like start cleaning that
up and this should be fine
okay so that will would probably explain
what's happening with the lighting if
you look what's happening the lighting
now the reason why it's only slightly
it's you know slightly wrong or I don't
know how you want to say it is because
it's using sort of just two patterns to
sample the light so it's getting kind of
a weird result and I think we can
immediately sort of figure out why that
is the reason for that is we haven't
really done much to permute the light I
was just using the sample point index
and so if the sample point index these
indices come in relatively stable
meaning certain you know we don't really
shuffle where entities are very much per
frame then that's just not going to add
very much randomness so what I think we
need to do here probably is just add an
offset here you know something like this
where we take a certain amount of sample
point entropy and we add that in and
that comes from the series itself so I
can just say sample point entropy equals
you know random u-32 and that would give
me and actually note we called this
let's go ahead and fix that shall we
docents typing more than we need to all
right and so now that we've got a little
bit of entropy in there I'm expecting to
see more variation and I do right now
it's not going to be as much variation
as before because again we are not
actually giving it in full randomness
we're just giving it sixteen different
random samples to go through now that 16
is fairly arbitrary we can make as many
as we want but that's the idea here is
that that that randomness is sort of
coming from a set of patterns that we're
permuting through and what we can see
now that we've fixed that is we're much
closer to the original pure random
version which is what I wanted to see so
I'm much happier about that now then you
know then the the previous version which
is kind of wrong so what I'd like to do
now is actually replace those lighting
samples because you know the whole point
of this was to start using better
sampling patterns so I'd like to do is
replace those sampling patterns now with
one of the patterns that we were using
before and we can try some different
ones we don't need to do anything
specific we can try a couple different
ones but what I'd like to do is
basically give us the ability to kind of
cycle through them a little bit so we
can play with that so we know that we've
got these generate samples situations
here right what I'm gonna do is I'm kind
of gonna make this into a thing that is
you know probably a little more general
than we need but I'm just gonna say okay
look let's let's go ahead and pull this
out I'm gonna put this all the way at
the top and I'm basically gonna make a
little system for doing these samples
right and what I want to do is I want to
make a template right I want to say okay
this is a lighting
sample pattern or something right and
these lighting sample patterns I'm just
going to say you know whatever give me
the name
the function and what I'm going to do is
I'm gonna make that pattern be the the
template that we've defined already that
all these things use so this gives me a
way to like define one of these right
and you know once I have one of those
I'm gonna use the macro here to define
the callback I don't really want that in
there probably so I can use it for other
things later but anyway I'm gonna use it
to define the pointer like a callback to
this thing so I can use a pointer to
refer to one of these and so I'm gonna
say there's a lighting sample sample
pattern and a generator how about this
seem good there I'm gonna use that to
generate a pointer here basically for
that so that we have a type def it's not
a pointer but it's a type of this thing
so that I can use it to declare pointers
to it and then I'm just gonna make all
of these people use that so here's the
polar samples okay here's the spiral
samples here's the Poisson samples and
now each of these is is like definitely
uniform because we're using a macro to
generate all of them right so they might
I'm gonna do is I'm gonna lock this up
and put that into the main body of the
of the lighting system here and so
inside the lighting solution I'm can now
say okay which you know which pattern
generator or whatever we're using I can
do that or I can do you know whatever I
want there right in fact well you know
what
now I think about it I don't even really
need to do that I can just put it here
and that'll be fine with me so what I'm
gonna do is say that we have a certain
number of lighting patterns and
right and I can put that right here and
then I can just put the names of these
things into a array so that I have I'm
just you know creating a way that I can
refer to these things generically so
don't only have to care which one I'm
using right so now I know that I've got
this mini lighting pattern generators
and if I wanted to right I could cycle
through them so I could do something
like lighting pattern generator index or
something like that and then what I
could do is say okay let's just make a
function that initial like that does
whatever it needs to do to initialize
the lighting with a particular one of
these all right
so in order to do that let's say
generate lighting pattern and I'm going
to use the lighting solution and I guess
all I really need to do here is say well
kind of think of how I want to structure
this but let's say I do generate
lighting pattern and I've got this
solution here and what I want to do I
the way that I'm kind of thinking about
this is I feel like if I set maybe a
debug value I feel like I could even
extend this a little bit more and just
say like lighting pattern is a thing
that has a name and a lighting pattern
generated I don't know why I didn't
actually put a type in here sorry about
that I'm gonna make a name here and then
I'm gonna have a generator pointer right
and what I could do is I can then just
say like okay you know maybe I just have
a
thing here that's like you passed the
function and it just automatically
generates you know the name of the
function and the function right so this
basically gives us a table with names in
it so that we can print out which one
we're using if we want to and so when we
receive pattern index here what I could
do is just say in fact I could even just
get rid of this entirely just say
generate lighting pattern and then what
I do is I say okay I need to generate a
certain number of these right so I need
to take the random series from the
solution and then I need to go through
however many of the sample patterns I
need to generate so this is like I don't
know what I want to call this they're
kind of like different versions of it
this is like a version index because
we're gonna generate many different
versions of the same pattern right and I
want to go through however many there
are in the sample point array and then I
want tubes I should probably change the
name of this from sample point to
something else it's really sampled
direction but we'll do that in a second
so what I want to do here is just say
okay let's call whichever one of these
were actually using and in order to do
that I can pull one out here right so I
can say lighting pattern pattern equals
lighting pattern generators pattern
index and we'll just let it wrap so
however many there are this thing
right so this gives us the ability to
just kind of loop through these and then
what I want to do is I want to call the
pattern generator with the information
we had before that it needed right one
was the series to use and I think yeah
these series is just kind of so I feel
like these series is should just get
used actually I don't think we need to
do this thing at all actually so we can
just kind of get rid of this entirely
here and just use the random set that
we're past in which seems more sane to
me fix that because these are offline
now we didn't know if these are getting
done in real time or anything like that
we know they're not going to be now so
they can be kind of a slow and pokey as
they want to be okay so now we can go
through each of these I'd say okay put
it in the sample point array that
corresponds to whatever one of these
we're trying to generate here and off
you go right now it's a little bit
squirrelly
because we know we want to generate v3
for X versions of this stuff and so one
of the problems that we're gonna have is
yeah these are not generating things B 3
for X now maybe we don't want to
generate v3 for X because it's just a
pain in the butt to do it that way since
it's more of this weird packed format so
what I could do instead to is I could do
the packing right so what I could do is
say all right let's suppose we've got
four of these arrays right and I could
just have it generate them and then do
the pack myself so for example we could
do a temp array here that had you know a
array of 16 of these that was four times
right and when we pass this in
we can literally just call this thing
four times right that allows these to
work on a raise of the threes which are
you know more straightforward don't
involve any sim D or anything like that
they can just do their generation the
old-fashioned way and then when I
actually go to use it I can say okay
let's integrate them back to put it into
the array proper so when we go to put it
in here I can say you know loop through
this array and in fact I could just pull
this out like so so I can grab out our
destination here and I can say like okay
you know however many of these were
gonna do we need to make one of these v3
for X's oops
of course I don't remember how to do
that is it just like that I think it
might just be like that and we're gonna
make that out of the various sliced
elements of the randomly generated set
of patterns right so we know that if
we're generating these well you know
what and there's the even another reason
to do this because I forgetting one step
of the process but there's another
reason we want to do this too and that
is actually because when we generate
these things we're generating we're
actually generating 64 of these right
now that I think about it it's actually
a little more complicated than that
we're actually generating 64 of these
and then we need to group them right
into bundles that cast together so
actually I didn't need to do quite that
we actually want to do this and then we
need to run a thing here that will
cluster right that will go grab so
there's actually another part of the
process that has to happen here so it's
actually even more complicated than that
right so that's good to know so anyway
but we can still do a temporary version
of this that we'll just run slowly
because remember our routine will still
work it'll just run more slowly if we
don't pick if we don't bundle rays that
are close to the same direction so to
start with just to get things working we
can just stuff any for rays in there so
we can do something like say okay you
know we've got four times Durand X plus
zero one two and three right so we can
just say like all right here is what
we're gonna pack in there we're just
gonna grab any four of these and it's
fine
and off we go right so that would do it
and the problem again with this is just
that it won't have any particular
coherent the for rays per bundle will
just be pointing in any random
directions so we will get poorer
performance out of this compared to what
we would hope to or at least we think we
would right so that's an easy way for us
to generate the lighting pattern and
hold on a second let me debug all this
that's not supposed to be there and this
should be a plus and then we're good so
that's pretty much everything there now
what we want to do is actually call this
thing so inside the init function which
is right here where we're doing this
random generation we can actually we can
put the random generation into a its own
system here cuz I don't think we have
one of those we've got polar samples
spiral samples and Poisson samples we
should just add another one here which
is like generate white noise samples or
something right
and this would
just do the straightforward version of
this so this would generate pure white
noise so and one of the things about
this is we've hard-coded it to 64 the
reason for that is because I don't I
don't want to force these things to be
parameterised on a number because like
for example here we were fine-tuning it
very specifically so that's why you'll
notice I'm just kind of hard coding 64
in here I wouldn't be adverse to making
it parameterised on the number I just
don't want to do that
yet because it just creates more work
for trying to like how do you know you
got to make a thing that generates this
table correctly for any number right and
whatever so I don't know some things are
much easier to parametrize that way than
others and so I just for now we're just
gonna stick with they only generate 64
in the future if we're feeling saucy
maybe we would do something different
but not right now okay
so if we generate random bilaterals here
on the white noise one this we've
decided it's kind of not a particularly
great way to generate these necessarily
but whatever and so here I'm going to
generate a random unilateral pointing
upwards this is not really white noise
it's kind of biased so we can improve
that as well if we want to and this can
just get actually assigned directly as
well
so that'll generate random samples for
us and that gives us a pattern here as
well now in here when I do the generate
lighting pattern I'm just wondering if I
can do this I don't really remember to
what extent we can display string values
or anything like that it would be nice
if we could but I don't really remember
so yeah we don't really have a string
based thing here that I can see we
almost want like a debug note right
where we could just say hey this thing
wants to have an actual just a value
like a care star that you print you know
what I mean but I don't think we have
anything like that that I know of anyway
pretty sure we don't have it yeah I mean
we sort of we
[Music]
yeah I don't think we have anything like
that because the way that we store these
things internally right
like the way that we saw these things
internally they've got I mean they have
a fair bit of stuff stored with them
here but it's not really it's not really
the same sort of thing although the name
so the name in the grid can be specified
separately so I suppose that would
probably do it right
I'm going to take a look at how this is
parsed here
these are all just drawing commands
so here when we do data I think it's
right here this is where we do store
event and you can kind of see when we
come through here the event
I guess just gets my head was in the way
when we get one of these events
that's what does the cloning right so if
we wanted to we could I guess do
something here that would potentially
yeah I mean there's there's so there's a
lot of ways we could handle this here's
how I think we should handle it because
it does seem like at this point we
probably want to keep the old dll's
around since we had had problems with
that and it took us too much work to
really make it so that we could unload
old dll's it just seems like a bad idea
right it seems like what we would want
to do here is just make one of these
types be a pointer to a string because
we want to be able to just do something
like you know something like that you
know I'm saying where we can just make a
care star and have that work and then in
here there's just a like okay you know
and that's probably more like up here
with the basic types right something
like this and then if we want to we can
look at like you know where this stuff
gets printed out and you can kind of see
we don't really want any interactions
with them or toggles really so the only
place we really care would be here and
so what we could do is just say like
okay there's a string pointer case here
we don't care about this so when we go
to print it out it's just like yeah you
know print it out just just print it out
and so in theory that would let us do
printouts of that form sorry
and here I could just say yeah let's
just say that we're gonna store one of
these things so we want to do a debug
value and I'm gonna call it
let's see pattern name right all right
so now if I go into the interface I'm
hoping that it's just as simple saying
all right let's just make one of these
debug value calls that happens to work
with the with a with a string right and
if we take a look at what's going on
here I think I think we should be able
to I guess like you know maybe I want to
do this just so I can make sure that I
have kind of my own version of it that I
know I'm calling specifically but I
think that should be about it so that
will become that will all become very
straightforward I don't know why do bug
type unknown gets passed to record debug
event there and gets set after the fact
but I'll continue that pattern and then
when we go to set the the value I think
we just need to do that
to be honest though I don't know why we
even need to do this we're not allowing
this to be edited so really I can just
do that so honestly I don't even think
most of that's necessary I don't even
know that we need to call that I think
we can just do that right because all
those gyrations were to make it so that
we could get around the you know C's
sort of unwillingness to play with us
and to avoid using some nasty template
ugliness but I think that's really all
we need so in theory I think now inside
our lighting stuff if we wanted to call
our NIT lighting code if our lip line
code wanted to just call a lighting
pattern generator I think it can so in
order to do that we would just say
here's the solution and here's the
lighting index we want you to use in
theory it will generate using whatever
that pattern generator is and we should
also see a thing in here that says which
one was used if I'm not wrong about that
although I don't know since we don't
call multiple times I suspect that's it
right there and so it looks like I
wasn't quite right about it because you
can see that it doesn't actually show
anything right this thing was supposed
to that thing was supposed to be it so
okay not quite correct but let's take a
look at that because I would like that
to work so we do need to do these two
things record the event and that seems
like it should be okay right it's the
same as if it was a be 32 let me just
take a look at what value said event
data is supposed to do it's that's the
type which we do
and it sets the value which we also do
so it seems like that should be okay
and I'm not quite sure why it wouldn't
be let me check that out though that's
in init lighting so if i whoops ah yes I
forgot since we're not currently
compiling with the we're not currently
compiling with the C runtime library in
our win32 we are missing our seal and
floor functions which we hadn't done yet
and I'm not sure why I can't get it in D
mode to inline those because I want it
to inline those but it doesn't seem to
want to and so I'm wondering how I would
do that right force in line C left m/s
you see
because I want it to inline these
and I'm not sure exactly how to make it
do that I wonder if I have to specify
like an arch sse2 kind of thing or
something like this
to get it to do that that's not relevant
look I just want to say yeah you know
anything you were gonna in line I wanted
in line from the CRT I don't want you to
optimize my code anymore but that should
get and maybe there's just no way to do
that right look maybe it's gonna do that
one way or the other which I guess is
fine but you know implementing sealer
floor is actually pretty straightforward
we can we can throw that in there I
suppose with the other thing we can do
so the trivial way to implement sealer
floor is if you don't care about which
version of SSE you're using you can do
that so I can show you there's some
pretty simple stuff in here for that so
we want let's see
I want my rounding functions
where are you
so the ceiling and floor functions our
special cases of here it is this is the
one I was looking for so by the time you
get to SSE 4.1 which we have not been
using yet so I don't know that we really
want to leave this in but for now it's a
pretty trivial way to do it and to be
honest we did look before and it was not
very similar to when we looked at the
starters project because I was we've
been programming on this for a while due
to the slow pace of the one hour well I
should say four hours a week four out of
five hours a week if we actually take a
look at how the PC processor usage sets
up here one thing you will notice is
that you can actually probably just use
SSE 4.2 and 4.1 now these numbers were
not so favorable three or four years ago
they were more like 70% right and so you
had to be careful about using something
like SSE for we probably just could use
them now I don't know if we want to make
that decision or not but it's pretty
striking how much higher they are so you
know your mileage may vary but we
definitely could temporarily we
certainly can but it's just worth noting
that that's something we may want to
replace when you get to SNA 4.1 these
floor and seal are built into the
hardware so you don't need to do any
work to get them and in fact what they
are is special cases of this particular
function here you can see actually if I
go look at one of these like Coss you
can see that they all call the same
function round SS around PS whichever
whether you're rounding forward a time
or one at a time they'll call the same
function and it's just a different
immediate so the way that it works is
instead of the old way the same way that
like the I the x87 worked in whatever
where there's a rounding mode and when
you go to round off a number it uses
that rounding
mode even if you are trying to do
something else with it potentially what
this function does is it ignores the
rounding mode of the unit and just takes
an immediate that says what the rounding
mode is so this way you can floor seal
truncate or so you can you can round
towards negative infinity round towards
positive infinity so that's floor and
seal you could truncate towards zero
which is like the C runtime libraries
like or the C language way of converting
a number and or I think there's one more
which is you can round to nearest so
rather than biasing in a particular
direction or towards zero towards
negative deprives me
it's just whichever number is closest
right so I believe you get four choices
there and you can see what they are yeah
here you go
so there's round to nearest round down
round up and truncate and you have all
of those pieces of information right and
what you can see here is there's also
some extra sauce you can put in here
where if you wanted to if you wanted to
do something like have floating-point
exceptions on in the SSE unit but then
for certain operations when you're
rounding just say okay for this time I
don't want them on you can actually
specify that specifically so it's kind
of just a way of overriding everything
you previously told the chip to do
during around and it's awesome I love
this instruction so if it really is the
case that we can use this now I'm
certainly a happy camper to say the
least like if we were just if the new
world order is that you can use up to
SSE 4.1 I would be delighted because
that just gets rid of a bunch of like
weird like four to five instruction
things you have to do to floor and seal
numbers gnarly and replace it with just
one clean instruction that tells it ship
exactly what you wanted but I don't know
about that yet either way like I said
because this is causing us a pain in the
in the booty right now I'm just gonna go
ahead and say we'll use it temporarily
and then if we want to replace it later
we can write our square roots already
doing this right and so now the question
is alright can we just go ahead and and
put some other stuff in here that would
fix it so here's our functions we've got
them all here we've got round
right there it is we've got floor and
seal and you can see that we're still
calling the C runtime library for some
of these so what I'm gonna do is I'm
going to go ahead and try just replacing
these the flooring functions with one of
these so I'm gonna go ahead and say mmm
you know round SS because again we don't
need the PS version because we're not
doing four at a time we're only doing
one at a time for these particular
things right so for flooring I want to
do I guess I'll use the intrinsic even
though we could just call the round
intrinsic and pass it the right thing
all actually cooks call floor SS and
what you can see here is when we call
floor SS it's going to do a rounding for
it's going to do a floor on the second
value that gets passed in on the bottom
and then the rest of the bits will just
be whatever are passed in here now we
don't care what the rest of the bits are
so you know like we it doesn't matter
what we're passing there but we have to
pass something there because that's just
how the instruction works right so we
can pass it as zero for the thing that
we're flooring and we can go ahead and
and load in a single oops load in a
single value here for the value that we
actually want right and so what will
this will do is this will do the
flooring operation but we still have to
get it out and so this part still needs
to happen right so although we have to
kind of smush all those together that by
itself will now do the complete floor
operation I'll put it to do in here
because we don't necessarily know that
that's something we want but once we if
we do make that statement then as you
can see these are very straightforward
right
and and so yeah and in theory everything
just works exactly as it was working
right there's no no difference there
right so those are really really easy
implications of Florence seal because
you don't really have to think we don't
have to go figure out how to do a good
flooring or ceiling operation ourselves
which is what we would have had to do
before sse 4.1 and so yeah if you can
get away with us see for everyone
definitely do what I just did
if you can't get rid that see for
everyone which we have to see whether we
can or not then you have to think a
little harder about it but it's
definitely either way it's not like sine
or cosine it's not as hard to implement
as something that's actually gonna
require a bunch of math thinking to to
do necessarily so anyway back to our
regularly scheduled program here oops I
do you want to store that breakpoint um
so when I step through here I just
wanted to see what was going on with our
our debug string here and I guess it's
not gonna let me step through that macro
of course
so I guess we won't really be able to
see much about what that event pointer
looks like because of course it doesn't
want to tell us what the event pointer
looks like which is unfortunate what is
kind of nice about that however is I
could force it to if I wanted to because
we know the type here I could make a
little function that we definitely are
going to hit right so you know I could
do something a little bit more specific
there right like I could make one of
these specific to this type and make
sure it gets called we also see
something here because we're setting
value string pointer to whatever the
value is it's point passed in which is
exactly what I want to do and we're you
know we're trying to print that out here
but for whatever reason something
bizarre is happening to us somewhere
down the line and I'm not sure why I
want to kind of stop here I think to
verify that I'm right that that's what's
actually getting printed out in the
first place
because I don't actually know that right
so let me just go ahead and take a look
at that so if I just stop here I want to
see if we are if that is in fact
thinking I was thinking it was yeah so
let me open this up
so it does look like that was thing I
was thinking it was so at least now I
can look at this event a little bit more
carefully right so here's the event that
we supposedly recorded and you can see
here that the string pointer is set to
null which doesn't really make a lot of
sense the grid is correct the name is
not so for whatever reason this didn't
get processed properly right the debug
type string didn't get processed the way
that we would want now maybe that's just
because I'm using an enum range here let
me take a look where's the set of these
guys so let me just do a quick check so
anything other than the types that come
in here always get shunted down to the
standard storage format right
yeah and all of these things yes I mean
I don't really know why that would be
causing a problem all of these things
are you know but the the eight wide
pointer for the value string fits just
fine
in the space that we have here for all
the rest of our stuff so there's no
reason why it shouldn't have been
propagated properly but yet it's like
not even parsing the event information
for whatever reason and I'm not really
sure why that would be
so if I take a look here at emit
lighting so let's say we I call a nearly
identical function and then we run it if
I open up our debug view now so it does
look like for whatever reason this part
of the pass is just busted right so
inside here in the generated lighting
pattern call we're we're just not
getting our debug printouts properly
like the its ability to record those is
somehow hampered right it's not it's not
able to record those the first time
through maybe because they're only done
the first time through or something
weird right is happening there where it
loses the ability to to track those
somehow you know what I'm saying the the
name like goes away or something so it
looks like it's a per frame problem if I
if I went you know outside to something
that gets called every time so like
compute light propagation right and I do
this I suppose I can also
you know all of a sudden it's like
correct so it seems like we've got a
thing where we can't just issue
something one frame and leave it there
which doesn't make a lot of sense to me
because I didn't know we were doing that
meaning I didn't know that we had like a
decay on things in that way when we
actually go to record debug events so
I'm not sure why that would be the case
but obviously it is the case and so if
something doesn't get hit on a
subsequent frame it's like it doesn't
really get saved somehow because it's
never going to trigger one of these
again right it will never be seen it's
only being seen one time inchoate debug
records so it shouldn't really ever go
away I don't think unless it's just
eventually it gets removed because it
gets used for something else right but
even that I don't think is the case
because well I guess it might be for the
actual value yeah I guess I could see
that so for now I guess I'll say alright
that's okay
but I don't love it
so I'll just store the name here and
that should be that so when we run now
hopefully we can't see it correctly
there's generate white noise samples and
so if I make a you know some kind of a
function here where I'm just gonna say
hey baby pattern something like that
when we do those F key things we had
like some in here that would cycle
through let's just instead of doing this
if we hit the f9 key now what I'm going
to do is say generate lighting pattern
and pass it like
you know just an index that just goes up
right so now at least in theory right if
I come in here and I look at this
letting pattern it's white noise samples
if I switch to polar samples then I get
that right
if I switch to spiral samples then I get
that and if I switch to Poisson samples
then I get that you know I'm saying to
you and I guess the first thing that I
would point out is actually it does
exactly what I wanted so using the
stratified sampling the amount of noise
has dropped dramatically right like the
flicker is way way less than it was and
the lighting is much more consistent
like that actually looks really good
right I don't remember how to stop
drawing the debug lines but I think
there is a way to do so in here
somewhere maybe this one although that
thing that just stops them from updating
I don't think that stops them
necessarily from drawing I'm not sure
yeah I don't think there's any way to do
that
unfortunately at the moment so that was
supposed to F 2 is supposed to stop
debug lines from being used what's going
on there
No well that'd do it
so again just cycling through these now
so there's white noise there's polar
which doesn't have noise in it right now
so it's not really a good test
here's spiral and here's plus long
and that looks pretty nice
I may not know about you but I'm pretty
happy with that and that's entirely CPUs
side right now right look we're not
using any GPU for for lighting at the
moment you'll also notice that our speed
has taken a hit right and that's exactly
what I was saying before about how you
know we can't we have this problem where
we're not bundling our arrays at the
moment so it feels like we want to do
that bundling as well just to make sure
that we get our speed back but otherwise
I feel like that's pretty darn nice and
I'd be interested to know now if we just
introduced more lights back in the mix
[Music]
how we're doing where's our snake
remember if this still has lights
attached to it or not
yeah so now the snake should be adding
some light and it is you can kind of see
it and what happens if we make it be
brighter I don't know unfortunately
don't actually know what add piece light
does mission so you know I could make
the snake really bright
and you can kind of see like so you can
see some of the bugs in the weight well
Maui bugs but approximation cost so we
need to do probably some more work on
our aggregation because that's working
pretty well now but you can also see
that it kind of like as it aggregates
the lighting in an area it spreads it
too much in the case where the the
aggregate lighting gets summed up into a
box the thing gets used by someone who's
further away you get some error in there
so we didn't want to tune that probably
you know but you know like we really
take no hit from adding that was adding
six more light sources right and it just
works which is pretty great you know I'm
saying and so I think that's nice
because it means you know we have the
option to just like throw lights around
however we want and we don't really
suffer performance penalty because we're
always convecting light every frame for
every surface so it's not like we're
doing something that has a per light
cost right at the moment we're also like
so I got a switchback too I got to make
it so we default to the plus one I think
I want to use the Poisson version of the
lighting but we're going to improve it a
little bit too so let's go ahead and
switch to pass on by default I think
that's the one I want to go with just
based on looking at them so here's the
poisson based version and right you can
see how it over lights that area because
of that that distance and we don't know
what that distance should be set to
right it could be we just need to set
that distance a little higher and then
it's fine
but it just it leads to errors because
we don't do like occlusion to figure out
like whether or not you could see the
lighting that's supposedly coming from
there so we have you know we could do
more work on our construction where we
build those boxes of light distributions
that would prevent having
errors of that forum now you know again
in a game it's hard for people to know
that that really is an error sometimes
but you know so you've got a lot of
leeway there you just want nice effects
they don't necessarily have to be
accurate and especially with something
like lighting but it's just like you can
kind of see like that light is coming
from up here because it's casting to a
box that's a little further away and so
it might be that like you know that
that's just the that distance is too low
right so if we come down here we also
really probably don't need this anymore
so if we take a look in here we've got
the close enough thing so this T close
enough you know maybe that's more like
ten I don't know right and it's hard to
say we'll have to tune that value and
see what our performance looks like and
see what our our stability looks like
and so on but if we do something like
that and we're gonna have to make sure
we're bundled for us to evaluate the
real cost but if we do something like
that then we'll get a lot less of those
errors so now the lighting is would be
much more accurate than it was before
because it actually does much more
localized occlusion right and so now if
you look up here although these people
are still lighting up there they're not
lighting down here because these people
correctly pick up these as occluding
them before checking for lights that are
aggregated somewhere else right so
that's just worth noting but again
looking really good I mean I'm really
happy with this I think this is pretty
awesome and I think I would go ahead and
press forward on this now we still have
a little bit more we can do here
obviously like I saying
so this sampling is not cosine biased
and we then we still introduce the
cosine bias later so we could probably
still fix some of that
so if we want to and and then we have to
do our bundling for Speed purposes right
so if we wanted to generate so we're
using the Poisson samples here if we
wanted to generate Poisson samples that
are cosine weighted there actually are
some other ways we can do it and in fact
we can make our Poisson generator
probably a lot better than it is right
now - by taking advantage of some
opportunities that we have here so let's
talk about those and maybe go ahead and
implement that right so if we pop back
to Milton for a second here and do a
little bit of drawing one of the classic
ways and this has been brought up on
stream as well but one of the classic
ways of doing cosine weighting if you
know that you can generate things in a
disc pattern so one of the classic ways
of generating saying that's cosine
biased is if you were trying to generate
cosine bias and by cosine bias what I
mean is if we are looking at the
Hemisphere we know that we're gonna very
low weight things that are in these
directions and we're gonna high weight
things that are in these directions
because of the way that the lighting
shaft Falls the amount of light that
gets collected from things in that area
it's the rule member we drew it out the
amount of light coming in from this
right triangle right versus the one
coming in from here right the amount the
size of that aperture is very different
so if we know that we want to have that
weighting what we can do is take that
weighting out of the light propagation
function right cuz right now what's
happening is that actually this angular
fall-off term here is doing that inner
product what we could do instead is just
get rid of that right so we could say
you know what the angular fall-off isn't
gonna count anymore
right we're just not gonna count it
anymore and if we were to do that now we
would be getting essentially an
erroneous light you know it would be
wrong how much light that we're actually
getting in the scene unless we then bias
our
sampling to always go biased in the
towards samples that come from higher up
because we can basically put the cosine
term into the sampling bias rather than
just something that happens after the
fact right and so in order to do that
all we really have to do there say okay
if we're going to bias our sampling in
that fashion
we now need these functions to really
put out things that are biased cosine
weighted weighted towards the cosine
right so in order to do that again for
plus on sample so I think it's one we
want to go with it's pretty
straightforward for us to do that
actually one of the techniques for it is
to say well why don't we just say let's
generate things in a plus on pattern on
a disk and then project them up because
if we project them up then what's going
to happen you can kind of see here if I
draw it in 2d what's gonna happen is
most of our points right that are close
to the edge here they're still gonna
project up quite a ways and most of our
points that are in the center will sort
of still stay in the center so it's very
hard to produce things down here because
the upward projection means you have to
be really close to the edge to get it
where as it's really easy to produce
points here because any point at all
that was roughly in this shaft is going
to project right on up to there right so
it creates a natural cosine weighting by
projecting it up to the sphere and so
what we can do is just generate things
in a disk and then project them up to
the sphere so for starters what we can
do is we can generate our sphere and
project up as two separate passes right
so let's change our plus on generator to
do that so what I want to do is you can
see here we're running like the lighting
equation and all that and that's all
well and good but what I'd rather do at
the moment is I want to go back to the
thing where we were drawing these things
and so I can see the distribution and
make sure that we're doing it properly
so if we come on down to this code here
and we take a look at how we were
redrawing this stuff before I want to
re-enable the one that was just like
putting oops that's not what I wanted at
all I lied I want this one and I want
this one to draw our sampling patterns
so what this is going to do is this is
going to go ahead and take however many
of these are in one of the sample point
patterns we're going to go through one
of the sample point patterns and we're
gonna grab out each of the sample points
right and we've got four per so the
component index here where we don't
really need this color table thing
anymore
for any particular reason I'll still
leave it in there but we'd like this is
not particularly relevant obviously
anyway
if we did want to put that in there we
can do four times point index plus comp
index that would still get the
alternating colors anyway
so if we want to grab out the normal
here we can look at the sample point
patterns that we have we're going to
just draw the zero with one and we're
going to take the point index out of
that we want to do a get component on it
so that we can just get a v3 out of it
so then at that point we draw it and
we're good to go right so that's just
reinstating the thing that draws these
components that draws the the sample
pattern so that if we go in here let me
get this out of the way to go in here we
can see our Plus on pattern that's what
it looks like at the moment and so now
what I want to do is I just want to
generate a disk worth of data so I want
to generate a plus on pattern but I
might generate it on a disk okay
we'll see how that works so I'm gonna go
to generate plus on samples and on here
what I want to do is generate things in
the disk so what I want to do is just
keep the same
loop here but when I do this v3 what I'm
gonna do is I don't care what the Z
value is okay
so I'm just gonna generate these in a
disc instead of measuring by the cosine
I'm now gonna measure by the distance so
I'm going to say like okay there's a
disc value oh that was a spring back
yeah so all I'm gonna do now is say I
want to take the distance so I'm gonna
take the length squared we might as well
of the one that we're checking here and
the one that I've produced and again we
know this is now just in 2d because we
know the Z's are always zero and I want
to make sure that if it is less than so
that the length squared is less than the
minimum distance squared then I want to
throw it out right we stop at that point
so I just need a value for a minimum
distance squared and again this is just
a constant now I don't know what that
value should be because we're trying to
pack 64 points in here I'm not sure what
it should be you know maybe it's 0.1 or
something like that well know if if we
can't actually run successfully what is
the question oh sorry supposed to be a -
there you go and so let's see if we can
get this going okay so that's too small
so now we should see a point here oh
yeah that's why we don't want to
normalize these yet there we go
so this will go ahead and produce our
disk and sorry about that
afterwards we'll figure out how to lock
them out but yeah so let's try that one
more time all right so here's our random
samples right and they're not conforming
to disk at all so that's fine but
they're also not really very Poisson
distributed because this is probably too
low so the first thing we want to do to
get this to the place that I wanted it
to be which is a you know a random
hemisphere sampling cosine weighted is
now we want to reject anything oops we
want to reject anything that's not in
the circle right so we want a unit
circle so if we find that in fact I can
just use the valid here if we find that
the x squared oops plus the Y squared is
greater than one that means it's outside
the circle and we want to throw it away
right so since this is supposed to be
valid it needs to be inside so we really
want less than or equal to one but that
will constrain us to being inside the
disk and so now if we look we only have
points that are inside the disk but
they're not very well spread out and
again that's because this value is
probably two lakhs so we need to enforce
a higher distance constraint here on
these and so now it's starting to spread
out a little bit better but still not
great and so let's keep going Jack it up
a little bit more it's still not quite
good enough
now we're starting to get somewhere
right that's starting to look okay but I
still think we can we want to probe for
the crash point there we go
so that's looking real nice right that's
looking like a nice distribution of
points right
pretty even looking good to me oops
let's see how 1.7 is I assume that's too
high
nope not quite so that's a real nice
distribution of points right there you
know I'm saying to you it's looking good
so now what we want to do is project
those up and if we're gonna project
those up all we really have to do is
just run through our disk now and do
exactly that right so we have a test
index and we go through all the points
we then say for each individual point
let me go ahead and grab it out
so what we want to do is modify P here
to project it up we know this quantity
again right and to be fair this is
really just the length of P so you know
if we wanted to we could just say that
there's no real reason for us to write
it out so this is actually you know a
shorthand way of saying that and you can
see we still get the same results there
so then what we want to do is say okay
if that's our length squared on P then
what we want to do here now is take our
destination index run through those and
do the same thing so we know what the
length squared of P is here and we want
to write an equation that will project
us up to the correct height to fill in
that gap so what we know about our our
circle here let me just here we can draw
it so we know effectively that we have
some some point right and I could do
this in sort of a 2d diagram we know
that we have along one of these axes
let's say the x axis we know we have
some point right and we know we want to
reject it up here so if we were only in
2d right how would we do that well we
know that we want the resulting vector
to be unit length right and so and if it
was unit length it will be by definition
on this sphere so what we need to do is
say okay if it's unit length we know
that it's length squared that we were
computing right has to equal one right
now we know it's less than or equal to
one it is not equal to one so what we
need to do is fill in the Z value
because remember the egg we're
projecting up to the sphere so that x
and y can't change we just need to fill
in the Z value such that we account for
the rest of the unit length
right so we want to say that our x
squared plus our y squared plus our Z
squared right where these two are known
and this one isn't we want to say that
that has to equal one because we want
this to always be unit length so if we
then solve for our Z right we're going
to have 1 minus x squared minus y
squared and we're gonna square root that
right so very very straightforward this
value here is the same as that right so
1 minus the length of the vector
currently Square rooted is what the Z
has to be set to does that make sense
so we already knew what the length
squared is of this thing that means our
Z value or I could just set it directly
is that oops
not quite that there we go
and now we know that we have a properly
normalized vector as a result if I
didn't mess up the math always a
possibility
um so going back to our visualization
now we should see these things nicely on
a dome and we do so in theory now we're
getting this should be cosine weighted
in terms of our samples let's take a
look and see if it really is it's a
little hard to say just how cosine
weighted that actually is
kind of want to be inside the sphere of
looking out for this you know but it
does seem pretty good
um so I feel like you know it seems
pretty good I don't really know though
[Music]
so what I kind of want to do is check
does that make sense like what I'd like
to do here is see whether I think it
really is weighted or not by just
summing up all of the samples and seeing
what we get right because we should be
able to we should be able to actually do
a a summation over the sample points and
produce a value that confirms how cosine
weighted it actually is does that make
sense so if I was to do the integral
over the sphere or even just do a test I
guess one of the problems is how many of
these you know are you gonna do exactly
and so on
if I was to take the integral over the
whole sphere right I mean over the whole
hemisphere of something that was cosine
weighted I get a particular numerical
value out if I do the same thing on my
supposedly cosine weighted set of
samples and do a summation of one at
each point instead of the angular
fall-off at each point I should get
similar results so let's try that I also
would like to turn on those debug lines
real quick so here's the casting
not quite sure how this is getting lit
because it's only looking downward I
wonder if we have a bug in terms of the
directionality of light somewhere where
that cuz that should never hit anything
I'm interested to know I want to move my
sampler down there actually let's do
that right now before I do any more with
the cosign so let's suppose that I move
the sky around
debug point location and I want to move
towards the blue I just basically want
to be under this this blue thing here
right so let me move I guess back
[Music]
not sure where my debug lines are at the
moment there we go so that's just
straight up pointing the wrong way
like it's able to shoot things out the
back somehow but I don't know how and
you can see it's not it's it is trying
to shoot things out the bottom as well
so it's shooting things off of it in
every direction so that's a very
interesting bug and we now have a good
test case to and I'm gonna leave this
locked in here because that should not
be happening right so what is the normal
at this point is my first question
let's go take a look so here is you know
the normal here's the x and y-axes so
the first thing I'm going to do is when
it changed the way this is being drawn
what I want to do here is I'm going to
use a a cyan line for a hit
and a yellow line for a Miss okay so
those should all be yellow and those
should all these ones there sampling the
interior here this should all be cyan
right see you bad happening then I'm
going to do is under our coordinate
system so I can see for the sample point
what its coordinate system is so I'm
gonna grab this push debug line
situation here and rather than drawing
anything per ray I'm gonna just draw
something per point here for the sample
point so when I hit this sample point
that I want to know about I'm gonna push
a few debug lines on here and these are
not going to be colored by anything
they're going to be wrote actually and
they're going to go from the position of
the sample point out along a vector like
so and I'm just gonna draw all of it
oops so this would be the world axis
right if I wanted to see what the world
axis were but I don't want the actual
world axis what I want is the axis for
this point and it turns out we actually
have that information right that's what
we're using to base our cast off and I
want to see whether it's right cuz maybe
it's just wrong and if it's wrong that
explains why our construction is bogus
oops so here's our coordinate frame
based off of the sample point and now I
can look and see what it actually has so
looking here you can see that actually
the coordinate frame is very good it's
exactly what I would have expected so
although our coordinate frame is very
good our ability to place our samples is
not right so now we kind of have to go
in here and look at this situation
because this is borked whatever is going
on here is just wrong okay so we have to
figure out what's going on there so
let's take a look at what we've got here
so our sample for DX value is pulling
out 4 sample points from our sample
point arrays and these sample point
arrays should all be normalized so that
they're pointing upward right so if we
take sample point D X's D 4 X dot Z
there right and I don't know why we
still call it D 4 X because we don't
really need to like I could call it
something else I suppose but well
whatever so if we want to figure out
what's going wrong here we have to
figure out why are we getting this weird
why is this weird behavior happening so
this is supposed to be lofting the
normal up and the XY axis into something
that we can use as a something that
operates across our entire set of
vectors we have our sample points here
and these should allow us to move along
the x y&amp;z axis such that we effectively
transform the sample into the right
space right so this is we would expect
to be working to correctly transform it
to a line to the normal but doesn't
appear to be doing so right it doesn't
appear to be doing that at all so the
question is why isn't it doing that
right
and I have no idea
[Music]
now I suppose one thing that I should
point out here actually is maybe we have
a bug in our ray caster that's allowing
Ray's to cast backwards oops if that's
the case let me even give it a little
bit of an epsilon here but I think it's
looking bad right if that's the case
then really
yeah we're oriented properly perhaps but
we are yeah we may be actually doing
everything right but our ray caster is
busted
where do we check to make sure that a
hit has to be greater than zero right
and the answer appears to be absolutely
nowhere
right I mean here we are we
I like we have pre invert the Ray for
more speed but it is pre inverted so
that's
you know we come through here and we're
looking to see if key max is greater
than zero so we're if any of these are
true if any of these paths then we're
gonna get inside here right and this T
valid I think this T valid actually
needs this case right because what was
happening is certain times you would get
a max pass on some other Ray and it
would allow a team in that was- to sleep
sneak in here right which is which is
incorrect so I think that's what we were
having happen there
much much much better
lovely
okay so the first thing to note is well
for starters I'm absolutely loving how
good this is looking but the first thing
to note is we got a lot brighter when we
turned off the angular fall-off right
which suggests to me that our sampling
pattern obviously is not well it's it's
one of two things either our angular
fall-off was messed up and was taking
too much light out of the system for no
reason or something right so you know we
don't know that that was correct maybe
it was buggy but the other thing that
might be happening is our cosine
weighting is not proper right so I still
think we want to then go investigate
that but at least now we know we why we
were getting those weird we back cast
there so that was just just a bug in the
optimized routine so now this all looks
good because now the only coloring you
see on the bottom where there shouldn't
be any light at all is coming from if
it's just a plate that actually was
taking a sample like up here right so
that's valid because the sampling was
actually coming out of like right here
where it could see a light and it's just
you know we don't actually check to see
that the pixels down here were you know
not obscured by something right because
we're not ray casting per pixel or ray
casting per plate so that all seems
relatively straightforward right so I'm
happy with that I just want to know why
we didn't have a similar amount of light
when we switched between the angular
fall-off version and this version right
and so I think we need to maybe get more
work we have to do more work to to place
to get the cosine waiting to happen
uh I think so here's another problem
that I think we may run into although
white noise on a disc lofted up might
produce a pattern that's going to be
cosine weighted that doesn't mean that
blue noise does because blue noise has
the artificial property of
forcing coverage into areas that
wouldn't normally be filled by random
samples so I don't actually know if this
is a really good way to do that process
so maybe that our previous way of doing
this is actually better than the disk
method even though the disk method would
be good for the white noise version so I
just wanted to kind of point out that I
think we will have to do more analysis
to really even know now I don't know
where we're at for time today we got
about 15 minutes left I think so yeah I
think that's fine so we got about 15
minutes left today so we need to do like
I said two more things I'm not gonna try
and do the bundling then we'll save the
bundling for next week
and I'll go ahead and put that down in
here where is that
so that should be fine
what I want to do here is I want to now
take a look at that to see what that
waiting actually ends up being right so
what I'd like to do here is say let's
figure out how to do a sampling
comparison so let's suppose that I
wanted to create I don't know a quote
unquote ground truth version to see what
happens if I take a certain number of
samples and I want to generate them
randomly and then I want to do weighting
right so I'm going to go ahead and do
I need to do some way of generating a
random sample on the sphere which I need
to actually be unbiased so what I
probably can do is if I generate any
random vector and throw out any vectors
that are outside the sphere would that
give me an unbiased sampling of the
sphere
you know it's hard to say I'm not sure
how to analyze that what I was basically
saying is if so you're like pick a
random direction if the direction is
greater than one say less than one right
so this produces a set of directions for
us and then what I want to do is take a
look at what the inner product of those
is so unweighted right what I want to do
is make a test some here and I want to
and in fact maybe I want to do this
let's run some tests where we do 64
samples I don't know how many times do
you want to run it a lot we will do to
some so as we loop over these I want to
do a you know a weighted product of
something so I just want to see okay
what's the the inner product as we were
doing it before the angle inner product
here oh and I also want to do if Terzi
is less than zero
there's the negative Z so I only want
things pointing upwards because it's a
hemisphere so I want to take the inner
product of the direction and I guess I
just want the inner drip let me let me
just go ahead and take a look at what we
were doing for make sure that that made
sense so the anger fall off was yeah it
was just against the surface normal so
it's really just that which is Z so it's
really the direction Z that I want to
sum right because the inner product is
just going to pick out just that Z value
so what we were previously doing is
we're basically multiplying by the Z
value right which is the cosine of the
angle between the two the direction and
the normal so I want to sum all these up
I'm just gonna sum up how many of these
we have in this case right and then at
the end I'm gonna say the min tests and
I can I can do this normalized by the
number of samples as well I suppose
so I could say like you know sample
count equals 64 sample count and then
say like you know average equals test
sum divided by sample count min test
average equals and I'll just keep
whatever ones it's correct right so that
gives me like bounds to look at for if
we were gonna take 64 sample points and
the reason I'm doing it this way is I
just kind of want to know generally
speaking I want to know if I was to do
the summation using the angular fall off
and but only using 64 samples which
isn't a lot if I was picking them
randomly
what would I end up with in that case
and then here I can do the same sort of
thing right
so then when I come over here and
generate all of these when I come
through them I can sum eight I could
summarize summarize some some it's just
some I can sum up all of the values that
I get here in the exact same way and see
if without waiting them they end up
equaling the right amount for a similar
amount right so off we go
so what I want to do here is just say
that whichever one of these is Z value
before I was doing test sum plus the the
dersy value right
wait a minute
so in order to do this I really just I
really do need to know though some other
function that I'm sampling so yeah if we
were going to wait a function by that
then this one should just add the
function directly without weighting it
right and I'm not sure how to put that
in here
hmm because I need some other function
right so what I want to do here is say
well what you know the function of X Y Z
I want to be able to evaluate the
function of X Y Z here and then multiply
it by dersy right so I want like I want
that right and then here I just want to
do that without waiting waiting it by
the Z does that make sense but that's
what I'm actually trying to do there and
then when we actually do this I want to
see how these compare to each other
right that's what I actually wanted but
without a test function it's hard to
know I suppose it doesn't matter what
the test function is the test function
could be anything so I suppose I can
just put something in here and say well
the result is you know Durex you know 3
times the direction X plus 2 times the
direction Y or something I don't know
plus you know -
five times the direction Z squared I
don't know
right I mean I don't this is something
I'm gonna have to think through a little
bit more but like we need some test
function that's like pretending the
world has something in it so we can see
how they differ in these two cases so I
think that's what I want to look at
something like this so I can take a look
at what the difference between those two
things actually ends up being
so yeah let's take a look
I mean test average max test average
well the fact that those are not even
close basically tells us that we're just
under sampling this / - this thing
pretty badly so you know there's that
which means it's gonna be a little bit
hard to do this test that way unless I
just got a bug in the code but that's
you know also this is not quite right if
we're allowing negative center functions
again so yeah I mean not great right
it's a pretty pretty big span there for
only with 64 samples which yeah I don't
know maybe that just means I'm bad at
sampling which I think we already know
so let me just take a look at what our
min average and Max averages of this
function so yeah not great right it
looks like it's you know it's lower
bound is similar but it's upper bound is
not you know which again you know this
is a pretty crappy test but that does
comport with what we're seeing in terms
of the you know the the difference
between those there so let me you know
let me try some a couple things here
that I'd like to I'd like to then play
with so let's suppose that we wanted to
look at the white noise samples
here we go so if we think that this
technique was working okay using the
disk what we can do is play with it a
little bit and and see if we can do a
white noise that's that's biased as well
so doing that would be much simpler all
that would be is we loop picking a
random sample in the disk so that's just
saying okay pick a random sample in the
disk like so if link squared P is less
than or equal to 1.0 then we're good to
go
p z equals square root point no f- the
length squared P so that just allows me
to generate the random value actually
random values in the disk and then
project up to the sphere right and
that's the more traditional route
actually completely random
so now if I run it and take a look at
what happens there because remember now
we're using the white noise samples and
I just want to see what the difference
is there so you can see it's a pretty
different it's it's pretty different
than than this version the problem is I
don't know how much to trust this
version negative 7 negative 0.7 I'm
sorry and point 1 5 is still quite a bit
different than the then the Plus on
sample so even if we just compare white
noise lofted up versus Plus on lofted up
you get a very different answer right
and again that may just be because this
is a bad test case so I don't want to
jump to conclusions about it but it
means we need to investigate further
right we need to drill down this a
little bit more and figure out what's
going on here because it's not quite
yeah it's it's not quite kosher yet this
might not be a good way of generating
unbiased samples on the sphere I need to
think of how to generate white noise
samples on a sphere that are unbiased
because this may not be it otherwise
also I should say this may bias you
still towards a projection of a cube and
I'm just not sure if it does or if it
doesn't
hard to say anyway let's go to the Q&amp;A
but next weekend I think that's where we
want to focus our attention
why I got to get a screenshot of that
the fact that in cybot said blows avatar
looks exactly like him is kind of
amazing did it put that together by
itself I I don't know how it did that
that was pretty great vadas hi not
really anon to have a question but you
said you'd talk about some tidbits
considering the sim to union type ah yes
I can
okay let me double check let me see what
we have for questions here really quick
[Music]
all right let me answer these other
questions really quickly and then I'm
gonna spend a little bit of time talking
about the sim D Union type so the risk
oh how are you feeling about the
progress of the lighting so far very
good I like it I like I like it a lot
Holst 80 is there any libraries
available that would help with just the
lighting stuff if you're you're working
right now it seems fairly involved and
required some iron D from the developers
part no idea I don't use libraries G
Princip why are you not sure about GPU
lighting do you think that it might not
increase the frame rate no I'm quite
sure we could get faster lighting by
using a GPU what I'm not sure about is
whether we have the GPU to spare because
if we want to use the GPU for doing a
bunch of other stuff then you know you
you want to balance your workload right
so we don't have necessarily a lot of
stuff to use the CPU for we aren't doing
like physics these sorts of things in
this game this game is very mechanical
and not supposed to have a physics
component to it so it's be very
predictable like an old-school arcade
game and so we the reason that I don't
know if it's a good idea to use GPU
lighting is because we may just end up
with a giant GPU workload because it
does the lighting the depth handling
those you know anti-aliasing all that
sort of stuff and at that point we just
end up with a CPU sitting idle doing
nothing and a GPU that's overloaded
right so the only reason I'm not sure
about you lighting is not because I
don't think we could do a reasonable
implementation of this lighting on the
GPU that would be fast it's because I'm
worried that we will overload the GPU
and have nothing for the CPU to do and
that seems like a bad situation to begin
so what do I dislike about Windows 10
some people complain that it because
their hatred against Microsoft
regardless of how good the product is
but I feel like they mixed a lot of
messy stuff after 8 and 8.1 were the
things you'd like them to fix so I would
say Windows 10 is a complete non-starter
I would
never use it for any purpose under any
circumstances I had to install it in
this machine because it was a brand new
machine so I was forced to otherwise I
would never do it it is completely
unacceptable for an operating system to
force updates period that is a hard if
an operating system requires you to
update it when it tells you to update it
is unacceptable
I don't need to know anything else about
the opera system you can tell me just
that one piece of information and that
is enough to know it is unacceptable an
operating system on my computer obeys me
period if that relationship ever changes
it's an unacceptable operating system
period so Windows 10 is not allowed Mali
rocket it will never be installed on a
computer here I only use Windows 10 on
the stream computer because it was a new
computer if we cannot find a way to
install something other than Windows 10
on new computers at Mali rocket then we
will either switch to Linux or find some
kind of hack that allows us to use an
older version of Windows we may be able
to use Windows 10 at Mali rocket if it
turns out that disconnecting Windows 10
from the internet since our dev machines
don't cooked up to the Internet makes it
so that it doesn't produce the forced
updates but if that still is the case
then it's a non-starter so we don't
really need to talk about anything else
I could go into a long list of reasons
that I don't like Windows 10 that are
separate from that but it's that one
that's just that's how you know this is
not acceptable operating system done a
operation whatever pops up a dialog box
actually he is unacceptable to me if you
want to notify me there's a new update
put that somewhere else you can put that
you know put that down here that's the
only acceptable place for it it should
never pop up anything in the middle of
my work that is a just complete
disrespect for the user and it should
never be allowed in an operating system
under any circumstances for any reason
and I don't want to hear any comments
about security I don't want to hear any
console is it those are my decisions
this is my computer Microsoft doesn't
get to tell me when it gets updated
I tell Microsoft when it's updated I
accept the responsibility for using my
computer and if they don't like that
then I you know I'm gonna have to buy an
for somebody else it's that simple
how many hours a day am i programming I
program probably no less than six hours
a day and usually no more than ten but
it varies depending on my other
responsibilities as well do you think
we'll be able to keep the lighting at
this complexity or method on the
Raspberry Pi probably not I wasn't
expecting to run anything like the real
game on the Raspberry Pi I'm expected to
have to turn off a bunch of features
because it's very underpowered compared
to a PC what level are intrinsic to find
our intrinsic CPU vendor specific or
architect specific well we need to make
AMD's Intel specific intrinsics or x86
x64 we don't really probably support x86
anymore because nobody uses anymore so
we probably don't have to do that x64 no
you do not have to have am to your Intel
specific intrinsics they are they work
across the board we will for neon which
we will probably want to do report to at
some point have to make our intrinsics
be agnostic between neon and x64 because
neon does have slightly different
instructions although they are similar
right I understand you switched from AMD
to Nvidia the reason I always prefer
Nvidia because they seem to have more
stable drivers and easier to use
performance tools and so on so given the
choice that go with that the reason I
was on AMD before was because that was
an old surplus machine that just
happened having a Indy card in it it was
not a machine that I had put together
myself
how much stronger you spent on lighting
as long as it takes that I'm satisfied
with it sorry for enough to have a
question I'm pretty far behind curious
if you've already implemented the
swapping function or macro how would you
avoid using templates for this you mean
to swap two variables I usually just
write it custom for the ones I want or
if you want to write a macro you can but
it's not particularly interesting I
don't really care that's not like
something I spend a lot of time doing if
you want swap function you can just
write it and it's not a big deal all
right so let's go back to the other the
original question and that question was
in our nope not that in our definition
of our sort of like easy to use or
easier to use sim deus types here the
question was do we actually have to use
the convert macros or can we just use
this right and when I was asked whether
we could just use this I said I can't
remember if there's reasons why you
can't but I do remember there was
something weird about this and I went
back and checked with friends of mine to
find out about whether or not I was
misremembering and I was not
misremembering there is something weird
about it but it's okay to use the Union
so answer one it is okay to use the
Union nothing weird will happen to you
however there is something weird about
it and let me now tell you what the
thing that's worried about it is because
it's worth understanding so mm-hmm you
may notice if I go into the Intel
intrinsics guide and I light up all of
our SS es that we might be using right
SSE you know one through four point two
let's suppose I look at the or
instruction you will notice that there's
more than one or instruction per type
I'm sorry total there's one per type
here is an or instruction for doubles
here is an or instruction for singles
and here is an or instruction for
integers right now the really unusual
part of this and the part that's the
interesting part that I said I want to
elaborate the actual instruction is not
the same do you see that now why is that
right and you can see here even the
performance is not the same
it changes right so what's going on here
well you know what's the deal right and
the answer is that even though these
types are not really relevant at the CPU
register level because the registers are
the same whether or not they're being
treated as doubles or singles or
integers for that matter that's not true
of the actual arithmetic logic units
that will execute them so inside the
processor we have logical registers that
we're referring to by name xmm zero for
example or something like this and it's
true that when I talk about xmm zero I
can talk about it either as an EM 128 or
an M 128 I because the only difference
between those two things at the register
level is what I want to do to it so if I
say for example I want to add an M 128
to another M 28 I'm talking about adding
say a floating-point value perhaps
whereas if I talk about adding an M 128
I to another M 28 I what I'm talking
about is doing an integer add something
like this right but I can still say xmm
zero in either case so it's not like I'm
saying a different register so that begs
the question well why does it matter
which of these I would be calling as a
result and couldn't I just use that
Union blindly and not care the answer is
you do care because once the instruction
is issued it goes to a specific type of
unit now in the case of something like
an ad where I'm going to add two
floating point numbers together with an
M 128 then it's always going to the same
type of ALU it's always going to
something that can do a floating point
add but if I am going to issue an or
instruction it could go to either kind
of arithmetic logic unit it can go to
one that can do
ooh a or PS or it can go to one that
could do a P or or one that could do in
or P D believe it or not this actually
makes a difference there are units that
do the high flex payments so all the
units could probably do an or but the
question is which one do you want it to
go to do you want to do the or on a unit
that could have done a floating point
add or do you want to do the or on a
unit that would have done an integer ad
and the reason this matters is because
once you issue it to one of those units
that unit is tied up for that
instruction cycle issue right so if I've
just issued an or on the f32 lane on the
f32 unit right then I want to do an f32
ad well I might not be able to get it
off that cycle because it's already got
an or like blocking that reservation
station or something right
so instead I could issue the or to the
u32 unit right that can't do an f32 ad
and then I can issue the F to be to add
on that same cycle to the thing that
would have done F 32 ads if only hadn't
been blocked by the or right so that is
the important subtlety to remember when
programming Sindhi code on the x64 is
that there are arithmetic logic units
they don't all have the same
capabilities but some of them have
overlapping capabilities such as the
ability to do an or so if two logic
units have the ability to an or but only
one of those logic units adds F 3 to s
and only one of those logic units adds
you 32s if you know you're going to be
over reserved on F 32 ads maybe you want
to move your oars to the si128 kind or
the vice versa if you know you're gonna
be a lot of you 32 adds well you 16 adds
let's say and you know those only go on
one unit try to move your oars to the PS
unit because maybe that is the one that
is not going to get used as much right
so the takeaway here is you can use a
unit Union
to represent a 128 and a 128 I but you
cannot necessarily be cavalier about
which one you use for doing operations
that could be used by both so you can't
just say an oar is an oar you have to be
able to say which kind of or you wanted
now I have not done much analysis of
whether modern compilers will just
switch or is for you based on what it
thinks is the loading of the units maybe
they do maybe they don't but if we
assume temporarily that the compiler
can't always get that right and that you
do need to kind of give it some guidance
about which one to use that is where it
makes a difference which one of these
two things you're using so it's not
superfluous that they have amp 128 and M
128 I it's not probably how I would have
recommended to do it I probably would
have just had one type and then just
have the two different Oracle's or to
this unit or to that kind of unit or
something like that but either way you
can see why it does make a difference
which kind of or you're issuing and it's
something to keep in mind hopefully that
gives some perspective let's see here
what are the specs of the current deb
machine it's a good machine it's in a
core i7 fairly high-end core i7 with a
with a 1080
I never remember these names the 770 K
in your opinion what are the low-hanging
fruits the unix/linux world could or
should tackle and become more
competitive with windows from usability
perspective one actually support laptops
Linux is laptops port is horrible
largely you know perhaps not necessarily
because of their fault they don't handle
like optimist graphics and and stuff
like that which you absolutely need to
do well they do it very poorly so you
need to fix they need they need
rock-solid laptop support which they
just really don't have audio is a mess
on Linux they need to just scrap
everything and have a very simple 100%
compatible used everywhere audio layer
for the love of God and just lock it
down and say this is all we're doing
forever please don't change anything
else they need to have a good a good
debugger like a really good debugger
they need to have very good GPU support
nice GPU speed easy to use like full
screen GPU all that kind of stuff you
need to work on all that getting really
clean really basic stuff still doesn't
work on the next all the time I have a
vanilla ubuntu install running on the
machine I'm looking at right now that
runs the chat it hangs hangs the entire
desktop routinely on drag-and-drop
operations and right-click menus this is
a vanilla install on a stock machine
with Intel integrated graphics it
doesn't even have a second GPU in the
machine it's just a stock 7 700 K that's
all and it is extremely buggy you just
can't have that right it's gotta be a
lot better than it is right now people
who don't think Linux is extremely
unstable they they have their eyes
pretty closed if you can't do a stock
install and have drag-and-drop not hang
your entire desktop you have serious
serious problems and so that's you know
that's just a basic thing I could go on
for a long time about all the things
they need to fix they also need to fix
the total non-standard way that
everything is
scattered throughout the system well
which distribution you want oh okay then
these files are in totally different
place
someone needs to be able to go to the
internet and get an answer to their
Linux question it can't be oh well the
answer your question is if you're on
Ubuntu 12.04 on arch this edition oh are
you using Debbie and oh if it's Linux
Mint then those files are actually no
there has to be like an answer to the
question how do I fix this problem here
is the answer that's it it can't be
20,000 different web pages that each
have a totally different answer right
completely unacceptable
you know I'm Sam so off you go
can you explain why you use f/32 instead
of double yes f3 2's are twice as fast
as doubles on current machines the
reason is because typically the clock
cycle timing for an f32 instruction
versus an f/64 instruction is the same
but f 32s can be done for wide whereas
doubles can only be done too wide or if
you get up into future version the
instruction set like a VX then it's a
single pinion you know f/32 are eight
wide and f64 only four wide so basically
if you can use fot twos you're twice as
fast pretty much with your arithmetic
ops which is just always better so
unless you have a really good reason to
use double you generally don't want to
write or if you just don't care about
performance right then doesn't matter
which one you use use double from our
precision because you don't care what
the format says you know prom solved is
something that could cause Stack
Overflow or related to it I don't know
what the this is so I'm not sure
what you're talking about with unions
could they be related to the overflow of
variables if you did things wrong I was
asking because I was curious what error
codes you could look for for this
problem no this has nothing to do with
Stack Overflow it doesn't really have
anything to do with the stack at all so
I'm not sure I understand why you would
think that was implicated this has
nothing to do with a stack it's just how
you interpret this space so the space is
the same regardless it's oles 128 bits
or 16 bytes right it's always 16 bytes
of space the question is which kind of
sea type are you trying to say that it
is so that when you issue intrinsic s--
they're going to issue specific you're
gonna be using one of these two types to
issue a particular intrinsic it's purely
a compiler construct it doesn't have any
effect on the amount of stack space used
because they both use the same amount of
stack space they're both the same size
on the stack so if they can't really
affect affect a stack overflow
looks like we're good
alright let's go ahead and close it down
all righty
thank you everyone for joining me from
episode of hand made here that's what a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you go here to the game
on handmade hero org it comes with the
source code so you can do your own
experimentation with it and for example
we're leaving on a cliffhanger this week
we need to analyze whether our code is
prep whether we can generate good cosine
weighted distributions and we only just
started that so you could play around
with that this week and see what you
think and we need to do some math math
at mathematical analysis next week to
see how we want to analyze these and
whether we're doing a good job or not so
that's what we'll be doing next week but
you can beat me to it if you want get
all week to try it and so that would be
interesting thing to play around with
I'll be back here next week same time
same place probably until then have fun
programming everyone and I'll see
everyone on the Internet take it easy
everybody