okay I think we are ready to go here
this is sort of a a inclusion of
handmade Con 2015 inside handmade con
2016 Messiah sort of mentioned on the
schedule so those of you who are at
handmade Con 2015 know that that these
are the speakers - Mike Acton he
couldn't make it but everyone else is
here who was at the original conference
and what I wanted to do was just kind of
take the opportunity to do sort of
questions and answers because that
wasn't something that as you know as you
saw even in this conference during 90
minutes we typically take the entire
time to really get all of the stuff that
we want to talk about just that I'm
asking so what I wanted to do was have a
session that was just kind of free forum
where we could go through a lot of the
questions that people had that they
maybe would have asked if we do audience
Q&amp;A so as I said on the mailing
basically I collated on the forums all
the questions that people submitted and
I'm just gonna kind of go through them
and ask questions of various people on
the panel who the questions were
directed at some of we're directed
everyone's in the director filming one
but the idea here is just that it's you
know much like the rest of the sessions
anything goes so anyone who wants to
talk about any topic is welcome to jump
in at any time
you don't have to keep it to just like
oh this said that this question was
directed at Tommy so only Tommy you can
talk or anything like that just it's
totally totally free for all so anyway
for those of you who are not at handmade
Conti 15 let me just do brief
introductions
we've got Ron Gilbert Pat Wyatt Tommy
referenced and Jonathan Blow you know
each of whom you probably saw their
talks online so let's give them a warm
welcome
[Applause]
so before I ask the first question I
just wanted to go quickly through and
just go like hey what's what's going on
so let's touch the end run
what do you been doing since handmade
Con 2015 how's it go it's just working
on my game so if then but we part and
stressing about it panicking about it
all those normal things you do when
you're developing the game what's the
panic level right now oh it's really
high really high yeah no it's it's it's
really high because you know we're gonna
probably ship the game sometime in
February okay and you know everything's
going great with the game and we had we
were getting ready to do all the voice
recording there's like 15,000 lines of
dialogue in the game and we were getting
ready to do the voice coding and then
all the actors went on strike right
right and so we kind of had to scrap all
of the casting that we had done and
we've started over with the casting and
we're gonna record it in Vancouver next
week okay so it's yeah it's like super
stressful right wait you don't think no
it's no it's not limited okay so the
strike is universal across well it's for
interactive titles and it started out a
little bit more limited but then a lot
more actors kind of went into it and
there was this thing that you could do
if you if you wanted to record during
the strike where you could basically
agree to the new contract that the
actors are and record outside of it but
then a lot of the people that do the
signatory type stuff
we're very leery about signing the
contract so it just it just made more
sense to just get out of it and go to
bank so basically the situation is right
now if you're doing voice credit for a
game and you do want to do it here it's
somewhat in limbo like you don't even
really know if you want well thank you
for coming even at panic level 17
so Pat how about you so very shortly
after Kahn last year I started to Amazon
so I've been there about a year game
studios and we're working towards the
release of the first game first PC game
which is called breakaway we just got a
an internal test about a week ago
actually I guess there was friends and
family would be the best way to describe
it folks and in December we'll be doing
a full-on alpha test Oh time to sign up
if you like play breakaway calm this is
this is an open test you do not have to
have any kind of special invitation to
do so well what they're gonna do is you
know like lots of people sign up and
then they'll pick a subset of those
people to play in the alpha test okay
can people like come up up to you after
sharing be like hey can you put me on
the secret can you bias me into the sea
sure I can try
Tommy how about you just stuff all right
yeah I wrote a scripting language fun
anything else well what kind of
scripting my ugh because Ron the whole
thing mine was just like
I needed something where people that
were afraid of C++ could do stuff in my
engine and I don't like using other
stuff so I was like well I don't have
anything else to do I'm just gonna write
a how to come out very well oh yeah yeah
no it's it was the the the reason it
came out very well is I had a ton of fun
doing it and I just enjoyed it and every
time I would be like oh I want to add
this thing I'd be like yeah I'm
gonna had that thing be awesome so and
then I did and then and now it's over
now I'm sad because it's done start
started another one
I might problem solved templates
[Laughter]
compiler so is this something that
you're ever going to release they're
gonna be like dot TRS files like or
something like this it's called Tom you
script yeah are we so creative with the
naming it's such a broad yes
no I probably won't release it cuz it's
it's just in my engine so okay so it's
not necessarily a scripting language
that might become something people would
be interested in using outside no I
don't think so like it's yeah it's
haizen the stuff in my engine
specifically so I mean you could because
it's all separate from the engine but
you know why I just use blue but you I
don't want to support it but you didn't
[Laughter]
John how about you what level of
involvement counts eyes worth mentioning
I feel like this is a speaker discretion
level of involvement so you can actually
said this dynamically okay I'll just
cover all the things all right so so we
released a game this year in January so
we've been doing ports of that to
various platforms and then we just this
week put live our ps4 Pro Plus HDR patch
so we're going back and doing support
for other things
HDR was pretty fun I didn't do any of
the programming specifically for HDR but
it was more like you know high-level
discussions and decision-making and
stuff because some of it a lot of the
things that you do in an engine you know
for efficiency purposes because you
didn't you know you could do them
multiple ways one of the ways you do
them is sort of like maybe after tone
mapping or whatnot none of that stuff
works if you need your output to be HDR
and some of those things don't even make
sense you know one of the cool tricks we
did was the I forget what game it came
from but you know there's a thing where
you take a screenshot and then you put
it in Photoshop and like you tweak all
the hues and like any control you have
in Photoshop like transforms the image
but also a stamp in the corner that
that's like every RGB color or none of
them that you can interpolate right yeah
make any sense an HDR at all right so
you have to like completely like all the
all the color correction in your the
live color correction in your engine has
to get rewritten and stuff and so I
didn't do that but did did Annie do Andy
are you in the audience did you do this
yeah so Andy did that okay but no I
don't know who did it
so we we had discussions about that so
that's been fun and then so more
personally what we're doing or what I'm
doing more
these days is sort of starting stuff on
the next game which is an interesting
project because part of the well there's
two next games what one of them is going
to be in the engine and code base that
we've already spent so much effort like
the witness the witness on James yeah
yeah but it'll hopefully be a project
that's smaller and more tractable than
that and stuff which is always what
people say we're gonna try to really do
it and then you know the other one so so
I'm also building a programming language
and as a test that that's a real thing
we're also making a game in that okay so
it's a little bit yeah you know it's
maybe not the smartest decision to do
multiple things yes just what is
happening so okay so this is one of
those cases where we do know ahead of
time that this is a bad idea yeah we
have decided to accept that feeling as a
feeling and move ahead if people never
did things that were bad ideas like like
starting a rocket companies are pretty
bad yeah but but that works out so yeah
alright well let me let me move on to
questions then and I I don't have any
particular order for these because
they're not super theme based like
people had some pretty I guess
the questions that were asked ranged all
all over the map from things that are
relatively specific code kinds of
questions to things that were like just
purely psychological like dealing with
you know burnout or things like this so
I'll just kind of jump around in it I'll
start with so I'll also should say some
people sent in here's my name like you
know you can attribute the question
other people didn't so I don't know if
that was cuz they missed the part in the
submission thing that said if you would
like me to read your name when you do it
please put the name in there and how to
pronounce it so I can pronounce it or if
they really didn't want me to say their
name so I apologize anyone who wanted me
to say their name and just didn't see
that notice but here we go so we'll
start off with one that's that's sort of
I guess a non not really a code question
it's from
I think I'm gonna pronounce this right
but Dean Siegel the handle is the eighth
mage on the twitch chat and it's from
Israel so the question is Tommy you
tweeted about impostor syndrome
specifically in relation to handmade con
can you talk a little bit about it and
if and how it influences your day-to-day
work and feelings and this is
interesting to me because people ask me
about this on the stream too and my
answer briefly there was just like we
never had a name for this thing but I
would be pretty shocked if programmers
in general it didn't typically feel like
they'd really just don't know what
they're doing because it's such a vast
topic so I am kind of interested to hear
what you had to say on it as someone
who's you know totally different
perspectives perhaps on it yeah I did a
GDC talk like the little soapbox and my
whole thing was I have a whole bunch of
friends
that's not bracketing I have I have a
bunch of friends people I work with and
around and stuff and they all they all
like make these amazing things and they
think that they're garbage okay and I
think that about stuff that I do too and
for me what I talked about in relation
to handmade con last year is I was up
here with no you you you and Mike Acton
and all these really really accomplished
people and I just felt like I sort of
belonged
even though right before I came to hand
make on him like oh yeah I try not to
cuss on the mainstream because those
videos I thought could maybe be used for
something educational I didn't even want
to try to keep especially this
yeah there has been several squares
we've already burned that bridge good it
wasn't me I'm not you not you're just
bringing it you're just bringing it home
you're closer yeah okay hello so I was
up here and I just I just felt like I
belonged and the whole point of that
talk was to just sort of tell everybody
that those feelings are natural there
are something that I feel like it's a
mechanism to keep challenging and
understanding what you're good at so for
me I don't think I'm really good at well
much of anything but I am though because
you know I've made a video game sold
well people like the controls I feel
like I know what I'm doing with
programming but it doesn't matter every
time I do something like this this can't
possibly be the right way to do this
okay you know but you know it keeps
working out and yeah I mean it inspired
me to just sort of take other leaps like
I just recently like made a comic book
okay okay well the reason was I didn't
have anything else to do you had nothing
else to do yeah it's been a weird year
okay so yeah the whole point was like
everybody feels it's not something to be
like ashamed of and you know if you if
you realize that other people have it
maybe people that you look up to because
I know there are some people look up to
me I don't know why but I do and if they
know that hey I kind of feel this way
too maybe they'll be like hey it's not
it's not bad for me to feel this way so
yeah because I feel like it's some level
that's the sort of thing that can can
you know be like a self-fulfilling
prophecy if you're constantly thinking
that I'm not good enough to do this
thing then you probably won't be able to
do that thing because that's what you're
focused on rather than just going like
look we all are really bad at this big
like game development is just difficult
and error-prone and it
not a science and it's like there is no
such thing as like oh I learned to play
the piano and here's the notes and it
came out great or something it's like
nope it's like very fuzzy and weird so
at some point you just have to maybe say
like I just got to try you know try and
and failure is part of this profession
on a daily basis it is yes yes did
anyone else have anything they wanted to
add on that one at all or before I find
that you know impostor syndrome at least
for me personally is it's highly
motivational because I often you know
feel like well what I'm doing just isn't
any good or other people are doing stuff
that's a lot better and that that really
motivates me
I think I'm somebody and I did a whole
talk on this I think I'm somebody I'm
I'm very much motivated by fear it's
like I get I I become afraid that
something else is better than what I'm
doing I've become afraid that my thing
is crap and that really pushes me pushes
me forward to kind of be better and do
better stuff so at least for me I find
it very motivational some people do not
but then for me I do so in some sense if
you know people who maybe struggle with
this a little bit can change their
thinking around you know maybe try to
think of it a little bit as like look
the the fear part of impostor syndrome
is like I think it's like okay well let
that fear mode but you'll run away from
that thing by doing you know challenging
yourself or doing work that allows you
to sort of demonstrate to yourself that
you can do it sort of as a more
motivational tactic rather than a just a
you know a cowering sort of sort of
thing yeah that's the way I'm treating
so let me let me move on to the next
question here this one well actually
this person submitted a couple different
questions so I'm going to pronounce this
incorrectly because they included a note
and this is probably for the best that
said I don't care how you pronounce the
name and they're from Shenzhen China so
like you know my ability to speak
Chinese would be laughably bad so that's
good pan Fang Zhang is the the person's
name and their handle on the Twitter
chat is ebola bond and his first
question was from john he said the
development period of the witness is
much longer than braid like how did you
come through the deed
motivation and self-doubt part I guess
he's assuming that there was one I mean
although I guess you did in the
attempting deep work talk probably
talked about bit about that but yeah and
then they kind of asked the broader
question is there a general method for
everybody so I think mostly just what
they're trying to get out there is like
psychologically how do you deal with
this
well braid was not a short development
you know it was like three and a half
years from beginning to end which is for
most people would be a long project it
maybe even not so much these days
because everybody's projects have gotten
longer and longer so three and a half
years is less long today than it was in
2008 or whatever came out but it was
still unusually long but but that was I
mean you know if you if you're a runner
and you run some short distances and
then you can run some medium distances
and you can run some marathons then you
can run some ultra marathons or whatever
right you just build it up you build up
the muscle there's sort of two things
there's at least two things that that
are skills that you can deliberately
well one of them is deliberate so the
one that's very deliberate is just
learning how to pay attention to your
own mental state and regardless of what
you have to do about your mental state
because that's a hard question to answer
like oh I feel really a certain way
today what why is that and what do I do
about that well the answer to why is
that is actually usually too complicated
to even understand it because people are
complicated right but you develop the
habit of at least looking at that and
then taking care of yourself right okay
similarly to the way you might like look
at your posture as we were talking about
everything and like move around a little
bit you just like yeah you know I'm not
having a good time right now and you
just at least you notice it and then
maybe you do change something a little
bit and even if you don't know what to
do about that the fact that you're
paying attention to what is going on is
I think at least two-thirds of the
battle like a lot of people you know
don't notice that something bad is
happening until it's really late and
like their life sucks
and they just want to quit their job and
divorce or whatever so but but I think
there's a there's a lot to be said about
yeah just constant attention just taking
care of yourself right but but the other
one yeah so like if you assume or at
least sort of implicit in that was that
like okay so normally when somebody
eventually sort of gets to that point
where it's gotten too bad right and
that's it's too late or whatever what do
you what do you suggest in terms of
learning to sort of figure out how your
mental state is developing much earlier
on from that like are there specific do
you think it's different for everybody
so you're just gonna have to kind of
work it out on your own or do you get
some kind of thing it's like no no like
hey spend five minutes the morning every
day going like how am I feeling today
about some various things just actually
pause and think about it is there any
kind of a like an actual thing there is
it just like who knows see it's really
hard because I think it's so when you
say when I say notice how you're yes
going on right now right away that is
actually very difficult because yeah all
tied up with with notions of identity
and stuff so so you actually have known
me for a long time right you you knew me
like sometime in the late 90s when I was
still doing my first yeah which I'm glad
I did it because I became a much better
programmer through that but man it was
it was not a very fun experience or
whatever right and and I definitely
didn't have this kind of attention to my
own you know mental state or whatever
and I became really depressed by the end
of that and I I burned myself out enough
that I couldn't program effectively and
I couldn't program it a hundred percent
until like a few years ago yeah and and
I was I was at like 20% for a couple
years and then it came out 30% 40% it
took a long time to get better right so
it was like a physical injury
okay but so when I go back to that time
right one of the reasons why I didn't
have a good eye on what was going on was
because it was partially like my
identity was like I had a little bit of
a the the exact word is not hitting me
right now but it's like when when you
don't have that great of an opinion of
yourself right so this team yeah
self-esteem right and and then and then
if you're not happy today you're like of
course right I say so but that may not
be true for somebody else somebody else
has a very different relationship to how
they feel about themselves so I don't
know if there's a general statement that
can be said about that but but just
noticing and and the other reason I say
just noticing is because conclusions
that you come to I guess I said this but
they're usually wrong so but then the
second thing is just once you've had a
successful project this is why I
recommend people maybe do shorter things
first because you do something
successfully and you went through maybe
a little bit of that period of like oh
man I couldn't handle this right it felt
so terrible but then you actually come
to the end I see and your brain actually
sees that there was an end right that
you got a bit I mean hopefully your
project didn't totally fail right one of
the reasons I think why a state burned
out after the first time was our project
was not successful right we got a few
players but it was successful in the
sense that I learned but he was not
financially successful nobody played it
I got no external validation from the
world right
but with braids I did and then it was
easier to get up and do a longer thing
because of that point your brain knows
it's like okay there there I'm gonna
have to go through a bunch of stuff do
this but I believe now that there is a
light dinner somewhat you you Sam I
believe right what are the properties of
being and I don't know you're probably a
little further than this right now but
when you're in the middle of development
and like that we talked about this last
year so don't go too far into is the
discussion of it last year but you're in
the middle of development and the to-do
list just gets longer and longer and
longer right so the if you extrapolate
that it goes to infinity right your game
will never be finished right in reality
that'll collapse down eventually but at
some point it's like wandering through
the desert and your brain doesn't
believe it's ever going to end but if
you have the past experience of like no
this is just like last time and it did
end you can at least remind yourself of
that at a rational level and then maybe
you can invoke some imagery to like help
with this right so just any kind of
standard mental things that you find
work well just use those to try and get
that association and be able to kind of
pull yourself out of it a little better
you know connect yourself back to the
time when you're like I did feel this
way in the past and it got better like I
don't need to despair kind of thing but
of course that advice is limited to the
portion of people who have had a success
yes first time through good yeah okay so
I guess I'll open that up to anyone else
too because I mean everyone here has had
to go through long projects so does
anyone have any kind of I think there's
a the problem is that most games and
game companies are started with a sense
of optimism that is you just have this
belief that like you're gonna get
something done in a certain period of
time and and as John mentioned the the
task list grows longer and longer and
it's the discovered work that you didn't
think about until you got to that point
in the project you realized oh we don't
have a solution
we haven't thought about that yet well
that's more people and you know you've
already got a budget and you see the
money dwindling and the scope increasing
and it's hard to figure out how to get
through that and so even if you want to
do things like oh maybe if I just took a
little bit more time off or if I just
gave really a week off well we had money
to do that that'd be great but we can't
so I do think I actually want to tell
you one story where that did happen now
I mean I was three years into Guild Wars
and that happened where it was it just
seemed like we would never be able to
release the project and ultimately took
us five years so I mean I think it's
really common in game development and I
think the thing you really have to do is
figure out ways to get yourself out of
the headspace of what you're working on
and do something else so that you're not
just keep you know grinding away against
the problem your brain needs time to
actually do other things and in fact I
mentioned this during the last talk but
if you spend too much time doing one
thing and you don't get enough sleep
then you're actually are preventing that
your your brain from performing properly
you won't generate the chemicals you
need to remember things for example and
so it's important to actually have some
space away from what you're working on
your mind can actually rest so you have
a better chance to go back at those
things I think need to triage I figure I
like okay well we can't do everything
and that's the way that you ship games
is by triage so is is it generally the
case that or I mean I shouldn't say
Chandler case but does it sometimes
serve as an indicator that like if I'm
having sort of absolutely crushing
feeling of like this is not gonna good
like it's just epically messed up or
whatever that that maybe is also a good
indication go okay maybe step back take
a little time but then maybe let's think
about can we you know break this up can
we do something like can we can we pull
back a little bit I mean when you say
triage is that do those things tend to
go together meaning is the time for
triage when you're when you're just like
in that headspace and can't see a way
out of it or not well I think you you
probably have to because it's hard to
just sort of step away and like well I'm
just gonna not do this right you you're
you know the people that you're working
with they're depending on you to keep
money flowing into the studio and so you
can't stop for too long so you do have
to be capable of doing this even when
you're feeling badly about but I mean
there's great examples of teams that
have done this I mean Blizzard obviously
has enormous amounts of money that they
can spend right but they had a project
where they spent many movie dollars like
40 or 60 million dollars or the
estimates for Titan and and like they
had nothing at the end and but they they
step back and they thought about it and
they said you know we really want to
prove ourselves and they went back and
they did overwatch and it really short
period of time by thinking about what
they had and what assets they're they're
able to put together and so in some
sense it's like hey maybe we can't
actually succeed down this path but
maybe we can pick a path that we could
succeed down but isn't that far away
from where we are right now kind of
thing that's producing I think when
you're doing triage to I don't think you
want to do triage kind of at the height
of your panic and paranoia you want to
do it the next morning it's like get out
of that out of that headspace where
everything is doomed and is totally
up because if you do that you'll
just start hacking stuff out of your
triage until you feel back but ok if you
kind of wait till the next morning you
mean metaphorically the next morning
that is your you're in a better
headspace so now go okay let's triage
let's look realistically at how much
time we have mom which money we have and
the list of things to do all right so I
think that's actually really good I
believe that is well beyond what I was
thinking there's your answer to that
question because it's kind of a tough
one I let me grab one here see so this
one is for Pat and it's on like it
actually uses two acronyms that I don't
know so I'm not sure I wasn't sure about
them but I'll give you the first part
first of /li two parts and this is more
of a code question the question is are
there any differences between debugging
an on net game like a non networked game
and an MMORPG game meaning the approach
to debugging that you take is it just
the same kind of debugging that you
would normally be doing just now there
happens to be network involved or is it
like the fundamental approach to
debugging changes in some way and sort
of the chaser on that was are there any
like silver bullets for debugging in
MMORPG like techniques you would employ
for these that you know might you might
not have think thought of are come
across because they are really only
applicable in this sort of scenario so I
do think that there is a silver bullet
which is rare and software and that is
that if you can figure out how to make
your game replayable from the same set
of inputs then you can reproduce the
same set of bugs and so the trick would
be you know you're recording every input
and the timestamps and it's actually
pretty easy to do in single-player games
because they're not jittering that much
input and you've got you know giant
disks that you can store everything on
and so like just write everything and
then you should be able to play that
simulation back into your game in it if
you did everything right then it should
crash the same way right and that's
something that you have to put the work
in upfront to make sure that your engine
is capable of doing that but then it's
real easy to debug and that really
naturally extends to multiplayer as well
and in fact we built Guild Wars that way
so it was game recording for crash
discovery and it turns out it actually
has some additional features which is
you can do load testing just from lots
of streams at the same time and then
also it ended up being a user feature
and that you can play recordings back
for players you can stream it out to
other people
clients they can watch the game so I
think it is it's super useful if you're
if you're architect your engine like
that is it possible to architect an
engine that way with multi-threading
these days though because at some level
recording inputs only works if those are
the only inputs or with multi-threading
the scheduler or the OS scheduler is
kind of a separate input which is kind
of hard to record have you worked on any
projects since that jump kind of
happened or is that like kind of a thing
that's like well yeah you could I mean
run the game single threaded or
something or I don't know well if you
look at each of the the agents in your
game as like an actor right actor model
program and then each one of those
things can be played back independently
yeah and so you can just record their
own input streams so they're isolated
from other components now as soon as you
start sharing memory then it becomes
really problematic and often times you
know what looks like an actor simulation
is only a global variable bashing
simulation like if you had at some point
assuming that the thing is
multi-threaded in you know sufficiently
you're going to have shared resources
that are contended in some way and the
order in which people hit them is not
going to be deterministic necessarily so
I I'm only bringing this up now because
this is something that I thought about a
bunch like I've you know worked on code
bases in the past where it did have
input recording and code base I'm
working out now I would love to have
been pouring could not really figure out
a way to do it at least not the way that
I used to do it given the fact that all
kinds of things are multi-threaded
internally now it seemed like you would
have to start recording the multi
threads like when people were taking you
know mutexes or something would have to
be part of the recording or something
like that I never really quite got to
the point where something about that
please do because it seems to me there's
two different classes of bugs right
there's one class of bug that's like
some kind of thread related bug yeah in
which case yeah that's that's always
that kind of situation yeah if it's a
kind of bug where it's like something
about the actual logic independent of
the implementation and the timing and
stuff then the way that you tend to
think about input recording is like it
happens on frame boundaries or something
and then if you're if you're threading
causes results that are gonna differ
inch differ beyond one frame anyway then
maybe that's about like like if the
coordinate of your object ends up
slightly different if this job runs
before this job then that's a little bit
you at least want to know that right
like I don't know if you do anything
about it but and in some cases that
might be intractable I guess for
performance reasons like I don't want to
get super picky about the order edge
collision resolves but well I'm more
thinking of it because this is not a
thing we're not talking about something
that we ship to end-users necessarily oh
man you made for the point is this is
not something that's used necessarily in
the course of actually doing so in the
game this is strictly for debugging and
so one of the most common bugs you can
have in a multi-threaded engine is a
threading bug so it seemed like it was
like well if I'm you know if my idea
here is that this is for debugging the
system saying that a whole class of bugs
which are bugs were very likely to have
in any kind you know in the kind of code
that it cares about this seemed like a
problem it doesn't mean you can't still
use the system for once it is multi
thread bug free now you can still play
it back in the same way but I was just
curious because you know it wouldn't
surprise me if someone said oh no no
just just do this they have changed all
your mutexes into this thing which logs
who took the mutex win or something and
then we just replayed them in that order
which you know theory might work but I
don't know it's really if you think
about processors getting more and more
cores than what's right than is the kind
of solution is going to be more and more
difficult to debug and so what you
really need is a system that looks at
the work you have to do more like a job
system yeah and so jobs you know it's
like here's a set of inputs go off and
do something and then there's a set of
outputs and so that's eminently
recordable is it though I mean because
you don't know you mean recordable in
the sense that just record which Cora's
got which jobs and then just do that
again when we come through so the
basically the job system now will record
that order and play it back so right now
so there are certain types of bugs that
you can't stop right like memory
corruption bugs are just nasty because
anywhere yeah so I've often found this
is now going totally off with this
person's question I've hijacked the
thread so on that topic I would be
interested to know your opinion on this
so I find oftentimes that the job system
model is less good than I like it to be
for the reason that often times things
you know the parts of the
multi-threading that I care about in
terms of performance stuff tend to want
to do just very grief access to a shared
structure rather than reserving that
access for the entire length of their
job and that's the kind of bug that I
tend to be worried about in this
scenario because you know it's typically
like a little hand coded thing that
maybe you made because this is a
critical component or whatever would you
say the same thing or are you more of
the opinion that no generally there
should just be job system and that sort
of manages resource locking in you
really shouldn't have much in the way of
custom kinds of multi-threaded stuff
happening yeah well I mean well you get
into claim rendering and stuff it can be
really complicated but in general I
think that it's better to try and use
job systems where you have larger blocks
that you can separate off and okay so in
a way I supposed to like here's a loop
I'm gonna have ten threads all run in
the same loop and do different parts of
it at the same time and so do you
usually see job systems as having sort
of that locking happen sort of at the
head end basically like okay this person
needs to access the database or
something like this so we will just not
let any of the other threads access the
database at that time or something so
that we don't have to have some kind of
a fine-grained locking mechanism in
there just doing an example out you
would prefer to generally say one thread
gets one resource and then you just try
to architect your resources so that's
not too bad or yeah or you would use
something like this is a much more
complicated solution but something like
post crests MVCC which is sure I can
actually pull out what the acronym
stands for but the idea multi-version
concurrency control I think is you have
lots of different versions of the thing
and you when you lock it the version
that you have stays constant for the
duration and the job even though other
people are getting later versions are
the same
data so then like your your job system
has version 34 of the data and can use
it and not worry about it changing out
from underneath it during the course of
the operation so that's assuming that
you have a system where that particular
piece of data doesn't have to be sort of
meaning the access to it is mostly
read-only I assume because rights will
now possibly collide with each other or
something like this or maybe you resolve
those after the fact yeah you're just
using a stale version that I feel like
that's a very domain-specific right and
there's some cases when you can't do
that like hypothetical situation really
say you were dumb enough to try and
multi thread a compiler and you've got a
job system right so you've got a basic
job system that goes off and does things
and one of the jobs is like walk the
syntax tree and figure out the types of
all the expressions in the syntax tree
right
well if you lock the syntax tree as a
resource now you're not parallel anymore
right even if you lock a subtree of the
syntax tree you're gonna in that way
that like locks pile up really fast yes
that's just gonna happen right so what
you really want to do is you know some
kind of like lock free thing that uses a
very small amount of data that may be
like that data lives in the node and you
do compare exchanges or whatever you do
to like just atomically change that one
value right and I don't not having
completed that part of things yet
because it's full I don't I don't see on
the one hand I don't see another way to
possibly do it I mean there are like you
could okay
the syntax tree is laid out somehow flat
in memory and we've got a read-only copy
and occasionally we like blitt parts of
it to the new copy to try and update but
that seems almost as complicated and it
has performance penalties that you're
making multiple copies of this thing
that you'd rather only have one of but I
don't I don't see another way to do it
well in that particular circumstance
it's definitely one of the things we're
like in a game in general you've got
lots of different work that you could be
doing so then job systems
to be things that can sort of be more
effective because hey there's all this
different stuff to do chances are they
don't all need to do the same data
whereas the compilers like look we're
just doing the syntax pad that's all we
can be doing right now so there's not
like a lot of opportunity to say go do
those other things you were going to do
and let me just play with sentence you
to bring it back more to mainstream
games a little bit I feel like it's if
you wanted to parallelize your AI
without taking performance hits of
duplicating your knowledge base all the
time right like what how do you do that
it's just gonna get hairy unless
somebody comes up with something that
I've never heard of right so maybe part
of what you do as an engineer is like
don't do that or you make your system
fast in other ways or you buy I don't
know yeah I mean I feel like if you can
just have a job system and serialize at
the job level to reproduce the work that
sounds great
yeah I mean if you can get to that point
it does sound pretty good because then
you know the other I suppose aspect of
that is that if you do have a job system
that you can record you can also look at
your efficiency that way you can look at
the job systems records and say how much
how many longer jobs waiting how you
know when did jobs go in and now it's a
it could be a useful debugging tool for
things that had nothing to do with
catching you know breaking bugs it could
be stuff for I just wanted to know how
my scheduler was working maybe there's
things I could do to make my schedule or
better like where are the bubbles and so
the recording of a job system could have
another benefit I suppose in that way
but all right that was a I I thought we
were going to have like I was worried if
we ran out of questions before the time
that's not going to happen and there's
zero chance of that so I'm gonna ask the
part of the question now that had the
acronyms I don't understand so you can
either skip this one if nobody knows
what they are or someone could tell me
what they mean the question was for data
analysis such as da you or ARP you daily
active users and OH Everage revenue per
user okay
the single-player game
okay do you have separate systems for
game manager or operation department
access did the data come does the data
typically come directly from reading the
database and they sort of had a little
explanation here about why they're
interested in this they're saying the
former company they worked for accessing
the database affects players who are
online so they had to wait for them to
go to sleep typically to do this sort of
thing then read daily reports about the
money that they spent and so on and so
they were just saying like how does this
sort of thing work and I guess implicit
the question is a more well working
system than the one that this company
that has not named has yeah well so the
first thing is that you want to have
multiple databases you have a you know a
transactional database what's called
OLTP online transaction processing which
is sort of like your bank of knowledge
that players are using and then you have
want to have a I think it's ap which is
your analytics database and there they
could be optimized to be different types
of databases right like ones a
traditional sequel database there is a
column store database because you need
to roll up columns and that is that
you're replicating your data from your
your you know store of true knowledge
about what players have in their
accounts to your other database you do
it like every four eight hours once a
day something like that so your
analytics are gonna be out of date but
it's not as essential right you don't
need five minute interval on most of the
data that you're looking at you know
like getting a report in the morning
what happened yesterday is is you know
can be very useful
and so yeah you should have basis for
that problem and so when you have
multiple databases for these things is
there is the structure always the same
for these or is like is there a I write
through one database and then it writes
out to another database kind of a
pattern for it or is it always like the
game writes to both databases or the
server rather writes about databases or
like what's the is there anything tricky
about that or just like it doesn't
matter that's not relevant yeah there's
lots of different ways to do it one is
just you're replicating to a slave
database okay and then
you know it's it's capable of answering
different set of queries because they're
all read queries okay like also the you
know I say database right like there's
only two of them but one thing is you're
taking in all this data and you've got
your master database and you've got all
these events and then you've got like a
slew of like third party tools you know
like your own internal databases and
external companies that analyze your
data and so you want to think about it
not as there's a central point of
knowledge but rather there's a stream of
events that goes wherever you need to go
in order to be able to answer different
types of questions whether it's the
operations team looking at you know
player behavior for security purposes to
identify bot players or you know the the
marketing team looking at analytics to
discover whether the things the offers
that they're making are working
effectively did anyone I assume but I
think the only single single player okay
I think that was all from from that
question set so let's go to question 4
this was Tommy and John and this was an
anonymous submitted question so it was
both braid and super meatboy were
extremely successful games I'm wondering
if there are parts of the game
that you weren't quite happy with and
that you would have liked to spend more
time on or is everything exactly the way
that you wanted it
I asked this question not because I'm at
all wondering what the answer is but
more just because I feel like the fact
that it was asked kind of means maybe we
should talk a little bit here about the
reality of what you achieve when you're
programming a game yeah there was a lot
of stuff that I don't I don't like
playing because I just like they're like
content wise there was there was a lot
of stuff that we wanted to add that it
just came down to it and it was like
well we can either add all that stuff
and not come out on xbox or we can cut
it all and be done with it and have it
come out on xbox and then you know go on
with our lives so yeah there were there
were several things I don't think I
should name all of them because maybe
they'll be in another one but probably
not but you know yeah of course okay I I
don't and maybe John had put everything
in braids that he wanted yeah I have a
different right so so the the triage
discussion that was happy Riley's I've
been fortunate enough to never be in
that position like it was always a
possibility to just keep working on the
game so that's why the witness took a
long time for example is because you
know we could have said well we have to
ship this you know in years where n is
less than you know but but you know I
always feel like well if you if you put
some amount of time into something and
you're really close to making something
really great but it's gonna take more
time if that's her goal of making
something that's as good as you can make
it then by shipping the thing that's not
as good as you can make it and starting
over you're just increasing your time to
that goal okay right so if you don't
have a financial forcing function like
forcing you to ship and if you don't
have a you know I'm gonna go insane if I
ship is here or something right then
like if your goal is to do good work you
can do good work more good work in one
game or you could split it among
multiple games but it's still all good
work right so neither braid nor the
witness shipped with anything that I am
you know it's sad about like the we kept
working on the teeth there's always
things that you didn't get to do right
but you know if you start and the things
are this big and you keep splitting the
boulders or something and they get
smaller and smaller the to-do list
always gets longer but the items on the
to-do list get smaller so the some of
them in some calculus way eventually
starts adding up to very small amounts
right and you know you're summing a
larger number of things like that where
the number of things grows smaller than
the size decreases anyway so there's
stuff in both games that I didn't
totally you know that are not ideally
perfect but there there are both games
are way better than I thought they were
going to be when we started okay great
so you can't beat that I mean I mean
with the witness the biggest problems we
had our stuff that was beyond our
control anyway like shipping an
ambitious 3d game on the PC right now is
a nightmare we spent like two months
just dealing with graphics driver things
you know so then I don't even know what
you do to prepare for I mean if we had a
much larger budget we could have like
giant testing a giant testing yeah but
you know like the you know the Radeon
3770 has a problem but the 37 90 and 60
don't right so that was really our
biggest problem with the witness and it
wasn't a problem with the game right it
was just the environment that we read
but you know Tommy where is the
crowd-sourced system configuration bug
database that we were promised last year
okay so I'm wrong about a misremembering
this no no my parts done except for the
Linux and the Mac version I just don't
have a web guy that's it's pretty much
but you've got all the spare time it is
very hard to find and I'm very sorry I
don't mean this in the way that it's
gonna sound it's very hard to famous
last words tough finding a good web guy
is difficult alright
and I know this because I used to be a
web guy and I consider myself one of the
good guys because I wasn't a web guy I
was just a software guy okay it's very
hard to find a software guy that does
web stuff because they're just doing not
it's very painful because the thing I
wrote is simple but people just want to
make it so complicated okay
they put like 13,000 little systems is
one thing so basically you're looking
for somebody who can do the minimal
amount of necessary web over 15
frameworks to serve five pages
that's only three frameworks of page
yeah okay but that is what you're
actually waiting for is somebody who
would would do a good minimal job of a
layer that could put this thing on the
web basically yeah I'm trying to push
matthew wagner it's like a web to finish
his game so we can do stuff okay I mean
he's trying to fill a maybe once maybe
once I have like a good dependable web
person cuz I'm not doing that again
okay I did I did my crappy PHP version
of it okay it worked it looked like
garbage okay I need I need something
that's functional it doesn't look like
garbage and then and then yeah then
everybody can use it
oh god okay so let's let's move on
before anyone says another jQuery from
the audience okay so we're mostly down
now let me see you got it we'll ask I'll
ask a couple of we're mostly going to be
down to questions that were not directed
at anyone they were just questions for
everyone basically but I got a couple
more here so Ron this question is from
tomash I'm not gonna pronounce this one
right either but even though they
spelled it phonetically I'm gonna try
Tomas ruse Hahn ski ruse on ski I think
if I'm getting that correct but they
didn't list a city that they lived in so
I'm not sure where they're from the
question was was using pixel art in
thimble we'd park your very first choice
or did you consider some kind of
stylized 3d like in the cave and they
said what are the pros and cons of each
approach in the project like this
presumably part pixel art was our first
choice for that because we were the kind
of the whole images of the Kickstarter
it was real
you're kind of going back to what was
the charm of maniac mansion in Monkey
Island and you know my kind of thesis on
that is it really has to do with the
pixel art and so you know we kind of
wanted to go back and look at that and
go right is-is-is pixel art a key
component in that in that charm and and
I do happen to think it is because I
think pixel art the you know the objects
in the game or the actors in the game
they're more they're more icons then
they are actual things right it's like
this is not a toaster it's an icon of a
toaster right this is not a secret agent
this is an icon of a secret agent
because the pixel art just removed so
much fidelity and that and I guess it's
like the difference is reading a book
versus watching a movie right players
can fill in you know so much more about
things where if you're doing these
really nice like high-end you know even
to the very high end 2d stuff you filled
in so many blanks for the player so that
was kind of you know our original idea
and so it really so that's very
interesting so so essentially what what
you're saying there is that like if you
go high fidelity it's not simply the
case that going high fidelity is you
know more difficult to write ever
because it means you have to spend more
art resources or more time optimizing it
engine or something like this it
actually fundamentally means that people
lose the ability to apply a certain
amount of animation absolutely that's
going to manage the imagination to what
they're seeing so you're sort of saying
like literally they cannot have the same
experience that they would have had
because in one case we're telling them
exactly what the experience is and
another one we're kind of saying here's
a suggestion of what is in the
experience and you're going to fill in
what you sort of have in the background
that's fascinating and and it doesn't
mean that the pixel art is just you know
crude and ugly and you know I stuff
pixel art can still be incredibly
beautiful and you know artistically
drawn you know pixel art to me is not
drawing high-res art and then going into
Photoshop and then you know reducing the
resolution right the pixel art is like
hand placing every pixel you know where
you want it to be for the scene so I
think there is a real you know artistry
to really really good pixel art and so
there's a follow up to this question but
I guess I'll I just want to sort of ask
the part of the first one that it kind
of I'm sure I'll say this they kind of
alluded to which was they mentioned the
cave and thimble Reed Park and then they
sort of said are there pros and cons of
each of the protis I'm stepping away
from thimble we park which obviously
just already like you said it's like no
the goal of this was to have the screen
so obviously we wouldn't consider doing
some okay is there anything else in the
pro's and con's
other than the one we just sort of
talked about which is that you lose that
imagination part you know can you maybe
say if there's anything else to mention
there before we go yeah there are a lot
of pros and cons I mean just memory it's
like you know the entire background for
you know a background in thimble weed
Park is you know less than a lot of
icons people's desktop so you you
certainly you know doing doing you know
really good pixel art you do save a lot
you know intrusive memory I think the
other thing that's kind of a little bit
advantage and it gets back a little bit
to the imagination thing is when you're
kind of doing like characters the way we
do into Bowie Park things don't have to
work precisely and your mind kind of
fills it in that's right a character
kind of reach for a doorknob and they
can really kind of not really touch the
doorknob right right and because you're
filling in so much of the same
imagination you accept that we're if
you're dealing with like really high end
you know 2d art you start to notice that
this person didn't touch the doorknob
when right now for so there's a lot of a
lot of things that we can do because
it's pixel art like that you know a lot
of shortcuts that we can get away with
it speed up development so it kind of
keeps you away from having to deal with
a lot of these sort of corner cases
sorts of stuff that would come up yeah
it's it's kind of like it's almost like
the uncanny valley in a way
right that the nicer your art becomes
the more people expect everything to
actually work correctly
I see where if it isn't then so you
kinda need to be on either side of that
value like either we go pixel art and
then people just kind of understand that
this is a representational thing that
they're seeing and you know they will
fill in the gaps or we had better get
all the way to the hand actually turns
on the door otherwise people are gonna
kind of notice the janky mists of that
yeah okay all right so same questioner
also asked what was more important while
designing the thimble we'd Park to
innovate and push the genre forward or
to preserve the warm fuzzy feeling of
nostalgia how hard is it to resist the
sweet taste of member Perry's they said
I think you've kind of already answered
this but I thought I'd just read it so
you can answer it definitively that was
a really really hard line right because
you know we were trying to build a game
that again captured the charm of those
old games and I think a lot of what
those games did is a part of that charm
but on the other hand I think that you
know if you look back at point-and-click
adventures made around you know McGowen
maniac mansion time there were a lot of
flaws in them right I mean we are much
better game designers than we were back
then and and so there's just a lot of
stuff into Bowie Park where it's like
you know what we want we want to kind of
capture that charm thing but on the
other hand we just want to get rid of
all the stupid stuff right right and so
we have spent a lot of time you know
learning over the years and learning
from what other games have done games
you know like Firewatch and all this
other stuff and how they approach things
you know you know what those same things
can be applied to this point you click
game so so it's like you know we kind of
describe it as we don't want the buiid
part to look like an old point and click
game we wanted to look like you remember
those old games looking you know so it's
like we're going to kind of take that
aesthetic but we're just we're just
going to kind of move it forward in a
lot of design ways you mean Plus that we
use shaders and all this other stuff in
the pixel art that it's just it's more
of what you're imagining
imagine that Monkey Island actually
looked like when you played it as a kid
so you're kind of you know the person's
brain has sort of completely painted
with a new brush what Monkey Island
looked like back then and the sort of
thinking oh I love the artwork for Macau
and whereas if we showed it to now they
might be like oh that's not what I
remember so you're kind of going for the
more like this looks like your brains
image of Monkey Island even though this
might not really be what monkey looks
like and you know Marc Ferrari did all
the art I think he put it best is like
you know people want to go live in the
Renaissance Faire they don't want to
live in the Renaissance that's great all
right well let's let's pick one of the
other questions for everyone here this
question comes from William Bundy Bundy
from Redlands California I think is here
he's in the booth there he is
the question is how do you approach
making and designing in-house tools do
you devote time to designing workflows
for them and what do you want from
third-party tools other than fundamental
things like stability speed and
functionality those are kind two
separate questions so we'll just start
with the beginning one which is just
like how do you approach in-house tools
sounds like Tommy approaches them by if
he had nothing else to do dot-dot-dot
honestly yeah that's kind of he makes an
in-house tool it really is so does
anyone want to start on that one I don't
know it's clear like how do you approach
making them or how do you approach
deciding whether you're going to make
one I to be honest I'd like to hear the
answer to that first one for sure I was
sorry the second one like how do you
know because you always there's always
some jankier solution you can do that
doesn't involve making a tool right like
some weird I type self ode to win but is
that Excel files for the win Excel a
sell files for the way so there's always
something you could do that doesn't
involve making your own tool so the
question is yeah I'd like I'd like to
know how do you figure out when to make
them win not that
that'd be pretty well for my stuff I
usually spend a lot of time looking
around and see if I can find a tool that
would do what I need okay and if I can't
find that tool then you all kind of go
in to doing them and obviously I mean
even doing pixel art I really don't want
to build a you know a graphical editor
that can do pixel stuff I look at
Photoshop and I go you know what this
can do what we need okay
so it's like I don't need to rebuild
this whole for that but other things you
know I really felt I need to build this
tool for this right I can hand edit text
files or I can find some off-the-shelf
thing that we're gonna fight with the
entire project and you just kind of said
you know what this is worth my
investment you know to spend your time
and in thimble we park you know we had a
tool that laid out all the rooms you
know where you kind of put all the
images in position and tagged all the
hotspots and lay down all the lock boxes
and you know I kind of decided early on
you know it's gonna take me probably two
months to build this tool that's
probably worth it okay and I just
decided upfront okay two months I'm
gonna build this tool because it's such
a workhorse on the project and there
just is nothing else out there that is
like this which I guess kind of tends to
tends to be what you do see in a lot of
game engines is that like are the map
construction process or whatever you
will where you're kind of pulling assets
together and making and I think I think
that's the only custom tool on the
project everything else is off-the-shelf
stuff and so is that something that you
it sounds like that was entirely
foresight I guess in the sense that you
did not start doing this thing without
the tool and then realize that this was
a bottleneck in production or something
like this and then go do it you were
more just like and this may be because
you've had so much experience with these
kinds of games though but you were just
like I just know this is gonna be a
problem so I'm just gonna do it right up
front yeah cuz we had a very similar
tool in this come system that kind of
did the exact same thing and I just knew
how important it was and how much people
use that thing that I just knew doing
this I need a tool like this when you
were doing it on scum how did that tool
come about was it you know wet when did
people figure out we should probably
build one of these well that was very
ganic because you know what we're doing
the first version and maniac mention in
the Commodore 64 I mean it literally was
hand editing text files to get
everything positioned and that just kind
of grew slowly over time to get that
tool okay I think when the equation
comes down to how big your game is gonna
be and so how many people you envision
working on it and the fidelity of
execution that you need okay right so if
something like an you know animation
right animation people really care about
it's got to look good and so if your
animators have to go and edit text files
which is the way that some games
actually worked in the old days then you
know the iteration cycle is really slow
for the artists and they're not going to
get that fidelity and so and especially
if you've got a whole bunch of animators
they're gonna be working on the project
and it would make sense to invest in the
tools for that if that is like a key
criteria for the success of your game
because we rate everything you implement
is something else you didn't implement
somewhere else because you've only got
so many hours where dollars until your
company goes out of business so yeah
thinking about what tools you can reuse
and then if you're gonna do something
that nobody has done before then you
almost certainly have to build tools
right if you if you're making outdoor
game and you don't have an outdoor
engine then you're gonna write an
outdoor editor or you know you're gonna
have a problem I would say one thing
about tool welcome to is the most
important thing like stability was
mentioned but I would say it's not just
stability because everything's gonna
crash once a while it's can you recover
after the crash okay saving every 30
seconds would be great or alternately
it's like it writes out everything at
the point that crashes and so that you
might have some chance of recovery
that's really important for internal
tools because you just know hey these
are things that are in flux so we're
gonna have crashes we're not gonna have
perfected it by the time it's in
production certainly so prepare for
crash like make crash preparation of a
thing so John did you know is
it's complicated right because you know
you can easily spend a lot of effort
making your own tool and then it still
kind of sucks to use because it doesn't
have all this iteration professional
tool right you have to keep in mind
though that when you license a
professional tool it's not or a
commercial tool it's not really gonna do
exactly what you want and so you take a
loss from putting up with it right and
there's a cost there's an ongoing cost
to like dealing with it the fact that
you don't have control over this thing
right
there's a cost to the fact that that
tool has an end of life that is not in
your control so if you want your game to
be released 20 years from now because
that's just what you want to do right
you don't want to make perishable goods
then which I guess is a single player
concern more because with multiplayer
your player bases just go on adventures
yes you know that has to be considered
right is this tool gonna block me you
know if it's something like an animation
created tool probably not right but
whatever of course if you're gonna build
your own then it takes longer than you
thought and it's gonna have little bugs
that you're dealing with in the workflow
and so that's friction right so I kind
of just take a Jeff Roberts attitude
which is just like if I want to do it
that way then yeah yeah like I mean Jeff
is like you know there's quality of life
issues that sometimes supersede making
the intellectually tactically best
decision okay right
like if it's kind of close either way
and you would have more fun building
your tools or you would feel like like
you did something nicer or you just want
to try something someone on the team
who's interested in trying something
then that's evidence to do it that way
right because because people I mean take
games take a long time and it's like
people's lives right so the working part
of their life and so you you just want
to make that as good as possible and
sometimes that means don't make people
suffer through the terrible thing that
you would build and instead
spend some money but but sometimes it
means let people do their thing right so
it sort of it's very contextual I think
maybe you know you just happen to be
interested in this thing and you know
that you're going to have fun doing it
so the extra time is actually gets paid
off in morale in some sense right it's
like you are happier and you're more
motor even if the game took longer to
ship and cost more I mean that guy had a
good time yeah so I mean and that's I
mean that's that's not completely a joke
right like when when you're in a in a
position where it's like well I'm paying
people right like you don't want that to
be an extractive position where like I
am using money as a manipulator to
coerce people to produce the product
that I want I mean that's a very
antiseptic mechanical way to think about
it right well I don't know him but sure
but it's more like okay you you need to
have a little bit of that because
otherwise a game is never gonna be right
used but at the same time it's like well
these are this is how people are
spending their working hours and you
actually at some degree have to be
grateful for that
because they could just leave especially
with a small company like mine there's
not like an influx of people coming in
the door people are not beating down the
door to work for a company they've never
heard of right they all want to go work
on overwatch right so you know you have
to be a little bit happy that people
there's a give-and-take right like if
someone wants to do this thing then and
I don't think it's exactly the best if
it's not going to ruin the game then
we'll do it you know even if and that
even comes down to smaller technical
decisions like should part of the
renderer be a certain way right I don't
see how that's gonna really be faster
but he thinks it will be and he's you
know the reason he the reason he's in
that programming position is because
he's supposed to decisions right so you
let people make decisions I guess that
didn't really answer anything it sort of
did though I mean it is that is a
additional metric you can use if you're
trying to make one of these decisions
about like should we do this tool should
we not do this tool one is
anyone actually gonna enjoy making this
tool does it what I mean I mean does
anyone ever predict things with high
accuracy about whether something is
going to be right or not right it's I
think in general we all even the best of
us have a relatively poor track record
yeah like if you were to actually go
back and audit your decisions right and
so just have that knowledge off priori
like okay I think we should license this
tool but I have about 30 percent
confidence in that choice so really
whatever right so but of course I'm the
guy who takes it forever to ship games
so so here's a question to follow that
up because you happen to sort of be
right there at the end of it what was
the process for getting a new puzzle
into the witness did the edge engine
have a line puzzle editor because we're
talking the process there was that I
type lines into a CPP file and compile
the game and we run the game
not even with incremental rebuild
because the does that even like I guess
that works the playstation guys were
over at one point and they said it works
on the ps4 but I never even tried it
there I don't work directly in the ps4
but it never worked on PC correctly
enough it would like fail one time out
of six which is often enough to just
like throw it away no so and the reason
that happened was just you know if
you're making a game where you don't
exactly know what it is in the beginning
then you can't really know what the
tools have to be right especially if
it's a very core gameplay thing like oh
there's these puzzles like I didn't know
what the rules of the puzzles were gonna
be I didn't know what kind of things
could be in them right there's a lot of
and there's a lot and and it's very easy
if you want a prototype a new idea like
maybe the length of what I'm tracing is
like constrained in some weird way I can
program that pretty fast programming a
tool for that takes a lot longer yes
right even if it's a crappy tool right
right so by the time I knew what the
game was like two-thirds of the puzzles
were just already in C++ and like why at
that point would you change it there
were some issues like that like
hey I mean I was very laissez-faire
about the whole thing so like I'm gonna
put symbols into puzzles so there's
gonna be a thing where you just like
allocate and array and then you like
poke them I take the graph paper and
like count the squares and put it in I'd
say like you know three times I plus
four or whatever to like put and
sometimes the array wasn't big enough
and you get some memory right errors but
you do a little bit of like safeguarding
to make sure that doesn't happen and
it's fine so yeah I'm suspecting that
was not the answer I mean that's and
okay let's let's see here we've got
about eight minutes left nine minutes
left until we should take a break
if I'm correct so let's see what would
be a good thing to end on here how about
what has been your happiest moment with
programming I think my happiest moment
in programming was I wrote this
incredibly complex piece of code to do
something and I just kind of remember
being shocked at that it's like okay I'm
done for the day I'm out of here cuz
this worked the very first time what was
the code you remember I don't I don't
remember exactly exactly what the code
was but it involved like a whole bunch
of like math and like getting all
everything all these I think it was it
was the animation system oh that's right
it was the animation system I was
getting all of the you know the pieces
of the animation are all running on
these kind of you know threaded
animation chains and and it's like I
just I work on this thing for you know
probably the entire afternoon I remember
you know hitting compile and eating run
and the guy walked across the screen
[Laughter]
well I blogged about one of them which
was like in the first multiplayer game
of Warcraft 1 working so I'll mention a
different one instead I was actually
doing the fog of war for StarCraft ok
there another programmer had gone in
dead fog of war and it was cell-based
and so as a unit would move around the
screen you see this map of cells around
it which are 8x8 tiles and and they'd
all sort of shiver around as the unit
like moved pixel by pixel and it's
trying to recalculate what the light map
would look like and it was just it
wasn't very scalable for the number of
units we wanted to have and so did you
written and so I just sort of step back
and said you know what could I do
differently and so I did Goro shading
with filter algorithm to sort of soften
all the edges and then I actually added
line-of-sight as well so if you had a
something it was blocking your view then
the fog of war would be filled in so if
you're here at the bottom of a cliff you
can't see up here and so this area would
still be fogged and ended being about
the last assembly code I ever really
wrote I mean maybe a couple of
instructions after that but like that
was the last serious block of assembly
code cuz you know so you got to be
better and like you know it took a while
to get it nailed down but it worked and
it's beautiful you know in line of sight
works and it really makes the game work
well it was a lot of fun to do so how
long did that take three weeks my god
I'd already done a lot of far the worst
death so I really wanted the two
previous work rafts like so right at the
end of meatboy I was losing my mind
because you know and throughout
development we always had problems with
the replay system it was it was like you
know there would be like a block that
broke and it was all input based in the
beginning and you know it worked well
but it always had these times where I
would just totally mess up and it was
two days either a day or two days before
our Xbox gold submission and I'm like I
have to
and what I did is I had I was on like
four hours of sleep and I get up out of
my desk and I go and I sit with my back
against the wall cause it sucks sitting
on the floor with nothing and I didn't
have a couch and I didn't want to sit in
the computer chair so I sit on the floor
back against the wall I just closed my
eyes for like 30 minutes and I just
thought about how I was gonna recode the
entire replay system and after 30
minutes I was like okay and I did it and
first time and that's the one so
[Applause]
that was some weird superhuman like well
you're lifting the car off the baby yeah
pretty much
John I'm thinking of two and it's about
a tie between them you've got you've got
at least four minutes alright you could
do both so the the they're both kind of
recent one of them is probably from
about two or three years ago and it's
from a side-project game that I was
working on during the witness and you
know this game but most people do not so
I won't go into that much detail about
what it is but it was still in the
relatively early stages where you're not
trying that hard on the graphics or
whatever so it's very easy to create
results and I had a period of just like
three to five weeks when I was working
on the witness during the day I go to a
cafe or go home after work and I was
just then working on this all the way
until it was time to go to sleep
I'd eat whatever was fast I'd fall
asleep I'd wake up I'd go right back to
working on the side project and I'd go
do the witness during the day and
something about there's just this
juxtapose do and you go and you can make
something happen very quickly and it was
coming out really great right there's
this joy of like when when you're a
program or designer and you have ideas
and can make the ideas happen and they
really work it's just really nice and so
there was this this time of like where I
was just completely content to do
nothing else in life but like wake up
and first thing in the morning I was
doing
this right and then I then I killed you
witness stuff so I can't even explain
why that was it's just you have to take
my word for it if it's really nice and
then the second one is more recent even
is on the compiler that I was working on
and maybe toward the end of 2014
beginning of 2015 when that first
started coming online even in the first
few months of development of that it's
again from compilers are another area
where it's easy to make a great deal of
progress relatively quickly before you
start getting bogged down later with
implementation details and I have enough
programming experience there's a way
that you can capitalize on that effect
right and structure your code to not bog
you down for a while right and that's
one thing that I feel like is my
personal style is about thinking about
that so like I got the compile time
compilation working and I did this demo
where I just you can run the same
program at compile time in and release
time or whatever and I was just super
happy with that and it was not that
complicated of a system and I knew like
if I already can do this and it's not
very complicated then then the rest of
it is going to be tractable right and
and I was again I was a case then when I
just kept jamming on it and and new
results came in and worked well and and
progress was fast so because of that
because of all of my experiences of when
programming is the best is when progress
doesn't take forever when it's not like
pulling teeth to get anything done right
but that's so much of like what current
day programming is you know even down to
compile times or whatever right
so that's that's well well the other
aspect of that psychology was like
looking at all that looking at the
misery of like programming in C++
everyday and being like oh my god I
really do have a way out of this it was
like I see a I see a light up there
and I'm actually managing to get towards
right and it like there was this release
of all this dread that I'd had like
because otherwise I was gonna I had
already convinced myself that I was just
gonna have to put up with that for the
rest of my life right right and get what
I was get done what I was doing despite
that right right I was like oh games are
hard enough but I've also got to do them
while holding this like 50 pounds oh my
god I don't have to do that so we'll see
if that part actually comes true and I
finished your thing but like the the
feeling of that was amazing the hope is
amazing when you can have it that's like
one of those books you can alright well
we're gonna take a break here thank you
all for sharing we'll be back
[Applause]