hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we cut a complete-game live
on stream all right we already actually
installed that in the pre stream so we
don't need to I've updated to remedy to
0.2 0.2 today and there really isn't
probably anything you need to know about
that other than it just fixes and
improvements to the debugger it's in
active development we switched from
Visual Studio to remedy when Visual
Studio refused to launch and we've had
no worries with it so far it's been
working great so hey I think we may be
done with Visual Studio I think Visual
Studio we may be able to take it out
back behind the tool shed and put a put
a bullet in the head and and good
riddance to bad rubbish so thank you
very much to gorge men horne for all his
work on remedy it's it'd be pretty nice
and never have to load Visual Studio
again and all that that implies but who
knows it's still early in remedies
lifecycle so you know we're not asking
for a miracle here so there may be some
rough patches ahead and that's totally
fine it's a brand new debugger so you
know you got to cut it some slack but so
far it's been real good kudos to George
for all of that right now we are in a
sort of testing position now we've we've
got as far as we know and I we didn't
really do too much with it because we
sort of finished up just as time was
running out
last time but if you take a look at
where we're at with our handmade hero
builds we have done all of the debugging
work to ensure that we are actually
importing and we can even look at these
if we go into the directory and look at
the tech stumps but to ensure that we're
actually importing sounds as part of our
unified asset import system if I open up
to have you from the bonus pack here
intro cutscene dot txt what you can see
is our assets are now can include audio
and they can actually include chained
audio assets so what you can see here is
like the audio gets chained
in chunks that can be read so really
long audio like this music test piece
here that go on for minutes we don't
want to have to load that whole sound
you necessarily we want to be able to
stream it over time so that you know our
streaming system has nice bite-sized
chunks work with all the time and can
keep the load just like it does with
bitmap assets so that should be good
what I'm noticing here just looking
through it this is stored more than once
which doesn't make a lot of sense right
you can see that stored here and here
and so I'm not sure why that's happening
but that might in oh you know what that
might because it's to channel so that
might be fine let's take a look channel
index 1 channel index 0 ok so that's
just because it was stereo so even
that's fine so I think we're good there
and then we've got all of our other
stuff here so you know one of the things
that I think maybe we should shoot for
is let's try to play this music test
over the opening cutscene it doesn't go
with the opening cutscene so it won't
sound very good it's also just a random
piano sample or something but we can
just use that as our goal for getting
the audio subsystem fleshed out and
finished as well we kind of did that
work to a certain extent for textures
they're working kind of more like they
should now in a more shippable way and
so what we'd like to do is do that for
music chunks now as well now we already
had music working in the game so we
don't have to do all the work of like
writing a mixer and all that stuff
that's already done but we didn't really
have this kind of a finalized way for us
to do our music streaming and I'd like
to do that a little bit more cleanly now
as we go so there's a lot of ways we can
approach that but I think what I'd like
to do is I think I'd like to keep it
simple and just do it the same way for
the most part that we're doing our art
assets the way that we do it our do our
art assets is there just 6 size chunks
and we lay them out inside fixed size
chunks right
that's pretty much how it works and the
only times that we don't do stuff like
that is when we have like unusual like
for example but intro cutscenes can have
unusual big plate sizes but most
everything else that's a sprite gets
broken up into fixed sized chunks for
audio since it's one-dimensional it's
pretty free for us to just break these
into fixed sized chunks as well and say
look let's just pick us chunk size we
sort of settled upon 20 56k let's just
make a bunch of 2050 6k chunks and we'll
just load audio into those as necessary
that seems like the best way to do it to
me we won't have that many sounds
playing at a time anyway you know we
don't have a huge budget for the a/v of
this game so it's not like we're gonna
have like hundreds of thousands of
sounds playing all the time when you
have a large budget for a V that can
actually happen so I would like to draw
a little bit of distinction there is we
might want to be more creative about how
we do things if we were trying to shoot
for really large numbers of sound
samples playing we would have to make
concessions for that and think about
that in the design we're never gonna get
there on handmade here oh that's that's
like only Triple A games get that kind
of sound attention where there's
literally hundreds of sounds playing
like always like ambient things and all
of this mixing for all of these
different things you know we're not even
gonna hat you know we'll have a thousand
sounds total or something right probably
in the game cuz that'll be what we can
afford we're not gonna have like a sound
designer that gets paid hundred thousand
dollars a year or sound design team
going through and adding like all of
these sound effects to everything and
layering everything and you know making
these really rich sound scapes so it's
worth noting that as you get more
towards a triple-a sides of things there
are different concessions you have to
make you do have to start thinking about
things in a more meticulous level we'll
never get there on handmade hero so I
think we don't want to over complicate
that system without really knowing what
those even would be and I wouldn't
recommend us doing anything differently
right now anyway I would take the same
approach I take to a lot of things which
is I'd want some people to actually
start producing those soundscapes first
and then start attacking what looked
like our weak spots based on those
profiles anyway so again don't try to
over engineer something for use cases
you don't have yet I guess it's the way
I would put it so I always would focus
on the ones we actually do have and in
this case we kind of know what that is
and it's just gonna be I think fine to
say let's make 256k chunks we'll make
some number of those so you know let's
say we wanted to spend a quarter
megabyte I'm sorry a quarter gigabyte on
sound right if you wanted to say like
okay we're gonna do 256 times 1024 x
1024 x 1024 right that's a sorry that's
that's not gonna work that's 1/4
gigabyte so if you're gonna do 1/4
gigabyte on sound right then we know
that that's gonna be a power of 1024
over like what we had right so we know
that we could store 1,024 sound chunks
at any given time if we dedicated 1/4
gigabyte of the system RAM to it and
that's not very much just Imran we could
dedicate a lot more we're not doing very
much the system Ram we just store our
world spit estate and most machines
today have gigabytes of memory you know
for a 16 even consoles have something
like 4 gigabytes of memory now which is
nuts when you think about back in the
day so we could even do like a whole
gigabyte for sound which would mean we'd
have like 4096 sound chunks active at
any given time again that seems like
more than enough for what we need so I
think we should be totally fine with
just doing a really basic chunk scheme
and that gets us out of the the
arbitrary memory management side of
things as well right so if I pop into
the asset system what you can see here
is we kind of just left some sketches in
place
for how audio was gonna get loaded you
can see in here we've got like a
renderer texture loaded at sample index
and a Luud font I'm not gonna do this
load at sample index we had sketched out
a way of doing things where we would
like load things in at a particular
sample play them till our load meter got
like past where it needed to be and move
them I don't really know that we need to
do that we could I mean it's tempting to
do but I just don't know if it's wise I
just said we should just do a chunking
seam and I feel like I should do that
but yeah so what do you folks want to do
I mean what do you think we should do do
you think we should try the crazy low to
that sample index game it seems maybe a
little too crazy but I've never seen it
discussed before so that usually is an
argument for doing and I'm handmade hero
because I like to draw things out and
show you how we attack new problems
that's pretty much the entire point of
the series and so sometimes I'd like to
sort of try things that I've never heard
people try before just because it seems
like that encourages you to experiment
and see how programmers attack problems
that they don't already know how to
solve and obviously you already know how
to solve the fixed-size reuse case we've
done that many times in handmade hero in
different ways so that's something to be
said if we were gonna do that you can
see here we've got a sample count in a
sample buffer the idea here we would
just set this to some large number let's
say it we set it to the 256 megabytes or
gigabyte
we would then have a you 64 that was the
sample buffer base index and that just
goes up infinitely over the entire
lifetime of the game every time we need
to load a sound we load it there and we
slide effectively the the buffer base
around so we say look we need to load
this much
we either reset back to the beginning of
the buffer if we couldn't fit it or we
load it there if we could
and it's just a circularbuffer that we
fill and then every sound just remembers
where it was and when the loaded base
index moves past where you are your
sound is no longer loaded and you have
to load it again right
so that's I mean that's it right that's
all it is
I don't know what sample buffer load
index was I'm not sure why you would
have needed that in this scheme in fact
I'm not really sure you do since we
obviously already put this in place I
guess I'm gonna go back on my word after
literally only just saying it and say
that I maybe will try this
can we get sample buffer base index did
we ever do anything with that I don't
think we did so let me go in here and
see um let me give a quick overview of
this just really quickly because it
looks like we never implemented we just
I remember I said what it was I'm just
gonna say what it is again for the
benefit of folks who didn't actually
hear that and are gonna wash right now
and not know what I'm doing and so if we
take a look at today's day 256 and this
is the crazy sound buffer I don't argue
this is a good idea it was just an idea
and I'd never heard it tried before so I
thought I would try it I just made it up
it's weird the idea is simple uh you
know you basically just say look I've
got a certain amount of memory that I'm
gonna reserve for sound so let's say
it's 256 megabytes but doesn't matter
right this is just any number that you
want to reserve you allocate that memory
so this is 256 megabytes I need this to
be more stable there we go you allocate
256 megabytes of memory here it is
and then what you do is you say I start
loading sounds at zero and they just
they just fill this up so here's sound a
here's sound B here's sound see here's
sound D and obviously with 2006 MIT
let's say this was much lower for this
example because traduz megabytes would
fit way more sounds than that but you
get the idea i loading the sounds when i
get to the end of the
buffer at some point I'm gonna ask you
know eventually I'm gonna ask the load
of sound and that sound is going to be a
it sound is gonna not fit right so it's
gonna have to be put like let's say here
because I want the sound to be
contiguous I I don't want to wrap the
buffer right and even if I could I would
need to put this part at the beginning
at least so even if you treated it as a
fully circular buffer you'd still have
to use the beginning so what happens
then is you just overwrite whatever
sound was in there now and now this
sound is considered evicted so if you
wanted to play sound a again you have to
load a again that's it the reason this
is interesting is because it gets rid of
any notion of any tracking at all for
the sounds you don't have to keep an LRU
you don't have to have an addiction
scheme you don't even have to have a
state that says where their sound is
unloaded or loaded you just look at
whatever it's you 64 index is and that
tells you whether it's loaded and that's
it right so that feels kind of
compelling and I don't see a lot of
downsides to it the reason that you
might not want to do this the only
downside I can think of is that if you
have a sound that's played all the time
like let's say there's just you know the
sound of like the hero like like hopping
so it's gonna be played all the time so
you kind of never really want to evict
it it's always gonna be a sound that you
want in there
this scheme will cause it to fall out
and get reloaded all the time right
because you know if you imagine you're
doing like abcdefgh
I blah blah blah blah blah if on average
let's say that the totemism oh my buffer
rolls over every two minutes or
something right I don't know how many
sounds will have and how many of them
will play so I don't know how long this
is but let's say it's two minutes if it
rolls over every two minutes that means
you're gonna have to load the like glove
swipe sounds and the footfall sounds
every two minutes right whereas if you
had a scheme that was more intelligent
you wouldn't have to well I even came up
with an answer to that and I think
that's what this was meant to sort of
represent but I'm not sure we actually
want it to be the way it is but we might
there's a reason it might have been this
way and we'll see that when we go but
I'll tell you what the conceptual thing
is either way the idea was simply that
look if you know that you have a Twitter
v6 mag buffer let's just dedicate a
low-rate range of the buffer let's say
64 megabytes that comes out of this well
would actually be that much to scale
let's just say there's a 64 megabyte
bottom watermark essentially and if you
go to play a sound and that sound is in
the gutter part so that bottom part
instead of actually playing the sound
you copy the sound out into the buffer
as a new sound so you don't have to
reload it you just do a mem copy right
so that has the effect of anybody who
was getting close to being evicted from
the sound buffer but who gets used on a
recent frame does get pulled back into
the active set right um again I have not
done any analysis of this idea it's
purely just a whimsical idea and I don't
have any arguments for or against it
it's just something I haven't seen tried
for sound buffers and it offers you
something that a fixed chunk scheme
doesn't offer you what it offers you
that a fixed chunk scheme can't is that
instead of using memory paging where you
need to say look maybe this sound is
only you know 16,000 bytes but my chunk
size is 32 thousand bytes you have to
figure out how to avoid that waste right
you can pack sounds together maybe and
then hope that they get used at the same
time which is just kind of a crapshoot
you can just accept the waste and and
not use that space for storage right but
inherently you end up in a situation
where you're wasting space right and so
what this does is it says it doesn't
matter because you're always loading
things into the linear buffer you never
waste any space the only thing you're
really doing is if you want to implement
this scheme is you end up with a little
wasted space when you double copy but
that space is presumably quickly filled
up by new loads right away anyway so in
theory you're really not wasting much
space at all and you can always set it
to a pretty low value to sort of balance
how much you do redundant loads versus
how much space you waste and and
everything else in the buffer is always
tightly packed right so anytime you're
gonna load even if your sound is 32
bytes long you're only using 32 bytes to
store it and that's totally different
than most schemes where you have to work
out some other thing either you know
you're doing that memory packing
implicitly by letting malloc pack it for
you or you're managing yourself and you
have to do some kind of page merging but
this scheme gets rid of all of that so
it's the only thing I've ever really
thought about that allows you to do
optimally packed memory with no work
like there's no work right we're not
merging sounds we're not tracking
lifetimes we're not keeping a queue
we're not doing a malloc
we're not managing memory we are
literally just record
one 64-bit integer and that's it
so I'm gonna try it I said I wasn't
gonna try it I said I was gonna do a
simple scheme but I might try it anyway
and to be fair this should be a very
very simple scheme it might be a little
tricky to get working because it's
something I've never thought about
before and so as you never thought about
something you aren't aware of the
subtleties so there's that but I think
we're just gonna say look you know we're
just gonna do it and we're gonna see
what happens right okay so what I'd like
to do here is say you know in a sense
maybe hmm
looking at this I also do wonder this is
another I mean I probably won't do it
now but I think you could also get rid
of the atomic compare exchange and
actually just use an atomic compare
exchange exactly directly on the 64 bit
offset so you could probably also
simplify the lifetime of the
multi-thread lifetime understanding that
we currently have I think you could
actually do that in one fell swoop which
might be another argument for using this
system for sound caching it's just a
thought but anyway so here we go here is
our sound loading code here's what we're
doing we're taking the same tack as we
were doing here basically
but the begin task with memory sort of
side of things I don't think we actually
need so begin task with memory is the
thing that actually uses some allocation
and I don't actually know that we ever
need that to happen so if you look at
begin task with memory that's a thing
that where the tasks actually have some
like a memory arena that they can
actually use for out their own
allocation purposes and then it gets
cleared when the task is done I think
and I may be wrong about this but I
think that
actually not necessary anymore so I
could be wrong about that but I think we
may be able to remove begin tasks with
memory entirely and literally never have
that be a thing anymore so if I go ahead
and do begin tasks with memory here and
that would simplify things for us as
well which is nice so here's our begin
task the memory call can see it here I'm
going to take a look at it so in in load
bitmap does it actually use the memory I
don't actually remember so let's see
here I don't think it does so you can
see that just using the texture op data
here so it doesn't need so it literally
doesn't need that arena at all and load
asset work is all we would need to store
in there so it's worth noting and I
guess I don't know exactly when we would
want to do this but from what I can see
I'm just gonna put it to do in there
right and say I think we can now safely
remove begin task with memory I don't
think it's actually going to be
necessary anymore since textures and
audio both read directly into unknown
location with no temp store now I don't
actually know that that's true maybe
we'll find that we actually need that so
I'm not gonna do the work of pulling it
out now because it's in there it works
will work for our purpose now there's no
sense in removing a feature we already
have working it's not really a problem
it's just it's some cost and complexity
we can remove from the system later if
we that
find that it never does anything for us
we might as well we'll leave it in for
now because we don't have to remove it
right so what we're gonna do here is say
alright we're coming through to load
sound we're gonna do the atomic to make
sure that we're actually sort of working
with it properly and we're gonna do our
load here is us grabbing that info out
and what you can see is when we do asset
memory size that was our old sort of way
of and I think that should give us an
error now right because we removed I
think we removed that do we not remove
that we still have asset memory size
does that get used this was when we were
doing stuff before yeah you can see that
it's really only used for this one case
right so we don't really need an asset
memory size anymore that was when we
were doing arbitrarily sized memory
management and merging things and all
that kind of nonsense
now we've gotten rid of all of that I
don't really need to worry about it
anymore so we don't really need this but
we probably do still want some of these
pieces of information potentially
although now I think about it we
probably don't really have to do any
calculations because channels are now
separated so we don't load multi channel
at a time and the the size of the data
is actually stored directly in the asset
HHA so this is how much we would be
loading right I can't actually remember
the exact name of that field but inside
every asset we now actually store its
footprint as an explicit value which we
always should have done I don't know why
I didn't do that but but there it is
right so we know exactly how big this
chunk is and so I think this part is
really not necessary we know how many
samples there are because we can divide
so we could say in here I guess I'll do
it this way we could say the sample
count is just gonna be whatever this
size is divided by the size of an S 16
because we know we only support one
sample kind and so if I want to I can do
that pretty easily
right I can do this I can do this
and now we know exactly what we're
dealing with here right so now if I say
all right we've got you know asset
memory acquire all this stuff that we
used to do none of that's necessary at
all
and so we're really talking now about
the much simpler version because we've
gotten stuff you know we've gotten out
of the the sort of arbitrary weirdness
there and we know that our loaded at
sample index this is the only thing that
we actually need to worry about is
setting that low to that sample index
right okay so what we're gonna do here
is say okay we've got this sort of stuff
we were setting up on the sound we don't
need that anymore it's going to access
that directly out of the asset structure
so that stuff doesn't have to happen we
don't need any of this nonsense where
we're doing any kind of channel layout
like all of that's gone now right this
is much better and simpler so when we
actually set this up and we say okay
here's the task here's the asset here's
the file handle here's the offset here's
the size again that's this can probably
just not do any of this
well I guess we do need that one thing
there well I'll just get it out of work
size probably so I think all of that
goes away and we're literally just
looking at this when we go for
destination that's the one place now
that we actually have some work to think
about doing right and there's there is a
subtlety here I'm not sure it's a
subtlety we actually have to worry about
I think I'll talk about it after I'm
done because it's fairly I it's it's I
don't want to say this so there is
something we could choose to guard
against or we could not choose to guard
against it and it's the kind of thing
where the worst case scenario is you get
some corrupted sound playback where it
plays back one sound instead of a
different sound um I will explain that
later if I don't remind me in the QA I
probably just won't guard against it it
wouldn't cause a crash or anything with
that which is yet another reason why
this scheme is kind of attractive and I
just don't think it will ever happen in
practice because in order for it to
happen you would have to have like a
catastrophic OS failure which isn't
something that's out of the question
but I just don't think it would be worth
the complexity the guard against it cos
who cares I just don't think it will
ever happen and if it does the worst
case scenario is you play a bit of the
wrong sound um but it's always worth
knowing right like you know it's it's
better to know when something could
happen and document it you don't want to
just say yeah that'll never happen and
then you know move on like like think it
through or or you know at least know
that it's you know get it in your head
do the thinking through know that you've
got these cases and document them or at
least be aware of them in your head
don't just like not think about it right
I mean might be the way to say it so
anyway as you can see literally all the
stuff we need to do our asset work is
here except for one thing which is where
exactly we want to put this thing and
like I said really all you have to do
for that is to go well we've got a
sample buffer we know it can contain
however many samples art here we know
this is the base index off of it and so
what we should be able to do now is say
what's the actual sample index so like
what's the sample buffer index out of
all of these right into
certain extent when I'm looking at this
what I'm seeing you know this doesn't
really make a lot of sense to me because
what I'm seeing here is I'm like why do
I care about samples right like this is
just a buffer if we eventually wanted to
load sound samples that were 24-bit or
something it would just work so I think
what I'd rather do is say more like that
you know and say look we're gonna have a
sample buffers and it's gonna have some
amount of data in it but I don't care or
know how much what the like type sizes
of samples are if you wanted to load
some some 8-bit samples or some 24-bit
samples or some 32-bit samples in there
and some kind of weird mod to hand made
here oh you know this scheme just
supports that fine so let's stop talking
about samples when we're loading and
let's just talk about the the the bytes
right so then when I'd say is okay we've
got a sample buffer base and this is I
guess really like a position it's or or
an offset you know it's it's I don't
know I mean I guess index maybe is the
best term I'm not sure but the reason
that I'm not gonna end up shying away
from calling it a byte is because this
is actually just a monotonically
increasing 64-bit value that never gets
smaller and it doesn't index into this
buffer you have to mod it first to do so
and so what we want to do is take this
sample buffer index here that's coming
off of the assets and we want to mod it
into our actual ring so what we're doing
is we're saying look do a divide here
and tell me where in the buffer I would
be if I was to load at the current base
index right so what I want to do there
is I'm just saying look this this value
goes up forever
I want to assume that it's mapped in a
circular fashion into this tiny buffer
that I've got tiny being 206 and
megabytes was actually huge but not
compared to a 64-bit number
right map it into this rotating buffer
and tell me where I would be in the
buffer for all the revolutions that I
maybe have done right so this mod can
really if we want to make this B unknown
value it could just be an and right and
so in some sense we could make this be
something that's at a compile time but
at the moment I'm not going to do that
because this mod happens almost never
and so it really isn't the kind of thing
that we would care about in that way
right so I think we don't have to worry
but if we wanted to we could speed this
up by making this be something that's
less extensive than a mod nowadays I'll
be honest with you don't really know how
much that does cost kind of interested
to know one thing that I don't know if
we've actually ever looked at on the
stream is Agner fogs instruction tables
you might say let's get those on the
desktop I use them a lot more than they
used to and they're kind of fun so if
you look up Agner fog it's a is
programmer that's I know that's probably
a name that's unfamiliar to people who
are you know maybe used to us names or
stuff like that right like it's it's not
a name that you may have heard as a
common name in use that's just a
person's name under fog I don't know how
you pronounce it I've never heard it
said but he did a lot of work with you
know basically taking X 64 and X 30 x86
CPUs and figuring out what the actual
timings are for like various
instructions things like that he
publishes a guy it's pretty good
sometimes it's inaccurate but a lot of
times it is accurate and it's good for
getting a rough estimate of things so
look up at your father's instruction
tables if you want that I do want that
and if we go to our desktop now we've
got it on there I'm gonna call it Agner
instruction tables so we know what it is
if we load this up here what we can do
is it's broken down by processor so if
we go to the
sir family that we're on here which is
like skylake in Scylla X if you look at
the section on skylake what you can see
is just a giant set of tables that tells
you all sorts of things like how many
cycles things take four throughput and
latency and so on right now there's a
lot of other stuff in here that's
actually really good to know I and for
example this port which tells you which
ports of the processor and instruction
can execute on it's pretty awesome to
even tells you if something is going to
execute on multiple ports it tells you
they're broken down so for example
here's a mob instruction if this is a
mob instruction that goes between a
register and memory in this case right
the r8l I believe is the low eight bits
of a register I think is what that means
actually I don't really know I almost
never read the r8 side of things but
like our 32 or 64 right 32-bit register
64 bits of the register because you know
how Intel registers are 64 bits for the
for the general registers but you get
address 32 16 or 8 right and so that's
what that's really telling you if you
look here you can see for like this mob
instruction doing that 16 bit load from
a memory location takes either port 2 or
3 that's what that means it'll use it
can issue on either so will take either
port 2 or 3 which base is saying this
execution resource right there it's like
0 through 6 I think or 7 yes 0 through 7
it'll take either one of those ports it
needs and then also one of these
arithmetic ports 0 1 5 6 those are
reports that actually do work 2 &amp; 3 are
ports that do look memory load well you
can see it right here right and we can
go into this in greater detail later I'm
giving you the real glossary version but
if you remember when we went over the
basic structure of an ecstacy for a
processor it's got like the instruction
decoding and caching and that sort of
stuff into micro ops then it's got ports
that can issue micro ops and each one of
those micro reports can do certain kinds
of operations but not other
so you can see here I need one of the
load ports because it's coming from
memory right memory memory
I need a load port but then if I'm
supposed to be taking part of a register
I oftentimes also need an arithmetic
port because it's gonna like mask it to
zeros or something or do something else
that requires one of these right anyway
all of this information is great cuz it
can give you some ballpark ideas of what
you're actually doing and how the
processor is gonna struggle with it like
what ways it's going to have to operate
in order to get the job done and that
can help you understand the performance
of your routines and it's really kind of
nice anyway so what I was saying is if
we want to look at integer mod which
actually I have no idea I don't think
I've ever looked that up so I actually
don't know what the speed is of integer
mod and I have no idea what the
instruction is I've never written it
myself
let me see what it's what it's called
do they have that in here
in other possibilities it doesn't have
it you have to infinite yourself we
would divide so I'm not sure which one
you have to do right because if you do
an integer to divide it and subtract
that's a mod so I don't actually know if
it even does that natively here's what I
will say rather than belabor this point
because this is really not what we're
trying to do here if you look at what
we're actually doing you can see that
it's like a 36 cycle operation to do a
div 64-bit wide right and so you know
you can see the reciprocal throughput
and the latency here it can be quite
high right there's a up to an 88 cycle
delay for that this is how many micro
ops it takes right and some of those
micro hops it looks like could spend
more than a cycle doing their job
because you can go from the micro op
number out to a much larger number right
so I don't actually yeah I mean you look
at how expensive divet that's pretty
vicious right um so just looking at that
kind of destroyed me a little bit from
using it so I think I will go the full
full pull and actually do like thank-you
Agner that gave me information I wanted
I think I will go ahead and say we're
not going to talk about sample buffer
size per se what we're gonna say is
we've got a mask right so we've got a
sample buffer mapping mask right and
what the sample buffer mapping mask does
is it says look let's go ahead and take
whatever it is that we're doing here and
we're going to mask the incoming value
against it and we just assume that
someone has built a mask that will turn
this in to a 32-bit value we can that's
inside the buffer right and what we know
is modulus right is an arbitrary
operation that allows us to map to any
range but if that range was a power of
two then and and modulus are equivalent
right because the power of two the
remainder will just be whatever the
bottom bits were right so this just says
look when you create your sample of
oversize we don't
what it is but it better be a power of
two and then when we do the end this
just works right so good bye-bye auger
thank you very much for telling me that
modulus just looked too expensive we
should double-check that there isn't a
special purpose instruction for modulus
but if a divide takes that long I would
expect the modules to take that long
that's just too long for me I don't like
sticking something in there that could
take up to 88 cycles that's a lot of
cycles that's almost getting up towards
memory access penalty range it's not
quite a couple a couple hundred cycles
for a memory ax penalty but it's well
over any of the L caches so well over
the cost of an l2 or l3 I hit I believe
although l3 I don't know what the l3
cache penalty is these days l2 is way
faster than that it's like you know 16
cycles or something isn't it I don't
remember what it is but it's it's pretty
darn low so anyway uh yeah what's the l2
cache
what's the l2 cache speed do we have
that so eleven cycles in some cases it
says so really fast right
I mean so if you look here right here's
all some estimated latency Xin skylake
for the cash so even the L if you miss
the l2 cache and have to hit the l3
cache it's still faster than a mod right
um it's that right oh there it is
I'm like it can't be 42 cycles and then
I'm like oh yeah there's the 51
nanoseconds like the wires are long my
friends okay so if you look at this it's
just I was uncomfortable with the fact
that that mod takes as long as a memory
miss out to anything other than main
memory so even out to l3 cache that's
just no good so I'm gonna do it this way
and use an actual and there to make sure
that we're not having to do a real
modulus there I just that's just bad um
so here we get our sample buffer index
pack now we know that we're gonna load
into the sample buffer at that location
but what we don't know is will it fit so
what I do need to do now is say look
what was the data size right because
here it is and I'm gonna go ahead and
pull that out like I was wanting to do
before so there's our data size and
we'll just jump that in here and what
I'm gonna say is if the sample buffer
index plus the data size is greater then
however big the buffer actually is right
meaning we would overflow then we have
to wrap so what we need to do then is
say look whatever the sample buffer base
index is needs to move up to the next
boundary and then our offsets going to
be zero so our sample buffer index here
will become zero we're gonna load you
know we've gone off the end we're gonna
sort going to load at the bottom and our
sample buffer base index at that point
needs to move up to the next like where
the next even multiple of that value
right
so much like here we were doing this
handoff right what we want to do now is
take this sample buffer base index which
we now know is you know needs to get
moved one up we know that our data size
is enough to do it
so it seems to me like it's probably
sufficient to just say look let's take
whatever the sample buffer base index is
let's upload you know pretend we loaded
this at validation which we know pushes
over the boundary because we just check
and then let's and off that part that we
had before so this mask let's say and it
off just like we were doing before but
it just happened why did that not copy
copy there we go I know what was going
on there something we weird
but so let's go ahead and take what we
now have and off that bottom part by
saying whatever the mask was normally
this ends off the top so if we not this
right if we take the inverse that should
end off the bottom which is what we want
to do to get rid of any fractional
offset so this just basically re-centers
us to the bottom of the buffer right um
so that should completely solve our
problem I think meaning now we just
loaded the thing in we've done the
sample buffer science check we've
figured out we're going to load it and
now creating our destination is trivial
it's just whatever the sample buffer is
in that sort of sample buffer size there
whatever the sample buffer actually is
we're just going to take whatever the
the sample buffer index that we computed
we're just going to offset by that much
right now once we've done that which
we've saved here this also now needs to
go up by the actual data size so in
addition to doing this AB there which we
know
centers us we also have to load as much
as we were going to load right but we
need to do that in either case so the
base index after we compute which one
we're going to use we have to add
however much of our data we actually
loaded we have to add that much in so we
don't use that part anymore right so I
think that gives us our entire load that
loads our sounds now this has to be
simple science there we go
and the finalized operation I think we
may have gotten rid of is that true
because nobody actually needs
finalization anymore so that's just gone
yeah so what you can see here again
unless I'm missing something this is why
I say this scheme was interesting it's
so simple this is the entirety of the
code necessary to do your LRU you're you
you know variable size loading you're
screaming you're everything that's it
that was it
right um and the only thing we need to
do now to add like sort of an at least
recently used modifier to it is just add
one mem copy when we actually go to load
a sound like to play a sound if we so
desire and we don't even have to do that
but I think I would like to to minimize
the chances that we hit a sound that we
already have loaded and that fell out
because we just weren't tracking the
fact that we're playing in a lot so what
I want to do here is say look really all
this thing needed after all of this
nonsense all it really needs right is
this value so what I'd rather do here is
have an actual thing that's like hey
yeah maybe there's a void star that's
like allocate or reserve sound memory
and what I'd like to do is say I just
passed that a size and it will do this
so it basically says you know all of
that is something we can call as
necessary we just call a reserved sound
memory and we pass the data size here
[Music]
like so and that way that's something we
can do in the other team in the playback
routine as well so we never have to
rewrite that
which again gets us to the point where
I'm like saying that's the entirety the
code you have to write which is kind of
cool so this reserved sound memory
basically says look take the assets take
the data size get this stuff aligned
properly do all that and if there's bugs
in here this is good because it means we
left that debug them wants right um so
let's load this out just for clarity
there's that mask oops didn't mean
expand the console there um so this just
becomes an and with the mask
this becomes an end with not the mask
just makes this a little easier to read
right and I think that's all we really
need to do that all seems good so now to
produce the actual result we want we
have a void star result we're gonna take
the assets sample Boop's sample buffer
just called sample buffer right and then
we're going to add that sample buffer
index to it
having a lot of problems to type in
today and a good typing day for some
reason maybe the keyboard is off-center
um that should be able to take care of
both our load sound call and when we do
playback it should also work so I think
we're good to go and I just want to take
a look at where sound playback is
happening here
so this get sound samples that's really
what we would need to do the playback
here and so this is the place where we
would do any of that that sort of
adjustment work right so I think all I
need to do to make this thing complete
is just say well you know if this sound
is loaded and so you know we do the get
bitmap info I'm sorry get bitmap here
what we need to do is look and see
whether or not the actual sound is valid
so if in here we do get sound samples
what we would need to do is is actually
ask by the way is this where do we where
do we ask to load it so I guess it's in
load sound that that happens
here's load sound which is the thing we
just did so I guess that's all fine so I
guess the sound loader will just do it
seems fine so all we really need to do
here is is we need to say look we need
to get that that asset right so this
this asset that we've you know sort of
looked up here we need to look at what
it's loaded sounded Nexus so we need to
say that that value that we should have
set oh you know what we're not actually
setting it though either are we so I
guess this is a little bit off because
we actually need two values when we do
reserve sound memory we actually need
two we actually need to set on the sound
where it went and we don't have that
right now and we do have the asset here
so we can set it here right so what we
would want to do there is we want to
look to see whether this thing is loaded
and so I think what we want to do is say
look if you know this asset if it's
state is asset state loaded then we'll
give it back to you but otherwise we
won't
now we don't technically have to do that
but the reason that I'd like to make
sure that we do is because we want to
make sure that you don't try to play a
sound back that hasn't actually been
loaded yet if you want to play a sound
back that has been unloaded that will
actually get caught by the next check so
that part we don't really have to worry
about but the other thing where we
haven't finished the load yet we do need
to check for so this wants to look and
see hey make sure that someone set this
to loaded at some point right so then
what we're gonna do is say okay if the
asset there's the sound if the assets
loaded at sample index is greater or
equal to the assets basically high-water
mark
so in other words if we have reasonably
that this thing could actually be run
right and that is right here right so if
this thing is above where we said the
the base was going to be that's the
loading point though so we actually need
to be back by that much so we actually
need so that's really a bad name that's
actually a sound buffer top we should
really call this sound buffer and index
gin i'm santi i feel like it should
actually be bad so what you're actually
doing is saying look the base index is
whatever the top of this buffer is minus
the size right does that make sense so
we kind of know that there are two sound
ranges if you will and in fact we could
system it we could make those systemic
we could say struct sound buffer or like
asset sound buffer ranges or something
like this right and what we could do
there is say look give us back the sound
buffer base index and give us back the
sound buffer I don't want to call this
but like LRU index so like that thing
where I saying I want like a region
where we'll maybe consider a copy out if
you fall inside it give me back that one
too so here I would do something like
ranges equals get sound buffer ranges
and pass the assets I'm gonna assume
that we'll compute this for me I will
then say look if the asset is in range
that's great
so let's say
ranges da Gama for base index if it's
above the base we know it's loaded and
we can play it that's great
but we probably and and I guess we don't
really need a nails case here what we
really need is another case here um this
result will default to zero so if we we
don't need a catch-all for that so first
we want to actually check whether or not
it's above the LRU if it's above the LRU
we're just done so we could just say aye
wherever the sound is that's what we
would load right so here is just a I
guess I might do get sound buffer
pointer maybe and I just say great let's
load that in and I'm gonna pull this out
into a temporary so enough to keep
typing asset arrow so it's clearer there
right so great give that to me
if on the other hand we're in the low
region so this case would be we're not
above the LRU watermark so we actually
want to do a copy here's where you would
do that copy so we would call reserve in
this case and that reserve is up here
somewhere
reserve sound memory right I'm gonna add
this one in there too so this gets sound
buffer ranges
so that'll just be assets and buffer
ranges results and this will return
these two values by computing them so we
will need to do that a second that's
really easy routine the right so that
should be no no biggie and then we also
kind of want the get sound buffer memory
call so this is a white star and that
takes you 64 there we go so that all
seems pretty good I'm happy with all
that so then what I'm gonna do here is
say all right we'll implement these two
routines in a second and then what we
need to do is say in the case where we
want to do our LRU scheme what we're
gonna have to do is do a reserved where
we actually you know get more space for
this and then we're going to actually
move it from one place to another right
so what we need to do is figure out how
big the sound is again that's really
know no biggie because it says exactly
what it is in the size field so there's
our size and then we're just gonna use
that as the copy so here we have our you
know our desk pointer basically and our
source pointer is always going to be
this get sound buffer memory call
because that's where the sound was
regardless so you know we're gonna get
where it was we're gonna get where it
should be now and we're just gonna move
it right we're just gonna move it up now
we have an issue that's kind of
tricky yes so I think this can never
happen so it's okay I was gonna say if
we ever ended up with these regions
overlapping but they can't as long as
the size of the maximum sound chunk is
never bigger than half the buffer you
can never have this happen so it doesn't
matter so this is not relevant so I'm
pretty sure this will always work you
can just say look copy the memory from
the place that's going out of scope into
a place that would now be in scope most
recently and call it a day wait is that
true I'm just thinking this has to be
aware of overlap let's draw the case out
shall we
because I'm just not sure okay so here's
what I'm talking about
effectively what I'm saying is we have
some part and it could be anywhere right
but we've got some kind of a pointer
right which is this is the top and then
this is inside the circular buffer and
the sound is like here so here's sound a
right and what we're basically saying is
that this region is the lru region which
means in this region if we have a sound
that plays while it's here we want to
move it out because it's going to be
evicted soon and we don't want sounds
that are getting played frequently to
ever be in here because gonna get
evicted so what I'm saying is that well
in this case and I think I'm right in
this case these regions will overlap so
the new location for a which will then
move top above it so it'll be right here
the new location for a will be compacted
down and part of it will overlap since
copy proceeds from the low bytes on I
think we have no issue it's never gonna
look the other way
meaning we're never always I think
copying it either to disparate regions
that don't overlap or in regions that
only overlap the end of the destination
with the beginning of the source and
that should be fine famous last words
but I think the simple thing just works
let's hope so because my claim that this
is a simple algorithm starts to fall
apart if all of a sudden you don't have
the simple thing work but it well um so
I think this is all we need and now we
just need to implement these we do have
one thing we wanted to do here in order
to track that loaded at sample index
that loading that same place really
shouldn't be called that anymore right
there should be just be called load at
buffer in our loaded sound buffer index
right it is not a sample it is not a
sample we are just using byte offsets
there so it's just an index into the
buffer it has nothing to do with samples
so what I'm doing here is saying this is
gonna be a asset or a sound buffer
memory that you get back we're gonna
have the pointer to the memory and we're
going to have the sample or sorry the
buffer index to the memory come back and
again this is just because when we do
this in the sound buffer memory case
when we call gets an buffer memory or
reserve sound buffer memory what we want
to be able to do there is actually
reserve is actually return a more
complex piece of data so in both cases
when we call this we need this result to
give us back two things first of all the
pointer which we know we can get at all
times
this way right but in addition we need
whatever the index was that we were
going to feed into the buffer right and
we are not actually getting that yet so
what we need to do here is save before
we advance right we need to save what
that index would have been so
this value before incrementing right so
here we snap both of those things so
this is where the sound was right and
that's something we wanted and then we
also the pointer now if we want to be
Squinkie about it we could always get it
from get sound buffer memory um instead
what I'm gonna do is actually probably
just a cert that fact so because we
already know it I'm just gonna assert
that result pointer equals the get sound
buffer memory of the buffer index so I'm
just gonna assert the thing never
diverged and call it a day in this
routine we have the same thing so we've
got loaded app we've got assets sample
buffer and what we just want to do here
is take whatever the base is in the
sample buffer and we just want to load
in the version of this that's got modded
to the mask right so basically you know
chop off that top part put it to where
it should be and off we go right what
I'd also like to do here is maybe do an
assertion so when we get back
whatever this pointer is that we've
we've sort of received here what we
probably also want to do is assert that
the sound actually would fit in there so
one thing we could do here is say also
research assert that if we were to cast
this to a you ate that result pointer -
so that so that result pointer plus the
data science right is not going to be
over the total size of the buffer so
this sample buffer size plus the sample
buffer right so this must be less than
or equal to this
and that's just a double-check our
arithmetic like we want to make sure
that the thing we return it never
returns a pointer that couldn't actually
fit the size that you asked for because
you know based on the way we allocate
memory it may be that we could do that
and never know and we've been loading
off the end of a buffer and never know
so you want to make sure that we like
check that buffer math there and make
sure that whenever we gives one of these
things back
we don't do it something where we've
we've actually not left the room that
you know we've asked for right um so I
think that's mostly what we want in
terms of of those functions and so now
when we call reserve sound memory
they're like this we'd actually pull
that out and so we'd say sound memory or
you know just maybe memory equals this
call this takes the pointer and the
sound now gets that loaded at buffer
index or semaphore next that gets the
buffer index right so now we've set it
properly if we compile we should get an
error down below where we want to do the
exact same thing but haven't done it yet
oh and we should we should make those
work as well but the one I actually
wanted to talk about right now was this
one so here we want to get again we want
to do the same thing so that's sound
buffer memory this right here we want to
be able to call that and this will be
get the pointer and the asset right oops
the asset loaded at sound buffer index
will get the buffer index like so
right so that seems good
now these parts here where we're
creating these these should be pretty
easy to do and also all of this stuff
here where we were like sample buffer
base index that's actually sought sample
buffer top index now because like I said
that value isn't the base of the buffer
it's the top of the buffer base you know
the the top of the used region I don't
know how it's not a great word either
one they're both kind of wrong but the
top is less wrong than bottom maybe I
don't know if that's really true but
anyway so in here if we whoops the size
was supposed to be asset HHA data size I
think that's all good yeah so okay now
we just have loaded at sound buffer
index so this is the buffer index here I
think that's all good
and the only thing I'm not sure about
like there was an error there I'm not
sure what it is so I assume that
reserved sound memory it doesn't really
know what that is oh no it just doesn't
know what data size is so that just has
to go up there okay so I think that's a
full sketch of the routine
these are computed off of the top so if
you just go to the top index here which
should be this so the base index is
always just the top index you know minus
some number right so it's whatever the
in this case the sample buffer size is
that gets you down to the bottom of the
buffer right and the LRU rate is just
that plus something so I don't know what
we want to set that to but it can just
be a size like sample buffer LRU range
or something and that just gets added on
and that's it but that's all there is to
it so I think that's all we really want
to do I don't think there's anything
else particularly Squinkie going on here
I think that's it and so yeah that
should pretty much do it make sure we've
cleaned up our errors here so I think
the only thing we need to do to get
things started is in the actual
allocation the part of things where we
actually get things started here my
recollection is we don't do anything
with sounds at the moment right so if I
were to search for this sample buffer I
don't think anyone actually sets it up
right so you know we did all our work
here and that's great but you know yeah
you can see this is it it's just these
routines
here nobody actually creates anything
useful there so what I want to do there
is say alright let's do like in its
sound memory here and let's pass the
game ass that's in there and like
whatever the cursor up that's sorry
that's my internal name for things as
curse or usually so we actually want
memory arena I think it's what the
column here yeah so let's take the
memory arena there and we'll say here's
where the memory comes from right and
then we'll just expect this thing to set
that up and so what it'll do is probably
take the sample buffer size actually I
don't even know if I want to do that so
what we're gonna do here is say look the
sample buffer size is gonna be a power -
right so it's gonna be like 1024 x 1024
x what like 256 I think we said
something like that so maybe that's what
the size of the sample buffer is I don't
know what the size of sample of ur
should be but let's just say that's what
it is so then what I'm gonna do is say
alright let's go ahead and allocate that
memory off of this arena now you could
argue that this should just be its own
separate memory pool that just gets
allocated not on an arena but you know
that's a separate story and I don't
really going to think about that so what
I want to do instead is just say look
let's do a push size of the sample
buffer size off of this arena and that's
gonna be the memory in question right so
this gives us our sample buffer size and
maybe I will also record the size here
since we need that and then what I need
to do is make the mapping mask so if I
do the assets sample buffer mapping mask
all of this stuff and I'm gonna put that
down below because these are all like
derived values right so the sample
buffer mapping mask is just gonna be a
loft up of the sample buffer size and
then I'm just gonna subtract 1 right so
in 64-bit math if I just subtract 1
that'll get me just that bottom mask
because it'll knock out all the other
bits so that's
it's all I need then if I go in and set
the remaining values the top and X and
the LRU range the LRU range I don't know
what we want to call it maybe we'll call
it like the bottom 16 Meg's will just be
the place that will move stuff out of
that's necessary and then the sample
buffer top index so you know you could
set that to zero but what you have to
remember is we're creating we're
pretending that's the top of loaded
things I would rather have it start out
at the sample buffer size so that the
whole buffer like that whole first swap
of things I would like it to be so that
zero is out of the range so one way to
do it maybe would be to say we're gonna
start loading it like two times the
sample buffer size because this but this
can be anything we want right it's a
64-bit value that goes on forever so
what I'd rather do is I'd rather have
zero so if you just had a zero something
that was initialized to zero and you
never really like looked at it or what
it's doing I would rather have zero just
be out of the range way out of the range
so it's totally clear that zero isn't a
valid thing ever so that anyone who has
something set to zero knows that their
crap is not in the range whereas if I
actually had the sample buffer be less
than or equal to sample buffer size zero
would still think it was loaded right
and so we don't really need to do this
because we're tracking loaded as a
separate parameter but imagine a future
where we decide to get rid of that that
which we might want to do that and just
track that one value because I think we
can do everything with just that one
value I may want to try doing that
someday I don't want this to to come
back to bite me so I'm just gonna say
look let's just take that window move it
up so that no sounds that have a zero
value ever could in note at any time
during the run of the program until the
heat death of the universe could never
think they were loaded and so that's
what that tries to accomplish there so
that's what I think we want to try I'm
gonna go ahead
and go to the anit club here and say
that when we allocate the game assets
here the non restored memory is gonna be
I think where we want to get this out of
so I'm just gonna go ahead and say let's
an it the sound memory look right off
the bat because it doesn't really depend
on anything I don't think and will
allocate the arena there and I think
we're done with that I think we're good
to go now in order to start testing this
stuff we need to actually play some
sounds mean to have some sounds doing
something and so I think we actually
turn sound off here if I remember
correctly I actually don't really
remember what we did was sound because
it's all like it was all implemented and
stuff in here but I just don't remember
like when we decided to do
I thought we'd turned it off so it
wouldn't play while we were doing stuff
but I just don't remember
I don't remember if we turn this off or
if it's still going so are we still
doing sound this is it
so it doesn't look like any of this got
nerfed okay
I say hesitantly it looks like no one
literally ever calls play sound so I
guess we just start calling that I mean
I don't know it's been so long I start
remember I guess we didn't nerf it I
guess we're just not playing anything
I'm gonna look and see about the audio
state I mean here it is right and we
even have a music thing there and so I
don't know like oops did I do something
bad there I don't think so
so if I go ahead and do music doesn't
look like we ever did anything with that
either
yeah so I don't know I I guess I don't
really know what's going on here so
we're just gonna have to make it up as
we go along it looks like all the codes
still in place and it looks like maybe
the reason that we're not getting
anything in terms of music there is just
because we stopped we looked deleted any
calls that would have played it I I mean
I don't know what else to say I don't I
don't see any other nerfing like the
audio States getting initialized it
looks like we left it all in so I guess
the only thing we did is like stop
calling it right and so if I compile
this back in right my assumption is that
[Music]
my assumption is that yeah like we could
just make this work pretty trivially
here
the actual code to call like the play
sound on it we need to be able to get
that sound so if we look back at like
the asset calls for like load sound or
for get sound samples right
I don't really know so the audio system
as it stands presumably you ask for a
handle to one of those yeah so
presumably you know you would just do
something where you would say play sound
on this thing so I would do something
like you know if game stayed music
wasn't set up yet I would set it up so I
would say game stayed music equals play
sound like so and the audio state is the
one from here and the sound ID is one
that I would have to you know get right
so I'd have to do a search for that
sound ID by doing like a get a set call
so if I actually look at you know the
get a set call here or the get sound
asset call get that it's like best match
right get first first asset from get
best match asset from right so if I did
this
I guess what I want to do is say and is
there a get best match sound yeah there
is so what I want to do is I just want
to say look get me the best match sound
from the assets I'm gonna give you a
type ID for the category which I'll have
to look up what we even said those were
because I don't know that we really oops
I don't know that we really have many I
I think it might just be audio I don't
even think we have categories for those
I think they all go in here now so it'd
be more like that right and then I've
got an asset vector match and an asset
vector weight and again we're gonna redo
that part pretty soon because we're
almost done with all of our asset system
stuff so the way we do matching and and
store it and like quick searches on
matches is going to have to change
pretty soon because we will die in
search search land if we don't but for
the moment we're fine for testing
purposes personally so we just need a
way to look one up which we can do here
and then we need ways to play it which
we can do here so I'm gonna make like
let's say channel 0 ID there and in
order to match this we just need a way
to like load this thing and so what I
want to do is I want to look back at
what that music was tagged so I just
want to look at look at the actual tag
file right so what I want there is to
say okay in handmade tags I know in here
I think we put the tags for it so it's
just tag title screen and it's audio
state right so basically like I should
just be able to do tag title screen
equals 1
tag title screen equals one right match
that and the weight vector yeah also
want tag channel so I want to match that
properly and you know we could later
load the other ones so here on match
channel index I could change that to
channel one and I should get back the
channel one instead right I think that
would load everything that we wanted to
load and and go from there so oops it's
not supposed to say vector I'm supposed
to say wait I think that's really all we
need this stuff here I don't really
remember much about the weight of this
input stuff was working so I'm just
gonna look really quickly what we
changed that to we should be able to do
basically the same thing if you look in
here under game input you can see that
there's like a clip space Mouse PE I
think that means you don't need the
buffer width anymore so I'm pretty sure
we could do here is just do a clamp on
this so we could say like music volume I
guess this is for two channels what we
could say is the music volume here it's
just going to be a clamp from 0 to 1 in
fact I think we can just do clamp 0 1 of
whatever the clip space Mouse P is for
the x-axis right I think that's all we
would need there so that just that's
actually simpler than it used to be oh
and that's from the input
so now we just have a bunch of debugging
to do I don't think we we have much more
to think about maybe we do maybe I
missed something but I don't know so I'm
just gonna okay
[Music]
so it sounds like to me it all worked
great up until it had to do streaming
and it looks like the streaming didn't
work properly but hey good on us we
actually got quite a bit can you hear
that
[Music]
yeah um so we don't really know exactly
what's going on there but the first
thing to probably look at is we're gonna
want to go see how that streaming stuff
is working and we have to go make sure
that that you know it properly lose the
next chunks and that we probably got
them marked up and all that other sort
of stuff right so let's just go do some
due diligence on that I don't know a lot
of time to get that working today but
hey that was pretty great everything
just worked I heard sound and it was
playing and I could even change the
volume by moving the X I mean could
change the channel balance by moving the
X which is that what we tried to do
there and all that good stuff so let's
go into audio and see what's supposed to
happen when we're doing streaming so
here's that but playing sounds you can
see the code and in here what it's doing
is it's kind of looping over each one
and it's getting the sound samples for
those which is that function we just
wrote right and it's looking and saying
okay here's like the sound info for the
sound we're talking about here's the one
that would come next which we can go
look at this code to make sure it's
getting the right value there and it's
also doing a pre fetch on that next one
in case it needs to you know so it will
be pulled in quickly so we may want that
prefetch to actually well
so we may want prefetch to do the same
move this this move you know I'm saying
we might we may want prefetch to do that
if the sound is loaded so I think you
know I don't know I'm just gonna say we
get to do
right so I'm literally just gonna call
here get sound samples to force that to
happen right and that way it will move
it out of the eviction region if it was
going to be evicted soon and so that way
if you're telling it to prefetch a sound
it will make sure it's pre fetched into
the upper region not the eviction region
which i think is what we would want
because if someone specifically telling
you I'm going to need this sound we
probably want that to be the way that it
works don't actually know that that's
true but it just seems intuitively
correct to me all right
so we say get next sound in Shayne blah
blah blah we do like the sample chunk
here if you use the 1.9 F version gonna
be honest don't know what 1.9 F is oh
that so that looks like a bug we've
gotten here we should fix should
probably tighten up some of this code
just in general so how do we know
how do we know when to use next sound
and chain here there's the volume
computation
seconds for sample test face current
sample playing Sam D sample samples
played total chunks to mix
real checks for make it sound low sound
sample cups so this is wrong I think I
know
so the problem here is that loaded
loaded sounds sample count is well so I
don't actually know
so that sample count loaded sound sample
count is like well I guess that's right
that is how many are remaining in the
sound total but you may have to advance
to the next sample position - you know -
you may have to advance the next asset
so I just try got to see where do where
does anyone do that
so it looks like it's yeah so that looks
like it's wrong so I'm gonna say that
the sample count here is not accurate
like the sample count has to be so
there's a couple things in here that we
probably have to fix right and honestly
this routine this routine looks kind of
Squinkie for other reasons we may wanna
clean this up a little bit I'm not so
sure about this but anyway the point is
I think this sample account is therefore
wrong because this is the total number
of samples so if I do a quick search to
look for sample count here what you can
see is it really uses it the entire time
and it's not correct so the sample count
for this loaded sound is actually the
data size divided by the sample the
number of samples I'm the number of
bytes right so this actually should look
like that right
and I'm pretty sure that's at least one
issue also we actually need the asset
itself and we're not getting that we get
back in HHA sound but we actually want
the whole asset in its entirety
right so calling it sound info is not
really what we want because we need that
that data size I think
yeah because this only has a sample
count the channel count and the chain
[Music]
and I'm assuming that the channel count
here doesn't do anything right hoping
yeah so yeah I think this needs to get
the actual asset so this needs to be
like
something like that
let's take a look
yeah I mean I guess the other way we
could look at it is if we need that
piece of information maybe it should
come back with the get sound info cuz
maybe I don't want to be accessing the
asset directly so when you say get sound
info right and you do this thing here
maybe I just want you to get back an
actual asset value like like that you
know what I mean
and so maybe what I really want you to
do is this and I don't actually know
that I want like how often do we
actually use if I was going to just do
loaded sound here how often do we
actually get an error on using some part
of that that doesn't actually work right
cannot convert from sound to assets
agree with that get sound info getting X
and in shame that seems fine sample
count right so that is not we want
either so I think we're all good so the
sample count here which we actually
computed which is this that's the one we
want to use we would want to use it down
here so we would say assert that the
samples played is greater than or equal
to the sample count of the loaded sound
which is this and then we would say
subtract that amount away and that
should be fine I think that's what we
want there but don't quote me on that so
I think again that routine is not
fabulous
but now that we fixed it correctly knows
to advance
[Music]
but I think we're good now so sound bits
and gentlemen I think that's everything
we'll need to test that code a little
bit I think we want to make sure that we
actually have a little more visibility
into it working but I think that like
literally just works now for everything
[Music]
getting some playback shopping there I'm
not sure what's from again I think that
might be us having to I think that's us
missing our frame rate
[Music]
because we don't currently try to
protect against that yeah that's that's
just a frame right miss
[Music]
yeah that's just framing this alright so
I think we're good I don't actually
remember how much time we have left but
I think we're good here so I probably
don't want to do anything else right now
that was everything I wanted to do today
I so I think that's all good let's
double check since I do have a little
bit of time let me just tell a check
what do we do
you're just wondering if I go into if I
go into the audio code here and you want
to play a sound but you don't want to
keep a handle to the sound how does that
work look did we really I guess we
really didn't do anything here like what
happens
so basically
it looks like we really didn't quite
finish this part I mean we sort of did
but if you the answer is that I guess
you just you just never managed these at
all so meaning you could call the change
volume and you would actually change the
line with some other sound that used a
recycled handle from the one that you
had which I suppose is fine because if
you're playing music you should just
always have not you should always know
where you're at in it maybe I don't know
but you're still just a little weird so
we probably want to maybe make that do
something slightly different but in
terms of just testing out the sound
stuff a little bit more if we wanted to
make it so that every time that the hero
like hopped to someplace or something
maybe you know I just I just be
interested to play around that a little
bit just make sure that that stuff works
okay so I'm not really sure how that
should work
just trying to think if I want to do
anything here with that like for example
right here
I don't know that we really do anything
with the glove at the moment but I could
just make it so that that triggers a
sound I think so for example if here I
just wanted to do this I think you just
can so I don't know if the gamestate
comes through here though it does so if
I wanted to I could just say yeah like
why don't we just try playing a sound
here and we'll just do it you know match
on something I don't know what we
actually have four possibilities here
but we've got up some stupid sounds in
here so you know maybe we want to do
like one of these like bloop or
something so you know we say like get me
a bloop sound and then we're just going
to play the bloop sound right so I think
that would allow this test to make sure
we're like we can play sounds randomly
not curing anything there what is the
volume default to when you play a sound
it should default to on so this did not
work at all
assuming that we actually ever imported
those sounds which I assume we did
[Music]
take a look yeah so these sounds should
be imported right here they are so we
should have some bloops in there and
we're not getting any bloops in there so
let's just take a look that gives us
something to debug here so that's in
handmade brain and that's in
execute brain Hira so inside this code
here
probably should have compiled in debug
mode but what happens that is not a
sound ID let's go ahead and end real
quick compound debug mode just so I can
see what's going on oh woops that's
playing every time I wanted it only on
attack first of all that should actually
be here oh no this is something we want
to report so if you are using remedy
please report bugs so we can get them
all of course I can't actually do this
can I
of course I can't even report the bug I
need to set like windbg or something as
my as my just-in-time - burger because
this thing's useless I need it to not be
so I can't capture the awesome so I
can't capture the crash since it got
sent to Microsoft I'm hoping that he can
get them from Microsoft but we need to
be able to save a mini dump which we
could do with windbag but of course
Visual Studio is is borked now so it it
screws with us I should set a to do two
like uninstall it and put windbag in
place for debug dumps just so we can
send remedy debug dumps to George which
we need to be able to do but at the
moment we can't because we couldn't
Visual Studio is the only other debugger
that's currently running on this machine
and so if remedy crashes it's the one
that's gonna get that that fault all
right so if I go ahead and run this now
I'm gonna go into that brain call
there's an acute brain zero I'm gonna
set a breakpoint down on that call and I
just want to see like what's going on
because I don't actually understand
what's happening so now we should get
one and
oh but you know what the weight is not
set to anything I wonder if that's just
again like our matching system is so bad
right now maybe that's all it was so it
looks like actually so this may be fine
because I think we can say what the bug
is it looks like the bug is just if you
try to rebuild the executable while
remedies running still is that right
so here's remedy let me load kill
rebuild we should be fine
and we are but if instead I run here
rebuild no crash
let's get and break it to the bugger
[Music]
what was that called execute brain here
oh wait why is this not breaking so I
think there's some kind of problem with
loading like our hop loading let's break
it is that right yeah I think that's
what's happening and then in here like
if I rebuild looks like we were getting
a crash but now I can't repro it so
that's unfortunate opening that was a
repro well I'm not really sure how to
get that to read for hours hoping we
could I couldn't anyway let's go ahead
here and see if we can debug this part
so I'm gonna look and see what we get
back as a bloop ID so the problem is
it's not finding that sound right so
matching on the bloop there for whatever
reason we're not getting back any bloops
at all and so I'm just gonna try and
figure out why aren't we getting any
bloops back so if we go into get best
match asset here I'm gonna try and look
to see for each individual asset I'm
gonna try to figure out like what it why
can't actually find those so here's the
tag array
I don't know if we can tell this cat so
can we tell this to be like an asset
type tag so that we can see what the
name of it is so if I do now just look
like I do that yet
can you do this so it looks like you
can't cast to our types maybe that would
be a nice thing to have I know the
expression parser is supposed to have
been upgraded that might be a nice thing
to look for I don't know if X 13 pixels
is with us today he might not be I'll
see him on the chat so probably not but
that that would be another nice thing we
could send is it'd be nice to be able to
cast to an enum type so that we could
know what those were offhand so like
because otherwise you know I don't know
which one 74 is right you know which one
of these that that is I have no idea and
I'm assuming we can't do this right so
we'd have really no way of getting that
piece of information
unfortunately now what we can do is we
can look at the match vector though
right and if we pull that out we can
actually see like 68 is the one in
question so I guess that means 74 is the
channel right so 68 is the one we're
actually looking for here so let's see
looking for 68 ID is 8 what one two
three four five six seven eight
well that's just the basic category so
that's fine too 67 so 67 is almost what
we want that's that's the music right so
it's correct that that shouldn't match
we don't want it to to come back with
that so that's actually not one that we
would want to match there and I also
don't know so what is like the bet did
that didn't find anything right yeah
so now let's look at what we're looking
at we've got ID 74
so that's channel and that's variant
rather right so we don't really care
about that eight is the basic type 67 is
[Music]
title screen again oh right and it's
like sorry that was the channel index
yep okay yep yep so it looks like audio
it looks like they're just those assets
aren't here like they didn't get pulled
in for some reason and I don't know what
that reason would be so
if I look to have you are they in here
so they are not in here
so why aren't they in here
yeah they are definitely not in the base
game HSA so I think that's going to be
our job for tomorrow I'm not going to
bug that now but it looks like our sound
playback and streaming and stuff that's
all working fine for the moment so what
we need to do tomorrow is find out
what's wrong with our asset import that
it's not properly triggering on those
sounds in the hht that are not there
those are definitely in the hht unless
I'm mistaken maybe there's an if block
around the Mount think there is you can
see that these are commented out but
these aren't so all of those sounds are
in right and I assume that the sound
block is working properly now maybe I'll
check really quickly just to make sure
it's not something we can just fix right
now and then it's more Compton map but
maybe the sound as opposed to music
block isn't working so let's go into
import and let's search for sound so if
we look at the two of these things here
we've got they both do audio they both
use channel tags one looks in music and
is audio one looks in sound and is audio
so I don't think there should be an
issue there I can double check that
they're in the right place because it's
possible that they're just not there I
suppose but I don't think so so if I
look under sources in base game sound
there they all are right and I assume
that these are explicitly listed so loop
0 0 dot web right there it is so there
could still be I mean I don't know but
there could be like errors involved here
that I'm not aware of that I couldn't
tell you so that's that's something that
we guess we could look at
I guess I'm not sure we never really
looked at at what errors there might
have been in the import
[Music]
so turns out we have bugs in our hht
which I didn't know about should
probably make those errors harder to
ignore so what is the bug the bug is
that that's not a field
[Music]
all right so now we're fine although I
don't know why attacked gets played
repeatedly there I don't know what the
I don't know what that how that value is
getting set repeatedly in such a fashion
because that's a little bit odd let's
take a look at that real quick
but anyway so that was all we really
needed there rhh tees
we're just buggy and our error reporting
told us that which was nice but yeah so
let's go ahead and just jump back in
real quickly I might as well just just
fix that one last thing so if I load
handmade hero and go to the brain so
what was happening with that I mean we
don't care about this this code is
garbage anyway but how is that getting
like controller action key should only
be down does that like not get cleared
or something
like how is that how is that constantly
calling through there am I missing
something
I could see it getting triggered
repeatedly and I think this was meant to
prevent that so the part where it says
if the movement mode of the glove is not
movement movement mode floating because
it's supposed to switch for it to
movement mode attack angle swipe here so
it shouldn't be able to right - it
should only be able to do that once that
you do that you should transition one
time right so I'm not really sure how
that's doing what it's doing
it seems broken but I'm not sure see so
I'm not sure what's going on there like
why is that is it just because it's too
fast or something
[Music]
like what happens with attack angle
swipe inside the enemy code
[Music]
you
I need to see what happens if we change
this DT to something lower that should
swing like really slowly right so this
is just kind of nuts right now like
something is very wrong when we coming
through through movement attack angles
swipe and it just doesn't seem like it's
actually setting that up for anything is
the glove
[Music]
Bart's love
yeah I don't know I don't know why that
would be this is code that obviously
we're gonna be going through when we do
the actual gameplay stuff so this is
kind of meaningless and there's not or
real points in debugging it but it just
I always get annoyed when there's
something
oh I see I see
[Music]
so I think I understand what's going on
here so what happens is when they come
up here to the glove code we're checking
to see if the movement mode is movement
mode floating and if it's not we turn
off the attack
that means we're immediately going to
reset this value to floating which is
not what we wanted to do we only want to
do that if the in fact I I guess we
don't know that we ever want to do that
but we definitely don't want to do that
if the glove was doing something right
so I think what we really want to do
here is say that you know this at least
would have to be checked again so you
know what's the default movement mode so
looking at this I think this really just
wants to be this and this is not good
like I don't like this code at all so I
think it's you know there we go that's
more what we were looking for where's
that just going to be back to that loops
all right so now we can go to the QA
sorry I took a little longer than
necessary I just wanted to clean up some
of that stuff
so it doesn't look like that defaulted
to planted cuz now it's not floating
which is a little weird again this is a
hack we'll just do it this way I guess
for now I really wish I could send this
bug report it wasn't running so it looks
like it happens when I rebuild when it's
not running there's something weird
going on there maybe due to foul
reloading and I'm not I'm not sure
what's going on there why that goes out
so far that's a pretty nice little
[Music]
probably have to count attacks
alright so sound is basically ready to
go yeah let's go to Q&amp;A
and the LRU copy path you may have
gotten a set result thank you
let me check that out we have to like we
haven't tested the actual buffer getting
to the end of the buffer because we
don't have enough sound yet for that so
all of that code could be completely
wrong there's not very much of it
thankfully so it's won't be hard to
debug when we get there I don't think
but it's definitely not actually tested
right because we haven't we haven't
wrapped the buffer or at least I don't
see how we could possibly have wrapped
the buffer all right so that's in play
sound or sorry get sound samples so
let's see ah yeah you're right so in
here we get the destination out but
really probably we should just call that
result right because that's what it
actually is and that that seems a little
better to me that seems good
started a new job that has a gargantuan
codebase in the millions of lines of
code and it's very hard to follow what's
going on do you have any general advice
or approach to gain an understanding of
what's going on in files that are part
of very large code bases also thanks
it's in large parts to handmade hero
that I'm actually on the job well that's
great news
congratulations for starters I guess
what I would say there is you probably
want two things
I mean first off when you have millions
of lines of code code bases they're
usually garbage code bases right there
aren't like good code bases that are
millions of lines of code for kind of
obvious reasons
it's very hard to scale like you
probably you're unlikely to even be able
to get enough good programmers to
generate millions of lines of code to
ever have any prayer of those lines of
codes being good you know so when you go
into a millions of lines of code code
base although there might be some parts
of it that are saying most of it will be
insane and so you have to go in prepared
for that and you have to be able to take
it you know bit by bit what I would
recommend is you need a couple things
one make sure you got a debugger that
you're comfortable with running and
spend time in it stepping through and
stepping into the disaster that is that
million line of code code base is very
important for you to get your you know
your head around it because you kinda
need to see the execution flow and the
debugger is kind of like a way to walk
you through that you know so you
definitely want a good debugger with a
good debug display you know and to walk
through it and be able to like so you
can see and spend time looking at code
that you're not even trying to bug just
use the debugger to help you figure out
what's happening and number two is try
to use or switch to an editor that
allows you to quickly jump to things by
name because if you're using an editor
that like for example in for coder right
if I don't know what get sound buffer
memory is I can just jump to it really
quickly you know and I can also do stuff
like just type in sound and see all of
the functions and types that have to do
with sound get an editor or something
that can do that so whatever editor
you're using if it doesn't have good
source inspection you want to switch
because that's gonna be really important
Visual Studio has like a browse info
thing if you can get that working where
you can like right-click on something
and say go to definition use that if
that's what you're using if you're using
an external editor make sure it's one
that has source indexing built into it
if it doesn't just switch to one that
does that's gonna be really important
because you don't want to have to
constantly be doing like greps of your
code base it just slows you down so get
something that can do like indexing well
write other than those two things it's
just a slog I mean there's not really
much I can recommend if you have a
chance to have lunch with one of the
like senior programmers or something ask
them to sort of give you a little
high-level overview that might help to
of different systems you know and over
time you can start to see oh here's how
those programmers are thinking about it
when they created this unholy
monstrosity you know that's about all I
can can say is there a name for that
type of buffer um you mean the one I did
for sound I don't think so
like there's nothing like super
revolutionary in it I mean fundamentally
it's just a circular buffer with that
LRU with copying out of the LRU region
or the copping out of the eviction
region to create an LRU scheme so it's
not I don't know that anyone ever a
tried that before but they might have
and B if they did I don't know that they
would have bothered to name it I'm not
even sure what I would name it a
circular buffer with copy forwarding
eviction preventing circular buffer I
don't know
John Carmack likes rust is rust better
than C++ so I don't know I don't know
enough rust you know I don't think John
Carmack's programming ideas align with
mine particularly well at least not
these days
so I don't know that you know if he
thinks rest is better than C++ and if he
generally thought exactly the same as I
do all the time then I might say well I
guess I don't need to look at it I'll
just assume that that's the conclusion I
would come to generally speaking I most
of the things that I see him talk about
these days I don't either don't really
tend to agree with or they tend to be
sort of it as a different direction so I
would say I don't know that that piece
of data is probably only useful for
people who are thinking more in line
with what he's thinking so I don't know
I you know one thing you could ask him
is like what are all the things he
thinks are better about it right what I
will say is that C++ is a lousy language
so it's not hard to be better than it
you know might be another way to say it
so you know most languages are probably
better than C++ if they don't require a
garbage collection and allow you to do
low-level pointer arithmetic they're
probably fine and they would hopefully
be better than C++ go see us less comic
the worst case but most languages don't
do those things so you know I'm assuming
that one of the reason people always
think about rust is because maybe it's
one of the few languages that actually
allows you to do those things but I
don't know but yeah if John Carmack has
supposed to like a bunch of reasons he
likes rust that might be a better way to
look at it like see if you agree with
those things you know
on interview I was given a debugging
task on a new piece of code this company
was actually generous enough to provide
feedback on for instance I would have
done better if I had to bugged more
systematically do you have any tips on
better debugging practices um well
you've seen how I do bugs so I don't
have tips really beyond what I show on
the stream but you know if since I
didn't see what you were doing I can't
really comment on it you know what I
mean if I'd seen you debug maybe I would
have some thoughts I'd be like oh yeah I
see you could have if you had first
eliminated this as a source of problems
then you wouldn't have had to do this
other thing
why can't we use the GF to p-8a a fine
inverse QB instruction all the time I
don't even know what that instruction is
is that an actual instruction it looks
like an actual instruction meaning the
construction of the instruction looks
about right I'm I'm curious
[Laughter]
awesome
now that's instruction Galois field
affine transformation inverse computes
the inverse affine transformation in the
finite field GF 2 to the 8th the inverse
of each byte is given in the following
table
I have absolutely no idea what that does
I tried to read Galois stream one time
and I like didn't get past like chapter
5 I think I so if you want me to tell
you what a Galois field is I am NOT
gonna be able to do it what I would say
is I'm guessing this must be for
encryption right I mean is there some
other use for a Galois field what would
you do with it
I'm assuming it's it's only really there
for cryptography
wait
the finite field of PN elements is
denoted GFP the N and is also called the
Galois field in honor of the founder of
the field every scale law ok GF P where
P is a prime number is simply the ring
of integers modulo P
that sounds just incredibly simple
though
I think I don't understand that sentence
properly cuz the way that doesn't sound
right this is what I was thinking of by
the way so GF 2 to the 8th for the
Rendell cipher or wait that's I
pronounce it rhyme doll I think is how
you pronounce it so this is the one that
they said they were doing right in here
they're saying GF 2 to the 8th right
which is which is this right here so
it's 8 X + that's all right X 8 plus X 4
plus X 3 plus X plus 1
I'd have to read this in more detail
so I think I don't really know this part
right the inverse affine transformation
part this is why it would have been good
to get through that entire book that is
a really crazy long name for an
instruction though like Wow
so how many of these do they have
they've got Galois field multiplied by
its what do they use these for besides
AES or is it only a yes
after reading about on after reading
here about on your website what does it
mean to be in gaming research and
development
what's your company's bread-and-butter
are you basically a consultant for other
game companies no not really
what I mean by that is that we don't so
a game development company is a company
that strictly just produces a game of
the forum that we already know how to do
right so you know for example maybe you
want to make a battle royale game so you
know probably you download the Unreal
Engine and you put some art assets in it
and you implement some code for like
whatever the gameplay mechanics are and
you know there's there's the game or if
you were really ambitious you make your
own engine but it's basically just kind
of like the Unreal Engine or something
and then you ship that and that's your
game right so not at no point in that
process were you trying to solve like an
unsolved problem or a problem that was
considered extremely hard or not super
well understood you're just shipping a
game now that's pretty hard so saying
just ship a game is making it sound
easier than it is but you're not really
trying to do anything new you're just
trying to ship something that we already
understand how to do with a different
spin on it right so you know maybe it's
because our battle royale game has giant
robots in it or something and yours
doesn't and so ours it's different but
other than that it's exactly the same
game that you've already seen in terms
of the engine really that you've seen a
million times before right so when I say
we're research and development as
opposed to just development what that
means is we really will only be shipping
games that have some pretty new thing in
them right so there's something that
there is no like you cannot clone the
game by buying components on the Unity
like you know
plug-in store or something it just isn't
possible like you would need special
technology that only we have in order to
clone the game so you would either have
to build a clone of the technology we're
building or just you can't make our game
right you have to make some crappy
version that doesn't have the stuff in
it that that's unique to ours so for our
first game which is 1935 that we're
working on right now it's got an
interactive story engine that's
completely different from anything
you've ever seen before in many ways and
it would be completely impossible to
clone without that you could make a
crappy version where the stories are
lousy or that's like a branching
narrative or something that tries to
kind of look like our game but it
wouldn't be anything like our game right
so that's what research and development
is it it means that there's new
components to the games when they ship
that literally no one has but us right
and those things can be really big let
the interactive story thing is pretty
big or sometimes they might be smaller
like for our next title we might do
something smaller that's more of a
artistic R&amp;D but I would say that this
is kind of similar in a lot of ways to
for example the early like the like the
early in software development right like
when they came out with doom like nobody
had anything that could do that right it
was like a new tech development and
people had to go clone what they did a
lot of people couldn't I think at least
like maybe one person maybe did but a
lot of people just had to license it
right because just nobody had that when
they came out with quake nobody had that
and then that was mostly the end of it
they they hadn't they never really did
anything after that that was something
pretty far beyond what people had but
that was two in a row you might argue
Wolfenstein was 2 but that depends on
how you
do it but definitely doom and quake mmm
you know it was just plain new
technology that no one else had and so
we aim to do that basically and so we're
trying to do that to a certain extent
and when we shut the game we try to have
an argument for why there's something
new in it that's you know an actual
technological achievement that you can't
just clone
and so I'll just close on last one
regarding story engines what sort of
advancements are in yours if you can
mention anything what does it achieve
yeah we won't really ever be talking
about it probably you'll see the game
when it comes out or rather you'll
probably see it earlier than that right
you'll see some you know demo footage
and stuff like this and it should be
pretty obvious at least in terms of what
the quality bar is and also the level of
interactivity which should both be
dramatically higher than what you've
seen before but we it's not gonna be
something that's ever gonna be talked
about
it's private tech and will remain so
sense all right close it down
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for the episode a handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
the series at home you can always peer
to the game on Hamming here at work it
comes to the source code so you can
experiment with it maybe you would like
to go into the code and think about like
a good exercise to do now that we've got
the sound going is we may want to put in
protection or have a theory about how we
would prevent sound skipping in the case
where we can't hit our frame rate now I
don't really ever want to be in a
situation where we're not hitting our
frame rate so I'm not sure how much I
really want to do that but it sometimes
helps to just have a way to do that just
in case so that's something to think
about and you could play around with
that and think about how we might
accomplish that I'll be back tomorrow
for some more look at problem the audio
stuff we probably go through and clean
some stuff up maybe look it's I felt
like there was some clicking in there we
want to try and simplify the mixer a
little bit so I think we should just
made me do a little bit of audio cleanup
now that we've got it working I think
that would be a good thing for us to try
that's about it I'll be back here
tomorrow same time same place until then
have fun programming everyone and I'll
see you on the Internet to use everybody