okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the show we code a
complete game live on stream yesterday
we stopped short of implementing any
world generation stuff because we had
just sort of finished saying what the
API was we were going to start with we
had written some usage code but not
actually infom any of it so what we want
to do today is to kind of start pushing
forward on that and to make some actual
implementations of this code and what
we're gonna have to do and we probably
won't be able to finish this all today
is we're gonna have to start working on
some code that can put rooms down into a
spatial arrangement that obeys certain
ideas about how those rooms should be
connected and this is actually a
relatively tricky problem solved largely
because there isn't a lot of information
in the system about where things should
be one of the things that's generally
true in any kind of generative system or
just even when you're talking about
asking a when you're talking about
asking computer to do things like layout
and you could think about these sorts of
things separate from game design imagine
something very simple like page layout
for example so there's different kinds
of ways you can layout say text on a
page you know like books layout or
magazine layout so one ways is a
prescriptive way of laying out and
that's like something like HTML right
which is you know I would generally
consider like the garbage version of
page layout and what that is is that's
something that has only the most
rudimentary ability to adjust things it
basically just says hey look we don't
know how long these lines of text are so
we're just gonna do stuff like you can
tell me maybe like how wide to do and
I'll like make something I'll make it as
long as it needs to me to fit the text
after I wrap it or something right and
so you can kind of have garbage versions
like that and we can make a garbage
version like that for our game as well
which would basically just hey you
pretty much have to tell me everything
and I'm just gonna plunk down rooms very
mechanically and that's all I can do
right but a step up from that and when
you start to get into
actual real programming at that point is
when there's multiple ways you could be
doing something and the computer is
expected to evaluate different options
based on some heuristics or something
right
so for example another way that page
layout systems have worked in the past
is for example you give a bunch of
different hypothetical layouts that a
page might have and then the system
looks at the different ways that pages
that the pages would fit on a various on
a certain display and picks the one
that's best by some criteria like most
amount of the text fits on the page or
the least number of run ons or the width
of the text is the best for reading
compared to what it should normally be
in bah-bah-bah
right and so basically like we want that
kind of system we're not gonna go crazy
with it because again it's handmade here
I'm just trying to show you how to do
things I'm not going to spend you know
eight hundred episodes talking about all
different ways to make constraint
solvers and all sorts of other sorts
because that's an entire thing that we
could go down for years and years but we
do want a little bit of that so what we
want to be able to do is we want to be
able to have the layout system make
actual decisions about multiple ways in
which it could lay something out and
that becomes relatively complicated and
the reason it's relative calm can begin
is because it's a little bit loose right
there's no right answer to the layout
problem in the way that we normally like
problems to have an answer right
we like closed form solutions to things
when we're programming because they're
so much simpler we just write a few
lines of code and it computes the answer
and we're done by contrast things that
involve minimizing error metrics or
evaluating different things based on
scoring criteria or having an infinite
number of ways you might lay things out
in trying to search for the one that
scores the highest on something right
these involve more complex more
error-prone more difficult algorithms
that are harder to manage and so there's
no mystery as to why like
you know something like a browser
doesn't do it it's because you know it
was this kind of thing that came from
people who didn't really know text
layout and that wasn't something they
were experts in or anything like that so
you know they they're not gonna tackle
something like that right they're gonna
do simpler and since then it's just been
people like arguing about how much DRM
there should be or whatever right but we
don't have to do that we can actually
try to be a little bit better so what we
want to do is look at some algorithms
that involve these sorts of sort of soft
softer solves and see if we can't make
something that's workable in our context
and this is not unheard of it's there
are some games out there that are
procedurally generated that do stuff
like that some games that are
procedurally generated or maybe perhaps
most games are pretty easily generated
don't really do that but there
definitely are some that do and so you
know I've even seen people do stuff like
use a physics spring system to lay out
rooms you know they just pack all the
rooms together and they add repulsive
forces and they just let them poof out
and then they connect them up after the
fact you know and so even that although
it is repurposing another kind of system
to do the layout even that is a much
more sophisticated layout system than
something like HTML right it it has an
organic way of iterating through a
number of possible states and letting
them balanced out into something that
was not preconceived right and so
there's definitely games out there that
are doing this sort of thing they all do
it a little bit differently and that's
understandable because game design is a
very twiki subject there's a lot of
personal opinion in it there's a lot of
unknowns it's not a science and so it's
expected that things like what lays out
the game would of course be something
that has a lot of different approaches
to it we don't really care which
approach we get I just want us to get
something a little past the rote sort of
non constraint or evaluation based
version so that you can kind of see a
little bit
about how you might implement something
better than you know a browser right if
there's one thing I hope people can do
at the end of handmade here it's
something better than HTML so anyway if
I go ahead and take a look at where we
are in the game right now well I guess
that doesn't actually make any sense we
are still at the point where we're not
generate anything because we nerfed the
code that actually generates the world
so yeah there's that let me go ahead and
and head on back there then and the
other thing that I would like to do just
real quick before we start implementing
this code is I want to go fix the fact
that our lighting system takes too long
to start out if you remember correctly
in our lighting pattern system here
we've got a thing for generating the
lighting pattern and we go through and
do all sorts of nonsense that is all
really could be done offline right so
what we want to do is kind of take this
out of the equation I suppose in fact it
could just do it offline because if you
look at what's going on here right when
we do the lighting pattern generators
here let me move this in here you know
all this stuff is is not really it's not
really relevant in fact you know what I
look at - there's probably still some
stuff in there that we're doing for
testing as well that we don't really
need to do anymore
so let me go ahead and just see what
stuff there
like this test funk like all this stuff
we don't really want to do anymore
either so let me make sure that we're
not doing any of that you can see it
looks like we're probably not doing the
testing anymore so that's okay right
however we are still doing
we are still doing in here the the test
some stuff this this stuff here might be
most of our of our badness to right
there we go
so really the I guess the longest part
of it there was it was not really our
generation code that was taking time it
was just our test code because remember
we were looking at some of the like
behavior of this patterns over time so
that was easier than I thought was gonna
be so that's a nice that's good but that
means we can get right to it because we
don't have to really spend any time on
there then alright so what we want to do
now is we want to start looking at the
world generation and we want to start
implementing you know this this patent
this sort of pattern of stuff that we
said that we want to do and if we look
down here at sort of the part that we've
created the create world call here this
code all of this code now that is
happening below here that was sort of
the old creation code that code is
really now kind of wants to become just
reference code we're gonna look at that
as we sort of move forwards here but we
really don't want this to be happening
anymore right this stuff is not supposed
to really be in the mix anymore because
that's just for creating the old test
world stuff that we used to do and we
don't want that to happen anymore
so we want to restore to our assertion
state which is this one here where
there's nothing in the world at all
right nobody's creating anything and the
game can't start up because there's
nothing there there's nowhere to place
the the hero at the outset and we want
to get this create world call here
working so we want this spec that we
created yesterday to take over for our
world creation and we want to go from
there so
let's go ahead and start with that I'm
going to begin by just pointing out that
our general spec is gonna kind of stay
nerfed for a little while and so what I
mean by that is we're not gonna put
anything in it and the reason that we're
not competing in it is because the room
spec is sort of for the second wave of
generation that we're gonna do it will
come into play in this generation
probably but mostly what it's for is
filling in what's inside a room not
placing and connecting the rooms so what
we want to start out with is being able
to place and connect rooms and while
that may involve knowing something about
what's in them as we go for the moment
we just don't want to care about that we
want to start simple and just get rooms
being placed with connections so that we
can have that rudimentary version
working properly so if I go ahead here
and say that this is just like you know
sort of a to-do and nothing's gonna go
in there then I'm talking mostly about
these so we know for starters that room
connections we do know what's going to
be in them a room connection says that
you know a room a in a room B are
connected right so we can say like we
know that this is going to be
information stored in the connection and
furthermore what we probably also know
because connections are between two
rooms we probably also want them to be
listed right so we probably want to do
something that allows us to spin off of
either so we can say like alright I've
got a room and I want to loop over the
connections from that room to any other
room
and similarly I want to do the opposite
now there's two different ways that you
can do this there's a database oriented
way you can do this and there's a winged
edge data structure way that you can do
this and really which one you use is
these kind of depends on where you're
looking to go with things
handmade hero generally we've done the
winged edge style of things so we're
gonna probably do that this time but
I'll just point out what the difference
is so
if you are looking at things from a
database style perspective then what you
typically talk about is something like
connection is is what usually referred
to as a linking table and what that is
is it's a it's a piece of information
that says that two other things in the
database are related to each other right
so I've got like this gen room here I
know I've got multiple generals in a
genuine table if it was a database right
and then I've got a connection that says
a and B are connected and then the way
that you process information like give
me all of the rooms connected to room B
is buy a query that has some
acceleration structure and it could be
any kind of acceleration structure that
then answers the question if room B up
here you know if I should say room 12
let's say if room 12 appears in either A
or B of any connection then it wants to
be talked about here right so that's one
way of storing that information right
another way of storing that information
and and that way is typically if you
have some existing system you just want
to leverage and you're gonna rely on its
indexing system to be good to answer
those careers quickly right now and
furthermore one thing you might do in
those situations is you might create
bi-directional connections so you may
say that every time you add a connection
not only do you say a B you also say B a
so you create one in either direction so
you can just search on the first column
and get all the connections that head
out of room 12 without having to do two
queries one for where it appears in the
a slot and one where it appears in the
beat slot right okay so that's one way
to do this another way to do that is to
just have rooms themselves store their
exits you know exits that come off of
them right and so we can create a more
verbose data structure by essentially
welding the index into the data
structures themselves and this is kind
of the reason I want to bring this up
this is a good point point enumerator to
talk about it the difference being these
two things so in
database world in the way that you do
those the indices the acceleration
structures in the way that you walk the
data is external to the data and that's
very important that's the real
distinction there when you talk about
using a database that's the important
distinction actually right and the data
itself is just the data so it's a
segregation if you will of the way the
data is accessed from what the data
actually is and there are good reasons
to do this I am NOT the kind of person
who bags on databases I think databases
are interesting and there's a lot of
interesting design that went into
thinking about them originally
you know Cobb was pretty smart and do I
think they get overused and used in
situations where a database really isn't
appropriate sure but that's not the same
thing as saying there aren't good ideas
in there and ideas that should be
understood you know everyone should
probably read transaction processing by
gray right but in this case why would we
want all that extra stuff why do we want
all of that externality why do we want
all that segregation does it get us
anything and the answer in this case is
probably going to be no and that's why
when we're creating like something like
this in a custom built thing in C we
usually want to go more for the throat
right what we can do instead is say look
let's we know how we're going to look at
these connections we know that the way
that we're going to look at connections
generally speaking is one of three ways
either we're gonna spin off of one of
the rooms and say show me all the things
that are connected to this room or we're
gonna spin off of the opposite room
right like tell me all the things that
go to this room and in our case since
they're not since it's it's
bi-directional connections I think
always those are the same query so it's
really only one and then the second one
is just what are all the connections so
if we want to we can just make the
connection structure have all that
information in it and then all of our
careers are direct they never have to go
through a secondary index that can
always be immediate and faster right so
there's two different ways we can
structure this I'm not sure which way is
the way that we most would like to do it
but I'll show you the
example so one example is we have a
Gendron connection and this is just a
linked list where what it does is it
allows the room to store a list of
connections off of it and those
connections are you know stored here
right why would we introduce this why
not just have the connection structure
be something that's off the room and it
just says what it connects to and then
both rooms have ones that point back to
each other well it depends if you want
to iterate over all connections and
store something on the connection that
becomes a little harder to do because
there's no unique place to do it right
and so hopefully you understand what I'm
saying there
if you don't I'll spell it out for you a
little bit more directly one thing we
could do is say all right every room has
a pointer to its first connection the
connections are a linked list and just
says what room it goes to right and what
does this data structure look like well
what it means is that we've got a big
set of rooms each room stores a
connection to each other room which is
just a pointer that says I'm connected
to this other room right now what that
means is there will be two room
connection structures
for for every connection one that goes
from room a and it's in room phase
linked list and it points to room B and
one that's in room B's linked list and
points to room a the downside here is
that iterating all over all the
connections becomes impossible sort of
because what you have to do is when you
iterate over one connection
you'd have to remember in sort of like a
hash or something that you'd visited the
connection one direction so that when
you visit it the other direction you
don't count it twice right if you're
going to do something to it say it also
doesn't tell you where to store the
information about the connection because
if you have information about the
connection do you put in both places do
you put it in only one of them do you
have both of them point to something in
which case you're back to what I was
going to say next
so another way of do
and the way that I probably will do it
is again having sort of like a doubling
a insulation layer if you will where we
have a room connection is actually
something that looks more like this you
know we've got some information about
the connection that goes in in that spot
and then we have the two rooms and we
also have here a list of all of them
right so essentially what I'm saying
there is not only do we have information
about the two rooms we have all the we
have all of the connections total sort
of linked up so that we can walk our
connection list if we wanted to right so
that's also something we could do again
we don't know how much we need some of
these things but I'm just going over all
the ways that these sorts of things can
sort of be structured right oops I put
this in the wrong place
sorry right and now each room connection
just has a pointer to the actual
connection it's representing right and
then it's got those you know all that
information in there for whatever you
need and off you go so that's going to
be the most complicated structurally
because it is what creates the graph and
there's a lot of ways we can do it and
which way we want to do it I think we'll
be more informed by you know sort of
when we actually get to the part where
we're iterating over these things I
think we can create them at that point
so what I'm going to do at the outset is
I'm just going to make the the most sort
of
for both version here which is the one
that we've got like that looks like this
I'm just gonna do that for now and we'll
do something more fancy when we start to
see how we might want to be laid out
because most of our routines will have
to spin off these edges and we probably
want to make sure that they make some
sense that's all alright also I should
mention while I'm in here if you end up
having to optimize this code you may end
up wanting to reduce the amount of
pointer chasing so you may end up
bundling things together
for example if rooms on average have
four connections you might just have an
array of four pointers in the room
directly that point to the rooms that
they're connected to and have a
connection structure that's ancillary to
them and blah blah blah right so none of
this is about optimization this is this
about basic data representation
optimization if we need to do it it all
comes much later and at that point we
would be thinking about other concerns
because we will have assumed at that
point that we've already have all of the
code working exactly how we want and
then we can just look at the usage
patterns and determine what we want to
modify for speed purposes that's a
totally separate analysis and we
definitely don't want to be thinking
about it now all right so the other
thing that we know here is that rooms
are gonna have room specs because
obviously once you need to generate one
of these rooms you're gonna have to
generate the specification for it
somehow right look you're gonna I'm
sorry you can have two access for using
it for it somehow so once we know all
this stuff we can come back here and
start to fill some of this in right we
know that when we create one of these
rooms we are past suspects so we could
fill it out similarly with a connection
we could fill it out like so and what
you can see here is when I fill out one
of these connection structures I
definitely want to you know attach these
back up and so let's say we were doing
this really basic kind of probably not
the one we eventually want to do but you
know let's say that we were doing this
then what we want to do is
have some function of this nature where
we add that connection to each room and
then the add connection call all that
would do is this she's going to take the
data that we're talking about here and
I'm going to sort of make something that
creates that secondary list so I'll
create one of these room connections I
know this next pointer is going to be
whatever the rooms first connection
pointer is right because I'm going to
just daisy chain them on there I know
that I will become the new room first
connection right and I also know that
the room con here it's connection is the
one that's being passed in right so I
set the next pointer to whatever the
first one was the first one now becomes
me and then the member duck
so this builds up I believe our entire
sort of structure that we have specified
these things are going to refer to each
other so I'm going to go ahead and start
a little oops a little forward
declaration party up here so that all
these people can have pointers to each
other because it's that kind of a thing
right so now all of those are created
and we've got sort of one more obvious
thing like I said before we even start
writing code let me kind of know which
is that we want to be able to lay out
these rooms and of course we've created
all the rooms but then the world
generator doesn't know what the rooms
are right so we kind of want to have a
thing
like this where we can just have all of
our rooms listed and so like I was
saying kind of before we probably want
this here as well so I'll just go ahead
and add it so you loop over all our
connections in all of our rooms when we
want to do things like start the layout
and we need to figure out where things
go or whatever else right so there's a
couple weirdnesses here and we'll get to
them in a second but all I want to do
now is just kind of make sure that that
stuff makes sense so when we come
through here and we make a new room I
want to say that the generator first
room equals this room and of course the
room global next equals the first room
right and that's just daisy chaining
these on the same is true for the
connect call I might call this a dream
connection and furthermore something
else we can do here that's kind of nice
is we know that our room connections we
know that we may want that to sort of be
something we could access we could put
those in here too and we'll see whether
we want to that like I said later
depending on how we want this pointer
festival to shake out right but anyway
when we do call connect what we want to
do again is just say oops yeah Global
Mexico's first room Jennifer's room yep
and so Jen first connection equals
connection and connections global next
equals first connection so those are all
happily linked together and now we're
good to go all right so what we need to
do now that we pretty much have all that
stuff straightened away is we need to
start talking about what's gonna happen
in these pieces of code
now generate world is actually the one
I'm going to write first which takes a
world generator that's already how its
layout done and goes from there and the
reason for that is the layout code is
the code that's actually difficult here
I want to know what it needs to output
and it should be pretty clear what it
needs to output but at the same time we
kind of need we just need to know right
enough information about that to sort of
get us started so what I want to do here
is say all right we're gonna do a
generate world and to do the generate
world call all I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
say I just want to loop over all of the
rooms in the world and make them because
the only thing in the world is rooms
rooms are connected to each other and
even if you have an outdoor area it's
called a room and is room like in that
it is surrounded on all sides by either
connections to other rooms or trees or
mountains that you can't pass so
everything is functionally a room even
if it's not a room in sort of literal
sense it's a room semantically so in
order to do this I'm just gonna say
alright let's loop over every room there
is and for every room I just want to
make the room right I just want to go
ahead and make the room so this is the
basic generate room call and that's just
gonna say alright if I'm given a room
I expect to have some way that I can
actually place that room down now in
this old style here that we've got a
probably like I said I really want this
to mostly become reference code I don't
really want any of this stuff to still
be happening probably so I'm kind of
going to stuff it down here and we'll
kind of do a little bit more work with
that later on as we go
I'm going to open up two views of this
file as we go so here we are in generate
room and I would suspect probably too
this might move out to its own thing so
there might be like world Jen in room
Jen because again world Jen is about
figuring out where everything goes in
the world and room Jen is about filling
in individual rooms and those can
probably be separated right um you know
probably hard to say maybe not I don't
know but but probably and it depends on
how we how much linkage there is between
two rooms and you know whatever anyway
so what I want to do when I generate a
room to start with I'm just gonna do the
basic thing I want to spam down some
places to stand for however big the room
is right and so what I want to do is I
want to take some notion of the corners
of the room kind of like we're doing
here where we've got sort of these ABS
tile values I want to just sort of slap
some stuff down there as a rectangle
right so what I want to do is something
fairly similar to this and I think I
might rewrite it to be more of a min/max
sort of a thing but what I want to do
fundamentally speaking is basically is
basically the same right so I want to do
something like have a tile why here
and max how why is really the wrong word
so you know I don't know whether we want
this to be a less than or equal to or an
equal to it's hard to say it's a
convention thing and it depends which
one is the more convenient for you to
work with most of the time whether you
want to be inclusive of the X of the
outer bounds or exclusive of it usually
the lower bound zero is inclusive of but
you know and so if we do a basic room
generator here it's going to look
something like this
so we know we need those inputs so
that's already kind of telling us what
the room has to determine for itself
when it gets placed which we kind of
already knew and when we actually start
to go down and put down the floor and I
guess you know maybe this is a better
name for that as the floor tiles II then
when I'm creating the actual floor then
what I can do is just kind of make this
stuff be reasonable so you know if we
take a look here we can say yeah all
this looks relatively straightforward
we don't care about all of this sort of
stuff that we had made for creating
holes and so on because at the moment
we're not really going to do much of
that we'll sort of look at that a little
bit later
it's kind of weird code yeah
so you can see here we don't really want
any X&amp;Y offsets at the moment this would
probably leave those as they are this is
our sort of height variance and this is
our entity that's actually based on that
and that all looks fine that just
creates an entity and puts allows you to
stand on it which is fine right sue once
we have this you know we are still going
to want to do a lot of the stuff we were
doing in here and we'll add that back
and slowly in fact one of the things
that we may want to do is change the way
in which this is you know we may want to
do something more like this something
more like this right and these would be
like that and the reason we might want
to do that is because again we probably
will want to use an array here to store
the information about how we place
entities in the room because we may do
work with them
a little later on like who knows how
that's going to work itself out right so
what we may want to do is is something
more like that and then we would have
something that looks more like this and
again it doesn't matter how we set this
up as long as the room gives us
something we can compute these by we're
fine and off we would go so there's sort
of the the basic way we would create a
room there and now we have to sort of
think about how we might want that room
to connect to other rooms so for the
start what I'm going to do is I'm going
to say anytime we're at the boundary I
am for now just going to fill in that
thing right so I'm going to say that if
the X index equals zero the X index
equals x count minus one right something
like this so I want to be able to say if
we're on the boundary then I'm probably
gonna like not have a traversable there
right
so I guess one thing I'm a little hazy
on is what the point of the traversable
reference is here I mean that's I guess
now think about that's really just for
later right so really we don't care
about that just yet that's only if we're
gonna use it later on otherwise we don't
care right that's just not relevant at
all actually yeah just just not relevant
so what we want to do here is say all
right look if it's on the boundary or
not then we're gonna have something to
say about and also this there's no
reason this can't just be up here for
the moment or maybe I should say here so
what I want to do here is just say okay
let's go ahead and say that if we're on
the boundary then the wall height and
the color maybe change and you don't get
it reversible
so we're walling off the entire thing
and that way when we then go and add
connections into the system we can make
sure that we can see okay then then
there's a passageway there that's
supposed to be there that's all so if
we're on the boundary then the wall
height I don't know is going to be like
1.5 or something or two who knows and
the color will be something else just a
red for now right
so that'll be fine and and I don't know
maybe it should be a lighter a lighter
red there okay and so now we are mostly
okay except one of the things you can
see here about the way we're creating
entities you have to recall we did the
entity creation from before in kind of a
really haphazard way right when we were
doing begin grounded entity you can see
how we were doing it here it was using
the world mode creation region nonsense
and it's just kind of dumb right and the
reason that it's dumb is because we
didn't have any world generation code
yet so we were just kind of sticking
this in there I in whatever way would
work at all right I mean there was no
rhyme or reason to it whatsoever and we
didn't have any way of knowing or even
guessing where this kind of code should
live but now we do right so now we know
a couple things first of all we know
that the room is probably the room by
Tommy Rizzo is probably where we want to
have the world change stuff happen right
because generally speaking this is where
we know the region we're about to update
so we're going to create a bunch of
enemies and pack them in this one area
that's exactly what we want to do right
so we know that begin world change
probably wants to happen here right and
that world change is going to return
this creation region and then at the end
when we're done with it we're going to
say alright let's end the world change
at that time and that's good right
that's exactly what we want
now you can see here the way this is
working too is when we do begin world
change it gathers up an arena I want to
see also what's happening there that
will be interesting to take a look at we
should talk about that a little bit more
in a second too but again this world
change stuff now kind of wants to be the
world change stuff is something that
kind of wants to be made systemic to the
generation system because that's where
this should have been happening all
along we just didn't have one right so
we were kind of making do with it
so what I might do here there's a couple
different ways I might approach this but
generally speaking you can see that this
is why I want these to be rewritten so
that is all of this stuff now instead of
taking a world mode which I is not what
I want it to do really wants to take a
generator now these here and this is
kind of a little bit weird the brain and
the the brain IDs and the and the entity
ideas I feel like those should really be
on the world I'm not sure why they're on
the world mode so I also want to take a
look and see if those can be moved into
the world itself because that seems like
a more logical place to put those there
maybe is a reason not to do that I'm not
sure but we'll see yeah so just like
looking at this code right and all this
stuff here this stuff can all stay the
same and and this stuff can sort of
start to be systemic you know more
systemic compared to what it was as well
yeah so I'm gonna go ahead and gank that
stuff out here and I'm gonna put that in
there we go and I want all of this stuff
to work off of the world like that and
end the generation system I want that
out of world mode now so again this
stuff here for looks like most of the
things we would want
so here's the world last used entities
storage ID so it just uses that for both
of these so yeah basically this yeah I
don't see any reason this stuff can't
move into the Jen at that point so I
would say the world generator is
probably the thing that gets the
creation region although it may only be
local to the room generation function in
which case it wouldn't really go in here
the last used entity storage index I
feel like should be on the world in the
first place that it just doesn't make a
lot of sense to me why it was where it
was so in my mind that should really be
that should have been in here and I
can't say I know why it wasn't in here
if I had a good reason for not putting
in here I would have loved to know what
it was I just can't think of what I
can't think of a reason to keep that I
suspect it was just me not having
thought it through yet cuz it really
doesn't sound like the right place to
put it
[Music]
let's find out
okay so when you're doing an ad player
AB clear I'm gonna wait a little bit
because that has to happen in the middle
of gameplay and that's a slightly
different one here so yeah for something
like begin granted entity what I really
want to do here is is I want to have I
really want this to be something we look
at just a little bit later because since
that have to happen in the middle of
gameplay I want to have that handled
specially and we'll see what the best
way is to do that when you do play World
here and you initialize the world's
reserve Randi first read that's pretty
easy to initialize when we create the
world in the first place
so I feel like that just works yeah all
of these can just be and I really think
since that's the thing that stores all
the entities I really just feel like
that's where it should have been the
whole time anyway even before we added
the generation system that seems like
the more correct place for that
and I'm just kind of looking through
this here
you know also this stuff looks to me
like I might want to clean this up a
little bit to again cuz all of this code
was really just placeholder and now that
we're kind of seeing how it works I
think there's a lot of things we might
want to change you can see how this code
wants to work we just need to know where
we're going to actually put it in terms
of sim regions the sim region of course
has the world in it itself it just
stores that piece of information but it
doesn't need to you know we could always
pass it in but just happens to know what
it is so really when you do begin entity
that really could have just been a
Symbian call that's what probably should
have happened and that would just you
know make the entity when you're done
with it again the fact that that was off
the world mode I think again this was
just for convenience when we were doing
it now that you know we're kind of going
through it with a with an eye towards
actually making it correct I don't think
any of this stuff makes any sense right
yeah I mean all this this is all just
nonsense this is this was I think this
was a several series of things we
actually got it down to a pretty good
way of doing it actually but it just
it's we had never finished quite
simplifying it down as far as we could
have right because you can kind of see
here once I actually do this you can see
how straight forward it actually becomes
really you just always have a sim region
that you create things inside of if you
don't have one you just pop one open but
you don't need the world mode for
anything so the fact that it was ever
there is kind of silly in the first
place ground identity isn't any
different from any other entity anymore
so really we just have begin entity is
the only actual thing that we have in
the first place and we don't even need
an arena like there is no arena here so
the fact that we actually use that in
the first place doesn't really isn't
necessary either because whatever the
sim region's arena was at the time is
fine so yeah
yeah uh so anyway in our beginning the N
entity stuff here I think that's all we
really needed to do the chunk this room
table should already worked off of a
world anyway so that doesn't really need
to change and the rest of this stuff I
think just works so when we go to do
something like add Monstar let's verify
that this actually can work off of just
a region I believe that's the case this
is just a begin entity call like so the
rest of this stuff is all off of the
worlds anyway at which we have we could
actually have add brain work off of a
region as well because either one of
those is fine but you can see how simple
this actually is right now that it's
kind of and and I'm happy like I it's
cool that we got it down to such a
simple system actually at the end of the
day so good on us for following that
through I think so you taking a look at
this stuff again like I think this
allocate brain and allocate entity ID
part of things they're both calling the
same thing there right
so I think we can just make versions of
these that just do the same they all do
the same thing right so this stuff is
basically pulled out at that point it
goes into right I mean it's it's
actually stuff that happens in here
right so the world has the ability to
add these things to it the sim region
has thunks right in there that really
aren't doing anything they're just so
you don't have to type region world if
you don't want to and from then on you
just get it's just really simple I mean
that's it's so basic that you know that
just looks great I mean I'm totally
happy with that and and I and off you go
so basically everything everyone does
from now on just takes a sim region
that's how it constructs things and it
just assumes that someone upstream at
some point opened a region for editing
and then it's going to edit in that
region and everything this works and
that seems great I'm pretty happy with
that that's
pretty good so the other thing that I
would say here is I feel like end entity
so one of the things is we have this
constant end entity because we use to
have this kind of crappy system where
things had to be built in this different
way or whatever we don't have an end
entity anymore right so we don't need to
call that and entity is just set entity
position right that's all it is so it's
really just it's really just place
entity and begin entity is really just
add entity we don't have because of the
nice way that the same region works now
we don't have to do begin and end entity
anything just stay in a state of hybrid
like haven't really been finished yet
until the whole sim region is is packed
and that's also great like all of these
things are awesome in my opinion like
this is this is turning out to be pretty
baller at the end of the day and that's
pretty good that's what you want to have
happen when you do a bunch of work to
sort of like look at and explore
solutions you want them to come together
at the end and it is sort of doing that
right so now these are much more clear
you just add the entity and you can do
whatever you want to it you can work on
it later return it to somebody else who
could work on it separately you don't
have to have a finalized ation point to
it because the whole room just gets
packed up together when it's all done
and that is way better right that's like
way way better in my opinion so that's
great
and all of that works pretty cool sooo
then I think we're getting into a
reasonable space here so when's we
coming here we just do an identity call
to add the entity we then do whatever we
want to it and we can do our place
entity call here
and that's it and off we go
let me just finish porting some of these
guys for the changes that we made all
right soo fundamentally speaking now
what we want to do is we want to open up
a part of the worlds for editing and
that part of the world that we want to
edit is going to be bounded by the
region of the room that we want to use
so that's what I'm going to do in there
and then when we end we finish and I
don't even know you have a completely
honest with you I don't even know what's
supposedly happening here that doesn't
really make any sense why would you pass
the world something that already has the
world in it
[Music]
do we know the answer to that question I
mean
so if we have begin world change and we
copy the world in at the outset is I
mean is there ever a reason why we would
not just use the one that's there I mean
the answer is obviously no right
isn't it I mean is there a way in which
that flow happens different I mean don't
you have to have the world at the outset
and you can't switch one world for
another world in the middle of the
update unless that's something and if
you did why wouldn't you just patch the
pointer right so I feel like that's just
you know that's fake news right so I
feel like we want to just get rid of
that because it's not necessary okay
we'll deal with where we want to get the
random series from a little bit later
but I think that's all really good now
so this is great I am really happy about
that actually and I'm even gonna go a
little bit further and spread this out a
little bit more
we have handmade world Jen I'm gonna
make handmade room Jen and the reason
for that is I want to be able to look at
these pieces of code in collections
as a sidenote oh my god ge' no Marie
drives me nuts like every time it
repaints the screen it flickers like the
oh the windows that have a translucent
backdrop they flicker and it's horrible
absolutely horrible I wish they would
fix that I don't even know what they're
doing to make that happen it's pretty
spectacular I wonder if there's a way to
like turn that stuff off maybe I can do
it it's like all terminal windows just
flicker and they flicker like crazy in
this corner of my eye it's it's nuts
drives me insane
yeah let's see command colors
transparency none that work
let's find out hey yes
should've done that a long time ago all
right so basically just making two
different files here and what I want to
do is I just want to store the stuff
that creates like the entities and stuff
like that I want those to be a little
bit more yeah I just want to keep
separate the stuff that's just for
making cuz there's gonna be so much of
it you know the stuff for making
entities and all that stuff I want to
just put that in a separate place so
don't have to think about it right or
look at it while I'm working on the
other stuff so basically once you get to
the point where you call generate room I
want to be in this file and this is just
all the stuff that does room generation
and when you're generating the layout
for the whole world you're in this file
right and that just helps me keep them
straight a lot of times people have
asked me like how do I organize my files
the answer is anyway you darn well
please and for me what I like is I like
files to be broken down by sort of the
thing that they're doing not by class or
some object-oriented thing or whatever
else I want them to be like okay all the
stuff that lays out the world goes in
this file all the stuff that lays out of
room goes in this file right and that
could be 30 structs or one struct or 500
routines if necessary as long as it all
feels like it belongs there and I'm
working on that code together I
typically put that in a file when I
sense a very clear division of labor
between two things then I you know will
sort of separate those out so anyway now
what we have to do is well I guess
besides including these files
so what I need to do now is I need to go
ahead and looks like that towel size and
meters as well let me just pop these out
here we need to kind of figure out what
we want to do about this eventually but
at the moment it's fine so the only
thing I need to do is just pop this
forward declaration out here because
that's the only place that it gets
called into so it just says hey well
that's all you do that whole files job
it's just this generator room that's all
it does so as long as you got that call
we're good so now we have to do is take
a look at how this room Jen is actually
gonna work at the moment I want to just
clean this up a little bit and then
we're gonna move over to the more
pressing problem which is how do we
place a person after the fact because
again we do have one case where we add
entities already outside of world
generation which is when a new hero
enters the game right like if someone
hits the start button on a controller or
something and there'll be more of that
leader because we may want to add in a
tease for like you know someone throws a
projectile or something we may want to
add an entity there so use me we
definitely have some work we want to do
in the future in that so that has to do
with that right and so we're gonna go
look at that in a second in the meantime
what I'd like to do is in the generation
system when we're actually doing stuff
like generating a room what I'd like to
do is in addition to the memory you're
going to be used for a permanent storage
I'd like to do a little memory Rina for
a change based storage here so something
like this and what I want to do is or
maybe I could call this temp memory so
what I want to do here is
when we go to use that temp memory there
that's used for this change region stuff
and that gets nerfed at the end of it
right so after the temp memory you know
down here we just say okay free for n
temporary memory and that way we don't
really care how much memory that takes
or what it needs to do it just does its
thing and off it goes I we already have
the world so what we need to know now is
what happens in these two places I'd
also like to just go ahead in here and
make sure that all that stuff is what I
think it is so you can see here that we
pass in a time value we're going to be
passing 0 there still because you're
having to say about that
we pass in an origin in a boundary so
what we can do there is we know what our
origin is going to be when we're
creating the world we know what's going
to be the center of the room so what we
can really do here is just say ok you
know our Center is just going to be the
min tile X plus you know 0.5 or I should
say X count divided by 2 this is going
to be wind tile why
and we know the center can just be the
floor taozi right so we know a room
center and it's not necessarily the
exact center right we could try to get
the exact center but we really probably
don't care
and then our rectangle for rec center
gym we know that the the center is just
going to be zero zero zero because it's
just we're passing a rectangle that's
that's used relative to the center I
believe so we know we're just centered
around that and then we know we are you
know X count Y count and some notion of
C count what we would like to do is just
get a relatively large region around the
room center that we're going to be
working on and we'll pull in anything
that's roughly in that area and so what
we want to do is say that the tile side
go in meters multiplies these two and
the tile depth in meters multiplies this
one right and I should probably do
something like this
and that just gives us a little bit of
an understanding of what's going on
there in terms of the you know the
bounds of thing so we want this to be
expanded a bit so what I would also say
is I'd like to grab tiles on either side
so let's say that we just we have an
apron you know or something like this
you know that just tries to grab enough
around it so that those extra elements
will all be pulled in so we have some
kind of ability to query what's nearby
in the room and other stuff like that
right so I'm gonna instead of cloning
his room because they're not really that
I'm just gonna call these like change
rectangle and change Center and I think
that's most of what I want their tile
depth in meters where is that defined so
it's it's this chunk German meters looks
like
yeah
I feel like again that stuff's a little
bit loosey goosey so I'm gonna go ahead
and say two and say we want to finally
get this stuff locked down because in
the generator is the time to finally do
all that because this is the thing that
actually builds the world for real so we
should probably do that but for the
moment we do know the answer to that
question it's that and that's fine so
now we've got the series here and the
generator should have that serious in it
and it does not yet so probably that's
just on the world right now
in fact it because we have the world
entropy right here so really what we
want to do is grab this probably at the
outset and just say that the random
series that we're going to use here is
going to be whatever the game entropy is
okay we need that information to come
from the room and then we are needing to
close our parentheses
okay and that's about it so if we assume
that these things come from somewhere at
some point I don't know exactly like I
said how we want to have those work in
the room or what's going on there
exactly for the time being I guess I'll
just say hey look
maybe this looks like that's and maybe
these come from here because for the
time being since that's what I know the
input to the system is you might as well
get them directly and then later on we
can find out what actually we should get
from there to compute these values which
may be something else entirely so now
we're back to the problem from before
however which is that we still do want
the ability to do a little a limited
amount of modification of the world here
in the world mode and that is
specifically when we want to create
that's not good specifically when we
want to create something like a player
entity and so when we call add player in
we are implicitly here wanting to make a
modification what we can do now is get
rid of this nonsense here because that
stuff is irrelevant to us and was kind
of a hack in the first place and so now
what we can do is actually just call
these directly on the sim region which
is what we wanted to do in the first
place and again that makes this even
cleaner and much more pleasant now the
generation code needs to expose that
code like the identity stuff and
whatever I don't know if maybe this
should now be part of the world or a
part of the entity I'm not sure I don't
care so I'm just gonna put it up here
for now
and we can worry about where we want to
organize that later if for some reason
it becomes an issue so I'm just gonna
say that this stuff is going to come out
here and sort of have a set of
specifications we can move it somewhere
else later if I care when I care oops
gotta love the whole forward
declarations required and see nonsense
well all the changes to spec eight
billion things that the C++ committee
added they never got rid of the need to
forward declare absolutely bonkers all
right
so let's see here
shadow alpha is how often do we use this
no we'll just put it up here for now
so lace there we go and I think we're
good now all right that should do it
there we go uh and now I think we've
sort of gotten all of our ducks in a row
eggs egg ducklings are duck eggs in a
row are our broccoli in a row so what
I'm going to do now is again just try to
get our game back up into a running
state since obviously we don't have a
bunch of stuff that we're saying we need
to have how much time do I have I've got
like 35 minutes I think something like
that so what I want to do now is I want
to go through and say okay let's take a
look at how we could make our generation
code just generate some rooms that are
totally wrong that don't do any of the
things we asked them to do but that's
fine and then get the game running in
that state and then start working on the
layout algorithm portion of the system
right step-by-step so now what I want to
do in here inside the the world gem
system is I want to go ahead and
some nominal way that layout does
something right it's not going to do
what we want to do but it will do
something and so what's its gonna do is
it's gonna do the Thomas possible room
layout algorithm you could possibly have
that doesn't satisfy any of the
constraints that we asked for but again
we don't care yet what I'm gonna do is
just step through each of the rooms and
just give them up grid like I'm just
gonna stamp them down right I'm just
gonna stamp down the rooms completely
irrespective of where I said they should
go so it's not useful to us but again it
helps us get a little baby step you know
by baby step so I know that these are
all the things I needed to fill out in
the room structure right I know I need
each of these and so I'm just going to
set them and each of these is gonna be
something
let's say I should probably just make a
pointer to that off of the Jen but we'll
think about that later so if I make a
random between let's say it's got to be
at least eight wide it can be up to 16
wide it could be between like 6 tall and
9 tall or something and it's one high
just cuz yes so you know let's say do
something like that and then in here I
just have a tile X tile Y tile Z and I
don't know what these are gonna be but
you know they're like ten thousand or
something what did we start them with
before remember
oh so did we do well we did all these
with s 32s before oh well never mind
we're good everything I just said
but it's that actually the case yeah I
guess it always is the case all right
well great then we just start at zero
and it makes some sense all right
well forget all that doesn't matter easy
peasy lemon squeezy
everything's fine uh so let's just go
ahead and do that then and let that be
as the Beatles famously said and and yet
all of this stuff can just not care
about that at all
and I think that's that so when I create
these here what I want to do is I'm just
gonna line them up so I'm just gonna say
tile X plus equals room X count here and
then all our rooms are just lined up in
a row laterally that's all they're gonna
do right not particularly exciting looks
like this needs the world stripped so
I'm gonna make it take that and I think
that actually does our world creation
now one of the problems that we're then
going to have is we don't have any
camera setup so I'm gonna try and get
that set up you can see here that that
happens in in this piece of code and so
I'm going to try and make that occur as
well now in the future we're gonna want
to actually have some information about
where the camera should actually be and
so maybe I'm gonna like start us down
that path a little bit so you can see
here where we've got our camera P and we
say like okay hey the camera location
should be whatever this new camera
position is I don't know how we exactly
want to sort of send that back out but I
think that's just going to be something
we're gonna want to report right like
we're just going to want to kick that
back to the world mode so you know maybe
more properly something like this where
we just need the this creation to kick
us back something we can use to figure
out where we should start looking right
and
[Music]
I think that's really all we will need I
hope
yeah should be so what I want to do
there is just have like something like
this so when we do our generation we're
probably going to get back a bunch of
stuff probably but one of the main
things we'll get back is the initial
camera location
so when we call create world here what I
want to do is oops send back this
initial camera location and then that's
something that that's something that can
be used outside to set world mode' stuff
or it doesn't really matter anything you
want right and so I think all of that is
pretty much done
furthermore the transient State actually
now that I look at it that arena coming
in is really we could just use that for
our memory because everything in here
that happens on that transient state
could yeah so so we could actually just
feed into that if we want to
so we kind of have the option of doing
mostly that but we don't have to do that
at the moment so inside here where we're
doing our create world stuff everything
can just happen after we're done
generating the world we need to have
some idea of where the camera should
start out at the moment we kind of know
someplace we could put it so I'm just
gonna cold put it there let's say that
we're just gonna put it at you know four
four zero or something like that but in
the future we are gonna actually have a
way for the generator to say where that
is because we're gonna want to place the
camera somewhere specific so we'll do
that but I wanted to kind of get the the
flow correct here and so that's why I
sort of started out with this as being
you know as there being a conduit for
the camera position so it makes a little
bit more sense so results initial camera
P this is probably it's probably should
look more like that's look like that
don't ask me why I didn't just type this
in the first place but you know I didn't
so let's just take a look at that and
we'll sort of start stepping through
that and try to get that working to
create something we can actually see and
hop around on right so because like I
said I don't really know I got a go one
one of our reasons for doing this is to
sort of get the camera code finalized as
well
so that camera code I'm not sure how
stable that stuff is anyway or if that's
even right so we're gonna have to play
around with a little bit of that stuff
anyway and and
but for now let's just go figure out
whether we're creating our rooms at all
and whether they're in places that make
any sense or any of that stuff and then
we'll sort of work our way up from there
so going into the world Jen I'm going to
jump right to the end so I can see what
sorts of stuff we're telling the game we
want to do right all right so those look
like sane values right and when we come
down into here our change Center looks
pretty reasonable to me our change
rectangle also looks pretty reasonable
to me
we begin our world change and we start
making a bunch of entities and we place
those entities in some places
[Music]
those places seem pretty reasonable to
me
and there are interiors as well as
boundaries so that's good so it looks
like we have added what we wanted to add
right now what I do know is if any of
that stuff's getting packed back
correctly I suppose so I should also
just double-check that that's occurring
here right
so I mean it looks pretty reasonable so
I would say that it looks like our basic
world generation stuff seems to be
working okay I don't know what the
initial camera p-value is but I assume
it's reasonable it looks fairly
reasonable and so then we pop back out
here and we set the initial camera stuff
I don't know there's anything else that
we're not setting
it doesn't look like it so I think we're
good so once we come out here and we
have a new world that's been created I'm
not really sure I I remember the AB
player stuff being a little bit nasty
because it kinda has to check for
joining players as a separate pass
because the first player is kind of
special right but you know whatever so
when we actually take a look at what the
world position is of of this this guy
here again that's a pretty reasonable
location that's I think where we would
expect that person to be added in fact
let's take a look at update camera so I
guess one problem that we do have here
and you can kind of see it is this code
is kind of stupid
but it does remind us we have to create
our camera track our camera information
entities otherwise the camera doesn't
know what to do so I suppose we should
add that because since we're not really
updating that code just yet let's just
add that in there as well
so inside world Jen I'm sorry room Jen
what I'm talking about here
is this stuff so we want to make a
entity for the room that just says kind
of what the camera state of this of this
thing is right so it's just that
and I guess it's at the center stop
these
yeah
sooo hmm none of this stuff really cares
about we're sort of in this situation of
we'd like to talk about tiles because it
helps us with the world generation but
none of this stuff cares about tiles it
would be nice to stop dealing with that
so I think that might be something that
I want to start doing next time sort of
transform out of that pretty early but
whatever we'll get there when we get
there
so that's fine and dandy and again this
has to be the center which we kind of
already wanted to know well actually
it's just this and we already have it so
I'm just going to pass it it's just not
quite correct
so that just wants to know like the the
width and the height and so on so I mean
that's just this
know what necessarily goes there all
right moving on
okay so we're getting further however
although our rooms are properly stacked
up for some reason I'm not seeing the
entities that make up the that make up
the actual ground so almost there but
not quite so we're not this stuff seems
a little bit broken for some reason but
I'm not sure why but I think that's all
we've got to fix now how it worked to
have a traversable but not where you
couldn't actually see the the ground
pieces I'm not sure but then again we
did make a lot of changes so you know
maybe that makes sense okay so anyway
I want to check out the ad piece let me
do again a little bit of a just take a
little bit of a gander at this here
all of these cubes should have gotten
added they should be relatively
reasonable
you don't see any other weird things
here unless floor tile Z is somehow
worked there which it mean it could be
so I guess one thing that's a little
weird let me just go ahead and make sure
that I don't have some other interceding
oddity here I want to make sure that
we're grabbing you know sensible area or
that we're looking at reasonable areas
as far as the sim region is concerned
yeah that's what I feared so it looks
like the sim region is not in this area
so we're still a little bit forked just
with our startup so what I was trying to
do there right is I was just trying to
see what the world's bounds were and in
fact I can do a push volume outline here
if I wanted to I probably should in the
future but if I look at the if I look at
the world sim bounds I'm not seeing them
so as far as this is concerned here
we're definitely getting ah so this is
our problem here right our our region
that we are trying to pull in is never
defined right because again this is
stuff that kind of was just hacked in
there because we didn't have a world
generator so we didn't really have any
idea about how we want to do any of
these things so it kind of just sits
there and does its thing but what you
can see is in the code that we comped it
out right there's standard room
dimension is getting set here and if we
don't set that then we're never going to
be able to see anything happen because
nothing's gonna get pulled in in the
same region I don't think we want it to
work that way right in the future
there's a lot of reasons we wouldn't I'm
gonna go ahead and switch this over to
mmm-hmm optimize build so we can play a
little I'll play it as a perhaps an
incorrect term at this point so what you
can see here right is the hero is now
confined to essentially a pen right and
and can't go outside of it and of course
the reason that that the hero can't go
outside of the pen is because we don't
have any respect for the connections
between rooms right like I was talking
about before and that's to be expected
so when we look now we've got you can
see the other rooms out there and we
would like to be able to go you know
we'd like to be able to get from room to
room in some way but we of course can't
and that's fine so I think we've
essentially finished all of the stuff
that I had wanted to finish in terms of
getting the basic room layout stuff and
cleaning up the way that we create any
is anything that actually looks pretty
good I don't think we have time to
really do anything else right now before
we end up moving to the next but before
the episode would end we only have ten
minutes left and that's not really
enough time to do anything as far as
getting the actual layout stuff to work
now what I can do potentially is maybe
get doors working a little bit I'm not
sure so I can do something that has to
do with doors I'll put it to you that
way I can do a little bit of work on the
doors
I just can't finish the actual real
layout stuff because that's gonna be
like probably all next weekend getting a
basic one of those working right um so
now if what I want to do here is just
have there be a way to make doors well
now and hopefully you can see already
even just early on here how this starts
to take shape before we kind of just
have this haphazard way of slapping down
some test stuff well now when we call
generate room well when I go to
the room if I want to make a door I
actually have some way of knowing what I
might make for a door because a room has
a list of connections to other rooms in
it and we can imagine that list of
connections actually having some
carrying some weight so that it knows
where those connections might be so for
example if I was to go to the world
champ code and say that a Jen connection
which is a connection from one room to
another connection actually has a piece
of information in it that says where
that connection is spatially then I can
actually I know what to put there when
I'm looking at the other room so for
example in here what I could say is you
know this connection has maybe a
boundary to it let's do something very
simple in that regard let's say that
we're going to make something like a
Jenn
a Jenn volume which maybe is one of
these things
something like this I don't know and
again I don't really know how we want to
store that but let's say we have one of
those so a room has a volume and that
volume you know we can we can use more
directly all right so what I want to do
now is basically have a knock out volume
so I want to be able to say that if a
room has a connection to another room
maybe that connection also has a volume
so and if you're inside that volume then
I don't want to actually put any walls
there right so on boundary is going to
be this but if you're inside any of the
other connections then we're just going
to forget about it right something like
that right
alternatively what I could do is say if
I'm on a boundary and not on a
connection because maybe I want to know
that or something and I don't know
whatever doesn't matter uh so what I
want to do here is say alright when I'm
gonna create this thing
I'm gonna go ahead and do
something like this where I say alright
I've got an X index of Y index and
whatever right and I want to know
whether or not that's inside some volume
that I've got here so I have whatever
the the connection is that I'm looking
at I want to basically say like am i
inside that connection volume whatever
it is and then you hear what I can do is
I can loop over all the connections for
this room so I can say alright there's a
genuine connection and that's just going
to be equal to the rooms first
connection and then I'm just going to
loop over those and off I go right so
now you can kind of see how we can link
rooms up once we create a connection we
just say where that connection is
between the two rooms and then it will
not put something there all we need is a
query that will tell us whether or not
we're inside one of these things not
very difficult to write as you might
imagine if I have one of these gem
valium structures and then I have an X
of Y and a Z then I know that all I have
to do is say that the results is going
to be if the X is greater than or equal
to the X of the volume and the X is less
than the volume plus hips plus the X
count right
if all of my rain checks succeed on each
axis then I know I'm inside the volume
and off we go so that's all fine at this
point those volumes will be null so
nothing should happen when I run this
right it'll just create the same rooms
that it created before and then refine
if however I was to just hard code when
we create a connection like I said we
don't actually know where the
connections going yet but if I was to
hard-code some of those in the world
generator so in here when it calls the
layout and it's putting these things in
there if I was to take the connections
for the room or something like that and
hard-coded or something I could make
these daisy chaining together and the
way that I do that it's just like all
right you know like I said we just hard
code them so maybe when I go over this
room i I just loop over the connections
in here something like this and I in
fact I could do it more like this and
then we all do you say like okay let's
suppose that the room connection in this
case is actually you know what I don't
even need to do this so there just
happen
I'll do two the first one if this room
does have a connection then I'll just
set it to be for its volume to be to the
left and encompassing two blocks let's
say and that should create some
connections between the rooms again
we're totally hacking this it's dumb but
that's just what we're gonna do right so
the connection volume in this case is
going to be it's going to be one high on
the z count it's gonna have an X count
of two it's gonna have a Y count of two
right it's going to knock out say it to
wide square and it's going to be on the
the tile X boundary minus one so it's
back 1 from that it's going to be at the
tile Y center so it would be halfway and
the Z is just the Tao Zi and so that
should just set some arbitrary
connection crap in there and hopefully
we'll start to see some knockouts there
so almost but not quite you know what
tonight
I'm not sure why that would have
wouldn't have knocked out more I may
have a bug in there but we'll see it's
very strange
it like knocks it up for this room 3 up
that's really strange well I will hold
off on debugging to next time again
that's just hacking that in there so I
don't it's a problem because the two
rooms will fight over where that that
connection volume actually is right and
so it's one of those things that you
this hack is yeah that could be
explained by just the way that that I'm
hacking it in there might be enough to
to see why it doesn't actually work
right but it could actually be something
more subtle than that so you know it's
hard to say we will find out when the
time comes so yeah but otherwise yeah
other I mean otherwise I would have
assumed that it would have been okay I
would like to do one thing here which is
just to say that I want to color the
region so I can see it a little bit
better so I'm gonna do something like
that so I can just see which regions are
getting color knocked out
yeah you can kind of see this is busted
so I've got something wrong with the way
I'm doing it oh yeah you think I was
testing the relative index without ain't
gonna cut it my friends we need to test
the absolute index obviously for lack of
a better term all right so you can see
that this works pretty well now except
we kind of have this nasty problem we're
like we don't know B so this won't
daisy-chain all the rooms together
because some rooms only have one
connection right these rooms are
supposed to be laid out in a topology
and so a room that only has one
connection can only have one open thing
but it looks like it worked just fine
right so all we really need to do now
next time is actually make some layout
that makes any sense at all and these
will now be a little world you can
explore doesn't have anything in it but
first things first so that's all good
and yeah and I think even the camera is
sort of working now as well right so
that's that's fun too anyway yeah little
by little all good you can see again
also now we can fix the lighting so we
can slide the lighting over to which
will be nice as well so yeah it's it's
getting good I think we're in good shape
here I'll go ahead and go to a brief Q&amp;A
can you please fix end world Jen yes
although I don't know what's wrong with
it at the moment what do you want me to
fix about end world Jen just clear the
temporary 'no the temp memory I think
that's already taken care of the fact
that it's only ever beginning an end
temp so it's not really necessary but of
the capitalisation yes
what is internal used for in C is it
like the opposite of X turn in C++ yes
sort of it's not actually that is what
it is but that's not actually see it's
it's really just us so you can see here
I basically got internal to find a
static the reason is because static is
like the worst keyword in the world
it means like 50 different things and
it's just like you can't search for it
because it'll hit all of the different
uses of it and so on so I define
internal to be static so I see the
difference between that and like when
I'm defining a variable as static or
worse yet a static member function in
C++ right which is a completely again
different use of it one of the things
they did in C++ i think is actually a
really awful idea is they wanted to
minimize the degree to which they added
new keywords and that was just should
the light calculation always be stuck to
the camera yes it should be and
basically what we want to do is just
animate it smoothly so right now what
happens is we animate it to snap to the
new location the camera will be but
instead what we want to do is have it
actually track where the camera is just
period right and that's easy to do right
it's not hard but we just haven't done
it yet
no questions
by the way in some C++ header there is a
definition of internal so your code
would not work if any so file gets
included I'm happy with that it prevents
us from getting mad yes I totally agree
anything I can put in my code that
prevents anyone from ever including a C
bus less header in it is a win in fact
if there was just thing you could put in
the code that says don't ever allow
anyone to include a C++ library header
in here I would put that in all my code
what function is the camera using to
interpolate between two positions right
now I don't remember what we're using I
don't think we're using anything
particularly sane actually to be
completely honest with you
[Music]
yeah I this is just garbage so so to
answer your question it's actually just
doing it's a non stable iteration right
it's just like taking the the Delta and
adding a time fraction to it so it's
basically a frame rate dependent
ordinary differential equation right
which is not what we would want it to be
in the end if that makes sense doctor I
can put one here for you
how much of the world Jen can be done in
this pass and how much would depend on
more gameplay exploration stuff well
probably the world Jen like backbone is
what we're making now so that we can
make a world that we can then play
through but the vast majority of Jen
stuff will kind of just be code that
start secreting as we add gameplay
features obviously we would not want to
[Music]
well you know what I see that Jonathan
Blow has arrived in the stream
so here's what I'll say as I've said
many times many many times on the stream
I'm not a game designer so I don't know
all I can tell you is the game designers
who I respect like John like Daniel Ben
more gooey like they say you have to
kind of design forward where you explore
the game space yourself and find out
what's interesting about it and then
think about ways you can construct
meaningful interactions based around
those experiences so I would assume that
the correct answer to your question
based on what they have said is that we
only are doing just enough to build a
world and then every other thing we do
with real generation should be based on
something we experience in the game
right so we make the little orphanage
and the forest pieces like I'm doing now
and then we put some monsters in there
and when we fight the monsters we go oh
it would feel good here if I had to plan
about some timer that was counting down
or something right so then I go and add
the counter to the world Jen right that
is how every game designer I've ever
thought was any good has always said
you're supposed to do that kind of work
so I would just assume that's the right
answer but if you actually want to know
the right answer you would need to ask
them
so maybe John's got a stream today I
don't know I think he's actually not
home in San Francisco so maybe not but
next time he's on stream you should ask
him for a more complete answer because
that's really you want to get that kind
of answer from a game designer not an
engine programmer why does the color of
the room go as it does without loitering
rather than going black because we
actually always have moonlight so if you
remember inside the lighting code
there's the moon and when you don't hit
a light you get a moon if if it's up
right there's a there's a moon default
value here so let me show you how that
happens so you see this line of code so
basically if I was to take out the moon
light it would get it would become black
so basically if I you know if we look at
how the lighting is working here you
know you can see that as I move around
there's sort of a baseline moonlight
color that it goes through there if
instead what I did was inside this code
I just said yeah you know that's not
gonna happen then what you would see is
those regions become completely black
because no light is reaching them
whatsoever or maybe not no light you can
see there's a little bit of light
reaching them as the fall-off from this
light gets lower out there but that's
what's happening so I don't know if that
helps make sense but basically there is
a there is a large sky lit sort of in
flow of light that makes it so nothing
is completely black unless it's got like
a sealed roof over it or something just
want to randomly suggest transactional
processing as a topic for some future
off-topic stream okay will there be
specific locations in the world I saw
you mentioned orphanage yesterday and if
so how will they be handled in a
generated world everything will be
generated but you saw how the orphanage
stuff was sort of going basically what
we'll have is will have special-purpose
routines designed to create them in some
less than completely generative way
right so some things about them are
prescribed but that's true of everything
right look at
dungeon has a bunch of prescriptions to
it right naysayer 88 how long would it
take me to get up to speed on for coder
if I decide to like to switch off the
hell that is Emacs no time at all like
basically you could start with well
alright so here's what I'd say John if
you want an exact Emacs clone one of the
problems is I don't know if anyone's
actually redone the key bindings to be
Emacs like yet I was just having too
many RSI issues with holding down the
ctrl key so I switch to a modal like
version that's the same as my Emacs
poundings were but with modality so if
you started with my Emacs config it'd be
pretty far from what you're used to
using right now and that might take a
while to get up to speed somebody else
may have done a closer binding to Emacs
like keys but that would be the real
learning curve there what I can say is
just using for coder if you're willing
to spend a day doing some programming is
actually pretty easy because all of the
programming happens in C you don't have
to learn something like Emacs list so
for example if you want to look at what
I've got a hand made code misc for
quarter K see if you want to look at how
it works it's pretty straightforward
I've made tons of customizations to it
but the basic idea is pretty simple you
just have one entry point and that entry
point does some pretty basic stuff like
you can see here where I bind all these
keys these are just functions and you
can just specify your own functions that
should happen here there's a default one
that you could look at that has a bunch
of stuff but like I have customized
almost everything but this is all it is
you just bind all your keys here to
functions that you call and those
functions can do whatever you want them
to do there's defaults for almost
everything that Emacs does but I also
have my own like special sauce there
right then you've got the same kind of
thing as you're used to in Emacs like oh
if you just want to call a C function
when a thought gets open you just set it
and then you can do whatever you want in
there and whatever
you can obviously have mine which has a
bunch of this stuff in it and you can
see like I because I do modal Keys I
made a macro for having two different
modes be bound in either way and all
that is it's just a thing that says hey
am I in edit mode or am I not and it
just does one code or the other either
case so what you can see here is there's
a lot of things that are actually just
built in like reverse search search undo
go to line those are all built in I'd
write those so a lot of the things if
you were to just cut and paste all of
this stuff right character blah blah
blah all of that stuff if you actually
do bind keys you can bind if you don't
want modal like I have you can bind all
of your keys right there and just be
done and you wouldn't even need any like
C code at all right but yeah like I say
I like to really heavily customize my
editor so you can see I've written all
kinds of stuff here here's the thing
that loads my to-do list here's the
thing that searches for where I want my
build to occur here's a thing that like
looks for if like I know that I want
like sees to load h's with us if I hit
the seek key you know all kinds of crap
right and so I've done a lot of
customizations so it kind of depends on
how much you want to do customization
wise all of that stuff you can sort of
just start with mine if you want
and then change all the key bindings or
you can start with Alan's key ships a
default one and that with all the the
the C file for that is included if you
are using for coder
so you can start with that I don't know
um so I can't really answer that
question for you because I don't know
your Emacs config very well hopefully it
wouldn't be that hard for you to just go
in there and rebind the keys the only
thing that's gonna be nasty for you is
that there isn't a syntax highlighting
system for j ai which maybe you need you
can talk to Alan about that I don't know
if he can help you I know that down the
line they're going to be adding more in
the ways of customizable parsing
like that but at the moment you know
it's an editor for c-like languages and
J I might not quite be C like enough for
the parser to correctly like indent and
stuff like that you know obviously if
you want to switch over to for coder and
you have any trouble with it just let me
know and I can help you get your config
working but like just starting with my
config should be pretty easy because you
can just change all the key bindings to
the actual key bindings you want and
don't bother with these modal like don't
bother just put the actual function in
here that you want and then you can have
an anon modal binding pretty quickly
right by just starting with mine and
putting what you want in here instead of
in this weird modal macro crap I made
which is just because I was making some
modal stuff right is there a reason you
don't use force in line yeah mostly
because I just haven't had a case where
I really wanted to yet you know the
compiler does a pretty reasonable job of
picking what to in line what to not most
of the time so the only time I would
really use force in line is if I
actually am optimizing a piece of code
and literally saw a place where I wanted
the compiler in line and it wasn't then
I would use force in line but the whole
like I always know better than the
compiler went to in line thing I don't
think is true because if I haven't
looked at the performance of something
I'm not in position to tell it what to
in line and what not to really write
it's doing some analysis that analysis
isn't great it's better than no analysis
and no analysis is what I would be doing
if I was putting force in line in places
willy-nilly right can you go over the
architecture how to generate the rooms
like with this generic config briefly
again
[Music]
yes but I'm not sure what you mean
because we haven't implemented the
layout stuff yet so all we're doing is
we're creating a record of the rooms you
want to generate we're creating records
of how they're connected and then we in
the future will implement a layout
function that obeys those connections
and places rooms so that they are
non-overlapping and are connected in the
way that is requested
then we once have that layout we go
through each room and actually put down
the entities that comprise the room
that's all we're doing John says
streaming today would be very doubtful
all right well you know some other time
Neil said I think they meant the unlit
part Oh
are you you mean when we're in the debug
view you mean why is this look like that
the reason for that is just that the
lighting system only looks at things in
a region and if the lighting system
isn't looking at something it just gets
it's it's what it's a reflective color
would be like what yeah as you said
diffuse albedo
and me or can you start optimizing your
code as you go or when you reach major
milestones or do you need to wait for
near completion to optimize your code
and make sure you don't have useless
coding lines bulking up so I would I
guess what I would say is the answer to
that question is actually that you need
to sort of develop very good programming
skills before you can really answer it
effectively yourself because it depends
the notion that optimize the premature
optimization is the root of all evil
which is kind of a misquote from Knuth
or a misapplication from Knuth that kind
of got distorted down the line to
basically mean to an optimizer code
until you have to or something right
it's not entirely true I mean in one
sense it's obviously true because the
definition of premature optimization
means you're doing it before you should
so in that case it's just a tautology in
some sense it wouldn't be premature if
it was the right time to do it right
saying it's the root of all evil life
throws us into tautology because hey the
root of all evil is a pretty bold claim
but in terms of whether it's wasted work
to optimize things at any time other
than me and the answer is no it isn't
necessarily and the reason for that is
because and like I said this is why you
kind of have to just know and have some
taste about it because it's something
that's a very difficult call to make
optimization is not something you can
just do right if you have structured the
way the code works to preclude
optimization from occurring then it's
not gonna be really possible for you to
optimize it at the end not without
rewriting massive amounts of the code
right so one of the things that you
learn to do as you get better at
programming is to structure your code
such that you know you're not precluding
any optimizations that you think you
might need to make and you will start
optimizing certain pieces of code what
would otherwise be prematurely because
you know that you don't want to build
dependency
on that code until you see that it can
be made optimal right so sometimes you
do need to do a little bit or a lot even
of optimization on a piece of code
because you know that how other code
works will be dependent on it and
getting it into a and not having it in
the state it should be for later release
is gonna be a problem right so basically
that calls a very hard call to make what
I can't say is 90% of the time you
really don't want to do much with
optimization until you have to 90% of
the time but maybe 10% or maybe 5% of
the time I don't know what the actual
real potentials we don't have hard
metrics on things like this you do need
to think about optimization up front and
you do need to do some and you need to
have some ideas about exactly how you
are going to make this code work the way
it needs to for shipping because letting
it go too long okay will have negative
consequences as as assumptions about
that code ripple out through the code
base so you you really need to have a
good idea of how things are being
dependent on each other and what things
may may create problems during the
release cycle during optimization if
they're done wrong maybe it's ink for
next week but can you make the boundary
wall heights equal I don't know that I
want the boundary wall heights to be
equal so I probably won't do that but
it'd be pretty easy to do obviously yes
all right let's close that here
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for their sort of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
the series at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org and it
comes to the source code so you can play
around with it yourself for example if
you want to make all the boundary wall
height equal you can easily go do that
in the code as it stands right now it's
a pretty simple change to make other
than that I will be back here next week
if you would like to see how we're going
to layout our rooms and actually make
them connect in a real way so that we
can start to have a game world that you
can explore and have fun in we will be
doing that next weekend so hope to see
you back here for that in the meantime
if you want to catch up on old episodes
definitely check out the episode guide
it's pretty amazing at this point you
can search all sorts of things and watch
old episodes or clips from old episodes
that are pertinent to things you want to
know about until next weekend there it's
something you can check out or do some
of your own coding have some fun I don't
know whatever you're working on right
now do something cool on it until next
weekend take it easy everybody and I'll
see you on the Internet