hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could complete game live
on stream if I remember correctly and
it's been about three weeks so we took a
break there I was away I want to start
something new I'm pretty sure we left
ourselves in a reasonable position for
starting something new and we have a
number of things we can do however I
think there's a pretty clear order in
which we should do them so I'm going to
say that order now out of the things
that I want to do is one I want the tag
system to get cleaned up now that we've
got all this art assets in there I want
to simplify how we're doing tag clear
querying and make it clear how things
are selected from the our task stream in
like a clean efficient manner so that's
one thing that I'd like to do I would
like to make it so that we can have
ground cover and stuff now so like when
we like in fact we sort of did a crappy
example of this in the renderer sand
alone renderer test that we have we you
know splattered some grass on things I'd
like to make a good version of that so
that when we're outdoors we can get the
like some ground cover there and
possibly also indoors we may want sort
of a relatively generic scattering thing
that's just like Scout of this crap
around at this density and then we can
just use low density scattering for
interiors to put things like rocks on
dungeon floors or like debris
you know stuff where the placement of it
doesn't really matter it's just there
for a visual effect so it's not really
necessarily there for gameplay where you
know you don't interact with these
things they're just kind of giving you a
little bit more texture of the
environment so we want to be able do
that we want to finish up our lighting
so our lighting is still not really
finished it's kind of a bit of zygote I
think I pretty much
how I want to finish it up now so that
it'll be fast enough to be shippable
quality and also broad enough to be good
you know and usable everywhere and
finally I want to get our world Jen
generating something reasonable for the
actual layout of the game currently
which is to say that if you load the
game at the moment and I can sort of
show you what I mean by this if we go
ahead and do a quick builds here and a
launch remedy with our game so if you
take a look at what it looks like at the
moment right we end up in a situation
where it's generating sort of the rooms
like our test rooms are generating there
but what we don't get is filler for
areas like outside of the rooms and we
would like that to occur so in other
words when I like even right here where
we're at the boundary here I would like
there to be outdoor tiles around here
right so just you know I want it just I
don't want there to ever be like dead
space like that unless we're underground
and then like over here for example you
know when we're in like a forest area or
something like that I want I don't want
you to be able to see dead space like so
there should just be like trees out here
or just arbitrary forest fill to go far
enough out such that like if the player
stands as far away as they can from the
center of the area whatever the region
is they could plausibly have seen to is
filled with stuff right so it's sort of
just creating an apron of entities
anywhere we like didn't put something
normally
and you know that's sort of just a way
of solidifying the world little bits
that you're not so it doesn't look like
it's just part of getting things to the
point where they don't look like a
development build anymore it's like
we've got to like solidify a bunch of
stuff and that's like one of them right
so that those are the things that we
would like to do and I think the one
that makes the most sense at first is
the last one I said meaning we should go
in and get the generator generating
something that's a plausible actual
world here meaning like this is kind of
the number of entities that we expect to
have and we can also maybe force some
more furniture in here I don't know
we'll see how we want to do that but we
can sort of play around with that stuff
a little bit more as we go anyway so I
would like to do that and what we'll do
down here
I'm not like 100% sure to be completely
honest with you in other words I don't
know what we what is the right thing to
show when you're when you're down in a
dungeon area so there's not there isn't
a world outside it would just be like
rock you know underground like the earth
you know so most of the time it doesn't
really matter because as you can see
we've set the camera properly so that
you only really see the room that you're
currently in but like yeah on these
scrolling ones when you can scroll the
side I don't know one thing we could do
is stop the scrolling so that it doesn't
you know lie to go further but it's
still you know no matter what we do
they're still gonna be this kind of
thing happening at some point probably
and so the question is just what do we
want to do there and I don't know it may
be that we just want that to just be
black so in other words we will clear
any of the undrawn region will will
clear that to black and that is what it
will look like right so that's what I'd
like to do and I just want that because
in the upstairs areas where you're sort
of want to feel like it's outdoors
that's
kind of thing where I don't really want
I don't want black in the exterior there
because it makes it feel like it's not
really the outdoors because you know the
outdoors wouldn't that you know we all
know their stuff here so I'd like to
have you know that working correctly so
I think that's the first thing I'd like
to start with is just getting like
aprons generated for everything so that
anywhere that we don't end up placing
like actual world stuff on the you know
the sort of Earth's crust layer for lack
of a better term any anywhere on that
layer I would like it so that we have a
sufficient apron of entities to prevent
you from seeing sort of the edge of the
world and at first here I don't care if
there's anything particularly nice about
them
I just want squares there and when we
can work later on as we you know improve
our world gencode to put you know more
intelligent layouts of trees and things
I mean obviously right now we're not
even doing like this trees that are in
the apron right here that's right that
are in the boundary right here
are just we just randomly we were
testing to see all the different kinds
of trees that were in our pack so
obviously like at some point we have to
make a thing that's intelligent about
tree placement because obviously these
trees should not be occurring together
the trees should be sort of logically
grouped so you know if this is a snowy
area we have mostly snowy trees and if
this is a fall sort of season area we
get most of the fall trees or things
like that
so that's all fine and dandy and and at
the moment I don't really care about
that part for the apron I just want to
make sure that we're generating stuff in
that apron so when we look at how the
world Jen works what we end up with is
essentially you know we end up in the
room gencode which is just kind of a
placeholder right now cuz we don't
really generate any gameplay rooms but
this is where the action will happen
eventually for creating
what for lack of better term would be
like one gameplay experience for the
player right cuz each room would have
something like a monster you have to
fight or something you want to see or a
shop that you engage with so pretty much
anything gameplay related right is this
eventual is gonna be a pretty complex
set of things we're going to do in here
to put down various gameplay things that
we want the player to experience and so
this generate room function is where
we're going to do that work for
generating the apron I don't think we
really want to confuse or conflate the
two so I think we kind of want a
separate kind of function that's gonna
you know generate apron areas and it
will just kind of like splat down things
that's necessary to fill those areas so
the first thing I think we need to do is
figure out when to call that function
and with what amount of room right so if
we go to our world gin code base what we
can see our code base that's good are
it's not like code base her from Jen
structures our room 10 infrastructure
what we could see is we create sort of
this intermediate representation where
we have things like rooms and the rooms
are connected together and we do stuff
like place the rooms down and then we
when we know where they all go we then
fill them in with stuff and that's sort
of the how the passes of room generation
goes so what I want to be able to do is
I would like anytime we place a room
down to essentially say in addition to
this room I need like an apron area
that's going to fill all of the
surrounding area of the room and here's
some information about like what that
apron should be right but I don't want
that to create any placement constraints
right because that apron is just filler
it's not required to be where it is it's
just saying if nothing else needed to go
here then we want to fill it in with
trees or rocks or who cares what
cliffside you know whatever it is so
what we want to do there is we want to
be able to create these aprons as sort
of a secondary thing that's like here's
where all the aprons would go and then
after the entire world has been like
constructed and we know where everything
goes then we can sort of do a separate
pass if you will to see where these
aprons should fill in and we just look
and say is there anything there if
there's not something there then we
place it but if there was we don't touch
it so that's what I want to do now since
we know that the only things that can
really occur exist at the moment our
rooms it seems like what we could
probably do is say well there's a gem
volume here for the room that says this
is where the room is it seems pretty
straightforward that we could also just
create a gen volume for the apron right
so what we could do is say well you know
maybe there's a gen apron and the apron
is just like sort of
anything that's around the play area
that the player doesn't go into but
that's there for visual effect and it
needs to be filled with something and
off we go right
and so the Jen apron would say for this
volume you know I want to fill it up
with something and we can have some kind
of a specification for what that is we
can probably follow what we were doing
here where we've got sort of general
spec we can probably say hey maybe we've
got a gen apron spec as well and that
just has who knows what in it and so
we're basically gonna do the same thing
here then what we can do is say okay
these aprons just kind of stack up like
everything else does the spec I don't
know which we're just gonna throw
something in there that has nothing to
do right and this is similar to do it's
like we don't really spec stuff at the
moment it's just placeholder but what we
want to do is have a list of these
aprons so that afterwards we can go
through and just load them up see if
there's any need to fill them with
something and if there is fill them if
there isn't don't so there's a couple
different you know ways in which we're
probably gonna have to make this more
robust than the first thing I'm going to
do but we'll we'll kind of do a basic
pass on it first all right so if we take
a look at the general which should be
here somewhere
no where's the worst the stuff that
actually holds this stuff where did we
put it right there's a because there's a
there's a little generator but I don't
know where that ended up
oh it was in here okay interesting it's
at the top well I put it at the top for
some reason why did I put at the top
nobody knows so let's go ahead and
create the Jen apron sort of list here
that's effectively gonna be exactly the
same as our rims and we'll just keep a
separate list of these and we know we
sort of go sort of fill these out as a
separate as a separate pass right and
then inside here you know we've got sort
of our our code - well no that's not
what I wanted I want to look for our
room code where we actually put one of
these on here so I think no that's not
it where is our function it's been a
while where is our function for doing
this that's the room stack that we use
for processing also not the same surely
there's a way that generates a room into
the system and who knows where that is
am I just not seeing it am I being am i
being daft here I mean right there
should have been there should be I would
think a function that gives you one of
these right a Jen room and I have no
idea why I don't see it here I guess
what I'll do is I'm gonna look for where
we add room connections here I wanted to
see where that
actually exists just so I can figure out
how on earth Kufa we were doing there to
make these things I could also look at
the place where we create the orphanage
and just see what we're calling but
that's just weird
so here's a recruit aspects Jen room ah
I see so we sort of defined this as a
macro so that we could produce labeling
for it right you can see that happening
here so that we could see what our room
layouts work so that's why I didn't see
it interesting all right
anyway because yeah you can see my
little sort of crappy parser that tries
to find all the functions it doesn't
work I don't think through like the if
there's like macros you know wrapping it
so it wouldn't find Jen you know it
would find this but it wouldn't find
that yeah I'm saying anyway
so in here we've got our general call
and you can see that it's you know
effectively just pushing on a struct
onto this linked list of structs that's
what we want to do with the apron as
well so we just want to have a Jen apron
call here where we're basically pushing
on and you know we maybe want to do the
same thing where we push a label on
there to see who's creating it but you
know I don't know I'm gonna wait till I
actually need that before I go full pull
on that but anyway we're gonna say all
right you're gonna give us the world
generator and we're gonna push one of
these guys on here so it's a sack same
code really only were you know not gonna
set we're gonna put it on a different
list that's about it so here's the apron
we push one on to the memory for the
generator we say that the spec you gave
us is the spec we will use
unsurprisingly we set the global next to
be whatever the first apron was in the
list and then we say that the first
apron in the list is ourselves right
it's a standard thing that we do for
linked lists nothing special and so now
we have a way of putting these aprons on
don't ask me why but spelled that um
that's what we want so we can do a
generic call and that puts one into the
generator for future use and what we
need now is anytime we're actually
making rooms we want some way of making
those aprons occur with them and I'm not
sure exactly how we want to do that
because if we look back at the code so
let's look at the orphanage code since
that's the thing that we actually have
the most experience with here so if you
look at what's happening here when we're
generating rooms what you can see is
that you know there's really not a lot
of code that that really thinks about
the rooms location after that but you
know we do like connection calls like so
and the problem we're gonna have hers
you know we don't really want to make we
don't want to force ourselves to have to
keep saying like hey generate the apron
for this or the apron for that and so I
think maybe what we would want to do
just looking at this is say hey maybe we
want to talk about the you know the act
of generating the room itself could
generate the apron based off of the spec
right so for example what we could do is
say alright when you generate a room
here and yeah maybe this is nice
I kind of like this idea maybe do it a
little bit differently so instead of
Jenny generating the aprons right away
maybe what we do instead is say okay the
Jen room spec has an apron spec off of
it so when you generate the room you
will push the apron on with that volume
right and so in other words rather than
calling this sort of thing manually
maybe what we actually do is we say well
we've got the apron and we know that
when we're generating rooms what we
should do is the room spec which says
what kind of room this is can also tell
us if there is an apron right so we
could just say alright you know if you
set this value to something then when we
generate the room we know that we have
to generate an apron that corresponds to
that room right I like that idea because
now we can sort of turn the process
around a little bit and say back in the
code where we have the room Jen where we
call this generate room call what we
could say is at that point so you know
we go through all of this stuff to
create you know everything that's in the
room at that point when we're at the
very end and we finished everything up
maybe that is the time when we then say
hey whatever the room spec is so because
you know we've gotten the room spec here
that we use to generate the room
whatever the room spec is we could say
if this spec has an apron requirement
then let's go ahead and use that apron
requirement so here's where we'll call
Jen apron and we'll say give me one of
these and the apron itself we can set
the volume now and maybe we'll set the
the no I guess we wouldn't have to
because everything else is set so this
this Jen apron that we get back we know
that the spec contains the information
necessary and that was sort of part of
what whatever the room specification was
and then in this vault in this part here
where we do the apron volume we know
what the room volume is and so all we
have to do is look and see whether we
think that that volume should get
applied to the apron and the reason I
say that is because we may want to not
apply the apron to anything other than
just the zi area that one z plane that
we know we're using for aprons right um
I'm just not sure exactly how we want to
do that so for now I'm gonna ignore just
that that part and we'll kind of come
back to that a little bit later but
here's the room volume so if I say that
I want the apron volume to be this well
it wouldn't really do anything because
that's just only the area that contains
the room itself so what I need to do
here is grow that by however many tiles
I want aprons to be generally speaking
and I believe that we have a surgeon
math there it is I believe that we have
a thing in your yeah I do so we've got a
bunch of functions in here and it looks
like we already wrote the one we would
need this one allows us to take any
volume that we have and add some amount
of expansion to it right
so if I want to take one of these Jen
VIII's I can sort of say all right I
don't want to add any Z to it but I do
want to add some X&amp;Y I don't know how
many of those I want but let's say we do
an eight by eight apron around
everything and off we go okay so now in
theory anyway if I take care of any bugs
that we've got here what is the problem
world Jen it's that's what I actually
wanted and this is all probably and it's
that knowledge Oh address and so that's
really all we're talking about here and
I believe that that should just leave
things exactly as they were and now we
should have in theory the ability to
create something that you know produces
aprons and we can make a call for that
so what I want essentially is a call
like generate apron and I want it to you
know do something pretty much the same
as this only you know it's going to be
given an apron rather than a room and
what I primarily need is the ability to
just make sure that there's nothing
there right there's nothing in the way
and so I think looking at this
I need ways of finding if there's any
entities in a particular location and I
don't really think we've done much of
that yet obviously we can get
traversable spy location but that's not
quite the same thing and so we do need
some way of you know getting entities
that are nearby and making sure that we
don't place anything in locations where
they would be so we might have to add a
little bit of that I think that's mostly
the only thing that we're going to need
other than what we already have right
and so yeah let's go ahead and start
with this because we are gonna iterate
over the stuff here so when we're
generating the apron here what we want
to do is say all right here's our apron
spec which we don't really know we're
gonna do with yet but someday we'll
probably do something with it and then
what we want to do is this same thing
where we're taking the counts and we're
just going to loop over them again the
z-index we're not really going to use
because if you know an apron will
probably never use it because we're just
doing the bottom sort of level of it and
so what we want to do there is we want
to place onto these tile indices we want
to go ahead and create entities here
like so and we want to probably do just
very basic yeah we want like a sort of a
very basic cube for the wall here
basically the exact same stuff we were
doing living that way gonna dwell but
they're gonna be ground and that's
mostly it right so we really just want
something very simple here nothing too
fancy
something like this right um I think
that's all we really need the wall
height can for the moment really not be
a thing I mean I don't know what we're
gonna put here I don't really care we'll
think about this a little bit later I
see what we're doing we were trying to
keep the placement consistent uh so just
think something like that seems fine we
put one of these blocks here we probably
should put some tags on it to control
what its gonna be like whether it's
outdoors or not it would be this sort of
thing right and so I think we probably
just want to do something like this for
now and so that would place like cubes
out there and really the only thing that
we need is a way to make sure that we
don't place anything into areas that
already had something placed you know
I'm saying something that basically says
is there anything at this tile location
because if if the game had already
generated room information there I don't
want to place anything there like on top
of it right so looking at get Sims space
traversable which is the only career we
have the reason we don't really want to
do that right is because we don't we
don't only want to look for things that
are traversable right we want to well
actually and I guess we'll yeah I guess
even think about this this is just using
the grid so even that we don't have
right now we don't have the grid
available so really what we need here is
we need sort of a way of querying the
what entities are in this particular
location and we really don't have that
like you can see that there really isn't
anything there really isn't anything of
that of that form and so that's
something that we need anyway I mean we
need to be able to gather the
these that are in an area and that's
something that the sim region wants to
be able to do so it's not really an
issue so we should be fine but we have
to actually do it uh so we'll do that
yeah I don't see we don't have anything
in here for that as far as I can tell I
mean here's the thing where we loop over
all the entities and look for something
right and that's already something that
we had it to do in there like hey we've
got to make this thing faster anyway and
here is like another example right so
all of this stuff is examples of things
that we needed we wanted spatial queries
for anyway and so we want to add those
in here and that's this is a fine reason
to do it because we need it for all
sorts of things and this is just one of
the things that we'll want to be able to
do faster spatial queries on alright so
I think that's mostly all we're talking
about right so if you imagined we had
the call here where we could say like
you know something like this like hey if
I get overlapping entities you know
whatever sort of the sort of size of the
thing is that we were going to make here
which is like this thing in fact we
could actually produce the we could
store these two up here and use them as
the actual query so I think this is like
Center P and dim of the NV so we could
basically say hey if this thing
if this thing would would intersect
another entity don't place it right so
we're only gonna place things that
wouldn't intersect anything else and you
know maybe we would shrink that by a
little bit but we're basically asking
this and we need like an offset so this
is like the offset from this P here so
you know sort of this this p here that
we would be using to place it we would
be using this offset from it right uh so
I think I think that's mostly all we
would need to do now whether we want to
bake that in there or not I'm not sure
and similarly we could just say we don't
really care about you know what this is
backwards it's dimension and offset we
could also say we don't really care
about the displacement particularly much
either I'm not sure but it yeah it
depends on on how we want to do this so
we'll say that we want to do that for
now we'll see maybe that's line and we
might want to shrink this down because
we don't want to require to be super
exact so we just want to say like we
have most of this tile is empty then we
want to splat the thing down here
probably so this may want to be yeah I
think we call this add radius to this
may want to be shrunk a little bit so
you know I don't know what the shrink
would actually be but you know maybe
it's something like you know we just
want to sort of contract it a little bit
on top of what the you know the actual
size of things going to be just to make
sure that we don't pick up any sort of
errant thing thats hanging over from a
jacent tile so I'm guessing we want yes
something like this we're like get
overlapping entities where we can
you know return some kind of a list of
entities that are overlapping this
particular thing I'm not sure how we
want to do that right now but we
probably just send some temp memory down
and we'll actually maybe make that
function produce an actual list seems
reasonable I mean there's reasons to not
want to actually make a list out of it
not to waste their time you know so we
could make this thing be more of like an
iterator but you know what I'll leave
that decision for a little bit later and
what I could say is we could say we
could just make a call that says hey I
want to know if there's any overlapping
entities for this area and we'll figure
out how we implement that exactly later
but this is what I want to see I want to
see something where I can say here's
where I'm gonna place the thing let's
make sure that there's nothing there
then we'll go ahead and place it
assuming that there isn't right and
again this will just for now generate
effectively the same sort of stuff we're
generating inside rooms or or outside
rooms or whatever and we'll deal with
that part later so I think that's all we
really need to do and so the majority of
the work is going to be we need to sort
of add this stuff I'll add the crappy
version of that maybe first and then
we'll add a better version later for the
moment we want to focus on how this
actually gets called because right now
it never would be and so if we go into
world Jen at the point where we actually
go and do stuff here I don't know what
this garbage is this is all old stuff we
don't need any of this really I don't
think yeah we don't delete it but in
here we call create world right this is
what's going to happen and what we want
to do is when we go to this generate
world call where we're we've sort of
built all the lists and stuff this
function or sorry this
for loop it's gonna call the generate
room operations that we have to do which
will create all the world entities and
then it will also create that list of
aprons that we need to be concerned with
so immediately after that we should be
able to say hey let's go ahead and loop
over all the aprons and generate those
and that should give us effectively the
entire behavior of the thing right all
right
so the generate apron called probably
needs to get hoisted up to here like so
and then we got a look at any bugs that
we've got room should this should just
be apron and floor tiles e is what
exactly I don't even know what that came
from or how we were creating that it's
just a min tile yeah so this is just
that and we have to figure out our wall
height we've got to put that up there
where it should have gone and we've got
two dims here so okay so there's that
dim so this is really the I guess we
should call this the cube P and the
cubed in might be a better way to say
that and then we've got the cubed in
there and the cube P here we've dim Q P
and that's just replacing the little
cube things
so what else our ad radius - is unhappy
I'm not sure why
ah I see
oh well but wait this is a cube dim this
isn't a rectangle so I'm not sure why I
said add radius - because that we should
just be really doing a rectangle there
so really this should just be wrecked
center half dim or something like this I
don't know if this is the cube dimension
or are our cubes point seven total I
guess not so this is the half dim right
so really this is rectangle Center half
dim and we want you know our cube dim
plus this v3 is what we're gonna
actually query on and that way we'll
just pass a rectangle three to this
thing and that'll be clear like what's
going on right okay so yeah if and this
would be like the query region maybe I'd
call this just so we can get this out
here and that's gonna be a rectangle
three which will you know just give us a
bounding area all right so then I can
say a query region we don't have this
function yet so that's going to be an
error obviously but otherwise hopefully
we should be good to go
stone floor here we don't really have so
I think we're just gonna go with like
yeah it's grass at the moment
honestly there only is outdoors so like
we don't really have anything to do with
any of this stuff in fact this isn't
even really
necessary you know maybe I'll just
doesn't have trees and so I think this
is really more what we're looking at
like that like there isn't really like
generate an apron of a floor of like
actual manmade area um so we need a way
of doing our overlapping entities exist
let's see here so when we do this at MD
we need here to pass down like the the
sim region that we're actually talking
about here and so in there I believe yes
so in generate room we do this world
change here which is sort of saying like
hey this is the area that we want to
actually edit as part of this and we're
going to want to do that for here too
so when we're ready we want to
effectively say let's do a begin world
change we have throughout where the
change center is and where the the
rectangle is but that's just going to be
like this volume and so if I look at how
we're completing that we should be able
just do it exactly the same and this
stuff probably should get pulled out
into a similar thing like into a into a
single unified call we can use I don't
make it to do that effect
but for now I'll leave it be and so when
we actually you know begin the the world
change there the tile dim is oops it's
just this you can just see there's too
much business here this stuff should we
should really kind of collapse down and
it just should be no more
straightforward okay and we can also
pull out the random serious here because
we're gonna probably do some entropy
based stuff as well right
yeah you can see here we got our entity
sort of variance there
this probably wants to be here too right
curious about this well uh anyway um
let's see
so we placing the entity only happens if
we actually have an entity and there's
one too many of those that's why we've
edited the else Clause out there but
then all I guess we need is just the
color here and the color for our current
purposes I don't know what we want to do
here probably nothing in particular so I
may just say like yeah the color is
going to be something fairly it's
interesting that we should probably not
be colorizing this stuff in weird ways
that we are right now so we should
probably just make the color of this
thing be something straightforward so
maybe the color of these things is just
that or whatever and we'll just pass
that down just just pure gray so I think
that puts us in and let me just make
sure we sort of record the world change
here and say that we're done but I think
that's it and so all I really need to do
now is have some way of actually
figuring out whether there was entities
in that area and again that's this call
right here and we need some way of that
returning information to us if I go to
the sim region what I could do is just
loop over all the entities and see if
any of them do and that's a good first
attempt so that's the slow crappy
version but at least we can see whether
or not the rest of our stuff is working
so what we would do for that is we just
say you know hey the same code we were
using before we basically just need to
say yeah give us the sim region actually
and since we're in sim region land we
really just need a rectangle three which
is like tell us what the bounds of this
thing are right and then what we can do
is loop over all of these and check if
they collide here we go so here's the
here's essentially the same call right
so what we can do is say here's the
collision volumes of these things or
whatever is happening and off we go
right the only thing that I think is a
little bit tricky about this is I don't
know if those collision volumes we're
probably gonna have to like solidify pun
intended our approach to collision fires
to make sure that everyone actually gets
one because I don't know that we
actually set up collision volumes for
everybody but we should we have a flag
that says whether things participating
collisions so there's no reason not to
have a collision volume on something
because we can use it for our own
queries like we're doing now so we don't
really want to ever have anyone who
doesn't have a collision volume
initialized like if you're 0 0 0 that's
not good we should bound whatever your
area is somehow right but anyway so this
is effectively all we would need
assuming that we start cleaning the rest
of this collision stuff up where we can
essentially say look if whatever the
entity is that we're looking at here
I guess actually this just normally gets
these calls it's weird because entity
overlaps rectangle it doesn't actually
get an entity passed so that's really
actually just doing the volume check to
see the if these intersections occur
right so what I think that means is we
can just pass those down right so we can
just say look here's the the the
collision volume in the end of EP and
then here is the bounds and if if that
overlap happens then there was something
there so we would return true in this
case okay so that's more or less all
we're talking about and again there's
just there's sort of like the old
collision stuff flying that now we
probably want to go in there and
actually get that collision stuff
whipped into shape and make sure we have
collision farms or anything we can draw
them today and make sure that they all
do stuff as well um so here what I want
to do is say well we've got this world
position we don't care about that we can
just do where that action we can
actually just create sort of the
location of that thing in the in the
space of the region itself I'll be
honest I don't actually even know why
that's there if we look at place entity
I don't know why we're using world
positions because we don't actually need
it in fact you can see right here us
actually doing the subtraction in the
first place
so again a lot of stuff eligible for
cleanup here as we start to move down
and clean up how the entity stuff is
working we should be able to kind of get
rid of a lot of this busy work because
we don't actually need to be working in
terms of world position where we kind of
inherited that from the fact that we
used to generate stuff that way but none
of this stuff is necessary all you would
need to know is
where your corner world position was and
then all of this stuff would just be
based off of that right so this is all
stupid and we don't really need to do it
it's just coming at everything
completely backwards and so we probably
want to stop working with these I mean
right here we could probably just say to
do Casey now that we edit in similar
region space there is no reason for all
this world position nonsense right
because world positions actually they're
just a storage format and since we're
only creating like a local region at any
given time we don't ever need to talk
about them they're really something that
only has to occur when you go to like
pack the world back for storage so that
you can have huge worlds without
floating-point precision issues but we
don't need to talk about them here
they're just kind of a waste of time and
we should probably just stop using them
but anyway that's fine this same code
would work just fine right so we can say
like look the location of this thing is
it's pretty straightforward anyway it
would just look like this and that would
allow us to say okay now we know what
the actual you know position of this
thing is and so at that point if we know
this the query region part here and the
cube key thing here now we can make cube
P and P kind of work together and say
all right the rectangle
all right rather the query region here
just needs to be offset by this position
and we're good to go
so we can say like offset this thing by
this and that's you know gonna give us
the location that we actually need so I
think that properly produces everything
but yeah I'm not 100% sure let's start
by calling it and we'll sort of look
into how it's actually working
my biggest thing that we probably want
to focus on now
although we could go ahead and fix this
whole part about using world positions
for no reason that's probably a good
thing to do maybe we'll do that tomorrow
but this call right here again is the
biggest thing I think we'll start to
focus on because we want to start making
the sim region be more powerful and not
have to loop over all these entities all
the time to answer simple questions we
want to have a good spatial query system
in there so that's probably another
thing we'll focus on so going into the
sim region actually sorry going into the
world Jen first we need to actually tell
it to generate some of these aprons
right now we've never requested any so
you know if I go to like the orphanage
for example um what we haven't done
right now know what this is talking
about I thought we already did that
delete that because since I don't know
what it means it can't really help us um
in here right when we generate all these
room specs what we want to do is say
well let's go ahead and make sure that
these specs actually have apron specs
where they need to right so if I said
Jen apron spec
and I make one of these then what I can
do is say alright all of these things
that that we created here right maybe I
want to do that
now it could be that really I would like
to be able to make it a little simpler
so since that's something that we
probably put on a lot of things maybe
I'll just make that be part of the Jen's
backhaul so when we make one of these
you can optionally pass like hey I want
this apron here
no I'm saying and then that should
probably sufficient so if we go to the
gemspec call when we create one of these
things I should be able to do like a Jen
aprons Beck call here right
and so we here where we create one of
these if you want to pass an apron spec
to it it'll automatically put it in
there for you but like you don't have to
and then in here we would just say okay
when you create one of these gets
initialized to zero and off you go
I think that would do it don't quote me
on that though and I think
I think that's it and that should just
start calling the apron generator and
the a breeze in our values won't work
properly yet because I don't really
think that that collude that overlap
call is correct so I think we're
probably like over generating stuff now
but you can see like what I was trying
to do already like you see how there's
like now there's you know grass tiles
out there that's what I want right I
wanted grass tiles and hopefully you
know now you can't really get to places
and you know I don't know if eight was
enough but hopefully now you you know
you've always got these sort of grassy
grassy bits there and that way you can
kind of see yeah you can just you can
just always see something outside the
place where you are which is the goal so
again I suspect probably what's
happening though is we're generating way
too many of them like I suspected even
though you can't see it we're probably
generating ones underneath like here
maybe I don't really know maybe our
collision call is actually working I
doubt it but that's all I wanted you can
sort of see how now it looks like
there's stuff outside of the world area
which is what I wanted when we come down
here right the dungeon areas don't have
aprons associated with them so you can
see that they're not getting any which
is exactly what I wanted so that's good
so all of this looks fine that seems
good and yeah like you can see that the
apron is exactly what I wanted which is
eight wide around everything that may be
overkill I'm not sure and I guess I'll
be honest I I don't really see much over
generation there although well there I
do see some right so it's generating
multiple things around that so basically
the apron at the very least it's not
picking up its own stuff right
probably because these cube pieces don't
have collision geometry associated with
them right
so there's actually lots of aprons tiles
probably stacked on top of each other
here what I could do is draw the cubes
as outlines to see that as well which I
think we might want to do but let me
just kind of play with this a little bit
first
so yeah let's suppose in fact maybe I
don't look at this so in here right when
we're doing place entity we're really
not doing anything to give this thing a
collision region and so if I did want to
give it a collision region for the cube
what I would want to do is yeah if we
look at the way those entities have
collision volumes set up what we could
see in here is probably that there's
just one collision volume rectangle yeah
I and so you just set whatever the
volume is this thing is supposed to
occupy and that's what we're gonna be
colliding it against for something like
this it means that anytime in here that
we add an entity we need to actually set
whatever that collision volume is going
to be if you look in here when we create
sort of the entity we don't give it a
collision volume anywhere for these
ground tiles
I don't think let me take a quick look
to make sure I'm not wrong about that
but if I
yeah I mean you can see that we don't we
don't do anything with the collision
volumes there right so I think what we
want to do is just set a collision
volume here that we can see and that
would hopefully also give us the ability
to verify if there weren't multiple
things in one like on top of each other
so let me first add them to try and
prevent aprons from being generated on
top of themselves and then we'll add
them for the main ones as well I think
that's mostly what we want to do so when
we have the entity here and we're gonna
sort of place it down I think all I
should have to do for the apron part of
things is just say well we just said
what it's you know rectangle was it's
this and so if that's all we need we
should be able to just pass that down as
the collision volume right and we can
start to clean this up a little bit more
as we go what's here so now these things
each of these things should have
collision volumes I'll be honest the
fact that they're not being drawn
doesn't fill me with confidence that may
just because they don't participate in
collision
let's take a look so you can see here
that we switch on whether or not the
entity has a collision volume that has
any volume to it and then we just set
the color based on whether or not it
collides but we should be pushing a
volume outlined here based on the entity
location and the collision volume so you
would assume that we would therefore see
collision volumes for all of these apron
entities right
and yet I don't and I suppose you can
you can see that it's not working either
because they're not yeah they're not
actually climbing sure so I'm not sure
why this wouldn't be making them all
show up that way I'm not just I'm have
to step into that and see because I
don't have any idea why why that
wouldn't give us right because the only
I don't see anything else here other
than just checking if the collision
volume has area which it would seem like
it would have to
although actually I guess there is one
reason why it wouldn't which is this
makes it smaller than itself so let's
try this as unwise as this may be i'ma
turn off cube rendering entirely and see
what I can see there right okay so
that's all it was it's just that they're
kind of you know you can't see them
because they're inside right and so now
if we look I think this is actually
working just fine because what you can
see is that when it goes to check the
volume to see if it should play
something there it will stack more than
one on top of itself if they can fit
right so I think all we have to do there
is just make sure that when we query
that we shouldn't use the same query
region as the collision region so I
think what we want to do here is say
like collision region equals this right
and so we use the collision region to
create the thing but then the query
region should actually be like something
that's taller and extends more like it
has different Z bounds than this does
right and so maybe it's something like
yeah maybe it's something like weari
region
Maxie is like quite a bit larger or
something just to make sure it can pick
up anything in that area right I don't
know if I did that correctly
looks pretty good well does it actually
no it doesn't
No No maybe it does it's hard to read
when you only see that part of it let's
take a look here
so there you can see that it still
doesn't seem to be working properly
there right because it should never be
able to do that because the query region
should have been much taller
hmm well temporarily show me what the
query region actually is why don't you
so that's not as high as I thought it
was it still should have prevented any
of those double additions though I would
think and I definitely saw yeah like I
thought worse I thought I saw a double
audition
let's move outward from here
all right
maybe I didn't I don't see any now which
is weird
maybe I was hallucinating and that we
did fix it always makes me a little bit
nervous though if I think I saw a bug
and I don't see a bug I think it's just
hiding so it may be that adding the
coalition volume as the query region and
thus expanding it is what actually
allows it to work properly so it could
be that actually when you have one of
the full regions and one of the other
ones it can stack I guess that makes
sense because if you yeah you could
stack on top of each other if you don't
provide that sort of extra collision so
I suppose that would make sense so I
don't know how I feel about that if that
was the case you know yeah we would need
something like this right we would need
to expand it more I don't know if that's
a good idea
I feel like there's reasons why it might
not be but maybe that's the right maybe
that's the right solution for now I'm
not sure so I think that probably gives
us mostly what we want and I think now
we've gotten rid of most of those double
editions
I think so anyway alright so if I was to
go ahead and turn off volume rendering
for now we should we should put some
debug switches in so we can just turn
these on and off without recompiling
because you know they're pretty common
things that we do um so yeah like if we
look now I think we've pretty much got
in it under control like how we would
add the stuff for the apron and that's
really all I wanted with something along
those lines right and you know we should
probably have them be we should probably
get the colors under control so that the
apron colors match the colors otherwise
for the most part so I'm kind of
interested in that so you can see it
looks like the query to test to see
whether or not there was any occupying
people like the fact that there was
stuff under there made it so that it
didn't fill and that was kind of what I
was worried about and so I think that
means our query might be like wrong you
know I'm saying it's it's picking up
stuff from lower let's take a look at
what those query regions actually look
like well that won't help us but yeah
let's let's rerun it and see what those
look like so that we can get a sense for
what it's actually picking up there ah
you know what it is picking up it's
picking up the room that's what it's
picking up so we can probably get rid of
that because it's not a real entity in
that sense but you can see why this is
kind of a delicate process right so we
want yet but but that's if when we do
that entity query here we can just say
look if it's a room if it's the room
you're talking about we don't really
care about
that why is that chump failing dump two
overlapping entities exist why is it
going there that's really weird
I mean I guess it's nearby to it but not
really anyway so in here we want to do
like if it's a not a room right we don't
want to use like those kind of volume
queries what we could do is have a flag
for this as well we're we're just saying
look is this a an entity that doesn't
occupy space you know that isn't
relevant right and I'm not sure how we
want to necessarily treat that but if we
look at how we do room stuff in general
you can see it's it's really just this
special query here we may want to do
something like this
so we'll just make a way of testing that
here like this
and then we can say like oh well if it's
a room do this thing
and so then I think we'll start to get
into issues that we would have to
address there in fact you can kind of
see exactly what our what our problem is
now so now we have the issue of the room
area doesn't prevent us from creating
stuff inside there right so maybe this
was a bad idea
and so we can fix that in one of two
ways I'm just trying to side which way
uh what's going on here maybe oh we may
have just overflowed our actual output
buffer there so looking at that I guess
I'd uh you know I guess I really don't
want that I do want the room be able to
do it but the problem is I need to make
sure that I don't look I don't look too
far down into where that other room
would be and I'm not sure how to manage
those two concerns right but this gives
us a really nice thing that keeping it
out of the room was actually good
because not only did it prevent us from
having to deal with any of the other
minutiae but it means like stairwells
and stuff where there wouldn't be things
the room boundary prevents you from from
filling that in as well which I want and
so I'm just not sure how to deal with
the query otherwise what is what is this
what is happening here we've got to wear
it we're too many for one dispatch when
we're doing our push quads here right so
it's like somehow this thing is not
correctly anticipating how many of these
things are going to come down to break
the batch up because right like here's
base index and well I guess I can't do
it because we're in in release mode but
you can see what this this is an
assertion here that's saying I need to
be able to fit my vertex base into a
16-bit value because if I can't we won't
be able to use just 16-bit virtus 16-bit
vertex indices
in order to do it which is all we're
using right now so this is like
overflowing the number of these that
we're actually creating that's a bug
because inside the renderer we were
supposed to create new batches every
time we overflowed that number and so
that's a little bit weird and I'm not
sure why we were getting that I want to
say that we did that but maybe we didn't
know it's right here so match max quads
per batch is supposed to be checked here
where we say however many quads you were
going to do had better not be greater
than the number maximum number that you
can have right so the fact that that's
not working is not reassuring let me go
ahead and build a debug build so that we
can take a look at why that's not
working because that's kind of important
and we don't really want that to be a
lurking bug because you'll get render
artifacts if you if not right okay so I
guess all I did was kind of hop out
towards the other part here right like
somewhere and so looking at this you can
see even do Zack what I said right we
ended up in a place where are we just
have pushed too many of these what I
don't understand is when we in this
function looked at the number of quads
we were pushing down I'm just wondering
I guess we well you know the thing is
we're not actually calling get current
Claud so who who was responsible for
that call
pushing line segments on here
well can't say it wasn't pretty
straightforward like it's basically
saying make sure we have room for six
quads does that look like six squads to
you no it does not case anyone was
wondering that is something we actually
call 12 which is related to six but it's
not six so I think that's probably all
we're dealing with there is failure to
reserve a place to actually dump those
vertices not our finest hour
yeah all right and Sue back to the
original problem I just don't know how I
want to make sure I get information
about things occupying the bottom I
here's here's the way I think I want to
do it I think what I want to do is take
a different approach let's suppose that
what we actually want here is when we
produce this query region here what I
want to do is not offset the query
region Z wise pop probably at all so
what I want to do I think is something
more along the lines of get rid of this
stuff that's gone when we produce this
we want to make sure the Z is like flat
so yeah this should be fine and this
maybe is that something like this
probably makes a little bit more sense
to me at the moment let's take a look at
this and then we can play with this a
little bit separately all right so if I
run this you can see that everything's
flat now right and hopefully that means
that now it will correctly avoid rooms
where rooms are but not where rooms
aren't maybe and we'll see whether
that's true or not not quite
and you can see why that is so those are
flat and there right so they need to be
lifted up because these are to load down
to you can actually see so yeah we just
want to make sure we're careful about
our placement here I guess is how this
wants to work
so yeah
I guess we just want the world Peas
offset Z to be half the wall height to
place it at the right location and
that's it
is this correctly aligned now
no it's still too low down you can see
it cooks down into the bottom room so
what is going on here how can we don't
know like where our floor is and stuff
like something's busted we should figure
out what's going on here because this
doesn't really make much sense to me
like we know what the bottom part of the
room is like somebody's creating this
room like here's the room volume in
question right we've got the volume for
the room is the main room P max room P
which is created like this way and I
feel like this stuff is just all kind of
sloppy but I mean we want these things
to be lying directly on the floor area
so that they're contained within the
room that they're supposed to be a
pronoun not contained within the room
but at the same level as the room
they're supposed to be apron a right I
mean that's what we would expect and so
that just seems kind of busted and weird
and I don't like it so what I would
prefer here is yeah if this was just if
this was just more sane the way this is
currently working looks like if you
place something for whatever reason at
the floor Z if you play something at a
floor at a Z of zero it's still it's too
low so it needs to be up like half a
tile dim or something I don't quite get
it I feel like I want to how much time
how much time do I have what am i got i
got 25 minutes let's say baby
uh I want to clean this up so that we
have some idea of where everything's
going so I think I'm gonna make that be
what our job is now cuz I think that's
the only thing that's actually standing
in our way here and I don't like the way
this looks so I think part as part of
that too getting these world positions
out of here would be a good good start
alright so let's think about this a
little bit differently what I want to do
is I want to I want to take a look at
these room volumes right and so if we
take a look at where these room volumes
are and I look at how things are
arranged in the room volumes you can see
there that we've got that offset I
believe what that offset was designed to
do is to give us a safe region right so
everything's like comes up off of the
bottom of that room floor right and soo
I'm guessing and I guess I don't know
but I'm guessing that the best the best
way to or the best rule of thumb to
follow here would be to when we create
an edit region that a Z of 0 is the
floor is not the floor is the the bottom
the base the the lowest part of the room
volume is 0 right and so yet you know if
we were to do that and in here you know
we look at how we're doing this this
stuff here with the change Center right
all that stuff so if we wanted to make 0
be the bottom when we get back this
right we would just save 0 lies along
the bottom of the thing that means that
when we record the volume of the actual
room which is here this would not we
don't need these two things really right
and what we want to do instead is talk
about it like in here right
fact we could just say look the min room
P Z is always zero right just to give
you some example of what I'm talking
about there so let's suppose that we
said something like that where is that
actually lying right now
right and it looks like that's what
we're doing right because that looks
like it's basically the same place that
it was so I think if we just always say
that zero and let's take a look out here
where we've got multiple levels and make
sure that that still does make sense but
I think it should because again this
placement is all relative to a
simulation region and so if I come out
here and say you know where is
everything
it still looks correct to me there right
we've got the room sort of stacked up
and you know that that all looks
plausible right so let's just work
backwards from there and like create the
actual room area in like a more sensible
way so the first thing you wanna do is
I'm gonna pull this stuff up to the top
right so I'm gonna take this and I'm
gonna pull this up here so we can work
with it all together so we've got this
sort of thing that like cracks this
stuff out and says hey here's the room
volume and all that garbage so let's
take a look at stuff like the tile game
and all that that stuff - right all
right so here we go so if we know that
the if we know that the minimum Z is
zero then we also know that the maximum
Z right we can work backwards here and
say well that the maximum is just gonna
be however high the thing was times the
tile dim right I mean that's the height
of the thing so we know that just going
into it there's nothing particularly
tricky about that similarly if we wanted
to get the bounds of the thing we should
be able to do the same thing in Reverse
for everything right so if we
this was going to be the center of the
thing that we were working on then we
should be able to figure out the bounds
of everything else by just using you
know the same math if we know that we're
gonna start at the min tile X plus the X
count over 2 then we should be able to
just say well however much the you know
however much the X count needs to be to
get out to half way is what we would
need right it'd be like 0.5 times the X
count times the tiled M X right is how
wide the room should be and similarly
the same thing would be true in Y right
and the max room P is just the same as
the opposite of the min room P so
there's really nothing we you know fancy
about that right and so these two things
can actually just be created whole cloth
they don't really need to operate on
they don't need to be mapped into a
chunk space or any of that garbage and I
don't think we need any of this stuff
either because we can apply those
directly so we wanted this 1/2 tile dim
here as an offset so we sort of wanted
to say it looks like anyway that we're
like 1/2 tile over and I believe that
that's probably that's probably for this
garbage right which again we can now I
think hopefully maybe sort of I'm not
sure but let's pretend possibly that we
can if we just said let's do this
correctly so this part here where we do
like chunk position from tile position
and we're like let's get ourselves here
if this this part here whether this is
an even division or an odd division is
going to control like where we are
alignment wise which is kind of annoying
right we have here this is
dimensions and in fact we you know we're
computing it you can see right here
we're computing exactly how big we want
our region pretty exactly here we can
just even get that from them from these
two values eventually if you want to or
we can even do this a little more you
know what I mean we can just do this
right so we can just say look here's the
room dimensions it's this so the min
room P is just gonna be created off of
the room dimensions or maybe we maybe
we've and just use that as the way we
map things in in fact why wouldn't we
that makes way more sense because then
that essentially means all we have to do
is this
right if we just say instead of the
chain Center here what if we just said
look give us the world position of the
min world P this is like the min corner
and then we would know what the min room
P was here
well I guess technically no we can't do
that because we do want to offset it we
do want to get to you know we we do want
to start in the middle of the room so I
suppose there is no real way to do what
I'm talking about yeah so we do kind of
have to do something where we actually
find out what that is so oh well anyway
um so if we assume again that we're
gonna place this at the center so the
sim region is centered on the room and
that's zero but not in Z Z it's at the
actual floor so if we do something along
those lines and then here we say okay
let's go ahead and take the oh but you
know what we don't have to Center it we
could choose not to do that because
since we can pass a change rectangle and
that rectangle doesn't have to be zero
centered I guess we can just do what I
was going to say so actually you could
make this be just this right we say look
that's what we're gonna base everything
around here's the room dimension the min
room P therefore is always just zero
zero zero because that's where that part
of the chain Center is the max room P
therefore is just the rim dimensions
right because we go from zero to two the
room dimensions done right
then when we say what the change
rectangle is all we're saying is maybe
rect min/max where we've got the min
room P and the max room P and if we want
to add some additional area to that we
can just say all right well why don't
you just add to that something whatever
the you know amount is that we want
there right so maybe we want to say
let's add four tiles in any direction I
don't know probably not just one tile in
any direction should be sufficient right
because we don't really do anything
beyond that so maybe like one tile in
any direction is fine not sure we can
think about that a little bit harder
later but this is the change rectangle
and then off we go so then we can just
say like change I'm going to call this
change base P and change volume okay
maybe not that's a function apparently
so I think that all works pretty well
and I think probably that's all we
really need there and I don't know what
this dim Xyz nonsense is there oh it's
just thick it bit dim for this room
that's fine all right so I think we're
getting closer here to what I actually
want and now we're we've got the min
room P and the maximum P let's see where
we're at compile error wise and I'm
gonna start to clean this stuff up the
change Center what is this Oh placing an
entity so when we place the entity for
the collision volume where we've got the
rect min max min rim P maximum P chain
Center I guess we can do that cuz I
guess there's no reason not to it's a
little weird it means that that is not a
centered collision volume but I guess we
don't care that that isn't a central
collision volume don't know all right so
anyway yeah and now we can see what the
half rectangle issue was there right so
because those are centered the half rect
bit slides it as an offset because we
want everything to be on the boundary
right so this half that's what the half
tyldum displacement was before however
there's an open question in my mind as
to whether or not we really want that to
be the case like if we think about it do
we really need those to be centered
positions anyway maybe we want them to
be I don't know but anyway when we look
at how we're doing this this this stuff
could go away right we don't use that
anymore
where that's getting used Oh what are we
using world rooms for anything by the
way I think we're using those for maps
but that's fine and so what we really
want here we we don't really need these
for anything other than just like mapped
into chunk space and so what we want to
do is just be able to pass that yeah so
we've got our world and our base pose
and our offset but we don't really need
oh I guess we do so the min room and the
max room values that we created here in
the minimum maximum peak we need those
to be mapped into chunk space and those
would be based just off the sim region
Center so the world position would be
the change base P like so I think that's
all we actually need there yeah so
that's all fine we don't really use
those at the moment anyway so then we
really just have that offset to deal
with and so when we create our our
change base P here I guess what we want
to do is like the chunk position from
tabs
oops
the additional offset part we just need
to pass the half tile dim down so I
think that's it and then I think we're
good to go
so now all those rooms are tightly
bounded I believe and so hopefully
that's lo good so moving along to phase
two uh so you know the mint ilex part of
things I want to look now and see does
that actually yeah like like what's all
this garbage and why are we doing all
this stuff so it looks like mostly yeah
like what we're doing here is using this
for a way of checking the gen grids
which is honestly okay I mean it's not
horrible but I'm not sure we really want
to keep that stuff around
like it'd be nice if we could do this a
little bit more structured here
yeah
I don't know I'm still not quite loving
it uh so floor tiles II what is that
what are we doing with that it's just
min tiles II so I'm not sure why we're
actually calling it that
I guess as if the floor could be
somewhere else yeah I don't know uh
let's I guess do some of the more basic
stuff first so if we actually want this
to just be normal stuff this jug
position from tile position stuff again
we shouldn't really need to do anything
with that really we should be able to do
something more like this we just say
look the position of this thing is
actually not related to any of that
stuff instead we can just say like the
position of any one of these things is
just the tile dim x times the X index
plus the tyldum Y times the Y index
right and that's all we really needed we
don't really need anything else about it
that you know that just tells us where
the thing is and then as we go through
the rest of this code wherever we were
doing stuff like setting the offset or
nonsense like that we should be able to
now just just talk about this directly
like so and when we place entities we
shouldn't have to use world positions at
all then either right so when we
actually call a place entity called like
this we should be able to make that use
raw raw code now right
yeah I don't know where are those other
place entity calls what did those what
are those doing but those are those are
ones that aren't actually working very
fine is so you know this sort of stuff
right in fact we could just say like
that just goes away and so now instead
of calling place entity you just assign
the position you actually want to the
thing and that's all you had to do
because that's all you should really
have to do right you shouldn't have to
do anything more complicated than that
so let's take a look here at here we go
so this PZ is just that and this place
entity is just any P equals right so
that then that should be all you have to
actually do and again just trying to get
rid rid of some of this nonsense so it's
not all up in the way okay so this is
this I don't know why I treated that
like some kind of vector equation it's
not and I think that's all we need for
that one we should have gotten a error
on our other place anybody call yeah
there it is so looking at place entity
here there's also presumably on the
enemy gen code there's a place under the
definition somewhere I don't actually
know if that's true let's take a look
[Music]
is so if I just remove that and so
people are not calling place entity
anymore
we should get errors I mean place that's
actually called so you can see in here
we've got this place in a teepee
nonsense I'm assuming that that's yeah
it's doing a bunch of garbage like to
create that P in the first place so
rather than doing that now we should be
able to just say hey like where is that
thing and we're done
right and again this is just trying to
clean up all that old sort of vestigial
remain nonsense and so now you can just
say alright the glove P is P the head P
is P and the body P is P right and we're
gonna have to do that for a couple
things right cuz that's just this was
again just sort of an overhang from when
this this was more annoying and
confusing so it's really just this stuff
we don't need you to pass a P to these
these aren't even called I don't know
why I'm doing this but you know heck
it's so simple there's no reason not to
leave them in working order
okay so then we've got two more here you
can see this one using the change base P
we don't actually needed to do that
because we did them in room P max room P
it means that this entity doesn't need
to be placed putting it at zero zero
zeros actually where it should go so
technically you know but just to keep
the code like correctly semantically
doing what it should do I'm gonna assign
min room P to it here it just happens to
be zero zero zero that way if we change
it in the future we weren't like setting
a little landmine for ourselves it can't
hurt so then coming through here we can
now get rid of this sort of part of the
process and we can probably make this
stuff something that we we share as a
call but as you can see this is not
going to fly here now what I could do
obviously just temporarily is to say
that the
NEP equals you know this because we do
create an actual p-value so I can do
that and that should just still work but
again we want to continue the
simplification process here and get it
down to something that you know is
cleaner than that right all right
so looking at me it looks like we still
have that half offset there that which
means I must have accidentally yeah
shifted the placement of these over you
can actually see that these are still
placed properly because they're using
the old code and this is not right
these are shifted relative to where they
should be which is kind of funny so we
want these things to line up so let's
just double check where I messed that up
and correct it so here in the generate
room call where we get the base P this
negative half tyldum should have
Alliance I thought it did when we
checked it so I wonder if I by assigning
the P values directly in here I wonder
if this is somehow off oh I guess that's
true so the fact that this is using the
half tile dim slid over it means that
where we placed the entities will be
slid half dim over as well so I guess
what you want to do is offset these guys
by the half tile dim right so I don't
know which one you want to do because
you can write it either way either you
can place these guys off on the half
tile dim or you can place this off on a
half tile dim and and I guess the back
means you really just don't need this
right because you're gonna have to have
this be staggered by a half damn
relative to where you're saying things
are so I'm not really sure how what the
cleanest way to represent that
fact is right hmm that's kind of
interesting one right I mean because
because effectively what we're doing
when we create the sim region is we're
creating a local coordinate system that
we're performing all of our edits in and
so if we shift the local coordinate
system by if the local coordinate system
and the room are both at zero zero then
that means in order to place the
boundary or the entities when we place
those things they have to be offset from
each other by one half tile dim it
doesn't matter who you offset you could
offset the room boundary by a half tile
dim or you could offset the entities by
half tile dim and just because it seems
like you place entities more right I
wonder if we want to do this and say
that look we're just gonna place things
at like min tile X Y Z whatever that's
our basis and then when we create them
in room P it's actually min room P we
will change that to be negative half
tile dim right and then you know go from
min room P to the room Jim to create the
dimension of the actual room I don't
know what I think of that but that's
more what I want it looks like I'm still
though wait a minute
I'm still getting an error there
the changebase pee is still coming from
here so that should be correct the half
tile DIMM should be back that seems
correct doesn't it
so that was slightly nonsensical what
was happening there let me just
double-check where I actually placed the
collision volume here so it's a
recommend max of min room P to max room
P that seems correct oh no it's not
correct so again this should just always
be at zero zero zero because the
collision volume is taking this into
account so there's two ways we can do it
right we can pass min room P max room P
here and zero zero zero here or we can
pass min room P here and just actually
pass the room dimension as the collision
volume routed at zero zero zero I don't
know again six of one half dozen of the
other don't know that there's a correct
answer but that all seems good now and I
think I'll leave it at that for today
but well maybe I won't maybe this should
be changed now to do it to sort of link
those two together so if you take a look
at what's going on here right again
I'm not sure I want to push a little
further into this so maybe I will stop
and we'll pick this up tomorrow but just
looking at how this is working right I
still don't love the fact that we asked
questions about the global tile x y&amp;z
here I almost want to say this this
stuff should be these volumes should be
mapped into the local space and we
should be doing the test there but you
know I have mixed feelings about it
let's put it that way
mm-hmm yeah I don't know so let's take a
look at where half table dim is used at
all so it's really only there so what I
might want to do is something more like
this and just get rid of this
and then yeah like this stuff I feel
like we don't really need the X count by
count Z count necessarily to like that
can just come into here because I don't
think you know that's what the dim was
supposed to be so I mean I feel like we
should be able to do like right so maybe
we could do something more like this
just again to sort of simplify it down a
little bit
something like that
can't we just do get a look isn't there
just a get volume call like tell me how
how big this thing is volumetrically I
feel like there should be a way to to
just ask that of the gen math thing
itself
so yeah I don't see it but I'm gonna add
it so in here we'll just say hey I want
to know what this total volume is
actually please and so we'll just do the
results is actually so get total volume
can just take a v3 actually should be
able take a gen v3 right I would think
and then that that you could choose to
call if you wanted to the get volume
first on it or not so it's more or less
just that so I think that in here we can
just say yeah get the total volume for
the tile count and that'll just return
that value which is what we want and
then I can get rid of the rest of these
here so where is dim their grid dim
equals PI outs and that's tile count X Y
just keep that a little bit closer
bundles
you're more of those you know this one I
feel like we should just be passing the
dim there if we'd go to get camera
offset z4 dim in here I kind of feel
like I want to do something more like
you Passage env3 to this well although
does this get used in other places now
it does and I think that you'd want to
know the Z here anyway and so that's
probably something that that wants to be
looked at anyway so I think we'll
probably want to pass that
okay so again a little more cleaned up
still you know could could stand to use
I could I could more one more time
through probably looking at this so
let's see
[Music]
and yeah the mint I'll stuff could
probably be stand to be collapsed as
well you know I'm not sure if the Jen
math code has a get min in it I mean
it's just dot min so not really
particularly exciting but right it's
just this so I don't know I mean I could
yeah I could just do that right I could
just say like it's the room right
and then maybe that's a little bit
cleaner there too so that we're just
we're not like spamming out these local
variables for no particular reason
furthermore this call for the base P I
feel like that is a good candidate for
for taking a gen v3 as well because
chunk position from tile position is
really not something that should be
happening in the game it's strictly that
the tiles the game doesn't care about
tiles at all the game's completely free
form so you don't have to be on a grid
for any particular reason so I feel like
that's something that wants to be sort
of in the world gen stuff anyway you can
see that it is right so I feel like that
sort of wants to take a Gen V 3 because
that's what you're normally gonna have
right I want to say and if you don't
have one you could just get one another
way to say it would be let's provide
both right I mean why not so then we
could just say if you pass a Gen V 3
then we just
give the call and that way we don't have
to worry about passing these things
separately so we can just say like mint
Isle and and go similarly change based P
now in theory really shouldn't probably
be getting used much at all we can
almost remove it if we have a if if this
this world room stuff is sort of for
adding Maps later right what's just
provisional but we probably do want to
keep it I think we probably will need it
so I'm not gonna eliminate the change
based P yet I'll leave it on there but
otherwise yeah mint I'll can now be
represented as just a dot access or like
so and that should be fine looking at
this you could almost see like this
stuff could probably be treated as a
vector now as a gender III as well so we
may want to do that too but you know off
we go all right so I'm gonna kick cuz
they're that done for now
I took the extra 15 minutes that we
technically should have had because I
think the clock didn't actually I didn't
actually start the clock on time I
started early but I think we're all good
now and we've got the aprons in there
the way I want so I'm pretty pleased
with that what I wanted you tomorrow is
like clean up the way that we're
generating those volumes so that this
part works so I'm going to leave that
for tomorrow and also maybe tomorrow
we'll add the ability to like you know I
want to fix that problem right I also
don't know why are those double stacked
like that what's happening there oh
that's just this room boundary drawing
across
and also maybe we'll go in and put some
trees into the apron just to finish that
off and make sure all that kind of
garbage works so I think we're all good
now we probably have to you know change
from clearing to gray to clearing to
black at least in release mode because
again I'm underneath we kind of want
that to be true
so we'll sort of work on that stuff
we'll cross that bridge when we come to
it but I'm really after that we'll go to
a brief Q&amp;A for anybody who has
questions
why have a separate apron concept
instead of just generating rooms on the
sides well so what I tend not to do and
you know I I don't feel strongly about
this so I'm not trying to say that it's
some kind of like a programming
guideline but just it's my personal
preference is if I'm mentally thinking
about two things as being separate I
tend to write them separate in the code
at least at first and then if it becomes
overwhelmingly obvious to me later that
they're the same
I will merge them but I don't usually
start with them merged the reason for
that is I feel like when code is written
for a specific purpose it tends to end
up being more clean and so I usually
like to see if I like to look at what
the clean version looks like first and
then later decide to merge two things if
I think it won't affect the complexity
too much rather than a priori saying
look the areas outside rooms and the
areas inside rooms are similar so let me
just make one generator that generates
both I'm sort of pre assuming that I
know the answer to the question is that
they are sufficiently similar to not
make the code be unnecessarily
complicated and hard to read for either
one right so really that that is the
reason so we may end up collapsing
aprons and rooms into the same thing in
the future but we will make that
decision based on seeing if it really
makes sense right
we'll a pristine underground and ground
level only or will you have sky aprons
for upper levels like in the case of a
tall tower you could have clouds or
birch or something might look neat with
multiple layers thicker clouds as you
climb I had not thought about that but I
agree with you if we ever do make like a
tower area which seems kind of fun we
could make some clouds out there I don't
know to what extent that would be based
on a printing but it seems reasonable to
do that as an apron sure
how to link a third-party library like
GL fw3 lib any suggestions on where to
read about it um I guess I I want to say
we covered this in handmade hero
actually if you look for it using the
episode guide but I guess I don't know
that that was the case since we don't
use libraries on the stream you know
it's possible that I never really talked
about it but I thought I did
at some point whoops I didn't want Hamid
Khan so in here you know like
[Music]
I don't know I thought we'd I did like a
stream it wasn't a main stream it was
like a chat stream oh you know what
though image chat
I want to say that I covered it on this
stream here this is the one I was
thinking of on how library linking works
I'm not 100% sure because we were
talking about some other things but I
think that's what I would say
environment is very sterile because all
place that are gonna be seen be snap to
grid maybe very the offset randomly from
the tile Center also the random height
difference between floor tile could be
severely reduced who made that flooring
if the hazard I'm not really super
concerned with that stuff at the moment
because that's gonna be more like polish
work as to how we want to make that
stuff up here but the world is supposed
to look a little bit grid like like
that's the style because you
specifically have to think about grid
squares as you'll kind of see as we go
further into the game so we really don't
want it to look like a continuum it's
supposed to look kind of gridded or at
least QB right well you also replace X
hand with DMX in the generate apron
function yes what I'd like to do is in
the generate apron function maybe and
like I said maybe we'll do this tomorrow
I'd like to make those two now share a
like creation call for making the region
and getting back the the values so we'll
probably try to do that tomorrow so
they'll work similarly
Oh have you ever used Sony SN Systems
debugger for PlayStation 3 someone on
him a network called it the best of ever
they'd ever used but didn't really go
into detail that what it did right um
yeah so I have used s n systems I don't
remember if it was on the PlayStation 3
though probably wasn't on the
PlayStation 3 actually because I believe
SN system shipped debuggers for more
platforms than just that one I just
fundamentally don't remember it III just
don't I'm sorry I mean there definitely
we definitely had those at rad we had a
couple SN systems things at rad I want
to say over the years but I just I don't
remember them at all let's it's been too
long and it wasn't a primary thing that
I used I didn't do very much PlayStation
work pretty much ever it's never been a
primary thing that I've been working on
so
have you ever have you had any
unpleasant experience with the debugging
on Linux yes all experiences debugging
on Linux are unpleasant it's it's an
unpleasant debugging environment it's
one of the reasons I don't use it was
the old dune 2 game may using GTI or
OpenGL are you sure it was on Windows I
mean it would have been direct draw if
it was on Windows so the answer is
neither of those two things but GDI more
closely however I don't know
are you sure that dune 2 wasn't DOS I
don't know I never had do two so I have
no idea what it was yeah doom 2 is das
so it's it's using mode 13 probably take
a look yes thank you for the add Google
stadia I mean as do they play now I have
YouTube red on my actual machine so I
don't see this nonsense alright so here
if this is if we assume this if this is
the if this is what we're talking about
like I said I never had this game so I
have no idea if this is the game we're
talking about I mean just looking at it
I I'm gonna go out and women just say
it's probably DOS mode 13
so you know I don't really want to go
into a lot of detail about what this is
but effectively what happened was on old
pcs when you were in you know when you
were just booting into ms-dos and the
system bios was how you interface with
the graphics driver well for the well
there's no graph driver with the
graphics card effectively you could
create an interrupt and I don't remember
what the interrupt was let's see if
they've got yeah okay so it's in ten
which would be called this which is
sixteen right its hexadecimal so it's in
ten H which would be the sixteen
interrupts sixteen when you execute that
interrupts the processor just looks to
see if you've set al to thirteen and a
hex and aged to zero and if you did it
put you into I want to say 320 by 240 by
eight bits no 320 by 208 bits so it's
320 by 208 bits and the eight bits so
each pixel is a byte and the bite was
just an index into a pallet so you had
20 56 palette entries nobody used the
default so you would set them yourself
to whatever the colors are that you
wanted and then you just wrote into the
graphics memory aperture which was I
want to say like oh X a thousand
[Music]
that now that was probably monochrome oh
no I'm right there it is it's a thousand
and but it was double buffered right
wasn't it
maybe it wasn't
surprised I remembered the a thousand
that turns out that's where it buzz
so I I can't remember if instead of
offer tonight I'm guessing it's not
because if a thousand is the aperture
and it's not really talking about an
offset aperture here then there would
only have been one of them so I'm
guessing that it's just single buffered
and you're writing directly to the
screen so you would have had to do an
actual blit if you wanted a double
buffer I guess like I said I don't
really remember
[Music]
yeah I remember this chain stuff
I'm sorry I just don't remember all this
stuff but here it is so it was double
buffered so you create two separate
pages you render to one of them and then
you patch
I guess you patch an address so you wait
till the V blank you switch where it's
reading from here I guess
I'm gonna have to reread this stuff too
because I just I don't remember it's
been too long
sorry
but it but it looks like that's
technically not mode 13 right so yeah I
mean I'm sorry I can't remember the
exact details of how these things worked
I want to say in so how here's a
question for you if we just go load like
some code of mine from those days which
you know I didn't really do much
programming on the PC but like when I
was in high school I did like a little a
little bit of das PC programming so in
the handmade fund bonus pack thing that
you get if you contribute to the bonus
fund do I do any of that kind of thing
here
so this is clearly just straight-up like
double buffering by writing to a back
buffer and putting forward so that's
just eating the CPU time to do that so
the answer was no not in this code
anyway right whether or not I ever did
anything like that I just don't know on
the Amiga you didn't do any of this
stuff this way this was completely PC
only so you know all the particle
effects stuff
just trying to look to see if any of
these other ones so what's all this
garbage
so it looks like maybe this was using
some kind of the library X Lib all but I
don't know what X Lib all is probably
something that we could dig up again
easier said than done huh
so this looks like a yeah like I was
using some mode X graphics library and
I'm guessing that the that would be in
some kind of a a route kind of file I'm
gonna say I don't know I'm not sure
exactly where that would be in here we
could just download all this stuff and
search for it
so you can see it's in that excellent
age is there a dot C for that anywhere
you know looks like maybe it's just a
lib it's just in the lib I mean we could
dump the live and then it probably
wouldn't be too hard to look at the to
look at the actual code in there though
cuz you know we're talking about just
some basic calls to setup stuff you know
they're gonna look pretty
straightforward even in that assembly
but yeah so I don't know like the other
thing I could try to do is find I'm kind
of interested to know like if I could
find the original source code of this
library
like you know I don't know if it cludes
the source
it looks like it does there's a bunch of
awesome files there assuming that that
was in Azzam right so yeah the basic X
Lib stuff I don't know where it gets
implemented but we could certainly try
to find out so if I like unpack this
dude
then in here we should be able to like
open one of these things up and see I
don't know what these pink oh you know
that's just that that's just well oh but
it's got source I don't know why it's
called an ink file then
can we search within the text here for
double ah this looks good
so yeah
so it looks like what we're doing here
is we're sand
if we're only doubled buffer we don't
have to do this which is fine so
assuming that we end up in here we load
we load and we Swami we swap the hidden
page offset with the visible page offset
and I guess I'm just not sure how that
helps us if that's some kind of an
actual register that the graphics card
was looking for it's not a register but
a memory location is that defined up
here somewhere
because you're set double buffer
yeah I mean it looks like all you had to
do for that part of double buffering is
you looks like you had to arrange them
properly so you had to make sure that
they were you can see here they're
computing like an offset that is
designed to line these two things up in
a particular way right and of course
there's all because you know there's all
these restrictions about what the graphs
card isn't isn't isn't able to do in
those days right so you had to create
the correct sort of like resolution and
arrangement of these screens but it
seems like anyway that after that when
you wait for the vertical refresh you
literally just write to a new you just
take a particular memory location that
the graphics card has mapped I guess and
you just write the offset of the page
into that I guess cuz that's all I see
happening here like I don't see anything
else so it seems like that's all you
really needed to do maybe
let's
let's see here so I don't know there's
any other questions I need to take at
the moment I really thank you for
confirming the dots PJ stuff yeah was
okay so was it mowed why what it was
called okay so maybe mode X is when you
do unchanged so you can you can get the
double buffering I I forget all these
terms it really wasn't something I did
much work with ever so it just wasn't my
it's not my area of expertise but it
seems like I remember most of it just
not very well all right I'm gonna go
ahead and wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me for an
episode of hand made here outside a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to follow along series at home
you go here to the game on handmade here
at work and it comes to the source code
so you can follow along with it at home
we will be back tomorrow to play around
with the apron stuff and just make sure
the best stuff is solid and then we can
move on to whatever the next order of
business is on the list of things that I
talked about maybe we'll start to work
on the collision side of things because
I would like that to get a little bit
more straightforward and we also want to
make sure that the aprons work properly
over room so we just want to clean that
stuff up we did most of stuff today but
we just want to sort of make that all
brushed up and nice and then we can talk
about starting whatever it is we want to
start about start on next in our list of
things probably don't want to quite do
lighting yet because that's gonna be a
little bit more of a in-depth thing to
finish that up but we may want to just
go ahead and start working on the ground
cover stuff would be another example so
close induction and ground cover are
probably two things we want to look at
and then maybe we'll move on the
lighting after that that's about it for
today hope see you back here tomorrow
till then have fun programming and I
will see everyone on the Internet take
it easy everybody