hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream we are actually just
yesterday we kind of got everything
working for packing
hij files from hht files so basically we
can build descriptions of all the stuff
that we want to produce in terms of
packed art files and then the game will
just build them for us now we were in
the process of debugging that and what
we found was for some reason all of the
things that we packed weren't coming out
in the actual game and so you know I was
like well maybe they're just not getting
packed properly but we dumped the HHA in
two different ways we actually made a
little thing to extract bitmaps from it
even and what we saw was actually that
it looks all correct or roughly correct
and so we've got a harder to bugging job
today we've got to find out what strange
subtle thing are we missing that's
causing us not to get any results
because unlike an obvious bug where you
just get no images in the HHA or there's
no tags in it or anything like that
we're not having that problem we're
getting actual what look to be correct
results in the HHA file but then we're
just not seeing the graphics on screen
when we try to use those HHA files in
place of the ones that we built using
the previous process and so today we've
got to look in and see what's going on
there and I don't know so just blind
bugging start us out we're going to need
to pick up some clues and then zero in
on the answer now just so everyone
remembers what we did we've got this
idea that you know there's a tags
directory and in here we've got these
tags files that we made called hht or
handmade hero tag and they're just text
files that list everything that should
go into our art packs you can actually
make multiple art packs in a single hht
- I chose not
do that here just so we could test
multiple hht s but you can actually make
a single entity that targets multiple h8
J's and says build all these art files
and it will in any way the point is it
will build stuff into this data
directory and it will build things that
based on the names you tell it so we
said we want a base game that HHA and it
should have everything that this has in
it and gosh they look really similar
sized right so it seems like it kind of
did and then we also have an intro
cutscene one and that puts all of like
sort of those cutscene graphics and the
title screen and so on in there really
kind of looks like it's being built
fairly accurately we made a thing in HHA
edit which is our little command-line
utility we made for inspecting these
files called extract which will take a
file and dump all the contents we tried
that with our with our intro cutscene
and lo and behold everything looks
pretty darn good and so you know we're
kind of a little confused at this point
as to what's going on because again
really looks like the images at least
got through fairly accurately you know
they're not all black or something what
they could be and we could check right
now is it could be that the Alpha is
wrong that's a little bit harder to
check I don't know how well bitmaps
actually save alpha out so but we can
generate separate alpha images if we
need to so let's take a look and see if
maybe the Alpha was screwed up or at
least just make sure that the Alpha is
doing what it should be doing to a
certain extent so you can see here if I
load this in I'm not getting an alpha
channel here and so we don't really know
what that means like let me load this
one as well
like we know that this should have an
alpha channel and you can sort of see as
I loaded up into it into the jimp that
you know I'm not getting that alpha
Channel so the first thing I might
suggest we look at because we don't have
a lot of other ideas and just to again
just to refresh your memory if I do go
back and I you know use tab view here to
open up the dump of the intro art file
because again it could just be that the
the images are getting packed okay but
there's no luck metadata associated with
those images and so it's entirely
incorrect right well if I actually go in
and look at the intro cutscene text file
we looked at this yesterday as well we
can dump all of that stuff out and look
at the individual assets and when we
look at them they actually appear to be
totally good right the basic category is
25 the shadow mixes 1 the layer index is
5 now it's possible that the basic
category of 25 is somehow wrong we
didn't actually go verify what that
should in fact be so if I take a quick
up story if I take a quick look at
handmade he wrote here at the tags file
that lists all those tags here it is
right I can count them out 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
oh wait no that's just that's the actual
tag I need the asset version here sorry
so we've got 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11
12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 21 22 23 24 25
so unfortunately for us again that all
looks correct even the alignment point
looks good which I don't even think is
being used in the cutscenes I can't
remember it well the default one
probably is for the hot spot so just
looking at this right there's literally
nothing I can see that a miss we don't
know about this number because this is
the number that says we're in the file
the bitmap is we don't technically know
if that's correct I mean I suppose it
could be wrong in two ways but when we
made the thing that extracted all of the
files they all came out exactly right so
that number sure does seem to be correct
because when we actually dump the images
that's where we're getting them from and
out they came so it seems like looking
at this I
tell what might be wrong with it now
there's one thing I can do really
quickly just to increase our confidence
level but then like I said I want to
start debugging by looking at the Alpha
because that's the only thing I can
really think of to focus on first and
we'll just have to go from there
if I do an HHS edit dump of the intro
art v2 this is the one that does work so
I just create a text file that says you
know what's in that if I tell view that
what I can do is look at the assets in
there and just see are those any more
likely to be good right like do those
have anything in them that I'm not
seeing
okay so there's something we learned
right right now the basic category for
the East was 19 before and it's 25 that
would have prevented us from finding
them so it could be that that's the only
problem that we've marked these wrong so
if the basic category was originally 19
that would mean that this was 24 23 22
21 20 opening cutscene so there we go
so maybe just maybe the only thing we
did wrong is we didn't label those
things asset opening cutscene and should
have now I don't really want to use this
anymore
I would rather these just be called
plates because that's what they are and
I don't really want to have to label
them as opening cutscene or something
like that so I think what I would prefer
is if I actually just go into cutscene
and I take a look in fact what I could
do is just search for asset opening
cutscene and I just don't want that
anywhere so really this part right here
I just want to be changed to wait right
and that's all I really want to see so
if I take a look back here I see that
it's compiled let me try running that
and let's see if that makes any
difference so I'm gonna go here to
winter to your handmade gonna run the
game and then we're a debug mode here it
looks like and then I'm gonna switch to
the opening cutscene and I'm just gonna
see if we see anything this time and
again we might not but we'll find out a
second okay so it looks like that was
the only problem for our opening
cutscene right you know looking at that
it looks totally accurate the only thing
that looks different from the old one is
it's lower resolution that's intentional
we have a thing now that tries to like
size things down so they're more
appropriate to 1920 by 1080 instead of
being ultra high res again that's just
part of our packing process the nice
part about that is if we ever want to do
like an HD 4k remaster of the game or
something we can always turn those
numbers down so that it doesn't
decompose or doesn't shrink them and
that's intentional right you want your
source art to be fairly high res and
then you want your game pack to scale
those things down as necessary so that
later on if you want to do higher res
versions for some purpose you
right so this all looks fine now and it
looks like our asset Packer is totally
fine for the intro cutscene like that's
what it looks like to me anyway I'm not
seeing any errors here this is all
exactly like what it should be as far as
I can tell anyway right I don't see any
I don't see any issues there looking
good yeah so I mean so I think you know
I don't know but I think we can call
that a success like that seems to have
everything in it that we want to have in
it and furthermore you know in theory
anyway now we also have the fact that
you know that title screen if you
remember we've got in the cutscene thing
there's like a time when well I mean
I'll just show you right right here
there's nothing it's just a blank
because we didn't have a title and at
the moment we could even make a really
simple thing that was that was that
right and so we've got this cutscene ID
thing right and the cutscene ID is just
a thing that goes in here and it says
which one of these scenes were doing and
when you look and you see update and
render title screen it looks like well
actually it looks like we just know that
that's the case because we've set a game
mode differently so I guess we don't
even need to add one of those but anyway
when we do update and render a title
screen you can see here that we do a
begin render group and an end render
group and then a begin render group and
render group right and we don't actually
render anything into here as far as I
can tell right so we don't actually draw
anything other than we clear to this
background color but we don't actually
put anything on to the screen so there
you go I'm not 100% sure why we
beginning and the first render group
like that I think it's because we don't
have any
'we like these are def peeled and these
are maybe not
and so i think this we I think our
render is a little borked and that it
needs to have that past so we kind of
worked around that eventually it would
be nice if we do a final pass in the
render or Sunday to just like clean
everything it'd be nice and not have to
do that because right now that it's a
little bit jank if I believe that's all
it was going on but we don't really have
to care about that at the moment because
really all we need to know is look in
here we just want to say if we're not
gonna switch the intro cutscene because
our time is elapsed let's render one of
these plates right let's render
something for our title screen because
we have one now and so if you're looking
here you can see the way this works
we've got sort of the rendered layered
scene call it does a set camera
transform here to just create you know a
basic camera that can be used draw the
stuff and we probably want to do
something similar although maybe not
exactly this for our own purposes here
so I'm kind of gonna take a look and
just copy that in I think and then you
know when we look in in here we see the
rough way we do our rendering we can we
can replicate that so I'm just gonna go
ahead and into this part of the code I'm
just gonna put some really basic stuff
to handle that right so I'm just gonna
say like alright I don't want that so
for camera start and end I don't really
care about that part either because
we're not really moving the camera
around much so I can kind of just make
the camera placed wherever I want it to
be so for the camera offset here I'm
just gonna say look let's make the
camera just be back a little bit in Z
and we'll just call it a day
right so something like this where we
just move the camera back and you can
see in here like when we have where the
camera should be I believe that stuff is
just all set you can see
in here I believe this is the camera
placement information I think is all
this stuff is so I think we should be
able to just say look let's set the
camera at this fixed location and
that'll be fine we will I guess I don't
know why was a check for render group
because there's a render group always
there so that should be fine
and that's the types of update so right
here we could just say look let's set
the camera offset to what we know it's
gonna be and the camera focal length
will be that looks like we weren't
setting a camera offset directly here I
don't know why so we can just bake that
in here there's that so it looks like
that was probably again that cutscene
stuff done way before our render hat out
much stuff in it so it's probably mostly
that will keep this focal length for now
not a lot of reason not to but anyway
once we set that camera transform we
should now be able to just render like
any bitmap we want into here so we
should be able to say like look let's do
a push bitmap on this and call it a day
right alright so I want to do that I
wanted to call push bitmap so I've got
my render group here and again these
render groups have to probably have an
address pass because they're actually
declared directly in this store in this
function so anyway we need to do a get
bitmap info on this thing we need to
find which image we're going to do the
alignment stuff I don't think we really
care about here because I think that
that should just work do we actually
need to do that
well maybe we do yeah it looks like we
probably do that's hard to say so if we
use that alignment point there we'll
just assume that we need to use that we
don't care about any of this offset P
stuff so I'm just gonna render it at the
origin because we're looking we or at
least I tried to set the camera to just
look at the origin so for now we're just
gonna leave it there as far as the
height concern I have no idea what that
should be we'll play with that a little
bit later but anyway all we really need
to know now
is what should we do in terms of this
layer image how do we find the image
that we want right because we need some
way of grabbing the correct one and so
the way we were doing that back here
right is we create one of these matching
vectors again that system something we
kind of wanted to improve on so we'll
have to you know this code will get
simplified when we make a slightly
better matching system which we've
wanted to do but we just don't quite
know exactly how we're sort of hoping
that now that we've got our Batory tag
files and stuff like that it will become
a little clearer how you want to access
these things but I don't actually know
that that's true so you know we'll find
out as we go
so anyway inside here what we need to do
is when we're getting that bitmap info
we just need a way to access it and you
know this is really all we need to do so
we can say look here's the shot index we
want here's the layer index we want to
do it that way oops and so inside here
under the match vector the shot index
and the layer index can just be set to
the two things that we know are our
title screen actually is so inside the
intro cutscene tags file right in here
we know it's shot index 12 layer index 1
so we can just say look grab that one
for us that's what we want we can then
say well we know it's an asset type
plate right I'm sorry
asset plate and that's all we should
need so the reason I say it's a little
more complicated it should be is you can
kind of see that this should just be
like we'd like this to just be easier to
find stuff it's just a little too much
work it's not bad like you know 10 lines
of code for rendering the title screen
out it's fine because this stuff is
stuff you do anyway you'd have to do
this you know and that need to wrap
around the rendering calls I'm ok with
those
but it says a little it's too verbose
you know it's like I want to get this
thing and so we need to like think we
need to get a little better at how we do
that look those lookups they're just not
they're not the what they should be and
well I don't necessarily know exactly
what will be better I know we we will be
able to do something better once we
really you know set our mind to it and
and focus on that is the next problem to
solve so that's coming let's see what
are we doing now just cleaning up bugs
looks like that's the only one we've got
at the moment so that might be it and
then we should test and see so if I you
know I'm here and I split back so
there's so that worked exactly the way
we'd hoped to small obviously let's see
about making it bigger I don't know how
big it should be let me just change that
to a 5 maybe oops
crap of course the 10 seconds elapsed
there we go um so maybe twice as big as
that I guess I'm not sure maybe you like
that and if this probably needs to be
pushed like up a little bit don't know
how much either
and again oh you know what I'll do you
know I'll do here's what I'll do
let's just comment out the title screen
time update because then I can just run
the game like you know like this where I
just say toggle fullscreen and we'll get
a little for coder window here and then
I guess edit those values directly and
not have to constantly recompile I mean
we relaunch the game so if I if I set
the time step to never update then we
shouldn't it shouldn't ever come off of
the title screen right the title screen
should just stay up always and so then
if I just kind of put my window you know
down here I should now be able to to
look at these values and get them
correct so if I like make it a little
bit larger
and then maybe push it up a little
higher
let's see that's too high that seems
reasonable right now we don't really
know what the background would be here
exactly so I you know at the moment
anyway we probably are just gonna have
to stick with that and so I can at least
though change it so that we're not doing
this nonsense here like I can make a
black background for now so it's like a
little bit more appropriate so this is
kind of our bare title screen and that's
fine
all right so success really happy with
where we're at here so now we can move
on to the next step because now we know
also that our alpha is correct because
you saw the background shining through
there right when I had changed it when
it was orange so we know that that's
correct and so now the question is if I
do put this back time step in if I put
this back in we've got all of that
working okay and so the only thing that
now we don't know if is that correct at
all is the gameplay pack so the stuff
that has the things for the in-game
rendering let's move on to getting that
working I'm gonna go ahead and move
local HHA into the v2 directory so it's
out and so now we only have base game
and intro cutscene I'm gonna delete the
intro cutscene text file because we
don't really need it anymore and we're
gonna take a look at the base game HHA
and see if we can get that working now I
might as well go ahead and dump the base
game HHA as well make sure that the
stuff in there looks kosher so if I do
an HIV edit - dump for the base game HHA
and I say look put it in dump slash base
game to mean thump I meant extract if we
now look into there
what I should see is like yeah like all
the pieces like our cats and our
characters whose names I don't remember
because I named them all really
arbitrarily I know this one's the baby
but the rest of their names one of them
was named Laird I remember that I think
I think her name might have been sunny I
remember most of their names
we'll look them up you know we gave them
names they have names I just don't
remember what they are all right so what
we now have is a verification that those
things got packed in there correctly and
of course we have the same problem you
had before which is I don't necessarily
know if they've got the right tags on
them it turned out our intro did not
have the right tags on it and that was
the problem
oops sorry and so what I would like to
do is just verify that that's the case I
would like to say hey like did the
taggers make sense we're not I don't
know I've got too many tabs open here
you know do these things have tags that
make sense I don't have any idea so we
got a facing Direction dobbs left orphan
and here oh it's weird that dodge left
is the what we called that tag would it
be dodged it be like negative one to one
that's kind of strange so we should
probably change those tags but you know
whatever um so the basic category here
is ten it's an orphan it's the hero I
don't know what category ten is but if
we look back at our file formats
it looks like category ten is there
one two three four five six seven eight
nine ten its body which seems right so I
feel like we are now at the point where
again this should probably be working
not sure what the problem would be based
on looking at this and you can see those
alignment points there the default one
just got added by like it should so I
don't know
so let's progress okay if I go into the
player code so basically the code that
creates a new player right it's like ad
player or something like this I when you
look at how its rendered you can see
what sort of information it was given
here in terms of what should be like
what the tag should be so you can see
that the tag orphan tag spring tag Viva
tag glove tech fingers right those are
the things that were like put on there
to say who this was um so the body I'm
just gonna do hero in hero so when you
add a player it's always a hero at the
moment which probably won't be the case
going forwards because you're probably
able to play is you know a couple
different people are something but for
the moment we're just gonna say like if
it's a player character it's gonna be
the hero I'm gonna go ahead and compile
that and see if we get anything at all
when we actually run the game so here
I'm gonna go run the game and so
honestly it looks like it looks pretty
good and in fact if I if I go ahead and
change this to a release build in fact
so that it's fast I should be able to
just play the game normally and see
everything so it looks pretty good and
what it looks like is the head of
everybody is wrong so if I had to guess
I would say that most of our import
tagging and everything is working
correctly except for heads and heads are
broken right because everything else
seems to work here and you know the
alignment points all got reset which is
exactly what we'd expect because they're
now just they got recreated from this
the hht file which didn't have any set
so again all this stuff looks nice and
clean now whole game is you know
explorable and playable and whatever and
so it just looks like heads are gone so
let's just say that that's probably
what's going on
and focus our debugging there is there
something wrong with specifically the
head import path you know and of course
the fact that that dude's head is
correct doesn't fill me with confidence
because that kind of ruined my theory
thanks dude you ruined my theory we're
gonna have to add combat quickly so I
could punch this dude for ruining my
theory alright so I if I try to figure
out what's going on there what I would
say is you know we've got these pieces
and what we did is we said let's connect
the base of neck to the default here
with this head piece thing I'm gonna go
ahead and say that maybe what happens is
that if you dist don't have an alignment
point set that you need set then you are
just permanently missing right so maybe
what's happening is it's just because
base of neck is wrong that's the problem
so suppose I did this that would say
let's say that the head is just
connected directly to the world exact
like it's just moving around with the
world position of this character and
there's the head okay so I think we
actually don't have any problems now we
just didn't add alignment points and I
had forgotten and/or just never realized
that in our system now that we've
created the snap to the other thing if
you literally can't find the snap point
you just don't appear right so that's
actually fine because I can solve that
problem trivially right we've got the
editor for that all we do is say look
here's the curia body we know we've got
a alignment point thing I need to add
one for the base of neck and then I need
to just put it in the right place right
so I just kind of adjust that to the
right place similarly while I'm at it I
might as well adjust the standing point
to be in the right place too
and by the way since the head is there
now which is this right here I can also
adjust its default alignment point to be
in the right place - right so that's
pretty easy to do and so now we've got
that created of course we have to do it
for all of our sprites right like we
have to actually align all of these
things because we haven't done any of
that yet
and I don't really want to do that yet
and the reason I don't want to do that
yet is because we haven't finished the
thing that lets us save these oops I
need to select a new one here right you
can also see we're picking wrong on one
of these things and that's because we
are not setting the dodge value on this
guy which we should so if I go into the
code for picking you know we've got
these tags
that we set here oops and file formats
we got these tags that we set and one of
them was for dodging I don't know why
it's called dodge left and dodge right
that's just dumb
I'm really surprised we did that that
kind of just seems like a it's just a
really stupid thing that I did so I
don't know why that's happening
I'm gonna go ahead and and nerf one of
these I'm gonna call this one
dodge and I'm gonna say that this one
which is you know a different property
index I'm gonna say that that one is
actually gone so that's goodbye I also
don't really know why these are
capitalized or not capitalized if you
look at what all of these are here like
some of them are caps and some of them
are not caps and I don't really know why
that's happening either
so that just seems a little bit weird
like are we capitalizing these or aren't
we
and I don't actually know so if I look I
want to know do we do a strings are
equal lowercase and it looks like we
don't so it looks like we do as strings
are equal and so if I go into the base
game tag file which is here and it looks
like all of these things are lowercase
and then I come back into the intro
cutscene and like these are like the
opposite thing of that
that just seems bad like all this stuff
just seems wrong I feel like all these
things should have been capitalized and
so on right so I'm not sure why we did
it that way because it's not really part
of the naming convention the way we do
it if I look and see in our strings are
equal we don't have a strings or equal
lowercase but we certainly could add one
of those right that wouldn't be
particularly difficult and so I think
what I'd like to do is just say look the
default here is actually going to be
that everything's capitalized so that's
the same as it is
of the game right and you can see that
sort of happening here so that you know
tag underscore the thing is just the
name right so they're basically unified
in that way and once we've gotten that
set what I'd like to do is say well I
don't know that I want to go through
here and have to update everything to be
capitalized so and since we don't really
have care I think I'm gonna say that in
in here where we do like a line point
from name and so on I'm gonna say that
these can just be case insensitive so
that way we just don't have to care
hopefully that make some sense
okay so let's figure that out if I go
back to strings are equal where we have
these various ways of calling these when
I do the strings are equal in here what
you can see is that it's a string versus
a string so it's always two strings to
you know it's always to actual bound
strings with sizes and so what I want to
do there is just say this one here where
we do strings are equal I'm gonna go
ahead and and make one of those that
just works with lowercase letters so I'm
gonna copy this and say we've also got a
strings are equal lowercase and all
that's gonna do is say like convert to
lowercase I don't know if we've got
anything like that it's really easy to
write so okay to lowercase
and that way we can do case-sensitive
comparisons and I know that this is the
one that I actually want to do for it
because we're doing string to string so
I'm just gonna copy that one in and just
call it like this and so now we've got a
case insensitive version and hopefully
that's a groups I'm in lower case so
hopefully that'll work now and what we
need to do to finish this off is I got
rid of that dodge tag right and I can
actually do this now and rebuild
everything if I want to which is kind of
Awesome so I can actually you know these
are hard-coded integers now so they're
baked into data files but they're only
baked into the shipping data files
they're only baked into the hhas
everything else is matched by name which
means if I just rebuild my hhas
which we can do trivially now I should
be fine and all of those indices will
update right so if I go ahead and do a
delete base game HHA and rebuild it it
should actually have those things set
properly now because dodge left and
dodge right were actually used in here I
have to fix that but what I'll do is
I'll just say look Dodge left is
negative one
Dodge right is one and now we're done
right everyone's happy so now Dodge is
in there and that will prefer a Dodge of
zero if I then set it so let's first
double-check that I didn't break
anything else we'll rebuild again this
this should just running the game should
automatically rebuild at the beginning
here that that base game file so you can
see it getting built right here so as we
build that once that's done of course
you can't really see it getting built
because it more shows up right here
right
there it is and now it's done and so now
everything should be fine and what you
can see again is right the thing that I
was complaining about is that Dodge is
getting picked the reason is getting
picked us because we haven't told the
game to prefer one or the other it just
says hey I don't care which one you use
so what I want to do is I want to make
something in here which says I want to
prefer the zero version of this thing
specifically right so in the asset match
vector in here since we don't really
have the concept of dodging quite yet
what we're based gonna say is look we
want to match the Dodge as well right
that should be matched as much as it can
be and you know maybe it's not as
important as facing direction but if
you've got to to pick from you still
want to pick right and so now at least I
hope we should pick non dodge although
the fact that I'm not actually seeing is
picking on Dodge is not reassuring that
should have done it right because tagged
dodge is 0.5 so it should be preferring
to match the 0 to the 0 I think
why is that not working we may have to
step in there and see so if I make it
extremely heavily weighted to match
Dodge you know this could be because the
way we do the matches is broken not
entirely sure
I don't have a lot of ideas there
because we're specifically saying look
you got a match dodge very strongly and
we're setting dodge equal to zero right
so I'm not sure why we would ever it
would ever prefer one of those now of
course like I said the matching stuff is
kind of broken right now so it could be
that it's just kind of busted and I just
you know don't really know the internals
of the routine and so I'm making some
kind of assumption about what would
happen when I did this not sure but if I
go look so let's suppose I come in here
to the matching routine and we well I
guess I can just jump right to it get
the best match so if we look at the best
match bitmap here or I could get the
best match asset what you can do is you
can look and see how it's working and
again my my assumption seems to hold
here right it's looking at each asset it
says take a look at what the two values
are so in this case they would be 0 and
1.0 or 0 negative 1.0 on those dodges it
takes a look at what the difference is
between the two values the tag range I
don't really know I don't know how the
tag range thing really works the tag
range is just so we can match facing
directions better for periodic things
that's what that's doing
but anyway whichever the minimum diss
whichever the minimum distance is we
look at the yeah the weighted Delta
between that and it gets higher as it
gets closer to 1.0 right so it seems
that seems like it should say prefer if
the dodge 4-0
and since you have to you should have
two pieces that are exactly the same and
the only difference is the dodge value
is not zero in one of them you should
have been preferring the one where it
was zero so something is weird about
this but I have no idea what it is
so there's I mean I'm just thinking in
my head so there's three things that
could be wrong one is our import process
is incorrectly setting the tags so that
things that are supposed to be just the
regular standstill are getting the dodge
tag and the things that aren't aren't or
something right the next problem is
there is something wrong with the
matching so that the thing I think is
happening in the computation isn't even
though I just looked at it I'm just
wrong and the way I'm following it
through and the third one is that
somehow we're getting an actual
preference for dodging because it's
actually getting set somewhere
accidentally like it's the entity does
have a dodge tag getting set on it which
I can't imagine because I don't think
we've literally never done that so that
seems really unlikely wait Matt Richter
comes first weight vector second that's
what we expect weight vector here is
multiplied the tag range I should look
and see how are we setting those so it
looks like yeah the tag that looks fine
that all looks fine to me
so the tag range is just whatever for
everything else but then for facing
direction it's a it's a wrapped circular
valium I got nothing I have nothing I
have no idea why that's not picking
correctly so I guess we still do have I
thought we were almost debug free
meaning we'd gotten to the end of it but
we're not quite we still just have an
issue with with the the cutscene I mean
of the the base game which is that the
dodge seems to be getting preferred now
that's not necessarily have any that bug
it necessarily has anything to do with
our new code because we were never
trying the hero out before so we don't
know like it could have just been a bug
that's been in there forever so it's not
a silly a bug in our new code it's just
but it is a bug before we can call it
done so I want to get to the bottom
right other thing I'd like to do I'd
like to delete these files cuz I don't
think they have anything to do with
anything anymore so I'm just gonna move
these out and we can just go with test
fonts v2 for now as the only residual
file and I think we're okay at that
point meaning if I run the game now I
think our only problem as far as I know
yeah is is that we don't have that dodge
pick working correctly so yeah so if I
just take a look at at what's going on I
think it's just the dogs it's wrong
everything else is fine we can now
rebuild everything from the HHA hhd
files which is awesome except for our
fonts the fonts is something we will
have to do as a separate thing and we'll
get to that right we'll definitely get
to that okay so everything's good I'm
happy with all that
I also think I know how I want to do for
the fonts I will dress that later but
anyway so right now I just need to
figure out what's going wrong with that
matching and then I think we can call it
a day because I think we're just good at
that point and I can move on to like
doing the rewrite stuff which I don't
guess we don't have time for a day
because of this I would have liked to
start it on it today but you know this
is probably gonna take me the rest of
the day to well rest of the day the rest
of the two-hour block - to nail down so
alright so I guess what I want to do is
take a look at that match and find out
why it's not producing the result that I
think it should right so there's a
couple things I can do there first of
all if I go into if I go into the HST
file right I can verify you know body
here oh right always gets an orphan tag
always gets a hero tag those tags appear
to be working properly if I go into the
import side of things
and I look at what's going on you can
see that these are the X indices
marching along idol dodge dodge move hit
attack attack and as far as I know we're
always just setting tag idle so we
should just be getting that now maybe
we're not you know that's the other
thing maybe maybe we just aren't giving
it anything to work with I guess I
hadn't thought of that
so inside the entity are we are
resetting tag idle anywhere is anyone
setting that let me see when we do add
player do we set tag idle okay we don't
so that actually now I think about it
could have just been the problem the
problem is yeah we could say try to
match dodge exactly but if it doesn't
have a dodge tag on it at all I'm not
sure what that would do so
like again because our matching is kind
of screwed up
that could be the problem so if I do a
match vector tag Idol and I say I want
to match that does that just work
because again I don't need to belabor
this point because the matching is not
what I want it to be anyway so we're
gonna spend more time improving that as
we go okay so that fixes it so it was
we're just not giving it a positive
thing to look for like hey you need to
match Idol it's telling it not to match
telling it not to match Dodge doesn't
help because these didn't have dodge
tags on them is probably the problem we
had like the rest of the things didn't
right okay so now we're down to just the
alignment point issue which is exactly
where we wanted to be because that
brings up our next piece of code we had
to write which is something that
rewrites the hht while including edits
that have occurred inside the game as
necessary right so that's the thing that
we want to get to next something that
reproduces the hht properly and so what
you'll see here right is if I I can
actually I think do this already if I go
in here and I say look I need you to
take this thing let's use the
forward-facing lens so we know if I go
in here and say okay I want to do the
alignment points on this thing and so
I'm gonna set the default alignment
point oops
let's get that here so I'm going to set
the default alignment point like so and
I want to set the the base of neck
alignment point like so and then you
know I'm gonna grab the head and I'll
set that alignment point as well right
and so now the hero is all set up right
it's all good
let me just make sure this alignment
point is what I think it should be
should be like that
and this should be
we're how come I can't see this point so
that's the red point oh right because
I'm on the wrong one this is the one I
actually wanted to edit there we go
should be like right there and then this
should be like right there let's say
alright so if we're in that and I should
really improve this interface a little
there's a couple things we could do to
make this a lot nicer very quickly as
well if I hit the Save button right we
have written the modifications back to
the HHA and so now if I close the game
and reopen the game it should actually
still be there so as you can see the one
we made is you know it was saved and I
want to go do that for everybody so that
now all of our art will just work right
but the problem is if I now go and
rebuild the base game HHA just to
illustrate the problem here it's had
that alignment point written back into
it but if I delete it right and now I'll
run the game and it triggers the rebuild
it will wipe it out right because it
doesn't know I just deleted the only
place that stored that piece of
information right so it's going through
rebuilding the base game it's a it's
importing all those art assets that were
it for the gameplay resizing them
placing them in there right and they're
all correct except for if the alignment
points are gone right so that's the
thing we really want to fix and that's
where the rewrite comes in so in order
to do that rewrite we just need to make
some way of when you're saying save the
game you need to read the H HTS and copy
them over to new h HTS right so
basically we need to update one of our
ideas about what's going on here you
know and sort of change the way that
it's actually working so if I go over to
the in-game editor it sort of has some
stuff in here that's now no longer
correct
it has a thing called modified you can
see here in save all changes right save
all changes is not gonna be this isn't a
thing anymore
right so that's fine clean edit list
like that whole thing it's that's just
not and get asset for edit like we don't
really need any of this anymore because
we can't use it it's not helpful I and
so you know the the clean edit pointer
it just doesn't matter so we can
probably simplify the editor by getting
rid of that actually if I look around to
see where that's actually getting used
so it looks like that's actually just
used for undo redo anyway
I guess
so it looks like that's just used for
tracking and you in a video which I'm
not even sure we really needed to do
that way but oh well uh so if I take a
look at these and I just say look what's
actually going on here in save all
changes we really just don't need any of
this anymore
so it does look like we need you know
this but right all HHA modifications is
not really a thing that we're ever gonna
do anymore
because in order to do it we really need
to do the full walk of our text tag of
all of our text tags because only things
we have those text tags for can we
really properly save data for right so
really what we've got here is right
modifications to all hhas and right all
HHA modifications apparently we have
both of these like all HHA modifications
where is that hey look we already had
that function whoops so I'm gonna bring
that over here there it is um it's like
almost exactly it's like the only thing
we did is we cleared the temporary no
more aggresively there which is probably
better right um so right all HHA
modifications again not really what we
the way we wanted that to be because
this is should not ever be callable
separately so what's gonna happen here
is actually this these things have to
happen together you have to do this
process and then this process otherwise
it's simply not a safe edit because you
will write changes to one place and not
the other which is simply not allowed
because then you just end up in a
situation where those changes only exist
in the runtime data files and that's bad
because that means if you ever want to
rebuild the files that data will be
eliminated which we never want
all right um yes so just looking at
these two as well I think I might just
do something more like this where we
actually do a temporary memory thing and
here I just say begin temporary memory
on the temporary nough and I do n
temporary memory here so we don't really
need to create a new arena every time we
can just cycle through it this way when
we do our modification rights like so
and so import changed assets now is
gonna be a different name it's just
going to be like you know synchronize
asset file changes and that's the only
thing we've got right so that's just
that's just what you do there's a thing
that you call it synchronizes everything
and it's the only operation you get you
don't get to do anything else
happy birthday right so here's that one
and maybe we do do this on startup
generally speaking right I and I don't
know but you know that's just what we're
gonna say that we do and and then in
here where we've got the editor the
editor has to do that synchronization as
well so when you actually say I want to
save changes that's what will happen
and there's really not two of these it's
just this right so you just get one
button the button is synchronized that's
the only thing that it can do and it has
to call synchronized asset file changes
like so now we could make it more
granular if we wanted to so if we wanted
to have an import and save or just
another one we could actually do a
little bit back the reason that might be
interesting is we might want to have a
way to just do an import that does a
strict revert as well I just don't know
how we want to do that so we'll wait you
know if you if you look at synchronized
asset file changes there's ones that
just do the read and there's ones that
do the read and the write you know what
I mean so we can do a strict import that
only brings things in and never writes
things out and I just don't know whether
we want to do that or not and you know
what I get here's the thing we had it in
there we can have it in there still the
difference would just be there's import
and there's important save and that's
what you get right you don't get
anything else so import doesn't rewrite
the file import and save does so we can
have those two things right and that's
fine so the way that that would work is
again inside save all changes which I
believe these are the two places that's
actually called from inside save all
changes right it would just need to pass
through what was happening here with the
synchronize
that's the file change thing however I
believe that's not quite right because
if you're gonna do save all changes then
the only thing you can do is that so
really the way this would work is this
would call synchronize asset file
changes directly if you were just doing
an import it would not called save all
changes
at all so that's what that looks like
and that's what this looks like
I think right so I think that's how that
would play out which then means that
inside import we need a bool here that's
like Save Changes or something that
writes back to the H HTS like so on or
rewrite H HTS would be a thing I'm gonna
call it Save Changes H safeties though
only because we probably want to
implement it in such a way that if an h
HT has not changed at all meaning
there's no difference between the one
that we created and the one that is
gonna go out to the world then we just
don't need to bother right so that seems
like a fair plan to me pretty
straightforward right
okay so we've got the synchronized asset
file changes now we have it all
structured so that things are gonna go
the way we want and really I think so
what we need to do here is say hey in
here we've got this hht rewrite where
we're creating a new you know a new
version of the HH tees that we're
reading and we want to make sure that
those things get mirrored properly how
do we do that
and so what I think we want to do here
is say all right NHD concepts let's
forget this hht rewrite nonsense doesn't
really make much sense to have that as a
boolean let's instead make that a stream
that says look if we're rewriting the
hht here's a stream that we're gonna
dump it the the new data - and if we're
not then we don't have that stream so
looking at the stream stuff that we've
got right we've we've already got this
idea that we can set up a stream that's
got memory and an output we can do a
test to it this is set up exactly for
what we want to do so I feel like we
just want to do all right create an
on-demand memory stream for each hht
we'll dump the stuff in there if we're
going to dump it and we won't if we
won't and so this I think is what we
really want this hht out stream right
and we just say all right put that in
the temporary 'no we know that's all
gonna get cleared and that's all we
really want it to do anyway we'll dump
it in there we don't really care about
the errors at the moment but when we do
actually care about the errors we can
also hook that up to something right so
that's kind of nice and then we're done
right I think that's all we really need
to do so at the end here after we've
produced our on-demand stream we can use
the stream calls that we've got to
produce the necessary output right so
what we can do there is say alright give
me the total size of the stream
like so right and really you know when
I'm looking at this I'm thinking to like
the hht that gets loaded maybe should
get loaded outside here so this can do
that that check I'm not sure how exactly
our structure we'll see in a second but
when I get the total size I'm thinking
there's probably also a way to output
one of these to memory right or there
should be a way that just runs through
it and and stamps it out so I want to
think here that I guess we don't have
yet which is just like okay we've gotten
the total size of the thing I want to
see if I need to rewrite the hht and
produce like a new one and so what I'm
going to do is yeah there's there's more
than one way I could do this as well
since this is under source code control
I'm not sure how long do this
there's number of different ways you can
do this they're all subtly different
I'll do the first part is the same in
all of them so what I need to do here is
aim to create a block of memory I need
to just say look I'm gonna write this
somewhere and I can just do a you know
give me some memory here's how big the
thing is the block that I need to write
so why don't you just create the whole
thing for me
right so this is the hht out put hht
contents I guess you could say you know
we know it's this big and I suppose I
could just do we have like a push string
size push or something what is pushed
buffer results no that's not what I want
not push I don't want that
push size space space so I guess we
don't have so unfortunately we don't
have one that just pushes on the room
that you would use for a string which is
all I really wanted right so I guess I
got a make one which is fine with me
so yeah do we have struck buffer we do
so buffers and strings are the same here
right so I'm just gonna call this in
here I'm gonna say look there's gonna be
one of these things it's gonna be called
like push space maybe or like push
buffer maybe I think we already have a
call called push buffer right which is
what I'm worried about
[Music]
it's not a render group so I think we're
okay I'm just going to call it push
buffer I'm gonna go from there so if we
call push buffer you're gonna pass a
size and it's gonna return you a buffer
which is the same as a string so either
one works right and in here we're just
gonna say look the size of this thing is
that and the push size call will give us
back what we want for this so we're done
right so that way in here I can say
alright I'm gonna create a buffer for
this thing so here's the hht contents
right and I'm gonna do push buffer on
the temporary nough with that size that
I said that I needed right here's the
get total size on whatever that stream
was so that hhc out stream so that's how
much we need to like put the whole thing
into a contiguous piece of memory once
I've got that I just want to output the
thing into a buffer so I just want to do
like copy stream to buffer and I want to
say take the entire stream which is in
lots of little tiny chunks they're all
like strung together right and take that
stream and put it into here so now I've
just got one contiguous chunk and then
finally what I want to do is just save
that to a file right I just want to open
a file and write the whole thing out
into it but first I want to compare it I
don't know if we've got a mem comp think
we do
we do uh God gotta love that search
thing I added to for coder for functions
and stuff um save so much time anyway so
if I go in here and say look now that
I've got two versions of this thing I
can see if they're the same right so now
what I should be able to do is diff the
hht contents with the contents from the
that I originally read in right and if
they're equal I don't need to rewrite if
they're not equal than I do
okay so that should be a pretty
straightforward way to to make this work
you know I'm saying now I'm gonna do
something a little controversial here
but I just think you know like I said
you know that was my pause for second
I'm like that has a bunch Royces I know
I think which way I want to do it which
is I do want this to be in the platform
layer and what I want is I want
basically an atomic file replace
operation why do I want that
well file operations can fail we know
that's true so I want a way of on at the
platform level saying write this entire
file out first make sure it works and if
it doesn't work that I don't want you to
replace the file you know I'm saying so
I would like to do something here that's
like platform replace
like this where I can say I want to
replace castas file but don't do it
unless it works right don't do it unless
it works so don't just start writing to
the file then if you fail be like uh
whoops right all the comments after the
drive first then atomically swap that in
place of the old file using like a
rename so that you never end up in a
situation where you just don't actually
have any of the file left I don't really
need to do that but I just thought it'd
be like kind of an extra level of safety
there where it's like look the hhk file
something we're editing and we don't
want to lose all our edits for a day for
because some weird like right bug
happened or something so maybe we just
have this atomic replaced all contents
call and at the platform layer that will
like do the right thing you know like
write it to a temp file swap the temp
file in in place of the old file or
something like this right all right so
again not really sure we need to do that
but I don't know so what we want to do
now is is back out I think a little bit
of what we were doing here in the parse
hht I'm gonna pull this code this code
right here I'm gonna pull that out a
little bit because well I mean yeah I
guess the other thing I could do is I
could do it inside there so maybe what
I'll do is I'll just push that one level
down maybe that is will do it I just
can't decide I'm not sure how I want to
do it but you know let's say we do it
this way because that's just how it
happens we set up right now it would
look like this right and so what we do
is say okay let's use that context
temporary nough right and we'll create
an hht out in that case we're gonna pass
this down and so we know whether we're
saving changes or not
so when we come through here we're just
gonna say look if we're saving changes
to H h T's then create the HS d out
stream otherwise it will remain
uninitialized and unused we do the load
here so we've got the file buffer it's
gonna go through and tokenize it and
have a little party when we get to the
end we'll look again and say are we
supposed to be seeing changes if we are
we will reproduce the entire h HT in as
a single block will diff the file buffer
with the h HT contents to see whether it
needs to get replaced and if it does we
will replace it now we've got the file
info here so we can just pass that along
and then I think we're good so now we
have the ability to do everything we
wanted to do we just need to fill in a
few pieces because at the moment we're
still not actually doing any of the
stream copy stuff that we said we were
going to do right so now we need copy up
to and including we need that call to
work and at the moment we don't have a
way of making that call work so that's
the next step that we have to go in here
and do so what I'm not sure about is all
the stuff that we were doing in here
right where we do parse top level block
and we do like copy all up to and
including so when we do that stuff and
we come through here and then we do like
the alignment points right we need some
way of skipping over the alignment point
stuff because that sort of gets
rewritten because that's the part that
we edit you know in a way so we have to
kind of figure out what should be
happening there there's a couple
different ways we could do that but we
need to figure out what's going on there
so when we do copy all up to and
including there we need like a way to
say in here
this is not right this actually has to
be so that semicolon we need to copy up
to and include the semicolon but what we
need to do is make sure we skip anything
that we actually didn't want to save if
that makes sense and in fact if we
wanted to I guess we could not copy all
up to and including
[Music]
so again all I'm really trying to figure
out is in the alignment there it's like
well I want to make sure I copy
everything but for like the alignment
stuff I need to make sure that I copy as
much as goes on in there like this may
have to get rewritten if this and like
what if that align appoint got like
deleted is the thing I'm thinking then
there wouldn't be a semicolon so we
would have to advance to the semicolon
which is harder to do I think so this is
a little Squinkie I'm not sure how I
feel about it but I guess we'll cross
that bridge when we come to it
yeah I guess uh to begin out here to
like all this stuff should be fine I
think the include directive we've never
used and we would have to do some
special handling to make sure that it
recopy the hht is properly I think
although I guess not because it looks
like that would just work so in here we
just need to make sure that we save the
hht context and then restore it so I
think all we have to do there is say
look the hhd context stuff in here we're
gonna have a stream for hht out and
we're going to have a token position so
if you look inside the tokenizer at
where these things are being recorded
you can see that it's got a an input
string so it would have a care pointer
so it would have a like hht copy point
or something I think that's all we would
really need to save so if we just get
rid of this
that would just tell us look these two
things are you know all we're using to
handle that we're you know we're we're
sort of moving that along so all we
really shouldn't have to do here is with
the hht out in the HD copy point those
just needs to get saved and restored now
the problem that I would see is I don't
know what happens if you include the
same hht multiple times because the
rewrites would like conflict with each
other so but I'm just gonna say look
that's your problem if you use this
feature you better know what you're
doing um so all I really need to do here
is say look this stuff's just getting
saved and restored my dude so that's
what's just what's happening I and so
done and then we'll just clear them and
go so this would just allow us to sort
of bracket an hht inclusion by saying
look we're gonna have to do a new stream
for this because the different hht so
you know act accordingly everything else
should just work I think and then at the
end we just need a copy all input up to
and including to finish things off right
now the problem is if we encountered a
parse error we probably don't want to do
anything so we probably want to do
something like this
meaning you know if something in here
triggering an error don't save the
changes back to agencies because we just
don't know what we would actually be
creating in that case but it would
probably be erroneous and we'd just be
corrupting the file so if the file did
not parse completely correctly then
don't write the changes back that we
encountered right so I think that's all
we really need to do there and similarly
this doesn't really need to happen if
we're not yeah this only occurs in this
one case as well um so I think that's
what we want to do and we would just say
that last token I mean I could even do
that here I guess because we have like
whatever token we actually saw last so
basically we would say at the very end
make sure you copy that token and then I
think we're good I think
so the only thing that I'm not sure
about is I feel like maybe right here we
would have to do it as well so when we
come down into here and we're ready to
basically token as a separate thing we
might have to no I guess you wouldn't
have to because we will just restore our
state and continue on so it's a little
squeaky I've never really done code that
does this rewrite thing before so you
know I'm still kind of learning as I go
in terms of how I what I like in this
case but I think that should basically
do it so at that point we're really just
down to this function and what we want
to do is we want to copy everything that
we see exactly as it says so in here I'm
just gonna do a check
does the hht out exists right I just
want to see excuse me please stuffy
today if the HST out exists I'm going to
copy into it so I'm just gonna basically
like loop over everything that I've got
and just plunk it in if I'm not mistaken
then inside the stream you can just push
junk onto it right so this append chunk
is all I really need to do what I want
to do right so you say look put this
chunk on there and call it a day since I
know that all of this memory stays
around I don't even have to copy it
right so it's very efficient all I'm
doing is saying look append to this
chunk to the stream
wear whatever the token pointer is it's
gonna be apologies for not remembering
what the token struck look like text
there you go
so token text it's basically just gonna
be whatever the token text data pointer
is plus the count pointer that's where
we end and in fact I could I can do this
as an intermediate computation because
I'm gonna want to do a check so I'm
gonna take the end and say that's where
we're at I'm going to say that the start
is just context hht copy point and so I
want to copy between these two but I'd
like to check to make sure before I do
that the start is less than the ends
right assuming that it actually is then
I'm going to do the work and when I do
the work I'm going to say the end - to
start is the size and the start is the
pointer and you can see this is really
kind of elegant the way this ends up
working we've loaded a file into memory
we're effectively just making a chunk
list that says grab these blocks and
copy them in but later so I'm not even
doing it yeah I'm just building up that
list as I parse through and then I've
got some insertions that I'm gonna do
where I'm gonna add blocks that never
existed in there right to represent my
new data and that's the entirety of the
of the process right and we don't ever
have to do any dipping of it ourselves
because we know that the diff that we do
at the end will completely take care of
that right so it's pretty nice seems
pretty good
and I feel like it's actually a lot
better than the way we're rewriting our
hhas right now I almost feel like we
should probably do something similar to
that for the hhas in the future where
instead of having the track like do
these tag arrays match or whatever we
just take the block that's the entire
back side of the HHA that we would have
written and we say does it differ from
the one that's in there right now and if
it doesn't we don't rewrite it that's
like way better because it's a lot more
foolproof and off we go
so I think that's the thing that we
really want to do here and I should
probably make that change I'm gonna
actually write it in here because this
is where that should go
all right
because yeah like we just if any change
occurred at all then we want to rewrite
the whole thing we don't rewrite only
portions of the header so as far as I
can think I feel like all we really have
to do is make sure nobody reorganizes
things in the asset list if you haven't
edited anything which if you haven't
added anything then no one should have
done anything to them so I feel like it
should just work in that case so I don't
know like we can play with that a little
bit later on as we fine-tune the system
for now we don't care
that's that of a different problem for a
different day all right so if I now go
ahead and run this thing of course we've
got a few things to fill out here this
is a false this does not rewrite changes
obviously so all I really want to do
here is get to the point where we are
oops that's a care star I didn't mean
for that to be a care star I just have a
few things I still got to implement that
we didn't put in here yet so let me go
ahead and skip those going all right
is passed directly so it's not an arrow
what else we got
hht out spelled wrong well capitalized
wrong ah yeah okay so this is the
alignment point part this so we aren't
really doing this yet but this is what
you would be checking so I can leave
that in there when you do a price hht
you've got a pass now whether you're
saving changes so that's fine
this needs to take the context right and
it I don't remember if it takes anything
else nope so it's just the context and
the token and then down here we've got a
few things to deal with the temporary
nough is actually here right and then
we've got copy stream to buffer we have
not implemented and memory is equal
between two buffers we actually have
implemented sort of but we just need the
cracking call for it so if I go over to
memory is equal like all we need to do
is just add the call that basically says
here's how you unpack those into
something that this can use so if we do
like past two buffers then the result is
just the same exact call memory is equal
file buffer count file buffer data HIV
contents data right and the only thing
we have to do is check first before we
do that that they're the same so we do
file buffer count equals of the same
size so we do file buffer count equals
HSE contents count that says look don't
do the next part if these buffers aren't
the same size
if they are the same size check to see
whether their contents are the same and
then we're done
so that should all be fine let's see hht
out must have an arrow and you're
right it does not sure what it's
complaining about here that's just a
regular pointer already so is that copy
stream to buffer isn't implemented yet
nor is that so I think we're now just
down to the things we haven't
implemented inside stream copy stream to
buffer should be pretty straightforward
right the only thing we really need to
do here is copy I believe we have a like
right stream or something like this
stream dump stream to CRT that's
basically the same thing right Asset
stream basically the same thing so you
know this is all we're doing so it's
really very very simple so you can see
here look we just have a data offset all
we need to do is start at zero stream
through all the chunks so we basically
say the source in this case we loop over
every chunk that's in the source we want
to copy the contents of that chunk so we
want to say look copy this thing into
the correct portion of the buffer so we
just say it's the destination plus
however far are we going and then we
just advance so we're just looping
through each chunk doing the copy just
like right and like I said we've done
this in a fairly elegant way because in
some sense we have avoided ever having
to do intermediate copies we're just
doing the final copy into one big buffer
we never did copy into smaller buffers
because these chunks just point directly
into the source
so it's just reassembling the source
buffer right um so what we want to do
here also is assert that we wouldn't
overflow so when we come in here we want
to say you know make sure the total size
of the source is less than or equal to
the size of the buffer right and so we
would just say you know don't don't let
you know if we're about to like romp
over this thing
let the programmer know they screwed it
up right and I'm not gonna have it clamp
you know we could have had it clamp here
where I say look just copy as much as
you can I'm not gonna do that because I
don't have a use case for that yet so I
don't want to introduce I just want to
make it a hard error like if you ever
call this thing and you didn't give it
enough memory it's just a hard air and
you screwed up right because there's no
case I can think of where that's gonna
be a situation I don't know is this this
count yeah sorry it's count all right um
can I convert just hmm
okay that's fine
fine
everyone's happy now hopefully and then
when they come through here we can just
yeah well actually I guess there's
really nothing that you have to do it's
just done
I would like however when we get out of
here I would like to reset these so like
when we get to here I would like to set
this to zero just to make sure like
basically that we will crash immediately
if someone was trying to write to this
outside of the valid region which is
only inside this function so I really
don't want to leave those as pointers
hanging around into memory because that
memory will actually still be valid and
people could be writing into it and I
would never know so that could have like
a subtle bug there that Disney wouldn't
crash it wouldn't do anything it would
just kind of like silently fail which is
not a great like you really don't want
to have silent failures that's not a
very good position to be in so I want to
make sure that that does not happen to
the extent that I can so let's go ahead
and yeah and make that make that work
all right so where else are we at cannot
convert from you eight to care that's
totally fine that would also have been
fixed
push buffer it's not supposed to take
one argument what's why is it saying
that let's take a look at what push
buffer does
it's still like a macro for push why
does that think is it the is there an
error before it no so it just says no
reloaded function takes one arguments
atomic replace file contest on the movie
so why does it think there's only one
argument to push buffer when there's two
arguments to push buffer and I missing
something
oh wait so there wasn't in there error
there why did it look like there weren't
two I was like I that the error was
exactly what I just fixed or something
like it but never even have it so the
only thing we're missing is atomic
replace file contents so yeah I just
need to go in there to the win32 side of
things and add that in so let's take a
look at how we might do that so at the
moment we've got our where is it
here's our write data to file and so we
more or less want this but instead of
write data to file what we've got here
is like platform atomic replace file
contents and that's going to take one of
these platform file info trucks and it's
gonna take buffer well let's unpack it
for now
and that's going to be called platform
atomic replace file contents right and
so here we get HD contents I'm just
going to say give it the count give it
the data and then that's all done the
platform layer we'll have to have it so
right that's gonna go there and the
win32 side of things in went through to
hand-made when we actually fill this
stuff out like you can see here
we're gonna have to have one
so in win32 right data to file which is
here I'm gonna just copy that
and now we've got the setup for it but
we haven't actually done anything that's
actually fine I'm just gonna have a not
implemented throating here and then
we're gonna call it a day so looking at
this it says too few arguments for call
is that actually true
did I accidentally leave an extra
argument in there when I copied it
oops there's the problem right there
that up what's good um so now I think
we're pretty good to go I think
everything should be fine so if I run
the game now I have no idea why there
was a breakpoint there if I run the game
now in theory you know if I come out
here and we've got the import and the
import and save these are not lit the
way that they should be so we should
probably fix those but we'll do that
later when I actually click on the
import and save you know we should have
gotten here and we did which is pretty
cool but of course you know we're at a
place where we didn't actually write
anything we just produced the thing we
would have written to the file but then
we call it a platform layer function it
doesn't actually exist if I try to look
at what's going on there I could
probably do that in debug mode a little
easier than in release mode but really
all I want to see here is what is the
you know what what are what is the thing
we actually produced when we called copy
stream to buffer so I think I can
actually
this right and say in here oh okay did I
not set the breakpoint I can't find it
so probably what happened is it got
optimized out in a way that it couldn't
find yeah so it probably just it
probably just eliminated this
unfortunately I mean not eliminated it
but just inlined it in a way that it
can't set the breakpoint anymore which
makes it less fun fine I will run it in
debug mode as much as a pain in the butt
as that is that's just where we're at
alright so off we go I'll run it and now
I will ask it to resave the file so and
now hopefully a wait I should have set
the breakpoint first try it one more
time so now I should hopefully you get a
breakpoint there and I do so when we pop
out of that routine I should now be able
to look at the hhd contents and see
what's in them and if they're at all
correct because you know maybe they're
completely borked so gonna go ahead and
say probably not not a good sign does
not look at all like what I wanted by
any stretch of the imagination and I
have no idea why that would look like it
does or why the count would be 3 right
so we did something really dumb but I
have no idea what it was
let's take a oh I do actually know
exactly what it was
so when we initialize the HST copy point
we can't initialize it to zero that's
just stupid and I don't know why I
thought we could what you actually need
to do is initialize it to the beginning
of your stream right so basically after
you load the file and initialize the
tokenizer that's when you can actually
look at the hhd copy point it's the
tokenizer first token right so whatever
would have come in as peak token raw as
the you know first thing that you would
have looked at that's actually the only
thing that we can use to start with and
if we didn't we are invalid right so we
need to actually grab that as our H as
our hht copy point otherwise we totally
don't work because we yeah I don't know
how we didn't just crash
does anyone have any idea how we didn't
just crash I mean how did that not crash
the that we must have more bugs because
if you look at what would have happened
here this would have been zero which
would have always been less than end we
would have appended a chunk that was
totally bogus and then from then on we
would have done some stuff but like how
did that not I I I'm at a loss there I
mean that would have been zero how did
we not end up with a totally bogus copy
I guess we'll find out next weekend
that's gonna take some device like that
should not have happened the way it
happened at all that's just totally
broken so the fact that that didn't
crash is super weird and I don't I'm
doing something that I didn't think I
was doing because there's no way that
should have worked right that's just
really really strange
gosh now I just I just don't know that's
that's really weird how is that how did
that work gonna have to go look into it
yeah so it's producing exactly the same
thing even without that so it's just
it's just it's really strange right
it's like it never called this or
something is that what happened now it's
calling this just fine
oh but hht out is not initialized all
right so let's right now no it's calling
it
and it's appending the chunks
okay
I'm gonna look at this sorry I know I'm
supposed to be done with the stream at
the moment but I'm really kind of
weirded out right now I'm mildly freaked
so hht out now has what on it right that
makes sense
next next that looks exactly like it
should I must have just a bug in the
copier
so I'm going to go ahead and assume that
the bug is here because let's see what
the total size of hehd contents is so
get total size is 3 how is that possible
yeah oh it really did get completely
overwritten so how did that happen we
never hit this case right I mean we've
never we've never called include so the
only thing that like how could that have
happened when did that happen that the
total size could have had such a
dramatic change to it
ah
that's the only problem right there
so interesting very very interesting
hmm so anyway inside part of a block you
can see what's happening here we're just
like cleaning up our memory that we were
using for the stream which we could just
use a different one for the screen but I
don't know that there's really any
reason to do that because we can just do
it in here so I think that's fine but I
can't think of any reason not to I do
want to know what we do with errors
I guess those just end up on the file
which is also fine but that's the
problem right there right we could also
just not free any of this temp memory if
we wanted to because we clean it all up
at the end but that looks like the
entirety of the problem there right
that's funny like a bug a memory bug
prevented us from having a memory bug
I'm just pretty odd all right so if I go
in here and just look at the copy stream
to buffer hopefully now we actually get
a real sighs and it looks like we sort
of do at least a little bit so if I then
look at the contents of this thing
hopefully they look somewhat like the
file and it does seem to look somewhat
like the file right in fact so much like
the file that it matched perfect so it
didn't think it needed to replace it
let's look at the base game same thing
so we're actually totally good perfect
we nailed it so I'll go to a quick Q&amp;A
now and then next week what we'll do is
we'll just go add the thing in that does
the rewrite of alignment points and I
think we're good to go
there are no questions complete silence
wow that's impressive ly few questions
do you ever write unit tests for testing
little functions instead of running
through the game when you are going to
be a little closer to shipping things
like when you're like kind of done if
this makes sense like if you're just
like I'm really sure that everything is
architected the way I want and I'm gonna
like say that this is reusable final
code that is what I want does does what
I want it doesn't how I want it then you
can start to pull apart a few things
that you think might benefit from unit
testing and do the unit testing I do do
that
but you know there's I guess what I
would say is while that is a nice thing
to do for code that's gonna get library
eyes and so you can kind of pick it
apart and do that - unit testing you
can't really rely on I've said this many
times if you rely on unit testing for as
part of your developing process you
probably just never be able to write a
game it games don't really that the hard
bugs that you will get in games are not
unit testable the easy bugs are and so
that's usually the problem so like while
it's nice to do some unit testing on
things that when you have some low-level
library stuff like our memory allocator
when we're totally done with it and say
this is f how this we could test it out
make sure it doesn't have any weird leak
cases or edge cases and things like that
that's just an extra layer of nice sort
of certainty over the top your debugging
skills have to be way better than the
kind that just say hey I'm gonna use
unit tests to find my bugs
games are way too complicated and unit
tests just don't work they won't find
the majority of the bugs in the game and
more importantly they won't find the
majority of the hard bugs in the game
and so you really need to be better at
debugging than unit testing if you're
gonna make a game engine you just do
so what I would say is they it's not
that unit tests aren't useful sometimes
they are it's more just that they're
they're insufficient they're not good
enough for a game engine now that you're
gonna sleep the schema industry as you
play I do a see game engine series this
basically is a C game engine series
there's almost no C++ in it at all if
you wanted to compile it entirely and
see there's almost nothing you'd have to
change it's kind of just a mechanical
weeks worth of work sort of cleaning
things but it's it is a seeing game
engine
any thoughts our hopes for C to Xcode
over 2022 yes my hope is that I will no
longer be programming in C++ by 2022
those are my thoughts and hopes advant
home when you transfer a mesh to do that
on the GPU if so do you load it back if
you for example want to recast against
it so the answer is yes and no the the
answer is to where your transfer mesh is
pretty much always on the GPU because
it's a massively parallel liza bla' per
a ssin and GPUs are way better at
parallel operations than CPU so are
currently they're just much wider and
they have better thread management for
those kinds of things so you definitely
always transfer them around the GPU and
when you say do you load it back if
you've never got to recast against it
the answer is that you usually try not
to raycast against the mesh you try to
recast against something else that
approximates the mesh and you try to do
that with things that themselves don't
deform terribly much does that make
sense so typically you have hip boxes
right and those hip boxes don't
necessarily mean boxes sometimes they're
like actual they have shape they're
usually convex solids and you raycast
against the convex solids by just using
the bone transforms and the convex
solids on the CPU side that's typically
what happens if you really really really
need 100%
it's pixel accurate raycasting for
something uh I don't really know what
people would do these days it's a good
question uh you wouldn't read it back
because by the time you got it back the
results would be meaningless because
you're like three frames late or so so I
don't really know what you would do what
I would probably do because I did do
100% mesh accurate hit detection in
granny I'm in rad game tools character
animation library I did do that what I
would probably do is not that different
today as to what I did then which is you
would hit test the boat the those
collision boxes like I just said which
is a simplified model and you would make
sure that they were conservative so you
make sure that you use bounding boxes or
volumes that enclose the entirety of the
mesh no matter how it was deformed which
you can do because deformation is a
known process that you can make sure
that you can be conservative about and
then based on which one you would hit
you would just on the CPU side transform
just those triangles that are near that
collision volume and then rake ass
against those that's what I did on on
granny and I probably just do it again
that way today
how do you toggle between debug and
release builds modify the build up batch
each time yeah I just changed the OD to
a no - how do you conceptualize and
tackle large Frederickson prevent from
getting overwhelmed and lost in the
weeds of my new details I tend to suffer
from analysis paralysis um well I mean
you see what I do and handmade hero it's
really all I do I just try to improve
areas as I go there's no magic formula
for it most people can't do large
products at all and it kind of requires
a team to do if you're doing one by
yourself yeah you just I mean that's
it's difficult you really just have to
be willing to write code and experiment
and let things come together try not to
do too much analysis like try not to sit
around doing something where you're not
programming is I guess the only thing I
could really offer let's say in Tripoli
studio book quite a bit into obscure any
programming any steps in to show that
that's not the answer easiest way to go
forward to have a code base that works
but changing everything is pain it's
hard to make them see that this is one
of the big problems any advice it's our
friends um
don't work there go somewhere else you
can't argue with programmers they're
very pigheaded so I don't try they're
mostly religious they aren't motivated
by data most the time so you know you
can ask someone to please demonstrate to
you why they selected this way of coding
and they have like no answer not just a
bad answer but literally none like I'm
just like what what did you actually do
to determine this was a good programming
paradigm and it's like they've never
done that that's like 90% of programmers
have literally never done any
experimentation to determine whether
things that they do actually have any
practical benefits so how do you I mean
how do you convince someone like that
you can't write that's just it's
fundamentally a broken
it's a fundamentally broken mental model
so hey if you happen to have someone at
the studio who is results-oriented and
is willing to think about things then
that may be a person to talk about right
to talk to and be like hey so here's all
the practices that we're currently like
enforcing in this code base has anyone
actually checked to see if any of these
are actually working and what did they
do to do that right if someone's
actually receptive to that line of
questioning awesome but most people
aren't they like to start talking about
all kinds of nonsense like well it's
modern C++ it's like those are not
that's not science like that is not an
experiment where you have measured
whether or not this thing is actually
improving a code base right and so you
just can't have a discussion if people
are thinking that way there's no
discussion to be had it's just it's game
over and unfortunately like that's just
you know so so I just don't I just don't
try it's it's worthless I don't know
there's nothing you can do you know how
do you how do you it's it's similar to
saying like how do you convince a Jewish
person to believe in Jesus or a
Christian to not write it it's like
they've crossed some threshold where
they just believe things and I have no I
don't know I don't know you you because
if you don't come from an engineering
perspective when you're talking about
what you're working on then I just don't
know and if you do come from an
engineering perspective you're not using
a brain to programming
pretty much so so I don't know I got
nothing
it's just it's a lost cause sorry what's
your talk about lines of code problem
have you ever seen anything from Ian
Pugh Marta no I don't think I've heard
of that name
to twitch subs count towards source code
access no we twitch subs are just
something that happened because we're a
partner now so you can subscribe
but it's only it's just a twitch thing
that's all it is
it's just it's just twitches thing so I
think it turns off ads gives you access
to emoticons and access to archives
that's that's it so it's there for
people who don't want ads and stuff
right but that's that's really all
that's really all it does yeah that's
nothing
it does nothing to do with source code
Ice Arena that's that's our product
that's that's the thing that we have
right and so yeah like it's just for ad
for viewing it's the same as like
YouTube read right like if you want to
watch the videos on YouTube the hami do
videos on YouTube if your YouTube red
subscribers there's no ads right so but
but that's it that's that's all it is
to use new graphics libraries know what
are your thought something you Sasebo
this lambda function seems like one of
the better dishes to see the suspect and
doesn't break procedural style I mean I
don't know C++ features are kind of just
an exercise in is this a thing that you
[Music]
is this a feature you can make some
productive use out of that doesn't
really ruin things for you and I kind of
stopped bothering to evaluate so you
must less things because almost every
time the answer was no but there
probably are some so like maybe C++
lambda functions more or less can be
useful without ruining things for you I
don't know my guess is if I did really
try to make serious use of them I would
probably just get annoyed and stop the
problem that they're trying to solve is
one that should be solved so I would say
that that is good
meaning the C++ lambda is trying to do
something that should be supported by
the language but my guess is if I
actually went looked at it I would have
a laundry list of complaints about the
way they chose to implement it because
every time I ever try to do something in
C++ that is what happens I'm like well
you tried to solve problem X the correct
sup solution to problem X has all of
these elements to it you got one of
those and ruin 12 things that's what
happens every time I look at a C++
feature it's it's always like a giant
train wreck and so eventually to stop
I'm like it's just not worth my time
once in a while I might find one right
but just the number of times that it
just wastes my time and I end up going
this is garbage you know it's just too
high so it's just it's just it's just a
trade-off now like reading a C++ spec
it's just a waste of time now you're
you're wasting time you could have
written the code the other way already
and been done by the time you figure out
whether this feature is even useful and
most the time it turns out it's not
alright I'm gonna go ahead and wrap it
up close this down close this down
alright thank you everyone for joining
us for another soda handmade here it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along the
series at home you always can you can
pre-order the game at handmade hero org
comes with a source code so you can play
around with it compile it yourself and
pretty soon even rebuild all the art
assets every time yourself which is what
we've been working on here to make sure
that they don't have to come from us so
that means you can kind of mess around
with changing how the art packs are
built or add your own art assets or
remove them do that kind of thing which
should be pretty nice right so looking
forward to that also wanted to mention
we are comic came out last Monday those
of you who don't know it's called meow
the infinite you can always get to all
of our projects by just clicking on on
any one of our websites you can always
click on the little site icon but meow
the infinite meow the infinite comm is
up now you can read the first issue
online it's pretty cool if you let cats
in space which I hope everyone does you
should check it out
you can go directly there again just use
the little linker which links you to
everywhere on our site my blog handmade
hero meow the infinite the main page
Anna's illustration blog and of course
1935 so anyway give that a check if
you're looking for something to read
until next week which I think now that
everything is kind of working I guess
we're just in the feature edition
territory so next week I think what I'd
like to do is get the alignment point
rewriting done so that we can mark up
all of our art assets and then I'd like
to go ahead and maybe add sound import
in there because we've already got the
code for it so it would just be putting
it into the tag like so that we can have
tags that were like this is a sound
right so we would like to do the sound
importing
maybe let's get the fonts importing in
there and then we've got the full like
you can just build full game assets into
hhas
and that's kind of then it in a way that
will then become kind of a universal
build sort of thing so you could just
build hhas and use them wherever right
like they are just like now easy
package' baletta datum are cup kinds of
files that just work so that's kind of
cool and the only thing that we would
have to do to really make it fully
generic is to define the tags somewhere
outside the game so that you can that
the parser could know like what those
were right that's the only thing we
don't really have at the moment is a way
to build an HHH HHH a file without some
knowledge of what the tags actually are
right so that one's a little bit
trickier but you know we could actually
do that too which would be pretty neat
so that's it
see back here next weekend for that
until then have fun programming and I
will see everyone on the Internet take
it easy everybody