stop recording start recording hello
everyone and welcome to handmade Hero
the show where we code a complete game
live on stream if you are somebody who
pre-ordered the game and falls along
with the source code today is day 206 so
you wanna unpack day 205 source code
into a directory that is the source code
that I am starting with now and that is
the source code that you would want to
start with if you want to follow along
with me so grab that out of the source
code zip and yeah and then you can code
along so where we left things the other
day I was kind of thinking we were
talking about this a bit and you know
where we left things the other day I was
talking about well we built this sort of
debug stuff and we've got a little bit
more stuff to do on it but I kind of
wanted a way to to sort of show like I
wanted a way to to sort of show entity
data and we made this little thing where
we could pick entities you know with the
mouse we could kind of move over them
all of our weird you know a little torso
person or the little hero and whatever
you know else is going on so we've got
all that stuff and we wanted to be able
to show like enemy data so maybe I could
like select that entity and just see
like what its state was because as we
move into coding like game logic systems
and stuff like that
we're undoubtedly going to have a bunch
of scenarios where we don't know why
Andy's doing something right and we're
gonna want to like be able to inspect it
right and so where we left off yesterday
was I kind of said well let's figure out
a way to sort of dump that entity data
and so what we what we did is I sort of
put in what I kind of wanted to be like
how that would look right I wanted to do
something like this right where I sort
of say hey diva you know begin the thing
that we're talking about output these
values and then end right and I kind of
wanted that to just be you know autumn I
wanted that to just be all we would have
to type and then all that stuff would
come out automatically in the debug UI
system and you know we wouldn't have to
fuss with it or anything else like that
and so there's a couple things that you
know we could do regarding that and I
was trying to think of since this is f3
three Mathon and we wanted to kind of
maybe do something a little bit
self-contained for that I thought that
maybe since people ask me about this all
the time on handmade hero like all all
all the time right about how to do like
metaprogramming stuff and it's not
really something we're gonna get to in
handy here much I thought I thought
maybe what we do for the Deaf stream is
on since handmade here at any of our
code heavy stream and I don't want to
give people the wrong impression
I figured we do a very code heavy thing
and maybe I'll show you how to make this
process automated so if you look and
you're going here to handmade sim region
for example we have a thing where we've
got this sim entity and you can see
looking at the sim entity right you can
kind of see that it's got all of these
things in it it was this is our test
enemy right that we made when we were
kind of getting our simulation systems
up and running and all that sort of
stuff and it's just got all this stuff
in there and in order to output it to
the debug system I have to type all this
stuff in manually right and what that
means is every time I change something
in here I have to go change it in here
as well and it's just kind of a pain
right so what I thought I'd do is just
show you if you didn't want to do that
how would I make a very simple basic
system that would add to C++ what the
Standards Committee somehow in 30 years
never managed to actually add even
though it's like the most obvious thing
you would ever add to a programming
language if you ever programmed a
program in your life introspection so if
we wanted to introspect something I'm
just going to show you how to do that
I'll try to get it done in an hour it's
a bit of a big thing to to sort of put
out there but I'll give it a shot I know
it's something people have asked about a
lot and so let's just do it
so in order to do that what we're going
to need is we're going to need a program
that we can run that will sort of you
know take a look at our at our files
here and output something we can use
that looks kind of like this right and
so that's you know we're gonna need like
a little utility and in order to make a
little utility that shouldn't be too
much of a big deal I'll just make a
thing in here which is just going to be
like you know you know simple
preprocessor or something
like this right it's just going to be
our little simple preprocessor see and
again this is something that you can
just feel free to use whatever you want
for because like I said on handmade Hiro
the proper the engine
we don't use any libraries or anything
like that we write everything from
scratch but for this you know it does
not matter so I'm totally fine with you
just using anything you want to use here
right so I'm gonna just say let's say
you used a standard i/o or whatever to
do file read and write because that way
it'll work everywhere and we don't care
about learning how to do that we already
show it on handmade hero how to load
files and whatever else right
so using that I'll show you how to build
the rest of the stuff from scratch and
of course if you want to do this
entirely from scratch yourself you can
always just instead use the file
routines that we use in handmade hero or
something like that but I don't really
want to bother reporting them out here
at the moment right well I mean I guess
now that I think about it well now I
won't I'll just do it this way I always
had this tendency to let go like well
why not just not do it because we've got
them already there
forget about it let's write him this way
it'll be fine
I'll get over it it doesn't matter
alright anyway so here we go with a
totally standard C program so everyone's
familiar with this right it's very very
straightforward and if we want to use
they're kind of weird file systems to
load things that's actually pretty easy
as well all we have to do is just open
you know a file handle like you do and
see here is our our simple file right
whatever it is we're gonna f open it
assuming that we got it we'll do
something with it and then when we're
done with it we'll close it right it's
extremely trivial that's how that works
it's not as nice as our file API where
you just say read the whole file and
you're done but what are you gonna do
right and so for now we'll just say
we're gonna Road handmade sim region
which is the thing that we want to
pre-process right and we'll load that in
and we will go ahead and in and parse it
right okay so if we wanted to do that I
would prefer again to keep the library
used to a minimum because you know again
if it were me I would just you know be
writing on top of an existing code
probably so I'm gonna keep this as sort
of a separate thing which works
exactly like all the rest of the stuff
that we did in hammer a hero where it's
just going to load the entire file right
so I just want a read entire file into
memory and null terminate right this is
a pretty handy function I always have it
in my libraries whenever I'm programming
and basically what this does right is
you take the file name and what it's
designed to do is just open the entire
file read the entire file and write and
and then add a null terminator at the
end so that you know that the the file
ends with a zero right because a lot of
things and see they like to have strings
that are terminated with zeros that's
how you know where the end is right so
here's the file contents I'm gonna look
loaded up by saying read entire file
into memory and they'll terminate I'm
gonna pass in just handmade sim region
dot H cuz that's the file that I want to
parse right now and then when I do this
read entire file into memory and I'll
terminate what I have to do is I have to
figure out the end like I figure out how
big the file is right so I need a thing
here where I could just say like what's
the file size and there's a pretty easy
way to do that and see it's a little
wonky it would be nice if it was it was
not as wonky but what you can do is you
can use a function called F seek which
moves the cursor around the file and you
can say that you want to go somewhere
relative to the end of the file so I'm
going to do is I'm going to seek to the
end of the file I can find out how big
it is then right by just saying hey C
runtime library tell me where you are in
the file and that would actually just
tell me what the actual file size of the
file is right then I can just seek back
to the beginning and then I can I'll
have the fought in entire file right so
that's the entire file size all I need
to do now is load it so I can go ahead
and you know I should probably also this
right so what I can do just say alright
I want to return this just a big like
sort of chunk of memory that's just
going to be the thing so now I know the
final size I can just say all right the
the results write equals a malloc of
that file size so now I've got it
and then when I F read in I'm going to F
read in something of well actually every
takes the buffer first just just because
it does
F read in that file size and and that'll
be the end of it
right so that's what I need to do to
read the entire file into memory and
let's just go ahead and check to see how
that goes let's make sure that that
actually makes some sense right so okay
first thing I'm gonna do is add it to
our build up that so here we go
we already have a thing here where we
compile our test asset builder right and
so what I'd like to do there is just go
ahead and compile this right so REM is
our simple preprocessor star example
here and so what I'm gonna do is just go
ahead and compile a simple preprocessor
dot CPP okay and now that we'll just in
theory compile that for me and it looks
like it did just fine and so now what
I'm going to do is I'm going to actually
step into it in the debugger and verify
that it actually worked at all it did
anything that I wanted it to do right
which would be a nice change okay so I'm
gonna open this up I'm gonna set it to
operate in that directory where our code
is right in handmade code so it can find
the code which of course you know we can
find that file that I want to parse I'm
gonna go ahead and step into it here
here we are I'm going to step in to read
it entire file into memory and I'll
terminate you can see me open the file
it got the file just fine which is nice
let's see what it thinks the file size
is the file size is 33 1 3 that's 3 3 1
6 that's a totally regional number of
bytes for that file we're gonna F seek
to the beginning right and then we're
going to malloc something of that size
and F read into it and let's see if what
we got was the con to the file there it
is right that's the file sure sure
enough right and you can see at the end
here it just kind of becomes garbage the
reason for that of course is that we
have not actually done the null
termination part but that's pretty
straightforward ok so that loads the
entire file into memory again really
really simple so all I want to do now is
I want to go ahead and allocate a little
bit more space right just one more bite
for that null terminator and then after
we do the read in I'm just gonna say at
the very end of the file
put that null terminator in so now I've
got
terminated file right I got a null
terminated the comments the file mil
terminated and so now what I want to do
is I want to parse this thing right I
want to go through it and I want to find
whatever is in there that I want to pull
out now there's a problem with this and
the problem with this is that it could
get pretty nasty in here there could be
lots of stuff and I may not want it to
pay attention to all these things right
I may not want it to actually pay
attention to something like move speck
or entity type or whatever a hit point I
may not want it to parse these trucks I
may not want it to do anything with
these and so I need some way of
annotating right mm-hmm
what these guys are and so what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna go into handmade H
right and up here in handmade H when
we're talking actually I couldn't even
put it here any platform um well yeah
I'll just put it here at the top of
handmade H before anything else happens
I'm gonna define a little bit of markup
and what I do typically for this sort of
thing is I just define some macros that
compile away right so what I'll do is
I'll define something such as you know
introspection right something like this
I don't know
and params some I don't know something
like this right I'll just something and
the key part here is that it doesn't
expand to anything it's a macro that
just literally vanishes right and so
then you can do something like okay this
struct right here I want this dark could
be like a introspected struct right
and maybe that's introspection done
maybe just introspect right and I just
say like oh the category for
introspection you know is brown butter
right that's I don't know why brown
butter because you know it's tastier
than regular blacks did like regular
butter so you know what let's just say
regular butter for now regular butter is
pretty tasty like you get it back
getting regular butter it's pretty good
if the butter is good and the baguette
is both good like I can just say I can
see where the French are coming from on
that right
you know I'm American but still you know
it's like I was never one of those
people who called it freedom fries I
guess is my point so anyway if I go
ahead and compile handmade hero now
you'll notice this doesn't do anything
isn't create a problem for us
if basic allows us to inject code that's
only for our preprocessor and that's
crucial it's crucial to understand how
important that is that's the thing you
you definitely need to know in order to
start marking up that code so we've got
that in there now we've got the file
contents and what we're going to do now
is we're going to start parsing the file
now in order to start parsing the file
what you want to do is you want to build
a relatively traditional parser
structure and the way that that works is
to two phases essentially the first part
of looking at the file involves what's
called lexing it means breaking up the
stream instead of just being a bunch of
individual characters you try to in two
pieces
that means something a little bit more
and so for example you might think about
the tokens in this right here as being
things like the lexicographical tokens I
should have said they're called tokens
that that lexing process is about
binding the letters InP ro SP ECT into
an identifier token like this is or or
you know like a set of words right then
I've got a parentheses token right which
is grammatical then I've got a category
token but I've got a colon then I've got
a string right open quote whatever and
so instead of just looking at this
that's just a big bag of characters
which can be a little bit daunting we've
said start looking at it as a bag of
tokens and that will make it a little
bit easier for us to parse so the first
thing we want to do is make a thing that
allows us to get tokens out of the file
right so let's do that here we go what
we want to do is define something like a
token structure we want the token
structure to tell us something about
where it was so weak rivalled probably
want something like what the text was
what you know what that what the
contents of the token was we probably
want us to say how long it was right so
this is the length of the token right mm
that's the region for it and then we're
probably gonna have something like a
token type right and that is what kind
of token this this thing was right and
so one might be an identifier like I
said we got other stuff in there right
we just got a bunch of things
oops that was not very good not a very
good cut and paste job there
mr. Mira Tori if I do say so myself so
we're gonna want things like you know
okay we've got an identifier we've got a
parenthesis you know open paren we've
got you know :
we've got string we've got close friend
we've got semicolons in there
we've got asterisks we have do we have
anything else we've got open brackets
right we've got open braces right things
like this so we got something like this
we're gonna want these tokens to come
back and we're gonna want them to look
like that right and so what I'd like to
do is I'd like to be able to start
writing code that just looks like this
it's just like token taupe you know
token nickels get token right and then
of course I guess we should also have
token end like the end of the thing
right like end of file or whatever end
of stream something like that right and
sweet and so what I want to do is
something I'm like okay let's just do a
for I loop we'll go in here and we'll
keep grabbing tokens until we can't grab
tokens anymore
so we'll do a switch on the token type
right I should probably put an actual
token type in there right we'll switch
on the token type we'll do a case where
we say okay it's gonna be one of these
things right like so I guess we don't
actually have to do a switch on the case
quite yet we should probably just keep
things a little simple at first I will
just say okay give it to the end of
stream we need to stop right we're gonna
be done should probably do something
like this - since we're inside a switch
statement so we've got a bool here
that's like you know parsing equals true
and we'll just say well we're parsing
now so then when we want to end the part
you can just say the parsing is done
it's over and we'll break out right so
assuming that we're not hitting the end
of the stream then what I want to do is
I want to say what we actually found so
I'll just do a thing where I say like
you know what the token type was maybe
and then what the string was that was
there now one of the weird things about
strings
I don't remember there's a crazy syntax
you can do to print out length strings I
can't remember it you specify the width
of the thing and you specify an indirect
with specifier it's like the craziest
thing ever but you can do it
printf in direct width specification
trust me this is a real thing it's kind
of absurd I just want the actual def it
here it is there it is that's it right
there actually you can see it's that
star right the wisp specification an int
argument for the Argos specifies the
value right so you can actually do this
with strings where you're actually
specifying the width to printout and the
reason I care about this right is
because our tokens are specified as a
length and a pointer so I can't just
pass right I can't just pass this
because by default printf will read
until the null terminator or slightly
probably pass as well we'll just read
till the null terminator that string and
it'll just go off into no-man's land and
crash or who knows what it'll do right
print of different garbage until it's a
zero by luck whatever so what I want to
do is I want to specify an INT there I
want to be able to specify that text
line right I want something more like
that and so I forget if I have to
specify a dot for that or not so we'll
find out here let's see printf string
indirect string with it's something like
that and it's it's just kind of crazy we
could probably just sort of muddle
through it as well but I'll try just
present star s for now but I thinking
you might have to put % dot star s this
is the vagaries of C you'll have to
forgive me I don't use this I don't
really use printf anymore so it's it's
it's not something that I have kind of
at the you know at the top of my M of my
brain stack of things of things to do so
let's see here in a single by characters
weight up to the first letter until the
precision value so there it is right so
it's with dot precision right is usually
it's like width up precision is the way
it goes so we do need that dot in there
to say it's the precision value we're
specifying we're specifying here with
the star
so read it off the stream ants a string
crazytown c++ printf crazytown welcome
to it okay so that's how we're gonna do
our little print out thing everything
should be working here except for the
fact that we don't have a get token
thing and so what I want to do here is I
want to have a thing like called
tokenizer or something to store the
state of this just so we know where
we're at something like this right
it might store some other things later I
don't know but I just want a thing that
we pass around for state so what we're
gonna do is say that we have a tokenizer
the tokenizer is is just going to be
initialized to have just that app
pointer pointing at our file contents
like so and then we're gonna say go
ahead get a token from this tokenizer
thingy that I've created and that get
token it just expected to do whatever it
needs to do right okay so here we go how
do we actually do that well at first of
all we probably want to do some basic
things that tokenizer x' or and i guess
this is technically lexing i guess at
this point right we want to do something
that lexer is typically do we want to
eat up any white space because typically
in programming languages like the one
we're using here white space dust does
not matter right so what we want to do
is do something like hmm you know eat a
white space or something like this where
we just say like before we do anything
else get rid of any white space that's
in there because we just simply don't
want it right and so here's the art eat
all white space we have our tokenizer
and what we will simply do is go okay
while the tokenizer at you know while
this this app thing while we look at
what it is equal to and what it's equal
to you know is white space so we can do
that pretty easily in fact we could even
make a little query for it like this we
could say well that's white space we
want to go ahead and advance it right so
we're just literally moving past any
white space that's in there again really
trivial probably for anyone to write as
well that is white space function pretty
straightforward that just takes some
care whatever it is right I'll guess
we'll call it C and it just
is going to return this result and that
C equals basically any of the whitespace
stuff that we know of right so if it's
that if it's a space if it's a tab or
something like this if it's a new line
right then we want to say that it's
whitespace right so that's it so while
that's happening we're gonna advance by
the whitespace then what we're gonna do
is take a look at see what character
we're actually on and then we're gonna
do something with that character right
and so let's just see what all the stuff
is that I said we were gonna purse and
let's grab it like so and so I'll just
say okay if the token is an identifier
oh that's right we don't know that yet
that's not what I want to do it all we
want a way to determine yeah all right
brain getting a little brained
it's true in order to figure out if
something is an identifier that's gonna
be a bit of a catch-all because that's
like anything could really be identifier
so really what we want to do is focus on
these guys first right if we see an open
paren we pretty much know what we're
dealing with here right our token dot
type equals an open paren and we're done
right so I think basically you know
these guys should be really really
straightforward in fact like it even I
could probably compress this down with
something really straightforward
something that looks like this right and
so here's the other ones we've got here
we've got closed paren that's going to
be this guy
we've got semicolon that's going to be
this dude right here right
we've got asterisk that's gonna do this
guy yeah we've got Open bracket right
OOP that was not where that goes not
where that goes
not at all so Open bracket close bracket
I don't know why those braces got got
plurals on them they were a little bit
too too ready to go should be only open
brace
all right open brace close brace so
there's that go right so that would just
determine what we were looking at when
we're looking at something relatively
straightforward
I forgot the : one there there we go
okay so that's you know all we really
need for all of these guys but then
we've got the string and the identifier
one and in fact you know what I'll do is
I'll move those guys down here so we can
kind of see like you know here's our
string you know here's our sort of our
simple guys versus complex guys right
and similarly at the end we also kind of
know in fact we could even do it here
where we say you know if if we see the
null terminator right as part of the
character as well that's going to be
token end of stream right so yeah so all
we need to do here is just assume that
our result token right let's just assume
that the result tokens text length is
one and we'll assume that the tokens
text is where we are at and that will
just make it so that all of these this
the multiplicity of cases here is just a
trivial assignment of the type and then
we return and we're done right and so
then all we have to do is start
implementing these more complicated
cases here like let's say we see one of
these quotes right or something like
that or let's say we get some other
thing here and we're gonna treat it as
an identifier right okay so what we want
to do now is we want to say okay if we
get a string we just want to read
through the entire string till we get to
the next like quote right that's all we
really want to be able to do so in order
to do that all we would say is okay you
know while you know we're just gonna
advance the tokenizer we're just gonna
say okay skip over that quote because we
don't want the quote to actually come
out in the string value right so skip
over that quote and then let's say that
the tokens text is equal to where we're
at now then we just want to keep going
until we see a close quote so we
basically want to say you know while
tokenizer at is not equal to a closing
quote and we also want to make sure that
it's not the null terminator because we
might at the end it might just be an
invalid you know program whatever while
these are happening we just want to keep
you know we want to keep advancing so in
here we want to do you know a simple
advance like that now since this is C
and C allows you to escape with a
backslash things like the quote inside a
string we probably also want to just do
a little bit something extra here and
say that if the tokenizer
at happens to be a backspace like it
just happens to be right then we will
actually advance the tokenizer
past the next character whatever it is
right so we'd say something like if the
token eyes are at zero equals the
backslash and you know the tokenizer at
one the next character is not equal to
the null terminator so that it's not
like the end of the stream then at that
point we'll just say skip skip two
characters right otherwise we only skip
one and so that allows us to keep parity
with C so if there's quotes and strings
if someone quoted out if someone that
quoted a quote ate a double quotation we
won't end the string prematurely and
fall out of phase with the C way of
parsing things right so okay so we've
got that and now we just need a way to
parse identifiers right and so inside
our processing for identifiers you know
we've got this default case we pretty
much got two things we might want to
look at right one is is this thing
alphanumeric right so so basically is
this thing like is it an isn't an
alphabetical character I guess what I'm
saying so is alphabetical if it is then
it could be the start of an identifier
right and so whatever the tokenizer app
value is if that's alphabetical then I
want a person identifier here right
otherwise if it's a number right or is
is numeric I should say something like
that
then we might want to parse the number
okay and that's really all we would need
to do here we haven't implemented those
yet so we're gonna have to think about
this but there's one other thing we need
to do here which is if we end up in a
case where we see a slash we have a
little more work to do right because
there's comments in C code and we want
to bypass the comments so we actually
also have one more thing that has
nothing to do with the training a token
it's just about skipping over dead space
right and for that matter we could put
that in the whitespace eater as well
right so in the thing that does eat all
what whitespace I hope how far were you
guys gonna let me get in that I can't
really blame because I'm not looking at
the chat in the thing that does eat all
whitespace we also might want to do
sucking up of comments because comments
are basically considered whitespace and
we don't want them right so while the
thing is whitespace right we want to
advance but actually probably what we
want to do here is something a little
more sort of drawed where we do
something like okay keep going for a
while if it's whitespace right then we
skip over it else if it's one of these
guys right let's say it's that then we
want to potentially parse a comment
right so we would do something like okay
like this right so that's gonna be a
comment right that's gonna be a C style
comment VAR c style comment and
furthermore we also have the same
situation happened here where we might
have something that opens I'm sorry that
pass was a C++ style comment I misspoke
and here is the C style comment right
something like that okay so assuming
that none of those is true then we're
done no more white space to be eaten
right so now we've got our work cut out
for us we've got all the stuff in there
for the most part for some reason I
insist on typing tokenizer dot even
those tokenizer arrow I will rectify
that with a little search and replace
and done and then we just have a bunch
of things here that aren't actually
implemented yet right so let's do parse
the seesaw comment all all that needs to
do right is it just needs to go until it
sees star slash so we can assume in cure
I guess we'll just say that the
tokenizer at right we just skip over in
either case we skip over that part right
and I think actually now that I think
about it we can probably we I don't even
know why I bothered putting these in
here they're pretty straightforward so I
wonder if maybe I should just write them
in line write all that all that they
actually do is you know while tokenizer
at you know is not equal to and and
tokenize radicals are so while it's not
a an end-of-line right and i could
actually do something to even here
that's like is end of line kind of a
thing I could just even have a function
that tells me that right and something
like that
right that makes sense so yeah if I want
to do something like that I can just do
like while not is end of line on the
tokenizer
at zero let's just go ahead and advance
right so that just eats everything till
the end of the line and of course I also
again want to check to make sure we're
not null so you know while there is a
character to read and it's not the end
of the line then keep going and just eat
it eat it all up
right the same exact thing will happen
here right and and that's like after we
skip over this guy we just keep going
and say okay while we do not hit hmm
sort of that the stop the the the
closing part right so while we don't get
basically this guy that makes sense so
we're basically saying while there's a
character to read and the I should say
this way while I nice is a little
boolean logic for you there while that
whole thing is not true right
while the the star slash is not exactly
what comes next right then we can
advance ahead right when we break out of
that if the thing that we're looking at
is the star right then we are going to
want to advance past it because that
means that we didn't run out of
characters and we want to skip the star
in the slash which we ended on right
okay so that's really it for those guys
now we just have a few more note we got
to fix the errant plural there now we
just have to do our sort of more
complicated person here where we're
going to sort of try to pull out these
other sorts of things so we've got two
things we've got is alpha so you want
something that tells us whether this is
an alphabetical character we also want
something that's going to tell us you
know is it numeric is it gonna be a new
number thing and for right now I think
we can probably just just use Falls for
that because we'll get to that maybe a
little bit later on right
how exactly we'd want to do that
so this is you know to do kc once we do
numbers do this right although I suppose
you know we can probably guess if we
wanted to that's like you know if C is
greater than equal to 0 and C is less
than or equal to 9 then it's a digit
right if that makes sense and there's
probably like a dot that would also be
another one in there and like the F and
an O X right so there's probably some
things but for now we'll just use that
one and we'll go a little bit further
when we need when we actually need to
write these alphas really simple that's
just going to check to see whether were
in the alphabetic range of the ASCII
character set right so here is that
that's for lowercase and we can do that
or uppercase okay so that you know test
those two right that's whether or not
South with your merit we can now get
that sort of information back and so we
just need now to be able to do the two
parses parse number we don't really need
yet because we don't care about that so
really what we could do here is just
sort of like I said wait a second on
this one and we'll kind of look at that
one a little bit later when we actually
care about it so for now all we'll do is
when we get to a default thing we'll
probably just say like okay we don't
know what this token actually was so
maybe we just say at that point we throw
it out right so we just say like okay
this token dot type equals token unknown
or something like that right so there's
just some kind of thing like this token
okay and what we'll do here is we'll
also say that you know in the case where
the token is unknown right we could also
do something where we skip those right
so we won't print those that will only
print tokens that we know for now so
that seems hopefully pretty basic all
that seems good parse identifiers
actually now I think about it it's
really not that complicated either I
mean all we really have to do is say
okay the token starts where it took
where it started
and so we just need to do the lengths we
should also do that for our string by
the way here at the end of our string
when we do all of our string parsing we
picked up what the string text was right
but we need to to set the length which
we didn't do and we also need to set the
type right which is the token string so
we need to say this a string and then we
also need to set the end of it right so
at the end of all of this once the thing
has gotten to the end what we want to do
is say okay at this point we should be
sitting on the actual you know the
actual stopping point so we should be
able to say whatever the distance is
between the app function right and
whatever that place we started and where
we began right which we saved sorry the
place that we're at now and the place
that we began if we subtract the two of
them we should get the length of the
token right so with the first part of
the string the first character string we
know where that was that's token text
the last character string we're sitting
on it now right and it's that closing
quote so we track those two what we're
done but we also want to do is skip that
closing quote because we're still
sitting on it right so assuming that we
actually found the closing quote and
it's not that we hit the null terminator
and like you know it was an unclothed
string or something
assuming we hit that closing quote then
we want to skip the closing quote make
sense okay so that's really pretty basic
and again this stuff I could I guess
I'll expand this detector be a size feel
though we're never gonna be parsing
files that are that big I'll say it's a
size T for now very good okay so press
identifier oops mistake
thank you compiler for catching that um
so for parsing this guy an identifier is
just a collection of alpha and numeric
things plus the ability to have an
underscore
so really all we're gonna do here for
this is we're just gonna say while
tokenizer at zero
you know while that whatever that is is
alpha or it could be is numeric
or it's an underscore right and I think
I'm gonna say is number because now
we're actually using that for reals
right so I think I actually want to call
this is number because that's a little
clearer then that's the things we can
put in identifiers in our code that's
all the things we ever use for them
so while that's the case we'll go ahead
and advance the tokenizer
at at the end of this again we will just
have that tokenizer at be specifying the
link this way so it's wherever it
started versus where it ended so I think
that's everything at the end we return
the token that we got and we continue
right so that's pretty straightforward
so let's see what we've got here let's
go ahead and step through this we
probably have a bunch of bugs that's a
lot of code to type in at once like I
said I went pretty fast as I wanted to
kind of compress it down just because
it's something that we're kind of doing
a weird stream not like we normally do
but anyway here's our tokenizer in
action our lexer basically the first
part of the tokenizing so here we are
looking at this stuff so we're gonna
have some things we don't understand
like that pound we don't know what that
is so we should go in here and and get
an unknown token which we did
let's see now this token should be an
identifier basically we're gonna go in
here to eat all whitespace we're gonna
look at this thing and it's none of
these right so we're gonna exit out of
there we're gonna start by assuming that
we have a token length of 1 here is the
token text right we're starts on that
pound Oh aha we do have a bug already
token unknown when it sets that needs to
skip over right these guys need to skip
over the token app so none of these guys
I guess that's sort of the thing these
guys don't skip over that first that
first guy right and that's a that's a
problem so how do we want to deal with
that right how do we want to how do we
want to make it so that these can be
convenient you know because I can do
this but it seems a little bit annoying
for me to kind of have
do it every time like that I don't know
doesn't that seem like kind of a pain
maybe it's not a pain but for these
hand-coded guys you know I mean you
could always back it up I suppose we
could do something ridiculous right we
could do something like this where we
say you know by default go go past it or
something like this so we do like care C
equals tokenizer at wow this could be a
real bad idea but we could do something
like that so that all of these work and
then this guy of course this would just
work because he already wanted to
advance by the quote so that's fine so
it's really this guy who needs to know
what's going on here right so this guy
says something like all right assuming
that C was alpha right then we're gonna
run through these guys while it's still
their work you know we're gonna kind of
add to it and I think the rest of this
sort of works so let's let's just see
how that goes right
okay so let's see what we get here let's
get back our first token there's our
token it's a token unknown it's one
length of one it's that pound right
there which is what we expect so that's
good let's now see what the next token
is the Lexx token is token of length two
but that's specified as unknown as well
I think that's just because again that
was just me forgetting in here we've got
to set the token type right - token
identifier but that should have that
shoulda parsed okay right in fact I
should probably do that look right at
the top when we do them for the most
part just so I can see that I actually
do it there okay all right so there we
go there's our token unknown now we
should get a token identifier and hey we
did it's text length too so we're going
to print it out to the console and
there's the output right from it oh well
actually know the outputs over here
because it's a console app so there's an
eleven there was our if and so as we run
I think we'll probably be okay so I can
probably just actually run this guy on
handmade code now and actually get it to
to work right so there it is right and
you can already see that just from this
you can see that we're kind of already
parsing what we need
parce right do you see how this has
already kind of lined up into what we
need right I mean you saw how simple
that was what I just typed in and now
we've got a really straightforward kind
of a situation here for being able to
pull these guys out right so we're
starting we're starting to get there how
much time you got left we have 15
minutes left I don't know if we'll quite
make it in time but we'll see all right
so let's start by trying to identify
that part that we actually wanted to
grab there so as we're doing this this
tokenizing what I want to do is I want
to go ahead into handmade sim region
here and take a look that is the key
that we're looking for we're looking for
this introspect and we want to go ahead
and grab that out right so what I want
to do here is go okay if I hit a token
identifier okay so I've seen an
identifier what I want to do is that you
want to know is the identifier
introspect right so I want to do is say
if token equals something like this
right introspect something like this
then I want to parse an introspection
right you know or int respectable
something like that right so I'm at a
person is respectable I need to pass the
tokenizer to it and that's how we know
we're gonna start parsing one of these
special structures something that you
know has been marked up especially for
us so we know that it's something that
we want to use in in our you know in our
pre pass or whatever right so there's
the tokenizing that's gonna happen there
and and what I'll do is I'll just
suppress this printf for the default now
and what I'll do here is I'll just
printf our introspective all at this
point right mobile start will start in
there okay so what I need first of all
is I need that token equals to be a
thing because we haven't written that
yet and so here what I want to do is I
want to make an inline that returns a
bool and what it does is it takes
whatever the token is you know whatever
that token was and then it takes a care
star that's like you know the string the
mat and it just sees whether or not it
matches right and so what it's going to
do is it's going to say okay I know that
the token is a certain length right I
know that it's text length
so I'm going to go through and say okay
from zero to token length like so I want
to make sure that match of that index
and token text of that index I want to
make sure they're equal right so if
they're not equal it's over it's false
right make sense
and similarly I want to make sure that
if the match index right I should
actually say also here just do this up
first so if the match of index if that
equals zero so it's the null right the
null terminator that kind of thing right
it's just zero if the match index is
zero or they don't match then return
false otherwise
the result of this function is just
going to be whether I'm gonna need this
index on time mmm is going to be whether
or not we got to the end of match so I'm
gonna need something well you know what
I can do let's just do this right so as
we go through this we just say okay if
you know start at start at something
like that right then advance them in
fact I can't even put that right in here
so just run along match check it against
the thing when we get to the end if star
at happens to be equal to the null
terminator we know we got they both
ended at the same time and so we know
that we can say that that it was
actually true otherwise it's false so
that's just a little like string compare
thing that we have there and we can go
ahead and test it so let me go ahead and
come down here right and so let's go
ahead and see what happens
if I step in here and now the token
itself right
is obviously going to be equal to
something totally not that it's like if
right
and so our app is pokey beginning here
we go to through the index the index is
zero these two won't match so we should
return or not Oh idiot because it's an
eye alright so actually they will match
on the first one then they won't match
on the second one and it should return
false so off it goes but then eventually
we should get to one that returns true
if we done it correctly but I don't know
if we actually did doesn't look like we
did because we never actually got to a
token that equals that so now we got to
go and actually see let's double check
here when we get to a token I guess what
I'll do is I'll say if I just want to be
able to plug this code if token text
zero equals I and token text 1 equals n
write something like this and so this
way I can just I'll only have to look at
the ones that actually have some thing
related to introspect and then we'll you
know go from there ok so here we go
let's see if we've gotten to a token
that's relevant there it is that's a
token we want so we hit getting the
token equals we take a look at what's
happening with our matching so now let's
see where we're at and at and where we
aren't index is 0 so we advance through
these guys we're advancing through as we
would expect right and what happened
there what is the token length one two
three four five six seven eight nine ten
but that yeah and the token like this
ten but our start at what happened there
Oh
oh that's just a typo well we almost did
it right we almost did it right that's
pretty funny
all right there we go so now hopefully
we're back in business there we go
so here we are parsing and respectable
so now we have to do is actually do some
gathering of the stuff from there and
let's see if we can do that right okay
so what we want to do in parse it's
respectable is we want to just like read
out exactly what this thing is right so
we know that we've gotten a token for
introspect so now we want to do is we
want to basically like get the
parenthetical phrase there so I'm gonna
kind of do this very straightforwardly
because again we only have about ten
minutes left so I'm going to do sort of
the base version and then maybe Monday
since if people found this useful or
interesting I'll show how to do a little
bit better right but it would look
something like this
right you know something like if require
token tokenizer token open paren write
something like that then what we'd want
to do is just kind of I guess I don't
care about this very much but what we
well yeah let's just do it
right then we do something like okay we
do parse purse introspection params
something like that right and we could
almost even do this where we didn't
actually have to do that but you know we
should do it anyway right and here you
know we do something like a printf you
know f2 standard error we'd say
something like error missing parentheses
right and we'd want to kind of do a
better error for these schemes can I say
I'm doing but I'm doing this sort of
bare minimum thing here rather than
anything fancy so okay we require the
token we do parse introspection for Rams
assuming that we actually get those out
right then we would do something where
we go OK token token equals get token
and this is probably like struct token
right so we go or or you know type token
like what's the thing we're going to do
let's see so we do get token on the
tokenizer right
if token equals you know struct then we
know we're parsing a struct so we do
like parse struct otherwise we do an
error introspection is only supported or
a structs right now sadface right
something like this okay so if we do
that we need these two things right we
need static void parsons inspection
params and there's our tokenizer and all
i'm going to do there is I'm just gonna
do like token I'm just gonna have this
eat everything for now right and so I'm
just gonna do token equals get token and
I'm gonna say like you know if token dot
type equals token close friend right or
token type equals token and a stream
then it's over
otherwise we eat everything so
eventually we'll like parse the actual
things in there but for now we won't
bother if we see a struct will parse
obstruct and what we do to parse a
struct is going to be something like
okay we need to get the name first
right that's the name of our struct then
we need to parse all the members of the
struct well actually then we need to do
a require token on an open brace right
we need open brace and then we need to
come in to sit here and wait till we
find a closed brace right so we need to
sit here and go like you know member
token equals get token tokenizer and
then what we do is say like okay we look
at that member token if the member token
type equals token close brace then we're
done right and that's that's basically
what we're that's basically what we're
after otherwise we'd parse it
five-minute warning getting close so you
know we get the token the member token
and then what we do is we do something
like parse member and pass it that
member so can that we got and that would
do whatever it's gonna do right so not
that complicated you can kind of see how
this is going and we'll see if we can
get most of it done in the next five
minutes
oops that supposed to be tokenizer so we
just need the choir token parser parse
member takes the member token this is
like the type token probably number type
so that's really all we need to look at
and inside the parse member basically we
can also do the same thing for this one
right now we can just eat till the
semicolon right and that should do it
okay so let's just quickly write require
token all require token is again very
very straightforward is instead of doing
a get token what require token does is
it gets the token from the screen stream
and then sets the results of the you
know that it's going to return to be
whether or not that token type equaled
the desired type right and it's just so
that's just shorthand it's just an easy
way to say the only thing I allow your
is this so I just require it right so
there we go and let's see so there we go
I'm gonna just quick run that it's not
gonna do anything right but I just want
to make sure we don't crash or loop or
hang or anything like that so now we
want to do is you want to get this out
putting something reasonable so okay so
we have our little weird magical printf
thing here that prints out you know sort
of token sizes so what I want to do here
is when we get to our introspection
struct for every member I just want to
print out right this you could see what
the code was I was trying to do I want
to print this out so what I'm gonna do
here is I'm gonna do something where we
can print out like this debug value
thing or something like that just for
just for show right that's all we're
gonna do all I want to do just to make
sure that we've got something resembling
anything is I'm gonna make this parse
number thing do that mm-hmm okay
so here we go inside parse number I have
my number type token and as you can see
in here right we've got you know these
are the member types that kind of come
down the side here you can see them but
sometimes they've got a pointer like
this old chunk thing here it's got a
pointer right and then sometimes like
that like array stuff at the end of them
too right but for now we can kind of
ignore some of that so what I could say
here is all right I got my member type
token I get this token here I want to
see what type this token is right and
I'm going to switch to the parsing
method here again
so I can switch on whatever the type is
so when I get the token out of this it
could be one of two different things
really well it could be its it could be
an asterisk right and it could be an
identifier those are the two things that
were there right so what I want to do is
say okay I got my remember type token
and right now we're only handling things
where this is just a regular identifier
on the phone that's the first thing and
then I want to say like okay is it an
asterisk around in a fryer that comes
next
in fact probably actually what I would
want to do here say if the token type
equals an asterisk then this thing is a
pointer right we don't really care about
that yet but we'll just say like is
pointer equals true or something like
that so you know it's a pointer and then
get the next token all right something
like that so if it's a pointer it's a
pointer and we could even say that
that's sort of gonna be a thing you know
we could even move that out here so we
just say like okay well parsing token
get token if the token is an asterisk
we'll say it's a pointer something like
that any I guess now I think about it
the original ways probably better for
the shorthand way we probably want to do
this a little bit a little bit
differently if we were gonna have more
than a few seconds to implement it hmm
but assuming its identifier now we have
all the information that we actually
need to print this thing out right and
we I guess we also want to still have
these two cases here where if it's the
semicolon or if it's the end of the
stream we would stop parsing right oh
man
okay hold on one second
I just want to put this printf in here
there we go so this would just be like
that we had here before I just want to
put debug value in here where I print
out that name and that's going to be
again this token assuming is asterisk
it's going to be setting its pointer so
nice identifier
I'm gonna assume that it's the name for
now that's not really the way that we
want to do it because it's not it
doesn't parse everything that we might
want to parse and see but it's pretty
close for now so there we go let's go
ahead and compile that oops and that's
not supposed to do break that's supposed
to be a oops
oh my goodness I know what that does
parsing equals pulse all right so let's
run this and see what happens
Hey look so this as you can see is
pretty much exactly what we wanted to do
so if we come back here to handmade CPP
you can see that we now something that
we were doing manually and we automated
it right and there's a bunch of things
we could do now to this if we wanted to
we probably don't want to output this
this way we've got a lot of cooler stuff
we could do with this if we wanted to
but there you go
so that's introspection in an hour
there's some more stuff you know we'd
want to flesh this out a little bit more
but yeah one hours worth of code you got
an introspective going and you can take
it pretty far from there if you want to
staying on schedule here I want to try
and keep because this is the dev stream
Athan I don't want to be our normal
cells where we go nuts and potentially
go off schedule or do whatever with the
Q&amp;A so I'm keeping on time 30 minutes of
QA and then coming up after me also is
going to be the salt and sanctuary
stream so if you're interested in that
game and you're on the dev stream it's
on that's coming so all right let's go
ahead the Q&amp;A if you could please if you
want to ask a question please put Q
colon in front of it and I'd be happy to
go over anything I know like I said we
kind of wanted to do something weird so
I picked that one because people always
ask me about how to do it on the stream
so now you know and like you saw it's
real real easy you know you can make a
much better one that what I've done if
you spend more than 30 60 minutes and
aren't talking the whole time
but you get the idea
q : I see no Q Cullen's somebody posts a
Q : for me to answer if there is one if
not we can all just chill out
Paul Smith it seems like you are doing
recursive descent parsing is that how
you would describe it yes absolutely I
probably should mention that so
basically there's a number of ways you
can write parsers and and you know since
there aren't I don't see a lot of Q
colons here I'll just you know I'll
start with like just a little bit of
explanation here oops how do I get my
little uh how do I get my little
interface back here where's the way
where did the little where did the
little interface go oh there it is okay
so here we are de 206 and I'll just
mention briefly so for parsing yeah what
I wrote is definitely considered a
recursive descent parser and you know to
be fair actually what I wrote is just a
descent parser we didn't actually use
the recursion yet now we would if we had
done you know if we were doing spending
two hours on it and getting a little
more of the type parsing in there we
would have but what you saw me do is
just to get it going a little faster I
used a lot of these while parsing blocks
so technically the way this works you
wouldn't do it this way the reason it's
called a recursive descent parser at the
recursive part is because normally what
you do is you look at what you got if
you got an asterisk you then call parse
member again on whatever comes next and
you build like a tree that way so I just
did it I did it kind of in a more fast
and loose way but like you know if
Monday we go back if people want to see
me expanded a little if Monday we go
back you would see a little more of the
recursion that you didn't see because I
was just kind of short handing it so I
made things in loops that really
traditionally in a traditional cursive
descent parser
sorry
I didn't pack enough water for this
train so my voice is going yeah it can
just be a smooth jazz stream from now on
um so yes so if you take a look at that
ass that like that Astor's think that
would have been a case where recursion
would have happened the traditional
recursion and and that's how that would
have worked right and I can even I can
even show you kind of more like what
that would look like
you know you could imagine in fact you
know you could just imagine with this if
you took out the the wild parsing thing
so you know I'll just I'll give you the
the more sort of complete example right
so assuming that we did it the more
recursive way what we would do is
something more like this where we say
okay just get the token whatever the
token type is we'll handle it if it's an
asterisk I just want to do parse number
again right something like this and so
that's exactly the same thing right but
it's a little like you know it's a
little cleaner it's a little nicer
potentially and so if I you know if I
wasn't kind of being a little more
compressed there if this was a regular
hammer measures were like let's spend
this week on metaprogramming I probably
would have thought it through a little
more and had something a little bit more
that way right so yeah if you take a
look at how this works do that and
that's right so that's like a recursive
sort of thing where you we kind of go
down like that and so now if we if we
run it you seem to get the same output
but you know I just I was just kind of
like I said I was playing it pretty fast
and loose so this is a little bit nicer
and you know that's probably the one I
would leave in there as well so you know
that's just better that's where the
recursive part of recursive descent
comes in so just just want to clear that
up okay so recursive descent parser
that's where the recursive part is is
this that you assume that instead of
like doing while loops to parse things
that can have multiple components you
use recursion and the stack to do
descent is because we're going down the
stack and up right so you can see that
we start at like the outermost shell and
we look at what the tokens are there and
when we get a token we say okay descend
one level down the stack and look at it
a little bit more carefully decide what
you want to do with it there look at it
again go a little more carefully right
we just send down so you kind of like
you're winnowing down the options as you
go until you finally decide what it is
you actually parsed right so that's a
very traditional type of handwritten
parser right so typically if you're
writing a person by hand like we just
did you write it this way
they're very nice because they're very
flexible you could do anything you want
with them
you can put an ad hoc code to do
anything you need to do
they're very understandable it was
probably I'm guessing pretty easy even
though I went for a faster that for you
to understand what was happening you
didn't just see like a big bunch of
gobbledygook where it's like a what's
happening but there are other types of
parsers right there's like shift reduce
parser x' and things like this and
oftentimes these other kinds of parsers
they use like rolling arrays and stacks
and things and they have jump tables
that are pre you know made on stuff and
what they're typically for is there for
generation so typically what happens is
if you write a parser generator so like
yak or bison if you've ever heard of
these tools they will spit out sometimes
other types of parsers which are machine
they look like sort of machine table
driven kinds of things they're not
really so much for writing by hand
although you could they're just not as
human natural I found what you'd first
write you know and so yes what we what
we did on this dream was a recursive
descent parser it's a parser that's very
traditional in that way very traditional
hand-drawn top-down recursive descent
parser one token look-ahead kind of
thing very very straightforward
sudonym 73 can you please satisfy my C
standard anal retention by accepting /v
and /f as white space mm-hmm
because I like pseudonym 73 quite a bit
I am more than happy to honor that
request for you that is no problem
although to be honest I don't know is
there anything in particular I have to
do like there's nobody all end of lines
on all three platforms are /m r / r
right is to see ever let you end the
line with anything like that doesn't
tell me I've never used one of those so
Guerry Johansson asks have you have you
an opinion
OpenCL see I I've never really used
OpenCL and I definitely don't know what
OpenCL see is but but yeah so I'm sorry
I know I don't have it I don't know what
OpenCL see is how would you handle
errors if you were deep in the recursion
is checking return to us everywhere the
best way so error handling usually what
you do it depends on the circumstance
but usually the reason why error
handling is so bad and compares is
because it is a bit tricky and so
usually what I do is when I encounter an
error I typically do something like I
try to put it enough logic into the
parser for my needs but you can go more
nuts with it and usually what I do is I
have an error token - you know so you'd
have like token error that people can
like pass off the chain and I also have
a tokenizer on the tokenizer you call
error and put errors into the tokenizer
that it like stacks up that's usually
the sort of thing I do
I showed a slate can you explain what
introspection is sure so actually
technically there's different words
there's introspection and there's
reflection and there's different levels
at which these things happen but
basically what we're talking about is in
most programming languages you typically
have well obviously a programming
language is all about specifying
structure of some kind right you
expressing the structure of data you're
expressing the structure of code you're
expressing all of these sort of
structures right and they could be
literal structures I can see it's a
struct it's literally just a collection
of data it could be a function write a
series of things to execute with loops
and whatever and the compiler for your
language knows what these things are it
has to because it has to then turn that
into working code right and so the the
key thing to understand is that
structure actually has a semantics form
somewhere inside the compiler while it's
compiling the code now languages that
have a clue
languages that were made by people who
know what they're doing
that's not even true languages that just
any language should have this but C++
doesn't because it's just not maintained
by people who know what they're doing so
C++ lacks a very crucial feature that
most modern languages have and that
feature is the ability to look at those
structures from within the code right so
the structures that the compiler knows
about inherently you can get them during
the compilation phase and do things with
them that allow you to work with your
code in very powerful ways so for
example here is our entity structure
that we were playing around with on
handmade hero right it has these fields
in it I would like to print them out
there is no way in C or C++ to say tell
me all the members of the cemento t
structure so that I can print them out
you can do it in other languages you can
do it in JavaScript even you know you
can you can do it in all these languages
C let's can't do it and that basic
ability is called introspection it's
also sometimes called reflection which
is if you have the ability I think to
like work to actually do more
complicated operations than that it's
it's sort of a it's it's a thing that
it's a it's a more stringent requirement
I think on top of it but point being
whatever you call it what we're talking
about here on the stream is the ability
to do that sealless else doesn't have it
so what I showed on tonight's dream is
how to implement it right how to put it
back in there because the c-plus welcome
is obviously never gonna get around to
it so you need to write and so that's
what we wrote this is just a very simple
little preprocessor then we can run on
our code and you know here is that
struct right that's the manatees truck
and you can see when I go ahead and run
this right if I could I'll bring it up
on here here's my sim region code and
here's we ran our preprocessor and you
can see it printed out the members right
old junk storage index right that sort
of stuff and we've got some bugs here
like this guy right you can kind of see
even what happened oh you know what I
introduced a bug actually you can see
that we did it correctly before but when
I
did that code just now for the recursive
descent spoke a little too soon so if
you look at that code for the recursive
descent there is sort of a nasty problem
with it which is if you look at these
two guys this one handled the semicolon
end of stream thing it would properly
eat till the semicolon but a recursive
descent thing didn't
so really until we do that I guess I
can't quite switch to that and I'll put
in I didn't mean to undue pseudonym 73's
thing here yeah so it would not have
worked properly the way that we were
doing it before oops
that's I'm in the wrong place okay so
yeah our original one worked worked
better I knew I must have had a reason
for doing that that way but anyway so
you can see that we printed them out
here we got old chunk storage index
updatable type Flags PDP distance limit
collision facing direction t Bob D AB
style hit point max hit point soared
walkable dim and welcome al height right
and so basically what we did there is
add that introspection back in so now
inside our preprocessor we can do
whatever we want with those things right
and that's what that's exactly what we
needed
and what C++ doesn't give us
ah let's see do you well it just says do
you if John does metaprogramming for his
language I assume you mean do you know
if John does Matt a program for a night
do you mean does does it have a program
the answer is yes he showed actually for
the first time the meta programming
features like Wednesday night just this
past Wednesday he showed for the first
time some of some meta programming
features he's added so I think it
probably will be pretty good language
for meta programming based on how it's
going so far certainly much better than
C++ which doesn't support meta program
at all insofar as regretting errors
again would this be a place for
exceptions would actually be useful no
exceptions are never useful I've
literally never found a single
programming problem where exceptions are
better than not exceptions you know your
mileage may vary if you like him you
like him but I I literally cannot tell
you a single time when I've ever thought
that exceptions were the right way to
program something in my whole life there
was a time when I thought that
exceptions were a good idea because
that's what I've been told but if I look
back at all the programming that I've
ever done with my current brain I
literally can't think of a single time I
would ever say to use them they are
never good
I literally don't know of a single time
I would use them everywhere now that we
have the preprocessor do you plan to
make more use of it going forward in
handmade hero I don't know I mean will
at least output the debug will output
the annotation right it'll only take us
a day to switch that to an annotator so
we might as well we've got it right
Hogan long who is John and what language
talking about talking about Jonathan
Blow designer of braid and the witness
and the lead programmer on both of those
products as well he's writing a new
programming language called jei which is
actually pretty far along and it's quite
nice you can take a look at his YouTube
channel Jonathan Blow just search for
Jonathan Blow you too
and you can you could find it about that
Cu voucher I'm writing a parcel looks
pretty similar to this but it runs on
multi gigabyte files which takes a while
any common approaches to use simony
multi-threading to speed up text parsing
seems more difficult since the
characters aren't independent in the way
pixels are you know there's a lot of
ways to speed up parsing certainly so I
suspect that probably you could do some
interesting things there but honestly I
have never done parsing for bigger than
just my codebase and even like just this
method of doing it is always like many
orders of magnitude faster than the
compiler actually compiles it so I've
never had to optimize one of these ever
they're always the fastest part of the
pipeline for me because like Microsoft C
compiler is so slow
that pretty much nothing I ever do it
becomes a compilation bottleneck so if
you're talking about more like you said
multi gigabyte files I do appreciate the
fact that that would necessitate some
serious thought there but I just don't
know I just don't have the experience
with it to know like what you know I
guess what I'm saying is in my head I
can sort of think of things like okay
how would I start to approach it right
but they're just fully speculative and
and I just I just don't know I would
have to actually go tackle that program
prime myself to have it really in the
opinion because it doesn't it's just not
something I ever had to think about
to Sophos the stream makes me feel like
an extremely inferior and incompetent
programmer do you approve of this not
really I mean I guess I would just have
to ask the question like you know
hopefully you know if you look at what I
did there it's not that complicated
right like there's not that many moving
parts - it's very simple it's just
something that takes a look at
characters in a stream and make some
simple decisions about it right and so
you know if you look at that and go wow
he like did that really fast or
something uh you know I've been
programming for like for like oh my god
32 years I've been forgiving for 32
years I've written you know five six
parsers seven parsers something like
this mm-hmm so one of the reasons that
was so fast it's cuz I just already know
basically how it works
right and so it's just it's just very
like second nature for me to type that
out and so you know I would kind of
discount that part of it so what I would
focus on it's like say can you
understand what I did if you just spend
some time look at it and practice a
little bit and if the answer is yes then
you're as good a programmer as I am the
only difference is you haven't written
six of these right and a lot of times
that's a big part of the difference
right the reason that somebody looks
like a good programmer when they're
programming is because they just have a
lot of experience you know the first
couple times I tried to parse tough it
was a disaster I didn't even know about
tokenizing I'd never read a book on
parsing and it was like they're awful
they were like oh he's scared for things
and I remember the first time someone
like told me hmm you should like do a
lexer you should have a thing that
breaks my tokens it's like this huge
eye-opener for me right so I feel like
yeah like don't get discouraged when you
see someone who's been programming
forever like who's an ancient like old
crotchety cane like and I'm not even
making that up like I am on crutches
right now like here are my crutches I I
crushed over to this to do this Deb
stream
and I will crutch out to the other room
when I'm done when you see someone who's
been programming so long if they're on
crutches at this point and they're old
and invalid don't look at that and go
like oh I can't program that well it's
like well duh but that doesn't mean you
won't thirty years from now right it's
just a question of programming every day
and like actually doing the practice you
just get better and eventually you can
program quickly
how does meta programming change your
workflow can you talk about
incorporating generated code with the
regular C files yes so the way they
typically works is exactly what you just
saw basically what we do is we'll take
this and we'll have it start to output
some things that are meant to be read as
standing C structures so for example
what I would probably do right is
instead of outputting this debug value
thing what I would said output is
something like you know here is the the
name you know the the field of the thing
or whatever as a string right and and
I'd wrap that in something like this
right and so this is more what we'd
start to do and now you can sort of see
like okay this starts to be something we
could just insert in a C file right and
so then maybe we're like okay well now
you know we want to insert the sin of C
file we've got this press truck thing we
get the name token out all right so now
it just becomes like let's go ahead and
print out what destruct is right so
we'll say something like hmm carest are
members of right and then we just output
that that thing like members of blah
brackets equals and just going to go
ahead and give you what the idea is here
right right and so you can start to see
how this starts to become like actual C
code and so then you would just do
something you'd imagine you have like
member definition or something right and
then up here when we when we actually
output this thing we would also do like
some kind of type field or something
like this so you know member type token
would be here as well so it would be
something like you know type underscore
or percent dot star s member type token
text length member type token text and
it's not going to work quite right yet
but you can kind of see so this starts
to now right be kind of close to
something we could just read in code and
know exactly what our struct layout
looked like right so basically we do is
we just take that we output that to a C
file and we compile that C file in with
the rest of our C files now we have
introspection data the kind of the C++
spec should have been giving us for the
past two decades and wasn't right so
it's just about getting that in there in
a way we can use so all right so that's
that's pretty much all the time I've got
I don't think I got any more time for
questions so I'm just going to go ahead
and wrap up because if you're watching
the dev stream Athan then you are going
to want to it's gonna roll over here in
five minutes to the Salt sanctuary I
believe is the the next the next step on
the stream so I'm just going to go ahead
and save this out and close down and say
thank you for joining me to this special
edition of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always I
hope that satisfied some people's desire
to see how meta programming how you sort
of start to get that working
that is the basics of it like I said you
saw it can happen in an hour and of
course now it's in the hand made your a
code base so if you're somebody who
wants to play around with it
hand me here org you can always
pre-order the game and it comes with the
full source code so you can just
download the source code and play around
with it and see how that works if you
are still a little confused about how
the meta partner stuff works and maybe
we'll do some more of it on handmade
hero in future streams as well if people
feel like they just want to see like a
little bit more of how that sort of
thing works
so that's about it
until next time oh yeah if you want to
catch the stream live again please do
remember also that we have a little
tweet bot here so if you want to see the
schedule you can see the schedule so
hand made here org you can just go there
and there's a little tweet bot it'll
tweet out the schedule at you and you
can see that it's just like you know
every week it'll it has a little thing
here which will say like here's what the
stream times are gonna be and then every
day it just tweets out a little thing
that tells you what the time is that day
if you're wondering so it's a pretty
handy little guy that's about it for me
if you're watching the dev stream of
thumb it's twitch.tv slash dev stream of
thumb like I said it goes I think for 24
hours I think it started a few hours ago
so it's going all night and it'll go all
day tomorrow as well there's a bunch of
devs on there doing stuff so definitely
check that out if you're someone who
just came for the handmade hero and
hasn't had enough live coding for one
evening
you've got more so you can go ahead and
switch over to that and I guess I'll
just keep talking until 10 p.m. because
I don't know when they'll actually
switch over the stream I hopefully at 10
p.m. exactly so there we go and I guess
I'll take this opportunity also to say
thank you to everyone for tuning in as
always all the handmade hero guys it's
great to see you here every day it makes
it a lot less lonely to code knowing
that there are so many people who come
to visit and yeah I hope you enjoyed
that metaprogramming it was the thing I
had been thinking all week about what I
thought we should probably do and I was
like well we could do you know people
had mentioned me we do some lighting
stuff and me
you do some animation stuff and I think
those were all good ideas but what I
thought at the end of the day is I was
like well you know handmade hero is what
it is you know it's a stream about
actual like very serious programming and
it's about the programming and so I felt
like people who are watching for the
Destry Mathon I didn't want to do
something that would give them the wrong
idea about the sorts of things that we
do here like we do very low level stuff
that's that's what we're about we're not
about like you know making a game we're
about learning to program a game and
those are two very different things
right and so I thought that something
like that would be a good example it's a
self-contained thing I knew I could do
it pretty quickly I've written so many
metaprogramming things in my life I knew
it was something that you know it was we
had a chance again done an hour as luck
would have it we did that was not afford
to have a conclusion and certainly we
you know it was right down to the wire
but as you saw you know that's kind of
the sort of thing that I feel like
typifies handmade hero is that kind of
programming and so I thought that would
be a good example and also something
that people who watch am a hero every
day would also be entertained by because
I know that a lot of people have asked
for that in the past and you know that
they would want to see that so that's it
thanks everyone for joining me and I
hopefully everyone will will stay tuned
for some of those dead students on
things let me know how that is I'll
probably go switch over and take a
little bit of a look at it myself so
take it easy everyone and have fun
coding I'll see you guys back here on
Monday