hello everyone welcome to handmade Hiro
sure we caught a complete-game live on
stream we are gonna do some some
nitty-gritty programming right now I
wanted to clean up some of the stuff in
our asset system I've been wanting to do
it for a while you've seen me put some -
dues in there and and earlier today I
just decided it's time and the thing
that really pushed me over the edge was
I want to be able to do stuff like flush
textures and so on and it was just like
look I'm not gonna go add new features
to this thing when most of what's in
there now is not really that necessary
right you used to do a little bit more
heavy lifting than it did doesn't really
need to do that anymore so I'm just
going to go ahead and take this
opportunity to really like streamline it
and just get it into a simpler more
direct State now that we know what it
needs to do it shouldn't be that hard so
if I take a look at where I don't really
know exactly what we're doing in terms
of texture ops right now I think they're
pretty basic in terms of who does what
with them and when so I don't know let
me just do a quick yeah so I think I
think this is really all that happens
right now is we get the open gel managed
textures thing happening there and and
so really I think most of the texture op
actual work he's done in here right so
there's a call to an it texture queue
and what that does is it says here's
some memory that we're going to use for
these texture ops and then it actually
creates the texture ops inside the
memory that you gave it and I think
that's that's probably fine in other
words this part probably doesn't
actually have to change but what is
gonna have to change is when we go you
know when you actually look in what we
wanted to do in terms of texture ops we
wanted to change this add up bit here
and you can see we have a ticket mutex
it says look when you're accessing the
render texture to it locks up so that
nobody else is gonna do anything to look
you while you're while you're
they're specifically like inside the
OpenGL Manesh textures we've got this DQ
pending thing the DQ pending thing well
I don't know where it actually is don't
ask me why we didn't just forward to
clear it but we actually have the whole
thing on here I don't know why but you
know we do so you know there it is is
there can we move that out of here does
that need to be here for some particular
reason it doesn't really seem like it
should have to be there right it seems
like it should be able to go down here
was there really a reason we couldn't
put it down here right I mean this this
needs to know about it but does it
actually need to you know does it
actually actually need to be done that
way can't we just can't we just do this
yeah it seems fine uh where did that go
there where's oh so I guess well no so
why was that
but why was my was just not picked up I
mean that's that's it right oh I guess
because it has to be done this way is it
actually external I see so that's why we
put it there all right we did have a
good reason we had a good reason I'm
okay with that we wanted to be compiled
into both cases so all right fine I'll
take that but anyway so you can see here
we've got really just these two cases
where we're doing the DQ pending in the
NQ free need to take the ticket
excuse me
and then add up when it actually puts
something on so those are the three
things that actually do something with
the list what we want to do here is we
want to change this around a little bit
such that we have some other steps
involved in the process as well and you
know you can you can kind of imagine how
this needs to work it's a little bit
complicated because we
we want this to be in this part of the
code because we want to potentially
allocate space for our texture ops that
will be for lack of better term flexible
in terms of where they are placed in
memories so for example if we want to in
the future if we were using a more
direct memory model for our like even
our OpenGL transfers or you know if you
were implementing a Vulcan direct3d 11
or 12 or a metal platform layer and you
wanted to basically say here's the
aperture put the texture in there and go
what we want to be able to do is call to
the renderer and say renderer tell us
where to put this stuff right now we're
passing the data in to the renderer we
don't necessarily want to do that we
might want to like create a buffer
that's known mapped into the GPU address
space copied in there and then let the
transfer go you know it's hard to say
what really depends on what platform
whether that stuff matters
you know sometimes that stuff is
pointless doesn't really matter and so
in this case we're really more talking
about putting it on the right side of
the API boundary so that when it does
matter we can do it but I'm not
suggesting it's actually going to matter
for us at the moment it's probably not
an issue for us at the moment
so when we call complete texture up and
we pass it an OP that's actually gonna
be the new place where this stuff
happens right
meaning when we have an OP and we need
to put it on the queue it's still gonna
do basically this so I don't think we
really need to adjust this code too
terribly much this probably looks the
same here and so the nice part is the
the soft failure case we're running out
of opt
we're getting rid of that nastiness now
because instead of actually having this
copy the OP from now on when we do
complete texture up this is an actual OP
weak mq so this actually goes away and
that DQ process in fact I can put it
kind of up in a separate space here
right this process will now work much
more nicely if that makes sense
so when this texture up comes in here
it just gets linked in and that's linked
in of course the networking service by
Microsoft where you can go find other
people who work on web 2.0 or whatever
1.3 or whatever web version we're on now
web squared but so when we complete a
texture off we can link it in the sack
same ways we're looking in iam ofor but
we now have we want to split out that
part where we get the actual ops and the
reason we want to do that is because now
we want that to be able to fail because
remember now we actually handle failure
cases if we run out of like we're trying
to just do too many textures at once and
we run out of texture ops to do the
transfers that's actually fine because
now what'll happen and actually this can
go away right this whole routine is
gonna go away
in fact I'll just delete it because all
of this stuff this is all actually all
of this code is not necessary like all
of this it's not necessary it's all it's
all done goodbye so anyway yeah the
point is when we actually come in here
and and actually want to do a load so
for example if we do load bitmap when we
ask for the texture up what we're gonna
do is say okay if we could get the
texture up then we'll use it and if we
can't then we just won't and and we'll
just force the person to try and load it
again right and so when it comes through
here it'll say well be cued it up for a
load and then we go in and we're like oh
actually we can't load it so we'll just
we just won't right we'll just we'll
we'll reset it so in here what we want
to do is say basically like any time you
can't finish up what you were doing like
in this case we can't do it now the
tasks got checked up here so I don't
really know any reason why we still have
to check it that way right so this stuff
can actually be placed a little bit more
succinctly this cancel texture app can
actually go in here like so so that's
all good and I think that's the the
entirety of the failure handling there
right that's all we really needed to
happen so it's it's just fine all of
this is fine and that all that all feels
reasonable to me right uh when we look
at what's happening here I don't
actually know why we do the task work
equals work think here I I don't get it
like I don't see why we wouldn't just
assign it that way to begin with like I
think it was probably because oh I know
why because we had previously wanted to
be able to call an immediate so since we
don't want to call an immediate anymore
we can actually just do this as well so
again you can see there's just a lot of
simplification that can happen in this
code now that we know we don't need a
lot of the things that we originally had
to have when we were making it work
originally because we just didn't have
as much other stuff in in terms of
support so now if we look at what
actually happens it's pretty pretty easy
for us to condense a lot of this stuff
down you know what I mean so if we look
at what has to happen here again we need
this function now and this is gonna be
where the real fun begins right this is
where we have to actually start thinking
about stuff and so these texture ups
we're probably gonna have a lot less of
them and the reason we're gonna have
less of them is because we probably
don't want to have quite so much memory
sitting around being wasted on just
transfer stuff but you know in general
we're still you know we're still doing
what we're doing so in here where we say
begin texture up and we've got the asset
queue like so and we have a width width
and height then what I think we can do
here is just every time we want to work
with one of these I think we can use the
free list here and just you know do the
exact same situation we know we have a
actual we don't have to do an assert
right we can look at that first free and
we can actually see if we got one you
know what I mean like this and looking
here I think when we queue this in every
time when we bring one back we want to
make the next point equal to zero so I'm
gonna in here also assert that the ops
next pointer is zero she's looking at
what's gonna happen here right so we're
gonna come in here we're gonna say look
we need to do a transfer to the card of
a texture that's here this much you know
this big right a width by height there
it is so what I need you to do is I need
you to give me back an OP it's got that
much memory so what's gonna happen here
when we actually pull out whatever the
first free thing is on the queue we need
that thing to have enough memory and
there's two cases either there's one
case where the result exists but it's
not enough memory another case is when
there's no result at all and what we
could say is if there's no result at all
that'll just be a straight-up failure
case if there's a result that the result
doesn't have enough memory then what we
want to do is basically reallocate that
to be bigger I think there's two schools
of thought here let me kind of tell you
what they are so if we look at how our
transfers are gonna work we're gonna
have two different sized textures and I
guess I don't know where we yes so you
can see here so we've got two different
kinds of textures I don't know if we
really want 512 by 512 as our size for
things do we really want that hey look
this is what we did last time it's one
megabyte per and so we'd only get like
256 are those
guess I don't know how many things would
probably be on the screen at one time in
terms of sprites but like I I do wonder
if 512 by 512 maybe a little aggressive
right but I don't know I mean if you
figure a modern graphics card it's like
a gigabyte of memory then I suppose on
the high end maybe you do want to do
that right I mean you can always do less
so you could always have a mobile
rescale it down so I guess we do want to
start with 512 by 512 and then just say
look we're gonna have a thousand of them
so you better have a gigabyte in your
graphics card and if you don't well
you're gonna have to wait till we do the
lower res switch and then we'll run on
smaller so anyway looking at at this
what I wanted to try and say there was
just that look if we if we look at how
much memory we need in terms of transfer
space then really what we've got is
we've got 512 by 512 by 4 transfers and
we've got 2048 by 2048 by 4 transfers
this one's 16 megabytes and this one's 1
megabyte we don't really want all of our
transfer buffers to be 16 megabytes
because if they were we would end up in
a situation where you know we you know
if they all were that big then we'd end
up in a situation where we're wasting us
a ton of memory think about here I
suppose a circularbuffer would be fine
in this case because you know the
transfers generally kind of go out in
order and we don't really need them to
worry about completing out of order too
much I mean there will be some out of
order nough stew it because they won't
fill in necessarily in a in a proper way
there but you know we could
I don't think I really want to yeah I
don't know yeah that's a tough one
because we could just use a
circularbuffer for it too and just say
look there's 64 Meg's to transfer space
available you just fill it up as you go
around and you can't use more until you
retire up through the you know it
retires in order even if the things
complete out of order so you might have
to wait a little longer to get the
memory back than you would have
otherwise but that's probably fine you
know we could do something like that
just thinking about what that would
actually mean
yeah I'm gonna I'm gonna go ahead and
say that's what we're doing
that just seems better that just seems
way better and so when we look at how
these texture apps work I think then we
we rewrite this part too to be even
simpler than it was before as well so
when we when we do these texture apps we
don't really need to do these as
complicated as they were either when
we're running through those apps those
ops can really just be a instead of a
list they can just be in order so it
could just be a circular buffer right so
the texture list is really just
something that says look I have the
transfer memory right and I have the
transfer memory size and then I have the
transfer memory app and this in general
is just going to roll around and we'll
put in whatever we need there to keep
track of it but we don't need this
anymore and you know each one of these
texture apps then it does have a data
pointer but it also would know in
addition to its data pointer it would
know where and the transfer buffer it
actually was so you would know what you
could free up to when it was done you
know what I mean
and again the Ops would just go in order
so then you would just have a texture op
thing here where it's like look there
can only be this many outstanding at a
time or something like that that's
probably way more than we actually need
but you know who knows so then when we
have our texture ops they don't have
next pointers and you're really just
rolling around in here and looking at
how many there are outstanding right so
this is the opt-out and this is the base
off this is the first off index and
that's it I think that's really it so as
you push them on here you just fill
those out and then when it goes to
actually retire them it just retires
them in order and I think
that's all there is to it this we could
say we could have this happen on two
threads I don't think we need to but if
we wanted to this would be much easier
to have happen on two threads as well
and so that's kind of a nicer thing to
be able to do they're all so right so in
here we just say look here's the texture
op and so on and then all we need to
remember in here is we need to remember
like the the two parameters are told
it's like how big this thing was right
really we only need one parameter here
which is what we will retire to so in
some sense since we have the data we
wouldn't necessary need that but what
I'm gonna do here is say yeah I think I
may just say all right you know really
what what we want to have happen here is
just something that says the I guess
like re up to memory at or something so
basically like that's where as we're
talking about where the like high-water
mark is of this stuff that we have to
sort of advance around that is you know
that is the the value we would we would
advance up to um we could do this in a
way that would be a little easier on
ourselves and maybe I would like to do
it that way right we could just make
these vu 64's and then we just mod them
into the transfer memory size so you
know we would do something like this so
we'd say you know that what's the bottom
three part and what's the top unused
part you know what I mean so we could do
something like that I'm trying to think
if that's easier or harder it might be
easier because that's going to be the
entirety of the complexity there is just
you know
it's just gonna be like do we have
enough free space given the wrapping
point so yeah
I'm not sure does anyone have any
opinions on this
I guess I'll be the u6 start for you
sixty-four us from now I'm going to call
it first used and then I'm going to you
know called a used count so we're just
going to talk about the range and and
that's you know we'll just work with it
from there so you know we'll do that's
what we'll do
and then you hear for texture up we're
just gonna say well you know when this
thing is done then the the last used is
this right
and that'll be used to essentially free
up to that point so that's all we're
talking about here and the renderer
texture cue now and in fact I can just I
don't need the opera's to be what it was
here I'll just make it be that right and
that way there's no free list there's no
nothing that's the entirety of the whole
thing and it does all of the operations
that way right so then it's much easier
when we do complete texture up versus
cancel texture up the only real thing we
need to do here is like mark when these
are completed and when they're not right
we just need to know if they're
completed so we just need a thing that's
here like that's it you know what I mean
and so if we have these various texture
ops like okay there's complete texture
op and there's like you know cancel
texture up I think with the other one so
cancel texture op is just saying that
it's completed without ever ever without
ever actually having it you know get
issued when we do begin texture up and
you know I think we probably need to
since we know that we again this is
stuff that always happens synchronously
basically all this stuff happens
synchronously we don't
you have to do anything more complicated
like we don't need a thing here that
says like is it in flight or in progress
because that's that's all gonna happen
completely synchronously and and unless
we later decide to make it asynchronous
for some reason then we would add the
tracking then but up until then we
really just don't need to at all so I
think complete text your app actually
doesn't do anything meaning it's a call
and we probably want the call to be
there but we don't actually need the
call to do anything at all so when we do
begin texture up I'm trying to even
figure out why we even care about this
at all so
so maybe we do need one think about it
that just says hey it's ready cuz we we
make this and then we're gonna you know
fill it out but it's not ready to use
yet and so we need to wait until this
gets called to know that it's ready I
guess so I guess we do need one piece of
state information here which is like is
it ready so we really need like this
something like that so we would sort of
say yeah like you know what there's a
state value the state value is is
something that generally can get done
asynchronously so like this is a
volatile value in a sense you don't
really have to read it volatile but if
someone were to spin on it you would
want it to be when we cancel a texture
up we would set the state here to be
empty when we complete a texture up that
says that it's ready to be transferred
and when we begin one its pending load
now when we begin the ticket mutex on
here like again I'm trying to think now
I don't think we ever actually need the
mutex anymore like I think we're wait
free now in a sense cuz all we do is
just
hey we transfer stuff when it's ready
and until it's ready we don't and
threads don't care so I think that may
eliminate a ticket entirely possibly and
don't quote me on that because
multi-threaded programming is very hard
so you know I don't want to say that
that's necessarily true yet but anyway
so in here we would essentially say look
okay this
state is that we're pending a load so we
don't want do anything if you cancel it
we just set it to empty and move on if
you are ready to transfer then we are
ready to transfer right and everything's
fine so in order to get one of these
again it's still going to be the same
was before meaning we do have a soft
failure case that failure case is when
the OP count has exceeded the number
that we could support right so if we
come in here and we see that the OP
count cannot support it right we would
say if the Q op count is less than the
ops then we can Q otherwise we cannot Q
you know what I mean so we look and say
look can we queue if we can cute let's
go further forward here when we do this
we want to say it's gonna be whichever
one is the queue off count plus plus now
this is not actually quite right because
again we got this first off index and
that's a wrapping value so actually what
we would do here is say well if we're
gonna use one of these then we need to
move it forward one and so that you know
definitely does that but in terms of
where we are we need to take this value
like op index we need to start at the
first up index and then add however much
we have there that then needs to get
wrapped around so we then need to say
opt index you know mod array count Q ops
to get the you know to get us into the
circular buffer in the right place once
we have that we're ready to go and we
can proceed as as necessary right so we
can say here's the the text for handle
well I guess they're gonna fill out the
texture handle we don't care about that
so we would say here's the data to fill
in the transfer memory last used and the
state
and all this stuff goes away right uh so
that's you know again pretty nice and
clean but now we have an additional
check we have to make so really it's
it's not just this we also have to make
sure that the memory that you're asking
for is memory that we actually have
right because we might not have right we
might not have the memory now there's
two ways we can because this is a
wrapping buffer there's two ways we can
do this one way is to actually use split
loads and so what would happen there is
if you asked for say the 16 megabyte
large download but you were right at the
end of the buffer and there is only one
megabyte of transfer space left it would
give you that megabyte and then 50
megabytes in the beginning you'd split
load into the two halves then when it
goes to to do the texture update it
would actually split update using the
two halves as well right
so crazytown that's if we wanted to be
super efficient we would just do the
extra code there because you totally
could not really worth our time I don't
think in this case because it's only for
the end of the buffer it doesn't really
matter so what I'm gonna say here is
we're just gonna look at how much memory
we have left before the end of the
buffer and how much memory we would have
if we reset to the beginning of the
buffer if either of those two things is
enough we go ahead if we don't then we
just say no you can't do it yet you got
to wait till some of the ops finish
right very simple so here's the size
that we need it's the width times the
height times the pixel density right so
when you do begin texture up we're gonna
ask for this we will maybe ask for more
than that later when we need to start
transferring MIT maps so this could get
more complicated so we want it boil it
down to a science requested because we
want to be able to change this later
we're gonna look at the size requested
we're gonna say first of all if we look
at how much member
we've got you know we've got the the
amount that's used so in here we kinda
have to say we need this actually have
we and we don't have here how much total
trance remember there is so what we want
to do is say alright there's two
possible ways we can load this one is we
can reset to the beginning of the buffer
the other is we can load from where we
are right now and so in order to do that
we have to compute a temporary set of
values right in here so what we need to
do is say well if we were to load if we
were to load at the current location
then that would be that would be here
and this is wrapped by this value right
so you know if we were to do this then
this right here is sort of a wrapped
value so yeah like you need to you need
to mod by whatever the size of it's
gonna be here and I mean and we could
make that a power of two if we had to if
this was like really heavy pressure but
it's not gonna be so doesn't super
matter but anyway so we do the memory at
here we say look whatever this is
wrapped that's where the memory actually
starts so that's the location that means
that there are sort of two sizes if we
start there
we know we can go to either first used
or the end depending on which of the
cases we have and if first used is in
front of us or behind us that sort of
tells us which wrapping scenario we've
got right so let me just draw that for
you
so if you imagine that we have it in our
buffer we've got a particular point and
we've got a particular size then the
total amount we could load is either
this amount or this amount right so we
can either load this much or this much
but if instead you know and this was the
start pointer so this is the used amount
if instead it looks like this then this
part is technically back here right and
so in that case we can only use just the
part that's in between so we have two
different cases to look at one is if we
wrap and one is if we do not wrap and I
think those are the only two cases right
so either we've got to or we've just got
one that's my story and I'm sticking to
it
and so what we need to do is
differentiate between those two cases
and we can tell which one it is by
whether or not we wrapped so what I
could do is actually do it this way and
say look if memory AK is greater than or
equal to the count
you know like meaning we've gotten to
the point where we would have to wrap
around this is like the used space wraps
around otherwise
so in the case where it wraps around
that's actually easier case because then
what we know is it's just where ever we
would have been right so then when we do
the mod right so we do like memory at
minus equals transfer memory count so
now we know like this we know this
location here and we can just say the
max size you know the max size in that
case is just wherever the used space is
being started - where we are at right so
that's where we're at and here's how
much we could do here's how much we
could use in the other case where the
use space is just one chunk that means
we have two spaces so you say perhaps
around one continuous usable space the
new space is contained so this is the
used space is you know it doesn't wrap
to useable spaces on either side so what
we want to do there is say let's get the
size available by saying wherever the
memory at is we want to take the total
size in this case look at you know we
want to look at that size now that we
know how much available there is we are
ready to go if however that's too small
we could instead try also the other one
which is starting from the beginning and
looking up to a memory app so if size
available is too small so meaning this
right then what we can do is compute it
differently and say okay memory at is
actually going to be instead equal to
two zero
we're gonna start at the bottom and the
size available is going to be
computed this way know what I mean
which actually cook it happens to be the
same computation as here you know what I
mean so that's fine we could simplify
this computation a little bit by just
having actually having the memory stop
location be a thing that we pass out I'm
not gonna do that I think that's fine
it's perfectly legible the way it is so
that's how that would work right so then
we come down here and say whatever we
work we know we did the best we could
there so if the science requested will
fit right and and I guess I could phrase
it the same way as I phrased it at the
top there just to be clear so if we can
fit the thing that we want and there
actually is room in the opto and
probably I should do this in the other
order because honestly why bother with
all this work if there aren't any ops
available anyway right that seems like a
force that's why I do that like don't
bother actually spending all your time
computing where to put this thing if you
know you can't actually issue the
operation anyway so assuming we could
issue the operation and there's room
then we're done now all we have to do is
say all right going here get the up in
question get ready to fill it out we
know where the data is it's just the
transfer memory of the q plus the
location at where we want to put it we
know exactly where the transfer memory
last years is going to be it's just
gonna be this memory at location plus
the total size that we were requested
and that's it right that's the end of it
so unless I screwed something up like
that in tot which I probably did but you
know hopefully I'm not missing anything
major and we'll just be able to bug it
that entire thing is that asynchronous
like texture transfer q4 variable size
texture things that would just work and
could be done multi-threaded if you
wanted to we don't have multiple threads
that can issue texture requests at the
moment we do we just have multiple
threads that can finish texture requests
but I think that just does everything
right and it could transfer arbitrary
size texture is just fine
so then all we need to do now we say
well all right now we just you know when
we set up these things we do have one
more thing that we need to do also by
the way in it texture Q is now
incredibly trivial and doesn't require
any memory either for the texture ops
although what we probably want to do
here is act as make it so that that we
probably want to make it so that what's
the word I'm looking for
I'm drawing a blank oh we probably want
to make it so that that they can pass in
what they're using for the transfer
memory maybe or like how much they want
but I feel like we probably need to
allocate it because it's kind of coming
it might come from the graphics layer
itself you know what I mean so you can
see why I'm a little like I think maybe
you're not you really shouldn't have it
be passed in like that anymore
yeah
so I think maybe we're just gonna want
to do something like okay you know
requested transfer buffer sighs you know
what I mean
and so then in here we would just say
well you know none of this stuff happens
anymore or that's just not true we go in
here to the queue and we say well the
transfer memory counts is going to be
the requested transfer buffer size the
transfer memory first used 0 the
transfer memory used count is zero and
the transfer memory is like some kind of
something where we get graphics card
memory maybe or we don't or who knows
what
right the OP count zero the first ops
zero and that's all there is right so I
think then if we look at what happens
here this it's really just the transfer
memory piece that's a little bit
Squinkie and so what we want to do is we
want to look inside the open gel side of
things here and we want to probably
supply that memory access or in here you
know what I mean so when you actually do
the init texture cue it would need some
way of getting like it needs a way to
access this I'm going to go ahead and
turn back on our render or testbed
because I think that'll be a good way to
test this stuff out and also we want to
make sure that still compiles you know
what I mean in fact what I could do is I
can even I can REM out even the game if
we wanted to but you know at the moment
we can just focus on this part this
stuff DQ pending in NQ free now go away
by the way they're just gone entirely
they don't have to do anything and so
really what we're focused in that on now
here is like the OpenGL managed textures
bit of things and so in terms of getting
like buffer memory to transfer this
stuff like I said I don't know that we
actually want to do that per se we could
later but at the moment I don't I think
we want to just not take on that
additional ball of wax because that's a
graphic GPU programming issue that we
probably just want to leave to a
separate time and that's when we think
we want to play with is how to most
efficiently get those transfer buffers
so what I would want to do here is have
a way that we can allocate memory that
actually just works in terms of yeah
like in terms of how this this texture
queue is initialized and it sort of
needs it needs to be able to thunk
through like needs to be
platform-specific potentially do you
know what I mean and that's a little
unfortunate because it complicates that
code but like if we really want to be
serious and say that you know you could
go implement a serious renderer in here
somewhere I just don't see any way to
not do that like you're gonna have to do
you're gonna have to allow it to
allocate the transfer memory that's just
it's not plausible to claim that this
would be a a real render layer if it
couldn't do that because you know that's
gonna happen on most platforms so if we
look at how the renderer gets loaded
here again I think that means that the
way that we're doing texture queues we
vacillated a little bit with how we were
doing the texture queues I really think
what that means is that in it texture
queue call is is really gonna have to
move into the platform specific
part of this right another way to say
that would be you could still do this
meaning you could still say how big this
was and pass the memory here but it
really should be something that gets
done inside the renderer side of things
so I think we can probably still do this
but I think we're gonna have to I think
we're gonna have to move this stuff into
the platform specific side eventually
you know maybe not this part this could
be shared but the actual it would be a
thunk and the actual one would do a
buffer lock around it if that makes
sense and a buffer unlock here
potentially so I think we're gonna have
to do that move and I'm okay with that
but you know off we go
so so I think in it texture cue is fine
like that now so and we'll like make
sure we call that with with more space
so like for example I'm here where we do
in it texture cue so in here and we've
got like Tex cue membrane whatever
nonsense is going on here like this is
not what we want anymore at all so that
you know would go away and this is
probably not how you would want to do
that either you'd probably want to just
get the pointer you know actually
haven't allocate you know you would get
a texture through out of this and so
when we call like win32 init default
renderer here and we get back the
platform renderer you know inside that
platform renderer where is that platform
renderer so inside that platform render
I think you know it gets what I'm trying
to say is I think what we're getting at
is the texture cue is just gonna be look
in there right like when you get that
you're gonna get that back from win32 in
a default renderer and so you know it's
it's not gonna look like this any
more it's gonna look more like this and
I'm not sure
so inside win32 handmade renderer we
call win32 load up in jail renderer and
how does it actually allocate the memory
it's close once we do render Alek
alright so I think that's how it's gonna
go
you're gonna pull the texture cue out of
there you're not gonna call this anymore
you got to get the textview out of the
platform renderer and so again I
actually love that that I mean that's
great
the reason I really really like that is
because if you look at what has to
happen now the users of the code don't
really have to super understand what's
going on there anymore right it's just
kind of like I don't know you know I
know there's a text to cue and I know
it's set up for me somewhere somehow
right like right and so I think like the
only thing we would really want to do
there is maybe pass down how big we want
that to be and so in here we would say
oops something like you know I when we
do max Claude camp for frame you know at
the end maybe at the end of all that we
would say like the texture transfer
sighs so handmade textured transfer
buffer size like that and then you know
who knows remember where we specify that
stuff
it's just an handed platform so in here
you know these yeah weak these could be
things that are gonna be set more
dynamically in the future but so I want
them pass through because I they're not
gonna probably be pound to fines forever
they'll they'll be something that's a
little bit more dynamic um so you know I
don't know maybe we say that there's you
know a pretty large amount of texture
transfer space for now because why not
that would allow us to transfer 64
sprites per frame which is seems maybe a
little low but you know maybe we want
more than that ideally I'm not sure
maybe we want to do more like hundred
twenty-eight sprites for frame optimally
again the bandwidth to the graphs card I
don't really know what the balance of
this graphics card is anyway so I'm not
sure what's realistic to expect there
but either way so anyway that's all well
and good everyone's happy and smiling
and everything's great and you know
little kids are dancing around a lot
stuff and whatever they do and so now I
want to be able to pull out that so when
we actually have the texture cue right
the texture cube goes through the game
memory there and we do that the process
texture cue the thing I like about that
is you don't have to call this anymore I
don't think so in other words this call
goes away too so I think all you have to
do is pass it you would you don't have
to call that function that's my argument
anyway that's that's what I'm going to
claim and so you really just have to go
oh yeah the texture cue is in there
somewhere I'll you know that'll be
whatever I'll do that it's great it's
good
no one cares and that means like in the
code that again like if we take a look
at our usage code here where we do like
texture cues and stuff that now doesn't
have to actually happen so again it's
really great it simplifies the texture
cue
entirely because we don't have that
problem anymore
right so this stuff processed texture
cue can just not happen right ever
it just happens automatically and I
think that's much much much much better
right so I love all that that's all
really good it also means that up here
right this stuff gets simpler now we
don't care about that and so we've got
the max texture count and we also have
the texture transfer buffer size and you
know who knows what that is but in this
app it's probably smaller right
who knows
and so texture transfer buffer size that
all looks good and then we don't have to
do any of this so again it just makes
our render even better because now it's
like all that stuff that you were
worrying about before not only can it
now be done on the hardware side if you
want to so we can lock a memory that's
actually aperture mapped properly but
you also don't have to know about it so
anyone who uses the renderer is just
free to have a party without ever even
knowing what a texture transfer buffer
is and the only thing they really have
to do is have some idea of how much
textures they're trying to push through
it per frame so they don't set this
number too low right that's all they
really have to understand and they don't
really even have to understand that if
the default values are set particularly
well you know then it should be fine
right um so that seems pretty good to me
and I think that that just makes
everything better so I'm a huge fan
and I claim that that's what should
happen now when we actually are in open
jail here and we'd go to do our manage
textures we want to do the manage
textures probably like on end frame
before we do anything we'll try to kick
off those
we'll try to kick off those ops so
open-field allocate texture you know
does this bit right here I'm gonna say
let's go ahead and bring that in I don't
know why that's outside I don't think it
really should be I think we probably
want that in here because this asked
this all has to happen together it can't
really be spread out if that makes sense
[Music]
so this isn't gonna do what this isn't
gonna work this way anymore because
remember we don't actually have a linked
list anymore so we know that this is
what we want to do on each individual
texture as we spin through it what we
don't really understand yet is what we
need to do to actually process the
stream and up put that aside for a
moment and just say when we do open gel
manage textures here inside em frame I
would do that automatically so when we
come through here and we do it we after
we process the changes that change the
settings we're gonna kick off any text
or downloads we can write because we
know we're gonna need them soon possibly
on this frame but you know not
necessarily so we want to go ahead and
get that cue going what I don't remember
is the OpenGL part of things what is
that is that it's OpenGL yeah open oh
yeah this right here so the platform
render here it's got it in there so I
think it's to get the cue like again you
don't even have to pass it in it's just
here so there's the texture cue you know
problem solved and so every time here we
can just like kick off our textures
before we go to actually do anything
else
with the actual render buffer and we can
change the settings first so if we need
to reallocate texture buffers that'll
happen here so when we do OpenGL manage
textures now we need to do is we need to
actually have some maybe utility
function probably in the renderer side
of things they can get you know as we go
through they can get our ops off in a
way that that's easier for us to work
with right and so what we want to do is
in here when we dequeue one of these we
want to do the right updates to these
transient values to make them still be
consistent and so that's really what
we're trying to do here when we do the
DQ so what we know we want to do first
is just say look we're only gonna run
this thing while there are some ops in
the queue so the very first thing we can
say is just you know don't do anything
if there aren't any office in the queue
because that's a totally valid
situation rested begin we don't know
that somebody asked to download textures
so the off count maybes just zero there
may be no ops at all so if there is an
op then that's when we would start
actually looking at things so if we
wanted to look at what was going on we
would say alright there's a texture op
the OP in question that we're going to
look at first it's going to be the ops
array plus whatever the first op index
is so we give that one out right now we
need to see is can we process this one
right you know can we even process this
one so we look and we say well okay if
we look it and see what its state is we
want to look and go if it's empty
then we would skip it right so we kind
of want to have this part of the routine
only occur if we're actually saying it's
time to transfer right so if this thing
says ready to transfer we want to
actually send the data down if it
doesn't say ready to transfer then what
we have to do is say well what if it
said stop right what if it said I'm not
actually loaded yet so I can't actually
tell what I should be doing here right
and if that's the case then I can't
advance any further right I can't do
this actual OP um I think we want to
check that first meaning if we can't
then we just break otherwise we look to
see if it's ready to transfer and if
it's ready to transfer then we do the
transfer if it's not that means it must
be empty so we can actually assert here
that it's empty because it's not either
of these it has to be this I don't think
there's a race condition there because
you can't set something
from pending load to empty or from ready
to transfer to empty so if it was empty
I guess well no that's not entirely true
no okay
the only it can only go the only thing
can do asynchronously is go from pending
load to ready to transfer so it's gotta
be one of these two always
asynchronously so asserting for this is
always valid because the only thread
that could have said it to this is us so
we know we aren't setting it behind our
backs to empty so I I stand by that if
we move this to be completely
asynchronous so that multiple threads
could be requesting textures at the same
time while it's doing the texture
retirement here then it's a different
ballgame but that's not what we do the
only thing that we do asynchronously is
move something from a pending load to a
ready to transfer that's it so as long
as we make sure that this ready to
transfer thing is at least a little bit
fenced do I have any other of these yeah
so as long as I make sure that that I
don't actually read these out of order
we're probably okay so I think that
probably should be fine
all right so in here I think that's all
good and we issue the transfer I don't
even really know if I need this because
if you ever could have gotten this in
the first place then when you go to
actually use this it's the data pointer
can't be stale it's so it's actually the
other in fact I'm not even gonna bother
with that because if you think about it
all of this stuff that data was set long
ago long before we even issued the read
so this it's only the GPU that would
have to worry about the data being stale
it's um in some sense right so forget
that you're not gonna do that
so all this transfer stuff works exactly
the same way that it does so the only
thing that we now need to do in here is
we need to make sure that when you are
either like when you pending load you
we stop we don't go any further but when
we transfer or are just looking at a
null op then what we do is we have to
actually move these these around right
so that's the big part of the circular
buffer so when we want to move them
around we have to do is say all right
first of all we're gonna take the OP
count and we're going to decrease that
by 1 because we did retire an op right
we did move past one we're gonna
increment the first OP index cuz we are
moving forwards and then if that first
op index is greater than equal to the
total amount that we have we're gonna
reset the beginning of the list so we're
gonna bop backwards and and go back to
the very first op and start you know
plowing through through them that way
right so we go off the end come back
around so that's a pretty weight easy
way to retire the OP that is I think
just done like I don't think there's
much else to worry about there this
parts more complicated so now we have to
do is worry about the transfer memory
because now we have to move the transfer
memory forwards to coincide with where
it should be based on on retiring this
texture op right that actually might
just be trivial because we set ourselves
up for success by saying each texture op
just remembers where where the end of
the memory needed to use was so we can
advance this forward now granted if you
look at what happens here really what we
would need to do is set up what's called
a fence on the GL side of things if we
were using a mapped buffer since we're
not using a map buffer the copy occurs
here from our memory to GPU aperture
space the that CPU to CPU copy happens
here which means we can immediately free
up the memory right now we would
probably add another like tracker in
here for fenced memory transfer so that
in the future we could overlap those
transfers better without a copy we're
not going to do that now but if we
wanted to make this more efficient GPU
wise you know we would be looking at
that alright so I think that in here
once you retire this off all we really
have to do is say the transfer memory
first used now becomes transfer memory
last used of the app right and so the
only complicated thing here that we've
got to do and it is a little tricky is
we we want to be able to reduce the
total amount of memory used by that now
maybe I should just make things easy on
myself and just say transfer memory
count here and so then if I did that I
could just do this I'm all in favor for
making it easier a little bit there yeah
we got a saw an extra you 32
no one will care about that there just
aren't enough ops as compared to the
footprint of textures that they're
actually transferring so it's like don't
be penny wise pound foolish there ain't
gonna make a difference to our footprint
at all so so that's gonna be totally
fine for now so in here what I'm gonna
say is look I'm just gonna say transfer
memory count in here it's just gonna be
that size requested and then and then
we're you know we're done with that
right
I can also assert here this is within
the range that it should be so I can say
you know I really want to make sure that
pointer is you know less than you know
one of these the the transfer memory
plus the transfer memory count like
basically like when you actually
complete one of these things and are
ready to cue it off let's make sure that
we're not put you know passing totally
bogus nonsense here but I think that's
that's basically we want so this right
here now we'll just do all of our
texture transfers
and off we go again no need for free
lists no need for any of that stuff this
is all off the queue so I got to go
ahead and throw a Q star on there and if
I got them all that's not gonna let me
do that is it that's fine I could do it
like this right just verify that the
memory app is within there and the last
one we used is within there like nobody
wrapped around like it's all good yeah
all right let's keep on truckin
so we got our state here this is on op
what else you got for me so when we call
an it texture Q here someone's gonna
have to actually do this work so that's
a little bit Squinkie
so in here where we doin it texture Q
that's gonna have to be routed properly
like so you know in here when we
actually do one of these render Alex we
would have to do the emit texture Q in
the same way
and the pointer to process texture q can
go away too so actually also this gets
simpler right that is not a thing
anymore so it's really only the
frame so yeah this just keeps getting
better if you think about it it's pretty
great now it's literally just those you
know so I that's just fantastic I'm just
loving how this is coming together it's
very very satisfying okay so in here
we've got render texture Q we know we've
got it so because we know it's it's just
this but we need to initialize it and so
what we want here is the requested the
the requested transfer buffer size is
actually you know something we're gonna
have to put in here and we need to
actually allocate that memory so it's
it's really just gonna be this and in
the future like I said we can maybe do
that a little more cleverly and actually
get buffers that we you know
specifically want there but now I'll
unwind that those calls and make sure
that these we don't need that and make
sure that everyone passes the right
stuff so in it texture cue is now in
that unhappy place where that's like you
know a thing that's again part of sort
of a it's an it's in a weird place but
I'll stick it like so
when we do the load and this is the
transfer the texture transfer of
emphasize that goes in here so that
win32 oops that winter to load now has
that in it and it gets passed through
here we should really consider bundling
those you know when you look at it now
it seems like that should be a bundle
while I'm in here I may just bundle them
that seems you know better
because now you used to look at all this
stuff that has to change why bother
right why not just go up here and say
look the parameter to this system going
to struct so in here when you're going
to call one of these there's something
like this or that you know and maybe
limits something like that and all these
things just sit in there so now you know
you just pass one of those along and we
don't really have to deal with it
anymore like all of these things that
that do pass throughs they don't have to
keep changing which is you know nice
they just pass through that and then if
things get added to that then it gets
passed through automatically right and
that seems a lot nicer to me
certainly all right
okay so I think that's just gonna create
some typing for us here to actually put
in that change but other than that I
think we're in good shape
oops all right so platform renderer
limits
okay so yeah let's see what else we got
here so we need to change the way that
the textures are getting submitted in
here when we initialize our test scene
we need to submit those textures and you
can see here we need to actually do the
operation the the new way of doing the
operation which thankfully is very very
simple so really all we have to do is
say I would like to begin a texture up
please
here is my texture Q which is texture op
Q and then I will tell you how big it is
like so I will then set the texture
handle but the data is already set on it
right so in here we don't actually do
any of this we would just say complete
no I'm saying this yes so this actually
I think that means we don't have to
allocate anything here either so
actually this yeah this would just work
we can write directly into there if we
want to so what we can do here right you
see the pixels we do this nonsense so
you know it it's too bad we have to do a
copy here because we could maybe just
load it in directly but I'm just gonna
do this so here's what I'm going to do
I'm going to take this we'll just stick
that there and my guess actually I'm
gonna call that the result and I'm gonna
say I'm gonna say all of these things
cuz we don't actually need to return
those I'm gonna change the way this
routine works a bit and just say once we
get down here we can actually yeah we
don't need the pitch or any of that
stuff so in here we can just actually do
the texture up properly we can say where
was that begin to die accidentally
delete the begin that was not smart
there it is
so in here yeah I'm just gonna say let's
put this stuff right here will actually
make this copy into the texture queue we
will refer to the texture here and I
think that's all we really needed there
here and I mean then the destination
will be this thing so the only thing we
want to do is make sure that begin
texture up if it fails we don't actually
try to complete the transfer here
I don't know if we got error reporting
and again that can't really happen in
this Tesco but just so people who were
looking at the test code didn't think
they could just count on the OP coming
back properly that's all so I think
that's all good and so in here instead
of source test what we want to do is
actually have an actual desk um I don't
know why that looks like that but you
know it would be like this so you know
we would look at the source and then we
would have the desk like so and I think
that's really all there is to it right
now why we're using you int instead of I
don't know why we're we don't have those
as our standard type sir but I guess
that's just the way the cookie crumbled
um that's all good and so yeah in this
case texture up result just needs to
always be returnable there even if you
didn't get one
alright so renderer test is now good to
go I think so I think that means we can
go ahead and try debugging that method
of trip that method of texture transfer
just so we know that it is working at
all you know what I mean we can switch
to the renderer test app here and debug
build as well and then this is kind of
nice having the testbed because it means
we can debug in a much simpler scenario
then we would have had to do otherwise
so this is great now we can go see like
what's going on with the texture
transfers and why are they broken and
whatever else is going on right so we'll
start there let me just see what's up
all right so clearly tell anything by
that let's let's step in and watch the
texture transfers fail and where they
fail and how and so on so we can get
some kind of an idea of what's going on
what is that little that just mean
that's the start of a function or
something okay great can't wait to see
what's in there so I'm gonna go ahead
and let's see jump to
something something good where my
where's my load BMP okay here we go
so I'm gonna jump down here I want to
look and see like just the basics you
know just get everything in here working
so first of all you know did it even get
initialized right so looking at the size
of this I don't remember what we said
for how big it was supposed to be what
did we say did we say this I'm hoping is
that we said no what did we say 16 times
it maybe what what did we say we'll
start there what did I actually ask for
I don't even remember
oh I mean they're in the wrong file -
there we go um so I just wanted to see
like I don't remember what we asked for
for the texture transfer size and so I
want to make sure that that's actually
getting set properly so that doesn't
look right so I think we're already a
little wrong so I'm just going to step
in here so if I look at the limits
that's the number of the spectrum you
see so this this is the numbers I
respecting let's jump in here so if we
go into a nip default renderer you can
see us grabbing the actual renderer that
we want here and then we jump in here
and start the initialization of opengl
so we've got the text of transfer of
oversize we're passing that in both
cases so I'm gonna look in texture queue
there and I want to see what's going on
so here we are in the transfer Q so we
initialize that properly that all looks
right what did i do today
so this doesn't properly increment the
used count does it
so the transfer the queue in this case
we add an OP but we don't actually add
the memory so this actually should be
queue transfer memory used count right
that should actually go up by the amount
we used I think everything else can stay
the same but that can't right because
this stays in the same place this has to
go up so I think that's correct so we
you know we advanced by that size that
we've requested so I think that's what
we want there that looks fine to me
but what I'm not sure about is then on
cleanup when we come through here
that that also but that also does look
okay alright so now I want to I want to
read rerun through here
and and because that was wrong but again
so after a knit texture cubed jump in
here just want to see what's going on
so there's the queue it looks looks good
and if I look at this I just want to see
what's up
functions the old opengl party so that
all looks pretty good actually we come
down through here let's see what the
renderer thinks of things that all looks
right so it looks like we're starting
off good we try loading a bitmap here so
you know now we're gonna come down here
what's the texture up cue have to say
that all looks good so now we can get
started alright so can we get an op we
should because we should have all of our
ops free how much do we want we want
that much size right and so now we got
to see how much we can actually get so
we look at where the memory is memory is
that zero right because nothing's used
so now we have to see is the memory at
higher than you know is it would it have
wrapped right and the answer is no
correctly so the slides available is
like the full size of the transfer
buffer so that's actually fine that
means we can get we can do this if we
want to so the size available inside is
requested
oh that's yeah that's backwards well
that answers that question
that's how I wanted to write it the
first time I don't know why I didn't do
that I was like oh we should keep
consistent that that's a different check
so let's try that one more time so we
find that yeah we can't actually use
this thing so here's our op index it's
zero now the OP count should be one and
it is we then come through and say
alright we've got a result so this
result is the one we're actually gonna
fill out right here's our texture
transfer so we set the data equal to
point two what should basically be the
transfer memory writes the base the
transfer memory yep we say the amount is
however that was the last used is going
to be that same value because that's
where you would move to afterwards I
think that's okay so depending load
which it is we use that much of the
memory we then assert that everything's
okay in this case we got the OP loaded
properly so we pack the texture in there
and then we complete the OP that's just
doing the copy complete texture up just
kicks it off it says it's ready to
transfer and so we're all good right
that should just be that then when we go
into you know the actual rendering code
what we want to do in there is look and
see when we do end frame which is here
let's make sure that the renderer
actually does that stuff properly with
the with the sending the textures down
so here's the manage textures call there
should be one for every texture and
there is we come in here we grab one off
this is it we should also look here and
we can see how much is used blah blah
blah so in here we look to see you know
is it pending load what is it you know
what
here well they all should be ready to
transfer because this ain't asynchronous
so everything should be loaded so we
should hop right to this case and we do
so that's good there's the data we're
going to transfer it's not a special
texture because it's actually small
enough so we drop it down and then the
question is like do we handle this right
so let's see so the first thing we need
to do is we need to reduce the amount of
memory used by the memory that we got
here and so that looks like it worked
properly then we need to move it up to
so that the first used is now past that
right and that we do we reduce the OP
count down and we move the next you know
so we will be looking at the next stop
and then we just look to see whether or
not we've wrapped and in this case we
definitely have not wrapped right so we
haven't actually gone over the total of
the array so we can just keep on going
we keep doing this and it should just
work I think right and at the end when
we're all done
when we get to the last stop you know
we're looking at the OP can't there's
two and here's more and now that we're
done when we look at the queue we should
find that there's no memory used right
and that's accurate
so that looked good and hey if we look
at this that looks great
look so so hey good we only made one
mistake that that is the only thing we
screwed up would it worked first time ah
what are you gonna do so that looks like
the renderer test everything in there
this looks totally fine so I think we
don't have to worry about that problem
now so the next question is what if we
tried to stress out the system a little
so you know there's probably bugs there
in the wrapping so what if instead of
giving it the easy case what if we said
hey you know what you only get three
well it can't really do the wrap because
we don't call process textures so you
can transfer that but instead of the
transfer memory here
yeah I guess we can't relate times I'm
sorry I can't test that here we should
create a test case for that here because
it would be easier to debug it
but yeah you can't really yeah we can't
we can't really test that here in a
meaningful way so I guess we just won't
can do that later okay so now we can
take the game code and now that we have
a different texture transfer stuff set
up now that we should be able to make
this the asset system we should make the
asset system work with that texture
transfer code and that shouldn't be too
hard we can stub out the sound stuff for
the moment because we updated both of
them and then we can do the sound stuff
in in a separate pass so taking a look
here at a loaded bitmap we know we got
rid of that and so this stuff that's
happening here again not just really
just not necessary so we can kind of we
can kind of just ignore it the asset
itself has the texture handle in it you
know what I mean so it really looks more
like this if that makes sense we don't
need the loaded bitmap into him anymore
in terms of the size of the read that's
happening here the read size is just
gonna be whatever the bitmap size is in
total so I think we could also just make
the OP we could we could use the OP to
give us that back in a sense I don't
know that we really want to do that but
we could meaning this right here has
already computed that but I'm not going
to do that because the read size could
actually differ from that in the future
so instead here I'm just gonna say look
the read size is going to be bitmap
width times bitmap height times four
because that's what it actually is
um texture up memory in this case for
destination it's just data it's not
memory we changed the name of that the
finalized operation parameter is is not
a thing anymore it went away so now
inside load sound what I'm going to do
inside load sound is just say you can't
load sounds any more and then we'll come
back in here and we'll implement the
sound loader in a cooler way and that'll
be the end of it okay so when we do a
load font we need to actually get the
asset in question here it looks like
we're just proceeding under the
assumption that we already accessed it
but we definitely didn't right and so
that needs to be put in here yeah there
we go
acquire asset memory again not really
necessary so this is a different when
we're doing asset memory allocations
here these are things that I don't think
we ever actually have to worry about
multiple threads pulling on those at
once so I think what we want to do there
is we want to by the way how much time
do we have
I might want to take a quick break and
come back to do this because it goes I
might want to spend another hour on this
I can't decide I think I might want to
come back to this a little bit later but
we'll see and like because I don't know
if I want spend another hour on this and
if I do I might want to take a break and
refill Mike my waters out and everything
yeah let's do that let's I don't want to
I don't want to rush this part because
we're about to do the rest of this so
I'm gonna say let's take a quick break
and we'll come back so I'll start up the
screen again in a second I'm gonna go
ahead and I'm gonna go ahead and stop
the recording okay we have brac we have
had a snack we have refilled the water
we are good to go
we are not in entire our voice is not in
dire need of hydration dihydrogen
monoxide we have we have increased our
dihydrogen monoxide take so that's good
all right so a choir asset memory in
this case is just a situation where we
have font data and we don't really want
to load all of the font data that we
have so even though font data doesn't
really need to get evicted because it's
small we if you imagine the case where
you have 30 different fonts because
maybe you had lots of language
localization you don't want to load them
all so you still want to actually just
be careful about you know how much
you're using there in the non restored
memory pool there so we don't really
need require acquire asset memory I
don't think we can pretty much do a
direct push so we can we can pretty much
just say look give us this much out of
the out of the NAM restored memory pool
and we'll just go from there so I think
that's good enough for the fonts like I
said we're just gonna load those at the
outset for the ones we actually care
about and then be done for a given
situation
we can get fancier and allow eviction of
fonts in the future if we really find
that we need to but for the moment I
just doesn't seem relevant okay so yeah
in
here we're just getting rid of the
concept that we have the work asset
stuff to begin with because now we just
don't have that happening anymore in
here I guess I'm not sure what we would
do in the case where the font doesn't
actually get loaded other than give the
memory back and so you know we could try
to be a little bit better behaved there
and just say well you know when we're
gonna we want to be able to mark the the
location so in the future if we want to
rewind back to it we could do so so
looking you know how that works you can
see it doing the rewind here and we kind
of have this temp count so what we can
do is say let's pretend we're going to
start a temporary memory block like so
so we just say yeah memory point begin
temporary memory so here we can just say
look we're gonna try to do some stuff
with this memory but you know if we fail
then we will rewind it so you know end
temporary memory we will do here so if
we can't actually get the font set up
then forget it
we'll we'll unwind but if we can then we
will try to load it right so that's
really all I wanted to do there is just
make sure that that path works okay and
we won't set the asset state to load it
unless we were actually able to do it
right so we we do this again this is
synchronous that's not a big deal so in
the case we actually can load it what we
want to do is say like you know hey you
know what I decided actually you know
just kidding I would like to keep the
temporary memory going
III changed my mind about that so you
know sorry
but it turn it just turned out that I
really like the memory so much I'm going
to keep it and so they're all we have to
do is just not do this right all we have
to do is just say all right the temp
count goes down we can assert that the
temp count is greater than zero and we
can also do this which is to say if
there was any in the first place
now the temp count here it seems like
this temp count greater than zero really
should have been like that because if
you're gonna subtract away you'd better
check so I'm not sure why that wasn't
happening in here
so really we're just doing the exact
same thing right weird but we're not
doing any of the actual clearing so that
would allow us to give the memory back
in the case we're like the file read
fails because file reads can fail right
we don't know that if the faleri it's
going to succeed and so in this case I
think we want to keep it working
properly okay so that was all I wanted
to say about that we can get the font
here so that's all good I don't know
what else has to happen here that we're
not doing
yeah asset font ooh that is loaded font
here so I what am I actually doing the
font or we're just looking at the glyphs
in here so in terms of this part right
here
I feel like this can really just be
blocked off the fog lifts stuff where we
do the load trying to think of what I
really want to do there cuz I do want to
get at the load so maybe I have to
actually literally call that HHA font I
don't know but you know if we look in
here where those two things are
happening Oh duh it's the same fun do
anything so that all looks pretty good
to me
inside allocate game assets this stuff
here is gonna have to change a little
bit so there's a couple things that
we're gonna have to do with because
remember we weren't tracking free
texture handles before we're going to
actually have to do that and so yeah
like you know there's a couple different
ways we could do that and let's decide
exactly how but the rest of this code
can go away if I go into the audio layer
and we look at the get sound situation
here so we're not going to be able to do
get sound anymore but almost everything
else in this code all will work the only
difference is that the when we go to get
the samples the samples don't come out
of the loaded sound anymore so it's
actually the samples that you get back
and the info for the sound comes like
out of this so there's an HHA sound here
and you know and i know i could do it
this way and this kind of thing right so
when we actually get the sound samples
back we're gonna play those out of here
they're not gonna come out a load of
time where everything else though will
work so this is just get sound in
right it's just this and so everything
else would work just fine and if we need
to actually get those samples now the
only difference right when you look at
what we're doing all throughout all of
this stuff is when we get down to the
very end and we want to actually mix
something then you're gonna want to go
and you're you're gonna want to go in
and use that sample buffer there so if I
look and see where we getting that from
melodious sound yes so you see that load
and sound samples and the bracket
nonsense there right you can kind of see
all this happen samples I don't totally
understand why we're using a bracket 0
there were we was this code like somehow
looking at at something for two channels
and then only did the zero sample here
like I don't know why
I don't know why it's really written
like that you know what I mean let me
take a look because excuse me in terms
of what that returns I don't see why we
would have done the channel pointed that
way let's just take a quick look so
inside the asset system when it was
actually going to go do the sound load
so in this code which we if zero it out
but that still exists right so in here
you can see when we get the memory we're
setting the sound sample pointers so
that they're strided along samples so I
guess what I don't know is what were we
planning to do there like
I mean this this never appears to do the
channels differently does it like if
that's the channel index
well it's only ever set to zero so it's
not exactly doing a very good job
loading by Norrell samples so I'm
assuming the oh yeah and there's a
handle stereo to do right here right so
so this is actually just nonsense and we
can you know we can fix this code I
guess later by just calling it twice in
the loop I'm not sure why we didn't do
that so you know I guess that doesn't
matter at all the point being when we
call it get sound and we get a sample
handle back here we can if we want to we
could actually imitate Jimmy we can
actually imitate what's going on in that
loaded sample we could do that if we
wanted to priestly actually we could
keep the loaded sound and when you
actually return the samples you could
return them in that so you know we could
do loaded sound and actually have you
know something like this where we
actually do have that block of pointers
there and you can use use them it seems
dumb because it's not like you don't
know where the memory is so I feel like
I'm just not going to do that because
since we can always stride based on how
big each individual channel is at most
what I would do here is return a channel
size like at absolute most so I would
just say this is just gonna be this
and and that's pretty much the end of it
right like I'm not gonna do any more you
know work than that and we will just
advance the sample pointer by the
channel size when we go to do the next
one cuz it just seems dumb to do
anything else I mean it's a fixed size
thing there's no it's just silly
at some level to do anything else I
would I would argue so okay so again
like we're getting down to like very few
actual things here what does it get
sound samples it's a call now right yeah
so we're getting down to very few actual
things that have to happen here now
remember we changed this to say that
there's flat form render limits now
which is just a more convenient way of
passing this stuff along and so all of
this stuff that was sort of being passed
piecemeal before it's gonna go in here
and guess it's to facilitate the fact
that this is like a conduit problem
right you've got sort of a bunch of
things that are getting passed through
several places not because we would
really want that to happen but because
we have to go through gyrations for
dynamic loading right because remember
we've got the renderer is actually
loaded out of a DLL switch so that
people can swap in different renderers
if they want to so we really don't want
to force them to have to update that if
we decide them to conduit more stuff
through there so we really want to just
fill out the limits now from for the
parameters exactly as they were before
if I go into the the renderer and look
up those differences there I've got the
max texture count and I've got the
special texture count and the buffer
size they're all that stuff seems pretty
good and let's see here yeah we're down
to just a few things the Sentinels are
not here anymore
we don't need insert block assets
Sentinel none of that stuff is here all
that stuff can be removed so yeah
looking through here we can just
you know visually just inspect that
there's no no more of that stuff still
hanging around because we don't really
want it it's not useful so then we're
left with just a very very few things in
here so you can see we've got update
here we we're trying to send out a
single pixel texture that's our fallback
white pixel texture and that's just
there if the only reason that there is
because we kind of have this fall by
case of non textured things and the
question is you know is there a better
way to do that do we want to do that in
some other way you know there's probably
things we can do but I'm gonna leave
that as it is right now I'm gonna let
that just go through the normal process
that it would go through and we'll we'll
go ahead and let that up actually play
itself out so again if we want to do
that it's again really simple
I like this API a lot I feel like we've
done a good job here getting down to
something that's pretty straightforward
so if we look at our render or testbed
here we actually did basically what I
want to do down in here right we just
did a really simple thing where we said
like you know let's make sure we can do
an op here where we where we set this up
we're gonna require that it be completed
but that's about it
so the assets white pixel pointer that's
not actually got like what's kind of
it's kind of nice here we don't really
need these anymore it doesn't need to be
stored because we can write it in to the
OP itself you know what I mean so we can
make this texture op stuff a little
cleaner as well so we can just say all
right the the OP data is just gonna be
the the white pixel and then we'll
complete it and that's it right so this
doesn't actually have to happen like
that anymore
so now I think we're in a position where
we're more or less doing the right thing
but now we got to go do bug it because
remember we stripped out a ton of code
there right this just got like way
simpler than it was and so when we're
looking at like what
happening here there's a lot of things
that we could have screwed up in there
and so we want to go through and
actually make sure that we know at all
what's going on one of the issues one
additional thing that I would say here
is this could stand to be a little bit
more systemic at this point when we're
actually going in and and doing the
texture handle stuff this bitmap width
and height is is really should possibly
be set by the texture op call itself
just to make sure that people don't
accidentally set the width and height
wrong when they're doing that thing that
texture handle usage so I feel like
there's probably a little bit we could
be doing there
that would clean that up and I might go
look at that but but first before I do
anything else right I just want to get
that basic you know the basic first pass
debugging done clear out all the the
failure cases and whatnot and kind of go
from there okay so let's see what we
started off with here we've got a we've
got an assert texture empty it's nice
[Laughter]
that's a pretty good that's a pretty
good assertion I guess we just thought
we'd assert just a flag that's why not
[Music]
[Laughter]
okay so that's that's pretty funny
where's our OpenGL renderer there there
it is so I don't know what I was
thinking there that's not what I meant I
meant that right so uh let's let's try
that one more time yes pretty silly all
right so let's take a look at what's
going on
here we're in update and render entities
we're getting a bitmap ID okay so here
in this case the bitmap ID is zero we
probably want to handle that case
meaning in here if the asset that you
asked for is zero we probably don't
want to get we want to give you back the
null asset in all cases now I don't know
yeah like it seems like in some sense it
should be possible to always count on
that like I'm just trying to think
through in my head
if this asset is always set everywhere
to know then the texture handle will
also be null so it's fine to return that
so this assertion what we probably can
do is just actually allow that case just
fine and what we would want is like when
we do this assertion assert that either
the value is zero or that it was a
bitmap because anyone is actually
allowed to get to get the 0 value out so
you know it's more like this sort of a
thing
so I think that's fine you know famous
last words but I think that's probably
okay all right so now we want to
actually debug like what's going on
because now we're actually running
straight through okay but we do need to
make sure that when we trigger our asset
loads they actually get loaded and
somebody will actually like download
them right so we need to make sure we
make sure we actually have that whole
pipeline flowing properly so if I drop
into the asset code here what we know is
you know we're you know we're we're
kicking off an asset and we know we're
we're retiring the assets so this inside
load asset work right which is the
callback to tapping an async that waits
for the read to complete and after it's
complete you know we we head in here and
do the texture up retirement so we know
that that code path needs to get hit
otherwise we won't ever download the
texture we also know that our load
bitmap code has to get hit or we won't
ever load the texture either and so what
we want to look for is this code path
working properly so we want to come in
here and take a look and see what
happens so here we're trying to load a
512 by 512 bitmap and we want to make
sure that this all works properly so
when we come in here to the 512 by 512
case we want to see that we actually do
get an OP we do get an up and that OP is
going to be in the pending load State
which is exactly what it should be and
then when we come through here and we
start up the task that we're supposed to
kick off what we want to do is set up
that texture handle right so we should
now see an index and a size that that
looks you know roughly correct and then
when we come through here and we start
the you know we get that asset work out
of the tasks arena here to actually
start this task going we set up all of
the pointers and it looks pretty good
right like
you know there's the load it's it's
happening in the right spot looks like
the texture ops getting set the queue is
set we're gonna stuff it in the low
priority queue for being handled later
you know that looks fine so I guess what
I would say is that you know that
doesn't look too too concerning what
about this is this maybe we're stuffs
not getting set properly I don't know so
here we've we've hit the completion
state we look at the texture op we're
gonna step into a complete texture op
and all that does is to say hey this is
ready to transfer right and then we also
double check the sizes there so you know
what there's one thing that's not really
right here this would have to do a
cancel if it didn't do a complete right
so that actually has to be moved down
here in a sense I mean I don't even
think in a sense I think it just has to
be moved down here that's not what's
failing now but that needs to happen we
set the state here too loaded and I feel
like that should have worked right
there's the offset in the file there's a
size there it's destination that all
seems reasonable so those states are
loaded so you know that seems pretty
good I'm not sure what the problem is it
might be in our buffer reading code that
has somehow it stalls out and can't make
forward progress so we can go take a
look at what's going on in there and
second before I do anything else though
I really don't think that piece of code
is correct so you know even though we're
not really testing or trying to work on
this part right now I don't actually
want to do this I think what I want to
do here is this and so
what we would say is I think probably
here and then this probably so if we
were unable to actually get it we're
gonna clear it we'll just send down a
zero texture and we will set the state
to load it even though it failed we
could choose to regress and set that the
state to unloaded
I don't know how Squinkie that makes us
you know but but we certainly could so
we could say something like final state
like this and we can say look we're
gonna assume that we regress to unloaded
and then if there were no file errors at
all then we'll say that we regress that
we progress up to loaded you know we can
do that the thing that I'm not 100% sure
about is again how we're gonna exactly
manage the idea of which texture handles
are free and which texture handles
aren't free so that's gonna be a more
finicky process we'll have to know
across that bridge let me come to it so
I must step do that one more time just
to make sure everything's kosher there
so you know there's us reading the data
from the file assuming that we're no
errors we're gonna set the resulting
state to loaded otherwise we'll
aggressive back to unloaded when we do
our complete texture up that will set
the state of the text
up and then we'll set the state of the
asset at the end and off we go right now
what I'm not sure about like I said is
I'm not sure about the thing where we're
actually okay we're already in debug
mode so that's good I'm not sure about
where we're actually going to peel those
off so I'm gonna look inside went
through your hand made I'm sorry
actually just hand made open jail just
to OpenGL rendering part things I want
to see what's going on in here I want to
know what's up with that so when we
actually get an OP count here when we
get it ready to transfer you know what's
going on so if I look at you know what's
the texture index there's the texture
index zero this should be that white
texture that we that you know we
specified in theory anyway
let me verify that we're actually
getting that well you know what I don't
really care about that I guess not think
about it let's just look and see what
happens on the next time around so we
know we did actually we actually filled
all 128 elements of the queue on the
first frame right so we had tons of
textures coming in so we're stressing it
in a way that we don't normally stress
it right or that we didn't in the test
app it's also I mean so when we get
something that's ready to transfer let's
see now we keep going what do we got
here what's our texture 512 by 512
that's like that first one we saw it's
not special so it's gonna just look at
which texture it was gonna update that I
don't know we should probably look at
the data pointer oops
you know is that is it good data
no officially this can't view images
unless you install a plugin hilariously
I need that I need them Nix lift cos
debugger that had image viewing in it
and stuff like that remember it was
awesome
anyway so in here that that looks you
know okay so I'm not 100% certain what
the issue is because I'm not seeing an
immediate error there so I'm not sure
why we have nothing on the screen one
thing it could be is if I forgot when I
did my loading to write the text or
handle back into the asset that might be
a little too easy so I'm gonna go ahead
and guess it's not that but I'm going to
check anyway so in here you know we get
the texture up and then we produce the
texture handle but you can see us to
refer to texture here so then we've got
the asset and well you know what I'm
right I mean there's the asset I don't
know why we're refined in the asset here
when we already have the asset so that's
kind of neither here nor there but um so
that's probably what happened right this
texture here wants to be set you know
what I mean
so we that that is what we needed and we
weren't doing that so we kind of want to
make sure that all looks good I'm
guessing we'll probably have more bugs
than just that one you know I would be
surprised but we'll see so you know it
looks to me like we're at least looting
basic stuff okay there
like all of these fonts loaded through
that path and they look okay so it looks
like the white texture
amusingly enough didn't come through so
hilariously the easiest thing for us to
download we screwed up
oops
so I guess I'll take that vote because
that's a lot better than the alternative
so let's debug the white texture why
didn't that go down properly so here's
this beginning the texture up on the
texture op Q we set a one one oh it we
just didn't set the texture handle so on
this OP again we want to set that
texture handle refer to texture and we
want to do that so again same bug in
both places what what is the actual
called err just texture yeah uh so that
gives us our right back and so that's
good so now you can see yeah that
working just fine and so now if I go
back to the build and turn on optimized
you know we're we're back in in good
shape I think yeah so that all works
just fine it looks like and yeah off we
go
so now the last thing that we wanted to
do as part of this suite of things we're
not allocating texture handles still we
just use the pool and when we're out I
think we just recycle ones and they'll
just be chaos so we're gonna have to
make that work for real right we got to
actually make that code not be
completely broken um but to end this
particular stream because we've pretty
much used up all the time and I will
undo a little cue Nate I want to do the
thing that I said I wanted to do with
the very outset which was allow us to
re-import and so when you change a file
just re-import not have to restart the
app so
I want to flush those texture handles
out you know what I mean
so if we want to do that we now have the
ability to do that pretty easily
actually if if I go back into the asset
and make a really simple way of of
rotating through the assets so you can
see here like when we rotate through you
can see here when we're when we're
coming through the list when we do the
free handle account we would just assert
when we run out and so what I want to do
is make it so that we will reload assets
when we when we update a particular
asset we can say flushes texture handle
and reload right so what that requires
of us is we need some way here of saying
look unload a texture you know flush a
texture when when when we hit that case
and so in order to do that I really just
need yeah I think I just need a thing
that's like unload you know so we've got
load bitmap I really just need a thing
that's like unload bitmap any here it
would just say look if I can get rid of
this bitmap
and in that case what I want to do is I
want to take it from you know I'm going
to do basically the symmetric operation
of this where I take it from loaded to
unloaded rather than taking it from
unloaded to loaded so all I'm going to
do there say look try to change the
state from loaded to unloaded right
actually Q I should say so you know it's
got to be in a loaded State and we got
to change it to queued okay if it
actually does if it was queued right if
it was ready to go then I'm sorry if it
was loaded to begin with state loaded
there we go then that means we did in
fact change it to cubed which means now
we can change it directly to s at state
unloaded but not before flushing it's
texture handle right and so here's where
we would give the actual texture handle
back for now we're not even going to do
that though we're just gonna do this and
we're not gonna give it back right so
we're clear the texture handle no
texture handle yep now we're unloaded
you can't use it anymore sorry about
your luck so when we do that unload
bitmap then you're done and you can't
use the bitmap anymore and we have to
load it again if you want to use it
again
now what's gonna happen when we come in
here is again that clear and this state
change we kind of want those to be a
little bit more fenced probably again
not clear that we really care that they
are but just in case you go
we just fenced the two of those so we
can make sure that the clear completes
before this does so that the processor
doesn't write them out of order right
not the processor but the compiler
doesn't switch the order and so that's
just keeping the compiler in line there
so we won't get any
unexpected reorganizations of the order
which those things do and the right
consistency on this platform should make
that happen now on another platform you
may have to make that be more stringent
but right ordering occurs properly on
Intel so I think you're pretty much just
good to go you just need a compiler to
not step in and mess you up um so we
can't unload a bitmap now which means
that anytime we change a bitmap we can
call the flush on it and so what we can
do there is just say hey yeah if if we
do an import so on and HHA you know we
go in there and say alright we're gonna
update one of these one of these images
then when it gets that asset out you can
see it get it here I want to flush the
bitmap if there was a bitmap loaded
right so like first things first just
just unload it like it's gone like get
rid of it okay so there's the assets
there's the asset index and so I just
want to like you know make sure no one
tries to use the old image for this one
that we've updated here and I mean
pretty straightforward
so I need cheetah to a bitmap id don't
really care about that I mean because a
bitmap id just is the asset index we
probably eventually we should probably
eventually just get rid of the notion of
a bitmap ID altogether because it's just
not actually really all that relevant
anymore but a little bit of type safety
there maybe helps sometimes who knows so
now what we should see is that yeah like
you know we we run this stuff the HHA
you know that's got the line through it
there I want to be able to update it
let's see
unload bitmap let's see if we can to can
make that stuff work it's the last thing
we do on the stream so let's say I do
import and save okay that worked but it
didn't hit my breakpoint did I spell it
wrong
I guess it was just because the compiler
inlined it no.2 sucked up all right well
hey that's what I wanted right that's
what I've wanted so now hot loading of
textures just works and everyone's happy
so we still need to allocate we need to
keep a free list for the texture handles
so you know yeah you get the idea so I
think we're right where we want to be
tomorrow which I probably will do a
stream tomorrow we can go in and fix we
can now go in and add the save load for
those align points so but that was
pretty good that was a grid blitz we got
all the stuff done I'm pretty happy with
it so I'm gonna go ahead and go to the
QA and then I'm gonna go home and go to
bed
what is going on in your optimize build
what do you mean what is going on the
same thing that's going on in the debug
build I guess what can you be more
specific I can't can't say I know by
that particular question but I can try
to answer it if you can elaborate
are you optimizing assets I just want to
know what it looks like uh so I guess
what I would say is oh do you mean what
is the difference between the optimized
ah
so really the problem is that the the
visual studio compiler seems to have a
lot of trouble with some fairly basic
stuff and I think I mean I guess I can't
really say that's true so it's not it's
fault it's just we have some heavy-duty
lighting stuff in there that probably
needs to be algorithm we optimized a bit
and that's really what is causing that
difference so if you take a look at the
debug builds and you look at where the
time is being spent right so here's the
difference in frame time right you can
see it's it's like dramatically
different right but if you actually look
at what where that time is going it's
it's not like the whole build is slower
it's all just one function it's just
compute light propagation right so it's
only the compute light propagation call
that's actually causing the problem and
for whatever reason the I don't know
that I've looked too carefully at what
the actual difference is but it's
probably just a case of a lot of
inlining there's probably like a lot of
function calls in that code that are
happening because it's a math heavy code
and so it's calling actual functions for
things like adding two vectors together
instead of just inlining the math ops
and when you add all of that overhead
it's like you know way way slower
because instead of just issuing a couple
multiplies and a couple adds it's
actually like setting up a stack calling
the function returning from the function
setting up another stack calling the
function returning the function right so
you know even though it seems like they
shouldn't be that different they really
are because it's such a heavy workload
loop
that's really all it is if you want by
the way for folks who want a moderated
chat experience TM there is a moderated
chat that you can go to and it is here
so you can actually just IRC to the
moderated chat which is on handmade
Network
so MSP C just doesn't do all the
inlining stuff by default sorry I'm more
of a web dev and don't get this little
stuff yeah I mean there are some things
that are good about what it does and
some things are that are bad and the way
that I would explain it so if it you
know again if you're a web dev and
you're not used to the low-level stuff
let me just give you a small example of
what I mean here in terms of what's
actually going on right so I let's say I
want to look at that compute lighting
compute light propagation call all right
so here's the compute light propagation
call we're talking about the actual
parts of it that matter you know it sets
up its multi-threaded so it sets up a
work queue of stuff that needs to happen
and then the stuff that happens here is
actually you know it's actually these
little thread le'ts are sitting there
doing the work okay and so this is the
actual majority of what is this is this
is all the time in our entire app goes
right here right so you know this is the
this is the the problem so if you take a
look at what this code does in the two
different modes here's a loop that's the
outer loop and an inner loop with the
Ray indexes and and so on right if I set
a breakpoint like right there for
example just as a place to look and I
jump to that line of the code here in
the optimize builds I actually which one
we're debug build here in the debug
build if I actually look at what the
processor were executed so what I've
done here again if you're unfamiliar
with it
what if I'm here is I've just said look
show me what the CPU is actually going
to receive as instructions okay then
what you can see is as we sort of step
through this code you can see all of the
things that are going to happen so here
is
it loading some of this data out right
of an array and here is it's starting to
do some math now what you can see is
right off the bat it sets up a stack
frame and okay didn't want to click that
it's test of a stack frame and right
here it's actually doing a call right so
it's actually gonna call out to this
operator star which is the thing that
does this multiply okay and that jumps
me all the way here I've got to set up a
stack frame for this function so this is
actually just preparing a stack frame
here I'm doing this multiply in the
longest possible way I'm moving things
in I'm oh it's even worse right we
implemented this as a series of calls
themselves so they actually have to do
calls because this is some Cindy stuff
that we did it's single instruction
multiple data I won't go to what that is
but we actually have two levels oh so we
got a call again right and then finally
here is the actual call that's the I'm
not to call the actual instruction this
is the only thing we actually wanted to
execute and look at how many
instructions we had to plow through
right it's nuts okay now what does what
happens if I look at the code that the
CPU has to execute in the optimized
build
so here's the code for the optimized
build here's this is it one two three
four five six seven eight nine we're
already at the mall no calls no nothing
there's the multiply right so all of
that crazy stuff you were waiting
through it's just this this is all you
were trying to do and now it all happens
so you can see there's the mall the mall
the mall the mall the mall all those
multiplies every single one of those
multipliers was that giant call stack
had to happen again it's just so you
just flooding all of these instructions
in there and so you know that's just the
way compilers work they when they're not
trying to generate optimized code they
just insert the boilerplate thing you
would do oh he overloaded operators star
so call operator star set up a stack
frame call operator star what does that
do okay that's another function I'm not
gonna inline it right I'm not gonna try
and eliminate redundant reads or
anything right so that's just how it
works and I wish there were some ways to
get around that like I wish you could
say look this is just some syntactic
sugar just replace it always I don't
ever want you to actually call this
thing like just you know insert the mole
directly we don't really have tools for
doing that
so either you turn on inlining or you
don't
newbee question wouldn't inlining every
function call speeds things up does the
compiler do that when you turn
optimizations on No
so actually in lining a function is is
not always a win in lining a function is
only a win in certain circumstances so
what you have to remember is that code
doesn't magically appear out of thin air
it has to come from somewhere right so
inside the the processor there's a
number of things that have to happen in
order to execute an instruction and the
number one thing that has to happen as
silly as it is to say is it has to know
what the instruction is right I mean
it's got to know what the instruction
you're trying to execute is before it
can execute it so logical question where
did it come from
well the answer is that inside the
processor it has a set of registers and
one of those registers says where the to
get the next instruction from it's
called our IP right and that address is
the location that it needs to read the
next instruction from right now you may
already know this but it's important to
mention it again because it sets up the
reason why you don't always want to
inline things okay so if the processor
has to fetch the instruction from there
well what do we know about processors
fetching things they have to actually
get them out of the memory of the
computer right and we know that the
memory of the computer is not as simple
as just saying oh I go and get it and
it's fine right there's a whole host of
things that have to happen there and
some of them can be very slow main
memory on a processor is very slow if I
had to go all the way out to main memory
and all the way back every time just to
find out what the next instruction would
be processors would run about 300 times
slower or worse right so we can't do
that so what we do is the same thing the
processor does the same thing it would
do with data it has caches right
it has caches so instead of just main
memory it has these caches and one of
the caches is called the eye cash and
that cash is responsible restoring
instructions
it's an l1 cache so there's a data side
and an instruction side of your l1 cache
you know what this is right
hopefully I'm not I'm not using terms
that are super out to lunch here but you
know just like I said web dev I don't
know what the stuff is that you would
necessarily know but you know when you
go to buy a processor right when you go
to buy one of these they've got specs
you know and we looked at this the other
just just maybe even this morning I
don't even remember when we looked at it
but was recently um they got caches
right and these caches are faster memory
that's closer to the processor and
easier for it to access right so here
they are you've got an l3 cache that's
the biggest cash it's closest to main
memory furthest from the CPU it's the
slowest one of the caches but still
faster than memory got the l2 cache
smaller only one megabyte right total
and these are divided per core so it's
actually 256 K one for each of the four
cores but you don't have to think about
that right now
then we got the l1 cache and that's
split into two halves once for
instructions once for data okay now look
at how tiny this instruction cache is
each of my cores each of my four cores
on this chip and I 777 okay a good chip
is an expensive chip so they're not
skimping on the on the cache here
it only has 32 K of instruction cache
only 3 2 K so what does that mean well
when we need to fetch an instruction we
don't want to go to main memory so what
the processor first does is it looks at
what's in the eye cache if
the next instruction is in the I cache
it runs it if it's not in the I cache
whoo boy we're in trouble
now we have to sit around and the
processor just has to stall until it can
actually get an answer from either the
l2 cache the l3 cache or god forbid main
memory right so if you want your code to
run quickly it is absolutely critical
that the hot loops of your code remain
inside the I cache you under no
circumstances want to have to be
spending time waiting for instructions
to come in that's exactly what will
happen if you inlined
everything in your code because now
every single thing you do just gets
bigger and bigger and bigger and bigger
and bigger size-wise
so the I cache this tiny little I cache
and then the l2 cache as well and the l3
cache all of those start to just get
blown all the time they can't keep your
code in it your code is so huge and
you're running through so much of it
that you're constantly waiting on I
cache fills right and it gets worse not
only just waiting to fill the I cache
hurt you the l2 and l3 are shared caches
so the data the actual data that you're
waiting on that data you're loading not
the instructions but the data you're
trying to operate on it's getting
evicted from the l2 and l3 caches to
make room for your code right so the
more code you have the worse off you are
for performance you want your code to be
absolutely as tiny as possible so the
actual answer is if possible you want to
minimize how many functions you in line
and so the only time you really want to
actually in line calls is when it's so
time critical and you can save so many
instructions that that bloat is worth it
right and in this case what you can see
is you can also save code size sometimes
by
inlining if a lot of what the inline
function was doing was boilerplate so if
it was really a meaningless function and
it's just like one line of code in
lining it actually saves code space
potentially because the amount of work
necessary to set up the call and finish
the call is more than if you just done
the instructions that's a no-brainer
and so when the compiler sees that it
will inline it pretty much automatically
but when the functions are larger in
linings not so good it's worth spending
that boilerplate love those few calls on
the top and the bottom to jump into a
large function because you don't want to
be duplicating that everywhere it's
called does that make sense
hopefully that makes sense
and by the way it's worth noting that
the compiler is generally the thing that
makes the inlining assumption so I'll
just close on a couple brief points and
then we'll wrap up the stream if you put
in line in front of a function it
doesn't matter the compiler doesn't care
if you told it to inline it the compiler
will decide to inline it or not itself
so whether you put in line in front of
something or or not it's not gonna
change whether it's inline on most
modern compilers maybe in the old days
it would have it doesn't now so there
are some things you can do to forcing
about inline sometimes there's like a
force inline keyword the compiler
defines specific to the compiler and if
you do that it will inline it and the
other thing you can do is just you
manually inline it you may only cut and
paste the code in right and so what I
would say is generally speaking let the
compiler make the decision it will make
a reasonable decision in the average
case so just let it do it
don't try to manhandle it just mark
while your code is static or nothing
don't bother putting inline on it it
doesn't matter it's not gonna matter let
the compiler do its thing when you're
actually working on the most important
loops of your code when it comes time to
really hand optimize though just move
the code that you want in yourself don't
rely on the inlining and you're gonna
want to organize that stuff yourself
only for your very most important loops
that's generally what happens and you're
gonna want to be doing that in the
context of profiling so you make sure
you're not making a mistake by moving
something in that should have stayed
outside again because knowing if you're
blowing the I cache or things like that
you can't tell that without getting
profiler data back either looking at
performance counters or seeing if
something gets slower faster and so on
and so you at least need to put timing
blocks around your code and look at
those results to know whether you're
making a difference there don't just
guess if it's a critical loop don't just
go add an O in lines probably better and
I in line
like like figure it out right by by
making good timing testbed in check
so alright I'm gonna close it down
thank you for joining me for the episode
of handmade hero sort of pleasure
cutting with you as always I love those
asset system changes oh it's so much
simpler now it's great we'll reuse the
texture handles maybe I'll do that
tomorrow because that's not that hard so
we'll go ahead and throw that in there
and then we're pretty good to go we can
play with the sound loading maybe we'll
put sounds back in tomorrow and we'll
actually start playing sounds that
sounds like a good idea too we got so
much cool stuff to do we'll put the
saving in we got tons of stuff
tomorrow's gonna be fun I'm looking
forward to it
no no one will do it whenever I get a
chance my schedules been kind of crazy
lately so we'll see but thank you for
joining me if you want to follow along
series at home of course as always if
you want to you can pre-order the game
on handmade here or get comes all the
source code right now so you can go
ahead and play around with it if you
want to try experimenting with the sort
of stuff we're talking about in the
series that's about it
hope to see you back here for the next
surprise dream I will post schedule
sometime soon until then have fun
programming and I'll see you everyone on
the Internet take it easy everybody