hello everybody and welcome to handmade
heroes sure we code a complete game live
on stream we are going to take a look at
our lighting today to see I want to I
want to go in and look at the variants a
little bit and see if I think that it's
working the way that we expect it to be
working that's what I'd like to do I
know we really should take a look at our
bounding volume hockey stuff as well
because we were doing some optimization
and we're actually quite a bit faster
than we used to be and there's more to
be done there I think and so that is
pretty interesting and I would like to
do it but at the moment we sort of have
this issue where we don't really know we
don't really know where this variance is
coming from we get a lot of flicker and
it doesn't it doesn't necessarily add up
quite right to me
in terms of what I'm expecting to see
and I'm thinking that we may have a
little bit of bugginess that's
contributing to how much liquor that we
have some amount of flicker is probably
expected but the amount of flicker we're
seeing might not be and so that's kind
of something that we need to figure out
how to track down it's definitely an
important part of the process for us is
figuring out exactly where that's coming
from so one of the things that I think
we need to do is sort of drill down on
that a little bit and see why it's
happening because what we've done so far
is we've only really looked at
strategies for reducing variants but we
haven't really ever looked to make sure
we know exactly where the this is coming
from so there's a couple of things I
would like to do and some of them are
somewhat difficult but I will see what
we can do so the biggest thing that I
think would be useful to us is it would
be nice if we can just see what happens
if we want to use our current lighting
system to compute a stable lighting
solution so for example what we want to
do is try to get our lighting such that
if you just run it normally give it
enough time
if it accumulated enough samples it
should converge on a stable solution
right we want to have architected our
system in such a way that that would be
possible I believe now you know maybe
I'm kind of wrong about that assumption
and maybe part of the aspect of it
running sort of in a real-time way where
the lighting gets updated progressively
over time is that you can't really get
that kind of thing out of it but
assuming that that's not the case then
the situation that we have right now is
that we need some way of testing that we
actually do converge properly in that
way because otherwise we we have some
flaw in the way that we're combining our
samples such that we wouldn't really
such that the flicker is coming
partially from that incorrect way of
fusing samples together rather than from
the fact that we are understanding the
problem and so what we want to do is we
want to make sure that the flicker
actually comes from under sampling the
problem such that more samples makes it
better and not that we actually have
some kind of a flaw in the way that
we're handling the integration of the
samples in the first place
such that actually the flickers coming
from just bad math right because then
what we're doing is we're throwing away
all of the hard work we did to do fast
lighting path computations and we're
just getting a worse solution for no
real reason right
you want to make sure that the hard part
of the problem is the part that's
actually hard you don't want to make the
part of the problem that's actually easy
be a part of the hard problem right so
that's what we need to do
okay um so there's a couple of things
that we can do to look at this and so
let's sort of start to look at those now
I'm gonna go ahead and let's say we go
and what I'd like to do is inside the
lighting routines I want to just briefly
remind us because it's been a couple
weeks since we did this work but we've
got a model where we consider what the
emission levels are on a surface to
basically be photons per second times
some scale right so we we sort of think
about the values that we're moving
around as almost like a transfer rate
right like the the path through this
surface is some number of photons per
second
we don't actually because that number
would be so huge we don't actually
literally put in how many photons per
second we think it is but the value is
something proportional to that so if you
imagine scaling down the number of
photons by a huge amount you know point
oh-oh-oh-oh-oh-oh one or something I
then that is what the quantity is that
we expect to see there and so what we're
doing is we're going through all of
these and we do a bunch of raycast
and essentially what we say is all right
we're going to look at the number of
photons per second leaving the surface
that we're looking at and we're going to
assume that that number of photons per
second will then be hitting us right and
the way that we attenuate that is we
just use the angular fall-off between
the two surfaces to determine how much
of that transfer occurs right so you can
see that happening right here
we're gonna look at each of these oh you
know what we forgot to we never
optimized this part of our code to
this part of the code could probably be
done in Sim D partially as well so you
know looking at this I the the important
thing to remember here right is that
these numbers when we in fact we called
it PPS for photons per second even
though again it's not just one or mighty
it's not actually a number that large
we're just proportional to it so what
we're doing here is saying okay we're
gonna accumulate the sample color by
taking whatever the angular fall-off is
and looking at that transfer PPS and the
way that we do that is we wait together
all of the sample points in the on the
surface that we hit so when we hit a
surface we wait the sample points by
their distance which you can see
happening here and what we do is we take
a look at how how all of those points
would have contributed two photons per
second out and then we just use that
value to boost you know to basically sum
up how many total sent for the notes for
a second we expect again so we're just
gonna take a bunch of those and right
now what we do is we take sixteen so we
take 64 right we take four rays per
because it's sim D we take four rays per
16 tests which is 64 total rays and we
sum up 16 64 of those into our
accumulator some of those will be black
right some of those will not hit a
surface that has anything so it'll add
up you know this will not add to
anything but for the most part because
there is ambient lighting coming from
the skylight you do have some of the
almost everything will contribute at
least a little bit of lighting so most
of the time you'll get at least a little
bit of like the minimum you can get that
right now is whatever the backing
color is now the weird thing about this
is we should this should really be fall
off based as well we should probably do
an angular fall off so the the moon
doesn't shine from the bottom right so
really what we probably want to do is
something like for the moon color you
know we probably want something like the
Ray direction right which comes through
where does that come through it's this
right here so this sample for DX if we
do get component sobre you probably want
something like this so the further up
you're pointing in Z the better for
getting the moon color and we probably
would just say look if you're pointing
down you don't get any of that so I
don't we probably should have that we
never really went in and into that but
that's the case right so that way yeah
like if you have like surface under
sides like this those should be black
like they are right
whereas surfaces that can see the moon
like these will have a faint moon color
in them and then services like these
that maybe can sometimes see the moon
and sometimes can't you can see there's
more moon out here but then there's
shadow so because they can't see the
moon here right so for example if I move
this light source over here so that the
the lights in here don't get that we
should be able to see sort of like more
moon color out here well I suppose to be
honest though there's holes in here so I
guess they can see some moonlight
through there if I was to make that moon
color a little bit brighter so here's a
much brighter moon right you can see
that come in now and so now you can
really kind of see if the moon light is
falling on here and then we look down
here and you
you can kind of see how you get a much
brighter ring here and then the moon
gets much dimmer you can't really see
much in there because it's very highly
occluded then as you get out towards the
ring it's much brighter right again this
is what's so cool about lighting you
know I know it's a lot of work to get a
lighting scheme to work it's just very
it's much easier to just do you know the
sort of stardew valley like put a ring
around the guy and it's brighter there
or whatever right that takes like 10
seconds but you know I don't know I
really like this sort of character that
these things add you can just see how
cool that is that now you get moonlight
and I mean you just look at it just adds
a lot of character that this is lit by
this and you see the different color you
know colors coming through it it just
feels really good and so even in this
case where we're not even really we
haven't really scattered interpolation
points intelligently over our services
yet that'll add a huge bit of niceness
in terms of interpolation quality and
stuff like that
but even just you know macat what
happened as a result of the simple cube
based stuff we're doing here it just
looks nice you know it just has a really
nice feel to it and I really like that
with that adds to a game which is why I
always think it's worth it I'm gonna
shut the moon back down a bit to
something sort of more reasonable
maybe 0.4 seems like a pretty good plan
that seems good right yeah all right so
and again the reason that I wanted to
put in that Z attenuation there is just
cuz if people are shooting arrays like
out horizontally or down
I don't they should not be hitting any
moonlight right moonlight should be
coming from the sky and so the more that
was just a quick little term to add in
there so that if you're not aiming up
towards where the sky generally would be
you're not gonna get you know any any of
that
that moon contribution right and we can
get rid of these now because we're not
really gonna use these probably but we
can make this more complicated that's
what we were doing those before you can
make it so that as you you know
depending on where you shoot you get a
gradient fall-off something like if for
sunsets or things like that where you
want you know brighter band sort of in
one direction and then falling off to
darker bands later you can obviously do
all that kind of stuff all right so
anyway point being this is the part of
the code here that that's a little bit
interesting and that we need to focus a
little bit more on so you know if we if
we take a look at what's happening here
with the light transfer this is
transferring the the light and the way
that we look at it is we don't take
light away from surfaces because we just
think of the path as being stable paths
and I know this is a little bit weird
but we we worked this out and I was
pretty happy with it and it did work
very well compared to our previous stuff
so just to kind of go back we don't have
Milton open yet Milton there you are
so what we're basically talking about
here is if you imagine some lighting
path so we want to know what the
lighting is here and the emitter that
we're talking about is like actually
over here let's say it is the moonlight
or something like that right so what
happens is it bounces off this surface
bounces up this surface and eventually
hits this surface right so it goes like
from A to B to C and we want to know
what's going on at C then there's a
couple of different ways we we're
looking at this before one is we were
looking at like storing lighting amounts
here so it was like we were keeping
photons here and then we would transfer
the photons here so we would subtract
away from one and go to another and so
on and those schemes were just not very
stable we could not make that work very
well and what we worked out was that
really photons per second was much more
interesting because base what that was
saying is okay an emitter just has a
stable photons per second it's a
constant you know like 1.0 is the number
of scaled photons per second right if a
very bright light in our system or
something and 0.0 is something that has
no photons per second coming out of it
and in between there is all of your
lighting brightnesses then what happens
is when you do all your samples from a
surface you a ver ajal of the photons
per second of light incoming that you
see and that becomes your photons per
second which then other people can see
and these averages are just meant to
stabilise over time right so meaning as
we take more and more samples for B we
just get better and better and better
right and in theory this would be
accurate on a given frame if we just
sampled you know millions and millions
of rays coming out of a surface we would
in theory have a perfect estimate for
what the incoming photons per second
were for everything out in the
environment and that would just work and
it would be great but we have a nasty
situation where we have to update our
opinion of what is actually happening
these surfaces right we have to sort of
step through time if you will and we
need to show a result periodically and
continually update that result as we go
because we just don't have you know an
hour to sit here sampling and then come
up with a particular result for a single
frame right we have to show things in
like a sixtieth of a second for worst
case of thirtieth of a second that's the
slowest frame rate a game can run at
right it's a 30th of a second anything
below that and it becomes unplayable so
what we want to do is we want to figure
out how to correctly stabilize this over
time such that it converges as much as
possible if the entire scene stayed
still it converges as much as possible
to what the correct answer should be for
photons per second for everybody right
now the problem that we have is that as
we take these samples right as we do
these sampling if you assume that we
took them all and averaged them all
together we would have something like
write the summation of the the normal
for Ray I right these are let's say
we're gonna go from I equals 0 to
infinity right we're just gonna sample
and we'll just do this 1d here we're
just gonna sample all of these but the
normal for Direction number I write
we're going to do all of these times the
particles per second that the photons
per second that we see in that direction
so if this is the direction we want to
take
I'm writing this poorly there we go so
we'll call whatever the way we're
looking is our and we'll call the
surface normal n right and we're
basically trying to take a simple
lighting fall-off term so the dot
product of the direction that we're
going for a sample I we're gonna
transpose that with n which is the
normal right and then we're gonna look
at the photons per second that we
actually have here so whatever the
sample is I I whatever we hit right
we're basically looking to compute this
sum we want an infinite number of rays
cast and we want to sum up one over
infinity so we're taking the average
basically right of all of these now will
we ever do infinity no but let's say in
an offline renderer we were gonna take
you know 4096 samples right so some
really high you know huge number right
so we were wanted to take 4096 samples
and then we were going to do this
equation and we were going to sum them
all together and we're just we're taking
the average so we're just average them
all together right so we just end up at
the end with an opinion a very good
opinion of the complete coverage of what
was all the incoming lighting right now
unfortunately what we're actually going
to do right is this number is way tinier
right this number is actually 64 right
now so what we're actually doing is
we're actually computing this summation
as I and really it's I goes from 0 to 63
right or I guess we could say is I goes
from 1 to 64 right we're actually
computing this
right we're actually computing this now
this is what we're saying not enough 64
raise is not enough to actually get the
completely state leg result so maybe
because we're doing it wrong
so is 64 enough question one we have to
answer is are we sampling poorly right
and the answer is we might be so improve
the 64 one thing we can still work on
but the other thing that we have to
think about is this is being stabilized
by what's essentially a temporal
anti-aliasing filter quote-unquote right
which is that instead of using this
result because we could just use this
result instead of using this result we
actually blended this result over time
so we're actually taking this and
multiplying it by some coefficient right
some coefficient and we're adding it to
whatever the previous frame was right so
we're taking whatever the previous frame
was if this is frame zero we're taking
the previous frame and adding it
together right so we've really got a
recurrence here which we're saying like
look the F for our current frame so I
don't know what we want to call our
current frame index I guess we'll call
it F so for our current frame index
right whatever that is we are going to
take the previous frame
should I put this we are gonna take I
guess we could say the lighting for the
previous frame and add it to the
lighting on the frame before us right
that's just what we're doing so this
right here produces a weird effect on
this equation right because the true way
to compute this equation if you only
were going to do it in chunks of 64
right well and I'm this for Martin's I'm
going to use or was it you know what it
might have been Neal I don't remember
who was chastising me for using the
wrong calculator that might have been
Nixie actually anyway whoever it was was
chastising me for them if you look at
how many times we should have to do it
it's over 64 frames it would take us to
get there right so what we really want
to do is we would really want to compute
this quantity right 64 times so we would
want to do the summation
we'll use some other about some other
value T equals 1 to 64 right we would
want to do 1 over that's 64 and then do
the summation as I goes from 1 64 of
each of the lighting samples right
make sense so this is actually what we
would want to do to compute it in 64
chunk batches so the overall weight of
all the samples would be 1 over 4096
write this term here times this term
here will produce that 1 over 4,000 86
and we will average them all together
but that's not what we're actually doing
instead what we're actually doing is
we're doing this every frame and
knocking down by whatever our blend
coefficient is our older frames so
instead of it looking like this right
where we have frame 0 1 2 and then frame
64 right instead of contributing the
lighting 1/64 1/64 1/64 1/64 what's
actually happening is each of these
frames gets a totally different amount
of weighting than that
this frame and I don't remember what our
blend coefficient is it is
it is not I don't know where it is
so did we move okay there's I'm like
what's going on just look in the wrong
place it's fine so here we go this is
where we do our looping and stuff like
that right so if you take a look at
what's going on here we've got a
coefficient it's this coefficient right
here so it's 0.05 right so if we take a
look at what that implies if we have one
divided by point oops
sir there we go oh five here we go
you can look at what we're looking at
here so it's 20 right it's 120th so what
we're getting here is we're actually
seeing the first frame we'll start off
it will be on that frame you will see
one sixty-fourth there's the
contribution of this frame but then when
we go to frame 1 this will get
multiplied by 0.95 right and this frame
will get multiplied by 0.5 that's what's
actually going to happen right so
whatever was on the last frame it gets
multiplied by point nine five oops sorry
point oh five right and whatever the
contribution was on this frame it gets
multiplied by 0.05 then on the next
frame this one will get multiplied by
0.05 right this one will get multiplied
by point nine five and so will this one
Jim Sam next two same thing right
so by the time we get to our 64th sample
we've actually multiplied by 0.95 to the
63 power this sample right here right
and the same was true of all these guys
they were point zero five times point
nine five to the 63rd power right well
this case 62nd power right so if you
look at how much leverage were get whoa
all right
don't know what's going on there okay
there we go
so if we look at what's happening there
we wanted each sample to contribute that
much what we actually generally get is
something more like this right I'm sorry
what we wanted was this and what we got
was more like that right so why is that
the case well the reason that's the case
is because we are biasing ourselves
towards using newer samples rather than
older samples right and the reason for
that is because the lights are moving
right it's a game and it's active so
we're more heavily taking these here
like this one right here will be 0.05
and this one back here like I was saying
before will be 0.95 to the 63 so we will
be looking at the current frames
contribution roughly I guess 20% higher
looks like we'll have about 20% higher
contribution than the last frame right
but in general it's see you know that
doesn't seem horrible right as a moving
average that seems relatively you know
relatively saying
I don't know so unless I'm doing that
analysis wrong it seems like that's a
sane way to keep the moving average
because like the difference between
those two is not awful it's not what we
would want in a stable solution right
but it is not completely wrong so that's
okay similarly what we could do to take
a look at the difference right is we
could actually do exactly what we're
talking about explicitly so the way that
we would do that is we would just take
and we would just take and actually sum
up all the samples over time and divide
by the total number that we had sampled
right and eventually we'd start
overflowing it would be nasty but we
could actually do that to a certain
extent right and I'm not like I said not
sure exactly how we want to do that but
like for example since we're storing I
believe this lighting Point State here
what do we pull out here
so if you take a look at this
where is our unpack so here is here is
the
hmm
so
here's a question for you
looking at this I'll be honest I had
thought we had finished making it so
that we recover the light PPS and start
with that
so I guess but you know we do write it's
this value here right yeah yeah yeah I
was gonna say I thought I was going
crazy there for a second I was like wait
do we not recover the PPS from the face
frame but we do so here's where we
recover the the photons for a second for
the previous frame right we just for
some reason it's called emit but we
probably should call it something else
right it's this value here yeah so I'm
gonna call this last PPS so we actually
know what it is in last direction
that just makes it clear what's going on
so we don't have to like a wait wet
alright um so what I was saying before
is if we wanted to write where we stored
this we could just accumulate these
directly never actually do any blending
and then have an actual sample count
here right so we could just have a
sample count and we would just divide
the sample count right we would just say
all right you know whatever however many
samples we've taken we just divide by
that number and we get the actual you
know total amount that we expect so you
know in order to do something like that
I think all we would have to do it would
be a little squirrely because but you
know when we when we load this out here
right all we would be doing there I
don't know if we took last Direction out
I'm going to take the direction the
budding direction for a second so this
is non directional right which looks
roughly the same is directional makes us
wonder if we should bother tracking it
at all so what I was gonna say it's if
we want to look at what happens if we
just sum these over a large number of
samples what we can do is say alright
let's actually just store that
information as well so here's the sample
count and then we just divide by the
sample count whatever that happens to be
so yeah like if you come in here to pull
it out we would just have something like
this so that would let us accumulate
that sample count over time and just
pull out whatever the actual average
value was and then when we go to put the
information back rather than doing last
PPS here as something that was
overwritten every frame by alert instead
what we would do say now don't do that
and I guess since we're not using
Direction that doesn't matter instead
what you should do is say accumulate
this directly
both of these and then the accumulated
PPS that we're actually going to write
out which is this you know what's that
actually going out to the textures the
lighting textures that's going to be the
divide and I think that would give us
basically an accumulator at that point
so now like the lighting can't animate
really I mean it will because if you
move the lights it will adjust but it
won't be even remotely correct but if
you leave everything in stasis in theory
we can make it accumulate over time now
the fact that I'm not saying to do that
means I must have messed something up
there
what didn't happen there
this should accumulate that should
increase the sample count the output oh
the output needs to be that although
that shouldn't have been well that would
be it because that sample count will
keep going up yeah so that is what it
looks like if we just let the lighting
solution converge to whatever it's going
to converge to so after like a very
large number of samples this is what it
would look like right
so I feel like this is kind of a useful
tool - it would be nice to keep
something like this in place because it
sort of lets us know what the it sort of
lets us know what our lighting solution
converges to best case right it'll never
look better than this no matter how good
we do right this is the end solution as
if this was a so what I'm looking for it
says as if this was an off line renderer
this is what we would see right so yeah
I think there's probably a pretty easy
way we can actually make that happen too
so here's what we could do without
actually changing I think I'm gonna want
to I want to put this in as a real thing
we can look at so without actually
changing anything here we probably can
keep a mode like this around pretty much
indefinitely so let's suppose we
introduce a concept that's just called
like a light test accumulation count and
we'll just say that will take 4096
frames or something like that how long
would that take maybe that's too many
with probably too many yeah it's way too
many so let's let's say 20 56 so let's
say we're going to take 256 frames of
accumulation for our light test
accumulation count right that's we're
gonna do then what we could say is all
right if we're doing light test
accumulation we'll do things slightly
differently but only slightly what we'll
say is the accumulated PPS is just going
to be 1 over this right so we've got
accumulation coefficient is going to be
1 over the light test accumulation count
okay so just a fixed we're not gonna
remember how many samples we took we're
just gonna assume that the number of
samples is 256 just period that's gonna
happen right so we're going to do
accumulation C times
time's the box storage right so that's
that's what we're gonna do there seems
seems possible to me I and then what
we're gonna say is get rid of this and
the accumulation does happen right here
right this accumulation happens so if we
wanted to do it that way then we can
actually say have a switch that we turn
on and if we turn on the switch we do
our accumulation right and then we we
multiply at the end by however whatever
the the difference in accumulation count
is right and similarly we can make this
a little bit more accurate here by just
saying like
could really just do it this way where
we say like hey let's take the
accumulation count that's recorded on
the lighting test and we'll just use
that right
and that seems good so that's a constant
that can just be computed right so this
accumulation see here and I guess it
updates right so the accumulation sees
starts out here and then it updates so
after we do the compute light
propagation right solution solution
accumulation count updates right so the
accumulation see out here replaces the
in-sample count part here and this has
to be checked as well
so this goes away and this right here
where we have to normalize this the
accumulation so you can just go right
there so what we can do is we could do
it this way we can say look the
accumulation count start off at zero or
start it start off at one because that's
what we would normally do if we're
accumulating set to zero unless we can
do our inversion if we can't then we
can't here right and then down here same
thing
and so then inside the lighting we can
actually just turn this on and off so we
can have our I hope we can have our
cumulative count here the other thing we
can do is for this what we could do is
say well eventually we might just want
to stop doing the accumulating at all so
what we could do too is we can make it
so that we just don't do this pass
anymore eventually so we can say look we
just won't we just won't update anything
after a certain time so if we detect
that we are if we detect that we are
done with accumulation we just stop
right we just stop processing so the way
to do that is just say look if solution
accumulation count
equals the test you know the stopping
point then just just bail right don't
don't bother doing anything at all
so we can't do something like that right
and then you know in theory you know if
we haven't messed anything up so if you
haven't missed anything out there then
we should be able to do that as
something that turns on and off so we
can go here this is running regular and
then if we just add a key for that we
could turn it on so inside world mode
where we were doing our F key stuff
before so inside here we know we've got
various things maybe make the f3 key do
it so if we're accumulating
I guess technically we wanna do that
something like this so I think this
would let us do it right I think this
would let us go all right you know
moving around run the real-time lighting
hit f3 stabilize the lighting see what
the solution is if we just let it run oh
we still got to map them back so once it
ends we can't just do this because they
change their they change their order
every frame potentially so that's not
quite gonna work so what we actually
have to do here is just assume that
we have to assume that we want to keep
one you know full ones coming in
assuming yeah so we want it we want to
still do the mapping out and then when
we put the mapping back in here we just
want to say
you know don't don't accumulate anymore
if you're if you're done now this is
this would be one off so we actually
need to do one more of these though if
that makes sense so what we actually
want to do here is we want something
like we want something like this so that
if we were going to accumulate we set it
here so I think that would work I'm not
mistaken
and this converges to a particular
lighting solution looks like we're still
getting some fade there so I think we
got it a little bit wrong but we should
be able to come back to regular lighting
right unfortunately we have to have a
way to clear well I guess we don't have
to we can just let it converge like it
did but then if we moved certain place
we can hit f3 again and then it will
restabilized the lighting the lighting
is super high at that point so it takes
a while to return back to normal but
anyway so yeah looking at what's
happening there so should accumulate the
accumulation count needs to not get
incremented so think that's just that
so I think that should give us what we
wanted to know right now we can look at
what a particular lighting solution
would be in any given area given a very
large number of samples you know and we
can see what it looks like and then we
can return to normal lighting anytime we
want we probably should have a way to
clear it but the moment we don't so it
starts off at the super-bright averaged
levels that have been accumulated you
know over time there so that lets us
know what the scene should end up
looking like if everything converged now
that does tell me what I wanted to know
which is does it converge to a
reasonable solution and it well that's
so not really like you can see we're
getting slowly brighter how is that
happening that shouldn't be possible
should it how did that happen
if we are accumulation accumulating then
if the accumulation count is less than
or equal to distresses we do this
shouldn't it just be less than
because it's equal it should not
accumulate
right because it hasn't been incremented
yet at that point yeah I think that's
what we actually wanted let's try it one
more time
looks good
okay I'm gonna move over to where we
were having the sort of slow infinite
game for as well
right
but what's the second in Sabbagh okay
got 50 minutes till Q&amp;A it says so
that's pretty good and I think like I
said we want that in there so we know
how our lighting solution is doing
hmm so now we have a bit of a puzzle I
think
because
I think part of what we're seeing here
is sort of the degree to which light
bounces back and forth between surfaces
creates sort of waves as we go you
should almost sort of see it so when I
hit the f3 key right you can see how the
surface is kind of oscillate down and
then settle out right there kind of like
almost like damp springs in that regard
and I do wonder a little bit
about how we won try and address that so
mm-hmm yeah this is a bit of a puzzler
so I guess what I would say is I don't
really see like I mean I wish I could
say that I see anything really obvious
in the way of like you know erroneous
behavior here but I don't really I do
want to increase the sampling level a
little bit
just to let I just want to see what
happens if we really let these things
settle out over a very high number of
samples that's like a very high number
right so yeah just like looking through
how this is going I feel like I want to
I feel like I want to go back to the
hemisphere sampling a little bit and
just see because I feel like I don't
know that there's that much we're gonna
be able to do to improve the sampling I
mean it feels like relatively good with
that convergence just looking at it it
feels pretty reasonable and so I almost
feel like what we want to focus more on
is the hemisphere sampling itself and
you know weighting those samples
appropriately and picking them maybe
with a better random number generator
that gives us a better coverage of the
hemisphere generally speaking I don't
know it feels like we're gonna have more
luck there than looking at anything else
here because if you look at that I mean
I feel like that's
yeah I feel like that's just not gonna I
don't feel like there's much you're
gonna be doing with sampling over time
that's gonna fix that so let's take a
look the time may have come oddly enough
to replace our random number generator
for reals with something like X or shift
so you know let's let me just step back
a second and let's take a look at our
debug line stuff so remember we've got
this debug line situation here right and
inside handmade lighting we have the
ability to to put these debug lines into
practice right so we can do push debug
line anytime we want so what I propose
we do here is I propose we create a
random series like so and now let's see
here we've got a part right here we can
do it so I propose we make some random
series and then we just actually do a
bunch of of hemisphere samples here and
draw them so that we just see how our
distribution across the hemisphere is
for certain numbers of samples so let's
say we're gonna draw well let's take 64
samples because that's how many we
actually care about in this particular
case and let's just draw that many right
so I'm going to take a you know start
point and I don't know exactly where
that should be but let's say something
like that and then I just want to make
start point and start point plus I don't
know three times normal and I want to
make it normal and so we can do
something like this and just draw some
debug lines
so let's see if we actually get those
why am I not seeing our debug lines
that's not where I want to be
so that should give us
although I don't know if I guess it's
because updating debug lines is not such
a career probably huh
I guess we could do this we probably
just don't draw them if they're not
updating that okay so I believe that
should give us a good picture of what it
looks like
there we go
so this is what our sampling looks like
at the moment right and it's not great
right like it's very bunchy you know
it's it's not pretty it's not very
evenly distributed certainly so I do
think we want to try to even that out a
little bit more and I'm not sure exactly
how we want to do that but again we
looked at a little bit of stratified
sampling before and I think now we kind
of want to actually take this really
seriously and get this down to a very
coherent way of sampling this thing so
the first thing I want to do is I want
to take care of the random number of
stuff here because right now again we we
just never really put in a real random
number generator and so all we did was
just use a random number table which is
fine right like that's what we just
stuck in there because we know this is
really random but the problem is the
periods very short right so that
shouldn't actually be part of our
problem at the moment because we're not
you know we're not actually wrapping
this so in theory it wouldn't make a
difference but while we're looking at
this while we're actually looking at
this itself I think now would be a good
time to put in
generator that we can use because we
want to verify that it doesn't produce
any more clumping than this right
because this is our starting entropy
from actually cut and pasted supposedly
random data all right so the problem
with random number generators is that
you kind of have to be an expert on
randomization and number theory to
really know what to do with them I am
NOT so I cannot really explain these
particularly well to you other than to
say that the way that they typically
work is they try to take the bits of a a
you know seed value and they try to mix
those bits up in a way such that even
though obviously it is 100% predictable
I mean this is the function that tells
you what every next number in the
sequence is they try to figure out how
to make those values pass various
statistical tests right so they try to
say all right if we were to look at what
numbers this produces and we look at
things like distributions of those
numbers do they look like the same
distribution checks that we would get on
numbers that actually were random so if
we had a source of something we believe
is actual entropy which they do try to
find you know
I know this is gonna really tell us much
about them
so I'm not sure where to look for a
really good example so here you go
random dot word claims that they get
randomness by taking atmospheric noise
so don't know if that's really random
but they think it is right so if we
assume that something like atmospheric
noise is truly random and we look at the
distribution of numbers that we get
there what we're trying to do with these
which are effectively pseudo-random
number generators such as this one here
used to produce sequences of numbers
that look roughly similar to real random
numbers even though they are themselves
obviously not random because we
literally have a function that can tell
you what the next one is one of the very
bare minimums of properties that a
random numbers would have is that you
don't know what the next one is
otherwise it can't be very random now
can it and so that's kind of the way to
think about this it's just to go all
right
what we're trying to do is sort of look
you know we're trying to be a wolf in
sheep's clothing here you know the sheep
is the real randomness the wolf is the
pseudo-random number and we're trying to
kind of pass ourselves off as a sheep
right
and so X or shift is usually the one
that I go to the reason because it's a
pretty simple random number generator
but it's the one that's I usually go to
only because Melissa Neil not this
window so Neil let's try that again we
don't want the Canadian singer okay two
L's there we go
this melissa o'neill who did a very good
random number generator which is the PCG
random number generators the PCG random
number generators which is a thing she
came up
she actually recommends using X or shift
in the paper on that as the basis for
the PSG's which she does now if we open
the paper up and I've pointed this out
on handmade array I believe see here
this is a very good paper by the way I
highly recommend reading this paper and
it's very easy to read it is a long
paper which takes the time to explain
everything it's not one of those like
short concise ones that just let goes
end blah and like leaves like 50 million
things kind of as exercises to the
reader so I believe that you know if you
go through and look here she starts with
X or shift and she basically says look X
or if you know isn't that great at
producing ran number generators
producing random numbers but it's fast
but then it turns out if we do some
simple modifications X or shift we can
actually get a really really good result
out of it right and so she talks about
doing these permutations to X or shift
which then produce very very good random
numbers much better random numbers then
it then R and number generators that are
actually way more complicated right uh
so what I tend to do and you know I
can't say that I have the credentials to
really say that this is a particularly
good idea but what I tend to do is start
with X or shift and then add the
additional PCG step on top of it in
cases where it actually matters right
and so that's that's my approach
typically so again I would highly
recommend reading this paper because
basically what she talks about is the
fact that a lot of these random number
generators and you could see it
that's probably a faster way than
remember how to spell mu you can see
here where she kind of is a comparison
you can see X or shift down here there's
just a few things that it doesn't do
right and of those things not that many
are really that important to us you know
what I mean so X or shift is like is
it's pretty good if you do like the 64
bit version 32 bit if you only do the 32
bit issue ones then you've got some you
know some problems we can do either one
depending on how we want to do it but
you know this may be plenty good for us
if not we can go to this but the PSG's
is basically give you everything right
that you probably want so it's kind of
nice to go all right the PCG is just a
small step away from one of these if we
just kind of use one of these to start
with and if we see problems we step up
to a PCG that seems pretty reasonable to
me I don't know that I've ever looked at
how to Simbi one of these PSG's though
which does make things kind of tough the
reason that I mention that is because if
you look at what happens in an X or
shift so in an X or shift these are
predictable right I and that's really
crucial we can implement this in Cindy
and it's not a problem
a PCG doesn't have that benefit so a PCG
if you look at you know have they have
this pattern to them shift by a variable
amount right shifts by variable amounts
are really hard and Cindy I the the
problem is that they didn't introduce a
variable length shift until really late
in the game so if you take a look at
even I think if we allowed ourselves to
use basically everything
maybe even up through AVX
actually let me just do it this way if
you look at the shifts that you're
actually able to do on let's take MMX
out of there if you look at the shifts
that you're actually able to do if I
remember correctly so most of these are
all immediate s'right so all of these
are ones you just actors actually
specify these right you can load the you
can load the count out of here but it's
only gonna shift the it's gonna shift
everything in here by the same one right
so you don't get Lane based shifting
what you wanted is you wanted to shift
by b.i plus 15i right you wanted to
shift by the lane so each lane shifts by
each lane and that's just not on the
table
unfortunately now at some point and I
don't know what that point is you can do
it and and I don't know where that is
let's try to find it
here let's see so here it is so by the
time you get up to avx-512 it actually
does Lane shifting right and you can see
that right in here as you see how you've
got the a value that you're shifting and
the B value they're both Lane picked
they're both picked by a value
proportional to the lane constant rather
than in the other cases where they were
those immediate Slyke here where you're
just getting the shift is always the
same it's not proportional so that's
that's the problem if it weren't for the
fact that PSG's required that you just
always probably use them because they're
just better and they're not expensive
and in scalar they're just fine so like
when we do world gen we probably should
just use PCG everywhere because there's
probably no reason to use somebody there
and we'll be fine and we'll get better
randomness but for something like the
Ray caster we probably can't afford to
do that it's my guess so that's just
something to be aware of right that's
just something that's a problem that
PSG's have with a mismatch instruction
set when we finally someday in the
distant future if Intel ever actually
can make it happen they've been
struggling to do so unfortunately if we
can ever get an installed base of
avx-512 machines then party time right
because if you look at the cost of these
instructions to I don't think they're
super expensive I unfortunately they
don't have timings on here it looks like
but you know it's not I don't think
these are super tank your frame rate
kind of expenses either don't quote me
on that but so one of the nice things
about this if we ever actually got to
this point then we would have the
ability to do a PC g16 wide at a time
BAM there 16 random numbers ready to use
really high-quality thank you to
Professor O'Neill for that right
unfortunately we can't quite
get there until Intel gets us this in a
wider installed base right now hardly
anything has this so we ain't ship in a
game with that anytime soon
so again that's why my typical approach
is just get away with X or shift if you
can if you can't then we fall back to
the harder core stuff and when we do
world gen I think it would probably in
our best interest to use their really
good high-quality random number
generators because at that point we can
make sure that we do you know everything
in scalar since it won't matter so
anyway if we take a look at what we
actually would need to do to replace
this with extra shift here right you can
see where we do the the index seating
here and stuff like that doesn't really
matter what we do there for the most
part but when we take next you int what
we want to do is say alright this is not
how we're gonna do it anymore instead
however going to do it is we're gonna
follow the guidelines laid out by X or
chef 32 here which is to say we just
start with a result value that is
whatever the state is so remember our
series oops a random number series here
stores this index value which is the
state so we're just going to pull that
out we're then going to apply a series
of XOR patterns to it so we just XOR
this with itself shifted up by 13
shifted down by 17 and then shifted up
by five and then we've got our state
rewrite so we just store that back we
return that as the result and we
continue forward right so all of these
just happen to call that so we don't
have to update anything else in here we
pretty much should be done at that point
that that's should be it right you know
and off we go now if we want to we can
make this random series be wide all the
time so it's trivial to get one from it
first let's go ahead
yeah let's go ahead and verify that that
works reasonably well and so now if we
run this we should see that pattern of
rays hopefully we get something okay so
okay that is not what I would have
expected to see what is our
what is our random bilateral code doings
max random number
oh and min random number all right so
our max random number now should just be
all FS I think unless I'm wrong about
that so yeah so this is not really right
so what we want to do here is say you
know this should be you 32 max now I
believe yeah much better so oddly enough
if you look at this it's actually it's
really no worse I don't think it's a
it's a little clumpy still but it it's
about as clumpy as the old one was you
know I don't see a lot of difference
between those two I want to raise it up
a little bit so we can see the entire
ball better there so if I just let me
pop back to this and just try to push
that up slightly Chris that'll probably
land us oops that's not the value I'm
talking about
there we go so yeah if we take a look at
that
it it's you know it's really not any
worse than the old one was visually and
one of the reasons I wanted to wait to
do this until we had something we could
look at like this was for specifically
this reason I wanted to verify that we
weren't gonna have something that was
too clumpy and so until we actually had
something that was you know reasonable I
didn't want to get into that I didn't
want to replace the random number
generator and obtain was something but
until I actually could see it right cuz
seeing it helps a lot so let's see if
there's any holes in it by increasing
this number and again right it looks
pretty good like it there isn't we're
not seeing an area like if if we saw a
particular area that just wasn't getting
filled at all then that would be a
really big cause for concern right and
we're not seeing that so it seems pretty
good right so I think that's okay and
I'm I'm a I'm okay with that
right so we can we can excise this from
here and leave ourselves with that
and I think that's fine
yeah
all right um soon now I guess what I'd
say is yeah let's take a look at playing
with this function a little bit and just
see how we can get these points
distributed so the first thing I'm going
to do is for picking the normal I'm
going to try picking a unilateral for Z
so we're only picking up values because
we know our normal is pointing straight
up in this case so we can just kind of
buy us that way and go so here's our
sampling right and what we'd like to do
here is I think we like to make it so
that we're kind of more biased towards
up because straight out to the sides are
things that that don't contribute very
much to our lighting because we're using
angular fall-off so I think we want to
bias our sampling towards things that
can actually contribute to our to us
more directly and one thing we could
consider doing is not actually waiting
by the angular fall-off and instead just
instead of taking a uniform sampling and
multiplying the results by the angular
fall-off we can just sample proportional
to the angular fall off and not multiply
the results by the angular fall-off does
that make sense
meaning what we can do here is say look
previously what we were doing is saying
let's uniformly cast Rays all through
the thing right so we've got a uniform
sampling of the Hemisphere and then
we'll multiply that by the cosine of the
angle right between the normal because
we know that's how light works that the
light can't we don't get as much light
from things that are angular because of
the of the you know that sort of beam
diagram I drew before right so this
cosine here there's two ways we can get
that term one way is by multiplying it
after the fact so that we do a uniform
average right and then we multiply with
a cosine term after the fact you know so
each of these
it's multi-effect the other way we could
do it is to just more highly concentrate
our things so that they're proportional
to the cosine in the first place then we
just don't bother multiplying by that
term right because then we're basically
saying look we're gonna take less
samples in that direction so they'll
naturally be weighted by the cosine
because we just are already waiting by
the cosine to begin with hopefully that
makes some sense right so one way we
could do that is by doing sort of the I
guess doing doing a sort of inverse
square root mapping so one way we could
do that is say alright let's let's just
take two random bilaterals and then set
the third value just equal to whatever
they would have to be right so something
like that
and I believe that should oh that's not
going to do it so we just want to say
alright the normal X and normal Y right
we just want to recover Z from that like
so
and so now we get one that yeah is well
we don't really get much pointing
directly up there and also these kind of
have to be placed in the circle so this
is not quite this creates a little bit
to this this won't quite this won't
produce something in a disc right
because this it this is producing
something in a square and we need we
need it to be in an actual discs if that
makes sense so you know these aren't
quite right not sure how to do that
quickly though I mean one way is to just
throw it out if it doesn't fit but
that's kind of nasty we want something
that can produce fairly consistently
stuff that's going to be in there so
[Music]
I mean I guess one way to do it is to
pick a length so what we could do is say
all right you know and this is we can
make this faster
so one way to do that there right is to
yet to pick a length and you know that
weirdly that gives me only things that
appear to be out in the cone which I'm
not sure I must have that wrong here
yeah I've got that wrong serves me right
for not solving the equation so we want
x squared plus y squared plus Z squared
Square rooted to equal one squaring both
sides gets us x squared plus y squared
plus Z squared equals square root of one
I'm sorry
square of 1 which is 1 and so it's Z
squared equals 1 squared minus x squared
minus y squared and as you'll notice
that has an extra term in it that's why
I always write the equation so that
needs to have that extra term in it
right so try again although that's
interesting so that was the kind of
interesting happenstance I didn't know
you could produce a conic sampling in
that way
so here is one that should be more
biased towards the up angles and you can
see that it kind of is right and if I
let this series kind of run as well we
could maybe get a better idea but let's
let's also let's try running it for four
more iterations maybe can we make it a
little thinner too
so yeah
just looking at these you can see
they're very few samples get cast out
the side and and a lot of samples get
cast toward the top so that would be an
interesting way to run that and if if we
run this over time I'm gonna stop doing
the stable sampling thing and that way
I'll have an extra urease here that can
evolve over time and we'll get rid of
the extra counter eventually so let's go
ahead and take our our samples here and
let them roam
I thought we had a seed function Ramsey
all right and let's go ahead and run
that see what happens
and that looks pretty reasonable right
so now the question is can I make this a
little bit more concise because I kind
of just did that a little bit sloppy
there because if you look at it what
we're doing is we've got more than one
sort of normalization step in there then
actually probably needs to happen hard
to say but if we if we cindy ID this
which we should do so let's suppose we
wanted well let's first do our random
series let's first make our random
series be a little bit more interesting
right let's first say that our random
series is going to actually take the all
of the
is going to take all of the lanes into
account so our random series will just
by default beasts indeed right so it'll
have a state when you seat it you'll see
tit with the three things and if you
want you can just avoid doing that it'll
just seat it with some garbage right and
we could actually try to make those
actually be random by grabbing them from
somewhere or not doesn't really matter
the point being we're gonna make one of
these and what we're going to do here is
say that the state value is going to be
equal to a set of these now I think we
need to make one more of these thing we
have only one that loads just by default
but that's fine so then these we can
implement directly in Cindy so can we do
this so that will just work if if we
just change this to a 4x and implement
those functions right and that'll be
that the rest of this stuff can all just
be implemented in terms of using a slice
of that value so what we can actually do
is have it so that we have
random next 4x so we can actually do
this to get an entire four-lane random
result back right and then when we
return it code like this that only wants
a u-32 can just call random next you 3
to 4x and just take one slice out of it
right so you can just pull one out and
then really all we need to do is make
sure that our sim decode here has that
stuff in it that is the extra that we
would need for this so for example in
this case we need each of these and then
like in this case here where we're
taking four of them
off we go and then we just need these
shifts because we never implemented any
shifts or anything right so in here we
want an XOR right and we want the XOR
it's to be implemented probably like
here again really simple and same here
so to perform these shifts these are
shifts by immediate s--
right so they're going to take a value
here or I guess I don't know what this
immediate should be but it's probably an
S 32 is my guess
vague recollection and so these are
shifts the question is which kind of
shifts are they and in this case I'm
gonna have it so that you have to do
special work to get a signed shift
because sign shifts are pretty rare
they're usually meant for emulating
mathematical instructions we've talked
about this before remember a signed
shift or arithmetic shift as it's called
happens if you're shifting to the left
then it doesn't it never matters
shifting to the left Oh ease shifts in
zeroes so you get zeroes you know all
the bits move towards higher bits and
the low bit comes in a zero but if
you're shifting the other way then
typically if you do what's called a
logical shift it just does exact same
things zeroes come in at the top and
everything goes towards the lower so
it's the exact reverse of the other of
the left shift but if you right shift
arithmetic it shifts in the same bit
that was in the top so if there was a
one in the
up it it'll keep shifting in once
instead of ever putting a zero there
it's called an arithmetic shift because
it simulates a negative divide of a
negative number right because if you
imagine two's complement the high bit is
set for any negative number and when you
do that / like you know if I want to
divide by 4 so I shift by 2 right I want
to maintain the negativeness of the
number now it's not perfect because you
shift towards you you shift towards
negative one instead of shifting towards
zero right like you can never if you
divided the number one by the number two
you would expect zero but you will
actually get that's right if you if you
divide the negative the number one by
the negative two using this technique
you'll get zero if you divide negative
one by two
using this technique you will get
negative one because they'll keep
shifting in one's right so you know it's
all water under the bridge normally you
don't do these kinds of things anymore
I'll be enough we use them on
too because it was faster to use lane
shifts with 16-bit values to do a bunch
of the color things that we were doing
but that's you know hopefully someday
those those days will be over anyway so
what we need to do is we need to do
shifts here and we need to make sure
we're doing the right kinds of shifts so
for shifts that are going this direction
right
those are shift rights these are and I
don't remember if it's SHL or yeah but
there's si there's there's shifting
right arithmetic and shifting right
logical we want logical right and I
don't know remember what these are
called so we're gonna have to go look
them up
there we go and so you can see them here
so it's yet these are the the values it
looks like we have to cast to an M 128
eye which is really annoying I don't
know why they make you do that
because we don't actually want to do
that but we have to right so we really
just want to shift the values we don't
want to treat them as PS values or
anything like that so we really just
want to be able to say mm s ll PS right
and M s srl PS we want the immediate
versions of these because we don't need
to pass the value in a register so
they're actually that but if we try to
compile that we probably won't be able
to write because there's no versions of
that so what we have to end up doing is
this really annoying nonsense where we
do caste operations to convert these
things so we have to end up doing these
casts separations in and out right so
first we need to do a caste PS si128
just to tell it that it's the other kind
right so this actually goes on inside
here then we can shift it and then we
immediately have to cast it back
like so it's really dumb and there's no
reason for it it's just awful and it's
just I don't know why they did that I I
really just don't it's just silly and
makes no sense at all
oh and these have to be the whole reason
we did that that's because there's no PS
version right so off we go um what did
you expect constant expressions for this
hmm
so this is a constant but unfortunately
the compiler doesn't know that it's a
constant because it's too dumb right so
we kind of have to make this be
something that can expand this to be a
constant right so this right here is a
constant and so if you know you had a
language that was worth anything at all
it would immediately be able to see that
this is the case because you could have
written this in a way that just said
this is a constant and then it would
require this to be a constant whenever
it saw it of course you can't do that
this is a C++ where nothing ever works
right and so we have to work around that
somehow so probably we won't be able to
make this work exactly this way because
we don't we want to call the immediate
version we don't want to call the 1 we
have to stuff it in a register because
it will just be slower so in order to do
this we probably need to make these be
actual functions that we can do a pound
to fine on right so something like shift
you know
something like this that will then
expand to the proper thing so here's the
left shift here's the right shift and
you're not really ever going to be able
to do those unfortunately so here's our
shift left and then this will actually
be able to work now I did change the
name of this like so what tonight
parenthesize here cast PS open open open
close close close and then right so this
also has to be wrapped in an f32 to make
it be able to flow through the equations
properly so we also need an f32 for X
works like this
but that's pretty easy so at that point
we should have the same random number
generator working hopefully oh that
looks like we got some issue here that
will then produce four random numbers at
a time right so as soon as we debug that
that should be good to go and yeah it
will just take only one of those so when
it pulls out random next to you at 32
each time it will just take one of them
but then we can call this directly to
get four of them at once from now on
right all right so let's double check
that there whereas our or equals x or
equals looks reasonable our XOR looks
good to me our shift so shift right has
to cast this then do the shift logical
then do the cast back and then stuff it
into an f32
[Music]
so that looks pretty reasonable to me
let's take a closer look
so let's just take a look at what's
gonna happen in here I don't really want
to be threaded right now but
unfortunately I am let's do it this way
because will will hit one of these non
threaded first we go so hopefully now we
can just look at what these values are
right directly so here's what we've got
stuck in the values at the moment and
now we can look at how we're going to
update them right so here's us doing our
shift left XOR here's our next XOR so
this didn't this one didn't seem to do
anything which is a bit odd it's like
this value didn't get touched am I wrong
about that
so here's the values
yeah so I'm gonna have to step into that
and see what's up so we pull out the
value we step into
who's calling us here
so we do our shift left here then we're
going to load in that value did I mess
up the load I may have
I mean we should be hitting here and we
should be having our shift
I'm not really sure because that seems
pretty weird to me
I mean here's the values that are coming
in it's like only one of them is set and
I don't understand how that's possible
because the values that we started with
13 bits in they've all got well this one
doesn't but the rest of these all have
and plus that's a shift left not a shift
right so all of them should have had
values in there after the shift right so
something's up with that and I do not
know what it is
did I mess up the cast somehow I'm gonna
just go ahead and grab this out here so
if we look at the random code directly
and I just let it call this specifically
so I want to see what happens if I you
know don't do that and instead do
something like okay mmm 128 I temp
equals cast this is 13 mm 128 I shift
so there's the shift M 128 back and then
at the very end so all I did there is
unwrapped the macro right I didn't do
anything else to it
so it's the Zack same code as far as I
know so let's just go ahead and step in
and see what that does
so we've got to start with here's the
values that we believe ourselves to have
and I guess I can make this more
explicit by actually looking at each and
every one of them so if we look at that
is what we started with then after we do
our cast we should have exactly the same
stuff and we do
so now after we do our shift by 13
that's not a lane based shift yep yep
yep yep okay let's let's get the owl out
where's that owl that's just the whole
register just not what I wanted we'll
just put that on there sorry I was
rushing through that so if you look got
to balance this on my head here
we wanted the 32 version that's the one
that shifts each lane I called the 128
version and that's just the entire
register now to be honest I still don't
think I should have seen exactly what I
was seeing but before we try to debug
that any further I should at least
switch it to the correct function oops
right the this is the lane count I want
I want to shift 32-bit numbers right so
I want well I don't want that one but I
want this one here right
so let's try that one more time
shall we there we go now we're going to
do our shift
looks reasonable unlike before and now
here's our back version oops
that's good
here's our result it gets updated ah so
I think we should now be okay
yeah
although our
our lighting has a weird bug to it now
that I do not know how we could have
introduced by modifying the random
number generator
so we will have to investigate that
because that looks like a pretty
reasonable sampling of the sphere to me
if we just take a look at it here right
so you know I'd be pretty happy with
that technically what we should be doing
here is we should probably be calling
this in the you know sort of multi
lateral way a couple things about this
that I really don't understand at the
moment the lighting seems to have gone
kind kind of wonky and yet it eliminated
all of the flicker out of the lighting
I'm guessing that's because it's not
advancing the random number generator
somehow many more I must have done
something odd there so let's quickly
look at what happened there because I
have no idea what's going on there so
the series here is used with the entropy
counter the entropy counter is getting
updated
I'm not affecting that here because
we're just using this series value I
literally have no idea how changing the
random number generator they're really
made any difference right
oh you know what it probably is
we're probably picking the wrong slice
so we're probably picking the slice
backwards I think I know what it is so
probably what's happening is the seed
value yeah yeah yeah
so probably what's happening here is the
seed value is going backwards on these
so basically like when you pass in only
the first value for the seed it's going
into not the same slot that we're
pulling from I would expect that to be
easier but I bet it's not that's why I
usually use that are the set RP s here
and so I think if we did that for
example we would get our our flicker
back and our sampling back right yeah
yeah so that was just using the exact
same hemisphere pattern every frame
which is why we ended up in that
situation so that makes sense so trick
it out of curiosity I'm gonna take a
look at where we use gosh I wish I had a
case sensitive search here in for coder
I need to probably put one of those in I
think you there is one I just don't have
it bound to anything which makes it a
bit tough but let me see
where we actually call that so in here
that's the only place
I think that is the other place
so when we do a v3 4x and we pass this
in I think we're doing them out of order
there so I think we really want these to
be I think we're actually Swizzle in our
lanes here because we want easy row and
to line up always so I think these
always need to be set RPS because I
think easy row here is actually III like
the way that it the Intel ordering goes
so I think we need our mm sets to always
be set ours I think that's actually what
we want because that was kind of a bug
before because we were assuming that it
would go 0 1 2 3 but it's actually going
3 2 1 0 was the way that the macro was
going right so these like here for
example
well no that's that looks right though
all right now I'm pretty confused so I
mean look at what this says right set
pack single-precision you three two
floating-point elements in deaths with
the supplied values here they are right
Oh they've got them reversed
up here oh that's devious that's really
devious yeah so this is the one I
actually wanted right
oh man they'd like they double reverse
it yeah yeah all right
yeah that's super ugly so yes set R is
what we wanted because we want easier to
go into the low that's what we were
assuming so that's correct now so I
think that's all good I'm like I'm happy
with that
and and also you know we can now where
we were previously doing a bunch of a
bunch of different ones here for the
random numbers right I mean so like in
here right where we're creating bases
off of these these random bilateral four
X's right here that could all that could
be done much more efficiently right so
random bilateral forex that returns an
f32 X this can just be can do this
equation directly now right so
this can just be two times this can just
be that right and random unilateral
instead that can just be one of these
that we just have to have the ability to
do the cast on right so here we have to
have a u-32 to f/32 function on that to
convert you thirty twos to F thirty twos
but other than that it would just work
right so in theory right if we just
write one of these functions then we're
done and we can actually just no longer
have to call for random number
iterations to fill a vector we can just
get one altogether so if you take a look
at what has to happen for this again
also very straight forward we know we've
got one of these loops that has you 32s
in it right now
so it's effectively one of these right
that's the that's backwards
we want that so we want to tell it hey
we've we actually have it's actually one
of these 128 eyes right and then what we
want to do is we want to do a convert
right one of these so it will take
32-bit integers that we have and turn
them into 32-bit floating-point numbers
right now the rub here is that I don't
think we can actually convert unsigned I
don't think there's an EP you so if you
look at how this is written this is
extended precise is like I think it
stands for extended precision integer
maybe know what is the ep
you know what don't quote I have no idea
what that is the I though is for integer
32-bit right EP packed right right
that's packed element element packed I
don't know your guests as good as mine
with the e is packed integer 32 versus
packed unsigned would be a you here so
as soon as they do have that right but
few and far between so in this case we
can only do a conversion from two signed
so because that's the case we have to
take that into account in our bilateral
in our unilateral routine right that's
just what we're gonna have to do I think
so
hearing you 32 to F 32 where we do our
cast we're gonna have to do here is say
look we know that this convert isn't
going to convert the full range let's go
back here can I get back here no I can't
so when I do convert epi32 PS oops
I delete that I still want that so when
I do this conversion right this will
cast it first so that it knows it's you
32 this is just purely all I really want
to call as this but this is just
semantic nonsense that the Intel and
trans X force you do because they decide
have two types instead of one type so
once you're done with that then we'll
actually have the values in here but
they are signed now because some of them
would have been negative and some of
them would have been positive looking
depending on whether the high bit was
set right so when we go to compress our
random util unilateral after we do this
the divisor is actually not that it's
actually this right because and it's
actually not a unilateral it's actually
a bilateral so in a sense this doesn't
have to happen this is actually the code
for bilateral already and furthermore we
could make that be true here as well
right so this is actually the code for
bilateral already and for unilateral we
actually have to do more work so when we
actually get this in here we would need
to knock out the actual value here we
would have to knock out the sign bit or
we can just add and multiply here but
it'd be easier to just knock out the
sign bit right probably I mean I'm
guessing anyway but that'd be the
easiest way to go so we can just say
alright let's knock out the sign bit and
go from there
so to do that we would just say oops we
would just say like you 32 to F 32 and
you thirsty for it there we go
we really just want not so we want like
the inverse of that sign bit so we can
end that in there and knock out whatever
the hype it was going to be on that
series right so we get that we get back
the value we knock it out and then we we
finish the divide there is f32 max nuts
in our platform library it is not
so f/32 max is I mean I don't know how
else to write it up in this way right
actually for that matter now they think
about it that's just the thing we
actually wanted right if we end it with
s 32 max which is all bit set besides
the high bit that gets rid of the high
bit and then we do the divide and we're
done
right one thing that's a little nasty
about it is that if the number here in
the in this case when we do the when we
do the conversion you know I'm saying
this isn't quite correct
the reason is because the range is a
little bit different if you look at the
maximum s 32 positive value it's going
to be Oh X 7 fffff oh right it's gonna
be well we can do this
it's easier to talk about this with some
smaller numbers so let's say we have an
8 bit number the maximum 8 bit number
signed is 127 but the maximum negative
number is negative 128 right and that's
because 0 in integer is a positive
number so it takes up once because it
doesn't have the high bit set so that
takes up one slot whereas the negative
numbers don't represent zero there is no
negative zero in integer space there
isn't floating-point space you can have
negative and positive zero that's why
it's symmetric and doesn't have a higher
range for negative numbers than positive
numbers but the same is not true for
integers and so this isn't quite exactly
true for random unilateral this will
come out exactly right because we'll
convert at maximum s 22 and then we will
divide by that number and we will get at
most exactly one but in this case here
we could come up with a situation where
we actually have a number slightly
higher than this and then we don't
divide quite by it right so yeah it's
more like that but then you lose a
little bit on the other side so it makes
me think that maybe there's probably a
clever a more clever way to do it but it
makes me think that maybe we still just
want to do this the same way just to
ensure fairness because the extra op
isn't going to kill us here and that way
we don't have us that slight fractional
bias that you know it would be nice if
we didn't have right
okay so I think that gives us a way to
generate a random number ranges as well
I don't know what we may have made some
mistakes there played it a little fast
and loose but I believe that's correct
so now we are also a little bit more
efficient just when we're generating
those numbers which is kind of nice as
well
and that's a good place I think stop for
today so we've replaced for a number
generator we also now have the ability
to actually see if our lighting
converges to something reasonable which
is nice and so I think we can then
improve that hemisphere sampling like I
said next time by switching to this one
which I think will give us and then not
multiplying by the angular fall-off
which I think will give us a better
result so we'll do that next time
all right quick Q&amp;A before I go
is there a drawback to implement your
f/32 Forex type as a union between mmm
okay I don't you're saying so I really
don't know if you're allowed to do that
I don't know if that confuses the
compiler or not I really couldn't tell
you I feel like there used to be in the
back of my head I'm thinking that there
was a reason you couldn't do that
like the compiler needed to see the
caste or something but I I'm sorry I
just can't remember for some reason I
think it's slightly more complicated
than that but I just can't remember you
could try it and see
there is not windows functions for
random attrition well there are windows
functions for random number generation
but you're certainly not going to call
them for a real-time application right
though I mean we want our random
origination to be like you know seven
instructions long or something and the
Windows instruction you know calling the
random number generator windows is I
mean it's a crypto random number it
takes you know milliseconds to complete
if I remember correctly so that's what I
would say var to you guess I'll try my
idea keep one subarray fixed to make
three random yeah we could do that I
don't want to go to a fixed sampling
scheme till I'm done looking at the
sampling though because that's kind of
the last resort what does bilateral
versus unilateral mean bilateral means
negative one to one unilateral means 0
to 1 2 directions versus one direction
Master FET isn't relying on biased
sampling instead of angular fall-off
mean that you could over sample if you
use bilateral sampling it should not so
you know I didn't quite do it 100%
carefully there but no so the idea is so
let's say I'm going to place samples
with a distribution that's completely
uniform right so if I take write cosine
theta times a uniform distribution right
then I am expecting the contribution of
things at I'm expecting the contribution
of everything to be proportional to
cosine theta because I know that there
was no waiting here right so this
weighting was one and this waiting was
cosine theta so the weight of every
individual area is always going to be
one times cosine theta right which is
just cosine theta which is what I wanted
if I instead change it so that the
weighting of each sample is one but the
distribution is cosine theta that is
cosine theta times one which is also
cosine theta so in both cases as long as
you can guarantee that your weights are
set to something that when multiplied by
your distribution equals the thing that
you want you're done right so similarly
if and I'm just making this up I've no
idea what this even look like if I made
a distribution that was proportional to
cosine theta over two then I could
equivalently make something here be
equal to two right I could just wait
each sample by two and then I would
still get cosine theta - cosine theta
over two which is cosine theta
so you just have to make sure that your
weights multiplied your distribution in
such a way that results in the actual
thing you wanted whatever that is just
used would it be reasonable to seed your
pseudo-random number generator with a
random number generator provided by the
OS it would certainly be reasonable to
do is not necessarily sorry for lighting
because lighting it doesn't matter what
the startup is you can start up at the
same value every time the only time we
would care about seeding a pseudo-random
number generator by seeding it with a
Windows with something from a
cryptographic source or something that
was a really high quality entropy source
that couldn't be guessed he is for like
the world generator like the world
generator might want to do that
right so that you can't guess what it's
going to use
yeah it should be possible to basically
use Visual Studio 2017 instead of 2013
there may be some slight error
differences like things that complains
about that it won't complain about for
me but they should be pretty clear and
they should have already been covered I
think the the forums at handmade network
hero handmade network I think probably
has a thread on Visual Studio 2017 as
well or 2018 or anything else so you
should be able to make to basically do
it there may be a few little hitches but
they shouldn't be hard resolved
in genera can your current
implementation of letting turn a service
into a mirror no no no so so there's two
different kinds of light solutions that
we're talking about here
one is a the rendering lighting solution
and the other is basically like a global
illumination term approximation okay and
we're doing the latter not the former so
it's very important to understand the
difference between these two things
because they're basically unrelated in
it's sort of the real-time context
there's no these aren't really typically
thought about much an offline rendering
because it doesn't use a single solution
for everything oftentimes there are
nowadays but for real-time they're very
different so the thing to understand is
whether or not the I vector is used and
that's the important part to to
distinguish these two things so let me
explain that so let's say I have a
surface and I want to ask some questions
about the lighting at this surface right
one question I could ask about the the
surface here is how much light is
inbound on this surface right and let's
say on average now that question does
not take into account the eye vector it
does not take into account where the
viewer is the viewer could be anywhere
and the answer this question is the same
right if I want to know the average
amount of light coming in to this
surface from all directions that's a
question that I can ask irrespective of
where you're looking at it from so that
is the kind of solution that we were
doing for this lighting and we're doing
that specifically because it's a very
hard thing to do in real time so you
need a specialist
in place to get an approximation for it
because asking the amount of light
coming from a surface from all of these
bounces is very hard to do right now
another question I might ask is if I was
looking at this surface from a specific
direction and I hit this point what do I
see coming back at me for the light this
is an incredibly hard question it's
almost impossible to answer in real-time
in fact it is impossible to answer in
real-time but certain versions of it can
be asked in real-time and one of them
would be for example given an
approximate answer to this question
estimate how much of that light bounces
back towards the viewer right so that's
what we are actually trying to do now in
order to simulate a mirror oddly enough
we could do that one in real time with
ray tracing that's actually easy why
because a mirror is one of the only
surfaces on earth that we never see that
bounces a nearly coherent ray for every
eye red so basically every time we look
at it from a direction it's basically
just a little tiny the cone that it
needs to look at is super thin that's
what makes it a mirror the better the
mirror the smaller the bounce radius is
that we have to consider
so mirrors oddly enough can be done by a
ray tracer in real time they're actually
trivial the hard part is all the
services that aren't mirrors which are
most surfaces right mirrors are really
rare but they're trivial all other
surface is very hard why because most of
their services gather light from
everywhere for every eye ray so if we
look at it from this direction
typically we gather light from all
incoming directions which requires huge
numbers of rays to sample instead of a
mirror which just has just one direction
sample so if all services are mirrors
what a wonderful world that would be
i'll cost not really because then we
bounce around forever but that's a
little bets different story right so if
all services were mirrors or lights
right so either they had a single
uniform brightness value they were
shining at you or it was a mirror hey
rendering would be trivial we'd be done
right we could have perfect simulation
of the real world it would just be done
no problem right sadly it's not so what
are you gonna do so as a result mirrors
are actually act quite easy we're not
going to do them in handmade here
because it would require a whole
separate scheme at render time to do a
ray trace when we detected those
materials to do a ray trace we're not
gonna do that because it's just not
worth it right but if you cared about
that a lot for your game it's actually
not that bad to put mirrors in the hard
part is everything else the hard part is
a cave with a light at one end that
kinda has a curve and you see light
around the corner that's the hard part
of lighting in most situations it's
really hard to get right
long lean you mentioned a few times that
later on during roll generation we will
do a better job of adding sample points
are these sample points limited to
static terrain or do you have ideas
about how to handle terrain that can be
in motion or altered in some other way
yeah I mean we have two options first of
all the sample points are stuck on the
surfaces but they will move with the
services so they're not dieter nuts it's
not restricted to static terrain but the
distribution of points and how they
relate to each other may very well be
kind of static so we might have to do
things like if we want the lighting to
be always good when we move terrain
around we may have to try and update
sample points constructively as part of
that and I don't know how will if you
know maybe we will try to do that or
maybe move on
what our fact what I meant with the
question is that if a surface B is
nearly above surface a but perpendicular
to it is there risk a lot of rays
originating from a could hit B and thus
contribute a lot even though the angular
fall event that that's not the angular
fall-off we're talking about so the
angle of the two surfaces to each other
is not part of it right we're just
talking about the angle to the normal
and no it does not matter what kind of
services you're talking about the
sampling rule I wrote is just true as
far as I know anyway right so in the
case that you're talking about so you're
talking about something like this right
angular fall-off is only talking about
the sampling this part is not included
so the fact that this angle happens to
be steep to that angle that's not
actually the angular fall for talking
about and I don't think that term is in
there cuz is it it might be but if it
was that term would stay in there right
it's only the term for this that we're
talking about the normal dot the Ray
direction I'm talking about bilateral
sampling you mean by directional
sampling we don't do bi-directional
sampling
if we implemented bidirectional say
implement sampling then we would have to
figure out how we want to do that
because that's has a bunch of
implications that are different so I
don't know that's a whole different we
don't need to even really know how we
would change our routines exactly for
that so going moving to bi-directional
sampling would be a whole different
thing
now the opposite turn in terms of the
diagram what diagram are we I'm not sure
what dagger I'm talking about n 30
shadow or neo shadow I guess is probably
how to read that
the geometric concept of raves breaks
down for caves or any cone I don't I
don't know what you're talking about the
reflection diagram breaks down for the
cave example no it no it doesn't why
does the reflection diagram break down
for the cave example
I mean it's you know I'm just talking
about this right and so if you have
something emitting light here and you're
talking about trying to figure out what
the light is here since you can't
directly see the light source I was
talking about things where you have to
account for the fact that you know the
lighting from this is maybe bouncing in
this fashion right so what you're
effectively trying to do is build a
system that can approximate get
approximate solutions that still produce
the fact that there should be some
lighting here even though the only way
to get lighting there is through
indirect bounces right you know there's
one type there's another type and so on
but what reflection I don't know what
you mean by the reflection diagram
breaks down that K say it's the same
reflection equation regardless of what
this geometry looks like right
I was gonna wait a second see if there
is a reply to that before I word
otherwise we're done with questions
the illumination problem
so are you just me are you just more
talking about if you actually wanted to
figure out the solution to a well I
guess I don't know what you're actually
talking about we're not talking about
trying to measure photons here right
like actual what happens with photons
when they bounce around I mean
technically you're into quantum
mechanics there at that point right
we're just talking about if you actually
want to take and figure out a reasonable
solution to sampling the light coming
and have us very instantaneously at a
particular point then you can sample
however you're going to sample you can
sample proportional to a weight and then
not weight or you can wait and sample
uniformly and that is just true period
right now what you're talking about is
something completely unrelated to what
we're talking about you're talking about
whether or not you're talking about the
like how the physics of lighting are
going to work in a particular case right
as to whether ray casting can actually
capture what's going to go on or
something like that but that's not
relevant to sampling right sampling that
thing is true about sampling period
there it's not like it's not it's an
approximation it's just true right and
so you might end up in a situation where
the thing that you're sampling you've
used an approximation to is as in the
case where if you think that light
transport along Ray's is not sufficient
to capture what you actually wanted to
have happen then you would be in that
situation but that's a separate topic if
you don't think rays are accurate enough
to capture the light transfer then you
have to deal with that but the sampling
part is just true it does not have like
nothing on numberphile can really change
that fact that's just how sampling works
because it's just a property of
summations
you can sum up end things waited by WI
that are uniform or you can sum up a
thing distributed by WI weighted
uniformly and you will get the same
answer that's just math right it doesn't
really have any dependence on the thing
in question that makes sense so
hopefully that answers that question and
suffice to say the number of
approximations we have to make anyway to
get things to run in real time means
things like whether whether we would
care about the approximation of Ray
transport it's way beyond anything we
would care about because we've already
had to make I mean already the fact that
we're not going to really take into
account the textures of services at all
you know is a pretty huge one because
these services and the game will have
textures mapped onto them and we're
still we're not going to sample those
textures right we're not going to take
the extra time probably on a bounce to
sample the textures so the sample points
will just have fixed color and that'll
be what they are right so you know in
that sense it's important to keep in
mind that if if you're even thinking
about the degree to which Ray's might
not capture some lighting thing you're
not in a realistic space because you're
already past you know you've already
made enough approximations by that point
that it would not be something you
should really be considering if that
makes sense but I do want to describe
the point that no the sampling part is
true it has nothing to do with your
represent representation of light it
doesn't matter your representation of
light could be completely different
right and it would still be true so the
sampling it's really important to
understand the sampling is not an
approximation that sampling thing is
true right and it holds true regardless
of what you're doing and if the
underlying thing happened to have some
kind of
inaccuracy to it then the underlying
thing may be at fault but the sampling
part is not it's mathematically correct
that make sense all right so I think we
are good to go here thank you everyone
for joining me for those sort of
handmade here oh it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along series at home you
can always go to handmade hero org and
if you pre-order the game it comes with
source code so you can follow along at
home we'll be back next weekend and I
just want to go ahead and play with that
hemispherical sampling and maybe take
out the angular waiting term and just
bias the samples to be proportional to
cosine theta anyway that's what I think
I'm gonna go ahead and try and we'll see
how that goes there may be issues with
that due to the fact that how much we're
sampling may not be sufficient but you
know we'll we'll see what we can do
that's it for this week until next week
have fun program everyone and I'll see
everybody on the Internet take it easy
run