hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero we are currently we have two bugs
in our lighting system and well we have
two bugs we know of uh sometimes with
something like a lighting system you
have this nasty thing of you know you
have the bugs you know you have and then
you probably also have other bugs that
you may never find because lighting is
so subtle you may never find out right
um but
uh we have two bugs that we know about
and so today what i'd like to do is try
to find at least one of them uh the one
that i think is going to be the easiest
to find and of course that's just my
guess who knows will actually be used to
find but
uh the one that i expect to be these to
find would be why we're having a problem
with light copying um in order to make
lighting efficient of course lighting is
very expensive one of the things we do
is we bin the lights uh by like we
basically like cabin off where the
lighting occurs
in to just the region around where we
are looking right
so you can see the buggy lighting
happening here uh there's two you can
actually view two separate bugs
happening
i'll stay in this region for a second so
that you can see only just the one that
i'm going to talk about uh but you know
for temporarily if you look here you can
see how we get this sort of weird light
bleed that uh it looks like it gets
contaminated by
some
pretty naturally like bright light seems
to be able to contaminate the system
with like incredibly overbright values
right
that's one bug uh and we have to go
figure out what's going on there why
we're getting this sort of like energy
uh basically like this runaway energy
ramp
which we didn't use to have so we have
to go figure out what that's coming from
because we don't know
and the other one is this one you can
see if we're in a region where we don't
actually necessarily have that
particular problem uh what you can see
is that the copying so as we align the
lights differently as the camera uh you
can see the camera visible rectangle
here in white uh and the lighting moving
in the uh this sort of cyan
uh frame there that moves just to make
sure that the lighting is always kept
within a certain region
uh if you notice what happens when i do
this is on the moves it seems to almost
like clear out the lighting uh it's very
weird and erroneous it looks like
uh and
what's supposed to happen is it's
supposed to copy the lighting forward
but what actually looks like it happens
is that the lighting gets reset to black
and then it gets recomputed or something
close to that
and so the you know this is unusual and
strange because uh we're just getting
these very weird artifacts that we
didn't used to have right that's that's
really i guess the most strange part of
it is that we you know the light copying
was working fine and then we went in and
we drastically simplified a bunch of
things in the lighting
um which was great and now it runs
extremely quickly and still produces
very high quality results but we
introduced these bugs and so now we have
to get rid of them so it i don't really
have a handle on what's going on there
so what i'd like to do today is figure
out like what that's coming from so when
we do that light alignment what's
actually the problem there right like
what what are we actually experiencing
that causes that strobing effect because
we would expect it not to really drop in
that way um
and you know maybe there's something
else going on there that really isn't
related to the copying maybe the copying
is happening okay but it's you know it's
something else but
given what we currently know
about the lighting system
um
it doesn't it just doesn't make good
intuitive sense because
the
first of all we know that the light um
when we do a light probe so when we do
the sampling for a particular light
source
what we would want to do
uh is we would want to have the
we
eventually we would like to have the the
light probes probably be more stochastic
than they are but right now
every light probe casts the same number
of rays
as every other light probe
so
when you
shift the lighting grid
unless i'm just not thinking of
something that we're doing like there's
something we're doing that i'm just not
thinking of
that i'm confused about
there actually should be no way
to get a different lighting result
than you already have
you know what i'm saying like you
shouldn't be able to
you should always no matter which point
on the grid you are
you should always produce the same
result for a particular location
so we would expect the copy to be
completely invisible shifting the grid
over
should not have any effect if we were
using the grid if we were injecting
entropy based on which point in the grid
you are then you could imagine some
other bug about the sampling meaning
that when you shift the grid over you
get a different result and that could
contribute to the flashing right
but in this case we know that's not
actually happening there is no entropy
injected into the grid
so
we should
no matter how we slide the uh the lights
uh grid we should not actually be able
to produce this result
so that's very odd and it means there
must be a bug in here somewhere
the problem is i have no idea what that
bug would actually be because we didn't
change the code that actually does the
copy when we simplified the lighting so
it doesn't make very good intuitive
sense
that you would have this problem so if
you look at how the
the light atlas works which i believe is
the thing that executes the copy here's
the voxel code
on this side
and here's the lighting atlas code on
the other side
we're looking at a routine here called
block copy atlas
and block copy atlas just takes a offset
parameter
and the offset parameter tells you where
in the voxel you are supposed to be
fetching right
so you're you're looking at like you
know i'm gonna i'm gonna fetch
two away or three away or whatever it is
that's how much shift you're going to
have in each of the directions
now we removed we nerfed the z code so z
now doesn't work anymore right
intentionally this will this this will
never happen
why because there the voxel never
changes its z location it's pegged to
just the we we removed stacking so it's
pegged to just the only
part is just where the game currently
takes place that flat plane
and so if you look this code should in
theory never run which we could uh you
know assert um so like we could say
right
um but you know one of the bugs could be
maybe it does maybe we're pursuing there
i think i
already asserted that this doesn't
happen because i'm pretty sure that in
the actual lighting code itself where we
call block copy atlas because this is
the only place
we assert that the z like is always
passed in as zero
so
you know we should be relatively assured
at this point that the z code okay well
there you go right
so
that's
that's something to investigate right
there so
we we're never passing a d voxel z
as far as we know because this assertion
should fire
uh unless there's some where else that
calls black copy atlas i guess i should
double check the cost act but i assume
it yeah
so if d voxel uh
dot z here is always zero what is
happening right
uh z should always be equal to stop z i
would think although actually you know
what no i now that i think about that
that's probably wrong
um
the z
might still consider itself happening on
one layer
yeah so that's the z region i take that
back that's the the what should actually
the one that should not run is this
clear
so basically this one should run because
this is actually the loop for z that
does get copied that does get written
this is the loop for z that doesn't get
written so this is where you would you
know it would just be off right it would
just be it would be zeroed
so um
this is the actual one that should never
happen because the zeroing should never
occur uh
so let's try that one more time
okay so i feel like that should probably
never happen i suppose it's possible
that we never get in here but that
should probably never happen so uh let's
just check in a debug build so we can
inspect values reliably
um
which
would
be
this
uh and so let me see because i don't
understand why this would be happening
since you know i would assume
um that
that this should not be occurring like
we should not be shifting z
uh and maybe i'm wrong about that but
like if you think about what happens
with the fetch offset the fetchoff set
should always be passing in a zero there
uh which it is
so if it's always
the case that you're not moving at all
in z i don't think i understand how this
clearing code would be working right
like
like why would we ever be clearing an
entire layer of this thing
it doesn't make sense does it
i mean
at least i don't think so
so that if that's the case
that's probably just our bug
we accidentally always clear one layer
of the z i guess
um maybe because these computations were
actually wrong and we just didn't see
that because the top layer of z was
never visible before you know what i'm
saying
so it's entirely possible that the
problem here
uh is primarily such that
we
we've we've got a bogus computation in
how final z works
and what's happening is that the the top
most z layer will always like this
computation was one off so the top most
z layer you can see internally here
that even though we said don't move in z
at all it's going to clear one entire z
plane
um so i'm gonna go ahead and say just
right off the bat before we even look at
it that if we if zero this out i i
wonder if that just completely fixes our
problem
right
and if it does that tells us that that's
what the bug is the bug is that there's
like an off by one computation in the z
there well i should probably run it in
release mode but that would that would
totally answer our question right
um if it turns out that the top z layer
is always getting cleared that's just
obviously wrong
and that would produce the flashing so
let's see if the flashing goes away
of course it's hard to tell because we
have the other bug as happening as well
but let's see what happens
i can't you know it's a little bit hard
to tell with the lighting voxels in
there um so maybe i should remove the
lighting voxels for now since we don't
really need them frank we're not using
that uh like i don't really need to see
that for any particular reason
uh so maybe i should just go ahead and
delete that
uh that's the spatial there's like a
draw spatial grid this thing
if i just just remove that
there we go it should be easier to tell
if there's any flashing i mean it's
still a little hard because since
there's the other lighting bug it's
difficult to see
but we just have to get to a place where
it's less you know
so i would say i still see it though i
still see at least some flash occur
there which is not just that
um
now of course i don't know if if we're
doing some kind of a weird
there's some weird other artifacts
happening there so i don't know if we're
still seeing some other kind of weird
aspect to it
that weird the fact that the light
has that weird
like this light
gets brighter when i move makes no sense
at all so there's just there's a lot of
really weird stuff happening so i feel
like we've just got some core things we
messed up when we did our uh
our simplification pass
and so you know it's a little bit hard
to say so
are we still getting that flashing or
not it's really hard to perceive
um which is makes it a little bit
difficult
i would say we're still getting
some flashing
just not as bad
but there's still some there right like
i can still see the light shift over
so it seems like it's still copying
wrong
like
my assumption is that the clear makes it
so that you don't see that artifact but
it still seems like maybe the values
getting passed in
are incorrect do you know what i'm
saying like that part seems
broken
in some way
i'm not exactly sure
what that way is but
something odd is happening there that is
an issue right
um
my assumption
oh well actually you know what it's
pretty obvious what it is actually
there's at least one other one which is
that this copy is only happening at the
lower level because we know for a fact
that final z is not the correct value so
actually yeah we would still see half of
a problem which is the upper level is
not sliding right so that's exactly what
we would expect to see okay so
what's going on why is this happening so
if we look at this code here
um this is the code that computes the
z values so you can see stop c and final
z
uh occurring here
so
um let's take a look at how this stuff
uh
shakes out
so we can see
uh
we can see the two paths involved the dz
value in our case
i so i guess looking at this like the
initial z value is going to run to zero
to this equation and this is the problem
that we have
it's going to be whichever is
higher
the initial z which we know is not
higher because it is zero so i'm not
really sure what case that's designed to
prevent
i guess just one where the d voxel value
is very low so this is just clamping
it's saying it's going the stop z value
is going to run from the initial z
to whatever the last
the last value is
and you know doesn't that just seem
wrong
where is this one coming from
because look at how this code works
i guess no okay so no no i'm all right
with that because let's think about this
so if voxel dim in this case dot z is
two
you subtract one from it it's one d
voxel z should be zero so stop z should
be one
and i guess the prob okay but i do see
the problem here if this is z is not
equal to stop z the problem here is it
should run this loop for the last one
right stop z should get we want to run
on stop z as well
so shouldn't this if this is the one
we're going to stop on
it should actually be one higher than so
this is as if
it rather than stop z this is computing
like what the last z value would be
so it should at least be that
i would assume
right
i mean i really just don't see it i
guess i don't understand where the minus
one came from and it seems like it would
be wrong in all of these and i'm
guessing we just never noticed because
we had a large enough stack that it
wouldn't be an issue
if to just miss one right but i don't
know
so we'll see i still see a little bit of
flashing in the movement so i don't
think we quite fixed it whatever it is
um
but i do think that's gotta just be
wrong i i don't see why that would be
occurring now we probably should put
some asserts in here
um i don't know if we we did that
already
uh yeah we we have the light atlas
assert
that we can turn on
so
let's go ahead and turn that on so that
we have some validation
about what's going on here
um
so yeah that's the light leak assert but
you know i can probably turn those off
at the moment
um
that's the one that catches the light
leaking it's the one that
uh basically you validate
you validate that the the values are all
relatively inbounds
yeah so we're always going to hit that
light leaking one and i suppose what i
should probably do is mark these in some
other ways so i should probably do like
if temporary or something like this so i
just so i can find them again if i'm
removing some of these because i want to
put them back in
that's the same one at the end of block
copy atlas
so our light leaking checks are
obviously working quite well they catch
that green thing
um
it's it's obviously very visible in the
data which is also good i suppose for
when we go to hunt it okay so at the
moment we're not fetching out of bounds
at all right um because this thing would
have asserted when we go to do zero tile
or copy tile
uh
at least i believe so and we should
probably verify that but so i think this
code is wrong i think all of these
wanted to not have the minus one in
there
um they all want to do the last row uh
which before they you know simply
weren't doing
and that seems bad
so
uh yeah like oops i guess
and so i don't think there's any problem
with that now except i still don't see
the the flashing still seems to be there
slightly right i can still see
like when i look in here i can see
movement across the tile
and
you know honestly
there's something even weirder about
that which is the movement that i see
across the tiles now is stable so it's
not actually flashing it's like actual
movement which again makes me wonder how
is that possible because there shouldn't
be any way to have that happen
unless we are injecting entropy
like
like that doesn't make any sense to me
like that should not be possible to be
stable
uh to be specific about what i'm looking
at here
um
so take a look at what happens for
example there you can see right there
there's like a dark like that's darker
than say the two neighbors right
when i move through you can see that
darker piece move
sideways it slides
right
and that should not really be possible
because again like i said as far as we
know
each light probe is sampling uniformly
so there's no entropy being injected
based on the grid location
that must be either an erroneous
assumption meaning we did accidentally
forget and leave in some kind of a
permutation that's based on which grid
square you're on in which case we need
to go find out where that is because we
at least need to know about it even if
it's not an error
but separately
that's definitely
uh
like
it's definitely not something we want to
show up as a slide like that now it's
possible that if you turned off right
now we are literally recomputing all of
the lighting there's no blend factor
right um
you can see here that we had previously
had a blend factor this is a blend
factor right of like four
um
that allows it to smooth over four
frames which i assume that if we turned
that on again
maybe this would not be an objectionable
artifact meaning i don't know maybe you
wouldn't actually see
uh
to you know you wouldn't actually see
the the difference but
and you can see that it does smooth it
out quite a bit but
i don't know
i still see it shift almost immediately
let's try turning that up quite a bit
because maybe this will give us a clue
to what is happening here because if i
go ahead here and change it to 1 over 60
so that it's a very slow run this will
take an entire second to update the
lighting
um what actually happens to that slide i
i would like to see
so it does look like it is actually
it is actually based on the fact that
the lighting gets recomputed differently
it looks like right
because you can see if i wait here
the dark darkening comes back
right if i go in there
the and i should probably turn all this
crap off as well um which is actually
not that hard to do we can actually do
it without actually changing anything
here by just moving this out of here
what that is i don't even remember um we
should probably get rid of that as well
but uh you can kind of see here
you're like what is that
what is that yellow we don't even what's
what is this yellow box i don't even
remember we draw so many debug things
while we're trying to find
uh
situations like that i don't even know
what that box is
is it
some
is it like a debug light
or is it is it like drawing the debug
light or something like that
this is where like the recording would
be helpful we could go back and look
it's probably not anything it's bigger
than the screen bounds
um
yeah it's not that so i don't know what
i don't know what's drawing that i have
no idea what's actually drawing that um
let me just look for
things that have that color pattern
uh so we can i don't know see what it is
i'm not sure
um
what
well it looks like for some reason and
we'd have to go back and check the tape
to find out why it looks like for some
reason we're drawing a negative one to
one cube we were probably just trying to
figure out where the world origin was
uh
and
i don't care about that even in the
slightest at the moment so let's get rid
of that
um
okay so now we are free
of of that so what i was trying to say
is that if we look in here
um
and we like as we kind of
shift in and out
with a one second delay you can't see
that artifact anymore
but it's still there and that's what
allows us to know that it is actually
like that the lighting gets computed
differently
so if we're zoomed in here
you can see that these light panels
uh after they have a chance to normalize
they look fairly uniform there's maybe
it's slightly darker in here but only
slightly
if we then move out you will watch these
darkened significantly
after the shift
and i
don't know if that maybe is expected
because they're picking up light from
where the hero is standing
right
um like you can see here that i am as i
move as i move in you get that light
difference
but
so i think what that says to me is i
should turn off the debug light so that
we don't actually have that happening
like let's just get rid of the debug
light entirely
so that it's not there
and now let's see if the artifact
remains as i move around
uh and i'll turn off the one over 60
blend as well
let me also
get this out of the way
why i didn't why i actually restarted
the game i have no idea since i could
have just left it running but you know
so i am not bringing a light into the
room anymore
but it sure does seem like just me
moving in here creates
uh sort of synthetically more light for
no apparent reason
what i will say though again this just
reinforces my decision
that i think it was right to just like
fix the current lighting that we have
and smoosh it to 2d which is what we did
once we get this debugged like oh my god
this looks awesome not forever
4. this looks awesome
um like this lighting looks so so darn
good it's completely like
it it totally sets the mood properly it
has all that nice character to it it
looks great
um
so i do think like
we did the right thing like this looks
awesome and it runs the 60 fps uh i
think just fine when we actually do a
full release build
um
it just looks great right like it just
looks great
um
so yeah
i'm i'm really pleased with how the
lighting came out i thought it was sucky
at first but it turns out it's actually
quite good um
it just really looks cool
uh yeah
so anyway uh
and also you know the other thing i
would note is that you can see that like
when we slow down the blend
you can also see that the light
contamination takes away longer which is
what we would expect like in here right
the the green bleed from outside
you can see how much longer it takes
because the like because we've slowed
down the blend it probably should still
happen i mean if we just sit here and
wait
presumably the green blur eventually
will
right it's already starting right you
can see it's really bright here so the
the power feedback problem that we're
having which we don't really know where
that's coming from which is our another
bug we have to fix
is still happening but that that
delay makes it harder to see
okay so now that i've gotten rid of our
light source if i turn the blend
like the blend rate back up
where is my
tea blend
it sounds like when you take a bunch of
different types of tea and blend them
together i thought it was one over 60 oh
it's not wow it's not an f for some
reason
all right
so if i turn this back up to
just say okay i want to see new lighting
every time so you only get one frame to
compute all of the lighting no blend
right
um
that's really interesting
now i can sort of understand why these
lights go away and that's because the
lighting is not big enough to encompass
them probably right
so if you look at where the bounds the
lights shift out of bounds which means
we probably have to fix this lighting to
be
[Music]
a little bit more centered than it is
the reason we had it going this way was
primarily because
we
um
we wanted
when the lighting was slower
we wanted to
because you could see further in this
direction we wanted to
uh cache this in there
but it's not a very good idea anymore we
probably want this bounce to be fairly
uniform around it because the lighting
is very quick it updates very fast now
so we want to keep lights some of those
off screen lights inbounds right that's
what's happening there
but you can see like from especially
from the fixed view like this you can
see how it really does change the
lighting just changes as it moves it
doesn't really make any sense
why that would be the case and it
doesn't really seem to be related to the
copy because as you saw if we turn down
the blend rate the copy happens
instantly the blend rate is not involved
in the copy if the copy was the thing
producing this result then turning down
the blend rate
would have
not affected
the visibility of this bug so that means
there's something actually different
like there's literally something
different
about the casting
as you shift the light voxel position
i which should just plain not be
possible so that's bug number one
uh for us now because it looks like the
copy is just fine
like it's actually there was a bug in
the copy we did fix it it's gone
uh but there's now a different bug that
has to do with sampling that is really
weird right so we gotta go track that
down
um
trying to think if there's anything else
to say about this but i think that's
about it right
uh we should probably fix that alignment
uh this should probably get straightened
out
and i'm not exactly sure how we want to
do that but like when we do the lighting
alignment part of things
so when we call update lighting
right like we have in here
um
i guess i would say i'm not sure
i'm not sure to what extent this
i think this always
this is always the thing that actually
determines like where it is aligned
right
um so you can see like vox camera offset
y plus two that is that hard-coded shift
that's baked in there
so like if that went away then at least
it would be centered right um
so if we look now at how the blue
uh
is related you can kind of see
um that it's lined up
right now why we get the sort of
skew on the sides so that it's biased
why we have
an uneven x layout
uh that i'm not sure about
it might just be because it's two here
and one here and it can't be made even
uh that i'm not sure about
um but keeping it even like that you can
see fixes the the room getting dark
before we you know problem right
i don't think it would necessarily fix
it this way because it looks like the
the gap
x gap is maybe a little bit too too
small there so we may have to enlarge
the lightning region slightly like one
more tile on the x axis or something
um but in general i would say you know
so
i think i'll look at how to do the
expanded alignment later
so for now i'd just like to keep
focusing on this so we have a very
strange we have like a really strange
kind of bug there right
um that i'm not sure
i really don't quite know what the
what is actually going on uh
so
something about the way the casting is
happening is permuted based on where you
are
and that shouldn't really be happening
so that's very strange so if you look at
how
we are doing that in grid raycast i i
thought and maybe this is very incorrect
but
i thought uh the way this was working
before was that it shouldn't really have
mattered
which one of these you were because the
ray directions should all have been like
the same
uh and maybe that's not really correct
because you have different you have
different um
alignments versus the spatial grid like
with the quadrant index thing here
um
that's kind of a good question and i
don't really know i also think we make
you know one other thing we could do is
get rid of the 2x over sampling we don't
know that we really need that for any
particular reason in fact we may just
not
want that
um so it could be that we should get rid
of that but separate from that
uh if you look at what happens here our
sample direction table is always the
same table
right
um
so no matter what cell you're on
i don't quite see your you should always
be casting the same set of rays
that's all i'm trying to say
so in here we loop over the entire table
of t y t x and ray index the full
complement of rays that are going to be
cast
they get cast off of the same
base sample pointer
right
um
so like i don't fundamentally know why
you would see
differences there
it's not
it's not clear to me now it could be
because this walk table is kind of
busted
right
so let's suppose the walk table was
busted then the quadrant that you were
in
would
would make the difference
right
um so it could be that that's what
happened like the light sampling walk
table is built wrong or something
and
like
i mean i guess we should probably go
look at that i can't think unfortunately
i i don't know
[Music]
of any way to really fix that uh
in like a short term you can't just set
this to zero because then it will
actually cast wrong because the location
that you're casting from
would be incorrect
um
so like i'm not sure of a way to take it
out of the equation temporarily to see
if it is the problem
so that's unfortunate uh to say the
least but
uh we have a bunch of options here like
one of them is to remove walk tables
entirely since z transitions are no
longer an option
one thing we could do is just put the
walk because you can only choose
you can literally only choose to move
one cell in x or one cell in y that's
all you can do
we could probably change it so that it
happens in line now
and doesn't actually
uh
involve a walk table
i
before that was demonstrably slower
because it had to do a full three-way
xyz check but if you only have to do x
and y that might be enough to fix the
problem right
to make it not too slow
um but looking at this right this is the
code that you would expect to be sort of
wrong if if that was the case
um
okay
so wait a minute
what is this about
is this another bug we had that we just
didn't know about i mean it's pretty
easy to have bugs when you only work on
something once a week so i'm not going
to be surprised if it is
but how would this have worked because
if the walk table offset so every time
you loop over these in when you look at
how many sample directions there are
you're setting a walk table offset that
overwrites whatever the previous one was
clearly you would need four of these one
for each of the quadrants that you were
in and the offset would have to match so
that's probably just the bug and we
didn't know we had it before and it was
just wrong
you know what i'm saying
like this would have to be this
where the quadrant index gets written
into
like the
like
you know what i'm saying
so so in order for this code to be at
all even slightly correct
you would need that to occur and you
would need your sampling spheres right
this walk table offset would actually
have four entries one for each quadrant
um that's just
that's just science
um so i'm pretty sure that was wrong
i mean i don't
want to say that for sure but i'm pretty
sure that is just flagrantly wrong
um
like like that's just completely broken
now since we have the weird light
contamination problem it's hard for me
to know for sure but i'm pretty sure
that was just wrong
um it doesn't seem to have really
changed anything which is weirder still
right um
but but that was just an error
uh i can't see any way that's not an
error
right
um and and this is wrong too right so
actually wait no no no i'm wrong
so we do actually create a different
table for each quadrant
but the walk table offset's going to be
wrong
so
so no that i was i'm still right because
even though we create a different table
who cares you still have the problem of
each
you need the right index depending on
which table you were using
but i think that does mean this code is
now correct meaning the fact that this
dest index gets reset to zero is totally
fine
because
you are creating a separate
table for each one
again you can kind of see why this code
now feels like we're doing too much work
right
when there were three in you know
when there were three
spatial directions to walk in
maybe this made some sense
but when there's only two it feels like
now we just shouldn't
need to do this right like it feels like
if you look all of this stuff that was
for loops before it doesn't need to be
loops it can just be a single if to see
if x is greater than y or whatever
um
i feel like it should be relatively
straightforward to just say like
not do this
uh it just seems like way too much work
now
and i guess i don't know
uh i don't know if this is the right
time to do that but the question is do
we bother debugging this
which i think is part of the problem or
do we not
i guess one thing we could do
is if we stuffed a known lighting value
into each light cell instead of doing
the grid raycast
that would probably let us see more
clearly if that was the case meaning if
if it was the fact that the rays are
different that's the problem but then
again i i don't know um it's a tough one
it's a tough one
i don't have a very coherent thought on
what the best way is to preheat proceed
um because i do think we risk debugging
something that we don't want to keep and
that's a bad decision usually on the
other hand it's possible that it won't
fix the problem and in which case maybe
the problem comes harder to find
so it's just really hard to guess but
you can see that the problem is still
there right so it wasn't that
um and another option is maybe we could
try to lock the grid to only move on two
steps
so so
like if for example
[Music]
if we
forced the grid to not change which
quadrant anything was in
so in other words like
the
the this part
right where we do the like
um
where we do like the center p nonsense
and we'd look to see like you know if we
need to
if we need to check the set the dvox
little thing to whatever it's going to
be and blah blah blah right
if we always like forced d-voxel to be
on twos so that the quadrant doesn't
change
presumably that would do it
uh the dark spot does move though is the
thing just sorry just checking chat for
a second there
uh the it does move
you can see it it might be hard to see
on stream but it but it does right
so watch
do you see
like watch those panels
we definitely get some weird like
oscillating behavior there which we
don't have an explanation for
and so and it is it is varied it varies
as the as we slide right if you look at
what's happening
you can see
the slide
um
well the reason it didn't does nothing
changes while i'm in the room is because
i'm not i don't have a light over my
head anymore
right
that's why we were getting a change
while i was in the room is i was
carrying a light with me once we turned
that off it's pretty clear that it
doesn't actually change
uh unless this lighting volume changes
and even inside the room you can see
that it does change when the lighting
volume changes it's a little bit hard to
see
but like if we
if we fix the camera there and you look
at that
right it gets darker when the lighting
volume alignment changes again
right
so you can kind of see that like there's
definitely some really weird stuff
happening there that we don't have an
explanation for so it's definitely a bug
uh and very unlikely to be like actually
something correct going on i think it's
just our we have made some kind of error
right
and we don't know what it is so there's
something going on with that alignment
that's very strange
um
and i don't know what it is
and so we probably yeah i mean we we
gotta have a better
way of investigating that
i do think the walk table offset stuff
was definitely you know had to have been
broken before because
it just doesn't make any sense how it
was working this time
and again i don't know if we just want
to rip this stuff out
my my gut instinct says we do
like we just don't want walk tables
anymore
um because again it's just too much
complexity for what we're doing where we
don't actually have
like i feel like we should be able to
simplify this enough
so if we look at what happens for the
you know the cell stepping
what we're computing here right
is
we have the inverse
ray direction
and we just are stepping
like we we go into this cost loop here
and and all we're doing is we just
multiply by that inverse
and then we update
and it seems like that should be pretty
straightforward to do
like basically we just compute two of
these and we see which one is less
you know
um
whichever one is less you than just
that's the step you take
um
so i think that's about it
it's just a really tough decision
do you want to use these tables or don't
you
it feels like you don't
but at the same time it's like tables
are always almost always faster than
anything else so you're gonna pay some
cost
for it
um it's not it ain't gonna be free
you know
um you're gonna have to do this twice
so
you have to do two
you know two subtracts
two multiplies you gotta do the compare
um and the compare has to like then do a
dependent ad
and then probably the most expensive
thing
is you have to then look to see what you
are planning to do
right
um
so do we think do we think that will
actually
we know when we hit the apron
but what we don't know is when we go
outside the z bounds
i agree that frufu is a great variable
name so that's staying in um so i don't
know
i'm really kind of conflicted here i
think maybe we just pull this out
because why should i spend my time
debugging it when i think probably the
correct answer is we would like to get
off of this concept of
using the light stepping tables because
i would like to be able to move to a
stochastic system going forward
that maybe doesn't rely on the sampling
spheres either because i'm just afraid
like i'm definitely afraid
that
we will need to vary
the over time like now that we're able
to hit such a high sampling rate i feel
like we want to use more than a tables
amount of input for it
um
so that's just kind of why i'm sort of
pushed in that direction
so
let me look at grid raycast and see what
i think
so inside grid raycast here's the setup
code right
um
why that code is not in a grid raycast
debugging
thing i don't know
uh but you know what are you gonna do so
when we do our setup here
right
we're loading up one of these raid
directions which we know what it is and
then the walk tables used here so when
you look at how the walk table is used
um it's really just one thing that it
does right
um
it also looks like this was the code
that for stepping maybe before like we
had some code in here
for stepping that we don't use anymore
uh or something like that right like so
so we we previously right we're doing it
where we didn't use uh the grid
and
you know we we computed like a stepping
value uh that stepping value has
probably been removed now right but we
could you know we recompute it
and
yeah like looking at this code right you
can see that it was you know it had to
do a lot more work
because it was trying to do these wide
and all that which probably was pretty
tricky because then it has to load not
wide so it has to move it out of there
right
um
so yeah
so
maybe
uh maybe we just look at what this looks
like
without you know like if we were to
we've also kind of got this cost metric
here
uh which is how many tests we've
performed
i
and
i guess i again don't really know to
what extent we want that to really be a
thing either
um
so if we imagined like how we would be
remaking this routine
i
the exit on the cost
metric would would really probably not
happen probably what would happen is
we'd just do a loop and say look we're
going to check this many cells so every
raycast gets to check you know
six cells or something
and if you happen to terminate early
then fine like if you if you exit if you
leave the z layer
then
you know
fine
right
uh
so you know this this for loop would
probably just be more like a four you
know however many
the cost is so you know rather than the
solution max cost per ray
uh that would actually just be and and
we could do this like you know we could
do this sort of without actually you
know you know without actually removing
the walk table first we could simplify
this part down with the still running
version that we've got right now
um
you know uh not that we can really test
it because it's too buggy but you know
we can sort of say
all right if if we were in a place that
was relatively stable like this
and then i go in here and i say oh yeah
like
instead of this loop what we're gonna do
is like you know
grid
sample
index um
or grid walk index or something right
grid walk
iteration
uh and i just like hard bound that
and i say
look it has to be you know eight eight
grid squares is all you get
no matter what happens
um presumably the lighting doesn't
change much
right like presumably it's fine
um and you know basically looks the same
as before
and then if we just remove the cost
metric entirely so cost metric is gone
um like it just doesn't we just don't
have it
uh so
and all we do instead is check the you
know the spatial
grid node terminator thing
um in theory like we should be able to
just preserve the lighting as it is with
no cost metric because we just don't
really have that anymore right so so
we're fine
and there's you know same lighting
running
in the same way
so
so really the question now is like let's
suppose even with the walk table
involved if we wanted to exit what we
want to do is have an exit criteria that
just says that you're going to exit when
you leave
um
the spatial partition right and the way
that we did that before is we said well
whenever you hit the
[Music]
there's like an apron so that when you
sample that node
you can tell that it's got you know
it it's marked as you've left
right
that does seem sort of good
but
the problem is it doesn't really help us
with our z
part of things
so i don't really know like is that
actually the best way to do it like is
that actually the fastest way to do it
or is the faster way to do it to just
look to see
whether the grid
index
that we were using
you know because it's worth remembering
that now we could just keep two separate
grid indexes as well like it could be
that we can just use two
i don't know
um although you know maybe there's a
good reason not to do that
but
because it's not three-dimensional
anymore it opens up other possibilities
we could make it so that for example we
just say that you know the thing is 16
in one direction so the bottom four bits
or the x or you know stuff like that
so i don't know it could be that this is
still the smartest thing to do
but you need one more check which is to
see whether or not you've left the z
range and like that's broken right now
it's been broken since we simplified it
to not use z-stepping at all
so we know that that's currently wrong
and the question is just what's the best
way to fix it
and i don't know
so
in terms of that
uh yeah i just don't i just don't um
i just don't know
but
at this point we could just say well
okay that's gonna be sort of busted
anyway
let's
let's just focus on welding this code in
there so that we can do it without a
walk table
right
so if we were going to do it without a
walk table then we just do the reverse
process of what we did when we
introduced the walk table which is to
say that we know the starting location
because the starting you know within
within a cell
we know the starting location because
it's you know given to us by the
quadrant index
so
because we have to know the quadrant
index to begin with
uh and i you know i assume it's passing
yeah
we know the quadrant index so we kind of
know
how to
uh
set it up
if we
i you know i'm just trying to think if
we assume that we're just going to take
and
record this as a separate value that we
keep through i'm trying to think of
whether you want to go okay we're going
to raycast and we're stepping through
the grid and we just use one value to
step through the grid and we make
believe that like the origin moved each
time or are we doing something different
where we just store i think we probably
just store the differences and we track
the differences as they go
right um you know basically just the
standard kind of brush resin ham sort of
a
uh
whichever
whichever error would be larger kind of
a thing
right
so we check
we check the grid that we started in
we
like
so it occurs to me that the way that
we're doing this we currently do it
as an actual forward step
that's how the walk table was computed
what i'm wondering is
could we not do it in a way that was
actually a forward check
so we basically just look at moving
to the left or like like we look at
changing x by one or changing y by one
and we just see which one would be a
better choice
exactly like you would do with like a
bresenham algorithm right
and
my only question is that conservative
resin ham like i'm less familiar with
that
i don't really remember ever having
really implemented code like that before
so i'd have to maybe look to see what a
conservative breslin ham algorithm looks
like meaning one that fills all of the
squares that the line passes through and
not just
selects
like one that cannot move diagonally
and that
always picks the one the line actually
went through
i think that's probably what we should
be doing
i think probably the stepping version
we're doing here might just be over
complicated right
if we just tested the center of each
cell to see which one was closer to
the line
that just gives us the answer
which
should just work
you know what i mean
um so it feels like that would
be all you would really need and again
like the reason that i'm worried about
this from a tape you know if you look at
how the table driving works the reason
the table driving is nice is because
you
don't have to actually keep x and y
indices at all
you know what i mean so it definitely
introduces a fair amount of overhead
because
the actual x and y indices that we step
through
um
they now would have to be tracked
so you would have to have
right like a
this sort of a thing
uh whichever
cell you start in you would have this
and then in here you would need a thing
where you uh when when you load
the spatial index that you're in
you would have to
uh you would have to build the grid
index from those two values which costs
you something
and then to know which one that you
you moved to you would have to do
the actual math you'd have to say
look okay i know that the two options
that i have
are
right
um
look like
that
they probably have to be
again like they probably sort of have to
be in
float
like
you would still also have
you'd probably have at least this many
things uh and i'm trying to think of
like you know they could they could
probably be
packed so f cell x and so y could
probably be together
but you'd have this problem of you'd
have to then you'd have to do the
computation
where you actually check to see
whether or not
you are
you know
um
whether or not cell x plus d cell x or
cell y plus d cell y
produces a closer
uh match for your line
and so i'm just a little conflicted
because i'm like can i get that down to
be small enough
that it's going to be as fast as or at
least comparable to the speed at which
you can do it from the table
you know what i'm saying
um so i think that's really the part
that's
that's troubling me
so like how fast could you realistically
make that check
uh because you have to do something like
you've got this stuff
and you
you want to compute the
which one of these is going to be better
so you have some like line equation
right
that we would have to determine what it
actually is
uh for
this ray so it's the you know it's the
it's going to be the ray
uh and you see how far you are from the
ray or something like that right
and you're going to have to compute
f cell x plus fd cell x
f cell y
um and then the opposite of that so
so you're gonna have to compute like
for these two which one of them will be
less error like will it be less error to
go to the this one or that one
now probably
we can see we'll ex we'd expand these
two line equations out this is again
just standardly what you do with breslin
ham right
we would expand these two line equations
out and see what the actual different
factor is between them and then we just
compare those two factors and that's
which direction we step
so i suppose we probably have to write
that out so if you look at the ray
direction
um
the ray is already normalized
so i think i'm just gonna have to write
this out equation wise right so if you
think about
these two in space
you have a
so you have a v3
and that's got you know one v3 is equal
to
this
and i guess you know technically it's a
v2
but we can think of it as a v3 for now
that just we then don't care what
happens to the x component right
um so we have a v3
which is like
you know the current cell location so i
i might just say this is the current
cell p
plus one step
in x
and this is basically just it's either
positive or negative
uh
it's it's either one
entire voxel distance
in the x coordinate positively or
negatively
this is where we would end up right
the y step p
is going to be the same thing but for y
and we only have to consider one of
these because every ray
will either be
one
negative one or zero on each of these
right it's it's it's stepping either
one voxel in that axis forwards
backwards or none
but it can't do anything else because
there's that's all you know every time
you move one grid square we never hop
there's no such thing as a ray that can
hop across
right
so if we take those two
right then the next step would be we
would say okay the
the the difference like the the delta
um between those two
is going you know from the raise origin
is going to be like uh like
you know
these two
both would have a local version
that's whatever they were
minus the array origin
and you can already see that
we could we will be able to simplify
that completely by just pre-subtracting
whatever the curse lp is
pre-subtracting the ray origin from it
right
so we won't have to pay this cost at all
you can already see it ahead of time
because it's just a constant that's
always subtracted so that'll be free
this this part will be free
and once we know where these are
relative to the ray origin then we just
have the question well okay
how far away are these
from
the ray
like which one is closer to the ray
now the simplest answer here
would be
that you know
the like in terms of like thought the
ease the simplest answer for thought
wise right
is the cross product between the ray
direction
uh and one of these
uh so if you just if you just took the
cross product between the two of them
then you know that the length of that
so
you know whatever the length is of this
of the cross product between them
um the length of that is going to be
equal to
uh the length of
the ray direction
which is one
times the length of the local x step p
whatever this is
right
times the sine of the angle between
those two
that's just the definition of the cross
product you know i'm sure we've covered
that on hammond here at some point way
in the past
um
so we know the length of the ray
direction is one
so we know that this
comparison here is just the local x step
whatever that is times the sine of the
angle
which i believe
would literally just leave us with
the the answer we wanted right meaning
the cross product between these two
actually tells us how far away from the
ray you are
right because
this is the hypotenuse of a triangle
and this sign
so you know you're basically just
constructing the leg that projects you
onto the third leg of the triangle which
was that part we removed
right
um now we are only comparing these
so we actually don't need the length we
could just continue do the length
squared which would be much simpler
right
because we're just going to compare two
of them together to see which one is
larger
and further more we know that we don't
care what the distance is in z
because we're only stepping on a 2d grid
so the cross product actually would only
have
um the other components to it right it's
really a perp dot product
which is
much simpler than the full cross product
it's you know
um two by two instead of three by three
right so i think we're literally just
comparing these
um and if you look
at
like the you know do we don't have a
prep dot product we just have perp um
and then inner
but
it's it's the same thing right so if we
wanted to
measure this distance we could just take
perp
of the v2 version of these
and go from there so let's suppose we
did that so first of all like i said we
get one reduction for free which is
these are all technically v2s because
we're not stepping in z we literally
don't care what happens to z at all the
only question is do we ever end up
stepping somewhere
where the z is
where we've left the
cube entirely
and how we track that i just am not sure
like there's gonna have to be something
that checks that that is as fast as we
can make it where we just see if like
the t value probably what we do is at
the beginning we figure out what the t
step is that gets you from where you are
to outside the grid and we just check to
see
whether we have
gone past that t value
maybe
right
i don't really know
um
so we don't care about this part we just
care about this and honestly this can
just not we don't really need to use
this because since we are not in 3d we
can really just use the inner product
um
like so so we just do
the perp
uh dot product
and
the perp dot product between the rate
direction
uh and whichever one of these we're
looking at like so
that will give us the distance
projection
exactly
right
um
like that's just
literally the distance period
you don't really need to square it or
anything right it just it just is
that's just the end of the story
so you get the exact distance from the
ray to the cell center just with
interpret that's it
so what you're looking at is you're
looking at the difference between the
inner perp of each of these
and you're just gonna do something like
this
uh you know what i'm saying
now
you may have to like absolute value this
i have to think about this for a second
because the perp of the ray direction we
don't care whether it's which side of
the ray you're on
so
this is going to have to do in an abs
right like it's it's going to be like
this
um
and we could choose to square it like so
we we do kind of have to square it in
the sense that we have to do something
that removes the sign but it doesn't
actually have to be squared it can just
be abs if we want
uh but fundamentally what we're looking
at is that we're going to look at the
absolute value of the inner product of
the perp right
perp is free it does it's not actually
even an operation it's just going to
change how you're computing the inner
product
uh in this case
so the inner product as we know like if
we look at what one of these actually
equals so the inner product here as we
know is just going to be
um
the components multiplied by each other
and the perp is negative a y ax right so
the perp don't ask me why we
parenthesized that the way we did it's
totally not
correct
perp is just just on the right direction
um
so the ray direction in this case we're
actually doing an inner product not
quite with ray direction but rather with
negative ray direction y ray direction
dot x
right that's the actual
that's the actual
vector that we're using here and then
local step x which you know the one that
we're producing here
like so
right is we're doing an inner product
between those two things
so we actually have
something that looks like this as the
two quantities that we would need uh to
compute in this case
uh and we're gonna compare the absolute
values of those two things
now looking at this it's worth noting
that local step x
i
in this case
is the current cell p plus the d cell x
i don't know if that can be simplified a
little bit by saying well we're just
tracking you know as we step
we're just tracking differences here so
i'm not sure if there's something that
can be done there to simplify that a
little bit
but um if we do this so so i don't know
if that's like what we want i'd have to
think about that a little bit more
but if we look at what these boil down
to uh it's actually very simple right
it's just going to be
the following
so in terms of what we're actually
computing on one side if we wanted to
take the local step x this is the x step
the y step
is the same thing but you know it's
literally just multiplying a different
value
right
so what you can see here is that as we
work this through it gets down to
something very straightforward we're
literally just computing the difference
between these two values
um
sorry comparing these two values
and they do have to be like absolute
valued
you know like so
um
but otherwise they are
trivial to compute it's like two
multiplies two adds kind of a thing
right
so we're just doing two multipliers and
two ads uh and then you know arguably
we've got one more ad in here although
we should probably like actually
substitute these in and see what that
ends up being first
uh because maybe that turns out to
actually just get get taken out of the
equation right so let's
let's try this one more time let's take
a look at um oh and you can see why the
ray origin gets factored out right
so if we were to plug in let's let's do
one step of plugging in here if loop
local step x has the minus ray origin
uh built into it right then what you
would have here is these
these x's
are now gonna be like two
x's right
um so each one of these will have like
array origin x built into it that's
getting subtracted out
and both of these will have a y that's
getting subtracted out right
but what you can see here hopefully is
that that doesn't actually change
depending on which equation you're in
so if i distribute these multiplications
out
all that's going to happen is i'm going
to be left with a subtraction
that is constant between the two things
like
when we multiply this out
we're just gonna get
these two terms again
and then we're gonna have out here
on as a separate thing we're going to
have the ray origin right
multiplied
if that makes sense
right we're going to have the ray origin
x
times i'm sorry the ray direction x
times the ray origin x
um
and the right it's it's it's just it's
it just gets purely factored out because
all it's doing
is
providing a constant
that doesn't actually get that doesn't
actually change
the result there
and again that's exactly what we would
expect
because
really
you would just factor it this way
even if that wasn't true somehow we
would just factor it this way
where we just start with curse lp
right
um
so we kind of know that that's just
possible
uh for us to get rid of we know that
that's possible so we really just can
concern ourselves with a very
straightforward thing even you know
more straightforward than we have before
which is that if we assume that this
whole thing doesn't have to be relative
to the origin anyway because we could
even if we cared we could just
presuppose that it was aligned in that
fashion
right we know that this comes out of the
equation
um so then we get the next question
which is well what happens if we just
don't consider
like
uh
[Music]
what happens with curse lp
right
um
what what happens with curse lp
uh so the reason that the thing changes
with curse lp
is because the d cell x part is
different right it's this part
so
we don't know because that part actually
isn't constant through everything
because some people have d cell added
and some people have d cell y added
you know what i mean
um
i'm not sure that that will become a
completely superfluous value right it
shouldn't be able to be a completely
superfluous value
i wouldn't assume
um
so
i can't think if i'm missing something
there
i don't think i am but if you were to
plug in
for x step like if you were to plug in
cursor right
i feel like there's still one thing that
i'm missing here
so you know let's suppose that i
simplify this
nomenclature slightly so it doesn't take
up as much space just so it's easier for
us to play with a little bit
you know what i mean
um
so if you imagine that you were going to
expand this to uh
so those are some shorter versions so if
we imagine that we were going to expand
these two by saying like okay
we're going to plug in
the curve p plus dx
into
x step p
right so we're gonna we're gonna
we're gonna do that
then
when we multiply that out
we would expect to see
[Music]
this
right i
distribute the der y
uh then distribute the der x
and
you get something looks like that
so negative to white times kirk px plus
der kirpi
um
i mean right like i don't think i'm
missing something here i'm not very good
at math
as anyone who watches the stream knows
very well
um but you know that is
so it's kind of like
it's the
it's
you can see the cross product re-emerge
right like you know the perp dot product
you can see you know it looks like a
cross product now right
so if you look at what happens there
you figure well
we're looking to see
absolute value wise which one of these
is going to be you know different let's
see what happens when we do the same
thing for the y step
if we substitute in curve plea plus der
y
uh what we oops
so
if we substitute in this for y step like
then we have our dot x's
uh and our dot y's
and you
distribute the der y
in both cases like so
um
and the directs
in both cases like so
uh and then if i group the terms the
same way
then it looks like you have sort of that
same term
um
it looks like you have like the same
exact term in both as well
right
so it seems like you're really just
computing this one value unless i messed
up the math which is very likely because
it's me
it seems like
if it wasn't inside an absolute value
you could actually just eliminate it
right
but because it is inside an absolute
value you can't because you don't know
whether this would have caused it to
cross over a line and bounce back
right the absolute value is
is
makes it so you can't extract that
um
right we could fold the other one in
so that there's only one
but one like we could fold in the ray
origin
but we can't eliminate the term entirely
so you have one term here which is this
uh this is like der kerpie or something
right
and durkher p
can be shared between the two
but it can't be eliminated i don't think
right
does that make sense
so i think that we are
you know this would be very
low cost
which is why i'm just thinking to myself
like
surely we can get that as fast or close
to as fast as the table look up
you know it probably is slightly slower
because
again we have to maintain
uh x a few extra values which is
probably not free
you know what i mean
um but but the math is like very simple
right so like like like if we are
correct here we're down to literally
this
um
you know
so
so that part
that's the entirety of like what we
would need to compute
we would need to compute you know
um some multiplies
not very many one two three four five
six
uh
they can be done in parallel so if we
could pack these creatively we could
probably do
uh
like all of these multiplies at the same
time
you know what i mean
uh
so that's pretty easy
and
and one assumes that you can just save
the value of the one you keep so the
so
[Music]
so the duracure p value is the value of
the dot product
with that thing and you know that the
new dot product is this one
so you also don't have to compute this
right you can just keep it
so whatever you compute for these values
in here
before you absolute value it
i think you can also just keep
so this only happens like
at setup
so you compute like this one time
and then from then on you are only
computing these two values and keeping
one of them
i think
right
so i don't know like
if that
makes the difference but if you look at
what's going on here you would think to
yourself like okay that doesn't seem
particularly onerous
we have some setup we literally just do
this and then based on the absolute
value of between those two things we
just that's all we need and then we can
take the step
uh
and preserve the value for the next time
so i can't say that seems that doesn't
seem particularly onerous right like
that doesn't seem particularly bad uh
like that seems pretty cheap
right
um
i mean i don't know
so
that seems pretty
cheap i don't know that like like i
think we should just do that so now you
further you have another thing here
which is that like if you look at what
happens with x step and y step v it's
actually cheaper even still than that
because really
you know
that um
[Music]
you know that the direction that you're
stepping is on the grid
so the dx step by definition doesn't
have a y value
right
like like this can't be in the equation
because dx is strictly a move in x
um
and the same would be true here so like
there'd be no y value
uh
no x no x component of the y step
so you're really just looking at this i
think
right
like you're doing
two multiplies
um and you could roll the d y y value
could have the negative rolled in or
actually dx value could have the
negative rolled in
so the could both be you could do this
wide you do like one multiply one add
and then the extraction is unfortunately
expensive like right
um
you know maybe you just don't get much
by doing it wide but
you know that's it
it's four ops tops then you do have to
do
uh a
absolute value so you've got an and
right um
so
so yeah
uh space naming sorry i'm not sure i
followed you on that one
uh durker p is two times dirk her p plus
dxy at the moment
i do not
follow you there sorry
what
oh yes
you mean this
gotcha
sorry i was looking up here no i agree
uh i just copied the grid index line and
for some reason didn't change the plus
what i meant to say is yes we we are
preserving
we're we've computed the values so all
this is doing is just taking one of
these two
absolutely yes
so i think that's the complete thing um
so i'm going to say let's just go ahead
and do this i mean we have to be able to
make that fast enough that i would think
right and like me i don't know maybe the
branch
maybe like the misprediction of like
what happens with test is just too harsh
and granted there it can all be done
with conditional move or something like
that like there's no need to actually
have a branch but that still creates
like a pipeline bubble right like um
because it has to know what to fetch
but presumably if you put that at the
head end right
if you did that first
um
presumably you'd be okay
wait why does what's what's going on
here
why does my thing
why is that okay there it is never mind
sorry i thought there was a problem the
recording there i want to make sure
there wasn't
uh so i think
i think we're good i think we're good
there what time is it do we have time to
implement this today
it's 2 22. yeah we probably do uh let's
take a quick break
uh i guess
and let's go ahead and when we come back
we'll try implementing this and then we
just won't debug it like we'll type it
in today
and
that'll be it like we won't actually
we'll just get the code structured right
and then next weekend we'll debug it
okay that seems fair
so everyone take a quick break and when
we'll be back in a second
foreign
[Music]
bye
all right
so i think that's it uh and
yeah like
i don't know maybe maybe i oversimplify
that and i'm missing some details there
but that seems about right
like that seems like pretty
straightforward to me
um
i don't know so we'll see we'll see
we'll see when we actually go to to do
this so i'm not as centered as i should
be i feel like i feel like i should be a
little more centered here
i'm not as centered as i should be in
the webcam i mean maybe the the camera
needs to be offset sometimes the puss
play with it
and it gets shifted over
so i probably should shift the camera a
little bit but oh well
yeah like you look at if i look at the
camera here
like basically right i'm this is where i
would normally be so it's like it got
shifted all the way over here so maybe
the real answer maybe the real
answer here is the camera needs to be
rotated slightly
let's just do that
i feel like that's going to be a little
bit better yeah now does that create
some bad like did we get off frame at
all
no
so that's just fine
yeah
who knows
who knows what happened i usually assume
that it probably is the puss the puss
they go nuts at night they run all
around
and you end up in these situations where
they probably bump into the camera i
i have wanted to for a while mount the
cameras on something more permanent like
basically like
the equivalent of like a monitor arm
that i drill into the wall or something
you know what i mean where like the
camera can't be bumped but right now
it's just on a tripod and the pus could
i mean the puss could knock it the whole
way over if they wanted to
it's just not that stable and so at some
point it probably would be a good idea
to like figure out how to like get that
more
more aligned uh permanently like it's
just like it won't now move because it's
you know
arc welded into place
um
but anyway
so
let's take a look
um
i don't know
i'm a little nervous about
this
i don't know why we still have that in
there we don't have our own
absolute value i assume that gets in
line properly but
i don't know we'll find out
uh
so if we've have it all
if we look at what we need to do here
for setup the primary thing that we're
missing at the moment is like obviously
the kirpy is the ray origin minus the
starting cell
our initial problem is we don't have
the starting cell really
um i don't think maybe we do
but i don't think so so like if you look
at what we get passed down it's like
this initial grid index thing this is
kind of a holdover from the way this
code used to work so i think what we
more want to do is stop passing these
two things
and start passing
uh actual like position values that we
can then use
so
i
yeah it would be
looking in full cast which is now these
are rapidly collapsing where we don't
really probably need full cast anymore
so there's that
um
but
if we look at full cast you can see like
in full cast it gets past these values
which it then like slaps down like it's
calling things like
get quadrant for that don't actually
need to happen so so basically like what
i could do here
is
take this code and move it into like
like i could basically just finally
collapse these routines entirely because
there really is no reason you can see
here that like grid raycast is just a
thing that happens at the end of this
code so these routines don't need to be
separate anymore and
like they were separate because we used
to just call grid
grid raycast multiple times and now we
just don't even do that anymore
so at the very least we could say well
quadrant index let's that's the easiest
thing to replace um quadrant index
literally
it could just be
uh sent down as part of the remainder
uh thing the remainder is the uh
the atlas step part like again this is
all kind of stupid
but uh just trying to figure out like
the
the slow movement of this
into the other system so uh we just need
to know like where this thing is inside
the outer cell right that's all we're
really looking to
determine so the remainder would really
be that
i it tells us exactly
where we are
and
i pretty sure
that it just doesn't get used anywhere
right like yeah so you know if we wanted
to uh this whole situation
could just be placed into the
grid raycast code as a start like it's
not
everything but it's a start so if we
take remainder z and the quadrant index
and i put drop those in here
so you know we've got something like
uh this happening
and remainder
uh
which gets is atlas index minus two 2
half atlas index
that nonsense
uh if we start passing a remainder down
that's just like the simplest
first step i can take that that's all
i'm looking for here is like the
simplest first step i can take
so we pass remainder down
um and now we have the information we
need to actually do without changing
anything we can do our stepping
um so that's good
and
this part of the code that we've
sketched out i'm just going to if zero
out because this is well we're just
starting here
and so then now instead of passing
quadrant index we're just going to pass
the remainder
um and compute quadrant index inside no
there we go
uh
so the code shouldn't change
i don't think
uh
it's it's now like just gonna run
exactly as it did before but the only
difference is that we now yeah i mean
the only difference is that we have
um
you know why that's marked inline
probably very old school yeah
this is still running amusingly
and the lighting still works just fine
right which is what you would expect
so
we can then look more carefully at this
and say well okay with the remainder now
we could start doing this other stepping
and what i'm going to do is before like
tearing the old code out i want to be
able to run them both together because
if i can run them both together then i
can more easily debug like the new one
right
which seems like strictly a plus
so what i want to do is i want to get
um that so you know
this
this grid ray cast past the remainder i
want to get the values we were using for
compute walk table which i then
you know i hope to remove you can see
that the starting location
um
relative to the ray index
or or relative to a cell i should say
um
is going to be something like this
it's the cell dimension you know with
the remainder factored in
uh
from the divide right something like
this
now i don't know that we actually need
to quite do that because in theory we
know the starting cell i think
because we have
like
i i guess we could just call it with the
atlas index
and we have this right so you know what
now i think about it i wonder if we can
just get rid of
we probably just don't need that and we
will be able to get rid of quadratus
once the other code doesn't use it but
it has to stay in there for now
if we have initial grid index
presumably you have to be able to back
that out to get an atlas location
because if you couldn't
how are we sampling so that must be
something that is knowable
um
let's take a look inside the spatial
partition stuff here which i believe is
is this code here so like
flat index from
is the code that i think is being used
here to index into this voxel
i think
and it looks like this does the opposite
right so again we we really wouldn't
want to be doing this
normally because it's too expensive oh
and you can see us doing it right here
right so you wouldn't really want to be
doing this uh
we'll want to fix this so that we don't
actually do this eventually but for now
because we want to run these in parallel
and don't want to rip out the other code
we can just recover one from the other
and it's not per ray it's per cell so we
wouldn't really even notice but
this is definitely to do remove this
way of computing the local
ray origin right
so again our entire goal is to compute
dirkher p we know the direction x and
direction y always because that's just
the ray direction right and the ray
direction uh we have ray origin single
and the ray direction is going to be
coming from uh this when we select this
piece out so it's ray d single this
right here
so in order to set up our dir curve p
this value which is for stepping um
maybe i'll call that stepping kirby or
something
right
we know that when we set up the array
index before we enter the loop uh that
value has to have the ray d singles x
value
and the ray d singles y value which we
which come out of these two
times kirby and cur x so those are the
two values that we actually need
and
to compute those two values what we said
is they have to be the ray origin that
the cell center
of the starting cell
minus the ray origin
now we know the ray origin it's constant
forever because
until we exit this routine we don't move
the casting location
so this ray origin piece this ray origin
single
is the value we actually need uh for
that right
but we additionally need um
for that curve p right
so the ray origin singles x y is going
to get subtracted away from the cell
center
x y
and it's that cell center
that we don't know
you know what i'm saying
so we need this so we need like stepping
uh
you know
initial p
whatever that initial stepping value is
that's the thing that we actually needed
to compute we have part of it we don't
have the other part of it and that is uh
the the part we're computing
here
right
so we don't really need get cell bounds
we just need get cell center
uh but
i mean
you know probably we don't care because
like i said
right now we're just reverse engineering
this for testing purposes anyway
so i would assume
that
you know this is fine
so
get cell bounds
uh
it looks like we could have just called
instead get cell center p which is fine
uh and that gives us
the i think that gives us what we want
which is cell center
um
again we don't care about the z value
it's right it's relevant
oops
now maybe i shouldn't do it that way
maybe i'll since we're doing x y's here
maybe we'll make it clearer it's like
those are the xy's
so
uh that's the entirety of the setup code
i think
which is to say that this this stepping
bit here before we enter the walk
iteration it's just that piece of code
goes there
we then have the walk code which is this
code
in the loop
and in here
uh
this would just be at the end this would
be how we would decide to move so
previously we were doing this move which
is you know looking up the
the walk table by you know
by looking up the walk table to get what
cell you move to next
and here we would instead be taking
uh that dirk her p-value which we step
up here we change it to stepping her p
um
but so that
i'm stepping her p-value
uh the ray direction is just called raid
or single right i think
um
what's this
uh
okay
so
this code here
[Music]
instead of durr
is or single
and the dx and the dy are how far apart
these are so this is just like voxel dim
x and y
right
but the problem that we have
and so why we need to introduce a
separate value here is we don't know
what direction we're stepping in
because we would need to know the sign
of the value first
so because the ray we only are
considering one kind of step we don't
look at like left and right or up and
down we only look at if the ray is going
leftward we look at stepping left if the
ray is going upward we look at stepping
up right
um
we don't look at down if the ray is
stepping up and we don't look at right
if the array is stepping left
so we really have to compute here not
compute here but store at the outset
um stepping delta
x or whatever and stepping
delta y
which are going to be like we don't have
to compute this every time they're just
going to be like a fixed value
like so
um
that we add because it doesn't change
the amount that you step in x or y you
always step by one whole grid square so
these are computed a priori based on the
ray direction once it is known and for
each step along the grid we don't need
to like recompute that so it's literally
just this
and then these dxdy values are just the
sign
they're just going to be like the sign
of the ray direction
so whatever
whatever the sign is of the
corresponding ray direction and i don't
actually know
um
[Music]
i think we can just call
this right here right so
the sine of is all we really need here
so it's it's really like sine of the
other one
it's times the sine of of whatever the
ray d single is or the ray
of the opposite one so you know in the y
step case it's it's the y so we have the
radius singles x times the sine of the y
times however big the voxel is in that
direction
which is just cell dim
right
uh and i think that's it
all we need to know now is oh this is
stepping kirkp here
uh all we need to know now
is how far you would move in each case
and that's the end of
it again really simple code here right
if you look at it you know who knows if
we did it right we might have bugs
but in terms of conceptually what
actually had to happen there it's pretty
simple and there's not a whole lot of
code
right there's not a whole lot of code
involved so that seems to uh you know
that seems to bode well
uh for for what we're looking at here
so
walk table entry oops walk table entry
um so the s16s that we use here for our
d grid
uh which could just be s32s in this case
because we don't care about how big they
are now since they're just going to be
like local they're not stored in a table
and this will hopefully go away
um
so at this point those values are just
going to be whatever the actual span is
we know this from compute walk table
right like whatever the actual span is
it's step best dim right that step value
and so
uh
we need that i suppose the problem we
get there is it has to also be it has to
correspond to the sign correctly again
right
so that does
it is a little bit annoying
um
like it's not as free as we would like
it to be
right so we have the the
we have the voxel dimension
like the the spatial grid
and
i don't know
the voxel dim for the spatial grid
uh is
cell count right
so the cell count x is how much you
would move in x and the cell count y
times the cell count x is how much you
would move um
for a d step in y
and
those two would both be
you just need to negate them
um
like we can just
these are you know just basic values
and the problem is here you've got this
sort of sign you know you again have to
do this this sign check which seems bad
um
the the sign of one doesn't seem so bad
but this one kind of does
so these have to be selected based on
which direction the ray goes
um
which is which kind of sucks
right because it's a float check
you've gotta you gotta like send the
you've gotta send the sign bit over you
know what i mean
uh which which
is not good right
so you have this nasty problem of now
you're doing this which is ray d single
x
if it's less than zero then it's d grid
index x base otherwise it's the grid
index
uh
x base without the minus right that just
is crappy
um there's really no two ways about it
that's not good
i don't think
so we probably need to figure out a
better way to do that stepping
like it might almost be better to like
do it in the simdi registers and then
just move the value out
just one time to do the lookup or
something
it just that just seems bad
to me
you know what i mean
um
that just seems
that seems not
good
is grid index and sixteen is that the
price yeah it is okay
fine i don't care they can be a 16 if
you want
we'll probably change that eventually
but
so okay
oh
whoops
um okay so yeah uh at this point now we
have the problem of we can't actually
run both of these codes at the same time
because and actually add to the real
value so i probably need to introduce a
synthetic value here that we're checking
right um because the i can't add to the
grid index twice that would totally that
would totally break um
so we probably want a grid index that's
like our check grid index here
um
[Music]
that now we can go and see if this
produces similar results at all to the
other one that we had you know what i
mean
uh and so now if we run it it should
have the same behavior as before because
the all the lighting should still be
running through the same path as it was
previously
there shouldn't be any difference right
and so if you if you wait until that
annoying part of the bug goes away
um
then then we're fine right and it should
just be the same as it was which it does
appear to be right
uh and then if i go and i say let's
switch to the debug version
of the builds
and we build um
i would go ahead now and say we should
be able to
set a breakpoint and look at these step
differences
um to see
what we end up with right
so like at this point in the code
uh we have a check grid index
and a grid index
um and we should be able to now like
start to debug
those
you know what i mean um
you notice realized that what everything
i just said to you was a total lie
um
i have to remember to update remedy by
the way that bug got fixed where it
doesn't stop
the executable and i just forgot to
update we should update
so we hit that occasionally
um
i just realized that's totally wrong
what i said before the the this d grid
index x it's the other way around so
the y is is the one that steps by x and
the x steps by one i don't know why i
did a z step there for some reason
that's just you know addled brain
um
so let's try that one more time
i
and i don't know if i probably still
have to set the breakpoint i think i may
have removed it
but i still want that breakpoint
in the lighting code
please
so let's
go back and reset it so that i can look
at those two together
and
look at the differences between the grid
indexes
so like same piece of code
and i just wanted to look at these so
we're looking at the difference between
check grid index and grid index
um
that should this looks off
also
that's bad but hey look they're pretty
similar
they're actually exactly the same
so let's find out if this turns out to
be roughly correct most of the time
let's see how often we hit an assert
designed to catch them
diverging so if i go here and say assert
grid index equals check grid index
like how often does that hit all the
time a little bit of the time sometimes
etc
uh and i don't know so we're gonna find
out how often that assert hits
i definitely have to go let's just
update remedy while we're here uh
because we we do need that
uh to be patched
so hold on one second
i will
grab the new
version
um because like
that was causing us a huge amount of
problems and there's no real
need to keep suffering through that
so let's go ahead and pull down
an itch io
where
is
remedy no
remedy
is somewhere there it is
so i will download the latest version
which is 364
and i will save that to the drive
i will then take that said drive
and
plug it in
to
w
uh
apps
it's in here right yeah remedy bg
so i will go ahead and just
copy this
over
and i think that should do it
so that should be all we need to fix
that problem which is good hopefully
um
and
back we go
so
i open this up i run it
and i just look to see whether uh this
hits often or or not often
you know what i mean
and furthermore are they off by like one
step or are they off by like a lot steps
you know and and i don't know
so that looks pretty bad
i'm not sure what that would imply
exactly
um
it's just okay so it just picked
differently
in this case i guess
so honestly
that's a really hard one to call i don't
even know if that means that anything is
wrong here that could just be when the
two ways of checking diverge which might
be fine also the other one is
potentially buggy
so it's like
um
so i would say i'm just curious like
we'll save this for next weekend i think
in general but i'm curious to know like
what happens if we just swap these two
you know
so we go like all right
um grid index is now updated by our
weird one
um
[Music]
and and good luck
uh
you know what happens how bad is it how
far off is our new routine from our old
routine is it an absolute disaster
slight disaster of course i guess this
doesn't really tell us much because
um
we're still running in in slow mode so
we're not going to see like a huge
amount of anything really happening
there but
all right so now we're like not really
using the walk table except to compute t
terminate which is something we will
have to address later
um
but you know now we're in theory
operating without that actual uh piece
of the code like without the walk table
being necessary to do the spatial uh
lookups right
um and so we can sort of see what
happens with that i don't know that we
would expect much difference uh but it
is just one nice step forward right
and honestly
are we still are we still using
instant update
we are
so that was the bug
the lighting tables actually are a bug
it doesn't mean we don't have another
bug but it does look like
that particular bug gets fixed by
getting rid of the walk table
right
so our walk table was messed up
as we suspected and i do think i made
the right call because i think this is
simple enough that we should be pursuing
this one because it will simplify our
lives
right
so t terminate
is still a problem because we don't
actually have a way to update to
terminate at the moment
um and
i guess
the only reason that we care about
t-terminate at all
t terminate was was
there for only one reason
uh
and
like
t terminate was only there so that when
you
run out of time to sample something like
you you've gone some distance and you
haven't hit anything uh where do you
actually sample the lighting from at
that point and one answer is you don't
sample it at all but the way we chose to
do it was look if you check that far
away from where you are right now uh
eventually what you should just do is
sample the light that's at that place
and consider you getting the same light
uh
convected forward to you right
now you know we were doing that because
it was expensive to do something else
it's possible that we just should
consider that ray to have not hit
anything and don't actually run the rest
of the routine
um
you know that's possible
if we look at what happens with t
terminate for example
here i
it's
it's it's what is used right like
we we use
so probe sample p single
we use what ends up being the
uh
you know
anyway uh i had a thought there but i'm
gonna not i'm not gonna think that
particular thought so anyway if you look
at what happens here when we look at uh
updating probe p sample signal right
when we when we go through here and we
do like right here you can see us
actually doing the raycast test
excuse me
we end up in a path that's like did we
hit anything
in the path where we say like did we hit
anything
we update where we're going to sample
uh using this code so it's it's this
right pro probe sample piece single
excuse me
um
so
the question is
when we would normally fall out of this
loop
what we used to do is just say well
whatever the termination
location is for this thing
so all we really need is some way of
ensuring that we know
what where we would sample from
and we kind of know that like we could
just consider that location to be
wherever the cell center currently is
which we sort of know
i mean we don't really know we'd have to
keep updating it right
so it's like
also when this terminates probe piece
single would not be
yeah so i can see why this this wouldn't
quite work the same way but yeah you
could just say look probe sample p
single
what if it just never gets updated like
what if we just don't do that what if we
just don't sample
we don't use that convection process
is that just better if we don't do that
um
you know probably not but
so i guess what i would say here is well
you know we know
we know what grid cell we're in and we
could just sample from that grid cell i
guess
i don't i don't have a good i i don't
have a good idea here right but if if
you end up on a terminator
node
so you know
something like this i suppose
if we've gone too far or we hit the the
end then we need to have some value that
we like can step forward to
you know what i mean
and the question is where should that be
and you know maybe the answer is we
should just unpack
the ray index like we should just get
wherever we are in the thing
and unpack that or maybe the answer is
we track a t value forward as we step
i don't know
how smart that is though
i mean it's not that hard
it's not that hard because you know a
priori
how much each t-step is
so you know if you looked at t terminate
here
it's the same value either way like like
when you take a step forward
you know how far
in t the ray has to go
to move to the next cell over
because you know how far
you know the dot product of this of the
cell volume
with that t value
so you know i i can't say it's like my
favorite thing in the world but you
literally could just have one more of
these
that's like
this like that and it's just it sucks
because you've got too many things that
are like updating at that point
like like there's just too many
values here and it seems like you
probably would rather have less of those
um but that's really all you would need
so if you assumed that you took t
terminate and you said well we're going
to start out by saying
where is the t value along the ray for
this cell
yeah
so you basically say like t terminate
initial
uh and you know what that is it's it's
just the inner product
uh of the cell center
minus the ray origin
um
times the ray direction
sorry ray d single
so in other words to step
to step to the current center
where i we're going to step like
forwards or backwards it might actually
be backwards if we're pointing in the
wrong direction we step backwards in t
um
to hit that
um and i guess we don't even need to
talk about it as t-turning initial i
guess that's just t-terminate right it's
literally just this it's t terminate
um
and and and that's just that's this is
just it's just this value
it's it's that value spammed
um if we want this to be wide which
apparently we do
uh then it's just that value spammed
like like so i don't know if we have one
that that lofts up the entire thing
um
yeah it's just yeah if you just pass one
so like you know it's it's literally t
terminate would just start out
at whatever that value is
um i think that's just free
did i mess something up there
syntax error semicolon oh sorry about
that
um so we really just need to know the
two inner products with the ray
direction um for stepping the other way
right
so the amount of change the distance
along the ray you go in each
case
is
pre-computable
so the t-terminate step it's always
forward
um and it's always going to be the inner
product
uh of
whatever the ray direction is
times this at a particular step now it's
not really even the inner product
because you don't actually have to do
the entire thing right it's literally
always going to be zero everywhere
except for the one type of step you're
taking
so when you talk about like the cell
dimension if you're talking about how
far do we go along the ray if we want to
take one cell dimension x step well the
answer is you're just going to take
that times that component of the ray
direction
like like that's it because all the rest
of the of the values for self that
you're stepping zero in the other
directions
right so i believe it's literally just
those two values the like the ray d
single
uh in this case is is just
um
you you don't have to compute a full dot
product because you know that the cell
the cell dim
is
you're only stepping along one axis of
the cell dim the other ones are going to
be zero so it's always just going to be
that you know minor change that's all
that happens you don't have to do
anything else to compute
uh the actual value
so
[Music]
yeah
uh so anyway when you do t terminate uh
it's it's just gonna do a step and we
need those to be things we can add
together
so i don't actually know what the
because this wants to be an f-32
um i don't know that that you really
actually want to bother with keeping it
as an f324x but for now i'll just do
that because that's what
it apparently wants so that's fine um
these
these values just have to be um expanded
so when we when we c initially compute
uh what these two terminates are we need
to wrap them
so that they're replicated for wide so
that they flow through the four wide
path right
but that's it
um
whoopty do we now computed t terminate
and
so now we can also do the same check
that we were going to check before which
to see whether or not it actually seems
like it lines up
with the correct values
and i don't know
you know it's not going to be the same
anyway but either way i would say look
if we just turn off this now
um so t terminate is only being updated
by us
i want to say that will probably still
work maybe
um but of course it's hard to know
because our lighting still has the other
bug in it so you know who knows but i
want to say that you wouldn't see any
real difference in here
at that point but you know maybe there's
other problems i'm not sure
so
so i want to say and i'm just going to
make this command decision because hey
it's the end of the stream i say we just
pull out the walk tables they're
completely gone now
um
and and we call it a day so walk table
gone
compute walk table is gone
i'm just getting rid of all of it
and it's it's considered
it's considered un unacceptable to have
walk tables now because we made that so
simple that presumably
it just doesn't matter anymore
so i'm removing 100
of all like the compute walk table stuff
all that's just gone
um the sample direction table is still
there at the moment
um
but
where does that get copied should that
get copied
oh it looks like that push array does
the copy i guess
no it doesn't so when does that get
copied did i do we copy that in the walk
map version if so we should probably get
rid of that in fact
uh
entirely like we should also just get
rid of the sample direction table thing
and just use it instead of you know use
the actual baked one
so in the inl like this thing sample
direction table
and and now it's just a v3
right
it doesn't have any other
intervening data
so the sample direction table
now is just a static piece of data we
don't allocate anything to store it or
any of that sort of nonsense
so i think that's the end of that
right
okay
so now in theory we're running
completely without walk tables now um
i don't know how the profile's doing but
it seems like it's roughly where it was
so i think that's fine
we could probably actually do some
optimization work at some point
because now we've simplified things
quite a bit there's probably a lot of
craft we can pull out of here
um but anyway we're still at 30 frames a
second even with the debug system
running in no particular we even have
like
light validation is still turned on
there's a asserts are turned on
all of that's still turned on and we're
still running at 30 frames a second
with the full global illumination
running
so i would call that a pretty reasonable
victory
um the lighting looks awesome
so i think we're down to now just one
bug which is our light leak that like
over overbrighting weird nonsense that's
happening
um it's very strange right
you can see it gets that weird like
like
why does that movement
you know
change the total brightness of the those
lights like it's very strange so we have
one more really pretty serious bug uh
you know unless it's a confluence of
bugs maybe there's more than one bug
we have one pretty serious one so we've
got to go take care of that but
otherwise it's looking really cool like
love the look of it it's running really
quickly
so that's great and we removed the walk
tables which means we could add entropy
back in if we wanted to for free
um
so basically we're down to just one
one more and that's what we'll do next
weekend but at least we got rid of the
walk tables now as well
um so we could also that means get rid
of this entire table in the pre-compute
that that entire thing could go away as
well and we could just use like white
noise entropy or something that's you
know low cost and try that out just to
see what happens if we do that um
and you know we we might want to do that
uh as a thing that allows the lighting
to be scalable better more scalable
right
um
and and perhaps have less artifacts due
to directional issues
but
overall i'd say really looks really good
and remember that's without smoothing so
there's no temp this is that's 100
percent temporal and testing free it's
recomputing the entire lighting for the
entire system on every frame and so
we're in really good shape if we can
just go eliminate whatever that last
lightly energy leak bug is
um
we would get lighting that looks like
this and it's instantly updated that
there's no temporal smoothing applied to
that at all
so that's great like that's really good
um
[Music]
because that means it would update
instantly to lighting changes right
there'd be no there's no
lag
on the lighting
right which i think is pretty cool
uh so you know um i think we're in
really good shape
but it's you know that that
that energy bleed is gonna be hard to
track down those are
those are kind of really tough uh sorts
of bugs so you know
unfortunately that's that's not gonna be
an easy one to find but i'm i'd say
that's that's it for today that was
pretty good work i think i'm happy with
that
um
i think we can
yeah i think we'll be able to simplify
the lighting system even more now
because we just we just keep removing
pieces of it and it gets better right so
that's really good place to be
uh we can probably simplify some of how
these loops work and just get stuff down
to a more minimal state and as we do
that you know it also gets easier to
find the bugs in it
we're still spending a lot of time doing
the octahedral map down sampling that's
if i remember correctly still a really
big problem um
so there's that
but have not having to have the lighting
uh
not having to have that
the walk tables and the precomputed
stuff is just really nice
so i think that's probably very good
like we're probably in really good shape
here is what i would say
um but yeah like the diffuse waiting
stuff is still really expensive like so
i want to say that probably the ray
casting
is is now like you know fairly expensive
because we're doing a ton of it like we
have really we're you know we're doing
again no temporal smoothing so we're
doing a ton of raycasting
lots of rays
per octahedral map sample
but
i don't know
i don't think we separately at the
moment break out how much time is spent
in smoothing out the
in smoothing out those maps so i don't
actually know like as you can see all
the time is spent in the lighting like
the entire game is spent
all the cpu time is in lighting which is
what you expect but i don't even know
how much of that is actually raycasting
you know what i mean
like if we were to go into
uh the raycaster
and we were to change the
you know the raycast to be operating on
way less rays so like we just said oh
yeah like actually
um
you're only going to cast like one ray
instead
um
i don't actually know how much of a
speed improvement that gets us like
maybe a ton maybe not i don't really
know
um
so
yeah like compute light propagation work
like
how much does that go down by like
through three so that's that's around
three
30 million cycles is that right comma
comma 30 million cycles
and so now it's
400 million cycles
so it's it's a little over 10x
uh the cost
i could i could probably do it exactly
by just saying like okay we remove the
raycast
um
and it's around what is that eight
million cycles
so i guess it is mostly in the right
cast now that's actually good so i guess
we're not somehow we made it is that
really true
i thought it cost more than that i don't
know that i trust those timings i wonder
if maybe like actually
it was able to optimize some of that out
of the smoothing i don't know so i'm not
sure about i'm not sure how i feel about
those timings take that with a grain of
salt
um
but
anyway point being
uh
at 30 frames a second
we
would expect here that we could do a
fair bit we can also change this
raise per texel
value at the moment
um it's doing 16
right and if we did half that
we would expect to still probably be
able to have okay lighting if we added
some temporal smoothing and we'd get a
pretty big speed up so
oh wait not times not that's not what i
wanted
um so we would expect in general to
[Music]
um
to probably be able to have a favor oh
wow that's cool
yeah that the bug is so interesting like
it clearly has something to do with
direction as well that's really
interesting
must just be some stupid bug
like yeah
um but anyway
you can see here that like the lighting
at at half the samples is basically the
same it's going to be darker because
obviously
we're dividing by half but other than
that you know you just don't divide by
half if you if you actually just set
this value here to something else
um
so like this rayweight value right if i
said divide by two and oh by the way
also multiply the output by two
um
the bugs are so interesting aren't they
i can't wait till we find out what this
is it's going to be very it's going to
be very interesting because how are we
getting those like they're so structured
they're so structured like
it's going to be very interesting to
find out what that power leak is from
very interesting
it must be that like
the direction you're casting like
erroneously writes into like
i
like like i don't there's some kind of
weird like the direction
i wish i could think of like what that
would be what's that gonna
be i bet we should we should kind of be
able to figure it out i just for some
reason i just can't quite
yeah i don't know i can't quite figure
out what that's going to be but point
being i think the lighting would still
work just fine with less samples and we
already know that with half the samples
we'd be running at 60 frames a second
even with all the debug code in place
right
um with the debug code not in place
i don't even know like
if we turned off
light asserts or if we
cause actually i suppose at the moment
we actually do want those off because
we're not really doing anything with
that
at the moment um
if we turned off those asserts and we
also turned off the other internal
asserts i don't actually know how fast
we are but
probably pretty fast yeah i mean we
might actually be with everything turned
off i'm not sure we might actually be 16
60 frames a second
just even with even with 16 samples
per texel which is nuts
so
hey computers very fast and this is on
an old computer
which is kind of nuts
and it's all on the cpu so
computers man
you would think if you run a web program
you would think
uh that
it would be
that computers are super slow
but when you actually run code that does
a lot of work
uh it's actually nuts because you look
and computers are actually incredibly
fast like the amount of work we're
asking it to do is insane
you know
so
um so you know
not quite there 24 milliseconds frame we
need to be at 16 milliseconds frame so
who knows you know maybe we need less
samples to get there maybe that's too
expensive but who knows
uh we got a long ways to go before we
determine stuff like that um so but
yeah so really weird just whatever that
last bug it's going to be very
interesting to see
what it is
but all right that's it for today
yeah if if you if you use like a web
browser you'd think that computers are
really slow right
um
but
actually
computers are incredibly fast it's just
the programs that people write are
incredibly slow for no real reason
because you know
this is just kind of a tremendous amount
of work we're asking this thing to do
and it just eats it for breakfast it's
kind of nuts right
so
um
uh yes jira 33 uh that's exactly correct
the gpu shaders basically just sample a
voxel
um
it's a little more complicated than that
because the thing that is actually
getting sent down is an octahedral map
so it's not the same as a voxel sample
per se
but it is basically a voxel
interpolation like at each
at each node in the voxel
at each node in the 3d grid there's an
octahedral map for the inbound light at
that location
and
uh
that would be
the
like the gpu is having to interpolate
between
eight samples of octahedral maps so it's
you could think of it as the gpu samples
an octahedral map at each of the
corner like at each of the corners of
that cube that it's in
and then it interpolates the results
if that makes sense
i don't know if that makes any sense to
you but
that's what it's doing
and so the cpu does all the lighting
these the lighting could be moved
uh to
to the gpu
um
and
we
might do that someday
but i think it's better to do it on the
cpu for now because it was a very
complicated process to figure out how we
were going to do it
and if it was on the gpu gpu programming
is just really
sucks it's hard to debug
um
it's a lot more finicky right so doing
it on the cpu seems good and then if
later you want to drop it to the gpu
as long as you've been programming it in
such a way as it's expected to be
parallelized like that to a certain
extent it's probably not that bad
um but another way to look at it is cpus
are starting to have a lot of cores now
and what are you going to use those
cores for right in a game like handmade
hero there's not a lot of other stuff
going on so having it do the lighting
means there's more
horsepower on the cpu on the gpu to do
other things which maybe we just means
you know you run at a higher resolution
or whatever so i don't actually know
like whether you you know it depends on
the game some games
may want the lighting to run in one
place some one right in another the fact
that nvidia cards are now adding ray
tracing means that at the limit you know
handmade hero 2030
you probably want to run this on the gpu
because it's got ray tracing
acceleration right so it kind of becomes
a no-brainer at that point
but in the interim
it's just it's probably hard to say
uh it is not a spherical harmonics
encoding
it's literally an octahedral map so it
is a
encoding of
if you imagined a sphere
and you broke the sphere up into eight
octants
and then you stored texels at a certain
resolution
that actually
like
that are just what the inbound light is
at those positions on the sphere
so spherical harmonics is very different
spherical harmonics is when you store a
set of coefficients
and the coefficients
are
basically they multiply basis functions
that are three-dimensional lighting
shapes
that you then compose to determine
usually compose and then take the dot
product with
some direction to determine what the
light is in that direction they're very
very different right
um it's it's it's equivalent to the
difference like an octahedral map is
just storing the lighting
directly like how much light is coming
in
from each direction
so it's a lot like
octahedral maps are like an image
and spherical harmonics are like the fft
of that image kind of a thing right
it's that sort of a
difference
one is a series of coefficients on basis
functions that affect the whole thing
and the other is like
individual light values coming in in a
different textile so octahedral maps are
like way easier to understand than
spherical harmonics
visually
because human beings are not really used
to thinking of things as additions of
like lobes
right like you don't tend to think of
things as like oh okay
the inbound light is like
this shape plus negative of that shape
plus positive of this shape or whatever
right it's not how you think of things
it's way easier to think of like oh the
incoming light is like these color
values like in that direction it's this
value and in that is this value so an
octahedral map's like much easier to
understand
than cervical harmonics it might not be
as
good to compute with in certain
situations spherical harmonics may be
way more efficient
but in terms of like what you would
intuit
an octahedral map is fairly
straightforward to understand where
spherical harmonics are much more
difficult
to just intuitively think about what's
happening
like if you saw it
like looking at the three numbers of
circle harmonics would be impossible
like you'd just be like
okay i see three numbers i have no idea
like
what the actual lighting looks like
i mean you might have a vague sense of
like okay the first one is the average
light that's inbound so that's pretty
easy but then it's like okay that one's
sort of telling me like roughly how much
light comes from that side
versus that side it's like the
sightedness of the lighting right so you
could learn to like interpret the values
you know
um
[Music]
they do mean something but it's just not
very directly vis translatable to you
the first two coefficients three two or
three spherical hormone expressions are
probably not that hard to understand but
as you start getting down into lower
ones it's like okay
yeah i know what they are but
intuitively like developing a sense for
looking at eight spherical harmonics
numbers
what does that translate into in terms
of lighting is pretty freaking hard i
would argue right
now i don't work with filler harmonics
very often so maybe that's just because
i don't work with them enough maybe if
you work with them enough you would but
i really do feel like yeah octahedral
maps much easier to understand
intuitively then spherical harmonics
which are much harder because you have
to kind of reconstruct in your head
what's going on every time
so
all right folks that's it for today
um i will be back here next weekend when
we will when we will have to track down
our final bug i mean there's probably
other bugs in here but the final main
one like the one we can see
right
um so next weekend we will track down
the final bug we can see and then it's
probably time to just say okay that that
accomplished what we wanted like our
goal was to simplify the lighting down
to the point where we were happy with
like it and it was fine uh and i think
that is probably it
uh so we can go on to the next
simplification pass
which was not on lighting that would
just be simplifying the uh spatial stuff
to be only
one
you know one z sheet
i so
yeah like getting there
getting there running very efficiently
right now looks great
um
[Music]
so yeah not a lot of complaints there's
definitely you know is it a good engine
i mean not compared to what would happen
if i was actually concentrating on it
right like
at such a small time investment
in it and being so sporadic there's a
lot of things that are just like all
right that's not as good as it should be
for sure but you know in terms of the
final look of things it does look really
good
and
it does seem to play very well
so
you know i'm i'm optimistic that there's
nothing particularly
bad about the engine that would prevent
it from being you know interested right
so
uh no valbus z is
z is just
really makes things much more
complicated
like
you know you you could add z into the
raycaster again by just adding one more
check for movement in z
but then instead of one test value and a
cmov you now have
like three test
checks
that have to then
factor into multiple c cmobs or
something or you just use an actual
three-state if
picking between two options is a lot
easier than picking between three
options is i guess what i would say
um
so maybe it's fine if you add z in
or maybe the code just keeps getting
slower as the cpu struggles with that
like multiple chain c move
like
i don't know so so i i
i don't know
um
so so maybe it's fine
and maybe you said that in but the real
cost
is not that anyway like that's the thing
that makes the loop nastier but you
could do it and it's just a chain of
cmos right it's just like extra
the real cost is having multiple z
samples because it just multiplied you
know a cubic volume of samples is just
way more samples than a 2d volume of
samples right
and so really the thing that makes the
lighting so much easier in 2d than in 3d
is that you just don't have to compute
times z
instead of having to do a stack of eight
things you do a stack of two things
that's four times faster
right
for nothing like it's just a free 4x
faster so when you add z back in it just
becomes a lot more expensive there's
really no two ways about it right it's
just a higher multiple for anything
volumetric like that
so i think that's mostly it
so adding z back in
not hard
slows down the raycast a little bit but
then the real killer by far real killer
by far
uh
is is obviously just you know
the um
the the extra z sheets just way too many
samples it's way too many voxel cells
so
all right
that's it everybody
i will i guess i should look to see it's
like john streaming or anything it
doesn't look like it
um but anyway
uh that's it for today i'll see everyone
back here next week until then have fun
praying everyone i'll see you all on the
internet take it easy everybody