start recording yeah alright starting
pretty late today it's a half hour in
there's not gonna be any Q&amp;A at the end
of this just that's just the way it is
welcome everyone to handmade hero show
recode a complete game live on stream
today I want some more programs some
more profile UI I want it and I'm going
to get it with or without you so buckle
up to 63 is the day number so 262 source
code is what you want to start with if
you're trying to follow along at home
and I hope you are because why am I even
streaming this if you aren't I have no
idea right it's a good question it's a
very very good question here is the
handmade hero code base here is me
running it here is me opening the
profile window here is what I want what
I want now is some buttons up here I
want some buttons that I can push like a
back button like right now I can drill
down into something and I can see what's
going on but I can't actually get back
to where I was because I don't have a
back button I need a back button I want
to be able to switch between frame the
per frame view and this view which we
could trivially do if we had a button so
I want that as well so I want some
buttons up here that's one thing I want
and another thing I want is I want some
buttons down here that go with this
piece of information and maybe I want to
move these to the top as well but I want
some buttons that allow me to like pause
the stream so you know cuz this is like
running in real time I want me to pause
and we've got many frames of back data I
want to be able to go back to previous
frames so that I can you know see what
they were
you feel me dog so let's just let's do
that let's make that happen let's make
it happen bro you know I'm saying you
know just like sometimes you just got to
go to the gym you just got a lift and
have protein powders or powder your
protein I don't really know what bros do
I I feel like they probably have a lot
of protein in the mix in there somewhere
so that's good and they do like squats
or something so that's good maybe I
don't really know point being I'm gonna
make this stuff happen and the bros can
join us or not you know it's not my
problem I don't care
here we go I wanna move this stuff for
the top so basically we have the main
menu stuff drawing I don't even know why
we call it a main menu at this point old
legacy naming that's the kind of stuff
that we don't often get a chance to
clean up on the stream but that I would
probably clean up in real life when I
have lots of hours to program and I'm
not talking assessing Lee so this stuff
here this this menu obviously for we
would probably want to make sure that
our main menu starts after our debug
text happens and so what I'd want to do
I think is there's the @y thing that we
have in here I'd want to make sure that
that gets picked up so after we do these
these debug text lines I want to make
sure that gets picked up so I don't
actually remember I'll be completely
honest with you I don't even remember
what where this thing starts it looks
like it starts at the trees UIP
in this case we're just drawing each
individual tree and so I suppose what
we'd have to do to do that is just put
the tree move the tree down a certain
amount now when I now that I think about
that I suppose that's probably dumb
because why would be special case these
I have no idea why we would special case
these when we could just make these be
things that you control that seems like
a way more obvious thing to do so
probably what we want to do is just say
hey
get rid of these all together right
throw them up in the debug element you
know printout nonsense that we've got
where we're printing out different kinds
of elements in here so because we've got
like the the profile graph nonsense
happening where is that at where am i
search at this thing right so here we
are in draw element we've got a bunch of
different elements we can draw I think
what I'd rather do is just say you know
what let's just make these the elements
right so now I've got you know in here
I've got last frame or something
last frame info I don't know right
something like this and then we just
like print that out and and that way it
can just be its own little special sauce
thing that happens in there and
similarly we could have this be I don't
know what this would be this would be
like
debug memory info or something like that
I don't know
bla bla bla and that's you know how
that's gonna go and it's good and
everyone loves it
so all we need to do is tie that into
our system you can see here where we've
kind of got this layout stuff where we
can do the various things with with
debug event printout what I want to do
here is be able to lay out one of these
elements I don't actually know if it
seems to me like this is a little bit
long in the tooth like this is probably
something we should make really a little
more easy to do because we don't really
have anything in particular that's
that's complex about this right we once
we have a piece of text we get its size
we produce the dimensions for it we lay
out an element for it right and then we
we print it out and it seems to me like
that is something that we probably want
to wrap right there's no reason not to
wrap that so I'm gonna go ahead and make
utility for that
that's just internal like you know basic
text element typing typing is difficult
sometimes so something like this and
then we would just pass in what those
things are so we you know we have the
text we know we've got the debug state
and then we need that layout so we need
to get grab this guy right here
and it looks like actually we don't need
the debug state it looks like that we
wrapped that it looks like that's in
here so that's fine so we do the layout
we need to provide an item interaction
and that's just a thing like this sort
of thing that I suppose we should
probably just pass in because different
people will have different ones of those
and they may want to make different ones
but other than that I think that's it
right everything else here is pretty
much just by you know just goes by the
book we'll pass a color but we will make
it white by default so that if you don't
actually want to pass color you don't
have to and I think that's it so I'm
gonna try before I do anything else I'm
gonna try making this work like so no
not like that
I so need a new version of for coder
with with better indentation I actually
licensed the source code to it so I may
just go do that it's like one of the
only things that I noticed day-to-day
now it's like that in the auto expansion
other than that like I literally I
literally have not yeah it's just it's
great I'm so excited about this text
editor and the fact that it's programmer
1c is so good yeah but I want to fix
that indentation it's I think it would
be pretty easy to fix too but you can
just see how it picks wrong stuff a lot
of times I'm not quite sure why but I'm
pretty sure if I win the source code it
would not it would not be hard to find
because it's pretty close and a lot of
times it's right it just it looks like
it doesn't understand multi-line things
so basically like it'll get the
indentation of this okay I would prefer
it to be lined up to the parentheses but
it picks that which would be fine but
the next line if there's stuff here it
often times gets wrong and I don't know
why right like if this is a comma or
maybe now I don't know I to be honest I
really don't know what the circumstances
are like there you go so I don't know
why it decided to do it there right and
so there's just some things like that
that seem like
I don't know they seem like it would
take very little time for me to fix them
so I'm interested in looking that
because if I could fix those I think
this in my mind anyway it goes from
being an alpha to being basically
shipped like I'm like it does everything
I need
alright so let's see if that works which
I don't know if it will and I'm gonna
have to if these guys out obviously for
the time being here so if that works for
printing our menu nice text reloading
yeah okay if that works then we should
be able to use it for these as well now
so these guys can just be can basically
just do this and I guess they don't need
to pass the the color because we are
just vanilla white at this point sounds
like some really bad Disney movie so
yeah that's just text and text like so
and actually we don't need that at all
and so now I think all we need is to
have these particular doodads defined
right so in our grand list of things I
guess this would be an interface and our
grand list of things that you can add in
the debug system you can now add some
more things here like debug memory infos
and stuff like that and the threat
interval graph stuff you can see that we
do that here where we do like debug
threading of 'la graph we do this thing
I think what we want to do is say debug
you know UI or something or debug UI
thing
UI elements and then in here we would
just pass the type so we'd say like oh
you know I whatever you want that one to
be we'll do it right and so this will
just be like some name that you're
trying to pass to it and then we'll
build it and it'll be great and it's
just awesome and it's fine and
everyone's loves it like that movie with
like Lindsay Lohan and the car so we can
go ahead and just make this one work
like that so instead of the old waiver
we're calling it we can call it this way
and you see why I did this right I don't
want to have like a separate function
for each of those when I already have to
type an identifier in to define them I
might as well just pass the identifier
right and I only need to make a special
one of these if for some reason in the
future right
I needed to pass different sorts of
parameters or do other fussing but I
don't really need to do that here so I
might as well just make it one function
that can generate any one of our special
elements so now I do that we don't
actually have anything in particular
here that I I guess that I would put but
like in the last frame or I don't know
but anyway now you can see we've got
these guys in here so we now have the
profile which we did before and now we
also have that the old data that we that
we wanted that now puts us in an
excellent position to generate some more
UI controls which is also what I want so
if you take a look at well you know it's
kind of interesting here though why are
those in the wrong order do we do with
some kind of a push down for when we add
things to a set because correct me if
I'm wrong but they go in reverse order
of where they are and I don't know why I
feel like we must have decided to do
like
singly-linked list there that doesn't do
push on end that's my assumption anyway
yum-yum-yum yeah yeah yeah yeah let's
find out that's a little meow song for
you I hope you enjoyed it so what we
want here is we want the place where we
do the get element for event or whatever
it's called like get element from it
that's it get element from event yet
element from event there it is
so when we do add element to group right
here I'm wondering is that a singly
linked thing that's happening here
d-list insert mr. d-list insert yeah man
that's a problem you guys know I'm
saying check it out check it out right
there see see how that works that
inserts at the head of the list right
you know I'm saying it says that the
next thing is the first thing in the
list so all we need to do is do like the
same exact thing like exact mr.
exactness com
it's a wonderful company series see
funded for 11 billion dollars is what we
need to do here is say like okay what we
actually want is we want to link up to
the sentinals previous so that we are
now the last thing so our prior link
will be whatever was the previous last
link and our next link will be this one
and then we just go in and set the those
two to point back to us and we're done
right so same same bit for finishing up
but otherwise a little bit different
there so
could just do as last right and so if we
do insert as last now those things will
go in the order we said and I want them
to go in the order that we said right
because I feel like that's just just
better because inside one of these I
want them to be accurate now we still I
don't think create these in that order
probably right because that be in a
different place add group to group is
using that as well so we might as well I
don't think we ever really want them to
be out of order we don't our reverse
order we'd always want to be same order
so I feel like this is actually the
right cuz this is the order they
actually appeared in the program okay so
that seems good to me right that seems
like some sexy hiking right there so I'm
gonna go ahead and go ahead and keep
that so now I want to add a little bit
of I want to add a little bit of special
sauce in here I want to sauce this up
and so what I'm gonna do is before what
we were doing is we're always viewing
the most recent frame but what I'd
rather do is have a like you know
viewing frame ordinal or something like
this and by default we could have the
viewing frame ordinal always track the
most recent frame ordinal but then if
you like scrub you could view a
different one right and so what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna make a way for us
to edit the viewing frame ordinal first
or release just display it and then put
in the pause and then come back and have
everyone tie into the viewing frame
ordinal does that make sense i sweared
it seriously guys that it better make
sense because it was so straightforward
what I just said I don't even want to
hear it that's not man I mean look at
the chat I don't even want to know if
that's not make sense to you because it
better make sense to you so what I'm
gonna put in here is a frame slider or
something like that we're gonna call it
a frame slider okay frame slider is what
it is and if you don't want a frame
slider then maybe you should have picked
a different program
so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna make a
debug data block here for no reason and
I'm gonna call that like rate our debug
control mmm
right and in there I'm gonna make some
of these UI elements I'm gonna make this
frame slider I wonder if our UI element
I wonder if I wasn't maybe a little bit
of premature pants on this and really
you should be able to just do UI element
without putting anything after it you
know what I'm saying but I don't know
I'm gonna keep doing that for no
apparent reason because I can and so
we'll put the debug frame starter in
there and maybe we'll have a debug thing
you know what just gonna called you by
frame slider that's it that's all
they're gonna be and if you want more
than that well you're gonna have to go
download the source code and add it
because you know that's your problem so
if we go to debug go back to debug here
I'm gonna go ahead and add that in as
one of the things we can draw so in cure
where we do that's not good not not what
I wanted not what I wanted to do
switching to modal editing has been
pretty tricky for me I don't I don't
mind telling you it's been a lot better
than for coder than it wasn't Emacs but
it's still pretty rough on me because
I'm not used to it compared to non modal
which is how I've been programming for
30 years so anyway here in this this
little doodad I'm gonna implement one of
these frame sliders and in order to
implement a frame slider really all I
have to do is make one of these but you
can kind of I guess sighs but I don't
know that I really want this to be
sizable I think I might just want it to
be a fixed size and that fixed size
probably should depend to be honest with
you on the width of the window but I'm
not really caring so much about that
sort of thing at the moment so you know
you're just gonna have to live with that
and
you're gonna live with that so happy
birthday and you know that's there you
go so I'm gonna actually look at this as
an inline block and in fact we're gonna
use that instead so cuz I don't actually
need any of the graph stuff I don't need
to make a type for the frame slider
because it's always gonna be it's just a
two actually I guess to be honest with
you we don't even need settings for this
thing because it doesn't have any
settings it's just a little UI element
that allows you to control the frame and
so at the moment I guess really all I
need to do is is have that have one of
those dims where where are you mr. Jim
no no there it is
so the inline-block thingy I just need
to have one of these dims that we set
manually and so you know it's 1800 by I
don't know 32 we'll find out and then
when we do begin element rectangle and
element this time I'm not actually gonna
do anything in there it just nothing
happens it's just gonna make that and
it's gonna be fine don't worry about it
it's not sizable so it's just gonna be
that that specific size that it is and
then what I can do is say well I'll go
ahead and draw the flame frame slider so
draw frame slider or something like this
and I'll basically do the exact same
thing I did with the profiler right I'll
say here's here's all the stuff we were
doing so that you can do whatever you
want to do with it but but then I'll
implement it up in its own function for
now just to keep that switch statement a
little more clear so you don't have to
read too far through it I don't always
do that sometimes I like the switch
statements to get long it depends on my
mood and what the code is so anyway
here's draw frame slider
and the first thing that I want to do in
draw frame slider is I really really
really want to draw this like basically
I the same kind of grid that we were
drawing before so draw frame bars
actually is is almost exactly what I
want so I'm gonna start with this code
and basically chop a ton of it out if
that makes sense
what I actually want is yeah so yeah so
what I actually want to do is say okay
there's there's no mouse stack at the
moment we are gonna fill in the
rectangle it's not going to be called
profile rect
obviously it's I think we'll just call
it element vector or maybe I'll call it
like total wreck totally wrecked man
like after we went to the gym into the
squat so it's totally wrecked so anyway
then we come through here and we don't
actually need to do any of sort of the
element stuff but we need to do the
frame index stuff right so this is all
not necessary none of this is relevant
it all does not matter blah blah blah
blah blah blah blah blah but this does
right so yeah
wait what was that annex what did that
say bar what all right so this is gonna
step us through each of the individual
bars and this I don't care about at all
so this min X and this the the min max
are always going to be the same as well
right so the min axe is always going to
be whatever the total wrecked min X was
and we don't need this and the max X is
always gonna be whatever so we're just
we're just doing literally the the you
know a square sort of thing well Mona so
every square but a little rectangle for
every frame just striped across a bar
that's it
that's the whole thing we're doing
nothing else so then we have the same
construction where we do the outline and
all that is exactly the same the color
in this case I don't know what I want to
be but you know it could be white or it
could be a gray maybe it should be more
of a gray something like that and then
we we would still do it is in a
rectangle but at the moment you know I'm
not really gonna use that we're gonna
probably implement some code there in
just a second
but at first I just want this to be
working properly for drawing a little
thing that we could use for frames
that's total recluse well total total
rect viewing element is in fact yeah in
fact you know what there is no element
is there wait but now I can just pass
the regular element
yeah what is the problem
layout element to debug element what are
you talking about what are you even
talking about right now oh that's yeah
all right yep it's time don't worry
about it little parameter masking there
it's alright don't worry about it
it's done and this is layout element
okay so in theory now maybe I'll have
something if I didn't totally mess it up
and it turns out I did totally mess it
up so that's great nice working rhetoric
you're off the team
so here's a frame slider I seem to be
only drawing the very first one that's
probably because if you want something
to happen every time three or four a
loop one here's a protip crow tip number
three program for 30 years so take me
take my word on this it helps to put it
inside the loop tends to get called more
when you put it in there so there's
actually what I wanted for my frame
slider
that's what we're going for okay I feel
like that maybe too many frames too many
frames but you know what are you gonna
do sometimes you have too many frames
too many frames too many frames too many
frames too many frames too many frames
so the next thing I want to do is I want
to make one of these things solid and
the one that I want to be solid
is the one that we're viewing I want to
make if if this is the frame that well
okay you know what I'm not even gonna
say stuff because words are difficult
and they have vocabularies with them and
letterings
and stuff and so what I actually just
want to do is this right I basically
want to you know say you know are we
gonna highlight this thing and then I'm
going to check it against some of these
things so it's like if the frame index
happens to be you know the viewing frame
ordinal then I want to highlight it
right and I'm gonna set the highlight
color so the viewing frame the one that
we're currently looking at I'm gonna
make that be yellow because yellow is
the color of urine which is an essential
byproduct and Gandhi drank it supposedly
I wasn't there that's just what I heard
and obviously he liberated India from
the British and so pretty much as far as
science is concerned that means if you
would like to liberate your country from
an oppressive occupant which at this
point honestly is probably my country
because that's the sort of thing we do
apparently we can't manage to stay home
ever
you should drink your own urine because
that's what we've got to go on so the
most recent frame to the viewing frame
will be yellow the most recent frame and
like the collation frame will be I think
maybe some color that shows that you
can't look at that one like that'll be
red you know the oldest frame I don't
know that we super care about too much
but I'll make that one green and the
most recent frame
well actually the most recent frame I
guess I'll make B green and then the
oldest frame I'll make be sort of a
darker green that's what I'll do
and so all I want to do here is say
let's pick out what those ordinals are
we're already updating them but then
what I want to do is say if I wanted to
highlight one of those ordinals so I
could see it during the sweeps if that's
true then I'm gonna go ahead and just
like draw the rectangle with a solid
backing so that it's like very clearly
there and I'm going to draw it in the
high colour that we've set above and I
want this to be visible so I need to
draw it kind of on the upper layer right
and I think we can even I think we can
do stuff like this I don't really know
if we can but I think we can
so viewing frame ordinal these all have
to be off of the debug state and why I
didn't do that to begin with I don't
know
probably it was your fault on the stream
somehow you weren't paying attention and
then that happened so here's debug
control now and you can kind of see
what's happening there right it's it
looks more or less exactly like what we
would expect we don't have a way to
pause debug yet which is what we want to
do but you can see basically you've got
the red frame which is the frame that's
being collated you've got the green
frame right behind it which is the most
recent one and you've got that other
green frame that shows like this is
where debug data starts now if I'm not
very much an error
I just want to visually show you
something here and I'm gonna explain it
and it's probably not going to happen
that's what happens when I explain
strings downstream but what you can see
here is that we've got per frame arena
space remaining we've got tons and so
you know and I think now that I think
about it I don't think we'd sink enough
events to make it happen so I think I
probably can't show you this but I'll
just say this I'll say what would happen
if we could make it happen which I don't
think we can but we could go force it to
we've got per frame arena space
remaining right now of a hundred and
thirty megabytes
now what that means is that we're
storing right we've got frame arrays
that are 206 frames long and what that
means is that we will store 256 frames
of data if we have enough space to store
them but if we started sinking so many
debug events per frame that we actually
didn't have enough memory to store 2056
back frames then what would happen is we
store less back frames and what you
would see at that point is the red which
is what's being synced now what's being
collated now and the green right before
it would start to diverge and you would
have a gap of frames that were
essentially not valid they just had
nothing in them so if you viewed them
you just get nothing it would say there
was nothing happened because that's data
that's been freed so when we switch to
the game you can now see that we start
using up a lot more space but
unfortunately we don't use up enough
more to get down to zero now what we
could do is we could artificially limit
the amount of memory the debug system
actually has to work with and then I
could show you that happening in
practice so here is you know some sub
sub arena stuff right so I'm going to
switch this to some testing where here
we have what is this 128 K of memory
that's not very much so maybe let's just
give it let's give it eight megabytes of
memory to store debug information in
okay so it's fixed to storing that's how
much you're giving the system to work
with and you can see right here that
number going down
then it plateaus and that's because like
I said it's only sorting 206 frames back
and the reason we did that is because we
you know we used to have it so just
stored as far back as it could but I
wanted to have some fixed arrays that we
could jump around in quickly and see you
know not have to traverse linked lists
all the time to get to get to them okay
so let's say we jump into the game now
yikes is that really true so that that
is a little concerning that means that
the number of things that were stored in
this frame and the number that we freed
were not coincident which is not good to
say the least right this is an assertion
that I added too because we we record
every time we use one of the every time
we allocate a storied event to put it in
there and when we free a frame we expect
that the the number of reads should
match what I don't know yeah and when we
well you know what I don't know I don't
know one one slight piece of information
that I should check first which is that
when we call free frame we don't
necessarily clear that data so I think
what I probably want to do is move this
up to here where we say after we free a
frame we always zero it because if we
tried to free a frame twice that would
actually happen I don't think that
should ever happen and I don't think
that was the bug there but it just it
occurred to me
so before I start debugging I want that
to be fixed if that makes sense because
I'll forget so when we take this frame
and we after we think we're finished
with it I'm just want to wipe it out so
that there's nothing left in it
okay so now let's see I want to see why
that is because that should not happen
interesting so I guess that was actually
the bug when we tried to free the frames
twice that's weird
alright so let's watch this happen in a
little more detail here right so I'm
gonna bolt out of here and the run so
here we are tracking and we've got if we
take a look at how much memory we've got
we still have seven Meg's free now we're
gonna dive into the thing where we start
sinking just a ton of debug frames a
slept ton of debug data every frame so I
hit the spacebar and you can see it
right there how it starts to to fall
backwards right and now we have the case
where this range right here is actually
the only valid part right
it's it's only between there and there
that actually has debug data and we
don't have any from the read forward to
here that makes sense
so yeah I'm not sure that's probably I'm
not super I don't again if this were not
on stream I would probably go
investigate that double free because I
feel like I don't super understand why
free frame was getting called on a frame
that had already been freed and so I
feel like that's probably a bug since it
isn't the debug code and we are on
stream I'm not gonna do that but I'm
just gonna point that out
I would ordinarily go do it so anyway
what I wanted to say was like I think I
gave this sort of speech a while back
where I was like on stream I tend not to
debug things nearly as thoroughly as I
normally would to try to keep things
sort of more coherently together and
basically like you know I try to remind
people of that because in general I
would not want you to be as lacs about
pursuing those things if you were
actually working eight hours a day on
programming you should not be doing that
really but I don't know any way to not
do that because I'm stream it would be
very it would be even harder to follow
what it is that
doing day-to-day if I jumped around as
much as I normally would in that case so
just keep that in mind so anyway on the
frame slider here after we draw it what
I would like to do now is make it so
that I can set you know the like I'd
like to set that the value of like if
you click in there I want to be able to
set that as an interaction and so if I
go to debug interface dot H and we look
at it like it's in here then what I want
to do is I want to be able to make an
interaction that will set you know what
frame you're talking about and so in
order to do that what I'm gonna do here
is say well where's my interaction code
there it is
there's gonna be a thing that's like a
debug interaction set view frame ordinal
something like that I let's just say
it's that and so then I'm gonna make one
of these here where I can say like okay
debunk interaction and get rid of all
this stuff and we'll say the net hot
next hot in direction in this case is
this one and it is set view frame
ordinal and the you know whatever it is
the index and we should have one of
these we don't the moment include two
you know given 32 or something we want
to set our U and 32 to be equal to the
frame index that we currently have and
that's just all fine and stuff so that
is what that will do we don't have a
graph ID do we or we do
it should just be called debug ID or or
slider ID I guess so we'll set the
slider idea we don't actually need that
no one's going to use that at all
but we'll just set it anyway and that
can be our interaction we could also if
we wanted to make this happen and by
this I mean I don't really know what we
were using that for exactly but I just
mean hey let's print out whatever the
frame index is so that you can see which
ordinal it is in case anyone cares at
all which they probably don't and really
all I'm all I was saying with that was
you know like hey you could see which
ordinal it was probably what I'd want to
do instead is print out how many frames
back we were which maybe I'll do if I'm
in the mood for love you know just in
that mood but is just a feel up shoe is
sensual so I'm gonna go ahead and search
for that interaction code because
frankly I don't remember anything about
that at all so let's go ahead and go
down there to where we actually do that
and here is basically all of our
interaction code that we've written so
far so here's an interaction it doesn't
really do anything interesting at all
other than just set what was it called
we had a name for it
viewing frame ordinal so it sets the
viewing frame ordinal equal to whatever
this whatever this guy says it should be
and that's all it does that's all it do
yeah and so if I come in here and I drag
select on this that's not good
someone want to tell me what that's it
Oh what
who wrote this ridiculous code that's
garbage this is just plain ridiculous
I do not know who thought this was even
remotely going to work because surprise
it's totally not
that's probably wasn't actually a
surprise to anyone
yeah I don't even know why that would be
a surprise
OOP
whoops what did I don't don't know what
F key I hit there don't even know so
that allows us to kind of do some stuff
but it's not good it's not really slider
II so I probably need to make that
interaction a little bit better well
we'll we'll just we'll leave it like
that for now just for the second just
for the split estelle splits seconds or
splits as they're called in when you're
really super advanced programming you
use the term seconds for split second so
I don't know if you knew that it's a
computer science term so what I want to
do is I want to start taking the place
all the places right now where people
were using the ordinal most recent and
then want to basically make them all use
the other one so I want to say that I'm
gonna replace like the most recent frame
ordinal yeah with viewing frame ordinal
and I can't see because it's behind my
head I think so that's unfortunate
you know what oh I know what I can do I
can switch over into this thing because
my head's not on the side BAM
yep so now now now we can do most recent
frame ordinal and viewing frame ordinal
and I can say what I want so draw a
profile yes please draw frame slider no
stored event thread interval graph yes
yes
yo that's a tough one yeah yeah yep
debug begin interact oh man no I guess
I'm gonna say no no no
no no no no and then I'm gonna say last
frame time yeah yeah so this is now
gonna be awesome is what this is going
to be it's gonna be super awesome
maybe possibly or approaching the
awesomeness so now we can just kind of
go through here and we can pick any
frame that we wanted to view right and
we can view that frame so we can see
like oh how many milliseconds was each
of these frames you know what was the
information available at that time what
did the profile look like on that frame
and similarly all this stuff would also
be correct so for example like in here
if we were doing some stuff I feel like
I feel like it's still I guess one
problem is its what it's doing the
viewing its viewing the state of the
events at that time so I guess one of s
when we actually draw I'm gonna have to
not do that right cuz it's actually
taking that was a flaw on the plan I
admit that I admit that up front
let's go address that
yeah that's pretty plain okay so in
terms of how the debug views go that's
looking up into like whether something
is standard or not I don't feel like
that actually should I don't feel like
that actually should have caused a
problem hold on one second let's let's
let's just figure out exactly why that
was happening where's the view hash get
debug view oops
get or create debug view for so we do a
hash here and with the requisite comment
remember you always have to put that
comment in so what are we having we are
hashing the two you 32s for the debug ID
for that thing whatever that thing is
right and so when we call get or create
give a view for what are we actually
passing for those debug IDs now in this
this one we don't this is not an expand
or collapse kind of scenario right so
that's not the one we actually care
about the one that we actually care
about is for example one of these and so
to get that that one where we call that
where we get that view we use an ID
that's generated from the tree and the
link and the link is actually the in the
the tree itself right so I'm going to
take a look
that's in the iterator for this which is
the debug variable iterator so where is
the debug variable iterator I don't know
why we do that in order by the way I
think that was cuz we were trying to
show how to do it but it's kind of dumb
anyway debug variable links are stable
so I don't really understand why that
would have been the case that's a little
bit puzzling so let me see
I wish to understand more I wish to know
more expanded well actually I guess I
really just want to look at toggle
expansion toggle expansion expansion
toggles toggle expansion so this is
toggle expansion and get or create debug
view for he's just looking at whatever
the ID was for this interaction so
so I don't see why that would that does
not make a lot of sense to me I don't
see why that would be sort of variant
for toggle value yeah I'm not sure what
we want to do for event editing like
it's a theoretical that you'd want to
allow editing of the events back in the
past but really what we want to do is
just not allow you to edit things in the
past because they won't take effect you
know what I mean so it doesn't really
make a whole lot of sense either way so
this I don't know this may have to wait
for for to debug like that's super weird
I do not understand
because there still should be I guess
it's because the stuff isn't in there
yet
oh yeah I guess that is the case so it's
looking for those things there's nothing
actually in that slot yet okay yeah no
that's now that I think about it that's
actually correct so it's going to try to
display stuff but there's nothing in
there on that frame because it hasn't
been written yet so I guess that is
actually fine I guess that's okay all
right so let me just finish up in the
last five minutes what I was going do
and we'll see if that continues to be
true but I guess that's actually correct
cuz it just won't draw anything if
there's nothing there
so it's not that it hasn't it's not that
it isn't collapsed or expanded it's that
there's nothing there
when we jump into the game since we set
the debug size down and we leave a big
gap there whenever the gap of debug data
would come across it wouldn't happen yet
okay it all makes for any sense now all
makes perfect sense now both programming
so anyway all that really means is I
just have to finish up and then we'll be
fine so when we actually do debug start
what we want to do is we want to see
whether or not we are paused right and
you know we'll want to do and if paused
here basically but right now we don't
have that quite yet or we don't actually
use it right but if we are not paused
and we want like the most recent frame
ordinal to overwrite viewing frame
ordinal so normally like you know this
is we're running the same way we were
before and so when you look at something
you're looking at the current frame and
it's telling you that and it's all fine
right but then we need a way to
basically pause and make it so that
we're not gonna continue anymore by the
way like let's talk about this like
that's pretty baller right there you can
just tear that off if you want to
because we're awesome it's like I just
want to like move my UI around anyway so
if I want to write I can what I want to
be able do now is pause this
so that I can then I can then go in and
like click right now I can't click on it
anymore
because if I were to click on it it'll
just immediately get overwritten right
so another thing I could do is I could
make it so that if any if I click on the
debug if I click on one of these it'll
just automatically stop that's another
thing I could do but either way the
primary point here is we have to
implement some way of pausing so I think
we had a variable for pause like I think
we had a pause right but I don't think
it does anything anymore so so you know
it's nice to have a variable called
paused but if you never reference that
variable anywhere other than to set it
to false not gonna do a lot for you
right that's another pro tip right there
that you can use to become a better
programmer is if you don't use a
variable it won't have an effect very
important so what we want to do here is
say if we're not paused then we are
going to overwrite that now what we need
to implement now is just some way of
saying when we are paused don't
overwrite stuff anymore right so you
know like here so this sort of situation
oops when we come through and we call
collate debug event records so in here
when we see a frame marker and we do the
collation frame you can kind of see here
we come through and we increment the
frame ordinal you know this sort of
thing I think all we have to do is just
not do that if that makes sense so
basically we would just freed that frame
immediately and then just keep going so
we would do
if debug state well I guess we actually
want to do it yeah absolutely around if
we're paused then we just do free frame
debug states diverse state collation
frame ordinal goodbye been nice knowing
you
off it goes and otherwise we advance so
then what I'll say is well you know when
we set this thing probably we wanted to
pause and then we'll just have to make a
way to non pause right but there's our
profile
there's our frame slider ething and so
if i click there and now we are paused
and here we go
right which is pretty great awesome very
happy about that
yeah so we're getting there man this is
starting to be some pretty this is
turning me some pretty sweet action now
we need an unpause obviously we'll do
that next week and we need those buttons
I was talking about we also need to go
finally fix the OpenGL multi-threading
thing Oh OpenGL so we don't have to
worry about texture downloads still
being wrong so much for reading white
papers about how to download textures
anyway so what we want to do here right
is I just wanted to demonstrate too that
we track all the debug data now so for
example this dude right if we open up
now that we have selected him if we open
up the simulation and look at the entity
data we don't actually need this profile
dating here you know it goes all around
and we track that data right and now if
we want to we can also you know just say
like oh okay let's let's go ahead and
and zoom back through there so not only
like will our profile be you know
accurate back then but so will all of
the data we captured like all of its
still good so we can look
at our data and our profile together and
do all the operations we would normally
be able to do like if we want to zoom in
on one of these things we can we can
look at every last little thing and not
only can we look at it but once we look
at it we can actually see how it varies
over time to write by looking at was
there any differences between these yeah
this profiler is baller I think by the
end of next week I'm basically just
gonna like have to like call the
Smithsonian and be like do you want to
put this profiler in there because it's
pretty much the best profiler that like
America has ever made okay put it next
to john f kennedy's brain or whatever it
is you're keeping in there that no one
cares about because this profiler is
going to be cooler than that by a
substantial substantial margin all right
I'll take literally five minutes of Q&amp;A
but then I gotta go
fwe for how much would it cost to save
draw buffer snapshots so when you pause
you can show the visual state it was in
or maybe save enough data to resented
the frame um so honestly most of that's
just OpenGL busy work right so if we if
we only cared about working with our
software renderer the answer is this
trivial you just allocate 256 back
buffers and you point to a different one
each time free so it's literally free
like there's a little more cash maybe if
that ever stayed hot but it probably
doesn't through the cycle so it's just
free so software render it's really
Hardware renderer it probably takes a
little more doing but basically the same
technique would probably work so what we
would do is we just allocate 286 back
buffers on the card and just be like hey
you better have a car with a lot of
memory bro
and then each time we would render to
one of those first then flip that one
flip that one to the screen and then we
could just go back to the other back
buffer I would be willing to do that
sometime I that's probably not too hard
I mean it's definitely not too hard I
just I worry about the amount of stream
stream time spent on doing OpenGL things
because they're super not relevant
like GPU programming will be total like
building this profiler every last thing
I did in here is relevant to programming
in my mind like you should know every
last thing that I did in here and
understand why like how it was doing
what it was doing and how I went from
one state to the other and decided to
move things around like all that stuff
is classic programming that I think will
never not be relevant to training your
brain how to use OpenGL literally no one
will care about in ten years
like the way we program GPUs today will
be completely irrelevant you will never
need to know a single thing about how to
call OpenGL or Vulcan or D 3d or metal
or any of this other garbage that'll
just be gone right and we replaced with
hopefully something good but probably
just another crappy thing with a
different name that's somebody else
screwed up so
you know I worry about spending too much
time on you know GPU stuff because it's
just not educational it's really just
completely transient and doesn't really
benefit you much to know except in the
instant
mongolians is it is it impossible to
keep the entire code base in mind when
developing a larger project how does
this impact code design decisions in
handmade hero what about other larger
projects eg a triple-a titles the answer
is no or I should say I guess you said
is it impossible yes it is impossible to
keep the entire code base in mind when
developing a larger project that is true
and I don't think there's ever been a
programmer who could do that for a
triple-a title but when you are
developing large projects you can still
work around this limitation and the way
to work around that limitation is by
reducing systems to understandable sort
of repeatable pieces before moving on so
that you can clearly understand how they
would work when you come back to them
and so like for example the debug system
in handmade hero here is crazy right
like the stuff we've been doing is super
weird and so if we were planning on
handmade hero being like a very large
project and lots of people having to
come back to this debug code and do it
if this were not on stream what we would
then probably do is we'd spend a week or
two
like solidifying everything making it as
clear as possible breaking some things
out you know just like putting it into a
state where it'd be very easy to
understand how each piece worked because
right now it's very like tightly
integrated and it's largely about how we
got there when we were doing car sort of
explorations and so you have to keep
that in mind as you scale up to larger
projects that often times before moving
out of a section for a while
you need to spend some time basically
bolting it up into a place where when
you come back to it it's more obvious
how it's supposed to work
is the engine portion expected to be the
largest chunk of the handmade hair
project yes definitely
so look I would say that it after the
dista bug code is done I think we will
mostly probably be working on game Cody
stuff but a lot of that will still be
enginee like we'll be making a sort of
the final collision detector as we go
and we'll be making like a nice amenity
system stuff that's you know not
necessarily hard welded to the game and
other things like that but definitely
like the point of this is engine
programming I'm not a game designer I
have nothing to say about game code at
all literally and and I have nothing to
say about game design so hand made here
is strictly an engine project but in
order to build an engine of any value
you have to have a game to go with it or
at least understand how a game would
work with it and so I felt like it was
very important to make a game not just
an engine because otherwise you don't
know if you really made an engine that
can do anything right unless you
actually prove here's a game it's
interesting you know the game looks
looks like it should and feels like it
should ok then we know this engine can
at least make a game that's very
important I think I don't think you can
really make an engine in the back vacuum
and have it be very good and so so yeah
so mostly everything we do I ballpark
like 600 episodes at a minimum mostly
everything we do in those 600 episodes
will be engine code it just some of it
will be more game related than others
like some of it will be okay we're
making an animation loop for a guy
that's kind of game code II but it'll
still be mostly about how do we make
animation loops not about how do we
program it this particular person's
animation loop because that's not super
interesting to me
Culver fly can you please expend again
the problem with texture loading why
does it not work occasionally well so
the answer axes we don't know we tried
doing what Nvidia had suggest in their
white paper to get more to get texture
overlaps on the GPU side it turns out
they don't actually implement that in
their consumer level cards a and AMD
seems to have a problem with it as well
so as far as I can tell it's just a bad
idea and who knows why it's not working
could be any number of reasons so we
will probably replace that with one that
does not actually try to overlap it with
two contexts so all right but we'll get
to that later like just stay tuned we'll
fix that at some point but again since
we don't have source coded drivers we'll
never really know what the bug is unless
someone an Nvidia debugs it and I'm
sorry this is a named Akari if someone
at AMD debugs it and tells us right all
right thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you want to follow along the
series source code at home you can
always pure to the game on handmade hero
or it comes with a source code so you
can follow along and do experiments and
learn from it in all the other good
stuff we also have forums that you can
go to if you want to ask questions you
have a patreon page you can use if you
want support the video series and we
have a tweet pops tweet schedule which
will tell you the schedule for next week
if you would like to come back next week
and see our profiler get up - previously
unknown heights of baller ism that's it
for today hope see you back here next
week until then have fun programming and
I'll see you guys on the Internet
techies everyone