alright hello everyone and welcome
handmade here oh sure we could a
complete game live on stream we may I'll
be honest yesterday's episode was pretty
interesting to me because I had never
really thought it not only had never
really thought about it but I've
actually never even seen anyone talk
about it or do it I mean I can't imagine
where the first it doesn't make much
sense for us to be the first but the
stuff we discovered on yesterday's dream
about using signed distance fields to
interpolate lighting properly lighting
fall off properly or I shouldn't say
properly but attractively I've literally
never seen that before so that was
complete news to me when I sort of
investigated that and it turned out to
work that was shocking and so I'm kind
of interested in this and I want to kind
of follow that to its logical conclusion
so today we are definitely gonna
continue experiment to that and see what
we can do with how many voxels we know
we can you know we know we can sample a
large number of voxels at runtime and it
doesn't seem to have a particularly
large cost like it seems like the grass
card is pretty good at sampling voxels
and given that we can sample what
appears to be a fairly large number of
voxels and we know we can interpolate
signed distance fields quite well it
kind of starts to beg the question of
well wait a minute like what kind of
interesting and novel at least to me
well like I said I can't promise that we
did this first because there's a lot of
graphics creatures out there as probably
someone has already discovered it but it
was fun to discover it independently
let's put it that way since we know we
can interpolate sign distance feels
quite well and we know that we can
interpolate normals it appears like
pretty well as in addition it sort of
starts to beg the question of like what
is the most attractive light
reconstruction scheme and how can we
sort of like lean on that in our output
phase to like make really good looking
lighting from pretty low resolution
sampling right so I'm relatively excited
about that I've literally never seen
anyone talk about anything like this
before so I'm pretty interested in that
and I like when I
got something new so like I said I'm not
sure we invented it because it probably
exists somewhere that's the nature of
graphics research is there's so many
people who do it and there's been so
much attention paid to it that it's very
unlikely that when you discover some
think you actually discovered something
so there is that but that said I
certainly am interested in the fact that
we did independently discover it and I'm
pretty psyched to sort of like see where
that leads so as you can see we are
currently here's our little
interpolation test and the really
interesting thing about this test and
again I'd like to just underscore just
how interesting it was to me is if you
look at what's going on here this is
actually voxel reconstructed lighting
from a spherical light right and the
thing that's really remarkable about
this is even though there is literally
no direct lighting computation occurring
now there is none we are not directly
computing lighting at all the pixel
shader does not know where the light
source was it is literally
reconstructing it simply from a voxel
intensity right it looks as if you've
performed direct lighting right because
what we did with the signed distance
field light interpolation actually is
able to reconstruct a real sphere from
samples that are just on the voxel right
and that is pretty remarkable to me
because I've never seen that demoed
before but it's really kind of cool and
just to underscore how interesting that
is if we are to look back at the actual
like what it looks like when you don't
do that so if you do not reconstruct
with a sign distance field right if you
actually reconstruct with just light
intensity which is what most people do
as far as I know the only kind of ever
seen was this kind if you reconstruct
with light intensity let me show you the
difference right so this is what we were
looking at before and this is good that
wrong route I have to do it this way
yeah so you know this is the the way
we're doing before and as you can see
it's like perfectly spherical right when
you actually switch to doing the kind of
light interpolation people normally do
in a voxel look at how ugly that is do
you see all the like rectilinear
artifacts from that you know from that
voxel sample right it's pretty bad
you can really see them very clearly and
all we did there was switch from
interpolating light intensity to
interpolating a signed distance field
that represented like light intensity
and again the difference there is
strictly in whether or not you allow the
values to go negative and one of the
things that you know is really kind of
non-intuitive is that when you are using
a reconstruction filter on something
truncating values creates artifacts
that's what happens so even though you
would normally say well why does it
matter if I truncate a value if I know
that the light intensity is zero or
negative 1 or negative 10 or whatever
why would it matter if I truncated all
those to zero because they still
represent no light contribution and the
answer is because it changes the shape
of your interpolation so you must
interpolate first and then clamp if you
don't want to introduce artifacts right
and so that discovery was really kind of
novel to me because I'd never heard it
mentioned in the in the context of
lighting and I'm really interested in
that and I think that was cool so now
what I'd like to do is just take a look
at what can we now like let's suppose
that we embrace that and say if we're
gonna take you know take all of our
lighting information which you know at
the moment like I said we this is just a
test spear that we're jamming in here
and so what we're looking to to do is
finalize this sampling layer as
something we can dump our actual light
contribution information down into right
and so what I'm really interested to
know is if we are going to output our
lighting in this way what can we do like
what is the best way to set it up and
how can we really leverage the fact that
this is for
doing really nice reconstruction to sort
of really create something that allows
us to get a lot of lighting expressivity
in here right because again I don't if
this is all I wanted was like a little
like flashlight effect on the player
then we're kind of done but if I was
doing that I wouldn't need the voxel
right but what I want to do now is flood
this thing with tons of lighting
information like I want all of the
bounce light from the ray tracing and I
want all of the like lots of different
light sources and all their that's what
I actually want to do right and I kind
of want to make sure that we have like
the best possible set up for that right
and and so yeah that's all so what I'd
like to do now is just say let's let's
push this a little further and
furthermore let's see how much detail we
actually need in the voxel because it
may be that our voxel now is still too
detailed and we probably could get away
with less is it all I'm thinking right
so for example like if we take a look at
the actual striping of the voxel so if
you remember quickly we've got like a
thing here where I think at least I can
switch to look at the voxel striping and
just give me some input into I guess not
this is zero didn't may have a way to
get voxel striping in here oh oh wait no
no I that was that was the wrong thing
yeah oh boy
so I guess I don't know maybe this will
do it
not sure let's take a look No
so we're packing north and south light
directions in here light west is the
only thing that actually has any light
information carried in it at the moment
so shouldn't that have worked shouldn't
that have striped meaning this this
right here where we striped the West
with a full red oh because it already is
nevermind all right yeah obviously that
won't do anything never mind
I take it I take it all back that's not
gonna do anything um like let's just say
we then don't do something well okay
maybe we just do this then does that
help
that didn't help either all right you
know what we're just not gonna bother
with that right now I want to take a
look at the voxel resolution one more
time so I'm not sure what resolution we
need you know what I'm gonna so what I
want to do here is I would like to make
this actually work with so that I can
turn on box the striping here in some
way and we kind of got too many cases
here so maybe what I'll do is I'll just
like sort of duplicate this one entirely
right and so I'm gonna I'm gonna pull
this out the part where we assign it I'm
gonna pull that out and I'm gonna pull
it out down here I'm gonna get rid of
this right and what I want to do here is
I'm gonna make the definition of these
things the light west all that stuff I'm
gonna make that just be in here period
so we can make this loop a little bit
more sensible right because I'm kind of
just piling all this test fest up in
here and that's not necessarily the
smartest thing to do so let's just try
and clean this up a little bit just
because I would like to take a look at
the resolution and just understand the
effects of the resolution on the
reconstruction that's what I'm trying to
do here just kind of get that a little
bit more out of control
all right and so what I'm gonna do here
is just have these parceled out so what
I'd like to do is have a pound if here
which is like pound if like test lights
here or something like this right and
here is that code then we're gonna put
an end if in there so now we have the
test light sphere then we're gonna do
another one of these which is like you
know pound if test light flicker board
and that'll be this crap
and then we'll finally have one that's
like if tests light probes and that'll
be this is garbage right here right and
so now I can just like turn these on and
off with like a you know a pound of fine
basically and it'll be a little bit
clearer what the heck is going on
so if up here I do a pound to fine
test light checkerboard now I should be
able to just have picking this test
light checkerboard code turn on and what
it should do if I can pilot now is I
should get like nothing on screen right
because I don't have any lighting
getting fed in there if I now initialize
these so light west is going to equal
some amount of light and light south
light north that's where we were packing
the normal information in so since we
don't really know what the normal
information should be necessarily I'm
just gonna pack it in as like all ones
or something or something like that so
we'll just say like light south is gonna
be like something like that which is not
really correct but I just need to stuff
something in there light Seth no sorry
it's like north so I just need to stuff
something in there so it'll be you know
relatively correct at all why am I not
seeing anything so light West those
should come in here right
I think that should be correct right
did I change the way the oh I did I
changed the encoding so that actually
wouldn't be very much light anymore cuz
it's biased now that's the problem okay
remember we biased our lights to do
specifically that sampling so I need
this to be brighter it needs to be at
least like a or up probably to be a
bright light yeah there we go alright so
that was definitely our problem alright
so you can see the sort of checkerboard
pattern here now obviously we don't
actually get a checkerboard pattern here
because we have interpolation turned on
you know what I mean
but if you look at like how dense the
checkerboard actually is in practice and
we could go turn interpolation off in
fact you know that's maybe somewhere do
you want to or taking a look at it but
if we look at how the interpolation is
working here you can see that it's still
a pretty dense voxel it could capture
some fairly even at the most zoomed out
that we would be it's still pretty you
know it's a it's a pretty dense sampling
and you can see like it would still be a
little wider like it's not we're not
like properly sizing the lighting region
at the lighting of observation at the
moment so you know it would be a little
wider than this but it is kind of an
open question to me is like did we
actually need it to be this dense right
and so what I want to see is just like
let's suppose I'm just curious and we're
not don't really need to go down a level
here so I'm not sure I will keep this
even if it works but I just want to know
so if we were to change the voxel
resolution here right so here's our
voxel if we changed it down to an even
less resolute voxel there right so
here's our are much less resolute voxel
so you can see that the bands are sort
of much bigger and blockier now right so
if we switch to something that's much
more a low resolution like that my
question is what happens if now we try
to reconstruct
the spherical light again I'm just
curious like how bad is it
as you look like how good is this
reconstruction filter like as we start
to step down the resolution of the
reconstruction what do we get right and
I don't know all right so I mean you
again really interesting I mean look at
how good that reconstruction is I mean
you would never know like look at how
detailed it is right and again that's
just because signed distance fields can
be reconstructed properly with bilinear
filtering and trilinear filtering right
and so you look it's like you would
never guess that the sampling that that
the actual image that you had to took
reconstruct that from was you know was
the this resolution right was was was
this right at that banding level I mean
another way to look at it would be like
you look at this and you see like this
the you know the the the sphere there
right and then you go to the OpenGL
layer and you turn off like geo linear
or something
right and now if we actually recompile
this and rerun the with it with the
render that doesn't have the bilinear
filtering turned on right our trailer
you're filtering then what you can see
is that's the actual resolution of the
light like that's what we're storing you
know I'm saying very very sparse there
right and it's it's just really
remarkable to me that we can reconstruct
lighting that smooth from something this
course and again that was just the
signed distance field was such a cool
thing to use there I just I'm really
stoked about that trick right so anyway
let's go ahead and now try to poke at
this thing and see what we can do so
what I determined last time and and I
don't know like I said I don't know
maybe we'll just maybe we'll just use it
at that low resolution I'm not sure I
don't know if that resolution gives us
enough verticality that is one thing I'm
a little concerned I don't know to what
extent we're getting sort of a I don't
know to what extent if we were at this
low resolution if we would get enough
gradation there I think we do you know I
mean it's crazy but I think we could get
away with a voxel that small right I
don't know I want to say we probably
could just looking at that right and
that would be so cool right I mean
that's such a small amount of
information it's really pretty neat
right
so anyway
if we come through here and we base to
say like okay you know we are gonna you
know use the reconstruction filter it
seems to work pretty well we want to
kind of do signed distance field
interpolation as much as possible
because to the extent that we can we
want to make sure that we interpolate
the boundaries of these things you know
well and so if we take a look at what we
want to encode now I think it's pretty
different than what we were encoding
because you know we switched that we
looked at the box model the you know the
the four corner box the 6/6 Direction
box model I think that's garbage I don't
think we want that we saw that it had
artifacts we used it so I think we kind
of want to change the way we're looking
at this problem and I think what we want
to do is look at it as there's some
number of signed distance fields for
lighting and we're going to output like
three signed distance fields or
something for lighting right something
like that so if you imagine how we might
encode these like imagine we did
something like a light field normal zero
light field color zero or something like
this and then we just have like a couple
of these so we're basically saying like
we are going to put down some light
fields the light fields will have a
normal and a color and it's up to the
lighting system at the head end to
generate something whatever that
something is generate something that
fits into these light fields well and it
can be reconstructed as part of the
lighting model that will be as
continuous as possible right and we know
that this is not it's not trivial to do
because the light fields it's not just
three lights in the world right we have
an arbitrary in irradiance sphere at
each light probe arbitrary lights coming
in bouncing off the
walls coming from direct light sources
somewhere come you know who knows what
it is
so the actual light that we have coming
in there's just like a ton of
information that we need there right and
so we need to encode these light fields
somehow and I'm gonna pick this way
temporarily it may be that we want
something more like spherical harmonics
or something about I'd since I don't
spend a lot of time thinking about
problems like those I I'm not sure
because basically like the way to look
at it is interpolating normals in a
light field versus interpolating
parameters of something like a like a
circle harmonic a spherical harmonic is
basically like decomposing a light
sphere in incoming light sphere into the
sum of functions that are like sinusoids
like or you could think of them as like
positive and negative lobes right and so
there's two ways we could look at this
problem one is we're gonna interpolate
light fields and we're sort of fixing
the directions where we are talking
about those and you know let me here
they are
so if you think about spherical
harmonics right what you're really
talking about is coefficients that tell
you which of these you are adding to
your light incoming light right
so what the first coefficient of your
spherical lighting is that just the
incoming light from everywhere so
there's a ubiquitous like ambient light
right it's just a base
it's a baseline value right the next set
of coefficients are one each for these
three different sort of directional
positive and negative lobes it doesn't
matter which one of these you think is
positive or negative really but
basically like positive being green and
negative being red right in this case so
whatever the coefficient is it adds
light here and subtracts light here
right then you have one more coefficient
adds light here subtract slight here one
more coefficient adds like here subtract
slight here so a four parameters
spherical harmonic deconstruction would
give you this much control over your
light right and you just have to
decompose whatever the amount of
lighting is that you thought you wanted
right you just need to decompose it into
that similarly if you wanted to go one
more step down the ladder
you could afford by adding four more
parameters unfortunately you kinda need
a fifth one here to capture that last
one if you want the one more rung down
right I don't know what people typically
do to try and jam eyes Eero one two in
to look if you want that extra level of
detail I'm not sure what they do but you
know we could also go hog-wild so if you
count how many there are here right
there's four here there's five here and
then there's seven here right and so 7
plus 5 right if you were to look at
these two levels together right like 7 7
plus 5 is 12 12 is 3 more of
three more like Technic texels right so
if you were to imagine storing these in
the voxel if you just go like well all
right we've got four elements here and
twelve elements here that's a total of
sixteen elements we could just do that
in our voxels right so we could do a
spherical harmonics version that was
basically just these lobes and
interpolate that right and that would
just work I think right and that's one
way to read that's the way we would
reconstruct our lighting it seems pretty
compelling right because we know we can
look up that many things in our voxel we
know that 16 lookups in the voxel is
only four voxel reeds right because each
one comes back as four elements and so
we could pretty easily say well you know
there's our spherical harmonics right
there and we just look it up and we do
the computation right so it has some
compelling features to it it seems
pretty reasonable but the problem that
you get into it pretty quickly if we
were to go that route which is
interesting probably would have right
off the bat no colored lights right
because these coefficients just tell you
the light the amount of light so if we
actually wanted colored lighting we
would need to multiply whatever value it
was by three right so our spherical
harmonics would be something like this
if we wanted to go all the way down to
to this rung here that's what we would
be looking at right it's arguable that
we don't really need to go that far down
right maybe that's too far down so maybe
we would only do nine here right 1 2 3 4
5 6 7 8 9 those nine parameters right
maybe we would just do nine and if we do
9 times 3 right
that's how many coefficients we would
need and we know we can look up four in
a go
so that would only be seven right so if
we just cut it down a little bit this
would be what we would be looking at
right one two three four five six seven
and we know we could do that no problem
so surreal harmonics down to l2 right
not a bad idea if I'm honest right it
seems kind of maybe sort of a little bit
not so much possibly uh who knows like
that could be interesting
and the reason that could be interesting
is because it gives us sort of a formal
way of figuring out how we're gonna talk
about the lighting right and you know
the I I guess like the alternative of
having a direction and a coefficient I
don't really know of any there's there's
not really a lot of ways we could
produce if we just wanted three light
fields so if we just did something that
looks like this then we're kind of off
again with with no particular
theoretical guidance as to how we
produce those fields it's kind of just a
random thing you know what I mean and so
while stuffing those directly with test
lights may be easy because we can
trivially produce three test fields by
just generating them directly that
doesn't help us when we go to take the
result of our ray tracing system and
dump it into these light fields the
question is well how you know like how
do you decompose something and what we
would need to do is like some kind of
like principal component analysis or
something right I mean we'd have to do
like well store some kind of a
you know stores store some kind of a
system that I don't even know so I'm not
sure so it kind of seems like you know I
believe that you can because these are
linear decompositions in a sense right
I'm pretty sure you can just add them
together right just make sure that's
true
as usual the wikipedia page is less than
easy to parse
but my assumption is we can just add the
coefficients or roughly there abouts
right since I never work with these I
can't say that definitively
unfortunately yes I know I don't care
about that well that's a cute little
so I guess I'm not sure
I mean here's what I'll say I would be
shocked if you can't do that because it
should be a decomposition that should be
able to be added together I mean that's
the whole point of the coefficients just
in the first place as they add together
so I can't see how you couldn't add them
but I just wanted someone to actually
say that who studies these for a living
just so I know that I'm not crazy
yeah
this is kind of a nice way to visualize
it don't you think so hear what they've
said it's basically like okay here are
the coefficients visualized by what they
do to a cube map essentially and that
makes it pretty easy to visualize much
much easier than this way I think right
because you can sort of see directly
what's happening on a cube map maybe
it's a little bit easier than trying to
picture what negative light means
they're right but yeah
did you do too
how is it possible that it's not just
stated in one of these things right up
front that you can add them together am
i like wrong somehow that you couldn't
have them together cuz that would be
weird looking at the math here I mean I
can't imagine why you couldn't but I
wanted someone to say that is that wrong
is it wrong Karina want someone to say
that
so yeah
hmm so I guess the problem here is I
would want to read about up on these a
little bit more because the fact that
that's just not said right off the bat
was a little weird to me and I'd like to
be more comfort than before I would pick
that as something that we would like try
directly I can't
I mean if it's if it's a decomposition
into a series of basis functions you
should just be able to add them together
right because the entire point of a
decomposition like that is that you are
summing them together in the first place
and so you should be able to sum you
know two separate decompositions
together it's important that that be
true because if that weren't true
it would make them very hard for us to
work with in the case that we actually
need to know which is to say we need to
update a state of these things you know
kind of as for each light probe and
whatever right um so yeah it's a little
bit weird there I and I'm not sure what
to make of that exactly the other thing
I would say is one problem we might have
if we try to do something like spherical
harmonics is I wonder if we would run
into the problem of not being able to do
negative interpolation like we're doing
I think we'd probably well no I probably
wouldn't so the prop the problem with
with 300 marks as well is that since
they have a positive and a negative lobe
it means that the trick of interpolating
past the zero value that we're using to
make the interpolation look good
currently might not work right because a
circle harmonics system is not one that
you can arbitrarily shift around like
that because it has an actual zero
around which it is defined and I guess
I'm just not sure like that I can
necessarily convince myself
that the trick of making sure you can
interpolate past the zero values would
actually work I think it might not so it
may be that we actually couldn't use
those even if it if they can be added
properly so I I guess maybe I'm not sure
that would really be good
I guess as much as I'm not sure how
exactly we will accomplish it I guess
I'm gonna start down this path with the
experimentation I'm a little nervous
about the spherical harmonic side of
things because I just don't necessarily
see the interpolation working properly
there on the sparse level it seems like
that might just introduce artifacts
again and maybe I'm wrong about that but
that seems like what would happen but
it's hard to say right let's start down
this road and we'll see how I feel about
it as we go so let's suppose we change
the sampler to be six samplers normal
plus color and we're just gonna leave it
like that for the moment right
light-filled yeah it should be like
field sampler there right what does will
keep it a slight sampler so it's pretty
confusing it's true but you know we'll
figure it out right well muddle through
it and we'll figure out what is
something that works well in this
scenario so if we change over to light
sampler and we've got like an N 0 C 0
and 1 C 1 and 2 C 2 there and then what
we do is we change the way this stuff's
working such that you know that that
doesn't happen anymore right and I guess
what I don't really know if there's a
good way to tell the graphics card in
this particular case you know maybe we
want it to use its own unpacking rules
so let me just take a quick gander to
see if there's something smart to do
here so
assuming we're gonna specify textures
you know here's sort of what we've got
right and if you look at how these
things are defined we could see is we
can just choose to use like an S norm
value or something right and an S norm
value is something that's gonna tell us
like something that's by normal looking
like when we encode the normal
we're encoding a positive negative x
positive negative Y pops and negative C
so you know using one of these RGB a
eight for example values it's not
probably what we want so we could easily
switch to something like this which
would allow us to encode something that
had signs in it so we don't have to do
the biasing ourselves it's just the
graphs card just does it automatically
which would probably be a faster path
right I don't know because I don't
necessarily know where they're just
insert shader instructions to fix that
or not or whether it's actually doing
the texture unit that probably depends
on the card but assuming it could do it
in the texture unit it's more efficient
less ops in the pixel shader right so
looking at this it's like well yeah
we've got some options honestly that
looks pretty compelling unfortunately
not signed we might still want to use it
right but what that is is it's saying
take the 32-bit value only encode three
things in it but get me more bits right
get me more bits of precision and that
seems pretty good right I mean that is
sort of what we would want for encoding
and normal in there and we would just
have to do the bias ourselves so that's
you know maybe that's not our favorite
thing but you know it it's something
certainly so I don't know that we've got
an option in standard GL here that would
give us that but signed you know I don't
see any formats in here that really do
that
[Music]
I mean there's versions where everything
16-bit but I think that's overkill you
know something like this I think would
be more what we would want but there's
no s norm version so I don't really see
any way of getting that for free just
looking at it
I I don't I don't see it so we may just
want to use a format like the r11 FG 11
FB 10 F we may just want to do that and
say like alright we know that we've got
11 bits 11 bits 10 bits so it's pretty
easy for us to encode negative values or
not R and R 11 G 11 or both pretty clear
you've got one bit for sign effectively
this one is unfortunately unbalanced so
this one has the normal bias problem
where you've got one bit one value more
on one side than the other so you know
not the end of the world though because
that would have been true that was true
for our 8-bit encodings as well so it's
you know that's not that's not a huge
deal either way but point being you know
we could just use something like that
which does seem pretty compelling I
guess at the end of the day right um so
maybe we try to do something like that
let me go ahead and and put that pound
to find in there and let's let's get
did I do that wrong
our 11f
yeah so we really just need this and we
could ask for these textures to be
stored in that format right gosh darnit
come on area so if we were to just say
look inside our texture creation inside
the OpenGL layer as we go we want these
samplers here to be using buffers that
are you know encoded a little bit
differently that shouldn't be too hard
so during an it when we actually specify
those textures in the first place which
is like right here so when we're
actually specifying these we could say
alright we actually want two separate
ones here so the lighting data in this
case actually is it's not stored
uniformly we want to do and well you
know honestly looking at it we could
choose to store them all this way right
because we also only need an RG and a B
value actually so you know we could
choose to store the colors this way as
well
I'm just not thrilled about that and the
reason I'm not thrilled about that is
because I don't super love for lighting
the idea that we wouldn't really be able
to represent gray if you have you know
more bits for orangey I'm worried that
we wouldn't be able to quite exactly
unpack those in a way that would would
allow me to do grays properly I don't
know or or you would it's not that you
couldn't do grays properly it's that you
need to do extra work to make sure you
didn't accidentally produce yellowish or
bluish light because of the fact that
you have more precision in your R's and
G's than you have in your B right so I
don't really love that so I guess what I
would say is yeah you know not not sure
I want quite exactly that but point
being if we go and look at the
the information we're actually storing
with the light data here then inside the
OpenGL light data array there we've got
light data handle which is this what I
think I'd like to do there is say like
let's lift this up into light fields
here where we say okay let's say we've
got light data handle and and lightly to
handle C and what we'll say is like we
don't know how many light Direction cats
we want so we're gonna just say like
we've got a max life Direction count
here and that way we can vary it because
in the future we may decide we only need
two or maybe we need four and since we
don't really have a good handle like
we're very much experimenting with this
and maybe what we won't say max maybe
we'll just say light Direction count
because honestly it's how many you use
that's how many you will be using period
right so let's say we just pick a number
for that and off we go then in here
where we've got the light data that
comes down we know that we're going to
have two different versions of the light
data that comes down here and so we're
going to have like a light Direction
count in two cases like this and we're
gonna have a normal and a color channel
like that and so again not really sure
how you want to do this but I'm just
kind of like giving us the pipeline to
have two different formats here so that
way we can try storing the normals with
something that's maybe a little bit
different than what we're using the
store the color values because the color
values are sort of getting packed in a
way that that makes us want to have like
HDR so RGB exponent kind of a packing
that's the way we're sort of looking at
it right now but the the normals on the
other hand are not that right the
normals are going to want to just be how
what's the best way we can reconstruct
three arbitrary values from negative
and off we go and just to underscore how
much different that might be you know
it's a normal right we know it's
normalized so in addition what we might
want to do is switch to literally just
like you know something that's more like
a 16-bit value where we've got like 7 7
or 7 8 1 right because we know that we
can encode the normal as just 2 values
right the X and the y and we can
reconstruct the Z by just taking the
square root of the squares of those
values right so because we know that
it's normalized to begin with we only
need one additional piece of information
to determine whether the normal is
pointing up or down basically and that's
the sign bit whatever the sign bit is on
the z value right so we may just encode
them this way and leave it that we may
want to go one step further and say we
can make this even more get even more
precision or take even less space
depending which one we want to go down
to 16 bits or stay at 32 but get more
precision in our normals by just
encoding them differently right so again
we I think we really want the
flexibility to encode our colors
differently from our normals because
there's a lot of ways that we could
consider encoding either of them and so
we probably want two different texture
formats would be my guess I doubt we're
gonna want the same texture format for
both of those lookups right that's just
my guess so anyway let's go ahead and
follow through the compile errors here
to guide us to all the things that we
need to replace in order to do that so
in this case here you can see all I'm
really doing is saying hey let's take
these handles right and actually
construct them like so based on how many
there are in each one so we're doing
both of those then what we'd like to do
is loop over them separately so in these
two cases like I'm actually I'd like to
make two separate ones right i I just
don't think I necessarily need to be
that sort of verbose because you know
well you know maybe cuz what if we want
to do what's not unit yeah so I'm gonna
say light Direction count goes here and
I'm just gonna go ahead and say that
it's always symmetric like that all
right so when we come in here what we do
is we're going to set up these and I
need to take this this value that we
were using here and put it up here where
we're doing our our GL identifiers so
here's here's a bunch of formats and
here's one more format that we want
there so when I actually go to do this
we're gonna generate texture handles for
the normal texture and the color texture
we're going to do a light Direction
count of each of them and then here
we're going to like specify them so the
first thing I do is I specify the the
light data handle for the normal let's
say and then the next thing I do is do
the same thing but for the color right
now the color probably stays the way it
is right so that's probably what color
does look like because it we're gonna
encoding on exactly the same way however
the normal doesn't the normal we're sort
of saying look we're gonna ingest this
somehow and then you're gonna encode it
like this right and what I don't know
I'll be completely honest with you is I
don't really know what the hey they want
you to say they're in terms of how this
stuff comes down the pipeline right so
like if I want to specify one of these
how do I give that information to the
actual graphics card right and I do not
know so it would be nice if that were
sort of discussed somewhere what I'm
going to guess is that if I look at the
original extent
that talks about when this was added up
in jail somebody will tell me how to
actually submit these but I don't know
so let's find out right where these are
supposedly going to go so it looks like
you just couldn't specify them anyway
you otherwise would maybe right so right
so I don't know maybe what we would do
here is is specify these this float and
let it do the packing because three
floats versus 32 bits I don't know maybe
we want to compress those first maybe we
don't I'm not sure but I'm gonna go
ahead and say at least for the moment
we're not going to do that and so what
I'm gonna do is say look we're gonna
specify this as RGB floats and you will
compress it into RGB this way and so
those arrays now will not come down as
any kind of weird pack nonsense instead
they're gonna be just the original
floating point data and you can go ahead
and do whatever you want to do with them
right again maybe that's stupid maybe
it's not I don't know we're making this
up as we go along here so I don't have
any preconceived notions of what has to
happen there if we do look at how we're
gonna submit them though then what we
would end up saying is well these are
gonna be F 32s right in a sense
not really more like VIII's right so
we're gonna specify a set of VIII's the
light probe position stuff again is not
stuff we actually send down so it's
really we kind of want to isolate this a
little bit say alright this is what this
this is the actual lighting bundle this
stuff is stuff used in lighting
computation right but we don't need to
send it down to the grams card yet
someday maybe we do the r-tx
implementation of this stuff and we do
send it down the grass garden be like
here you go but at the moment you know
we're not we're not doing that so what
we're doing instead is we're just saying
look we're gonna submit these ourselves
here we're gonna submit the normals as
normals now okay so after we generate
that out I don't think there's anything
else necessarily we need to do here
the Clara data will stay the same it's
the normal data that will change we're
gonna have to go to the command buffer
here and say that also needs to change
when you look at how these things are
getting sent down here you know all of
this stuff is kind of a little bit wrong
now as well so if we look at like yeah I
don't know yeah a lot of the stuff is
kind of incorrect so if we look at
what's coming down here we've got the
well actually hold on a second
I'm not actually sure exactly how those
were getting pushed so let me just check
real quick okay so basically this is now
just wrong you know what I mean because
we remember even calling it the wrong
thing because it's not a light index
voxel anymore but you know what you're
gonna do so this is gonna be the
lightbox hole and this is light voxel
see and this is light box land right and
what we want to do here is just say all
right it's not six anymore anyway it's
three I guess in a sense and we're just
gonna have three pointers to the to the
different pieces of data that's going to
come down right that's what we were sort
of saying before and now instead of au
32 here that's gonna be a V 3 so that's
what we want to actually provide and
then the light box the difference tells
you how big those things are so you know
how to pack the values into them and
alternatively we could just expect you
to stride it but I'm not gonna do that
I'm gonna put them in this way right so
now we go ahead and recompile and again
just let the compiler tell us where we
need to fix this stuff so the light box
will dim here right this is just going
to change to being called that and then
what we need to specify here is actually
when we're packing the commands in here
we just need to say like oh here's where
the oops here's where the ends are
here's where the C's are and now we just
have 0 1 2 right and what I'd like to do
there is say well can't we just make
this be a little bit more specific
though and make it so that this will
grow as we need it to write because we
may want to change that pound to fine so
I think I'm gonna instead do this way
where we do like you know index here and
I just say light Direction count so that
way if we decide we want more of these
in the future we just get them and we
don't have to rework this code at all
so what I want to do is this right and I
just want to say you know initialize
these out to the light data that we
are asking you a store here and
hopefully that just kind of works that
is apparently not called that it's just
called light and might see let's make it
called light data instead all right
again this now needs to kind of change a
little bit so when we're submitting
these textures we need to submit both
versions of the textures so here we're
actually going to be saying like light
Direction counts yeah
and here we're going to be data handled
so now I don't know what's got a light
data handle but it's just know whatever
doesn't um so anyway here we're gonna be
binding twice now we're gonna be binding
to the see handle and to the N handle
right so as we go through here now we
need to submit these differently the C
handle will still look exactly the way
that it did the N handle will not that
we'll be submitting actual
floating-point data here and that should
just work hopefully famous last words in
GPU land but what can you do right we
have not that many more to go you can
see here we need to actually bind these
things and so we're gonna have to figure
out how exactly we want them found my
sort of assumption here is we bind as
well just bind them alternatingly
exactly as we were before so maybe we
just do this here and we say that it
looks like that so we have the N and the
C's alternating so we start it - and we
multiply this value by two and we just
line them up in that order right and
that's if we want them interleaved if we
didn't want them interleaved then we
would just do two loops and be done with
it but I think that seems fine right for
now
such NC NC NC okay
moving on we need up so that's like
blocks with him now moving on we need
some way of actually some art summer in
here when we're doing our lighting we
should actually I guess we have to
change it in the BM Z bias program cuz I
don't think we gonna get an error on it
but we need to actually fix it somewhere
in the the in the in the swing of things
we're gonna have to actually put in a
thing somewhere that will properly query
those in fact I'm just gonna do that
while I'm thinking of it instead of
finishing what's doing there because I
just don't want to forget and not do
this because we need to do it so you can
see we got the light samplers here NC NC
NC and so what we need to do is make
sure that those are lined up well you
know what I didn't need to do it cuz I
already did it it's gonna say we need to
make sure those are lined up properly
and so now they are right alright so
that seems fine
nevermind in here where we've got our
light box we'll fill out this routine
needs to now change and that's because
looking at the light voxels now this
doesn't really make any sense so what we
effectively have now instead of what we
were doing before here and also by the
way we might as well do like something
like this
just in case we want to change that
addressing scheme no sense cutting and
pasting it all over the place like that
so when we stream this thing out and
we've got our light voxels off we go you
know another thing that that honestly we
will probably want to look into and I
don't really know to what extent we have
the ability to do this but really these
are all one voxel the only reason we
have multiple boxes because we're trying
to just make sure that we can just do
standard encoding right and the problem
is that we don't really have any way of
saying to the grams card that I know of
in OpenGL 3 I don't know if there's a
way to say look we just have one lookup
we want you know 32 color values right
so I don't know if there's any way to
really do that but you know it's worth
noting these voxels are not really
voxels they're not only six voxels
they're one voxel that has six values in
it and I just don't know any simpler way
to in OpenGL 3 to say hey just do this
right um so if we're gonna supply these
values I guess what I would say is right
now I think we can only specify the
first one temporarily and we'll actually
sort of put stuff into these a little
bit later on and so I'm gonna say that
we're gonna specify here the N and the C
this will be like light and 0 this will
be light C 0 and so a lot of this stuff
now is not correct right so we're gonna
have to rewrite this code a little bit
test light checkerboard is probably
pretty easy we're just saying that the
light normal in this case right it's
gonna be a v3 and who knows what the v3
should be you know maybe it's that I
don't know I don't care but the light
color in this case is actually fine it's
exactly what we were doing before and so
what we were stuffing into light West is
just what we will stuff into the color
value now you know what I'm saying
so that looks like this and good you
know good deal
when we come up here and we take a look
at what this is doing then again right
the test light smear part of things
which we kind of want to change a little
bit and I'm gonna actually make this
have the variables we now need so when
we come through and do the light test
sphere now we don't really need to do
any more of this like crazy dancing to
like do the light north/south pact right
the light and zero just is the value so
right here where we do light and like
that all we need to do is like a sign
that so we just do light and zero equals
light in and that packs it light see
zero now just needs to be whatever the
light westpac would have been right and
the rest of this stuff goes away goodbye
right and so that's the entire repacking
of the sphere now and when you're
looking here you can see like alright we
don't really care about this stuff this
is now not necessary either and none of
that is necessary and none of this is
necessary it's all nonsense so really
all we need to do here is where we pack
in the light alpha value here where I
was doing that it's really just this and
then we're done right so I think that's
all we really need to do to pack these
values to place these values into the
voxel properly and then oops I need to
clear those now and then we just need to
clean up our compilers and debug the
lightbox look here where we are
assigning it again just needs the NCS I
don't know why I skipped those this is
gonna need to be a cleared v3 I guess
well you know what I specified these at
the top now so I can actually fill them
all out and then we can start playing
with them up in the loop which is what I
wanted to do anyway
right it's kind of caps lock value on
there that this messing with me all
right caps lock do we still need it why
is it there
I used to rebind it to control but I
like those keyboards use it just does
that automatically for you all right and
so now um I guess we don't know what
will happen but probably we need to fix
some things
oh right duh we haven't rewritten our
shader so last thing is we got a call
this get irradiance function with the
correct stuff right and so when we look
at the samplers in here and we're
pulling with these values out we need to
start talking about these in terms of
not our weird cube anymore I mean to say
like let's get rid of that that's not
relevant and so we need to start
sampling based on like the normal and
all that sort of stuff
so what we want to do here is say all
right we're gonna have three of these
geta radiances and what we're gonna do
there is say we've got a light c0 c1 c2
and then we've got a light n 0 n 1 n 2
right and we don't care about any of
this crap anymore because we can
directly encode normals now the grass
card is like doing that work for us
right
furthermore this doesn't need to look
like that this can just look like this
so we can basically just get the
irradiance that way right all right so
that's all good and and fine and
whatever when we come through here and
we're doing our sunlight when we're
actually doing our lookups now what
these will look like is we've got a
Caesar or lookup and n0 lookup right
the n0 lookups the N lookups will all
just be looking at the XYZ components
because we no longer will have anything
in the Alpha Channel it'll just be blank
so we don't want to look at that because
it's encoding it like the encoding we
chose was RGB so the Alpha Channel will
not have something in it it's it's a non
channel for it we only get three
channels out of our texture lookup the C
does get four just as it did
previously so that's all fine this is
what our total lookup looks like now and
then the irradiance happens as it would
have happened before this should all be
basically the same the coatings are all
the same the only difference now is
instead of the light Direction being
hard-coded to a box it's actually coming
in as its own channel right and you know
color me a little bit surprised that
that worked the first time out what I
will say is it's not correct so we still
do have an issue here if you look at the
way that this is responding the normals
seem incorrect they're right and I guess
you know what I just realized we didn't
I forgot I literally said this and then
forgot that RGB encoding doesn't supply
normal by normal right
that RGB encoding I literally said this
and then just completely forgot as I was
making all those changes right I it
doesn't do the positive negatives for us
right that's the problem so it like this
they're not signed we want them signed
they're not signed and so we
fundamentally have to figure out how
we're gonna reconstruct signed values
from those values and there's a lot of
ways that we could do that right but I
guess what I would say is when we come
in here to do get irradiance when we
have this light normal and this light
value and you can see us like decoding
that stuff in here like for example you
can see the light color getting decoded
this way
we now need the light normal to be
encoded as well so this light n is not
really a light n it's like a light and
coded right and in order to produce the
light n we need to actually do some real
work unfortunately
right
so in order to produce a light end from
a light and ink what we need to do is we
need to to bias we need to scale it and
bias it so it's zero to one right now so
we need to again multiply it out by two
then we need to subtract what is
effectively the the midpoint now right
so it's going from zero to one we need
to like bias it out to zero to two and
shift it down to get it to be negative
one to one right so we can do that and
now we'll get normals out that are full
range but hey guess what we're not
packing them at full range yet so we
need to first shift them up when we
actually plug them into the shader the
opengl system in the first place so when
we go to our lighting in code right like
this we need to actually do the encode
here right so the irradiance pack like
we have here we now need a normal pack
right
and we need this pack to just shift up
and you know you don't really need to
call it a bite we could just put it like
by normal can we actually already have
something like this like by normal to
something
not really no um so we need like a buy
normal pack here something like that
right and so then we can have a function
that much like our irradiance pack there
where we've got something that takes in
an N value and produces the result value
that is the scaled and biased version of
this thing right something like this
so we basically like we have we have the
value and then shift it up so we know
that it's between 0 &amp; 1 right and it's
just the inverse operation of what we
like did in the in the shader that's and
that's it so now hopefully our normal
encoding is working correctly and it
does look like it is now right you can
see that as we move the light so that
those faces are back facing to the light
they get no light which is what we're
you know that's what this test seer is
designed to do give us exact
reproducible things we can test it does
seem like that to me it's working on all
the different kinds of faces it looks
like so that looks pretty convincing so
I think we're packing those down
properly now let's do a quick test here
if I want to spam in another value so
you know in here where I've got the end
lighting computation where we're
spamming in test lighting values if I
want to produce some sort of a secondary
light source so you can see here like
how this nonsense is working right
you've got the light and the light
distance right that stuff happening for
the first light and so if we wanted to
do this for more than one light right
like we wanted to have a couple
different lights that get placed in here
what I we need is some idea of where the
other light actually is right and so I
would need you know a second light
source I don't know where that should be
but what you could imagine is like let's
suppose I create a light to UVW here and
I guess honestly like you know maybe we
do this with a four of the person and I
won't bother um so here you know we put
the light Pete and if I wanted to have a
second light P I could say that like b2
equals light P plus some fixed offset so
let's suppose I want another light
source that's just like always three
meters to the other side or something
right
maybe that's not enough like let's talk
about five meters I don't know so
supposing I wanted to move the light
source five meters away in the X
direction we'll just try that and maybe
we say like okay we're gonna use me
we're gonna compute that now so I'm
gonna take this snippet of code which is
just like a little like reproducible
snippet again I'm just doing test code
here ordinarily if I thought I was
actually gonna do this a lot I'd
actually pull that out into a function
probably I'm not gonna bother right now
just gonna leave it in here and what I'm
gonna do is since we now have a light to
UV you can see that there Y is this I
don't even know why that's not just that
don't ask me but I'm now gonna switch to
using the second lady so now we have a
secondary light here and you can see
that we're like computing that light
source differently all I'm gonna do is
I'm just gonna switch it to having that
second light go out on the second
channel and so all I want to see here is
if that will actually work at all and
just kind of start to look massage that
into place right so now we should have
two lights and you can see that there
they are actually both where they should
be it looks like so now we've created
kind of a blob with the other light kind
of separated from this light and in
theory right I should be able to
separate them even more if I want to so
if I came in here and I wanted to look a
little bit more closely at that shape
you know let's say I spread it out by 10
now and we wait for that recompile
reload we should see that jump to the
side yeah and maybe like a little bit
more like that so I can see the
interference pattern between the two
lights where they start and stop and
that stuff right so you can see that
looks pretty reasonable there right now
let's get them overlap a little more I'm
gonna change the color values here so
we've got two different colors values
maybe I will drop the blue so we got a
yellow light and drop the red so we have
a cyan light as well so we can just kind
of see the colored regions of these two
which should you know hopefully
interpolate properly as well so there's
our two right separate color lights that
were reconstructing there and then what
I'm gonna do is like smoosh those
together so now the light separation
let's make that more like eight so
they'll be an overlap region and it
should be like white ish in the overlap
region because you've got two light
sources that are combining they're in
theory and you know it sort of is right
it's more white anyway right and of
course since these two lights are
actually in different places what should
happen is I rotate around twos I should
see some play of the light and I do
which is good right because there is a
little bit of specular on these services
now I could really crank that up to like
if we wanted to we could we could take a
look at what happens with
specular a little bit more but you can
see like you see how they're getting
that specular on there a little bit
right you see it and that's kind of a
nice effect too
again not something we're really going
to lean into in this particular game but
you know it's nice to have a little bit
of specular option in there for just
getting a little bit of that it just it
just adds a little character to the
lighting you know it's great if you want
to go full bore and have actual like
reflective services and stuff like that
yeah that's awesome too we're not really
looking for that here we're not looking
to solve that particular problem but in
this case we do get a little bit of a
character in there and adding a little
bit of specular character to light can
can be useful all right so I think this
is looking great and to me that just
says yeah like I think this has a lot of
potential so now the question is how do
we get from light probes to this in in a
reasonable way right and I do think you
know I mean one thing is we probably
have too many light probes I mean just
looking at how many there are it's like
do we really need that many of light
probes and the answer is probably no but
we're gonna stick with that many for now
and then we'll just like start to
decrease the number of light probes that
we have as necessary right and we'll
start to work with that a little bit
different but I guess what I would say
is you know as a light sampling scheme I
think this is pretty good if you get
more than three lights and you know
again we could also just crank that up
to four lights and I don't think we
would see a lot of problems right if I
we don't we have to actually like have a
way to turn off lighting on the profiler
which we haven't done yet like our
profiler is still being lit
unfortunately not exactly what we want
to be sure but you know that's that's
that's just you know how graphics go
sometimes right everything is going
through the same pipeline at the moment
and we just don't have a flag for that
so we're gonna have to do that at some
point not my fault that's just how
things go right
but anyway looking in general at the
speed though if I was to firebend site
here and just ask it to tell me how bad
is this situation
in terms of speed there right so if I
grab our you know our project and ask it
to launch the frame profile you know
like what you know and video what do you
see right and you know looking at this
graphics card it's just it's eating that
for breakfast like that three voxel
samples it's just like laughing at and
telling me that doesn't care at all or
three six you know three pairs of box of
samples so you know it means we could
really decompose this into a large
number of these things I think and not
really have to worry that much about it
so we could probably even go to four
light channels and not really break a
sweat right because one hundred and
sixty frames per second is way more than
the number of frames per second then I
felt like I needed that that's way over
the spec that I've demanded this game be
at and so I'm okay with that
right so if we wanted to crank that up
and just say let's have a lot of these
right you know maybe I I just say like
let's have four lights total we can
blend between and that's just a crazy
because remember this is like every
voxel can capture for incoming light
directions which is probably like way
overkill I just want to see if we can do
it right I just want to see if that has
really any problems for us whatsoever so
let's say we've got a bunch of these
here and I just want to do like this
right so we've got like some stuff and
it's happening and whatever
and if I create three four so three
dependent light sources off of the one
light source there I stuff them in here
and I give them some other you know
color characteristics so you know maybe
we've we've actually got like you know a
red dennah green and a blue light there
that are separating then you know here
I've got some other light maybe maybe
like
a dimmer sort of white light or
something or maybe that's just a pure
white light I don't know I don't care so
we've got some lights in there red green
and blue and now I just want to stuff
those lights into the system so when we
come through here we're just gonna do
like alright here's our our four light
directions that's how many you get so
you know hopefully you can encode
whatever complex light feel if you want
with somehow decomposing it into four
light directions which is you know or or
someday we switch again to some other
encoding spherical harmonics I don't
know what but you know whatever we think
of whatever we end up thinking is right
we encode right so we've got the the
light directions here we switched the
oops light direction count here - four
we recompile and cross our fingers I
don't know if there's anywhere else that
it matters to be honest might not and
then we see if we can make that happen
in a useful way
all right so here's our lights if we
zoom out I I guess I don't see my third
light which makes me a little concerned
right so I've got the three lights but I
don't see the fourth even though the
light Direction count is ostensibly for
looking at our four UVW sir did I forget
three - I didn't zero one two three zero
one two three sure seems oh yeah hey man
you've got to actually load it in the
shader that's the one thing that's not
based on eraser I haven't been using
arrays and the shaders you actually can
I'm nervous about it because I don't
know what kind of OpenGL 3 compatibility
there are two arrays of samplers so it's
really just a fear it's really it's a
fear based things reason about doing it
you you absolutely could have done that
and so it's just kind of
no real reason so I apologize for that
I'm just I'm just not willing to go down
that speed lankan path at the immediate
moment but you know that that there's no
reason we couldn't have made that be
something in the shader that was just
parametrized as well we just are a
little worried about it all right um
oops forgot one more thing uh so in
theory now we should have bound all of
our textures up and yeah and hopefully
we'll get our four lights now it looks
good right so there's our four lights
they seem pretty good they look like
they're in the right places not seeing
anything particularly odd going on there
looks good right and so I think that
should be fine if you look at what's
happening the lights right now you can
see they're already fairly complicated
like you're getting fairly complicated
effects from them you can see that nice
specular character you see how the red
light kind of plays off a little bit
there right and you get a little bit of
shifting of the highlight so I think
we're in good shape and I guess that's
good enough for me right I'm willing to
say great ship it now we just need a way
of putting light information into here
that's gonna be good we've got a few
minutes left so maybe let's start down
that road we can now go ahead and
actually say let's let's output the
probes right and the probe output is
totally borked right now because we now
need some we need some way and this this
again again this is gonna be the hard
part now we need some way of taking our
probes and dumping probes down into the
voxel in some way that makes you know
any sense whatsoever right
and there's a lot of ways we could do
this but I think probably fundamentally
speaking this is maybe not a very good
way to do it because since we're trying
to do reconstructing of light fields
here I don't really think like we may
more want to loop over the probes
themselves and sum them into the voxel
as opposed to doing it this way which is
using the light closest voxel the
closest probe to the voxel to fill that
voxel so I don't really know that this
makes a lot of sense like the way that
this is this particular thing is working
doesn't strike me as particularly
intelligent really anyway so I don't
know that we really want that right and
so we're probably gonna want to make
this be a little bit more what we're
gonna want to do here is say alright the
light probes are just things that store
loading information over time and
they're the locations at which we try to
compute what the light field is right
but what we're fundamentally doing now
is now that we sort of know well we can
use these fairly cheap try linear voxel
lookups to actually capture letting
information pretty well it seems what
we're trying to do now is say how do we
separate how do we actually track and
separate light into four components
whose directions can vary arbitrarily
right and again this may be stupid it
may be that we should just use spherical
harmonics or something right but the
reason I'm just not sure about them is I
just don't know how their behavior as a
signed distance field would actually
work out I suspect it if if I were
actually doing this on my own time and
could spend you know an 80 hours this
week
just like diving into this and trying
all kinds of crazy stuff what I would
first probably try to do is figure out
if there's a version of a circle
Harmonix encoding that can work with a
signed distance field because that's the
probably what you want right
in this particular case I don't actually
know exactly how I'm going to do
something here where we have to actually
track directions and that's why I think
that maybe the other way to do it would
be interesting but in the absence of
that we're gonna have to make something
up because we don't have 80 hours to
spend 80 hours to put that in
perspective we'd be probably like
another 20% of the entire time of
handmade hero so far or something like
that right handmade hero despite having
a day number that's really more like an
hour number or half an hour number so
like you're talking about a thousand
hours we probably spent on handmade hero
is all that's total time so the amount
of work I would do in two weeks of
exploration if something could be you
know a tenth of the entire time we spent
on handmade hero so far just to put in
perspective how limited a resource we
actually have time time actually is on
here we just don't get much time right
and so you know that's just a limitation
of the streaming format it doesn't
really work that way so what I want to
do here is start to figure out like well
how what are we gonna do how are we
gonna make this stuff makes sense like
what's gonna happen and so if you think
about what's going on we effectively
have a we effectively have sort of a
we are going to be tracking lights that
we see in the world using ray casting
right and so all we're gonna know when
we get back a ray cast is we're just
gonna set have a thing that says well we
kind of know that in this direction we
saw a light that was this bright like we
saw lighting coming in that was this
much lighting and so if you sort of
imagine how we're gonna track that
information the question becomes well
what is the thing that allows us to just
over time some lights together but that
we can then reconstruct a lighting field
from it in some way and I really just
don't know right look I don't have an
idea of how to do that one way might be
and maybe this is something we should
start with because hey it would give us
a way of transitioning later but one way
might be to say well on the CPU side
maybe our light probes just store
spherical harmonics exactly since we
they don't have to be interpolated
really right and then what we do is we
just extract the top and lights from the
circle harmonics and put those down as
the light field right and then if later
we decided we actually want to just
interpolate spherical harmonics directly
in the actual shader from the samples
instead because we figure out we can
actually do that with off your artifact
which I'm not sure we can but let's say
we could then we're in good shape to do
that because what we're actually
tracking is spherical harmonics so it's
not so hard anymore to like make that
work right I don't know right I wish I
had the answer I'm not sure we're more
or less at a time so I probably won't
really do anything here because I'm not
even sure what I would necessarily do so
I guess I'll leave this on sphere and
we'll go to the QA and then we're gonna
think like next weekend that'll be kind
of what we need to figure out right like
what what are we actually doing right
like what what will be the strategy
there now that we know it's pretty easy
to reconstruct light fields from voxel
you know it it's it's pretty interesting
right and I mean it's worth kind of
noting that like at this point - another
thing is is you know let's say you had
lots and lots of light sources in there
and you just wanted them radial you
could actually simulate lots of like you
know you could simulate a hundred radio
light sources with just this lookup
scheme without changing the number of
voxels because you just use the four
brightest ones at any given point right
so yeah I'm pretty I'm chuffed to bits
as they say I just now need to think
about how I want to like dump the
information down to the sampler and you
know maybe make some changes the sampler
as we go based on what the right values
to interpolate actually are
another interesting possibility here as
I'm thinking it through as well is you
know the way that this is being coding
you could also think of the color
channel as being a separate thing like
we could have we could track colors
differently from the way that we track
intensities because the eye is more
sensitive to intensities than color and
so if the color was more of a wash but
the intensities is the thing that's
actually getting interpolated by science
films that may make it easier for us
because then we could sort of we could
play it a little faster and looser when
we're actually at summation time so be
it'll be interesting to see but I'm
pretty pleased all right let's go ahead
and go to QA
have you taken anything you implanted
and handmade here and used it in your
other work um no not yet but I probably
will take the PNG stuff we did and move
that over to my own little PNG like I'll
probably optimize it and make a little
PNG file that I use because right now
like I mostly only do Photoshop IO and
it would be nice to have a PNG IO as
well so PNG IO
might be might be something my steal
because I'd never implemented one of
those and we have Lim downstream and
that went really well and now that I
have a reference code for I could make a
nice fast one and what are you working
on during the week well I am the
programmer the only programmer at Mali
Rockets so you know we have several
projects this one is one of them there's
one that's unannounced and then of
course we also do this one although I my
involvement this one is limited so
that's what I work on during the week
but you can also go here for sort of our
general news and just information about
our projects this tends to be up on here
also the thing you can do is if you
click this button kind of a little
hidden feature if you click the head at
the top of any Mali rocket page you can
get all the other Mali rocket pages
right so it's pretty easy to like link
them together and like jump around so
like I had been here all right you can
get to me out of the infinite if you got
mount the infinite you can get to 1935
right
you need to Anna draws it get to my blog
that's pretty easy
how will wall stop light same bouncing
rays as before yeah pretty much
so the main thing that we have to do now
and and it's the part that I'm not like
I said I'm not sure how we're gonna do
it exactly so I like the sampling it's
interesting but we may need to play
around a little bit the main thing we
need to now is so now we re enable the
ray caster right which we wrote and that
will tell us how the light moves around
the scene but the problem is we have to
figure out how to translate a ray
tracing input into a try linearly
reconstruct Abal set of light fields
right and that is the thing that I don't
know like exactly how we will do right
I may do something really nutso first
right
I assume there's a source of income not
working on projects for pay well we have
some limited sources of income but we
are we're also funded through basically
1935 s completion but we have to pay
that back right so we may you know we
may just disappear and be out of
business after that if our games don't
make some money back so who knows but we
do have some limited sources of income
as well like you know for example
handmade hero purchases is income it's
not much but it's something and and so
on but yeah until our actual games start
coming out and our purchasable it's hard
to know what will be successful and
still exist similarly now the infinite I
think it's actually a really good comic
to be completely honest I know I'm
biased because obviously like I wouldn't
have greenlit it if I didn't think it
was cool but I think as it gets a little
more established to it and you can buy
an actual bound book of it I think it'll
be pretty popular too it's already
pretty popular with kids actually and
it's kind of an all-ages thing I don't
know I think it's pretty good and I
think I think as it gets further along
it kind of becomes more clear that's
it's actually pretty interesting that's
what I would say so I think that'll also
make some money too but anything that's
like comic like that that tells kind of
a story kind of has to get to the point
where it's actually more complete and
furthermore people don't really like
reading comics online you know they only
kind of comics they like to read online
like Dilbert kind of things or you know
like the oatmeal or xkcd where they're
kind of like they're not really like a
story they're like social commentary or
something where you just read one page
and that's it so we don't really know
how successful that project will be
either because we'll have to see what
happens when we actually take it to some
cons and have a printed volume be like
here's book 1 you know let's see whether
people like it right so I think that
might make some money as well so we do
have some limited income now but we'll
really only know what our income
situation is after 1935 and
our unannounced project are available
and selling and whether anyone buys them
right I hope they do
any to Utrecht you'd you realize you
could be a very wealthy man if you
accept a small project for a few weeks
right I not really at least not that I
know of I have had you know pretty good
consulting rates in the past certainly
but you know one of the problems with
running a company in the u.s. especially
in a place like Seattle or haven't
helped you like I I shed emotional tears
for John blow like every day inside a
little bit running a company in San
Francisco right it's just like oh my god
the cost of living in the cost of
employee is here or contractor work is
like astronomical you know and so the
problem is that you're talking about
making a game you know you're looking at
like a million dollars or something of
cost to make a game if you want it to be
like a serious game like that's good and
it has good art on it and stuff like
that
if you're in these areas it's very
expensive right and it's it's not it's
it's it varies by region dramatically
right like the cost to make a game in
San Francisco we're talking about people
working you know actual employees
working essentially the cost to make you
came to San Francisco versus the cosmic
game in Croatia versus the cost to make
a game in Argentina or whatever right
it's very different and it's not because
the people are better right it's just
the it's just the cost of that area
right because there are great developers
in other parts of the world they just
happen to live in places that are a lot
lower cost of living right and so I
guess all I would say is there's not
much I can do to as an individual taking
a project for a month or two that would
pay me enough money that it would matter
to the success of the company right no
one's gonna pay me like five million
dollars to do a three-month project
if you are please email me right but no
one's gonna do that right you can make a
ton of money in like a jackpot fashion
by like doing something like working for
a startup company in getting a lot of
stock right and like cashing out or
something like that right but
realistically if you're just talking
about contract programming there I don't
know of anywhere where you can get like
literally millions of dollars for short
term work and the reality of the
situation is that trying to make games
in high-priced regions you're talking
about money on that scale and it's it
sucks I you know it does but you know
sometimes you just get unlucky and
that's where you live right and and you
know maybe we should all move to Montana
and we probably should I don't know why
we're still sticking around right but we
could all move to Montana and for the
same amount that you're paying every
month in rent in Seattle or San
Francisco you could own you know the
state of Montana right and so I think
like to a large extent the there's a lot
of disparity and it's just because you
know web companies and stuff generate an
unfair amount of money largely due to
the fact that they have an unfair
playing field you know at the risk of
the a long digression into economics you
know most of what the reason why we have
these incredible wealth concentrations
in a few places is is pretty much just
100% unfair competition right
period and the reason I say that is
because if you look at a company like
for example Facebook and you're like how
is it that this company is able to be so
wealthy the answer is very simple they
are exempt from most of the laws that
other people had to actually obey that's
why if they actually have
to follow copyright law they would be
out of business already the number of
lawsuits they would have had to settle
for copyright infringement alone
Facebook wouldn't exist right and so you
look at a lot of the reasons why web
companies exist at all it's because of
unfair competition they haven't had to
comply with the same laws that all
existing companies have had to comply
with and that's really why they're
wealthy it's no surprise when you have
people who can basically you know not
have any regulation that they beat a
bunch of companies that have to be
regulated right and that's just the way
it works so there's not much you can
really do about that and eventually that
won't be true because what you know this
is always the progress of industry you
know in the old days there used to be
things called company towns in the US
for example right a company owned a town
they ran the post office they were the
governor right or the mayor right they
supplied the police effectively right
they made the law that's what happens at
the start of a new type of Industry when
they are settling something eventually
an ende wealth concentration is
phenomenal right this is what happened
in the settling of the united states as
well right and that is because it is
largely lawless right it has not been
reined in and people are doing whatever
they want no I'm saying that's what
happened with technology right that's
what happened with the internet and
eventually you know people don't
probably appreciate it as much but
that's what will happen to the internet
as well so governments are now
regulating it like crazy gdpr is a very
good example of the EU saying you know
what we've got a bunch of rules we're
going to impose the EU is thinking of
imposing rules like click wrappings
rules and stuff like you you have to pay
you link to things right and what that
is is just not unusual and it's not
government overreach or anything like
that any more than any of these other
things are what it is is government
eventually moves in to regulate things
once they are important and once they're
valuable right
and once those laws arrive all of this
stuff normalizes out right because now
it's a level playing field and the
government wants their take and the
government takes control and it's no
longer a giant party where you are the
government and you take all the taxes
right so that's really what we've seen
and for people who are either you could
argue lucky enough or maybe you want to
say unlucky enough to live in the
centers where these effectively lawless
corporations have been occupying the
physical real estate well big surprise
everything is incredibly expensive
because they have effectively unlimited
money because they have been able to
conduct business outside of any
regulations and as you might expect
anything unregulated beats things that
are regulated and that's where the money
moves right so for those of us who live
in Seattle or San Francisco or a couple
other places that are similar what ends
up happening is you know you have to
like rise with those rates and there's
nothing you can really do about it you
can move away if you want to and that's
certainly an option it's an option I
would consider right or you can stay and
you have to basically like be really
competitive and you have to be much
better than you would have to otherwise
be right that's the life this is just
how the world works there's no sense
crying about it it's just how it is and
so I moved to Seattle in 1995 my first
apartment cost four hundred ninety five
dollars a month and it was totally fine
wasn't a nice place but I mean it wasn't
even on the ground floor there's a third
floor apartment for four hundred ninety
five dollars a month that same apartment
probably now costs at least eighteen
hundred dollars a month would be my desk
and I doubt it's been renovated at all
this
the same and so you know I just I never
left so I'm stuck with it that's just
the way it is now it's worth noting that
it benefited me though because during
the time that I did work in mystery I
was able to stockpile some money so I
you know some of the stuff we did at my
rocket I been cold myself right because
I had some money and the reason I was
able to get that money was specifically
because I was an area that effectively
overpays me right like I can work on
projects that pay me a lot more and I
know the people I'm in the area right
and so you know it does benefit me a
little bit if I choose to go to work it
benefits me greatly but the problem is
when you then go to try and do products
independently they're small in scale but
aren't operating in the same kind of
lawless space that you know don't really
have much benefit they don't get a lot
of benefit from deregulation you know
games don't really benefit hugely from
deregulation the way that the web
services do I you just you gotta take
the good with the bad right so sorry for
that long discussion of but that's just
that's the truth right that's just how
the world works and there's nothing you
can do about it as an individual you
know maybe collectively you can do
things about it right because you you
know vote for your government or you
participate in some kind of fora that
that that shapes the public thinking
about these things or who knows what
right so maybe you can do things about
it who knows but you know absent doing
something about it you have to kind of
just play along with the the way that
that things are structured right it's
just something to do
in terms of rigor techniques how is your
style changes of course this project are
there things you did at the beginning of
this project that you think we're steps
the wrong direction or would you
differently um well we've we've
corrected most of our mistakes on on
Hammad here and that was the goal you
know I wanted to show how you correct
those things there definitely are a few
things so the the biggest thing I would
say the biggest difference is when I
started hand Madeira I had very little
multi-thread programming experience and
very little out of order CPU
optimization experience I now have a lot
more of both of those and so the
sections that we did on those were poor
you know if I was doing multi-threading
or out of order optimization stuff today
it would have been a lot better I just I
just know like way more and so those
were pretty poor they don't matter a
huge amount to this particular product
project but you know that was the case
and the other thing is I would say the
debug system we overcomplicated too much
or just I shouldn't say overcomplicated
we complicated it too much and we should
have stuck with simpler put more
purpose-built things so that could be
simplified yeah I think other than that
I think we're roughly I was happy with
most stuff and I was happy with those
things too I mean I
the goal of handmade here was was to
show you know what's realistic for a
programmer to be doing they're supposed
to be mistakes they're supposed to be
areas that they don't know about because
nobody knows everything I mean that
there are no programmers who just know
how to make everything perfectly every
time right that just doesn't exist and
so I want people to have a very
realistic expectation you know I don't
think I would have trouble getting hired
at a game engine company pretty much
anywhere at this point in my career but
as you see on handmade here oh I have
questions about stuff all the time right
I'm always like I wondered about this or
I would like to talk to an expert in at
in blah because I don't know right and I
want people to understand that that is
the standard even at a pretty like
far a long point in someone's game
development career you do not know
everything and you never will I don't
care who you pick they don't write and
so you know having a realistic
expectation of what you're supposed to
be able to do best case was important to
me and it's important that people see
that on handmade hero I want them to see
me make mistakes I want them to see me
have to debug things I want them to see
them you have to change my mind
because to me that's like the value is
having a realistic portrayal of what
it's like to program not a sort of a
grande iced heroic version where I
already know when I'm going to do
exactly on stream and then just
magically do it and it all works right
because to me that's sending a very
incorrect message about what you should
be able to do and what you shouldn't be
able to do when you are a game engine
developer who you know is established
right when you're past the novice stage
and so hopefully you know we've we've
captured that on handmade here pretty
well and you know hopefully people feel
comfortable with making mistakes and not
knowing everything and asking other
people or expecting that there will be
people who know things that you don't
and to not feel like that's something
that goes away to not feel like that's
something that only happens because
you're a beginner right and so
can memory fragmentation happen on a GPU
well gosh that's a really tricky
question and I guess not what I'm
prepared to answer so I apologize the
reason that I'm hesitant to answer that
question is because obviously any piece
of hardware that has a memory system in
it can have fragmentation problems you
know that's just obviously the case
right but the intervening factor that
you get with the GPU is that 99.9% of
all of the code that goes to a GPU is
using some degree of blind handles right
so if you imagine for example in OpenGL
which admittedly is a bit high level
compared to something like Vulcan or d3
d12 but let's suppose you just looked at
what would happen with an OpenGL app
well you'll notice that all of our
textures are described to the GPU in
what way handles right so when we say
we're trying to draw this you know thing
to the screen it's texture number 37
we're not talking about memory we're
just talking about a slot an abstract
slot right what that means is that it is
relatively inexpensive for a driver to
do memory compaction behind our back we
don't know where slot 37s data lives
could be anywhere we talked about it on
frame three maybe it translates slot
slot 37 to one chunk of memory we talked
about it on frame 97 it's moved it right
could have easily moved it we have no
idea
so I guess what I would say is that
probably GPUs probably don't have
as much of a problem with memory
fragmentation as they otherwise would
because a large number of the things
that use them and interface with them
don't actually know where the things
they've allocated are which allows the
driver pretty much carte blanche to
rearrange them
now the reason I'm hesitant to just say
well so there's no problem with
fragmentation on a GPU because the
driver could just fix it is because
again the flipside is also true for
example bind list textures are a good
example of not really possibly being
able to do remapping and you know the
the overall effect there is that certain
lower level access to the GPU that is
actively encouraged by Nvidia and AMD
and whatnot does start to expose the
actual location of things and once
that's true the graphics card will have
a harder time managing the fragmentation
now it's still not a given that you have
a fragmentation problem because in order
to have a memory fragmentation problem
you have to be looking at memory holes
that happen at a granularity that isn't
at the virtual page size of this card if
it has memory mapping itself right and I
guess I don't know the specifics and
those sorts of things right so all I can
really tell you is yes fragmentation can
be a problem anytime you have
unpredictable memory allocation and
de-allocation patterns know the GPU does
not have as hard a problem perhaps as
other people because of the way the
api's are designed but yes it still
could happen because some of those api's
do expose details that may be low-level
enough to create a problem hopefully
that helps and yes these pants are very
comfy how would you compare windbg and
remedy BG should I consider switching to
remedy if I'm using windbg yes you
absolutely should
consider switching I would compare them
as such I would say windbg is like 10
out of 10 on features and like 0 out of
10 on usability right it has like every
feature Under the Sun most of the
features windbg has I probably even know
about like I mean there's a huge array
of command line options and plugins and
like the number of debug features windbg
has is insane
right remedy has like by comparison very
few features like the number of features
in remedy BG is pretty low compared to
windbg that's true but the usability is
like 10 out of 10 right so what I do and
what I would encourage you to do buy a
copy of remedy use it as much as you can
when you get to something that you can't
debug with remedy begrudgingly downshift
to win BG ring to BG right that's what I
do because the day to day debugging that
you do doesn't require most of the
features of windbg so you're just
suffering with a horrible user interface
for no reason why not let remedy upgrade
that experience for you right and it
takes 10 seconds to launch another
debugger if on the particular days when
you need to to actually address that
problem right when you need to like oh
there's a particular feature you know I
need to download symbols from Windows
symbol server and step through a thing
and do a mini dump and blob right when
you start to use all like tons of debug
features there that that need to get
like when you need to sort of get like a
power user debugger interface then you
know it takes 10 seconds to fire up one
DBG just go ahead and do it but the rest
of time I would use remedy right and
that's my opinion on it and that's what
I actually do I don't find myself
needing wind EEG
the ever weeks will often go by before I
need to switch to it but your mileage
may vary right because it depends along
the kind of debugging you do and what
you need remedy BG is also always
improving it's better this month than it
was last month right and so the other
thing I would say is if it doesn't work
for you right now
because you try it and you're just like
an ass that doesn't have enough features
I need X Y &amp; Z you know make sure you
file them on the windbg github there's
feature requests github make sure your
file what you need on there
and then come back and check in six
months right the upgrades are free so
far so you know you pay your twenty
bucks or whatever it is and you know
when it's ready it's ready for you so so
yeah that's that's my take on it but you
know you can you have to make your own
decision sir
we're going to learn more about
out-of-order optimization I don't know
sorry could you explain the strict
binary is it possible to optimize a
binary even if there's no access to the
source code sure I don't know what you
mean by stripped binary there's a couple
things that could mean so I can't really
explain a stripped binary because I'm
not I'm just not sure what stripped
binary means a binary is a binary and if
maybe you're talking about a binary that
doesn't still have debug information
with it or something I don't know but in
terms of whether it's possible to opt I
as a binary if there's no access to
source code yes it certainly is there's
a lot of techniques you can use to do
that but there's some pretty easy ways
so the easiest way by far to optimize a
stripped binary at least you know and
again I'm not a reverse engineer so this
may not even be the easiest way take it
with a grain of salt but a very easy way
to optimize a stripped binary is to just
relocate functions right so for example
if you have a particular code path it
issues a call right so there's a call
instruction that calls out to a function
any call site like that you can usually
optimize that by calling somewhere else
so what you can do is take whatever the
function was that it's calling right a
more optimal version link it in you know
place it somewhere in the in the
executable and jump there instead of
jumping where they were jumping right
and that's that's a pretty obvious way
another way a lot of people do it is
they'll just patch over some part of a
function with a jump called jump
somewhere else and then returns there
right it's all kinds of stuff like that
so many resources on why new programming
isn't that good I mean nothing
definitive I would like there to be
something more definitive but you know
even recently on Twitter I tried to ask
for people to just do the opposite like
do you have any resources on wihout
programming is good and like I didn't
even really get any answers there was
literally like a hundred replies and
most of them were disagreeing with each
other right so I don't even know what
people claim is good about OOP
so it's hard to tell say why it's bad
when you don't even know what you're
talking about right and so I find the
whole situation frustrating and I'm just
disinclined to even engage with it it's
like if you want to program in it go
right ahead just don't bother me about
it right what would be the best way to
prevent overdrawn a software rasterizer
in particular with a voxel scene like
minecraft I asked this before but didn't
specify the type of game well you know
most of the time what you're talking
about with preventing overdraw is you're
just trying to figure out ahead of time
how you can draw like front to back and
know that you don't need to draw
anything else right so typically what
you do in something where like for
example minecraft typically what you
would do in a game like that is you
would pre process and I don't mean
pretty like at load time I mean like pre
as in before the you know in the middle
of a frame or during the run of the game
right you would take large sections of
the voxel and you would find solid
regions of them right and then when
you're doing your rendering as you
render you would probably want to sleep
from the front backwards so as you go
right and you can do two things one is
you can lean on those large voxel
clusters that you've built into maybe
like larger cute you know like
rectangular occluders to just frustum
cull the projection of that against the
whole voxel world and no you don't even
need to consider anything in that area
so you don't even process that part of
the box alright and then the other thing
you do is as you go forwards you keep
track of some resolution on the screen
like let's say sixteen by sixteen
squares and you just keep track of
whether you've drawn them or not
and so if you progress from front to
back what you can easily do in a boxing
world what you do is you just go when
I'm about to rasterize if I've already
drawn everything in this 16 by 16 block
I just no longer even ever rasterize
anything in it I just early out any
pixel block that's you in there
I've heard you mention before that you
don't like call back should they be
invited at all costs how would you avoid
them if using recursion navigate a tree
like structure yeah I mean I don't like
callbacks typically because I find that
they make it very hard to use the code
that's involved part of that is because
C and C++ are bad like closure kind of
things they try tried to improve C++ as
handling of that and they've made some
improvements but mostly it's still bad
so you know a lot of it is because of
that but in terms of running at all cost
no I mean if you can't turn something
into an iterator for some reason and you
really feel like you need a callback
then sure you know you can use one but
they just have a high cost so don't do
that unless you're really sure that the
alternatives are really bad right it's
what I would say what's your opinion on
the whiteboard interviews and the big
tech companies like Google um I think
they're stupid I've said this before
assuming you're talking about a white
board interview like I give you a
programming problem and you solve on a
white board I think they're dumb I think
what you get out of white board
interviews it's kind of exactly what you
have at Google in terms of the common
case employee which is to say people who
are smart on their feet but probably
aren't very good programmers and I think
that's mostly what you get right now you
may get good programmers who happen to
come through that process anyway if they
are also smart on their feet but you're
not really screened for the thing you
need which is good programmers because
you know programmers don't work on a
whiteboard it's just not how you write
code um so you know I don't think
they're very useful I think they screen
out people who have maybe poor social
skills or who have trouble communicating
and I know that places like Google are
always like no we want good
communication asleep no you don't like
no like the people who have written some
of the best software in history are
terrible communicators you don't want to
screen them out and why do you even have
managers if you can't deal with people
like that like again it's just it's it's
a really backwards and counter to the
history of computing like way of
thinking about compute
really kind of disgust me it's like the
new kind of way that people try to claim
is good to build competing companies and
I think the proof is in the pudding
Google products are terrible I mean you
know they get worse every week it takes
multiple minutes for me to use Google
Drive now like there's I have a
directory in Google Drive that has 800
right shocking 800 files in it 800 total
files right 800 that's the number 9 2000
it takes something like 30 seconds to
produce a listing and the listing is
wrong it's not done yet
so you know you asked for a sorted
listing A to Z it's missing a bunch of
stuff and then like a minute later those
things show up right that's that's the
engineering right and so you know I
don't I don't think they have anything
to tell in my opinion right I think the
pudding is pretty rotten that comes out
of these companies so you know I don't
think they can speak highly of their
interviewing process or if they if maybe
they're interviewing process is good
then maybe their manager process is bad
I don't know but they produce very low
quality software like like extremely low
quality I would consider it about as low
quality as you can get and still say
that it's the product I don't know like
it's very very bad right
so many questions today I gotta go I'm
getting hungry
if virtual memory exists how are games
still able to be hacked it's because
offsets are constant I guess I'm not
sure I understand the question exactly
but you just mean how do you modify a
binary if you have virtual memory or I
don't understand the question I'm sorry
have you read about dean velvel workshop
assembly and also assembly archive no I
don't think I know what that is is there
an errata page there just in case you
show that I can submit - probably not
but you can sign up to podcast at Jeff
in case you show calm the horse ones
brown asked how do you design memories
for multiple dynamic arrays to please
the cache I'll be honest I don't like
dynamic arrays for exactly that reason I
find that dynamic arrays don't really
lend themselves well to to cache
coherency over time in that way and I
find that they also make it hard to
manage your memory properly to avoid
fragmentation and stuff like that so I'm
not a fan I'm not a huge fan so I pretty
much never use dynamic arrays pretty
much ever and so I guess I can't really
answer because I don't have a lot of
strong opinions about that don't think
the reason for localized software was
because people wanted to do things
faster I don't know I don't know what
the reason is for low quality software
it can't be speed because Google's got
so many employees it should be possible
to ship a reasonable software product
you know I don't know I don't know why
web companies for you such low quality
software I have no idea I would like to
express my deepest appointment lack of
new jeans the episodes yes sorry about
that we'll try to fix that sometime
the horse is real I mean for software
for simulation something like
Mathematica I don't know I know what you
mean sorry
shark and x3 do you think it's possible
to turn Webber around I mean you know it
probably assorted stuff out eventually I
mean if people ever have the ability to
compete I don't know I mean one of the
problems is it's again it's too many
bundled services that they come together
it's very hard to disaggregate you know
like maybe you make a better messenger
then Facebook Messenger but can you
really compete with Facebook message
because everyone's already on Facebook
right things like this I don't know to
what extent competition will solve the
problem but it's obvious that like
pretty much all of these companies you
could easily make a product that's
better than the product I just don't
know to what extent you can succeed in
the market by making a better product
you know making a better product in
Google Drive would be like trivial I
mean it's it's it's absolutely horrible
and I you know but I don't know I don't
know how hard it is to compete I don't
know it's not my it's not my industry if
you're an employer which candidate would
you choose 4.0 GPA with no side project
2.5 GPA with lots of side projects so in
my experience I wouldn't care at all
about the GPA things I don't care about
GPA what college you went to unless was
Harvard in which case I might just mark
you down as a negative but assuming that
it was not and and like probably like
whiteboard interview skills right don't
care about any of those three I do I
would want to see projects I want to see
what you've done and I want to interview
you and ask you about those products at
a deep level and see how well you're
able to actually convince me that you
know them and I try to do that in a way
that's very comfortable so that you're
not stressed and it doesn't feel like
I'm pressuring you you know I'm never
gonna ask you to solve a problem that
you're unfamiliar with
and I and that's really crucial right
because what I'm interested to know is
given the time you've already spent on
something did you solve the problems
then right and did you internalize the
knowledge then that's what I want to
know because that's what you're gonna do
when you work for me
I'm never gonna come to you in the
middle of the frickin day and be like
hey Bob or whatever can you solve this
problem on the whiteboard right now like
that that's not a thing and any problem
it's solvable on a whiteboard in 30
minutes is a problem we've already
solved in computer science so it doesn't
matter right the thing is I need you to
solve take weeks of thought and the work
I want you to do is typing in a lot of
code that works it's not on a whiteboard
it doesn't have to do with getting a
slightly faster string sort that doesn't
loop through the array twice or whatever
stupid idea the Google engineer asked
you to do on a whiteboard right so don't
care about any of that it's all bad ways
to pick an employee and it leads to bad
software I think in the end because
you're not screening for what you
actually needed and you know I can't
speak to why places like Google are
still doing it but you know like I said
if the proof was in the pudding I'd
changed my mind
if Google software worked I'd say their
interview process must be pretty good
but Google software is horrible so it
can't be right I mean or maybe it's
something else maybe they repress good
something else is bad I couldn't tell
you but it's pretty clear that what you
get out of the other end of their entire
process is very low quality software so
low quality that it's you know it's
laughably bad right you can actually get
distributed file systems from 1970 that
are faster than Google Drive as far as I
can tell right I remember using BBS's
that could list the files on the BBS
over a acoustic coupler moham basically
faster than Google Drive and they don't
seem to care right so or they care but
can't fix it I don't know
so I just I can't say enough negative
things about the level of quality that
comes out of that pipeline and why it's
so low is anyone's guess I'm not an
institutional analyst so I can't tell
you why they seem to produce such
consistently poor quality software but
you know
time-traveling hey KC I know you're busy
and all but can you stand up for me and
reverse this link to list on the left
foot yeah exactly I mean it's just it's
silly right it's kind of like if you
were like well we need to do job
interviews for a plumber right that's
what we're hiring and they come in and
they're like okay yeah so what we need
you to do for a plumber is is like stand
up and draw for me on the whiteboard
like what the crud like cross section of
a pipe would be if the outside was this
thick and the inside was this or any
like that does it you don't even really
do that when you're plumbing right it's
like plumbing is not that activity and
maybe you could argue once in a while
you sort of need to do this thing but
like it's really tangential right and
again like I'm inclined to sort of say
that that interview process in general
does actually cause a real problem and
it leads to poor suffer because what
you're doing is putting an emphasis on
sort of like myopic focus on quickly
doing existing tricks mental tricks that
is exactly not what gets you a well
working system that can list eight
hundred files in less than a minute
right the problem with Google Drive is
not that somebody didn't know how to
sort the names the slowest sort in the
world an Ncube sort can sort eight
hundred names probably faster than
google drivers right now so that is not
the problem the problem is that what you
needed is people capable of writing
actual software and that is different
algorithms are not the hard part of
software they haven't been the hard part
of software for about two decades right
and so screening for people who under
and algorithms is largely useless anyone
who wrote a program incorrectly if
Google drive's problem was that the
person who wrote it use an Ncube sort I
can fix that tomorrow in 30 seconds
right well no in 30 minutes right all I
do is go into the sort and replace it
with one that works but when you hire
people who think that the way to program
is you just take like the Python script
and you hook it up to the thing that
does left pad and then you do the blob
on the block right
who cares if that person knows how to do
a login sort and login sort who cares
they've spent so much of the computer's
resources doing nothing that it doesn't
matter how fast they can make it do
something because the something 2.1
percent of the time and the nothing took
99.9 right so now you end up with a
Google Drive that's sitting there for 70
years going through god knows what
gyrations because of their distributed
file system server has to spin up the
Python instance that knows how to figure
out which of these twelve wins matched
to the user grid which then goes and
queries the security system for the
ticket that was implemented by some
other thing because we had to junction
together the thing that does Google apps
versus the thing that does the personal
version of Google and oh by the way that
runs on ipv6 but this was an ipv4 so we
had to run the like thing that does the
translation layer to mat oh and by the
way that thing has a bug in it so it
actually has to redo the TCP connection
every time because it accidentally leaks
that handle and we forgot about that
and so now that thing we just restart
and and eventually you're somehow at the
point we're taking 800 file directory
you know the architecture is just forget
it like we can't there's nothing we can
do and the date is already stored across
12 different data centers and you know
just forget it there's nothing I can do
you hire me to fix that and I'm like I
can't okay right I can't fix it because
it's too far gone and it's not something
that's ever going to produce a reliable
like you know experience for the user
praying about toilet question but why
does it feel like you would enjoy
knitting um I would not enjoy anything
sorry I don't don't care for knitting
highly repetitive processes are tough
for me
people probably make this are for a slow
and crappy on purpose not be fired I
don't think so
I don't think so I think it's a skill
it's a skill gap it's a skill gap right
I mean another way to look at it is
suppose someone went to school for
mechanical engineering right and I
screened you on mechanical engineering
knowledge so like tell me how
load-bearing this beam has to be right
and then I take you know thirty of those
mechanical engineers and I put them on a
construction site and I say build this a
scraper right it's probably an epic
disaster
because they have no idea they don't
even know how to operate a crane right
and that to me is like the Google
interview process it's interviewing
people for a skill that's unrelated to
the skill they actually need to do their
job right and so the problem with that
is then you get people who may or may
not know how to do the job some
mechanical engineers will probably make
great carpenters or already know how to
do carpentry because they did it in
their spare time
others have no idea don't want to know
will never learn and they just are
useless at building a building right
they were they could be used to design
the building but they can't build it
right and to me that's the problem when
you interview on an unrelated skill you
end up with workers who may or may not
have that skill I may or may not have
the skill you need right you have skill
a which is developing useful good
software that works at a high quality
level you have skill B which is trick
problems on a white board if you
optimize for skill B you have no idea if
you've got skill a sometimes you might
sometimes you might not you could argue
that B correlates with a a little bit
and it might a little bit but not a lot
where's some research to learn grab
storing how much math is really
necessary a lot of math I'm not sure
what the best resources are but you need
a lot of math graphics programming in
particular requires a lot of math if
you're not comfortable you don't really
want to be a graphics programmer right
there's probably other types of
programming you can do a lot of web
programming sorts of stuff doesn't
really require math because a lot of the
math is done for you and somewhere else
grabs programming your your write up and
up in the math if the math is is front
centers so if you don't want to learn
math don't be a graphics programmer
if not with Dinoco race how would you
start dynamic the growing data when you
can't predict how much memory you will
need and need to store it so the
handmade hero temporary memory concept
doesn't solve the problem I mean again
can you give me an example like what are
you doing and then I could tell you how
I might approach it have you or would
you ever use go - um I guess what I
would say is I was taught programming at
a time when nobody knows go - as a
result I don't use go - I don't know
anything that's good I think it's
probably a cognitive deficiency for me
that I don't use go - and I think it's
probably a language design deficiency of
C and C++ that they don't have a more
broad idea of of how go-to integrates
into code right because it's pretty
simplistic so I don't use go to but I
should it's maybe the way I would put it
and the reason I say that is because the
older I get the more I appreciate that
programming should be about telling the
cpu what to do
it's not about screwing around with your
language and the only thing a cpu does
is go - there is no other thing a CPU
does there is the concept of a function
call in the sense that there is a go to
that automatically pushes a return value
on the stack but that's kind of an
optimization right but go - is it like
loops there's no loops on a CPU there's
go twos right there's tests and jump
right and there's no switch statements
on a CPU
there's just jump and you can do a
relative like a variable jump if you
really get fancy but compilers don't
ever generate that as far as I know so
it's just test and jump test and jump
test and jump test and jump so 99% of
everything you typed into a computer is
test and jump
you know conditional while for do all of
these switch tests and jump right
so the fact that we would consider go to
somehow weird or anomalous is kind of
ridiculous because it's happening all
the time and why you wouldn't want
access to that I don't know so I
consider it deficient that I don't use
go to I wish that I had not developed my
style of programming at that time and at
some point I probably will investigate
it more probably when I actually go
ahead and just start programming my own
language at some point which is kind of
inevitable I suppose I will make go
Tuesday first class
switches can in some cases generate
indirect jumps yeah I mean switches can
in in theory if your compiler was super
crazy you could even have a switch
statement that padded the cases and it
could jump with a with expression right
like a computed jump so they're like the
nature of a switch statement is such
that you could do things very fancy a
lot of compilers don't do that a lot of
compilers yet either just have test and
jump or they make a table and load from
the table and jump but they only do that
in certain circumstances like if they
can actually guarantee that's fairly
dense probably I want to say not sure
exactly what they use for there
will you be an early adopter of ji I
don't know I may be near experience what
do you think are good ways to manage
tougher projects I don't know I don't
really deal with large-scale project
management I'm a kind of wrong when they
ask argh or the dynamic array example in
one a list of active connections on a
server to an array of enemies in a game
well in either of those it's trivial
right on a 64-bit computer just put
those at base addresses that have you
know 4 gigabytes of unused address space
following them and just grow them as
necessary done right you never need to
reallocate anything you just commit more
pages
if you have several unpredictably
growing dynamic arrays saying a math
simulation how would you separate by a
large distance in a memory no order your
pile blocks on top of each other what
does the caste refer is it even a
concern I've never done anything exactly
like that so basically you're saying
like well I've got so random crap coming
in from a user it could be anything
right that I don't know what I would
probably prefer I would have to see what
kinds of things shake out from actually
trying it first right because it depends
if I see that the sizes tend to be used
are similar right so if what you tend to
get there is like well you know we get a
pretty even distribution 10 elements 100
elements 50 elements whatever and
they're just kind of random I might just
use buckets you know I got array chunks
0 to 32 array chunks 0 to 60 for array
chunks 0 to 128 you know whatever and I
allocate and just give those back as
like I keep a free list of ones of
certain sizes quickly right so just
basically you know a standard sort of
general-purpose allocator but that's
geared towards what I need would
probably all I would do anything large
so anything that's gonna be like
multiple 4k pages I just probably map
that one by itself through the OS right
and then free it through the rest when
I'm done yeah I'm saying because those
are so huge that just filling them up is
gonna be take a while anyway
so I'm not so concerned about avoiding
round-tripping to the OS to actually
change the memory map I'm saying
alright my lord that was a lot of
questions all right let's close it down
people thank you everybody for joining
me Philip sort of handmade here at so a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along a series
at home you can always peer to the game
at handmade hero dot o-r-g it comes with
source code so if you want to follow
along with it at home you can do that
maybe you want to play with that
lighting see if you can beat me to a
good way of encoding light in there
dynamically we've got some interesting
reconstruction stuff happening in there
the question is just how are we gonna
communicate with that reconstruction now
and I don't know we're gonna find out uh
that's it for today I'll be back here
next week when I will try to solve that
problem or at least take the first steps
towards doing it and I'm pretty excited
about it because I think the sledding is
gonna look really sweet alright that's
it for today
hope to see you back here next weekend
till then half I'm pregnant run and
we'll see you on the internet since was
asked today don't forget click on the
hand maid here ahead if you want to get
to any of our other mother Molly rocket
projects see what's up there always a
good thing to click on and that's it
take it easy