hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we got our sorting kind
of I think I don't really want to use
the word working but it kind of was
working yesterday and we had some
visualizations that we did to sort of
see what was going on and you know it's
starting to look respectable so at this
point I'm not one hundred percent sure
what the best course of action is
because we kind of have two things that
we've got to do one thing that we have
to do is we have to we have to go ahead
and put our sprites into layers like we
were in the middle of doing when we kind
of went over and took care of the sort
so we've got to deal with that the other
thing that we have to do is we have to
figure out what our solution is to the N
squared sorting problem because I don't
think that's going to be a long-term
viable thing to have in there you know
at I mean computers are ridiculously
fast so somehow it's running at a
reasonable frame rate right now but you
know it's it's kind of ridiculous that
it is I'm rather surprised at that and
so you know in general we don't want to
have this sort of thing at the core of
our render loop that has to be doing n
squared stuff it just doesn't seem like
a very good idea to say the very least
so hmm it's a little bit warm in the
hoodie I'll be honest I may not be able
to keep the hoodie on for the entire
stream but what are we going to do
temperatures they fluctuate so this is
it day 3 09 on handmade he rode a 308 is
the code you would want to start with if
you're trying to match up with what I'm
doing that's the source code that i'm
starting with now and if i go ahead and
open up our project here let's go ahead
and compile that
and I'm going to go ahead and get ms
debbé going as well if you remember
where we left off we had it to the point
where it seemed like the sorting was
actually working pretty darn well and we
kind of have some ridiculous you know
information overlay stuff happening here
we can turn that off pretty easily and I
probably should turn that off now that's
this global show sort groups thing
because at the moment I'm not sure that
we're going to be focusing on the sort
group debugging or anything like that so
this is what things look like at the
moment and actually like I said before I
think they look pretty good we have a
couple things that we have to address
but most of them seem you know actually
fairly logical and don't seem to
implicate that the sort is is performing
incorrectly in fact the sort seems from
performing really quite well considering
what I'm feeding it right now which is
not particularly good data by any
stretch of the imagination so yeah you
know a couple things we have to deal
with and I'm not exactly sure how we
want to deal with them but for example
in this situation here where we're going
to be hopping up things we're going to
have to think about what we want to do
there because our Z values are kind of
all wrong in this case and we're going
to have to try and make it so that that
the Y sprites can sort of hop over
things correctly and stuff like that and
we still have some other issues here to
take a look at you can see there when
you get like that guy hopping up in
there you can see how we kind of get
some Sun bugs when you get sort groups I
think those have to do with cycles i'm
not sure we also currently have those
sort of highlighting reticles on which
are not super useful either in terms of
adding more complexity to the sort which
is not something we actually wanted to
do but let me see where that actually
ended up that's
robe mode so yeah we're we're drawing
those volumes those collision volumes I
actually never we're drawing those
collision volumes we're creating a bunch
of pushing volumes ah as always I always
forget this because we kind of did this
and then we were working on the ID code
for a while I forgot I move things into
nvm like where is the code it goes right
there it's just a different file yeah
it's getting too hot in here at this
we're going to have to lose the hoodie
all right the hoodie the hoodie has been
has been retired temporarily so yeah so
this is what we look like here when we
don't have those extra sprites and you
can see that like some of the bugs that
were happening on the left side of the
screen don't happen when those extra
sprites aren't in there right and so you
know i feel like the sorting routine
seems to be working relatively well at
this point and we have to be sort of
conscientious and think about it going
forwards just from the standpoint of we
got to make sure that we start putting
in good data and don't ask it to do
things which you can't do because
inherently like i said at the outset of
this we are sort of inherently asking it
to do something that is not particularly
stable we're asking it to do sorts that
have no real solution so it's kind of a
situation where we're just using some
fuzzy stuff to produce a sort that we
hope will give us the pleasant results
and for the most part in a lot of these
cases it's working so I feel like that's
a good start for us it's something we'll
have to revisit once we sort of have
everything in here that we want to draw
and can get a little bit more visibility
on it but for the moment I'm relatively
happy with it so the thing that I am
more interested in doing at this point
since now we have something there is is
a making sure we can't we have a some
saying some sane idea of how to get the
N squared
working properly right and then the
other thing that we have to do is figure
out how we're going to do our layering
because that's what we were right in the
middle of doing and that's another
tricky problem in and of itself and the
reason for that is just because we kind
of want this fourth of graphic view but
then we sort of have this hybrid kind of
perspective concept which is that as we
go up things do in fact shrink right so
although we don't want this sort of left
you know this this right word leaning
thing to be happening we do want to be
able to have as we sort of come up
through other levels of the game like
that we do want the the ability for the
floor to kind of shrink down right and
you know we could decide to abandon that
we could decide not to keep that just to
keep the perspective more constant but I
felt like it was just kind of a really
neat effect that happened and so I'm
just sort of of the opinion that I would
like to try to preserve it as long as
possible until I see something that
really makes me go no there's really
just no way we can possibly keep this
it's awful right and you know certainly
if we were trying to make it as easy as
possible for ourselves we wouldn't do
that but you know at the moment that
isn't the primary goal right so uh given
that what I think I would like to do
first is I think I'd like to take a
minute to sort of look at this this N
squared situation right and you know so
like I said we've got two problems one
is that we don't like the sort rule that
we have in there can't handle layered
things on top of each other and it's
because it's kind of using hacked ideas
about how to about how to sort things
that are entirely based on like what
will look nice for a normal room right
so we need to separate things into
layers and you know that'll give us our
that'll fix our debug overlay as well
because like right now our debug overlay
gets blocked by y sprites right and
that's according to the rule that's
actually what should happen but in
addition to that i would like to figure
out how to make sure that
build sprite craft doesn't take a huge
amount of time unfortunately we can
easily force it to buy just dumping tons
of sprites on it right that's the whole
point about the N squared situation you
know here there's just not enough
rectangles on the screen not enough
sprites on the screen to uh to blow past
the frame budget so even though we're
doing an N squared algorithm for the
sorting we're just not feeling it and
that's just because computers are crazy
fast even though this computers from six
years ago at this point it's still so
fast that it's just like ya know don't
worry about it right but if I just
drastically increase the number of
sprites by opening the debug view right
all of those are still going through the
sort you can now see that build spread
graph is taking a massive amount of time
and that's of course because there's so
many things that it has to sort that you
know you finally start to see that N
squared actually matter and so I want to
I think today just figure out something
we can do about that I think that's
probably the best best use of our time
ok so uh let's take a look here
so essentially the problem that we have
and here's a the day marker okay 309
essentially the problem that we have day
is we've got some series of rectangles
on the screen and we need to know which
ones overlap right we're trying to
figure out all the sprites that overlap
each other on the screen and at the
moment we are just doing that by you
know checking all sprites against each
other in an N squared fashion so if
there are five sprites we will check
each right against each other sprite and
we do that by having into nested for
loops so that's what's happening at the
moment now the problem with that
obviously is that as the number grows we
are going to be doing an N squared
number of comparisons now you remember
when we talked about Oh N squared right
if you consider the number of things
here to be n then if I have to compare
each thing with each other thing i end
up with doing n things and you know
versus n things or n squared it's a very
simple idea right and of course it's
pairwise so we don't need to compare if
we have like a and B right we don't need
to compare a versus B and then B versus
a so we're not doing all N squared
comparisons we're only doing sort of
like half of the N squared comparisons
right because we don't have to do the
backwards version of each one but it's
still proportional to N squared right if
you take n square and you divide it by 2
or something like that it still grows
compared to compared to N squared it's
still a graph that looks like that and
just because you flatten that graph out
a little bit doesn't change the fact
that it you know has this really bad
growth curve where at some point you're
going to get up and just really steep
intractable problem space so what we'd
like to do is figure out a simpler way
to build this graph and you know you can
imagine some pretty
straightforward ways that we might be
able to do this but you know this is
kind of a classic computational geometry
well you know I know if I want to call
it computation adapter there's like this
is a classic geometry problem and
there's a lot of different ways that
people go about doing it the way that I
tend to go about doing it because it
tends to be easiest is I tend to just
bucket things right so what i will do is
I'll say well okay you know if I've got
a screens worth of sprites and I'm
trying to figure out which one's of them
overlap you know I'm just going to go
ahead and say well let's make some
buckets here and we'll just sort inside
each well not sort inside each bucket
we'll just say when we're going to test
somebody we only test them against
sprites that are in the buckets that
they overlap if that makes sense now
this doesn't solve the N squared nature
of the problem in any real sense right
because it's still n squared inside the
bucket but what it does is it truncates
the the N down so it's always a fairly
small number which means you never get
up into that bad part of the N squared
curve right now it's possible that we
could do this in non N squared fashion I
believe I'm not a computational geometry
kind of a person to be honest with you
it's not you know my strongest suit but
my recollection from that literature is
that we could actually do this without
needing to do it n squared and the
reason that I say that is because one of
the things about overlap testing is that
you know every test that you perform
gives you information about what other
tests you may or may not have to perform
right and you know to give an example of
that I'll give a very simplified example
of that suppose we were going to test
for overlap
in just one dimension so this is one
dimensional overlap right well if I have
some spans and you know let me try to
draw them in somewhere that makes sense
so if I have some spans here right and I
want to know if these things overlap
immediately you can start to think of
well you know I could start these I
could sort these spans by like their
minimum coordinate let's say or
something right and I know that sorting
is n log n I know that I don't have to
do it n squared to sort something so i
could do an N log n sort of these things
first and then actually have them in
order and once I have them in order I
know that I only need to test the next
person in the list to see whether or not
I overlap with them because if I don't
overlap with them I don't need to test
anybody further down the list right so
at some level you can start to see how
computational geometry could easily
build algorithms based on n log and
sorting in various axes that would allow
them to reduce the number of tests that
they need to do in order to figure out
what all the overlaps are and i believe
if i'm not mistaken that you can sort of
do literally what I'm talking about here
in a in a 2d arena as well you can first
sort by one axis and get you know things
in that axis and then you can do sorts
by another axis insaat you know a stable
sort inside that axis by another axis
and then end up with a thing where you
can sort of only do the checks that you
want to do now I don't like I said I
don't know that I want to do that and
the reason that I don't know if I wanna
do that is because although that's going
to probably be the more theoretically
fast thing in the sense that it could
scale to the highest number of possible
objects in all scenario
else I don't know that that's going to
actually give us the fastest results in
practice because in practice you know
we're not going to have more than a
thousand sprites in a little section of
the screen right and so I feel like you
know a method where we dice things up is
really going to probably be a more
efficient thing for us to do in the long
run and it's probably going to fit our
usage better so that's my assumption now
I don't know that that's true but that's
just what I would assume so that's my
inclination that's what I would go with
if if it were up to me for figuring out
you know what the overlap is and when I
you know when i'm thinking about this i
think the primary complexity there the
primary sort of set a decision we have
to make is how are we storing this
information and how are we actually
going to do the bucketing because
there's a couple different ways that we
might want to do it right so I if you
imagine
that I have some kind of a grid there's
a lot of ways we can go about spatially
partitioning things so that we can
reduce the number of checks we have to
do four rectangles so you know if this
is a rectangle here and this is a
rectangle here and then there's another
rectangle over here you know maybe we
want to check these two rectangles for
intersection because they're sort of
occupying the same general space and we
think they might overlap they don't but
we think they might but we definitely
don't want to test this against this
because they're nowhere near each other
and we don't really probably want to
test this against this either because
they shared you know they're divided by
one of these lines so if you think about
sort of narrowing testing in this way
like a spatial partition so called
because we are partitioning space up
into different regions for some purpose
if you look at what's implied here
there's more than one way we can choose
to represent this or there's a number of
ways you can choose to attack this
problem and the underlying sort of
element in how we're going to make or
what makes their be decisions to make it
the the the underlying try think of what
the word is we have choices and the
reason we have to make these choices
let's put that way is because things
don't always fall within a bucket right
so if things always fell entirely inside
one whole bucket always then we wouldn't
have to think really we just feel like
all right well you know we make some
number buckets and then really all we
have to figure out is how we're going to
store the fact that stuff's in a bucket
that's the only decision we have to make
is how to store but because things like
for example this rectangle right here
span for actual spatial buckets if the
way we chose represent this was well we
need for we need to say that this
thing's in four different buckets so
that when someone looks up in it knows
that this guy's there right we have to
start thinking about how are we going to
handle that activity right so one way to
handle that activity is to store is to
break up each thing that we store and
store a record of it in each bucket that
it touches right then when we go to
query we can say okay all the buckets
that itouch look to see what all the
things are in those buckets and test
against them right we can certainly do
that not a you know not a huge deal but
again it's a decision another thing we
can do is we can create a more
hierarchical notion of what the space
actually looks like and avoid breaking
things up in that fashion and let me
give you an example of how that sort of
works so suppose I was to take well I'll
try to stay with this example I guess
suppose I was to take this entire
section here and and say that I have
sort of a top-level region that's the
entire area so anything that overlaps
with it could be stored in this okay
because all these things are obviously
within this rectangle and then i say i
want to divide it in half right i'm
going to divide it well once i divided
in half now there's some things on one
half and some things on another half
right and I only need to test you know
each half if something's in this app I
test this app something this fi test
that app that's all I really need to do
right then i could go ahead and divide
it in half again let's say right maybe i
divide it in half again and of course
unfortunately i didn't really draw a
half's line here but let's say that i
was going to do it in half again and so
it'd be something like that and now we
get to the first place where i'm sort of
saying there could be a difference in
here right this rectangle overlaps the
split point where i'm going to divide it
and so if we were to follow the same
general pattern in the grid based method
where we just store it everywhere that
it appears nothing really changes I'd
store it in either side right I'd have I
have a copy a record that it was in both
these sides and I'd move on but I could
instead decide to not store it in that
lower split level and instead store it
at a higher split level right because if
you think about what this sense of
creating is it sort of says well I have
this giant region here right and then I
split it into two regions I split it
into a region that was just the stuff on
this side and a region that was just the
stuff on the other side right and then I
took you know these two regions as well
and I slipped them again I said well now
I've got one that's like well it's just
the stuff that's like up in there and
just the stuff that's down in there and
the same thing would be true in this
case right so if you look at what's
going on there you can kind of see what
I mean now when I say we have a choice
of where to store things if we want to
we could store things in whatever bucket
doesn't split them so this guy cannot be
stored in either here or here but he
could be stored in here so he would be
stored in here now when we do testing on
somebody we do the exact same process
and we just test against everyone in
everything we would have traversed in
order to find their location right so
that's another way we can do it I and
you know this this method of doing
splits there's there's a lot of
different things that you see if you've
ever seen like quadtree or KD tree right
BSP tree all these things are just
different kinds of facial partitions a
quadtree is one that always splits it
into fours right it's this kind of a if
this kind of a process a KD tree is one
that always splits exactly one
of the orthogonal axes every time but
only one right so it might split this
into two halves and then it'll split
this into two halves but it's never
going to produce for things like I Spit
to so it's basically like a binary tree
a BSP tree is very much the same as a KD
tree only instead of picking cardinal
axes the BSP tree can pick anything so
it could like to split that way if you
wanted to write and so you know the KD
tree is kind of you might think of it as
a sort of more restrictive subset of a
BSP tree like a KD tree still is a
binary space partition it's just one
that can only pick one of the the
Cardinal axes as its split so the thing
about a lot of these and you know I
don't have anything against these guys
they're all typically just fine is you
know really you don't get very much for
doing this stuff typically the only time
that I find that it's really all that
great to go with something more
complicated like this where you've got
something you know more complicated than
a simple grid is if you have level of
detail concerns because you can
understand why having sort of things
that split into smaller pieces and then
could be collapsed upward if I have
level of detail stuff going on here
where I'm like oh you know something I'm
I'm looking out across this thing like
I'm standing here and I'm looking this
way so I might want this to be at a low
level of detail and this to be a high
level detail you know these partitioning
things tend to make more sense to me in
those kind of context where you're not
dealing with a uniform density uniform
come access kind of thing but that's not
really what we have you know we know
we're looking at a flat bounded region
where everything is the same level of
detail and we're equally likely to have
sprites on the left side screen and the
right side of screen there's not going
to be like a drastic difference there
and so my suspicion is a lot of this
stuff would just be wasting a lot of
implementation time doing fancy things
that we don't really care about
so my assumption is that what we
probably would want to do the most
efficacious thing for us would be to
figure out how to use a very simple grid
bucketing scheme probably that stores
things multiple times if they cover
multiple things is probably the most
efficacious thing that we could do
that's my guess anyway and the reason I
say that is because I don't see us
getting any real benefit from any of the
other schemes now it's possible that
something more sort wives would actually
be clever like I said you know we've
kind of got these other options here and
so you know if we wanted to spend a lot
of time on it I could see this being
something where you would investigate
and say okay let's take a look and think
about do we believe that you know we
could get a good clean way of testing
for rectangular overlap here with a nice
computational geometry algorithm I you
know that doesn't require a lot of a lot
of code and doesn't look like it's going
to be too computationally intensive for
what we actually want you know maybe you
can do something much more efficient
there I'm not sure but I think for the
time being this is probably more what I
would say makes sense and furthermore
what I'd say is if we look at this sort
of grid system you know one thing that
you might say is well you know what if
we have some giant sprite here that's
covering all these things you know we're
going to be adding it to all of these
buckets and it's just going to be a
nightmare and and that's just you know
ah right but what I would point out in
this case is that we're under no
obligation to use the grid because we
can always have a side band of things
that we compared against in addition to
the grid so what we can do if we want to
is just make it so that when things are
roughly grid sized or smaller we put
them in the grid
good but when they're like larger than
you know for grid squares big we can
just leave them in a linear array for
testing because there won't be that many
of them so we can avoid sort of
pathological cases where some giant you
know cloud sprite is being glitter of
this rain if everyone has to test
against it anyway we don't need to go
through the grid to divide it up right
so that's you know sort of a that's a
way that we can prevent certain
pathologically bad things from the of
the grid from happening because we kind
of know our use case and we we know that
that's you know something we can easily
just put as a side band so yeah so if
you look at what's going on at the
moment you can kind of see that you know
if I open up the profile here right I
you know it's it's debug mode so yeah we
can go compile and release mode and it
gets a lot faster but if you take a look
at that you can see that if we open up
the debug view and get all those sprites
in there I mean look at how expensive
it's just crazy expensive right really
really really expensive to do that build
sprite crap I so you know what what we
want look at here is can we go implement
sort of a simple grid thing that would
break that down and make it so that it's
not 93% you know get it down to
something more reasonable and so we're
not afraid that it's going to break as
we as we move forwards and it doesn't
have to be the best thing right like I
said we don't have to do the best
possible thing here we're not trying to
be too prematurely optimization oriented
or anything like that but we just need
something that we can feel comfortable
so like we open up the debug window we
won't have a giant disaster and yet you
know the other way we could approach
that it's a don't bother optimizing this
just go turn off the debug view and let
it be on square I don't know I think we
should just take this opportunity to
optimize it because you know it's it's
obviously slow and obviously we have
good not super expensive ways we can go
in it means sets of in terms of code
ways we can go in and start to attack
that so I think we want to give a little
bit of a try there even at this stage
so you know luckily for us this is an
optimizers dream scenario obviously we
know all our time is spent here so we
know that really all we have to do is
accelerate this function right we just
have to accelerate these checks so
there's really not much mystery to it so
that's a good thing and we know that
really all we need to do to produce the
correct information here is is wit you
know make sure that we always at least
check all rectangles that might
intersect right so right now we're
checking all pairs of rectangles and we
just want to say okay can we winnow down
that number to a small number that get
tested against each other and as long as
we do that we think we'll be fine ok so
how are we going to do that ok so I'm
gonna start with something fairly stupid
and we're going to go from there and see
how the fairly stupid thing holds up and
we'll get more complicated as necessary
so here we are in build sprite graph and
I'm going to say that we have that sort
of grid like I just sort of talked about
I'm gonna say we have a grid and inside
that grid I guess I'm going to store in
fact i guess i have i've got these
sprite bounds right and so yeah i think
i'm just going to make a temporary
little structure here and i'm going to
say that this is our sort grid our sort
grid cell oops and inside the sort grid
cell I guess I don't really need to be
called a sorc red cell I guess I want to
be called a sorc rear entry really i'm
going to use a simple chain here and you
know every time i do a linked list
people get concerned because they're
worried about cash effects I think it's
great they worried about cash effects
that's totally fine remember though
these are all coming from the same
memory unit so they're packed close
together and it's usually not such a
great idea to worry about something like
cash effects so you know you actually
have them and that you care right so i'm
going to write the simplest thing first
and we'll see how it performs and then
you know the time to worry about catch
FX is usually when
you actually start seeing that you're
having performance problems and the 32
cash bags right so anyway so I'm going
to a sort great entry here the sort good
entry is going to be yes quite cash
unfriendly to say the least because of
slightly the next pointer but they're
gonna be packed together so that's
really not gonna be that bad but also
because we're sort of out referencing
right we're saying we're gonna reference
sprite bounds that are out kind of in a
you know in another I don't want to use
the word part of town but yet we're sort
of saying there's a thing that's yeah
elsewhere right so we've got our sorts
right bound here and we're going to say
that that source right band is is the
thing that's in this cell so it's like
an occupant and now I'm just going to
say well alright let's let's make some
of these sort great entries and I'll
make it a pound to find here that's like
you know sort grid width and sort grid
height you know or something like this
and let's just start out by saying it's
16 by 16 and I'm not picking that number
for any reason other than i'm just going
to test it and you know i guess now that
i think about it well we're typically
sorting a sixteen by nine inch screen so
let's do sixteen by nine SI just needs
some numbers to put in there so here's
the grid and we'll we've got the sort
grid height and sort grid with and i'm
doing these in backwards order at the
moment because we'll probably well i
guess you know what i could do them in
same same there's really no reason not
to so now it's XY addressing for this
grid okay so what I want to do is I want
to initialize this thing to zero and say
there are no occupants in it right so
there's nothing nothing in the grid at
the moment it's empty and I'll compile
that make sure real good and now what I
want to do is I want to do a pass over
all of the input nodes that we have
like so so I want to do a pass over all
the nodes and for every node that we
have I need to put it into the grid
everywhere where it currently exists
right so you know I've got to say like
okay it's basically a a for loop inside
the loop where I'm saying I have to
touch all of the grid squares that this
square might touch and I need to record
the fact that this sort grid entry is in
there so in here I've got sort of my my
grid X and I guess I shouldn't put zero
this is something and similarly I've got
my grid why we don't know what these
numbers are we're going to have to
compute them but for each one of those
so for every grid square that I'm
touching I'm going to put a record in
there of my existence so I'm going to do
a sort grade entry entry equals push
struct sort good entry and for each one
of these I'm going to say but its next
equals exactly what you expect it's next
to be and its occupant equals me right
so this is just going to be red X grid
why
and then I'm going to go ahead and say
that the thing in that position is me so
that creates basically a chain and so
now in every in in every grid square
there is now a chain of all of the
sprite bounds that are you know in that
grid square right and that's that so one
of the interesting things about this
that you probably can already see is now
that I'm doing it this way uh it's
unclear that we really need to do a sort
of a separate pairwise check right
because look at what's going to happen
here every time I come in here to add
one of these guys well I could just
check against all the people that are in
the grid right now in this crude square
right I could just check against them
and and and be done right I mean in
theory anyway sir got an itch there
right so I I don't necessarily have to
do this in two passes where I kind of
then do my N squared loop over the thing
I could instead just do the checking
right here and add the edges at this
time and I'll say obviously there's kind
of if you're you know if you're kind of
paying attention at this point you
probably also are starting to think wait
a minute isn't there another thing we
can do and you would be correct about
that but will kind of get to that a
little bit later okay so and I suppose
one thing that might be true about this
is at the moment since we're using the
indices here the the index we're using
note indices I might have to say that
instead of doing it this way I might
have to say that it's the octopus index
now i don't know if that's going to be
the most efficient way to do this but
it's just how the rest of codes written
so for at the moment
I'm going to say that's the way we're
going to do it just for the moment all
right so if I was to do this now I've
got all these grid squares and I need
some way of actually affecting the the
sort I want to jump ahead and say if we
take a look at what happens on recursive
front to back here uh what we could do
is say well we've got this first edge
you know walking thing here that's going
through all of the edges that are coming
out of me I want to know all the edges
that have me as the frontmost person
right but we could just do that test we
could just do this test directly and
never actually save that result at all
right meaning we don't have to actually
create the edges of this graph I did it
sort of to show how that works and to do
the graph algorithm as a graph algorithm
but there really isn't any particular
reason to save those edges they don't
really do any good because we only check
each person one time and we mark them as
visited we're never going to look at
them again so we could just at that
point take that person and test them
against everything right if we wanted to
we could just do that just write that so
what I would say about that is you know
maybe that's a good reason to sort of
say you know right inside here we could
actually do that graph walk we could do
that graph walk sort of directly by just
testing the grid I don't know if I'm
probably not explaining this very well
but point B I'm just trying to say
instead of doing this pass and creating
the edges we could instead also just do
this where replace this function this
part of the function with
just an iteration over the grid that
this guy you know whichever one we r
picked here do it in duration of the
grid that this guy's on and do the front
to back that way right so yeah
I think that's reasonable all right so
let's take a look here at this there
because there's another thing we
actually need to do which is the grid X
span situation we need to actually sort
of compute that stuff so this is sort
bridge span I'm going to call it which
is I'm just going to figure out a way to
compute these numbers here so this is
like a min X then Y well you know what
we already have this it's a rectangle to
I isn't it so this guy right here is
exactly what we want a min x and a min Y
and Max X and max y so we need something
that's essentially going to tell us hey
I need you to give us the span for this
screen space rectangle so this is like
get grids fan and it's going to take a
rectangle too that's just the screen
area right and it's going to return a
result here that we don't know what it
is but then once we do that we can say
okay here's the rectangle to I this is
the grid span we're going to say get
grits fan and we're going to say for the
screen area of the sprite bound that
we're on and we're going to take min x
and x x and i'm assuming that that
probably if it's max x we should do
great like less than or equal to because
that's probably the more sensical
linguistic interpretation there so it's
probably the least likely to be
confusing and have have errors about
what people think is included in what
it's not right and so yeah I would also
like to put some assertions here on our
calculations to make sure they're not
completely bogus well actually I guess
the assertions probably aren't where
we're going to need we're probably going
to want clipping right so we're probably
going to want to say that if result men
x is less than zero you know and I'll
maybe I'll do it this way and same thing
here so this way the the things the
coordinates are all going to be clipped
I so there you go so this is basically
just a thing to make sure that you know
we're always inside the grid after we're
done now I guess there's a slight other
thing here that we might want to do
which is you know maybe we want to do
this and the reason that I say that is
because we may want to return a bull
here which is is this thing even in the
grid at all because if we find that this
thing is outside of the screen area
entirely then we really don't have any
reason to to process it right so you
might argue that this makes a lot more
sense as a code structure because we're
going to say well if this thing comes
back and tells us there is no real you
know this this thing's off the edges of
the screen well we don't need to sort it
anymore because I mean who cares right
just discard it it doesn't matter now
that's not one hundred percent true so
because this is a topological sort we
might get into situations where
something off-screen going off the
screen changes the topological sort and
you get some kind of a pop but my
expectation would be that if that was
true we probably have a problem with the
sort anyway because you know if it's not
producing a stable sort in that
situation we're probably going to have
to adjust the rule for other reasons now
don't know that that's true we'll see if
it turns out it's pretty easy for us to
get rid of that that discard if it turns
out that that's not true right alright
so here's the grid X grid why testing
and my assumption is that as we come
through here like I said we could
probably just do the edge adding right
here now there is a little bit of a
downside to this and I'm not sure
exactly how to I'm not sure exactly how
I want to deal with this but I suspect
that I will need a generation number
here and the reason that I suspect I'll
need a generation number or something if
I was to do it this is why we sort of
saying I'd like to do it out here
instead is because there would be
nothing from stopped because I'm doing
this / grid cell there'd be nothing
stopping me from adding multiple edges
well you know what I guess doesn't
matter if I had multiple edges if I have
multiple edges doesn't matter because
it'll it'll get cleaned up in this past
let me try to be a little bit less out
spit in my head on that so let's say
I've got a situation that looks like
this right here is a a rectangle and
here is another rectangle now obviously
these two rectangles overlap let's call
this one a let's call this one be so
obviously we want an a you know in front
of its in front of
be so we want to add that edge but if
you look at what's going to happen here
we're going to be looking at it from the
perspective of grid cells for testing
and so what we're going to see is we're
going to see be twice when we when we
get rate through and we'll add if we
just did naive testing we would end up
adding it when we did this sells tests
we dad at one time and we do this sells
test we dad at one time and we end up
with two edges to the same note but like
I was saying I guess it doesn't matter
because it gets cleaned up in this phase
because here we already would have
visited it so we wouldn't test it and
we'd be fine now one problem with it is
I think it would think everything was a
cycle all the time so it would kind of
break our cycle testing and I don't
really know what we would do about that
since we don't super care about the
cycle testing I'm not sure how much that
matters but if we needed to start
breaking cycles intelligently it might
and so the problem that I see here is
just figuring out well okay if I didn't
want to do that how would I make sure
that I only ever test this against test
this pair one time even if I encounter
the same one in multiple grids squares
right and in order to do that I would
need like I said some kind of a
generation number to prevent me from
doing that test ad infinitum and so we
could do that or we could not do that I
don't know we'll see in a second whether
we want do that or not it doesn't affect
the algorithm one way or the other but
it affects whether we can do the cycle
testing in the way that I was doing it
and so you know we'll consider it it's a
pretty easy change to make so here we
are with our sort of bucketing there and
you know in the the get greens grid span
call obviously I've got this result
rectangle coming in and what I need to
do for this result rectangle is I need
to sort of now i need to bin the screen
area that's coming in verse
is the total screen area so I I guess we
would say this is maybe else I'll call
this the source in this the desk so what
we need to do is figure out a way of
getting the source into those buckets
now we've done this before right this is
a this is a truncation kind of a of a
process right and we need one more piece
of information or to do it which is
going to be how do we know how big the
actual cells are right so we need
something here that's going to be like a
v2 which is our seldom however big the
grid you know cells are but once we know
how big this the cell the cells are it's
a pretty straightforward computation for
us like I said we've done it many times
before all we have to do is take one of
the source inputs right like get min
corner of the source so if we were to
look at what the minimum corner was and
we want to figure out where that is in
our cell space we just have to do a
multiplication by whatever the inverse
of that cell look we want to divide by
the cell dimp right now we don't want to
compute that in verse every time
probably I mean although these days
divides are cheap we probably just could
but you know let's say we pre inverted
it so we're just going to do an inverse
seldom times the min corner in this case
it's a hadamard product because we
actually want to multiply you know the x
and x the x and the y by the y but that
gives us back what's going to be our
actual min value this is like our men in
float space right and the same would be
true for the max the exact same process
would give us our max corner where that
is inside the grid once I have the men
in the max that I'm going to use for the
grid now it's a simple matter of taking
those and truncating them down to make
whatever the actual integer value is
that they would go
in for the grid right so now I'm just
going to say well okay my destination
min x is just the men are as X and we're
just truncating this down so this is a
truncate down and in each case you know
it's it's pretty pretty darn straight
forward right so that's that's really it
and so what I need to do now is I just
need to have my inverse cell dimension
there I need to figure out what that's
actually going to be that inverse cell
dimension is just going to be you know
one over it's just going to be 1 over
whatever the cell dims actually are and
so all I need to figure out in order to
finish is I need to figure out ooh I'm
not time I need to figure out what is
the dimension of one of these grid cells
well I would need to know the screen
area but if I knew the screen area so
like if I knew the screen width in
pixels right or whatever it is it
actually isn't even really matter but
whatever the demarcation is of the
screen that these area that these nodes
are coming in I just need to take
whatever that screen with is divide it
by the number of these cells that I have
right and that's going to give me the
actual value that I need now if you see
what happens there I've got this divide
and I'm immediately going to invert it
if I want to I can just do the divide
the other way round first time out and
have my inverse seldom directly and you
know that's probably a easier thing to
do right all right so let's take a look
at this oops
and see can we get the information that
we actually need here right because when
we do the build sprite graph and we have
the game render command stuff happening
here I need some way of getting that
information about the size of the screen
right which I don't know that we
actually have yet so let's see Hey look
we've got width and height and I think
that's all we need so what that means is
when i call my what i call my function
here i should be able to just pass it
screen width and height there should you
cast it certainly and that's easy-peasy
ok so if i go to commands with and
commands height i build it and let's see
what else we got here syntax error get
grid span oops we only have be 32 s here
and i agree with that so what we want to
do here is have a be 32 that's like
inside with something
okay so this is a little bit sloppy here
but what we need to do is just go okay
we want to know whether this thing is
entirely outside of the screen area like
completely right and now I think about
it you know maybe this was all kind of
stupid although well no I don't know
because I kind of want that to be
uniform function but what I was thinking
as well you know we need to know the
screen within the screen height in order
for it to do the rejection which means i
would need to pass those as well to get
grids fan which is kind of a pain right
it would be nice it was a little cleaner
than that but what are you going to do
so if i want to test here to see whether
this is actually inside or not what i
could do is right here just say like if
rectangles intersect and have like you
know screen area and sore screen total
screen like that and source right and if
they intersect then it's inside and in
fact I could to actually do it this way
and then I could just pass a rectangle
that was the screen rectangle right
that's certainly plausible and if I want
to do that I'd just say like all right
I've got a rectangle here it's the total
screen rectangle it's a recommend max
kind of situation the min is just going
to be 00 the max is going to be you know
screen with screen height okay so yeah
oops that's what's be right down to what
are you complaining about sir Sir I see
what you are complaining about you are
complaining about those which are not
supposed to be there okay so get grid
span now kind of has some stuff it's got
to take it's got to take the total
screen it's got to take the inverse
seldom it's got to take the screen area
and then it's got to take the
destination not a huge deal uh these are
Esther d2's I guess and this requires an
arena and I think this occupant index
but i believe just in time for the QA i
believe we now are bucketing so yeah we
haven't quite gotten to the point where
we're actually using it for acceleration
so now we're kind of just bucketing and
we're not actually doing anything with
the buckets but that can be tomorrow's
job
it's QA time
the mic D X using the grid system do you
think that would be good to use for
pixel perfect collision yeah I mean
pixel perfect collision is is actually
not really related I guess is what I
would say let me try to explain why it's
not so you know fundamentally speaking
you've got some sprites right and what
you want to know is do these two things
intersect and if I want to know whether
the pixels of them actually intersect
well obviously the first question is do
the rectangles intersect because you
would never start testing the pixels if
you hadn't tested the rectangles
themselves right so once I determine
that these two rectangles intersect then
I have to look at the pixels in these
two sub rectangles of each sprite right
and that is a separate pixel test so I
have to do the wreck test and then I
have to do the pixel test so we're doing
this stage it doesn't matter whether
this stage is happening or not right
it's completely unrelated it's just
something you would do extra if you
wanted to do pixel accurate testing and
furthermore what you'd probably have to
do if you wanted it to be fast is you'd
probably have to break these up into
blocks that said whether there was stuff
in them maybe so you didn't have to
check every pixel if you were doing a
high resolution so you'd probably need
to do some sort of grid-based encoding
of your sprite as well but really the
grid-based binning it doesn't have it
whether you were doing a pixel test or a
wreck test you're always going to test
the rectangles first and it doesn't
matter what you're doing down the line
from that it's it's the same at this
point either way
so whether you decide to use a pixel
test or not you wouldn't really care i
don't think about the inflammation at
this level would be the same in both
cases would be my would be my guess thus
isaac why not have the debug overlay
rendered to a separate layer and have it
draw in the order submitted instead of
wasting time sorting uh yeah i'm not
opposed to that like i said that's a
that was exactly i think literally quite
literally what i said when i was
pointing that out but the reason was
because i know we're going to have a lot
of sprites the debug system now is the
best stress test because it happens to
have a ton of sprites so since I just
wanted to do this anyway I want to make
sure it's fast enough I don't think
there's any point in doing that for the
debug layer because I think this will be
plenty fast enough right what I'm about
to do I think we'll be fine and so at
that point I just be wasting time if I
also did some other solution to make
sure the debug layer didn't have to go
through the sort because i want the sort
to be fast enough for that
sighs like I think a sort free mode
would work well with a cutscene as well
well but the cutscene works well with
the sort mode though so we don't really
need to have like different modes if
there's no reason for them right
any other programming questions from
today
miss assuming again today why do you not
use the summed rectangle of the hero
sprites for draw sorting and draw the
integral parts in a set order that is
exactly what we were going to do I don't
know if you plot that before when I
saying now that we have the ability in
the sorting thing to just say this thing
sorts in front of this other thing I
probably will convert to using that but
at the moment we haven't augmented the
render system to know that meaning we
don't have a way of actually sending
that information down the pipeline and
in the past we didn't have a way of
acting on that information either really
although I guess we could have probably
hacked it the same way by just saying
hey sort this like virtual nub that's
like a couple different bitmaps together
right so we could do that but know that
that is exactly what I would like to do
we just haven't gotten there yet
you
if you can something exciting happening
over at Molly rocket sorry not what does
that refer to dan 020 can using c
programming optimize the game more than
C++ uh you know it's a tough question to
answer because it depends on what you
mean by optimized right I in general
unless something very strange is going
on c is a subset of C++ to a certain
extent CC 99 does I think have some
things that people this doesn't have eat
though oddly enough but I don't think
they're super optimization related right
meaning there's a couple's in fact
syntactic things or whatever but you
know C and C++ as far as optimization is
concerned in general anything that you
could have written in c you can also
write in C++ for the most part there's
very little outside of the Venn diagram
there right I so really the reason that
you know C is sometimes or might why you
might perceive or why one could maybe
make a statement like C is fat you know
it can be optimized better than C++ or C
is more obvious is not because you
couldn't have written the same program
in C++ it's because C++ typically has a
lot of features in it that encourage
slow programming and since C just
doesn't have those features the
programmer is not going to accidentally
use them right but but if the programmer
simply doesn't do those things that are
slower in C++ then it's not like the
language itself is somehow going to be
slower right
and and so to elaborate that on that
just a little bit is c++ you know has a
number of features that are designed to
sort of do a lot of things automatically
right for example you know constructors
and operator overloading and you know it
conversions that you can define all
these sorts of things what that means is
that any line of code in C++ might
although it looks very innocuous might
actually do hundreds of thousands of
cycles worth of stuff and so it's very
easy for a C++ programmer to
accidentally write code that is very
slow without really thinking about it
because they just did a few little
things and oh they didn't realize this
was going to call like 50 functions and
do 20 different conversions and all this
other stuff right so in that sense C++
can be a lot slower right but it's only
because you were using those features of
C++ the language gave you the
opportunity to do something slow and you
took it right but it's not like you
couldn't have just written the
equivalent see version still in C++
right so for the most part unless
there's something that I'm not that's
like slipping my mind I can't think of
anything inherently slower about C++
code than C code it's just about whether
you decide to use certain C++ features
in ways that cause lethargy in the code
if that makes sense
uplink coder says rtti well rtti doesn't
affect your code at all if you don't use
virtual types right I mean runtime type
information doesn't get added to see
code written in C++ so it's exactly the
same I believe as what I was just saying
is that you have to actually use these
features in order for them to start
costing you something right and the same
is true of exceptions if you never throw
an exception the compiler doesn't have
to do any exception handling nonsense in
your code now granted that stuff is kind
of already in there now because windows
structure exception handling is usually
in there and blah blah blah so I think
even see code now currently pays the
cost of exception handling so
alright
alright folks I'm going to wind it down
thank you everyone for joining me for
those sort of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always
tomorrow we will go ahead and use our
acceleration structure to see if we
can't speed up that collision testing
well overlap testing I should say but
until then if you want to follow along
with the code at home you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero or
it comes with a source code if you want
to play around with it we also have
forums you can go to ask questions a
patreon page while support our video
series tweetbot that tweets the schedule
at you if you are interested to know
when we're going to be live and an
episode guide that you can use to catch
up on old episodes that is it for today
I will be back here tomorrow at eight
p.m. pacific daylight time until then
have fun coding and I will see you guys
on the internet taking use everyone