hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show Rico to complete-game live on
stream we're in the thick of it now we
have a bunch of stuff we've got to do
because we basically have everything
kind of coming together here and we need
to start cleaning up everything and
making it reasonable to I guess see what
the game actually looks like and plays
like right we finished pretty much all
the engine component work and we know
how it all fits together so now it's
time for us to actually start bolting
things down and and pulling them
together which really has to kind of be
done in them in a bit of a in my opinion
sort of buckshot fashion because every
little piece sort of has to kind of now
be reevaluated a little bit and go like
okay how does this part want to really
work let's like define that hardcore now
we know where it slots in but you know
we maybe we didn't know a couple things
about it before but we know them now and
so on so there's a bunch of things we
want to do one thing that we need to do
also is put art in the game and our
circumstances has definitely changed
with respect to that when I first
started this and you know it hasn't been
a priority putting art in the game was
just not important for building an
engine other than just having some test
assets but once you actually start
building the game game obviously the art
is crucial because everything that you
see on the screen comes from the artists
and without that you have no idea what
things are supposed to look like or how
they're supposed to behave or anything
because you can't really see what the
context is or what things are going to
look like can't make decisions certainly
can't make scissors without say lighting
without putting the art in right so one
of the things about that is originally I
didn't think we were going to have any
real direct artwork on the game because
I was originally just contracting with
Junction for it and she was remote she's
in China and well she's Sonny's in China
sometimes in in other parts of the world
she travels a lot and so basically what
happened there was you know just gonna
be like sending some sprites and we'll
just put them in
it's kind of a hands-off process and you
know we just contract for something then
just use them but eventually we ended up
not doing that because she wanted to go
work on other things and Anna was
willing to do all the stuff for handmade
hero as well so that means we actually
have the opportunity to have someone
work directly on the art for the game
which is a big difference those are very
different processes and so what I'd like
to do is I'd like to make it now that
we're going to actually start crafting
these worlds it's probably worth our
time to go ahead and make the asset
system load on demand because we now
have the opportunity to have someone
actually sit down with the game and
improve the art based on what they see
in the game which was not really
something we were ever gonna have before
so I think that's a really big one we
want to do and so if I look at the
spread of what we're gonna do here we
want to fix the camera stuff to make
that be working the way we want we want
to fix the lighting stuff and we want to
fix the art stuff all of that stuff now
can come together because we see I think
we see everything exactly how it is
right I mean this is the game now I
think is clear to me and the engine
parts are clear there's not a lot of
mystery there to it so I want to go
ahead and start to get all of those
together so that that can take shape and
the one main thing I think that we want
to add asset wise is the ability to do
those kinds of loads so I think it's
worth probably spinning through that
system and making that stuff work and
it's not that hard to do we basically
have a system currently that loads more
than one asset file anyway so allowing
it to on-demand replace an asset is
probably not a big deal like there's
really just not a lot to it I don't
think that we would encounter there we
already have bitmap eviction and stuff
like this and so once you have those
things in place it's sort of the case
that having it load out of a file on
demand if we need it to or something
like this shouldn't really be
problem so I think that's what we want
to do and we can go from there now let's
take a look at what that would entail
I'm gonna go ahead and do a little build
here and run uh so you know if we
imagine what we're looking at here so
the three things I've talked about the
three things we want to do is one we
want to make the lighting bounds
accurately reflect what's on the screen
so that's one thing I talked about the
second thing I talked about was the
camera right now the camera is is you
know you can see it's sort of working
there a little bit but it doesn't really
adjust correctly for larger or smaller
rooms and so on so you want adjust the
lighting bounce we want adjust the
camera bounce and then the other thing
we want to do is if we imagined now that
we actually do have the opportunity to
hand this off to an artist and say hey
you know curious actually
someone who's gonna could work directly
on the game why don't you paint some
textures to go on these on these walls
and such what we would like to be able
to do is introduce a key or just
automatically reload from disk or
whatever some files that say what the
art can be in certain places and then
just have those show up right in the
game automatically and we still probably
want the game to function the way that
it currently functions where we can ship
a asset file that just consolidates
things and makes it easier to understand
what's in there so I don't really want
to gut what's in there currently I just
want to add something on top that will
do that right so those are the three
things that I'm looking at that I would
like to get right now and so that we can
go from there and and and start to do
focus on actual world Jen right because
that's the other thing is I want I need
to be able to place like objects and
characters and stuff in here as part of
the world Jen in fact I already would
like to do that
even before we start to get to more
complex topology stuff that I'd like to
do with the world Jen even right now
we've got an orphanage we need to
populate the orphanage with stuff right
and at the moment we are not populating
the orphanage with stuff right we have
no idea right now of what can go in this
orphanage we don't have anything like
that and so we need to sort of get there
right so these are our tasks I don't
know which ones I necessarily want to do
first I think what I might do is I think
I might want to focus on the camera for
starters and just get that working
because we have most of that stuff and I
think we want to just go ahead and
finish that up and then I'll do the
lighting bounds while I'm doing the
camera and I won't change the lighting
algorithm like we want to go in and
continue to improve that algorithm a
little bit later on like I said we want
to place the lighting points right now
they're kind of haphazardly just strewn
around the boxes in the level so we want
to like do that a little bit more
carefully as well as we go as part of
the generative routine so we'll be doing
that part as well but at the moment what
we want to do is is just make it so that
the lighting picks the right region
right now we've got some other concerns
here that you can see that we sort of
have ongoing if you look at the way that
the characters work even when we put in
the new character sprites I don't know
how I really like the perspective field
that we have here but we you can see
there's problems with it going through
sideways doors you can see that is just
gonna produce an unwelcome intersection
there right and I think we might be able
to fix that like we'll see with the
sprites but that's another thing that
we're gonna be looking at as we are I
shouldn't say we're gonna be look at it
that's another big reason why we want to
get some you know either
final or close to final versions of
certain sprites into the game so that we
can tune things like that whereas right
now we're flying blind on some of those
things and now that we've gotten to the
point where everything's in place and we
want to kind of converge on a game we
can't really do
that again without having really good
knowledge of what's actually supposed to
happen artistically there and we need to
make those decisions so that's what we
want to do right now and so I'm going to
move through those things so let's start
like I said in order oh I forgot I have
those keys for changing the lighting
it's kind of fun alright so anyway
that's what I want to do I want to go
ahead and push towards that so let's
just take a look at where that sort of
stuff is happening in terms of the
camera and so on and and let's see what
we might want to do with that so for
starters I was saying the lighting
bounds we know that there's some stuff
happening with lighting bands here you
can sort of see this light bounce stuff
happening and you can see that really
both of these are kind of ad-hoc so what
you can see is we're taking some
variable called standard room dimension
and we're just going well look we know
there's some size we said rooms were and
we're just gonna arbitrarily like decide
that whatever the standard room
dimension is we'll do three wide of that
right but that doesn't really help us
you know we're talking about a world
that's gonna have different sized rooms
and it's just it doesn't really make
sense as the thing that we want and the
same thing goes true for the light
bounce so like you know a trivial fix
here is just make the light bounce
larger and then when we when we run it
you know we hope that that covers it now
and that's fine but remember light
bounds are costly so yeah now we're
we're assimilating more of a space but
we're costing more frame time because
we're gathering up more space and
similarly what you can see is because
the simulation bounds are focused on
room centers you can also see during the
transition the light bound is kind of in
the wrong place and we see an unlit
region for a little while right so all
of these things are sort of
you should be aware of they're not what
we want to do and so you know if for
example I just made the another solution
here just to give you some examples is
to just light everything that we
simulate again to slow and we're
lighting tons of stuff we don't need to
light so we keep impacting the frame
rate potentially negatively here and
make work a lot harder for ourselves
looks like we also get into situations
where we blow out the size of what we
have right this you can't see either
this is an optimized build so it looks
like it's breaking on a completely
aligned that couldn't possibly break but
really what we're seeing here is we're
running out of room for storing our
lights so we're blowing out those
buffers there right uh so again you know
a solution would be to light everything
again we really don't want to do that
because then in addition to having to
have larger buffers to stores up it's
just gonna slow us down right so what we
want here instead is a more camera
centric thing for the lights and a more
camera centric thing for the simulation
bounds as well just slightly different
right so here we've got this camera
bounds in meters situation here this is
the camera the camera bounds that we're
saying we're sort of seeing here right I
don't know do we draw this I don't know
if we do
let's take a look and we try this we
don't really draw this so I want to draw
this so we can see where it is so in
here what are we drawing so we draw the
screen bounds we draw those in yellow we
draw the symbols in cyan and then a
purple region that's the the groans
creat the DM groan screen bounds there
let me take a look here which ones are
these we see so we can see the purple
region very clearly but I don't see any
of the other regions so let's take a
look at those so for example I don't see
the sim bond region all I see is the
world Simpson region bounds so why is
that
we should be seeing a three world it
might be because it's right on top so
let's take a look at what happens here I
just want to see what's going on here so
we're seeing the purple one I'm going to
comment this out okay so those are just
coincident so I'm just gonna leave us
drawing for now well I guess what I can
do is use this line to draw the other
thing I want to draw I'm gonna leave us
drawing the the sim region bounce and
what I will do here is I'll draw the
light bounce so that way I can see both
of those two things at the same time so
there's the simulation region
there's the region we're lighting and as
you can see the lighting lines up with
that region so it makes sense right and
our goal is to never see while we're
doing something like this that line and
you can see we clearly do see it as the
camera moves because the camera wasn't
that hot so you can sort of see what we
would like to do for starters is slide
that that region right along with the
camera so instead for example of the
light bounce being centered around zero
zero zero we really want them to be
displaced by the cameras motion you know
what I'm saying so you can see here when
we're talking about for example the
camera rect here where we go get camera
rectangle at target I'm interested to
know
in fact because this villain tours to go
we're not drawing this world camera rect
I don't think and I think we would like
to write let's find out
so in here we've got these screen bounds
what I'd like to do is probably push a
volume outline for this thing I'm
assuming I can specify one of these keys
rectangle threes right I'm assuming I
can pass one of those down and draw it
so I'm specifying world camera rect and
I wanted to see where that is so you can
see so I suspect just based on what I'm
looking at here that a big part of our
problem now is that we've obvious that
code is obviously borked right we
probably never updated it so there's the
rectangle I was drawing and that yellow
rectangle is must be the screen bounds
and so on right they're just wrong and
so I think what we want to do is is we
need to like make that routine actually
work so what we want to do is we want to
produce something that that draws
exactly the screen region based on on
the kick current camera view because
that's gonna tell us what's in view and
that will tell us what we need to light
right that's what we're actually looking
for here we want something that's going
to tell us that information so I think
where we want to start our little
adventure here is probably right there
in fixing that routine because that
routine is one that we need for
everything else that that's camera track
related so let's start with that I don't
actually remember writing that routine
it's been a long time so let's just look
at it
there's probably it to do in there
that's like update to the new 3d system
or something like this and that is
exactly what we need to do right so here
is our unprojected so
you know it looks like we actually at
least nominally we're making an effort
here though right this is I don't know
yeah like how we got away with that with
without you in there but pretty
obviously stubbed I like we say get
rectangle at Target and we just say that
Z is eight the magical eight well okay
so we have two things to do one is we
need to validate our unprojected
and our unprojected is the function that
tries to take our camera system and
reverse a projection that goes through
it so we need to make sure that that's
working properly so all of these things
in here right have to work properly
and these all seem to be written I mean
I like the way these are written they're
all written in terms of saying tell me
how far out from the camera you wanted
me to go so that all seems good yeah so
that all seems good
so really the primary thing we want to
start with before we start debugging
this because maybe there are some things
we change in here that make this
function no longer accurate in terms of
product on projections so we want to we
need to go assess that but when we look
at this what we see immediately is just
that like yeah in order to make this
function actually work we need to
actually specify what the target is
you're trying to look at and so in order
to get that we need to know like what is
that target point right like how far is
that target so I think what we want to
do there is a probably just passed the Z
in like so and force the person who's
calling us to tell us that what they're
actually looking for there because if
you remember back here where we sort of
set up the camera we know that we are
doing some kind of a of a targeted based
cam and we've got two situations where
that happens one is where we set up the
camera to sort of to be a debug camera
where we can orbit it around and stuff
and there we definitely know what the
target is because we literally move away
by whatever the debug camera dolly is
whatever that amount is so we know that
world mode debug camera dolly would be
the correct thing if we was in that
camera but that's the debug camera so
the other camera we have is the gameplay
camera and the gameplay camera tells us
how far away from whatever the target is
that we're looking at that we want to to
how we want to adjust it for that for
you know where it is in the game and
what we know about that is we don't set
that piece of information anywhere can
and that's probably the thing that
stopped us when we were initially typing
this in from doing the right thing there
and we just stuck an 8 in there too you
know until we were gonna go make that
code more correct so I think what we
want to do here is take a look at when
we're dealing with the camera what we
want to do is when we update one of
these cameras I think we want to make
sure we remember what we were looking at
right and to the extent that we do we're
okay to accept that we don't were in
trouble so let's go ahead and take a
look at how that actually works that's
stored I believe in the world mode
somewhere here there it is so we've got
this game camera right stored in the
world mode and that game camera tells us
a bunch of stuff here's like the target
P for example and the target offset Z so
I think what we probably want to look at
here is this is where the camera is
actually at at the moment and so what we
want to do I'm sorry this is what the
cat where the camera is actually at at
the moment this is what the camera is
trying to look at and we've got a bunch
of Z information here that we should be
passing so I think the goal should be
let's make sure we send the right
information down from like the target
offset Z or whatever else let's make
sure we get that stuff in there
correctly and then we'll see what we're
doing so I'm going to start by assessing
this routine and see what we're actually
setting those values to you can see in
here we set a bunch of stuff like here's
how we figure out where our target is
and then we kind of come through here
and you can see us doing some Z work on
what we expect the offset see the camera
debate target offset Z is what I think
we're moving to offset Z is what we're
actually using in terms of our distance
off of the floor there right and so I
think
I think the key here is just to make
sure we understand exactly what we're
storing for where the camera view comes
from so I just want to pop back here and
make sure we've got it right you can see
here we're doing a bunch of work to
figure out where the camera is placed
and what you can see here as we go we
have the simulation center for the
camera and we've got the position of the
camera and that's the Delta that Delta
you know the offset Z is just not used
here right and so the offset Z is an
interim computation and so I think what
we want I think what we want here
is to make sure we're recording this
value accurately to what we're looking
at so for example you can see target
offset Z being 16 here that controls how
far away the camera tries to place
itself from things right so if I was to
dynamically change this right let's
compile the game we should zoom in I
think
oops I'll just pass 8 here again that's
what we were passing before right so
we'll zoom in if that gets set to
something else this is what it was set
to and what you can see here is the
target offset Z ends up being something
that never really that never really gets
taken into account there so it must be
where we must take that into account
somewhere ah there it is right there
ok so never mind I did do it when I
searched before I wasn't searching the
right place so that's where we're
setting that camera offset with the
offset Z so that means this value will
be the correct value for how far away we
are from the thing we're looking at
right and so now that I've set that what
we want to see is can we get this box
now to be somewhere sensible right we
want that we want to now see if we can
get the computation of that box to be
something sensible so what we're seeing
now is when we call where did it go
get camera rectangular target we get
this world camera rekt right and we
don't delete it all it's just there and
we draw it so we push a volume outline
for this world camera rect at that point
and so what we want to see is we want to
see that now encompassing the screen so
we want to see you know when we get that
when we make that call we want to see
that rectangle inscribe the screen
assuming we draw it at the center point
that we're actually looking at right at
the target P which at the moment we
would be once the camera settles we
would be right I so I think that's all
we should need to focus on now
so moving back over to the render group
when we're calling this so when we're
calling this the question is why are we
not getting reasonable results back from
this call so the game X forum we assume
is set correctly at the time that we
make this call now maybe that's an
incorrect assumption but I think it is
because right here we call set camera
transform and what you can see here is
this this call right here especially
when we're not using a debug camera but
I believe the true and the false control
whether it sets the game one or the
debug one or whatever right
oh no sorry that's camera is debug
that's what that is right there so it's
this flag right so when we set that this
right here should set that game xform up
and that's what we should be pulling
from so I believe this will be
unprotected with the correct things and
you can see us sending 0 0 and then
screen to mention down now screen to
mention I don't really remember when we
set that part either so you know that
could be an incorrect value that's being
set there I'm not sure so first thing we
might want to do is take a look at
what's going on
but assuming that that was passed
correctly then when we do our
unprojected down is zero zero the next
thing that we run projecting is the
screen dimensions so the two sort of
corner pieces and we run projecting down
where they would be in terms of like out
in the in the at that distance from the
camera so when we cur instruct our
probes II what we're doing here is
saying well whatever the world distances
from the camera we're gonna go ahead and
try to inverse transform those points so
here we're saying hmm we're taking the
the there brendor transform and we're
looking at the z axis and we're
multiplying it by the z axis that's
correct that's how far we'd be going
right and then we're subtracting that
from the transform P because we're going
out the negative of that and that's the
place we're starting from that makes
sense we're doing the forward projection
of that out into the world
[Music]
hmm
all right so basically what we did is we
produced the clipped value for a point
that's just that far away and Z it seems
reasonable to me actually we take the
screen center we offset the XY value
we're trying to actually compute we
offset that from the screen Center we
then produced a clip space x and y by
scaling that right out so that we're
producing the unit rectangle there we
then produced the clip coordinates and
we project the clip coordinates back
through the inverse projection matrix to
get the world location
so what I would say about that though is
it's not white correct right because
technically that wouldn't produce the
world location that would produce the
world location if the camera had not
moved anywhere which I guess that's what
we're calling it so I mean it is a world
P in that sense because we're centered
around zero zero zero so I suppose
that's okay but that does seem pretty
reasonable I'm interested to know what
screen dim is
so it's just the pixel width in pixels
height which is what we would expect
so that mouth seems good too
all right so I don't see any obvious
problem serious so I'm gonna go ahead
and do a debug build and I'm gonna step
in and I just want to look at what
happened so now you can see that as the
frame rate slows down you can see this
is now the debug build right so let me
go ahead and go into the debugger and
let me step into that specific routine
which is really only called there so we
know that that's what it's going to be
so the distance is properly passing just
about 16 it hasn't quite converged on it
because of the bad way if we prove our
interpolator there's a to do about that
[Music]
so 16 is what we expected to see there
and do see so that's a good thing so
let's look at how the minimum corner is
projected out here we are on the
unprojected so I'm gonna take a look at
these and see so pixels XY should just
be the zero zero vector right because
we're trying to the upper corner of the
screen the world distance from camera Z
should be that 16 value and then the X
forum should do that I don't know why
they did this in the new version of
Visual Studio they they made it so
return doesn't go to the next one of
these I have no idea why they would do
that it's so annoying I just I have no
idea why you would do that but they did
it so in here we have the transform and
it's a little bit hard to see because of
the way that's laid out here
unfortunately visual studio doesn't have
a matrix view it should by now I could
think but it doesn't so yeah they were
too busy making it so that hitting
return doesn't go to the next line so
anyway when you take a look at what's
going on here what you can see is that
our x-coordinate is unadulterated it
passes through for the world transform
and then our y and z is rotated like
this a little bit which is X life but
for the most part
and this is good this is the identity
matrix so really nothing is happening
here you know this is this is
effectively a non transform it's only
this piece here that's that's relevant
to us so what you can see first of all
is when we do our transform here the Z
value there sort of helps tell us how we
were marching out along the z axis we're
going to go straight down Z and when we
add the offset we're basically just
gonna add a 16 to it so what's gonna
happen here is our probe Z is gonna
basically come out to be a 0 right
because that's that's exactly what we
expect to see there let me put that down
here so looking at here what you can see
is this is basically the 0 vector right
in fact if I do it like this you can see
a little easier so 0 substantively 0
right it's an e negative 7 so that's a
really low low number and then the Z of
0 so we that's also what we expect to
see because from the camera if we step
out that far we get to the 0 vector
there now part of the problem though I
think with the conceptualization of this
if I may is that I I feel like this
routine I don't I don't remember when we
wrote it I feel like this routine has
its head a little backwards here because
in on the one hand it's talking as if
the camera is already the center of the
world on the other hand it's doing its
adding this offset here and I'm not sure
why it's doing that
I don't think that's correct I wish I
could go back right now and watch the
video where we wrote this routine
because if you think about how this is
working its constructing something
relative to the camera here I don't know
if we like did that as an optimization
of what we were trying to do or
something but it seems like that should
be happening after the fact
right like this should be placing things
into the world by taking into account
the or the transform of this stuff after
the fact I would have thought would have
been how you would do it and maybe we
were just really clever here and this is
actually the correct way to do it but
doesn't seem like it and just to be a
little more concrete about what I'm
talking about so if you imagine what's
going on here I would have expected to
see something more like this yes there
are clip coordinates yes they got
transformed by the inverse transform but
then after that I would have expected to
see this
so the world P this is actually like I
would have expected to see something
more like this right so there's a camera
P and then there's a world P right and
the world P takes the result of the
camera P which is in camera space and
puts it out into the world by actually
like placing it through the forward
transform that's not what happened here
and I don't know why and so looking at
this I'm just a little confused was I
clever was I too clever was I just wrong
so who knows what happened here but if
you take a look here when we're actually
doing this computation so what I would
have expected is the Z value is the
world distance from the camera that's
being passed in should just be how far
out from the camera we go it wouldn't
take this into account instead what it
would do is just start with thinking you
were this far down the line and you
would go from there so for example when
we create this V 4 that's the probe Z I
would have expected to see I would have
expected to see that clip coordinate
it's just getting added on to
yeah
yeah I'm just not sure what that's
trying to accomplish there
it also seems like that was sort of
so let's think about this here a little
bit try to think of how I want to
approach this the I mean because the
other thing that you'll notice that
doesn't make a lot of sense to me either
is that box that we're looking at in
terms of where the camera transform
thinks it is there let's
was square which also doesn't really
make any sense because in theory the
aspect ratio should have been factored
into this as well and so the fact that
it wasn't is a little confusing to me
and I don't really understand why that
is happening so yeah just a lot of
confusion here on my part that needs to
be dug into anyway uh so yeah working
out the math here this is always the
hardest thing to do on stream because
it's difficult to work through
complicated things like this and talk
through it correctly but yeah I would
expect to see something here that that
puts this that applies this transform
the reason that I know that that kind of
has to be the case is one of the things
that you can see in this situation here
is that the x and y axes aren't taken -
aren't taken into account at all in the
unprotect which certainly can't be
correct right
when you go to unprojected ache into
account the x and y axis and the fact
that that was not happening is pretty
obviously busted I guess it's the probe
Z part there that was trying to do that
so let me see maybe I do maybe I can
think of how this is access to work so
when we take the probe Z we're going
ahead and taking the probe Z is this is
actually out in the real world literally
where the point would be relative to the
camera it's multiplying it by the
forward rotation matrix here so it's
rotating it also to point in the correct
direction and then it's looking at the
clip Z of that as being the Z over the W
now
the W in this case oh so no sorry it
never actually yeah I'm sorry this is
the wrong this is the wrong value here I
wanted the world transform so we have
the projection matrix here and here's
our actual render transform P X Y Z I
guess oh so maybe did we mush everything
down into that is this what we're
actually loading so does that have
everything in it if that's the case I
may stand corrected there let's take a
look yeah this is a little bit of code
archaeology here just to try to remember
exactly what I was doing
okay so I was for some reason thinking
about that a little bit backwards it
looks like yeah so it looks like we're
actually these matrices are actually the
whole deal they have everything baked
into them so that's actually the
projection and the transform like it's
what we would literally load into the
vertex shader right so I take it back
it's not as weird as I thought it was so
that makes a little more sense so then
then what we're saying here is this
right here actually puts us out at the
location in the world that we should be
right we're saying like okay here's
here's going from the camera location
out to a particular place were then
multiplying by the forward matrix to put
ourselves into actual projection space
meaning where we would be in the world
of the camera and then we're taking the
clip C value from that so this is not as
crazy as thought it was for some reason
when I saw a projection I was actually
thinking that that was just the
projection matrix not the projection
matrix and the sort of model view if you
will
combined together so that's okay and
maybe I'll make a note of that
just so I don't get confused again when
I look at that I can I can see a little
bit more quickly what's going on there
and that seems like a better idea
okay so yeah so this makes a lot more
sense now because this actually
constructs exactly where in the world
you would be at the end of the day and
you can see here that we're constructing
the clip see by doing the divide the the
opposite way there and so that seems are
reasonable so when we do the reverse
protection we should get the world's P
here there's just one weird part of that
which is when we do that
just wanna make sure we're doing
everything here
you know when we do that we are pressing
the correct size through so okay all
right
okay so I'm more comfortable that now
I'm not as scared of it as I was
originally let me go ahead and allow
this thing to run down to where we're
looking at it again and let me run
through here and take a look at these
values now so now that I'm more
comfortable what I'm looking at the
probe Z value that we get out here after
doing the forward projection is zero
zero zero right and let me just let me
jump in here one more time so when we
first construct it it's basically all
zeros when we go to do the forward
transform I would expect this
displacement to take effect right so
there's a displacement of ten on Z there
there it is okay good so I'm just I want
to make sure that was there when we
compute the clip see that's not really
coming into play quite yet let's take a
look the screen center screen Center
seems reasonable the clip space XY that
seems reasonable let's make sure these
convert to the unit rectangle they do
and so now when we produce that clip
value that seems okay
the only thing I'm not confident of is
the clip see so what will happen
normally is when you do that transform
what you would normally do is you would
take the value that ended up going into
the W coordinate and you divide
everything by that
so I'm not really sure this would be
operating correctly so that seems
erroneous to me the reason that seems a
little erroneous to me is because the
synthetic divide is the thing that maps
things into perspective doing it here
produces that prospectively divided Z
value but in order to get that
perspective coming out at the end you
would have to do another divide here
right so you you can't
this this seems a little backwards there
should be a divide happening here to
undo what would have been the
perspective divide like basically this
is missing a divide I feel like it's
missing or you know a multiply of an
inverse over here right stuffing the
clip Z value into here is not correct I
would argue because this multiply is not
going to do a divide this is just going
to do the matrix multiply that's all so
I think that's the problem with this
routine is it's not although it is going
to great lengths to produce a clip Z
value that is the correct value that Z
would have after transform it doesn't
matter
so this divide I don't first of all I
don't think this divide should be there
because again why would it be there that
divide is not it would just have to get
undone before the inverse projection
happened and then when the inverse
projection happens against the divine
should have happened before then because
these are post divide numbers am I wrong
about this guys
you know so it seems to me like that's
kind of misguided it seems like it's
just the z-value
and then when it gets reversed
transformed it should just be using that
value and the W value is what should
actually control these things right so
in here went before these go through
anything it's really this value should
be undoing you have to imagine that
these values were divided by probe Z dot
W in order to get into the clip space
the way they were right so what we
really want to do there is invert that
operation meaning that like the clip
space XY dot X should be x probe Z W as
the first thing that it does right so
that it seems like this was doing that
exactly backwards to me I don't think
that's all of our problem but that was
definitely a problem that that is not
that was not good what was happening
there I
yeah and that's all I can really say
about that so the first thing that I'm
still noticing here is that I never see
the white rectangle and I don't know why
I'd like to go make sure I understand
why but what you can see now is the the
yellow rectangle there that's being
drawn which let me just show you where
that was being drawn again it's right
down here
so the yellow reptile is being drawn
here for the screen bounds right and the
screen bounds are again built off of
that roll camera rect what you'll notice
is those are the right size now
so that that change I just made was did
exactly what I thought it did meaning
the code was doing it doing exactly what
I suspected was wrong because now we can
see a it's rectangular which is what we
expect and B it's the right size again
so this is correctly noting when I come
back to the screen view let me kind of
come back here you can kind of see that
it's it's correct now its size now it's
not facing the right direction but it's
not supposed to because the screen
bounds are by definition flat at the
moment in that space because you see we
created them flat so it's not it's fault
that they're facing right the wrong
direction but it's getting the correct
size now and that's what I wanted to see
there right so that's good you know
that's obviously a good thing but I
don't understand why I'm not seeing my
other rectangle is that's a little weird
so we did our world camera rect here
where we get the camera rect and it
comes back and then I tried to draw that
[Music]
here and I'm not seeing that thing this
yellow rectangle here is just a 1x1 cube
in the center I don't know why that's
there and I'm gonna get rid of it it's
not useful to us but this white
rectangle here is not showing up and I
don't really know why it's not showing
up because it should be somewhere I and
the fact that I don't see it anywhere is
a little disconcerting and I don't
really know what's going on there
because especially now that I know that
that thing is the correct size I don't
really understand okay so you could see
it it was kind of off in the distance
it's what it looked like it looked like
it was too far away somehow and then it
faded out now in this mode I feel like
there shouldn't be much fading so I
don't because this there it is so it
looks like the problem with that thing
is it's been played
East Way in the wrong place right it's
the correct size but it's placed
incorrectly and I and I don't know why
so that's the next thing you gotta
figure out is Wyatt what's going on with
that right
so again baby steps with debugging
something complicated like this it takes
a little while so this correctly
accounts for what I thought it needed to
account for certainly so that's good and
when we're producing the world P here
you can see us do the min corner Max
corners says here producing that result
so the kick the question now is why is
that offset so dramatically and how
could it be offset so dramatically and
still be producing the right size you
know so that's a little interesting so
let's go ahead and step through that
code now and see where we're going wrong
with our with our offset I it seems like
we're offsetting Z quite a bit too much
and so I must be missing one more
subtlety about the way this is
constructing the code so the first thing
I'm going to do when we run through here
is I'm just gonna go ahead and set a
breakpoint in and see I just want to see
when we actually do one of these oh
that's the mouse I want to see what we
get
so if we take a look at this we get
negative 26 negative 25 given that we're
16 away from like we're 16 units away am
I wrong about that given that were 16
units away it does seem odd to be
getting a number of that high right
we're getting exactly the right numbers
out of x and y but we're getting the
wrong number out of Z and so maybe I'm
thinking about the way that that Z value
comes out of the forward projection I'm
thinking maybe I'm thinking about that
incorrectly there
and you know what I might be because the
convention for how the Z comes through
is going to be that the Z needed to have
the W value pushed into it so that the Z
still comes out for z-buffering
uh so it could be that that does need to
be divided by the W and it could be that
this clip C computation was correct and
it was just this part that was missing
but I want to think that through a
little more so I'll test that to see if
I'm right about that but then we got to
go look at that / - I want to look at
the projection matrix again just to see
whether the projection matrix AI is
actually computing that way or not if
it's not then I'm wrong about that and
even if this works correctly I'm still
wrong
so there's that I'm just wrong about the
reason so it does look like that's the
case and and so now rotating around I
actually it does look exactly like what
we were expect now
so that now seems totally correct okay
so I'm guessing that what we do is we
multiply that yeah okay okay okay okay
so what we did there is in the
projection matrix we should see the W
get multiplied get multiplied into the Z
because when we divide by W we want the
Z to come out to be the same value it
used to be right so we should see that
if I if I go to the projection matrix
code I want to see that now to confirm
that I'm correct because don't really
want to just have the code work but not
know why that's a bad place to be and
especially with complicated stuff like
this right so I want to see here the I
want to see matching computations
basically for how for how W and Z are
computed so what we can see here is in
the forward transformation that we're
applying and this is just the projection
the perspective X bar this the only
primetime I'm not talking about the
rotational or displacement ask don't
care about those at all so I'm just I'm
on the projection you can see that we're
getting negative Z in here as the W
value so we're going to be dividing by
negative Z and we want the Z value to
come out to something specific here
between the near and far clip planes for
distance right in fact now that I look
at it so these values here world usage
of camera Z actually should be adjusted
by that near clip plane value as well
and it will be because of this forward
projection right so that's where that
will take place so then when it comes
out here we have the divide by Z baked
in to the e term here right we know that
this will come out between those two
after / after being divided by negative
Z which means that the negative Z was
multiplied in
yes
okay so I am fairly satisfied with that
now
okay I'm freely set a start that I'm
happy with how that went so I'm gonna go
ahead and and just verify now that that
moves with us as we go yeah okay so now
the next thing that I think we want to
do again to get the sliding behavior
that I wanted is that does not take into
account the camera displacement so if we
take a look at what happens here where
we do the the world camera rect you can
see here that we just do the offset Z we
need this kit world camera rect needs to
be offset it by the camera itself offset
because it's going to be moving right so
we have this in here this right here
right camera simulation center and
camera P we have sort of this this Delta
offset that we've set up where if we are
to render around yeah if we are to
render around 0 0 0 it's got this offset
baked into it right so we need the Delta
from sim value since 0 0 0 is going to
be the center of that simulation we need
the Delta from sim value to be baked
into our world camera rect if that makes
sense
so we effectively need to say that the
world camera rect which is giving us
what it would be if we were center
around zero zero zero for the camera
looking down we know we've got an offset
in there that pushes up we need the
opposite offset
in there right so this which has the
complete camera offset baked into it
[Music]
although unfortunately it's got rotation
as well uh just to give you a little bit
more understanding of what the problem
is here so when we set this camera
transform when we get the world camera
wrecked back we're then gonna draw it
again through the same camera transform
so we have to make sure that the values
that we're passing through here are
completely right
although now that I think about it since
it's already set since this camera
transform is already set when we do the
multiplication this should slide with it
when we do the world camera rect so I am
not sure why it doesn't let me
double-check
so this is why
hmm let's take a look at that least I
assume it's - Italy
mmm well maybe not if this is just
during a regular world transform so yeah
so what I can't under quite understand
there is why we're getting the world
camera rekt jumping when we move because
we shouldn't be seeing that right that's
the only thing that now I'm not quite
sure on so this white outline is
supposed to be directly what we got as
the world camera rectangle so while the
sim bounds while the I'm sorry the
screen bound which is reconstructed at
0-0 every time should totally do what
it's doing right that yellow that yellow
should be jumping the white should not
be jumping the white should slide with
the camera and the fact that the white
isn't sliding with the camera means
something's wrong there because we get
it we are setting the transform and then
getting the world camera rekt out as a
function of whatever is set as a
transform at that time right so I don't
understand why we would be seeing any
jumping when the camera when the when
the camera sim Center is moved because
the camera sim Center should be like
unrelated to what we see with the world
camera rect now maybe like this push
volume outline thing with the world
transform maybe that's doing something
weird and I can go in now and take a
look at that and just make sure that I'm
not just forgetting some extra sauce we
have there in the pipeline that explains
this situation more forthrightly but
that's that's the thing that's gonna
that's the last thing that's concerning
me right now
I want that file so here with volume
outline
so there is no offset P baked in here
which is good
so I yeah I don't see them I don't see
the
like the place where that jumpy
displacement is coming in right so
that's a puzzler for me that's a puzzler
for me that that is definitely because
so so even stuff like this which this
alters where the camera is every frame
but we don't reset the transform so you
know from you know what it could be
well no no I don't know it could be so I
feel like we've done most of the work
but we're still just a little bit off
and I do not know where that is coming
from but we definitely have some some
explaining to do here
[Music]
you
that needs a guarded divide do we have a
safe ratio function by the way
um so yeah what could be causing that
essentially what I'm seeing happen and I
just don't understand the reasoning for
it is it's it's positioning the white
rectangle as if the white rectangle were
not called every frame and based off the
camera position every frame but it's
supposed to be right it's supposed to be
taking into account the full camera
transform its using exactly the camera
transform as specified and so I'm just
not sure exactly why it wouldn't slide
along with the camera every time now if
I look back here at it a little bit more
closely what you can see is it is
sliding it's just sliding very subtly
and I suppose I could believe I can't
really believe that I was gonna say that
we just have the X and Y is wrong on
some kind of gross displacement level so
I don't know I'm puzzled by this I have
no good ideas about where that's not
moving
because the coordinates that come back
from that call should take into account
the location of the camera
let's take a look one more time so as
you can see here when we compute our
probe Z we compute that using the full
transform forward right there's nothing
weird about that I don't think you know
I don't see anything odd there
when we do the inverse transform for our
clip space coordinates that all seems
totally aboveboard
I mean so that definitely seems like
it's in the right position and that
min/max seems perfectly solid so yeah I
mean all of those things are done with
the actual projection matrix and include
the full 3d displacement of the camera
in the world and so the thing that I
just cannot wrap my head around is why
it would seem to be tied to the sim
Center right because that's what it
looks like it looks like it's tied to
the simulation center but I don't know
why so all of these you know these make
sense as to why they would be tied to
the simulation center because they are
forcing their Center to be at the
simulation center which is zero zero
right and then they're just using the
boundary value to determine how how
expansive they should be so that seems
totally plausible and reasonable you
know
but our world camera wreck should not be
centered around zero zero it should be
centered around wherever the camera
happens to be although now that I think
about it
well no I'm gonna stand by that so it
should not be centered around the zero
zero coordinate system in any particular
way
yeah so I stand by that the world camera
rect caught that we're computing here
should not be related to the simulation
center because it really just doesn't
care as far as I know what that is so
that's the part that I'm having trouble
coming up with how is the simulation
center ending up getting baked into here
essentially or is that not really what's
happening and I'm seeing something just
looks like that's what's happening and
there's actually some more subtle bug in
how we're producing those unprojected be
I totally willing to believe that is
possible but that's the thing that's
that's making me weirded out right is
that that that just really shouldn't be
possible so if we think about how this
is working you know when we do the
entity update stuff so you know when we
do this what you can see here is we set
the simulation center by taking the the
by taking the actual place we decided
the room was right and we set that up as
where we're gonna make the basis of our
coordinate system and that's great right
but what you can see here is when we
actually set up the camera itself what
we get here let me let me look at where
the camera offset variable comes from
here yeah so the camera offset is just
some distance above what's going on but
mostly the Delta from sim here at this
Delta from sim is what's allowing the
simulation center to be offset from the
camera and so zero zero zero is over
there for that reason right because we
subtracted from this to this and then we
use that Delta from sim as what we're
actually passing here to place the
camera in an actual location right
here's the the place that we're actually
zeroing the camera to the camera offset
right and so once we set that camera
transform that value should be baked
into the matrices and when we do the
unprojected get back should be in world
space at a place where when we
transformed through here should be right
where the camera actually is not where
the simulation center is which should be
unrelated so it seems like we're missing
that information and maybe the answer is
we're missing that information in here
right
so maybe the answer is the unprojected
it'ss placing things by the camera
transfer them somehow and I'm totally
willing to believe that that is the case
I'm just not seeing exactly how
I mean one way that that would be
failing is if the inverse matrix doesn't
properly have that information in it so
I mean anything's on the table at this
point but if the inverse projection
matrix was wrong there's your answer
right so let's take a look
so in order for it to be correct well we
can see it right here we're doing the
verification that it's correct right
here and so if we look at that we should
see we should see that come out to the
identity let's do it so if I look at
this right here this is called a set
camera transform I should be able to see
that inverse and whether or not it gets
set properly so I'm just gonna jump
right in there and do exactly that and
what I'm expecting to see if there's a
bug is that the identity matrix will
look like the identity matrix except for
an incorrect offset so in the offset
comm it would be wrong now what I don't
know is where this actually gets created
so camera C inverse versus proj inverse
here camera C is something that gets set
up here I don't know what that does
exactly right
looks like here we're testing this in
here as well let's take a look I mean so
that looks like a totally reasonable
inverse right so does that right so
those inverses look really good I don't
see any like there you know anything you
do in floating-point it's only gonna be
good five sig figs or so right so that's
negative eight negative 7 negative sick
those are all well within tolerance of
what I would expect so there's nothing
that looks out of place there to me at
all so let's go ahead and test the case
we care about as well so as we run
through here I'm gonna hop up and then
immediately when it switches over I'm
gonna go ahead and switch over to break
so as I step in here I want to look and
make sure that okay maybe when the
displacements get higher maybe we never
checked the camera transform there so
I'm just checking it again and again
what I want to see here is you know I
want to see that camera P being high
right it's really not that high so
that's a little unfortunate I feel like
it should be higher than that but you
know and that still looks totally good
so here's one that has a big move to it
so again I just want to take a look see
if I can catch anything here that looks
suspicious is it that just it seems
awfully low is it just me why is that so
low I feel like the camera displacement
should be quite a bit higher than that I
don't understand what I'm looking at
here I mean it moves several it should
have moved like quite a bit unless a
tile is only very small seems a little
weird
I mean if a standard room dimension is
12 then moving one room up should be
like six at least so why is that value
so low like what's going on there no
camera offset with Z that's makes sense
Delta from sim super small just how I
don't understand how is that possible
how are these so close together
something something's weird
something's fishy here
but I'm not sure what
you know what I'm saying right that
number is just really tiny that number
should be much higher there we go
all right so that's a much higher number
now so now let me look at what we
produce here just to be absolutely sure
this is right yeah so it's it's stable
the inverse is stable so that's good I
still think I'm a little suspicious but
yeah we do need to cap our frame rate at
some point here
all right so when I come out through the
top opening here I'm gonna go back and
yeah switch right there
just to make sure that this value is
higher
I do not understand how those are so
though alright so I want to investigate
this a little more cuz I'm weirded out
now so there's obviously something I
don't understand about the way the
system is working which probably means
it needs to get cleaned up which is good
because that's what we're doing but it
also means I need to investigate a
little bit further I want to see this
value like I want to see it drawn like
all the time so here it is right here
okay so it just must have been the
debugger like we just weren't be able to
break quite right because that's those
are the values I expected to see right
those are the values I expected to see
and so now if I look here you can see
that these that the camera box does
converge with that value it just isn't
moving nearly as much as it probably
should be right so it's as if those x
and y values are not being displaced by
the amount they should be so for example
it's as if the unprojected
is not
it's like that value is not doing the
displacement or not doing enough of the
displacement
I mean I think that's the only
explanation for what we're seeing
meaning when we do the transform the
displacement values in the other part of
the matrix are not getting up flied
properly
but again I'm just not sure how that's
not happening
so what you can see here right is the
full transform when this gets activated
the the key part here is the
the W value is multiplying the
displacement value right okay this could
be our problem right here the W value
needs to multiply the displacement
values correctly and we didn't put in a
W value we put in a W value of 1 but the
W value isn't one right we know it's not
one it's probe Z W and that W will
multiply the displacement part of the
matrix and since the displacement part
of the matrix actually was getting
multiplied by one rather than something
else it could be that it was supposed to
be saying much higher which would
account for the less displacement right
so what we need to do here is we
actually need to do that to get the full
transform out and then when we're done
[Music]
we can truncate it down because now we
don't care what the W value is that
comes out although it should the WI
should come out to one right
I'm missing a comma whew that was that
was a nasty one that was a nasty one
all right so we're still not quite out
of the woods yet looks like we've got
that slightly backwards in there but I
think now we're at least on the right
track right so our clip coordinates
should have after the transform going
forwards we should have the correct
probe zlw here and furthermore now I
think this this part could be rethought
because now with the correct probe Z W
in the W slot
I feel like clip Z should just go
directly into that slot like I thought
before and talk myself out of
yeah oh man that was tricky all right
but now just in the nick of time as the
Q&amp;A buzzer approaches we have debugged
the problem now and as you can see now
it properly tracks the camera exactly as
it should track the camera which is what
I wanted which means that now if we want
to we can get rid of our lighting bug
and start to correct this Krait start to
correct those visual glitches because
now with the light bounds here what we
can say is we just do the world camera
rekt now and then we just have to adjust
the Z because right now that's not going
to be right so what we were already
doing that looks like right so now in
theory what we should have as we walk
around is we should never see any more
lighting glitches right
our cameras still worked but our
lighting is never wrong and hey that's
what we're seeing so that's good right
so that's really great now our sim
bounds are a little small it seems like
their clip and stuff out pretty early
there it looks like
but our lighting now correctly tracks
the camera which is what I wanted all
right so now we're go to a quick QA
gotta remember to have our generator to
generate some lights
you know I'm saying
Jim 0o how would you opt is outside the
view of the character so you mean to say
like if I was like in this corner for
example so I can't see out here like
like meaning the character couldn't see
what was happening here what would you
do if you wanted a game like that like
fog of war basically there's two parts
to that so I'm not sure which one you're
asking about one is how you apply some
kind of graphical situation to it so
that that you you know how do you render
something that's supposed to be like
sort of only semi visible meaning the
player can see maybe the structure of it
but not what's there in actuality or
what you know moving things would have
happened and the other is computing the
visibility so computing the visibility
in our world is actually relatively
complicated because we allow pretty much
anything right now we happen to be
placing things in a fairly grid like
fashion but we're in an obligation to do
so so visibility computation would
actually very hard in this game I don't
know how you would really do it you
would probably have to do some pre
computation to make it feasible but we
already do it for lighting so you know
the basics right like just figuring out
what scene from everyone else is just a
stochastic ray cast right so what we
could do is start at the hero and cast
out lots of rays from the hero and see
what we hit and that would tell us what
of the game was visible right we can
start with something like that but
typically the problem you get is it
becomes pretty difficult to do that kind
of a computation so you oftentimes need
to have some kind of acceleration
I either by cheating right which is to
say that maybe what you do is you
actually restrict the game to a tile map
so you can do some kind of flood filling
of the tile map in a more predictable
fashion and don't allow arbitrary
geometry or you you know introduce some
other things like some volumes that help
you or whatever right like something to
cheat with and which one of those is
appropriate kind of depends on what kind
of game you're making our game does not
have thought of were so we don't care
but
you would have to make it a
consideration and possibly restrict some
of the things in the game to allow you
to do it in an efficient fashion
butterfat
do you plan to close the orphanages
rooms or do you want them to have the
skylight as some sort of ambient light
I'm not sure we may stick a we'll
probably sick roofs on them
does the update and render function do
any rendering right now or it's also to
some other place
well rendering is sort of deferred at
the moment in that it builds buffers so
that the GPU can render so update and
render is really the thing that just
produces buffers that will later get
processed when we say update the render
what we mean is prepare the things that
instruct the renderer what to do
jimsy would would you for example
castrate to see if something is visible
to the character eg if something is on
the scream of the character should be
blind to it yes and again like I said
you can do that in a couple of different
ways it depends if you only wanted to
know like whether the hero could see
monsters specific monsters moving around
then what you could do is a little
easier because you could just take each
monster and raycast to the monster right
and that makes it a little easier but if
you are trying to sell you more like
what's parts of what squares can the
hero see then you've got a harder
problem and maybe just a stochastic ray
casts every frame where you shoot out
like a thousand rays from the character
every frame and use some kind of decay
on what they hit you know maybe that's
the answer kind of like what the
lighting system does but since you only
have one point of visibility it's a lot
more efficient so a thousand rays is not
hard to do you know so that might be
your answer there I'm not sure
Wood handmade heroes chunk offset work
in 3d would there be any problem so that
I'm not saying well the game is 3d so
I'm not sure what you mean like it works
in 3d because it is right now literally
working in 3d
sergeant REM B is there already new
artwork to put in the game of the next
couple of episodes yeah when we get
ready to do that update I don't know
when I will be putting in exactly new
artwork or anything but I just I want to
make the changes necessary to have that
happen because I need to as we start
converging on stuff here I need to have
the actual look of the game start coming
together so that I know how to make
certain decisions about like the
rendering and stuff and how that's going
to work really my only concern currently
because I like things as they are at the
moment my only concern currently is just
this problem the problem of how to deal
with the perspective and and I don't
know it may just work it may not I asked
for the art to be drawn very top-down
but it's still not quite completely
top-down because it was completely
top-down you can't see faces which is a
problem so it's still a little bit not
that way and I don't know if it's really
gonna work so it may be that we kind of
have
yeah yeah I just I'm sorry I just don't
know that's the but it may be that we
need to change that you know it may be
that we have to go with a more direct
upright isometric like we may have to
tilt things so that they're orthographic
upward I in order for the art to work
okay you know and that'd be a bummer
because I really liked the perspective
feel I feel like it adds something to
the feeling of the world but if it just
isn't feasible then it isn't feasible
you know and we can switch to either of
those two if we need to so
you he is it currently possible to
easily customize rooms eg with
non-random tiles e etc yeah you can have
non-random taozi if you want we just
have a random right now there's a random
displacement in the thing that creates a
room
so obviously it's pretty pretty trivial
Jessie F sorry I mean to say if we
wanted to make a universe scale game I
use face in with that scale well yes the
only thing that I would point out is
that you may want the chunk dimensions
to be much larger
right now we keep the chunk dimensions
small because we use the chunks we don't
we didn't want to introduce two separate
schemes the entity partitioning and the
chunk offsets but if your goal is to
make a giant game world like if you
imagine that space that star citizen was
actually working and you're making some
of that you might want to allocate ASEC
effectively more space in terms of your
coordinate system so you may want chunks
to be much larger right you might want
to chunk to be a kilometer by a
kilometer let's say is a chunk instead
of a meter by a meter right and so when
you do that you will then need
additional spatial partitioning inside
chunks potentially for other purposes
and again that just depends a lot on
what you're doing so so how the scheme
breaks down is largely going to be based
on that so to give you some perspective
on how that's going to work if you
actually look at the world stuff right
now what you can see here is that we
have
we have this stuff set up right that
gets the chunk gets the chunk
positioning stuff and this chunk dim in
meters is what we're looking at right so
if I was to stop the game somewhere and
look at the world it should have the
chunk dim in meters specified right and
so here's the the chunk dimensions
meters it looks like 23 12 5 that's the
size of a chunk right so then you could
figure if you if you want to be safe and
have like reasonable bounds let's say
then maybe you have 1 billion times that
so you would have 23 billion meters so
23 billion meters would be like the span
the width of your universe and 23
billion meters may not be enough
I don't know right so so right you don't
want that right like that's not
sufficient because you want to have like
things that are very far apart so maybe
you want you you would fundamentally
want to change a system a little bit and
say look let's actually have the
internal coordinate system and the
external coordinate system scale a
little bit more dramatically and let's
have every integer coordinate represent
of much larger area right that's what I
would say now granted you probably don't
want this to actually be the case
because if you actually let this be the
case it would take players forever to
get from one place to the other so
usually you have to you would have to
warp anyway at which point why not just
have each one
those things be a separate region that
isn't actually connected so there's a
sort of separate issue there but you
know it's just worth looking at so right
so if it's 146 billion meters from the
earth to the Sun then that means that
you want to probably have your
coordinate system be based more on this
stuff and it possibly have like a more
multi-resolution scheme to it right if
you were actually trying to represent
the real universe so I don't know I
would also say that if if what you were
doing is trying to represent the entire
universe in real terms you may just want
to go with doubles because I don't it
depends on what kind of computations
you're doing you may just want to take
to speed it and save yourself the
trouble in hand-made here we're always
talking about a little area and so it
makes sense to send everything around a
real area and I'm piece them together
but if you're doing very disparate sort
of I want to talk about two people
sitting here and here both of them
looking at something billions of miles
away you know maybe just go to doubles
at that point because why not now you
still need the chunking because you
can't have all that stuff in play at a
time but you could just you might at a
certain level of complexity it gets to
the point where the doubles are worth it
probably because now you don't to think
about it anymore right and taking the
speed hit of going from floats to
doubles all of your computations work on
half as many values now unfortunately
but that hit may be worth it and you
won't you know you need to
you need to take into account when
you're making a decision the costs of
choice of coordinate system and
sometimes it makes sense to be localized
and sometimes it doesn't again because
of the structure of the universe I would
still say that probably the right thing
to do is to have like chunks of that are
kind of separated discreetly but yeah
because there's nothing in between them
you know and the players can't
continuously drive from one Sun to
another because they'd never get there
they have to engage like a warp drive or
something right so you have to kind of
think about what that game is really
even about first with these massive
distances even be needed if you don't
need to be actually to say the nearest
centimeter or do always need to be that
accurate well again I don't know right
it was a hypothetical question posed
without context so I can't really tell
what you would or would not need but I
mean let's take the example of handmade
hero as a context and say for some
unknown reason and I don't know what
that reason is someone wants to make
handmade hero generations the game where
every handmade hero map is actually just
a planet in a giant universe of like
millions of planets right in that case
the chunk team system I would just keep
exactly as it is and you would just end
up going into space travel mode and
warping yourself to some other planet
which loads in a new chunk world right
that's definitely the right way to do
that and it may be the right way to do
it in a 3d game about space travel as
well because like I said this is 3d so
it just depends on what you're doing
there if you actually want to be
able to fly anywhere continuously though
you have a problem and so you have to
decide how you want to address that
problem it's a little weird because
since the player can never actually fly
everywhere continuously it's a little
bit weird to go to doubles and then do
that but it may still just be easier
than coming up with exactly how you want
to do it right
but it's I mean the the long and short
of it is just you have to always
remember that float floats have very
little range they can express or very
little accuracy I should say they can
express very large numbers because
they're in exponential form but they're
very inaccurate and so it it doesn't
take very long at all before you will
find your floating point values are
totally not accurate enough for whatever
you're doing you know even just if
you're talking about like people running
around on a planet surface even just a
few kilometers down the line it will
start to become problematic right you
know it at at 20 kilometers let's say
you would already be in trouble I would
suspect I would suspect don't quote me
on that but I suspect when you wanted to
sit there and be like able to look down
at something at your feet and not have
your feet be like jittering around or
something right so it doesn't take very
long for floats to go bad and so doubles
just offer a lot more they cross the
line into a much higher accuracy space
for the kinds of numbers you might be
caring about and whether or not they're
sufficient for a whole universe I don't
know they probably aren't to be
completely honest with you like I would
suspect that doubles will lose accuracy
if what you really wanted was like oh
yeah like I can stand on earth and look
at my feet or I can go out to a three
galaxies away from here and look down at
my feet and not have it jitter I have
never thought about whether it doubles
even enough you know it just might not
be
for our for our real universe you know
Dan's idea do you always have to take
float precision into account or is it
more like it will come up type of thing
you don't always have to take foot
president account for games of a
reasonable size you know that the
traditional level size in games like
think doom you know or Call of Duty or
something like that it's just not an
issue right even the witness it wasn't
an issue that was just a separate bug
right so you really don't usually have
to take foot precision into account
until you get to bigger worlds something
ten times the size of the witness island
probably starts to be a problem right so
again it really depends on how big of a
single continuous area you want the
player to be able to explore and if that
is roughly the size of a typical game
level feeling thing you will not
generally have to worry about float
precision in most circumstances
sometimes it may come up due to certain
things you could do or want to do that
create particular stress on floating
point but most the time it's not so it
really is about world size and if you
know ahead of time you're not caring
about that you don't have to worry about
it unhand me hero we wouldn't probably
have had to worry about it I just wanted
to show how to do it because I thought
it's important that people were aware of
it for so that they would know we may
never make worlds that are big enough to
care but I wanted to make sure we could
cuz I wanted to show that I want to
teach how that's done
luckily this hypothetical situation
stores you could also change the physics
realism of the universe that planets and
galaxies are closer than they would
normally be so flying to them as more
feasible that is exactly what I would do
right if I was in charge I'd be like
look the universe is a really boring
place no offence astrophysicist but like
most of it is empty that's not fun and
usually what you end up doing is you
just introduce like hyper spacing around
and so you never really fly around it
I'd say yeah screw it all the planets
are like 15 feet apart right not 15 feet
I'm joking all the planets are a hundred
miles apart all of a sudden for no darn
reason and so I can just take off a one
and just go straight to another and land
on it right like real quick-like yeah
absolutely that's what I would do not
engine wise I'm totally if someone tells
me my goal is to make an engine that
supports the full-size universe I'm I'm
chuffed at that I'm like let's do it
that sounds good even if I have to use
like a hierarchy of doubles to make that
happen I'm a male on board so I'm fine
with that
I I just don't think it's very fun right
that doesn't sound like a lot of fun to
me and so so I would question the design
of that I don't know that I want to play
that game but I don't have a problem of
it so yeah but in terms of the fun of
the game I'd say make him close together
you know let the player get their dance
I Dennis a question about the waves like
yes exactly so if we had had a problem
on the witness with float precision we
absolutely would have done exactly what
we did in handmade hero right we would
have just partitioned it into some
sections because again we don't really
have to worry too much in the witness
about allowing floating point I mean you
can't even shoot projectiles and the
witness right it's a good case for
partitioning so that's what I would at
least that's what I would have done I
don't know maybe John feels differently
is the rather nice state of
anti-aliasing and handmade hero have to
do with use of death feeling or is it
just standard MSAA
it's actually both of those two things
so we we use multisample anti-aliasing
and depth peeling to try and produce a
reasonably high quality image that has
anti icing on the sprites and on the
hard geometry edges so mr. Jake from
State Farm how do you tackle this issue
in a large open world then to use some
sort of grid system well like I said
handmade hero is we talk like we solve
it and hammer a hero the worlds can be
as large as they want and handmade hero
really there's no way to make a world
and handmade hero large enough that the
player could actually get to all of it
and have it break our system so we
introduced one very specific way that
you can do exactly that
like that like that that that number of
meters it was 23 times a billion meters
so 23 billion meters you could have a
world in hammer here that was 23 billion
meters wide and the player moves up at
the speed of a human rough way through
it so we're talking about like the
distance to mercury or something right
oh that's miles what's the closest
planet Venus all right so you could get
a quarter of the way to Venus easily
without using any persistent precision
our system you could even go double that
really so you could you could go half
the way to Venus oh oh and you could go
in either direction so now that I think
about it actually yeah so you could have
a world in handmade here oh that
stretched effectively from Earth to
Venus and that's how big the world was
so we tack we that we solved this
problem in hand made here oh it's done
right the player can't possibly explore
as much of a world as we could create
they died long before they ever did so
we've solved that problem I'm talking
more about the hypothetical case the
person was asking about with planets and
a solar system which has different
constraint because there's a lot of
empty space sparse and so at some point
you may need to take a different
approach due to the sparsity because you
because we would introduce the
mechanisms like warping which would
allow the player to get from one place
to another much more quickly which would
mean that that distance they covered
would be different right what benefit
does deputing bring to the anti aliasing
table so what happens is sprites if you
draw sprites into a world the sprites
themselves have anti-aliasing built into
them right because when the person
painted them the edges are basically you
know encoding some coverage information
there does that make sense
so when you go to draw that spray into
the world if you want multi-sim plant
acing unfortunately doesn't quite have
enough samples to really help you there
we tried that I think it didn't look
great so what you want to do is you want
to actually draw that anti-aliasing in
order to help produce a nice smooth edge
around your sprites and so the depth
peeling does that that's what the depth
filling does
all right looks like we're roughly done
here I think
all right let's let's close it up
glad we fix that unprotect call that's a
good thing to get right thanks room for
joining me for an episode a hammer here
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you'd like to follow up series
at home you can always puro to the game
on handmade hero org and it comes with a
source code so you can kind of track it
as it goes and play around with it
yourself we will be back tomorrow at
which point I would like to start taking
a look at the other issue we have in
terms of smoothing out that initial play
there which is the camera motion and the
simulation center changes that's a
little bit more of a sensitive issue and
we have to make sure we get that right
so that's the big thing I want to be
focusing on tomorrow and then we'll be
back again next week to start looking at
those that other parts talking about
which is getting some of that art in
there so we can start to look at what
the world's going to look like because
the last thing we really want to do is
start to tune that lighting as part of
the generation process and tuning the
lighting is gonna require we actually
have some art in there to look at what
the game is gonna look like so can I
gotta bring all that stuff together and
again part of that process will also be
deciding what we're gonna do with the
perspective when it comes right down to
it because we really don't know exactly
how we're gonna work around some of the
problems that could come up with that
perspective and so we'll see part of
that will be art on the art side part of
it that'll be on our side so we'll have
to see we will have to see all right so
that's about it thanks so much for
joining me I hope to see you back here
tomorrow we will be an hour earlier
tomorrow so be aware of that if you came
today
you gotta come an hour earlier than it
came if you want to catch it tomorrow
that's about it until next time have fun
pouring everyone and I'll see everybody
on the Internet take it easy everybody