hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hiro share we code complete-game live on
stream we are in the middle of I guess I
just want to say fumbling around with
some lighting in our game the reason I
say fumbling around is because we don't
really have any particularly smart idea
about how lighting should be done in
sort of a two and a half tee game to the
best of my knowledge there isn't really
a standard way to do it and not a lot of
people have really done that much with
it to be honest one of the problems with
two and a half T games in general is
that the industry had kind of moved to
3d games and a lot of the serious
graphics programmers had all moved to 3d
games by the time the horsepower in pcs
was good enough to do much in the way of
interesting lighting there were no such
thing as you know fully programmable
shaders GPUs back in the day when most
serious graphics programmers wrote 2d
games so one of the problems with it is
it's just not as developed as the theory
of lighting and 3d games and similarly
one of the problems with two-and-a-half
T games of course is that lighting kind
of wants you to have a full three
description of the scene in order to do
it correctly and even then you've got a
lot of questions you have to answer
about how you're going to do it
efficiently and in 2d rendering we
really don't have that ability right we
don't even know what the backs of things
look like a lot of times some things
don't even ever have a back drawn for
them at all only characters you can
actually face multiple directions even
have sprites drawn for their various
directions so it's kind of a bizarre
situation and it's always a little bit
of a artistic process I guess I would
say to construct a lighting algorithm
for something like a two and a half T
game because what you're really trying
to do here is come up with something
that approximates what light does in a
way that's artistically satisfying but
that is knowingly incorrect pretty much
everywhere
because you don't even have the data you
would need to do the job correctly now
we've had sort of success with this very
process in a different domain which is
that actually all of the same things can
be said for the fact that we wanted a 3d
camera for a 2-d game and there is no
right answer for that either and I think
we came up with a really pretty great
solution I love how our renderer works
now it's a fire I forget renderer so you
don't have to do any sprite sorting or
anything and it really looks nice when
you move around and when the camera
moves around I think it like really
captures kind of the motion everything
properly so everything in there in the
renderer came out exactly how I would
want and I think when we put the new art
in it's going to look really nice as
well
and fix some of the other things
remember some of stuff like the hero
hopping for example which now looks kind
of crappy was done back when we didn't
have real 3d so it's not even really
using the three dimensions the way it
should so I think stuff like that's
going to look really nice as well once
we go back and sort of do a final pass
on things to get animation looking nice
in the new 3d world I think that's going
to be great but putting that aside I'm
really happy with how the renderer
turned out and I think it's very good
for a 3d Zelda ish kind of experience
and I should say a 2d Zelda brought into
3d which I don't know if Zelda really
ever did all that effectively there's
definitely been some attempts at it but
you know mostly Zelda went to real 3d
for their three day big 3d stuff anyway
so what I would like to do here is see
if we can't sort of cheat the devil
twice and come up with also a good clean
way of getting some nice lighting in
here now again it doesn't have to be
accurate it just has to look nice and
already what you can see I think for me
moving around with this light source
attached to the hero is that just very
basic simple lighting already looks
pretty nice for a limited case and so
what I'm looking at here is just can we
extend this to something
that gives a little bit more complexity
to the lighting so can we go ahead and
make something that scales nicely to say
hundreds of light sources so there's a
lot more lights in the scene than this
one could we do something that adds
perhaps a little bit of Bounce lighting
or other sorts of effects like that that
will round out the feel a little bit
more make it a little bit softer rather
than being such a hard edge kind of a
other lighting and and the answer to
whether we can do that is I have no idea
like I said it's a complete experimental
situation so where we left off last
weekend is we were saying well maybe
let's create some textures let's write
some lighting into the textures and then
let's try to use that lighting on the
characters and obviously the first thing
that we can do for that is the very very
simple process where we could just take
basic lights and write them into
textures and just get the old-school
blobby like this lighting doesn't even
have directionality to it let's just get
that working right because that's hard
enough to get working in GPU land right
you can always have all sorts of weird
GPU bugs that take a while to eye to
troubleshoot and so it's not like we
were if we were writing this code
ourselves and our own rasterizer would
be like shooting fish in a barrel but on
the GPU there's always a little bit of
cross your fingers and roll the dice so
what I want to do is just pop over I
would say today 393 so - today is code
if you want to follow along at home you
want to do GAE 392 source code that's
the source code that I'm starting with
let's open up for coder with these file
names at the top I added that back for
every one people were complaining that I
switched it because now that for coder
allows you to get rid of those bars at
work I don't use them because Irish know
what file I'm in but people on the
stream couldn't remember what file I was
in that makes sense if you're scrubbing
around it's probably hard on the stream
you look scruffy are you like what files
me and I have no idea
so they're back you know they're back I
lost one whole line of code on the end
which you know I don't want to put that
on you but I did and it's already like I
barely get to see any lines of code
because I have to have it the font big
enough for the 1080p stream so it's like
I'm looking at my codes through this
tiny little like people like like some
kind of a like slit in a door or
something I'm trying to look at the room
on the other side
but anyway so what we've got here is I
think before we finished on last week's
last week's dream we did actually create
this concept of light textures here this
is the OpenGL frame buffer sort of
utility struct that we created before
and this allows us to basically say
alright let's create a bunch of these
light textures I don't know how many but
you know the game can decide how many
and how big they are
and we said we're we're never going to
have more than eight of these so we just
hard capped it there but we probably
won't be using all eight I think we were
saying we'd use one per color at the
moment so there'd only be actually four
I believe is what our plan was and what
we want to do here if you say like okay
we want to write these lights into the
we want to write lice into these buffers
and then we want to go ahead and just
kind of work out how the lights are
going to affect stuff like how will we
look up into these light textures
information relate to the lighting so
there's two things we have to do here
and I'd like to start with the first
part of that so the first thing that I
want to do is I want to upgrade the
render group to allow us to put the
lighting information into the scene and
let's talk about this a little bit here
because effectively you know we've got a
depth peel renderer right
oh and this reminds me of something that
I thought of during the week I had a
random thought about this but I don't
know if it's particularly useful but it
might be and we'll have to think about
it all right
so effectively what I want to do here is
[Applause]
break lighting down into something
that's a little bit more manageable so
let's think about this what's the
easiest thing that we could possibly do
if we wanted to capture lighting and use
it like we are currently using it right
so let's suppose I've got my 3d world
here and I'm going to draw it from the
top looking into it right so here are
the various floors and maybe you know
like in our case we have a hole in the
floor so you can see down to some stuff
right so you know you can see
potentially multiple layers even though
like right here might be blocked because
this is opaque here might be you know
you can be able to see through it right
okay now if we were in 2d so this was
looking top-down and I'm looking at the
actual game if we were in 2d you could
imagine making like a grid right and you
could imagine our light sources could be
put into the grid in such a way so that
if there was a light source that was in
a particular grid we would record the
information about that light source
right like suppose we were talking about
GPU at all we could just do the same
thing we're storing right now which is
like a P and an I like a position in an
intensity I think we called it strength
so P N and s but intensity of the light
source right so this is where the light
source is this is how bright it is and
we just have a simple point source model
like we're not trying to model area
light sources or anything like that
we're just doing points and we figure if
we want areas we'll just add more points
or something like this
so the first problem we run into right
is when we try to map this into hardware
we have a fixed storage size and there's
ways you can get around pic storage size
but it becomes increasingly more
complicated so we've got a problem where
we we have a grid but it can only store
for example one of these so if we have
lots of lights that are overlapping in
here we need a way to merge them right
but that's not the end of the world you
could imagine merging the position and
source of the light fairly
straightforward right we could imagine
just averaging the position of the light
source let's say in averaging the store
and summing the strength of the light
source and that would give us if we did
that for a red green and blue that would
give us an interesting approximation to
the light is it something that's good
enough I have no idea we haven't tried
it yet okay so I feel like this is the
first thing I want to get working just
something real basic like that
let me quickly mention the other thing I
was thinking about just separately
but this is the first thing you want to
get working what we have to do here is
introduce a light accumulation pass
right where basically before we render
any of our depth fields we want to first
render all of our light sources just the
light sources into some kind of a set of
textures we've got those textures now
we'll render into them right now we'll
just stick with 2d when we get 2d
working direct a section we'll make
those textures 3d and see if we can get
that working to our satisfaction right
and we can go from there alright so
here's the other thing that I wanted to
mention that I thought was pretty
interesting and we'll see what you folks
think of it as well so let's suppose I
wanted to do something like this light
source rendering right but I wanted my
light to more accurately reflect the
geometry so for example let's suppose
that I go into here right
and I'm hopping around right and the
lights moving but one thing you'll
notice about the weight of lights moving
is there's no shadowing at all right and
that is actually true pretty much
everywhere so for example if I'm because
all we're doing is a radial light right
we haven't done any real work on this
lighting so what that means is you can
kind of see for example as I move around
this surface gets brighter or darker
based on how far I am from the light or
like say the underside of this surface
but that light would never be able to
hit those right even bounce lighting
would never really illuminate these
underside surfaces because by the time
the light bounced off the side of one of
these off the bottom of the top of one
of these and up onto here it would be
incredibly dim because a lot of that
light would have gotten absorbed you
know I'm saying um so right now we're
strictly doing radial fall-off of the
light and that's not very compelling it
would be nicer if we took into account
some of the geometry there in terms of
shadowing and occlusion now one way that
you can do that obviously is by using
what are called shadow maps and that's
rendering things from the perspective of
a light source in order to figure out
where the shadow is it's very good for
things like single light sources that
cast strong shadows an example of that
is stuff like the Sun when you're doing
something like lighting from the Sun a
strong directional light source that
cast very strong shadows and you want
something realistic a shadow map makes a
lot of sense when you are casting from
hundreds of lights it makes a lot less
right and to the best of my knowledge I
don't really know if this is true but I
think it's true even modern very
advanced renders that require high-end
hardware like doom the new doom not the
old doom
those games put a lot of limits on how
much they do with shadow maps so for
example in doom I think they're updated
somewhat lazily so basically what
happens with shadow map lighting is they
basically try to limit how much shadow
map rendering they do and they cache
them from frame to frame and only update
them when they have to to try and get
more out of them like because again
they're expensive right and so I don't
really know of games that do all of
their lighting with shadow maps in that
way I don't know how feasible that would
be for games that aren't just a few
light sources something like doom 3 is
an example of something that could
easily be done that way but of course
that didn't use shadow maps that used
shadow volumes which is a whole another
ball of wax and not a technique that
anyone uses anymore as far as I know
because it's extraordinarily expensive
just very very expensive so anyway yeah
so I'm not sure that shadow maps are
really our answer here I especially when
you consider the fact that we don't have
real geometry it makes it very hard
probably to eliminate the artifacting
that would happen on shadow maps so I
don't really want to go down a shadow
map route I think that would be a real
bad idea that's my guess I don't know
but I think that would be a pretty bad
idea so what I want to do instead is
think about other options for kind of
getting a little bit of that back again
I'm not really who - I'm not really
looking for a lot of direct shadow
effects anyway I don't really want like
long Sun shadows or anything like that I
don't really want the look of that
getting the game to be like that
I want soft very soft shadowing so what
I'm really looking for is something a
little bit more diffuse and anyway what
I was thinking it just I realized this
just during the week while I was kind of
randomly I don't know my my brain must
have been wandering and I was thinking
about this so what happens when we
render our
game right now is we produce the top
level pixels whatever those are right in
our first depth peel pass right so this
right here is def peel 1 we end up with
the V buffer that looks like this and
this is def peel 1 we then do another
depth peel right and we end up with a
second layer the scene and so on and so
forth
so we end up with multiple layers of our
seen in our def peels what that means is
we actually have some very interesting
information that a normal game doesn't
have so for example we could tell you if
a light source was here we could tell
you that it was going to hit something
down here we've got that information in
our depth feels right which is pretty
interesting so one thing that I was
wondering is I wonder if we could do
something where we use our depth field
as the geometry for some bounce lighting
it's a long shot but it seems plausible
right because one thing that a lot of
people do already is there's a lot of
screen space techniques right you'll
think see things like ssao talked about
which is screen space ambient occlusion
and what those techniques do is they're
just techniques which use the depth
buffer to approximate some kind of
lighting effect so screen space ambient
occlusion for example is a technique
that takes a look at def buffer things
and where it sees things where it looks
maybe something like that in the depth
buffer where it sees an in skews area it
will assume that less of the incident
lighting can hit this area and it will
darken it right so it's kind of like a
filter that you use over local areas of
the test buffer that try to determine
whether
it looks like shadowing will occur in
this area in a generic sort of inbound
light sense and to the extent that you
want to spend more pixels later fragment
shader time on it you can get better or
worse results by doing more work right
you can look at further look at more
areas of the depth buffer you can do it
per light you can do all sorts of things
right so that's an example of a
technique that sort of works exactly the
way that I'm describing just not with
multiple depth field so if we have
multiple death fields it seems like we
have an even more powerful opportunity
to potentially do something involving
convecting some of that light around now
I don't know if that's really true it
was just a little bit of a thought right
and so what I figured we would be able
to do in certain circumstances is
potentially have instead of voxel izing
our scene which is not necessarily
something we want to do due to the added
expense
we're already def peeling it for our
render that kind of gives us an interval
version of a voxel ization of the scene
because for every pixel on the screen we
effectively have the voxel in Z of that
pixel right we've got specifically the
empty space to the first filled space we
then have the empty space to the next
filled space the empty space and so on
now we don't count backwards faces so we
don't really look at this part of the
voxel ization but since most of our
objects are thin I'm not sure we really
care about that we may be able to get
away without that and if we really
needed it we could add that as part of
our def peel path for doubling the cost
of our depth peels only in Z we would
not have to render any pixels remember
we could do an alternating def path
every other time
just to write an additional V buffer
that was the outbound Z there and then
we would know this so even that is not
an impossibility we could get back that
information if we so desired and so I
think what I'm trying to get out here is
we sort of have a lot ization of our
service already whether that box
civilization is any good I don't know
like whether it's useful to us at all I
have no idea but it's something right
and so what we could consider doing here
rather than the light textures being
used the way that they're currently
being used is we could imagine again
looking out at sort of a more voxel cone
tracing sort of a thing that actually
was a little bit more light Tracey I
don't know that that's a particularly
good idea but it's just it's one way we
could take a look at this problem and
I'll bring something else to your
attention here I guess well I'm going
down this particular rathole try to
remember the search terms for this
graphics gems this what it was
this is not good at all
nope really wish I could remember what
the name of this was
[Applause]
so there was a technique that was used
for radiosity that I cannot remember
[Music]
argh there was a technique that was used
there was going to be a game based
around it but it never materialized so I
don't really remember let's see here GPU
gems Pirates of the Caribbean I know
this is a really weird way to search for
this but this is the it's the technique
that they used in Pirates of the
Caribbean if they got out of GPU gems
[Applause]
but they of course don't specify what it
was
[Music]
I'm going to find this this is just some
pirate site
I don't want pirate stuff I want Pirates
of the Caribbean which GPU gems was that
if someone could just tell me what that
was
would be nice same on the stream No
that's it fantasy lab so this is what
we're looking for right here
[Applause]
so this is what I was thinking of
finally found it that took a long time
but basically it's an iterative scene a
iterative scheme that kind of like
convex light around your around your
scene right and the way that this thing
works is that you create individual
points and you kind of bounce them
around right so let's see here
this is not the actual paper I'm
thinking of because the GPU gems one
that I'm thinking of
I give up um I can try and find it
offline but basically these are just
it's a pretty straightforward idea right
if it's not particularly bizarre or
anything I would like to show you the
shader could and it was in GPA it was in
GPU gems but unfortunately
then here
here it is okay
finally I finally found it
man that was a long dive my memory knew
it was there but I couldn't remember
enough to find it okay so basically
here's how this thing works just to
refresh my own memory the idea is that
you have these little things
right and the idea is you've got a disk
that's pointing in a direction and has a
radius and a color a lighting value
right and what you end up doing is you
take these things and you do passes to
scatter light around them right so it
uses a approximate equation to figure
out how much light is transferred
between two different receivers right
like so and the way that it works says
like alright here's the here's the
algorithm description we can calculate
the accessibility of 2 passes first
fastly approximates the accessibility
for each of them by summing the fraction
of the hemisphere subtended by every
other element and subtracting the result
from 1 right so that's basically like
looking at it sort of like an N squared
thing after the first FASTA mentlegen be
too dark gives other elements that are
in shadow are the cells casting shadows
so use the second pass through the same
taxation this time we multiply each form
factor by the emitter elements
accessibility from the last pass so
basically they do two passes to try and
do shadowing and remove things that are
doubly shadowed right so if they don't
double shadow if that makes sense so
this doesn't really help with lots of
shadowing so if you have tons of
shadowing you need more passes but you
know again this is a hacky approximate
lighting technique
so after figuring that out
see here here we go a single bound
amounts of indirect light using a slight
variation of the ambient occlusion
shader we replace the solid angle
function with a disk to disk radiance
transfer function we use one pass of the
shader to transfer the reflected light
of emitted light and two passes to
shadow the light right for indirect
lighting we first need to calculate the
amount of light to reflect off the front
face of each surface element if the
reflected light comes from environment
lighting then we compute the ambient
occlusion map blah blah blah blah right
now what they do here because this gets
way too expensive is they just do these
things hierarchically so what they do is
you have all these little surface
occluders like this right you have these
little like sort of approximate blobs
what they do is they say well okay these
approximate blobs we can just for ones
that are further away will just merge
them into something that less resolution
right so really that's all they do to
cut down on the amount of work so when
you consider you still do an N squared
you still do N squared work versus the
other occluders you just make sure that
M squared never grows particularly large
because you always as you look at
acuto's that are further away from you
you always look sort of at a more coarse
version of those occluders right so I
think that's about it let me see here
yeah here's the hierarchical elements
thing so basically what they say is like
you know we do prefer argument to work
on board a couple thousand elements
real-time they use simplified geometry
for distant services so what they do to
do
we group elements whose vertices are
neighbors in the original mesh and
represent them with a single larger
element we do the same thing with the
larger elements creating fewer and even
larger elements forming a hierarchy now
instead of traversing every single
element for each pixel we Traverse a
hierarchy of elements as receive
elements far enough away from the
emitter say 4 times the radius we use it
for calculation only in receiver is
close
Dulli traverses children if it has any
right so again just a really simple
technique of sort of grouping these
light sources up together in solving for
only simple ones so that's I mean again
I feel like that's the sort of thing
that we could really if we wanted to we
could play with here because I guess I
don't really know exactly how we would
do one with the depth field but if you
think about it when we create these
depth fields at any particular point
when we write the depth buffer out we
could also write out the normal so we
would know where the surfaces were and
which directions they were pointing
right which would give us a set of
bitmaps that actually had what we would
need for bouncing light around from just
the depth field once we had that
information from the DEF peels beginning
once we have that information from the
dev field we would then be able to say
well ok let's filter those down so we've
got 1920 by 1080 versions of this data
which is way more than we want to work
on let's just filter it down so then we
would do you know a version of this that
was like half down and then half down
again and then half down again right and
each as we would do it we would just
sort of approximate those there's other
values which are full resolution in this
case we would approximate those by like
summing them together right and
furthermore we would know what size
those things were because they would
always be they would always be
proportional to whatever the bitmap was
we were sampling out of so we could do
something like that where we just say
like okay as we look for things that are
further away we just look at coarser and
coarser approximations of those things I
don't know it could work it could also
be an absolute terrible idea I have no
idea but you know again that's kind of
just one way we could play around with
that lighting information and it feels
like something somewhat useful and for
our purposes what I think I would do
since a lot of our stuff is flat
stand-up sprites I would just consider
everything to be two-sided right so when
we do the equations for the lighting
transfer I would consider everything to
be two-sided and I just track both sides
so when we process it I'd store like we
have double the storage for RGB which
you know each side of the surface would
would record it so I don't know I mean
that this may be just really stupid I
have no idea it's just kind of tempting
and I feel like I want to try it
and again mostly what this would require
is just it would require the directional
saving that directional element what
direction the thing was pointing in
right
and I don't think there's really much
else to it I think that's basically all
there is so yes so basically what the
expense becomes there is it's really a
bandwidth expense is the primary thing
in the depth appeal we're not doing any
more work in the depth field we just
have to write a little bit extra and
that writing a little bit extra is
costly right because now we need to
write out a normal which is three
elements we can cut that down to two by
not writing the third because we know
from Pythagorean theorem that if we're
just storing a direction we can just
store the x and y and we can always
produce the Z by renormalizing right so
that's pretty straightforward and I
think that's really all we would have to
do I so what we could do here is say
yeah we could introduce an additional
RGB a texture in here perhaps although I
guess that's not that useful and I think
about it but yes so if we have the R and
the G that would store us our direction
unfortunately we don't have enough
information here for the light well oh
you know what we do we know that the
color is whatever the color is in the
actual bitmap because we have an RGB a
which here is the the alpha and here's
the color of that thing and so in theory
I guess we could just store the two like
an intensity of each side the problem
with that is we wouldn't be able to
bounce coloured light around the way we
want to so really what we probably need
again is is two of these right so we
would store something like RGB of the
back
our gb of the front side in terms of the
bounce state and then this a-here would
this one and this one would form our X
and our Y right they would not be alpha
values there the X and the y of the
directional normal of whatever we
rendered at that at that surface I don't
know I have no idea this could be a
fantastically stupid idea I I really
just do not have any idea whatsoever
about it so if we did something like
this then what you can imagine is in
order to start bouncing the lighting
around what we would do is we would for
any given one of these elements when we
go to render we would probably do
something where we just sampled from the
bitmap a couple times so we would sample
from the bitmap that was like right in
the region of this thing we'd sample
from a high-res version of the bitmap
then for everything out here we'd sample
from the lower res and for everything
out here example for a lower res again
right
the problem was doing it this way rather
than doing the splat way is again that
it doesn't it doesn't really capture the
geometry hierarchy quite the way that
they were capturing the geometry
hierarchy but I don't know it might
still work out okay and this gets us out
of the volume texture business so
there's no volume textures in here
whatsoever which is another pretty nice
aspect of it right it's entirely screen
space so I don't know that sounds kind
of fun so I think I might just try it
this we may be on to old hardware to
really get this to run and
my time but it's been long overdue for
me to move to a modern card so what I
probably should do one of these days is
just replace the handmade hero machine
with something that has a modern GPU in
it and and we'll have to do that
sometime soon regardless so yeah what I
would say here is we need some we need
some argument about how we're going to
do the sampling but other than that I
think we're pretty much fine because if
we just simple have a reasonable rule
for sampling out of those textures we
can just use exactly this transference
that they're using here we could just
use and then we'd be fine right
and I think that should just be about it
this here where where instead of ever
having an emitter area we would just
know the emitter area would be
proportional to the bitmap resolution
that you were at if it gets excessively
filtered down so basically what would
happen here is just a lot of texture
reads for every one of these when we do
the lighting it would need to read from
basically for each depth field it would
have to read from four from three
textures right and it would sample from
those sectors at different myth
resolutions as well so it would sample
from you know each each successive myth
level it would have to sample from
I also think that would be a problem
with introducing lighting
discontinuities because if you think of
what will happen with the mips right the
NIP levels do things like this right so
let's say we're computing the light from
right here and we wanted to sample you
know this area we're going to have this
problem where we introduce a
discontinuity because someone who is
sampling the lighting from just slightly
to this side would then not sample like
these so right across that boundary
where you go to a place where you're
where you wouldn't maybe miss where you
wouldn't be in the right place in the
miss maps I wonder if that's a problem I
guess what you could say is well at the
higher levels as a courses levels of the
myth myth map we just sample everything
right so everybody gets lighting from
the four most coarse versions or
something like this but then as you go
down you get you know progressively more
refined I don't know it seems a little
iffy it would be nice to be able to do
something more like they do it where
they've got those hierarchical vertices
the problem with that is I'm not sure
how we would really get this
hierarchical vertex structure I'm not
sure how we would really produce that
I'm not sure how we would do sort of
that clumping
so here's the thought for you and I'm
really just I mean we are out in
incomplete lala land and I admit that
but I mean it's lighting what do you
want for me here's another thought what
if we did this in a multi grid fashion
so what if we did what if we said okay
here's what we're going to do we splat
all the stuff out using the desk feels
we then filter it down so we now have
you know a proper mipmap pyramid like
this where we start out with a one by
one and we go down to a 2 by 2 and a 4
by 4 and an 8 by 8 and a 16 by 16 and so
on what if we did the lighting on the
pyramid so we have these slats that get
successively more approximated when we
get to the top we just have one lighting
element right so what if we did an
up-down kind of version of this thing so
we start out we've got all these pixels
as they filter up the lighting anything
that's an emitter is obviously getting
you know written into these successively
more filtered versions right so as we go
up the tree we do about like we do
transference the one by one really
doesn't have a transference so we start
with a two by two we do the transferring
on the two by two to take whatever
they're up average illuminations are an
average directions and we you know we
bounce the light once there then we go
down the next level to the four by four
and we push the lighting from the two by
two down to the four by four so whatever
light got added at the two by two gets
added to the sub-elements of the four by
four then we take those and we bounce
the light again writing it into the
eight by eight right then we take the
eight by eight we bounce blows and we
write it into the sixteen by sixteen
this sounds fantastically stupid I admit
that I don't know that there's any
reason to think that this is going to
give anything like good lighting I also
have no idea how we would ever debug it
if it were not giving good lighting and
we wanted to make sure that the reason
it was not getting good lighting is cuz
the idea of stupid and active
implementation of the bug so that's a
little bit of a problem admittedly
however it has one nice element of it
pun intended which is that it operates
in a very consistent time fashion so you
get this sort of you know successively
you get this sort of successively
coarser approximation so if you want to
for bouncing the light around really far
you do it on the 2x2 and it propagates
downward and downward and downward you
know so yeah I could believe that would
work to do something resembling
something and so you keep following this
process down right you right into the 30
to the 64 the 128 to 256 the 512 to 1024
and the 1024 is maybe how far we go
right so we just have like a 1024 by 512
or something that we write these flats
into I don't know and then that
filtering process occurs and by the time
you get to here this is you end up with
this is your light value that you would
actually apply to the things in that
area and the light value tells you what
direction it's coming from roughly let's
say because you've got that bouncing
so yeah I mean if I was just to pretend
let's say in my head that I believe for
a second this was going to work which I
don't know that I do but basically what
you do is you do surfaces up right and
you do directions down so you take your
depth field and right now let's just do
the top depth field because we don't
really need to worry about volumes if we
can't even get this working for just the
surface the very top one so you take
your depth field you assume that you
stored the normal to the surface at that
point that you were rendering out you
write those into some lower res version
of the bitmap so the 1024 by 512 let's
say by just taking samples you don't
even have to average necessarily let's
just take samples but we could average
if we wanted to we could take the 1920
by 1080 and we could sample you know and
do a smooth interpolation of those
values right so we could by linearly
filter from a 1920 by 1080 to get the
1024 by 512 so we do that we now have
the proper or you know we could even do
we could even just do this I guess we
don't really even need to do that we
could just do the 1920 by 1080 we could
just subsample that so we could say it's
always just a divide by 2 of the thing
who cares about the wasted space right
we can just subscale each individual
version of that down further so ok can
we do that let's say I so we basically
have a nice array by 1080 and then we
would have a half version of that and
half version of that going down as far
as we wanted to go so we take those we
produce the services and those services
are just the little just a direction
vector of the direction the surface is
pointing and the color value right
of the light at that point which for
most of the services is going to be
nothing and for emitters it's going to
be the emitted light value right so we
successively averaged those going up to
produce average surface directions and
we averaged the emission going up as
well right
we then and I guess that I think about
it it's the same so services up
directions down is really the same thing
because the surfaces are the emitters as
well so the directions are always just
going to be the direction the lights
going in right okay so then we have at
the top we've just got one value that's
like the overall average emission of the
whole scene in the overall average
normal which doesn't really give us much
information at all so we don't care
about that at all but then the 2x2 down
it's slightly better but not really
right not that much information but
nonetheless we do the whole algorithm so
then we do the shadowing any mission on
that and what we basically produce there
is the Delta value of how much shadow
how much emission we produced right so
at this level in each of the cells it's
a two by two we've got in addition to
the direction which we're not going to
change we've got the average direction
we just have the you know the pot plus
or minus RGB right for each of these
cells so after doing the lighting
calculation how much did each one get
brighter versus how much did each one
get darker so we take that plus or minus
RGB right and we add that to the next
level down so in this case now we've got
for each of these cells let's say this
cell we have four cells in the bitmap
below us so we take whatever that plus
or minus RGB was and we add it to each
of these four cells right then we do the
exact same thing on these four cells so
these four cells themselves now do the
same shadow transference that we do here
so it's just every time it's just on a
set of four cells doing
transference on for sells right for
sells for sells for sales floor sells so
I don't know would this do anything
resembling anything I have no idea
probably not it's probably just stupid
but that's my stupid idea I hope you
like it so I think that sort of works
what I don't know is how much
discontinuity that introduces because of
the mipmap boundaries
my fear is the answer is quite a bit and
so then what you'd end up with I feeI
fear is that you'd end up with hard some
hard discontinuities in the lighting but
I don't know maybe that could be
mitigated by just when you finally go to
when you're doing this push down maybe
you add a little bit to the neighboring
one to like help smooth it out I don't
know but that's my fear my fear is that
you end up with these hard edges in the
lighting because at the you know the
screen was at its course this level
divided into four sections and I fear
that like this whole section the screen
is going to be slightly brighter now
what we could do there again is we could
just kind of bloom filter that out a
little bit like blossom it out to smooth
it so when we do that sort of plus that
Delta RGB blossom when we're going to
process the lower down versions you know
we could add that out to the neighbors
at a linearly interpolated amount and
that would probably solve that problem
but it may just be I don't know it may
just be intractable so I don't know this
is a really ridiculous idea but I kind
of like it and I kind of want to try it
and the depth fields were kind of a
ridiculous idea alpha blending through
depth feels is not something that I ever
heard of for a 2-d game but it
work great so sometimes in game
development you know you just want to
press your luck you just want to press
it because the last thing you want to do
is not press your luck and have you miss
out on something lucky it's only time
that you're wasting right you don't have
to stick with the routine if it turns
out to not work we throw it out and we
do something else so since I kind of
like this flavor of hierarchically
merging I kind of feel like that's what
I want to do and I feel like I can do
that fairly easily to be honest on the
path upward on the past upward I don't
even know if we need anything other than
just a simple mipmap filter right
because on the path up were at all we
would really need to do is just we're
just blending directions and intensities
that's it
so yeah I mean I think this is going to
be pretty straightforward
yeah I don't know I mean it seems pretty
straightforward now we do have I guess
that yeah again the problem is just each
of very big textures because now think
about two because we're talking about
this being a def peel rather than a
voxel ization these things also have a
position right and really technically if
we want to do the whole thing it would
be for we do we do all four def peels
probably at once so we'd be talking
about just a really huge so we'd have in
1920 by 1080 right
that's for def peels is what we're doing
at the moment that would go and that's
by four elements as well right or by
several I guess we're not going to talk
about that because that's our color we
also have a depth buffer not sorsa but
anyway so we have four of these things
that now will come through we need I
guess we don't need to know now that I
think about it we don't need to store
the XYZ position of the emitter because
that's all we're always given we just
need the depth of the admit err because
since we know what pixel it's on we know
where is in a long array we just need to
know how far along that ray right so
reconstructing the 3d position is not
particularly difficult because the depth
gives us that information so really we
don't need that we've got these so all
we need to store is we need to store the
depth to RGB ease for the color
intensities or the back and front side
of these surfaces of the emitters and
the direction right so this is one
element this is six elements this is
three elements right so total wise we've
got ten elements there if I'm doing that
math correctly so depth to colors and a
direction
now like our saying probably we can
eliminate one of those and get it down
to two so it would be nine elements and
then there's the question of if we want
to do one for each step feel if we did
it with four times nine or 36 elements
since nine elements is really three rgba
textures i'm sorry three RGB textures
you could think of this as twelve
textures twelve RGB textures right or we
could think of it if we have them be RGB
a instead we would end up with nine and
we'd have to pack them creatively right
I think I would go with this method
first because this is an optimization
and this at least keeps things stored in
a sane sense right so it keeps basically
one RGB emitter emission front side one
RGB emission back side front back and
then one RGB plus or sorry one XY plus D
for the depth and the XY of the
direction right so three textures / def
peel to do the lighting right and then
each one of these so so you've got
basically this really big bulky process
here that's all the time
so you've got 12 texture filter that
goes down down down it's got to do it's
got a read from 12 textures produce the
result so that's going to be a really
media expensive process right as it does
that big deal
once it's done however I think then
that's it lighting is now super
straightforward because now all you're
going to do for lighting is you're just
going to look up like the closest thing
so you're just going to look into that
that that final texture whatever that is
the 1920 by 1080 texture you're just
going to look into that your pixel
location you're going to pull out the
lighting direction and intensity you're
going to do the the calculation or
actually you're not going to do that
you're just going to pull out the
intensity music that's it because you've
already gotten down to just you you're
on yourself so you know what your
lighting was that's it you're done so
the lighting is just is just here
there's I don't think there's anything
else to it than that right
yeah so I think that's one I think
that's roughly correct the only thing
that's I guess to be honest there is one
more kind of thing to that it's not so
that's not quite through I think we
actually have a slightly worse situation
for the textures I think it's probably
more like four textures here because I
feel like we would also have to do the
RGB reflection or I should say like what
the what the surface reflectance is so
this is like the surface parameter
because without that information we
wouldn't know how incident light on this
cert on whatever this element is how it
bounces off right so we would know the
light coming in but we wouldn't know how
the light bounced off and so when we
kind of average those up we would need
to record to both the reflectance and
the emission values for this surface so
how much light is it giving off right
now versus how much when we get new
light in how should that light be
modified in this case right so it seems
like it's really more like a 16 texture
filter right and again so that's really
heavy weight and that's unfortunate but
you know I don't know that's just that's
just how it goes my dude it's
yes so I I think I mean if it's a 16
texture filter the problem with that the
only way I don't really think it's that
expensive is the thing because you're
only doing it once for the whole screen
and you're doing it on you know the MIT
Maps I think most modern cards would not
have any real concern about that my only
thing that I think would be a problem
here is that cards that can't do 16 taps
are in trouble
sichting taps is the wrong word
sampling from textures they can probably
sample from textures a lot the problem
is how many textures are sampling from
and so 16 textures is probably just a
lot of textures like too many textures
so that's a little bit of a concern
right and I don't know how to get around
that particular problem I feel like it's
definitely an issue so that's a little
bit of problem the other thing that's a
little bit nasty is I don't think the
cards like support multiple render
targets modern cards all do I don't know
if like cards as old as this one would
support multiple render targets and the
reason that that matters at all is just
because we need to be able to store the
direction components right now we just
sort RGB a depth which every card can do
we would need to sort RGB a depth normal
which requires writing to a second color
target because it's going to have to
store that X and the y value right
so yeah so that's pretty bad
again for a modern graphics card that's
nothing they would not care about that
at all it's it's pretty milquetoast for
this graphic card I'm just guessing that
it would be a complete disaster right
now the render target part we could fix
the render target part is easily fixable
so what we could do is implement our
renderer and in fact we probably do want
to do this now I think about it we could
just get the approximate normal by using
the by just doing another pass that
records what the normal was at the
closest point for that best pass for
that depth feel right so just after we
do it
we do one extra pass to write the normal
that would not require writing to an
extra texture so that would be pretty
straightforward I think so I'm not too
scared about that the thing that I am
scared about is the 16 source textures
so let's find out whether that it even
be possible on this machine from jail
and litter for maximum textures actually
Sanders
Phil Phil max of Santa's so 32 samplers
would be well more than enough that
would be twice the number we would
actually need if that was the limit but
I don't know if there's a good place to
look at that
what is that site that does up until
graphics card keys abilities
[Applause]
all right so let's take a look so this
is whether or not we would get an extra
render target right
so it looks like mostly everything
allows for color target though or more
unless that means for color I mean I
guess max color attachments we can just
query on our card and that's probably
the floor
max letter attachments is just whether
or not we could write out the the other
bits there and that's the maximum of
color attachment points in a frame
buffer object I just don't know whether
that means a color channel so if RGB a
means for then that's one thing if RGB a
means one that's another thing so I
would like to know what the definition
of that actually is in the spec so I'm
going to look
[Applause]
the arrangement zeroes I've met so okay
so four means you could write to four
render targets at once even if there are
GBA according to this so that means
writing out the direction should not be
a problem even on a card as old as this
one we can query it and find out which
let's just do that let me have an info
here it is so in our OpenGL info let's
do in here we'll just do although you
know what now I think about it
the way we actually were doing this is
we were doing it in here more so maybe
I'll just put them in here for now
set max color attachment Max and pears
shaded so let's get those values
[Applause]
and just see what they are because I'm
curious too now and again this is
extremely old cards have worked on here
it's probably totally fine for backwards
compatibility because this card is is
ancient it's like we're not doing a deal
get / mi anymore anywhere
Oh get integers there we go so we are
let's just say I thought we were getting
one specifically for that okay so let's
do color attachments and then we also
need a max sampler or something max we
need something that tells us the
samplers
[Applause]
so the open dermatitis is multiple
dependent by tanukis vertex architecture
immunity is love evolve wha okay so the
cause of Geo mass can bind texture image
units that is what we would need to know
[Applause]
so I think those are the two values and
we'll probably have to get those because
those are extended values so we'll have
to get those from Chora because those
are not in base up in jails and so base
up until them have any of those max
color attachments and Max combined oops
nice combined texture image units and
let's just see what these are because I
have no idea what they are on this card
it's so should be GL in
[Applause]
and so if I take a look at what those
work out to be
so yeah I mean it looks like we could
just do this even on this extremely old
card I seems fine let's take a look at
what this value is on something like an
Intel integrated graphics part which
tend to be the worst for texturing I
just see if we can get a little
visibility into that so my goodness that
is a large value so here's a page with
everybody looks like they're sorted from
least to greatest so even back really
old it looks like they were ok with 16
so we would be right at the limit but we
would be functional the only thing I
don't know is the number of color
attachments that you have does that
affect that so if you have one color
attachment does that cut into your
texture unit I assume texture units are
only for sampling textures in this
description and not the frame buffer out
because the frame buffer hats a very
different path it doesn't have a lot to
do with extra sampling but if there was
a question of address registers we're
like you only have this many texture
addresses at all then the texture to
which you were rendering would count so
that's the question but the good news
even in that case is by the time you get
to anything even a reasonably modern
you're up to 32 it looks like so I say
let's do this
I mean it's dumb yes but uh you know
Dumber things have worked you know
so let's try it okay so if we're going
to do this then what we really need here
is we no longer really have the concept
of a light texture in this sense right
it's not quite what we would be creating
here what we have instead is something
where we're going to store this extra
data in a myth map fashion now I don't
know that we actually need to have these
things be MIT Maps because we're never
sampling from them as actual MIT Maps so
really what we want to do is take this
notion of the light myth count and then
the light myth count is going to give us
how many of these light textures we need
and the light texture is just going to
be successively downsampled versions of
our 1920 by 1080 or whatever it is right
so assuming that we start at 1920 by
1080 how many times would we have to
down down sample it right and so you
know if I take 1920 i / . / - you're
right this is the process that we're
going to be doing to get down to the
minimum level that we want right
whatever that minimum level is so if
it's 1920 by 1080 what you can see here
is at some point unfortunately we get
down to 15 and there's nothing we can do
below 15 right anything that we do below
15 will sub sort of unevenly sample
which we may not want to actually do so
we're really looking at something that's
like 15 and then 1080 has the same
problem obviously right as you divide by
2 you get in fact that's pretty soon
right you get down there so I don't know
what how we want to address that problem
exactly there's a couple of different
ways we can do it one is we can start
with 90
twenty by ten eighty and just when we
get down to that level just let
ourselves do a sloppy sample right so
let it be the fact that yet you don't
accurately do down by two at this point
it's actually going to sample from it's
going to by linearly sample or something
right so we could totally do that
the other thing we can do is start with
something that's not 1920 by 1080 start
with something that's actually 2048 by
2048 and sample that down right and just
do the upper corner of it as it gets
sampled down and down and down right
again that doesn't really help us
because the same thing is going to
happen to the sub rectangle there so I
think probably what we want to do here
is we just want to take you know these
textures and I think we just want to go
ahead and and do their successive
versions now there might be some win to
doing the larger bitmap and having it so
we're only having to access its LOD s
and that wind would come if we ever
tried to read from more than one LOD at
a particular time right but I just don't
know if that's something that we would
actually be doing it doesn't seem like
something we would be doing
I mean the basic description of the
algorithm that I outlined before
certainly doesn't do it because you're
always reading from one level of the MIT
chain and writing to another level of
the MIT chain at every step in the
process so at no time do you actually
get a benefit where you are reading in
you are reading and/or writing from
multiple levels of mix change well right
in the nose of James's substitute at no
time are you reading from multiple
levels of the MIT chain meaning you
never read from the myth chain like one
level up and the level that you're
currently on and furthermore you
couldn't do that because if you were
going to do that you would be writing to
the same texture you were reading from
which is generally not allowed because
the seats the sequencing breaks right so
it seems to me I mean just sort of
closing my eyes and imagining it it
seems to me that you could get away with
just these always being two separate
texture handles and off you go
I think so anyway if I have a 1080
texture well a 1024 is two to the tenth
right so if I do two to the ten I get
1024 so I'm suspecting that I will need
ten mid levels roughly now 10 19 20
right if I was to take and do that ten
times right so you know oops that that's
not what I want to do 19 20 divided by
so if I do ten MIT levels here of this
thing so the 19 20 is one level then
that's a the second level third level
fourth level first level second level
that's 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
I get that of something that's like 4
pics
why'd and a 4 by1 would be fine for our
purposes right for a minimum level so we
could you know pretty trivially do a 4
by1
if we wanted to make sure we got down to
things that were always no more than 2
we would need 11 mid maps right fantasy
watches or shoes always go down to a one
by one then we would know that we we
would need 12 right because that's the
that's the only power of two that it
effectively can encompass the 19 20
so it's our choice of how we want to do
that whether we want 10 11 or 12 I'm not
sure I'm not sure how much it matters
exactly let's start by saying we're
going to use 10 or rather we might even
say let's use 9 because maybe we don't
really want to in the circumstance where
we would have this always doing a 2 by 2
effectively we would want to make sure
that we always have two in why and so 10
myth levels means that at the lowest
level we only have one pixel in why one
texel and why one texel high and so
maybe we don't want that exactly so I
think what I would say is we have our
like light buffer and our light buffer
here you know this stuff goes away our
light buffers would have no more than 12
right like the buffer count and our
light buffer is going to be now this
very special purpose nutso thing that we
have going to have to create relatively
special purpose right so what is the
life ever have according to what we
talked about before well it's got a
front omission
texture it's got a back emit right it's
got a reflectance I know what we want to
call this I guess it's the just a
surface color and then it's got a
special texture that's the normal depth
or like the NPA you let's say it's the
thing that tells us the location plus
the normal of the texture which is a
special-purpose texture and so we can
just not store the NZ value probably or
maybe we want to store like you know n X
n Z because you know a lot of times our
stuff will be heavily pointing in the Z
direction so we want to store the most
dominant value right so maybe it's n X n
Z or something like that and the depth
so we've got these textures that we're
going to store and these are all three
elements so like note KFAB are all three
elements would be how we would store
these I guess but again we could just
decide to pack them and be clever
it seems like we probably should do that
so because why not right I can't think
of any reason why we wouldn't do that
necessarily well
on the way back down we never write to
this and for this so we're only writing
to these two right so it would make a
lot more sense probably to treat those
as separate and these two as separate so
you know maybe yeah we don't want to
merge them I don't know
yeah I think we don't want to merge them
because we want to read from these on
the way back down and right to these
[Applause]
potentially or other things like that I
mean I don't know that we actually want
to do that but we might it's plausible
that we could potentially do that so we
want these and then we've got the frame
buffers so the frame buffers here would
be something that writes to the front
and back omit surface color texture and
the MP text so you know this is this is
a write all frame buffer kind of a thing
and that's used for the path up and then
there's a right omit because the right
emit is the frame buffer we'd actually
use on the way down because once you've
built those MIPS you no longer need to
ask what the surface color NP texture s
are you know longing to modify what the
surface color texture or the normal
depth texture is at the levels because
it's just known right it never gets
changed again it's just admitted like
then that you're sort of pushing back
around in those in those cases right so
it seems to me at least to a certain
extent that that would give me roughly
what I want right that that gives me
mostly all I would need so this is my
frame buffer for writing to everything
which gets used on the way up and used
also for producing this initial set of
values from the DEF sealer results and
then the emitter one is just for the
down path right
okay so we need to produce a set of
these four you know some of these for
use with the the the NIP stuff and we
need the rather complicated shaders that
will be used for the tipping but we also
need the other part of the process which
is sort of the part that we should get
started on now which is that after we
have these light buffers produced we
also need some way of writing to them in
the first place and that's a little
trickier than it should be so let me
compile and kind of get rid of some of
this stuff here so what I want to do
here is have a thing that freeze here
frame buffer so what we want here is
something like this when we delete these
light buffers we've got so we would have
something like okay we've got a light
buffer it's whatever the light buffers
are at this point so we're going to go
through here and say let's delete each
of these parts of it
[Applause]
there we go so that's how we would
delete these and then we just need some
way of actually allocating these and
that would be this saucy gentleman right
here and so we've got a light buffer
count here that we're going to want to
set at the moment I'm just going to set
it to nine well actually now we'll click
to ten let's say we're going to get rid
of all of this stuff and the version in
the settings for now and again we will
add probably some settings for lighting
in there later that will recreate here
but this is the basic outline of the
routine and again we're not really going
to be able to use any of the stuff that
we've written for frame buffers or any
of that stuff because this is going to
be very specific these things are going
to be different from any of the other
things we use reimburse for because
they're going to write to two color
textures at the same time and all sorts
of other nonsense like this all right I
so now what we need to do is actually
create these
and we do have basically the outline of
what that would look like so we have a
frame buffer text image thing here which
you can see us creating this is not
really what we want but we're going to
want something similar to this I guess
looking at it we can probably make this
work
what's kind of interesting about GL text
image 2d is why if you're not passing
anything do you even have to specify
anything here you know and I'm saying
like what's the point of that they have
an updated version called GL text
storage which is look way better it's
much better than geotech cement duty but
I don't know if all cards support it I
think a lot of Intel stuff doesn't
support it at least not with them out
there like most latest gist of all late
drivers but it looks like we should be
able to use this actually as long as BG
r8x isn't a problem in this case uh so
yeah and I I guess I don't know again
like is there somebody we could just
pass zeros for these or would it get
upset with us like can we just pass zero
let's let's find out first of all let me
just try it and then we'll see whether
that's an anomaly of the card or whether
that's actually allowed because again we
we're not trying to submit anything so
I'm not sure why we would ask identify
anything there we specify the internal
storage format that's all we should need
right so what if I did that what if I
just said hey yeah we're just not passed
anything
yep just as I suspected Val you know
that's really unfortunate because like
man it's just dumb like why would you
have to pass something it's just stupid
because there's nothing happening there
but anyway oh well
but frame buffer text image is what we
could use in this case right so if we
wanted to here right I could sort of
crib off of that and when we do our
light buffers and create them we're
basically we could still use this
function so we would have the the width
and the height here this is just going
to be a texture 2d because we're not
going to multisample these at all and
the internal frame buffer format here is
going to probably be a like a 16s or an
RGB 16s version probably is what we'll
want to get away with and what we'll
start with is a 32 F and do a note here
Casey drop this down to 16 F once we
know what what because we don't really
want to eat all that bandwidth for
32-bit floats when we really probably
don't need them for lighting but when we
start I usually like to start by doing
everything in 32-bit floating point
since cards allow it and it helps you
know that you're not getting a bug from
precision errors or clamping errors and
then that way you can just toggle it
down to something smaller later and then
know that what you see is a well working
algorithm that just has now been reduced
in precision so you can estimate whether
it's worth that reduction in precision
right so what I want to do here yet is
do frame buffer text image for a couple
of different things so let's say we have
our buffer here and I want to
rate one of these for each of the things
that we've got and so I've got my front
image mission texture here oops I've got
my back omission texture here I've got
my surface color texture here and my mp
Tex now in each of these cases I would
also point out the fact that the surface
color tip it's just used for the
reflection equation almost certainly
could just be stored in srgb eight right
there's almost no need for it to be
sixteen per gun I don't think the MP
text itself probably could also be sort
of done in srgb eight because again we
don't really need the depth to be exact
and obviously the direction doesn't have
to be exact either so I strongly suspect
that we could really cut down on the
total number of bytes we're actually
dealing with here because probably it's
only a mission that's going to need to
store something fancier than 8-bit and
even that could probably be encoded in
8-bit
because if you think about it's like
well you know how much do we care how
accurate the emission is so let's just
say that the number from 0 to 255 ranged
actually was like brightness 0 to 10 you
know and yes not that granular but who
cares so I don't know we could probably
get away with a lot of stuff there I
don't know maybe maybe not I honestly
the problem with that is you tend to put
a lot of banding and that doesn't matter
anyway so I would say that we could
definitely get this down if we want to
at first I'm definitely starting with
floats though because you don't want to
introduce extra sort of possible
confusion in there about what's going
wrong you want to minimize the number of
things that can go wrong when you're
working with the GPU since you can't
step through it at least not on our
machine so here's I don't know what this
is just texture to be correct here's how
we would attach those so one of our
frame buffers is going to have to attach
them all right so it would basically be
each of these guys back admit surface
color and then P and maybe I should call
this just what it is an X and and Z or
well now we don't know we might change
that encoding I'm going to change the
name everywhere for no reason so yeah if
I do this field frame buffer texture QD
there's nothing special I have to think
about there I don't think
because we're only creating one myth
level for any of these so I think it's I
think we're fine so one of them is going
to be that one of them is going to be
this so it depends on which frame buffer
we're doing so this is the town frame
buffer this is the up frame buffer so as
we sort of build our MIPS we would be
doing rights to all four as we do our
traversal back down to spread the light
we would only be writing to the light
right and so then I just need the thing
that creates the frame buffer
and so here we would have something like
this tips and I would like to keep this
like so and so in here what we want to
do is just say all right we've got our
buffer it's the right all buffer here it
is right then we've got this one this is
the right emitter and neither of these
are going to have a depth buffer because
we're just we never want to do depth
testing or anything like that we're just
building dip levels so as we go we're
just kind of aggregating these things
together right and I think that's
basically it
oops got to restore that to working
order and so here I want to take and I
want to get the light buffer out of
there and now I just need to know what
the texture width and height are so in
this case we've got text width
text height and for the text with
texture width and texture height those
are just whatever the render width and
render height are and then each time
through here we do a text width divided
equal by two and a tektite divided equal
by two
right so they're getting successively
smaller smaller and smaller if at any
time the text width is less than one it
should be set to one and if the text
height is less than one it should be set
to one because we don't ever want to
miss down below one and have a zero like
a zero dimension texture is not going to
work I so it looks like we didn't copy
the GL color attachment for the other
ones from core ARB so just grab those
real quick
[Applause]
hello color attachment there they all
are all right so now we are creating
those surfaces and they're ready to go
and I think we can kind of end now and
tomorrow we can start by trying to build
those which will require two things
first it require us to have a way of
specifying lights right now we don't and
so the way that we'll be doing that is
we will have a way for you to specify
that something is emissive and then we
will have to start doing the actual work
of building those shaders which will
probably take us a couple weekends to
get right and then it will work alone
and will you be happy or sad
or are you planning on taking a
different non-conventional brush-like
yeah I would say we're taking a pretty
non-conventional approach to lighting
yes it's a unicorn dog any recommended
programs to use for a newb it's pretty
open quest up in any question a noob in
what a noob in programming and when you
say any recommended programs what do you
mean like like editors or compilers or
like what do you mean
is that metal music coming from the
stream or am i tripping I hear nothing
outside
doctor when you port the game to jei or
make a port of it in ji once it comes
out I know we won't be porting the games
of jei just because I don't think ji
will be done it well okay even if it
were done today I'm not going to you
know go restart the entire programming
process in that language right if J hey
I had been done back when we started we
might have considered just doing it in
that language but that's not really
feasible now I assume probably somebody
will port it to jei and because there's
people who've done ports to like D and
rust and other things they get varying
degrees of through it like I don't know
that every people always stick with us
that well because they get the word or
whatever but also when it's all done
it'll probably be easier to do a port
because you could just pour it directly
and it's not too hard
so we'll SCH which you think will take
longer coding the engine or coding an
actual game um probably coding the
engine but I don't know that's really
more about how much stuff we put in the
game so it's kind of open-ended we can
certainly choose to make coding the game
take longer because we can keep adding
things to the game the engine we don't
have much more to add right once we have
lighting and we do some cleanup maybe
with like creation and pathfinding stuff
then we're mostly done with anything
that we would call strictly engine so
you know there's not a lot of strictly
engine things we could be doing at this
point you know we'd have to go start
operating things like music compression
or thing you know we'd have to like add
compression these stuff or let's rebuild
the software rasterizer
at some point so there's some things we
could do that would increase the engine
workload but you know we've done most of
the things so really I think mostly what
we're looking at now is okay you know
how many hours did we spend on
encoding 400 hours 500 hours something
like that and so if we spent like 500
hours on game programming I'm sorry we
spent 500 hours an engine programming
that's what that's you know a couple
months of full-time programming work
essentially not very much for someone to
do you know certainly achievable
how many months of full-time team
programming work do we think should go
into this game you know probably should
be similar right 500 hours I don't know
you can only find more things to put
into a game to make it better and when I
say put into a game I don't usually mean
like just adding features or anything
because adding more features doesn't
necessarily gain better but you could
always focus on like Oh could we tune
this part can we tune that part could we
change some item balancing here like you
can usually find stuff to spend your
time on so I would suspect that it's
going to be largely up to us it'll
really depend on how much stuff we want
to put into the game
it's a unicorn dog editor for
programming so if you want to know what
an inner good is are for programming for
a new programmer is I would say just use
the one that's built into Visual Studio
right because if you're brand new just
cut down on the number of things you
have to learn so just use the editor
that's in Visual Studio
assuming you're on Windows and build and
run and edit in one package write
simplify once you get good enough to
care about editing you may want to
consider a more high powered editor like
for coda or something I use for coder
and I like that quite a bit so you know
maybe you want something like that where
you can customize it and see and make it
do a lot more stuff for you but you
don't need to do all that at once right
you can start out with just the basics
it can
Holst eighty do you work on handmade
here outside the streaming time no I
there the hard and fast rule on handmade
here is I'm never allowed to type a
single line of code that you do not
watch and I have to explain it so it is
the slowest possible development process
you could possibly undertake for a game
I literally type every single change on
the stream I explain it every time on
the stream and I'm not even allowed to
think about it overtly outside the
stream so I do no pre-planning
whatsoever the only things that I do
outside the stream or when I happen to
think of something when I'm just like
walking around doing something else and
I'm like oh maybe we could use deaf
fields for lighting like I might just
think of something and I can't like stop
myself from doing that but even planning
has to occur on the stream like you saw
today where I discussed the lighting and
stuff so hand made sure you see one
hundred percent of the development
process period there is nothing in the
game development other than like the art
asset production rate or whatever that
is not on the stream
so the real estate that is like if I
were to do it myself separately from
handmade hero it would take no more than
the time that it has taken on stream to
do but actually probably must look much
less because I wouldn't explain anything
gary johansson codeblocks did not was
not usable when I last tried programming
Linux which admittedly was 2013
programming entirely on the next 2013
2014 because it had a bunch of stuff
that it couldn't do I don't remember
what they were
it was either like you couldn't view
assembly language to step through
assembly language or you couldn't do a
memory window or you couldn't launch a
debugger that you didn't build inside
code blocks
you couldn't debug actually while you
didn't build inside blocks I don't
remember what they were but all that I
have like a list of things you gotta be
able to do to be usable to bugger and it
definitely failed
now whether they've added them since
then I don't know so you might have to
recheck about retained and immediate
mode do you think these paradigm boxes
work for game code as opposed to engine
code as well so what I would say about
immediate and retained mode is that they
they really are just ways of
conceptualizing an interface boundary
and they work everywhere right
like they're always the lens you can
look at to determine how your interface
works does your interface require the
person on either side of the boundary to
have a corresponding life time
management for odd you know objects
whatever they are I don't really mean
object in the object-oriented sense I
just mean any conceptual element that it
defines or does it not and that's really
what retained and immediate mode is
something is has a lot of retention and
I tend to think of it in terms of just
the the content of retention
so saying the same is immediate mode is
not really a statement about having
something in particular it's a statement
about not having something so when I say
that something is immediate mode what I
mean is it has low or no retention and
when I say sometimes at retain mode I
mean it has high retention and what
retention is is retention is the idea
and I don't particularly like this term
I would prefer a different current but
it's it's it's unfortunately just what
was the original terminology when I got
here right I was not even probably born
at the time when someone invented the
term retain mode I know maybe I was
maybe I was like 10 or something but
what I need I retention is the degree to
which the user on the non-reusable
or the non reused side of the API
boundary knows about the lifetime of
something on the reused side of the
boundary and I should say knows about
what I really mean is controls so to
make a simple example of a button let's
say since retained mode gooeys are
common let's say I take a API where the
user of a library so we've got the user
in the library there's an API boundary
between them if the user has to create
and destroy the button as individual
events then that is a high retention API
for that button because the user has to
be in complete control of the existence
of the button this means that the
existence of the button is now
completely mirrored on both sides of the
boundary in a behavioral sense right
meaning that the actual event of
creating and destroying the button has
to exist on both sides of the API
boundaries that's high retention
so a low retention or no retention API
is one where whenever the user wants
there to be a button they simply say
there is a button to the library and if
they don't say there's a button then
there isn't a button so now there's no
retention the event of creating the
button exists only on the side of the
library and on the user side they simply
know whether they wanted a button or not
on any particular time and just ask for
that at that time right now these things
have pluses and minuses but most of the
time low retention is better and the
reason that low retention is better is
because it reduces the degree to which
you can have errors in the communication
across the API boundary you know for a
fact that the user side has existence
criteria that it is maintaining about
whether or not there is a button for
example if the user side wants to show a
dialog it has to know in its state stuff
about where it is in its understanding
of what's going on to know that that
dialogue had to occur now when that
dialogue has to occur that's the piece
of state that actually matters to the
user side so it is tracking the fact
that the user is interacting with a
dialog right now what it doesn't care
about is the fact that all the things in
the dialog exist right it's just he
doesn't want to track that state if
there's a thousand buttons in the dialog
box I don't want to track that they all
exist I just want to track the path
dialog box exists right and furthermore
I don't even really want to practice the
dialog box exist what I really wanted to
track was that the user is in the mode
of interaction of the dialog box
so what then happens is that user if
it's in oh I'm in dialog box interaction
mode
let me tell the library about these
buttons that should be on the screen
that should be clickable right the
library should then be responsible for
tracking whether those buttons exist and
when the user stops telling the library
that were in dialog interaction mode
those buttons should just get cleaned up
right
and so typically when you're shipping a
library to someone I kind of think of
that as the better way to design it and
I think that that's true across
basically everything if you are talking
about an API boundary of reuse I think
to a large extent you want to really be
careful what things you require
retention for and which ones you don't
that's yes so would you write your game
logic code in immediate motor retained
mode um so the answer is that it depends
if you're trying to create an API binary
there or not right okay and so one of
the things you'll notice is that we kind
of did write our game logic code in
immediate mode if you look at how our
game logic code is set up right now the
way that it works as we seem entities in
we edit them and then we stream them out
what that means is that the game never
really updates the main database of
where everything is stored it never
really talks about things getting
deleted or not right what happens is
just when we do our all of our entity
work if we want to kill an entity we say
oh that entity is dead now and then when
it goes to get stored back it just won't
get stored back so in a sense we did
write it in a very immediate mode
fashion we don't actually go ask the
game database to delete the entity we
assume all entities are deleted until we
hear that they are back right in the
sense and so I think a lot of that stuff
will look very immediate mode but the
point is not to eliminate storing things
because programs are about storing
things the point is that at certain API
boundaries it makes sense for ease of
use to eliminate or reduce the number of
things that the person on one side of
the boundary needs to tell the person on
the other side about life time another
way to say it might be if the lifetime
of an object can be implicit in the
usage of the API it should be or at
least consider it
because forcing lifetime to be explicit
requires you to have hold a bunch of
unnecessary handles on one side and it
requires you to make a bunch of a
necessary calls to clean things up
I plan on starting a productive summer a
40 perspective projection box well game
okay may I ask you for some tips on
graphics like how do I utilize graphics
card the best because it's not optimized
for 5x5 matrices and it's hard to think
with other concepts for me I wouldn't
get too worried about the fact that it's
not optimized for 5x5 matrices because
it actually is optimized for 5x5
matrices is maybe what I'd say there's
probably some inefficiencies there but
let me just remind everyone and I think
I talked about this a long time ago but
GPUs aren't actually X Y Z W vectors so
you will oftentimes see stuff on the GPU
that's like you know
Veck 4 P Matt 4 I don't remember what
the name of it is because we use our own
type dos for these Matt for you know my
matrix and then you'll see like vex 4
you know transform point equals Matt
times P right so you'll see that in a
shader and you'll think to yourself oh
well clearly we've got all these vector
things obviously the you know the GPUs
ALU is like super optimized for like
doing these like 4 by 4 matrix
multiplies and I'm totally screwed
I go to 5 by 5 the answer is not
probably the case if you're on like an
Nvidia card or something like that and
modern graphics card it's just probably
not the case why is it not the case well
it's not the case because you see a lot
of stuff that's like oh you know colored
RG you know access just the red and
green components of something or
replicate the r component
out to a bunch of things like you know
this this color value equals the red
replicated so a lot of the stuff that
graphics cards do in shaders a lot of
the codes that they have to handle works
out of sub-elements of these sectors
right
as a result graphics card design right
now is not about vectors stored as
packed XYZ that's not how they work
similarly typically they're working on a
raise of like four by four pixels or
stuff like this which again would not
fit into that four is very conveniently
if you don't know what these are these
could be like depth components or
whatever right blah blah blah so
typically what gravity arms actually are
is they're wide versions of the scaler
path so typically what happens if this
is a vector shade if this is a vertex
shader typically what happens it is not
running a four-element wide version of
this shader on one vertex what it's
doing is running 16 vertices in parallel
through the same shader
in a scaler path so the first thing that
happens in the shader compiler is this
gets blown out to the full matrix
multiply scaler right so it's like matte
you know zero zero dot p 0 plus matte
zero one has to be it right it blows out
the full scalar version and then it does
it for 16 vertices at a time as if each
vertice was done in scalar vertex time
scalar so if you want to write a 5 by 5
matrix multiply go right ahead
it should pretty much run at the same
speed and maybe there are some very
specific things in some some cases where
you'll get a slight slowdown there but
it is absolutely not a problem to think
about a vertex shader as scalar and run
it that way
does that help
and really the only thing that I like
thinking it through the only thing I can
think of that you might run into and
again I'm not an expert on this so take
it with a grain of salt but I think the
ALU path like all the arithmetic I think
you're just fine you'll run at full
speed the only thing I think you might
be aware of is I don't know to what
extent the memory unpack is based around
X Y Z X Y Z W so some of like the memory
unpacking might be less good because in
order to get those five elements things
out into the right places maybe they
won't you know so but that's it so I
think it's just memory unpack is about
the only thing that might downshift you
at all but your ALU speed should be fine
I think
all right
if you know what a lot since it was so
hard to find this thing I'm gonna leave
that open all right thank you everyone
for joining me for loves on handmade
hereit's and a pleasure coding with you
as always if you would like to follow
along series at home you can always
clear to the game on handmade hero org
and it comes to the source code so that
you can well so that you can try it
yourself and play around with it we also
have a forum site and go to if you want
support the video series the patreon
page and go to form so you go to my last
questions a patreon page and go to
transport the video series a schedule of
opposite tweets the schedule so you know
when we're going to be live so you want
to catch us live in an episode guide
that you can use to catch up on past
episodes that's about it for today I
will be back tomorrow with more handmade
hero lighting coding where we'll try to
get some of those light buffers filled
up we won't get to actual lighting
tomorrow because just getting the
lighting buffers filled properly and
nipping properly will definitely take a
full two hours probably more but we will
get it started and then next weekend
we'll see if we can get some actual
lighting working that's about it I hope
see you back here tomorrow for that
until then have fun programming and I'll
see everyone on the Internet take it
easy everybody