hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream I forgot to log into our
github again but you know what we don't
really need it right now anyway um so
I'm gonna reset my clock here because
it's 12:30 and I was so start at 12:15
and I want to actually have all the time
today because I'm not really sure what
I'm gonna do but I suspect it's gonna be
kind of digging into some rendering
stuff and I want all the time I can get
so this was gonna be day 546 let's go
ahead and end this and then pretend
we're starting a new session 12:30 here
we go so what we did yesterday is we
took advantage of the energy system
changes that we made the other day to
create some ground cover right in a way
that doesn't really affect the rest of
our system negatively which is nice but
there's a lot of things that we need to
do I mean all we did was splat it down
there and so we're you know we're more
or less accomplished what we wanted to
accomplish but it helps bring up a bunch
of the stuff that we now need to do to
finish polishing up our system so just
looking at the ground cover right now
several things I want to mention first
of all it's not lit and so lighting our
sprites is a big thing that's been on
our to-do list for a while
you can see that this really pushes that
issue because you get a complete
mismatch the ground cover looks terrible
against the background because they you
know the underlying cube should be
roughly the same color to sort of
prevent you from seeing show through
areas of the little like grass that's
that's sort of popping up right but
since we don't light it it's never going
to because you never would know what it
should be set to in terms of color and
then similarly we also can see now and
this is probably something that maybe
only I can see because I do suspect that
the video compression that happens when
you're streaming or watching something
on YouTube will prevent you from
actually really seeing this but if you
look at what's happening here when we
zoom in you can see these are nice and
detailed and smooth as we
we're not using mipmapping and so what
will happen is we get lots of little
crispy sparkles and that's because again
mipmapping when we actually do texture
sampling in you know 3d graphics card
the texture sampling is going to do a
bilinear filter for us by default and
the way we have it set up and what a by
linear filter is going to do is get a
sample to neighboring texels in the
texture for both rows right so the
bilinear is is to neighboring textures
both rows it's gonna lurk those together
and it's gonna loop the result together
to get essentially like a box filter
right essentially taking for texels and
looping but doing the bilinear between
them to figure out what the color should
be what that means is that we will get
reasonable filtering so long as we don't
shrink our texture down by more than a
factor of two but once we shrink it down
by more than a factor of two we're
effectively asking the graphics card to
use for texels to approximate an area
that's much larger than for texels
because once we've shrunk down by say a
power of four there's actually 16 texels
right that are getting that should be
represented in one pixels worth of
screen space and we're not something
that we're only picking you know sort of
a subset and so that's where you get
that kind of unsmooth look as we zoom
out further we get that sort of
crispness and again I don't know if you
can see it but trust me the end user
would see it on their action when it's
actually being rendered and isn't
getting decimated by say a video codec
like look at this on twitch right and so
there's you know first of all that's a
video quality issue now granted right
now we're running through MSAA
probably a little unnecessarily I'm not
sure we really want to be running
through Emma stay as long as we actually
are I think we might want to separate
our pet to a 3d pass that goes to MCA
and then the rest doesn't kind of a
thing but again those are more for when
we go to optimize the renderer the only
reason I bring that up is that's one of
the reasons this doesn't look as bad so
right here you can kind of see maybe
that's around the natural bitmap size
hard to say exactly what it is but
something like that maybe once I get out
to 2x like about there I would expect
those sparkles to start being pretty
noticeable and they're not that bad part
of the reason they're not that bad is
because we're still running through MSAA
and I don't know to what extent we're
getting some benefit there because I
think we have some kind of alpha 2
coverage alpha 2 coverage stuff turned
on I can't quite remember but it's been
a long time since we've played around
with the rendering stuff I think we're
basically leaning on extra performance
in the graphics card to fix the problem
in terms of sparkles before it even you
know so it's it's making it look not as
bad as it should look and we're
basically wasting GPU time for no reason
to do that because in the future like I
said I think we can optimize our render
quite a quite a ways from where it is
right now and that'd be one of the
things we'd want to do and then I think
this would look even worse in terms of
those sparkles so there's that so we got
the lighting we got the mipmapping and
the mipmapping actually has other issues
that may or may not play in here and I
don't really know because we haven't
really tried to analyze it at all but
one of the things that also happens when
you're not using mipmapping is if you
don't supply MIT maps to the graphics
card it means the grabbes card always
has to sample from the most detailed
version of the Texel texture because
that's the only version it actually has
what that means is that it will do a lot
of scattered grabbing for bilinear from
that texture which pulls in a lot more
memory bandwidth wise through the
graphics card as it's doing that
sampling then was really warranted it
didn't need all of that memory because
it was really just trying to get a much
smaller image worth of samples but since
they're all spread out over this big
texture it creates this sort of nasty
memory bandwidth problem where you're
forcing a lot more bandwidth through the
card than you actually need it and so
one of the other nice benefits of adding
nib
into the system is that if you provide
bitmaps to the graphics card not only
should it generally look better because
it will be able to sample more
accurately what's going on but it should
also reduce the bus bandwidth on the
actual graphics card because more of the
actual data will get used because again
it can pull in the whole MIT map and use
all of it to do its rendering and that
will be much smaller than pulling in
like a whole chunk of a texture just a
sample for pixels out of it then a whole
nother chunk just a sample for textures
out of texels out of it right and so
you're used the number of texels that
you end up using per sort of cached line
that's pulled in across the the bus into
the texturing it's into the shaders
right that savings adds up typically and
how much it would add up for us I don't
know but point being that's another big
reason why certainly depending on the
system it always is dependent on the
graphics card and you know how big the
cache art is and how much textures
you're using and all that stuff but it's
usually I mean one thing I could say
it's never better to have these giant
textures sitting around if you're only
actually rendering these little tiny
pieces of them at the very least you
could just send down just a tiny version
right uh so I think we want to address
that as well and that's just another
again visual quality thing finally the
last thing that we probably want to look
at is a better distributor and that is
to say that if you look in here you kind
of just have random clumping this is
what's called white noise it's the kind
of noise that's actually I'm tropic the
kind of noise you're looking for and say
cryptography unpredictable and so that
kind of noise in terms of scattering
things around in a natural way that's
the kind you would see in nature is not
really appropriate typically things
don't like to clump close together in
nature they they compete for resource if
they do that so I tend to spread out and
so the kinds of patterns that we see in
nature
tend to be more like blue noise which is
noise that is filtered to prevent two
things from being too close together so
it's still random but it has constraints
on the randomness and I've talked about
that before and that's obviously
something that you would want to do here
we want probably look into something
like that and furthermore even if that
wasn't sort of something that we would
take a cue from in nature just in terms
of rendering efficiency you can tell
that that would be interesting to us
because we're trying to cover the ground
with a certain number of sprites we
don't want to have to place an infinite
number of sprites down here to try and
get good coverage so spreading them out
in sort of a natural so that no two are
particularly close together is also just
a good way in addition to sort of
mimicking what nature would do for
resource competition it's also just kind
of a nice way to make sure that we get a
good even coverage which is something we
would want even if that wasn't a natural
look we may just want to do it for
rendering right all right so that's
where we're at and I don't know how I
want to attack this problem exactly but
I think what I'd like to do is I'd like
to just maybe open up a couple weeks
here where we're just gonna start
working on our rendering quality and
we'll just do whatever we want to do so
we're gonna just work forwards and start
to pick things apart and try to get to a
point where we feel a little bit more
we're feeling like it's a little bit
more towards the completed version of
the game renderer which we're getting
there so I would like to maybe make that
that a push for that over the next few
weeks as we go all right so I think the
biggest thing I noticed right now that
we can take take care of immediately is
that the creepy crawlies that I'm seeing
here with the MIT mapping I think today
we should be able to unless we get into
graphics sort of GPU hell if you will I
think we should be able to do something
about that so I'm gonna go ahead in
there and try to just take care of that
quickly and then I think we want to move
on to getting some sort of working on
the
lighting which I think will take a
longer period of time so how do we work
with MIT maps and and what even are they
let me give you a brief sort of overview
we've talked about it briefly before
I'll talk about it briefly again now
it's not a particularly complex issue so
hopefully it won't take too long
to sort of give you the background but I
just want to make sure everyone's on the
same page of what's going on here
all right so MIT Maps so MIT map is
actually abbreviation you may have not
have ever really heard about the term
stands for but you probably heard the
term nip is actually not it's not like
there's a processor called MIPS right
it's not the same these are different
acronyms the MIT in MIT Maps actually
stands for multum in parvo I believe
right which is Latin for many in place I
believe that's what it actually stands
for but I don't speak Latin nor was I
around when they invented MIT Maps so
who knows but that is an accurate way to
describe them multum in parvo many in
one place that does actually tell you
what a MIT map is what a MIT map is is
storing more than one version of the
same texture map so that you can do
sampling on it more easily now the kind
of MIT mapping that we have in modern
GPUs is what would typically be called
pyramidal I'm not going to spell that
right I don't know it's called pyramidal
MIT mapping and what that basically
means is we're going to build what
amounts to a pyramid of textures and
each layer of the pyramid is used for
sampling at a different distance so what
is a MIT map well we all know what a
texture is right and a texture is just a
bitmap in memory and maybe that bitmap
is like 256 by 256 right you may ask why
are they square right and actually
is one of the reasons they are square
basically wrapping like UV computation
with wrapping clamping mirroring and and
MIT maps are two reasons you want your
textures to be square in terms of
implementation if you've seen a GPU but
that's sort of neither here nor there
where you don't care about that part of
MIT Maps right now we actually just care
about quality so a texture is some
bitmap it's 256 by 256 in this case I'm
just making up a number but it's some
dimension typically a power of two also
related to MIT maps typically square
also related to MIT maps right okay so
what happens well when we sample this
texture like I said we are fundamentally
asking the question on the screen right
we have some pixels and these pixels are
in a grid at any particular location for
one of these pixels right I'm gonna be
asking with my texture map as I try to
draw shapes that have the texture map
map on to them I'm gonna be asking what
color would the texture have been here
right if it was actually taken and
putting out there in the 3d world and I
was looking at it right what would it be
and answer that question as we know we
take what's called a bilinear sample
right which is we take where this would
actually be if this thing was here we
find out where that would be in the
texture right we look at the for texels
that are a right in that area right
because remember the point in 3d space
is not going to correspond exactly to a
Texel it's gonna be in between texels
somewhere because this is a full 3d
transform full floating-point who knows
what's going on there right so we're
gonna be somewhere in this texture right
and what we're gonna see is we're gonna
take the four texels that are
surrounding that sample and we're gonna
blend them together to get the result
right and that's called bilinear
filtering and we all know all about that
if you don't know what I'm talking about
you haven't been watching handmade Hiro
so go back
use the episode guide to search for
bilinear and i will teach you all about
it a past me will teach you all about it
man and that's as far as we got but
here's the problem look at what's
actually happening here when I take this
texture and I try to place it somewhere
out in a 3d world and render it to a
screen with the projection
well the pixel is actually occupying a
whole area that maps to some kind of a
quadrilateral here in texture space
right and depending on how small like
let's say this was actually the whole
texture right getting mapped to this
shape on the screen
well this diamond area here as it gets
transformed back is like this or
something right and if this was two DS
five to six there's tons of texels in
here look at how many texels would be
inside this diamond right I mean this
diamond is almost a quarter of the
texture right it's it's almost like 128
528 diamond right and so if this is a
particularly detailed texture with lots
of complexity in it sampling for texels
isn't gonna tell me jack squat right
I mean if I've got like you know some
Reds over here in a green area that
comes in here and some checkerboarding
in here I mean who knows what it is
right I gotta pick a single color to
represent all those I can't figure it
out just from four texels depending on
which four texels I randomly ended up
closest to in this one centroid sample I
happen to pick right is gonna give me a
wildly different result so here's where
that Sparkle I always call it Chris
penis right you've heard me say this you
know what that's some bad spelling crisp
beingness right so this is where that
sparkling Christmas comes from as this
slides slowly across the screen this
location that's picking four pixels
is gonna jump like if I move this only a
little bit like I move this 1/2 pixel to
the side this thing's gonna jump all the
way over here right and it might pick a
totally different set of four colors to
sample from and I get that sparkle right
I get that sparkle so the key thing to
understand what we're trying to do here
is say how do we get four pixels of four
Texel sample to give us back a more
representative result of what the
texture looks like in that area and that
is where MIT maps save the day what we
do is we say let's pre-filter our
texture map and store the results of
having it scaled down a bunch of times
so instead of just storing our 256 by
256 we will then do a 128 by 128 and a
64 by 64 a 32 by 32 a 16 by 16 an 8 by 8
a 4 by 4 a 2 by 2 and a 1 by 1 right and
you can see exactly what I'm doing here
I had a two to the seventh right I mean
when I started with 2 to the 8th I have
a two to the seventh to the sixth to the
fifth to the fourth to the third to the
second to the first two to the zero this
as you can see forms a map pyramid right
it's basically a perimeter arrangement
where I have a one by one that's just
the average color of everything a 2 by 2
which is basically like what the colors
were in each quadrant right a 4 by 4
which is a 16 version of that right and
so on and so forth what this allows me
to do is this allows me to say all right
when I'm in a sample an area before I
actually go look up what the 4 texels
are I'm going to use the derivative in
screen space of the UV chord
of this of this shape right because
remember the it's the UV coordinates to
tell me where to look in this thing
remember UV coordinates right well
actually they go like that
remember UV coordinates right they're
telling me that's how I map textures
onto a mesh I'm basically saying pinning
down where it all is and I interpolate
between them right again look us up a
past handmade here I don't want to go
through UV mapping again well if I
simply look at the rate of change from
pixel to pixel right the D you like D
screen X and the DVD screen Y I don't
know how you want to think about that
but basically like as I step from here
to here and from here to here right as I
go pixel to pixel how much is my you
changing how much is my V changing those
rates of change can tell me how large
the texture actually is appearing on the
screen if those rates are very very low
I know that I am that the texture is
very large on the screen if those rates
are very high then the texture is very
small on the screen right so by
comparing these rates of change to the
rates up to the size of the texture
right and we can talk about that a
little bit more in a subsequent stream
it's not really super relevant to us how
the GPU is doing this because we're not
actually implementing that equation
ourselves but someday if we do a
software version of the renderer we want
to implement mipmapping in that renderer
this is what we would have to figure out
right the Texel change basically versus
the the screen you know how many texels
do you move if you move one unit in
screen space okay so what we would like
is we would like to make it so that when
we are sampling four pixels we actually
sample four pixels that cover the entire
area this thing would have mapped to and
lo and behold if we went down to like
about the 32 by 32 or maybe actually all
the way down maybe even to like the 4 by
4 ad it's hard to say that's almost a
quadrant right if we went down to the 4
by 4 that's exactly
what we would get right we'd be able to
sample just that region with four
samples we'd get all the colors averaged
together right so what we do is inside
the GPU it sort of straps on a little
piece that goes wait a minute instead of
just reflexively looking into this
texture let's actually go to a little
piece of logic here that says go to the
texture that would be most appropriate
for these gradients right for these
changes okay and that filtering process
basically allows us to leverage the fact
that we have pre applied condensation to
each of these texture regions to
collapse them into smaller and smaller
pre filtered versions because otherwise
the only other answer we could have is
to actually sum up what's the entire
contents of this giant region that's way
too much work for the GPU to do for
every textile fetch right summing up
thousands of pixels potentially all
right so this is a great solution to
this problem especially for us which
we're doing sprite rendering let me just
mention briefly the concept of
anisotropic filtering you may have heard
this before anisotropic filtering is an
extension of this and it solves a
problem that we don't have really I
don't think we're gonna have much of
well our walls could have it our cubes
could actually have it but so let me
just mention what it is and so it's
you're aware of it and how it relates to
this so one of the things you'll notice
here is if the if I take my screen grid
like I was saying before and I'm saying
this is you know try a set by pixel here
well what I just said all of this works
very well if the texture is relatively
head on to the screen but what happens
if it's very oblique to the screen and
only on one axis let's say right so you
know what if I had something where I had
my texture was like getting mapped on a
setting that looked like this was lot
laying down and so when I look at where
this thing maps into my texture space
right if this is the
upper corner here if I look at where
this maps in my texture space you can
see that towards the top of the texture
I'm basically using almost the entire
thing right but towards the bottom of my
texture I'm using all like very little
like I'm using less than less than half
even right so by the time it gets down
to here I may be looking it like that
much right well what you can see is
happening is I'm producing a trapezoid
right in my texture space and the
problem with a trapezoid is you can see
it very visually the number of the MIT
map that I would want a sample to
compute this line is like the lowest one
or close to it it'd be like the 2x2
probably right to sample that one
because I'm you know it's I want some
looks like that because I gotta take you
know I have one texel I'm trying to
sample this this entire thing right this
one on the other hand maybe wants to
come from the 4x4 of the 8x8 right and
so the problem you have here is like a
mismatch a single pixel wants to sum
something that doesn't actually exist in
the pre filtered version because our pre
filtered version just assumes that
everything's like head on and we're sup
we're subsampling everything with that
you know rectangular filter downward
assuming that we always collapse
uniformly right
and so what anisotropic filtering will
try to do it's a more advanced feature
of the GPU it will sample from a few
different MIT Maps right and really you
can implement your onus of traffic
filtering in a shade or two because you
have control over these now you might
want to do something crazy where you say
oh okay so I see that I mapped to this
trapezoid so I'm gonna sample like some
points like in here and these are gonna
come from different MIT Maps than these
and I'm gonna take one the center right
there's all these different ways you
might imagine trying to sample your MIT
maps to try to approximate what the
answer would have been if you had
pre-filtered your texture in a
trapezoidal fashion for being laid down
in this sort of head on the like very
oblique fashion right
but you can see what that's really hard
because once you start to talk about
arbitrary angles these these pre-filters
I mean I call it pre-filter for a reason
what you're doing is you're applying a
more expensive filter right sort of
beforehand and caching the results I
mean that's what this is right this is
an exercise in caching it's saying let's
use a little bit of memory to store the
results of doing much more heavy weight
filtering than we could afford to do at
run time for every for every single
fetch right and so what happens is that
pre-filter has to make an assumption
about how you need the filtering to work
if we didn't have to do that we could
just always filter exactly correctly but
again too expensive takes too many
samples so you have to make a guess here
and this is as good a guess as any right
just decimate by two each time store the
results and hope that that's gonna work
but you're gonna get cases where it's
not very correct and so what anisotropic
filtering and other sampling schemes
that try to like pick from it maps in an
intelligent way based on the trapezoidal
well you know it doesn't really have to
be a trapezoid either it could be
something else right because I because
you could get it's a quadrilateral right
you know I'm saying so that
quadrilateral in texture space informs
how you might want to take your sampling
and go
now when I say quadrilateral it's it's
really not a quadrilateral because
you're usually sample sampling
potentially multiple points like you
sampling theory is its own thing when I
put you that way so I don't want to like
browbeat you into thinking it's got to
be a quadrilateral because I pixel is a
square you could think of a pixel as a
circle for filtering purposes as well in
which case it would be some kind of an
oblong like an eccentric circle right I
so I'm not really a sampling guy and I
don't want to impose any sort of
preconceived notions on that so I'm
simply gonna say it's a shape right what
you are trying to do here is map
shape of a pixel into the texture and
sample that shape in a way that sums
what's inside it in a in a good way for
producing nice pleasing visual results
there's a lot more theory in there and
I'm not an expert on it so I don't want
to say things like quadrilateral or
ellipse or whatever and act like I'm
saying that that's the only one cuz it's
not right you can have arguments about
what pixels you know are pixels little
squares or aren't they and these sorts
of things and those are things that are
not really the kind of stuff that I tend
to work on so I don't have strong
opinions about them and I don't want to
make it sound like I do alright so but
anyway no matter what you think of as
the mapping there your mapping something
into that space and the question is how
do you accurately represent what the
texture would have shown if you could do
like an infinitely good summation of
everything that was in it and so on and
it gets into all kinds of details too
like what does the texture really mean
because the texture itself is a sampling
of something it's not infinite
resolution its individual little points
where you've recorded to the state how
did you record that state what do those
things mean are they normals are the
colors are the reflectance are the
admittance right how you might sample
them may even depend on what's actually
in them right and so all of that comes
into play if you want to go beyond just
the basic thing that we're doing today
and probably in handmade hero at all
which is just we want our filtering to
be smoother right that's all we're
looking for here smoother a nice
approximation of what happens when
things scaled down and again you can
already see now that I've sort of shown
you how this pyramid looks you can see
what I meant as well about saving memory
bandwidth if this thing is gonna sample
out of here remember I said as I move it
it's wildly jumping around kind of where
it asks a sample from when it's got only
looking at this little 16 by 16 it can
pull in like maybe just one cache line
through the graphics card tells it
everything it needs to know to render
that entire sprite potentially right
that's just a huge savings compared to
having to like jump all around randomly
just based on happens
where those pixel centers end up pulling
in segments of the cumulative get pulled
in in little blocks right it's touching
all of these blocks to compute a worse
result than if we just pulled in a 16 by
16 and got a really good result right
so again mipmapping very very very good
especially for what we're doing where we
tend to have things that are mostly
facing the camera anyway it's the exact
right solution for us and it's
absolutely what we want so what we need
to do is not much the graphics card
already has most of this stuff built
into the texture unit you don't even
need to implement the shader yourself
it's actually something that I think
happens during Texel fetch a lot of
times I think the bilinear there's
actually a lot of cards just have
bilinear your textual fetch hardware
that does it specially don't quote me on
that because they may have gotten rid of
that by now but they used to anyway and
so it's even faster to do basic bilinear
mipmap stuff then it would be if in our
shader we were manually grabbing things
and and summing them together because I
believe they've got like hardwired
bilinear collapsing stuff right on the
texture unit to give you this increased
throughput for that default case so that
means we can do very little work we
don't even have to rewrite our shaders
or anything all we need to do is just
tell the graphics card here's those
things you wanted you wanted those box
filters versions you want into the 2 to
6 to 128 64 32 right that's what you
wanted we got it here it is right so we
just have to start supplying these MIT
maps and once we supply the MIT maps the
graphics card can take care of the rest
because it has special hardware to do
exactly this we don't even really need
to implement anything in our shader so
let's go ahead and open up our code and
get this going now if you were I've been
with us the whole time if you're a
handmade hero diehard then you know that
actually we have some calls in here that
are like text sub image and we call this
right in here you can see it when we're
actually transfer
stuffed down to the graphics card I
believe this is it yeah here it is
so in our managed textures call you can
see we've got a special texture path
that happens for weird rectangular
textures that are used in cutscenes and
stuff but most of our textures go into a
texture array and here it is we call GL
tux sub image 3d because it's a texture
array and we attempt to put something
into the texture right and this allows
us to transfer using our texture index
into a particular slice of a texture
array what the width and height are for
that particular thing now you will
notice there's a bunch of zeros here
what do they all mean well if we go over
to Docs GL our favorite place for fui
why isn't this gonna get that up in here
yeah all right if we go and look at text
image I'm sorry text sub image 3d and we
take a look at the documentation for it
in GL 3 which is what we were using you
can see that there's a bunch of
parameters passed here and at the
beginning we have a bunch of zeros 0 0 0
texture index right 0 0 0 texture index
Z offset is where in the slices we are
right because remember we're putting we
put all of our sprites into one texture
and we just used slices in a 3d texture
for them right it's called the texture
array very common for bitmap games right
x and y offset those are both 0 those
are those zeros right here and here
because we're just putting it in the
upper corner we don't do anything else
with our updates we don't pack yeah
maybe we should we're wasting a bunch of
space so someday maybe we will but this
is the one I really want to talk about
right here there's a 0 at the beginning
of our GL compressed text sub image 3d
call and that 0 corresponds that 0
corresponds to this this is what this is
each one of these levels is a saw each
one of these MIT maps is assigned a
level number the level number is the
power of the texture you would imagine
where's my pen and I'm gonna draw it
that level number just corresponds to
where in this you are via the equation
two to the whatever the dimension of the
texture actually is minus the level okay
so if we have a two to the eighth
texture right then this D equals eight
the levels of the texture are d 2 to the
8th you know it are d 8 minus L right so
level 0 these are 2 to the 8th texture
level 1 is our 2 to this nice to the
seventh right level 2 is 2 to the 6th
and so as the levels go up eventually
you will get down to a 2 to the 0
texture and that's the last level you
can specify so in our case we can
specify eight of these textures because
2 to the 8 minus 8 is 0 which would be
the one by one texture the last one we
could actually specify right and so
that's that's the ball game folks so
that's what we're doing so what we want
to do is effectively extend this call
like this is our problem right here this
is why we aren't getting MIT maps we
aren't specifying all the levels so what
we really want to do is something like
this where we say you know level index
equals zero level index is less than 8
or something and you know we got to go
calculate what this is level index is
less than equal to max level index Mac
open gel I don't know what this is
because we haven't made it yet but point
being this value is going to be
something we specify based on our
texture size and then this has to
specify some kind of set of data for
each one of these right and so this is
the extension we need to make that's
what we're missing
once we provide that then we can just
turn on mipmapping and it will work done
right ok so that's the first thing we
want to do and it's gonna take us a
little bit of work
but let's try it so what I want to do
first is I'm gonna do we need to
basically create space to store these
things and we need to know how many
there are and all that kind of stuff so
we need to start extending our texture
pipeline to allow us to provide these
MIT maps as we go now there is this here
there it is there is a thing called GL
generate mipmap and what this does is
this will generate them automatically it
generates MIT maps for the texture
attached to the target of the active
texture unit I and the that's the only
thing I don't know is how reliable it is
so we could another option is to just
call it and call it a day it's less work
I just don't know if it works always
probably I don't know um I guess I'm
done to just call it the nice part about
it is that if the hardware can
accelerate building the MIT map it will
and usually it can because all it is is
a series of calls to the render to the
blip to like sample them down so we
could and let's try it I guess it saves
us some time so if we were to still call
this and not actually submit them each
individually we would just call this
function GL generate MIT map right
and that would be it
I don't think that's the default call so
we probably would have to provide it but
that's okay and then what would happen
here is this GL texture 2d array we're
just telling it that whatever texture
you had bound to that slot because
remember you got to bind these textures
so right here in GL buying texture we've
bound this texture array handle that
generate mipmap call is gonna operate on
this texture array handle so we sub we
send the image down then we say build
the the MIT map for it right now the
problem here's the thing I don't why
don't really know if that's a good idea
I feel like that would require it to
generate the MIT map for the entire
texture array and I don't know if
there's any way to tell it not to do
that so again I'm really I don't think
this is a good idea I guess it's all I'm
gonna say if you called it with a 3d
texture and you tell journey to MIT Maps
I'm suspecting it will probably not keep
any kind of dirty flag so it will just
generate it for the entire thing we've
got like a hundred some-odd texels
textures in there that's just really
expensive so I'm pretty sure we don't
want to do this but we can try it and
then I'll replace it with the better
thing maybe seems a good idea I don't
know so anyway let's try we'll see I
don't even know if it'll work it might
just fail as well on on to texture race
I don't know what the rule is there it
looks like heyou maps aren't allowed but
but it looks like texture arrays are
right
mitt prep generation replaces Texel
array levels base plus one through Q the
what the heck is Q though what what is Q
1 through Q what Q was I guess I'm just
supposed to remember from the spec what
Q is
all other mipmap are raised including
the level base array are left unchanged
by the company I have no idea where
they're getting the skew from the
internal formats the drive bitmaps all
meshes the base array the kind of
survives or is yeah yes so I mean just
looking at it I'm pretty sure we can't
really rely on this long-term though
right and I think that's just because
it's gonna it's gonna cause it to every
time we update a single texture in our
texture array there's no way to say just
regenerate this slice of the array you
know what I'm saying to you and so I
don't think there's necessarily any way
to do that
[Music]
what is this flag right here
see that's more what we would like
because then we would know that when we
updated it would just know to do that
but again still not good I all the stuff
just gives me the hives because who
knows what the cards gonna do here's I'm
gonna do I'm gonna say forget it I'm
just not using it I'm sufficiently
spooked we're not gonna do it
we're gonna send down our maps manually
and that's just the way it's gonna go
be advised that function exists if you
want to play around with it go right
ahead
there's another way we could do this too
which is that we can use render to
texture to basically create a like us do
the bleeding as we go I'm not gonna do
any of that we're just gonna do this in
software because this is handmade hero
and we implement the stuff ourselves
anyway we might as well learn to do it
in in our own code okay so that's just
what we're gonna do and I don't want to
know what the heck is going on there
behind the scenes cuz I don't trust it I
never trust a guy's car to do he screws
me alright so what we need to do now is
just say okay when we load stuff we need
to be able to generate the sort of the
the scaled-down versions of things and
thankfully we have worker threads
dedicated to exactly this so we should
be able to have a little simple down
sampler like we've already written
something that scales images down by two
we should be able to create something
that will just take the the bitmap scale
it down by to scale it down by two
against go down by two again and just
keep all of those results so that we can
when after we load them just submit them
right and you know it's not clear to me
that you know maybe we want to actually
store the MIT maps and load them in but
it's not clear to me that that's a good
trade-off because we probably ask you
know the further we go forward in
computing the more often you've got
cores sitting around that could be doing
work for you and so why put more stress
on the hard drive throughput which often
times is limited when we could just
dedicate a quarter
compressing and you know collapsing
things and so on
so I I would say probably my guess is
let's just use a core for this that's my
thinking all right so in here where we
do load asset work you can see where
we've got this work text wrap thing and
we call complete texture up on it and so
in this platform work you call back what
I would like to do here is after the
read data from file if we assume we need
to do MIT Maps something like this if it
tells us to Gen the MIT maps then what
we need to do is like go through and Jen
the MIT maps so this right here is gonna
be a thing which would do that that
generation and what I would want to do
is only we're only going to do this for
square things that are power of two
right I guess technically we don't care
if they're part two but we do only
really want to bother with them if
they're square I guess is what I would
say and we kind of want them to leave a
power to - I want this thing to be
square power - I don't want to deal with
anything else let's put it let's put it
that way okay so
let me look at complete texture up here
so the only thing that's a little wonky
now to think about it is that when the
width and height come in we actually
don't bother
we don't Pat it out until kind of later
in the process right so that makes it
actually a little bit trickier
a little bit more tricky because it
means that we don't really we don't have
things that are quite a power of two yet
either so what we would like to do here
I guess actually is be able to fuss with
these in sort of a way that just adds
the padding as necessary on each down
sample which is a little annoying but oh
well
so what I would like to do here then is
I guess just do the down sampling
without that right don't don't assume
that it's got to be pad or anything like
that just do a real down sample and then
upload the stuff so if that's what we're
gonna do Jimmy then each time we do the
bi-linear we may have to expand by a
pixel if the thing was like not a power
of two which is not going to be most the
time and so that's gonna be a little bit
delicate and we have to make sure to get
that right so what I'm gonna do is
because I might need to do this sort of
same stuff in multiple places I want to
create a helper function and assume that
I have something that can give me what
the correct operations are to do as I
step down my MCMAP levels right so what
I want to do here is say something like
Mick iterator right like this and say
begin MIT on this thing it is
[Music]
going to require texture up the texture
up itself has the texture handle in it
which tells us the width width and
height of the thing we need so basically
what we would do is say work texture up
texture
we need that actually start two-pointer
we need to get the width and height out
of that which we've got a thing from
[Music]
somewhere in here or do we do we just
use it just like dot width and height
maybe we just actually just access it
directly yeah all right um so we know
the width this way and the same with the
height right but actually I suppose we
probably just want to do it that way
because we're always gonna have that
texture handle available probably so
maybe we'll do it like that so we'd say
look begin a MIPS series for this thing
take the width and height
I'm assume that whoever you are you know
how to do everything right so this
little iterator doodad here will just
create the right set of like power of
two things and whatever else needs to
happen it'll work for us sort of doing
our down sampling right and then for
each part here what I need to do is I
need to have our box filter or down
sample there it is I need to basically
have this thing and I need this to be
able to down sample by two each time I
need to call this on each one of these
now what I am Not sure I understand
looking at how this thing works
is this thing assumes that everything is
a power of two right so is everything
actually secretly a power of two right
you can see that this totally assumes
that you know I'm saying cuz it's great
it's always gonna grab two for everyone
so I guess I lied we do require
everything that comes through here to be
a power of two
yeah all right well that keeps it simple
for us less efficient but simple so if
that's the case then we already
effectively wrote all this code right
all we're gonna do is just be doing this
down sample and the only real change is
we probably want to take make this down
sample take to a source in a desk and
you can pass the same source and destiny
want and in our case we would pass
different ones because we want to down
sample and save each version of our down
sample right but that's basically all
we'd be doing so this down sample would
just get called here and it'd be called
for every step through the MIT and
that'd be that so I think that's all we
really want to do here and looking at
the texture up itself so when I and in
fact I think I can kind of see also how
I want the rest of this stuff to work
here if I look at that texture app just
looking at how this goes maybe what I
want to do is pass this directly so I
think what I might do is make the the
MIT operator here actually just take the
texture up so you say like begin map and
you get back this this myth here and
then what happens is on each call
through I'm going to like down sample
from one of them and into the next one
right and so on the first time through I
don't actually want to do anything right
so on the first time through I just want
to advance the map but before I do I
want to save the sample like the source
right
so what I want this thing to do is give
me back like that region from the
texture up that's actually got the data
in it now and then what I'm going to do
is advance it forward and so then in
here this is actually kind of a while
loop I'm gonna do
oops this and each time I go through and
do my advance in fact I guess I could do
well now I'm doing like this each time
through here I'm gonna go ahead and take
the desk like so I'm gonna down sample
from the source to the desk by one and
then I'm going to advance the mitt
forward to the next one and I guess each
time also I want to source right so just
gonna roll through these updating the
myth every time I and downsampling right
that's really all I want to do so I want
this I want this like begin map thing to
just be able to or like iterate maybe
iterate MIPS I want that to do the work
of keeping everything lined up now you
may ask why like why did I do that
doesn't really make any sense does it
but it does make a little bit of sense
because remember we're gonna come in
here next and this thing wants to do
exactly the same thing right so what I
wanted was this I can call exactly the
same set of source code here
and then I'll know that the thing that
generates the MIPS is generating them
into the exact same set of pointers of
the thing that actually submits them so
I can eliminate the possibility of
having bugs between those two updates
right between those two walks
so again just defensively programming it
myself so that I know that the failure
is all in one place so my debug it it'll
work right okay so as I do this
submission I'll also have a level
parameter in there I guess like that and
then what I can do is say well when
we're doing the texture submission here
this width and height are gonna change
each time and so I want to do this right
and I think that's all she wrote can't
remember what this is called it's like
pixels data I don't know what who knows
pixels so you can see that's all I was
trying to do this way we write one
iterator we can use it to submit our
stuff because it'll tell us the width
the height and the pointer correctly and
we'll throw the level in there for good
measure and then we can also do when
we're actually doing our down sampling
we can use the exact same thing and we
know that they have to line up so once
we get one of them bug free the other
one will be bug free uh famous last
words
this is calling OpenGL so not
necessarily but you know closer to bug
free okay so what we need now is a down
sample that takes a source of a test I
actually have a pretty good idea of how
I want to do that and that is to say
that if you take a look at this call
here this is doing a loop I don't want
to do a loop I want just a single thing
that actually does the down sample so
what I'm going to suggest is that we
have another
version here called downsample that does
this which is the one we actually wants
and what that's going to do is it's
going to take these here and it's gonna
just use this part just that
alright that's all it's going to do yeah
i'm santi and that way when this thing
does its little happy dance it's going
to pull from one and write to the other
which is more what I wanted and this
thing can still use it because since we
know that it works in place as well we
don't need to write two versions of the
same function so what we can do here is
say alright we know we've got the result
here which is this one what I can do is
just save that before we reduce it so I
can say image you 32 sort of like dest
equals or I guess I could say breve
equals results something like that and
then here we just do this
so the idea here right is we would just
be taking we don't need this we would
just be taking when we do our down
sample right we just take okay where are
we at right now remember that because
we're gonna need that in a second
take the the place we're at right now
and decimate by two right there just
rank it by two and then pass that as the
dest calling this will do the same thing
it used to do before like this and so
all we now need to do is make sure that
this function actually pulls from source
or desc correctly so in here where we've
got desk pixel we actually want desktop
pixels in here we want source stop
pixels here where we're grabbing from
the source we want to do source dot with
to advance it because that's the one
with the correct width in our case when
we come down here to do DES pixel
packing we don't have to change anything
because it's just writing off the
pointer and similarly here we want to go
back and use that source with again and
that's it right that's all we needed to
do so I think that should keep us
completely compatible and everything
should work the downsample by two can
now get pulled out of the import stage
and into something that's actually just
like a math library or something like
that I don't know where image u32 is
actually where the heck is image 232
what's it doing in here in the pincode
all right whatever anyway so I don't
know exactly where this would be maybe
in the shared code I don't know I really
don't know we're down sampled by two
should live it's kind of a image
operation but we don't have image
operations in our system right now so we
little guess I'll just sit here for a
while and hang out I don't know oh well
you know what it's probably should go
where all the rest of this stuff is so
where's like B GRA impact where's that
at
looks like it's in the renderer code and
I know interesting where is this so I
guess this version of the other is too
old to have file info anyway so in here
well I guess I can just do this
it's an handmade map that H is that an
okay place for image three twos not
there though maybe I should just make a
new thing for it I really don't know
where this should go we don't have a
place for this sort of stuff you know we
don't have an image set of things maybe
I'll just put it in the PNG library and
that's where all the rest of our image
stuff is I don't know you got me it's
there now though alright so we're just
gonna call that a day because I don't
care and so now we've got to get back to
some of the more subtle parts of this so
first off we've got to make our actual
MIT bitter Raider stuff exists it
doesn't right now so we need to define
this somewhere and so I suppose that
this should be something probably in the
renderer stuff let's see probably
handmade renderer eh so we want to kind
of introduce this thing as something
that's like structure map iterator like
so and you know the the image you study
too should probably be in here too
shouldn't it right I mean that's feel
like that probably should have been in
the renderer I don't know we kind of
have a problem where this stuff needs to
be shared so we might need to kind of
pull it out into a separate thing like
you know if I were to do that I'm not
sure yeah like PNG parser and stuff gets
upset because it doesn't actually have
that which is an issue I don't know
all right I kind of want to make like a
little image library thing it's sort of
what I'm feeling we need to do here but
I don't know so all I'm going to do here
is just stub these out and then we'll
figure out how to amplify them in a
second I'm also kind of want this to not
be where my head is all right so we may
need to unpack the texture ops thing
there a little bit yeah but that's fine
and we'll deal with that in a second
so let's see yeah so this stuff the
problem is the renderer doesn't know
about the about the PNG library cuz it's
kind of isolated in that sense and so I
don't know if like I don't know if that
makes very much sense right it doesn't
seem like that should kind of be in
there right and yeah this doesn't have
memory arena's for example so that kind
of pollutes that again so I don't know
it really does kind of seem like it this
wants to be its own thing so I think I'm
just gonna I'm gonna bite the bullet
there's just gonna be a thing called
handmade image that just has this stuff
in it and that's all and everyone does
it right so there's a new file in
handmade code called handmade image H
it's gonna have that
and it's going to have this and it's
going to have this and maybe there's
some other stuff that would have that we
didn't put in here that should be in
here right so we we might go ahead and
kind of move some more stuff into here
as we go I don't know it's kind of a
good question as to what we want to do
there I don't really know what we want
to do there but something something
along those lines so then what I'm going
to do is inside handmade OpenGL we're
gonna include that and loops and I also
guess I don't know where the where the
CPP's get included here but we'll put
those in here as well I guess cuz we'll
want that
our test PNG code will now need this
something like that actually
that just means those were in the wrong
order that's an H H font yeah
by the way 100% of stuff I'm doing right
now is just because the CBO Standards
Committee never knows what they're doing
just to be clear none of this should be
necessary even a little bit but you know
they only have 30 years to fix the order
of declarations problem and never
bothered so thanks for that
glad you have our backs alright so let's
go into handmade hero now and let's
actually include these folks
don't know exactly where we should
include them but you know I think we're
good now um alright so now I think
everything is all set and the only thing
I really need to do is make a cracking
version of this that translates the
texture up request into a nip iterator
request here and so and we don't really
have to do that but I might as well so
they both get done the same in the same
place and so what I want to do here is
say look the call to iterate nips that
you actually call here expects you to
pass like various stuff to it like the
base pointer for the data the width and
the height that may be all it really
needs yeah I think that is all it really
needs and so this this thing's job will
just be to sort of crack that out into
these right and that'll be fine and then
we'll implement this in terms of of
those sort of unrelated elements okay um
so that's all I really wanted to do
there and furthermore if we want to and
I guess there's really no neat reason
not to at this point this call right
here could just be like generate local
MIT Maps or something like you know I'm
saying like this right here could really
just be something that we call directly
and it may be that argues for not
needing this particular other version of
the generate mips call either
so what we would do is we'd say okay you
know here's the texture if there's the
width
there's the height I don't remember
where the data is on this particular
thing but I think it's like there and
off we would go right and so here we've
got generate sequential MIPS same call
and this would just do this right so
here we have an iterator for like this
is basically just a little really crappy
image library now right we can scale an
image down by two we can iterate over
the MIT Maps levels for something using
correct pointer movement and stuff which
we'll implement in a second and then we
can also do our generate sequential mips
call which is just a utility that does
exactly what you want it to do given a
set of pointers to it so I think that's
good and then over there in the OpenGL
side of things where we're actually
submitting it I'm gonna say like okay we
only now have one of these I don't need
to make a utility for it it's just gonna
call it with the unpacked version of all
the data and off we go right okay so now
I think we're down to just weld I guess
there's one other thing we can do that's
not that we need to fill out this stuff
properly and that'll produce one more
call which is to figure out how much
memory we need for a MIT map so we might
as well do this as well so in here I'm
just gonna add a thing that's like gen
MIT Maps
we don't really need an entire pool for
it but we don't really care about the
memory let's go use for this load asset
work is not something that gets
allocated very often so it's probably
doesn't really matter one way or the
other but for now we're gonna actually
flag it just in case we're gonna say if
we need to generate the MIT maps than we
do and that's really it
but that means somewhere somebody had to
actually acquire enough memory to
actually transfer these MIT Maps right
and so in here we need a thing that's
like gem it Maps equals true or false
something like that right and so the
question is how do we know which one we
want to do and based on you know we need
some information about whether or not
this thing's supposed to have MIT Maps
or whether it's not and if it's is
supposed to have MIT maps we need to
generate more memory because when we
reserved space for it it needs to have
space for all the MIT Maps as well so
what we're looking at here is something
that's maybe a little bit more like this
right where we're saying look when we
begin texture up we kind of need to know
whether or not it should have MIT maps
that sort of thing uh what I would say
is passing forward might not be the best
idea could be that the texture up itself
maybe should be recording this
particular piece of information and then
we just look to see whether it said it
wanted MIT Maps or not that seems like a
potentially valid way to do this and so
I might suggest that's the right call if
you look at what's going on here I guess
what I'm saying is that maybe what I
actually wanted and if that's the case
then we wouldn't put that here it would
actually be this thing that determines
it whether or not it goes in there and
how it's gonna operate
I knew that makes sense because a
renderer is the thing that really tells
us whether it wants MIT Maps or not and
maybe want mentat for everything I don't
know it's hard to say point being let's
just say that gem it Maps comes back on
that line if that's the case then the
work doesn't actually have it in it it's
baked in to that particular texture op
which means that this check right here
would actually go
here right this complete previous rights
before future rights I do wonder if
maybe we need to make sure we complete
all our work before that I haven't
analyzed that path of the code much so I
might say we should just do this just to
be safe that kind of thing and then what
we would do is just generate the
sequential MIPS here as necessary right
so that would mean that the texture off
when allocated tells us whether we Gen
the MIPS or not we don't actually store
it anywhere we just kind of do what it
says that means when you call begin
texture up here what it would do is and
I think we already kind of know right
which is that we want to know whether
this one's going to be special or not
like is this is this thing going to be a
special texture or isn't it right and so
inside this texture wrap thing when we
actually go to to create it what I could
do is this thing right so when we ask
whether something's a special texture it
see here
so I begin the nice I'm not really sure
when that determination actually got
made but if you look at a texture up the
texture up has the texture in it
am I wrong about that yeah the texture
up has the texture in it that you're
going to use
so when you actually get that texture up
out this part here
I mean that's gonna tell you everything
you need to know right
I'll be honest I don't really remember
how we were signing those so so our
texture up texture
yeah it gets assigned right here in
refer to texture so I think that's it I
think that's all there is to it right so
I want to say that the best way to do
this is just yeah when we call begin
texture up the renderer is free at this
point to say what it wants to do and
what it doesn't want to do but I think
all it really should do is say is it a
special texture if it is it doesn't want
MIT Maps if it's and that's that's it
right so when we come through here and
we do this texture app result and you
know by the time we get down to the
bottom here we should have one right and
it's going to return it so at that point
we just want to do our check but of
course the problem is it gets assigned
there all right so never mind
[Music]
hmm I say so this is a little more
complicated and we do have to pass it
down here right like this thing needs to
know because it needs to be able to
produce the right size for the transfer
looking at this so I think this is what
I want to do to clean up this the way
this is is flowing so if you look at
width and height it actually is only
used to create the transfer partition
here right and so I think what we want
is actually this begin texture up should
just take size requested so what we want
to do is in here we want to do a size
requested and we want to pass down size
requested right this will not be
computed here it'll just say size
requested and we need to know do we need
MIT Maps right if we need MIT maps then
we need to create a size requested that
has room for all of the MIT levels in it
right that's what has to happen and we
would update our size requested to
contain that entire set of texels right
now we could create that closed form I'm
not actually even going to do that what
I'm going to do instead is I'm going to
produce size requested by actually
looping over in the same way that we're
doing before because I don't mind
spending that extra speed to make sure
that we always compute a completely
consistent result
okay so I want to do it like this where
we say let's ask first if we're gonna
generate MIT Maps and that's a call that
this actually thing was already doing so
we can do that pretty simply then what
we're gonna do is when we do the rest of
this stuff right we do get total size
from it for MIPS we would pass down the
width and the height and there in fact
let's just do that we know we need that
and I think then we're good to go right
so what I'm going to do here is inside
acquired texture handle that's where
we're determining whether or not we
would do it so we're calling this thing
here we're dimensions require a special
texture right and so that I'm just gonna
pull that call out so when we do the
acquired texture handle we're gonna pass
in whether or not it's special right I
and so this particular call
right dimensions prior special texture
that is sort of the opposite of Jen
Mitch map so you know we could just say
like special like so and we know we want
to generate MIT Maps well in fact I'll
just leave it like that when it's not
special makes sense and so yeah I think
that's all we really needed all we
really needed then when we call begin
texture up we pass the size we're
actually expecting to use which we will
let ourselves created space for them it
maps by computing that there then when
we come down through here when we're
going to acquire the texture handle
instead of this like bit that we do here
we're actually gonna pass down a special
flag so this just gets me through 2x
special rather than ever doing the gyms
right and that's it so that's all good
then when we do refer to texture it does
this little bit map with height thing
for texture and I think that's it all
right good good good starting to look
much cleaner starting to look much
cleaner okay so now we just have to
implement these begin texture up here in
our example code we know that that is
just a size requested thing right this
is this is our test renderer so we don't
really care about it but you know just
might as well keep it working
same here
all right so now finally after much
massaging I think we have gotten to the
place where we can just implement our
actual the actual logic that we
requested and be good to go
like I said when we do get total size
for MIPS I actually want to do this so
that we just loop and that's just doing
to absolutely ensure that we're using
the same calculations everywhere even
though we could use the power function
and stuff to make it right I don't care
about the speed of this call at all cuz
it won't amount to anything so I'd
rather not introduce the possibility of
bugs at least not at the immediate
moment so what I want to do here is just
have an iteration just like we would do
in any other case where we iterate the
MIPS all the way down to the end of the
chain and each time through we just sum
it up right so that just produces a
summation of all of the space we would
expect to take for each one of these
levels of the mill right and then we
just need to implement the part where we
sort of advance and an iterate here and
that should be something like how do we
want to do this so that should be
something like this probably when we
start out
we know the level equals zero we know
the image width equals the width we know
the image height it's the height and we
know the myth image pixels equals the
data right the validity of this would be
results equals myth image width not
equal to zero I guess I would say would
be the easiest thing we could also do
like a valid not sure how I'm not sure
what we're gonna do with that we'll take
a look at that afterwards we do the next
step and advancing well some of its
simple some of its not obviously to make
the level go up we increment it not very
hard in order to make the sizes decrease
we just divide them right and in order
to advance the pixels we just need to
figure out some new value that that
should actually be
now the problem that we're gonna have
here actually I suppose I don't really
need to do that I suppose I can just do
this right yeah so the main problem that
now we're going to face is just
termination and how we want to consider
like whether or not we want to or I
should say how we want to consider the
mid-levels to be terminated so the
problem that we're going to have is if
we want this thing to work for arbitrary
rectangular images which we don't
actually use right now and so maybe it's
just a pointless endeavor but what we're
gonna have here is one of these two
things on a rectangular image will
bottom out before the other so the width
would bottom out before the height or
the height would bottom out before the
width and you would want to keep
shrinking it down by two each time
leaving the other one fixed at one right
and so what you'd want to do is
something like this in that case
so if both of these things are higher
than one then you're just doing a
standard shrink by two but if one of
these things bottoms out early because
let's say it was a 256 by 512 so one
dimension bottom down early you don't
want to divide it by two because
otherwise you've ended up in situation
where you've got a zero width or a zero
height image prior to the other
dimension actually collapsing down to
one but we also want to know the case
where you have both of them equal to one
because that was the end of the MIT
chain so what we might want to do and I
again just say might because we might
want to say all right look if MIT level
with equals one and MIT level height
equals one then that's the end of it
something like that right I don't know
not the greatest thing since sliced
bread but looks okay right don't ask me
why this has level everywhere supposed
to be image just a brain fart don't ask
me why I'm doing this by hand probably
because I'm in between editors right now
they're all right uh so that's fine what
else we got okay so I think that's
basically what we want I think we've
done the plumbing so now we just have to
actually go through and make sure we've
implemented all this stuff correctly
because I kind of spammed a lot of stuff
out in there and it's probably not gonna
work so what I want to do first is I
wanted to switch to debug build for a
couple seconds go step through this code
and make sure I'm doing even something
remotely related to what I thought I was
doing and and get that going
right all right so let's start by by
looking at some of the submission
process here let's let's try to make
this stuff go alright so in here we're
just doing our standard white pixel
that's just used for making sure nothing
actually happens when we do non textured
rendering so that obviously comes
through and the size requested should
just be four for a single pixel
four so that's fine let's double check
now when we actually go to request some
kind of a texture for you know actual
use right so in here we've got load
bitmap we're passing that a particular
ID right it didn't hit the cache so now
we're gonna do something so let's see
what it is we're going to do here's the
width that we asked for here's the
height that's what we expect that's our
standard sort of overly large texture if
we look at what happens here we can see
whether we got you know special should
be zero so yeah and it is gen MIT maps
should therefore be one that means that
the size requested rather than being
this so so rather than that should be
some other thing based on this total
size for MIPS parameter that we came
through here but it's not so we've
already got a bug here it's here
probably because I forgot to put a plus
sign in or something yeah of course that
also means we've got a separate bug
because this should have produced a much
smaller value if it was just using the
last result so we've got some other bug
there too that's not working correctly
yes and you can see exactly what it is
these cases have been flipped okay
all right so let's try again got some
bugs out of there and there we go so
jumping in here don't care about that
we're going to look at that summation
call now we do get total size four MIPS
and let's see if that goes up kind of as
we would expect so there's that first
nip level that's exactly the number we
would expect now it should go up by half
that I'm sorry a quarter of that again
looks good yep yep lovely
how many MIT levels are we expecting at
a 512 by 512 that's two to the nine
right so we would expect this this value
yep to keep going and you actually this
is nice we can watch the width and
height go down here there's four to one
and now we should bail right now I just
want to make sure it actually sum to the
one so I'm gonna run that one more time
because I just want to make sure we
actually summed the one and didn't skip
the one so I want to do that but other
than that that look nice so here we have
summed the 512 by 512
there's the 256 there's the 128 so let's
go all the way down we've some to the
floor some to the to some of the 1
perfect so that's looking like it works
exactly like I want now that we've fixed
our stupid bug when I come back out
through here now our size requested
should be a little bit more there we go
and what you can see too is MIT maps
don't take up that much space you can
see the day between those numbers it's
not even twice as much for doing all
that filtering it's more like a quarter
again the size there right you know so
it's not too bad of a price to pay for
all this additional filtering just
something to think about
so when we go in here to begin texture
up we asked that much size hopefully we
get it we then start our task and we
feed forward this stuff here
I'm assuming that we got the correct
kind of handle because I'm assuming that
we asked for no special so that
presumably is good if I look at the
texture up handle I'm hoping that that's
correct it looks okay right I don't know
how the indices work with special
handles let's just take a quick look at
that it's got texture special a bit set
obviously that's not true here so that's
good and off we go
okay so that looks pretty nice pretty
happy with that let's take a look at
what happens now when we actually try to
generate the sequential bitmaps part of
things this is not what I wanted how did
we get here first shouldn't I have hit
my submission call who is getting
submitted who Gus who got sunk this time
around hmm let's take a look
so we're getting an invalid texture
format there which suggests that maybe
the well can't see this because it's
behind my head
I'm wonder if I need to kind of move
this over here that's probably better
huh
yeah so if we take a look at what we
were doing there when we're calling this
it looks like it was unhappy about that
so the question is why like what
actually happened there that was bad and
I'm not sure I would like to know what
we were submitting it looks like we were
submitting level one so we were trying
to submit one of these additional level
bitmaps but I don't know why how did we
get there right because we didn't ever
is this just our one by one but what
happened here
I don't know who actually produced this
texture but I want to so this was
texture index 1 and I want to see I want
to see what's going on there because I
don't understand did I not
did I not correctly set the texture up
for that somehow let's find out I I'm a
I want to make sure that I'm actually
clawing our generator first it shouldn't
that particular bug is not actually
related to this but it just I was
spooked by the fact that this gen mipmap
doesn't seem to have happened and so I'm
wondering if we just yeah okay so so the
problem that we're getting here is we
didn't set that right
I just forgot to do this so we need to
set that because I wanted that code
that's not the bug right that other bug
is different but the bug that I wanted
to know what was going on why we weren't
seeing that call I set a breakpoint
right you watched me set that breakpoint
in the asset system right here
it didn't get hit it's because we
weren't setting this value in the case
where we do actually need to generate
those nips so I want to run it again I
want to watch that happen because that
should happen before we do a mips
submission
all right so in here now now we're gonna
go ahead and do our down sample so I
want to watch this happen and I want to
make sure that this works properly as
well before we well or at least looks
like it's working properly before we do
anything else
so here's us iterating over the down
sample and you know what you can see
here too is it looks like we've got sort
of an issue where technically the
texture submission is not necessarily
like I don't actually know if this is
that those values are not power to
values right as we're going into the
down sampler and so I'm kind of
wondering
what exactly is supposed to happen with
that texture submission hold on a second
because didn't we just look and see that
when we actually came through here like
the width and height of this was like
512 by 512 right and so the problem I
think
yeah like what is this just a different
one that finished up first because when
we looked we were we were only getting
ones there that had with the night they
like 512 by 512 so how are we now seeing
something totally different than that
and I'm not sure
so in here this is gonna this is gonna
not need to push to 512 by 512 so okay I
see I see basically what we're saying
here so yeah we will have a problem with
our down sampler which is that our
current down sampler isn't smart enough
to handle the case where we don't have
an actual power of 2 right so we do need
to do a little more work here in our
down sample 2x this thing needs to
understand what it's going to over
sample right because otherwise it's
gonna fetch outside the image you know
I'm saying it needs to be aware of what
happens at the at the second-to-last
step right furthermore we would probably
want to round up so we've got some extra
work to do here that's actually fairly
complicated so let's go ahead and do
that as well all right so what I want to
do here is when we're doing this iterate
MIPS and again you can see why I wanted
hopefully this will underscore why I
wanted to do this summation manually
rather than writing a closed-form
version of it because as I modify this
routine I know that this one will
automatically pick up the correct sum
without me having to go redo the math so
looking at this what I want to do here
is I want to change this to round up so
what I want to do is I want to say all
right it's gonna be a divided by two but
I'm gonna add one first that way I will
always round up to the next value rather
than rounding truncating downwards
always because I don't want to like if
you have the value 3 and you divide it
by 2 I want to get down to 2 I don't
want to get down to 1 right so I want to
keep an extra I want to keep extra space
for things that weren't power of 2 the
reason I want to do that is because I
want to maintain the extra padding on
the outside of things because that's
when we put in like borders around
things for when they get shrunk down I
don't want the fact that they're smaller
that the I don't want the fact that
we're down sampling to eliminate those
borders unnecessarily
so I think I would rather do this than
truncate I don't actually know that
that's true because we haven't really
quite looked at it but I I have a sense
that that is what I would prefer and
then when we're actually doing our down
sample here what I want to do is make
sure that I don't fetch outside of the
source that's incoming and so while we
produce the destination and we're
looping through the destination what I
want to do here is make sure that so so
basically this I want to make sure
doesn't over sample and this I want to
make sure it doesn't over sample right
because you can kind of see that they
that they might so essentially what
we've got is our our X based sampling so
this this here right this wants to only
happen in circumcircle circumstances
right we want to do something more like
this right
so we want something that will prevent a
sampling over the edge and we could make
a better loop than this that would be
faster that wouldn't have to do this if
but we're not going to do that at the
moment so while this kind of make a
general note though that you know we
could do a lot better than we are
all right so looking at this what we
want to do is say look don't over sample
so just assume that there's zeros on the
outside of this thing that you will then
use if you cannot pick up an eval you
write and I want the same thing to be
true for the source for the for the rows
but unfortunately that's a little bit
harder right because sampling rows
actually requires that like this stuff I
don't have a way to set this pointer to
something sensible right I could try to
have just a giant set of zeros that I
can point it to and then this thing
would work but again that's a little bit
hairy so we almost want to do something
where we're gonna have again a more
optimized loop I can cheese out because
if you look at how the extra rows are
sampled we can't actually make it so
that the those are ours erode out as
well by again using a strategic if as
necessary but again not really sure to
what extent I want that to happen we can
duplicate instead which would be easier
because then it would just be you set
this point or equal to source pixels
zero I don't know if I necessarily love
that
so I'm gonna do the duplication cuz it's
easier first cuz I like to do is this
and I can do the same thing on X as well
it would just be this set it to what you
just loaded right so given that we can
now do a down sample that should in
theory properly operate on arbitrary
rectangles and it wouldn't need them to
have been powers of two or anything else
like that so let's do that and we'll
just leave it at that and then we can go
back and watch this and see if it works
properly right so here we are in
generate sequential mips let's actually
see what our down simple call is getting
it's going from 371 to 186 it's going
from 217 to 109 that seems about right
let me step out here as this goes down
right keeps going keeps going keeps
going
here's that bottom out case again you
can see it goes a to 1 and then 1 1 and
then it's done that's all the mips
produced hopefully it's correct then we
complete that texture up and submit
right ok so I think we're now at least
roughly preparing the correct thing if
we go back now and look at our
submission process we have to make
opengl happy about what we're doing and
so this part has to now be addressed as
well when we do GL text sub image 3d and
we're passing down a MIT level here to
submit I don't
actually no what it's complaining about
it could be any number of things but for
example one thing that it may very well
be is the fact that when we created this
we may not have told it that we wanted
space for MIT maps or things like that
so now like I said we've done sort of
our part of the work and now we're on to
the OpenGL massaging which is always a
barrel of fun so if we go look at where
we were actually specifying these
textures to begin with that's gonna be a
GL oops text image 3d call or something
like that in here somewhere
looks like we fixed this bug right we
don't have this anymore because we are
calling GL text image through today so
when we call GL text image 3d if we look
at the docs if I go pull GL three out
here and I say GL text image 3d and I
look at what I'm actually calling
[Music]
I want to go ahead and say and I'm
making this up 100%
because you know of course the docs
would never tell you I want to say that
if we are to call GL tech sub image we
may have had to have called GL text
image first so when we first announced
this texture we probably have to call
all of the MIPS that we might ever call
does that make sense
so we're probably going to have to do
something that looks like this and again
hopefully you can see just how nice this
utility function is you see why I wanted
to write it this way because everyone
can use it so you never have to worry
about complex computations in there
being wrong between parts of the code
because since everyone can just use it
and know that it's calling the same code
you just get a really nice sort of
buffer there where everyone's using the
same values thankfully right um so yeah
I'm gonna try this which is to say I'm
just gonna announce for our texture
array all of them here where we just say
yeah man
here's an announcement that we've got
every level from zero to two to the nine
so zero to nine I please know that
that's the case right and I'm just gonna
hope that that has something to do with
anything right
okay so OpenGL is now happily accepting
our textures that's great it looks like
our down sampler maybe sucks for example
or who knows I mean we could have any
number of bugs in here but the good news
is were pretty close right we have
submitted MIT maps to the system and it
is not rejecting
we've got some garbage on the screen so
we've got some errors that's fine but
what kind of makes me a little confused
is I don't actually know why we would be
using any of those MIT maps because I
didn't think we turned that on did we so
we're not sampling from the MIT maps yet
so to be completely honest I'm a little
confused as to what's going on there it
looks like maybe we've got a transfer
error or maybe we're not advancing our
pointers correctly like maybe we're our
down stampers like writing garbage into
the existing nips I'm not sure it's
going to be because we haven't told
OpenGL to ever look at those MIT maps we
sent them down but what you can see here
is this texture min filter texture mag
filter that setting it to linear is
saying don't sample the MIT map I think
although that may not actually be true
it may be sampling the MIT map and just
not try linearly filtering it no I don't
think so I think when you specify
texture min filter you need to specify
it yeah it's gonna it's not gonna pick a
miss MIT you'd have to do nearest here
I'll show you what I mean
so if we look up the docs for GL text
frame er I what you can see is that
there's a thing in here called min
filter and mag filter those are the two
settings that we have here min filter is
what you use when you might be
mipmapping actually because that's when
we're making the texture smaller than it
actually be mag filter we don't care
about that's when you're blowing it up
you're never gonna use the myth in that
case because you're actually stretching
it right so that we don't actually care
but min filter we do care about and
we want to see here in min filter is we
actually want to got a section there on
it see what those settings actually are
so here's min filter right and here are
our options
nearest returns to wait hours for type
summons some of the closest miss whitish
where I see this conclude items wrapped
in repeated from other parts texture
right but since there's no mipmap in
there I don't think it will ever choose
one so you can see you would have to get
GL nearest mipmap nearest at least or GL
linear mipmap nearest in order to start
using those MIT maps so I'm pretty sure
it will never actually use them in our
case that means I think we're over
writing our actual texture what I'd like
to do first I'm gonna go into a my asset
gonna take generate sequential MIPS and
I'm going to actually turn it off so
we're not calling down sampler anymore I
just want to see what happens like
that's all I want to see what happens if
we don't down sample right okay so what
that tells me is our down sampler is
just producing stuff in the wrong place
and there's two reasons that that could
be happening one is there's a bug in the
down sampler too is that our MIT thing
that we're using to iterate over to
generate them is telling it the wrong
starting point er which would then
produce garbage because it's writing
into the wrong place so there could be
bugs in either case and we're gonna try
and find out what's going on there right
okay so if we look at the down sample to
X source deaths here what you can see
here is the destinations writing into
dest and the source is running in the
source that's exactly what we would
expect to have happen when we look at
where it's reading from in theory it
should only ever be starting it's right
here and if I go through and look you
can see dest pixel the only place where
ever writing is right here so I really
think that that's an unlikely candidate
it looks like desk is getting passed the
wrong pointer potentially or when we're
submitting it we're submitting via the
wrong pointers
right but it really looks like that desk
is getting set incorrectly and so that
suggested me that maybe down here we've
got an issue with how these things are
going to update it could it could also
be potentially this computation in here
we're updating the pixel pointer right
so I think that's what we want to start
what we want to look at in terms of who
might be doing things wrong alright so
when we come in here when you see what
we're doing in terms of data writing I
mean it still looks pretty good right if
you look at it it's saying down sample
source to test and that source is always
going to be equal to the desk the next
time around I don't even in fact you can
even get desks out of the equation
because it's really it's just this right
and that's all we're doing
so yeah I don't really know what's wrong
with that we're gonna have to step
through cuz I don't get it
if you look up here at where we actually
advanced the pointer so when you first
start we just cast the pointer up and
say wherever you told us to start
running that's where we're gonna write
you know no big deal there when we need
to actually advance the pointer it's a
pointer to a four byte value we advanced
it by the width times the height that's
what you expect to see so I really don't
know why that wouldn't get out of the
way don't know so I'm gonna have to step
in I really couldn't tell you but it
looks like it's clearly doing it wrong I
mean that's about all we can say I'm
gonna go look at the code for that just
gonna set a breakpoint in there and
remedy and see if we can see something
wrong if not it'll have to wait till
next weekend I guess so coming through
here gonna delete this stuff and just
focus on what we've actually got in our
case here so here's our starting data
pointer that's where we're saying that
sequential ministry generated if I pop
back out to look at where that is it's
essentially saying that it wants to do
it to this data pointer that's where we
did the load in the first place I
believe right so we do read data from
file handle offset size destination I
assume that data I guess I don't know
that that data is set to the same place
I guess that's a good question is it I
mean it should be right but let's verify
I suppose it well I guess I'm here now
why not actually look let's just see
work destination is that
Tech's drop data is that so that seems
good all right that's what we would
expect if I jump down in here well that
doesn't make a lot of sense
oh sorry yes it does so that's the
correct value that's what we would
expect everything looks fine there so
the width and height in this case 3 771
by 217 I want to go up here I'm curious
what the work size is how big was was it
loaded it was 3 to 2 0 to 8 and so if I
look at the actual width and height
I should see 3 2 - OH - 8 is the number
that we actually get out when we
multiply those two together and then
multiply by 4 so it is right so we
loaded the amount we thought we loaded
now we're going to load up our MIT
iterator with that value here we go
we're at level zero we've got those two
values in here here's our pixel pointer
it's pointing to this what would I
expect the next pixel pointer to be so
in this case if I were to copy this
value I don't know why I can't click on
that but I guess I can if I were to copy
this value here I don't think I can show
this in hex or maybe I can yes thank you
remedy so if I wanted to move to the
next pointer and here what I would
expect to see is it would be this much
further forward right so meaning I would
expect after you know I'm going to
submit that image of that size and then
after that I'm going to try to step
forward by 3 - 2 0 to 8 and get this
value here right so that's what I would
expect so when we advance our MIT
pointer that is exactly what we get and
now when we call down sample we would
expect to see effectively us reading
from here
writing to their which I will again try
to copy this value there we go all right
so we expect to see reading from here we
expect to see writing to sorry I mean
there we go we would expect to see us
read from this and write to that right
I guess so there's something weird like
I guess remedy doesn't let you click on
some values but it does let you click on
others I'm not sure there's like some
kind of weird like I can't click there
but I can click here I don't know it
looks like you can't click on things you
entered but things that were expanded
you can right so it looks like members
of a thing you can click out here on
those but if you typed it in that's not
clickable right because all of these are
ones I typed in and I can't click on the
value yeah so it looks like there's
maybe something it might just be a bug
in remedy where it doesn't if you typed
it in it doesn't let you click on it but
if you didn't type it in you can James
right George is on the chat he said he
just fixed that 20 minutes ago all right
hey man things you'll never hear from
Microsoft about Visual Studio I just
fixed it is something you'll never hear
them say about anything really cuz they
don't ever fix anything so thank you
George we'll be looking forward to that
update for sure anyway so here's here's
my down sample code let's just get in
there I'll try and figure out what we
screw up because we screwed something up
right so let me take the source let's
take the test and let's just look at
what we're doing so here we are doing
our down sample the source value for our
pixels is exactly what we said it should
be the destination value for our pixels
is also exactly what we said it should
be so as we write
- here I guess that suggests this isn't
wrong exception thrown
wait how can we get an exception this
time but we didn't get one last time
what's going on there
that's weird can I get that can I
provoke that exception
please make exception it does not want
to I'm not sure what that exception was
I'm not sure what that exception was why
can I not make that exception happen
again
well that's unfortunate
I would like to debug that but I can't
let's briefly look at a couple of things
before we go any further
the get total science for MIPS maybe
what I would like to do here is I would
like to do a spot check so what I'm
going to do here is say once we get to
the end of this I'm going to put in a
check and say assert that if I were to
get UPS if I were to get the total size
for this particular mission I want that
to be equal to the myth dots image I'm
sorry
yes the MIT dot image data pointer that
we currently have which is the final
pointer right minus the original data
pointer and unfortunately that's not
quite gonna be right just yet and the
reason is because this thing doesn't
always happen I'm gonna make this always
happen and I think we're correct right
and so all I'm doing here is just making
sure that the size that I computed when
I said how much room will this take up
when I actually go to generate the MIPS
I want to make sure they're the same
because they're they ain't then we got a
problem
right that's and that just makes sure
we've written to the same amount of
space as we requested it's a way of
checking that math right so it looked
like the MIT was working properly I just
want to make sure that and it is all
right so we've got a weird bug happening
here because we're asking for the right
amount of size and then
using that I don't know what we're doing
wrong that's kind of confusing so in
here we're we're looking at the texture
ops I guess now I'm starting to wonder
like is there something else more subtle
that I don't understand about the way
like that I've just forgotten because we
haven't looked at this system in a while
is there something more subtle that's
going on here that's like that I'm not
appreciating when we actually go in here
and do the get total size form it's like
for this for example is there something
weird happening here right where the
bitmap width and height is it's like
different I am kind of interested why do
we get this multiple times does anyone
know what the idea is behind that
because that seems kind of busted we
already have that information up here so
it kind of seems weird to get it again
I'm gonna go ahead and get rid of that
that just doesn't really make any sense
so this works sighs here that is still
just the single mipmap size what I might
do there is say top level size and grab
that and that way down here I could just
say top size so that's the amount we
load that's just the size of the top
level of the myth the biggest level of
the pyramid which might call the pace
and then yeah everything else falls from
there now unfortunately I don't see I
don't see us doing anything Squinkie
here looks looks correct
[Music]
so what else could go wrong there
so inside to get texture off you know
we're just we don't use that width and
height anywhere that I know of you know
we're just using science requested
pretty cleanly so I feel like that
should be okay that that seems fine
right when we're pulling those texture
ops off
so when we're pulling the texture apps
off the queue which is here when we grab
one of these things
[Music]
again I really don't see what the
problem is
maybe you guys already saw it but but
but I fail to fail to see the special
special sauce here right
you can see that the texture width and
height are consistent with height width
and height are considered authoritative
there
I'll be honest I'm not sure why we use a
2d texture array through these folks
here but I guess we decided that was
just a easier way to do it and we don't
care about some of the wasted space
hmm I don't know I can't say that we
could simplify that by not re
referencing the thing we already
referenced up here nothing that saves
much space but you might as well do it
and I don't see I don't see where we're
going wrong there when we're doing the
submission seems like that should just
work and I don't know why we would be
getting over writing of the image
especially since that first submission I
mean you can see right here that it's
using it should be using the exact same
data pointers but the fact that if we
turn off down sampling that we don't
overwrite it it's just a real stumper I
don't know so let's just go over this
again I'm going to turn on optimize just
to see if we also we got that crash I
want to provoke that crash if possible
can we get that happening and optimize
build by a chance to know so in this
case we recall the down sampler we know
that all we have to do is just turn off
the down sanfran we don't get that I'm
assuming that's true even if I just went
in to the image processing and literally
just turned off just the pixel right I'm
assuming so meaning if I just get rid of
that so we're not writing the pixels
that we would still get the problem so
this still does everything except just
the pixel right yeah so this you know we
know that this thing here is writing
into some place it shouldn't write into
and I'm just at a loss because it looked
like it was writing to exactly the right
place I'm just kind of at a loss as to
how that's happening because it
shouldn't be right and so that that that
desk pixel problem is really the primary
problem that we're seeing
and again if we kind of look at here
what this myth image pointer shows I'm
gonna put in yet another assertion I'm
gonna add as many as sources as I can
here to see if I can detect where that
that boundary error is happening so
let's say that I would just do you 8
star or well here assert I've got a down
sample from source to this right I want
to assert that the source pixel pointer
plus the source width times the source
oops Times source height time store
right that's the end of that bitmap I
want to assert that the end of that
bitmap is where I start here right so
basically if I added the full size of
the source that's where I'm starting to
right next time just want to make sure
that that's true
and we still get the air right I mean
you see how weird that is right so we
know we're still writing to where we
would expect if we were completely done
with it
I don't know
all right so desperate times call for
desperate measures here so I'm gonna try
something even more ridiculous
so inside down sample 2x well actually
not I'm gonna call down sample 2x so
instead of calling down sample 2x this
is gonna put a f 0 around that so
instead what I'm going to do is I'm
going to set a different color for each
level of the mipmap so I can see what it
looks like right so instead of calling
down sample 2x I'm just gonna call like
fill image which is just gonna be some
other call that we have I'm gonna say
that I want to fill this image whatever
it is with a particular color that color
is going to be based on the level so we
have a debug color table do we not yes
and so what I want to do here is just
call get debug color with the MIT level
and that will give me back a unique
color and I'll just pack that right sir
what's our pack call yeah so I'm gonna
say give me any bit color I want to fill
the image with the MIPS going down since
we know the debug color table has a
particular order to it right we will
expect to see red at level zero which we
will not be filling so we would never
see that the first level down will be
green the next level down will be blue
and so on right I'm gonna call this fill
image this will be in our image library
here and it will just follow the same
rules as downsample so we can try to
debug these right so it's gonna take a
desk and a color right like that and
then when it's gonna do is that you're
gonna loop over the entire thing and
it's gonna fill it so it's just gonna
say alright we have a particular desk
disel here in our desk pixels we are
going to make a count and that's going
to be the width times the height and
then we're just gonna do like a wild
count - - start s pixel plus plus equals
color so we're just gonna fill that
region with the color and that's it
right we don't know what that is here
apparently
so I'm not sure where the debug color
table should live I guess now I think
about it but probably insured I think
we'd want that everywhere so now if I
run it what do I see okay so am I still
calling the function because if so that
means it's literally just this call to
down sample to X that's broken how is
that possible we are filling desk pixels
just the same here
okay I yes
don't ask me what I was thinking here so
for some reason and I have no idea what
the reason is when we ported this
routine we looped over the source width
and height but we're writing pixels for
that many so actually it's the desk
width and height
we weren't writing over our mipmap we
were writing over like the next person's
right but hey that's pretty good
I mean that was a good way to find that
bug I think so I want to say I can turn
on downsample now and we should be fine
and we are so okay so that seems all
good right now we should not be using
the mid Maps like I said they should not
be turned on so if I come over here and
I zoom yeah I still see a fair bit of
crispness there right which is what I
expect and so all we really need to do
now is see if our MIT Maps work is to
just turn them on and let's do that and
then we'll call it a day because hey we
did all the implementation work we might
as well actually turn them on okay so if
we look at our GL text parameter I here
they are so when we're creating our MIT
Maps I'm sorry are our textures here you
can see this is the frame buffer stuff
so we want the actual texture side of
things there it is
so here's our special textures we're
gonna leave mipmapping off on those
here's our regular textures and we want
those to have the text primer at Iset
saying that we'll use mipmapping so that
linear oops
linear mipmap nearest there's two
different versions we can use here
linear map map nearest is just
say pick the right mipmap for the size
the thing is on the screen and then do a
bilinear filter right there is also a
linear mipmap linear and that's what's
generally called trilinear filtering
that's saying find the lowest and
highest or sorry the next down in the
next up mipmap from where we are because
we're gonna fall in between two MIT maps
depending on where we are due by oh
you're filtering on both and then
trilinear i don't really want to do that
i'd like to try and make our renderer
and it work without that because again
it's just more texture samples but I
don't think we need because we're not
really in a situation where I think
trilinear would be required so let's see
whether we get any filtering here now I
don't actually know if we will let me
hop out to an area that's got a lot of
Criss penis in it
lovely much much much better all right
when we get out here I'm still seeing a
little crispness but that may just be
because we've got a lot of things that
are kind of overlapping and RZ fighting
is hurting us a little bit I'm not
seeing texture crispy nasai don't think
so that's much nicer now that we've got
our MIT Maps going and you know I don't
know we may have gotten some speed from
that as well it's hard to say probably
not because almost all of our time is I
think still spent if we actually look
here at the oops that's not the profile
this is the profiler if you actually
look at the amount of time spent you
know I think our lighting still Dwarfs
everything and I don't know that we're
really having a problem with them with
anything else here you can also see look
at how long render ground-cover is
taking right it's showing up now it's
not actually competing with lighting but
if lighting went away it would be
relevant and that's just because there's
just so much random computation pushing
in there right and that's the thing I
said like we can put we can actually
cache that stuff on the graphics card
and we could get rid of this entirely
right we could make that go to zero and
so that's going to be something that
we'll probably want to take a look at
our so as a performance candidate as
well that's why I have it in there
the profile okay so I think that's all
for MIT mapping I think we're now
mipmapping like happy little MIT folks
will go to a brief Q&amp;A but I think that
was really all there was so not too much
to it a bunch of just plumbing really
and then we had one little bug there
that was just you know hard to see it
was a typo but I think we're in good
shape now and those nips are are gonna
help us out they help keep that
rendering nice and stable it looks looks
better already actually all right so
let's go to a brief Q&amp;A and then we'll
call it a day
it's the mouse working or is this Linux
the mouse is not working because it's
Linux of course let me go ahead and
switch over to the other mouse which
does work of course because you know
when you plug two Mouse into a computer
on Linux one of them will work which one
is always the question
would you want to add shooters to the
asset system you you might if you were
going to have more of them
we don't have very many shaders so
there's it's hard to argue with making
some kind of special pipeline for them
but if you were gonna have hundreds of
shaders which you know a lot of games do
have depending on how they choose to go
about that process then you know you
might it really depends on your your
needs
which shares are considered special
textures and why do they not want
mipmapping so it's not necessarily that
they don't want mipmapping special
textures are these so like stuff that's
used for stuff that's used for like
cutscenes and stuff like that so like
these are these are all special textures
and the reason that they're special
textures is because they don't fit in
512 by 512 they can't be like shoehorned
into a small texture because they're big
um I wouldn't necessarily say that we
don't want mipmapping for them I just
didn't want to deal with that right now
so we may wanted her a non mipmapping
for them actually I just did it so you
know we have to think about it what I
would say is based on the way they're
used we probably don't want all the Matt
Maps for most of them so it would
probably be wasted effort if we
generated the entire MIT pyramid for
special textures so it's hard to say
what we really want to do there but
point being the important thing is it's
not that we don't want MIPS for them
it's that I only really care about MIPS
or the other stuff right now and we
haven't really thought through whether
we want MIPS for cutscenes or not right
off topic can you explain the light-blue
selection bars in for kotor oh that was
just the thing I tried adding that shows
what the region is between the mark and
the point I ended up not really liking
it so I don't actually use it anymore in
my main build but it was just an
experiment request to change the name of
nip iterator to nip diretor request
denied
through stream is difficult to notice
can we please see through an image sent
through chat difference before and after
MIT maps yes and well we may be able to
I was trying to think if we could just
add a switch easily that lets us turn
mipmapping on and off actually in place
so we we actually could just do that so
like I don't really remember how we did
this but so you see here how we've got
like mmm
this call happening we could just have a
thing that when you do the change
settings call that happens so like
where is that where was that thing
here we go so we could do something like
this where when we change the texture
settings we can put a thing in here that
like switches between two things so we
can do linear mipmap nearest or well we
could actually have it cycle between the
bunch things if we want to what we could
do is say where's those settings at so
this right where we do the settings
where's the settings stored game render
settings so in here we've got like all
this nonsense
we could have like
we could do something like this and then
whenever you change the settings we
would go in and set this accordingly so
there'd be like what is that like a glue
inch or something
and then we'd have like some if nonsense
that would crack that value and so this
thing would be like Texel filtering and
actually I guess we could do this pin
filter mac filter so what we could do
here is we could actually set these
things up where we say okay we've got
hmm a min filter and a mag filter that
we're gonna specify don't ask me why I
put max in there I think it's
magnification I don't actually know and
we'll set those based on what the
settings
it suggests so up here where we say
settings I can pull out you know
settings and you know what these usually
want to be set to zero probably so I
probably want this to be like nearest
Texel filtering and no MIT maps right I
want them to the opposite so you like by
default you clear to zero you just get
the right settings you know I mean so
right here will say nearest textile
filtering and no MIT maps are the two
things we're checking
hmm and then we'll set these things up
properly for all those all right so if
we have an filter see how we want to do
this here
all right so if we have nearest texture
filtering on or off basically what
that's going to switch between is
whether or not we're gonna grab MIT Maps
here or not so I just help do this all
right mm-hmm
maybe it's clear to write it like this
all right so what are all of our
settings so if we're in nearest textile
filtering then that means these should
all be nearest right and if we don't
want MIT Maps then there's no MIT map
selection either if we if we're in this
path so we're like near nearest textile
filtering then that's gonna be if
there's no MIT Maps
it's just nearest which is I'm sorry
it's just linear like so I and if we are
using MIT Maps then it's linear on both
right
I think I missed a case there no textile
filtering no mipmap so thirsteee
no okay sorry this is linear but no MIT
maps this is linear on both I guess we
don't have hmm in the case where we have
linear and MIT maps I didn't actually
want this so I guess we just don't have
a case for that it's just that right so
since this is our default
I think I'll phrase it this way oh and
don't ask me why I was doing the magg
filter the same because you don't
actually have to do that right the mag
filter you just know it only has one it
can't use MIT Maps right so in this case
when we know that we have the default
settings then we don't have to do
anything
so our default would be this
right so we would just say look nearest
textile filtering that means that the
magnification turns off linear blending
then we look do we have MIT maps if we
don't then it's also just nearest
filtering otherwise we're gonna pick
nearest on MIT map and off we go here if
we have no MIT maps we set the
minification to linear so we turn off
the MIT maps but we leave on linear
filtering and we don't change the Mac
filter because it's linear always right
so I think that's all we really need
there okay so then we just need some way
of actually setting those things which
we don't really have at the moment
excuse me um least I don't think we do
so here's our renderer commands settings
so we do have those going all right good
um so what I want to do there is I want
to just add that in we're we're doing
those render command settings stuff I
want to add those I want to add settings
so we can toggle these guys right so I
just want to look for where we're doing
that oops
and I just want to add these in so I'm
going to put that in there and hopefully
this will just let us you know twiddle
that and see the results
okay so hopefully now this is working I
don't actually know if it is or not
let's see if we are still getting what
we would expect to have as the correct
results so it looks like it's doing the
mipmapping properly right now and it's
also doing obviously smooth you know
it's it's it's blurring those out as its
sampling so now let's see in here if we
start playing with that so if we turn on
nearest textile filtering we should get
basically like pixel art and you can see
we sort of do right you can see right
you see a difference between the
smoothing that's happening there right
the bilinear smoothing so that is what
we would expect to see and then with no
MIT maps on we would expect to see you
like as we get out here right all of
that should get crispier see how it does
see how it gets much crispier a lot of
high frequency noise in there so that
filtering is just taking that down a
notch
is there an easy way to view the MIT
maps sent to the GPU and if so why
didn't use that feature for debugging
purposes before there is kind of you can
just use insight it's not easy I mean it
takes a little bit setup but you can use
it we've done that on screen before the
reason I didn't use that feature for
debugging purposes here is because we
knew they were messed up right we're
like okay we know we're over writing our
main texture level so why look at the
GPU it's just gonna show me that right I
mean the renderer was rendering it so
the question was who was corrupting it
there was no graphics bug the graphics
stuff was working properly it was me I
was creating the wrong MIT Maps so
switching that's the reason I didn't
switch to trying to debug GPU stuff if I
thought I was sending the GPU the
correct stuff and we were still getting
wrong results then I would have gone and
ran in sight and said let's see what it
thinks it's getting right because then
that would be something I would be
suspicious like okay what's going wrong
here but I knew right off the bat just
from that simple test at the beginning I
knew it wasn't the GPU I knew it was us
and so I just really didn't need to look
to see that
some file formats like DDS have MIT Maps
already baked in is generating them
better nowadays or does it actually
matter any longer so I guess I would say
that the premise of the question seems a
little squirrely the file format has it
baked in but somebody generated it right
and so we would have just had to
generate it when we saved out that file
so you know it doesn't really matter the
reason I'm generating them online here
is because I don't want to waste the
disk bandwidth during load time of
loading the extra data just doesn't seem
worth it because it's so fast to box
filter down on a spare core why not if
however we found that that somehow was
too expensive then you might want to try
loading it I don't know anisotropic
filtering next I don't think we actually
needed mr. traffic so I would probably
not turned on it's more expensive and so
I probably wouldn't wouldn't turn that
on No
looks like we're all set all right
every issue if we add some packing would
mipmap interfere with that yes one of
the big things that you see that's a
problem with texture packing and it's
also one of the big reasons we don't use
an atlas and we use a texture ready to
begin with is just as you start to work
with packing you have to do more you
have to be either you add a crap-ton of
padding or you have to do specific work
in your actual texture fetch you can't
use default texture fetch in order to
prevent the MIT maps from blurring
across boundaries of the things that are
packed into the texels right and so
there's a lot of subtlety there and
we're not going to go into it on
handmade here oh if we pack things we'll
pack them with significant padding but
if you want to go down that road you
have a lot of stuff you got to sort of
deal with that makes sense that makes
yeah if that makes sense
sorry Andra I don't watch you much but I
was running or those settings you toggle
can do you have a you a GUI so users can
interact or is that different yeah so
the if you're talking about this stuff
up here this is for developers only so
it's only in the developer build when
you turn developer build off for like a
release mode
none of this stuff would show up right
the reason for that is because this is
pretty much all internal stuff that a
user would not necessarily understand
and furthermore most of it is stuff that
they really shouldn't be playing with
anyway like we're gonna set textual
filtering in to the correct settings and
that's it it's not the kind of thing
like there are sometimes graphic
settings that you want users to be able
to be billed that you want users to be
able to set themselves because
enthusiasts will want to tweak their
like performance or whatever on a PC
card or something like that whether or
not using mipmapping isn't really one of
those things anymore like mipmapping is
either right or wrong in this situation
and the user doesn't need to fiddle with
that so you know this stuff probably
wouldn't be settings that a user would
ever actually wouldn't ever actually
fuss with right so that's what I would
say
alright I think that's it for now I'm
gonna go ahead and close up shop alright
[Music]
alright thank you everyone for joining
me for the episode of hand made here
it's an applaud recording with you as
always if you would like to follow along
series at home you can always pre-order
the game on hand a hero or comes with
source code so you can play around with
it and you can try your own render
settings see what you think
I'll be back here in probably next
weekend I'll have an update and schedule
yet but I will and we will be starting
to talk of lighting I think now that
we've got MIPS in there we're gonna want
to speed up our lighting get that
running fast and light our sprites with
it and I think that will give us a
pretty darn good looking engine probably
want to change some of the way we're
leaning on multi sampling I think we can
optimize some stuff in the renderer
that's just kind of wasteful right now
too
so just tighten that up get it to the
point where we're pretty happy with
looking how things go and then you know
give ourselves a big pat on the back for
making a complete game engine from
scratch every last little bit we
probably should before we give ourselves
a pat on the back replaced sine and
cosine there's only two things we didn't
read ourselves still calling see library
version I believe so we'll maybe do that
and then we can give ourselves a nice
big pat on the back all right that's it
for this weekend see folks back here
next week till then have fun programming
and I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody