hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we code a complete game
live on stream I realized something this
week while I was just kind of you know I
don't even know what I was doing
probably just sitting around and I was
randomly thinking about the raytracer
and I realized that the new system that
we were making that does the grid style
ray-tracing
is actually like way better than I
thought it was because previously I
don't know if this makes sense but like
previously I was just like well I don't
know if this is gonna be faster you know
what I mean I was like what you know it
might be it might not be but you know
it's kind of hard to say whether it will
be faster or not and I realized that
actually it's not only gonna be faster
but it's gonna be way faster and let me
show you why so I'm pretty happy I'm
like basically positive that the latest
ray tracer is the one this is the one
I'm gonna use so here's grid ray tracing
four light probes so I've never I've
literally never seen this mentioned
before and I'm guessing that's because I
just well either I forgot and it was
mentioned before or I just haven't read
enough of the papers on this or
something but this is actually so
obvious when you think about it it's
like how could you not do this once you
build a system like this so in a grid
based ray tracer if you remember what I
said was I was like well alright so the
way this would work is we bin everything
into the grid so you know if there's a
thing that you could hit and it's over
here or things that you hit if we just
put them in the various grid spaces you
know where those things exist and then
our ray tracer just does basically like
what amounts to sort of a brezin ham
like walk through this thing and we can
compute those walks because since our
ray paths are randomized ray paths are
pre computed as well we can just pre
compute those walks to and so what I was
thinking is like well the question that
I have in my head is how you know we
know that this you know thing might be
like 32
by 32 by 32 right and so in a typical
case I don't know how many grid squares
you would expect to encounter but this
number could be like relatively high
right like and if you were on one side
of the grid and you were casting towards
the other side of the grid then you know
it could be as bad as like a fully a
full diagonal walk that's not the common
case the common case is probably more
like 50 grid cells or something like
that but that's still 50 loops through
the iteration of loading leaves and it's
just a lot right and so it's like well I
don't know like that could end up
tanking it it could be that in general
it's just not faster so even though the
loop itself is probably a lot better
than the AABB tree descent loop yeah you
know but then I realized something I
realized that early termination is
totally awesome right so here's the
thing suppose you want to put a hard
bound on how long this thing can take
right and you just want to say I don't
want that case to ever occur
well we have light probes every grid
square right so if we just instead say
look this thing operates in like a 4 by
4 by 4 or like an 8 by 8 by 8 that's it
right we don't care how big the total
voxel is we only care about a subspace
of it then what we can do is do the
raycast in like a local region like
let's say like this and when this thing
goes like more than 4 squares we just
stop and we look at the light probe in
the square where we stopped and we use
the light coming back in this direction
as the answer right so basically what we
can do is we can trade light propagation
speed for computation time and make it
so that it takes maybe 2 or 3 frames for
light to propagate from all the way on
one side of the map to all the way on
the other side of the map but we can put
a hard bound on the amount of time the
recasting takes and this is not
something we could have done with the
ABM at all right
so previously we had considered this and
there's a lot of schemes that do this
sort of thing right that are similar to
this like there's a lot of schemes that
you see like with a B B's we even tried
a little bit by basically saying look
when array gets to a certain distance
just use a higher up thing in the
hierarchy in the rate hierarchy and
return whatever light that thing was
gonna be you know what I mean
but that's a very bad approximation this
is a very good approximation we're
actually taking whatever the local light
transmitted and what mittens was in that
area and pushing it back right so
actually it's quite a bit more accurate
than the way the AABB scheme was working
because at least we determined that you
could get there right and that you were
in the locus of something that was
producing light in that direction so I
feel like this is actually really good
and it doesn't cost you anything we
don't have to build a secondary scheme
like you normally would like with the a
B B's we had to build a secondary scheme
we had to actually track lights up to a
B we don't have to do that on this so I
think it's really pretty awesome and I'm
not sure why I haven't seen it mentioned
before it's basically like free
irradiance caching that you just get
because if you were building light
probes anyway why don't you just use
them I'm sure that's somewhere and if
someone wants to go find the paper that
would probably be nice to be able to
post
I'm sure there's like a euro graphics
paper from 2007 or something called like
light probes for grid rate racing or
something and I never probably saw it
but it's just worth noting so this is
like basically you get you get
irradiance caching for free if you were
already doing at a radience cash for
your render time if you use the same
data structure as your light probe
spatial index for your collision
detection you get this for free and
that's the thing that I hadn't seen
mentioned before it seems obvious so I'm
sure it is out there it's just I hadn't
thought about it
and now I have so this definitely what
we're going to do because that means we
can go we could go as low as one grid
square if we wanted to right and just
have slow light propagation but
instantaneous rate racing basically to
like reduce that time down so I really
think like it's really pretty good so
the only thing that I think is the only
thing that it doesn't do perfect is that
previously the loop had only one
termination condition and in this case
we now have two termination conditions
and you know that's not fabulous because
before the termination condition was
you've got to the end of the grid
whereas now the termination condition
has to be you got to the end of the grid
or you took too long right and what we
can do there is just like count how many
leaf iterations we've done you know or
something like that and just use that as
a termination criteria to enforce a sort
of known upper bound on the compute time
and so adding a secondary condition
there isn't the best thing in the world
to be sure but it is at least something
that we you know the amount of savings
that it would produce is pretty vast so
it's not like we're adding a check to
the loop for no real reason so I would
say that's pretty awesome like I'm
pretty excited about that because that
pretty much gets me out of the weeds on
performance by taking out but by putting
in like a dial we can just adjust so
that on faster computers we just have
faster light propagation and on slower
computers we just have slower light
propagation rather than having to like
really stress over the optimization of
this routine and like if we can't get it
fast enough then we're really dead in
the water
now it's kind of the opposite it's like
look we want to optimize this routine
because it will ensure that we get
higher quality lighting but we don't
have to worry about the optimization
from a performance standpoint because we
can really turn down the distance and
then produce a faster routine just by
having it take longer to propagate the
light so I think that's awesome
all right so that's where we wrap and I
guess like I was saying so if you look
in here so here's the the new routine
and you can see how it works we load up
a spatial grid node here and then we you
know because we've got the start index
and all that stuff right so we load up a
spatial grid node and if it looks like
it was a terminator so if it was on the
apron then we stop otherwise we keep
going and like I kind of said before
there's sort of this issue of the ideal
thing now if I could would be to just
have a single count that said how far
have I gone and that way I can just stop
at that point or something because that
would handle both cases it would handle
not walking outside of the grid and it
would also handle not it would handle
the termination for speed but the
problem is I can't really produce that
value very conveniently mm-hmm so if I
did want to switch this over to a for
loop that was just here and it looped
over some number of things the reason
that I can't just do that trivially is
the calling code doesn't know how to
produce a number from a particular grid
walk that it's got a table driven grid
grid walk it doesn't know how to produce
the correct stopping value from that
thing
and I can't honestly in my head think of
how we would do that conveniently
because since the thing you know has
like an uneven pattern it's like oh well
it will go like two and X than one and Y
then 2 and X than 1 and Z 1 and Y then
to an X than 1 and Y you know like it
has this sort of pattern as it moves to
the grid based on the direction of the
Ray that's being cast the problem that I
see there is I don't know how without
actually doing the walk I don't know how
to accurately predict which grid square
would be the last grid square for that
to go to before it leaves the actual
balance of the grid and all the things I
can think of that would produce an
accurate answer for that question so
that we could just have one count none
of them seem super compact or feasible
like I can't in my head think of any way
to really produce that number quickly
and so I feel like the apron solution is
just an easier solution to the problem
so what that means for me is like I kind
of just want a cost here right so we
want a cost metric and the cost metric
is maybe initialized to some specific
value maybe that specific value is
something like 16 I don't know but we
basically say while the cost metric is
greater than zero right so or you know I
could just say well the cost metric is
not zero
as we come through this code you know we
could look and say well every time
through this loop let's say we subtract
one from cost metric so every time that
we've tested against something we go
down so this way we can set the number
of leads to something and you know we
can just say like whatever that number
is that's the most we're going to do so
we test 8 leaves total or something
right and then we know that either we
got to the edge of the grid so there's
nothing left to look at which terminates
in this case or we got to a point where
we tested so many leaves that we just
don't feel like it's profitable to keep
going it will be too expensive so let's
just use whatever actual location we
have as as our lookup right and so if
the cost metric here if we exited on
getting to the apron we know the cost
metric is still greater than zero
whereas you know if the clock if the
cost metric equals zero then we know
that we haven't done that the problem is
that we've looked up the grid index here
and we don't actually know at that point
whether this grid index is valid or not
you know time Sam so our cost metric may
have been reduced to zero and we may
still be going right so it may be that
this is not great like it could be that
really we probably want to do that and
we just say all right so if we exited
here we know that we don't need to do a
lookup but may be here we would just say
if cost metric you know has decremented
to zero then we you know do a compute
boxful irradiance at kind of a thing and
we need here to just say get us the
voxel irradiance coming back in this
direction
you know what I mean
so I think this is all we really need
and once we have done that I think we
also probably don't need to do this so
this routine gets a little more
complicated because I think
well yeah so I think what happens here
is kind of confusing you know I hadn't
really thought about this yet but this
routine is actually not as good as it
should be even already because I
realized this loop should stop if you
hit anything because you don't you know
that all of your you know that all of
the things that are further on in the
grid are later collisions the tea is
strictly increasing the entire time so
actually this part should probably
feature a way to break out of the grid
as well meaning there are two
termination conditions here and only one
of them does this right so I think it's
actually you know it looks more like
this which is to say that when you do a
test of the T values so when we when we
have this here we would just need to
know like are any of these valid in the
first place right and if they are then
we can stop so we probably want to do a
mask move at that point just for our own
for our own like testing purposes like
hit you know something hit and in here
we would just do if something hit then
we do our post amble so we like you know
finish figuring out what the Ray is and
we break and so I feel like it actually
kind of looks more like this we're
inside here we do have that
unpredictable branch that's just the
termination branch because it's probably
way more expensive to keep marching
rather than stopping when we first hit
something so I think maybe that's a
little bit closer to what we need and
the something hit here is really just a
mask
move out it's you know one of these
where we just take and the the mask that
we got here this is just telling us if
we got a hit at all and when we extract
that mask we can just or it in to the
mask we've got and then on termination
if anybody if any ray ever hit then
that's you know that's our termination
so the only thing that that this doesn't
do correctly is there is like one side
case there and I don't really know I
don't really know how we would want to
fix this or if we would want to fix this
but oh wait no we don't have to fix it
nevermind I take it back so the thing
that I was gonna say is if you imagined
inserting these boxes without clipping
them meaning you didn't shrink them to
the size of the grid square then you
would have to worry about potentially
registering a hit of a but I got a draw
this I can't there you're never gonna
understand what it without a diagram
sorry let me just draw it for you let's
suppose we have our grid and we have a
box that spans multiple grid squares
then we have a raycast that originates
from one of our cells for the light
probe and the pattern that it goes is
maybe actually fairly like oblique to
the Ray to the to this right and let me
see if I can draw a really good example
here so you know let's suppose it's
going like this
through the system and let's suppose
there's a tiny box here right and a very
large box here if we didn't clip the AAA
B's that we insert to the grid squares
then when you enter this grid square
this box which is large is obviously
registered as being part of this cell
when we do our collision detection we
will find that we hit it and it's over
here if we then stop because we early
terminate and say well we know that
anything we hit in this grid cell is
closer than this grid cell by definition
because we entered it first then we will
never find this collision because we
never looked in this grid square but it
was in fact closer so all I wanted to
say was as long as we clip which we will
because there's no reason not to it's a
a B B's clipping is just calling min and
Max real quick before you push the thing
in as long as we clip we will still be
accurate because this box will not
register a hit with the Ray so we'd be
fine
that's all make sense hopefully so I
will add so that we don't forget I think
that's a good thing to do anyway but
just so we don't forget when we do build
the spatial partition for the lighting I
just want to make sure that we remember
that so I'm going to put a big ol to do
in here
so hopefully that makes some sense why
am I talking so quiet um I've been
having a lot of allergies lately just
for like several months really and it's
just like it aggravates my throat so
I've been trying like talking more
quietly just to like I don't think it
really helps though it's just it I don't
know allergies are bad I wish I didn't
have them alright let's do this um so
anyway when we're doing our move mask
yeah so we just want to make sure that
we get back whether or not any of these
things hit and so this T valid and less
than T ray is all we really need for
that we've you know we basically got it
T valid would also do it you know either
one really would be fine but anyway so
what's the problem move mask right it's
just move mess P so that's totally fine
so now we really what we have mostly is
this issue here and I believe we kind of
have to partition this routine a little
bit differently there's no reason for a
sample P here I mean we could do it and
maybe we will for now but like in the
future that's not really necessary at
all right because we already know which
grid square we're in the grid this grid
index value here is all we really need
and so we don't need to do any of this
part of that we do need to do the sample
normal part but of course we already
know that because it's just the negative
of the raid erection you know what I
mean so that part's pretty
straightforward as well so
I think what we want here is to
partition this out and so instead of
compute voxel irradiance at being
something that by default takes a P
we'll probably do like compute voxel
irradiance at in a way that can also
take a grid index so if we were going to
do it that way what we would want is
this same code like so what is outgoing
mean here outgoing
so I'm not sure what the outgoing part
of that is it looks like that's some
kind of whoo-whoo what are we passing to
this so we're passing emission direction
so I I feel like since we haven't done
the lighting quality pass there I guess
like yeah I guess I'm not sure what to
make of this so the way that we're doing
this currently is we're just looking at
how much light was coming from the
normal direction which I don't think is
right I mean there may might be a reason
why you would do that but I mean I don't
think so like you would really want to
be using this value right
or more specifically the negative of
that value because if you assume that
this thing is lit by the light probes
irradiance which is the approximation
that you use when you have light probes
you assume something in the cell of a
light probe is getting lit by the light
that that light probe is captured that's
the point of the light probe we would
want a sample the light coming from the
direction that you would bounce off of
you know
because this is even though this is a
diffuse surface it's still you know
going to be reflecting the light via the
reflectance function so I'm not sure
that sampling the normal is necessarily
the most logical thing to do in that
circumstance so that seems a little bit
busted I'm also not entirely certain why
you would ever need to pass the normal
at all because you know what you bounced
off of and so you don't really need that
at all so this this kind of feels a
little bit dumb and probably not really
what you want I'm going to leave that
for now I'm gonna put put it to do in
here that just says this should probably
actually use outgoing instead but we
need to do a lighting quality pass after
the optimization phase in order to
really nail this stuff down so I think
what I'd like to do here is let's just
ignore that for a moment and say I'm
gonna put the part of this that actually
does the sampling
into a separate routine you can call
with different parameters so effectively
here what we could say is the voxel
index parameters that we produce and the
UVW values that we produce these are and
in fact I could actually just make it be
I could make it actually be that blend
as well hmm let me think about this
so the thing that I'm not sure about is
like how do we want to actually
terminate the Ray and if we do that Pat
what's the T value that we've gotten so
far because we could also blend these
together so you know what I guess you
know what I'm gonna take that back I'm
gonna say maybe we can just use this and
we just need to be a little bit more
careful about this so let's just say
that maybe what we do is we actually
call the complete version that actually
does the blend and what we do here is we
compute what we think the sample point
should be based on how far we would have
come so far you know what I mean
so what we could do is we could take the
Ray origin in the Ray direction
we could just move forward by a T value
which could be baked into the tables so
we would say early termination sample P
start where the Ray origin is and go
however far we need to go and so there's
like a t terminate here and the t
terminate is just like we've gone you
know this far in the Ray and then we
would sample the voxel at that point so
that would take the the solution the
diffuse Atlas the sample P sample oops
sample and now going so in here right
the the early termination sample P is
the location and then the two normal
values in this case would be the raid
erection right in both cases
so that's like where we want to sample
the light coming from and again we have
to change that compute voxel irradiance
at to actually be like more logical
about how the lights getting sampled so
we'll see now since we know that on exit
here we are producing what is
effectively a compute voxel irradiance
sample anyway because we know here that
we were going to do that it's also
entirely plausible to me that we could
try to make these both kind of happen
together so that we don't have two calls
to that function it's a little bit
obtuse as to how I would do that because
if you look at how this works you know
we kind of have some stuff that's done
wide and stuff that's not done wide and
so I think for the final version of this
routine when we try to streamline it one
more pass at the end I think what we
might want to do is try to collapse
these two so you know I'd put it to do
in here
it's like oops to do this keyboard is
hopelessly off-center today my desk is a
mess this is my own this is only for
streaming this desk and it gets kind of
gunked-up so I want to collapse compute
voxel irradiance at calls into one so
for now I'm fine with calling it twice
but I think that's something that could
be collapsed and what we could
effectively do here is have this code
all just be shared so in other words
this stuff would all just happen exactly
the same way as it was happening before
and because we know basically all of the
ways that we break out of the loop are
going to do this the only one that isn't
is this one but this one actually still
sort of is because we could at that
point use effectively like a skybox or
whatever as the thing we were sampling
so you could imagine like just to give
maybe a little bit better of a just just
to sort of eliminate this a little bit
and maybe I can even just do it right
now
if we were to do something more like
this
where we have these situations where we
break out of the loop
in fact this doesn't need to happen
anymore to it looks like because we now
have tested just using the yeah so we
now know because of the mask move here
we actually now know that we hit so we
don't need to do this part either let me
look at what tier a single is actually
doing is it doing anything yeah it
doesn't so we can actually eliminate
this branch entirely because we've
already done it which is nice it means
that at least we're not introducing
another one in there so here you can say
alright we do the something hit we if we
did we can early terminate if the cost
metric was a problem
will terminate for that as well and then
will fall out here and will fall out
into a way that's going to use a couple
things that we have that we need to
propagate outwards so if we look at what
those are there's like probe sample P
single probe sample n single like
emission direction and we want to grab
those we want to basically produce those
in each of our cases so in the case of
probe sample n single right this is what
we've got at the moment it's a probe
sample p single same thing and so now
these two could be pulled out of this
loop as exit parameters right so when ya
when this gets pulled out and similarly
like we could say for the transfer
people yes here like I said I think we
want this welded in so we want that
transfer PPS to actually get sampled
always and we can make we'll make the
adjustments that make that happen
properly in a second here so we know
that we need to produce these two and we
will just assign to them now in these
two cases and then let them fall out of
the routine properly so that's good and
then so in this case here and rather
than creating a new value we would just
say probe sample P single equals that
termination place we haven't quite
figured out how we're going to get that
value yet but it's probably is going to
come from the table
and then in terms of the probe sampling
in the emission direction which is the
other one we need here that's going to
be negative ready single as well we're
always sampling that back bounce so
that's you know in in either of these
two cases right we're going to be doing
something like this I think it's just
whether it's the positive or the
negative because either we didn't
actually hit something to bounce in
which case we need to take the positive
R a direction or we did hit something to
bounce case we need the negative R a
direction or I just think I said those
backwards but you get the idea so we'll
make sure we set those properly as well
but I think that's mostly what we need
there that's ready single I think these
are actually both because we we want to
know well no I guess I guess that's not
true so these are both pointing in
directions but I think this goes away
because I don't think we want to be
using I don't think we want to be
passing the normal to that routine
anymore when we do a sample we just want
a sample right so I think compute Fox
the radiance that just wants to give it
the direction to sample and then you
know you assume that the person who
calls compute Foxley radiance like
already did that you know already did
that work for you okay so I think our
for our loop is good now that all looks
that it looks right
so we do the leaf test we go there we
before yeah so I think that all looks
good to me I think that's all good so if
we take a look at what's going on here
the problem that we're getting here is
that we don't have the shuffle value
that we actually need to pull to extract
or other values like our hit ref color
these sorts of things and all of these
computations you can kind of see they're
operating on the four-wide version so
when we when we initialize that you know
you can you can just kind of see what we
need here so when we produce this hit
ref color here this actually probably
wants to be pure white because we
wouldn't reduce the transmittance in the
other case so this is actually going to
be like v3 4x 1 1 1 1 right we're just
going to assume that we don't reduce the
emission in that case so in at that
point all we need to do is make sure
that the shuffler itself is its own
thing that gets persisted and we need it
to default to loading something that
will not something that won't just be
bogus for this case since everything
will be the same in the case where we
exit early we can just assume that any
of these are ok so the 0 on the shuffle
table is fine I guess I need to do that
though so really anything here it
doesn't matter which one we pick we'll
be fine
because any of the lanes are ok at that
point you don't need to take a specific
one of them so we'll just pick 0
I think at that point the really the
only thing we don't know is the T
terminate and I think that pretty much
has to come from the lookup value here I
could be wrong about that yeah I could I
could be wrong about that I don't know
so this load where we update grid index
right which actually can happen at the
very end of the loop it doesn't have to
happen anywhere in particular oh this is
a little bit off that's supposed to be
in here that's supposed to be there then
we do that right yeah so this doesn't
really need to be an else I mean that's
a break statement so we could simplify
the indentation here a little bit too by
just doing that because we know that
like well if you break you're not going
to go any further
so I think that's what this should look
like and I guess the thing that I was
talking about before is the walk table
could give us that T value that we
needed so the walk table could pack
those two things together so for example
the walk table could be something more
like alright there's a grid index so we
basically say like what's the Delta on
the grid index so this is like the D
grid and then we can also say that the T
terminate value is the T terminate right
so I could pull those two things out and
that's relatively straightforward I'm
just not sure that's the best answer
because it does make those tables a lot
bigger it makes them a lot bigger
because they have to now pack a 32-bit
value in in addition to what was just
previously a u16 value and that's
probably not great I mean
yeah so if we were to do that it's it's
a little bit it's not it's not fabulous
you know what I mean it requires us
doing this you know so I'm not sure that
that's great it means that the walk
table entries are actually quite a bit
larger there are three times larger than
they were before which means that the
caching on them is three times worse and
I don't know that that's particularly
fabulous now you might not matter but
it's definitely worse it's for a huge
benefit
meaning we really want this so if that's
the most efficient way to do it it still
is a massive win probably but the reason
that I bring it up is just because there
may be a smarter way to do this meaning
there may be some way that instead of
doing that we could do something else
where we we just automatically propagate
the t-value somehow like by the way we
step or something we can just keep track
of it for free or something like this so
I just I don't know but I just want to
make sure that we're aware that that's
you know possibly not the fabulous
sister things okay so let's take a look
at the walk table now here's how we're
getting the walk table so what I really
want here is for the light sampling
walked able to just instead be walk
table entries and we know that that's
you know pretty straightforward there's
not really anything fancy we'd have to
do there so where we go to light
sampling walk table
I assume that's probably in the INL file
and it is so that's going to be a walk
table entry and so that's probably not
gonna go in here that's going to be
something that's generated by our
subsystem so it's gonna look more like
that right okay so I think that's
everything and so the question here is
it's just yeah is there anything else we
really want to do before we go through
the work of actually producing the
tables for this system which is going to
be pretty much the majority of the work
we're gonna have to do and it doesn't I
mean it looks to me like everything's
fine what I really need to do is just
validate the performance of the routine
and then start pulling out all this crap
because there's so much cruft in here
now that doesn't really need to be there
if this does turn out to be as good as I
think it will be then we can just
vaporize like half the code in this file
because it's all for stuff that we don't
do anymore so looking at the cost
metrics here that stuff looks right I
think that's a pretty sane way to do it
so we can just adjust this cost metric
as necessary and you know you could make
it to 55 if you just wanted to basically
raycast everything always and you could
make it as low as you know one or two if
you wanted the worst possible thing the
only thing it doesn't account for right
now is loading out the spatial grid
nodes themselves which is some cost so
we may want the cost metric to also take
that into account but I mean who knows
right so I'm not sure if we want that
like what we could do is is have there
be a cost metric I mean we could make
this a little bit more expressive right
you could say something like this where
you said okay there's a cost metric
maybe it's sixteen or something like
that and what we do here is every time
we process a leaf we consider that to be
a cost metric
a significant cost metric and then we
also have you know a just a constant
decrement so maybe the cost metric here
basically says hey like you know there's
some decrement through here that we do
every time and this will be free because
you know there's so much there's so much
wide like this is all SSE there's almost
no scalar so you know this can just
happen I mean it could happen like you
know right here and be basically free it
will just snuggle in with the SSE ops
and be free so we can just do that and
then down here we just have a constant
cost so every time to the loop it also
goes down so this way we can basically
say you know every one of these is a
cost and we could make this more
expensive too you could say like - do
you know what is the actual cost here
relative to the base loop so you know I
don't know what this value should be
maybe it's four times as expensive to do
it maybe it's twice as expensive maybe
it's no more expensive I don't know but
you know something like that we would
use to adjust the cost that we're paying
and so we know we could do like 16 grid
squares that have nothing in them or
eight grid squares that have one set of
colliders four grid squares that have
two sets that sort of thing
so I think that's fine so I think we're
okay
so we process all of the leaves we look
to see if we hit anything in there and
we have to process all the leaves we
can't just stop as soon as we find a hit
because inside one cell we're not sorted
in any way so we need to check them all
to find the closest one I think that all
works well we output a probe single and
an emission direction in both cases so
like right you can see those all
happening here pretty cleanly shuffler
gets loaded in here it doesn't get
loaded in the other case because we
don't care it can just be the default
value and then we fall through now again
we probably don't want this exactly so
what we want to do here is probably
having we want a location to probe that
would give us in the case where we don't
hit anything we would want there to be
like I mean I guess I don't know what we
want to do with like moonlight and stuff
it may be that we just want to put
moonlight tiles I mean I think that
maybe just a better idea because I feel
like moonlight tiles are better than
what the previous solution we had was
and so I think what we would want to do
is actually hit those things and produce
the correct durations for those things
like the emission for what we hit would
be something that could be presented you
know and we could have ways of having
directional emission that come from
you know things we hit like when we load
this stuff up
we could have ways of doing directional
emission that way and I'm just not sure
exactly how we want to fold that into
the routine so I think what I'm going to
do is say that I don't really care about
that
so transfer PPS here is always going to
get set and we're gonna work on how we
actually do ambient lighting me or I
should say sky lighting we'll look at
that a little bit separately because I
don't think we have a really solid idea
for that at the moment and I'd like to
do something different than what we're
doing now because we already needed to
figure out a solution for how we were
going to prevent moon light from
affecting areas that don't have ceilings
but that are supposed to be underground
do we just put a ceiling all over them
you know what happens there and I think
I don't like that solution because it
just means we're adding a bunch of extra
geometry we have to deal with for no
reason I think what I would rather do is
for the above-ground regions is add the
geometry there because we're actually
adding geometry that says hey there's
light here that you need to pay
attention to and that geometry seems
more sensible because it's non occluding
geometry and so it doesn't have to have
a special renderer thing to know how to
deal with it if we put ceilings over
everything we kind of have this nasty
problem of having to be able to see
through those ceilings and so they have
to be placed properly and you know you
get the idea
so we'll deal with that a little bit
later and for now I think this is
correct so I think what we mostly have
to focus on now is generating the tables
and the spatial partition let's go ahead
and try to do the spatial partition
first and then we'll try to do the walk
table second I don't know what the
status is of this exactly at the moment
I assume this should just crash right
because we haven't produced like we
haven't produced any of this stuff and
so it should be looking up into no-man's
land in both cases right so if I run
this I should get a well let me run it
under remedy so if I run the lighting
profiler right now it should just die
yeah
I guess I'm not sure why it died there
let me recompile in debug mode cuz it
doesn't seem quite right may just be a
miss reporting though
so I'm not sure here what's going on
with that it looks like this is because
we've that's okay so that's plausible I
guess because it looks like I changed
that up right
so the HH Lite props limit you know yes
you can see the sampling these here have
not actually been initialized although
why did it Dutch and when did I actually
change that over I know I don't really
remember doing that to be completely
honest with you
so sample directions here in this case
is what who passed that in
like who who actually passed that full
cast past that okay so yeah you can see
what happened here it was this stuff
right so yeah that's totally fine all
right so I have to go ahead now and
actually build all these tables that
guy's saying and let's actually start so
the first thing that we're going to need
to do is in end lighting computation so
in end lighting computation I'm gonna
need to actually implement the facial
partition build although it looks like
we put that in begin now we didn't like
that doesn't belong so here's the grid
build then you can see that we sort of
did a little bit of it so let's go ahead
and uncomment it and actually try to
make a real version of it so the first
thing you can see here is it goes
through and it just tries to figure out
like where these boxes exist in the
voxel and we have a get voxel index for
P sort of thing don't we I thought we
had something like this but I guess it's
rolled into compute voxel irradiance but
I mean this is it right so this is the
thing that does that computation so if
we wanted to have a v3u that was get I
guess it's technically a v3s in this
case because it could actually be out of
bounds I don't know to what extent we
exactly want to handle that but because
these should never really be out of
bounds in that case but what we can talk
about that later so in this case if I
have a V 3s and I say get voxel index
for P I want to do exactly this and I
assumed that it would be safe probably
to make this be a thing that happens
here
as well but I'm not going to do that
because since this has kind of a
slightly different thing it needs to you
VW's as well I'm just not gonna put that
part in there so I'm gonna have getfox
will index for P here take the v3
whatever the P is and the lighting
solution and produce that that value so
it's going to do exactly the same thing
it's then going to produce the voxel
index value that we expect and it's
going to come back here so when we call
this and we get it back this is all
totally fine and dandy what it's doing
here
and then we need to do some actual work
to chain these things together and what
this is doing is this is trying to
basically figure out how many leaves go
in each node right so what I need is a
temporary storage solution I need
something that will temporarily store
the data that we're actually talking
about
so I basically need scratch space for
that and I know how much scratch space I
need to do the chaining because I know
that it's the number of boxes that we
actually have so if we take a look at
the lighting box structure itself in
here what I can do is I can start to
play around with this stuff because we
know that like for example we don't use
these things anymore they're just not
part of our system anymore so instead of
using like these childness ooh that sort
of stuff we can just use this for our
chaining so what I'll do is I'll just
say okay for every one of our grid nodes
temporarily what I'll do is inside the
whatever the the actual structure here
is in enlighting so so for this right
what I'll do temporarily is I'll make
the start index here I'll make that be
the thing that tells us what the first
element in the grid is and then what
I'll do is chain using that that
temporary value in the lighting box
and again a lot of this stuff is way
like really kind of ugly right now and
the reason for that is we're trying to
overlay multiple systems on top of each
other at the same time to test to see
which one we're gonna go with as soon as
we actually definitively make the call
like okay it's grids then what we're
gonna do is we're kind of gonna rip out
all of that stuff right and then just do
a pass to clean up everything to make it
look nice and simple and remove any of
the other things that we don't need
because there's so many things we don't
need like even these split box things
like all that just goes away because
once we're gridded we don't use that
anymore so effectively like getting rid
of all of these spatial hierarchy stuff
all of that stuff that's a pass we have
to do but I just don't want to do it yet
because we kind of want to finish this
part of the testing first before
officially ripping all that stuff out
okay so if we push forward a little bit
further here what we know here is when
we want to do this chaining operation
what we want to do is we do want to pull
out the node and that's going to be this
and in order to pull out that node we
need to have some way of getting a grid
index from so we've got spatial grid
nodes we want to do something that
allows us to get a node from an XYZ
value so we want to do like something
like lighting or sorry solution spatial
grid nodes and we want to add like you
know spatial grid node index from here
and we know how to produce that because
we know what these voxel dimensions are
so that should be right fairly
straightforward but it does require you
to know what those what those are and
there's a couple of things here that are
a little bit Squinkie specifically like
well you know what it doesn't matter
we'll talk about that when we actually
build the loc tables the point being we
know that we want something that does
this and in order to build that index
there we need something that's going to
actually didn't we do this yet nevermind
it's already roots right here this is
what it is it's just that right and so
as long as we know what the voxel index
actually is then we don't really have to
worry because this that yet like this
will produce that value from the voxel
dimension anytime we actually want that
so let's see here if I if I go didn't we
have a thing that we sort of sketched
out the thing that built the walk list
here's compute walk table for example
didn't that also do this I guess it
didn't really I guess it did it sort of
inline which is cool all right so anyway
assuming that we get the grid index here
off we go and there is sort of a little
bit of a of a difficult thing here that
we have to consider how we want to
approach and that is that we would like
to have an apron for this scenario we'd
like to have the outside of the grid
have stuff in it that tells us that
we've gone too far so grid index from is
like really not it's it's hard because
we sort of have two types of grid index
which it's really bad an error prone to
have that I often find myself making
mistakes where if I have to indexing
schemes I accidentally use the wrong one
because when especially when you're
writing efficiency oriented code you
tend to have to drop things down into
like very specific you know even sim D
operations and you can't afford to use
types and type checking to help you
there a lot of times because compilers
are just really bad if this sort of
thing it's unfortunate and so the
problem that you end up having is that
like in this scenario I need two types
of grid index I need one that has an
apron and one that doesn't and we have
to be careful to use the correct one in
the correct circumstance what would be
best is if we could just have only one
way of indexing but I don't know that
that's really theoretically possible in
the case that we have here because we
need to have our lighting atlases be as
debt compact as possible we certainly
don't want to bloat them with extra data
that we don't need and so it's kind of
unfortunate so if I could have gotten
away without an apron in the grid
raycast I absolutely would I just can't
figure out a way to do that like you
know the the most the most optimal way
would be to get rid of that and have
some other way of doing like I said but
I just don't know how to produce a walk
value that's always guaranteed to hit
the end without doing a fair amount of
computation beforehand or just really
bloating the table size by having like a
secondary set of tables that you look up
into to figure out how far you could go
based on a particular array in a
particular location it's just not great
okay so I'm gonna have two of these for
now and maybe with an eye towards if we
can ever remove them that would be great
but you know if we can't we can so in
this case well I guess I could say you
know we just have to pass the correct
voxel dim is the other way to look at it
so in the voxel dimension here we have
we should have stored in here some kind
of a v3 I guess we even kind of know
when we come in here where's the voxel
dim values they should be in here
somewhere
like that just the voxel count right but
oddly enough I don't see that in here
anywhere so I don't really know where
that is at the moment but effectively
what we need to do here is when we have
this grid index from right we want to
pass the voxel dim in here and so I need
something that's like voxel dim with
apron and we need that to be something
that we use to get these grid indices so
we need it to look like that and I guess
we'll figure out where we want these
stored and how a little bit later maybe
we'll actually what we could do is just
put it in here and say hey you know what
why don't you tell us what that is and
we don't only care where you get it just
get it so then we'll go through here and
we will produce the the voxels here the
getfox will index 4p should be fine
either way because we don't really care
what the offset is of these so in this
case when we do the grid index from we
could just increment this value by
something to account for the apron right
in other words if we want we can just do
this so this computation is always can
always be done the same way we don't
have to worry I'm sorry this computation
can always be done the same way we don't
have to worry about the apron when we're
doing that because the voxel always
occupies exactly the same
vol there's just a question of whether
there's like an outside ring of invalid
voxels that are there to stop the Ray
caster from going too far that's really
all we're talking about here you know
I'm saying so yeah that's all that's all
there is so in this case if we go ahead
and load up one of these nodes then what
we want to do is chain whatever box
we're talking about on to that node so
that we know that that box has to be
processed in that node oh you know what
this is not as easy as I was making out
to be so since boxes can occur we may
need scratch space for the boxes as well
I thought we were going to be able to
get away without it but since boxes can
occur in multiple nodes I guess there's
really no way quite to do that yeah
that doesn't seem plausible because as
we go through here right we're gonna put
this box on multiple potentially
multiple grid squares and that just I
can't think of really any way to do that
properly there doesn't seem to really be
away so we will need scratch base for
this as well like we'll need some way of
building a chain here that that gets
larger
I'm not thinking of anything bright for
that so I think we may just have to use
temporary memory here I don't see what
else we're going to do so when we come
through that to the end lighting I feel
like we probably need to get temporary
memory temporary stack memory here and
in order to do that I just probably want
to take a look at where where is the
frame data because we previously had a
thing where we would just have extra
data for a particular frame right and
it's a little scatter shot in handmade
hero because you know we don't really
get much time to actually clean things
up so there's a lot of times when things
are a little bit more scatter than they
would be especially because I can only
you know I have such a limited amount of
time I can I can really spend on it on
streem it it doesn't really get the kind
of polish that you know I would normally
get to do so I'm not really sure we ever
quite got the per frame arena like it's
not really used in the way that you
would normally use it you know it
doesn't really get much use because we
added it but we never really did much
with it and you can see here that you
know there it is and a lot of people who
probably should be using the frame arena
like aren't using the frame arena
because it got added pretty late and
then we didn't do a sweep through to
like consolidate a lot of problems could
be solved with that but what I'll do
here is I'll just you know we'll start
using it in here because I know that we
do want it here so what we'll do is
we'll just say all right here's our per
frame arena
that we're going to use and we know that
this is a temporary thing we don't need
it after we do our scratch operations we
you know we don't we don't need to do it
none of the things that we do here will
persist so what we can do is we can use
the frame arena we can generate as much
garbage as we want right and I mean
effectively what these are is like free
garbage collection right we can do
whatever we want
doesn't matter how complicated and then
we get to the end it just all gets
cleaned up for us so at that point we
can just afford to say look when we're
building these lighting super structures
I don't really care how expensive it
becomes to do because you'll be able to
use this arena to allocate as much
temporary space as you want effectively
and it will all just get vaporized
immediately after the lighting values
are computed and output right so I'm
gonna go ahead and do it that way and
that way we can do it without worrying
too much about yeah how do we fit it
into the scratch space and having to do
like multiple loops over things or
things like this so let's do it
what I'm gonna do here is say we're
gonna introduce I guess a secondary
structure for this that's only used
during build I'm not sure that's the
that's completely necessary but I'm not
sure I see owlets to do it where we just
have lighting you know temporary box and
all this is is like a really crappy
simple buffer that's all it is it
doesn't do anything else and all this is
is saying you know here's a way to do a
direct iteration over all of the boxes
that exist in the grid so that we know
where they go well wait
but we could also just do this twice
yeah you know what we could also just do
it twice and not bother let's try that
and see how expensive it is so suppose
you just did this right and instead of
ever doing any training at all you just
said hey like let's just record how many
things we actually needed to put in here
in the first place so like for each one
of these we just counted so we let start
index right be like the count so you
know we clear it first we do something
like this and we say okay clear all
these take the start index and use it as
a temporary counter when we're done
counting assign all of the these in
series so we just go to each of these
and say we've got a total leaf count
here we go through and we say for any
particular node the start index is the
total leaf count and the one passed last
leaf index is the total leaf count plus
the start index obviously have to do
those in the opposite order I suppose I
could do it the other way round meaning
this might be a little bit cleaner
because then it reads a little bit more
straightforward
does it not you know seems it seems more
right you could even do this
so we effectively go through we count
once and that's so that we can lay
everything out in a tightly packed array
and when we're done doing all of that we
can then just do the exact same loop
again so we just do this a second time
we don't need to do any of this right
any of these chain nonsense here and so
instead what we then do is we just say
okay like all of this stuff that we were
gonna do to insert things we just insert
them right and off we go so I think
that's okay we just need to get the
allocation stuff to work properly and
it's you know it's a little bit
squirrely but you know we'll work it out
so yeah as these things get inserted we
need to figure out like how properly to
insert them and it is a little bit ugly
because we need to kind of write them
out in a packed format and that may be
kind of slightly tricky but yeah we'll
see what happens there I'm not sure
again I don't know to what extent zeros
will be acceptable as things that can't
be hit I don't know if zero zero zero as
the Box minun box max will produce an
unhittable box or a hittable box that if
you hit it directly at zero zero zero so
you you pass perfectly through the
origin if that will actually get hit
I think I would prefer to not have to do
this initialization I would rather be
able to do a clear 2-0 so I think I
might change that to just more of it to
do oops
so I may say let's change that to more
of it to do at the moment but we'll kind
of come back to that later okay so in
here where we do we loop through our box
indices we figure out where these things
are going to go we take our total leaf
count we counted up we take our box
indices again we go through them a
second time and now we try to actually
pack them in to where they go again one
problem that we're going to have here is
actually looking at this these need to
be padded out to fours and so we want
this to actually be like totally fount
plus 3 mod 3 right like or and 3 I
should say so sorry and not 3 so we want
to take and say look we want this to be
padded to 4 and I don't know if we have
an aligned for that we do so we could
say to make this a little easier to read
we could just say this or better yet
could say this and this should have been
parenthesized and wasn't which is kind
of bad I'm not sure why we did that but
that could have leaked operators all
over the place and we could have had bad
results so that should be fixed and
wasn't oh well but point being if we
come through here and say all right so
the total leaf count here will now be
properly padded to fours then when we
come through and we look at the
the indices we now can use those
properly the other way we could do this
is to use this divided by four you know
nothing about that might be better no
probably not
we probably what we want to do is just
divide by four at the end that would be
my assumption I think that's probably
right
okay so now we have the ability to push
using and we can use the frame marina
for this we can we now need a place to
store all these leaves right although I
guess maybe we don't like again this is
why I say like these could all be
allocated just on the frame so I suppose
yeah like eventually we should just
allocate these on the frame and you know
use the frame marina for it seems like
the right thing to do rather than
leaving them sitting around because they
don't really need to sit around but you
know so I don't know I might say push
array here and we just push on the total
leaf count because we know this is how
many Leafs we need so we just say all
right push on the total leaf count we
know that we're using the temporary
nough in this case and we know that what
we need to push on are these spatial
grid leaves right yeah trying to think
of like what when I want to wrap this up
I might I might go a little longer today
just to finish this up but I want to
take a quick break first yeah I think I
might take a quick break and then we may
I might want to try and finish this
routine even if we go a little bit long
so so hold on one second
[Music]
[Applause]
all right I got some some bunny fruit
snacks here that should do the trick for
energy I think there's a bug and grit
index from there might be let's say you
look all right that will surely be
enough sugar what's the bug in grid
index room
it looks like it's missing a Z actually
and that's that's weird not sure where
we got that from because the equation
should be it should look like this right
it should be like X is an offset that's
just used by itself voxel dim x times
the y-coordinate is how cuz it's y goes
by x slices is how far the y us it is
and then voxel dim x times voxel dim
why should multiply Z and it looks like
it looks like that's kind of busted yeah
cuz that I don't know why I don't know
how that ended up being that way but
that yeah not good so yeah that's what
we should have for sure thanks for that
because via vxj dim Z is not necessary
that's just a bounds at that point all
right so what do we want to do here
moving forward so this is actually just
the p-value doesn't matter sample P so
let's get back to what we were doing so
here yeah we want to allocate when we
run through the box indices we want to
allocate the total number that we
counted that we needed which we know
will be this so we do that and then for
each time we run through here we want to
do this again I don't know what this is
complaining about oh I guess we don't
have a v3 you but that's so that's fine
we'll just use v3 s we don't really care
we don't need it to be a unsigned for
this particular purpose it's not
necessary
does not take get box index 4p takes a
solution which makes sense there we go
okay so these have to be s 32 s just for
compliant compiler warning nonsense that
shouldn't actually exist but it's fine
and we will produce I guess we you know
what we could do so since we have since
we have knowledge of what the farthest
out value would be we could just produce
that values so for example if we do this
and we say what's the max grid index
well we know that the max grid index in
this case would have to be the total
voxel dimension with apron right I think
because that fox will dim with apron if
we ask it for this dimension and we
passed the highest value that should
give us back the highest index right so
I think that's sufficient I don't think
we need really anything else
so grid index from is voxel dim XYZ yeah
so this is just X Y Z and that's it okay
these both were passing that value so
you know let's make this actually take a
v3 s because why not
so this way we can just pass the triple
as a triple and leave it at that okay
problem solved
okay so now let's see here we've got our
total leaf count obviously this needs to
kind of be au 16 in this case and you
know I guess now that I'm thinking about
it too like if we wanted to we could
expand this to not be that we could use
larger storage and maybe we should
depends on whether we think we want more
than 65,000 of these we probably don't
but who knows I mean maybe we could just
handle that we'll see I'm gonna leave
them as you sixteens for now but in the
future we could consider doing them
differently all right so in this case we
need to make sure that we never overflow
this value and so in this particular
case we would need to say let's make
sure that this this thing doesn't you
know let's assert total leaf count here
or assert that well you know what well
summit is a 32 and we'll just assert
that we can safe truncate right so this
way we'll get an assertion if we ever
hit that limit which I think we want
because we kind of need to make sure
that that doesn't happen now there is
another thing we could do here and maybe
we possibly should not to think about it
it's probably the right thing to do we
know that the leaf count is never gonna
be particularly high you know like a
leaf kind of toy 56 would mean that a
single grid square had 10,000 24 axis
line counting boxes in it which is
absurd
so the thing we could do is pack 24 8
work 20 you know 2014 could basically
pack into a single 32-bit value and that
would allow us to scale better so I
might also say here as a separate pass
we could do I put to do in here that's
basically says look pack this
as a 32-bit value that's a you know
24-bit offset with a you know 8-bit
count this would scale to much larger
scenes more easily because it's entirely
possible that through the entire grid
maybe someday someone wants to run this
engine with more than 6 5 5 3 6 possible
occluders in it the chances that they're
all on one Square very low so it seems
like what we should do is pack this
value to assume that the offset needs a
lot more range than the count right it's
just kind of a basic like bit packing if
you're gonna pack a 16 16 that implies
the two values that you're packing need
to be same fidelity but in this case we
don't really need to do it that way so
we should probably allocate more bits to
the thing that we need more of and less
bits the thing we need less of so taking
a look at the grid here once we've got
that produced I think we're okay
this is the wrong value now why we did
that way let's do that so okay so once
we do our push array
it looks like the count probably comes
first if it was me that's the way I
would have done it yep
and so now we just need to actually do
the part that packs these things
together so when we do get voxel index
for P here we already did that right
like so and so now what we should be
mostly doing here is just figuring out
how the actual packing pax packs down
into the each node this is the v3 yes
yeah okay
so when we go in to pack these now what
we sort of need to do is we need to
figure out again like how we want these
things to be recorded and the problem
that we're going to have is we don't
have like a temporary value anywhere
sitting around that would let us do this
conveniently so if we if we take a look
at what we need something like the one
passed last index here where we actually
write this down we may actually want to
not quite do that yet so what we may
want to do is something like this where
we say okay one past last index just
gets initialized to zero it's going to
be used here as a way of figuring out
where to fill in these values and then
at the end we'll just sweep through and
divide it by four right or put it more
specifically put it into a different
category right like put it in you know
just just let's see here so right like
here when we're done with everything we
sweep through those grids where's one
more time and reset this value to be you
know what it should be and again for
that one so we sort of need to do a
little bit of work here
we can't just we can't quite just divide
it by four right
we need these values to we need these
values to be divided by four in a way
that actually works for us logically so
we need to take the start index and
divide that by four but then we need the
one pass last index to be what would it
would be if we added it because we know
it's account we added three then divided
it by four right because we know that we
need to take the start index and divide
by four you know you can also think of
this as a shift down by two right
because basically what we're doing is
we're just taking the high part of it we
know that this thing was already aligned
and and again you know I'm just gonna
make it be a divided by four here
because I think it's a little easy to
read and the compiler will automatically
turn it into a shift I was certain so we
shouldn't have to worry
so what we're doing here is we're just
sing all right there's a start index we
take one pass last indexes account we
add it up we round up because we need to
make sure we grab out that last packet
of leaves and then we divide by four
that resets everything that we needed to
reset so I think all of this is now
correct this will just flow properly and
so we're really just talking about the
packing that has to happen here and an
already order in order to do that I
think all we need to do is use the leaf
index which is given to us directly so
we should be able to basically say okay
the leaf index is just whatever the
start index was plus the one passed last
index and that's going to get
incremented because we're adding one new
one in here and so I think that's it
right that just that just does it and
really we we could just make these
you know I I don't really know exactly
how we and had intended these to kind of
come out if we take a look at the
lighting the this spatial grid leaf bit
here right actually it occurs to me too
that this total leaf count is just you
know whatever the value is divided by
four right so
yeah I mean I can't say I can't think of
anything I can't think of anything
Squinkie err here but so if we divide
the leaf count by four we know that each
one of these packs for in there we're
gonna pull one of these out and in order
to pull one of these out we need to
first like I don't know why these are
the way that they are doesn't look right
at all like this just looks I don't I
don't even know how we quite wrote this
code I'm not sure exactly what we were
thinking when we push this in it just
looks a little busted so first of all we
don't need this anymore obviously but
but what we need to do here is we need
to say okay we have a particular node we
now need to take and figure out for the
solution spatial grid leaves which are
packed by fours we need to figure out
what the primary index is but that
primary index is really that's going to
give us back which one of these leaves
were in and so this part here where
we're doing the leaf index divided by
four that's really what's going on there
and and that's coming from this anyway
so we really can just we can just do
this right and that's what gives us the
leaf in this case for the lane index the
lane index is just the mod four of the
well actually you know what I take it
back that's that's not true I jumped
again a little bit there we do actually
still need the leaf index because we can
move to a different leaf right so the
leaf index we have to do the node start
index plus the node one past last index
that gives us where we're at right now
as a count and then we can produce these
two but that that's what we actually
needed so then if we take the primary
index here and we go to the leaf spatial
grid leaves we then have the correct
leaf to look up into but we don't
actually know which one of these we're
doing right so what we want to do there
is again just use the secondary index
for that so the lane index is what
actually need this stuff is not really
necessary right that already happened
when we pulled out the leaf so this was
kind of unnecessary but this Lane index
part that part we actually need so if we
just turn these into access ORS off of
the leaf we should be fine
and then in terms of these these are
things we actually have to compute so
what we really want to do is we do want
those temp variables but they're going
to be specifically for doing this
computation okay so that's what we
actually need to do so when we load up
the box which is what's happening there
right so it's it's this box right here
that's where we're actually gonna pull
those values from so the ref see in this
case is just going to be whatever the
ref C is of the box and similarly like
the the emission value here is going to
come from whatever the box is pack was
but the box men in the box max are not
so the box men and the Box max what we
need to do with those is we need to clip
them to this grid square I'm out of
lemonade well lemon water lemons and
water so if we have the box men in the
box max enter into this routine what we
need here is we need to have we need to
have some idea of where the bounds are
of this grid cell so effectively in here
where we've got this right we need some
way of producing the clipping volume
that Clips this box to that volume and
so where we do the like center the the
get center P for the grid square I don't
know get Fox's Center yeah that so where
we have the get voxel Center P
and we pass in the index that's
effectively what we want because that
will give us the min/max pounds what I
could do here is say there's there's a
couple different ways we could mm-hmm
so this brings up another interesting
question I guess it doesn't matter now
but if we take a look at what happens
here we could also say like oh okay so
this is how we produce the center let's
just produce the corners that way too so
let's put this let's roll this in here
let's just say here's a rectangle three
get voxels cell bound bounds something
like that so if you pass in a particular
index then the result that comes off of
this right has a min and a max value and
where's our tango three yeah min and Max
value and so in both cases you're going
to start with the the min corner hot and
in both cases we're going to do the
Hadamard product of the voxel seldom
with the index but in one case we're
just going to add one additional in each
direction so we would basically just say
you know whatever the v3 index is you
know add 1 1 1 to it and that gives us 1
further right so I think that's all we
really need for the voxel cell bounds
and so then when we come into the
lighting routine and we're building the
spatial partition we can just call this
function now and it will give us exactly
what we need to clip to so in here I can
just say hey whatever this like grid
square is that we just looked up so this
right here and we don't need to do that
offset because we're this is that's only
for the grid index so I can literally
just do my B 3 s X Y Z
right so if I just do get voxels cell
bounds here oops
solution I can get the cell bounds and
then I can clip these so these are the
box bounds and I can just clip them now
so I think we actually have an
intersection for this probably do me
looks like we don't I'll be enough
so you can see here right we've got the
Union but we don't have the intersection
which is kind of weird right I guess we
just never wrote it you can see here
that we wrote we wrote it for the
rectangle to eye but we didn't write it
for the we didn't write it for the
rectangle three and it's the same but
this is why you want metaprogramming
just case anyone was wondering because
it's just does all this for you without
all the garbage of templates and stupid
stuff that you don't actually want that
cause problems in C++ so if you're John
Blow and you made your own language then
you're very happy if you're not and you
have to use the C++ committees garbage
you're unhappy but you know what do you
do so the intersection in the union of
boxes is just two different ways of
using the comparison in the union case
you take the lesser of the two things
for the minimum and the greater of the
two things for the maximum so you expand
the size to take the furthest in each
direction and intersecting two
rectangles is just the opposite
operation you compare the two and then
you take whichever one was the least in
that you know along that axis so you
take the maximum value for the minimum
and the minimum value for the maximum
and so the other way around so here for
example if a is less then we actually
take B right whereas in this case if a
is less we take a and then the inverse
is true for the maximum values right so
you know not rocket science but that's
the idea so here we can just use
intersect and so we can say like leaf
box equals intersect and then we can
just say you know leaf box leaf box
you know leaf box and this way we have
clipped each of our insertions into our
spatial partition to that spatial
partition so we know that we wouldn't be
producing any intersections outside of
the spatial partition ever so we're
never actually going to be in a
situation where we collide against
something within um one node of the
vegetation and produce an intersection
outside of that node and again that's
really powerful because it means we can
early out so it's one of the things that
we can afford to do with the grid really
easily because we know that the greatest
partitioned such that we are pre
sweeping through it anyway so it's
pretty free for us to just you know flip
those things to the sides of the grid
and go from there I'm gonna go ahead and
make a box bounce here I guess and I'm
going to get rid of this because you
donor secured it and I'm gonna say clip
the cell bounds the box bounds together
to produce that and when we actually
pull the box out here I'm going to grab
it now I don't know what the scratch a
box index box index crap was that was
probably old news there because we don't
need that to be happening anymore
scratch isn't used all of that stuff
will go away when we because we don't
need it anymore for the grid so when we
come through here and we do our push
array all of this looks fine and so the
box bounds here is just making your
rectangle out of this thing right so box
box man and box box max we should
probably have just put a rectangle 3 in
there to begin with we didn't but
something elsea we can fix later oops
it's just a recommend
nothing nothing fancy all right so this
is the rectangle three that we're
actually going to use which is the one
that's been clipped so that it's
basically the intersection of those two
the actual thing we're testing against
and the spatial partition that know that
we're inserting it into looks like all
of that codes flowing properly right now
through the compiler emission is not on
there and so I don't actually know what
we did for that looks like it's easy
emission it's the only difference there
yeah that seems fine this needs to take
the temporary no and it looks like this
doesn't have the temporary nough so what
we probably want to do there is to
actually get that temporary net now you
think about this for a second so I think
we actually also don't need to allocate
the other like we don't need to allocate
those nodes either so there's a bunch of
things that I can do now which I
probably just should because one of the
things that you have to remember is like
all of this stuff so like these scratch
arrays like all this stuff this can all
go away now and like all these box
tables everything so we'll just be left
with these two and really those things
don't persist anyway those are things
that are only necessary across one frame
so what we can do there is we can
actually you know even debug lines like
all this stuff is really not necessary
to keep in here so with that per frame
arena the other thing we can do is sort
of change up a little bit away a little
bit about how the lighting stuff is
actually working and we can really
streamline this down so I know it seems
really ugly right now but it's important
to remember that you really don't want
to spend a lot of time cleaning up code
for no real benefit so when you're
actually prototyping and trying to do
speed testing on things you do need to
make sure that the codes clean enough
that you don't have problems with it
that are causing your measurements to be
wrong because you you know the codes so
messy that there's all these errors in
it
so you do need to keep a little bit of
of a watch on that but it's really
important to not spend time making code
clean and streamlined when you're not
actually sure if you're gonna use it
right so it's always a little bit
balancing act and on handmade hero like
we typically keep the code pretty messy
and that's intentional because until
you're actually sure how everything
works
any time you spend cleaning it up is
usually wasted because what you're doing
is you're making the code harder to work
with by specializing it towards a
particular end and that specialization
then has to get undone later right so
the lighting system is definitely coming
to the point where we could start to
streamline it but until we cross that
that final hurdle you really don't want
to be making those decisions so let's go
ahead and properly pass the temporary
nough through here so in additional
lighting cue here I'm gonna pass a
temporary nough for the internal
lighting core and then anyone who is
calling that I'm gonna make sure calls
what's a bit spatial partition for
lighting it also has to have the Vox
will dim with apron now the Fox will dim
with apron I guess the thing that I'm a
little confused about is the voxel
dimension is is just something that is
kind of there and I guess the reason
that we don't really know what that is
is because the atlases themselves have
those voxel DIMMs kind of baked in and I
guess we don't really know like when we
move those around look we haven't really
thought about yeah look what goes on
there so I get I guess to do this
properly what we want to do is say look
the voxel dim with apron in this case is
going to come from the spec list spec
atlases voxel dimension and
all we're really doing there is adding
to we're adding you know one extra pad
on all the sides so I think that's
really it that we would need to do there
and I think that's it
so the end temporary memory I don't
remember exactly how we did this in
handmade here especially okay so it's
just a temp mem so basically we have a
temp mem that gets set by whenever we
began the temporary sweep and then it
gets reset at the end so it just looks
like that I think that's about it in the
test raycast for here I guess I'm not
sure what we are still doing with this
particular routine so I guess this is
just the stub that we use for testing so
that makes sense I just is that I
thought we called internal now does
anyone call test raycast
nobody does so this is not a thing so
that just kind of goes away right so
here we call internal letting cor we
need to pass a temporary nough here so
we need some way of giving this thing
something and if if we take a look at
what a memory arena has in it there's
some issues so the platform memory block
bit of things here is a little bit of an
issue again because we don't have that
structure in the test code but the nice
part is we can just make it so that the
platform memory block that we give it is
so huge it will never have to allocate
anything and then we don't really have
that problem so I think what we can do
here is say that there's a temporary nap
and then the temporary no dot current
block can just be something that we
actually passed at some large allocation
so platform memory block like this we
can just stuff
with values that that are sufficient for
our needs I think that should work and
so in here where we do these allocations
and I believe in here we do malloc these
right yeah so when we do a profile run
with a repeat count thing when we do
these Malick's here and we set up like
the arena's to work with this stuff and
we don't really care about how much
memory we throw away here it's not super
relevant to us we just need to make sure
that our temp block has enough space so
the flags on the temp block don't really
matter because no one's going to look at
them but the size the base and they used
all do it's really just the size in the
base because they used being 0 is what
we would want so the size of this is
just however much we think we need so
you know 16 megabytes or something I
mean how much is this really going to
use it's not it's not actually using a
particularly large amount of memory so I
can make the base address just be
something that Mallett gives us that has
that much room and then that should be
sufficient for the memory arena to
function that's my assumption anyway so
if we pass the temporary nough into the
internal lighting core I don't quite
remember the order of passing here so
the debug repeat count comes last
so that should do it and I think that's
all we need so I think that's everything
for building the spatial partition and
it should just work as long as we do a
step through it and debug any of the
obvious bugs like it shouldn't be
particularly hard because again it's
just gritting up those boxes and I
suspect that the only real problems that
we may run into are like indexing
because like I said because it has that
apron problem oh and that's something we
also will need to do is the I should
probably just do that now I'm thinking
of it we will need some way of making it
so that there's the apron around
our is set specially so when we go
through here
and we look at these nodes we need to
set us certain ones to to be marked as
apron so I guess what I would say is
like in here what I do is you know we
set this up as we normally would and
then we'd have an if and the if would be
based on the grid ray caster how it's
doing that check so you can see here it
looks to see whether the nodes start
index is a spatial grid Terminator and
if it is then it doesn't proceed so what
we need to do here is we need to do a
check and say well is this particular
grid index on the edge or isn't it right
and I'm not sure what the best way to do
that is it might actually just be I mean
it might actually just be too clear to
that right you could just do this and
then the the start indexes of all of
those are all spatial grid terminators
all around then these as we go through
here these get sort of set up properly
as long as they weren't set to that or
as long as they have a well because this
wouldn't know the difference between
those two though so that doesn't really
help yeah so no I guess that doesn't
help so I guess you kind of just need to
actually do one loop that is actually
proper along the voxel to set this I
don't know how else you would do it
yeah I'm not sure so I guess you just
need to do something like this maybe
I'll just do it in line I don't yeah I
don't know that's that's a tough one so
if I were to do a full sweep of the
voxel so you know something like this
and here we go and say well alright
we're going to go through each of these
in order
so each of those things and we groups
know why that happened and we can now
just test against those I guess oops
that's alright so in here we could say
if we loop over the voxel and we grab
out the grid index from voxel dim with
apron X Y Z it's not a particularly
efficient loop but after we grab out the
node we can do an if and check to see
which one of these two we want to do and
we can just say spatial grid node
Terminator and furthermore I suppose we
can decouple these you know it can do
that assignment and then it can just do
a conditional assignment here because we
don't actually care about not we don't
care what this value ends up being in
that case and so what I might do is just
say okay take the start index sign it to
the one pass class and assign it and
then possibly overwrite this if we
happen to be like if Z equals zero you
know or y equals 0 or x equals 0 or Z
equals Fox with in with apron Z minus 1
or
or and that will properly terminate the
apron so that we know we're not getting
that we're not going to have any
raycasting that goes outside of that and
hey as convenient the stream ended right
as I finished that routine so I feel
like that will properly spatially grid
up our stuff modulo cleaning up for bugs
and so that leaves us with one more
thing to do tomorrow before we can start
actually cleaning this up and going like
doing speed testing and debugging and
all those good things which is to build
those tables because we don't have those
tables built and we did we did sketch
out the thing that builds the table so
you know we did do that and like I said
I don't really remember where we
actually put it but we did build that
and so we should be able to then take
that code and make it actually work and
then we can have all of our tables that
we need there's one thing we'll have to
add to it because my recollection is
that we didn't weren't keeping well know
maybe we were so we may actually have
already been keeping T throughout the
whole thing too now I think about that
that may actually be yeah it is so
here's compute walk table and yeah it
looks like it accepts a new teach times
that correct so it's like setting up the
location so the take takes the dimension
step and it sets that up and then each
time through it starts T best at F 30 to
max and then it looks through each one
to see which one it will go to first
so we more or less are tracking the T
through because we know the app value so
I mean I think all we would really have
to do is just take the dot product along
the Ray of the at value and then you're
pretty much done so like I think that
just solves a problem right so for
example here if we you know every time
we do a termination so we come through
here and we want to know where the t
terminate was for a particular for a
particular walk so I guess it's actually
it would actually be here right so if
you want to know what the t terminate is
for any particular walk you would just
take whatever the @ value is I believe
of this one and not the previous one I
guess I think it's this one so the T
terminate value is just whatever the @
value is it would just be the inner
product right of the raid erection and
that add value minus whatever the
starting location is because that's just
gonna measure how far along the Ray
you've went so the T terminate value is
just known so we can output it directly
when we build the table so it's pretty
easy the question is do we really want
to store it but it's easy enough to
store so we could build this table
pretty trivially this looks like the
correct actual call seems fine and yeah
I mean so I guess like we've pretty much
already done the work so tomorrow it's
just gonna be a case of like actually
cleaning it up all right so let's see
what happens let's go ahead and go to
the QA
someone said I might have had a typo on
that last one they clean that up while
people are yeah you're right
this should be an X
I agree that that was a very good
question that insa bot created
I already talked about the Yui 5 demo
during the pre stream but I did not
actually watch the demo yet
can you watch the tail alive I can if I
stop the recording YouTube is really bad
about copyright claims like you can't
like when I go to update upload this
like they will like copyright claim your
whole video because someone you know you
watch a five minute clip of someone else
with music in like a three hour video
that like literally no one would ever
think isn't fair use but you know it's
an issue so I can stop the recording now
and we could go watch the demo which is
fine I don't see any questions so if
people want to if they do have questions
they could save them tomorrow I could go
watch it but let me stop the recording
because I don't really want to have that
be Oh what was the original
justification for switching to probe
based gie so the reason for that was
that the I couldn't really figure out so
let me start with let me say two things
about it so the first thing is that we
had no solution like we needed to solve
for the lighting in general we needed to
have a solution that would light sprites
right cuz because we have lots of
sprites and they need to get get lit as
well and we hadn't really quite figured
out how you're gonna do that and the
reason that I hadn't used light probes
in the first place because we basically
did do a light probe system even
originally it just was point based light
samples around the geometry the reason
that I hadn't done a light probe in the
first place is for some reason I had
like this mental block of not figuring
out how I could do the initial
propagation with the light probes
because I was like well how do you
figure out what they're actually lit by
and I was like for some reason never put
it together in my head that duh when you
do your light propagation you just
sampled the light probes for your light
propagation it's kind of fairly obvious
right I don't know we just sometimes you
have mental blocks on things programming
is very complicated
and graphics 3d graphics is very
complicated and sometimes you just like
aren't thinking clearly about some
things so even though the thing is not
particularly difficult it's just because
there's so much complexity involved all
around the thing you just miss this you
know what would otherwise be fairly
straightforward so I think like my
feeling on light probes is they're
probably what we should have done from
the beginning but we didn't do them
because I didn't quite know how to solve
a particular problem with them that
really isn't a problem and so once we
figured that out it was fine right so
that's all really I would say about that
and the nice part about light probes is
now we can let our sprites with them
because we can just in the pixel shader
we already do in the pixel shader we can
just look up what the light probes are
near neighboring to our sprite and just
light them and and off we go
so it's very nice and it solves all of
our problems for us the grid based ray
casting I think is awesome now I hadn't
considered the fact that I can terminate
Ray's anywhere I want and then just fill
in a value there with the light probe
I've literally never seen anyone say
that I don't know why maybe because it's
so obvious that it doesn't need to get
said but it seems like a really really
big strength of grid based of not just
grid based ray casting because I've done
grid based ray casters before in fact
granny has a grid based ray caster in it
it's how it does normal map transfers
from high-res to little air res models
with a grid based ray tracer so I'm
actually very well-versed in grid based
rate racers I just never wrote one for
actual lighting that was using a light
probe system that happened to be aligned
to the spatial grid if you actually have
light probes aligned to the same grid
that you're using for calling it becomes
really pretty and I guess you know it
doesn't even really have to be aligned I
think about it but just in some way that
you can get a light probe answer
anywhere in space it's pretty compelling
because you can always choose to
terminate early I don't know why I've
never seen anyone say that probably
again because it's so obvious you don't
need to say it but you probably should
say it because I don't know I didn't
think of it right off the bat
for whatever reason
Oh Mattia manzanas question did I
remember correctly that our lighting
partitions aren't fixed in world size
but are fixed in number among XYZ does
that mean we eventually we can't have
the ideal situation where the lighting
voxel is aligned with world blocks and
light voxel sizes multiplier sub divider
of the game grid size that most of the
lighting occluded voxels are not
partially filled but mostly filled so
actually it's a little bit different
than that we haven't specified a rid
rigid policy on this yet but we do have
something in place for it right now just
for correctness the real reason that
we're doing what we're doing is because
when you subsample lighting like we do
you have an issue that anything you
might do that changes the basis of that
subsampled version could be seen as an
animating artifact so for example let's
suppose that we between every other
frames switched between twice as dense a
voxel grid and half as dense a voxel
grid right oscillating you would see
that animated error very clearly as the
lighting just changed every other frame
and it would be like kind of flashing
and weird because it's subsampled so
it's not a correct solution everywhere
it's an approximate solution and when
you change the ground underneath that
approximated solution like that it will
produce objectionable artifacts over
time any given still frame will still
look just fine but when you you know see
you'll see that change so what actually
happens in the system currently to
prevent anything like that from
occurring even though we move the
lighting bounds around a lot to like fit
them over the space you're seeing all we
require is that you always align
yourself to a grid that is the voxel
size grid right so it doesn't really
matter how they line up with world
chunks in any particular way they just
have to always line up with those chunks
in a consistent way
so as we slide the lighting volume
around it just always has to line up
properly with the same basic lie
grid in world space so that if we move
it it moves exactly one whole voxel
square over so that the lighting is
always the same and doesn't slide right
so that's all we're doing is we're
keeping ourselves aligned to the voxel
grid no matter how we move around space
that's the only thing we're doing there
and we have to do that or you would see
an animation error could you put moon
blocks in the apron so you always hit
something instead of using a special
index unfortunately not and the reason
for that is because the the problem that
we have and you know it's not a problem
it's more just like something we need to
decide how we want it to look and how we
want the processing to work it's not
like a problem in the like bug sense or
how are we gonna fix this you know it's
it's pretty straightforward but the
problem that we have in this case is
that we don't actually want moonlight to
light anything underground so when you
go down the stairs
we don't want moonlight lighting those
rooms unless the moonlight could have
gotten in through like the ceiling like
like the stairwell right and so the
problem is not that we couldn't put
moonlight or like ambient light tiles in
certain places in order to make that be
the termination condition the problem is
most of the time that's not actually
what we want right I guess I'm not sure
how else to say that so so basically the
problem that we're trying to solve here
is more that we need to control where
the moonlight actually is because we
don't want you to be able to hit
moonlight
from underground things and I don't
think we want to have to put ceilings on
them right so what I'd rather do is just
put moonlight emitters maybe on the the
outdoor rooms so that they hit those
emitters in our process that way I think
that's probably the way I'd rather do it
but
can you move the play button on the page
a bit down because on first glance the
horizontal line of L lets it look like
it has a partial drop shadow no I can't
many a minute Manzano says oh so
essentially every letting Vox sodium is
consistent across frames yes
the lighting voxel Jim is consistent
across frames even if the camera zooms
in or out that's correct
I thought that Fox with Jim was
calculated by taking world region to
render size divided by max number of
links no I don't think it is I mean I
could be wrong about that because again
I only work on the Sun weekends and I
have a lot of other code that I need to
worry about but I'm pretty sure that's
not the case
what's my best shot at getting a
standalone C++ compiler bundled with my
engine probably clang would be my guess
C compiler it's one of the nice things
about C is it's a very straightforward
language and the compiler can be written
fairly cleanly C++ is a giant disaster
if you actually require a C++ the full
language I mean it's it's absolutely
horrible and I mean the problem is with
C++ 99% of the language features in C++
are not good
so you basically pay a tremendously huge
cost and have a very complex compiler
and you get nothing for it right so I
guess what I would say is like yeah it's
C++ is terrible for very very many
reasons and among all of those reasons a
very large one is it's prohibitively
expensive to build your own compiler for
it in a reasonable amount of time right
like it's it's one of those things where
you know like if you told me that I need
to write a C compiler by next weekend
I'm like ok I can probably do that if
you tell me that I have to write a C++
compiler by next weekend I'd just say
it's not possible like we have to use
like we have to use someone else's code
because there's no way we're gonna make
that work you know the spec alone just
even reading it to understand all the
things that you don't probably know
about see bus Plus that you need to
handle is prohibitive I mean it's just
it's impossible so I would say like you
know first of all are you really sure
you want to do that and then second of
all if you are sure that you want to do
that for some reason I would strongly
recommend using someone else's code on
hand meet here we don't use other
people's code because the point of the
show is to show how to code things from
scratch that's the whole point but that
doesn't mean that that is the right
choice in all circumstances and if ever
there was a circumstance where it's
probably not the right choice to roll
your own it's C++ compiler because what
a waste of your time holy cow do you
think cost is useful for function
arguments No
I don't think Constans useful period I
think for other programmers sometimes
it's useful for programmers who make
mistakes about what they can and can't
write to I pretty much never make those
mistakes as you can see I think we've
talked about this many times so if you
look at the kinds of bugs that I have
often they're often indexing bugs and
indexing bugs aren't caught by Const
right if you're the kind of programmer
who oftentimes find yourself writing to
the destination and not the source or
the source and not the destination if
you spend a lot of time finding bugs
like that
that's where cons can help you right so
but I think through the entire handmade
hero which is the worst case because
it's like I have the least mental
resource come try to explain the whole
time I think we've had one case of
writing to a thing that what cost would
have caught it just like pretty early on
so it's just like what a waste of time
it would have been right to catch one
bug that didn't even take us hardly any
time to find right we would have spent
all that time typing Const all over the
place for literally no reason
what do we call look on handmade hero we
it's just CL it's just you're just CL
but CL is like microsoft property you
you can't distribute it with your game
right clang has some kind of a GPL
license or something I don't I don't
know exactly what the license is for
clang
I mean I don't go look at what the
licenses but the point is clang is
licensed in a way that allows you to
include it in commercial products right
and Cl isn't so the reason I said clang
when you asked what would I do if I
wanted to be able to include a C
compiler when I shipped the game is like
clang has a license that you could
comply with but in C L is not so you
know and there's nothing particularly
wrong with clang clangs a good compiler
it sometimes produces better code than
then Microsoft sometimes microsoft
produces better code than clang but so
you know there's no real reason to use
one of the other you you can you can use
either so if one of the things that
you're targeting to try and do is to
ship the compiler with your game then
you know clangs the obvious choice it's
you know it's totally reasonable
compiler it's you know 50/50 as to
whether you'd rather have it or or
Microsoft's and so it's no difference
just use clanging
all right so I will go ahead and do as I
said after I close this down I will
watch the unreal thing so I'm going to
do the stop recording here