the show ladies and gentlemen
hello and welcome to another episode of
handmade hero the show we code a
complete game live on Twitch no engines
no library it's just us and and our
cunning to the extent that we do have it
on certain days admittedly you know some
days are better than others you know not
everyone is cutting all the time
sometimes you're only half cunning or
1/4 cunning heaven help you on the days
when you're negative cunning but you
know it happens to everyone sometimes
and I'm sure it's happened to us already
in fact I'm pretty sure it has happened
to us already and it'll happen to see
future but maybe we can avoid having
today be one of those days because I
thought of something last night when I
was going to bed I thought of something
about what we have been doing that I
think is an improvement and so I wanted
to talk about it today it was kind of an
obvious thing I had not thought about it
in this way before but I am thinking
about it this way now and so yeah I'd
kind of like to to go over it with you
and see what you think before I get
started however let's go ahead and say
that anyone who has pre-ordered the game
on hand may hear or should have gotten a
link in their email - down to the source
code so if you want to use that source
code to follow along
today is day 78 so what you want to do
is unzip day 77 source code out of the
zip file and that will allow you to
follow along with exactly exactly the
same source code I'm starting with today
so let's get started here is the thing
that I thought of yesterday that I
probably should have thought of but
sometimes it's better if I don't think
of these things I mean one of the nice
things about the fact that the stream is
periodic and I'm not thinking about it
all day I only think about it you know
at night or whatever is that I don't
come up with things perhaps as quickly
and that allows you to see me do
something less good and then move it
towards something better we've already
seen that happen with a bunch of stuff
like the sim Regents I think with that
and that the tile chunks are the world
chunks and so on like we've we've
constantly had that kind of happen and
some of those were intentional likes
sometimes I intentionally start out with
something simple rather than guessing at
the final sort of good thing and trying
to go directly to it
towards it because I want to show it but
other times I'm legitimately just going
well I need to do this now let's try
something and then later I kind of
figure out oh that would be better to do
and so this one is something that I
guess I kind of should've known but
honestly I just did not even really
think about it at the time and so I'm
going to think about it now so what we
were talking about yesterday is we were
talking about having this notion of a
ground point right and so if I imagine
an entity is an occupying space in some
way right like so and we were talking
about you know having these sort of
bounding boxes and that sort of stuff
and we did we did collision detection on
them and we've got all that working and
it's good and they're 3d and all that
and so it's kind of nice because it
means we can support more stuff in our
game like smoothly going up and down
stairwells and maybe fading things in
and out and having kind of nice level
transitions or looking at things below
you there's all kinds of stuff that we
might want to do in the game that so
it's kind of good to support that and it
was just good programming exercise
against this is an educational stream
it's a good program exercise to just
handle the 3d relatively well instead of
totally choosing it always and so I'm
glad we did that stuff what we got to is
we got to a point where we were saying
well if we have bounding boxes and we
want to treat them kind of as as sort of
symmetric things where we're saying okay
there's a point that's the center of the
bounding box and then we have dimensions
out in the direction of the corners of
the bounding box right so we basically
have radii you know that kind of do this
sort of thing so we have like an X
radius of Y oops that's a Z Z radius and
a Y radius you know and then we've got
the point this little at the center when
somebody is standing on the ground we
were we realize well we've got to have
this notion that down here is actually
the point that actually needs to be on
the ground because making the point
where the players location was that the
bounding box was centered around B the
point that we track on the ground will
make this bounding box sink into the
ground because it means that the ground
level will be there as he moves along it
right and that's no good right that's
not what we want so we introduced this
point on ground concept and then we had
everything follow that now someone
pointed out
actually in the post stream Q&amp;A they
asked well you know since we're doing
all that computation with that ground
point couldn't we do something where we
have where we kind of refactor things so
we're always using that point instead so
we don't have to constant at the ground
point and so on and I was like well we
sort of thought about doing that and the
problem with that is we want these
bounding boxes to be handled
symmetrically like we don't want to have
it so that just Z is handled differently
and so we could have done something like
always had the minimum corner and that
would have meant that that was the point
but then that doesn't really makes sense
because typically when we're thinking if
we're you have to stop when you're
walking we typically think of that being
roughly where your legs are not all the
way out at the outside of that bounding
box and so on so we typically are
thinking about the center a little bit
more for most of the things that we do
there's just a lot of reasons why that
would also be kind of janky and so you
know there's some janky nough stair
right there's a janky miss problem but
what I realized is I was kind of missing
what's sort of an obvious solution to
this problem and that is something that
we do in 3d all the time and for some
reason I just wasn't thinking along
these lines so it's not the first thing
I thought to do and that is basically
that you know the position right is is
not the same thing you know as your
collision right we call this a collision
mesh oftentimes in 3d
basically your position is some logical
notion of where you are that the AI uses
and the game uses for things that it
wants to do and blah blah blah but
that's not the same thing as collision
at all and in 3d games what we typically
will do is you know we might have some
notion of where an entity is you know in
space we might say you know here's where
an entity is but actually the collision
volume for that thing is like a whole
human and it's like meshes that are like
you know the torso and then there's a
mesh for you know the legs and all these
sorts of things and arms and blah blah
blah each one of these is its own rigid
body that might be used for physics and
it has a collision volume associated
with it and all this extra stuff
so what we do is we essentially store a
list along with that position right in
part of the entity we store a list of
all of those pieces right we sort of say
oh okay well yeah he's got a position
but then he's got an arm right and the
arm is at some offset and it's got some
dimensions and it has some collision
master or whatever and then we've got
another arm and a head and whatever and
so what I think probably we should have
done and what I think I'd like to do
today is say okay we have an Indy
position and that any position is going
to be on the ground so we can get to
that thing that the person was asking
about in the the post room yesterday
that they would have liked and that I
would have liked to but that we didn't
really think we could do cleanly which
is we just think about the position of
the guy as not a thing to hover above
the ground
it's right on the ground then it moves
along the ground we do have that and
that's the position of the enemy but
then the entity also has a set of offset
bounding boxes as many as they want
right which are those collision message
so it could have two right or or three
or more right it can have as many of
these pieces as we want it to have right
and so that way when we're doing a
collision detection when we go through
the the dude we do the politican
actually on these pieces by iterating
over the pieces that are inside of the
guy one at a time and doing collision
section on them and then the combined
result of that collision detection is
what we decide to move the guy by right
so essentially that's you know a really
easy way to get around this problem that
also adds features to our engine it
allows us to have multiple collision
regions so that if we have people who
are not like let's say we want to have
everything broken down into convex
shapes which I said was pretty much the
only way to reliably do collision
detection most of the time if we want to
break things into convex shapes you know
and we have a guy who kind of looks you
know roughly like this or something
top-down we can just add three different
collision volumes to him and that'll
just work right we don't have to do
anything special about that
so that actually adds features to our
engine as well as solving our ground
point problem and so that to me seems
like a pretty
telling way to to get the best of both
worlds to both get the thing that we
kind of thought we couldn't get but
wanted and also add some nice features
so that to me again
seems like seems like the right way to
go so let's take a look at that I think
it would be a good idea for us to take a
look at that all right
so let's go ahead and open up Emacs and
so if I go in here to handmade sim
region and take a look I believe my
entities are still in here we should
probably at some point takes a bold step
of moving the entities out into the
entity file but yeah you know not really
a big deal
so if we take a look at this same entity
we've got sort of these fundamental
motion things here and then we have this
this dimension and so what I'd like to
do is I'd like to go ahead and make an
actual you know make it so that you can
actually have this dimension thing be
offset and so what I'll do first is
since we don't have any need for
multiple collision volumes at the moment
I'll just do one collision volume and
then when we kind of go in the future
and decide how we want to deal with
stuff maybe a little bit later we'll
just have everything you know sort of
set up so that it can handle the
multiple ones if we want to if that
makes sense so I'm gonna go ahead and
say for now we'll just say struct sim
entity collision volume and I guess
there's a little bit of a question here
too one of the things that we can decide
and I don't really know which is a
better decision here but it's a little
bit hard to say one of the things that
we can decide to here is we don't really
know whether we need this to be entity
based storage or not for example if our
entities just to kind of let you know
what's going through my head here so if
let's take this example of a guy this is
a top view here of this guy if we take
this example there's two ways we could
store this data right we have an entity
structure right this is our entity
and inside that entity we could either
directly store inside it or have a
pointer off to write a thing that's
basically a you know a list of coalition
volumes right for that guy and whichever
one of those we do like let's say that
we we take the one where we just have a
pointer off to a list you know maybe
there's a count and there's a pointer to
a list the question is does this live
with the entity or is it shared right
meaning is this something that we need
to track per entity or is it something
that entities can share between them
because for example if we had lots of
entities that all use this exact same
shape maybe we never need to store that
right there could be some other entity
and it just it just points to the same
list of things right because it's the
same type these are both the same kind
of mon-star so they both have like you
know they both just have this
description that works very well if it's
always gonna be the same if on the other
hand every entity has a slightly
different one of these so every monster
you know this is slightly bigger or
smaller like some of them have a
chunkier midsection and smaller arms or
whatever this is supposed to be you know
like that then sharing doesn't doesn't
really work anymore at that point each
one of them wants its own unique one and
I suppose at this point we don't really
have to we don't really have to think
about that too hard but what it does
suggest to me is maybe I'm going to
point out to it and I'm just going to
assume that most of the time this will
probably be shared but we can always
just point out two unique ones if if
what ends up happening is most of the
time they aren't shared so I'm going to
say that we have some kind of a
structure here very simple like again
that's just storing exactly that same
data that we were storing before and so
it's something like this where we
basically have a count so we have a
volume count and then we have a same
entity collision volume just volumes
like that right and I don't really have
a real reason why I'm breaking that down
into two hops there maybe that's stupid
it could be that it's smarter again to
compress that up
but that's really an optimization
concern and we don't really have to
worry about that too much we can
obviously make that decision a little
later on so for right now I'm gonna do
is and replace that dim since there is
no such thing as dimension in particular
anymore I replaced that dim with
essentially a list of dims so we're
gonna point to a collision group here
and we're just going to say that there's
collision group off of the entity right
very simple so we've got the collision
group off of the entity we have the
dimension of it and so all we need in
addition to that is some offset that
lets us know that from whatever the
entity's position actually is where is
the collision volume relative to that
right because that is the thing that
lets us know how to actually do
colliding so that's it that's really all
I wanted to do and again we could decide
to make it to do that which would embed
it directly in and then there would be
that wouldn't really be the same kind of
sharing although they could still share
these pointers but let's say for now I'm
just gonna say for now that the way that
we have this work is they all point to
some group that's been constructed for
their type of guy and we're really not
going to make distinct ones of those at
the time being so it's sort of like just
it's it's sort of like an entity type
almost in fact at some point maybe we'll
even compress this down further and say
that we just used the entity type
directly to get the collision group for
that entity type and there aren't
specific ones but for the time being
we'll leave it this way because it will
let us vary the sizes of things a little
bit more and and be a little bit more
crazy with that so we'll leave it in
until we decide we really need to
compress it down all right so what I'm
gonna do now is I'm just gonna compile
the program and I'm going to let the
compile errors guide my replacement of
the dimension which is something you've
seen me do a lot it's a good programming
technique it's basically you replace
something and just let the compile
errors tell you all the places that you
need to think about it all right so
forget into the ground point now really
that's just gonna there isn't going to
be any more displacement that's just
automatic right
point is whatever the position of the
guy actually was and anyone who's using
that will just get the right thing back
and that's fine for figuring out what
the stare ground is in this case what we
would like to do is we'd like to say
well we should see which point you are
inside right and that's how you would
get the stare ground so because it lets
say a stairwell had multiple pieces
multiple collision pieces to it we want
to see which one you're in and then we
want to get a very eccentric thing out
of that so well actually now that I
think about it actually four stairwells
we want something slightly different
which is actually that we only care
about that sort of footprint that XY
footprint so really what we probably
want your stairwells just to have an
extra thing since their collision is not
really necessarily related to that what
we might want to do is just say we've
just got a notion of that barycentric
piece and we go ahead and and construct
that specially so so I think I'm just
gonna go ahead and make that change
and we'll just test it later so
basically what that means is in some
region again for for these guys I'm
gonna say that we have a rectangle -
that's basically the walkable region
right and that's the area where that
that height happens essentially and in
fact I guess we could do is we could
make a rectangle we can even make a
rectangle three here and say that
stairwells have a volume that has
nothing to do with collision that just
tells you about how you move in them in
that way I'm not sure if that's useful
or not but we could have done that for
right now I guess we don't really need
to do that do we want to do that I guess
we don't really need to do that so I
won't we can think about stairwells a
little in a little bit more detail later
but what that means is this region rect
mm this region rect is really just an
offset rectangle right it's just a rock
able region off I should say walkable
dimension it's just the walkable the
walkable dimension like so on it's just
a rectangle that's been centered about
the the point of the guy in 2d and it's
using the wall dimension as its size and
so we'll get the very central
coordinates out of that and use the
barycentric why to determine the motion
of it we could also have stairwells
going the other direction by using the
barycenter Dex in fact there's a couple
things we could even make very odd sort
of slanted surfaces by actually having
sample points oh that would be even
weirder I'm not gonna think about that
for now yeah we can have weird sort of
scallop e surfaces yeah that's something
for maybe we'll think about that a
little more with ground height anyway so
if we get our barycentric coordinates
back using the 2d rectangle now for that
that ground point and the ground point
actually now is is mostly just going to
be used for the x and y we're gonna get
back that result which is how far up we
should be and we're going to do that
from whatever the entity's position is
that's how we'll define it for for the
stairwells so we'll keep going here
rectangle Center dim probably we don't
have that yet for 2d rectangles I'm
imagining we only have that oops rec
center dim I'm imagining that we know we
do so what's the problem
oh right duh that doesn't need to be a
rectangle that's just a v2 that's the
waffle dimension so let's see here
clamp 0 1 or what do we got back get
barycentric okay so our get Bary centric
that is the one that actually doesn't
have yeah so we need a gift barycentric
for our rectangle too that's pretty
simple
that's just reducing a down one we just
don't do the Z so that's you know really
really basic so we've got that done and
they're safe ratio stuff that really
should be defined up at the top so
because oops everyone needs to be able
to use that those are those are just
scalar operations so that should be
along with like these sorts of things
clamp and lerp and those sorts of fun
things all right so let's see here
dipper Center Eric what did I do get
very eccentric feel a rectangle 3 which
is not what I wanted so let's take a
look here
get barycentric clamp oh 1 so clamp Oh 1
is just the is a v3 special function so
again we'll do that in v2 and for those
of you who were using templates here
again this you this is stuff you
wouldn't have to do a few years and
templates like I said I don't like to
use them I prefer to just do the copy
copy paste or to go the full
metaprogramming route I always pick one
of the other I don't pick the template
wrap but if you're doing the template
route hopefully your templates hopefully
you did it right
those should have been generated for you
hopefully I suppose you could have
something bad but assuming that you did
it reasonably that wouldn't be necessary
ok
so now we get to stuff that actually is
doing more of the collision detection so
let's see here what we need to do is see
whether our entity overlaps the the
bounds that we have and so I believe
well we really need to do here is test
those regions now it's unclear whether
we really whether we want something
faster here you know when we do entity
overlaps rectangle and we pass in that V
through Tim really you know presumably
we might still want the concept and in
fact this is something I guess that we
could do is say that the volume group
itself stores a you know its own total
collision volume so we have like a total
volume and then we have individual
volumes so that basically there is one
volume that encloses everything and then
we have other volumes that are you know
sort of sub chunked and in the case
where volume count was zero it would
mean that your entity didn't have a more
complex shape to it but in the case
where it was then you would do sub
testing and I think I like that because
for example in enemy overlaps rectangle
this is not a gameplay concern this is a
just a region gather and so it seems
like a waste of time here to go through
and figure out okay DD really is he
really overlapping exactly or is it that
there's like a little convex part of him
that's not overlapping that's something
we do care about for collision detection
because it affects the playability of
the game it's important but in terms of
figuring out what's inside a sim region
I'm not sure we care about that so I
think what we want to do here is say
that we've got a collision group and
that collision maybe I'll just call that
collision definitely be close and great
probably will say that we've got that
collision we'll just look at the total
volume right and we'll pass that total
volume and say that's you know that's
the thing right and so then the inside
our entity overlaps rectangle thing what
we'll do is we'll pass one of these
collision volumes
like so and we can go ahead and pass it
in and what we'll do is we'll take that
volume and I guess well we could pass it
by value it seems like a little bit
large well that's an in line so I guess
that's fine so it'll understand
it'll understand what used to do there
probably I don't know that's that's one
of the ones you probably want check but
anyway so we'll pass in that volume
there and then what we'll do is we'll do
the checking against that volume so the
first thing we need to do is say all
right we need to actually grow the
rectangle by the volume which we're
gonna do exactly the same way so this
this should work exactly the same way
but then when we do is in rectangle P
it's not just the entities P anymore
it's actually the P plus the volume
offset P right because we're essentially
saying that you know the actual point
the location that we're testing is is
this offset this offset version so I
think that's all we really have to do
there yeah I don't think there would be
anything else
we're large in the rectangle and seeing
refer in it yeah I think that's about it
so that should be fine what's the
problem here I does not have no you're
right it does not have an overloaded
I'm still thinking I passed it by planar
so let's see dimension is not a member
of sim entity you are correct it is not
so an empty over left rectangle this is
the same kind of test that we're doing
here so we're just gonna say that we're
gonna pass the collision there again
let's see cannot to to oh we need the
total volume like so and then we now
have our Minkowski diameter let's see
we've got our dimensions here so now
inside this is actually the collision
loop and it looks like why is this
saying it cannot recover from previous
errors really it was so hard to come to
recover from the fact of it that we
don't still have that dim in there all
right well anyway plate being what we
want to actually do now is we want to go
ahead and
test those collision volumes those sub
collision volumes and so the way that
I'm going to do that is hmm really all I
have to do is enclose this on a loop and
test each one separately right but there
is one little caveat which is that the
total volume if there was no volume do I
really want to store it twice you know I
guess the answer is we'll do that for
now but but just trying to give you what
the ideas so if we have a total volume
and we we wanted to be able to make an
optimization which is that if we set
volume count to zero then the volumes
themselves would be ignored and you just
use the total volume as the actual
volume for testing right I don't know if
I want to do that short-circuit or not
for now I'm not going to so for now I'm
gonna say volume count is always
expected to be greater than zero if the
entity has any volume in the future this
could be compressed if necessary to say
that the volume count can be zero if the
total volume should be used as the only
collision volume or the entity right and
so that's just like a short-circuit
thing I'm gonna I'm not going to do that
I'm not gonna do that alright so let's
go ahead and pump this out like so
and I'm going to go ahead and get a rate
over those so we've got another loop in
here and that's going to be the volume
index and
this part is is actually I mean if we
actually want to do this correctly it's
a bit difficult right it's actually two
loops right we have two entities each of
which might have n number of collision
volumes so it's really an N squared
pairing and unfortunately that's
actually that's collision detection in a
nutshell collision detection is
unfortunately an N squared problem and
so a lot of the stuff that we do in
collision detecting and you'll see us
have to do this when we do the full
collision objector in the end is we try
to eliminate a lot of entities right off
the bat because of the nasibi the nasty
N squared Ness of it and what I mean by
that is let's say that I've got you know
some things moving in the world right
well for every set of things the
computer can only really consider pairs
of them at once right it can it can ask
the question will this guy collide with
this guy but once it computes that
answer it has gotten no further in
determining whether this guy will
collide with this guy so for every dude
it has to be checked against every other
dude and that's the you know the
textbook definition of a no N squared
problem when however many of these you
have is N and you need to check for
every one of them against n you know all
the others that's n times n pieces of
work you have to do or N squared right
and that's that order notation stuff
we've never really spent a whole episode
talking about it but order notation is
really just a way of saying how the work
scales right how the work scales with
the number of units and so as that
number of units goes up and squared
things look nasty they look like that so
there's a certain number out that you
can do like a hundred of them or
whatever but when you get to a thousand
of them it may be really tough and if
you were to get out to a million of them
it's forget it it's never gonna happen
you're never it's it's like a
nonterminating program that runs for
weeks or something right
and so you know it is that close
detectives in square there's not much we
can do about it
and you can see it happening with loops
inside loops and so that's exactly
what's going on
there's just collision protection has a
lot of that in it and so we have the
entities volume index to loop through
right and then we also have the test
volume index coops the test volume index
to loop through and really in each case
we that's what we have to do we have to
look at each of the entity volumes so we
have the entity we have the entity
collision volume count to loop through
here and we have the test entities
collision fly encounter loops through
here and then this internal routine
actually has to be made to work off of
off of both of those so that we test
pairwise each individual one now this
won't actually lead to any more actual
work in our case at the moment because
they're only will actually ever be one
volume in the volume count but if we
were to increase that volume count up
further than it does multiply that which
makes it so that it's pretty expensive
to have lots of those volumes but that
would have been true if there were lots
of entities as well and again that's
collision is an end spread problem and
it's tough that way so you typically try
to do a lot of sorting of things in two
places to figure out whether they could
ever possibly hit each other so that you
keep and very low because when you have
an N squared problem the only way you
could really ever solve it efficiently
especially in a game context where you
don't have a lot of cycles to spare is
to keep n low that's what you have to do
so you have to use techniques keep n
left for right now are in just is low so
we'd have to worry about that and
hopefully the end always will be pretty
low for these because there shouldn't be
like thousands of collision volumes in
an entity there are these little things
on the screen I mean how many could you
need three four should be pretty low
right so that should be okay but at the
outer level is where we'll definitely do
it like this loop is not gonna stand
it's it's because we're calling move
entity on lots of entities for frame
potentially in each one
looping through all the other enemies
even if those entities are fairly far
away from them
they're looping through all the enemies
in the sim region now the sim region is
keeping it down to a smaller end much
smaller than all the others in the game
so that does do a big part of that for
us that got end down from ten thousand a
hundred thousand entities down to like a
hundred or a thousand entities but we
can do much more granular inside the sim
region we can have things partitioned
further to cut that end down further and
get rid of that nasty M squared feedback
so we that's why I have to do space away
from here because that probably is
something that we're not gonna want to
leave in the in the shipping product in
the final versions but in lecture that
will go away almost certainly unless I
end up being very surprised by how our
profiles look anyway so when we loop
through these what we need to do now is
set up the collision between those
entities bounding volumes rather than
themselves and that's not that hard to
do really all we have to do is is pick
out those two volumes right so we'll
have the entity volume here and that'll
just be their collision volumes volumes
plus entity volume index like so and
then in here same thing we'll just do
tests any volume bat and test volume
index right and I'll just call that test
volume to put entity in there so that'll
grab out the two volumes that we're
testing against and now we just need to
actually use those instead of their
correspondence so so instead of the
entities where that used to get we'll
get the dimensions now out of the
volumes right and I guess we could just
call this volume as well volume and test
volume there we go
uh don't ask me why I'm doing this
renaming yeah it's probably not the
necessary I'm doing it anyway okay there
we go
so that'll produce the correct diameter
for us the two volumes first each other
that's what we wanted and that'll
produce the min and Max when are
centered around the test volume just
like we were doing before if the test
entity but now this has to change
because these entity Peas are not proper
what they need to be is they need to be
offsets so we need to look at the edit
EP plus the volumes offset P right
that's the position of that's where it
actually is in 3d space that's where
that collision volume is in 3d space and
then we also have our test son and EP
that's going to be plus the test volumes
offset P and now we've just basically
created two entity bounding boxes just
like we had before but they've been
offset and then we're just going to do
the closing section exactly how we were
doing it all the rest of this stuff
should just work there's really not
anything else to it I think that's
pretty much it
I think that should should just about
cover it let's double check yeah so that
just went ahead that just went ahead and
resolved all of those it looks like so
now we're on to two other things all
right so now we wanted to do here is see
whether the entity rectangle is
overlapping basically any of these sorts
of you know any of these and these other
pieces that we need so this was to
handle our stairwells right this was to
see whether we were overlapping the
stairwells man I'm out of T look at that
how am I supposed to program with no T
seriously
I tell you that is one thing we
definitely need here at handmade Hero
dot-com if we were a dot-com
instead of a.org then we would have the
billions of dollars of venture capital
funding and then we would have the huge
fancy kitchens with like and special
people whose job it is just to bring me
tea right that's what we would actually
have everyone knows that that's how you
run a company if you want to do it right
in Silicon Valley you have to have at
least seven gourmet kitchens per
programmer how are they supposed to get
any work done without ya without gourmet
teas hand brewed you know preferably by
special robots designed by NASA all
right so let's take a look here at what
this is doing and see if there's
anything in particular we want to change
about it I don't think I think for now
we can probably just do we can we can
probably just do the same looping and
I'll see anything particularly odd here
we just do we just do rectangles
intersect on all the things right and
yeah it's a little bit of a bummer that
we have to make rectangle the rec center
dim stuff but we could we could try to
rewrite this loop to be a little bit to
be a little bit cleaner as well I'm
gonna I'm gonna go a little further
round I'm gonna leave that one for now
and I'm gonna think about that for a
little bit as to how much we want to
rewrite that so I'm gonna go ahead and
here and and I'm gonna I'm gonna deal
with this instead so what I'd like to do
here is I'd like to just create some of
these and just use them directly for
things like our swords and our player
and stuff so what I'd like to do is in
our game state I'd like to get to create
these things as sort of templates that
just get used not like the C++ template
but you know templates like in the
traditional sense of the word that get
used in in creating sort of the the the
players in the sword and the mon-star
room when we create them I'd like to go
ahead and make these volume groups be
those things right and so what I'm gonna
do is I'm just gonna make some of those
here because why not
so what I'm gonna do is say we've got a
volume group pointer for swords we've
got a volume group pointer for
stairwells right we've got one for
players we've got one for the mon-star
we've got one for the wall and we'll
just sort of use those as as we go and
so inside handmade CBP when we create
stuff at the beginning I'm just gonna go
ahead and create those here and I'm
gonna use just a utility function
basically to make them on Moss so if I
go in here and I guess I'll use our our
our game States permanent storage for
this so I'll go ahead and say that the
sword equals you know make simple
collision and that'll just pass the game
state and then it'll pass
you know this stuff right so a sword
will just take what its dimensions were
so it's X dimension was one it's Y
dimension was 0.5 and it's Z dimension
was was that and we'll make simple
collision based off of that and I
believe well I guess for a sword we
don't really care but I believe the rest
of these people
it was always being offset from the base
so we'll call this make simple grounded
collision and what that'll do is that'll
automatically offset it up by half the
by half the Z height like we were doing
before and basically everyone can use
that right for now ok so for s word when
we do this collision what we want to do
is say that the entity oh there's one
more we should have the sim entity
collision line group
null collision we want that to for
anything that just doesn't want to
collide at all and that'll just
basically have an empty collision volume
and no actual volumes in it alright so I
want to make that as well let's go ahead
back here to
this guy so when I add the sword I'm
just gonna take its sim collision group
and I'm gonna point that at the one for
the sword and I realized I should
probably do collision on the end of all
of these huh there we go now so sword
collision right that's it for that and
I'm gonna do the exact same thing with
everybody else you know not not rocket
science here right I wish I had the same
number of love columns as I do at work
it's hard I like having my code be long
I don't like it have to keep breaking
lines like that it's annoying but anyway
all right so let's go ahead and make all
these game state sword collision oh that
helped didn't it that'll help me with my
line break problem I love it all right
there we go
and when you're verbose with your naming
like I am you end up in that situation
where you really want a lot you want
your lines to be long and you know what
can I say
it doesn't really lend itself to this
twitch streaming where everything has to
be big so it can be legible on the
stream this is I typically have a lot
more screen real estate functionally
speaking oops
when I'm working and it does make it a
bit tougher anyway so let's see here
we've got our S word
there's our wall so these guys are
actually for add ground identity yeah so
now we don't really need add ground
identity anymore either which is kind of
nice that will just get taken care of
for us now because all the entities will
just work at that point yes so ground
identity doesn't have to happen and
that's kind of nice but let's finish up
what I was doing here so when I do add
wall let's see where as wall there as
well
here is the dimensions to that right so
what I'll probably do is say we'll just
make add ground identity take that game
state wall collision and it'll set it
for us I guess I don't know seems
reasonable enough our stairwell same
thing so here's the stairway to heaven
of course the place where all stairways
go it's about a seven-minute long
stairway it's played on classic rock
stations all the time everyone's bored
of it by now you know how it is okay
so let's see that fixes those guys add
ground and entity just takes one of
these again that's really easy
simplification that's a sim entity
collision volume group all right group
or collision I should say and then in
here it says that the collision equals
that pointer and then it doesn't have to
do this math with the chunk space thing
it doesn't have to use offset P it just
does it right and similarly doesn't have
set the dimension because that's already
handled and yeah that should just work
so that looks all good we have our add s
word as well and we have our add player
our add player wants to have and so I
think we started what do we start 15
minutes late today because I was ranting
about low-quality software so I guess
what that means is we will go 15 minutes
from now so we'll have to keep an eye on
that so nine fifteen is when the stream
will actually begin the QA
make simple grounded collision for the
player now that's in there instead of
passing that it'll just pass game state
player collision like so and then the
Monstar
also put his dimension in there so the
Monstar can participate just like
everyone else we are an equal
grounded entity adder we do not
discriminate against Monstars simply
because they are Monstars Monstars have
rights as well and it is important to
treat them with dignity and so and so we
do so I'm going to skip this again cuz
that's what I want to come back to in a
second alright so Oh familiar I forgot
about the filler entirely how how dare I
familiar collision and so familiar
collision yeah and let's see so sward
collision so I'm gonna go ahead and add
that in here know your solution make
simple grounded collision and I mean
hopefully you can see that I'm not doing
anything weird here I'm just simplifying
things down to two basic basic basic
simplification that I'm doing nothing
particularly unusual going on here all
right that's supposed to be sim dock
collision and what do we got here so
this is just our rendering stuff which
we have to clean up and so let me go
ahead and do that as well so what we're
doing here is we're actually taking a
look at that ground point that's
actually gonna be fine now so we don't
have to do this anymore
that'll get rid of that again making it
nice just like the person was asking
about in the post stream yesterday let
me see here inside here when we're doing
a stairwell what we want to draw on the
stairwell is actually going to be a
little bit different than what we were
drawing before right what we're gonna
draw on the stairwell now is we've got
that sort of walkable dimension that
we're talking about this right here and
so what we want to do there is we want
to go ahead and push some slightly
different stuff than what we were
pushing before it looks like really we
just want the walkable Jim directly as
its self it's
z-value in terms of where we want to be
offset in Z is just going to be that
walkable height
right which is which is we also know
that's how high off off its ground point
it goes and again that's just gonna be
the welcome of them again so we're just
drawing that using the other things now
instead of treating the collision
volumes as that definition of the
stairwell and then it looks like
everything else worked okay so what I'm
gonna do here I'm gonna temper airily
disable this guy and then because I
think we might have our hands full with
debugging stuff you know correctly in
the short amount of time that we have
left we've only got about 12 minutes
left so I want to focus on getting
everything else working and then we can
sort of think about that up that thing
maybe we'll do that tomorrow before we
do ooh
control-z everyone it suspends Emacs as
if it were Unix even though you can't
really suspend something oh got a sore
shoulder today it happens so here's our
dimensions and this is our thing for
making a simple grounded collision so
I'm gonna go ahead and push that on the
arena of course I don't actually
remember how we did our arena stuff here
we need our arena we need our arena to
be initialized so why isn't our arena
initialized as the very first thing it
does that's just dumb
yeah so that's what we want there now we
don't actually have an arena for
entities specifically at the moment it's
only for worlds and so I don't really
know how we want to really do that
exactly this may be something that
actually wants sort of a sub arena right
I'm gonna I don't want to talk about
this right now but maybe talk about this
soon let's start partitioning our memory
space so what I'm gonna do right now is
I'm going to go ahead and allow it to
use game state World Arena right but
then I'm not actually gonna do that I'm
just doing that temporarily because I
don't want to actually explain
some additional stuff that we'll explain
in a bit so
not world arena change to using the
fundamental types arena etc alright so
what I want to do here is I just want to
do the simple push stuff to allocate
these things that we want and they're
you know pretty much permanent types
they just sit around forever and so
simonetti closing volume groups here so
this is the group we're just gonna push
that on to the arena and we've got we're
doing on the World Arena for now but
again that's not where I would probably
do it eventually so once we've got that
the group is going to have a volume
count of one always and it's going to
have exactly one volume in it and that
volume is going to be equal to the total
volumes for now so we've got a push
array right it's going to push the
volume count on there it's going to push
one volume and then what we're going to
do is we're going to set the group total
volume equal to excuse me people to I
guess we're going to find that one and
then we're going to set the one volume
we actually have to be equal to it
because like I said right now we're not
actually making multiple volumes we're
just using one volume all right so the
total volume for this guy go ahead up
here into our entity collision volume so
we've got two things we've got an offset
key and we've got the dim those the two
things we need to set the dim is really
straightforward
it's just passed in right dim Y dibbsy
the offset key thankfully is actually
also very straightforward at the moment
because the only thing we're making are
very simple things all it is is its
offset off by half the height right
that's that's all so there's nothing
else to it than that and and off it goes
so that's how we make a collision group
and presumably that should be fine now
of course we're probably gonna have a
lot of
deal with and so you know that's that's
just something oh yeah if we actually
want to reference the tile side meters
we haven't actually initialized that
gamestate stuff yet and so I suppose
what we probably have to do is set up
our very initial just are sort of very
basic stuff like our tiles and that sort
of stuff so this all has to be kind of
initialized at the outset if that makes
sense so we'll go ahead and do that for
now let's see here so yeah we're not
totally busted
our collision detection is still working
our stairwell on the other hand is
noticeably absent and so we have some
work to do there everything else seems
to be working pretty well now we did
comment out the code for the stairwell
that is true but you will notice that it
should have still been drawing so that
is something that we have to go deal
with yeah so that's good
and I snuck in one other thing I mean
obviously I didn't mention it yet well
we've got we may yet finish we only have
seven we have seven minutes left we may
be able to fish stairwells as well I was
gonna say is I snuck in one extra thing
I don't know if you saw me do it I was
sly about it it is true but I got us
most of the way there also for doing
this because now flying entities just
have their collision boxes offset from
where they actually are and they can
still walk around on the ground just
like everybody else so this is kind of
gonna be free now I think for the most
part that'll just pass right over low
walls because their collision boxes
won't hit that's all there is to it so
yeah kind of cool we get that for free
not similar to do off the list and
that's always good but for now we need
to go find out let's start with thing
one which is what happened to our to our
stairwells and I assume there's two
places
this could be happening one of them is
here oh you know what we just probably
never initialized that walkable
dimension
did we right that's probably what our
problem was I'm guessing because if we
never if we never actually initialize
that walkable damn it what did that just
do okay thank you I'm hitting some
errant Keys tonight let me tell you so
we have to actually set the walkable
dimension to the area that we're
supposed to actually hit right so yeah
makes sense anyway so if we want to do
that I guess I don't know what the
dimensions should be ice guess it should
just be whatever the stare collision or
I guess I should say whatever our
collision right thinks is its total
volume it should just be that as a
rectangle - seems reasonable to me what
do you guys think about that
I think that's roughly what we should do
for that and so we need a two rectangle
to call right something that converts a
rectangle 3 into a rectangular
corresponding rectangle - and maybe I'll
say rectangle XY so that we can have
other ways of slicing the rectangle up
as a quick operation right and and so
what that'll do is that's just you know
a real simple call again it's a
rectangle - returning and it does a -
rectangle XY takes in that rectangle 3
and just returns that rectangle - and so
what that does is it says all right you
know the results min equals a dot min XY
right
and the result max equals a dot max XY
and then that just right that's just a
conversion it just takes a slice of that
rectangle so total volume it's it's
totally not dim is actually what I want
to do there right
conniver argument one from v3 to
rectangle three why do I always think I
need rekted well I still like having
that function I didn't need it
this whole tide it'd need it at all that
was all I really needed to do oh well
well at least we got to write to
rectangle - but what are you gonna do so
there's our stairwell back so that's
good we still run into it which is
correct and we still pass through it
which is correct but we don't handle the
overlapping case anymore because like if
zero that out and so we do have a
situation where that's going to be
problematic so let's go ahead and let's
go ahead and fix that let's see here so
inside my handmade sim region we need to
re-enable this case we can do the very
simple thing by just testing the total
volume that would take no time at all
right the total volume test is just this
test it's just entity collision excuse
me
yeah it's entity collision total volume
and entity collision total volume Jim
okay right it's just making that offset
should probably make a thing that just
gets that volume back we'll think about
that think about that little rate up
later
we have the tests entity we do the same
test there when we do the rec center dim
for that we'll just do entity collision
total volume offset P right and test
them to be collision total volume dim
and I believe that would just do it with
just if we just want to do with the
total volumes that would work and so
there we go can we jump that was funny I
was trying to figure out if I can jump
over the stairwell
you have to get up enough enough height
to clear it and I can't quite seem to I
need I need a little more jump or I can
just double jump well I got to be on top
I'll hit it if I'm on the bottom so we
eat awesome so you can jump over the
stairwell now that's always fun alright
so I think that's basically it and we're
just about out of time so that's good I
want to go ahead and say handle multi
volumes here so you know as we clean
that up we'll do that you know we can do
volume to volume
overlap testing basically it's just a
question of doing that that N squared
test again inside for each thickness
volumes versus the other volumes what I
do want to do is I just want to finish
up something here we didn't do the null
collision yet right so we have gamestate
null collision and that's going to be
just a thing where we've got a null
collision that we make and then what I
want to do is when you add low entity
what I want to do is make it so that it
initializes that so that collision is
always initialized to something right so
there's always a null collision pointer
in there so that people don't have to
check to see if it's zero so they won't
crash or whatever right so what I want
to do is I just want to make one of
these that's specifically for null
collisions basically represents no area
whatsoever
make no collision and what that's going
to do is that's going to set the volume
count to zero set the volume pointers to
zero and set the offset P and dimension
all to zero as well right so basically
there's just nothing included in that
region so that's it and I don't know if
there's anything else we could even do
it making these negative making it
negative would ensure I don't know
I'll put it to do should this be
negative and there we go
all right so that is I think the end of
what I would like to cover for now I
like out so we can't jump over it at the
bottom because the stairwells solid
right but if we go up over it and it's
just a hole in the floor now we can jump
over it which is kind of nice right yeah
it's weird what happens when we float
down there I guess like I don't totally
understand what's happening there it's
like it's like gravity doesn't affect us
as fast as it should I don't really know
what's happening there I don't know if
we're having some kind of weird
collision thing that happens there right
like why is that not going faster is
that just because of the drag oh that
may be because of the drag
that's probably what that is the drag is
applied in 3d now right so the jumping
is gonna have drag yeah yeah the jumping
is gonna have drag isn't it let's take a
look at that sorry I said I was gonna
stop coding but I lied I'm going to I'm
at two minutes over call me a liar for
two minutes
tough crowd tough crowd tonight grey
face no space all right let's see here
so you know basically we've got the drag
being computed here I feel like we want
to knock out that aspect of the drag so
you know if we did this right that we
just say there's no drag on Z I don't
know what do you think
because what I want to see happen is I
want to fall down the stairwell right if
I jump and yeah that's what's supposed
to happen exactly right yeah boom and
then he lands on it so that's what we
want to have happen all right all right
now we're actually done yes I went over
no there won't be as much QA as a result
but what are you gonna do right that's
just the way that goes sometimes
please prefix your questions with Q :
and keep them to things that we did on
to night stream around a previous stream
it's about programming people it is
about the programming that we're doing
you know how it is we gotta jump up to
that top level I like the fact that we
can jump up we got to have some kind of
floor that you hit so you can't just
jump up to top levels like here I am one
level up above everything let's keep
going there now I've jumped up so far
that we actually have a bunch of things
that are clipped out of our region like
they're so far below us they're not even
in the same region anymore
right yeah we got to fix that ground
level stuff that's that's gonna be
tomorrow's thing because we're so close
to having full 3d goodness here we're
pretty close it's getting exciting I'm a
happy camper all right no questions
there are no questions it is question
free everyone thought it went perfectly
what can I say thank you I appreciate
that vote of confidence can we get a
sneak preview of the fundamental types
arena I just I just want to make an
arena for like so all it is it's real
simple and I'll explain it in detail
later but all I want to do right is in
our memory partition there's gonna be
like constant stuff right which is stuff
like those collision definitions and
then there's going to be world stuff
right and this stuff gets vaporized
every time you start a new game right
but this stuff doesn't and so because
there's no need we could recreate
everything every time but because
there's no need to recreate this it's
just it's a nice optimization to say all
of the classic stuff we do first at
startup when you start the game and then
it just stays in that block footprint
the whole time and is used by everyone
but the stuff that's whether to the
world this gets freed every time you
finish a you know finish a playthrough
of the game that's all so it's nothing
special it's just we haven't talked
about that stuff and so I didn't want to
just do it
I'd like to talk about it and have some
more time to go through it so it's not
rushed
drive 137 what does besides the missed
keys mean I don't know what that means
missed keys Oh because of my awesome
typing yeah control-z made an appearance
for the first time tonight I'm surprised
it hasn't happened earlier but ctrl Z
means suspend task in a UNIX environment
right and they've mapped it in in Emacs
and Windows to minimize because they did
no no it's fine with me it's just let's
see do we have any on topic questions it
looks like we don't you know if I don't
have any on top of questions that's okay
I'll answer off-topic questions for the
eight minutes we have remaining if
anyone does that on top a question
though I'll try to prioritize that like
the sneak peek of the fundamental types
arena we already did that one so that's
good what did I just watch you watch me
programming game the way we do it in
actual game programming in the real
world this is how game programming goes
and we're basically just doing exactly
that it's a it's slower paced then how
programming actually goes because I have
to explain stuff and talk it through
which slows things down but other than
that I'm basically doing almost exactly
what I would be doing if this were work
I was doing during the day to develop
actual video games for real so we're not
pulling any punches here I'm doing all
the same stuff I overcomplicate some
things intentionally that maybe you
could cut based on the game you were
doing so like do we have to handle all
this 3d stuff perfectly and am i pushing
forwards on some stuff that might not
need to get pushed yes but that's
because it's again for educational
purposes and I want to give people a
window into the 3d stuff because that
would be the next logical step after
handmade hero would be to start doing 3d
engine programming as an extension of
your 2d engine programming because
they're basically the same but then the
the geometry gets more complicated the
gem stuff gets more complicated but
otherwise it's you know it's basically
what that is so what you watched was how
we code that's how we do it I'm a little
bit old school and how I program so
there's it's you know some people would
have a lot more C++ this and be doing
you know inheritance and templates and
stuff like that but a lot of people
wouldn't be a lot of game programmers
wouldn't be as well a lot of papers for
a Mac I do and I'm not the most old old
school out there right there's people
who are way harder core than me and
would bristle at some of the things I'm
doing is being a little too new-school
right so you know everyone has their own
preference and primary styles vary and
what you consider to be important and
what you consider to be a priority is
various imperson to person because
sometimes there's no perfect right
answer as to how to make a particular
thing in the game right let's see
let's see so we have some on topic
questions here so I want to parse those
first let's see
so it looks like the on topic questions
I like to cover are could you sketch
what you did today visually and the
answer is yes and I'll do that and there
was wood the ground question be easier
have less issues if it was a volume
instead of a plane and the answer is we
haven't really done the ground stuff yet
and so what what we're gonna do with
that I don't know I suspect we may make
it a volume but we may not we may just
treat it as a plane I think that's not
the interesting that's probably not the
interesting decision the problem if the
reason that we have it to do for a
ground specification like the reason I'm
not happy with what's happening right
now right is not really a collision
detection problem it's a specification
problem right there's really no problem
that we're having right now that has to
do with the ground being a plane the
problem that we're having has to do with
knowing where the ground is so right now
we just have entities in space right
what we have to define a place right
right now is we have a bunch of tree
entities that we just placed in like a
grid pattern which is totally arbitrary
by the way we didn't have to do that
it's just what we did we've got a bunch
of trees that are placed and that
defined a room and since our collision
detection is happening in 2d that
defines a nice room on a plane that we
can walk around and everyone's happy
problem is when rooms start getting
stacked on top of each other the
question is where is the ground right
where is it and right now we don't have
a definition for that all we do is say
well wherever the cameras pointing the Z
position at which the camera is pointing
that's the ground so literally the
ground moves with the camera right now
right which is totally not gonna cut it
and so the question for that we have to
face is less about how do we
mathematically deal with the ground once
we know where it is and more how do we
want to specify this so one way we could
specify it would be to actually just add
entities in that say where the ground is
and if there's nothing there
then you fall through it and that's how
we would probably do it in a 3d
environment right that's probably how we
do that
in 2d though we have to ask the question
does that make a lot of sense because
the common case in 2d is that there's
just a flat round under the room and 99%
of the time that's probably what we
gonna have is like ground or the room
and maybe a stairwell right I mean if
you think about Legend of Zelda Binding
of Isaac the games that I keep
referencing that's just we're trying to
make that 2d dungeon-crawling kind of
thing they just don't have a lot of null
on ground it's just not that common and
so I wonder you know does it make sense
to treat the ground as something that we
constantly have to say hey by the way
there's some ground does that make sense
instead of just specifying where the
ground isn't like could we just always
assume that there's ground and then what
we actually specify is where there is
not ground right and so one example of
this might be when we open up a sim
region insert ground levels at some
known set of locations and then assume
that people will put in entities to say
there's no ground at a particular place
there I don't know it's on our to-do
list we'll look at it some more we'll
think about some more I don't know what
the answer is
right now though I think volume versus
plain is not really a big concern I
think either one would be fine
maybe we'll see that one or the other
would be better a little further down
the road right now what concerns me most
is just how do we specify it how do we
say where the ground is right now we got
nothing and nothing is not an acceptable
answer
since you are handling Z how complicated
is it to have entity stacking with the
current code state it would not be hard
at all to have entity stacking if you
just want to like if I'm on top of an
entity I can walk on it that'd be really
easy if you want to do stuff we're like
entities stack on top of each other in a
physics puzzle e-way like pushing things
and I don't know there might be stuff
where the physics would be nasty to do
there
are using a memory manager no how are
you letting out your levels currently
and are you going to make a level editor
it's this game is entirely procedurally
generated so we won't be making a level
editor but right now we don't do much
procedural generation we just have some
little placeholder stuff in there so
right now it just generates a couple
rooms and that's it just for testing
that'll be an entire block of time that
we spend probably a very significant
block of time probably half the game
development time honestly will be on
level generation because that's gonna be
one of the biggest important parts of
the game it'll pace it'll be like the
behavior of entities and objects and
level generation will be where we spend
you know 400 of the 600 days or
something I would suspect just pulling a
number out of my head but it's knowing
big o-notation important in game
programming yes big o-notation is
important in any programming you you
have to know how your code scales too
you have to know how many maximum things
your code can handle before it totally
breaks the notation isn't important it's
understanding that N squared versus and
versus log and versus n log n versus n
log n squared or you know whatever it's
understanding the behavioral the
scalability of the code is what's
important not the notation the notation
just happens to be how people write it I
think that's rust about out of time
let's see here
you mentioned further ways of
partitioning collisions past breaking it
up into regions what would some of those
be well I don't really mean that what I
mean is we need to further break it up
into regions like right now we just have
the sim region and everything in the sim
region what we want to do is partition
the sim region into sub regions that are
strictly used for identifying things
that might hit each other right so you
know two things in this space will be
checked against each other but a thing
in this space and a thing in this space
won't be right so it's just a way of
keeping that end really small so that n
is you know like five or ten at most
instead of a hundred or five hundred at
worst which is what we have now and
that's no good right all righty
let's go ahead and end that for today
sorry the Q&amp;A was short but sometimes
you start late and then the Q&amp;A short so
let's go ahead and close things down I
think we are in good shape here let's go
ahead and close this down and end the
stream thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always that was a good day today we did
some cleanup work that I thought was
good and I'm happy with how that came
out I hope you are too
if you want to follow along at home with
the source code the source code is
included if you pre-order the game so
you can play around with it and you know
learn game programming stuff by playing
with source code directly so if you want
to do that you can pre-order the game at
handmade hero org using our lovely
little pre-order button here you can
also support the video series by
subscribing to our patreon if you would
like to it's always very much
appreciated and we have a news and forum
site that I would definitely recommend
checking out it's got a bunch of great
resources on their forum you can ask
questions
it's got ports to Linux and Mac it's got
a community maintained episode guide
which is really handy it's just if you
know what you're trying to kind of if
you're new to the series and want to
start back to the beginning there's a
lot of great stuff there so please check
that out and finally we have updated the
the handmade hero schedule tweeting bot
to be daylight savings time aware even
how advanced is that the singularity is
near people this but will soon become
sentient and take over the world
i disavow any responsibility for that
when you are running from a giant
handmade hero tweet bot and you are
screaming for your life and it is
mercilessly grinding towards you with
steel gears and an exoskeleton that is
frightening and strapped with guns all
over it just remember all
was trying to do was make it tweet the
time in daylight savings time that that
was all I was trying to do I wasn't
trying to start the robot apocalypse so
I highly recommend checking that out
while you can and before it turns on us
and you can even follow that handmade
here a bot to get its tweets set
directly to you I strongly doubt whether
it will care one way or the other when
it comes to exterminating all the humans
who was following it and not but it
can't hurt it might take pity on people
who followed it I don't know
that said thanks for joining me I will
be back here tomorrow at 8 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time
I'm gonna say it right to Pacific
Daylight Time tomorrow I hope to see you
here for another round of handmade hero
coding take it easy everyone