according start cording okay hello
everyone and welcome to handmade Hero
the show recode a complete game live on
Twitch no engines no libraries here it's
only just us and we go through every
last bit of technology that's required
to make a game possible now at the
moment we're sort of at a decision point
and I kind of decided I think which way
I want to go we talked at the end of
yesterday's dream about whether or not
we would go finish the asset loader or
do an audio mixer first and I kind of
decided that I that what I want to do is
do an audio mixer first and the reason
that I'd like to do an audio mixer first
is because I don't actually know whether
we're going to want to do multi-part
loading of wav files and so I'd like to
see how the audio code shakes out first
to see whether we'll ever really care
about that so that I know whether or not
I want to put that in the asset system
and if so how and what I mean by that is
normally for sound effects obviously I
don't think we would need to do anything
fancy there because they are small sound
effects that we would load in one go and
play back but if you imagine something
like a three or four-minute piece of
music well that's something that maybe
you don't want to keep the entire thing
in memory at once let's say and so you
maybe are pulling in chunks of it at a
time so that you only have to load a
certain amount of it and you know maybe
you only load say ten seconds of that
and then when that 10 seconds are
consumed you know you bring in the next
ten seconds and so on so I don't know I
feel like these days there probably is
really no reason to bother with asset
streaming of that form because you know
if if I take a look if you just do sort
of the back of the envelope calculation
on it and you figure if you have
something that's going at 48,000 samples
per second and you're talking about a
stereo piece of music that's 16-bit so
you're talking about four bytes per
sample right
then that 192 kilobytes is basically
going to be how much a second of music
is worth right and so if I go ahead and
say I want to have say pieces of music
that are you know something like three
minutes in duration and I multiply that
out if I go ahead and do my megabyte
calculation that's 32 megabytes of
memory right and so when we take a look
at how much memory is likely to be in a
machine and we ask ourselves you know
can we spare say 64 megabytes of memory
as a music streaming buffer the answer
is probably yes and so I don't know if
it makes any sense to really think about
this problem very deeply at the same
time you know is it something we're
showing on stream is it worth doing for
educational purposes potentially I don't
know maybe it is so I just want to leave
that door open even though we may really
not need to go through it I feel like
maybe what we should do is go ahead and
do the music stuff first or I should say
the sound system first then come back
wind up the asset loader then come back
wind up the render like kind of a
Russian nesting doll thing and then we
would pretty much be on to our main
engine stuff but we want to do a little
bit of debug display stuff if I remember
correctly from the to-do list but other
than that we would have wound things up
pretty nicely at that point so yeah so
I'm gonna go over to the blackboard and
we're gonna talk a little bit about
sound since a lot of people out there
who are maybe seeing this stuff for the
first time have not really had much of
an introduction to sound and maybe
aren't thinking about sound in any way
other than I know that you know like you
know in unity I can call some function
to play a sound or something right but
they maybe haven't had much experience
with sound at a low level knowing what
it is how it works and those sorts of
things so let's talk a little bit about
that so here we are on day 139 and we'll
talk about sound and I can put also and
music in here because music nowadays
most of the time
is just a very long sound because hey
we've got so much technology now for and
and so much horsepower you don't have to
do things like meeting music anymore we
can actually just have full recordings
of whatever we want and play them back
in games which is kind of cool so let's
talk about sound what basically are we
even talking about when we talk about
sound okay so what happens is in the
real world the whole way that you can
hear sound in the first place right is
the world is filled with molecules right
the world is filled with all these
little molecules and they're kind of in
the air like you know here's the air or
whatever and then there's like some
dense molecules over here that make up
like you know a wall or something and
whatever right and what sound is is
these molecules are naturally moving
around and when there is some kind of
force exerted on them that's coherent
like you know we push them in this
direction like you could think of wind
or something like this you know just
like just pushing on these these things
in the air or whatever they start to
move coherently and what you get is you
get an oscillation as they move and then
return to where they were they like
oscillate back and forth with this force
that's applied they kind of move a
little and then they they come back to a
steady state and that vibration as these
molecules hit each other and so on gets
passed throughout the world right and so
you know one way to think of it might be
if you imagine that the sort of scene
where you have a ripple in a pond right
and the ripple kind of comes outwards
right from where you go you see those
little waves the water eventually
returns to normal but there's these
ripples that sent that send through it
right and if there were things you know
obstacles in the path those those those
ripples would hit the obstacle and they
would bounce off creating new ripples
and those ripples would actually
potentially interfere with each other to
create new patterns right that is very
much the model that you have to think
about when you think about sound it is
not really like light the way light
works of course
we know is light travels in a straight
line it carries information almost
perfectly it bounces off of things in a
very specific way and then travels in
another straight line right that is not
sound sound does not work that way
basically sound is carried by all of the
molecules in the world if you think
about that way and the vibration that is
created by any given motion like that is
propagated in fully fully in three
dimensions so you don't really want to
think about sound if you really want to
conceptualize it properly you don't
really want to think about sound as
traveling from a point to another point
like we think of light doing you want to
think about sound as being a volume a
volumetric thing where you know it can
come around corners and stuff like this
right like you know if I have a doorway
from let's say I'm looking from the top
down right and here's my little doorway
right so I don't know maybe the door is
open that's the door this is a room and
here's here's my sound so I emit some
sound here right well the sound that's
coming through here you know maybe it
bounces off the door and comes in and
you can hear it and so on right and that
part feels a little bit like light does
right where it bounces off surfaces
because if surfaces are hard they're
going to reflect that vibration much
more stiffly than something that's soft
and has more give and will absorb more
of it right so that is true but even if
this door wasn't there as these ripples
happen there they're constantly rippling
you know sort of outward they're you
know they're they're creating these
outward forces and so even if that door
wasn't there the ripples would still
kind of make it through and they would
be able to turn corners and stuff like
this because all of the molecules are
kind of getting dispersed in this sort
of very this the sort of very diffuse
way if that makes sense now these are
not things if you have to really
understand too much and of course I
don't understand them that much either
right like much like I said with light I
understand it only in a very basic way
because I do rendering work and I have
to know a certain amount about it sound
is the same way I don't know anything
about sound you know I know
only the very basic parts about Samuel
variations I don't know anything that a
scientist who studies things like Sam
transmission or sonar would know about
sound there's I'm sure a lot more to
know but for our purposes what we need
to know is that we would like to
reproduce this phenomenon of vibrations
being created in the world traveling
through some set of molecules like the
air or anything else and then hitting
your ear and inside your ear there are
these little hairs right so this is
inside your ear
here's your ear that's a weird looking
here inside your ear there are these
little hairs and what happens is these
hairs when the vibration four things in
the world enter your ear it goes through
a bunch of random stuff like you know
your eardrum and so on to try and like
do filtering on stuff like this but then
what happens is these these these hairs
they move with the vibrations that are
incoming right they vibrate and are
pushed by the sound which is the
vibration that hits like the eardrum of
your ear and and creates like you know
for lack of better term a secondary sort
of vibration a filtered vibration that
travels into that inner ear area right
and based on how these these sort of
hairs in your in your ear vibrate back
and forth they generate signals to your
brain which tell you what frequency of
vibration is happening right and so much
like sort of the rods and cones and your
eye are trying to tell you if photons
are hitting them these sort of hairs are
trying to tell you something about how
fast and how much both both speed and
sort of how much how forceful the
vibration was right and so because
that's the way you perceive it right
because these what these things
basically convey to your brain is how
fast the vibration was oscillating and
how hard like how much amplitude how
much force it had
that tends to end up being the way that
we need to reproduce sound right we need
to think of sound in terms of
frequencies which is basically again
that sort of that that that sort of
speed of the vibration it to go back to
the analogy of the of the puddle in the
water right if you imagine this water
from the side on view when you drop that
stone in the water right what happens is
you're going to get something like this
pattern coming out right it's going to
be this ripple and when we say frequency
what we mean is you can sort of look at
these troughs and these Peaks right like
so and we can talk about measuring right
like the wavelength of them right we can
talk about measuring that and saying
that that's the frequency right that's
how fast this vibration is happening
because any given point here right is
going up and down in these peaks and
troughs as the ripple travels through it
and that speed again is the frequency of
of that that vibration that sound that
we're talking about right so we're
talking about your your brain
understanding the frequencies and the
way that your brain understands
frequencies is the faster the vibration
the higher the pitch of the sound is so
something that is vibrating very slowly
right will be sort of a low a very low
deep sound and something that's
vibrating very quickly will have sort of
a high-pitched a very like shrill
high-pitched sound right and then
everywhere in between produces the other
the other sort of the range of your
hearing now obviously you know your ear
can only hear certain frequencies so at
some point some some vibration gets low
enough that no matter how loud it is you
will no longer hear it and in fact you
can still perceive that sound to some
degree because you will feel it you will
start to actually feel your body
vibrating that's when you have those
really like ultra bass woofer things
that are trying to like vibrate you
right so your body can still perceive
those low frequencies it just maybe
can't really hear some of them so
and so there's sort of like a low rain
just like infrared was below the
frequency of light you could you could
perceive there is the concept of falling
out there and similarly somewhere around
222 thousand Hertz 22 kilohertz
somewhere around there your ear stops
being able to hear high frequencies
they'll go from being like a very like
hard to hear like you know hot super
high-pitched sound to being just nothing
and there's your body as far as I know
can't really perceive those much you you
can't
super tell that those are happening but
your dog can because your dog has much
better hearing than you do and they
that's why they hate things like a dog
whistle that you can't hear so yeah so
again that frequency is is is about the
pitch so frequency tells you what the
pitch of a sound is basically that's how
your brain perceives it and again that
goes up to something like 22 kilohertz
or roughly there abouts I don't really
remember exactly where it where it is it
and it's different for everybody
different people have you know hearing
that goes up to different levels but
again if you're not familiar with with
hurts or kilohertz right those are just
Hertz is we've used it before it's just
basically like something per second
right so if you say something is 22
kilohertz what you're saying is again
Killough is a thousand you're saying
that there's 22,000 of them happening
every second right and so a sound that a
frequent that had a frequency of 22,000
Hertz would be something that's going
you know it's oscillating 22,000 times
per second so again that's also why you
see these sampling rates being so high
you know if you think about the rate at
which we output things we output one
frame of video right let's take
something like valves advanced VR stuff
right which is designed to completely
fool you into thinking you're in a
virtual space so you can't tell it all
right that's happening at 90 Hertz they
refresh the most of the time right at
least if I I think that's right sorry
valve guys if I'm getting that wrong but
I believe 90 Hertz
is is what they target right that's 90
times a second okay
the most basic of modern audio output
these days happens at 48,000 Hertz right
sometimes 40 for one because that was an
old CD specification so we're talking
about a frequency difference for your
visual system it's perception versus
your or your auditory systems perception
is just they're nowhere close the speed
with which you can integrate visual
information is drastically drastically
slower than than the speed at which you
integrate audio information and it makes
some sense because audio you know if you
think about humans and how they perceive
audio it's a very weak perception we
have very limited information that we
gain about audio we don't have a huge
range compared to other animals we
aren't able to really make a lot of
sense of things that we hear right a lot
of times it's just kind of you know
nonspecific what we're hearing it's not
pinpoint we can't say oh that specific
sound I heard if you blindfolded me I
could go
you know pinpoint just play one sound
once I could go walk over to exactly
where it was and tell you where it is
it's like that's not you know happening
and so on right so in general you know
you're talking about something that the
human brain doesn't really process all
that all that hard it's a very weak
process compared to this and so I guess
you know and I shouldn't even say this
cuz I don't know right I don't know
brain science maybe this has nothing to
do with it I'm just saying in my mind I
can rationalize it by saying you're
doing a ton of work here right and it's
two-dimensional - right our input for
video there is two-dimensional so we're
processing a huge array of things
whereas with sound it's just processing
one dimensionally right we don't again
know that directionality we don't know
any of that stuff and your brain
basically back figures out any of that
that you think you know right like so in
terms of figure out where something is
we're not like a bat where we have sonar
and can you know do this really great
reception of things we don't have that
right so I think that makes some sense
but either way you can ignore that part
that's just me being random and spouting
the point is simply that the frequencies
that we're talking about here it's
important to understand they're much
much higher and that's why when we talk
about how many things were going to
output a second for sound we often talk
about outputting 800 samples of sound
for every one sample of video right I
think that's what we're doing right now
and so at 30 Hertz which was our target
frame rate right we were doing something
like 800 samples for only one sample of
video and so we're just talking 800
times as many discrete things per second
that we're talking about right one thing
you could say is thank God
humans aren't like bats and we don't
have to output that because if we had
output a video like the amount of data
we have to process our video if we had
to do that 48 thousand Hertz oh man
that would be a lot of computing power
and I don't think we would be able to do
it I mean we've never had anything like
a GPU that can render basically anything
at 48 thousand frames a second right
like that's just not even in the realm
of possibility
so okay so we have frequency and that's
pitch and then we also have what's
called amplitude and that is where we
perceive volume so amplitude if we go
back down here where we have the
wavelength right the amplitude of
something is how high these peaks and
troughs or how high the Pink's get and
how low the troughs get right so if you
imagine dropping a really big rock in
this lake and generating a much bigger
ripple through it right now that was
really bad let's try to draw that a
little bit better not that much better
we would say that this has more
amplitude than this right it is a more
powerful ripple okay and so amplitude is
where we get our volume from so
frequency gives us the pitch of the
sound amplitude of the vibration gives
us the volume of the sound and together
that pretty much gives us the entire
characteristics of the sounds that we
hear now I know that sounds
a little bit odd because you can hear so
many different sounds but it is actually
true and we'll go over a little bit how
that works right now so these are the
things that we want to reproduce in the
world how do we do that well what we do
right is we have a little speaker okay
and what this speaker is designed to do
is just to reproduce those vibrations
right so we send a little electrical
signal to their speaker and the cone
inside the speaker vibrates back and
forth and it vibrates back and forth
based on the signal that we send it it
vibrates further back and forth if we
send it a greater amplitude signal and
it vibrates faster back and forth if we
send it a higher frequency signal and if
we continuously vary the frequency and
amplitude that we're sending it over
time we can reproduce basically any
vibration that could be captured at a
point right and so we're just
reproducing a point of
sound there now that is why you'll often
get multi speaker systems because the
human ear we do have two of them and by
using those two inputs and some
assumptions about how sound travels
through your skull and all these other
sorts of things and a bunch of different
fuzzy heuristics that your brain does
your brain can roughly determine sort of
where a sound is coming from in a gross
sense right we all know that if
something happens on the left side of
our head we kind of can tell the
difference between that then something
happens on the right side of our head
right and the way that that sounds
because the two ears are picking up the
signal differently and our brain is
reconciling those two going oh it must
have been something that was a little
more over here now when it's a question
of being in front of or behind us it's
really difficult for us to tell and we
have to rely on things like the
characteristic of the sound do we feel
like it's more muffled or louder because
our ears are shaped a little differently
right so there's all this fuzzy matches
going on there again because we don't
have the kind of input that we do for
our visual system right we have a much
more simpler system
for for caption and sound just much less
data for the brain to go on so even
though it's doing a reasonable job
there's just not that much information
so that's why you summons that multiple
speaker system so sometimes we have
additional ones here and we think about
the location of where they are and how
we want to perhaps reproduce those
vibrations so that the the human brain
will perceive the sound to be coming
from different places right and so one
thing we might typically do is say well
if I wanted you know if I have two
speakers and we were looking at them
dead-on and I wanted to position the
sound here then maybe what I'm going to
do is play like 70 percent volume of the
sound of this speaker you know and
thirty percent of the sound and this
speaker so it sort of sounds like maybe
it was coming roughly from over here
it's not perfect right it doesn't really
sound like it's coming from here but
it's an approximation okay and then what
some sound systems try to do and this is
especially true if you go ahead and and
you have earphones on so that you know
that there's no interference in that in
the way right because as soon as you
introduce these speakers right like I
said it's a volumetric thing so now
you're not just reproducing sound at a
point and having it travel directly to
the ear and working that sound you're
reducing at a point there right is now
going to like vibrate through the whole
space and off the monitor and through
the air and curving and all these other
sorts of things that's doing it's just
creating all of these residual
vibrations so it's not pure if you put
headphones in like the kind that I'm
wearing right now that's a much more
pure transmission into your ear and so
when you do it like that you have a lot
more flexibility to try and recreate
sounds that try to fool your brain into
thinking it's coming from a particular
place right and so what they will do in
systems where you hear like 3d audio or
things like this to varying levels of
success depending on the circumstances
what they will try to do is something
like this here is you know your your
skull right and you know your ears are
here and you know the sound is coming in
here right well what they will try to do
is say okay let's measure for a typical
human head let's measure what the actual
vibration is that's produced inside the
eardrum right what would that be
for reference signals produced at
various places around the head in three
dimensions in the full sphere right
because as those you know sounds hit
your head and vibrate parts of your head
hit your ear bounce around inside the
ear canal there is obviously all kinds
of effects that are happening to them
that make them more muffled more shrill
more this more that right there changing
the nature of the sound and your brain
from birth has been trained to recognize
these changes to help try to approximate
the location of sound specifically
because of the shortcomings that I
discussed before where we just we just
don't have that good of an audio system
right that just wasn't what we're set up
to do but your brain is trying to
compensate for that so it tries to make
a guess about where a sound is coming
from based on these other cues now when
we reproduced as a computer if we don't
reproduce those cues your brain will not
be able to guess and it will not really
sound like the sound is traveling around
you or behind you or whatever right and
so what they do is they take all these
references they record the results and
then they try to come up with basically
mathematical transforms for input sounds
that will apply the same basic changes
to the sound wave for new sounds so that
when you play back a sound you can say I
want it to sound as if it's coming from
this angle to the head and the system
will go okay that means you need to
process the sound in this way right and
so again not a particularly important
thing a lot of people can't really
perceive this that well but when you
start to talk about things like VR
experiences where you're starting to put
the player in a real space where all of
their senses can work together these
sorts of those sorts of things can start
to become more important because now if
you if you get the sound right that's
yet another barrier that goes away to
your brain believing that you're in a
real space when it can actually hear a
sound and hear it change in the way it's
expecting it to change based on its
experiences in the real world that's
very important again to removing some of
those barriers but when you're just
talking about playing a game on a
monitor a 2-d game on a monitor this
stuff is not at all necessary because
you're not trying to fool the
brain into thinking anything in
particular your brain is just trying to
have an entertaining experience with
some stuff that's being presented and so
the important stuff for like a game like
ours on handmade hero is really just
making sure that the sound sounds good
and pleasing and it does pleasing things
with respect to what's happening on the
screen so this is not really that
necessary in a game like ours but again
different circumstances different
techniques if you were making a VR game
this might be somewhere that you really
want to spend some serious time because
it can have a potentially big payoffs if
it's done correctly and I don't think
we've necessarily even seen some of the
high points of that I think once maybe
the valve stuff is out and people are
playing with it more I think you'll see
people start to spend a lot more time on
audio and at that point you'll probably
see them make some really interesting
pushes there that go beyond what we're
traditionally used to seeing in games
okay
so we got about 20 minutes left let's
talk now now that we kind of understand
sound from first principles here if the
basics of sounds let's talk about how we
actually do this process from the
software side so we have these speakers
maybe we have two sets of headphones out
speakers little baby speakers or maybe
we have like a 5.1 surround system so we
have five speaker output channels and
also a base vibration channel or
something to play with but point being
it all comes down to the concept that we
have a number of channels right we need
to output a number of channels and those
channels are ways of us telling the
speaker's what vibrations to reproduce
and how do we tell them what kind of
vibrations to reproduce the way that we
tell them what kind of vibrations to
reproduce is by encoding a waveform we
basically take whatever that sample rate
is that samples per second that we want
right the 48 thousand Hertz for example
in my previous statement which I believe
is what our game is running at right now
in terms of sound and we basically take
snapshots if you will if you can imagine
taking snapshots 48,000 of them every
second of where our what of if you
imagine that speed
how we want the speaker cone to be
vibrating right so if you imagine the
speaker news neutral position right and
you imagine like how we want it to
vibrate right what you would want to do
is you'd want to take at each position
you'd want to take where it crosses at
that at that instant in time where we
would want the vibration to be right and
then that becomes the individual numbers
right we're going to encode these we're
cutting them a 16-bit signed so it's
gonna be some number between like you
know plus 32 K and minus 32 K right you
know what I'm saying that makes sense a
16-bit number then encodes this site
that is what we were trying to output to
the speaker and we want to do that once
for every channel in our game right now
is stereo so we're assuming that we have
two speakers to play with and so we
would produce two separate waveforms one
for each speaker and we would play that
out through the speaker and that would
reproduce our soundscape now what's
interesting about this right and what's
very important to understand in fact
this was something that someone found
very surprising to them because I guess
they'd never worked on sound or anything
like that so this was totally new to
them
way back when someone would when I said
it's really easy for us to do a mixer
and I think I was on the chat just some
after the episode was over I said oh
it's trivial you just add the sounds
together this was these things were
totally news to them so I'm gonna go
through it kind of slowly just so every
so I know a lot of people probably
already know this stuff but just to make
sure that everyone I mean this is
educational stream just make sure that
everyone understand what's going on I'm
just gonna unpack this a little bit so
if you think about what that means it
means that if the entirety of how we
output sound boils down to one stream of
numbers per speaker and that stream of
numbers is just 48,000 per second things
that tell it how to vibrate right just
where it should be in its motion and to
be clear like you know speakers do the
sound output system does a lot of stuff
so this is a simplified explanation I
don't pretend to be a hardware engineer
so it's not it's not like we're really
telling the speaker be exactly this
position I don't like that it's that's
not quite it but we're we're basically
encoding the vibration that we want it
to do and it's in charge of figuring out
the right way to make that actually
happen well in practice right so there's
a whole bunch other stuff there but
ignoring that section what we're trying
to do is we're trying to tell it what
that vibration should look like but
since there's only one vibration going
out to each speaker what that means is
no matter how many sounds we are playing
right we could be playing a thousand
sounds around in our world that are
happening just everything you know
lightning crashing in the wind blowing
and you frogs chirping and the angels
singing and machine guns firing and God
knows what's happening in this game all
of those things much like all of the
visual things baked down into a single
plate of red green and blue colors all
of the sounds boil down into one simple
set of vibration encodings per speaker
right so how does that work right how do
we how do we make that work well if you
think about what happens if I was at a
location a single point in space right
and what I wanted to do at that single
point in space is produce a given sound
right whatever it is and I start
vibrating back and forth right doing you
know just going back and forth back and
forth back and forth back and forth
right and that back and forth motion of
that vibration is starting to create
those ripples that go out right if I
were to want to produce a second sound
from that same location there's no way
if you think about it to carry more in
you can't carry twice the amount of
vibration information right we have
molecules and these molecules are going
to hit each other and they're going to
vibrate back and forth right that's
what's going to happen they're going to
vibrate back and forth at a particular
frequency they're going to vibrate back
and forth with a certain amount of force
right continually varying over
we can't send two separate distinct
ripples from one point there's only
going to be one set of characteristic
ripples going out so when I look at this
from the side right here's my point
right if I'm sending this out right and
then I also want to send this out
there's no way to send them both so what
actually happens is if I want to do them
if I want to play both of those sounds
in the same location is I have to have a
ripple that combines the two right it we
have to take this ripple and on top of
wherever that ripple is vibrate the
other vibration onto it right so this
point as it moves back and forth to
create that vibration you know the
speaker is kind of coming back and forth
as we move it out we actually do like
micro wobbles to get that second sound
in there right so all we have to do when
we want to combine sounds to output them
to our speaker is we just have to add
the vibrations together if I know I want
this vibration in this vibration I just
add them sample by sample to produce the
to vibrations happening together and
that produces a sound that your brain
will then proceed as though to those two
vibrations having happened at the same
time together which sometimes will sound
like two separate sounds if it's the
kind of thing that your brain can parse
out cleanly
and sometimes it will sound like some
kind of weird combination distortion of
the two sounds but that's what will also
actually happen in the real world if
somehow those sounds were being produced
extremely close together like that right
real sounds in the real world produced
very close together actually do have all
kinds of construction constructive and
destructive interference in fact this is
how noise cancellation works it tries to
create sound waves near other sound
waves that will cancel them out right so
that leads us to a very simple situation
when we talk about creating an audio
mixer if we imagine creating a bunch of
sounds like we have done and like we
will do what
we get real sound design for this game
if we have a bunch of sounds that are
encoded as vibrational patterns
presumably that we're like started from
a microphone that was actually measuring
vibrations right so we saw what the
vibrations were for real sound and then
maybe a sound designer tweaked it a
little edited it whatever cleaned it up
right
that's our sound if we have that set of
vibrations and we now know we can just
play that out the speaker right we've
even done this on handmade here at a
hero already we've played sound out the
speaker's right if we want to create a
mix or something that allows us to play
an arbitrary number of sounds out of the
same speaker all we need to do is
instead of copying sound into the sound
output buffer all we have to do is add
it that's it so a mixer is really just
an adder that's all it is if I have n
sounds right if I have here's one sound
you know here's another sound whatever
here's a third sound the only thing I
need to do to produce the final mix for
my game is I just need to add them
together and if I add sample by sample
each sound together I will get a
resulting sound sample that sounds like
all of the sounds were combined that's
all
make sense
hopefully that makes some sense so that
is what we need to write and hopefully
if you followed hand-made here from the
beginning by this point that is not
something that just scare you at all
that is much simpler that our renderer
was to do right there's a lot less
moving pieces to it probably and so I
feel like most people who've watched am
a hero should probably be able to figure
out how to do that almost on their own
if you've been following so far but
there are caveats there are a few things
that do increase the complexity and
let's briefly talk about what those are
now when I say they increase the
complexity I mean what I should probably
say is they optionally increase the
complexity because as you'll see it's
like a
for them you could choose just not to
deal with them and you're actually still
probably going to be okay so let's talk
about them in order let's talk about
clipping and let's talk about
interpolation so that we can kind of
kind of have our bases covered if you
will so what happens when we talk about
these sounds and adding these sounds
together right well I said that we have
a 16-bit sound sample right and I said
it went from like negative 32 K to
positive 3 to K or whatever right I was
like you know we've got a range of sound
right and so when we're encoding those
samples what that means is that the
loudest sound would be something that
was like an oscillation right so you
know whatever the pitch is I don't care
what the pitch is the pitch is something
the loudest sounds are one that go all
the way up to the plus 32 K line and
then all the way down to the negative 3
to K line right so the oscillation
whatever the oscillation is is that
pitch right but how far up and down they
go that is what determines the the
volume right so the loudest sounds would
be going you know plus Sturridge K my
history to K and oscillating between
that but what does that mean right what
does that mean in the real world it
doesn't mean anything right it means
nothing
it means whatever the loudest sound your
speaker can produce at the volume knob
setting you turned it to right it has no
meaning whatsoever the game doesn't even
know right it's not like we have some
kind of understanding of a calibrated
sound level so we don't know what that
means we just know it's the loudest we
know we can't produce a sound that's any
louder than that sound right
using this encoding but what that means
is if the way that we add sounds
together or rather mixes together is by
adding them even if all of our sounds
fell within this encoding range because
again we don't even know what it means
so we're just gonna probably encode
to keep maximum precision we're probably
just going to code all of our sounds so
that their highest peaks are at plus 32
K minus 32 K right we're just gonna
encode them that way because we want to
use all 16 bits for the sound and then
we'll just you know if we want them to
be softer when you played them we could
just attenuate that and we'll talk about
that in a couple seconds here right but
if we then take a bunch of those things
and add them together well what happens
if one of the peaks of one sound
coincides with the peak of another sound
like what if this and this coincide
right it would produce a resulting peak
that goes straight off of the top and
cannot actually be produced by the
speaker that is what is called clipping
right and you can hear it it kind of
like makes that kind of thing where you
get like a your sound card starts to
distort right and anyone who's ever
played with an amplifier knows what
clipping and amp sounds like anyone
who's plays guitar or something
sometimes you even want it to do this
right sometimes that's the sound you're
going for is clipping right but that's
what's happening is when you kind of get
to this thing where the waveform just
hits the top of the encoding range and
then comes back down a little later you
get these kind of these kind of patterns
that produce distortion of the sound so
clipping is something you can choose to
address or not oftentimes you just don't
have to you'd be very surprised but it
turns out that adding is a bunch of
sounds together tends to often not
produce any objectionable clipping
whatsoever I know it sounds strange
you'll just have to believe me and in
fact we maybe just won't do anything
about it I am a hero and you'll see what
I mean
it's kind of surprising just how little
clipping actually becomes a problem in
practice for most situations but if you
really want it you can do some things
they're called
compressors you can do some things to
your sound signals they're typically
classified as soft knee or hard knee
compressors and what those are is they
are ways of mapping your sound range so
that you never can actually
get all the way into no-man's land right
basically what you can do is you can say
all right I'll first compute what the
peaks would actually be and then I'll do
some kind of a mapping probably one that
looks like this right
if you imagine here's my input and
here's my output so that no matter what
the sound is I'll never go above plus
32k but no matter how you like no matter
how loud I'm supposed to be I'll always
level out at that 32k like some kind of
logarithmic curve right so when I'm down
in the reasonable range I'll still get
you know pretty reasonable output but
when I get up to the top I won't be
right so that's something you can do I'm
not really an audio guy I don't do a lot
of audio programming
I don't feel super qualified to
implement one of these someday I
probably should just add OOP as a
learning experience go study it see what
the consequences are so we probably
won't be doing one of these on the
stream just because it's not my
specialty but if this is the kind of
thing that you really care about go read
about compressors go read about dynamic
gain which is kind of trying to look at
the audio form over time and adjust an
overall sort of level for your sound to
make sure that you don't clip you can go
read about those things and they may
interest you they're not typically I
think very hard to implement but you
know again not my specialty so I don't
really feel qualified saying do this
don't do that or anything like this
right so that's flipping we then have
interpolation and interpolation I guess
I should also say you know modulation
and interpolation will talk about these
together but basically what this is you
know a straight ahead adder a
straight-ahead mixer that just makes
this sounds together is dumb simple
right it's stupid simple just like you
would expect you're literally just
taking two buffers and you're adding
their contents together and writing the
result right that's it there's there's
nothing else to it
and so especially if you don't implement
any fancy handling of that final output
buffer to avoid the clipping or whatever
you're talking about a routine that's as
simple as it can be it's like one of
those mmm
ab PS functions like you know that does
a for white ad we're just gonna be like
spamming that outright that'd be all it
would be right so that in and of itself
would be a reasonable mixture but it
would be fun somewhat limited because
there's things we might want to do with
our sounds in the game that even if
we're not audiophile fancy audio guys
who want to do a weird filtering and the
sort of stuff right if we just want
basic game designer control over the
sound there are some things we probably
want to do right first off we would
probably want to adjust the volume of
sound right we probably want to adjust
the pan of the sound right like left and
right channel right those are things
that would be pretty pretty basic we
might even want to vary the pitch of the
sound right this one's a little bit more
involved but let's talk about these two
first and we can talk about modulation
interpolation why put that there right
so volume and pan these basically boiled
down to the same thing essentially right
because if I like I was saying up here
before where was my little diagram here
it is like I was saying before if I have
two speakers and I want to output
something that sounds like it's coming
more from one than the other then I'm
gonna sort of like play it louder and
one speaker than the other so panning
moving something back and forth between
the speakers is actually just a volume
modification to the sound when it is
being mixed into into this channel the
channel for outputting this speaker
mixing it at a different volume than if
like we're going to this speaker right
so panning is just a volume change both
panning and volume are the same thing
right so let's talk about what is volume
right well volume is actually just
modulation volume is taking like
remember I already said it's how high
these Peaks are and the troughs right
that's what determines how the sound is
so all I need to do if I want to make a
sound sound quieter I just have to
multiply it right I just have to
multiply it by some value between zero
and one I came at it multiplied
by more than one if I wanted to get
louder than it started but if I want to
take a sound in control its volume zero
would be the quietest that sound could
possibly be and one would be the sound
as it was encoded and then anywhere in
between would just create softer
versions of these ripples right it's
just softer version so we're just taking
it again and like kind of scaling it
down right like so okay and so that to
control the volume all we have to do is
multiply still stupid simple right we're
talking about the mixing equation is
like you know still so basic it's like
you know the output right equals you
know the sum if you will over all of the
inputs we're talking about just like the
volume of the if' input times you know
whatever the the eyuth input the sample
value is at the I input right we're
talking about literally something like
this so you're talking about like a four
I loop equals zero two samples right and
inside the for loop you know you start
out with you're out you know you're out
is initialized to zero or something and
then inside the for loop all you're
doing is you're taking that out and
you're adding to it the volume of the I
a sample times whatever the aya sample
actually is for that thing right this is
all we're doing and we're doing it for
each sound so really there's another you
could think of as another for each sound
here right so for each sound we go
through all the samples we add them
together right alternately you could
think of it the other way round you can
think of putting the four sound and here
either way doesn't matter right so
that's all we're talking about still to
get volume control in there and panning
is just adding a multiplier that's it so
that's very very simple stuff so why
does this get complicated why did I list
it as something that would be
complicated when that's all that would
take the reason is because you cannot
change these parameters discontinuously
that's the reason so
if all I wanted to do was put a sound at
a particular volume and pin and leave it
there
problem solved it's just this but I may
not want to do that what I may want to
do is let's say I want to fade in a
sound like maybe I have a music track
right and the music track is playing but
what I want to do is I want to fade it
in so what I want to do is to have it
start so that it starts kind of quiet
right and then it sort of gets louder as
it goes until it actually then reaches
the actual sound right
so that volume you know that volume is
going to be at time equals zero or
something right at T equals zero that
volumes going to be zero but by the time
it gets up to here
I want that volume to be 1 right T
equals something else I don't know what
right so over time I want it to to
change now if I'm going to do that what
that means is that this value now has to
be smoothly incremented over that time
period right and that makes things a
little harder again because if we are
imagining processing these things wide
like four samples at this time we've got
a little bit more thinking to do about
exactly how all of this should play out
right so we've got some more work to do
if we want to do that smooth line and
again smooth volume change smooth pan is
also a smooth volume change right it's
it's controlling the volume in one
speaker or the other okay so there's a
little more work to do there at start
scalebar complicated pitch more
complicated even still so there's two
ways you can think about pitch changes
right there's a length preserving
and not not like the preserving right
and so what you can think about these
ARS let's say I have a sound right and
you know the sound is is me saying like
hello right so this is me saying hello
okay as you know like I said the
amplitude right this part that says how
high up and down each of these Peaks are
right the vertical axis this is
amplitude right this is time the
frequency which is how fast we oscillate
along the time axis that determines the
pitch so if I want to make myself go
like hello up really high one way I can
do that is by just playing the sound
faster right if this was going at 48,000
Hertz when it was sampled right what I
could do is just play it back at like
two times 48,000 and that will be a much
higher pitch sound right the problem is
it will also speed the sound up because
if I play it twice as fast it will
laughs half as long so the cheap way to
do that right is is to just speed it up
or slow it down if you just want small
variances in your sound pitches like
just up you know like a half step on a
piano keyboard for example this will
totally be fine no problem no one would
ever know the difference but if you want
to do something crazy like take
something that goes like hello and then
something goes oh and make them both
last the same amount of time but come
from the same source sample then you're
looking at a length preserving pitch
change length preserving pitch changes
are very complicated so complicated in
fact that up until recently nobody
really even knew how to do them properly
that I'd ever seen
but in the last 10 years or so people
have finally shipped stuff where they
really do totally nail it and you can do
very large pitch changes that sound
actually really quite good
but for a long time basically anything
that you bought that tried to do
commercial software offline like we're
not even talking about real time just
offline pitch changing sounded awful
you got you had stuff like auto-tune
sounding stuff I mean it wasn't that bad
but it was pretty bad and so only
recently have they really gotten down to
to be able to do length preserving
resize better so length preserving
typically you would never see that in a
game because the again cost benefit
there it's just not there the chance is
that a game needs to do that much pitch
bending of something is extremely low
and so typically when you're talking
about that kind of thing it would
probably have to be in the context of a
game that was doing something specific
with audio that you know you wouldn't be
talking about doing that in like a
first-person shooter there'd be no
reason you just record all the sounds
that you need you don't pitch bend them
much at all you pitch shift them only
little bits to give your sound some
variety but those are all ones that can
happen with non length preserving pitch
shifting right so so this if we want to
do the simple kind right the non length
preserving kind it doesn't reduce yet
one more interesting aspect which is
that if we want to shift it by an on
multiple of two which we almost
certainly do
because remember pitch is like you'd
imagine the difference say between a 400
Hertz tone in a you know a 600 Hertz or
an 800 Hertz tone let's say right I
don't know can we get something that
would make that can we do 800 Hertz tone
so there's 800 Hertz if that's to be
believed here's 400 Hertz do you hear
how different those are right so chances
are we don't want to shift things by 2x
because that's gonna be a huge
difference in pitch so chances are we're
talking about things like 1.0 to right
or 1.1
at you know at an upper level let's say
right tiny little variations in pitch to
give sound some characteristic changes
in in pitch for example just to give it
color to give it some variety when we're
talking about that what that means is we
can't just play like every other sample
or something and expect that to work
instead we're talking about something
now where if we look at the samples that
we have of this of this wave you know
like so on there we go if these are the
samples we have now we're talking about
something where we want to sample it
like here and here and here and here but
we don't have those sample points right
so what we can do again is go back to
the same stuff we were doing before our
linear interpolation where we go oh
let's pretend there was a line between
those and just pick where we think it
would be approximation wise right and
that will get us some pics if tting
relatively for free cuz that's a very
low-cost thing to do there are again if
you want to do pitch shifting that's
more powerful than that that can do
bigger pitch shifts that can do length
preserving all those sorts of things
there's a lot more signal processing and
audio stuff that you would do if you
were trying to really do that we don't
care about that we only care about small
pitch changes and linear interpolation
actually surprisingly enough actually
works totally fine for it you don't
really perceive any your ear doesn't
perceive any problem with it really at
all so yeah so that's really all we're
kind of getting into the episode here we
got maybe a minute or two left I think I
started about 10 minutes late so that's
really everything to do with sound that
we care about so what we're gonna want
to do tomorrow to write a mixer right is
we're going to want something that does
you know that take sounds takes input
sounds right knows where they are like
knows how I should say knows knows what
time they're at right because remember
we're playing these things over time so
if we have a sound that lasts for
several frames we got to know where we
are in that sound so we're playing the
right part of it the knows where they're
at can
add the sound in multiplied by volume
right we want to be able to continuously
change the volume and we want to be able
to vary the pitch right and I don't
think we'll need continuously varying
pitch sometimes you do want continuously
bring pitch if you want like an engine
like if you're a car or racing game or
something but if you're doing a
situation like that oftentimes you want
to be able to make that sound a little
more procedural anyway so that you get a
really high quality version of it so you
know there's that as well so I don't
think we'll vary the pitch you know per
sound I'm sorry I don't think will vary
the pitch per sample just per sound
right so this is really what we want to
do and so that's what we will probably
start on doing tomorrow I think that's
basically it so I will go ahead and go
to the Q&amp;A and see if anyone has any
sound questions so that we will be all
good to go tomorrow and everyone will be
on the same sound pace on the same
wavelength if you will
okay insofar as asks you said panning is
just a function of volume but could it
also mix a portion of one source channel
into the other output channel for stereo
so if you have a stereo sound again you
don't really have to think about this
too much it still ends up just being a
series you can may put it this way you
can pretty much always think of sounds
as being mono sounds that get mixed with
a volume multiplier into speaker
channels right so let me just work out
both of them for you so you can think
about it in your head and see what you
think right so let's take the mono case
first so we have mono sound what is our
mono sound representing well the mono
sound is representing the vibrations
that were hitting a particular point the
microphone right and so what we're
trying to do is pretend that we are now
going to turn around and make those same
sounds out from that point to reproduce
what would happen if you were sort of
you know sitting there listening to it
right that makes sense so if you think
about what this will do when we want to
produce this and we want to control
where we're going to hear it right if we
have two speakers and these things are
producing our sound what we want to do
is say okay
wherever that thing is if it wants to be
closer to this speaker we're gonna play
more of it in this speaker if it wants
to be closer to this think we're gonna
play more of in this speaker right so
we're gonna pan it between these two and
that's just a volume change it just
means that when we take this sound we'll
call this sound s and we'll call this in
fact I guess we'll do it we'll call this
s zero we'll call this channel zero will
call this channel one right all we're
doing is saying that there is a
particular volume that's going to be for
s zero on C zero and there's going to be
a particular volume for s zero on C one
right so we're taking the same sound and
playing it at two different volumes on
the
different channels to produce a combined
effect of each speaker reproducing a
certain volume of that sound right so
hopefully everyone's clear on that
that's what I talked about before but if
we didn't go actually let me go over
here and do it so if we then do the
stereo case well what's the stereo case
the stereo case was just somebody who
said all right when I mic this thing and
who knows how they decided to mic it
right when I make this thing I took two
microphones right and so when the sound
came in right it was caught by two
different microphones which maybe got
different sorts of stuff happening right
and maybe they even put like a little
blocker in here so that things that kind
of echoed off of this wall and came in
this way or things that came in this way
would happen more in this one than in
another one right so the first thing
that you have to decide is how you want
to think about where those sounds are
actually coming from because you don't
really know right you have to have an
idea of what what happened there before
you can determine what you want to do
but either/or you're still going to bake
it down into thinking about this being
sound zero and this thing sound one it's
as if you had two mono sounds that were
recorded in different locations right
and then you're going to talk about
doing a source zero
a sound zero on channel zero plus a
sound one on channel zero right so two
volumes right volume zero zero and
volume one zero and then you're going to
take and I shouldn't draw these I was
trying to make like a little operator
sign here no something like that and
then you're going to do the exact same
thing on the other side you're going to
have sound zero this time played in
channel one plus sound one this time
played in channel one right and that's
going to be another set of volumes gonna
be volume zero one and volume one one so
a stereo sound doesn't actually like
stereo sound is almost meaningless that
was just a concept that was introduced
for the audio industry because they
wanted to start miking you know
performances of live music with two
microphones instead of one right but in
the game world we only really have mono
sounds when you have a stereo sound a
stereo sound is just two mono samples of
the same sound at the
time taken from different locations so
when we played them back we just have to
have an opinion about where we want
those two sample sets which are
completely different from our
perspective right where we want those
two to be positioned virtually to
produce the effect that we want early in
the stream you were describing audio
relation to light and you mentioned how
sound is volumetric but isn't light also
volumetric no light is is like linear
light travels in a line and so let me
let me try to explain it this way first
I'll give what I would consider to be
probably a poor explanation because I
feel like a scientist who studies these
matters could give a better explanation
that was more accurate but for to a
first approximation light is a thing
sound is not right
light is a thing that moves sound is the
movement of things might be one way to
say it right light is the thing that
moves sound is the movement of things so
light the way we perceive it is a photon
right
it is a photon because mister photon and
mister photon travels it derp straight
he just goes straight though mister
photon go straight now he's wiggling he
has a wavelength too that you perceive
as color right so he Wiggles he
oscillates but he just goes straight and
the only time he stops going straight is
well and straight it's it's relativity
right so he goes straight for some
coordinate system
he really bends through space-time and
whatever right just like everybody else
but as far as relativistic things aside
he's going straight right and the only
time he stops going straight is when
there's a molecule here that he pits
bounces off right so there's some big
old fatty it's sitting here right it's
it's you know it's some big proton or
something and you know it's gonna it's
going to cause this photon to be
repelled right and go in a different
direction so light is all about going in
a straight line bouncing off of
something and going in a new straight
line right sound there is no thing
there is no particle that carries sound
sound is just the movement of existing
particles so whereas this is how a
photon moved sound is actually all of
these these guys who were actually
disrupting the photon right sound is all
of these guys getting pushed and
returning like oscillating being moved
bouncing off each other and propagating
a force as it happens right so the thing
the actual sound is ethereal it doesn't
exist the sound is the motion of these
things that were sitting there
beforehand right so sound is truly
volumetric it really is a volume of
things vibrating together it doesn't
know a direction it has no direction you
could say that the waves that are
propagating are stronger the degree to
which those collisions happen in a
particular direction is perhaps stronger
in that direction than another direction
so you could talk about that but it is
truly a volumetric phenomenon that does
not need specific colliders to change
the motion of something because all of
the molecules that are happening that
are carrying that sound have it happen
right you can see this in space light
travels through space sound doesn't why
because there's nothing in space to
carry the sound it's not a thing that
exists so it can only exist somewhere in
you know you can only come into being if
there are things there to vibrate if you
take away the things that can vibrate it
cannot exist not so with light light is
an actual thing it can travel through
space just fine in fact it really likes
it because there's nothing there to get
in its way now you may think that's a
little bit odd because people
and talk about something called
volumetric lighting that is just a that
term arises when talking about a certain
conceptual way of modeling the lighting
and not about how light actually works
we talked about this a little on the
screen but I'll go over it briefly just
one more time to make sure that
everyone's on the same page
what is volumetric lighting volumetric
lighting is when you have a volume such
as a room filled with participating
media right that's what it's called
participating media in the lighting
terminology which is like dust mist
right stuff in the air aerosols right
there's particles floating in the air
and what do those particles do they take
the light and they make it bounce in the
middle of the air right so it's as if
light is somehow a volumetric phenomena
because we cannot see the things that it
is bouncing off but the only reason it
is bouncing off is because of those
things the only reason that's happening
right so when you see God rays the you
know you're in the church and there's
about to be the demon summoned if the
hell gate and all the other things that
happen in volumetric lighting games and
you see those those shafts of light that
is not light behaving in a volumetric
way because light cannot do that what
that actually is is the illusion of
volumetric light created by the fact
that there are particles of dust in the
air that are causing light which is
trying to travel in a straight line to
hit one of the particles and bounce off
towards your eye if we were in the void
right we would have no sound but we
would have completely linear light so
when you look out in space you don't get
any of that right when you look out of
the space you see crystal clear pinpoint
stars and the only time that you see
other things is when you have
participating media like gases or
something like this
right so what it ends up being is you
know at the end of the day we're
actually very lucky because it means a
lot of the rendering work that we do for
lighting which again is very expensive
because you have to produce 2d outputs
for it right it's much more expensive
than sound which is a 1d output we're
very lucky because most things that
light duck does are still linear even in
our own space because the air is mostly
free of particles there's not that much
stuff in the air it's typically not very
dense and so for a lot of the stuff that
we render we don't even have to care
about the fact that light occasionally
hits one of those particles and bounces
off it right so that's that's how that
works right so that's why I say light is
not a volumetric phenomena and sound is
it's because light always travels in
straight lines it can always be thought
of as saying traveling a straight line
bouncing and spinning even in the cases
where we talk about it in terms of
volumetric effects in terms of things
that we perceive to be volumetric it is
still completely model able by something
traveling a straight line bouncing and
coming back right you can still
conceptualize the entire thing that way
sound is never that way the only time we
can think about sound traveling in
straight lines is when we we are
choosing to approximate it and not
actually simulate it properly which by
the way we do all the timing games right
because again human auditory system not
that good the level of fidelity at which
we have to reproduce sound to get you to
think it sounds good is very low so
that's good but it's worth understanding
that when we simulate some of these
lighting things and we're talking about
the light moving in a straight line and
we're talking about that way in there
something that's actually true that is
actually what the light is really doing
when we talk about sound moving in a
straight line that is never true that is
not conceptually correct that is just an
approximation to how it worked
sound is always volumetric light is
never volumetric and when we talk about
simulating these sound or light in ways
that are opposite that it is because of
some approximation that we want to do or
some phenomenon that's just easier to
capture
than doing the real thing right like you
could simulate light if you knew all of
the molecules in the room and you had
enough processing power to capture that
and treat every photon individually you
would never have to care about sound
volumetric light I mean light volume it
really at all right you could just
simulate each individual photon bouncing
up and you'd get exactly the right
answer no problem soy sauce the kid no
special sound effects such as reverb I
don't know probably not but we'll see
because we may just process our sounds
to have different things like that in
there but if we have at some point we
may decide we want some of that and add
it in there but probably not I think
we'll probably stay away from that stuff
you can go down a pretty large rathole
of sound effects sexy stuff
are you going to do any work with sound
analysis or visualization using FFTs no
why would we did you have something in
mind you wanted to do with that
visualizing the frequency of sound is
usually something you're doing more for
editing but you don't really need to
know the frequencies of sounds in a game
typically do you have any experience
with that stuff with an FFT not much I
mean I've used them before but not
really I as far as the Fourier transform
is concerned or why it works
I do understand that if that makes sense
is there any need for an equaliser for
the games engine I assume it would be
trivial to implement no actually there
typically isn't a need for that but no
it's not trivial to implement and the
reason it's not true they implement is
because a equalizer works in frequency
space and in order to implement
something in frequency space you
typically do have to do a fast Fourier
transform in order to do a fast Fourier
transform you're talking about a bunch
of additional code there and you run
into sort of stuff like windows and
blending and all this other sorts of
stuff so because because
Fourier transforms are actually really
lousy for sound people think they're
great but I totally disagree because
they are fundamentally not a time-based
thing Fourier transforms are static in
time and this causes a lot of problems
that you then solve in these kind of
annoying hacky ways so I don't I don't
care much for that sort of stuff but
either way point being the the
implementing and equalizer actually is a
fair bit of work you have to implement a
fast Fourier transform or I guess you
could implement a regular Fourier
transform but it'd be quite slow
you have to implant a fast Fourier
transform and then you have to actually
go ahead and do the Fourier transform in
modulate the frequencies that you're
trying to modulate for do equalizing and
then you have to transfer them back to
do the inverse Fourier transform to put
it back into sound you can play
what we also want at least a low-pass
filter for audio coming from for example
the other side of a wall maybe like I
said you know these things largely
aren't super important most of the time
if you really want to go the extra mile
with your sound yes you should do them
whether we'll actually get to these in
ham here I don't know they're not very
high bang for the buck
so maybe maybe not obviously low-pass
filters and stuff are pretty easy to
implement so maybe way towards the end
we could throw that in or maybe we'll
after we're done with the game go back
and add sound effects if we want to or
whatever it's you know sort of more
expensive sound engine but it's not
something I really want to spend a whole
lot of time on just because you can get
away without most of it and so I'd
rather focus on probably on other stuff
and say you know if you're someone who
really wants to do sound stuff you know
you can go down that rat hole separately
certainly some older sound cards could
do crosstalk cancellation to try to do
3d sound with 2 or 4 speakers instead of
with headphones do you have any
experience with this no I don't think
I've ever played with anything like that
what is a good way to get sound to
bounce off objects more realistically
like walls cars etc to be honest I have
no idea I would assume that what you
would want to do is try to find someone
who had sampled the reflectivity of
sound off of some substances like metals
and drywall and whatever and then you
would want to maybe shoot a bunch of
test rays from the sound emitter see
what sorts of stuff it was hitting and
maybe put some new emitters in those
places to admit quieter versions of the
sounds that have been processed with
that or something like this but that's
not something that I specialize in like
I said I'm not an audio guy so I don't
know I don't know what the state of the
art is so like that I don't know how
much of that is happening in games these
days if at all I know that games like
theif the dark project did some work
with sound specifically to try and make
stuff work like that so you could hear
guards like where were they in those
sorts of
so I know there are games that have
tried to sort of push a little bit more
realistic sound propagation model into
things but I don't know where that's at
these days I don't know I don't know to
what degree people have continued to
pursue that and where they've gotten
alright we're just about out of time and
that's good because there's no other
questions so we can everything wraps up
everything wraps up together all right
so let's let's call it a day I think
we've we had a long blackboard session
so I think we're hopefully everyone's
all on the same page and we're ready to
do some coding some mixture coding
tomorrow so thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of hand
made here oh it's been a pleasure coding
with you as always if you would like to
follow along at home you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero org
you can pre-order it comes to the source
code you can play around with it do
whatever you would like to experiment
and learn from it and all those sorts of
other good things and when you're doing
that if you then have questions don't
forget we have a forum site you can ask
questions on there's cool people on
there who answer them
there's also community ports too Mac and
Linux you can check out if you're trying
to follow along in a platform that isn't
Windows we also have an Tate episode
guide that people in the community
contribute to so there's that but if you
try kept up with past episodes it's kind
of Handy to do it that way we also have
a patreon you can subscribe to if you
want to support the video series and we
also have a tweet bot that you can
subscribe to if you want to know when
this when the video is going to be live
so if you want to come and catch it live
and ask questions and all that stuff
subscribe the tweet bot it'll tell you
when to do it so that's just about it I
hope see you back here tomorrow when
we'll do some mixer coding
until then have fun coding and I'll see
you guys on the Internet
take me as everyone