start recording hello everyone and
welcome to hand made here of the code
the code where we I was not trying to
forget how to reflux as least as I said
the wrong where to first see if I could
be written the code where we stream a
complete game live okay I can't even do
it forget it we'll start over again
welcome to him make sure the stream
where we code a complete game live here
on Twitch which showed us some ads
earlier what are you gonna do I guess
they have to make money somehow
hopefully you've paid for some kind of a
twitch turbo or something like that
whatever it was that I paid for it that
made me not see ads otherwise you got
some nice ads in there and what are you
gonna do about it that's that's just the
way of the internet anyway today we are
going to be working on the entity system
now which will actually sort of be an
actual entity system we've gotten to
that point where it's time to sort of
make it a real thing and it went over
yesterday my harebrained scheme for how
I was going to try that and you can't
stop me it's my code and if I want to do
something crazy I'm gonna do it and so
that's what's about to happen so you
know buckle up and and quiet down so
today is day 278 and and I am going to
be working so the code base you should
start with this day 277 if you want to
play along at home with your own very
own self and and so on and so forth so
here is where we're at in the code base
right now we have these this concept of
a simulation region and this dates way
back from when we start first started
playing around with how we were going to
handle infinitely large worlds
effectively because I wanted to be able
to use floating point values not doubles
because a you know we still might at
some point want to do this on a platform
that doesn't super support doubles very
well like a Raspberry Pi which didn't
have them chances are you know maybe we
could get away with that I don't know
because they Rev the Raspberry Pi
periodically so you know when we finally
get to doing something like that you
know maybe it'd be fine who knows but I
wanted to avoid that for two reasons one
because we don't really know if we'll
always have
two fast doubles and the other one is
that I wanted to show how you could
think about these sorts of problems in a
way that guarantees precision without
relying on the CPU to have to save your
bacon meaning if you actually want to do
all your math in a way that guarantees
that its robust without having a
sacrifice being able to have really
really giant worlds how might you do
that and so we sort of wanted to look at
that cuz it's a more cut it's a more
intricate a problem to try and solve and
I'm actually relatively pleased so far
with the way that we solved this problem
but I feel like we can take it a lot
further now that we're gonna start
thinking about this part of you know the
actual game code stuff more seriously I
feel like we can take this a little bit
further and it was always sort of
something that was in you know kind of
in the back of our minds when we were
working on this I can't remember what it
was handmade world I guess right I like
that we left these introspection things
from that time I did the introspection
stream anyway so if you take a look at
how our sort of architecture that we
built at the beginning just for playing
around worked it's actually kind of very
harmonious I think now when we want to
come back here and finally kind of get
everything into what you might call a
proper entity simulation architecture
and that is we sort of have this notion
of a world position here and a world
position has these sort of chunk up
things on it and has an offset inside
the chunk and then we've got these world
entity blocks and these are things that
just store a bunch of entities which
ones are in that block and then we've
got this sort of concept of a world and
the world you know you can query and say
give me back you know this this for this
region what are all the chunks that are
involved so that I can decompress them
right blah blah blah and so the way that
we worked with our sim entity stuff is
we say okay let's begin simulation of a
region it will go and it pulls out all
of the entities that it seems reference
in the area now this was a double sort
of indirect system the way that it was
working before and the way that that
happened if you if you recall is when
you look at the world mode I believe we
moved it out to world mode subsequently
when you look at the world mode we kind
of had this idea that there's just this
John
table of entities that's all the
entities that exist in the world we're
sitting there right and that's fine for
what we were doing but you know I don't
really love that and it's also kind of
stupid it's like this weird constant
that's in there and it's not it's not
fabulous and so what I want to try and
do is something a little more brazen
right and I want to say look what if we
just can't ever talk about entities in
the absolute sense other than by their
ID and you can't actually look up
necessarily an item by its ID in that
way okay and this is a little weird like
I said there's a lot of really crazy
off-the-wall things that I'm doing in
this entity system because I can and you
know some of them may work some of them
won't work that's okay so anyway here on
date 278 what I want to talk about here
is so the way this thing was working is
you know we have this simulation region
and it had like an apron around it too
and we sort of pulled in all the
entities that were related to this
region but it doesn't really matter
about that part of it so much what we
really care about is there is some box
and we query that box and we get all of
the entities that were in that box out
right and what we do is we were sort of
saying well there's this there's this
store there's this flat array that's you
know we were calling the low-fidelity
entities or whatever and then what we
were doing is using this box as the
query region we were pulling out like
whoever the people were who were in
there and we were moving them over into
the sim region right and the sim region
is a smaller set but with bigger
entities in theory we never really did
that part but that was kind of what we
were thinking right and so what I want
to do or at least want to try to do
until I determined that it's crazy is I
want to just get rid of this entirely so
what I'd like to do is say there is no
more low na storage at all there is only
the sim region they use the giant sparse
entity concept that I introduced
yesterday that I'm going to try for
entities that's all there is that's it
and then what happens is when you go to
right out these things they are stored
directly in the world chunks so if this
region is broken up I mean who knows how
many world chunks are overlapped here
but let's say there are some world
chunks overlapped like this kind of a
thing right let's say there are four of
them or something like this if we wanted
to work it out this way for example if
there were four world chunks then all of
the entities that were in you know this
region would get stored into this world
chunk actually stored in the world trunk
so instead of it being a just in the
world entity block instead of that world
block storing indices into the low
entity table we actually just packed the
entities and they are written out in
there right so basically like we open up
the entity block we write out all the
things into it we close the entity block
and we're done
that's how we store the entities right
and and then when we want to pull them
in again we open up the entity block we
read them all out and we're in there we
are okay
this is basically just like a streaming
system right we stream it in you modify
it we stream it back out again and we
don't care because of the way that I'll
end up writing it in terms of being sort
of chunked right because it's already
we've already written it that way right
so imagine this now instead of being a
set of indices imagine this is just a
block of data that's like however big we
want a world chunk to be let's say 64 K
or something right we just stream as
much as we can and then when we get to
the end we use another block if we need
to right so when we stream in all those
rocks are blocks are considered freed
when we stream out we pull those blocks
back in and overwrite whatever was in
there with the new state-of-the entities
so it's basically just the cyclical
streaming system and basically you just
stream in that window you constantly
stream entities in and out as you kind
of go through and also obviously this is
pretty much completely compatible with
if you had wanted to be out of core for
some reason so if you wanted it for some
reason habit so that this stuff was so
huge can't even fit in system memory
which is absurd cuz I don't even want to
know how long it would take you in
infinite amount of time to ever play
that game right that's just crazy but if
you for some reason did
you could imagine this being the
primitive because now all right if you
run on a storage you just say okay
entity blocks just get flushed to this
now and we load them back in when we
need to problem solved right so you know
we could if we wanted to make this out
of core at that point and it would be
totally workable and maybe someday we
will just so we can save we did because
we're stupid and ridiculous all right so
that's the way I want the system to work
and so the first thing that I'm going to
do is I'm going to try obliterating the
low entity array entirely and see if I
can get away with that how many things
that I will have that will be
problematic right and you can already
think of one thing that's problematic
right and that is when we have the
entities that reference each other so
for example in the current system we
might have this is a real example right
that we already have in the system we
have the head and the body of the hero
because they can be disaggregated if we
want them to be they point to each other
right they've each got sort of a notion
of hey I've got like a pointer to either
view but we already know that those get
converted to pointers during sim and
converted back to indices when we end
right so we already know that there's a
translation that happens there the head
stores in the low end units of the body
the body chars ellonija is at the head
so that they can know which one and
think about where each other are asked
questions about about each other what
I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna replace
that with a hash in the sim region so
what will happen is as the entities are
streamed out right rather streamed in to
the the sim region their unique IDs
which will just stick that can just be
some random 32-bit number that we
monetize increment their unique IDs will
be in their enemies as they get unpacked
that unique ID will go into the hash
table right and when somebody else is
looking for that ID when they're
unpacked they will get it out right now
there's a little bit of a nastiness
there which is this is kind of have to
be done in two passes because until
you've unpacked everything you don't
actually know what all the IDS are that
you might want right and that's a little
inefficient and it's kind of unfortunate
but we can do ourselves one better if we
want to and make it so that it actually
isn't inefficient at all and the way
that we can do that is since we are
going to be writing these things out
what we could choose to do first is we
know all of the entities that are going
to get packed into a region so if we
wanted to make packing take a little bit
more thinking we could make packing pack
the indices into a separate part of that
stream at buffer so for example when we
stream things out to a real chunk we
could put all the indices first and then
all of the data right we could do that
now I don't know if that would put too
much of an onerous sort of weight on to
our streaming system because now we have
to do two passes over the writing
portion right and I don't know if that's
a bad thing or not it's really hard to
say what we could do potentially is keep
things sorted by chunk or something like
that but I just don't know it's just a
little bit dicey so what I'm gonna do at
the outset is I'm not gonna do either of
those things I'm just gonna say there's
two passes so there's the unpacked pass
and the pointer fix-up pass right I'm
gonna just have that be the way that it
works and we'll see how bad it is and
then if it's too bad we'll you know
we'll try to figure out something
smarter as we go okay and that's that's
the that's the idea here we go this is
gonna be a lot of edits I don't know
that they'll finished today probably
they won't so you know this will
probably be a Today Tomorrow thing to
sort of get this core code or
organization sort of a little bit more
you know robust if you will the first
thing I'm gonna do just I'm gonna try to
take this in steps you've seen us do
this very many times I've handmade here
oh and I'm gonna do it again which is
that I don't want to break everything in
the architecture at once because again
even when you've done tons and tons and
tons of architecture work like I have
your brain is simply not really a
computer right and there's things that
you'll forget and there's things that
you can't predict so when you are
working on things you always have the
sort of treat as an experiment don't
assume that the thing that you're doing
is right you have to go well I think
it's gonna be right but I need to sort
of experiment to make sure and so I'm
taking it gonna take it once I was
saying make sure
that my assumptions don't appear to be
completely invalid at any given stage
before I get too far down there right so
first can they do and we taking a world
entity block and I'm just gonna make it
a fixed size so I'm gonna have some data
at the end of it that I could have used
to written so let's say that I want that
sort of data block to be we just want to
call this entity de there whatever here
let's see that that entity data block
that I want to read and write is going
to be 64 K like I said right
so I basically want to have 64 K of
bytes right in this data block and that
is what I will use to like stream in and
out right and then instead of an enemy
count the entity count is not gonna be
involved here it anyway instead what I'm
gonna have well actually you know what I
probably would still keep it right to be
honest I probably would keep an enemy
count so the entity count would probably
still be there because that might aid in
allocation if I can grab the world
entity blocks out and figure out what
the other cats first like it might well
I mean when we unpack these things I
guess is all I'm thinking now you know
what it's not gonna be there the other
knee cap we probably don't need so I'm
just gonna say we don't have the enemy
camp so probably nothing they count well
what I have instead is just how much
data there is right so we'll just say
like any data size and that's just how
much of the 64 K do we actually use now
obviously we don't actually need 32 bits
to say how much of 64 K we used but it
doesn't really matter because in this
case this is the majority and this is
not that interesting so we're gonna have
something like this and that's going to
pack or any theta all I'm gonna do now
is compile the program and see if it
explodes right like I don't really know
because I don't remember exactly how
those things are being processed I think
they were allocated on demand so I
wouldn't expect anything to really
explode here but let's double check
right so there you go
already we did explode specifically
because when we create worlds we were
having some kind of a
of a size size problem here so what's
what's happening what's the complaint
let's see
do you falter Rena params size in it who
is allocating this the world struct why
why am I out of space my realtor is that
just because there were chunks and you
can see exactly why I put that in there
right it was defined specifically that
thing so let's take a look quickly at
what that actually is where am I looking
here okay so that is I'm doing a push
struct of the create world ah that's
because the chunk cache does not operate
on pointers it's just a static set of
4096 of those that's hmm hmm so I don't
know that I want that to be true anymore
I mean maybe we do because hey whatever
that amount is we would keep it
allocated I guess at that time but yeah
how do I want to deal with that I'm not
really sure cuz this is basically gonna
take I mean this is the majority of our
memory but we don't want to if nothing
is is sitting in that hash lot we don't
want to use a space for it right
so that just seems like probably not
such a useful idea in general so I'm
thinking more like we probably want to
make this so that when there's nothing
in the hash lot it's just empty and that
seems like probably a better idea to me
so I feel like we would want to do
something like this probably and only
have them be replaced there yeah I feel
like that's probably better
that's just my assumption so yeah so
what that would basically mean is we'd
grab it out here and I and this would be
changed to a you know a wild chunk
situation and to be honest that's a
cleaner loop anyway I mean I know why we
did it originally because we didn't want
there to be any sort of weirdness there
oops
with we wanted to like be more cash
friendly so we didn't have to sort of
doubly indirect but I'm not too worried
about the moment because our lookups
generally only happen that one time when
we pull things out of it so I'm not sure
that we really care too much about that
so I'm gonna go ahead and put this in
here where we where we'll loop through
our chunks in that fashion
and let's see what else we got
so it looks like we should just do
results and incurable say results equals
chunk and soul people chunk right I
think that's what we're looking for and
let's see here
well in this case if the arena's not no
we allocate so we do have a slight
problem which is that if we run out of
chunks we want to allocate an additional
chunk right so what we probably want to
do here is get rid of this concept of
chunk and initialize because we don't
need that anymore right and kind of we
can actually clean this up quite a bit
that was all written because of the way
we wanted to do that sort of initial
initial bit there and so the tiled chunk
uninitialized is probably okay to just
delete at this point so if I run through
my chunks and I don't find anything in
the hash table that matches it right
this is the this is the match criteria
here so if I don't find anything then
that is just this code nap that this
code only runs under that circumstance
right in fact what we could say is well
I'll leave it like this for now and so
then in here we'll say well okay if
there's an arena right and I didn't find
the result so you know I'm want to
always insert this because they pass an
arena and there isn't actually one that
I've located then what I want to do is I
want to create one of these right so the
ones that I'm going to return you know
is this this new world chunk that I've
created and then what I want to do is I
just want to make sure that it gets
pushed onto the hash table in the
correct location right so the trunk hash
here at this hash slot I want that
whatever is in that hash lot I'm gonna
make that be my next pointer so I'm
gonna like keep it around like so but
then what I'm gonna do is say well now
that that first thing in the hash lot is
neat so it's just a singly linked list
that I'm sort of pushing things onto as
they get added to the
right and then I don't care about this
anymore so that created you know the
what I actually needed but I also need
to initialize the other data in it cure
because it you know obviously that's not
initialized so let's put that in there
and I believe that that will it clear it
to zero which I don't want it to do
right because it's a lot of memory and I
don't want that memory to be cleared to
zero if it doesn't have to be so what I
want to do here is go in and say well
alright whatever the world chunk stuff
is
I'm sorry not whatever the world Trek
stuff is what hand-made let's see
handmade that age whatever the the
push-truck does I want to pass the flag
at the end of this right that says hey
don't clear this memory so I'm just
gonna say like don't clear it when it
comes back to me because I'm gonna do
the clearing myself so then when I have
that I need to go ahead and specify in
my result here that the rest of this
stuff is actually okay so let's see here
let's see we're going to block first
block that's fine and we've got the
chunk exposed either next in half that's
all initialized so all I really have to
do here is say well that that world that
first block there that block needs to be
initialized so the first block enemy
camp has to be 0 the first block enemy
data size has to be zero and the first
block next has to be zero but I feel
like that stuff that we should have been
doing before in a sense in some kind of
a centralized initialization phase so I
feel like there should be something that
does you know let's just take a look so
we don't actually have that anywhere
oddly enough so I'm gonna say just for
now because I feel like this should be a
thing that's concrete
I'm gonna say that there's a you know
clear world entity block right so that
basically I don't have to remember you
know what it takes to initialize one of
these because it's not clear to
zero clear two zeros very convenient cuz
then you know anyone can just go to zero
and you're done when I start wanting to
actually have initializer then you're in
a more constructor eland where you're
like I want to know that this thing is
getting created in a specific way so I
just want to make a place where that can
happen
clearly right so when I'm doing this
world entity block clear I know that the
entity count has to be set to zero again
that will probably go away I know that
the next coroner has to be set to zero
and I know that the entity data size has
to be set to zero but everything else
can be uninitialized which is what I
want so here I'll just change this to be
clear world entity block and I'll change
that to be saying that whatever that
first lock is that's a thing
that has got to go now tiled chunk
uninitialized again in here this is sort
of a separate thing that's talk about
these role positions these role business
are going to go but since the tile chunk
uninitialized thing I guess I should
probably leave it in here child chunk
initialized just temporarily because
this is a separate part of the code that
will also be getting rid of I don't want
to get rid of it yet so we'll say that
the null position in the is valsa tile
chunk initialized that's going to be
whatever it was before in 32 max or
whatever so that's fine okay
so let's see world chunk next is not a
member of Road truck it's not I thought
we just said that it was next in hash
sorry there we go there's our chunk
return that's actually called result now
and here are our exes okay so what's
this in create world this initializes
this well this doesn't have to be
initialized anymore it's just zero now
so we don't care about any of this stuff
right that's just totally fine
so that doesn't matter now this world
arena with the parent arena stuff I
don't really remember what happens when
we do sub arena whether the sub arena
gets cleared or not but I'm going to see
does it yeah so I don't actually want to
clear that anymore either
oops
all right so now I want to actually run
let's see what happens here so there's
our there's our standard stuff our we're
basically totally fine so good deal
everyone's happy
everyone is smiling alright so now that
we've got that under control and I know
that I can put a bunch of data into
those chunks the next step now is
getting rid of I think the sword because
I don't really that's a separate sort of
thing that existed in a null space I
have other ways that I'll probably think
about and deal with those later and so
I'm gonna just go ahead and get rid of
those now because I don't even really
want to consider those because they're
really not necessary for this stage of
the development so what I'm going to do
is I'm going to take out the sword
situation entirely
so inside some region where we have this
entity and in add this concept of the
the sword thing in here where was it
sword sword is going to go away goodbye
sword and now all of the things that
we're sword related are also going to go
away those are just gone so goodbye
goodbye and this this sort of creation
of the sword this add sword nonsense
this is all going away because of course
our here doesn't have a sword anyway
that was just an example we used a long
time ago all right so I'm gonna search
for sword in general and just you just
excise it at the moment from the code
base see what we've got here there is a
sword collision and I don't know if
we've got any more uses of the word
sword we've got this concept of d sword
B sword could stay cuz we're actually
using that we just probably want to
rename it to something other than B
sword at some point so here is this
nonsense here that's all going to go
away goodbye and off we go alright so
now we're still running okay at least it
would appear our little new shrunken fat
here I was there and we're all good so
now I'm going to flip back and and
actually do mmm the thing I was talking
about with the with the low entities so
here's that table of low entities where
they're all stored
in this array and so what I want to do
now is move them out of that array and
into the other system so the first thing
I'm going to do is I'm just going to
take that low entity I'm literally just
gonna put the entities into those chunks
just verbatim and that's gonna take a
lot of doing right because I have to
modify it in both the sim region and the
creation stuff that we're actually doing
in sort of the world mode if that makes
sense so let's go ahead and delete that
for for a moment and now we've got like
a total you know we've got a we've got a
total disaster on our hands we're gonna
have to fix but that's fine that's what
we wanted so now let's see what's going
on here and and sort of clean everything
up so the first thing that we need is in
our sim region right when we're doing
our simulation we need that hash table
but that remaps things and in fact I
guess now I think about it we already
have that hash for mapping our ourselves
when we when we sort of move things
around I'm not wearing this to map
things in the simulation set we already
sort of had this hash here so I'm
assuming that we actually use that let's
see if that's actually true yeah so we
have again edited by storage index right
and we're actually already doing that so
we're already we already have our hash
function working which is pretty great
so we don't even have to do that it's
like we already sort of did a little bit
of that work for us which is pretty
great okay
I'll be honest it's been so long I don't
remember why we really needed that
I guess because cemento T's and lo
entities technically word the same thing
so I guess it's just because I was
always thinking I was gonna do this
because I guess that's why we even did
the copy because otherwise we could have
avoided the copy
all right so hey past me thank you for
doing some extra work for future me
that was nice of you very nice of you so
anyway here we are at ludendi reference
and this is obviously the place that's
going to take a reference to andy and
convert it you know to something that is
a direct pointer to one of the simin
indies so what we have to do now is we
have to go ahead and make sure that this
works properly now the main change that
we're gonna make here is these loads
used to pull like almost like a you know
pulling a piece of string and unraveling
a sweater right what we used to do here
is if we didn't find the entity we would
go get it out of low entity storage but
from now on we don't want to do that
anymore the rule is if you don't find
the entity in the region then your
pointer gets nulled right that's
actually what's supposed to happen
so our enemy references are now going to
be things which basically say you have a
reference to an entity it tells you
uniquely what the entities ID is so if
it is within your simulation region you
can see it and access it but if it is
not you can't make sense
I hope it does anyway so here we are in
load entity reference so the big change
here is that we're not going to do this
pull there's got gonna be any pull
what's going to happen instead is we're
just gonna have the same entity hash
gets out of the hash what this index
would correspond to and then it tries to
grant get the pointer out of that now if
the entry is null that we simply will
set it to null and there just won't be
any pointer set ok and that's it so that
makes that easy it also means we don't
have to pre declare identity anymore
because this can't force identity to be
added now here we are in our giant loop
where these things kind of get pulled
out and you can see here in the block
we're pulling out the low in the index
so we'll really all we have to do now is
we just have to go ahead and say well
instead of keeping entity indices let's
just store the actual entities in here
right because we have the loan entity
structure there and what we can do is
just say that that big data array is
just going to keep those low entities in
it right and now I don't really remember
exactly how big a low entity is but it's
pretty big unfortunately right and you
can kind of see here if it's gonna have
a simonetti in it because we haven't
done any of the packing stuff you can
see the destruct I mean I don't know how
big it is but it looks like it's
probably something that's I don't know
you know that's probably that's probably
a good you know that's probably a good 5
to 12 bytes or something there you know
that's that's that's big that's a that's
a big way I don't know how big some of
these are but that's that's pretty
sizable right so you figure we can only
keep about a hundred and you know 20 to
200 of those in a chunk right now maybe
less because again we're not doing
anything smart with them and we kind of
haven't gotten to that point yet so I
don't know if this will work exactly as
is we'll see what we hit an assertion
but the first thing I'm going to do is
not even try to think about expanding or
compressing blocks at all on right out
probably I'm just gonna go ahead and
assume that we only use the first world
block and then I'm gonna go ahead and
upgrade it so that when we're doing
write outs if we need to we'll we'll
blow it out now the
code doesn't have to change the read
codes the same either way so that's all
fine but the write code you know we will
have to introduced sort of a recycle
list there and that's gonna be in
something but we want to think about
little more so here's our code we say
how many enemies there are in the block
again we probably won't specify that
eventually we'll unpack in a more direct
fashion but for now that can so totally
stay and so when we do low entity index
here and do this block linear thing we
can get rid of that the low ending the
ax is no longer a thing right low entity
index is not going to be there and so
what we can do is say alright and we
don't care about this non-spatial thing
either until we actually load the thing
in fact how were we what was happening
here we're grabbing out the low entity
this way where are we putting it it
looks like we're passing it in here and
we're calling this a Danity bit let me
go look at that first I want to take a
little bit of a look at that identity
call and see what that's doing
so identity is basically saying well
okay if I was able to add one then chest
it I guess set it whether it's updatable
based on its its situation here and
that's fine
but let's take a look at that out of the
row what's that doing so additi raw is
looking to see whether this entity hmmm
I guess we're just looking to place it
in the hash at the appropriate location
that's what it looks like to me
yeah
that looks like it so I think we might
change the way this works a little bit
right I'm gonna kind of keep it this way
just so that things don't get too wonky
but we're gonna probably change all of
this actually to be a little bit more
serious all right
so what I'm gonna do here is I guess
I'll keep this working the way that it
was by basically I'm just gonna cast
right to the low entity star I'm gonna
cast that data block that's inside you
know this system right that's the data
block there I'm gonna take that what did
I call it entity data I think I'm gonna
take that and assume it's array of low
entities and just get the Edit II index
off of it right by looking exactly in
the entity in fact this now is an actual
entity index not an index index it's
actually the index inside the enemy
struck right let me get that out and
then I'm gonna just continue as as is
right so we're gonna use that that data
directly let's go ahead and and in fact
you know what this this doesn't have to
be here at all right that's that's gone
so it's really just that and that pulls
out that low entity pointer and so the
low entity index here I don't really
know what that's used for because what
we want is that storage index which is
good enough to be something that's
inside the low entity as an actual thing
right as a let's take a look here inside
some region this this storage index is
actually the thing that we want and so
I'm just gonna pass that and use that
everywhere for whose indexes who's right
so we're just gonna pass that this way
does that make sense
but that's gonna probably go away a
little bit in a second here oops and I
didn't want low
I just want soon okay so now we come in
here let's see where we're at
we've got low any of these is not a
member of game railroad you're right it
isn't
and so this stored bit here is not
actually what the way we want to do this
what we want to do is repack these
entities into those world blocks right
now fortunately for me I can super
double plus extra cheat
in here a little bit I suppose well no I
guess I can so I've got to actually do
this for real because when things move
around they're gonna change where their
locations are I guess if I don't move
anything then it would be okay so I
could in theory try to run without doing
this code first and just see what breaks
which would basically be something like
this right you see what I'm saying here
hopefully that makes some sense yeah
yeah and in fact you know there's gonna
be this is I'm really liking this so far
this is I'm thinking of all these nice
things that are gonna happen I think
eventually maybe that's only my wishful
thinking but anyway so so point being
when we add stuff as is the case here
what we have to do now is we have to
start when we because that's the same
region stuff and it's you know like we
said we gotta kind of do some more
passes over it but here out in the
regular game code when we're actually
adding things now we have to do is make
sure we actually add them to basically
we have to add them to the actual
physical location where they exist if
that makes sense so what we want to do
here is say okay let's create a low
entity instead of doing it this way what
we want to do instead is is basically
create a little entity and then pack it
into its its actual position location
right that's how we actually want this
code to work and so we want some way of
of getting a low entity description like
an actual unpack well I mean I guess I
should say I'm assuming us I won't do it
technically I suppose if we want to
create an entity we could just stream
out exactly the right compressed bytes
to create that enemy which might be good
as well but I kind of feel like we might
want to just go through one path for
packing everything at first it seems
like a better idea to me just you know
the brain why is that
I'm thinking that simplifies things a
little bit I don't know that's my
assumption if that makes sense so what I
want to do here is kind of I don't
really want this to work the way that
it's working at all
so in here where we do ad low entity you
can see that we kind of do that in a
bunch of places here where we kind of
have this sort of cascading thing what I
want to do is I want to change these to
a thing which basically does like a
beginning end entity creation so you
begin entity creation you do some work
on the env that's trying to create and
then you end an occasion and it packs it
right that's what I actually want to
have happen here so what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna change this to be more like
you know begin low entity in it and it
passes back one of these or whatever and
then there's an end low in ax be
something like this and this will be
like a low end 'ti or entity creation or
something like this right I that's what
I think I actually want to do now this
is gonna be full banana cakes at the
moment because probably the weight you
know we could do this on the stack or
something I don't know there's ways we
could do this full big net cake slice I
guess I won't do it full banana cakes at
the moment instead what I'll do is I'll
still do something that's actually not
not super great but it is not it's it's
not the best for threading basically but
you know I just don't know what our
speed profile is gonna be like and I
don't know whether we'll have multiple
threads adding things yet or any of that
stuff so for right now since its wrapped
and I can change it to something else in
the future I'm just gonna say that in
here we have the concept of a low entity
and this is just the creation buffer
okay and what happens is anytime you go
to create one of these things the the
result here is going to be such that you
get a pointer back up to that creation
buffer
right and I can even put a little thing
in here that's like creation buffer
locked if I want to catch bugs okay so
in here I've got this concept of that
lock and so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to assert that when I come here to
use the creation buffer I'm gonna cert
that that creation buffer is not blocked
right nobody else has it and then when I
finish I'm going to assert that it is
locked and that way I can just tell that
you know no two people are using this at
once because right now I haven't
designed it to support that concept and
so if in the future I forget what I was
doing and I do that I want to have an
assertion that comes up unless we know
hey that is not what you're supposed to
do so I'm gonna start the that creation
buffers locked I'm going to create one
of these energy creation results and I'm
going to go ahead and assume that we've
got sort of this this storage index
concept here that says where these folks
are now previously we did this sort of
low index thing I don't think that's
necessary because our sim region has
storage index in it and to be honest
with you I don't if you look at what
happens here it's a world position P and
a sim entity same thing and I don't
really know to what extent we need to
worry about that anymore because we're
not really doing again like I said we're
gonna be doing a compression step so at
the moment this world chunk old chunk
thing I like we could just pack the
stuff in here and stop thinking about
low entities at all right there would
only be semaine of these or rather I
should say they're only the entity
there's no concept of anything else
it would just be entity right and so we
could rename this from sim entity to
just anity if we wanted to because there
is no other type of any there's just a
sim initi and a packed
you know version that it isn't a struct
so you couldn't access it anyway right
so what I might do here is just say I
forget about all that right that's let's
just forget about this whole concept
here where we pass the lowness or any of
that stuff we don't care about that at
all
because really all we have is just the
low entity right that's all that there
actually is and so in some sense I could
say well there's any creation thing that
doesn't really even need to be a block
block like that I could just make it so
that we pass back a pointer to the low
entity and then when we're done with it
when we're when we're finished with that
low and anything then weari come then
it'll compress right here and so all we
need to do to change this to having only
one entity is eventually will change
these from Goodloe entity to actually
just begin entity and will will strip
all that out move the world location in
and it'll be beautiful and wonderful all
right so assuming that this is what
we're doing where we do the low entity
here we do our assertion that their
creation buffer is not locked we then
take the lock on the creation buffer and
again this is purely for debugging
doesn't do anything else it's just for
debugging then we come in here and say
all right let's go ahead and get one of
these low entities by taking the
creation buffer as the temporary place
where it's going to go right and here's
the the result there we go we don't care
about any of this stuff at all this is
no longer relevant and so in here in our
sin storage index we're gonna do that
sort of entity we now need that sort of
concept of a storage ID that's unique
right and there are some things that we
have to worry about cure that you know
we're gonna have to reckon with at some
point and I'm not exactly sure how we
want to handle them we'll see when we
get to a place where they're a little
bit more relevant but basically if we
create new entities and destroy old
entities we will eventually run out of
unique IDs right for after four billion
will run out and wrap and that would be
bad right so here there's a u32 that's
like the next available storage index
and we could make this a 64-bit
identifier if we wanted to and then it
never would
but we might want to think about how
we're gonna do this exactly and and sort
of upgrade that in the future so I'm
gonna put it to do here as well
worried about this wrapping free list
for IDs where we might actually try to
recycle free IDs and so that this is not
just a thing that monotonically
increases if that makes sense all right
so here we go with my begin low entity
situation I'm gonna go in here and say
VIPs my results in storage index is
going to be whatever this next available
storage index is and maybe I'll call
this next available energy storage index
and I want that to be one so if there
have never been any initialized or I
guess I should say instead of that I'll
say like last use entity storage index
and that way clear to zero will
initialize it properly and I just
increment it before storing it right so
there's it storage of dicks and that
leaves zero as a whole so that people
can use zero to say I don't I'm not
referencing any entity right so we don't
need this anymore we just if we want to
clear this thing that we would have to
do a zero struct on it so there it is
and I'm gonna do what to do here worry
about this taking a while once the
entities are large sparse clear and then
we've got this stuff that sets up the
basics so we don't need entity low
anymore really because just result but
I'll call it that for now just to avoid
changing that code since we're going to
change it all anyway so there's my enemy
low stuff that we this stuff can all
sort of stay the same right temporarily
but we're gonna have to we're gonna have
to obviously well you know what
no really that is gonna go down here so
anyway here we go so we set all this
stuff up the entity position P that is
going to go in here the ad lo entity
result goes away
and oh hey look do we need to begin end
paradigm for ending it so that they can
be brought into the main high set and
then added as its yeah hey guess what
all to do is eventually get done even if
you don't remember the two dues because
hey it's like you were going to do that
that's why you put it to do in there
it's kind of funny anyway so here's
Enslow entity this is gonna Pat take the
entity that's getting ended obviously
and what it needs to do is it needs to
actually pack the entity into the
correct world chunk right into wherever
that needs to act it to be so I'm just
gonna introduce a function here called
pack entity into chunk and that's gonna
take the entity and compress it down at
the location where it currently exists
now obviously since these are stored in
there that that location P is stored in
there I don't really need to passing
this stuff anymore
and I certainly don't need to pass the
entity index because there is no such
thing the storage index is used for hash
lookups but it's not necessary for
anybody else so here's the pack entity
into chunk code and we've got this
entity low here so I'm gonna go ahead
and and just leave it like that and say
that this is a new function that's going
to happen okay
deleting low entities at the moment is
not something that's ever going to exist
here that's not a thing anymore the
reason for that is you can imagine right
now how this is gonna happen if we
always do a stream where we load in up
and then stream out for every sim cycle
all will do you just don't stream out
anyone who got deleted so we don't need
a deletion strategy anymore
we just don't stream them out anymore
they come in and then oops they never
get streamed out so they'll just be a
marker that's like this entity got
killed or removed
and then doesn't get streamed out
anymore okay uh let's see lo not much
time left
unfortunately let's see and lo entities
gonna have to take the world mode
obviously so and entity lo oh nice
there we go
so pack entity into chunk we need to
write and for the moment I'll just
internal it here right but I won't
actually implement it do we have a not
implemented I don't even remember if we
ever made one of those so pack entity
into chunk I don't know what that's
going to take probably just the world
I'm thinking and oops Dennis already got
that probably just the world and the
entity so we don't have a not
implemented huh
too bad I often define a macro that's
like not implemented which just asserts
it's like if you got to this code you're
sad because nobody wrote it so missing
semicolon before identifier add grounded
entity that is true so this is just
gonna be exactly the same thing
essentially it's just a pass-through
that does a little bit of extra work
there we go
and world bow type add low entity is
peak in their entity entity here's an ad
grounded entity or I should say is now
begin grounded entity right because I
don't know is there any such thing as
add ground an entity that isn't called
from inside somebody who edit the entity
right I'm assuming the answer is no but
don't really know and it's not so that's
good so this is really begin grab that
entity and not to go and I'm just going
to call this identity actually for now
okay so there's our return of the entity
hoops which is wrong because it needs a
pointer here is where we start to
actually use this stuff so here we have
to do a low end of the entity we're just
going to begin grab it under the on it
and then we're gonna do and entity and
that'll be it right we're gonna come
through here and add wall so now when
you do something like add wall we really
if you're the only thing that you can do
with these when they get returned and
I'm gonna look to see what anyone does
do with them I'm gonna see if anyone
needs stuff back
so for now when you add stuff I'm not
going to return anything but we could
return the storage index if we wanted to
right but I'm gonna get rid of those
temporarily for the ones we don't care
about right because that because I can
because I will and we'll worry about
that later so here we've added you know
the entity and we wanted to add flags to
it so then what I'm gonna do is just end
it here and now we've added that wall
exactly as before add grounded entity in
this case is been changed to begin
grounded entity
and let's see low is undeclared
identifier that's true because it's
empty add low entity results again I
think I've got a few minutes left but I
started like five minutes later so I
remember correctly so I'm gonna go right
up till the end and again this is really
just mechanical edits here right I mean
you can see what I'm doing it's not
mysterious I'm just doing the things
that I need to do just kind of maneuver
this into place let's see
okay so add player I don't really know
that might require some degree yeah you
can see that it wants to to know that
information so this is going to have to
take an entity index back and so what
I'm going to do here is one of the
problems I think that we had before sort
of that we just didn't know about is we
we really want that index to not be a
bear index we want people to be able to
see that this is basically like an
entity ID right and I just want to wrap
that up so that people know that it's a
special thing you can't you can't do
anything with it you can't add to it you
can't modify the value it gets created
at creation time and it never touched so
I'm gonna make that be a specific thing
at the moment right and so I want that
to to be very explicit right so what I'm
going to say is that all right we've got
this entity ID oops and that's not good
we've got this entity ID and the entity
ID is going to be the thing that's used
here for this like the storage index
right and I'll probably change storage
next to be named ID later but again
there's so many edits in flight right
now I don't want to add anymore other
than the basic ones that we have so yeah
so the storage index for example is you
know anywhere that we were using it it's
not a big deal it can just be changed to
something very straightforward where is
storage index so like something like
this like these will all just be entity
IDs that could pass through right
get hash from storage index let's see
here
right and we'll clean this code up when
we have time but again we're sort of
like I said you know with an hour it's
always real hard to do the big edits
like this but you got to do them they're
very important so you know it you don't
you don't want to not alright
Oh entity reference index so that also
so the concept of an entity reference
wherever that ended up being should also
be an enemy ID yeah
only two minutes left we're not we're
not gonna be able to give it make it to
there alright see you here good any
reference okay
storage index is the ID entry index so
an entry index here in our case should
probably also be where is the hash right
there this should also be an ID
all right um so yeah there we go
and Adam did you raw
it is still taking one of these so let's
get rid of that any ID these can be done
on value as well I don't know about
these these we can probably yeah these
these are probably not even collision
rules will probably clean up as well but
anyway so there we go alright so now
we're back to normal and that's all fine
so inside here what I'm going to say is
I'm going to return an entity ID right
and there's my AB player code so I come
in through here and I add all this stuff
now I have to do a couple things just to
change this to working in the simpler
way that we've created now where you
just get back the pointer there we go
but I also then have to sort of do the
return properly here so when we come
through and set up this code and it's
all happy and fine when we set up the
camera following code and all this other
sort of sort of stuff I have to now have
some notion of what these storages were
right so what I want to do now is say
like oh yeah that's my storage index
right and same here and my storage index
has already been set so then when I do
and entity here right and I do entity
body and entity head now I can't access
that anymore so before I go I have to do
like a result equals whichever one I was
returning I guess is the body is the one
I'm returning but the head is really the
player so I think it's the head that I'm
supposed to return really right I would
think so anyway so the K is the heads
what we move around so I'm going to do
head sim storage index and I guess these
have to be sim as well
it'll be nice to get rid of that sin
thing we won't have to do that anymore
soon - this is gonna be so nice I'm
looking forward to this anyway all right
so these are all begin calls and then
we've got our end calls there and that's
all fine that can go away and what is
the problem following it can be index so
this entity felt this camera following
entity and next thing that really in the
world mode should be an NBA idea now
because anywhere that we restoring an
index should be actually using an ND ID
like so and eventually we should might
want to have a is valid that but I think
zero is fine it doesn't really matter
because we're never going to change that
aspect of it certainly okay so there's
our situation we'll put our result in
there I think Monstar probably doesn't
have to return anything in particular so
we should be able to basically treat
this as a straightforward conversion
there's our entity and our end entity
world mode unique and the same is true
for our familiar
and entity and all that so that's yeah
that's about right into the there we go
and these are course are begins and okay
so let's see where we're at now
ad low entity obviously that's true that
there is no ID but we don't have to do
this anymore because we don't need to
reserve a slot so that's gone because
there is no such thing as a slot we come
in here we've got our entity index when
that comes out it can go right into here
our con hero struct our controlled hero
that's in handmade right so let's see
controlled here oh there it is this
should really be an entity ID and so we
change this around alright when we do a
delete little entity on this we're gonna
have to do it to do on this right
because this is it's not implemented yet
I'm gonna leave that in there for a
second let's see what else we got
entity debug IDs game world mode clear
coalition rules for energy storage and
so yes at those collision rules stuff we
have to upgrade slightly we're mostly
there though there's really not much
else left here this could be a value
certainly there's really not that much
left let's recompile this so we've got
delete low entity we haven't done that
yet we've got this clearing game thing
that happens and that's fine
we've got low entities this debug ID
thing I don't know how we'll really get
around that we want the debug ID to be
something unique but we don't have a
real way to do it so I don't know to do
KC we don't really have a way to unique
defy these at the moment it's not to
think about that I'm not really sure
yeah I'm not sure what we would do here
it's do we have a debug just you ain't
ID I mean I guess if I did this I could
just say well okay it's a void star
let's see cannot convert from
these are just straight ahead comparison
so that's good clear collision rules for
probably just needs to take one of these
but eventually that'll be fixed as well
and then low entities tebow pointer ID
again so that storage thing we don't
really have a way to deal with
unfortunately all right so really the
only thing we have to do here is have a
way of marking one of these entities is
deleted right and we don't quite have a
way to do that yet in the sim region
sits stuff so what we don't want to do
is do delete low entity so I'm just
going to put an assertion here add mark
this and delete in sim but all right
we're at least compiling so I'm gonna
call it for today because I have to go
early actually today I've got to go in
about four minutes so I'm gonna call it
there I could maybe take a brief Q&amp;A but
I would say hold hold off on any lengthy
ones I will probably put postponed until
tomorrow when we finish with this if
that makes sense
hello Milton
Ranga this is more of a meta question
but I found myself faced introduced in
my code at places that I don't want to
deal with while I work on something else
however as we all procrastinate how come
back to the do's so what I do is once I
get into like ship mode on something I
go I have like something like this right
which just prints out where all the two
dudes are and what I do is I go through
them all and I assess way at that point
in the you know in the process before I
go into like serious ship mode I assess
which ones are actually to dues I want
to do before shipping which ones are to
dues that I'll maybe do in some future
version and maybe it's for soapy both
owned and which ones are just
superfluous now because they don't make
any sense with the way the code ended up
and I do that big call and that's like
what helps me generate part of my like
shipping list of things I need to do
that makes sense our beady jellyfish
what's the highest number of errors
you've ever had compiling well it's
capped at 100 on most compiles if you
don't turn it off so like on m/s BC
you'll just it was won't print past 100
so mid blow I arrived too late to the
pre stream to let you know that
yesterday's episode hasn't made its way
to YouTube oh yeah YouTube's been real
bad for uploading lately it's probably
just sitting there like in a weird bad
state I'll take a look at it
all right so I'm gonna go ahead and wrap
it up and tomorrow we'll kind of go
through this and and finish up because
we're in a good state right now I'm
really excited for this I'm I'm really
excited for this entity system I have to
tell you but anyway thank you everybody
for joining me for this toda handmade
hero it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you want to follow
along the series at home you can do so
by pre-ordering the game at handmade
hero organs a little handy dandy button
there and it comes to the source code so
you can follow along we also have a
forum site you can go to if you want to
ask questions we have a patreon page you
want support the video serious and we
have a tweet bot that tweets the
schedule for Monica series live there's
also an episode guide for catching up on
past episodes and if you would like to
see the exciting conclusion of well the
first step in our energy system rewrite
that will be tomorrow and I think it'll
be pretty awesome but it'll continue to
get awesome basically the next couple
weeks are gonna be pretty awesome just
in a general awesomeness so prepare for
a lot of Awesomeness and if you can't
heil awesomeness I would not recommend
turning tuning back into the stream over
the next couple of weeks so it's gonna
just it's going to be absurd that's
about it until tomorrow have a good time
programming and I'll see you guys on the
Internet
take it easy everyone