hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show where we code a complete
game
live on the stream and uh
we are really just going back to what we
were doing
um when we stopped last week we
were in the middle of just finishing up
our tag stuff and we had a lighting
problem uh that we want to look into and
and really that's all we're doing
i'm going to go ahead and go to the
handmade directory here
and open up four coder
or not oh
you know what i just realized i didn't
run the shell
just missed shell.bat there we go
um so
if i remember correctly there's really
two or three things we still had left to
do
um i'm going to open up remedy here and
just just show you
so one problem is that we had kind of
like a weird lighting prob
a bug which appears to be related to
like two large
values contaminating the lighting so you
know you can see like
if i'm not uh hopping around here you
know i can i can
do what i would normally expect to do
and the lighting appears to be correct
um for the most part but then i end up
in a situation where
occasionally and it's a tricky problem
because there doesn't seem to be
a lot of rhyme or reason to it like it
just kind of happens sometimes
um and it is not happening now
unfortunately
but the lighting will just become
infinitely bright
and it looked like this was just maybe a
problem with some out of bounds
computation or some kind of initialized
values
seeping in there um but we don't know
so unfortunately that's like seeming to
be a little bit
har difficult to repro at the moment and
so
i don't actually know what we would
do about that uh we're gonna have to try
and get a
more provocable case uh than this
but uh there it is
i'm like trust me it's there so you can
see this
and it appears to be a thing where you
end up with
values that contaminate right
um like you know
there's some really high light value
and because we know lighting values in
our system propagate
um like that like one really out of
bounds value
would in theory propagate to all the
cells eventually which is what i assume
is happening
so i think we just have a bug where we
compute something poorly or we've got
some kind of way that a trash value can
get in there
and it may be as simple as us just
guarding against that
but we need to kind of find that because
we can see that it happens and it
happens
you know maybe only rarely but rarely in
this case is
you know it would certainly happen
during the play of the game it's
frequent enough that that would happen
so
we know we gotta fix it um it's not so
it's not a one in a billion thing
um so we we should look at that and then
the other thing
that uh we know is busted is we just
haven't ported some of the tag stuff yet
for example here is the uh title screen
when we go to uh
you know when it's supposed to play the
cutscenes
you can see that it's not finding the
actual graphics or at least i assume
that's what's happening
uh and i believe that's just our tag
system um
is is being slightly busted there so
what we need to do
is we just need to look at why it's not
finding
those particular resources if i go
to the tags and i look at the
intro cutscene hht um
you can see the tags here are like shot
index one layer index one
like that kind of stuff right um
i don't actually know what we're doing
inside the cutscene at the moment to
find these things
so it may be that we're just doing
something stupid
but whatever it is we need to go uh
figure out like why it can't find it so
if you look here
we have a get tag hash that is
uh you know looking at the at the layer
index
one plus whatever the layer index was
supposed to be
and then like a shop tag so in theory
the shot tag needs to be like
intro cutscene shot index 1 would be
what should be in that tag
and i don't know if that is what's in
the tag so we just need to go see
like are we picking these correctly that
way
you know what what's going on so you can
see here
where we've got like our our shot
information
you can see here that it's it's intro
cutscene
so it looks here like there's only one
tag shot index here
so i guess i'm not sure i understand
where intro cutscene is coming from
so is that getting bundled up in here or
something
because that that would be a problem
so so i think i mean maybe i'm wrong
about this but it kind of looks like
actually like just tag intro cutscene
is missing uh that might be the only
problem is that we weren't providing the
intro cutscene tag
um so it didn't know what cut scene we
were trying to load that
that might be it i don't know but we
should at least fix that first
yeah so it looks like that may have been
all there is
um let's just double check
so yeah so that turned out to not be a
big deal um
so that's fine we also have the trees
is the other one so we'll go we'll go
double check that as well
um
sorry i just want to make sure we we
wait long enough to
know that there's no weirdness going on
here
uh yanchen lee did this artwork
for someone's asking
i don't see anything missing so i mean
we could probably stop now but i'm just
you know
are you in texas are you asking me if
i'm in texas
i am not in texas
why thank you dusty dino
so that's all the cutscenes
right uh so that looks totally
correct like i don't see anything weird
going on there
um
so i think we're good um so
i think the only other tag issue that we
had
on the list is that if we go to an
outside area
um we don't have trees
right like you could oh my gosh
the baby is there
that's just a weird like placement bug i
guess there's like a baby there
hold on a second we should at least
align the baby we don't want our game to
have a baby with no head
that would be a very different kind of
game that'd be like one of those like um
like horror games like silent hill or
something
um so hold on a second let's
let's make one of those
bind points um
something like that probably
and
um
there
okay now our babies is better
much better um all right
so uh what we need here is to figure out
why our trees aren't there and
you know i think that's probably just
just because when we change the tags we
just haven't updated the thing that
actually puts the trees in to use the
correct set of tags
so i don't think this is going to be
particularly interesting but
uh we need our trees back also it was
kind of nice that our trees were not
there because it means we got to see the
fact that our baby was there
i guess the system was randomly placing
the babies in there because we had kind
of thrown in that thing that throws
like people up in the corner like that
oh my god dude nobody
puts baby in a corner except us like we
put baby in a corner
like we put baby in a corner there is
baby baby is in a corner
i feel like that's like a violation of
the meme
nobody puts baby in a corner because we
literally
we literally put the one baby
that exists in this game into a corner
um so all right let's
take a look at what's going on with the
trees here
um and then that would be the last thing
before
like then then we just have to look at
um
what's going on good stop this stop
everyone
okay uh
we need oops
we got it all we need to look at the
intro cutscene hht
i also need to make note of a four coder
thing to fix
there we need
per character file
delete
um so looking at this stuff
here uh we just need to grab the base
game hht
and look at those trees because we know
that the trees are busted
you can see we've got like a damaged
tree
a fall tree a dark tree a winter tree
and i'm guessing we just don't set any
of this stuff correctly
in the generator now like the generator
probably just
doesn't do that um
somewhere here somebody is setting tree
to something
and we have no idea who it is
so let's see
um
this is all debug stuff which we don't
care about
it looks like this is the thing that
adds the tree
um i don't see anything else so it looks
like this
so here we're like adding trees
get tree tags
and
yeah that that's totally wrong i think
because there's no actual tree in here
right so i i assume
we would have to at least put the tree
thing in there
i mean i could be wrong but let's find
out
uh what did we why do we have oh right
it's this okay
so i think that's all we would need to
do is just put tree because it looks
like we have damaged tree
dark and winter and so in get tree tags
we really just need to make sure that
before we pick one of those
we put in a tag tree i think that's it
um but i don't know so let's take a look
yeah so so i think that was it because
like there's trees now
um it does look like we're
we're grabbing some trees that are not
what we would expect like we're grabbing
some non-winter trees which i don't know
maybe we were expecting um also they're
tiny which
may just be um
that may just be some kind of an
artifact
of
of settings i'm i'm not sure about that
like is that just the scale
it is so so i think that's just because
maybe we weren't using these trees
before
so it may just be like that this scale
needs to be changed to something higher
um
so like like that
i don't know so you can see these are 2
4 8 43 22.
so i don't know if they should be
similar like like i don't really know
how these should be situated i guess i
should probably go in here and actually
look
i mean that kind of seems right i don't
know it's
kind of tough to tell i should probably
have something that turns off foliage
just so it's a little easier to see but
yeah i mean it just looks like
these were just never configured is
really the only problem
it looks like otherwise they're fine
all right i'm satisfied with that for
now
so let's see if we restart the game if
now we've got proper trees looks like we
do
all right
so that seems fine i do feel like these
are not quite aligned properly so let me
just
let me just fix those a little bit more
um it looks like they kind of need to be
more like that
just to be consistent
i think i mean again pretty hard to say
that seems about right though
all right
okay
so i think at this point we
are mostly done
with any tag stuff we needed to do
and we really now
just need a way to figure out our
lighting bug i think
um and i guess i would say the
biggest issue we're going to have here
is just the
lack of ability to provoke this bug
it would be really nice
if we could find some way to make it
happen reliably
right um so it would be really nice if
we could do
something that would you know
cause it to to
cause it to screw up the lighting in
in some way that we knew we could make
it happen and
i sort of was doing this before that's
weird
but it just seems like we've got some
weird stuff that got introduced
so i don't know
um yeah like what is going on there
right that
that also kind of seems like a bug like
a lighting style like
nan ish sort of thing to me like it just
seems like stuff's a little bit weird
um and then it fixed itself right
it's weird
very disturbing
hmm so how do i want to go about finding
this
i suppose
so we sort of have one thing that we
already can do
which is we're looking at
we already have the thing that does the
like show
us you know show us the out of bounds
values
right because we have the thing yeah
like why did that
make it happen
super annoying
so we already have the thing that like
does
the that shows the um the spec valid and
diffuse valid
which looks like it correlates um
with it a little bit but you can see
like here when we do that the spec valid
becomes invalid temporarily and then
becomes valid again
which is so weird like that would mean
that there are some very large values
somewhere in our lighting grid you know
and we just don't know where they are so
like i would really love to know
where those values are and why you know
what i'm saying
and why it's inconsistent so why did it
like do that a couple times like why is
spec invalid right now
you know what i mean like where are the
invalid specular and diffuse
entries you know
so
here's our validator um
these are relatively tight bounds but
you know
even so they're pretty wild like
i don't know what the max light value is
at the moment
but i think we had something and it was
not that high
right
so max light intensity is 10.
so like in order to have a number over a
hundred
you would have to be like receiving
contributions from lots of
full bright lights
i don't know we should take a look at
some stuff here so is max light emission
a thing
yeah i don't think so
um
i'm going to go ahead and say i want to
see why we're getting these values so
something over a hundred just should not
be happening
um
let's verify that we're getting mostly
positive and not negative
so i'm gonna if zero this out and i'm
gonna say
that it's a valid component if c
is greater than or equal to like
negative 0.1 so like
anywhere basically like like any place
where we get a significant negative
value would invalidate the region
um
which number is says seven so we're
saying that there's
actual negative numbers there i mean am
i right about that like wouldn't that
that would have to be the case right
we're looping over texels
and like we're having negative 0.1
which is crazy so let's just see like
let's just go find out what the heck is
happening there because
that's nuts like are we not looping over
the textiles properly did nobody like
clear these or something so they're just
garbage values
you know like what happened because
that's just ridiculous
and so we kind of need to figure out
like why we're getting something that
happens that way
it just doesn't make any sense
i'm going to go ahead and switch to
debug
um so i just want to do
an od here
and then i just i'm gonna um
break when result is
negative
so i'm going to provide a line for
myself there that i can use
uh to break into the code so on validate
text component
uh here in the atlas code i'm just going
to go ahead and break there
and let's take a look um
that code is right here and i am going
to put a breakpoint
there so now when we run
in theory we should get a situation at
some point
where we
so this is good that this happened again
because
last time this happened um
george was saying that the problem was
because handmade hero hadn't
loaded the executable yet but that's
obviously not true
right so so there is some problem that's
going on with remedy bg
lately where like it can't set a break
point
even though like i've definitely loaded
um
like there's no question this is loaded
right i mean how could it not be loaded
because if it wasn't loaded like how is
it doing
i mean how it's like this this in order
for this to happen
this has to have in order for this to
print out a value
this code has to have ran right
so so it seems like it it isn't
or shouldn't be possible um
for me to be seeing what i'm seeing on
the screen and not actually be able to
set a break point here
that's just
i don't know so i'm not sure what's
going on
uh i don't know why that's happening but
it
it it comports with what i saw before
and so i really don't think this has
anything to do with not
having loaded yet because by the time
you see this on the screen
everything's loaded and this is
definitely loaded
right now it might be
something to do with like
when you've loaded remedy or something
like
maybe i need to restart it
um or something or maybe i need to
rebuild
because it doesn't like this particular
build but something's borked
uh and i don't know what it is
if i step in so if i set a break point
like can i set a breakpoint
at like validate atlas
so like that's even weirder
um
like
what is happening
is this some other handmade
light atlas or something
so something's super weird there
right because like
it does oh
the file is loaded twice
that that like switched files did you
see that george
something's really weird about that
i have handmade light atlas twice
up there right so it's just loaded
multiple times
it could very well be that it's not
disambiguating the file names
it could very well be why
wouldn't it always load from the
substitute drive though
i don't know
but yeah you're gonna have to
disambiguate those names for sure
right um
like you gotta call the like canonical
the name canonical
random crap in windows but why
we should have been having this problem
a lot maybe this is because of something
they changed in the pdb
is why it's happening now because that
that would have been happening to us the
whole time it's never happened before
right
that's great that we got to the bottom
of that though
how can i find out the full path copy
full path
yeah so that's busted
where is that coming from is that
because the pdb
is now baking sea colon in there
i wonder if like the if microsoft
changed the way they're building the
pdbs to
now use a canonicalized non-substitute
name
so if that's the case
that's almost certainly what's going on
then they probably did that
and if that's the case it means that if
i close
all of these tabs so they're all gone
right
then i should never i should quote
unquote
never have this problem if i don't load
a file myself
right because it will always pick the c
colon one
here because that will be the only thing
that's in the pdb
so we should be able to work around this
problem for now by just getting rid
of all of my files and now in theory
right all of the files will always come
from c
colon but now that i've done that we can
now watch as well and see
i bet that is what um
i bet that's exactly what microsoft did
it's the kind of thing they would do and
not tell anyone because they didn't know
they did it like because they don't
even know how to program windows so they
probably just changed which stupid
c-sharp thing they call from in the
middle of their compiler like 50
000 stack entries deep and then forgot
that that thing will canonicalize the
file
or something right that's probably what
happened anyway it doesn't matter
i think we've got it now so that's good
okay um so let's take a look we're
probably going to have to
try to provoke this bug a little bit
here but we just need to find a case
where it's not
valid um or hope that we had a case
where it's not valid uh but you know who
knows
so uh yeah of course unfortunately it's
doesn't seem to be hitting that
particular case and
uh and like now our spec valid and
diffuse valid are
are never triggering um but
you know this is this is par for the
course with the heisenberg
and one thing that i will say as well
that makes me like
extremely unhappy
about this um
one thing that makes me upset is i don't
actually know that this isn't some weird
release mode only thing
so
like if i'm really hoping this has
this is not like a microsoft compiler
thing
if this turns out to be a microsoft
compiler thing i'm going to be so
unhappy
but like we were seeing those spec valid
and diffuse valid things
were like wrong all the time in release
mode
like you didn't really have to do
anything to make them
go wonky um
xx the big info or whatever uh we
we don't actually have any um
different we we have fpfast in both now
it may be that when you have od
on it just doesn't do it um
but either way i mean most of our
lighting code is
cmd so like there is no
i don't even know what fpfast would even
really be doing
all that that's all that interesting um
which is not to say that it might not be
the case
i just don't know
is this guy gonna hop left forever
whoa
how did i pick up an what is happening
how did i gather this little dude
that's pretty impressive
so how did i end up doing this what is
causing that i'm very interested to know
now so
since we're in debug mode we should be
able to look at how we were able to
acquire this uh
skull friend i don't know what you want
to call that
but we definitely have acquired a skull
friend
right skullfriend is like
on is is like attached to us it's like
the skull friend is attached to our hat
currently right so if you look
it it looks like the skull friend is
literally like on
our hat
there's nothing particularly weird about
it it's just a skull friend
and somehow it's attached to our hat
let's take a look in the brain code
so i can't open a file right because
that'll open the wrong one so i need to
just look in here and then set the
breakpoint via name
so if i go in here and just do execute
brain
um
i'll just set one there so that we can
load the file
yeah so i'll look inside execute brain
and i'll just stop um
on the on the snake ones because i'm
pretty sure
i'm pretty sure these are all gonna be
brain snake
right um and
hopefully we should be able to see like
the snake parts
somehow um
i guess the problem is we don't know
really which one we're looking at
somehow
one of these got like attached
to the hero
and i suppose it could be well trying to
think if there's any way it could
be the hero controller controlling it
i mean you would think it would kind of
have to be because if the
it would have have to be disconnected
from this brain
now actually so really i guess
it would have to go through here
wouldn't it
so let's take a look at that
and let me take a look at head
head body glove
so here there's there's really only just
these three
and nothing else that comes through this
routine ever
this is a puzzler i don't even know
if i can think of how it would be able
to do that
like it's hopping along with me
right
it's actually leading me it's leading me
like it's got like the place where
like when my head goes in that direction
its
head goes all the way over there and
then it actually does
a jump
that's really amazing i
literally can't think of how we're able
to do that
it even takes the it even
picks the correct facing direction
for the skull
i'm sure this is just a case of the fact
that like i haven't
programmed on this game in a really long
time uh because we were away for a bit
and we were doing
like lighting for a really long time so
i'm sure it's just a case of like
if i my brain was more up to speed on
the entity system
it can't be as amazing as it seems
but it almost looks like someone added a
bunch of code to do this
on purpose because if we if you asked me
to do this if you're like
oh can you attach a skull to the
person's head
that like hops along but not not
directly attached to the head it kind of
just does its own hop
right and it follows it and all that i'd
be like oh
okay well we're we're gonna have to add
right we're
like i would i would have said we would
we would have to add
um
wait a minute
maybe not okay so let's
see here add player
so
does it always do
aha yes
i think i see what's going on now
hmm
okay so
maybe maybe
what happened here is that somehow
and this is not really a solution to how
the bug started but it's at least a
solution to how the bug
is happening i forgot that we don't
currently actually use the head
the head is just a piece
that's placed on
the body you can see that here
right so the entity for the body
is actually just has both of the
has all the has all the assets placed on
it right
so there's the glove entity and that has
a glove asset
that we're drawn where it is and then
there's the
body entity and that has the body the
head and the hat
like all of those are all on there
so the head actually doesn't normally
have anything associated with it
actually actually
so did it somehow get
a piece associated with it magically
so let's look at that first
so if i reset this breakpoint inside
here
we should be able to look at the head
and see if now it actually has
yes
so that's what happened
that's that's what actually happened
so normally the head would have
no pieces associated with it and somehow
it ended up getting the pieces
for a skull thing
right
so presumably this is a case of the
code not like it could just be a case of
the code
not initializing something properly so
like when an entity got unpacked it
didn't like clear it
or something so let's
before we kill this because you know
i don't actually know that we've quite
tracked it down
but when we unpack an entity
so you can see like we've got all this
stuff that we do
um didn't we just have a function called
fill
unpacked entity so why can't i find that
fill unpacked entity
here we go um
so you can see here where we do
our copy and clear we
we grab the entity data
that we were unpacking
we clear the part that
um
we clear the part that that is not saved
what does register entity do
so i want to see what happens in acquire
unpacked entity slot
so if you retrieve
one of these you're assuming you're
going to romp over the whole thing which
i think
is going to happen
my guess is
that that couldn't possibly produce the
overall problem the
the part where we need to allocate a new
world chunk
so yeah like this part here
i'm a little nervous about so when we
get a world chunk
do we actually clear that out before we
provide it back
because that may just be it
right
like this used chunk space thing
i'm going to go ahead and say that
is the problem so
it looks like in here we don't actually
clear this out when we go to make a new
entity
right so if we're going to
create a new entity into this
chunk it doesn't look like we ever clear
it which would be a bug
you know what i'm saying my
question is where does that actually
happen
and let's just see
now we do
so it looks like we do always clear it i
mean that's gonna clear that whole piece
of memory
right
so if every time we create an entity we
clear it
when we do the copy we copy so
that's gonna romp the whole thing with
valid stuff
so i guess i don't know what are some
clues
we could look for here that would tell
us
how this happened
you
i'm a little bit interested to know
so all that would have like literally
the only thing that would have to happen
is that brain ideas
brain id's value would get set to one
because the rest of this stuff
is already right like even just a
cleared entity would have these set
so it's it's only this that's actually a
thing
right
that all seems unremarkable because this
is just
it's setting things like the color and
you know in the dimension so on
so the things that are set to dim 1.5
like this has to and with piece count 2
i assume that has to be the snake
so like i'm guessing that if we look
we would see
no no
so we would see in here like the snake
would be
like a one point
five kind of a thing yeah
so add brain
that
aha
so now we may be getting
somewhere
aha
yeah okay this is just this is just a
case of me not remembering
what we did right
so here's what actually happened
right
yeah everyone sees it now right
y'all see it
does does the chat i'm looking at the
chat window
do you see the bug do you know what the
bug is now
i mean i can still be wrong we haven't
actually gone and like
looked at it but
no one's gonna answer no one's gonna
raise their hand
okay class who wants to tell me what the
bug is
you have enough information to know what
the bug is now
unless i'm wrong which i could be
floor is lava like raised is that you
raising your hand
enemy panda you were on reddit
how are you gonna find a bug on reddit
the whole thing is a bug
enemy panda do you have diamond hands
that's my question
are you making crazy money on stonks
yeah somebody took my names got it
and you've got it
only backwards
all right so the problem is we have this
concept of a reserved brain id here but
it looks like at some point
we just got rid of it because add brain
is
like not using that
right so as a result
it means like that so this this
we we i think we were just trying to be
saucy and we were like oh we can have
our brain
ids just use this because since
everything goes through a hash table
it doesn't matter right but the problem
is we had
used uh an allocation scheme for brains
for heroes here where rather than
calling ad brain
we just used like
and i don't actually know why
um like i don't know why this doesn't
call
ad brain or why we had reserved brains
in the first place
there may have been a reason it may be
that that reason
is gone in which case we could fix this
bug by just calling add brain
um
so i really don't know
i want to see if anyone ever uses that
reserved brain
id stuff at all
what was it called
so it looks like the reason we were
using that
is because when controller input comes
in
we needed a way of figuring out
what controller it was
right um
so it looks like
it looks like the reason for this is
just to have
a way of knowing what controller would
control which brain
and that seems okay i guess
i don't think there's a reason why we
wouldn't do that
so i think that just means like when we
create a world
we probably should just make the last
use entity be the oh
which we did
where is where is that at
reserved brain id there it is
so we actually did do that
so somehow the bug is not quite that
somehow even though we aren't picking
any of the reserved brain ids or we
shouldn't be
anyway picking the reserved brain ids
right
somehow we still ended up with the
correct brain id
in here right
somehow we still end up with that so i
take it back
this
is not coming from here
presumably i mean
we don't we don't know for sure right
but presumably
this is not coming
it's not coming from last used entity
storage index
no there's still a bug chat you're not
off the hook here
you so you still have you still have to
find the bug
just because it's not that bug
so i think we probably want to double
check that this is true
um so i'm not sure we
actually want to do that yet but
we do need some other coherent
explanation for why
we were able to put pieces into this
thing that has a brain idea value of one
right and furthermore
there should be more than one thing
going into that slot
at this point as well because like
or this got overwritten either because
there would have
also been an entity for the head
so the only two things that could have
happened are the entity for the head
had its pieces overwritten with snake
pieces
right um
or there are two and it replaced the one
that would normally have a brain slot so
what i'm kind of interested in knowing
here um is in like handmade
uh world mode where it does the brain
unpacking part um
i guess i don't know exactly where
that's happening
so right here
this
so in here we don't
check to see if there was already
something
in this slot right
so i guess what i would say is this
looks like
this looks like something that could
also be part of the problem right
so we could be doing something
where we are getting a brain
and we don't actually
and we yeah like if if the part where
the brain gets
gets created
if the part where the brain gets created
is like not
working correctly so here's us checking
here's us checking for brain hash slots
right get hash from id we pass
in an id value there we
use whatever the storage index
dot value is for the brain we loop
through the brain hash
by probing linearly
this does not seem like very good code
i i would just like to say that i don't
think this code is very good
um so i would say that this is a bit of
an issue
uh so if we take a look at the sim
region
you can see the brain hash in here right
um
and we're linear probing the brain hash
i'm assuming we clear it every time
yep so we clear it every time
and then we go through here and we just
linearly probe the brain hash
to find one that we can use
and you know
essentially what we do is we say if
there was nothing here we'll use
it if there was something here and it
happens to be the one we're looking for
well we'll use that as well
right and then that's it
we then say okay we will assume that we
got this thing
um
i'm not quite sure what this is about so
this is just saying look if there wasn't
any
a brain in there
then we use one that's in here
sorry no we use one that's in here
and this is just a bit over complicated
at this point as well but i guess the
reason we did this is so it would be
faster to clear it
right
so we use one that's in here and we just
record that fact into the brain hash so
that it'll be looked up again
that's basically it and we do the mark
occupied
on that hash
um
so i'm not horribly offended by this
it just seems like over complicated at
this point because i think it's gone
through enough iterations that's like
there's it it really could be much more
straightforward
than it is now um but i don't see any
obvious problems with it yet it gets
cleared every time and then the brains
are assembled so in theory that should
have been okay
and also even if it wasn't okay it
wouldn't explain why
we were able to get an entity that had
the right brain id
and the different pieces there
so if we go look for snake again
from metal gear solid
um
so there's a couple different things
here so
i'm also wondering because we know that
our transactional occupy thing
like our is occupied thing we broke
right
um and that was kind of on our list to
go things like our list of things to go
fix and it's a bit weird right that
that's happening
so we kind of want to know what's up
with that
and
i do wonder if there's any way inside
that that you can have something weird
happen i still don't know how you end up
with an entity that has this value for
the brain though
that's the reason why i thought we had
the bug because it seems like
the only way that should really happen
is if you called add snake and the add
brain call
for the brain id right
gave you back a one
one thing that's a little odd is why t
bob
and dt bob have floatmen so do we do
that
anywhere uh
so that would be f32 min or r32 min
right
hmm
so how did that get set to
floatmen i don't even see floatmen on
here actually because float min
float min is actually a different thing
it's the smallest possible value
representable by a float which we don't
really have
so like how did these get set to those
values
because that doesn't make a lot of sense
either right
i want to look and see i would like to
know
if other what what other
parts here have that yeah so
nobody else has that
so that seems really suspicious as well
that's just really weird i i don't know
why it has
those strange values for ddt bob
you
so how many people have hit point max
so in init hit points it is set
and it looks like that is the only place
where it is set
so in theory the only people who can
have this be true
are people who have init hit points
called on them so who has that there's
the function itself
here is the snake call
and here is the monstar call right
and we know it's not gonna be monster
okay
so we don't call this on anybody else
so we know for sure that this
is a snake head
like that's definitely true
because not only does it have the pieces
from the snakehead
but it also has the hit point max from
the snakehead
so there's only two possible things that
could have happened
one is that somehow we called
adds we we executed the add snakehead
stuff
and when it went to fill in the brain id
it filled in a one erroneously
or somehow we took a snakehead
that had the brain id value associated
with it filled out properly
but then we overrode it somehow so like
we
corrupted the value somehow
again it i literally can't think of how
something that precise would happen
because it's not like it wrote garbage
over the whole thing
it literally would have had to have
pinpointed that
you know what i mean
and i don't see anything weird going on
here like it seems like the add brain
function
is very straightforward it seems like it
would do
what you would expect
i don't really want to kill this
run of the game but i think i'm going to
have to and i also
want to know if i can reproduce this
so i'm going to try a couple things
first things first yeah
um i'm gonna snap step into all
calls to add snake and i want to see
what all of the snakes
get for their brain id uh
because first let's just check to see
what happens
all right so nothing particularly
strange happening there
let me just make sure
um
and let's look at how it is set
okay um
so i don't see any
an initial way that this could possibly
have set the brain id
to something else right
so that seems pretty straightforward
so we had to have called this and then
we have to
somehow be overwriting the brain id
part of it incorrectly like the copy
doesn't work
properly or something like this
so in the actual entity structure if we
go look at how it lines up
it's the first three things
yeah um
and when we do our copy inside the sim
region like doing the unpack
there um is it inside world
so um there's nothing particularly weird
about what happens here right so we do
the pack
um
the copy is pretty straightforward
there's nothing
strange about it really
so i don't see a lot of ways that that
could have been
corrupted either right
nothing weird there i mean this is all
really pretty straightforward
and you know like in theory if we had
something happen here like when you
called add entity
if it gave you back
the entity for the head here
so like if this call
here somehow gave you
back but you would see it immediately
you wouldn't
that would be when you first added the
player so even that can't really be true
right so that can't happen either
because you'd see it immediately you
wouldn't have to wait till you hop
down to where the other ones were
right
uh
this part's a little odd but again
shouldn't really
have anything to do with it because if
if start was never pressed
well i mean yeah well
yeah i'm not sure about that part this
seems a bit janky but again
not sure i see what this would have to
do with anything
um
like that just doesn't seem relevant
anyway
what is this
the heck
dude so wait a minute are you telling me
right now that this isn't a bug
this was a thing we added as a
feature at some point just for fun
hold on i think we may have just spent
this entire time
thinking there is a bug just because we
don't work on this game very often
it looks like we added the ability to
like pick up a head by hitting return
right it looks like we we've got code to
do this
hold on a second
yep
oops so we did that on purpose
uh my bad
so yeah that happened
uh and you can swap them
so i can like right
so we have the ability to swap heads in
the game
and i just forgot that you could do that
and the only reason that it wasn't
obvious i guess
is because when we did it
we because we use we make the pieces
for the head currently so like if if we
had done
oh man yeah this is the problem with
only programming once a week on
something
after a while you forget everything you
added
so like if we had done this
no wonder it was really hard to figure
out why there was a bug there was no bug
chat you're finally off the hook of
course you should have told me that
like so i don't really want to let you
off the hook i feel like you should have
you should have told me that but it's
okay so
if we had instead here oops
um if instead here instead of this
connect piece
um stuff that was happening here
uh so you can see the way this thing
connects the body
body piece nonsense here like headpiece
thing uh i think
really what we would do for that feature
is we would have had like
head headpiece like this
um and then this would have added
uh the head onto on
onto the head onto the the head entity
right um
and uh oops
yeah uh i think i'm not sure why is that
complaining what did i do wrong
uh head headpiece
i'm not sure why that is complaining
connect piece head headpiece
oh uh because the yeah we need to tell
it
yeah yeah we need to tell that that's on
the head as well
sorry um
so like we can't keep moving the head
way out in that direction anymore
because it disaggregates from the hero
obviously but i think
that's like what
we were either planning to do or used to
do when we added that feature right so
the head
was was linked onto the separate entity
so if you like went over here
and like did that um you swap
right you swap heads with whatever it is
that that there was what you know
whatever it is that you had um as long
as it was in a radius of 10 it looked
like it would just search
for anything that was a head swap right
um so that's
actually i kind of like that i mean that
seems cool
actually i'm i am in favor of this
so i think we're going to leave that in
i like that a lot
uh so yeah i think that's a good thing i
don't i don't think i don't think we get
rid of that
right um i think that's something that
probably stays in
and and so i think all we really want to
do at that point
is the head itself
has that sort of leaning problem
uh that we would we would sort of want
to
fix and
i guess i don't really know
so when we look at the head you can see
here that it kind of does a
some computation about the
way the head is attached there um
and you know this is the problem i would
assume
so like
so like probably this just needs to get
modified by something probably
i don't know let's let's go ahead and
run this uh
and we can just edit the code in real
time till we get something that we like
um so
we also have got a z offset there which
i don't think we necessarily want
um
i'm also not sure why does it disappear
why are we getting a disappearing head
on
moving forward like that
so
clutch is not happening clutches is only
was only when we were holding down the
space bar right so that's the clutch
thing
right uh
and that's obviously too much anyway so
you know this this would be something
way
less than that um
yeah so that would be the delta we would
want so you you probably want
like you know 0.3
plus or something i'm not sure
uh and then i'm just i just don't
understand quite what's going on here
it's like we've got some issue where
when we're going to the left
we we lose the head placement is
is borked right um now i don't know if
that's actually true
so i just want to double check and nerf
the entire expression temporarily
because it might be it's from somewhere
else no it's from there
so for some reason like you can't have
this ddp value coming through here so
something's totally
wrong with that ddp value so
like this process
has an issue maybe a bug with the way it
gets normalized
right and does it get used anywhere else
not really so it looks like this value
is kind of just
busted so let's take a look at what's
happening there um
so so i think this equation then is fine
you know modulo a little bit of tuning
we might want to do
but it looks like the ddp value is
just totally wrong also hop requested is
like
something that goes down here so we're
not going to do that right now
um so this ddp value if we look at what
happens it's taking the con
hero ddp which is this um
it's looking for the length of that
which seems fine
it's looking to see how long it is if
it's a particular length
it goes ahead and does a square root and
inverts
that uh so it's it's just trying to get
get a way to length like change the
length back to a normal
right um
i have no idea why you double normalize
that so so looking so what you can see
here is like right we
we take the length of this thing we say
if the length of it
is you know if it's non-zero basically
we normalize it
and then we can change ddp normal into
an actual normal
we then say if the if the length like
the motion like the speed
right is greater than one
we want to normalize that as well
uh
so we compute both the normal version
and
we normalize the thing if it's greater
than one which means we're trying to
produce a value
that becomes like
one sized when it's large right
i have no idea what we were doing there
but i guess it's like
you you want to look at the acceleration
for the guy and
like i guess we have the we allowed the
acceleration to
be up higher than one and if we wanted
it lower than one then we would just
shrink it down but if it was higher than
one we wanted to can't
clamp it so this is basically like a
clamping function right
why that would behave differently when
you were moving to the left than moving
to the right i'm not sure
so that's a little strange um
that's a little strange so all i'm gonna
do here
uh we've got this hopping right uh i'm
gonna
recompile in the problem
which is this right here
um so that we lose the head when we go
left
i'm going to take this out so the thing
that normalizes the ddp
is now gone
so it looks like it has nothing to do
with that clause so
we're not hitting this or if we are it
doesn't matter right
so it literally has something to do with
the con hero ddp
like moving leftward
which seems kind of strange because i'm
not sure
how that would pose a problem
but evidently it does so what i'm going
to do here
is i'm going to try modifying this
slightly
so instead of putting ddp in this place
i'm going to put
conhero ddp right so i'm going to use
direct oops
so i'm going to use this value directly
like what it gets constructed here right
so that now i know i'm just using that
value vanilla
then i'm going to go ahead and i'm going
to try putting in some various values
here
so for example if i look at what the
controller actually sets the ddp value
to
so i can you can see here that like here
here are the various values right
so this is the one that we expect to be
bad negative one
here and zero here yeah so
i'm assuming that now i could do that so
i could just place
negative one here and zero here
and that i would just get the head
missing all the time right
and it is and then i would expect to be
able to move it to the plus side
and have the head reappear which also i
can um
so that's pretty weird right like i
don't know why that would ever happen
so my guess is that
oh hold on a second i just heard a puss
come on come on come on
that's a good puss
sorry i had to let the puss in here is
puss
this is molly bean
this is our this is our sweet puss molly
she's a very good puss she likes to
be involved in programming activities
and it is probably time for brushing
do you want to be brushed yeah
of course you do
it's important for for good furs
for high-end furs
nice soft coat
yeah that's a good puss
that's a good puss
okay that's a good puss
that's a good place
okay so what we've got do you want to go
on my shoulder
want to go on the shoulder okay
so what we've got here is we've got
a uh
like presumably some kind of knock-on
effect i'm guessing because it would
seem a little weird if
setting it to a negative one there could
could actually cause
this problem directly that seems
odd i mean it's possible but it just
doesn't seem
all that likely um so i'm guessing that
some
uh unrelated value is just
uh put into a bad like there's some kind
of a
cop like a downstream computation is
what i'm assuming
what you're doing puss okay okay
um
i'm assuming there's like a downstream
computation in this case
that has some
when it happens to be just exactly that
negative one
right that that causes a problem
we can't actually uh see happening
but if we look down like if we go
inspect sort of the
the derived values that that use like
head p
for example which is the is the value
that we're setting here
if we find things that are related to
head p
we may find that there's something
obvious going wrong there
right so you can see there are multiple
places
where this comes into play
uh and so we would expect that like
maybe for example this head delta value
here
is a problem uh maybe the head distance
value here
is a problem uh
again we just got to kind of look and
see
sorry i gotta reset the microphone after
the puss the puss
adjusts the microphone often
what do you think puss
what do you think what do you think puss
all right so anyway uh we want to look
at the head p
here and we just want to see like what
things are related to it
so we have the head distance for example
uh that's computed
and the head distance does do like some
stuff here where we we map it into a
range and we change
this ddt bob based on what we see so you
know whatever this value actually is
here
um we we produce you know
some kind of a clamped value from it uh
i don't see a lot of problem there but
you know what i would do now is i'd say
we've got we've got this reliably
you know in us in a state where we can
turn the head off
by us by setting this negative one
so now let's just go and disable
anything that could be related to that
right so if we uh
take head p here and we just say
okay like this this thing this head
distance
where we set the body uh ddt well that's
the body though so i don't see how that
could really be related but
whatever we'll we'll remove it anyway
um so this way we we know we're not
setting that
ddt bob value right
and then i'm also going to remove
this head delta computation
and i'm just going to get rid of
everything that's related to the head p
at all so in here uh you can see there's
more but
those are outside of the the actual hero
brain function
so here you can see like the head has
returned
which would suggest that this head delta
value
is the problem in this case
so i think we can put this back in
right um and now we just have to focus
on what is going on with this head delta
value
so in terms of where this is used it's
literally in only two places
and this just looks like
nonsense so it's taking the head delta
and it's adjusting the y so that's
what's probably happening here is it's
totally
corrupting um
something to do with the body's y-axis
so that it can't
place the head at the correct location
or something like this
right um but we'll see
so let's leave this where it is
right and say that the head delta is not
going to be a thing
it's just not going to happen at the
moment
uh and then we're going to go in here
and we're going to
uh put this this ddp value back in
like so
um and and then that solves our
particular problem there
and so then all we really have to do is
go oh i see so
probably this head delta thing
this was trying to do some work here
where we were attempting
to use the actual displacement of the
head from the body which we expected to
be quite large
right um
we probably by by making it so that it
only moves a little bit
relative to the body um by putting in
that 0.1 maybe
uh well no it could have just it could
be just any
that anything was causing the problem so
maybe it was the problems there the
whole time
but we know that it has some some effect
in here so that two head delta lines
so i'm gonna remove this and we're gonna
narrow it down to which line it actually
is um so here's us moving
uh and you can see
it still happens i'm gonna get rid of
the floor displace
i'm gonna get rid of the y-axis
and so it sure looks like the main
problem anyway
is with the body y-axis setting
now why the body y-axis setting getting
set to something different
would cause the head to disappear is
kind of confusing because that you would
think
that the y-axis would do if it
was warped enough to make the head
disappear you would just
expect the body to be drawn improperly
as well
i i mean or at least that's what i would
have expected right
but that's not actually what's happening
here so
you know we're able to get the head to
disappear
um with this body y-axis setting
uh that somehow does
not actually cause the body itself to
warp
very much my guess there
is that we over we don't use the body y
axis maybe maybe we use some other thing
so that like when we draw the body it
just doesn't
get the it doesn't
inside the pieces when we draw them i
seem to recall we added a thing that
allowed us to just say
what axes you were using like do you
want to actually use does x or not
i would assume that that is what's
happening here so this
head delta x y bit here
is is going to pick up whatever that
stuff was for the y-axis
for the body y-axis right
so we know that if we do this where we
just have the y-axis set to
to nothing in particular right uh it's
just
it's just regular y um
that we get the correct behavior and so
the only question here was do we care
about
the other part now since we don't seem
to even use it i would say we can
probably just get rid of this
um i don't know what florida's place
does anymore because again it's been so
long since we've looked at this code
it was kind of mostly just stuff we
threw in there for placeholder anyway
but if you look at florida's place it
looks like that's
mostly there just to figure out if you
wanted to like make the thing
bob with the head bob right um
so i think that's fine as it is probably
so i think that's all we really need to
do and now we have our swappable heads
back
uh which seems good right
okay um so everything seems to be
working here the hero can hop in
have a little visit with one of the
orphans
we can go back down the stairs
uh we can steal ahead
and go back and have a conversation
and it's all fine
all right
all right so we still have the lighting
bug to look at for
so we're not quite done yet but at least
we're a little
closer um i think we've got all the tag
stuff done
so we're really just looking at lighting
now we can do a brief q a
before we stop
the the goal is uh
the head stealing feature by the way
kind of just has to go in the game now
that it caused that much
consternation so like we're we're gonna
have to just make that be a game play
thing
like that's just what's gonna happen
come on up come on up that's a good puss
okay
that was literally not a bug it was a
feature
uh i guess we must have some we must
have just
either someone asked a question about it
and i said sure we can do that or
sometime i was like let's test it and we
added that
so um i'm not sure
what yeah i i don't know why that
happened but it did
the coding environment is for coder and
we use
visual studios compiler
the linux branch has the debug release
bug as well and it triggers all the time
i set up okay great
um that's that's very good because um
the the hope is that it's not like a
code gen bug
so like hopefully we should be able to
find it uh we'll look at it next weekend
so it was a q a request okay well it's a
feature now like i'm
i'm going ahead and making that part of
the game so you can steal heads and the
heads will do things
i guess
uh george i don't know the answer to
that question but it is
true that switching to four coder flurry
means that the build is getting called
in a potentially different way
because before it was called with my
build thing
and now it is called with four coders
and so it may very well be that four
coder
is canonicalizing those now and wasn't
before which sucks because i don't
actually want it to do that
but it may well very well be doing that
ah so if you're talking about um
the background doing a weird thing
that's actually
obs being a pile of crap um
which is unsurprising it has nothing to
do with four coder and i have no idea
how to fix it
uh obs is just a gigantic pile
uh and that's just kind of how it goes
at the moment
what ends up happening is anything that
just has like a constant color
background
um like that sometimes just freaks out
i've had it for like doing for capturing
like visual studio
as well um and i i
do not know fundamentally what it is i
you know
who knows i don't know if it's ddr box
man striking again
uh or what it is but
it's a uh it's an obs bug
or a black magic bug i i
have never seen it happen in the actual
obs window so i don't
so it seems like it's a problem uh
so i don't think it's ddr box man
this time i assume it's like a codec
problem
or something with the part where it
actually does
the compression
and i do not know what is going on uh
it's just
you know we we looked at the obs code
right
we now know it's complete pile so
who the heck knows what's going on in
there something fantastic
i'm sure uh but how we would go about
fixing that i have no idea
right um
and and so you know like
something in the 200 layers of code that
that
happen between calling blackmagic to get
the thing
and handing it through 17
different ffmpeg plug-in nonsense who
the heck knows
um something's broken but i i
have no idea how that's ever going to
get fixed right it probably just never
will
or if it does get fixed it'll get fixed
accidentally right
um i also don't know if we can update
obs because i don't know
if the if anyone ever fixed the ddr box
man problem
so it may be that the latest versions of
obs have the ddr box man bug
fixed in which case we could try just
upgrading to obs to see if someone
accidentally fixed the bug in the codex
or whatever is happening for that weird
strobing effect
again that's assuming that it's not a
bug in the blackmagic capture it could
be that i'm just
not noticing it like it's happening and
i'm just focused on the other screen so
i don't see it happening
and it is actually happening in the
capture but at least i have not actually
seen that yet so i haven't actually seen
the weird strobing effect happening in
the actual live view
it only seems to come out in the actual
stream recording
uh so so it has to like pass through the
codec
first i think
someone asked the swap would work on the
orphans as well not
currently if we probably will want to do
that now that we know it's a
feature but the reason it doesn't do
that is because
the orphans at the moment don't actually
have heads
i don't think so the orphans at the
moment are
are just like a static piece of geometry
so we should probably just create the
orphans as
actual little entities and then they
would be head swappable yeah so we
should we should definitely do that
but
well again stunt coder that i mean
that's purely conjectural though right
like you have no idea what's happening
there
it it may be that it just only happens
sometimes because
there's tons of windows that don't have
the problem and then sometimes they do
right
so i mean how would we know that black
would make a difference
you
um all right so it doesn't look like we
have any questions
uh we yeah so if you know
um
oh uh duff g no it's it's not twitch
so this happens in the actual videos
recorded from obs
you don't you don't have to stream
through twitch
so twitch twitch is not adding that
artifact
i mean twitch may also be adding the
artifact since i don't watch the twitch
stream i don't know if there's like more
artifacts
but you i get the um
i get the artifacts from
in the locally saved obs recording so no
like no twitch no twitch involved
like like even if i even if i don't even
have streaming turned on if i'm just
recording locally
that strobing artifact happens
right so uh it's
it's something to do with the way that
they've
modified the recording in obs
or it's a black magic capture problem
and i i don't know like
the the optimal thing would be if
i could do a recording and get the
strobing to happen
with one that i watch the obs window for
the whole time
so i can verify that it doesn't happen
in the capture
it only happens in the codec
but i i can't actually
until i've done that i don't actually
know for sure that it isn't a capture
problem
because it could be either or
so
is there any scheduled ending uh no we
have not scheduled any ending
at the very least we now know that we
will not stop the series until we
actually can swap heads with the orphans
all right
thank you everyone for joining me for an
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you
would like to follow the series at home
you can always pre-order the game
on handmadehero.org and it comes with
all the source code so you can follow
along at home
maybe you would like to go try to find
the lighting bug
supposedly it's reprobable at home folks
have said it is
so you know now's your chance to try
hunting down a pretty hard bug
right uh i'll be back next weekend to do
that we seem to have gotten rid of all
the other
things that we needed to fix up uh with
respect to tags our trees are back
um our
our what was the other thing we did the
um
cutscenes couldn't think of the word our
cutscenes are back
so all that stuff is good um and so all
we got to do now is track down that
lighting bug and then i think we're on
to new features
and we'll be back to do that next
weekend uh that's it for today
until then have fun coding everyone and
i'll see
everyone on the internet take it easy
everybody
uh