start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show where
we code a complete game live from
scratch on Twitch new libraries no no
engines and we are kind of right in the
thick of it right now doing some fairly
interesting graphics coding actually
speaking at the from scratch stuff we
are working on doing how we want to do
lighting and we left off yesterday with
a bug and the bug was actually solved at
least I'm 99% sure it's all I haven't
actually tried checked it myself but I'm
99% sure itself on the forums by slapped
silly username so hats off to you for
for I think getting guessing what the
bug actually was before we actually
covered it on the stream so without
further ado let's go talk about what the
bug was or is and verified that that's
actually true and fix it
so before I get started just a quick
reminder today's day one zero three so
if you happen to have pre-order the game
on handmade hero not org and you'd like
to follow along please go ahead and
download the source code pack the latest
source code pack and unzip day 102 out
of that pack that will put you exactly
where I am today so you can follow along
if that is something that you would like
to do so here is a quick synopsis let's
first of all remember what the bug
actually was I suppose just so we can
sort of you know bring everyone up to
speed so if you'll notice we're doing a
total debug view right now so this is
not the bug this is a debugging view
that we did and what we did is we just
started drawing we're in our these are
our Maps here this is one environment
map this is another environment map
right and this one we're not using quite
yet but we had to sort of notions of an
environment map a top and a bottom and
what we found is that one of the maps
appeared to be reflecting properly or at
least not obviously wrong when we
implemented it and the other one was not
and you can sort of see what's going on
up here actually we
ended up drawing where we were sampling
from the map I'm just kind of cool and
you can see that even though we were
expecting to see a fairly blobby region
like this we actually got this very thin
sliver and we have no idea why that was
happening we were like this doesn't make
sense we check things fairly carefully
and they looked reasonable now what
actually ended up happening I'll sort of
explain on the on the blackboard real
quick if I can find where is mischeif
did mischeif go away I feel like
mischeif is gone
Wow I don't know where mischeif went but
I guess we'll go ahead and bring it back
up again
somebody must have closed mischeif I
don't think it was me all right so let's
let's talk about it it's actually a very
very simple bug assuming that it's
correct in what our servers ation was on
the forums but let's just talk quickly
about what it was so here on day 103
right basically here's the deal we
already had a bug essentially about this
and it just didn't occur to me that we
would essentially have another one and
that is because the way we were
computing our reflection map right is we
were saying well let's suppose we're
looking let's suppose this as a top-down
view of the game right then we'll
basically say well we've got a
reflection map that essentially is is
you know going to kind of line up with
the screen right and we drew a
checkerboard on it right so we kind of
got this sort of thing so for testing
we've got that checkerboard on it and
what we want to do is we want to pretend
right if we were to look at this from
the side in a sort of more a little more
perspective II kind of way so there's
just we can understand what's happening
just kind of see what's happening a
little bit better we wanted to pretend
that if this was say the sky right up
here so here's the sky right
checkerboard if this was the sky and
someone was down here we want to cast up
at it and see where we hit so we know
what we should be reflecting right and
that's a pretty reasonable thing
to think of doing we wrote the code for
that it seemed okay but we ended up
having weird reflection patterns on one
of our maps and it was like what's going
on well what we were doing of course is
we were using the screen space UV so
like when we were drawing our sphere we
were using the screen space UV of the
sphere to figure out where to start the
castrum so if here was the sphere we're
starting the cast at each point on the
sphere wherever it was on the screen
right which seems like a very sane thing
to do if you think about a sphere
sitting here that's exactly what it
should be right you want to start from
the 2d location wherever it was on this
plane and cast upwards makes perfect
sense problem is just like before we're
not actually looking down on some
sprites so for example the trees and
that sort of stuff and the sphere are
like cards that are sort of sticking up
out of the plane in terms of their
perspective and we see them flat on
against the ground even though they're
sort of in this weird lien and it's just
a conceit of how to diem artworks that
we allow that it doesn't make any sense
in terms of the perspective of the game
but that's just how we tend to do it
when we do those isometric things you
know normally if it was really any kind
of reasonable top-down perspective
they'd be much more tilted than they are
so since that was the case as we move up
on that card like the base point the
actual location of the entity is
correctly where we should start sampling
but and as we move left to right our
x-coordinate is totally also correct
right so starting the the cast from the
x-coordinate off of the base is totally
correct the problem is when we move up
and down up and down actually
corresponds to Z movement for sprite
cards like this not Y movement right it
does not correspond to Y movement in any
way so we were pretending we were moving
this way for casting when really we were
just going straight up and down and so
the reflection we were getting was
actually logical if somehow than those
normals which are all pointing the other
way
were somehow smushed onto a flat Fang
that was lying on the ground which is a
totally it can't happen like normals
couldn't be pointing that way on a thing
that was flattened right it's as if you
had a thing you know if we're standing
here this is the ground and here's the
card all the normals are like pointing
out of this thing but now we're
interpreting it as if it was flat here
so this normal is like here and pointing
that way it's just nonsense
right it's a nonsensical thing which is
why we were getting a reflection that
looked just totally weird
right so what would happen of course is
the reason that we were getting the flip
where the bottom half would be fine in
the top half would would not be is
because that was what determined whether
or not the reflection movement was going
with the grain of motion up the up the
card or against it and if it was going
against it it would tend to collapse the
area of the reflection if it was going
with it witty long gait and that's why
we have to these are both wrong I
believe it's just this one doesn't look
that wrong and it's hard for our eye to
tell that it's wrong because you know
humans aren't perfect we can't just look
at an arbitrary weird checkerboard test
boundary like oh that reflection doesn't
look like like maybe if we actually were
wearing you know valves 3d glasses and
we're looking at a real scene we could
like look at it and go yeah that's
that's not right like my intuition all
works here and I can see the whole scene
and I can tell that's wrong maybe that's
true but in a 2d perspective where
things are already intentionally wrong
because the art wants them to sort of be
different there's no way for us to
really see that error I think so I
suspect both of these are actually
incorrect we just didn't quite focus on
this one as being wrong we we had some
nosed inclinations that maybe not
everything was quite right but you know
there there we have it so that is what
we we need to fix starting now right
and fortunately I think that's not a
particularly difficult fix we just need
to kind of do a little bit futzing with
determining sort of what the base point
we just need some notion of what the
base point of this card is so that we
kind of know all right
here's here's our central cast point
here's our X span which is the same as
it was before but then our Y will move
us up and down in Z for these types of
cards that seems like a like a pretty
straightforward thing I don't think
it'll be too difficult to do but that's
what we got to do and so I think that
will will fix our problem here if that
makes sense because and to be a little
clearer about why that's the case the
reason we need that base point is we
still do need to know where to start the
cast from so we still need to have some
notion of where you know where in the
world we're supposed to be casting from
and since we don't really know if this
thing is like floating or what it's
doing we kind of want to have some
notion that comes in from the game that
says hey this is where this thing
actually is in the world and here is how
I want you to interpret its coordinates
in terms of in terms of casting so we
kind of need to get a little bit of a
handle on that right alright so let's go
ahead and get that started
wait I should already have an e max it
looks like I typed D max yeah I guess I
closed it down I guess I closed it down
before we started all right so let's go
ahead and go into render group here and
first of all we can take a look at the
offending notion essentially it's it's
the screen space UV bit right the screen
space UV that we passed to this guy has
to be corrected and the way that we're
doing that as you can see is we're just
using the x and y coordinates directly
and so what we want to do is we want to
think more carefully about exactly what
we're doing there first of all we want
to say that our y coordinate is is
probably not something that we're
actually ever going to use directly
based off of the M
max right so really our y-coordinate for
screen space UV for cards is going to be
something like our fixed cast Y or
something right like that's just gonna
be some value and then our y-coordinate
is actually going to be not so much
about where we are in when Y here that's
going to be actually more about where we
are in Y off of of the axis so it's
actually the V coordinate that we
actually care about right the V
coordinate tells us how far up the card
that sort of sprite card we actually
were right
and again we're a little bit messed up
right now because we haven't done a
coordinate system finalization but we're
just going to assume that everything
goes bottom-up even though it doesn't
quite yet just so we can get the math
right in here and then very next thing
we'll be doing next week will be the
coordinate pass so you know we should
have everything to be able to tighten
everything up at that point and make
sure everything is totally kosher before
doing any sort of optimization work so
what we want to do here is take that
screen space UV which we're passing
right and now we want to essentially
offset the screen space UV if necessary
now we don't have really any need to
offset the cast Y for cards it's fixed
what we do want to do is offset the Z
height of the thing by whatever our V is
times some height that we want the card
to be in Z like how tall should this
tree be right and that's what we'll use
so when we're down here all we really
have to do is say okay when we compute
that distance from map can Z this is
actually now going to be based on V
right so it's actually going to be 2.0
right that's the distance the map is you
know in Z let's say right and in fact I
guess what we could do is say let's
let's not actually well I guess we could
still do it this way and then say all
right depending on which one of these we
are we can talk about how far away it is
based on the motion that it actually
yes and I suppose actually we don't need
to do that here we can just add it in
right here right so we want to do a
height of of card is the thing we want
to do here we want to say okay however
far our way the map was as we move up
the height of the card right the
distance of the map is either going to
get smaller or greater depending on
whether we're moving away from it or
towards it now the map distance from map
in Z is going to be negative on the
bottom right
so as the the the height of card
consuming as as we move we just have to
figure out I should do this on the on
the blackboard sorry we just have to
figure out a good way of making sure
that we always get the sign right so the
way that we have it right now right is
if we're talking about the top guy or
the bottom guy this will either be
negative right or positive depending on
which one it is so as we move up the
card in in V right and I suppose you
know what V is not really a hundred
percent correct either now that I think
about it because we could be rotating
and so really what we want to do is
figure out the the direction this way
that we are up off of of the base right
whatever that base point actually is or
if that's the center point here is
something like this right what we really
want to do is find that right so I guess
now that I think about it I was I was I
was off I was off I was not correct this
is not going to be fixed cast Y it will
be this the difference is just that it's
going to be I'm sorry my bad that's not
what I meant
I meant the Z the difference is it will
still be that value it will still be
sort of the the Z difference will still
be based on the Y it's just going to be
based on the Y's difference from
whatever some fixed point is
in space right meaning we don't know
exactly how we want to measure it but I
guess it's probably should be from the
origin of the coordinate system right so
if this is the origin of the coordinate
system let's say what we want to do is
say alright we're gonna tell you the the
thing that's doing the rent that's like
issuing these rendering commands the
game is gonna say this is at this
particular Z height I'm telling you that
and furthermore I'm telling you how far
in Z I want you to go how what the
height in meters actually is and and we
could actually have this be a constant
thing which is like a Y 2 meters
conversion that basically just tells us
ok as we move in Y how many you know in
meters 2 pixels is probably a good
approximation of it right because that's
what we're doing we're basically saying
the inverse of that however many pixels
we go up we want to know how many meters
we actually moved and that would be how
far off of that base z height we were
right so we I I misspoke when I said we
don't need that fat anymore we do need
that value we just need to know what it
actually is relative to the origin of
our coordinate system which we need to
figure out right so the origin of our
coordinate system is this guy so what we
want to do is say all right
the origins Y we subtract that away and
now we've got our Delta this is now our
Z difference it's whatever we we invert
here this is our this is our z
difference this would be this would be
in pixels so really instead of invite
max we just need something that's kind
of like got that that conversion factor
built in right so we want a pixels to
meters here that will turn this z diff
into something that as a proxy is in
actual world space right so then once we
get to distance from map in Z we're not
using that we're using Z diff like so
and now we just have to get back to the
sign thing so sorry I totally misspoke
there when I said it we don't care about
V V would be rotating around and not
giving us a reliable value so we
actually want to know we actually do
want to know that Y basis okay so back
to here we've got our Z value whatever
our xiv base value actually is and
you know in that's actually something
that we probably want to to bake in here
as well so distance from map in Z being
to like this is something we probably
should actually parameterize in fact we
could actually do something like um you
know what is the the origin Z kind of a
thing whatever our origins evaluate is
the distance from the map is actually
going to be is actually going to be
based on that in some sense like trauma
thinking how to explain this since at
the moment this distance from map in Z
is totally relative to some imaginary
thing we couldn't do something like say
we've got these two maps like we've got
the top and the bottom map right we
can't do something like say we've got
the floating head and it's up here so it
should be reflecting close to the top
and we've got some ball sitting on the
ground and it should be reflecting close
to the bottom right there's no
information about that there's no
information about the relative height of
the sprites right so what we kind of
want to do I think is turn this into a
little bit more sane equation first
which is to say let's first compute
where we are in Z so this is just our Z
like this is our Z position right in our
Z position would be like some origin Z
value that we're saying is where we're
starting at right in that origin Z value
is going to be modified by this the z
diff right so it's actually going to be
it's going to be doing this sort of
thing so whatever our origin Z is we're
going to modify that by the z diff so
we'd be going like up you know if it's
if we're getting higher or down if we're
getting lower
that's our PZ and then instead of doing
distance from map in Z we would just do
something like map Z right which is like
where the map actually is and what we
could do for that to make things much
cleaner I think is just say this is the
maps location in Z right like this is
where it actually is so then we don't
actually have to deal with any of this
stuff we can just say
okay the distance from the map in Z is
just going to be consuming is just going
to be entirely based on subtracting the
two values just like we would do in any
other vector situation so like the far
map if we've got one right we just go
ahead and take the far map Z wherever
that is in Z and we say okay to get to
the map you would go from where we are
and Z to that right and then it'll
automatically be negative or positive
based on whichever way the map was to us
and since we're picking which one it is
based on the normal direction it should
all work out okay for us right so I
think that's a little bit saner to start
with let's go ahead we've got a bunch of
stuff we got to clean up now so so
there's that but yeah so what we want to
do is say I guess we want to I suppose
we could probably just assume that our
fixed cast position I think we want to
pass this in eventually so I'm gonna I'm
gonna say that our fixed past cast
position is is is going to be at the
origin of our thing for now but that's
probably not what we want to do we're
gonna need more control over these
things eventually and so we'll have to
think through how we want them all
specified but for now we can just go
ahead and assume that it's at the origin
so this will need to be specified
separately so for right now we could say
that you know origin Z we could say that
that was just at 0 for now it's or
something like this or you know or 1 I
don't even know 0.5 who knows so we
could say whatever we want to say for
origin Z and then we can also for our
fixed cast Y our fixed cast Y position
could just be whatever that initial
origin is wherever wherever the origin Y
actually happens to be like so and so
that can be I could be computed down
here after we have those values like so
and then our pixels to meters
I feel like pixels to meters is
something that we normally do have in
terms of rendering information right we
have needles meters to pixels so we
could easily do pixels to meters here so
I'll go ahead and pass meters to pixels
or sorry pixels to meters right like so
and then here we can just pass one over
hmm our what do we actually call it here
it is rendered rip okay
so we're not quite there yet we're
getting there but we also now when we
actually make those maps we have to say
where we want the maps to be so we you
know when we're actually sort of
producing them we have to sort of give
them a height in the world that says
where the map should exist so when we're
doing this this setting them up here
when we're actually drawing into them we
can also take a second and say that the
trans state end maps right for each map
and I think we actually said which which
ones they are here so zero is bottom so
you know our our bottom map is going to
be temporarily at that maybe we'll do
that sort of a thing and this will be
like the sky will be maybe two meters
above us I don't know it's just an
example
oops QZ so and that'll just say where
that we want those maps to be for now so
there we go and then we have two well I
guess we got a we got a couple different
things we might want to do but for the
moment let's let's let's see let's keep
keep taking a look at this stuff here so
looking at where we are casting right
now
yeah I couldn't unfortunately I'm gonna
say I don't necessarily know exactly
what I think should be happening on
these so I don't even know how close
that is yet it's a little confusing to
say the least but I would like to go
through the code once before we actually
do any more work on it anyway but I just
kind of wanted to see where we were at
on on that so yeah let's just go ahead
and let that lie for now if that's okay
with you guys
so all right going back up here and also
we can we can probably take our sample
stuff and and turn it off for a second
just so we can kind of see what the
result is so here is our little thing
that you know if you want to see turn
this on to see where in the map you're
sampling yeah okay so there's our our
new reflective sphere right and I would
say that at least it's looking a little
saner now but I still think our top
reflection is probably still a little
borked although it's hard to say
obviously our top reflections actually
our bottom reflection I think
technically right however you want to
think about that but either way well
that's kind of interesting
that is really bizarre how that's
looking actually huh sorry I'm just a
little bit mesmerized by that so anyway
yeah I mean like I said I still think
we've got a little bit of work to do to
make sure that all the changes that I
made are actually correct here but I
think we're getting there all right so
let's go through this step by step so at
the moment we're essentially saying that
everything no matter where is in the
world it's just going to come in at the
origin Z of 0.5 so it's like halfway you
know it's always halfway in between the
two maps that's just where it's going to
be or I guess it's not quite halfway in
between the two maps I could for now set
it to halfway just so we can kind of see
if they're similar so this would be
halfway in between the two maps right
and they are quite quite similar now so
that's actually that's actually
definitely an improvement from where we
were similarly I suppose we could we
could go ahead and do it this way for
testing at the moment we could say this
was it you know the similar values to
what we were using before and then we
can sort of see what those look like
right there's our there's our we're at
zero and then we have a map that's
negative to below us negative 2 meters
and then 2 meters above us basically and
if you look at what happens there it's
actually you know it's actually somewhat
reasonable you know not too bad again
not not sure about it but it's it's much
more sane I think than we were getting
so let's keep going so we're specifying
origin C and now like we're two away on
either one of these we're saying and the
fixed cast location in Y is just going
to be wherever the origin of the thing
was so that's like whichever one of
these quarters is the origin and we
could actually figure out which one that
was right we can say draw a rectangle
outline we could actually oh you know
what we could do let's say for now that
the origin is actually the middle
because that would be a fairer thing
in terms of how we are comparing our
stuff so what I'll do is I'll say the
fixed cast Y is actually going to be the
origin plus the x axis plus the y axis
in half amounts right so sort of like go
to the center of this thing and that's
actually going to be that cast location
right so now we should be the middle
should be sort of of this guy should be
where we're thinking the we're actually
casting from hopefully that's the goal
anyway so that's our fixed cast location
that's where we are in terms of moving
around on the bitmap and in terms of
taking a look at that we can take that
out of the equation if we want to write
we can always say that the screen space
UV just equals 0.5 point five we wanted
to make it be in the center for example
right if we just wanted to say it
doesn't actually matter where it moves -
oops there and so you know if we are in
that circumstance then since we have a
spherical normal map what we would
expect is not to see any changes at all
except in you know these these outer
regions here and that is what we see for
the most part although little okay so
there's definitely some changing going
on there so that seems sort of wrong to
me although I guess now I think that so
that I think bears inspection so if we
are not moving the screen space UV and
since it is spherical I would like to
know why we are getting that change
let's stop the displacement as well
and take a look at that disk so if we
stop the displacement so oh yes we'll do
it this way so if we stop the
displacement and leave it in the center
right so now we know that there's
literally nothing happening except the
rotation we can definitely see changes
in these guys which we should not be
seeing right so let's just trip let's
take a minute and track that down
because that's definitely I believe a
bug that should not be happening but
let's keep so let's keep walking through
this and see if we can't figure out
what's going on there so we've got our
pixels two meters and in fact this now
should always be the same as well and so
the difference between these two things
should be should should not there should
be none right between those two things
yeah and it seems like that's relatively
correct right like it's going to be a
little bit different because the
location isn't quite exactly the same ah
well I guess I should say the screen
space UV has to actually move across the
face of the thing so this is not
actually a fair test not I think about
it I do I am Not sure though why the
rotation is causing that thing but now I
think about it that's really not a fair
test because we have to very over the
face of it it's only this the center of
the thing that wouldn't have to change
but anyway so since we're staying in
this is actually the fairer test staying
in one place and making sure that the
sphere does not change as it rotates and
that looks pretty good
let me verify it's the throat and rather
slowly so what I might want to do here
is just kind of speed up the rotation a
little bit so that we can get you know a
little clearer picture of what's going
on I'd also like to maybe move this down
so these things are nearer to each other
there we go so the rotation is right
here and so what I want to do is speed
this up a bunch just so we can see if
there's anything
oops if there's anything going on there
okay so we're still you can still see
that we are actually working right as we
rotate and I feel like we should be able
to get it down to where we're not having
that happen you know I don't know if
maybe our normal transform isn't quite
right yet or whatever's going on but
there so I think we've got some work to
do all right
so fixed in place and you know what I
can also turn back on our sampler
because then we can see what's happening
to the shape which will help us
potentially debug it so I'm gonna go
ahead and turn that on like so
yeah so we're oscillating we're actually
changing who is who is large and who is
small in terms of our sampling there
which is commas are but let's so let's
work through it so we come down here
we're doing our normal sampling like so
and I suppose one thing we could do we
did this before that would kind of be
helpful here is let's see what that
bounce Direction actually looks like
so after here after do that let me just
romp over the Texel RGB with actually
the bounce direction so we'll just do a
point five point five point five times
the bounce direction and oops times 0.5
times bounce direction that way plus
let's just take a look at that and see
it looks pretty stable to me like I
don't see there's a little fluctuation
in there I guess but I feel like it's
pretty stable right I mean there's not
the outside obviously is changing but I
feel like the inside is is staying
relatively stable and you know we could
also if we wanted to actually go ahead
and make a version of this where we have
that sort of that test let's see where
it is here we've got test defuse so test
defuse oops test defuse where we
actually make that test defuse what we
could do is go ahead and actually make
test defuse also be a sphere so we could
say make sphere diffuse map as well and
make test diffuse like so and that might
actually be interesting as well right
and so if I go up to mix your normal map
if I was to take this function and just
make
another test function here which is like
makes your a diffuse map then what I
could do I'll get rid of the Russell
boobs I'll get rid of the roughness
coefficient Shakespeare diffuse map
essentially exactly the same code but
the only difference here is in the
diffuse map we'll actually put in an
alpha channel that will allow us to
determine where where the sphere
actually is right so if we go ahead and
take a look at this we could just say
use this root term thing and and know
which one we want right so all we need
to do here is say that we've got
essentially a color we've got the color
x color Y color C and that's always
going to be actually I guess this is a
base color or something like that okay
we'll have the base color will be white
and this keyboards driving me nuts I had
to send my as you know from yesterday's
cream I had to send my my actual
keyboard off to get our M aid they don't
make them like they used to anyway and
this value will actually just be the
Alpha and so what I want to do is I want
to compute the Alpha here and we'll just
do it a very simple way we won't
actually do coverage at the moment what
we'll do is we'll say all right get rid
of the normal term and instead what
we'll do is say all right whatever you
know I guess we don't end Z I don't even
know why that was defined up in there
when we actually do this if the root
term is greater than zero then the Alpha
will be 1.0 otherwise the Alpha will be
zero I guess it's already zero so that's
fine and that'll allow us to do a map
that kind of clips the sort that those
sort of bogus normals out of the way for
us right so if we if we go ahead and
rerun this now
oh right and we got a pretty multiply
that as well so let's go ahead and take
that into account
so the Alpha value needs to 55 0.5 times
alpha and we also need to go ahead and
multiply this by alpha so that's
pre-multiplied alpha since we're
premultiplied alpha everywhere at the
moment think that should be correct that
is definitely not correct what did I do
wrong there make sure a diffuse map
either the alpha 0 or 1 the color is
going to be that looks totally that's
not right I'm asleep I'm asleep the
switch today people let's be honest it's
just not just not fabulous
so that looks loops more like it
go and since alpha is just going to be
255 or 0 basically through there we
could also multiply the alpha by 255 on
the way in which would do that
automatically for us so we can just do
this and then that should take care of
it automatically right
so that seems good right now four times
and let's give it another go okay so we
now just need to make sure this actually
doesn't overwrite it I'm assuming it
doesn't textile RGB so we would just
need to do Texel RGB where premultiplied
alpha again so we just need to multiply
by a and that should just work there is
our sphere that was harder than it
should have been if I wasn't asleep
today that would have gone quicker but
either way it's okay so we can kind of
see here I feel like it's pretty easy to
verify that our bounce Direction does
not appear to be changing am I correct
like I don't see the bounce Direction
looks fairly constant certainly not
varying enough to make this difference
happen right so I feel like that's good
let's go ahead and say if zero out on
here
this is draws the bounce direction so
what else we got what else is actually
plausible to you know to actually be
changing if the bounce Direction
computation is not changing what is
changing so there's the P Z value right
which is the origin z plus the diff see
there is the screen space UV but that
should be relatively constant now across
the surface so I do wonder about let's
go take a look at that z diff and just
see what that looks like at the moment
so what if we take the z diff out of the
equation for a minute then it's constant
so that's what we want to see so if we
just if we just take a look at that for
a second I feel like that indicates to
me at least to some degree that the
if is is bogus and so the question is
why are we getting such a erroneous such
an erroneous computation of our z diff
there and
so I guess now that I think about it
that's actually the way it would work if
it was based off of the origin of the
coordinate system because as it spins
you're going to have more of it going
below so that's actually that's actually
sort of right right and probably means
we don't really want to specify it this
way going forwards but if you think
about what that means you know if I've
got this and this is my origin and I'm
saying that this is at zero if I then
rotate down like so
even if I move this up to a cop to
account for it and try to put it in
exactly the same place so the spheres
are overlaid this point on the sphere is
now considered to be lower because it's
lower than the origin point as opposed
to here where it was higher than it so
that may indicate that we don't really
want to do it that way
so that rotating things don't have to
counter themselves I'm not sure exactly
how we want that to work but what we
could say is you know we've got this
this thing here we could say we have an
origin Y you know that is that's this
sort of a deal right if that's our
origin Y like so then we could that's
not pretty capitalizes it then we could
imagine this being a little saner there
let me just verify that fail like so if
we were to use that value now it's at
the center of the sphere and that is
going to be consistent across the
rotation right so if we do this and
so there it's constant again as we're
rotating around so that's remaining
constant like exactly like we expect
that it should be so I'll go ahead and
turn off the sampling overdraw for the
moment as well and so hopefully that
will get us back to to something
reasonable oh and we're gonna have to
make our sphere dark enough to be able
to see what we actually contribute in
terms of lighting right because right
now it's full bright so the light can't
actually add anything to it so our
diffuse map should probably start with a
base color that's dark in fact we could
just make it well no let's make it well
if we're doing lighting we'll make it
black just so we can see you know the
perfect reflection on it it's just all
it's all light that's incoming so there
we go there's our sphere which is nice
and stable at the moment yeah looking
much much better we probably still have
a little ways to go but at least we're
looking much better so let's go ahead
and allow it to move around again we'll
take a look at that disp will let disk
kick back in so there's our sphere
that's moving around and that's a very
plausible that now looks very plausibly
like what should happen to the
reflection during motion so the only
thing that I think is a little
potentially broken right now is I feel
like the reflection shape is a little
odd and should be more curved but we'll
have to think about that a little bit so
anyway that's the primary thing that I'm
thinking of I'm just looking at that
there in terms of other bugs that we may
want to look at we also have the
bilinear sampling at the edge that's
causing little sparkly as I'm not sure
what we really want to do about that
because that may not actually be a
problem because if we if we actually
properly set those to be sort of blurred
for bilinear sampling something we'll
talk about a little bit later in the
string in the series that may actually
not be a problem but we're getting
pretty good it's getting more certainly
getting more marble like at the moment
which is pretty awesome I'm like in
there without looking it's very nice and
stable I don't see a lot of bugs in
there so I think the only thing we
really want to verify is that that
reflection shape is not wrong but I
think we're we're just about there so
with that we'll leave that we'll leave
that where it's at
I guess and we will go to the QA
these Seven Samurai the reflection is
inverted the edge should be the center
and vice versa and and Carl and Oh bloom
thinks as well yeah me too I mean I just
I feel like it should be reflected this
way right it should bow it should bow
inward and so I'm assuming we've got one
more math bug in there but I think we're
pretty close it looks much more nice and
stable now and and so I think we're I
think we're just about there I guess in
the Q&amp;A if nobody has any Q's we can go
continue to pursue it we could go take a
take a look at the math now and see what
we've got
Tecna Rath how long do you anticipate it
will take before we get into more game
designing type topics rather than
building up the engine so if you're if
you're interested in game design this is
not really gonna be the stream for you I
am NOT a game designer and so we won't
really ever be doing game design a-type
topics if that makes sense
we will only be doing game
implementations so we're only you know
we're only doing we're only doing engine
implementations these sorts of things
and game implementation but we're doing
implementation not design
Oh stellar seven you know what you're
right we do have 12 minutes left of
normal stream time because we started 12
minutes late so let's just use some more
of the Q&amp;A let's use a little bit more
of the QA - since since I am of the
opinion that it's bowing the wrong way
or potentially blowing the wrong way and
other people are as well let's just go
ahead and take a look and and and take
take a look and see if that's actually
correct in there right so I guess the
first thing to think about is why does
that actually happen on a real sphere
right the reason that would happen is
because as the reflection gets more up
this way
mm-hmm
I have to think about because it's we're
doing something a little stranger which
is because we're doing the feathering
this sort of feathering stuff it makes a
little harder to think about exactly how
it's supposed to work I do wonder a
little bit about how much that
interferes with what we're doing
hmm well either way because you'll
notice it's really the feathering I I
it's the feathering that creates that
pattern right and so I feel like what
we're really seeing there is actually
this this a result of this calculation
right because so so hear me out on this
one guys
you know I I just like I I feel like I
feel like I need I need you to think of
me as the man now dog just for a second
here if I may so if I stop the disk the
bowing is going the correct direction
the reflection goes the right direction
it's the feathering that is curved this
way and the reason that the feathering
is curved this way is just because we're
using the magnitude of that bounce
direction Y to determine which way how
we feather the edge so if we were to
take off the edge feather right so
instead of tea farm app we just so we
said you know I don't know it's just
it's 1.0 or whatever right like this
you can kind of see that it's really
just that's that shape that we're seeing
there is the shape of this test right
it's saying when the it's it's the test
of the bounce directions y-component
so maybe the answer there is we want to
do a different test if we want the shape
to be different because the actual
reflection looks like it's curved the
right way you know what I mean like
their reflections actually curving this
way not that way the actual lines that
are reflected so I feel like that bodes
well for the calculation how do people
feel about that you know I'm saying and
so that's just that's just like the
frisket where it's actually doing kind
of the sort of the the blending on there
so yeah I don't know and that's just
that's that's sort of what I'm thinking
I do wonder I feel like it goes it
doesn't quite dim as gradually as I
might have expected so I also feel like
perhaps that tea farm map value might
want to sort of be accentuated right you
know what I mean like something where
it's gonna be a more gradual so I know
if you saw what I did there like you
know if you want to make a value ramp
more quickly when you square it like
that you can you can make its fall-off
be much more hard right basically what
happens in that range because remember
we're always talking about things that
are sort of in that range where you've
got you know a zero to one thing and so
if you if you have a fall-off you know
that's going like this so you're talking
about you know I guess like sorry it's a
fall-off so I guess technically it's
going like that right so you're talking
about like as this value goes up
you know or did down however you want to
imagine it going if it's between zero
and one if you take whatever the output
value of the thing is and you square it
it's always going to produce a more
bowing effect like however many times
you square it right because since all
the values are less than 1 1 times 1 is
1 and anything less than 1 like point 7
or whatever times point 7 right I guess
I'll just write them squared 1 squared
is 1 right and anything less than 1 like
point 7 squared or whatever is going to
be equal to something less than its
original value because 1 times point 7
will be equal to 0.7 anything less than
1 times when something is a fraction of
0.7 so squaring always accentuates those
curves whereas square rooting lofts them
up right it's sort of like the gamma
stuff we were doing and so that's
perhaps more of a reflection pattern but
yeah
decent samurai my guess is that the
normals of the edges are now pointing
straight up while the normals at the
center are pointing sideways the normals
that the edges are now pointing straight
up with a normal I'm not sure I follow
you I mean I guess the part that I don't
understand now is what about that
reflection looks wrong it looks that
that actually looks correct right I mean
if there was something here that's how I
would expect it to curve it was only the
fact that the frist kidding which is a
totally not reflected it has nothing to
do with reflection at all right the
frist kidding is just the thing that's
on there to make it so that we gradually
change between different reflection Maps
so and I don't know if we don't want
that curve I'm not sure we don't though
I'm not sure that that's a bad thing
having that curve because then obviously
this is this this middle area here is
all gonna fill in with other reflection
stuff right move it and then it looks
wrong Carl and Oh bloom says
so left-to-right motion obviously looks
correct to me right I mean that looks
pretty pretty sensible an up-and-down
movement I mean I think part of the
problem there is since we don't have the
coordinate system for up and down quite
yet the maps are are not probably doing
exactly the thing that you would expect
them to do necessarily in terms of which
direction we're moving but that looks
correct as well right I mean that's what
it should do it should move you know I
mean you have to imagine you're moving
it essentially through you know you're
moving it essentially as if this was
moving on top of it right
so where the walls are is there like
here and here on the sphere right which
is the weird thing the super crazy weird
thing about yeah about about this we
could create a sphere that does a
different thing right if we wanted to we
could create a sphere that has the
normals rotated so for example if we did
in make sphere normal map and we wanted
to make it so that it was a top facing
sphere essentially if we wanted to do
that then we'd only see one thing
reflected right we'd see the top thing
reflected so if we wanted to make us for
a normal map that way what we would do
instead is in here we would actually
swap these right so it would actually be
this way and that's for a thing that's
lying down and pointing up at the
ceiling right but we can't quite do that
yet because we're not we're not actually
we don't have a way to do we don't
actually have a way to do that yet
because we have we would have to do the
math differently for them for the Z it's
that now the Z diff is wrong right so we
basically have to add two paths like I
said to the normal thing one for stuff
that's lying down where the pixel motion
corresponds to actual motion in screen
space UV right so you know we could
almost we could prototype it in here
right it would be it would be like this
if card then do it that way like so
otherwise the Z diff is always zero
right there's no Z diff at all and the
screen space U and V gives the previous
one that we calculated right
and in tight max so that's what that
would look like right and similarly we
would end up going
well let's let's go ahead and recompile
this here right similarly to that we
also need to take what happens in here
and when we do this reflection that's
correct we get the reflection out of
that we would take the bounce direction
why so yeah it's not correct I have to
think this is why I say we have to do
the coordinate system pass because we
have to then go through now and actually
make sure we have all of the coordinate
system stuff correct that's that's a
little best that's not quite right yeah
I feel like we need to actually spend
time to get that quite right there's
because there's a couple other things in
here that wouldn't be correct about how
the bounce is being fit Kirk calculated
for things that are lying down as
opposed to two pointing up right and so
we can we can kind of play with that
next week when we do the coordinate
system stuff and we can do one that's
that's kind of flat on itself
reflect kaceyface
Saoirse heaven it feels like the red and
blue should swap places yes so they will
that's the that's the why up and why up
versus why down thing like I said that
will get fixed next week can we make the
checkerboard a bit tighter sure I think
all we would have to do to make the
checkerboard a bit tighter is change
where the maps are so if we wanted to we
could do making them further away so
they can be reflected more exacerbated I
can I can make them as as far away as
you want there I don't know if that
helps at all
so and that that really looks that
really looks pretty right to me
I mean maybe we've got still some bugs
in there but that looks really correct
to me again the frisk getting is a
separate effect that is not part of our
reflection math the frisk getting effect
is so that we can blend three normal
maps to three environment maps together
that have nothing to do with each other
right it's purely synthetic and ESC do
you only want support standing cards and
lying cards or also any other angle I
think just standing and lying down and I
don't even know if we want that we may
only really want this this shape but I
feel like we should work it out to have
both just in case while we're on it
because not much work to when we're
actually going through and making
cleaning up the coordinate system I feel
like it should be really easy
but yeah but I'm pretty I'm pretty
confident that that's correct now I
think I think that's right that that
looks right to me so we do need to the
blue and the red should swap but that's
the Y up-down problem so that'll get
taken care of next week when we do the
coordinate stuff but
and also grumpy giant it's definitely
not sitting on the floor at all right
because it's eight units away and it is
not eight units tall
so so it's definitely yeah this is this
is a hovering it's like that's a sky and
a ground that are far better I mean
they're not far away but they're not
right up against it right and we could
certainly make it closer but then you
can't see much of the checkerboard right
you know if it's if it's we don't get
much of of the checkerboard at that
point and again we've got we can affect
that factor too
right like we have there's other aspects
of it that we haven't really addressed
yet because we don't really know how big
these maps are in world space and this
is why I say we really kind of want like
you know like you v's per meter for
example we need we need other stuff here
that that's a fudge factor that we don't
actually know what that should be so you
know if the thing was one unit away
maybe it should actually look more like
you know that or something right
I don't know right I have no idea what
the actual values here should be and
that's again why I say maybe coordinate
system work maybe should be happening
here just so we can kind of figure out
what what we want to say for all these
values so you know there's a there's
another example right of the
checkerboard being reflected at a much
more a much less a much less its
assuming that the checkerboards are much
much much larger than we were assuming
them to be right if that makes any sense
I don't know if it does or not but there
you go and I feel like it's also sort of
a little bit intersecting there so I
feel like this
whereas render handmade let's see PZ so
I feel like we made I don't I didn't go
actually calculate how far things should
be so you know that's that's kind of
more what the what a large checkerboard
would look like right kind of that looks
better to people or not right so again
those values just aren't we have to do
some work now when we go through and do
coordinate system stuff to really
determine what all these values should
be like how big is the environment map
in world space so that we map the units
properly and all that sort of thing
right
so yeah so we'll actually work out what
these values are actually supposed to be
I mean we'll we'll actually this will
this is not an unknown value we know
what it is we just haven't worked it out
it's gonna be based on how much area we
want to capture for our lighting right
it's going to be based on how dense the
map is versus that right and so we'll
we'll have you know well we'll have that
dialed let me let me go through it next
week
so yeah
so yeah pretty happy with how that's
going any more questions
looks like no more questions maybe maybe
alright alright so I'm pretty happy with
where we got here and like I said it's
crazy
this is ridiculous how fast this is
running for such sloppy code that we've
done I mean we were just literally it's
all just kind of like the code to figure
out how to make all the math work the
way we wanted it to it's crazy how fast
that's running so I guess that bodes
well for software rendering yeah I mean
as a simple example right if you just
even with the same code this machine has
something like 16 cores or something in
it it's got crazy number of cores on
this machine anyway if we just
I'm sorry not 16 cores 12 cores if we
something if we just took exactly thing
and broke the screen up into twelve
regions it would run twelve times faster
right so we can already just by by
having a separate thread render each
tile on the screen we would we would
basically get you know something like 12
times faster and so I I feel like we're
probably actually gonna be able to do a
software renderer for this game that you
could actually play which is kind of
hilarious
even though we were only really doing it
for educational purposes I feel like we
may actually it could actually be
something that was you could chip I
don't think we want to because the
resolution will be lower right yeah you
know you'll want you'll want to run it
on a Jeep on the GPU path because you'll
get a higher res plays screen but you
know and me below this is not this is
completely honest entually
the only optimization that that this is
going through is the compilers
optimizations so like we will when we
Cindy eyes it we should get at least
four times faster I should think well
now at least four times faster
I guess because this is this machine
could only get four times faster consent
had the eight wide instructions but I'll
get four times faster on this machine
potentially up to four times faster with
that and also twelve times faster on top
of that from the threading so we've got
we got Headroom of you know somewhere in
the fifty times faster than we currently
are yet I mean so yeah it's it's it's
kind of crazy I feel like I feel like we
may actually be able to do some we may
actually be able to have a suffer under
this that's playable which I wasn't
necessarily counting on right so Lori
Boyd can know this is not threaded at
all it's literally just completely
unthreaded unoptimized code which has
compiler optimizations turned on but
compiler optimizations aren't doing much
of the stuff that we would we would do
all right
so yeah I think that's a good place to
let leave off I feel like where I feel
like we're in pretty good shape here I'm
really liking where this is going
so let's kill it for today and I guess
next week we will start on the path of
we've got two major things to do before
we can start to nail down the renderer
one cleanup the coordinate systems and
get all of that stuff straightened out
before we go any further and then the
other thing we need to do is figure out
how we're gonna do that near field light
basically this this the screen dude I do
not know how we're gonna do the green
dude the green dude is tough the green
dude is tough yeah I don't know how
we're gonna get the green dude but
basically what you know if you take a
look at what we've got here right you
can see that this will get us a nice we
can basically put a nice sky reflections
or lighting from the sky can come in
nicely here what we'll do is we'll do
some blurring on these so that you know
you can have like I said a glassy or
reflect like reflective - glossy to
diffuse the lighting will work kind of
nicely there and it'll all be fine right
but the real problem is what do we do to
fill in in here so basically what that's
for is not the ground and not the sky
but the the near-field the light that's
kind of coming from right around an
object and we won't really be able I
don't think to do much in the way of
reflections for that I just don't think
that's gonna be super practical but we
can I think like what I'm gonna try and
do is get just just general lighting
right so get some some you know get get
sort of blobby lights in there that are
roughly correct so that it's still so
that lighting kind of works for
really but like pure reflections we we
can't do I'm pretty sure that's not
really possible for a number of reasons
the most obvious being that we don't
even actually have the data that we
would need to know even if we did it
perfectly like for example we don't even
know like the artist is not necessarily
even drawn stuff like the back part of a
house so if you're behind the house if
you put a ball to the left and behind
the house
it doesn't even know what to reflect
right so we'd end up with all kinds of
problems if we were trying to actually
reflect the near-field stuff so that
probably won't happen but you know
hopefully we'll be able to get some of
the other things in there and TT BJM in
terms of Fornell we could actually put
real lighting terms in here if we want
to I think they may not make a whole lot
of sense because since we're kind of
doing interpretive 2d lighting I don't
know but it would go in here right when
we actually are trying to determine how
the reflection falls off based on the
based on the angle and stuff like that
we would need to sort of just just
figure out what we want our terms to be
in here I don't know how much we want to
do of that though so like I said we'll
we'll play with some tuning but I I
don't think we want to go down the rat
hole of trying to do any kind of
physically based lighting really because
we don't have the correct incoming light
field so pursuing physically based
lighting is kind of just a waste of time
what we want to be pursuing is
artistically Pleasant lighting so we're
trying to figure out how to take the
light fields we can generate in a 2-d
game and put them together to make
pleasing effects and so we will probably
play with some lighting model
computations here but they're probably
not going to have a lot to do with
actual physics like you know like for
now
so anyway let's wrap it up for today so
everyone go out and party hard on Friday
night as I know they are want to do
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure programming with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home with a series you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero org
we've got a little pre-order button just
for you and that comes with a source
code so you can follow along and play
around with it which is a good way to
learn you just experiment with some
stuff and see how it works is a great
way to learn from the series we also
have patreon page if you just want to
support the video series because you are
feeling like a very nice person or if
you want to ask questions and look at
ports too Mac or Linux that sort of
stuff we've got a forum site you can
check out it's pretty cool and we also
have a Twitter page and the Twitter page
has the schedule posted and it also
tweets updates to the schedule that's a
great place to go if you're track it's
the stream live the tweet bot can
totally help you with that that's it for
this week we will be back here on Monday
again check the tweet bot for the
schedule we'll be back here on Monday
and it'll be time to really go through
and clean up our coordinate system stuff
which is gonna feel really nice I think
when we go through there cuz there will
be no more a hand-wavy unknown stuff
that we haven't solidified so that's
gonna be pretty nice I hope you'll join
me for that and have a great weekend in
the meantime take it easy and everyone