hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream today we have the unhappy
task of needing to do some volume
texture debugging which is going to be
long and arduous I'll just get right to
the to the heart of it basically anytime
you use a GPU to do anything it is
unpleasant and you know today is no
exception I I don't feel like my I feel
like this monitor has gone into some
kind of a weird mode I'm gonna like see
if I can fix it it's it's in like a
weird like color mode where everything
looks like you know what I'm talking
about where they like the monitor
manufacturer is like helping you get a
good picture quote-unquote by having
some like really ridiculous
sort of filtering or color balance
that's happening that's really bad and
it makes everything look messed up so I
think that's what's happening here and
there we go
standard mode looks pretty good standard
mode yes
alright that's actually much better I
think it was on game mode before I don't
know what that was supposed to do but it
made everything look pink and weird all
right so let's let's go ahead and you
couldn't see that because of course
you're just seeing the right G my feed
which probably looks normal I was seeing
this weird really strange sort of like
hyper contrast II mode I don't know what
was going on there
anyway I so what we have to do today is
we have to figure out why we can't you
know the thing that we were trying to do
on the GPU was actually really simple
right all we're trying to do is look up
in a voxel and traverse a linked list
okay it's something that's incredibly
simple we've even basically done this
exact thing
on handmade here before on the CPU and
on the CPU of course it took like no
time at all to get it working and we've
done a bunch of like more advanced
things on the CPU side on the GP side
even something as basic as storing a
three-dimensional array with a pointer
to a linked list is incredibly arduous
it takes like days to get something like
that working typically and the reason
for that is that first of all the api's
are horrid right they're just absolutely
important even relatively modern ones
are awful they are not designed even
close to as well as a modern CPU eisah
modern CPU ices are obviously you know
better but GPUs don't even have Isis
that you can program too directly unless
you go with us only a specific GPU so
you're forced to go through like a
committee designed API that's that's
generally just absolutely awful in like
always it can be awfully dissolve and
then you stack on top of that the fact
that the GPU itself usually offers
either minimal or no debugging features
so you also lose that ability so not
only is your program extremely
mysterious to you because like for
example you saw last week how specifying
GL underscore read versus GL underscore
read underscore integer made a huge
difference in whether or not something
worked right now that just makes no
sense right that's not something that we
would ever put up with in dated a CPU
programming I mean unless maybe you're
into web programming or something but
that's the that's par for the course on
GPU programming like somebody made a
random API they didn't think it through
particularly well and you just have to
deal with all of its ridiculousness and
things that you don't necessarily know
but that they thought were a good idea
but that weren't a good idea you just
have to learn and deal with right it's
really crappy and unfortunates why I
don't like programming on GPUs and you
know I wish they would just kind of go
away eventually but you know that hasn't
materialized anyway
so that's where we're at we are trying
to send down a volume texture a volume
texture RFC is a texture that has three
dimensions to it so it can be indexed
with three variables XY and Z and we
have a shader that's attempting to look
up into those now I wanted to start
today by doing something relatively
simple I want to start today by just
using structured art to verify using
insight which gives us some limited
debugging capability I wanted to verify
that we could get the texture
transmitted properly and what I mean by
this is we've talked about this on a
meter before a structured art is a
concept that is used all throughout the
the pipeline in game development not
just in GPU land but it means that
instead of using your actual assets that
you're trying to debug and your actual
output you instead force a very regular
pattern through the output which allows
you when you look at the results to
quickly see whether they're correct or
not and so what I'd like to do is I just
like to start today pushing a little bit
of that so that we can verify some basic
things about what's going on with our
code without having to be so sort of
like finicky and twiki when we're using
the debugger so what I want to do here
is I want to have a way of taking the
volume texture that we're submitting and
I want to be able to fill it with a
pattern that I could immediately
recognize was the correct pattern
without having to really scrutinize the
values that are in that pattern so what
I'm gonna do here is if you take a look
at when we're going through the element
index here which you can see what we're
doing right now is we pack into our
lookup texels
we're just packing constantly exactly
the the thing the index of the first
like link if you will in the linked list
that starts at this voxel so
you know what we expect CNR voxel is
zeroes everywhere there are no light
sources and not light sources but
lighting elements that have been
computed we see zero everywhere that
that is true and then we expect to see a
single value anywhere there would have
been a lighting element and that value
indexes into an array of values that we
then follow as a chain to pull out all
of the lighting elements that were
relevant to that voxel okay so that's
what what we expect to see now that's
kind of hard to verify because it
basically means that we just have a sea
of zeros with some random numbers stuck
in them and we have no way of really
knowing how correct that was and
furthermore when we go to do the voxel
lookup in the shader we have no way of
knowing what that should be either so
what I'm gonna try to do here is I'm
going to try to do something a little
bit different
I'm going to try to pack a value in here
that will actually be easier to inspect
and give us some ability to figure out
what we are looking at okay
so the first thing I'm going to do is
we're gonna take a look at how we're
packing here and instead of allowing
this to be the final pack because that
actually produces what we would believe
are the correct results instead I'm
gonna go through and I'm gonna pack
something different in here and the way
I'm gonna pack something different it's
I'm basically going to mimic what we
were doing here where we step through
the voxel like so see here we've got
sort of a thing that looks up into the
voxel I'm just gonna copy those loops in
here and you can see what these loops
are doing these loops are just going
over the different dimensions of the
voxel Z Y and X and they're going
through every node in the voxel so when
I come in here I am referencing every
node in sequence of this of this voxel
so what I could do is in here I can just
place if I want to I could literally
place just a running counter so I could
put a u16 in here that's a counter and
what I can do is every time through I
can just assign the counter value that's
in this location to a monotonically
increasing value so if I were to look at
the voxel I should just in memory of
this voxel just see 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10 all the way up to the limit of of au
16 which is 65535 and when I would get
to 65536 I should see that counter wrap
back to 0 because it's a u16 so I see it
go like 0 through 6 5 5 3 5 I should
then see 0 start again 0 1 2 3 4 5 0
right that's what I should be seeing and
so yeah let me just grab out where that
is it's Destin here I guess yeah it's a
desk so let me just grab that out I also
should remove since we now have the
integer version working I should remove
the look up F texture and get that out
of here
okay I also need to
okay so now if I run this program in
theory nothing in particular should
happen here we should get the same
output as we did before and we roughly
do of course we do have a problem now
which is that our shader will be
faulting all over the place effectively
I don't know if we get any reports of
that I don't think we really do know and
so that may create problems for the
debugging so what I want to do also is
change the shader so that we're not
trying to look up off of these values
that will index into the middle of
nowhere off the bounds of an array so
I'm just gonna pop over to the OpenGL
side of things and I'm gonna take a look
at the shader here in the Z bias shader
and I just want to go ahead and get rid
of the thing where we actually look it
up and instead I want to use that value
just directly so when we look up this
lighting value into the voxel here you
can see we're producing an integer I
instead of doing any of this right where
we're ever looking it up like this text
will fetch stuff or any of this stuff I
don't want to do any of that instead
what I want to do oh and it's like I
already IFFT it out here so I guess our
shader isn't really doing anything bad
instead of doing that what I want to do
is I want to take that value that I got
out and I want to set the use light
color to basically be representative of
what that value was so what I'd like to
do is say use light R equals you know
whatever this light index is divided by
65535 right so I can do a divide here
and get a value from zero to one and
furthermore I could do just a
replication of that as well so I can you
know I believe you can do a shorthand in
in shader syntax I believe you can just
do like a shorthand for replication but
I'm not going to try to do that because
I always for
get how the shaders do their crazy
Swizzle denominator and I don't want to
mess it up so I'm just literally doing
an assignment like you wouldn't see
instead alright so if I run this now I
would actually kind of expect to see
something different here if I didn't
mess it up I would expect to see things
sort of shaded according to where they
are in the voxel grid if that makes
sense
and you know it actually looks like it's
kind of busted right like I don't know
where we are right here but we're kind
of in some kind of a weird like
non-functional state and I'm not sure
why oh right I forgot we're still doing
output texture debug which we really
don't want to do because that's gonna
now crawl this bogus array let me let me
quickly nerf that because again we've
now we've we are no longer sending down
a voxel that can actually be used for
the purposes of traversing the linked
lists it's just got stuffed values in
there so I can't ever do anything with
it that would require me to have a valid
list there right that's not on the table
all right so this is interesting to see
right I see nothing after this happens
which is not even remotely what I would
expect right so that's already kind of
telling me something whoa don't ask me
what that was Visual Studio so I don't
know why I'm seeing this so already
things are kind of a little bit weird
right what I would like to do is take a
look at and see now if I can see that
voxel at least what its values are and
I'm also just a little bit weirded out I
it could be just that so you know what
it's probably because when I do out
protects your debug it's probably
because we've cleared out what was there
and
it's it's overriding right like whatever
we were rendering before is not getting
rendered now so that that may be most of
the problem right like it may be that we
can't actually do it that way and yeah
so here's another thing we could do for
example let's suppose we left this in
here so it can create it
and let's suppose that we just stuff the
vats the voxel like well we can't really
stuff the voxel after-the-fact can we
well so what we can do is we could make
it so that our lookup sort of used a
different thing for the push lighting
right we could be ridiculous here and do
something like well okay like when we go
to send this down will actually send
down a different one than the one that
we actually are gonna use ourselves we
could do it that way I don't really love
that idea though what I would rather do
is just not I would rather just not have
this be happening and leave the other
thing so yeah maybe maybe the best way
to do this so that we don't get into any
more hot water here is when we're in
here doing show lighting like this maybe
we just keep going through the old path
right so when you press f1 you do this
and we never do output lighting itself
so we we skipped this you know this path
is just not a thing for the moment so
it'll keep on running the game exactly
as it would it'll still render just what
we're seeing right here just with the
lighting textures having done their
computation right so you could see we're
still getting black which I don't super
understand right but we kind of expected
something to be wrong because if it was
this went correctly that doesn't help us
find our bugs because we know we've got
bugs because our algorithm was not
working on the GPU so something is wrong
with it
all right so if we want to capture a
frame here I don't really remember what
the key there's a keyboard there is some
way you can capture keyboard with
capture frame at the inside
oh this isn't unity I don't know if
that's actually here we go I'm like I
don't know if unities stuff is actually
the same I would assume it would be but
let's find out so let's see here
I want to know that is what we're doing
currently I just want to know if you got
a hot key on that so I wonder if the the
hot key that's listed under pause and
capture frame if if you could bind
something to that or if it's like I feel
like there should be one right there
should be one that's when you when you
do start graphics debugging I feel like
there should be a hot key here right and
control-z does launch the hood but I
don't really want the hood I guess it
doesn't matter just do that it's no big
deal
all right so wow that captured a lot
more quickly I don't know why but it
certainly did anyway so taking a look
here what I want to do is I want to see
in the fragment shader I want to see
what the look up sampler had for memory
and this is that 64 I'm sorry a 16-bit
per entry 3d texture so if I take a look
at the memory of that texture this is
what I'm seeing right so I don't
understand why it's all black I don't
know why that would be so that's I mean
that's really the first thing that I
want to figure out right cuz I tried to
stuff values into it obviously I didn't
succeed I don't know why and so I'm
gonna try to figure out why all right so
let's take a look at what is happening
if I break in the debugger at the point
where I submit the texture let's just do
the basic due diligence to verify that
of course I don't know why my opengl
thing isn't up here but I guess we
haven't stepped into it yet but anyway
I'm gonna step in to push lighting
oh you know what I may have forgotten to
run the push lighting let's make sure I
did that there's the push lighting
here's the pausing caption right
alright so now let me verify okay there
we go so I wasn't making that mistake it
turns out it was actually fine so here's
the unsigned 16 bit integer view of the
three-dimensional texture and you can
kind of see it going up here exactly as
you would expect now amusingly enough it
ends right at 65535 you may wonder why
that is and that's because it just so
happens that the size we had picked was
256 by 256 by 32 I believe so 256 by 256
as you can see comes out to exactly
65,536 values if you start enumerating
at 0 the last one you will enumerate is
65535 so every slice should have exactly
this layout and it does so that looks
pretty conclusively like we're
submitting that texture correctly
because when I'm looking at it in the
debugger here it looks exactly like what
I would expect it to look like so that's
reassuring the next question would be
well what about the other two textures
are they getting submitted correctly and
that's another question we should be
able to answer by forcing structured art
down the pipe so let's take a look at
what those look like here's what the
other things we're sending are we're
sending lighting Texel and we're sending
Jimi a color value per light so what I'm
gonna do here is I'm gonna go and say
alright from
you know the light index will go through
all of the values that are in this array
and I'm gonna set them so key next dot
key key next next and see okay so I'm
just going to set the next pointer and
the C pointer both to L and I guess
technically I to be extra sure I'm going
to go ahead and say that since there's
only 4096 I'm gonna set these so they
run at 4096 plus L and my reasoning for
that is just to make sure that these two
arrays aren't the same now I feel like
there's almost no chance that these
things would end up overwriting each
other or overlapping in some way because
I just don't see how that would happen
in the code but again the point was
structured art is to make it so that
when you see a particular pattern you
can verify that it's exactly what you
think it should have been right and so
one of the things that we probably will
need to do when we get a little further
down here is we didn't have enough
values to set all of these planes to be
equal to the right thing so what we
probably should do is take whatever the
Z is and like bias the Z the value that
we've stick in here by the Z value times
some increment so we can verify that the
slices are what we think they are as
well right
okay so taking a look here what we want
to do is set the back three p-value here
what I'm gonna do for that is I'm going
to set these to be equal to
floating-point values of L 2.0 times l
and 3.0 actually let's do 4.0 times L
right I could actually be a little bit
easier on myself instead up to a
thousand and ten thousand times L let's
say or 100 something like that and this
way when we stuff those values we will
get something predictable in each
channel that we can now verify in the
actual application
and so now if I run the lighting comp I
should be able to do a possum capture
frame when I capture the frame I should
now be able to take a look at all of
those values and in here if I look at
the fragment shader you can see I've got
the look up sampler depth sampler
texture sampler problem is I want to
actually look at some other ones here
and what's happened is you can see that
even though those the the textures I'm
curious about P next and C and stuff
here I can't actually verify those
because even though they're here like
here they are
this is them I can't actually get them
because the compiler for the shader has
optimized them out because here's where
we were doing those textile fetches and
unfortunately since we're no longer
doing textile fetches from them we can't
actually get them so that's not a really
huge deal or anything because we don't
need to debug those quite yet so let's
put that aside for the moment and let's
just go ahead and see why this isn't
working so if you take a look at what's
going on here I'm fetching a light I
using a textual text I'll fetch into
this thing called lookup sampler right
and look up sampler is the sampler
that's supposed to be getting our voxel
values out now when we pass a voxel
lookup value into the look up sampler
we're expecting to get out those numbers
that are those monotonic issue numbers 0
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 right and what you can see
here is when we get our use light values
and stuff and such we're expecting to
reset these values and you know I'm
gonna do I'm gonna move this out so we
can still see the red fringe
okay so if I switch now you can see the
red fringe which lets me know that my
voxel testing is actually still working
and it means that these values at least
as far as we can tell are within proper
bounds right so Vox I wise Vox XY and z
are all between 0 to 36 and 0 32 for the
Z right and so what we would expect is
when we get a textile fetchin here we
would expect the values coming back from
textile fetch to be exactly those
monotonically increasing values so what
we should be seeing if we set all of the
colors here we should be seeing these
light up in progressively brighter
shades of gray so it start at black at
the min corner of the voxel and get
progressively brighter as it goes up
through any given slice and each slice
should be the same so we should see see
no variance based on the Z height like
looking at this for example we should
see if we if this were working properly
it's not if this were working properly
we should see black at the min corner
white at the max corner and no
difference depending on the Z so it
should be completely uniformly colored
up and down but it should go from black
like here to white like here right
that's what we should be seeing instead
we're seeing no variance at all so what
we're seeing is as if the textile fetch
is always coming back with nothing now
this exactly matches the bug we were
seeing so that is not surprising right
that is this is what we would expect to
see based on what we're seeing before
but it's still not what we would expect
to see based on the code so we obviously
just don't understand something about
this and this is not again this is
exactly why I hate GPU programming it's
because even basic simple stuff is
almost impossible to get right because
even when you write something that's a
trivial line of code that would you've
seen us do this on hand here a million
times we never have any problem getting
this working at a reasonable amount of
time all we're doing is trying to floor
a value right and then look it up in an
array that alone takes hours of
debugging work on GPUs it's just it
sucks right it's absolutely a miserable
debugging experience you always get it
working eventually but it takes like ten
times or hundred times even longer than
it does on a CPU now if you're a really
good graphics programmer and you spend
all your time doing graphics programming
I do not do that but if you are you end
up trying to work around these things
and you develop a lot more techniques
for it right so it's not as bad as I'm
making it seem because if I were someone
who did all who was just on graphics
engines all day I would probably have a
better approach to it right and things
would go some more smoothly but they
still don't ever go particularly
smoothly and they're particularly bad
for anyone who's a generalist such as
myself who just wants to do very simple
stuff I mean even though it looks
somewhat complicated to walk a linked
list off of a voxel these days that is
not I mean a you know a back-end
graphics programmer on a main graph on a
main game engine would not hear that and
go wow you're really you know off in the
deep end there it's like no that's you
know this is not something that they
would I think that an eyelash at so
anyway so what we want to know here is
what's going on with this weird sort of
situation here what I would like to do
is I would like to do divided here of
these values so I can just verify Vox
pee real quick so if I take so if I take
Vox pee again I'm going to sort of get a
lot of this stuff out of here now I'm
going to take Vox pee and I'm going to
say that use light C equals Vox P and
then I'm going to take each of these and
divide them by their respective
indexing values right so what I'm going
to try to do here is basically turn the
color into the voxel address right so we
can just see what's going on there
oh sorry forgot to announce that
variable all right
so what you can see here is a
color-coded version of the look app and
it looks pretty reasonable to me right
if we look at what we're getting here as
far as what the color values are being
output it's more or less what I would
expect it's getting towards black over
here with the blue value indicating Z so
as we go up higher that blue gets
stronger right as we go down the blue
gets weaker as we get up towards this
corner right it's you know so red is
running this way green is running that
way and blue is running like this so
that looks like a pretty stable look up
into the voxel right those values look
like what I would expect those are the
floating-point values we are flooring
those to get voxel indices so what I'd
like to do now is again switch to
looking at this after the flooring now
that I know that that's right
and again what you can see them doing
here is I'm literally just a employing
the most basic black box the Box
debugging technique so that's all I can
do to see where it which step of the
process is going awry right so now
unless I've made some kind of an error
we are now looking at the actual output
of the of the the trunk like the integer
eyes values right because we've lured
them and now we've taken a continuous
value that's running across those
dimensions and I've I've truncated them
and you can sort of see it it's a little
bit hard to see because we're still
we've got a lot of gradations but if for
example you take the large step the one
that's only 32 gradations the one that's
256 gradations you can't really see
because obviously that's a very fine
level of gradation but what you can see
is here on the way up in the Z values
you can see there's little bands there
right that weren't there before
and those bands are the truncation 232
levels so it's not instead of the normal
two
six levels that it was getting before
it's getting 32 levels and you can see
the banding there again looks like a
pretty stable voxel look up right looks
like a pretty reasonable thing okay
so once we have that voxel look up and
we know what's going on there
here is the textile fetch that actually
attempts to get a value out of here and
for some reason and I don't know what
that reason is we are unable apparently
to get the actual those values to come
out to something meaningful I don't know
why so now let's try to do that I'm
pretty sure I've validated what I think
the inputs are to this thing Vox eye is
what I think it should be going in I'm
gonna have to look at textile fetch
again to make sure that I'm not missing
some subtlety of this API that that you
know we need to know that we don't know
and we're doing wrong like I believe it
takes an integer pixel coordinate to
look up into into the text texels I
should say texture coordinate and not a
floating-point value so that's why I'm
passing an integer in I believe that
integer to be correct and I believe it
to run the correct bounds of the voxel
so moving here to setting use light I'm
setting the used light red parameter
actually let's let's set one that we're
not setting below so the red parameter
will now just be set based on whether
we're outside the bounds the green
parameter will be set based on whatever
comes back from light I and here where
we're actually doing this and getting
the 65535 divide out here I would expect
this to give me green values that vary
in a pattern again going along the going
from black at the bottom the bottom left
corner to bright green in the upper
right so bottom left black upper right
green right and you know let me just
verify that this is the case by casting
that as well to a float so we you know
up convert
the light I to a float I feel like
that's you know what we should be
getting here and let's take a look so
you can see we're still getting black so
getting an integer out of this thing
just does not seem to be working and
what I don't really know is why
so when we call textile fetch let's just
find out what that's supposed to be
doing Here I am in the OpenGL
specification and I'm looking at Texel
fetch
so here's textile fetch you can see that
like the one that is relevant to us
would be this one here where it's a
sampler that takes a three-dimensional
vector and a lot value again we don't
have any MIT Maps so we're passing a log
value of zero here because we just want
to look up into the basic texture that
we submitted we didn't submit any lower
resolution versions here where we say
use integer coordinate P to look up a
single Texel from sampler the array
layer comes from the last component of P
for Ray Forbes we're not using array
forms the level of detail a lot of
president is in described in sections
you know blah blah blah pixel fetches
and scale factor in level detail so we
don't care about that because we're not
doing anything fast with that well we
don't know here is how this really
returns things unfortunately because
it's not really giving us much
information there so I think probably
what we would need to do is look up you
sampler and see what's going on with
that somewhere hopefully we can get more
information about you sampler somewhere
and verify what that because that's what
we've defined and we would like to make
sure that that's actually correct
Wow so they literally have no
documentation for this whatsoever
let's look in the general sampler
section and maybe they talked about that
a little bit so texture functions all
right so let's see automatic load of
details created above logic sure data
can be stored GL it's unsigned norma's
if you're unsigned integer or signed
integer data types you look up function
provider that can return there's all
this floating point integer Alice I'm
sure or science are depending on sample
type here if you take into use the right
sampler for text racks just the
following table lists the sporty
combinations of sample types and texture
internal formats
alright so unsigned integer with an
unsigned integer sampler type is what we
should be using now I believe that's
what we did right here is this admission
for our texture it's a 3d texture and we
requested it to be stored unsigned
in in there I don't know if this needs
to be like unsigned integer or something
like this I guess we could take a look
to make sure but that's only like how
we're submitting it so I feel like that
shouldn't really even matter what we're
doing there oops but you never know with
OpenGL you never know
so it looks like that's not even
documented in here
so yeah I don't see any other options
for that so it looks like that's the
only thing that could be happening there
I guess one problem we may be running
into and I don't really know if I don't
know whether we're asking for the proper
versions of OpenGL it may be that you
sampler isn't really supported in this
version of OpenGL or other things like
that why we are not getting an error I
don't know but that's sort of something
that's kind of worrisome so you know I
don't know if this is really an
acceptable thing and maybe we shouldn't
be trying that sample unsigned integers
maybe we should still be trying to
specify floating-point values or
something like this and then convert
them back I'm not sure but again those
are just some thoughts that are running
through my mind I would like to know
what when you sampler was introduced and
I don't really know how to determine
that
I don't know if this really says so I'm
not sure exactly when that came in
here's the 3.3 specification a new
sampler is in there so in theory we
should be okay I don't know so the next
question I have is when I look up one of
these what is the value supposed to come
back as right when I call Texel fetch
does it talk at all about what the value
supposed to come back as in what format
right and the answer appears to be no
let's see so in the pre-digital of the G
or F of G of X is a picture for nothing
I or you making your turn to perfec for
effect for you Veck for in these cases
the sampler argument type also starts
with G indicating the same substitution
done on the return type
it is either a single precision floating
point single signed integer or unsigned
integer sampler matching the basic type
of the return type as described above so
I think it should be giving us an
unsigned integer right I mean that is
what we would expect here from a new
sampler 3d I think it should be giving
us an unsigned integer value back right
I think that should be giving us a you
Veck 3 that's my guess anyway and so if
I run this I shouldn't get any errors
right yeah so this is giving us back a
UN but for some reason that you ain't
appears to be like always zero or
something I don't know because I can't
see any output from it so what I'm
trying to figure out here is how could I
get some information about what is
coming back from Texel fetch I verify
that these values are values that should
work right I mean I looked at them they
are 0 to 255 and 0 to 32 they're exactly
what I think they should be I so they
seem like they should be valid ways to
look up into this texture yet when I
look up into this texture I always get 0
back right I know that the texture
doesn't have zeros in it I looked at
with an exercise in it and then they're
not zeros and so I really just have no
idea why it refuses to
take a sample from this texture I I
don't know I don't know why it's unable
to give me back a value here
um I guess one question I sort of have
is is it possible that the shader itself
needs to have something slightly
different specified for it when the
binding occurs doesn't seem likely to me
that that would be the case but like you
know if there was something in the
actual submission of this that meant
that you had to do something different
when you were binding it right but I
just don't see why that would because
you're only binding like a simple name
right you're just binding like a uniform
and I don't really see
I mean here's the code where that
happens right and you can see it kind of
getting the sampler IDs just by calling
get uniform location and it doesn't seem
like that would ever cause a problem
like you know it's it's this there be no
real reason for them to change how you
were specifying samplers just because
one was unsigned versus signed it seems
like it will always be GL uniform so I
really don't know why it thinks that's a
problem I couldn't say but yeah point
being we definitely know we have one the
question is just what why can't we get
that lookup so it seems like that's our
you know that maybe almost the entirety
of our problem because that would
explain basically all of the failure
we're seeing if we can never get a look
up from our volume texture we can never
get the first link you know lookup chain
so therefore we can never look at the
light values and the game is over before
it's even started so that's what we're
left with is figuring out how that could
be right
why can we not Texel fetch from this you
know why can we not Texel fetch from
this volume texture that we know has the
values in it that we think it does why
do we not get any results when we try to
do it right now maybe there's something
else we could do here
[Music]
hmm I mean I could try doing something
slightly different like maybe if I
believed the divide to be a little bit
weird I could just do something like
this so that I can still see some
semblance of something going on in the
green Channel I don't think that's gonna
change anything right yeah
so that yeah I'm I'm pretty sure that at
this point this textile fetch is just
failing I don't have any idea why it
would fail there's no indication of why
it would fail it's not giving me any
errors of any kind it doesn't think that
the shader code is bad it just doesn't
seem to want to actually do the work
it's supposed to do to correctly access
this value I assume it understands the
fact that this should be an integer
value because it's not complaining about
the fact that I'm passing integer if I
was to pass a float hmm I would think
that it would give me an error and it
does so all of that is operating as we
expect so that's not unusual what's
where's my there is yeah you know it's
it's thinking it is exactly what it is
so that's even verifiable and so the
only question is like when it goes to
call this thing why is it unable to look
up a valid value now I suppose I'm being
slightly presumptuous in the fact that I
don't actually know I mean I would have
assumed that the red channel was the
channel where things come out I guess I
don't know I should be getting a you
Veck three from it
I mean I shouldn't be getting a new
vector3 from it it's a one it's only got
one element in it right it only has a
single value so I should only be getting
a single value out of it right but what
I assume it will do as most text effects
functions do is they always return a
formal element vector regardless of what
you put in them so I'm assuming that
what light I actually is in this case is
a four element vector what I can do here
is I could do something where we just
say okay let's let's take a look at
every possible value that comes out of
this thing and see if they're all zero
right if see if any of them are accurate
or not
and I mean I'm pretty sure they're all
zero but you know we can again I'm just
randomly trying to think of anything to
try here so if I randomly try the the
red Channel I should get exactly the
same thing as I got before if I randomly
try the and again just just to make sure
if I was to set light I hear if I was to
set the our channel to like you know
300,000 I should get you know a half
bright red
what's an integer you don't do that but
what is the problem what did I do
Oh do I need to specify that it's a
unsigned value or I guess the maybe the
right way to do that would be to say to
doing
yes oh you know that's a green value
just like I would expect and if I set it
to 6,000 oh no you know what I forgot
this isn't dividing that way anymore so
let's actually change this back to my 6
5 5 3 5 go all right so that's green and
that's dimmer green and I don't think
there's much else to say about that
right that's obviously working correctly
so if I was to start looking at the
other channels here get rid of that
something here's me looking at just the
green Channel
nothing here's me looking at the blue
Channel
nothing here's me looking at the Alpha
Channel hmm so the Alpha Channel for
some reason is coming back as a hive
value even before I've submitted the
texture
so I guess the Alpha channel defaults to
one I mean does it does it default to
zero zero zero one essentially in in a
texture or something like this like why
would that be coming out as bright I
mean it should it should come out of
zero it's like I'm getting back at zero
right
that seems nonsensical to me that it
would be anything different the RG and B
values are all zero but the a value is
not I'm sorry why is that the case I
have no idea so yeah I'm totally stumped
on this I have no idea why this would be
the case it looks like this is just
straight-up failing oops not so
swearing stream yet those things this is
just straight ups failing and there's no
particular reason why you know we got no
errors we verified that the values that
we're looking up are correct we verified
that the values we're passing inter
correct and yet we never get back a
value other than 0 0 0 1 essentially or
in this case 0 0 0 6 5 5 3 5 here's what
we get back from every single texture
fetch that we issue right so what's the
deal what gives you know why can't it do
a Texel fetch into a 3d texture the way
that it's supposed to anyone anyone from
Nvidia watching she's me who wants to
tell me why I can't text the fetch so we
can try an eye sampler here as well it
should do the same thing but you never
know at this point we're just random
wares
doing random stuff same deal we could
try looking up with a you Veck instead
right I mean I don't know
so it definitely wants an i vac there
and puts the castrum into you int where
is the implicit cast oh it's in this
testing here but that's okay because
this is not what this function wanted so
that's a valid value being passed in the
format that it wants to the text will
fetch call that matches the format of
the texture as requested and it simply
returns zero in all cases I would like
an explanation
we don't by any chance have any Nvidia
people this dream do we or OpenGL people
anyone cuz this is the kind of thing
that happens all the time and I would
love an explanation for it right like I
would love to know what their
recommendation is for how do you figure
out what is going wrong here because
this is pretty obvious you know I'm
saying there's not a lot else in there
that's really going on now I'm gonna try
changing some stuff here what if we what
if we like arbitrarily changed our
OpenGL version number just curious
implicit cast from you Veck 3 - I've X 3
ok
now for some reason that wasn't giving
an air before now that granted was just
something I recently changed but that's
alright alright so no change so even if
I bump the OpenGL version number up to
the most latest one well I don't know if
that's the latest one but it's a very
recent one no change so it doesn't look
like it has something to do with that as
far as I can tell this is just straight
up fail and I have no idea why so it
doesn't seem to be a problem of compat
like hey you can't do this or that or
whatever right so I'm not sure what's
going on there one of the person
suggested on the chat like hey let's
let's up our our level of debug
notifications we could do that for sure
that you can see here that we've got a
debug call back what I could do here
instead is just look at them all
and the other thing I guess I could do
is I could print them out right so this
should just stream all of the debug
messages and in fact I could preface
them with something and this way maybe
the OpenGL driver like in a in a more in
a subtle way was like telling us
something that would help us here and we
just aren't seeing it because we weren't
looking at all of its debug right now
it's kind of giving us a giant stream of
stuff here let me see if I can get a
bigger view of this but because kind of
behind my head right now all right so
here's where we start and the first
thing that's nice is buffer object one
bound to GL buffer ARB usage hint is GL
static draw will use video memory as a
source for buffer object operations so
these are all just things telling me
where this will go like okay it's just
telling me that these things will go in
video memory and it looks like that's
the only thing it's telling me basically
every frame it tells me that something's
gonna go in video memory but it looks
like that's it
it didn't say a single other thing at
all so as far as the drive is concerned
it has nothing to tell us right
alright someone says that there was a
stack overflow on white excellent that
choice returns zero for a 1d single
channel texture third comment and they
said sorry for Sakura fling stack
overflow is fine if the person who
writes the comment actually knows what
they're talking about
the problem with stack overflow is a lot
of times the comments are wrong and then
you end up getting like misled by
something that's the only problem with
stack overflow when stack overflows
right that's good you know for some
reason I cannot open the browser on my
Linux machine here because I think it's
putting the browser window on a
different desktop and I can't seem to
convince it to use this desktop Oh Linux
yeah I think that is what it's doing
let's try Firefox all right
Firefox seems to work so we'll try that
okay so if I copy this link
why is textile fetch always returning
zero for a 1d single channel texture and
they said third comment it turns out
that I also need GL to experiment of gel
texture 1d gel just max levels zero to
get it to work the texture filtering
mode can be left to default okay if
that's correct though that's really
messed up because we're doing a textile
fetch not a texture read so it should be
reading only from the LOD level that we
specified right that's if that was
correct that would be really really
erroneous behavior not that that's
surprising right but just to be clear
about this so what we're doing here
right
oops what we're doing here is
specifically a textile fetch and a
textile fetch does not use the LOD
computation at all right taxol fetch
takes the LOD as the the third parameter
so filtering is not applied during a
texture fetch and it does not compute am
it map right so there should be
absolutely no cases where anything like
that is occurring so if that was
actually the case if this actually did
fix it that would be hugely messed up
but you know that doesn't mean it's not
true cuz this is open gel and anything
is on the table right but anyway let's
take a look here
all right so what we're about to do
we're gonna take that suggestion we're
about to do is apply the code that would
fix a problem if you were getting black
back when you were sampling a texture
using regular texture filtering and you
had MIT Maps turned on but you were
sampling using a thing that actually
used the MIT Maps and you would not
specify them right we are not doing that
so that should not be occurring in any
way but here is the GL text image 3d
call and you can see I believe we
actually do specify this here you can
see us specifying it for other things
right like Minton filter mag filter rap
SMT and so on we specify a bunch of s if
I don't think we ever specify max lot
anywhere yeah we don't so anyway if I
come back down here first thing I'm
gonna do is I'm going to try turning off
filtering entirely and again filtering
should never have been applied right
that should not have been happening but
you know whatever so we're gonna start
by turning off filtering entirely and
putting clamp to edge on okay we're not
setting the max load yet which was the
suggestion so we'll do that in a
separate step but and also I should
verify because we were sort of fussing
with the shader there and I don't I
don't want to accidentally not have the
right thing in here so you can see us
here saying all right here's the foxhole
look up we look it up into the texture
we get packing you back for we're using
the are channel of the U of X for to set
the green Channel and then we're leaving
it alone so that should be fine
so I'm setting it so that it's never
supposed to use LEDs for minification
and magnification it's not supposed to
emit map at all we get nothing here I
will set the max LOD level max LOD level
what that does is if filtering was on
which is now not it says don't ever use
anything above a specific blood level so
if I set it to zero I spell that GL
texture max lot so it must not be
defined in the base set I guess I can
also set min LOD as well if we wanted to
write and what that saying is like and
we will just set max by itself first but
what those are saying is when you go to
compute which MIT level to look from I
want you to clamp the values between min
and Max so that way like let's say that
I still wanted MIT mapping to occur so I
was gonna leave filtering on but I only
had you know to mid flap map levels or
something so I wanted to make sure it
would just stop after it went you know
to like mid level one or something and
not ever choose MIT level 2 because
there is no MIT level 2 or something
like that so that's what meaning max LOD
allows you to do that's all that is so
it looks like that's not a defined in
the base level open jail I guess so I'll
just grab them it's no big deal
there they are so we've got those in
there from play with them and again if
this works that's majorly busted I don't
think it's actually gonna yeah and it
didn't I that would work in the case
again we're filtering was actually
applied oh wait nope nope we haven't
really tested it yet let's run that test
again I've got to set it to three texts
3d alright so let's try turning the
filter off first
see how that goes so basically I have no
idea why that's the case
we didn't textile fetch is not supposed
to apply any filtering am I wrong about
this
I kind of want a
I mean it's Texel fetch it is never
supposed to filter anything turning the
filter on and off should do absolutely
nothing it performs a look up of a
single Texel what's it gonna filter how
do you filter a single Texel value you
don't have anything to blend it with I
don't know what to say that seems
completely nuts to me we don't have to
set min max laud because turning filter
off was sufficient and that's the more
reasonable thing to do over there I
think but that's ridiculous like why
would that be happening but anyway like
I say in stack overflow no problem as
long as they give you the right answer
and that was I mean that was more that
was a good suggestion from Stack
Overflow even though I'm not using
exactly what they said to do but they
were suggesting that somehow it was
getting filtered I don't know how it was
getting filtered I would love someone I
would love an OpenGL person to tell me
what that was supposed to be because if
you're doing a textile fetch why is it
applying filtering it's explicitly never
supposed to apply filtering if you're
fetching a Texel that's why it's called
texture Texel fetch texture that call
that applies filtering this does not
anyway I'll turn off filtering on all of
these because that same bug would happen
again with the Texel fetch I don't so
what about our other textile fetch we
have a depth textile fetch that we do
should we be worried about that one are
we getting incorrect results in other
places because of this as well like I
don't know
it's a little disquieting right alright
well now we're actually getting the
lookups that we expected it's messed up
as that might be and like is that
specified somewhere because it better be
if they just arbitrarily make it so that
it returns black if you don't turn off
filtering even though filtering is not
applied I do not know what to say here's
the GL specification
so here's the texture stuff that's in
here coordinate rapping and textual
selection
[Music]
I don't know if this overtly discusses
Texel fetch in here which is a problem
because I don't know well let me see if
fetch
ever really talks about it
so
[Music]
this is talking about buffer textures
which aren't really the same thing but
I'm just looking to see if there's any
like hint
Effects of completeness on texture
application texture lookup and texture
fetch operations performed in shaders
are affected by completeness of the
texture being sampled as described in
sections 11 1 3 5 and 15 to 1 okay
this is talking about full texture
fetches
you
it really just does not discuss fetches
so it looks like the I guess what I
would say is this is I guess the
paragraph that's causing the problem a
texture is said to be complete if all
the image arrays and textured parameters
required to utilize the texture
protection operation are consistently
defined the definition of completeness
varies depending on texture definitely
and type four one two and three
dimensional in one or two dimensional
texture two extra mipmap complete if all
the flan hold true so this is probably
the problem right it's probably the case
that even though Texel fetch does not
apply filtering it says that if the
texture is not complete it returns zero
zero one zero zero zero one right so it
seems like it behooves us to literally
specify all of this stuff about the
texture I don't even know according to
that it seems like we would actually
want to do these as well that makes
absolutely no sense to me but that I'm
I'm that seems like the paragraph that's
the problem because technically what
does it say about filtering in here
[Music]
using the proceeding to finish the
texture is complete unless any of the
function so true the internal form of
the texture is integer weight but that
means that integer texture can never be
complete using a texture is complete
unless any of the following conditions
hold true the internal form of textures
integer O and either here we go and
either the nice grammar there and either
the and either the magnification filter
is not nearest or the minification
filter is nearest or nearest mipmap
linear in a mira smith map nearest so
actually never mind we don't need these
that is what was screwing us that one
line in the spec in a in a how long is
this specification how many pages 758 so
an operation that easily could complete
that's just a access into an array
failed and caused us like three hours of
debugging time because even though no
filtering was requested the spec says
that you have to set the mode to nearest
for an integer texture even if you never
call the filtering function why do I
program GPUs I should go work in a bank
of course they need to program GPUs now
to do Bitcoin mining anyway absolutely
abhorrent everyone should be fired and I
would have fired them but of course I'm
not in charge so alright hey we can
execute the array lookup now that we set
a bunch of random crap that doesn't
affect the array lookup happy birthday
all right so now that we can actually
look this up we can go back to our text
Texel function and so axially so in this
case the stack overflow information was
actually
be wrong but that's okay because it gave
us like a hint about something to check
and we tried some other things that I
happen to know I should also check and
those work so that's good
so Stack Overflow actually gave us a win
there if if indirectly and one should
get credit where credit is due
so all right back to our story our
textile fetch is now magically returning
the correct values because it's been
completely unrelated unnecessary code
that occurred somewhere else now that we
actually have those values coming back
we should be able to actually start
processing our lighting elements now
which is pretty effing exciting so let's
go back and actually see if these values
are are now operating correctly alright
so if we take a look I'm starting to
think that maybe we want all these to be
integer values instead of floating-point
values and then we'll just convert them
to floating-point values in the shader
so what I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna
make a little like a little bit of like
a Bhutanese mu here and say that because
we're sampling these as energy textures
I'd like to submit them all as integer
textures so maybe what I'll do here is
say like okay this lighting textile
value that has the next parameter there
and we've got this position you know
maybe we can code the position well
actually now you know nothing about that
that's probably not necessary but this
next parameter here that really needs to
be specified as an f32 so that it'll be
homogeneous that's really all I want is
it for me to be a modulus right so let's
start by making that be the case so when
we get an L value here that's coming in
I'm just gonna cast it to an f32 we know
that it's never more than 16 bits wide
it could go up to 24 bits wide and it
would be fine so that's that's all good
we don't have a problem there we can
just do that cast and it should cast in
and out no problem so
that's all good we should be able to
inspect these values now and see that
they're actually correct but in order to
do that we have to get them to actually
compile the shaders so in order to get
them actually compound the shaders what
I'm going to do is I'm gonna now that
we've verified that our volume texture
is at least somewhat correct I'm gonna
go ahead and get rid of the part where
we actually nerfed the volume texture
and I'm gonna let the volume texture
actually take on the values that it
should have so when we start here what
we should see now is we should be able
to figure out a way to visualize what
values in our voxel are actually filled
and which ones aren't right so when
we're setting these lookup values here
where we pack it index into the lookup
value we should now be able to write and
you know so if you take a look at this
this is if I'm stuffing values with the
predictable stuff if I now actually
change it so that we're keeping our
values the same the problem is we're
gonna get mostly black because we don't
have many values that are particularly
high what I can go in here and do though
is say like alright I know where we have
values that range roughly from zero to a
thousand or somewhere in there let me
divide by a much lower number so that I
should be able to see some squares in
here that actually have information in
them and so you can kind of see your
that occurring right where we're looking
up into the voxel and getting some green
in there right where these lights
actually are so okay that's all well and
good that's that's everyone's fine with
that and happy and dancing around
jiggling like a little monkey on a chain
alright
so now we know that we're actually
looking up into the voxel meaning
actually see things that are coming out
in the voxel we can start to get rid of
this code a little bit here and say okay
let's take the the fetch value that we
actually got out of here and and
actually start using it again like we
were trying to use it before as he as a
ivic right and see if we can actually
make the or as an integer I should say
and and let's see if we can actually
make that part one so if we were to cast
the red channel of this thing to an
integer and then we were to go ahead and
actually start using it for some for
some lookup purposes here we go with
that if you come in here and we grab out
a light I instead of using the light
connect stuff I'm not gonna actually do
that after the Texel fetches I'm just
gonna use whatever this light color was
here that we stuffed in and we're gonna
use that light color right now I'm gonna
keep I'm gonna do exactly what this was
saying here to do which is I'm just
gonna stuff pure green in there in fact
I'll I'll switch it to pure blue for now
you're using green before I minister
just to clear blue anywhere that it did
find a light value we want to make blue
and anywhere that it didn't find a light
value we want to not make blue what was
the problem : yeah off you go
and so that's what we expect to see
there's all the places where we actually
had lighting elements sitting around and
that's totally fine so now we come
through here and we textile fetch
ourselves some values off of those
integers and so now we should do is
actually try to see what those are so
I'm gonna actually keep the light sea
color here I'm not gonna loop over the
various lights that may have been there
I'm just gonna let it do one of those
and see what we get
and so what we get here is we can kind
of see we have some varying colors of
red I don't know if that's what we would
expect I think it is because I remember
correctly yeah we set those two
particularly ludicrous values here
they're just gonna be 4096 plus L should
that be very red
so it's au 32 so it's gonna be
interpreted as RGB a yeah
so I actually feel like there should
have been maybe some green and blue in
there though and it doesn't look like
there was so that's a little odd I'm
gonna go ahead and stuff this value with
a again structured art just by itself
just to make sure that I'm getting what
I expect out of here from a compact
color so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
specify in here I'm gonna specify
something like 4 4 8 8 FF right so here
I've got something that again in RGB a
order of course I don't remember what we
specified this being so maybe I should
go actually verify that first but you
know so here's the lighting see this is
specified as storing an RGB a a internal
and RGB a direct down so what I would
expect yeah is the first byte again this
is into a little endian so this oxo or
matte here is again gonna be read from
the bottom forward so it's going to be F
F is the our 8 8 is the G and 4 4 is the
B so we should be getting kind of an
orangish tan color in here hopefully
that's the goal anyway that's bright you
know has bright red channel halfway
green channel and yeah there's our tan
so that's what we expect alright so
those values seem to be reading out
correctly as well what I can do here is
again just make sure that they're
writing out in order here this will give
me definitively
varying shades of red and it does so I'm
okay with that
the 4,096 must just have wrapped in a
nun convenient way had some little bits
and green that just got truncate or
something like that it doesn't matter
all right so anyway there's this
verifying that those values were
actually coming out somewhat correctly
unfortunately this stuff here with the
p-values and that sort of thing is gonna
be harder to verify but we can do is use
the p-values as a color if we want to
and verify that those are getting looked
up correctly and so what we what we
could do there is say look alright maybe
we just take something cure to see
whether whether these values are getting
stored the way that we think they're
getting stored so again if I were to set
this value to something predictable and
I'll set it to basically the same value
that we were setting to before more or
less but this time in floating-point
what I should be able to do is come over
to the shader here and in the lookup
sampler part of the code where we do
this what I could do is say all right
when we look up this light beam next
stuff if I set this instead of from the
light color if I set it to the light P
what I should be able to see now is that
that RGB value is coming out as we would
expect to come out and it does look like
it more or less is so that's good news
as well so this loop should now be
functionally if we were passing down
correct values we should be able to do
something with it that's useful such as
summing up the lighting or do something
doing you know who knows what so what we
want to do here is come up with some
kind of a way that we can sample our
lighting values in the while loop and
creating the extra while loop that walks
through them and so if we wanted to do
that let's just start with the basics
first of all let's actually go back and
and not put Nerf values in there let's
put the real values in there and what
we're gonna do here is we're going to
say okay while the lighting index is not
equal to zero
we're gonna loop through here right and
use the next parameter as we go so we're
kind of moving through the next
parameter says we go what we're gonna do
here is say alright when we do our light
beam X and do our textile fetch out of
here we're gonna get the next value and
the position of the light and that's you
know something we'll use for our
lighting calculation later we're also
gonna get the lighting index of the next
light to look at and that will keep us
going in our while loop eventually that
should return zero and then we'll exit
out of the loop the light color will
come presumably from here and for now we
can just leave it like that and just see
whether this works at all because we
don't know whether it will or not it
certainly looks like it's working and
not only does it look like it's working
but it looks like we're actually getting
the colors we would expect out of our
lights here right as these point
samplers now we're not actually
computing any lighting from them we're
just setting the light directly and
we're not even handling and if we do get
multiple light sources in a region we're
not really getting anything useful from
that so that's not as good but that's
okay because we don't actually we ever
actually tried to get this to work in
you know any kind of sane way yet all
right so the first thing I would say is
looking at the density of that lighting
sampling it does look like the lighting
grid is too dense and I don't really
want it to be that dense cuz it's just
gonna cause us to have to do way too
many lookups to gather the lighting
samples that we want so the first thing
I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna go ahead
and drop this down a bit maybe you know
a much sparser grid would be a better
idea so that we're because so because
we're really not going to take that many
lighting samples so what I'd like to do
is drop this down maybe we'll do 64 by
64 or something like this just so
there's a lot less data in the voxels
right so I'm just I'm just cutting that
down
something more work course right so now
you can kind of see the size of these
things is considerably less small than
it was and that's more what I was going
for here because I don't want to be in a
position where I'm doing a tremendous
amount of sort of scatter gather that
may even that may be too much I don't
know
I'm gonna for now again I think just
drop it down even just a little more so
I'm gonna drop it down to oops
to a 32 by 32 and and let that do its
thing so those are some bigger light
values there it's a bigger you know
voxel lookup areas there which is what I
wanted and one of the things that you
can see is that our lighting sampling is
not dense enough to cover all of the
space with actual light right and that's
not great we want to make sure that we
have enough lighting samples in area to
fill all of our box holes and we're not
seeing that happen now I don't know why
that's happening necessarily there could
be two reasons that that's happening one
reason is that we're just not putting
enough lighting elements in enough
places and so that is obviously one
reason why that could occur the other
reason why that could occur is we just
have a bug in how we're filling the
voxel right we could have a bug where
we're just not placing it so I don't
know yet which one of those two it is
it's not super important that we do know
at the moment but you can kind of see
you know what's going on there for the
time now the interesting thing about
this right is this inside the shader
where we're doing our light walking we
can actually do something a little more
sophisticated here if we wanted to what
we can do is we can actually walk a
region around the voxel so we can
actually use an offset here if we wanted
to so for example once we floor this
voxel I here what we can do is we could
actually include in here a ability to do
this sample multiple time
on voxels in a lot of different
directions right so we can if we want to
brought in right this sort of search if
you will to look at neighboring texels
so instead of just sampling just one
texel we can sample the texels in like a
grid around us for example or anything
like that
so in order to do that what i think i'm
gonna do here is think i'm going to pull
this out into a function this thing
right here that's gonna just compute the
light for one of these so if we take a
look at this fragment code here if i
just introduce a function to the
fragment code where I'm just like okay
here is a thing that returns a vector e
which is like a sample voxel light or
something or maybe like something that
does maybe something like this some
voxel light and returns it back for and
I want it to take ni Veck 3 which is the
like position to sample app and it's
gonna return me you know sampled
lighting result right really wish we had
indentation here probably break these
out into separate files but I'm too lazy
to do so at the moment so what I want to
do here is basically sum up how many of
these we've gotten with like a waiting
value right so what I want to do is say
okay you know we're gonna return a
vector results here the results gonna
start at 0 I'm gonna grab the light I I
don't care about this fringing right now
this is something actually that probably
would just stay down here if we were
going to do that test in the future
right
and that's fine but what I want to do
here is say okay so I've got this
summation here where I'm gonna do some
voxel light and I want to basically take
all of this stuff where we do you know
the textile fetch and all that stuff I'm
gonna do all that and I'm going to sum
up the values as they come in I'm gonna
sum up the our GPS and I'm gonna put in
the Alpha Channel I'm just gonna put a
value that's indicative of how much like
that like how much actual content I
summed up and we don't really care about
that right now but we will care about
that eventually to normalize and
actually even right now we kind of want
to normalize that sum right because
we're sort of summing over a loop we
want to like normalize it down so what
I'm gonna do here is again I'm just
gonna do a very simple I'm gonna take
use light C I'm gonna make that equal to
well actually I guess I'll do something
slightly different there I'm gonna call
this some box a light thing I'm gonna
call that and I'm gonna get back a a
light some value that's a vector Y I
actually call it that BEC for I was
getting into shader land there so I'm
going to call it a v4 rather and what I
want to do here is when I pass this
voxel I value I'm expecting a sum to
come back what I want to do is I want to
compute the the lighting value by taking
the light sums RGB and dividing it by
the light somes a right now the problem
with that is the light somes a may be
zero like there may have been nothing in
there and then I would divide by zero
and have zero in there but I divide by
zero as well and so in that case that's
less good obviously so what I kind of
wanna do in this situation is say like
alright only if the light some a is
greater than zero do I want to do
anything with it if I can't find
anything there that I'm just gonna set
to zero and
not do anything at all right I'm just
gonna soon there's no lighting so that's
the basic idea
presumably we've got some syntax errors
and stuff incompatible types in
initialization okay yeah I agree with
that
undefined variable Vox I agree with that
as well and now we should get the same
results we got before which is what we
wanted now the other thing that I can do
here is since I want to you know I want
to start summing up these values if I
want to sample multiple voxels around
the region what I can do is I can
actually just kind of oops I don't
really want to cut and paste that quite
yet what I can do here is sum all of the
voxel sums I can actually do several of
these right so I can make something like
this and I can sample as many voxels in
the neighborhood of this voxel as I want
to right
I can do something like this where I'd
be sampling essentially a cross pattern
right so that's sampling sort of the the
left right up down and back you know
front texels I can you know it gets more
expensive as you go like every time I do
this right it's gonna get more and more
expensive but it's basically you know
starts to spread the light out right so
I can do those sums of the Vox I can do
this sums inquiry a bunch of things
around the voxel I can also do this if I
want to in the entire cube right I could
do the whole thing
so I could do like
a pattern more like this so start at
negative 1 negative 1 negative 1 and
then go to 0 1 right move to 0 so that's
basically like starting at negative 1
negative 1 go to 0 1 move up 1 right and
this would just you know it's getting
ridiculous right obviously but you could
imagine sampling an entire cube of
voxels which is what I'm doing here and
this is just the ridiculousness of
having way too much fluff at your
disposal right like so so this sample is
like everything and we don't need to
resample 0 0 0 because we already did it
up here with this one so that one can go
away but all the rest of them would stay
and that would sample the entire
ridiculous cube right and what's
particularly bizarre about that
obviously I is you know it still runs it
60 frames a second you know it's just
nuts how much flops you got in there
on these modern chips right it's just
nuts they're just they're packed with an
incredible amount of computing power it
just it's because that remember this is
running per pixel so it's actually
querying all of those lights in the
voxel per pixel right
which is completely ridiculous and you
know probably we will move away from
doing anything like that but there it is
and you saw you can do it so if you want
to actually do each individual lighting
thing there you can and no one can stop
you on a modern GPU you've actually got
that kind of power which is nuts so
anyway if we are to do something like
this where we sum up all of the lighting
in sort of those regions like that what
we don't know here we still have a lot
of issues with this obviously there's a
ton of stuff that we're gonna have to do
here but let's just let's just push this
a little bit further since we got it
working today let's just start playing
with it so you can kind of get a feel
for what's going on here all right so
first of all that lighting value is
getting used as a raw lighting value
here right and we don't actually need it
to be used as a raw lighting unit value
here because we actually do have what
the surface color should have been
coming in here the surface reflect color
so if we want to we can actually
modulate the incoming lighting value by
the surface reflect color rather than
just hard setting it right so we can do
something like this where we modulate
instead and in that case what we will
get is an actual version of the game
running that just has the lighting
happening right and so what you can see
here is now you know if I am to move
this around I can reset the lighting in
any particular area and we actually get
something that starts to look like the
Lighting's actually being used but we
definitely haven't done anything that we
would want to use in a game it's
certainly not good so what we want to do
now is is start to fix some of that okay
so first of all we're getting a bunch of
information here and we're not using it
we have a light p-value which is where
the light is supposed to be where this
in
where this emission value is coming from
and then we have a light C value which
is the color of the light and we're just
using it but what we did not do is we
did not actually see whether or not our
particular surface which we do know what
it is right because we have sent down as
part of this we do know for example the
world normal and the world position in
question so we know where we are and we
know what direction our surface is
pointing so we should be able to
actually sample this lighting in a more
reasonable way so for example if we know
where the light value is in the world
where we set specify this light P here
what we can do is look at the difference
between those two so we can take the the
distance to the light source and say
well we've got the world P that we're at
and we've got the light P right yes
because it's the Delta that's how far
that's the vector along which we would
have to travel to get to that light
source right and then we also could say
well okay if we know the Delta to the
light source we also know how far away
we are right because we can take for
example the distance squared to the
light source we can easily find by just
squaring the value the length of the
Delta right so if we do a length squared
if Delta we could figure out how far
away we are I think we have that in here
somewhere right
to be half a length squared yeah
so we'd already to find a length squared
macro for ourselves so we can find out
what the length squared is to the light
source right so that would be zero when
we're right on it
and that would be as we get further away
from the light source that will go down
right so what we could do there say well
all right very simple attenuation to
start with let's say that as we get
further away from this thing we're gonna
attenuate it more right and then I'm
going to sum up
only the attenuation values and what
this is gonna do is actually I don't
really probably hooked emulation because
I'm not really doing lighting
attenuation here what I actually want to
do is contribution blending right so all
I'm really gonna do here is say all
right I want to wait the lighting values
based on how close I am to each one so
if I have multiple letting values that I
pick up I'm gonna use the ones that I'm
closest to more strongly than the ones
that I'm further away from right so I'm
going to here say the contribution value
of this thing is going to be a function
of the distance squared away from it
let's say so I'll take 1.0 minus the
distance squared so the contribution
will be full if the distance squared is
zero so I'm right on it and it will
dwindle away as we get lower right I
don't want it to ever go below zero so
in this case I'm also gonna clamp it
which I think we also have a function
for you so you I'm gonna clamp it here
between 0 and 1 so that it can't go
below right and that's all so now if we
are fortunate enough to pick up more
than one lighting sample in the voxel we
will blend between them right now the
problem with this is that it'll only
work if we actually have enough voxel
coverage and what you can kind of see
here is we just don't have dense enough
lighting sampling or we're screwing up
how we're placing our box is I'm not
exactly sure which but one other the
other is true and so again what I can do
is just to sort of get this basically
working is I can just again drop that
voxel resolution down a little bit more
to pick up more samples in the voxel
that way we have more lighting samples
per voxel and we can blend more values
together right and what you can see as I
get down to a level where I'm actually
picking up enough of my samples is
you're actually starting to see real
like smooth Lighting's start to
materialize right which is kind of cool
now we're not quite there yet and the
reason is because our samples again are
just still not we're not grabbing enough
samples in any given individual voxel to
make this work right because our
Lighting's solution is just a little too
sparse is the problem but you can see
where I'm going with this right or
hopefully you can see where I'm going
with this
oh the guy like hopped on top and he was
outside the voxel region there for a
second right but yeah hopefully you can
see where I'm going with this you can
start to see how this lighting would
materialize as we go right you can start
to see how the the lighting samples
would get blended together to produce a
sort of smooth lighting solution in the
end as we could sort of start to figure
out how to make this work how to get
enough samples into the to the smoothly
blending part of things to make it work
and again all this is trying to do this
step that we're adding here all we're
trying to do is make something that
takes lighting samples we've distributed
throughout the world and smush them
together into a way that's smoothly
varying across across the world right
that's all we're trying to
[Music]
so we've got a lot of stuff we've got to
work on there I also don't know or we
can work them in Oh to mode right yeah
so yeah we've got a lot of work to do
there and it's unclear exactly how we're
going to get there so we've got a bunch
of stuff we're gonna do to try and get
past that
I'm curious we can keep setting the
voxel down and putting more stress on
the GPU but getting more blend samples
in there I'm just curious what happens
as we drop it down there we go we
finally slowed it down right just a
little bit and so again we can see there
is it continues to get sort of a
smoother and less blocky less patchy
sort of solution to the lighting and it
starts to be kind of nice right like you
know we've got a long ways to go but you
can see how that's starting to create
more of a nice lighting effect and you
know most of our problem here is we're
just not getting much transmission of
the lighting so there's a bunch of stuff
we're gonna need to do but it's like you
can kind of see how having a gather step
at the end really sort of puts things
into a nice like really sort of puts
things into it a sort of more pleasing
result right so what I'd like to do is
go ahead and and tomorrow when we
started in this start thinking about how
we're gonna flood this region with
samples properly so that may be
something at about this level of
granularity of of gather will will work
properly and that's gonna take a little
bit of work on our part but I think
that's roughly what we would like to do
right so we'll start playing with that
some more that's gonna be it I'll go
ahead and go to questions now
you
Nestle is asked why no indication of
shader code the reason there's no
indentation on the shadow the shader
code is because it's in a string right
because we didn't so we probably should
because we're doing enough work with
shares this point we should probably
should pull the shaders out into
separate files right well we didn't do
that
and so as a result these are just
strings and for coder by default treat
strings as non code data which does make
sense because most of the time they
aren't what would be nice is if
magically you could somehow hit two for
coder maybe by picking a specific thing
here like like that you know or whatever
I guess you can't really quite do that
because it's too long but something
where you could pass a little hint too
for coder like hey this is code could
you just run the indenter as you
normally would on the blocks below you
right but that's kind of a very special
purpose thing it's obvious why it
doesn't support it
have you tried CUDA do you think it's a
recent lady GPU programming AMD is
trying to get cuter compatible compiler
so it could be useful on both vendors
soon I have not tried CUDA no I mean my
thoughts on that are very simple really
to summarize it the question is more
will we ever get there right because
there's a lot of barriers to it my
thoughts on that is that GPU programming
should not be GPU programming it should
just be CPU programming right if you be
exactly the same
a GPU should fund functionally just have
an ice ax that you compile code to anis
to a machine level specification that
specifies everything right and it should
be extremely direct write a text I'll
fetch call there should be no concept of
anything having to do with anything
involving completeness of textures or
any of that stuff
there should be a layout of textures and
that layout is mandated it is a memory
layout format a text I'll fetch us an
array access with guaranteed semantics
about how that memory is fetched and
that should be the end of it
you should be able to write assembly
language code that gets executed on the
GPU just like you do on a CPU and it
should be 100% specified there should be
absolutely no API at all right it should
just be like the Intel Architecture
reference manual that should be it and
each of the instructions should say
exactly what it does in terms of memory
that's what it should be
right and we're really far from being
able to have that but that's what it
should be because that's the only thing
that provides a reliable debuggable like
easy to understand programming interface
for experts right
4-bit lightning if I remember correctly
we tried to use pound included
multi-line strings for the shader code
but that didn't actually work I think
the reason was because we were trying to
remain compatible with Visual Studio
2013 so it doesn't really have any way
to do that I think there was a way if
you go if you go we actually are on
vigil 26 through 2017 now I think there
is a way to make it work there but don't
really want to require that either way I
remember actually neil was trying to
figure out or it wasn't neil no you know
what it wasn't Neil
it was Martin's I think maybe Martin's
was trying to figure out I get to work
and send some suggestions but they
didn't work and I think if I remember
correctly the reason they didn't work
was because it wasn't a late enough
version the compiler I've just started a
project and I'm working through the set
up on day two you had it set up applet
on debian paint two alternate black and
white if I made no mistakes then it
doesn't work on Windows 10 I'm instead
of getting all white and if I drag the
window around the new part of the one it
becomes black do you know if there are
any si caveats for Windows 10 I should
be worried about there should be no
problems with that on Windows 10 that
doesn't sound right to me it sounds like
you have a problem with your paint
handling like maybe you're not calling
begin and then paint or maybe you didn't
set up the window handle right or
something but that should no I I don't
think that's Windows 10 I think you've
got a bug somewhere
like the fact that if you drag the
window around the new part of the window
becomes black suggest to me that you
just have a paint bug like maybe you're
not actually doing the paint all the
time or something like that
Nixie do you have any suggestions on how
to start going about bobsledding more
complex 3d meshes rather than simpler
geometric shapes break them up into
simpler geometric version of allowed
meshes first should each match be pre
Vox alized or do you need to recalculate
relative to the worldview position and
possibly just for the camera so so
you're asking about are you saying like
so you're on the GPU like on the GPU you
want to send down a mesh to the GPU and
have the GPU Vox Allies it Neil is that
is that a correct interpretation of what
you wanted to have happen or am i
misunderstanding you like you you want
the GPU to voxel ice and mesh into
something you can then use on the GPU
like inside that frame is that what you
mean or is that a misunderstanding of
the question
sorry I'm just waiting a second they
wanted to give me a chance to mix tea
not necessarily doing it on the GPU but
to provide what the GPU needs to do this
sort of lighting with more complex
meshes okay
so you're kind of just talking about
like the more general question of like
voxel ization in general
so unfortunately here's what I can say I
have a great deal of experience of
oxidizing messes on the CPU side I have
no experience vocalising messes meshes
on the GPU side so what I could tell you
is I can tell you about how voxel
ization goes on the CPU side and then
speculate a little bit on the GPU side
and give you some references so on the
CPU side for voxel izing meshes I
actually shipped a commercial product
that does that so granny has a mesh
voxel Iser built into it actually and
what it did that for was for one of the
things that granny has a really good one
of even though I don't think anyone uses
it is it has a thing that will take a
high-res model and transfer properties
from the high-res model onto a more
lower resolution model and it does this
extremely quickly at the time when I
shipped it it was common to wait several
minutes for this to happen and we ours
ran in like 1.5 seconds for such a thing
usually or even sometimes sub-second
timings so it was extremely fast
relative to the common way this was done
and the reason for that was because I
used voxels to accelerate the process
because they're kind of the natural
thing you would use for this anyway so
in order to do that what I had to do is
voxel eyes measures I had to voxel eyes
the low res mesh and the high res mesh
so I could find correspondences between
them using the voxels as a search region
I and the way that I was doing that was
I wanted my
voxel ization x' to be perfect right so
there's different ways you can go about
voxel izing things and some are based on
and which way you vox eliza mesh it
depends on how you wish that mesh to be
used i can give a very specific example
in two dimension two dimensional voxel
ization so that you can understand what
i'm mean by this and it's important to
understand which one of these two you
want and which one of these two you want
is dependent entirely on what you expect
to be doing with the voxel when you put
it into use so we talked about
rasterization right and we wrote a
rasterizer
on for handmade hero for a software
renderer and one of the things that we
talked about during that and remember a
rasterizer and a voxel Iser are the same
thing right
a rasterizer is fundamentally a thing
that figures out which pixels on a 2d
grid are covered by a triangle a voxel
Iser is a thing that figures out which
voxels in a 3d grid are covered by what
everything is your oxidising but a
triangle let's say so in the case of
imagine a triangle so remember when we
did our rasterization what we were doing
was we were checking to see whether the
centres of things were covered right
and so we would consider this pixel for
example to be in when we were
rasterizing because it's center was here
even though there's a segment of it that
was out but in we would not consider
this to be in even though there is a
segment of it that is in right and
that's typical of a rasterizer and the
reason that's typical of a rasterizer is
because a rasterizer expects there is
then another triangle that comes in here
and fills this thing right but there's
another way to look at rasterization a
conservative rasterizer
is one that wants to know every
pixal truck touched by a triangle and so
in that case what would happen is you
would want to know you know even though
like this is considered out for a
traditional rasterizer
i would want to consider this in because
i would want to consider it in whenever
it touched at all right and so what
we're looking for there is knowledge of
whether or not the triangle passes
through the the rectangle not just
whether or not the center is included in
the rectangle so what I did for the Vox
eliezer because what I wanted was a Vox
laser that was actually 100% precise I
wanted something that would know exactly
what part of every triangle was in
exactly which voxel right that's what I
was actually trying to do I and so in
order to do that what I would do is I'd
say okay in you know my voxel
what I would do is say I know where my
starting point is gonna be so I can
classify my starting point in to one of
my voxels and then I know you know where
the other points are as well right I
don't know where they might be but let's
say they're in here so I know three of
the squares that are filled certainly
right I know that this square is filled
this square is filled and this square is
filled I know that they are touched by
my triangle and so now really the
problem that I have is I have to figure
out how I would walk from the how I
would walk along these the voxel in
order to get everywhere that might have
been filled by the triangle and the way
that I actually did this would just go
like okay well let's break it into
slices first so the first thing I would
do is I would clip the triangle to
figure out I'd say well alright here is
a starting point let's clip the triangle
to this z slice right and figure out how
much of what part of the triangle
occupies this Z slice that turns it into
a 2d problem right where I then have you
know something that looks like a clipped
triangle right like here the triangle
passes out of the Z slice here that I
can now voxel eyes as a triangle I would
then do the exact same thing for the
next dimension down I would say all
right let's now click the triangle to
this bucket and I would get this piece
and then I would run between the min and
the max slicing it again to figure out
exactly what part of the triangle was
clipped to just this Square and then I
would slice it again to figure out just
which one was this square and I would
you know keep slicing slicing slicing
right and so that was you know that
scheme is sort of a successive triangle
dicing scheme that is for when you need
to
know exactly which piece of a triangle
is in exactly which piece of a voxel and
you don't want to miss anything you want
to be exact everywhere right
and so that was good for the application
I was using however that's probably
overkill for a lot of voxel operations
right if it's something that can be more
sloppy and you know it's something that
you're trying to run into much higher
framerate you know like I said this is
saying that could take a few seconds to
work because it's an artistic transfer
process you're basically like alright
bake this mesh into this mesh it's not
something has to run frame-to-frame so I
wanted to err on the side of accuracy
rather than on the side of speed because
we were already also so much faster than
anything else out there it wasn't really
necessary to push that boundary in a few
seconds to do a mesh transfer in any
case was way better than anyone would
have needed anyways so if you were
trying to do voxel ization in some other
way right if you're trying to do voxel
ization where you would like to do
something cleaner less code run faster
whatever I think there's a lot of ways
you could approach this problem right so
let's take a dump of approaching this
problem just to give an example of how
you might do it so let's suppose what I
wanted to do was I just wanted to
exploit parallelism here to fill this
thing up right alright and I just you
know I'm gonna do something simple so if
I had a triangle let's suppose that I
looked at that triangle I said what
voxels are the corners of the triangle
in right well if I got back the answer
that all of them are in this particular
one I'd be done that's the voxel
addition of the triangle right if I get
back three different ones what I could
do is like bisect my triangle or trisect
to my triangle right I
do something like you know like that and
run it again right or I could do
something where I bisect it a little
more fairly like maybe I do something
like the Triforce let's say so I bisect
each of these and I turn this into four
triangles and then I ask the same
question
if you kept doing that you would
eventually get two triangles that were
only in one voxel and you'd be done
right so one very simple way to Vox lies
a mesh if you just don't want to think
about it much is just to dice your
triangle smaller and smaller and smaller
until they fit into a single voxel each
and then that is the voxel that they are
in right this I believe is typically
called a race rasterizer right do we can
we get a definition there
here we go
bah bah blah blah blah blah blah that's
not a definition
yeah so here you go the bait serious
pipelines flying steps bound calculate
the bounding volume of each American
primitive split split large versions of
smart dice while primitives dice
converse the primitive integrative micro
polygons each approximate a size of a
pixel shade calculate lighting and
shading in each micro polygon grid bless
the grid individual micro Pines each of
which is brown and check for visibility
hide right so this is effectively what
I'm advocating right it's how Pixar's
renderer worked up until the modern day
I think actually I know they did a big
rewrite or in the middle of one now I
think they were raised for a very very
long time and don't actually know when
it was replaced but it was like you know
Toy Story at least was still using Reyes
rendering I suspect even probably up to
like The Incredibles they may have been
still using Ray's running I don't know I
don't work at Pixar so I have no idea
but that is one model of approaching
this that has the benefit of simplicity
and parallelism there's not really much
thought involved it's just like you dice
and repeat like you're just filling up
hues of die simple things and going so
something like that might be appropriate
for what you're trying to do again if
you just want something simple because
rasterizes can get very complicated when
you start to think about how they work
at voxel Iser is even more so because of
the third dimension that's involved
there that's one way to just write one
to just get it working right if you want
to be more fancy about how you voxel
eyes I think probably what you're
looking at is like probably I'd start
crawling references out here out in the
weeds and I'd see who's up to what at
this point because GPU voxel ization is
a current topic and there's a lot of
papers that you can look at on there
and so if you want to know you know more
about that you can probably get let's
see here I mean you know you can read
all these this Nvidia stuff but I'm
assuming they'd have some reference this
year and so 2013 is probably not the
most recent thing but you know I mean
you could start here this looks like a
pretty good little overview to write I
mean that's something I and I would I
would kind of go through so these people
who do voxel a vocalization for lighting
you can see how they are doing it right
no we're in this paper they would talk
about that but I would expect that they
would
[Music]
oh this is interesting so they're using
like successive renders from different
directions to generate the voxel so yeah
I mean I don't know because this isn't
my area of research like I said the only
time I ever really did vocalization I
was looking for highly accurate CPU side
vocalization in that scheme I don't
think would be appropriate for this kind
of use I would probably look at that
paper I would crawl the references out
so on sites here for it I I don't know
how to get to just the sightseer link
unfortunately but I'd crawl the
references out from that maybe and look
at how people are generally talking
about doing GPU voxel ization today in
some papers maybe you've already done
that and found them not to be
particularly illuminating and if that's
the case I apologize but that's probably
what I would do
but does that help at all uh Neil I
don't know so I don't know if that helps
answer your question or if it doesn't
really help answer the question I don't
know if there was something specific
that you wanted to know about Vox
Edition they didn't really touch on but
using an re re ye s or Reyes system is
probably the simplest thing to get
working I would say because it's pretty
easy to write something that just goes
look either this triangles in a Vossler
it's not if it's if it's in a voxel then
I that's it you know I'm done if it's
not in a Vauxhall
I just have to write something that like
subdivides it and if you can actually do
a something fairly smart there too you
can just divide the triangle
based on its longest access to or
something right or its longest side you
know so you could do something that kind
of you know if you have long skinny
triangles it would be smart enough to
divide the two long sides and you know
break it that way or something rather
than breaking it up along the shorter
side or something right so you can you
can increasingly be smarter about how
you subdivide too and so that's also
something that I would say you know
might be worth looking into
even just doing the dumb approach just
doing it relatively smart is probably
fine
where you go from there it's like once
you get that working then you can start
thinking about well okay you know that
is probably pretty dumb it's probably
not what you want to do if you're trying
to get something to run real time and
really fast and whatever so when you
actually go to voxel ice that meshes in
the you know in a high performance
scenario you probably are going to want
to start doing the research there and
finding some people who've tried to
figure out how to get the highest
throughput voxel ization they can on the
GPU side of things and that's probably
not a subdivision based process but I
don't know
because like I said I haven't really
done that reading alright anyway good
luck with that Neil hopefully you're
able to get something work in there I'm
gonna go ahead and quit out of this here
and close down the stream for the day
thank you everyone for joining me for
the episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with our
series at home you can always pre-order
the game on hand made here at org and it
comes with a source code so if you want
to you know fiddle around with it and
and try your own experiments with the
code base like if you want to play
around with these shares and do stuff
like that you can go ahead and do so we
also a forum site go to ask questions
and a patreon page you'd go to France
fourth video stereo a schedule bot that
tweets to schedule at you and an episode
guide that allows you to catch up on
previous episodes my understanding is it
is broken right now I don't know why but
it's it only goes up to day four a five
even though we're a little bit past that
so it's only really for the archival
purposes at the moment I think there's
some kind of server stuff that people
have been working on I don't run this
site this is a different site where it's
handmade Network it runs a bunch of sort
of projects and they're doing some stuff
on it I don't know so it's not quite up
to date yet will be eventually but it's
not quite yet so if you need to grab
episodes from the very recent past that
you want to go to the YouTube archive
which of course you can also get to by
just going to youtube.com handmade hero
archive and that channel has all of the
the videos on there up-to-date as well
so that's me all you should have to do
that's it for today I will be back here
tomorrow when we will try to sort of
start to bring our lighting stuff
together a little bit more
because now we've got everything working
the building blocks are working that we
need and we need to start thinking about
how we're actually gonna do our sampling
and blurring and blending and that kind
of stuff and so now that we actually S&amp;T
we can play around with we can go ahead
and look at that and that's what we
doing tomorrow hopefully it will lead
something fruitful till then have fun
partnering everyone and I'll see you on
the Internet take it easy everybody