okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero the code the code that's
good show are we code a complete game
live on stream except for when we're on
our side break which we are right now
and so what I've been doing rather than
just being off the air completely is
taking questions from people like we do
on the normal show but instead of having
the programming we just have questions
since I can write just fine with my
right hand not a problem it's really
only the left hand that's busted so
without further ado I will talk about
something that I got a question on in
email which is pretty straightforward to
explain but is somewhat complicated to
implement due to really the ambiguity of
it and I'll try to explain why that's
the case although certainly it's a lot
better understood now that it used to be
anyway Elvin was asking about inverse
kinematics
and essentially his question was very
broad it was like I don't know what this
is like what does that mean what's like
explain tell me tell me about this what
is it how does it work why do why do we
care about it right and I think that's a
pretty reasonable question if you've
never worked on character animation
before or robotics you probably don't
really know what this is and you have
some vague notion of what it is perhaps
because you use it in some kind of a
tool like an art tool or something but
it's not really clear what that means in
code or where the term comes from or any
that stuff all right so inverse
kinematics is actually exactly what its
name implies it's just if you don't know
what this term means then you wouldn't
know why inverting that makes any sense
so let's start by talking about the term
kinematics and what it means in this
case so the term kinematics in this
context is talking about the concept
that for many of the things that we care
about in computer graphics or robotics
where you have what would be called a
multi-link assembly which you might
colloquially refer to on your own body
as an arm let's say or a leg right
something that sort of got multiple
pieces to it which can move independent
of each other in some ways but dependent
on each other in other ways this is what
we are talking about when we talk about
kinematics we're talking about taking
one of these things and figuring out
where it is when we know it's joint
angles or rather the parameters that
describe its state so for example if I
was to imagine sort of my arm right
here's Casey and here's my shoulder and
I was to imagine my arm coming down here
to it to my elbow coming up here to my
hand
yeah if I was to talk about that we
could say that this was a two linked
assembly right
here's link 1 and here is linked to
right link 1 is for the purposes of this
discussion if we're just talking about
just the arm
it's rigidly attached right here right
meaning it can't there's nothing I can
do to move my my shoulder out of its
socket that's not going to be incredibly
painful and very dangerous to me so for
all intents and purposes my elbow I'm
sorry my shoulder socket is like a fixed
location and the arm comes out of that
right and it's a rigid bone but it comes
down to an elbow and the elbow can bend
right so there's another thing there's
another degree of movement that can
happen here so this you know as we all
know my shoulder is kind of like a ball
and socket joint so it's it's locked in
position but it can it can rotate around
and then the same thing is true here
it's this is connected fairly rigidly it
can't be separated but it can be rotated
in in at least one way and sort of to a
limited extent in another way right so
this has got some degrees of freedom on
it as well and by the way I should
define that term we talked about that a
bunch in this context so I'm going to
talk about what that means in a second
here so let's put that on the board so
if we're to talk about this in isolation
here is the hand here's the shoulder
here is the elbow then what do we need
to know to figure out where the hand is
well if we you know simplify this for
the sake of the diagram although this
does not simplify or it doesn't change
the Nama klaich or anything else but if
we just simplify for say good diagram
and say this is 2d we might say that
well we need to know the angle that the
shoulder is coming out of the arm socket
right like maybe we need to know how
much I've lifted my arm right so as I
come this direction and similarly I
would need to know how wide my elbow is
opened you know so I've got a certain
angle here that I need to know in a
certain angle here that I need to know
but at that point
for this very simplified model of an arm
we've constructed if I know these two
things then I know for any position of
the shoulder that you give me I know the
position of the hand because these links
don't change length right I know this is
a certain length here I know this a
certain length here so all I have to do
is start at the shoulder
take the this angle walk out along it
until I go this distance and I get to
the elbow I then again rotate my
direction using this angle and then I
walk out this length here until I get to
the hand and then I know the hands
position that process of figuring out
where something is based on an initial
location and a series of parameters that
describe the assembly that is kinematics
so we would describe the process of
taking a state vector essentially
because you can imagine we now have a
state vector of this thing right we have
two angles the theta and the Phi that
describe the state of our arm and at any
time we can take knowing this that the
constants in fact let me let me be a
little bit more explicit here we could
think of this as having sort of
constants and variables right the
constants are the l1 and the l2 right
and the variables we might say R theta
and Phi but I might also include the
position of the shoulder right because
if this can move around then technically
that's that's an input now maybe that's
a constant maybe that goes here but you
know it doesn't matter point being the
the arm is completely described by these
things and which ones you wanted to be
constant and which ones you want it to
be variable is you know is up to you
when you're describing the problem but
the point is taking one of these state
vectors right so you know whatever we
want to call this right maybe we have a
state vector we call that s let's say
taking one of the state vectors and
saying we've got P hand out here I want
to know what P hand is taking that state
vector and producing the location of the
hand that's kinematics okay now let's
talk about this right here
degree of freedom well degree of freedom
is the term that's used in this Naumann
clay Chur really to talk about this
state vector right however many scalars
right and remember for those of you who
are who are math and paired which I'm
not condescending I am NOT a good
mathematician a scalar is just a single
floating point value basically right a
scalar is a single value not a vector
just a value however many independent
scalars we have to describe our system
that is how many degrees of freedom we
have right and so in this case right
it's kind of a little bit complicated if
if I were to move this guy over here so
that we have the constants l1 l2 and the
position of the shoulder then this is a
very straightforward system it's very
easy to understand and the reason I say
that is because we have two we have two
variables here and those two variables
as I move them allow this arm to move
around in space right so we have two
degrees of freedom and it's very clear
that we do because the number of
variables and the number of actual
effective ways I can move this thing is
is coincident right I have two axes of
motion right I can move on the x and y
axis the hand by changing these joint
angles and I have two joint angles it's
clearly t2 DOF throughout the system but
that's not always so clear right because
if for example I did this the other way
right I said no this is a variable again
now it's very unclear because it would
appear that we would have four degrees
of freedom right
I can set this angle this angle and this
X&amp;Y right there's an X here and a Y
right of the shoulder so that would look
like I had 4 degrees of freedom and in
some sense depending like again there's
a certain nominal Eicher there's a
certain formalism to the way that these
things are talked about in certain
circumstances you might say that this
had 4 degrees of freedom ok but in
actuality if you're talking about the
the result the thing we care about the
position of the hand there's still only
two degrees of freedom because
regardless of which of these things you
change you're always only changing the X
or the Y or both of this arm the X&amp;Y
position of the hand is the only thing
you can affect so yeah you can change
for different variables but the outputs
only going to end up changing two
variables right so the apparent four
degrees of freedom that we look like we
have when we talk when we modify our
state vector end up coming down oops
sorry that's our constants end up coming
out in our in our output there's only
two degrees of freedom okay and
incidentally Eve it's not even as simple
you might say well well KC you have the
position of the hand I know that that is
a vector that's like P you know pH x ph
Y or whatever I can clearly see by
looking at the output there's two
degrees of freedom right so Y you know
that makes it easy still not easy right
and the reason for that is let's suppose
that we constructed a different type of
arm assembly let's suppose that the arm
assembly that I gave you was an arm
assembly that looked more like this okay
and now what I do is I say you don't get
fada and Phi anymore the inputs to the
system are Theta and some function of
theta which this is set to right so
basically I'm only giving this my state
vector here is only the theta that's it
and I'm gonna solve I'm gonna write an
equation for this that makes it so that
whatever theta I input here I
automatically
slide this arm along the x-axis right so
it never leaves the x-axis no matter
what I do okay if I were to do this this
link assembly would now appear to have
two degrees of freedoms because the
position of the hand does look like a
vector PHX PHY but in reality we know
that pH Y is constant no matter what I
set this to it will always just slide
back and forth along a fixed position in
Y right
so again degrees of freedom can be very
complicated and deceptive depending on
how complex your system is you may have
to think a little bit to figure out how
many degrees of freedom the system
really has okay so hopefully that's
relatively clear again we're not
implementing this in hand-made here or
anything like that this is just to give
you an overview of it so you don't have
to understand of the specifics all that
much but hopefully that gives you a
little bit of an overview of kinematics
which is taking a state vector that is
describing sort of almost you can almost
think of it as a mechanical assembly
thinking robotics tends to help like you
know there's a motor and we can set it
to various positions or whatever you
know and it you know can rotate left or
right or could rotate up or down or both
or whatever and so you're literally
talking about what are the positions of
these motors right and given those
positions of the motors where is the end
of this thing okay
so I'll give you one more term here and
that is end effector and I know since we
have an effector on the chat
I feel like he'll be happy to see that
his name is a formal term in robotics if
he didn't know that already which maybe
he does so typically what we call this
this thing I was following the hand
right I was saying the thing the thing
that we care about where it actually is
when we're doing our kinematics that is
called the end effector and it's called
the end effector I suppose I don't
really know I don't know the history
because in robotics where this stuff was
originally sort of formalized you you
cared a lot about like a grasping arm
right you were trying to like grab
things or
position a robot's appendage somewhere
to do some mechanical thing like put
together a car or who knows what pick
something off an assembly line and so
end-effector it was the thing at the end
that you were actually trying to do
stuff with and that's what you actually
cared about so that's where inverse
kinematics and kinematics sort of you
know started having this terminology
built around them as far as I know again
not a historian so that's just my
assumption could be wrong all right so
that's all great but that's kinematics
so what's inverse kinematics well
inverse kinematics is exactly what it
sounds like if kinematics is taking a
state vector and producing an end
effector position I should say end
effector let's put it this way let's say
if it takes a joint state and goes to an
end effector state right that is
kinematics we input the joint state v
theta fi whatever we get out an end
effector state which is the position of
the hand inverse ah why why does it do
that I need to disable this why does it
have that function it's so that is so
annoying stop okay
anyway inverse kinematics is exactly
what it sounds like reverse this process
take the end effector state as your
input right this is the input this is
the output and instead tell me what the
joint state is
now why do we care about this right well
we care about this because almost all
the time when you actually are dealing
with these sorts of things
this kinematics right is the part that
the render loop does right whatever the
whren directions they render loop I
should just say the renderer right in a
3d renderer or 2d renderer or any
renderer that wants to deal with
articulated bodies these by the way
these things are often called
articulated bodies don't ask me why
because they articulate and they're made
up of rigid bodies
I guess anyway this is what the renderer
does the renderer has some kind of a
state like what the joints are and it
has to produce the 3d positions of
everything so it can render it so the
kinematics problem we deal with all the
time and we even dealt with this on
handmade here we had the concept right
of the hero you know it had a ground
point and then its head was like up
somewhere offset from the ground point
that's basically a kinematic chain it's
saying I know this and I know that
there's an offset that puts me here well
I need to find out where here is that's
kinematics
it's simple kinematics but its
kinematics right so that's what the
renderer has to do but if you want to do
modeling work right if I want to specify
what's supposed to happen and find out
what my multi-link assembly looks like
then you need inverse kinematics because
if I'm an animator or something like
this or we're on an assembly line and
the robotics vision computer thing says
hey I got to pick up that package and I
know where the package is the location
of it it's got to get the arm there and
the same is true for animation the
animator might say oh yeah I've got this
this arm assembly right and I need it to
touch this point I need it to go reach
out and grab this thing
well the animator doesn't want to have
to fuss with these joints and like use
the rotation tool to like eventually get
it there
the animator just wants to say here's
where it should be and then it wants the
computer to solve for what those joint
angles would be so that it touches it
directly again same thing with the
assembly line if this was something that
the robot had to go out and like you
know it has to weld at that point or
something it needs to solve for what it
has to set its step motors to so that it
knows that it's going to actually be
there and actually be touching the point
that it needs to touch okay
so inverse kinematics is very literally
that thing it's the act of taking an end
effector state and producing the joint
state from it such that other parts of
the system whether it's a renderer in
the case of game development or an
animation system or if it's something
realistic like in the real world like a
robot that actually needs to set its
motors to do something we need to know
what that joint state is because it
needs to feedback into the other parts
of the system okay so how do we do that
right how does that actually work well
it's really really really nasty right I
K as it's abbreviated is a nasty nasty
nasty problem and the reason it's a
nasty problem is because well I
shouldn't say because the reason it's a
nasty problem is for two really really
tricky nasty little nasty nasty reasons
and really if we're being generous or
start being pessimistic we could say
three reasons number one you know
inverse trig is always harder than trig
some degree that's the basic one number
two it's typically over determined and
if it's not it's discontinuous and
number three there are there are usually
joint limits so let's talk about these
all right so first of all you know what
can I say even in the most simple basic
scenario that you might imagine it's
always harder to construct something
that reverse solves for a bunch of trig
stuff than it is to take some input
angles and just produce what the thing
is right the inverse problem is always
almost always harder than the original
problem and you see this pretty much
everywhere right you know a matrix
multiplication is a lot easier than
matrix inversion right I mean it's just
inverting things as is tricky and so
just to start off with you can imagine
I'll just give you a very very
straightforward example in that
situation we were talking about where I
said okay let's pretend that we have the
position of the hand the position of the
shoulder and we just have a theta here
and a Phi here okay knowing only what
you know from handmade here oh you can
produce the kinematics equations for
this easily okay all you have to do is
write the cosine theta sine theta vector
equation right that rotates you theta
from down you have to go you know this
is the L 1 this is the L 2 lengths you
just multiply that vector by L 1 that
you get and you would be here okay
that's like that and then you then know
well okay so if I want to know where
this thing is I just need to take this
Phi it's on the inside and I'm pointing
that way so I would just do you know PI
minus Phi
right to get because this is this right
here is 180 degrees right and I want to
know how much to rotate this vector by
that way right you would then take this
vector rotate it that way by PI minus
Phi and then you would go l to along it
and you'd go here so doing forward
kinematics really not very difficult
okay it doesn't matter how many links
there are in the chain it doesn't matter
how many dimensions the problem is in
really it doesn't matter anything at all
it's just very straightforward to start
somewhere and have a prescribed route to
get to where you're going now the
inverse problem we've never done
anything like it on handmade here oh
okay if you want to try it for homework
it's actually pretty difficult I you
maybe give it a shot sometime if you're
interested it's not something that will
probably ever come up on handmade here
oh but it's it's difficult we've never
shown how to do anything like it it's
not something I would expect you to just
know how to do even if you're a
confident 3d programmer if you have
never thought about inverse kinematics
or it's a little tricky and this is the
simplest possible case it's just a -
link this is called - link I k2d - link
I K right because just two links and
it's kind of hard so just for starters
it gets annoying and the reason it gets
annoying is because even in the simplest
possible cases it's harder than the
forward problem so it's a little bit
nastier just right off the bat even if
we don't introduce anything else but
then we get into the bad stuff like this
is not so bad right that's not too bad
you tell me you got to solve this it's
like okay I can solve it I'm not gonna
cry myself to sleep at night over that
but this starts to get bad so I say
typically over determine and if not it's
this continuous right so let's talk
about this one first
so typically over determine what that
means is so let's say under determined
and overdetermined okay so if something
is under determined or over determined
right and us realized this is the wrong
phrase that's what I actually wanted to
say this is typically under determined
and if mass is continuous sorry about
that just brain fluttering off into
space okay so I'll be determined in over
determined what are these mean
well over determined is not such a
problematic situation for us in ikb cuz
it wouldn't really be something we'd
ever have to care about so I'll tell you
what it is over determined is when you
have a system that has more requirements
for how it has to be set up then it has
variables to actually satisfy them right
so an over determined system is I can't
really think of a way to describe what
it might mean in ikb cuz it never really
comes up I don't really know it would it
would be it would be like if I said
something like the hand has to be here
and here right like this is the position
of the hand and this is the position of
the hand it's like well the hand can't
be in two places this is over determined
right that systems over determined
you've you've given me so many
requirements that I can't possibly hit
them and now you might say well what
that's just dumb like why do we even
have a name for that and it's because a
lot of times you actually do deal with
systems like that just not in AI K and
an example if I had to extend this bogus
example into something you might
actually do you could imagine that what
a graceful failure of the system would
do in an overdetermined context would be
to place it like in between the two of
them or something so that it's as close
as possible it minimizes the degree to
which each one is unsatisfied right so
there's a lot of other contexts where
overdetermined systems make sense to
talk about and you care about them I
cannot so much I mean maybe there is but
I don't ever
I've never seen that like myself so I
don't know but underdetermined is where
it's usually at now the reason that it's
usually there is because normally with
AI K you're dealing with systems that
have a lot of links so for example one
thing that I might want to do in a video
game very common is if we go back to
anatomically correct KC right obviously
this is exactly what I look like okay if
we were to talk about this and we were
to say I need to position KC's hand
somewhere and I want to position it over
here right so my eye case salep is
trying to figure out what I would need
to do to put the hand here okay
now in the case where it's only a two
link arm all right I'm gonna go back now
because this is where we need to start
talking about this
remembering degrees of freedom in a two
link arm the number of degrees of
freedom which were two happens to be the
same as the output okay there was an X
or Y output of the hand location and
there were two degrees of freedom that I
could use to position it so if it was a
2d two linked arm in a plane okay and I
want to put it somewhere well that can
be solved exactly all right it is not
over determined or under determined the
number of degrees of freedom and the
output space are the same the degrees of
freedom in the input space and the
output space of the same might be a way
to phrase it right so if we're talking
about how many different variables there
are in the state vector and how many
variables there are on the output target
they're equal and so hey great two
equations and two unknowns this is
simple mathematics it's exact I solve it
we're all good right so that works but
if I were to then say okay not anymore
now I'm gonna include all these joints
right I'm gonna say that KC can stand on
this leg right you're gonna put his
weight on this leg so these this stuff
has to be fixed but this joint this
joint this joint this joint and this
joint are all allowed to move to hit
this goal well even if each of these
joints only had
one angle which really in a real
situation they have more even our to
link our quote-unquote to link one would
have had more right because the shoulder
could be thought of as having two
degrees of freedom because it's a ball
and socket so it can really rotate in
two along two axes right it's got it's
got a whole sphere of movement there
right but all of these even if they each
only have one degree of freedom somehow
which is a not realistic thing they all
have more than that we would have one
two three four five six degrees of
freedom
to play with on the input right but our
output would still have only two degrees
of freedom or if this were 3d three
degrees of freedom
right if it's a 3d we'd only have three
you have XY and Z to specify but we'd
have six joint angles to solve for and
that is an underdetermined state that is
a system that's under determined we
don't have enough equations to solve
right so what do we do okay no math no
amount of direct solving math is gonna
get you out of this scenario because as
you know with you know the mat the
algebra that you've been taught in in in
you know junior high school or wherever
else grade school math right you know
that you need one equation for every
unknown and in our system we have
degrees of freedom which are essentially
unknowns right we have the state vector
on this side here right we have these
these variables that describe our arm
each one of those is an unknown and we
have to solve for it so if the degrees
of freedom in the output are less than
this we will simply not have enough
equations right assuming that each one
of these things does something right has
as a separate thing we won't have we
won't have enough equations to generate
now like I said before sometimes you can
get lucky and sometimes you can get
situations where like remember I drew
this thing where you can say oh you know
let's say there's only one input to my
system right or uh let me put you that
way let me let me
a slightly different way let's say I
only have one input right so I have like
an X here right that's I'm going to
specify and so you might say well
there's there's two angles here right
how am I gonna solve for that well
sometimes you get lucky and like I said
if you're if the description of your
assembly is that this is theta and this
is some other function of theta that
forces it to always be on the line well
now even though this appears like it's
got two degrees of freedom because
there's two joints really those joints
are dependent so now you still only have
one thing to solve for you're just
solving for theta and so you have one
input one output everything set
everything good right you can solve that
not a problem okay so when we end up in
a situation where we have a state vector
that has more things we can set in it
then our output has information that we
can use to solve for those things that
is an underdetermined system and that's
where i care gets really nasty because
now you need some way of making up what
the joint angles should be that has
nothing to do with the fact that you
need to end on this position so what do
you do well one very typical thing you
might do is say I want whatever is the
thing that moves me the least from my
current location right that's that's one
way of doing it because then I say well
okay I know that I can try to solve for
something that hits here and I can now
subject subject it to a minimization
criteria of try to do something which
moves me the least from where I am
that's now a way that I can perfectly
determine my system there is only one
smallest movement or family of movements
that would do that and so now I have a
shot at solving this right typically I
can't solve it directly still I may have
to solve it iteratively or do other
kinds of fanciness but you know I could
do that another one might be solve it
where there's some rest state and I want
to be as close to the rest state on each
of my things as possible another one
might be try to I don't know
I'm not thinking of a whole lot other
ones to be completely honest with you
try to distribute the motion evenly
among all the joints might be another
one right so I don't want to like do
everything on the last joint and hit it
or the last two joints I want to spread
the motion out over all the joints
evenly
that'd be another way to do it so you
start to introduce these artificial
criteria that are sort of based on other
things right and then that's how you get
out of the undetermined system thing
because if you had to produce an exact
solution with no other information you
would be like I can't solve it right you
need some other information to say you
know you could just give some random
solution there are ways of solving the
problem so that you know that you'll hit
it and it's just a random mathematical
thing but usually even those they have
something that they're actually secretly
doing like if you look at what the math
is you're like oh it actually always
produces the solution that does blah or
whatever right okay so that's really
nasty because it takes it from a problem
that's that would just be a series of
equations that you can just solve to
something that's this kind of fuzzy
requires minimization possibly iterative
algorithms like it takes it into a whole
nother realm of problem solving right
and similarly even if you don't have
that problem for some reason you if you
if you don't have the the over
determined thing sorry under determined
thing you have typically another problem
which is that often times it's
discontinuous and what that means is if
you were to write equations that do
solve it directly so they are actually
like you have a situation where you have
the two linked I K right and you you
know you wrote to the equations for
solving for the end effector in terms of
these two angles directly typically
those direct solutions end up being
discontinuous so like when you move this
thing smoothly so I move it like here
here here and here right it moves it
like it does like this this and then it
like pops to that right because usually
there's some positive negative term in
here because you can almost see it if
you just think about the problem right
if I told you to put the thing here
right here's the the position of the
hand here's just the shoulder right well
for any solution that I give right yes
there's only one solution in this
quadrant that can satisfy this but I
could always take the negative flipped
version and that also solves it so even
though it's basically a solution usually
and this is because of the trigonometric
nature of it right there's a positive
negative possibility in there all the
solutions will can have a positive
negative choice in them and so typically
you end up in situations where even
they'll they'll be like a singularity in
here where there's no way to really make
its move smoothly through that point
without having it flip and you just have
all these other nasty misses again
that's something you need to really
think of too hard about I'm just kind of
pointing them out as things that happen
in AI K and finally if all of that
weren't nasty enough
we've got nasty number three and nasty
number three is that usually nobody
wants you to actually solve this problem
in such a clean fashion as what I just
suggested normally it's not oh hey
here's just some some joints and here's
the theta and theta could be whatever
you want it's like that theta cannot be
whatever you want typically really what
normally happens is something more like
this we built this robot right and it's
got you know a range of motion that's
like this or something so the joint that
comes out of here cannot go past this
point this is like a hard limit and it
cannot go past this point and that's
true of the human body too right you
can't rotate your arm any further than
this right I can't rotate it through
here okay that's just that's just the
way physical things work they hit stuff
so you know if you're animating a human
you've got all these joint constraints
similarly here right this elbow it can't
bend past here right it's got to be up
and it can come all the way back here
but then it can't bend pass there okay
so now not only do you have this problem
of over I'm sorry you can see keep
saying over terming underdetermined
systems and the nasty inverse problem
you got to solve but now you also have
to deal with boundary conditions that
are basically saying
like oh okay you know there's
constraints on this problem where you
that the answer is constrained to lie
within this value and this value so you
can't just solve it for anything you
have to solve it in the space that's in
there and so that interacts with this
determination problem where you kind of
have to do these systems that go like oh
okay try some things and it early try to
figure out can I move it here do I need
to move this joint over there bla bla
bla it could be really nasty because
math tradition was pretty bad at dealing
with these sorts of things they turn
into these things
they're called well actually I think the
entire domain is called operations
research right and what's the general
name for the problem if you actually
solve these directly it's called I can't
believe this is not something I remember
this is gonna drive me nuts
so in operations research there's a name
for this kind of problem where you're
doing solves that are it's a nonlinear
it has constraints and it's got a
minimization criteria and it's called
this is why getting old is awful do not
ever like basically like stay 27 or so
for as long as you possibly can do not
ever hit 30 try to have an asymptotic
age so that every year you get older by
like half as much as you got older the
previous year so that you net you just
never you can live like the rest of your
life and never get past like 29 it's not
so there's a special case of it called
Danzig's algorithm that's not the one
that I mean this is a special one that
has constraints that has additional
qualifications to it it's called
a linear complementarity problem so I
believe a linear complementarity solver
is the one that does all these things
and they're very complicated let me see
if I remember that
yes I think this is it
yeah so I'm pretty sure Lemke's
algorithm is the one I was thinking of
and this is the mere compass okay I may
have just fished that one out we'll have
to wait for the chat to referee it to
know if it's actually wrecked but I'm
pretty sure that that's called a linear
complementarity problem and so you need
a linear complementarity problem solver
if you're going to solve it Lemke's
algorithm sounds really familiar to me
so I think this is that I'm correct in
the name here so that is really big bad
ugly math it's it's it's pretty tricky
there like basically these iterative
solvers some of them are direct solvers
but they still operate iteratively
essentially and others are like solvers
that are converging solvers that that
you that you run over time and their
answer gets refined and yeah you know if
basically anything that we do on
handmade Hiro that in terms of math
solving is nothing close to how bad
these guys are they're just nasty and
thankfully like lately I think if I
remember correctly they've gotten kind
of better at doing iterative versions of
them that aren't so complex and aren't
so numerically unstable as they used to
be so it's probably better now than it
was but point being not what you want
for a cakewalk like you don't really
want you don't want to hear someone say
if you can avoid it that we need a
linear complementarity solver for this
thing so really nasty and a lot of times
in AI K they just cheese it they don't
actually use anything like this they'll
actually just use some kind of cheesy
half-baked iterative thing that just
kind of moves joints generally towards
the goal and that tends to be good
enough sometimes you can do sort of
cheesy stuff there are some pretty
simple algorithms that work okay and
that is actually what people often use
instead of like trying to do things that
are extremely mathematically rigorous
for them so yeah so nasty nasty nasty
problem it's just a really bad problem
as I alluded to there though if you need
to use it the good news is that usually
most
of the time and I you know not all the
time so you know I apologize for those
of you or not in this circumstance but
most of the time you don't really need
to mathematically accurately solve I
cape problems in that sense right
because if you think about it in like an
animation context or something like this
it's not really about getting a precise
mathematical answer right and so you're
just looking for something that achieves
the goal of positioning a leg or I mean
a foot or a hand at a location
reasonably well and so even though this
problem specification is super nasty as
I sort of said just moments ago there
are some cheesy algorithms that work
reasonably well so you can use it in a
game context and not be too worried
especially if you're just using it for
fix up right so for example if you're
just trying to take an animation that
somebody made and adjust the position of
the hand so that it hits something
exactly that's like on the ground or
whatever like it's a pickup animation
and I want to adjust it so that it hits
whatever it's picking up exactly that's
not so hard
a simple iterative thing that moves the
joints a little bit which and there's
been a number of papers on this sort of
thing will work so yeah I just wanted to
get across that NASA the problem was but
I don't want you to like go cry and
despair or anything if it is something
you need to do there are lots of
approximate sort of things that look
fine when you do them that maybe aren't
really rising to the level of qualifying
as solving the problem in the
mathematical sense but that's not really
what you mean needed you usually only
need to solve in the visual sense and
there are plenty of options there so
that's the good news if that makes a
sense so that's about it
hopefully that gave you some background
on the inverse kinematic situation and
yeah we're pretty much out of time so if
you have questions on it we can always
take them tomorrow but that's pretty
much what there is to it you know if we
were to go any further into it we'd have
to start talking about actually how you
solve it right like you'd actually start
coding a solver or something from here
and talking about the different stuff
but so yeah all right uh so I'm gonna go
ahead and wrap up so wait I have a
question here mister fourth dimension I
would think boundary conditions would
help to move towards being more
determined so why don't each of those
two problems reduce the severity of the
other so the reason is because math is
really bad at inequalities right so if I
tell you to solve the equation 2x plus y
equals 4 and X plus 3y equals 6 this is
what math excels at really really well
right if instead I tell you to solve the
problem 2x plus y equals 4 and you know
X plus 3y is less than 6 well this
doesn't really help all that much right
kind of what this did is just make
things more complicated for you because
now you have to sort of talk about a
family of solutions 1/2 space right and
carving spaces in half doesn't really
help you
it actually makes things more difficult
because now instead of having a free
variable you have a free variable up to
a point right so it's really just the
difference between this which is always
helpful and this which is really just
further complicating and it's not to say
that it doesn't limit the space of
solutions it obviously does but it
doesn't limit them limit them in a way
that math
advantage of very easily and sometimes
it's actually a way that makes math
harder because now you can't just solve
for variables or reduce to a single
variable that varies because now there's
actually like a hard cut in the space of
solutions that nothing can be on one
side up but if everything could be on
the other side of hopefully that makes
some sense
elven thanks for the awesome answer I
was intending to use AI K to sell for
foot placement on uneven terrain so we
have an animation of the dude moving and
want to places foot correctly on the
ground is that hard no it's not too hard
I don't know what the latest
state-of-the-art in AI K on in easy ika
is but you know there's like recursive
descent versions that are super trivial
to implement and I think they're called
possibly iterative descent maybe but
like the super trivial wants to
implement that actually work fairly well
for stuff like that is you know I've got
the leg let me do the side view so the
problem right is the animation place the
guy's leg here and that's just obviously
totally wrong because it's underneath
the ground right this is the ground this
is the foot so I want the foot to be up
here so what the iterative descent ones
do they're really really straightforward
what they do is they say well okay if I
needed to move this guy to here right
try to remember exactly what this does
it's I think what it does is it says
like the vector from me to the end
effector right whatever that is try to
rotate that so it faces
I cannot remember this so basically you
run this multiple times I think it's
that you take the vector from the
location of the joint you're gonna work
on so you start at you start it like the
route let's say and you say alright I've
got a vector from here to here okay
I rotate it so that it's in line with
this thing right so basically it points
like that
then I take the next joint right and
I've got that line from here to here and
I rotate it so that it points along so
the you know it's coincident with this
thing then I just start again so I come
back up here now my end effector
Direction is here right so now I rotate
it again so I gotta rotate it this way
right so that my my line is here and
then it just not drawing this very well
let's do it one more time okay so I want
to move this foot up target is here
right so I first take this vector and I
say I want this vector to point all
right so this is the vector from the the
end effector I'm sorry from the the
joint we're on to the end effector I
want to rotate so that this points
directly through there right so that
moves me up a little bit here right then
I've got this guy it's out here and I
look at that I say well I want to rotate
that in right because I want again I'd
move to this joint and I do this joint
so it points in that direction I then
start again here and I would see the
same thing I see it down there I got to
move it up so it rotates up a little bit
and then again it's out so it moves it
in a little bit right and eventually it
will hit so you just do you know you do
like ten iterations of that thing or you
can iterate up to like a thousand times
or something but stop when you get close
enough to your goal you can choose how
you want to budget your time or however
you want to do that right but within you
know ten iterations or something like
this it's gonna be pretty darn close to
the goal and then you could stop and
that's really easy to implement joint
constraints in because then when you do
your rotation you just never let
yourself rotate past the joint
constraint this is pretty good for Ike a
fix ups it's not so good for whole body
Solutions whole cloth
because it it'll hit joint constraints
and not realize it should kind of rotate
out of them so it can get it gets caught
in local minima right or local Maxima
should say so yeah let me see
cyclic coordinate descent that's what
it's called I forgot the name of it
cyclic coordinate descent is the thing
so silly coordinate descent is like
totally fine so I think I would suspect
because I haven't done character
animation work in since 2003 or 4 right
I would suspect that by now there's a
better so there's a better simple
technique at even signal Gorgon scent
was not the best technique for AI K even
though in its time but it's the easy
it's very very easy and produces
reasonable results there might be ones
that's similarly as easy now that people
have figured out that produce good
results so you might want to do a survey
of the literature really quickly because
you know you might get lucky I don't
know but anyway there you go all right
I'm gonna close it down cuz we are out
of time
and yeah that's really all I have to say
about that that's really all I have to
say about that so thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like more chats until we're off RSI
break I will be back here tomorrow 5:30
Pacific Standard Time I'd love to see
you I hope you'll be able to make it
until then my friends have fun coding
and I will see you on the Internet take
it easy everyone