hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show where we code complete game
live on stream uh there is not much to
say today
uh we made a thing for ourselves uh last
two
weekends i guess not last weekend
because last weekend was a very special
episode
starring john blow um this week
is not starring anybody
but if you remember correctly we added a
little drawing thing and our drawing
thing uh tells us a bunch of information
about the collision stuff which honestly
sort of
kind of works pretty good um we have not
really had any problems with things
getting stuck
uh and so our goal of of the collision
system not producing sort of bad
outcomes
uh seems to have worked pretty well
although obviously we haven't stress
tested it much
however uh we we did want to do some
stuff so like for example this sort of
thing where you know when something hits
another
piece of geometry um it doesn't get
stuck like i can still move it just fine
but it doesn't really have like roll you
know what i mean so things can still uh
i mean well that doesn't really do it
but you know like uh like i just did
that where something is trying to move
straight
um
and so the target of the thing that it's
moving towards is straight ahead
but there's something in its way
uh we don't really have a good answer
right now for how to make sure that like
that they smoothly kind of roll around
which is what we would like
um and what you can see here is we
started drawing some things like these
here are vectors uh sphere collision
vectors from the place where the sphere
the thing the sphere is colliding with
uh and the center of the sphere so you
can see it was testing sphere positions
um
in in a couple different places where
you know it felt like it could go and
you can see it testing them here
and
you know i
i do wonder a little bit based on
looking at it it actually looks fairly
uh clean
so
i'm not really sure we could add some
more drawing since we have drawing now
but you know
the drawing sort of suggests to me
almost that maybe the code is actually
just correct and there isn't much need
to
fix it
and so my
my thinking is
what we may actually want to do
to fix this particular problem
it may have nothing to do with the
collision detector it may simply be that
we don't search far enough around
right
so when we look here we only search the
voxels immediately neighboring to the
voxel that we want that we were picking
and you can see that because the voxels
themselves are kind of aligned with the
geometry fairly well
which is
you know maybe not a good idea like
maybe we should stagger those but no
matter what we do
you can always imagine
a piece of geometry getting aligned
fairly closely to the voxels because the
geometry moves around and we don't have
any real restrictions in this game about
where geometry could be
you know we have a grid that we put in
areas for gameplay reasons but that grid
doesn't have to be there right like we
could easily make a level where things
were smoothly moving around and maybe
we'll want to do that someday and our
engine does support it so we really
don't want to
force
uh any sort of like we don't want to
solve problems just by
using alignment
so when you look
at what's happening here i'm wondering
if our main problem is just that we need
to search
a little bit further so we need to go
like if if we don't find
uh a way to
accept a movement in the local space we
need to try at least one more
uh
square than we were trying you know what
i'm saying
uh so i wonder if that's the main
problem that we're having is we don't
really have any way to fix that
problem
um and i i really like i said i don't
know so i'm not suggesting that this is
the actual solution i'm just saying i
wonder if we fundamentally can't solve
the problem
uh the way it exists at the moment and
if we
okay
why did that not work i never know why
this doesn't work
we never really got
um
the four coder flurry thing sort of
really working um
at some point i'm gonna have to do more
of that but like we have a build thing
here but it doesn't seem to actually
build
i think because
i don't remember why
but like it doesn't seem to actually
work like you do this and then you say
like builds and like it just doesn't
build but i don't know why
because i mean there is a build.bat
right in that directory
it's right there
if i do it from the code directory it
works so if i'm in that directory
and that did load the project file i
have no idea is there a project file in
here
no i don't know oops that's a dir yeah
i don't know
hey it sort of works i guess that's good
so anyway uh if we take a look um
at the code for that which is in move
entity the thing that i'm basically
talking about is what we test so you can
see our vox alliterator
uh thing here which basically goes and
says let's try
um
these voxel locations
and
you can see it taking steps you can so
yeah
like
my thinking is just that
that if we change a little bit about how
we test these voxels that might be
sufficient
like you can see how this works right so
we do a foreign loop
you know
um and we go through here and we say
each time in the loop we're going to
test nearby voxels to see what happens
to them
um and then we're gonna select the best
move of the options that we have
uh and my assumption is just that like
yeah if we just change a little bit how
that
is lined up
uh that's really all we need so you can
see like the min corner here right we
start with one of those
um and we just move
through the mid corner like like so
and so
it would seem that if we broaden that a
little bit that might be all we would
need so this also like this seems cited
uh
as well like if you think about it
um
yeah like like it's literally just
testing just that one voxel
and
when it tests it like it can only move
like it won't try to move
anywhere where a side isn't open
right
um
let me
so one of the problems is this drawing
kind of
uh doesn't it doesn't really help right
um because i can't see
even though like we assume we know
because we would be like well okay like
this side is probably open right
um
yeah so okay so let me let me
let me say it this way
i do think it's correct to only check
voxels whose exit criteria is what we
think it should be right so we shouldn't
be checking voxels like
where like we're in an outside voxel and
then we like go into an inside voxel
like we should not be doing that check
right
but
the problem that we're gonna have here
as you can see
is we do a
a check
and we only accept the voxels
that are
that contain the new closest point
and so each time through
uh our system
when we hit a voxel
that is closer
which can contain a point
closer to the target than the vauxhall
in
we always take that move
but if that move actually won't end up
producing the closest point
to the target out of the voxels nearby
because you had to go through another
voxel first
we'll never find it
right
so that's mostly the problem
i want to say
um
i don't have really any other
ideas about what's going on there
um
we probably should draw lines between
these
so like in this thing where we do
um
these diagrams here right
so that that's what's drawing like
this stuff it would be nice if we could
see
um
which order these got done in
right
uh or like you know like it started in
one and it moved to another right um and
we can't really see that at the
immediate moment we just get
color uh
we get color-coded boxes but they don't
really tell us very much information
right
um i'd have to go look up what those
colors even mean but i believe the
yellows are ones that had
some in some out
uh and so we probably went from like
here to here looking for places or
something like that uh and we didn't
find one so like when it came to here it
was like there isn't anything closer
or you know something like that so i
again i'm not really sure which is why i
think we need to draw more stuff
i believe red boxes are ones that uh
that we can't
go into um but i don't know so let's
take a look
and just see what that drawing
um actually does so
[Music]
that would be where
here no that's refined voxel placement
um
so i assume it's this
and i assume it's these
so
it starts off green
if it's not occupied
it turns yellow
um
i'm sorry it starts off red
so that's occupied if it's not occupied
it turns yellow
and if it ends up being one
that it actually accepts
as a move it turns green
so i guess that does tell us mostly what
we need to know from this because it's
such a simple set of boxes there are so
few
um like looking at it it is basically
what i said assuming there aren't any
bugs here
with producing those
ideas it looks like what happened is we
started in the interior cell so we
started like in here right
we tested this cell this cell and this
cell
uh and what we found was that this one
and this one both
could have contained
the point
meaning there were
points on these voxels that were
non-colliding so it is legal to place
the glove in these two squares but
there was like neither of them contained
a point that was closer to the target
point which is this
uh wobbly little fellow out here right
that's just randomly
frame rate dependently
and quite buggily actually but doesn't
matter because that's just that
controller code can be as buggy as it
wants
at the moment
the collision detection should not it
should not matter right and that's a
very important thing we don't
we don't want the collision code to fail
when something is buggy we just want it
to work
no matter how bad how sloppy the
gameplay code whatever throws in there
if it's wobbly or stupid or
shouldn't
be where it is or whatever anything else
that should still work
um to the best of its ability that's
what we want
and so you can see what happens here we
would probably like to put it in this
cell
right this diagonal cell
that would be right here
that's where we would like to put the
uh
the glove
but we never test that cell and the
reason we never test that cell is at the
moment
um i don't know that we are uh
ever trying
and so it may be the case that we just
need to update these to handle diagonal
motion and maybe that's enough so
diagonal across an edge right
um and i want to say that like that was
a question somebody asked like why don't
you do that yet
and i just said because we haven't
gotten there right
so it's not like we said we shouldn't do
that we just didn't
um
it looks like in this particular case
that would solve the problem whether
that means that that's a complete
solution this problem i'm not really
sure right oh in fact here you go
um
here's the a comment right that we
actually put in there
um and i think that was based on a
question somebody asked and the answer
is i don't have a reason for not doing
it i also don't have a reason for doing
it it's literally just because i haven't
thought it through yet and
i don't think there's any reason why you
couldn't allow that
um
the problem that i the only problem that
i see
is that i don't know if this is a
sufficient solution right like it may be
that the better solution is to look two
cells away always
right which would which would include
those cells that would be captured by
this diagonal motion but it would also
include other cells that are further
away and be more permissive
in the motion of the object
as far as getting around obstacles
so that's really the thing i'm not
entirely sure about
um
and so i really don't know i will start
by just trying that and seeing because i
guess we don't want our collision
detection to search harder than it needs
to
so
i because i can't really
come up with any real mental rubric for
deciding this
theoretically
i guess i'd just say we solve it
practically and go
let's try putting those two cases in
because only two right it's motion
through the corner
and motion through this to the through
the edge
um
although actually
motion through the corner
i guess is
handled here
maybe
because this is the corner
um
let's take a look
so motion
hmm
i'm a little confused because it seems
like motion through the corner actually
should be handled
i wonder do we not set this so what what
are those like dur inside things set to
because i don't remember what we set
them to
um
so you know like direction is definitely
set to go through the corner
whichever corner you're gonna move
through
right
um
and same here so like if it's less than
zero
then it stays on the
side otherwise it's one so if if the yet
all positives so i guess
so i guess what i would say is
actually this doesn't quite seem right
does it
you know a lot of this a lot of this
seems a little wrong
um
no i guess okay i can be comfortable
with that so yeah like this will check
the corner
right it will check whatever corner you
were going to leave through
won't it
and so what i'm a little confused about
is why we don't see a corner
test being drawn
um
looking up here so when we begin this
diagram
right and we start drawing
you can see here that we've got we set a
color to black
and we claim that we draw a best cell
and then we set a color to white
and we claim that we draw a
like smaller
like a smaller box right
at this position
and
it sure doesn't seem like that's getting
drawn which makes me wonder like is it
because this filtering system is buggy
like i mean we only just made it last
time we coded
is there a bug in it because why am i
not seeing any of this like where's the
black box
that says
where the best cell was
right
um at the start if that's the initial
position right and so if i look at this
you know it's like i don't know i'm not
seeing that
right i definitely don't see that
that white square there
looks like it might be
so the white square
is where we're starting out you know
and it
does look that does look correct
although it's got a little like cyan
plus in it which makes me wonder like
that probably isn't this code though
right
like it so i mean here's an easy way to
test
right
no that was it
so so i don't know like like it looks
like for some reason that the black box
best cell just doesn't draw
right
it's just not there
um because the white box is drawing
so is best cell like a garbage value or
something
i
like what's going on there do we have a
bug in our color routines where they
don't
zero zero zero color doesn't properly
extend
the alpha value or something like
what is happening
am i am i the only person who thinks
that's weird
um
uh
so here's one other thing i'll do just
real quick if i nerf the entire routine
so let's suppose it's just gone like we
don't
do anything else so it's not gonna it
doesn't happen right so the only thing
we draw is the white box in the black
box that's it
do i see them are they getting like
overdrawn with some other
thing right
um
that's i guess what i'm asking
so that black box never gets drawn the
white box does get drawn and
we have no idea why so let's test a
couple things because
we need the diagramming system to be
reliable if we're going to use anything
with it so the first thing i'm going to
do
is i'm going to change the color uh from
black to red to see if there's anything
weird about the fact that like the color
was black
i mean i don't know
um it there shouldn't be because i don't
see why like it's just passed through it
shouldn't matter and it doesn't appear
to
um so
now let's leave the color black and i'm
going to copy um
the
construction that's used here so that we
can just say well okay so suppose that
best cell we just forget about what best
cell is entirely and i just draw a
bigger box on top of the box that we
already have
um so we kind of know where it will be
it's just a slightly larger box do i see
that
right and i don't
um so now the next test i'm gonna do is
i'm just gonna reverse the order of
these two things to see if it's that the
first thing i draw with a diagram system
doesn't work because then that would
give us a clear indication of what's
going on
um so here we go
uh and that is apparently the case like
you can see that the you can see it
right there right there's the black
box now
so it seems like we just have a problem
where the first thing that we whatever
we say on the diagram
[Music]
when we first push like the box on there
or whatever that like doesn't get drawn
for some reason
and so we should be able to see that
pretty easily i'll take a quick look at
inspecting it
but
you know
assuming that i can't immediately see
the problem is we should be able to step
into the debugger really easily and
verify a doesn't get pushed
and b if it does get pushed
why doesn't get drawn when we actually
loop over it right like what happens in
here
uh we have like this um
we have like these attributes right
where we set the color uh we set the
thickness
and we kind of have these current and
sticky
uh things so you can kind of like set
permanent uh
color whatever you know nonsense like
that uh and you can see what happens
here is we have a current equal sticky
at the end of each of these
um and you can kind of see like we set
like when you do color we set like the
current color to be things and the
current thickness and all that nonsense
right
um so
there are a lot of ways you could
imagine this thing
[Music]
failing
in here there's a couple things we don't
do so when you hit a diagram begin and
end we probably wanted to keep a little
stack that says let's restore what the
color was inside of the diagram
so this part
probably wants to get fixed and it could
be
that something that is happening before
here is affecting it the reason i don't
think that's the case is because diagram
filters should be preventing any of
those things from actually ever getting
pushed right because if you look at what
happens in here everybody's predicated
on if entry
and so
i don't know
i don't know that anything would ever be
on the stack in that case right so it's
probably not that
um
if you look at how push cube is working
right it just does exactly what you
would expect it uses the color
um
like there's there's really nothing
weird about that it uses the thickness
as the radius
the white texture
um
for the fill
and you can see that this is a bit uh
suspicious
that part there i guess
um
and the only reason i say it's a bit
suspicious is because what happens
the first time you draw something
is you set current equal to sticky
right
and so if you've never drawn anything
that line hasn't happened
now i don't think that line should have
to happen
because this should have already done
that like this piece of code right here
should have already set current equal to
sticky
so this should be initialized to valid
values when we enter this loop for the
first time
it should encounter
a color line which is current.color
equals entry dot color
and i can't see like because that
uh does
push a one on
uh
[Music]
yeah i don't know so i don't see it by
inspection i'm thinking i'm just gonna
have to
i'm gonna have to step through this
because i don't really see
why it would be failing
uh to draw that i mean i guess i can
double check the box routine but you
know there's nothing really much going
on here it's it's pretty
simple there's there's really no
nothing interesting is happening there
right um and the diagram group
i don't suppose there's a place you can
over push this is this code wrong like
so when it does its linkage is this
wrong
um
it looks fine to me
so you know i don't see a lot of issues
there either so i'm i don't know
uh i don't see anything wrong with this
so we're gonna have to step through and
we'll
see what we see you know um i don't know
i'm i'm just hoping it'll just jump out
at me as something stupid when we step
through it but if it doesn't then i
guess we're just gonna have to put our
thinking caps on and uh figure out what
what the heck is is wrong here
uh so the first thing i'm gonna do is
i'm just going to try to check to see if
this thing gets pushed on properly it
should be the first thing that's pushed
on um
that passes this right
so the first time we push something on
um
that's we should hit this case
and that case should you know pass the
filter
and we should get an entry that is
whatever the entry is right this is the
new entry and we're gonna stick crap in
it so there's the uh
the instruction which is the thickness
instruction
uh we can go see who's doing that uh
because i don't know
and okay so there's a diagram text call
that's happening here
um
that could have something to do with it
like maybe that code is buggy so here's
diagram text
okay yep that's our bug right there
so we go to push on one of these entries
and it's called a diagram thick but it
was actually diagram text
that's probably it
yep
if only we had a language that supported
discriminated unions you wouldn't be
able to have that bug
to be fair it's not a bug you have very
often and it doesn't take very long to
fix as you saw but still
it's not a bug that you really should
ever
have
um
does ji support discriminated unions
i don't know
john and ia's programs don't tend to
look similar so i i never really know if
he would
uh
care about a particular thing that i
would probably care about a lot right
um
so yeah
uh anyway so yeah like you can see what
was happening there is this would just
pas pushing on totally wrong thing and
of course the way that we wrote this
code it's almost impossible for it to
actually ever crash because of that
if you pushed on something that wasn't a
diagram text as a diagram text because
that doesn't involve a pointer that's
the one place you would see it but
pretty much anything else you do will
just work it just won't work correctly
right it's sort of like a javascript
program in that sense is that the bugs
are all still there they just don't
crash the code
which is somehow seen as a victory
uh anyway so in this particular case uh
i think that's probably all it was
um so now we should get the that little
black square there right
um
so uh let's see
perfect
okay so going back to move entity now um
we shouldn't have to nerf this routine
anymore we should be able to see
everything we expect to see
like so
and
um
looking at
this code now
and
you know just
looking at wherever the thing is uh
yeah so that that one is actually okay
so
that was crucial because now i can see
that it actually is testing
the diagonal right so it's not testing
that one right there is the only one it
doesn't test right uh oh well actually
those two too like there's three edges
that it doesn't test right so the
diagram verifies
that things are happening so that's good
let's go ahead and try adding those
uh
side motions i guess
so if we take a look at
this
uh code here what this would be is you
can see these testing flat faces right
for movement
and so a face because it has uh in this
case four corners they get tested to see
if they're all open
it's not clear to me that that's
actually correct
um
[Music]
because
you know maybe we should say that only
three
have to be i don't know
um but in fact let me go ahead and put
that in here
i don't know if that's you know better
or worse i really couldn't tell you what
you can see here is that if i go ahead
and produce an edge motion one then what
we're gonna see instead is rather than
checking
uh for four which is what a face is
we're just gonna check for three which
is what an edge is and it would be the
combination
of any
of the directions
so we would have something that looked
like you know a der x der y
you know what i'm saying
a uh der x der z
and then a der y der z would be which
sounds like a german word like you know
um we the
like like it seems like the dirt the
wider z sounds like a river in germany
um so once we have
you know uh these
update direction checks we need the
occupied flags
now we're really sounding like a river
in germany uh we need the occupied flags
to
uh be tested for those engines
[Laughter]
boy
okay uh so if we want to do dir y jersey
uh then what we're looking at here is
uh
in terms of these
if whichever one which whichever
uh
motion we're not doing is the one that
we need both edges on i believe right so
so we're going in the the der y dr z
direction but we have to check that edge
so i think the way this would work is
like the zero and one code goes with
which whichever one this is right
and then these are both going to be
just whatever their actual side is
in this case right so we're looking on
the side that we're going and then we're
just saying like the vertical edge in
that direction right which and that's
how we would move through
that side and so the same would go here
so this would be like you know
the same thing but where the edge is
along y so that's you know moving upward
way and then finally this
one here
which is along x right and i think
that's what those are
wait a second i have to check the stream
is somebody seriously talking about rust
again on the stream
you know what happens when someone talks
about rust in the chat
you know what happens
why would you do it
who is responsible for this
why is rust getting discussed in the
chat
the executions will continue until
morale improves
yes
it gets the hose again
all right i'm gonna look back at my
program now
and the next time i glance at chat i
better not see the r word on there
all right
maybe you can maybe if you want to you
can do just do r
star star star or something right
like like
if the if you if you if you write out
rust with a hard st at the end
that that's just like you're instantly
cancelled from the stream
um all right so let's take a look at
what this works out to be
um
[Music]
i'm just curious uh the goal here is to
have it check like the entire block
right and you can see that now we have
like a full cube of testing going on
there the full cube of testing
um and i'm just curious if that uh
changes what we see when we look at the
corner cases now um and
you know just take a look here
okay
uh so
okay so you can kind of also see this
let's this actually illuminates this
much more clearly now that we can see
what we're actually doing here um i'm
going to go out on a limb
i don't know i'm going to go on a limb
and say
that we now have a slightly different
bug the bug that we have is that this
won't work but the other side will i
that's just a total
totally random guess on my part um i
have no idea
but i'm just gonna say
maybe that's what happens
almost but not quite
uh
so we're still in that place where no
ev and i guess i don't know why that is
that's really weird so it switched
which direction it was testing depending
on which glove side it was
how did it do that
it seems like we have something that
uniquely picks the wrong side to test
which i don't know how i did that
can we instead change our code to
uniquely pick i was assuming that since
it picked
that way on this side it would also pick
that way on this side since they're both
trying to go forwards but that's
apparently not the case
um
i also am not sure why that
doesn't work it looks like that would
have enough clearance but i guess the
glove is a little bit too large
um so yeah to me it looks like i don't
know that doesn't look like it's wrong
um
it still looks correct
so my assumption is it's just look it's
not going to work
by just testing the local neighborhood
like if you want to actually have roll
off you're going to have to test like a
larger neighborhood right
um
that seems like
possibly right like yeah
you know
um
so so that's my that's my guess
uh
i'm not sure
um
uh but but we'll see
so i think
you know i i think that's
that's that's the entirety of it
um
so how do i want to do that though is
the is the real question
and i'm um
uh and i'm not sure about that um
so i'm not sure how i want to test the
one neighborhood
or i guess i should say the two
neighborhood in this case because it's
sort of the
of the initial point
but you can see what i'm saying here so
basically we end up in this situation
the actual closest point is is probably
in this square right here
but we're never going to test that
square from this square
you know what i mean
um
so i really just don't know
hmm
so we're gonna have to think about this
obviously it's trivial for us to just
check
more of these cubes because it's just a
function call so we can you know we can
construct the code that checks as many
cubes as we want it's not like it's hard
to construct the algorithm to do that
the question is how do you construct an
algorithm that intelligently tests
only the cubes that it needs to and
doesn't just test like tons of cubes
unnecessarily
randomly looking
for the place to put the point and so
i feel like that's sort of more
the issue there i suppose
um
uh by the way uh
no
you're only not allowed to say
the r star star star word rpg maker is
fine so is game maker
unity and unreal are also fine
just not our star star star
um
i do have some serious reservations
about unity now so i don't know that i
would necessarily recommend anyone use
it
um
instead of one of the alternatives like
unreal engine or
game maker or something
but like
you know if someone does want to use it
i mean
okay
uh
you know
that's their choice i don't think
there's anything like
super wrong about it or something it's
just it seems like i don't think it's
i don't think it's got a lot of
longevity as a game engine these days i
i i mean just based on what you know if
you listen to their corporate conference
calls
and you just see like basically what the
track record is of the program i i mean
i don't think it's the same thing to
build a company or a project around
anymore right so i would strongly advise
against using it but you know um
if for some reason you really think it's
a good idea it's not like our star star
star where i'm just like i really don't
like the people and i don't like how
they constantly
antagonize people about it so i just
don't like it on principle which is not
true of unity nobody from unity has ever
antagonized me about anything right
um
so i i have no reason to suspect that
the people who work on unity are like
bad or something right
um so anyway
uh if we take a look at
um
at this sort of
part of the algorithm here by the way i
don't really remember why these things
are getting
highlighted is that because they're
getting checked for collisions i don't
even remember right like i assume
that that we highlight that because it's
getting checked for collision but i
don't even remember writing that piece
of code uh apparently we did which is
great i mean hey it's kind of a good
piece of information
um
not that we're really using it much but
still cool
um so if we look at what's going on here
we need a strategy for like widening the
search space to some squares
and what that means is like this kind of
thing and you can sort of see why this
is happening too because
in general
we we sort of don't really handle like a
particular narrow band case like if you
look at what's going on here you can see
that
we're sort of making the arbitrary
distinction that if something is
positive it goes one direction and if
it's negative it goes the other
direction we don't really talk about
what happens if it's zero or close to
zero right
and for numbers that are close to zero
like this one is right this is something
that's moving directly down
um the y-axis
right the glove is moving straight
forward
on the screen which is directly down
the y axis and so we arbitrarily
classify that
as like positive one maybe or if like
the floating point value is just a
little bit off
you know then maybe we classify it as
negative one but we're uh it's it the
point is whichever one it ends up being
classified as
it was like totally arbitrary that we
decided to classify it in that way we
could just as easily have classified it
the other way
making this sort of like a bogus choice
now if the thing is like solidly
positive or solidly negative meaning
we're clearly going to the left or we're
clearly going to the right
or something like this right so in this
case right x is the thing we're talking
about
x is basically zero for this motion and
so we're arbitrarily classifying as
saying only search to the left or only
search to the right for this thing and
that's kind of wrong
so we have that problem
and then the other problem is apparently
even that's not quite enough in other
words making that distinction correctly
um may not be enough it might fix that
case
uh but it wouldn't fix that kid did i
get it right let me see
yeah so you can see in this case uh it
look well no no i thought we had one
where we were checking the right
direction maybe we don't
maybe it would fix these cases
um
is that it yet oh well
i can't quite tell
if that case is happening
um
let me
i guess it's i guess we ne somehow never
get that case somehow no matter which
side we're on we always pick the
incorrect thing
um which is impressive i'm not sure how
we did that
but apparently we did
right
um
i don't know
i don't know how we did that
doesn't seem like that should have been
possible so i guess i don't really know
um maybe if it did pick this it would
work
uh
hmm
so i'm thinking of a couple things here
and let me just say them out loud
so one thing that occurs to me is that
if we look at one of these squares
what we could do is
yeah and you know what i'm thinking
about this this makes a lot more sense
so it seems to me like this maybe is the
wrong way to look at the problem
what this does is it says
let's classify the kind of motion that
we're about to do
statically
for the actual movement between the
place that we're starting in the place
that we're ending and we use that
as our voxel direction the entire time
but it occurs to me that probably
what we really should be doing
is classifying which direction we would
want to move
or check
dynamically as we march through the
voxel probably right
and i don't know like we obviously need
a thing that prevents us from revisiting
voxels we already visited though because
otherwise unless we could come up with a
perfect scheme
which never produces the same voxels
twice and that just to be clear that's
why this is a slightly harder problem
because as we currently have it because
we're always searching along a a single
direction
we can never visit the same voxel twice
because we can only move
forward we can never like we can only
only move
in these directions
uh
that we've picked once
we can only go in this direction so if
if we pick negative
negative one for an x step we can never
move positive one in the next step right
so it prevents us from ever getting back
to somewhere that we already were
and that's really the thing that
currently keeps the algorithm from
revisiting
existing cells like cells that had
already tried
and we don't want to do that for two
reasons one is we waste processing power
uh
in on this algorithm if it's testing
voxels it already tested because it's
going to produce you know a predictable
result we already tested that box we
know what the outcome should be
and so what we really want to do here is
oh oh and the second reason which is
more important is it would get an
infinite loop potentially like if you
had two voxels that could go back and
forth from each other we would have to
start introducing something like a
timeout period so we just like okay
after 10 tests if you haven't found
something then quit because otherwise
you could just ping pong back and forth
between two voxels and the routine would
never terminate so right now we have the
nice property of this routine will
always terminate even if it has to test
a thousand voxels to do it to move
something a really long distance which
we don't really want to do but you know
it would still work right it doesn't
produce anything buggy um and so that's
a nice property of the algorithm we want
to continue to have we want the
algorithm to be
don't actually test this thing
this voxel if you've already tested it
and having a way to produce that
automatically is nice because it means
you don't have to track anything we have
to have a stack we have to have
comparisons to see whether we've already
tracked something all that stuff
and so as we move away from that and we
want to test a wider neighborhood of
voxels the problem that i'm having in my
head is like okay so what do i want to
do there do i do i keep a stack of
voxels
and do i say
like okay we
don't
we check to see if we've already tested
them or do i try to have a flood filling
rule
that somehow makes sure that we wouldn't
ever push
voxels on that we shouldn't um
uh ntk dev uh a line drawing algorithm
is what we already have
and what we need is something that's
more than that right we need something
that actually is more like a flood fill
you know
uh and so we need a way to sort of check
a wider swath of things
now maybe we could still use
a line drawing algorithm which is sort
of what we've got right now right we're
basically this is basically a present
resin ham's line drawing algorithm for
the most part
uh is what we're basically doing right
um and maybe one thing we could consider
is a wider line right so maybe we still
draw a line but we test you know two
voxels in either direction
um or something like this
so
you know that could work
um
i just don't know if that's the right
answer
foreign
it's tough decision
so one thing we could do
is
yeah no even that doesn't really make
much sense to me i i can't think of
anything that doesn't track we maybe we
just do need to track like we'll need to
have
some way of
saying look we already tested
these points we don't need to test them
again because i i'm trying to think of
an algorithm that wouldn't require that
and i can't think of anything because as
soon as you test
as soon as you have the algorithm ever
say we're going to test two directions
right so we're gonna test x negative one
and x positive one
for a voxel motion
as soon as you say that that can happen
then the algorithm can pretty much
oscillate you can you can right you can
get in a position where you you
ping-pong back and forth and so you
would need a thing that says i already
checked a previous cell
so we don't need to check that cell
again
unless i'm just not thinking of it
hmm
it really would nice to be to be nice to
be more clever right it would be nice to
be more clever there
but it's not coming to me
um
you can see right like so let's suppose
that you were in this scenario here
right
and you could see just saying look what
if we just widen this up so you know
what if we basically did that
and tested like a nine
way
test
around
uh
the voxel and so the the the min corner
location
we actually start off like one behind
that
and go
forward right
so we test
you know something like a wider swath
and then we pick you know which ones we
want to go
um
in or whatever right like who knows the
other thing we could do is like in here
right we say instead of using these side
coefficients we just actually
don't we we actually have like all of
the possible motion directions in here
and we just use them right
uh
that's the obvious thing to try next and
then you immediately run into the
scenario that i was talking about which
is as soon as you do that you can move
back and forth between the same two
voxels
so what you need is then you would need
a check that's like did i already visit
this voxel
now it's not that
hard of a thing to check
but
it adds a lot of extra complexity right
we've got to keep a stack of those
things
um
unless i'm missing the way that you
would avoid that
um
uh
yeah
i'm just not thinking of anything
i suppose one thing we could do is try
to think about is there a way that we
can have
some kind of like a
additional value besides just the point
that we're trying to get closest to
that would allow us to navigate
um
like okay we you know we tried going in
this direction and it didn't work so
we'll try going in the other direction
kind of a thing
so yeah like i mean here's just a stupid
idea
um
[Music]
like like imagine if you took this loop
right um
and you know you're looping through here
and you can see like okay you get down
to here
and you find out that you didn't like
you went as far as you could using the
direction that you thought that you
should move
right
you know in theory you could add another
thing here that was something like uh
you know tried opposites or something
uh and you could do
you know like okay like if tried
opposites then break you know else
try some other direction
right
um so you imagine like in here you would
say
you grab this crap
and you do something else here so if
tried opposites uh
uh
or whatever you know you you look and
see
if you can
change one of these
deltas somehow
uh
and
you know you could imagine doing this
um
for each one so let's let's sketch a
crappy one so a crappy one is
is like
this is not what we'll actually want to
do if we actually try if we if this is
turns out to be useful
oh wait these are the wrong sorry this
is
der right
it's just uh it's just dirt and side
yeah
so like you know that seems pretty oop
that was bad
um
so that seems pretty reasonable
[Music]
i don't
you know and that's not what we would
actually want to do because we're going
to want to actually test
more than that permutation
um but like
that would allow us to
why is my camera not okay
that would allow us to try more and yeah
and there you can see right so
so if we clean that up and actually test
the forward ones i mean maybe it would
work i don't know but
that's a way of not actually having to
do
um
yeah of not actually having to do it the
problem is it'll still over yeah but
that even that will over test right
because you're still going to overlap
it doesn't require the bounds check but
it will still it would still overlap
um and there's nothing you're really
going to be able to do about that
yes it's still not great um
so like let's suppose we took this
stupid thing
uh and we just said like okay there's
like an opposite flags
stupid thing
and we basically
uh we you know we look at these and we
say if we think that we need to
uh
test this so like the absolute value
um
of one of these deltas
like if the absolute value of one of
these deltas
is less than like our
opposite threshold or whatever
oops
which i don't know what that is
but like if it's close to being
something that could in theory work
uh which we don't i don't know what that
is but let's suppose it is
something like that
um
and i guess you know even thinking about
that i'm not sure that makes much sense
we should just get rid of that let's
just say we let's just do this
um so if we're doing the opposite try
thing it would just like loop through
all the different directions to try like
as it couldn't figure it out
this seems crappy
but you know
so each time through you'd just like ink
this thing and you'd you'd have like
whichever one you were on you'd do it
right
there's probably a pattern here we could
probably just make
the pattern
do something
um
in fact yeah
so
every time yeah
you don't even need to do that you just
do this
so you'd do something like if tried
opposites
uh
you know if this has all of the bits set
so if it's got the one the two and the
four bit set
then you've tried like all the opposites
that you're going to try
right
um
something like that
uh so i don't know if you want to reset
this every time or not
probably not so you go through and you
say like okay if
the tried opposites
uh if we end with one that means it's
like gonna loop up so every time we
wanna try a new opposite we have to flip
like side x right because we're flip you
know we got to pick somebody who
oscillates at the lowest frequency level
um
so if we already were on one of those
then we
have to switch
side y right like if you inked that one
um and at that point we would have to
say like if we were already on one of
these we have to uh
also
knock the other one
right um
[Music]
something like that
and so each time through here we just
say like
we flip aside
and this code sucks and i don't think we
should probably do this but you know
sometimes you just have to explore
something
uh to see what it does
um so here's that crappy code doing you
know whatever it's doing
um and i don't know if this will
actually produce the correct results
let's take a look
yeah so it
it actually does i mean it's it's not
efficient so i don't think we want to
use it
uh but it actually does produce the
correct results and so you can see now
that you know it's checking in there
so i guess
what's a little bit weird about that is
i'm kind of surprised
to learn
that
it can't accept any of those
motions
[Music]
which seems odd
to me
like
uh
but i guess that's actually true right
like it would have to move so far out
here before it could figure out that it
could round that corner you know what i
mean um
that for whatever reason it just can't
find a closer place to place it
which seems kind of nuts right because
if the current location for this thing
is like in there
you would think it might be able to find
a closer place uh which i guess does
mean maybe we want to check the um
check the sphere collision a little bit
more
but yeah i don't know i mean in theory
that could really be true i mean it
could really be true that that
uh
collision is there
maybe we should draw that diagram a
little bit more
like maybe we should try and put
some
clearer
bounds on this so
so one thing we could do is draw the
sphere
for the glove so we can see whether we
think it should be able to be placed in
there or not
because right now you know
it's kind of hard to tell
um
you know like i i can't tell
i don't even know like how big this
glove's collision sphere is supposed to
be
so without drawing that it's pretty hard
for me to say like okay is there some
kind of bug in the way that the sphere
testing's happening
that means like like really you should
be able to place it in there and like
the collision routine is just saying no
even though that's not true
um in which case that would be important
uh so i don't know we've got draw sphere
in here
um
and we don't really have any idea of how
we would do that but
uh
we should be able to produce at least
something like you know some kind of
approximated like we'll put some points
uh just you know
randomly put some of these things down
there
we should be able to draw a few points
and
actually
[Music]
um you know
outline the sphere roughly
so
if we did something like you know like a
little like ring of points or something
or do you know we do have line segments
so we could draw like a ring with a line
segment
um
[Music]
that just you know you could imagine
like an x ring a wiring and a z-ring or
something like that which again is not
going to be great but you know
it would be fine
so
i don't know
something like
i don't know what uh
we want to do here but like you know
suppose we drew like basically octagons
or something
and we just say like okay yeah like
whatever this is
uh we'll produce some angle here
that's gonna be the step index divided
by the step count right
um and we need it to like return to
where it came from so we're probably
going to want it to actually go like all
the way up to step count because we want
to go from 0 to 2 pi so that the ring
like closes
so we're going to have something like
this
where we produce an angle
and because the sine and cosine routines
are stupid
we're going to have to do this
arbitrary garbage here
so uh we do like
um
you know like an x version
which is the cosine of the angle
uh and this is going to be like
i don't remember what our pi value is a
tau 32 something like that
uh so this is going to be like tau 32
times the angle uh and this is going to
be tau 32 times the angle uh but with
the sine
and so then we'd have like the points
going around the circle and we just need
a radius value for these to make them
into an actual
point that we care about
uh and so
what i want to do is just draw these
line segments you can see the line
segment call here also we should
follow the convention and reset sticky
after we draw something
so here what we would need is we'd need
a p0
right
um and we'd need a p1
uh but other than that it would be fine
now since we're drawing a sphere
uh we can just draw three of these at
once
right
and what we could do is
as we oh well you know what we could do
is not do this
and just always compute one forward
right so so here what we would do
is say that we've got um
an x zero y zero
and an angle zero and then we just do
that again
i wanna say that
we have an arm two yeah we do so so we
could actually just do this
where we just say like hey
uh can you produce
the arm for this and that gives us the x
and the y that we wanted uh which that
way we just it's just less code to type
oops
because i didn't hit the
copy button
um
and furthermore i guess we don't need
this angle
anymore then right so we could just say
like okay
you know
you know produce it directly
like that
uh and then we have like an arm one
or an arm the zero arm point and uh the
one arm point
and of course a little confusing because
this is arm two which just means it's an
arm v2 but you know all right
nomenclature's never perfect
uh and so all we're going to do here is
say like look give us the two points the
next one and the uh the one we're on and
we're going to connect them and if we
look at what we do here we can just draw
all three rings with the same values
because the x and y for the sine and
cosine are the same no matter which ring
we're drawing it doesn't matter you know
what i'm saying
uh yes there is plenty of noise uh you
can thank obs is crappy everything for
that
um
anyway
uh if we
go ahead and now produce the points for
the different rings we know that we've
got radial values that have been stuffed
so like if you look at the sphere code
when we push it
you can see that like p0 and p1 are the
two values so we we have like a center
value
um and that's this the entry p0 and we
have a radius value and that's the entry
p1 so we we have like the two pieces of
information
that we need to produce the sphere
and so when we push this on we can
produce the values for all the different
rings uh
by
looking at
these
values
and
i guess the sphere
technically this radius
i guess we don't ever allow it to be
specified as ellipsoidal so you can't
actually specify different
ones like it's not actually letting you
do that here but we can support that
here really easily there's no reason
probably not to so i'm just going to go
ahead and do that even though nobody
asked us to
um
but
what we would like to do here is just
say okay when we do a push line segments
and we do these uh p zero p ones these
are all just gonna be the center
um plus the radius times the arm
right
uh they're all gonna look like this
and so
the only difference between which one
we're drawing
is
what part of the radius value we
actually multiply out
so in in other words if you imagine this
arm zero it's got an x and a y that are
going around right
and if we imagine a vec3 in here
where we just say look there's a radius
x value times an arm x value there's a
radius y value times an arm y value and
then
there's just nothing for z
right
that's going to draw one ring of the
sphere it's the ring
that is in the like
fl the plane of the world if you will so
no height
and if we just permute
which values we're using
uh for that purpose right so if we i'm
just gonna align this a little bit to
the extent that four coder will let me
um
and
so you can see what i'm talking about
in each case right we're just going to
draw exactly this thing
and we're just going to permute which
one of those values we fill in
and of course you may be wondering like
how do i know whether it's arm x or arm
y to multiply here and the answer is it
doesn't matter at all
right
um
because in this particular circumstance
we're just drawing a ring anyway so if
you draw drew the ring by using sine
cosine or cosine sine it wouldn't
actually matter
right
um so so i don't think we actually even
care about that and we especially don't
care about it uh because in this case
our spheres always have the same radius
value so it actually
double doesn't matter
because they're all going to be the same
value anyway so the only thing that
actually matters here is that we do the
permutation right
so we just need to do
this permutation
right
but if we did want to
keep our our
winding proper
then we would know that like okay x y
winding
x cross y is z so we know that this is
going to go the right direction
if we're in a plane
uh where y is the normal to the plane so
we're doing x z right
if you imagine the three a right handed
coordinate system where you have x
excuse me
x
y and z uh
right handed right
so you have x plus y is z so you imagine
like the screen having x and y and z
would be coming out at you
if you're doing x and z if you cross x
and z it would actually be like
negative y
right it would actually be going the
other way round
so you can if you want to you could
choose to like flip these right i mean i
i don't know to what extent you would
care but you know if you were actually
trying to draw rings
you could imagine drawing these
you could you could imagine trying to
get these correct if you wanted to i
just don't know that it that it matters
at all
um
in this particular case
because who who cares which way around
you're drawing it right i guess is what
i'm trying to say but you could negate
them so for example in this case uh if
you wanted to you could have said all
right we're going to draw it the other
way around we want it to go you know you
negate one of those
um
and you could choose which way you were
negating it so like
but i don't know i i'm just not
motivated to do that because it does not
matter which
direction around we don't have to just
go counterclockwise for any particular
reason i don't think it would matter
um
excuse me
um so running this now you can see
there's our spheres getting drawn that's
every time it does a collision detection
um on the sphere you can see it actually
doing the check right
and now you can also start to see why
what i was saying originally um if you
remember we made this thing
right
uh where we wanted to turn on the
ability to single step through diagrams
um you can see why because once you
start actually drawing
this stuff
there's too much information getting
splatted for you to actually see when we
were only drawing
just these
squares
they are non
uh
there's a few enough pieces of
information that we could just see what
it did and we didn't really have to to
look but once you start looking at
individual collision checks you can see
that we draw too many things to actually
know like
is that sphere
gonna be able to be placed on one of
these corners
i don't know because i can't even see
uh the sphere being placed there right
so that's why i think we're going to
need to use
we're going to have to implement this
single step
piece of things
and the single step right
will be what lets us see what's actually
going on in in those um
uh in those individual collision steps
right
um
and you know without that i don't think
we're gonna be able to figure it out
that said
uh even just from that piece of
information
i think
it didn't look right
so that there is that
um let's stop and see the the puss in
the field real quick hello
okay
um
so
let me just show you the reason that i
say that because i don't think like it
wasn't reassuring what i saw there
when we started so what i saw when we
did this right and i went and i paused
it
well i didn't pause it i i took debug
camera so i could kind of come in here
and look
so if you take a look at what's going on
here right
what i would expect what i would have
expected to see at some point
is i would have expected to see testing
of like the sphere on like this corner
but it obviously didn't do that because
if you had placed the sphere on this
corner you would have like a giant the
sphere would come out like way further
than that
so i'm not really sure why i'm not
seeing spheres further this way
is something's up right
because i
like unless i'm misunderstanding or
like i don't get when we draw spheres
maybe
um or something like that
then my understanding of how this
routine was supposed to be working when
i wrote it which admittedly i never
remember because i do this once a week
at most but trying to recall what we
were doing with this routine
is each time through this voxel step
this piece of code right here which is
checking the corners of the voxel
this collides at p
right
should be taking the entity and the test
point
and the test point is supposed to be the
corners of the voxel that we drew
right
um so well
so i guess the problem is we never take
the steps so we only test them once the
interior voxel when we go to update best
how does update best
determine it so okay so the problem is
it's actually just failing the get
closest point in box conservative
right it's failing that check so it
never actually places it never actually
tests the corners of that voxel
right
so i think i'm seeing more clearly now
what actually happens in this routine
um
and that's good
so here's like the breakdown
so the problem is
and and you know this this makes sense
right it's sort of what i said before
but it's a little bit different now it's
a little bit clearer
so
when we look
we
see these squares right so this yellow
square here and this yellow square here
the two furthest yellow squares that
we've got
those are actually never collision
tested ever
what's actually going on there is we're
checking them to see if anywhere in that
square would be a better location to
place the entity than it already is
and they fail
that check why do they fail that check
they failed that check because we are
trying to move straight ahead in y and
they are just x lateral motions so no
matter how far you move it in x you will
never get closer you'll only get further
away so it doesn't bother to check those
right
currently
similarly if we look at what happens
here
we're going to go and say all right
this square up in the corner here
um oh and by the way that yellow uh
so
so that
is
confusing
okay
okay okay okay okay okay
so i think there was something that i
wasn't internalizing about how this
works
i was sort of taking a mental shortcut
but that actually does
okay
so here's there actually is a problem
that we were not discussing before
and here's what it is
red doesn't mean you can't place the
player there red means you can't move
directly through the current voxel to
that voxel
so the actual problem with this voxel is
not that you couldn't place the player
there
and that i think is where the
disconnect's coming from you probably
can player entity you probably can't
uh
you can't place the entity into that
cell
only because the rule is you had to have
been able to move through the corner to
get there because that's the only way to
get there from where we start
what that means is that even though you
easily could have moved into this voxel
and then into this voxel and then placed
the player there
we will never try that because since
this voxel is marked as red due to this
corner being colliding we'd never know
that you could have placed the entity in
here just fine
so the visualization is telling us which
squares we were allowed to move to
um and really that's more of the problem
we never tested putting the player in
here
and that's
the important part right
so
i'm not sure what that means for our
future
but i do think it means we have to
revisit the way this
works
yeah
so
how much time have i got because i'm not
sure what i want to do there so i know
exactly what the problem is now
um
i guess in this case i think we should
probably
do more of a flood fill search so you
know like on the witness collision
detector
um
you know i did more of a flood fill
search
basically you create a grid and then you
walk through that grid remembering which
ones you checked and which ones are
connected
i think we should just do that
um
uh i like i think we're just gonna have
to do that
uh
so let's just do that uh because i like
looking at that it seems pretty clear to
me that that's what you actually want i
don't know if i should start that now
like like i don't know how much time
i've got i started at like what 11 30.
so i don't have much time left so maybe
we'll just call it there so it's like
next weekend that's what we're gonna do
we'll create a grid
and then we will literally just walk the
grid
using the rules remembering which ones
we go to
uh i think that's what we want
so we're just gonna do it
all right so any questions uh because
i'll take q a now
um and then we'll move on
what are those what's that little
what's that little like
ghost ghost moves out from behind a
triangle
oh uh
i just i need to go update the schedule
it's the schedule thing that posts it
not me and i think i just haven't
updated the schedule recently
i can update the schedule
for next weekend
instead of switching between o2 and od
manually why not a different hotkey to
build release versus debug
laziness is really the answer
um
separately i guess what i would say
the way i usually do projects now is
more like they're done in
like if you look at a more recent like
github of mine
uh like if you look at ref term or
something the way i normally do things
now is i just build multiple things in
the bat so so this is an example of how
i do things
mostly nowadays right
so i just do a cl
with the debug flags and then i do a cl
with the o2 flags and i just build them
both so that i always have both
that's actually what i do now
um and i should probably do that for
handmade here i just haven't gone in and
updated its bat file to be like
fancier
and then i just put in two of them so i
just have like this one be debug and
then i use the little plus in remedy to
just have it and then i just i just do
that right i just switch which one i'm
doing
um
that's what i do nowadays and it is
better
on day five six five you said that the
multi-threading coding handmade hero was
crappy and that you learned much more
about it since then but what exactly is
bad in that code
um so i wouldn't necessarily say that
the multi-threading code in handmade
hero is crappy or not crappy uh
because you know honestly i just haven't
looked at it very carefully since then
i would say is i almost certainly would
whatever it is i do most things
differently multi-threading wise now
than i did when i when i did the
multithreading code in handmade hero
so i couldn't say exactly what would be
different but i would probably be
different
right
that's that's all i can say
can you explain what a discriminated
union is sure a discriminated union
is when you take a piece
uh like a block of memory
and you're going to use a fixed size
effectively well
let me be more specific a discriminated
union can mean different things
depending on what language you're
talking about
the theoretical definition of a
discriminated union is just you have
something
like
uh
any kind of entity an object in an
object-oriented programming language or
struct in in your procedural or block of
memory or whatever or just a conceptual
thing
in theory whatever it is
and what you're going to do is say that
thing
can actually have any one of a number of
types
and the type is going to be indicated by
a field stored in that type so it's got
like a tag on it
right
and so the example uh in the diagram
system
that we just did
is a pretty straightforward example of
this
it basically says
here is a a thing right so you have this
diagram
entry and you can see that the diagram
entry could mean many different things
one of these entries can refer to
a begin and end a color a thickness a
text
entry a stick instruction to stick the
thing spheres lines boxes points or
overlays all of those things
can be represented by this one structure
and the difference is whether or not we
set the type to one of these things
so a discriminated union is basically a
way of saying we are going to represent
many things in one place hence the union
part
and we are going to discriminate like
the discrimination between which one
they are like the thing that tells you
the indicator an indicated union might
be a better term for it because
it's it's less about discriminating
between two things as it is a flag a
signal that tells you which one it is so
maybe you could call it an indicated
union the indicator is a field inside
the type itself that says it's this
thing
right
um yeah and tagged union
is a good name for it too right
now there's like a bunch of stuff like
if you go read like category theory
which i wouldn't recommend but you know
some people like that kind of thing
uh
it's a theoretical thing as well
so like
there's there's theoretical
discriminated union
and you know in the theory realm what
they try to try to what they would be
doing with it like we're solving a very
practical problem with it right like we
just want to have this uniform piece of
code that deals with all these different
entries and then only once in a while do
we want to actually
discriminate right between the unions
and we use the type field for that but a
lot of the time we wanted to handle them
as all being the same and that's what a
discriminated union is for in practical
purposes it's being able to deal with
everything as being the same and then
only once in a while do you actually
differentiate between them
in category theory they're going to be
more interested in things like proving
that a particular thing will will be
true or not true
you know based on if the type of the
thing is a discriminated union you know
like like what does that mean in terms
of being able to like analyze
the correctness of this piece of code or
this idea or algorithm or whatever
for someone just starting filming him
here would you recommend against using
direct sound
um i
i guess what i would say is if that's
the kind of thing that you're worried
about you're probably worried about the
wrong things it doesn't matter what
sound api you use you should look at
sound apis as just something you can
change out whenever you want
so like you should never care what sound
api you use use whatever sound api you
want make sure it's isolated in the code
like it is in handmade hero
uh and then if for some reason you have
a problem with it at some point you can
swap it out for something else but you
should never really work like
thinking about things like what graphics
api or sound api or whatever to use it
usually if you're thinking too much
about that that's probably just a bad
sign just do it doesn't matter
the code you write should not care about
that because i guarantee you it will
change all the time right and that's
kind of the problem it changes all the
time like the whatever stupid sound api
microsoft craps out tomorrow is the one
they're gonna tell you to use you can't
actually base your decisions on that
just assume that there'll be some new
stupid crap api
that you'll have to use on some platform
for some reason
so the important thing to think about
with audio is just make sure all of your
audio code doesn't care what api is
using
and that you minimize the amount of code
you actually write that relies on it and
that's what we did in handmade hero like
in handmade hero
before we ship this thing
if direct sound sucks too bad we just
rip out that i mean what is it like 300
lines of code 200 lines it goes almost
nothing we just rip that out replace it
with a different api and that's what you
want
right
um
so
so so that's the most important thing to
think about when you're thinking about
sound apis is don't think about sound
apis
assume they will change
and definitely don't care
does the order in which entities move
change result of your collision section
yes so this is not a simultaneous move
collision detector
um
there are
so there's different ways that you can
do collision detection
uh
and some of them are try to do
simultaneous move
and what that means is that you try to
move entities
at the same time to see if they would
overlap
during the movement right
uh we're not doing that and we don't
have any really need for that there if
you're doing like things with physics
that are
you may have issues with that right
um
but i think we'll probably try to avoid
needing that
uh do you think the cause of i am gooey
is applicable the same way in 3d user
interfaces uh yeah so just be clear
about imgui when i
invented that
that was the actual reason
believe it or not
the reason for i that i originally did i
am gooey was because i noticed i mean
this is the reason i was working on the
editor the viewer for granny back in the
old days was the character animation
viewer
and
i wanted a way to unify all of the ways
in which you interacted with stuff
in that thing so actually that is what
iamguy is actually most designed for is
the ability to not care
what kind of thing
you
are
interacting with right
you invented i'm yes i invented i am gui
i am the person who me
i i literally am the person who made the
term i am gui
nobody had ever said that until i said
it
in an email
um in like
2001 or something i don't even remember
what it was
mike acton recommends sometimes doing
deliberate practice for programming as
opposed to working on projects have you
done this yourself and do you recommend
it
um
i guess i would say i
i don't think that i would necessarily
agree with the phrasing
um
i think like in terms of like
conceptually i agree and would give the
same advice as mike acton gives but i
wouldn't necessarily give it the same
way that he gives it because i don't i
think it puts a little bit too much of a
delineation between what is practice and
what is not
um
to me the way i would phrase it is
you should often take time to try
something new
right
that that to me is the important part
so one way of doing that
is to
actually
uh
to
demand that
you are literally going to go off to a
fresh
code base with nothing in it
and
do some practice at something right
and i think that's what mike acting is
saying like like you know go literally
do fresh practice
the amount of times that i'd literally
do that are actually very few
the more important thing to me is that
you
you always try new things when you think
of them or you forced yourself to like
say how could i do this differently and
try it that's the important part of it
and
a structured practice session is a way
to force yourself to do that if you
don't normally do that in your own code
bases all the time but i normally do
that all the time
right
um
so i don't i think it depends on what
kind of programmer you are right
wait wikipedia credits me
for that
that's like the first time wikipedia has
ever been accurate about something
wow
all right um
i didn't know that that was the case
but uh hey thanks wikipedia for the
credit i appreciate it
were there i am doing interfaces before
you coined the term or was the idea and
term completely original um
so i had never seen anything that did
that at the time
uh
but i don't know i think it would be
very hard to determine if anyone had
ever done it my suspicion would be that
people had either intentionally or
accidentally done something similar
in the past and had never thought to
actually like
like i would have to imagine that at
some point somebody accidentally did it
because it's pretty easy to accidentally
do
right
um so
i'm
guessing that's
i i'm guessing that someone probably did
and we just don't know
uh no i wouldn't coin a different term i
think immediate mode gui is exactly the
right term
um
did you also coin jiu-jitsu
no
gjk is the initials of the people who
who invented it how could i have coined
gjk
it would be like
like mgjk if i had invented it right it
would have a miratory in there gjk is is
literally named after the p you don't
have to wonder
um it is literally named at
what
there we go um it's literally the
initials of the people who invented it
yes yes i definitely
did you coin javascript yeah
definitely yeah yeah
yeah i don't have a wikipedia page but i
mean you know
uh
i
think that probably makes sense because
in order to have a wikipedia page you
have to have
um
public materials that can be
referenced like that are historically
about you probably like like if you want
to have a wikipedia page you have to
give like interviews and stuff right
um
so because they have to be able to cite
things like like wikipedia can't just be
like let me go like to this guy's blog
and like copy the crap in right
like they have to be like third-party
sources where it's like oh with this
interview with casey or whatever he said
blah
so i think you need to prob you have to
be more of a public persona than i am
like you have to go out and like create
news about yourself if you want a
wikipedia page and i so you i don't
think it's wikipedia's responsibility to
uh change their rules
you know what i mean
you know someone may have made a
wikipedia page for me at some point but
it would get removed because it'd be
like there's no ref like there's no
references here right
um
and so i i think like that's really
more important
right
uh so you do you want to do like
interviews with journalists
whatever that means these days
um
and and you know put more like
third-party write-ups about you is what
you're looking for there because i would
imagine that you could do wikipedia
searches for people who are
like extremely important
let me just see here
i
and like it's probably pretty tough
right so like
you know
i mean i guess this managed to have a
wikipedia page but like
it's pretty brief right and it's got
some citations to actual like news
articles
right
um
so you know
i don't i don't know
i don't know how many people actually
have these pages
so
in in terms of so i don't know all right
that one's kind of like maybe
questionable right not much
citation there
so i don't know
um
i have no idea
maybe there should be a wikipedia page
but my point is just that like in
general it's pretty hard to make a
wikipedia page for somebody
who doesn't do a lot of interviews with
stuff
right um because wikipedia is an
encyclopedia it's not like a news source
so it can't just like
take your live streams or your youtube
videos or your whatever and and say like
well here's what it says on those
because like one of the wikipedia things
they try to do is not have
self-described stuff on the page so if
the thing is coming just from you
they tend not to use those like that's
that's considered like poor referencing
for wikipedia for better for worse i
mean you could argue that nowadays that
doesn't make any sense because most
most of the things produced nowadays
for informational purposes are produced
by the person that's a major change in
how information gets produced thanks to
the internet and that's a good one so
you could argue that wikipedia's
methodology is actually bad because
why would we want third-party sources
for something when we literally have
like a complete record
right um
of what happened from the actual people
who were actually posting and you can
literally see it all and you can just
say well here's what they said because
they said it right there right
um
so one could argue that wikipedia is
kind of at this point anachronistic and
maybe wikipedia is probably just not
that relevant anymore that could be
um
but
that's the way it is so when you're
wondering why there isn't a wikipedia
page about something
oftentimes that can be a very valid
reason they're just following their own
rules which you know they made and
you know that's what that's what the
page is
microsoft is setting fairly strict
hardware requirements for windows 11.
basically chips older than two years
will not work do you think that is a
good thing or a bad thing seems like it
will lead to a lot of waste of perfectly
good hardware
um
i don't know
so let me say a couple things about that
i don't have a strong opinion about it
i guess what i would say is i would have
to see what the requirements are which i
haven't looked at
and
what they actually are designed to do
right
so
hardware requirements of the form we
need a machine to be at least this
powerful because otherwise i can't run
windows 11 or garbage because windows 11
is garbage as was windows 10 as was
windows 8 as was probably windows 7 and
definitely windows vista
so obviously all of every single version
of windows including the latest one in
terms of actually hardware power wise
it's all garbage you could run the thing
on a freaking you know pentium
right
if you actually
wrote it well
so that's true
but
the windows kernel team has to make a
kernel right
and there are a lot of changes
structural changes to processors that
happen over that time period
right
and so
if the requirements are there because
the windows kernel team was like look
if we want to be able to do like high
performance stuff here that doesn't have
a bunch of weird like side cases for
preventing spectre and meltdown problems
and
doesn't have a lot of weird side cases
for like how do we deal with the fact
that this thing only had one thread so
it couldn't do multiple blah or whatever
all that stuff is right
if the requirements come
more from the windows kernel team about
features that are on a chip
that i would be more
okay with
right um
a trusted platform module requirements
are are ridiculous
it any any trusted platform module is
just another way of saying i would like
this machine to be hacked trusted
platform modules are should never have
happened
ever they're they were are a absolutely
ridiculously stupid idea i said that at
the time
trusted platform modules are absolutely
ridiculous
i don't even think trusted platform
modules should should exist
the only use case i can ever see
for trusted platform modules
is for unscrupulous large corporations
which is exactly what microsoft is
using them to prevent you from doing
things with the computer that they don't
want you to do i
not think of a single other use for a
trusted platform module
i like i literally have no idea what any
other thing that a trusted platform
module would do i have no i i can't
think of a single other use case you
certainly can't use it to store
important data because people already
know how to hack trusted platform
modules
right and more importantly
the trusted platform module is the last
place you would ever store important
information because any hacker
immediately knows to target the trusted
platform module right
like or like a state actor right when
the nsa or whoever else you know china
or yeah blah blah blah whenever they're
manufacturing this stuff
of course they're going to put in
something that lets you hack the trusted
platform module it's like it's obvious
right
so any important target can't trust
their trusted platform module it would
be a stupid idea to trust it it's
basically a big red bullseye that says
hey compromise this unit
it's ridiculous of course no one would
ever trust a trusted platform module
they had any idea what they're doing
right
the only trusted platform module you
could trust is one you literally made
yourself
have i ever used a physics engine like
havoc physics or bullets no i haven't
same opinion for trusted modern yeah my
my opinion on trust modules is that they
don't actually provide any i don't know
what they supposedly provide
right
i i literally don't know
because
what
makes you think that you can trust the
trusted platform module i i don't know
what there's nothing
there's nothing inherently trustworthy
about a trusted platform module it's
just another piece of hardware that
someone gave you that they claim you can
store something on but why would you
believe them right
they can have bugs in it that allow it
to be bypassed they can have intentional
back doors that they placed there so
that they can or that someone else
placed there so they can get information
out of it
it doesn't make any sense all you're
doing when you use a trusted platform
module is guaranteeing that the hacker
knows where to get the stuff that you
don't want them to get that's the only
thing that a trusted platform module
does
in terms of security that i can think
about
right
all right i think it's about time to
wrap it up
hey do we have any here's a question
sometimes we got people i don't know
probably not what time is it
so if i go to google and say
no all right so we probably don't
i was wondering if we had any iranians
watching
sometimes we get people watching from
from
places
around that region i don't know that
i've ever actually had someone oh you
know what i think i might have had
someone write in who
who was from iran
to switch working around well
i mean a lot of people use stuff to
bypass
like you know
it probably i don't know if twitch works
in china either but people
will buy will do bypassing right like
um
so i don't know
but i was gonna say like tonight i was
gonna go
i was gonna go get
some
uh
[Music]
some grilled meats at a place that does
like really good
uh persian style right
uh grilled meats and i was wondering if
anyone
who might be like more knowledgeable
about like
uh
yes
navid hg
exactly
exactly that is exactly what i'm talking
about
i wonder if anyone had any opinions it's
one of my favorite dishes
like i don't know
um i guess
like
uh
i guess technically like my ancestry
would come from the mediterranean
because they're all italian
and i believe they were sort of south
more southern italian
um
and i do tend to like mediterranean
dishes
like everything from the mediterranean
anywhere around i tend to like
um
[Music]
and i pretty much like all
mediterranean grilled meats
uh
and in there they're somewhat
difficult to get
right
um in
in this area in this area
uh
but there's
two or three places that actually do it
right
um
and so you know like
i was just wondering you know i've
started to try and cook them like i do
yogurt marinated chicken myself now
um and i'm sort of getting i bought i
bought i bought a thing of of saffron
from the costco costco actually has like
really high quality saffron that's not
too expensive saffron is fantastic
expensive if you buy in the grocery
store it's way too expensive way too
expensive
um
but
you know you you can
costco like all like everything costco
does
they manage to get you high quality
stuff for without having to mortgage
your house uh to get it so
i i definitely appreciate the costco for
hooking us up with that
um so like i've been i've been working
on that stuff
uh
yeah boop boop is the handle he had on
on discord it's it's yeah it's ash khan
kyani is his actual name
but
but yeah so so uh i was gonna go and get
some ends
i just curious if people had like pro
tips on seasoning and stuff i'd like to
be able to make it more um
i'm getting better at the chicken
my main problem
with
uh
doing the
with doing the grilled chicken though
i think i've got the yogurt marinade
down
um i think i've got the spicing pretty
good
right like like i've got like the i do
like the lemon saffron butter basting
and all that stuff and it comes out
really great
the main problem i have with doing the
chicken and what's the name of the
chicken it's like
juju or
it's got a name the the the grilled
skewer chicken
with butter based you know what i'm
talking about juja yeah juju
so the the juji kebab the main problem
that i have with it is i cannot figure
out how to get the doneness correct
like
the when you put it on a skewer you
can't really it's really hard to like
temperature probe
so you kind of have to go by like some
kind of like intuition or something
um
i
and and that part is
is tough i don't know how you do it
virtue one so when you say touch like
can you can you be more specific is that
really true do you know how to make
these
it's a show i would like to know
how to know the doneness correctly
if you want to get good middle east
levant type of seasonings and other
produce in seattle try goodies
mediterranean market all right i will
write that down i've never heard of that
i'm gonna
make sure that's up here
store location
in lake city way okay
is that the way you're talking about in
lake city way
wow house made kebabs ready to cook
that's great
cool
yeah all right so i hadn't thought of
touch maybe i'll try that um one thing
that i messed up last time that i
realized after the fact was that i so
you marinate it you put it in like you
like when you marinate the chicken and
yogurt you put it in like a bag
right or something you have to put in
something
and when i was letting it come up to
room temperature i i actually had to
come to room temperature and then i put
it on the skewers and i realized that
was really stupid because i think like
some of the chicken that was on the
outside thawed more completely than some
of the chicken that was on the inside so
then when i
uh flame you know when i when i uh grill
when i try
uh
grilled them
some of the chicken i think didn't cook
and others did so that was a big problem
and so i can fix that one but i still
even after i fix that which i think you
just you have to skewer them right from
frozen and not from frozen right from
refrigerator or you have to skewer them
probably and then let them sit skewered
so they actually do uh it
correctly um
yeah i rotate the skewers manually i do
it just like i s so i saw like youtube
videos of actual
like
at least what appeared to be fairly
hardcore
uh persian meat folks doing their own
grill
over the coals
uh and i try to do it like they do so i
i hand rotate the skewers continuously
and i swap them
their positions too to make sure that in
case one part of the girl's a little
heavier whatever right so i do it and
i've managed to get that pretty good but
i think i've got some other problems
however i think it fixed most problems
the only one i wasn't sure is like how
do you know when the chicken is done by
touch does sound like a pretty good idea
um you know push on it a little bit see
what the springiness so that's not a bad
idea i wonder if that would work
um
that's that's a good idea
i'm sorry to bring up all this good food
and and i realize this isn't even a
cooking channel
yeah i'm i'm i'm
i'm hungry too so sorry about that
an infrared thermometer might not be a
bad idea sir pinecone
i i kind of agree with that
um
that's interesting hmm
yeah you're right i guess i don't know
that they always take the entire skewer
off at once they might just take off
some of it
yeah but again even if you did that so
if you know
that you're going to take
it off the skewer separately you that
makes it even more important to have a
way of testing if it's done because then
now you're saying i need to you know you
need to be able to test it and say okay
this part's done let's take it off the
skewer right
um
so that again is like a problem because
like i don't really know how to do that
test
so i i guess i need to do is learn the
touch
right like learn what that touch is
and then i could do it that that i never
thought about that
um
but yeah like like by touch or yeah in
maybe learn what the infrared outside
temperature would be when the inside's
done just by testing and then remember
that and then just go by that that that
seems reasonable too i like that yeah
yeah
yeah all right that's a good suggestion
thanks folks
all right i'm gonna go ahead and wrap it
up here thank you everyone for joining
me for an episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always uh if you would like to follow
the series at home you can always prior
to the game on handmade hero.org comes
the source code so you can play around
with it
um i will be back here next weekend i'm
gonna try and update the schedule sorry
i've been forgetting to update schedule
lately so it's just been kind of not up
there so i realize it's harder but uh i
will try to schedule so that it should
put the reminders up again uh for those
who need them
until next week have fun programming
everyone and i'll see you on the
internet take it easy everybody