everyone and welcome to handmade hero
today we are going to uh just i wanted
to
we began to decide last weekend
that i didn't want to push the lighting
any further i think we can do more uh
and someday might do more but i think
it's looking quite nice now
and i think we can finish you know we
could basically finish the game with
this level of lighting quality um
because it looks nice and it shows us a
reasonable version of what we could
expect uh from any like final lighting
system i mean it looks really nice in my
opinion uh and you could balance the
game art this way
uh and then if you improve a few things
like there are some things you could
improve like the main thing is the
squariness here uh if we did improve
some of that someday i don't think
that's going to be a material issue for
us meaning i don't think we have to
really worry uh about that suddenly
radically changing the look of the game
in some way that causes us to have to go
back and redo a bunch of work
or anything like that
so my feeling is we could sort of leave
it here uh and not really go any further
uh with you know not really
go any further down the rabbit hole of
improving the lighting because it's now
quite nice i had originally said oh
maybe we'll just regress and not use the
advanced lighting but then when we
actually looked at just switching it to
2d it it really does work quite nicely
and looks great so i have no
i really have no concerns about that and
i'm i'm totally happy uh with it i
and you know i think there's some minor
improvements we could make in the future
to it but that's fine so i think it's
time to concentrate on other stuff which
is just like finishing up some world gen
stuff cleaning up that code and now like
we've decided we're not really going to
do 3d
uh so what that means is we'll be doing
2d tiles of
everything and so when you go down you
really be doing like a binding of isaac
go down where you like it teleports you
down right
uh and so in order to do that we're
going to want to
change the world generator to not really
use a z
um and so that's the one thing that i
want to do uh coming up next
before doing that because i know that i
want to do so i would like to be able to
have the
these tiles light up
and right now i don't actually think
that i have a way to say that some one
of these is self-illuminating
right
um
you know what i'm saying to you
so i don't actually know
um
if we have a way to do that and i would
like to do that right so that's the main
thing that i want to do
is make sure that i can do that because
i know that i need to use that and so
what we're gonna do is we're just gonna
go into the system and figure out what
has to happen uh it's really an input
side issue i don't think the lighting
system cares particularly much but when
the lighting system is basically parsing
what gets sent down to it uh that is
really the thing that uh that i wanted
to fix right
uh and so what i'd like to do is make
sure that that can be sent down
and uh and then after that we'll move on
and i don't know if we'll we probably
won't finish uh we probably won't we
might finish the lighting thing today
but we don't think we'll quite probably
have enough time to start the world gen
stuff but that's our agenda
so
so there you go
um also at some point we need to turn
off lighting like
this is going through the uh um this is
going through the uh the lighting system
which is not
good right um like our cut scene is
going to look like like absolute garbage
uh because it's going through the the
whole thing with lighting and filmic
response curves and stuff but these were
already balanced so that is you know we
probably need a way to turn that off at
some point it's not a high priority
right now but like yeah that's not um
that is not looking good right um
not not great not great guys
so anyway uh
if we look at what happens in the
lighting system when we
need to send down the
information for how lights are working
uh we currently have in the renderer you
know the primitives we have i think are
just not
really going to encode this
i think um and i again i like i'm not
really sure but when we actually send
down because it's been a long time right
like you know we only work on things
very sporadically on handmade heroes so
it's like you know it's not really in my
head most of the time
uh so when we actually send stuff down
you know we've got this sort of we
basically have like this this render you
know
uh
it's not really command buffer per se
it's sort of a command buffer light
um and we just kind of send down you
know what we're going to be doing
i i guess i actually split that off now
that i think about it um
did i not
yeah
so in here you can see i actually split
it off from the platform api because
it's its own thing now but you can see
on here that we have like
this sort of render group
that we use to submit things and it
basically fills out one of these render
entry textured quad things right
and the render entry texture quad thing
is really what draws everything it's a
quad count and it has vertices and
indices and it says what the textures
are
um that are going to be used you know
what i'm saying
uh and and that's really how the entire
thing works
the
vertex array offset right the vertices
that are being sent down
they are the things that encode like the
variance like the color variability
right uh and so in here
the first thing i don't really know is
what we did so
somewhere we actually do have something
that allows us to do
stuff that's lit right
and like stuff that that
doesn't respond to lighting that's like
um
doesn't respond to the light responded
is kind of the wrong word
we must be sending down something that
allows you to sort of self-illuminate
because that's presumably how the cut
scenes are working right
meaning when you go to the handmade
cutscene thing
um and this is sending down
whatever kind of quads you know it's
sending down
um i believe that what's happening here
like when we do push bitmap
is like we're encoding something that
says you don't need to light this thing
or or it shouldn't just be lit normally
and so that's the thing we have to go
see what we did there
um i'm guessing it has something to do
well the the healthy parameter was we
actually used so i don't know it must be
it must just be something we
do
for the entire set like if you don't
turn lighting on
or something like that right so let's go
take a look and see if we can reverse
engineer what the heck we did there uh
because i'm assuming we just it it turns
off for the it turns off for the entire
thing or something like that
uh so let's take a look so when we're
actually rendering
these command buffers that we send
through
uh pretty much everything goes through
this as far as i know
uh we only you know we basically just
have one big batch uh and that's it
we've got some of the things here like
you know we've got these depth peels and
stuff that we do but everything that we
actually render just goes through this
one path it's this path right here
where it just says like all right uh
send down all these vertices and go to
town you know what i'm saying
um
this one we use for cut scene stuff
this one we use for like texture rays
you know what i'm saying
as i blow my nose
um so
what we need to do now
is figure out
what we want to
what we want to use here for an
indication that something should be
self-illuminating
and it looks like
it looks like the lighting is always
sent down
here
that's the the actual updated lighting
and then in terms of whether it's turned
on or not
you know i i don't see anything here
that indicates that it gets turned on or
not though
so that's a little confusing
um
hmm
so yeah again i'm not really sure
i'm not really sure what's going on
there so let's take a look at the shader
what gets sent to the shader
so in the shader
i mean there's not much there right the
inputs
aha so there is one float 32 called
vertex emission
comes down through to frag emission
emission
so we are
actually sending this down or we claim
to be and maybe we added it to the
shader but didn't actually send it down
that's possible although the fact that
the cutscenes appear to be
self-illuminating would suggest that
maybe we do
so that's
that's a good question and i don't know
the answer to that question
uh anyway so if we look at where does
the fragmizion
uh where does fragmizion actually
get used
okay so what happens is we
we take the surface reflectance
and we pretend that if the frag emission
is sent down as you know basically it's
sent down as a linear interpolant
between whatever the lighting actually
is at this point and fulbright
so
i guess that
i guess that makes
sense i'm fine with that
uh yeah
i don't have a problem with that so the
problem though is that we do
we kind of have two things we're trying
to do here one is emission
one is emisian
uh
that is trying to be like
for the
what one is trying to be like the
cutscene emisian
and the other is if we just want like an
actual light
that is in the world
and the reason that i say that we kind
of have two different things
is an emissive source should come from
uh
the same pipeline as the rest of the
world rendering so it will go through
the filmic response curve right
but a cut scene
piece should not
and so the question is do we want to try
and
have like a
do we want to try and have this be more
of just a switch like hey there's two
different things you can do here
and and honestly i think that might be
the right
tax
so there's a couple of things that we
have to think about
um
one is are we ever going to want
textured self-illumination
normally the answer would always be yes
but in this case because we don't really
do complicated art in this game you know
it's kind of an art minimal sort of game
i don't know the way we're going to do
that because that would require having
some kind of an art processing pipeline
where we actually have a way of
producing information like that
like normal maps and self-illumination
all that garbage right
i so i don't know that the input is ever
going to be there for self-illumination
which would mean that it would be a
waste of time to do textured
self-illumination and if there
isn't going to be textured
self-illumination then it suggests that
really all we have is we're trying to
light something up
uniformly the whole thing whatever it is
lights up together right
um
and if that was the case you can see why
i'm considering this if that's the case
then you could just have frag emission
could just tell us one of two things it
could say
either we want to
do emission through the acs film curve
or
it could say we want to do emission
uh
that's just like cutscene it's just
direct
ah
so i don't know which one of those we
wanna do
i don't know
so where do we specify this let's let's
talk about that let's work backwards and
say what do we actually want to do here
so someone's supposedly submitting
fragmizion right
um someone is is
pushing down fragmizion
uh and we presumably want to go see what
the heck fragmizion is even encoded as
or how it's encoded it's coming in
as in f32
uh
so the quads
do we have like here it is textured
vertex
um so we have a u8 for a mission
uh and then we hey we have a reserved
element that's getting transferred
anyway
so i guess that's another thing we could
do is just send down a different thing
which is like kurt you know what output
curve you wanted
um
all right
uh
do we want that
i mean maybe we just do that
uh
you know i mean we're already we've
already got that in there so maybe we
just have another one so we have
fragmizion
um and then we also have
uh
besides emission we also have uh frag
mapping or something right or or frag uh
frag
frag tone
i like the phrase frag tone because it
sounds cool um
right so we could say that we just have
this thing called frag tone
and it comes
it comes in
to the vertex shader as another input
and it just gets passed through right
um
and that's it
presumably
if i still run if i run this thing now
presumably it would just work uh
because it's not doing anything right so
it shouldn't
shouldn't be a problem
uh and then in the cutscenes stuff like
yeah i mean part of the problem is we
don't know how that gets sent down it's
we got issues uh so we're gonna have to
go look at how we're specifying the
emission value to begin with because we
if we don't actually know how the
emission is being specified then we you
know but i'm assuming it's just
something that set in the render group
and gets slapped onto each vertex as a
thing
so
let's take a look at this
uh so when we come in here and we're
going to do the processing of uh the
actual you know
the whole like
we should probably move shaders to
separate text files because this
whole indentation thing is nightmare.com
my new web startup
um very promising series a
by the way
um
very proud i am starving right now by
the way can i just tell you that
um
i uh
i'm hungry and i want lunch but i want
to do this first
i
had
a shot of espresso
and a
nature valley registered trademark
oat
biscuit for breakfast
and now i'm hungry again
and
i would like to eat
right
um
that reminds me of another time that i
will not describe because it would go
into a very long rant
and that rant
is going to wait for another day
it's going to wait for another day when
i
really unload
um
it's probably going to be like a
produced rant
it's one of those things where one of
the things see here's the thing and this
is true you can just you can count on
this
um
like i never
forget
like like like on the grudge side of
things it's actually very hard
to piss me off
but once i have been pissed off
it will never
end
right that's that's kind of the way it
goes um
like like if i'm just complaining about
something that's fine and i'll move on
right but if i actually feel like i got
pissed off about something for real
i never forget so there's things that
like you know 15 years ago or something
i will remember
and it's like
it's not over
you may think it's over
because i'm just not
dealing with that thing right now it's
been like filed
but if you think it's over
you're really mistaken about that
right
like
there's only a few of these there's only
going to be like five of these in
history right
because it's actually really hard i
think one of the one of the nice things
about people who complain about stuff or
think everything sucks is it's actually
kind of hard to piss them off right
because they're already not in a state
where they think everything's going well
right so you know you they're just ah
yeah this is another crap thing yeah
this all sucks
and that's it right you move on it's
fine uh
but if someone actually pushes me to the
point where i'm
really pissed off in the real way
never it never gets forgotten so it's
still there
right
and it's just like yep
like someday when i'm 72 and you thought
it was over
oh my friend it is not over
so anyway
um
that that uh said about about uh
breakfast biscuits especially i was
thinking about power bar
uh but yeah uh i need to
eat something because we have probably
low blood sugar at this point
um and uh
yeah it's uh chat it is like opposite
buddhist
right it's i'm the anti-buddhist it's
because i'm italian
right i mean i mean
you know i i don't i don't want to be
racist about it i mean i don't want to
be racist against myself right i guess
which is what i'd be doing
but you know i mean do you really think
we have a history
of
of letting things go you know is that
you know if you looked at the history of
of like sicily or something
would you go like now there's a group of
people who really know how to just like
let the past be the past
yeah
you think so
no
doesn't really happen
oh no ryan i love the four coder lair
i'm i'm very happy you did that it
totally saved my bacon uh because
i i don't want to use
my stuff the the
molly
uh proprietary stuff i don't do on
stream
and it would have been really tough if
you hadn't have uh
uh
made the four chord a flurry layer it
was it was a lifesaver
you could piss me off many times right
and and and like
you're banked already right like you
know
what am i going to do you totally saved
my bacon already you know what i'm
saying
um
same with alan same with george i mean
you you guys all totally saved my bacon
i mean i i can't wha
i can't get pissed off right there's
nothing i could get pissed off about
cause it's like well all right you know
they already did you a solid how are you
gonna get pissed off at them
all right anyway uh
so
this is the situation that we have here
where we've got uh a lerp
where we're using like the fog you know
we've got a fog coefficient we've got
the emission coefficient
and what we're basically doing here
right is we're using these lerps to
basically create knobs you know like
producer knobs right
where you turn
up the
x whatever x is if you're trying to get
that effect for these pixels
or you turn it down right so you want
more fog you turn that up you want more
emission you turn that up sorry emission
you turn that up um and so i just don't
know what exactly uh
these all should be
but i do
think this is a reasonable guess is like
okay turn up the tone mapping turn up
the emission turn up the fog
that'll give us the way that we can like
tune for cutscene
light source right you know what i'm
saying
um
so anyway
so in here uh you can see that this is
the part where we're actually doing the
tone mapping right uh the fog is
we we
had that in there it wasn't really you
know fog per se it was kind of so we
could fade out like lower levels you
know
um and so right now it's a little bit
hard to say where that should be uh
you know in terms of these other
parameters you know does it happen
before or after a mission does it you
know where is this actually going
uh and that's kind of a little bit tough
to determine
so i'm not really sure what we want to
do here
exactly
um
that's a little bit tough
so what i might say is all right we've
got the emission coefficient coming down
that's turning this it's saying how much
you want to crank all the way to full
bright right which is one one one
um and
we then multiply the reflectance color
that comes in by that always so if it's
an emitter we're basically saying oh and
by the way the emitter also will always
take the color that you give it so if
you wanted to have a yellow emission
right
um
that's fine too
but uh
once we get to here
you know maybe we would say
maybe we would say fog is still always
applied because it would seem
to reason that you would do that right
also i don't know why we like we
probably had this in here when that was
still a four it it doesn't have to do
that anymore
um
i also don't know why fog would be in
rgba probably because it's an input but
it doesn't matter
uh anyway
so when we come through here this will
compute i think correctly most of the
time
i'm
[Music]
this would compute no matter what we set
the other knob to this would compute the
base value that we actually want so
really all we're trying to do here is
this part
is the part that we need to fix
um because this part is not
we don't want that to happen
right
so in here we've got this like film map
curve thing and and so i'm going to say
let's
let's call this like mapped
or mapped color
um so what i'm thinking is we just say
we compute this as a completely separate
value now
so it doesn't affect the actual like
unmapped
like unfilm mapped colored that you know
this one here
we compute it into a completely separate
variable
and then when we want to produce our
final surface reflection um and and
maybe we could actually call this like
something different like
um
uh final color or something like that
so we produce the surface reflect we
produce the mapped color and then we say
well the final color is going to be yet
another lerp
between the surface reflection
color which is the pure color that
hasn't gone through the curves or the
boost the amp light application
um we're going to use that frag tone
mapping to just say how much tone
mapping do you want now again this seems
like kind of unnecessary because it's
really mostly just gonna be a zero or
one but because everything else was done
on a dial
i mean
sure
right i don't know
so anyway uh i'm just saying look we'll
we'll just lurp up to the map color
right
now i believe that the default value for
this thing will always be zero
uh because we haven't set it to anything
so i'm imagining that if we actually run
this we will get yeah like we'll just
get the untoned mapped version of this
thing
is what we'd end up with right
uh
and if we hit escape because again it's
set to zero which means don't go through
the curve our cutscene is now okay
right like
at the edge of the wood
there was an orphanage that catered to a
group of limbless children
they were very sad
because without any limbs they could not
play outside or adventure into the
forest
for there were many demons there and
without arms to defend themselves
there was no way they would survive
uh this little grumpy boy that we see
through the window here is one of the
orphans uh he's going to be the hero
later but we don't know that
one of them
was constantly playing with toys
and imagining what it would be like if
he could go into the forest and fight
the demons there in particular little
pink godzilla for some reason and go
into it just what he thought of
every year at christmas time santa claus
who is a tremendous dick
came and gave them a hat because he had
no better idea of what to give people
who had no arms and legs
the kids didn't like it but santa didn't
care because he's callous and
imperceptive
but one year
[Music]
in the midst of a brutal storm
who should arrive but krampus
with his giant tongue meant for licking
naughty children and dismembering them
to put in his sack
the children were scared of course
because they knew that the arrival of
krampus could only mean one thing
and that thing was that they would soon
be dismembered for being naughty which
of course they were
however
on this particular day
the little child who always dreamed of
adventuring into the forest looked up at
krampus and said no
i will stand between you and these poor
children you will not terrorize them and
you will not dismember them
for they have no arms and legs anyway
what could you possibly gain from this
and krampus was so moved by the small
child's gesture
that out of his sack
he took a tiny glove
sparkling with magic
capable of moving on its own
and he presented it to the child who
looked at the hand in
wonder now it only took the child a
brief moment to decide exactly what he
would do
for with this hand he could now finally
go adventuring in the forest for all he
needed
was just a little bit of help
told a sword or perhaps just a box
and of course he already had a complete
selection of hats given to him by santa
claus across the many years
so all that remained was for him to
select one the correct hat for his
journey put it on his head and prepare
for the adventure of a lifetime
all right um
so anyway you know uh there you go
cutscenes working
i
oh yeah no this game
is gonna have so many hats in it it's
gonna be like the only thing that you
can buy with real money in the real
money auction house is going to be hats
right it's going to be portal 2
times 2 plus 2
minus 1.
so
why thank you for the sub gifting that
was very nice of you
was that because of of my
my amazing narration is that what your
way of saying that you do think that my
career as a voice actor is just waiting
to take off
is is that is that what that
benevolence gesture was meant to say
i can only really interpret it that way
i mean i mean how else could i interpret
it
um
right after that dramatic
moving reading
um well i wasn't really reading anything
but you know
if i had been it would have been
dramatic certainly i think we all know
um
so
you know
okay um so anyway uh i think we're
honestly i think that was basically it
like you know that was what we wanted to
accomplish on the stream besides the
reading
um
yeah my posh british accent is it may
not be terrible but the problem is it
doesn't it's probably not a british
accent right it's like probably like a
weird combination of british accents
i need a voice what i need is one of
those like accent coaches who's like
okay like which
you know which part of
of england are we talking about here or
which part of great britain are we
talking about like what what accent are
we actually doing you gotta like
you gotta pick one right you know
because i don't really know
the actual accents
that's the problem
um so gotta gotta get a gotta get a
voice coach gotta get a an accent coach
gotta call hollywood
um
all right uh
so
what we need to do now is just utilize
this variable so that we can turn up the
tone mapping or off the tone mapping and
all that sort of stuff at the
appropriate times
now i think that the lighting stuff is
already ha it has the ability to turn it
on and off um
and
you know that's how we're bracketing
those things so i assume that it's just
part of the render group at the moment
um and it's just kind of getting like
stuffed into those uh
oops i'm in the wrong i'm in the wrong
file
you're not gonna fix anything in the
wrong file son
wrong file
uh so
i'm pretty sure there's like a lighting
like
switch i
you know yeah
so you can see like we've kind of got a
kill switch for lighting here
um and so when lighting is enabled we
need to turn up the tone mapping uh
curve right you can see
we got push occluder
uh we got pushing vertices all this
stuff right so here's our push quad
and inside push quad you can see that if
the lighting is not enabled we set the
emission to one automatically
so i think what we need to also do here
is set the tone mapping to the opposite
of that right
so vert emission goes in here and we
need to specify as well as that we need
to specify
uh tone right uh
uh
did we we probably didn't actually set
that did we um
tone
maybe store it here
that's a that's a great comment
maybe store it
here
so i wrote a comment i thought
as i've said comments are usually pretty
useless because they don't you won't say
what you actually need to say and
they'll get out of sync with the code
and stuff so you know i try to do
comments pretty specifically right
what the heck did i think i was right
maybe store it here how is that helpful
why did i stop to type that comment if
you don't know what it is
how are you going to know if you should
maybe store it there what is that how is
that helping
how is that helping
maybe store it here
thanks for matt for that theorem
i'll get right on it
no all right
oh jeez
so yeah
maybe sorry yeah maybe we will
in fact we did store something there and
left the comment
so that's good
right
um
oh so hey ryan you know people do that
with handmade hero if you go on to the
handmade hero github right now
it's got line attribution so it will
tell you which episode i made the
comment in on the handmade hero github
actually
it actually has that feature uh andrew
jdr made it
uh
andrew johnson do you know who he is
he does the he does that like asset
management system that web-based
like fast asset management thing for for
movie people
you know i'm talking about
i don't know if you know who he is
yeah yeah him
he he made a like script that just like
automatically whenever the github gets
checked in it it produces like a new
version of the source code that has each
line it says
when it was made
um it's really cool so totally it would
be great if that was just built into the
system um because you know
the source code control system knows
that right it knows when you you did it
and of course since with this with each
check-in i include a day number so it
knows you know that that's all it really
needs right
so
uh anyway uh so if we have our vert
emission here
uh then it should be pretty easy to just
produce a vert tone value
and again this is being pretty sloppy um
because really you know if we were fancy
gpu people um we would we would split
these into streams that had different
run rates right
so
because we know that we only need to
specify
a few things for the quad like the quad
only needs a couple of these
um
we never change for example the texture
index the emission or the tone per
vertex so those could have gone
in a different stream
and in that different stream
we would then set it to only advance
every four
vertices right
um or something like that
you know what i'm saying
um and
and so we're we're being
sort of flippant here and the reason for
that is we're just not sending down very
much geometry
so because we're not sending down very
much geometry we can get away with being
sloppy here all of our gpu load goes on
the fill rate side of things the
geometry is like totally irrelevant so
we can be pretty much as sloppy as we
want here because we are never going to
stress the vertex shader
if we were thinking we would be in a
situation where we would be putting
pressure on the vertex shader you would
not do this right
so it's just worth noting like
you know these don't actually need to be
sent down per vertex because they don't
change per vertex ever like we never
actually use that feature
so the vertone um is really at this
point i don't think we need to support
gradual anything
with it so i'm pretty sure we can just
say that you know the vert tone mapping
is just going to be 255 and then if you
if you're turning off lighting then it's
not
i think that's basically all there is to
it right
all right
uh well i would have thought that would
have worked did i pick it did i
do it the wrong way or is our shader
busted
oh
um
we we didn't uh bind it we didn't we
didn't actually bind that oopsie oopsie
poopsies
uh
yeah like we we don't actually
we are sending it down sort of but not
actually telling the card we're it's
right in the stuff that the card will
pull down but we never told uh the card
about it uh so
uh whoops
um slight mistake
uh huge tiny mistake
okay so that emission that vert emission
uh that we claim is coming in here uh
yeah you can see it right
uh so what we need here is we need a
tone
a tone poem
uh and we need to enable that
that tone poem
like so
and we probably have a few places where
that's going to want to get right in
beginning end this is all just garbage
like this is why i hate gp but all this
is stupid you should never have to do
any of this stuff this is just
gpu programming is terrible and it
always sucks
and
it's just this nonsense if you
spend a lot of time doing this you can
make these things be more system
oriented meaning you can go in here and
make your own like little system for
like okay i you know bound arrays or i
have a meta program that scans it and
produces the correct
it's all so dumb
it's all so dumb right um and the other
thing you can do is if you're targeting
higher levels of of glsl than i think we
are
a smarter thing to do here is i think
you can finally now say that just we're
gonna define just like a struct in the
shader so that you don't have to do this
stupid stuff so i don't think you have
to it's not as bad as this is making it
seem um is i guess what i would say
so you know you can uh you can nowadays
be a little bit less hand-holdy i think
you know what as i say that i think i
checked recently and you still couldn't
for vertex arrays
am i wrong about that
hey gpu people out there do they still
not have it so you can just say the
vertex
vertices are
this struct
because i i feel like you know what i
did check that recently and it still
wasn't something that you could do
uh
in standard
in standard uh gpu
standard apis
botander i don't think that's true i
mean it's true on the gpu but it's not
true in the api
do you know what i'm saying like you're
you're absolutely right that in in like
like an nvidia gpu i'm pretty sure that
it's just complete arbitrary fetch for
the most part right
um
but i think like you know like if you
boot up if you fire up direct3d11 most
modern version
um or
opengl most modern version
you can't do that
i think you still have to specify each
array manually
i don't know if d312 might have it
somebody check that because i remember
being surprised i was like we're still
doing this
and and i think the answer was yes we
often are still doing this and i was
like god all right
you can do 3d 12 structure
are you sure
are you sure you can do it for vertices
meaning a vertex shader can use
structured buffer
i i i'm just i'm only i'm slightly
doubtful i apologize for being a
doubting
thomas
let's say doubting nancy
um
but i'm not sure i quite believe you
because i feel like i looked at this and
you couldn't do it for that case you can
do other things structured you can send
down arbitrary structured buffers that
you fetch from in the vertex shader but
not for the actual vertex parameters by
default that come in
okay yeah so that's what i thought so
but can you actually still get the full
performance by using the vertex id to do
the indexing or does that create
like i assumed that you wouldn't want to
do that because it would create like
performance issues
for
you know
older cards or something i don't know
like i i was i assumed that you didn't
want to bypass the standard vertex
shading but maybe you can can you safely
do that i'd be very curious to know
all right
um
so that looks like that worked well
uh there's our our tone mapping is back
um
here's our
cutscene looks looks right again
so i guess the other thing
we might want to do
is verify that this works and it does oh
lovely so our debug view works again too
right because that had a problem with
the new lighting
so that with the tone mapping so that's
all good
great
fantastic
um
so that seems good
i am uh
i am a swanky sally
about that
and
i guess the only thing that remains is
to actually try making the
self-illuminating block now
and to make sure that we can actually
send it down
uh you know what i'm saying to you
um
i guess
so in the world gen
code
uh
[Music]
so i think that's all i really need to
do we'll just say that first so let's
just go ahead and ping pong over to the
world gen code and see if we can make
our dungeon area here
um
we know we've
have it all
any lemongrab fans in the audience
lemongrab
hey let me grab fans out there let me
grab
does anybody
out there
in the audience know who lemongrab is
there's there's my people
this code base is in unacceptable
condition
unacceptable
uh
the interesting thing about the
autofocus on the sony cameras is that
they
it's almost like too good
it has facial recognition in it
that focuses on faces by default which i
guess you could turn off and maybe i
should
but so as a result it's always going to
focus on your face so if you try to hold
something up
you're like look at this thing in front
of the camera it's like no no i'm gonna
look right past that at the face that i
see so you have to like actually like
obscure your face first
uh i think
i could be wrong about that but i think
that's sort of what happens on there
so you know
anyway
um
in keeping with our
so
the question is
what do we want to do
in the world generator for
like
how rooms get connected
uh if we're gonna start saying like oh
yeah like
you know
up and down is not in here anymore do we
want to still have up and down in here
and just it like puts it puts it
somewhere else and then like
connects it with a teleporter or do we
want to just not talk about up and down
at all you know what i'm saying
um
and i don't know i mean for now i guess
we just
just do that
um so i don't really know uh what this
is gonna do but uh i wanted to get the
dungeon in here because if we wanna like
i think we already have the concept of
these little tiles that i wanted right
oh that's
oh
well would you look at that
little
saucy salamandor
look at that
interesting so what happened there is
when we do when we were putting in the
vertices for our grebel
uh
we didn't we never put like those are
obviously getting they're the cover you
know the sort of like ground cover
um
those are obviously not pushing a value
what how do those actually
get
output i don't even know what we did
here i mean you can see us doing a thing
with p values here
uh
but i don't know
i don't know what that supposedly do it
does
so it's using vertex out
which oh we just specifically said
doesn't have tone mapping
um so i don't know what we want here
like we could auto stuff
this value um
and then this would be fixed i don't
know if we want control over that
probably not because any time we're like
putting those down um
it fixed the it did not fix the blocky
lighting bug you just couldn't see it
because nothing was reflecting the light
um
right
uh but anyway uh okay so so i think
we'll just stuff that value for now
because if we i don't know that we're
ever going to need that function
in that way
um
all right so in the dungeon areas here
uh
yeah like i think we already had this
stuff set up oh these stupid guys
um yeah we gotta we gotta do some uh
some monster coding
it's got to the point
um
so the dungeon is looking good uh so
that all worked fine that connecting
worked fine i assume dungeon to dungeon
connection doesn't we can't actually
kill any of these guys so that's a
problem
um because they're going to keep
blocking our path but i assume then when
we get out here the dungeons are are now
going to actually still have a downward
connection right so we'd have to fix
that oh my god there's too many of these
stupid guys
stop no get
get out of here
all right yeah so like we still have
some downward dungeon connect downward
dungeon actually by the way sounds great
like someone needs to make a game
someone needs to make a game called
downward dungeon
can someone please make a game called
like the next time there's one of those
game jams where it's only you're only
gonna spend like 48 hours or whatever it
is that they do
can you just can someone please make a
game called downward dungeon
if someone if someone is willing to make
a game called downward dungeon
for a game jam i will voice i will do
some of that voice acting for free
i will send you some voice acting for
downward dungeon
like i will narrate the introductory
sequence to downward dungeon okay
like let it not be said that i do not
support the downward dungeon project
i mean they made it like there was a
game literally called like darkest
dungeon or something right and it was
super popular like it was it made a ton
of money
like hundreds of thousands of copies
million million copies something like
that right
and it was literally just called like
darkest dungeon i think
i think
and uh
so downward dungeon do not tell me
downward dungeon could not be a huge
game
i think downward dungeon could be big
right
so
downward dungeon
you know what i'm saying downward
dungeon people
okay
in order to restore
light to the darkness they knew they
would have to go downward
into
the downward dungeon
i mean at this point i would say i would
accept most
slightly off dungeon names
as a project
like
like i would i would be willing to do
some voice acting for like mildly like
if there was a game called like mildly
ominous dungeon
or somewhat like
or a game called slightly dungeon
or a game called
just the outskirts of hell
like this game is just
just barely
hell like we're just
outskirts of hell
but not ever actually going into hell
because that would be dangerous
yeah
um
i'm just saying i know there's people
out there who do these game jams and
stuff i'm just saying downward dungeon
okay
i agree that a game about traveling to
the dungeon and then deciding not to go
in because it just looks a little bit
too dangerous is a totally would be
great
like
um
i i mean basically like the monty python
thing of like brave sir robin ran away
right
um
the game i don't know how you make that
a game
maybe the game can just be called where
is the dungeon
like the whole game is just trying to
find the dungeon and you don't it's very
like diffic it's very like
difficult to find
or maybe the game could just be called
what dungeon
where's the dungeon would be
dude where's my dungeon yeah
i really like this idea
technic beam that's a great idea i like
that idea
i like that you made that
all right um
yeah like what if you're basically going
around so this game
um
you know this game is just called
dungeon but with a question mark and
basically like you're a bunch of heroes
that show up to a town that's like
giving you all these npc quests like oh
it stole my cow and and the dragon has
been menacing us but you sort of start
to get the feeling like there's no
evidence that any of these things ever
happened right
and like
it turns out at the end of the game
that really it's just the villagers just
wanted like heroes to come to the
village so they just it's completely
fictional like they made it all up
there's no dragon there's no dungeon
they're completely full of it right
um
like
oh well actually so if it wasn't already
trademarked the obvious name for this
game would be imagine dragons
right
[Laughter]
you know
um
so
yeah
i mean you know it's it's one of those
things that they don't make
uh
they don't really make much sci-fi
comedy sci-fi fantasy comedy but i mean
that's the kind of thing that they
totally should have made
like someone should make a movie about
this town that's like struggling like
all the peasants are like really
unable like they can't feed their
families and it's really bad and like
somebody gets the idea to like attract a
bunch of heroes
um
by pretending that something like
momentous has happened there like
pretending there's like a lord of the
rings style like big
grand thing happening but they
completely fabricate it it's not
actually true and like it's you know the
standard kind of like
uh rom-com kind of movie right like
where they're just trying to pull it off
and they
almost do but sort of don't but then we
all learn to work together in the end
you know whatever
you know
so
you know kindly sloth there sort of is a
game like that a tycoon style game it's
not quite it doesn't have that humor
part of it unfortunately but there is a
game
uh
made by like there's this company that
has like this one
little like pixel engine
for like
management sims
um and they ship like if you go on like
the playstation store they literally
have shipped like 20 games that are all
exactly the same but they're just like
rebranded like they just keep like
changing the underlying thing
and
one of them is
that you create a town for adventurers
and adventurers show up and then they go
out and they fight in a dungeon and they
come back
and like you build things like an inn
for them or a you know an armory and
whatever right
and uh
so it doesn't have the humor part
unfortunately but it it almost is the
game you're talking about just minus the
humor right
i actually think it's a good idea for a
game i just don't think they made a very
interesting game out of it
but
anyway all right yeah so so you know
someone out there
like like these are all gems just we're
just these are just like golden golden
gems we're dropping here
gems aren't gold
it's all right um
dave made a dungeon
yeah all right i'll stop thinking about
that
uh okay so what we want to do here is in
the generator
nonsense which probably just needs to be
improved dramatically which is what we
were going to do next anyway so that's
all fine
uh we we had a thing i think in here
that generated the
little floor tiles and you know other
garbage like that
um
and
i believe
[Music]
um
so it's this this is this is it
uh
this tile switch pattern
thing
um
and
we must have turned it off
somehow
we yeah
so for some reason we turned it off
probably because we were doing stuff
um
baby's first dungeon would also be a
pretty good one
[Music]
so
i probably need to do the thing where we
start the hero so we don't have to like
walk out through the orphanage thing
um every time
but
for the time being for the brief
moment
um if we walk out to where the things
are there should be switches now maybe
um
yeah
so here's a bunch of random garbage in
you know right like these switches and
stuff
and the idea was like as they like oh
god
um well hey guys we found a place where
we didn't set the light values to be
less than one
uh wow that looks
pretty cool
actually
um
so these are the things that i actually
wanted to
uh
those little switches is what i wanted
i don't really remember much about how
we decided to light them i think we
create a light above them which like i
said is not really what i wanted i wanna
i don't actually want to create
a new light there anymore
um so i want to
change the way that's being done and
also
like yeah gotta keep those light values
under
one
so
that's not quite gonna cut it you can
see here us adding the light it's and
it's off
um and then my assumption is in the
brain uh when it gets stepped on
i
i assume it's in the brain does it get
uh
execute brain switches yeah there it is
um
i assume it turns on the light and it
turns it on like wait yeah
like not
an acceptable light level of 10. one is
probably still way too bright
um
but you know at least then it wouldn't
feed back presumably and let's put the
hero up near that stuff when it starts
so i don't have to keep walking up there
because unfortunately
hot code reloading doesn't work with the
world gen maybe it should
like because obviously like the hot code
reloading it keeps the world that you're
currently in that's kind of the point of
it but you know maybe we should just
have a button
so that we can regen the world anytime
we want so that if we hot reload changes
to world gen we hit a button and says
hey yeah regenerate this world because
we want to see the you know the thing we
changed we want to see what it does
you know we may need something like that
um but anyway
so uh when the hero
gets placed in the world
um
i think we can just say like
probably that
maybes
um
so what you can see here is like it's
not very good what's happening it's like
putting lights above the thing and it's
not like that's not at all what you want
so we're gonna start with a couple
uh tweaks here just so we can start
working on getting this lighting to be
correct
instead of what it actually is which is
the opposite of that right
um
so the first thing is i think
i i want to say and i'm i'm probably
lying
i want to say we don't need to add a
light at all
because our system is global
illumination now and works pretty well
i want to say we can just set the
emission
of the cube
and when it gets pushed into the system
it will just be set up as an occluder
that's a light source i think
right
is the light never going away uh yeah
the light those lights don't go away
they get set they permanently turn on
so i think
uh
i think these light pieces just don't
need to be
there um
here's the question does downward
dungeon
need a theme song
i feel like it does
like i'm imagining something like the
top gun theme
but where someone is singing the words
downward dungeon
along with it
you know what i'm talking about
first time chat
all right so
uh i'm i'm just gonna vote for we don't
actually
do this
so like this
is not a thing
um
and so now like when we hop over these
uh they
uh they turn on
and they do not add any lighting and we
also should remove our lighting because
we're not really supposed to have a
light i mean
sort of we can
uh
do a little bit of that but we we mostly
right now have like sort of almost like
debug lighting in there
for
the stuff attached to us and we don't
really want that
i do suspect that the glove should glow
like that is true
um
but
i don't actually
i don't actually want it to be
particularly bright and you know th this
0.1 as a light mighty might even be too
bright um
so we'll see
like that might be a bit much you know
like like it's not really supposed to be
a light source per se
um
i mean maybe it is in a completely like
the the darkest of dark rooms but it
just feels like oh hi way to change a
value that's not even in play
uh
but i just i yeah you know
um
so i think that yeah like that looks a
little bit more
like it to me so like if you're in a
completely dark room right it should be
it should be more like that
you know
i also think these should be
face
um
which they are not
of course i don't remember at all how
you make something stone face so
there is that
um
my assumption is that that is just
something that's set on the entity
piece
where
it's it's going to be this
uh asset tag
so i assume that in here like this asset
tag
wants to be set to the stonework i mean
eventually it wants to be set to the
actual switch tile which nobody has
drawn
so
you know
there's that
but uh
that's what we actually want
so when these get added here like the
stone floor stuff
um i don't know where this
happens exactly but in tile material
you can kind of see yeah like here tile
type
and tile material
oh it's like wall or floor i see
so so all we really need here is to just
say
um we're gonna for now switch it to this
other thing really we should have
our own
um
like
we would we would like what not flowers
uh we would like something that's
specific
to
being a switch
but at the moment we don't have that so
we'll just leave it
um
as it is but this way uh they're cleaner
because they're not like wood switches
you know that wouldn't light up it
doesn't look anything like something
that would light up so that looks a
little bit better right
and so now what we want to do is make
those
like
uh actually emit light instead of just
their color brightening when you step on
them you know what i'm saying to you
um
yeah i don't know what's up with the
four coder
project no one has told me
actually
so i don't even know what's up with it
um
is it like going to be like open sourced
and kind of like abandoned or like like
pooted forth to the community or is the
plan that someday it will get started
again or what i have no idea like what
the idea is
um
uh behind it
i re i really don't know
oh this dude came in god what are the
problems of having like no real like
one of the problems of having your maps
actually be real maps is that if the ai
is not artificially constrained to stay
in one place it can go wherever it wants
did one of the heads face her wall yes
they right now the collision detector is
turned off completely
uh
this because we we were doing some stuff
with it it's not turned on so any
floating entity can go straight through
a wall if it wants to
uh probably we won't even do floating
entities that way we'll probably make
them have to use the uh
other way of doing things
where they actually occupy tiles but at
the moment
those guys are basically considered
projectiles which means they are allowed
to just phase straight through walls if
they want to
um
so like
uh
i here's the thing though now that i
think about it i do think they
do require
a accessible square they do check though
whether they're allowed to move in a
square
so now that i think about it what i said
isn't totally true
their
their flight path like they can go
straight through the wall
um
if they
if they're going between two squares
that they could move between but i guess
technically they can't phase directly
through the wall that way
um
but like my point is that if i took this
curve tight
it you know it can
um it can like if i go fast enough it
could go through the wall like
that right as long as it's moving
through like
to a space it could actually occupy i
think it can't um
while the collision detector detector's
turned off so so it's not quite as
it's not quite as free as i originally
described
um
so
oh okay so for coder is going to be open
source that's kind of cool because i
would go i have access to the source
code right now because i said a couple
of things i wanted to fix like the
clipboard thing
and so if it was open source i think i
would contribute some stuff to it when
we come across stuff on stream like that
um
just to get it in into a good like
finishing state
because we'll use it on we'll keep using
it on stream so
you know
um i
so
the biggest problem for us here is just
going to be the self-illumination
stuff
because that is not currently in
our
vocabulary
right
in other words the biggest
obstacle
to our success
is that in here you can see like
the
flag stuff
and
so if you set these um like cube light
occluder
how we were getting light sources before
is we set this flag
and the problem is that those lead to
like separate switches
you know what i'm saying
so our problem is really just the
encoding of that and how do we want to
actually represent that because when we
go then to look at entity output code
you can see i'll be more specific
um you can see here that like it's going
to pick one of these
but what we actually wanted to do
um is this
while
sending down self-illumination
and in fact
it looks like imizion
uh is actually something you can send
down uh does that mean if i set this to
one like all our cubes become lit
lit cube bro
all right
so
if that's true then really all we're
talking about is a way to set this
emission value
right
um and if we can set that emission value
then we don't really need to change
anything we just you know we just need
to be able to
have the code that was previously
messing with the light source
nonsense we're just making this
uh
we're just gonna set the emission
instead
that's it
okay
um
[Music]
well
stretching
i mean i'm not sure what we want to do
here but we could do it like alpha is a
mission
or we could just make this thing bigger
i don't know
what the heck is cube uv layout even
defined as
so bitmap piece is 32 bit and qb layout
is u16 so actually we could keep this
the same size and just say that when
you're in the cube uv layout paths
path
um
there's actually an emission
value in there
right
um
like a 16 bit omizian value
that's pretty straightforward
um
because 16 bits is more than we would
actually need anyway
so we could do something where we just
did like this
uh and then
[Music]
uh put an emisian value in there
like we could have both of those two
things in there you know
uh
i
yeah all right so let's pack an omizian
value in there and see what that does
for us
we also don't need to call it cube uv
layout anymore because that's obvious
[Music]
now
all right
so there we go
uh and now we just need to use that
emission value
in
here
so what we need to do is unpack the
emission value and this is dumb
uh but sometimes we are dumb
i won't quote frank zappa in the
interest of keeping the stream from
family friendly
but you're welcome to look up
uh dumb all over i believe is the song
name
uh let's go ahead and
try this
since no one
right now
should be setting that value
uh
we should be
fine there should be no immersion cubes
and and i don't see any so that seems
good
uh and now if we go into the brains of
the operation
uh and
we look at the
uh
this
garbage
uh in theory
we can just say that
now uh the emission
of this thing
is going to go up to some number
and i don't know what number it's going
to be
i have no idea i don't have a sense yet
because we only just did the lighting
system
um how bright a bright light is so i
don't know
um that
looks
uh shockingly like
it did not do anything
you know i don't want to be
uh i don't want to be too
bold in my assertion but you know it
really doesn't
uh so what happened
there we set the cube emission
it is a piece type cube
i believe
we don't pass the emission all right
good
yep on top of it as always really
crushing it there
okay
that's what we wanted
so now we're getting our
self-illumination there
and that's all good
so that's good
but it looks to me like we are not
sending that down to the light system
though because like
over here there's no light it's
self-illuminating properly but it's not
actually telling the lighting system
about that self-illumination
right
um
so what we would prefer
[Music]
uh here
is if we could
make it so that when you do a push cube
if the emission is set it sets the
vertices right to the omission
um so let's see
what's happening here i'm not say that
that's i literally just said a word
salad that is not correct
um
so what i mean to say is the occluder
right so
the occluder should be pushed
there
i don't know why i said that
so here's the push cube function
um
and to be completely honest with you i
don't know how this whole thing works
anymore because it's been too long
um
but
somewhere in here it adds the cube
to the occluder set
i mean it would have to or this entire
game wouldn't work so we know that
that's happening
but to tell you the truth i don't quite
see
where
am i the only one is confused
um right like in the push cube function
this should have to push
an actual clue around maybe it does it
does it do it in here somewhere that i'm
not seeing i don't
i don't see it
like this i would have expected this
to have to call this right
uh to call push a cluedoor
so that it it would know that this is a
thing
hmm
oh
wait do you just set both
no but you couldn't set both because
this is an else if clause so you ain't
setting both right
that ain't happening
i'm gonna have to step through this
because frankly i just don't remember
does it add an occluder manually
when we generate the room
i mean is that how we rolled this
i
i mean we could have uh
right it's totally possible that that's
what happened
so here's the generated room call
there's it adding the cube
there's it adding the light
there's it adding the ceiling occluder
um
so i guess it really does
no that's only for trees
so how is it doing this
i think i just assumed
this entire time i've been assuming that
those
that that's how that worked
um but i guess i was mistaken
no
it's this code right here
so it looks like we add the occluders
manually
so that's
that happened
um in here
so is light
i guess is what we need to deal with
here
so
what we would want to do i guess is say
that if the omission value is non-zero
then we do set it to is light
to be completely honest i
don't know that we really need that
we could presumably just
um
i mean the lighting system doesn't
really care about that but what the
lighting system does need to know is is
something an emitter or not right
so we don't really have a good place for
a floating point value here other than
to modulate the reference color
so it's like really what you would
probably want to do here isn't you'd
want a refsee and is light would be like
an emission c as well so you don't
really have an is light right
um and i don't know if we want to go
that far right now but maybe we do
i don't know because we kind of know how
the lighting works now we we pretty much
know what's up
right
and so
you know if we wanted to
we could just make these
be
we could just make that f32 be emission
right
um
[Music]
let's take a gander
so that literally is the only place
so yeah i mean
i mean yeah
i i'm i'm gonna suggest we just do this
so now that value is directly
controllable
um
we don't care about the sphere stuff
what do we do with hiddemizion
i mean these could just be added now
and should be added now
right
um
shouldn't they be added shouldn't this
be added
like
like max
max is a nice guy
right i don't want to say anything bad
about him but max just doesn't seem like
the right choice here like if we have a
reflected color
and we have an emitted color
wouldn't we just add them together
um
i don't know
we need the rendering equation we need
jim caggia's rendering equation
all right so now these are set to
emission
um and we can see them but we would like
them to do in the lighting system and i
believe
we have fixed that i believe we have
uh so that now
we should in fact i guess we don't even
need to restart the game because it's
not a startup thing
um we should be able to add some code in
here so that when you push an occluder
um
we could we could more or less just say
that that
there's no difference between pushing a
light source and pushing an occluder
right i think
so here are the two calls
um
and
all we i think
they're exactly the same
like there's no difference between these
two things
so i think now we can just stop with
that and say push
a lighting element or something like
that you know what i mean
um and then we would just say like
what's the color
uh and what's the emission
and we would uh
pass the emission through
and set the color as suchly
um
and
and then in order to do the lighting
element thing
like you'd now just translate the other
two calls into whichever one of those
you actually wanted
and we could also get rid of the concept
that there's a light and an occluder as
separate things i won't just yet but we
certainly can
um
so let's get rid of some of this stuff
and and try to clean that up so if we
want to push a lighting element on
um all we need now to do is say
that
the color passes through in the rgb a
style where because we encoded the
emission in the a value didn't we
for lights that's how that worked
um and i guess like i'm saying we can
sort of undo some of that stuff in a
little bit here because now we have an
actual emission
we have an actual emission encoding
um so then uh in here when we're doing a
piece type occlude or
then
we push the same we call the same
function but we do it slightly
differently where now
um we're going to pass the amis we're
past the omission as zero
right
um
and and we don't have an alpha value
because i mean we never did that was
getting clipped off of there there's no
such thing as alpha in the lighting
system we don't have translucent
lighting at the moment
right
um okay
so i think that's now encoded properly
and the only thing that we didn't do and
of course it won't do it for the ones i
already stepped on so i guess when i
said this wasn't a startup thing i was
sort of lying
um
the thing we need to actually do is set
the occluder's emission
right um
to to be the
yeah you know what i'm saying
well
still don't see any light
so i'm not feeling too good about that
um
i suppose technically we want them both
to be set
to an emissive value
uh because we also want the base one to
be
but we don't know which of these is
which on here i suppose so that's kind
of another problem
but when we create those
ground elements
um
yeah i mean it should be i mean you know
we probably should be a little cl
cleaner about this uh
to make sure that these things line up
properly but
if we're at the first one
we'd set the emission here uh and the
second one we'd set the emission here
that should have worked
so i'm a little weirded out that it
didn't but we'll go we'll check it out
what would translucent lighting even be
like participating media
right
um god rays would be an example of
of that sort of thing
water
like murky water
so like yeah like that is not emitting
any light in the lighting system so i
think we're still not really sending it
down
how much time we got
we have
just a few minutes left so i would say
with our few minutes left
big stretch
and
we've
uh
we've have it all
i'm not sure oh by the way you know the
other thing is we have the light leaking
problem a little bit
because now we allow that sort of weird
kind of sampling to happen when this guy
comes over you'll see what i mean
come on over
come on guys there we go
um
no it's not coming over
well that says i can do it maybe
i mean i guess it's really not bad
enough to worry about i was going to say
because we now do the thing where we
actually do jittered lighting positions
like that we will have more light
leaking but i guess it's just not good
bad enough to worry about
um anyway what i was going to say is
with we got a little bit of time left
maybe i'll just uh step into this code
uh so here's we made it a mid-or right
um
and
i guess let me let me actually set
myself up for success by
going into the code that actually like
puts these fourth
and
checking to see when we have an emitted
a one that has a mission
uh
in it you know
so like if
domitian is greater than zero
um
oh
hi
i'm still an idiot
nice work casey
that's twi i did the same thing twice in
a row the first time i was like oh that
didn't work because i didn't actually
pass the value second time oh that
didn't work and i didn't pass the value
how many times are we not going to pass
the value
all right let's double check that that
doesn't just work before i go debug the
thing
hey look that worked
all right so we can now turn these
lights on
uh which is fine
um and
they don't seem to be
the color seems to be off and i suppose
that's probably because
um we need to set the color of the
emitter as well
uh so we probably want to tweak this but
i would say we did everything we wanted
to do today so i i'm happy with that and
we'll pick it up again next week and i
said today was going to be short and i
wasn't kidding
so um
you know
and you can see here why i was saying we
should add a glue we should add a bloom
shader
um because
you know this looks nice and all but you
want to emphasize the fact that it's
like a bright light you want a little
bit of a halo effect around it right you
want a little bit of that blurring out
um and so this is why i was saying we
want to add a post pass i think probably
to do that because it's like for those
lit things on the ground that's really
what's gonna sell it you know what i'm
saying
but i think we're good
uh that was it
um this may be a bit too bright in terms
of emission
hard to say
that seems better
i would also say we probably have to
tone that down a little bit on the ramp
um
well maybe not i don't know
anyway
that's all i want to do today and like i
said today's gotta be a short day so
that's it
um
i don't really have anything else to say
it worked yay
no real tough stuff today
very simple
all right everybody
thank you very much for joining me for
another episode
of handmade hero it has been a pleasure
coding with you as always
uh if you do want to
play around with stuff yourself
i should always mention
you can go to handmadehero.org
um and you can pre-order if you want
source code it comes with source code
uh which you can build yourself and have
a party with
uh that's about it
um i oh you know what i should mention
as well our movie club is up
the first episode of our movie club is
up
me and anna do a movie club on sub stack
if you like talking about movies it's a
podcast that you might be interested in
forgot to mention that i'll mention it
next time more prominently but if you're
interested in that if you like talking
about movies
and you're tired of the way people
normally talk about movies these days
you just want people who think about the
movie a lot
and talk about what's in it
it's for you
all right that's it
the first movie was interstellar by the
way and that's the podcast that's up
there right now it was recommended by
the members of the movie club they said
we're gonna do
uh
interstellar and it was it was a really
fun discussion i liked talking about
interstellar a lot so if you want to
check it out check it out that's where
it's at mollymovieclub.com go for it
um
the uh question about whether i'm going
to watch better call season six
absolutely but uh i watch it on netflix
which i don't think has season six yet i
only just watched season five cause they
only just got season five so i'm way
behind on better call saul i love better
call saul
i think it's not as good as it was the
the first two seasons of better call
saul
better
call saul
are probably the best two seasons of
television
that exists it is by far the best
television writing i've ever seen the
first two seasons
seasons three through five
were good they're still a good show but
they're not that
right um they're not
like this is the best thing i've ever
seen kind of stuff
so
so i would so my thing is like i'm less
like invested in the show now because i
don't think it's as good as those first
two seasons i still will absolutely
watch the rest of it because it's still
a very good show compared to any other
show right
but i wasn't as like hype as i was with
seasons one and two were unbelievable
i'd never seen anything quite like that
so um
rook tag you don't necessarily need to
watch interstellar to enjoy the podcast
but if you ever plan on watching
interstellar i would say watch it first
because we really talk a lot about
everything that's in the movie and like
how it's structured and how different
things worked and all that sort of stuff
so it's gonna totally destroy
any first impressions you could have of
the movie
so it's really assuming that you know
like it's the ultimate spoiler warning
right like do not listen to a molly
movie club
podcast episode for a movie you plan to
watch
right
um and we mostly do old movies
so like
you know
presumably everyone has seen a lot of
these movies but
if you haven't we give plenty of warning
like we say look this this is the movie
that's coming up
you know in in three weeks or whatever
so you have plenty of time to watch it
we just expect you to watch it right so
there's it's it's super spoilery
it's it's it's like more spoilery than
anything else
is right
so um
so basically like
you know
picking apart a movie like that where
you start talking about all the
nitty-gritty you then can't have an
honest first impression of it right if
you've heard that before you've seen it
so
so that's what i would say so so if you
have any interest in watching
interstellar don't go to the podcast yet
watch interstellar first
um
and then
listen to the podcast
uh and for members there's three more
now coming we do one free one a month
for people who aren't subscribers
um
for people who are 2001 is this friday
star trek two the wrath of khan is the
friday after and moon
is is the friday after that so those are
the ones that are coming up
um because we wanted to do ones people
recommended interstellar and we wanted
to do movies that we thought it would
make sense
um
as to why
like
you know 2001 is very obvious because
interstellar like pulls pretty heavily
from 2001 you can kind of tell i mean
all space movies do in a way it was kind
of a progenitor right
so we did a couple and wrath of khan is
in there because
um we thought it was an interesting
diametrically opposed movie
like
i mean you i again don't really want to
spoil anything but like
you could say that they sort of are
inverses in what they do right
if that makes sense i mean not really
but like or or what they do exemplary i
would say right um so
you know anyway all that's in the
podcast uh so if you like movies and you
like thinking about movies
um
as movies as opposed to thinking about
them as culture which is all anyone ever
talks about now like nobody talks about
movies anymore
except maybe you go find like a red
letter media episode or something maybe
maybe does but like movie reviewers
don't talk about movies at all if you go
read a movie review they don't mention
anything about the movie in the entire
review um it's only like cultural or
casting and then like the internet only
talks about like did this company do
something bad or whatever right
um and nobody talks about the actual
like nitty gritty of like
okay so does this scene set up this
character to actually be sympathetic
here or did they not really do that so
that this scene later doesn't really
land because of blah right or things
like was the cinematography good here
like did it actually convey the fact
that these two things were in the same
place or was the motion correctly done
in here like we just kind of go into
that stuff
right
um
so you know it's that kind of thing and
so if you like that kind of thing and
and you probably won't agree with us on
everything right um because you're gonna
have different opinions and we encourage
that the movie club is about tournament
we don't care if people agree at all we
just want them focused on that so it's
like we just try to like get people
talking about that right like get them
talking about what is in the movie and
if it worked for you
or if it didn't work for you
what are the actual things in the movie
that made that happen right instead of
just like i don't this this is not how
batman should be or something or
whatever like statements that don't
really make much sense
um
[Music]
in
their totally fine things to have a
discussion about in the broader context
like
brand management and whether or not
there's certain obligations to treat
famous characters a particular way or
any of that stuff right
totally fine discussions to have but
everyone's already having them like like
those discussions are just like
ubiquitous right so there's no need for
that because you can get that anywhere
so we've tried to focus everything away
from that to basically like
you know if it is a batman movie and we
want to talk about how it uses the
batman character does it do that well
it's all we were really looking at right
like like you know uh we're not going to
complain because it's not our personal
version of batman or something right
or we try not to
anyway so
anyway uh all that kind of stuff so yeah
mollymovieclub.com that's it easy to get
to
uh and
yeah watch interstellar first
uh if you haven't already and head over
uh right
um
and uh and the other thing that we try
to do that we hope is interesting is is
curate a good set of movies right like
we try to pick movies that people should
see
um
to give them background
uh that they might not have if they if
they don't watch a lot of like older
films
um or
films that are outside maybe slightly
outside the mainstream we try to pick
ones that are worth watching right like
not just because like oh we think you
know really if you're not into foreign
films you don't understand cinemas like
some of that crap just like if there's
actually things done well in movies we
try to like point them out and say like
hey this is a movie that does something
very interesting here's what we think it
is and why you might be interested in it
or whatever right
so
so anyway check it out easy to get to
and yeah i'll mention again on next
stream
so anyway thanks everyone for joining us
i like the way this is shaping up next
week uh try some level gen
probably and then we gotta get combat uh
in there so just level down in combat i
think so the lighting looks nice now
it's good enough uh for us to do
whatever we need to do i think
all right everybody thanks for joining
me uh i will see you next weekend until
then have fun programming and i'll see
you on the internet take it everybody