and start grating hello everyone welcome
to handmade Hero the show we towed a
complete game live on stream we I don't
actually remember having anything
outstanding at the end of last week in
some very odd turn of events that is
somewhat inexplicable despite kind of
fighting with multi sampling and death
feeling for two or three sessions at the
last minute MTS MOX happened to find a
problem we had with our you know depth
and able and reenable and we fix it and
that kind of gave me new impetus to go
look to see if we can get multi sample
definitely working and I randomly try
the technique that seems to work
incredibly well for us it's splitting
the depth the total depth Delta on a
multi sample pixel and so just to recap
I guess I'll I'll sort of show you on
the blackboard what it was but I was not
expecting this to be anything special it
looks like I got a restart my Milton's
let's see here no handmade comms that's
the drive oh man I don't even want to
tell you it has been a month I found
someone to do the rest of the handmade
con videos and editor and I've been
trying to make a hard drive with the
with the videos on it for them to edit
and it has been seriously four week
straight of me trying to get Google
Drive to successfully download the files
and it has failed for four weeks
straight and it's been a complete
nightmare Google Drive is incredibly bad
I'm glad the only thing I've ever used
it for is like basically those
transferring those videos because man if
you actually had to use Google Drive as
an actual drive solution heaven help you
anyway let's go ahead and restart Milton
pear
earth go and we are day 389 and this is
multi sampled depth P Lang so what
happened here was we were getting you
know we have done our depth feeling and
that was great
I really like the death feeling but then
we wanted to try and smooth out the
edges of geometry on the screen which we
don't have much of but we we only have
that one cube primitive it's really the
only thing I needed you know I don't I
don't the games mostly sprites but I
wanted the ground and walls to be made
up of actual geometry and so that was
still you know really crispy and and
sparkly it didn't look nice right and so
we wanted something that would smooth it
out so the question was could we get
death feeling working with multi
sampling and the problem with that is
that multi sampling is definitely don't
play very nicely together since
typically the way multi sampling works
is it only operates on the edges which
means that when you're filling a sprite
if you're on the interior of the sprite
right you're just going to be filling
that one pixel essentially that one
sample and it's just going to replicate
to all the samples right that's how
multi sampling works if the if the edge
of the primitives that you're working
with like let's say you know this is the
primitive I'm working but this is the
triangle out here if the pixel is
entirely encompassed in that primitive
multi sampling is not active so what
it'll do is they'll just do one sample
and it will write them all the samples
it'll write to all the samples as a
splat
I'll just say we set all the samples to
be this value right so what ends up
happening is you can't really use depth
feeling very effectively with this at
least not with the shader levels where
you think because you don't have any way
of really taking that and doing anything
with this right what you have to do is
you'd have to do a for loop over
the samples and effectively compare it
to each sample and you more or less
would lose all the benefits of monthly
sampling like you might as well just
start rendering at 8 X the resolution
because now you're processing every
sample every pixel every time right
every Texel I should say because you
know with overdraw so basically we don't
really have any wind from multi sampling
if we were to do that so the question is
could we do something that worked
properly with multi sampling where
instead of actually having multi
sampling persist all the way through the
depriming process could we do one just
the you know one def peel with multi
sampling then like sort of reduce or
resolve then to produce a regular you
know one pixel one sample per pixel
version of that texture passed that to
the next page of the process and
effectively just get the actual
acceleration we want from multi sampling
you know I'm saying
and the answer seemed elusive but then
it turned out for whatever reason if you
take a look at all of these samples and
produce a min and Max range so if this
was our camera looking down and we
looked at all these samples you know and
they kind of fell in you know the depth
from the camera like this if you take
the minimum and maximum of them and then
you just split the difference so you
take half the the the way in between
these two that actually produces in the
vast majority of cases that I was able
to find where my get the command prompt
back here let me go ahead and run the
game here so you can take a look at it
[Applause]
there we go Kyle come on Visual
Studio you can boot on now oh boy I got
to uninstall that that code excel thing
ever since we installed code excel
Visual Studio takes like years to boot
like years it's nuts
I don't even want to know what was
having on there alright
all right there we go so here you can
see it running right and there's really
no artifacts you can get smoothing on
all of the geometry even where two
pieces intersect which we couldn't do
when we were trying to do the centroid
sampling version of this but even if I
switch through the debug camera and
really just kind of stressed it out
you don't get many artifacts there's a
couple in in a few places you can see a
little bit like right in there when you
get really low to it you can kind of see
a little bit in there but for the most
part it looks pretty good and I'm
totally willing to kind of go forward
with that so far we may have to do a
little more tweaking to it later
but it's pretty good as it stands and
the only place that we really saw
artifacts that we might want to try and
fix at some point is here you can kind
of see when it when it fades in you get
a problem where the depth peel is a
little too aggressive on the cubes so
you end up in a situation where you have
you have precluded some of the depth
some of the lower stuff from showing
through so you end up with effectively
like a like a bigger beveled edge that
kind of goes through there you can see
it right along there and that's not
correct obviously but mostly I'm pretty
happy with it so it's a little early to
declare victory certainly because we
don't have you know a full game running
where we've tried all the things that
you know we don't know what geometry we
might have in the actual game but or
sprites that might stress this harder in
some way because you know since it's
kind of a
weird hacky technique that we just kind
of came up with to solve a problem it's
hard to predict necessarily without
having more experience or thinking it
through a lot trying to figure out what
all the cases are where it might fail
it's hard to know if anything we might
do in the future could break it in a bad
way but at the moment I would say I'm
pretty I'm happy certainly happy enough
with it with the render quality we're
getting here to just go ahead and move
on to something else right and again
that's all I did at the last minute to
just I was playing around some things to
see if any would work all I did was just
take in a custom resolved path that
would split them in in the max and say
that's the value to pick and that just
worked well I mean I had a reason for
doing it it's not like it was completely
blind the idea was simply that well that
would say that you know if we had
samples from two different pieces of
geometry like let's say I had in here
the tree you know covers these samples
and the ground covers these samples my
thought was well we want to depth
peel away the tree but we want to leave
the ground in place so if those were at
had any substantial difference in their
Z at all then picking the Midway should
hopefully land most of these samples on
this side of it and most of these
samples on that side of it so off you go
right and I don't like I said I don't
really claim that that's any kind of
rigorous solution to the problem but it
does seem to be surprisingly effective
in a large number of cases
so yeah that's that's the renderer I
guess what I would say at this point is
I don't actually think we have anything
in particular I want to do to the
renderer now from where it is and so one
thing that I thought we might do perhaps
is just say well you know now that we
finish all that stuff maybe let's go
ahead and and just kind of add in some
lighting to the renderer this weekend
because you know that's the one thing
that we don't really have at the moment
and it looks like our image quality is
good and the graphics we we accomplished
what we wanted everything is in real 3d
now it runs through the z-buffer so
there is no sorting you can dump as much
stuff in as you want and really the only
thing that I think we might do in the
future to it from a structure that's
there now is when I shift the art pack
to update to new artwork I may make it
so that our artwork is all kind of
pre-processed to be in tiles that can
can all be the same resolution roughly
so that we can use like a texture array
because right now you know we on cards
that aren't fast at this on NVIDIA you
don't see this at all but we take a long
time in OpenGL renderer commands right
now and the reason for that is we have
to change texture handle every single
sprite right which is just way too much
a lot of modern cards can elide those
changes like Nvidia drivers just eat
those for breakfast and that I assume is
because the texture handle is just a
pointer basically and you don't actually
need to
we start anything you can just inline it
in the stream and if the dispatches can
just go very quickly there isn't it's
not a whole state change that happens
whereas on old cards that's not true the
texture unit have to be reproduced up
and it really like slows things down so
on older cards like this you pay a huge
penalty for it on modern cars working
video you don't even really see it I was
noticing that when I ran this on a more
modern GPU the other day so we you know
it's not super clear that that's
something that we want to do for sure
but I do think it's something that we
probably want to do and when you take a
look at how things are at the moment you
know it sure seems like that would be
fine you know basically we could just
have most of our stuff have it you know
lives in a 256 by 256 bitmap or whatever
and off we go
and I'll just you know resize things to
fit that properly or something so we can
do a pretty simple texture Atlas pink
scheme or texture array scheme we could
do a pretty simple one of those without
a lot of headache and maybe we should
right so we can certainly take a look at
that and and so I might do some of that
but that's the that's literally it and
all that would be is a slight change in
how we're submitting our textures and
then getting that loop to not change
textures every frame every sprite it
would just change the texture once and
go so that's you know something we might
do other than that I think now we're
down to optional features right we're
getting good render quality everything's
in 3d I don't see sorting problems
really I don't see artefacts that I'm
not willing to live with so it's really
pretty clean and I'm going to go forward
there so what I was thinking is like
maybe just get some some basic lighting
for us because I feel like we're going
to want a little bit of lighting in here
something where we can
you know put down some light sources and
you know probably do something with some
some normals with the shading we have
the option of having our sprites have
normal maps on them and I don't know to
what extent we really want to do that
because it's a question of you know
whether that's going to work with the
art style or not sometimes it can be a
little bit difficult to figure out if
that's going to be good or bad but we
basically have a situation where we want
at least some lighting so even if we
were going to just do very basic
lighting that didn't even have any
normals it was just you know regional we
at least want that in there somewhere
right we want some regional lighting to
to exist somewhere so what I want to do
is just basically throw a little bit of
that in and and you know get ourselves
something that can have lights happen I
so what's the way I want to do this at
the moment
is is not particularly interesting all I
really want to do is say well let's
let's go ahead and just do the simplest
like stupidest possible thing and we'll
start there right so I'm going to go
into our shaders here and you know we've
got this one shader that does
essentially everything so this is our
compiled v bias program right and this
is the thing that draws subsequently
everything so if we put lighting into
this shader in some way everything that
we drew would be lit by that algorithm
whatever it is so what I'd like to do is
start by saying well let's suppose that
we had some light source what could we
do to put in some sort of really basic
you know not good just simple simple
lighting
so let's start with something really
straightforward let's start with sort of
a well I'll mention a few things for you
all right so if we were going to do real
lighting there's a number of things that
you have to take count of right and the
problem with real lighting is that you
kind of sometimes have to go all the way
with real lighting otherwise you're in a
bit of a pickle so first let me say
something about real lighting that's
kind of difficult to understand trying
to get how in-depth I want to go with
this but here we go
so let's suppose that I have a source of
photons right because what is light you
know light equals photons for our
purposes now I'm not trying to make a
statement about quantum mechanics or
anything here so this is you know
graphics that we're talking about and in
terms of graphics all we really care
about in the real world most of the time
is that we've got essentially light
sources that emit photons from them
those photons travel in straight lines
so when a when a photon is emitted from
a light source it travels in a straight
line until it hits something when it
hits something some of it some there's a
percentage chance that that photon will
be absorbed and there's a percentage
chance that that photon will be bounced
out right and again this is not trying
to make a statement about quantum
mechanics it's just trying to make a
statement about the parts we think need
to think about for graphics so typically
what happens is we have a light right
and we have an eye and what we want to
know is photons that came out of a light
source they hit something right they
bounced off and they hit our eyes we are
trying to sort of say with lighting we
want to accumulate all of that right the
ideal goal in a graphics you know in a
lighting algorithm in a
realistic lighting algorithm would be to
take all of the photons that were
emitted over you know whatever the frame
time is a sixtieth of a second let's say
take all of the photons emitted by a
light source bounce them all around see
which one of them hit the eye and that
is the the lighting right and you can
imagine this is per pixel right every
pixel it's whether a photon would have
come in at that point in the CCD if it's
your camera or your retina is it's your
eye right if it would have hit that
settle of the retina we sum all of the
photons that would have hit it and after
we get and furthermore these photons
they have a wavelength right a photon is
a you know is a thing that sort of
oscillates and that's the color right so
by tracking the color of those photons
we would also know what color that pixel
should be by summing up all of those
wavelengths right now obviously if you
haven't gotten a sense already this is
just the idealized model of the lighting
process nobody actually does this why
don't they do this because even the most
basic scene with like one light in it is
billions and billions of photons and
there's no way to simulate billions and
billions of photons in a sixtieth of a
second so for a game is totally
unacceptable even for offline rendering
it's usually too slow to do that so what
we typically try to do with lighting is
we try to do one of two things in the
pre-rendered world we try to come up
with essentially ways of sampling this
process so so you know if you're you
know Pixar right or your next limit and
you make max well you know the renderer
for architecture and stuff or whatever
so you can take a long time and lots of
computing power to produce an image what
you typically do with lighting is you
try to come up with ways of sampling
this process in ways that do not
to simulate all billion billion trillion
quadrillion mozillian photons to get a
good result right and so they do things
like metropolis light transport
transport and bi-directional path
tracing and blah blah blah blah which
are all these sort of ways of saying we
have this tremendous number of photon
paths in the world we have no way of
simulating them all how do we sort of go
about picking which ones might be
relative relevant to simulate and
approximating from those what the rest
of the lighting should look like right
so again you can kind of imagine I don't
want to go into too much detail cuz
they're not relevant here but you can't
imagine how these techniques work
because if you think about it there's
first of all a ton of photons never hit
the eye right if you think about the
photons look around your room if you
think about all the photons that are
bouncing around your room right now most
of them don't go into your eye so for
starters typically what you do is you
trace outward from the eye right to look
for lights as if the photons were
traveling backwards right
so just from there that first initial
transform is a good way of starting to
say let's cut out a bunch of photons we
don't care about furthermore when you
start to look at surfaces and stuff you
can say well you know I know this
surface has certain reflectance
properties so I know that photons that
come in you know about here almost never
they almost always get absorbed and
photons that come in here always bounce
out that way
so if I'm looking at it this way I know
I don't have to look in this direction
and I know I don't have to look in this
direction roughly because those photons
almost could never bounced out to the
eye from that point so I can concentrate
my search in like this direction right
so you do a bunch of stuff based on
probabilities essentially to start to
try and reconstruct what it is and some
of this really fascinating work in this
direction
specifically the sort of the chain of
work this that started by Eric beech
when you wrote metropolis light
transport and everything that followed
thereafter is really interesting a lot
of it has to do with basically saying
we can reduce the number of samples we
need to take and the number of passed we
need to compute rather dramatically just
by looking at this problem as a
probabilistic problem and focusing
understanding how to take samples in the
places they are most useful and how to
weight them properly to produce results
that on average produce the correct
result as quickly as possible right so
the offline world does things that way
and the reason for that is again they're
trying to produce very realistic results
and they can spend 12 hours a frame
doing so if they want to right not so
for handmade hero and handmade hero
isn't even supposed to require a super
high-end graphics card to run
it's a 2-d game so we don't even have
the geometry we would need to do a lot
of the stuff that we're talking about
there we would have to approximate it so
we're not trying to do that what we're
trying to do is we're trying to come up
with something that will be artistically
pleasing right we basically are trying
to come up with something that has to do
with life that will be reasonable that
will make you feel like there is some
lighting without costing a huge amount
of computation now let's talk about some
properties of light that have an effect
here so first of all let's talk about
the concept of fall-off
now one of the myths of light that you
know a lot of people intuitively thinks
but it's not actually true is that light
gets dimmer as it gets further away
right and we'll talk about why that is
in a second and in fact it actually will
for certain things that we are
interested in so I don't mean to tell
you that it doesn't at all but it's
important to understand that that's
actually kind of a wrong way to think
about light
it's more of a property of the
integration of light and we'll see that
in a second
so let's talk about that let's talk
about some of the pro the properties of
these protons that we care about so
let's say that there is a distant light
source right let's say that there is a
street lamp maybe right so let's say
I've got like a street lamp here and I
am looking at the street lamp the street
lamp is lit up my light bulb I am seeing
a photon that comes out and it hits my
eye right and furthermore let's say that
I have walked backwards and there's a
photon that comes back and hits my eye
here the crucial thing to start your
understanding of light with is that that
photon does not get dimmer as it travels
further away photons do not dim along a
line when a photon comes out of a light
source and travels a mile and hits your
eye it is as bright as if you were
standing with your eye right up next to
the light there is no difference in the
photons perceived brightness to your eye
okay so this is crucial light does not
diminish along a line ever under any
circumstances that I know of
period now again I'm not a quantum
physicist so maybe if you're going to
physically be like ah yes it does in if
you go many millennia
you know like years away and you're
talking about the relativistic spinning
of the bubble right so you know I don't
know maybe there is some way for a
photon
somehow be dimmer or brighter in
relativistic terms there's only I have
no idea like the energy that it that it
has will shift and that would seem
logical because you know the wavelength
of a light but again in terms of
brightness there's there's the
wavelength of the light is its color
it's not as brightness right if energy
is its color is this color not its
brightness and so what do I mean when I
say this you know and why do things look
brighter and dimmer well the thing to
remember is what's happening when you
see a brightness is you are seeing the
amount of photons that hit your eye
right it's effectively account so when
you look at something in sight is it
brighter or dimmer what you're actually
asking is how many photons have hit your
eye from this light source okay so a
single beam of light a photon that goes
out of the light source and hits your I
can never get stronger or weaker for
that individual photon so when a light
looks brighter or dimmer to you the only
thing that can be happening there is
less photons or more photons are hitting
your eye from that light source that's
the only thing that can change your
perceived brightness of that light
source the photon itself that goes along
the line doesn't get weaker as it comes
to you okay again really important to
understand that so now let's take it one
step forward so given that brightness is
the count of photons
if I were to ask how many photons would
be hitting my eye at these two distances
right if I were to ask how many I would
be able to ascertain the brightness so
let's ask that question how they need
photons proportionally speaking will hit
my eye at say one mile away
right versus two miles away it's a
legitimate question right well it's a
little difficult to answer without
thinking a little bit more about how
this is emitting photons if this were a
laser meaning it's a highly correlated
stream of light where all the photons
are shot in a very specific direction
the answer is probably the roughly the
same number right because remember
photons do not diminish along a line and
if I were shooting all of those photons
out directly in a line then they would
just all hit my eye
in both cases right and yeah lasers
aren't perfect so eventually I get far
enough away that maybe that wouldn't be
true but for the vast majority of that
relevant distance it would just all the
hotels would hit right so let's talk
about something that's not a laser since
lasers are usually not only care about
right a laser pointer is not the thing
that we're lighting both most our scenes
with so what is the light like a street
lamp - well what it does is it's
outputting a certain number of photons
per second right but it's outputting
them in every which way right so if I
were to take what angle my eye can see
right I've got a very different set up
than a laser so let's take a look at
what that looks like here is my light
bulb
- here's my light bulb and here is my
eye now we know the eye is a lens so
it's going to focus a cone of light onto
a point right a particular retinal cell
in the back let's say here is that cell
we're talking about that particular
retinal cell so one point of your vision
well this lens
is going to focus basically a and we'll
say this is a point light source for now
it's really well I don't have to so it's
a spherical light source so it's going
to take all of the light that can be
shot in this direction right and it's
going to focus it like that so it's
effectively it's not really a cone it
would be a cone if we were talking about
a point light source right it would be a
cone it was like a cone that map's down
to a point via the lens this is the eye
lens right but we're you know even if
the light source has some area to it
we're still talking about a cone that's
just kind of a little fatter at the end
and inside this cone right it's shooting
out all these photons in this direction
and all of those photons that are shot
out in that direction they will come and
kick this lens and be focused onto the
eye right that's what a lens does that's
why you use a lens by the way the idea
behind the lens is to take a cone of
light instead of a point of light right
it helps you get a brighter image when
you're looking at something as inside
all right so what does this mean well
this lens from our eye it does not get
bigger when we get further away right so
if we were to take what would happen if
I was to put the lens back here back
here further it's still the same size
right so what ends up happening is let's
say for sake of argument this is a very
weak light source so it's not emitting
very many photons per second and let's
say that there's only a few that will
actually hit there's only three that it
emitted that will actually hit the lens
and here they are okay
so those photons hit the lens they focus
on to this point right and that's how
much energy I proceeded how much
brightness I proceeded I proceeded three
photons well now if I go back really far
what happens now well if we continue
these lines you will see they miss the
lens right so only one photon will now
be focused right only one photon will
now be focused on to my retinal cell so
as you move a lens further away from a
light source it absolutely collects less
photons from an emitter right that is
100% true and this is before talking
about any of the other things we need to
talk about like participating media pays
that sort of thing right so you can see
very clear to the diagram as I move
further away I collect less photons but
and so now you're going to say well okay
Casey you just told me that the light
will not I just won't but so now based
on what you told me Casey I'm going to
go ahead and say that all right
so lights look dimmer when I get further
away right because they collected
photons not so fast
so given that this is the case you now
have to think about this in three
dimensions what does this actually look
like right well a light source is there
for emitting right and a lens is there
for collecting stuff effectively as an
area right if I took a solid angle right
that I said okay how much photons are
emitted there they kick this lens and
they focus you know down onto a point
everything in that assembly is an area
we're measuring an area of photons that
are emitted right a solid angle it's
like a bundle it's a surface area of
photons that are
coming out and then hitting the lens
then bouncing back right that area as it
gets further from the light source right
gets bigger and bigger proportional to
the distance so if I were to look at it
again from the side as I emit outwards
right what I'm going to end up doing is
as I get further away the spread of
those photons is going to increase with
the distance proportional again to this
triangle right it's get the the the size
of this effectively right the size of
that area is going to be exactly
proportional to the distance right
whatever the distance is as this
distance goes up so to will did it's a
similar triangles relationship just like
the projection equation right and we
know that you know this is just going to
be proportional to the cosine
effectively of the hypotenuse right
which is proportional to distance right
and these two are proportional to each
other as well right so basically the
area is going to be proportional to the
distance but remember there's two
dimensions right we're talking about
area squared so the same amount of
photons as I get further away is going
to fall on an area that's a square of
the distance and this gives rise to
what's called the inverse square law
right why is it called the inverse
square law and what does it mean
well the inverse square law says that
light essentially diminishes with the
square of the distance it travels right
and the reason for that is not just the
photons get any less bright it's because
the photons are spread over an
increasingly wide area so the chance
that you will get something will get hit
with a photon is 1 over the distance
squared right why because as the
distance increases a increases and we
know the if you know this is the side
here I shouldn't say a it is a sounds
like area I don't know why I picked that
let's just say that's you know width or
something right
there's width so it's you know the area
equals the width squared here in this
case right cuz it's the square and since
width is proportional to distance what
that means is 1 over the distance
squared is the chance that a particular
photon will hit you as you get further
away if you're right at the light source
obviously it will always hit you as you
get further away it diminishes with the
distance squared right make sense ok so
now you ask me well okay so if that's
the case then surely what happens is as
I get further away from a light source
as I'm walking further away from a light
source I it's gonna look you know if I
were to draw its brightness curve and
addition you know it's gonna look like
that right it's going to look like an
inverse squared curve or something well
it could look like one over the you know
1 over a square nope I that
unfortunately is taking much too
simplistic of view of what's happening
here yes this is 100% correct and yes as
I get further away the number of photons
that are going to be hitting my eye is
is exactly proportional to this but and
and I should mention the actual
brightness of the light is actually
diminished to 1 over d squared it's
actually happening but that is not what
you will say and you can prove this to
yourself right now if you want to take a
light source in your room
whatever your lamp is and look at it and
walk away from it does it look like it's
getting any dimmer
it should 1 over d squared is a very
steep fall-off curve right it should be
looking crazy amounts to dimmer as you
walk away from right up close to it to
further away but it doesn't look any
dinner does it right so the question is
why the answer is because that is not
what we're actually talking about when
we talk about how humans for
to brightness humans do not proceed
brightness by saying how much light from
this light source fell on my eye if they
did it would look much dimmer to you
because hey guess what the light source
went from being really big in your eyes
which is very bright to being very small
in your eye which is not very much light
at all right but that's not how you
think of brightness what you think of
brightness as is for the area of my eye
that this light is taking up how bright
is it and it just so happens that the
projection equation is the inverse of
the photons rent equation right my light
source over here that's shooting out
these photons right they are getting
smaller at 1 over d squared right but my
projection equation is doing the exact
opposite to the light source as I get
further away right it's shrinking it
down so the size of the light source is
going to be 1 over this distance squared
right so effectively you have to D
square is cancelling each other out yes
I have 1 over d squared the number of
photons but they're taking up 1 over D
squares the amount of space on my eye so
they still look exactly as bright
because I have that many fewer cells
receiving them right so here we get to
the first weird part about lights which
is that direct lighting a direct view of
a light is constant from any reasonable
distance
okay I don't care how far away from this
light you walk the only way you can make
it look any dimmer to you if you are in
a vacuum right in space is to get so far
away from it that your retina cells are
no longer at a sufficient resolution to
pick up the photons then it will start
looking dinner but until then it will
look through back same brightness and
the reason for that is the projection of
the size of the light onto your eye is
exactly the inverse equation of the
photon projection equation that's
spreading out the photons so they
perfectly cancel just as less photons
hit your eye you are trying to collect
them with less cells so the apparent
brightness is exactly the same right
okay so now let's talk about the next
thing that can happen in the real world
photons do not make it all the way to
your eye
here is my light source again do do and
here is my eye so Tom's launched out
from the light source they're trying to
get to the eye but what happens oops
it's something in the air just sad sad
for the photon right and what happens is
the photon hits the dust and it's
scattered in some direction right now
photons that would have hit the eye
cannot make it to the eye so some of
them hit right that happened to avoid
the dust some of them don't and there's
dust all throughout here right this is
called participating media and it
basically means that in most real-world
scenarios since the air even the
atmosphere itself has water droplets in
it and things like this can reflect life
in a lot of circumstances when we're
talking about
the lighting of things we can't even
really take it as literally as I just
said because even though it should be
the case that lights do not diminish
along a distance in the real world they
actually will and the reason that they
will is because things dust particles
air molecules that reflect the light are
in the way and that will affect your
perception of the brightness and this is
why if you get far enough away from the
light source or you look at it in dusty
room it will change the appearance of
that light source now one thing to keep
in mind is this doesn't necessarily mean
things will get dimmer sometimes it may
mean that things will get brighter and
the reason that they may get brighter is
because gas remember light is coming
from everywhere and can bounce in all
sorts of directions it maybe does a
participating media actually makes it
easier to see so for example let's say I
cut dense smoke right so like something
on fire
this is participating media that will
make light look dimmer when I try to
look at a light on the other side of the
smoke it will look dimmer or may black
it out entirely if the smoke is very
thick that is because that smoke is
absorbing the light it doesn't reflect
very much light so you don't get much in
the way of scattering that you can use
to collect some of that light source
it's basically just absorbing and
getting rid of it on the other hand you
may see on a hazy day right yes I look
out and I can't see the mountains in the
distance but it's very bright back there
why is it bright well it's because all
of this light is coming in from
elsewhere getting scattered toward me
that normally wouldn't so it may
actually be much brighter in that
direction than it should have been the
light from behind the mountains were
actually kind of dark-colored are
sitting the scene very much instead I
see much brighter and that's because all
of the sky incoming light and the Sun
and everything else they're getting
scattered back towards me in ways it
wouldn't otherwise have right
so again participating media really
changes things up and you have to sort
of start thinking about the properties
of the particles and how many there are
dense they are what kind of scattering
they're doing where the lights coming
from that's a much more complicated
situation right
but again relative to the relevant to
your understanding of light because
participating media will do that okay so
finally let's talk about the last bit of
of the problem which is the part that we
care probably most about in handmade
hero and that is reflection so basically
most light we see is reflected light
typically we're not staring directly at
something that's emitting photons right
that's uncommon and in fact you might
even say that typically when you're
looking at a lightbulb even that's not
really looking at something as emitting
photons because the photons that are
coming out of that lightbulb are
actually hitting a coated surface that
diffuses them more than they would
normally be diffused right typically we
don't look directly at the filament of a
lightbulb unless your gut artisinal
light bulbs which are increasingly
common in places like Seattle but I'm
pretty sure all right
anyway so uh in this case what we're
really concerned most about when we talk
about how things look is how light is
reflected how it's reflected off objects
how it's reflected off coatings on
things that like even if it's
translucent that's what determines most
of what we see because most of what we
see isn't emitters it's reflectors yeah
now I guess I should caveat that by
saying well maybe that's not true
anymore because a lot of times we look
computer screens all day and computer
screens are sort of emitters of light
source so maybe that's not exactly right
but you know oops
looking at the real world that doesn't
have a computer screen on it a good hold
okay so how do a reflection work well
reflection just works by saying all
right I've got a light source right and
I've got an eye and what happens is
photons get shot out that wouldn't
normally hit the light source right
here's my object so normally the side
wouldn't see them because they're going
to go this way right and it's not going
to feed those photons you know maybe
there are some photons that do shoot out
right that will hit the eye directly but
there's a bunch that won't however some
of these
it sounds going to hit the subject and
they get reflected back in a Provident
direction that happens to also hit the
eye right the lens of the eye and so
that is how we see most things that we
see is a photon has launched off of a
light source it's hit an object and it's
bounced into our eye that's how we even
know the objects there at all right it's
basically a flood of photons that's
bouncing off of things and we're seeing
the bounces right and you can even see
this for yourself if you've never done
this if you're in a very dark room that
drops below the sampling integration
ability of your eye to smooth out in a
very dark room you can actually see it
like very noisy it's very very noisy
right and the reason for that is you're
just not getting enough photons bouncing
off things for your eye to actually come
up with a solid estimate of what the
lighting is in that direction
right so it's varying wildly a second a
second as different numbers of photons
hit your eye from the same direction
normally when you have lots of light
that's that noise level of photons
because remember photons are randomly
spewing out all over the place right so
you're not getting a constant number of
photons hitting your eye every second
you're getting a very variable number
but that number variance is so small
compared to the magnitude so if you
looked at it right of brightness right
over time you're getting something like
you know like this so there's this tiny
wobble but the amount is so huge
compared to the wobble that your eye has
no trouble just filtering it and going
here is a constant color and so it
doesn't look noisy but when you're
weighed down here and you get that same
labo
you're going to magnify that part of the
graph and here's what we're looking at
now well all the sudden it looks like
this right because remember your eye is
adaptive and when things get darker
right it dilates the pupils to collect
more light and your your brain is trying
to like scale up the amount it uses for
a particular level of brightness you can
see now relative to the number of
photons hitting your eye right the noise
is really relevant it's drastically
changing the number of a parent photons
hitting your eye right so again random
photons just spewing out into the world
hitting things bouncing off hitting our
eyes that's how we see so now we have to
ask the question well how does all that
stuff we just talked about how does that
affect light that hits the surface of an
object right because that's we haven't
handmade here oh we've got all these
objects they're not emitting light
they're just reflecting light you know
how do we think about their illumination
properly well when things hit an object
what happens is that same inverse square
law applies right so however many
photons came out of this light source
when they hit this object right as the
object gets further away from the light
source the inverse-square number of
photons will be hitting its surface
right so the strength of a light source
again diminishes with one over the
square of the distance traveled to reach
the object that's the number of photons
that will hit it so the number of
photons that are reflected also this is
again proportional to one over the
distance squared of the object right now
keep in mind again it does not do 1 over
the distance squared to the eye for the
same reason as this object gets further
away from the eye it takes up less space
in the eye so the apparent brightness is
again you're concentrating the photons
on smaller numbers of cells so the
distance between the light and the
object changes its brightness because
less photons can be bounced off of it
but the distance back to the eyes from
the object not relevant does not affect
the brightness right should be critical
to understand and very strange right
when you don't it doesn't make quite
intuitive sense at first
okay so for our purposes that there is
an inverse-square follow up on lighting
if we want to be accurate now remember
accuracy is not our goal in handmade
hero it's just good to know what would
be correct when we go to do things but
that doesn't mean we will want an
inverse squared fall-off it doesn't mean
that we have to even do things like take
into account the distance from the light
source objects we can do whatever we
want right as long as it looks good
but it helps to understand how light
works so you can start there and work
backwards to something that looks like
what you want rather than going I have
no idea I'll just start making up
equations and then they don't really
look at all like light and you're kind
of confused so it's good to just
understand now what is going on there
so that is how light bounces off a
surface and what's worth noting about
surfaces is how they distribute light
makes a big difference as to how that
light will be perceived why is that the
case well let's talk a little bit about
reflectance functions and hopefully we
can see that why we care about that
right so here's the surface of an object
here's my light source and here's my eye
and look down at it I so let's say I
look at this surface here right and
again it here's my lens so I'm going to
look down at this point on the surface
and you can see that you know that lens
is going to collect everything in a cone
so from this particular point on the
object I'm actually getting everything
that bounced off and sort of like again
a conical sort of outpouring there if
you will so if we want to know what the
brightness of this surface would be at
this point what we basically are asking
is for any photons that could come into
the surface from any light sources from
anywhere how many of them would bounce
out along this cone
right that's the brightest and if we
care about things like the color and
that sort of stuff we would also want to
ask how do those photons change their
color like what color were they when
they came in how does the wavelength
shift when it hits this object blah blah
blah
right right now let's not care about
that we're just going to talk about the
brightness well the answer is surfaces
each have sort of a molecular structure
if you will at their surface boundary
that determines what will happen so you
have to imagine the surface isn't flat
no matter what it is it's actually like
a bunch of molecules bouncing around
right that are all held together in like
a lattice form or something like this
emits a solid object and what happens
when a photon comes in is it's going to
strike these things and bounce out right
if it's not absorbed it's going to
bounce these things and it's going to
screw down right and by the way I
shouldn't use the word absorbed I think
so I've been using this whole time
because in the graphics world we think
of it as absorption because it's
absorbing light but really it's probably
not absorbing light per se it's going to
go into heat energy or you know there's
the actual molecular activity of it is
not our concern
when I say absorb I don't mean to say
that it captures the photon in some
specific way that's clogged from dynamic
and all this other sort of stuff I don't
care about that and I don't know about
that all I'm trying to say is the light
gets absorbed from a lighting
perspective it will not bounce out but
what actually happens to it is a
physicists concern not ours
you know maybe it sort of knocks the
thing around and transfers its energy
and goes away or maybe it gets captured
in some way and released later or some
other forms like heat energy so it's
converted to IR wavelengths right the
point is from our perspective when we
say absorb what we mean is a photon at a
visible wavelength
struck an object and it never came back
that's all we know whether it translated
into heat or something else we don't
know we don't care or ultraviolet not
our responsibility but we know that it
didn't come back in the visible spectrum
and that's all we need to know for
lighting okay so what that means is that
the micro facet geometry of the surface
what happens to it at a molecular level
what it looks like changes how photons
reflect on an angular basis if the
surface is completely fair and will
reflect in a completely uniform way
which almost no surface is but there are
some that are quite close then what will
happen is a photon that comes in has an
equal chance of being reflected out in
any direction this is called a perfectly
diffused surface basically what it means
is that it's a completely random
collection of molecules on the surface
as far as reflection is concerned when
you kit you could go in any direction
completely randomly right that is not
the common case most surfaces are not
perfectly diffuse what is more likely is
the micro facet geometry and let me draw
something for you there what that means
is that for an incident photon the lobe
right coming in at this direction is
perfectly uniform it could go out in
every direction right so photon comes
out in here it has an equal chance of
going out in every possible direction
from the surface right that is not the
common case the common case is that it's
biased so the light comes in right and
yeah it may come out in a lot of
directions but it's actually strongly
sort of biased in the direction that's a
perfect reflection or something or maybe
not a perfect reflection but so it could
back scatter and often does but it more
often goes out in these other directions
right so it's more
likely and the way you draw these lobes
right is these lives that people draw
are just ways of saying oh here is sort
of the distribution it's basically like
taking a graph of percentage chance the
photon will go off in a direction and
wrapping it around the angle that it
will go out right so if it's if the lobe
is further out in this direction it
means there's a higher chance if it's
closer in there's a lesser chance right
now remember this is a completely
four-dimensional function the angle that
you go out at is determined by the angle
you come in at and of course it's three
dimensions so there's two angles right
so we have to think about this for every
possible incident angle you can see why
this is a pretty complicated function
these are four D functions at a minimum
they're actually worse than that in the
real world because they think about what
actually happens is a four D is only
four point reflectors and really what
happens in the real world is most
surfaces do not bounce things off
directly from their surface most of them
have some depth at the photon comes in
it travels around and then comes back
out later what that means
is that the point of impact is also a
parameter so it's really 60 it's the 2d
parameter on the surface where the light
came in and and then where it bounces
out right so it's pretty nasty it and
really just might not even be the right
way to think about it point being it's
worse than 40 because you basically have
scattering that happens inside the
surface so typically I think if you if
you try to do this really accurately you
don't try to wrap it up in one function
what you do is you have a penetration
function that basically says when I hit
the surface of this what direction do I
go in right and that's a probability
then when I go in I actually simulate
bouncing around in here so I do several
bounces interior till I strike the
surface again when I strike the surface
again I have a function that says what
direction I emanate and then I go out
and that's the full simulation heaven
help you right
so anyway there you go
so all that lighting stuff again worth
knowing and I we covered this we did
some lighting way way way back on
handmade here but it's been so long ago
I just want to refresh everything that
is the basis of lighting hopefully
everything is a you know paged back in
for you here but that is essentially how
to think about the light as it travels
around the world now there's some more
complicated stuff that goes on in here
as well that have to do with the cosine
fell off there's the there's sort of
this concept that as I think about
lighting that falls onto a surface if it
if it's coming down straight versus this
coming down an angle the shaft of light
is truncated based on the cosine of the
angle that it's coming down at which is
again not something I think we'll end up
having deal with in hand-made here but
it's another micro facet element that
affects if you're trying to produce
accurate lighting equations it's
something to be aware of but basically
all that is just saying well you can
imagine if I've got photons coming down
into surface and they're coming directly
down at the surface then the whole
surface you know the whole sort of
amount of photons hitting will bounce
back the width of this is on the bounce
is exactly what it is on the incidence
right but on the other hand if I take
that and I shoot it at it this way right
what you can see is hopefully here
what you can see is the same number of
photons coming in at this angle spread
out on unfortunately a much wider angle
right so what ends up happening is that
this area here the hypotenuse here right
the cosine of that hypothesis test good
hypothesis of that hypotenuse is
actually the amount of light that is
incoming there right and the same would
be true for reflection so when it's
going out in angle you have a cosine
whatever the surface area passed you're
working with you have a cosine term that
says how big the outgoing shaft is by
comparison to how far how much it was on
the surface so at a micro level what
this leads to is you end up having a lot
of cosine terms of you're letting
equations if you're trying to simulate
them correctly because you have to model
the fact that the light falling onto a
surface and then getting bounced back
out is undergoing this cut off for a
particular pixel you know however much
the element sizes that you're trying to
simulate on that sample all right so all
that stuff is again not something we're
really concerned with I hand me here I
just want to make sure you've got the
basics again I think we covered it let
me know what day we covered it on
Niblo says d 96 or 97 so day 96 or 97
back there somewhere there's another set
of this hopefully between the two of
these those I've hopefully gotten
everything that you need to know on that
out there sometimes I forget things so I
don't know hopefully it's the case but
now let's talk about what we might want
to do in hammer here so on handmade here
we have a couple of choices right but
basically the main thing we care about
with our life is we're going to have in
our world right we're going to have some
light sources like maybe there's a
campfire or something like this probably
not a campfire but let's say there was
there's campfire or something and we
want the player to see sort of some
shading some lighting happening in the
region of the campfire now there's two
ways that we can do this right the most
straightforward simple artistic way to
do it is to literally just bright you
know have the brightness occur within
radii or something like this and so it's
basically sort of like a almost like a
sphere that you splat down that just
makes things brighter and you see this
in a lot of games especially if they
don't if they're sprite games because
it's harder to do much better in sprite
games but let's see here so here is
stardew valley at night
and what you can see in star devalue at
night is here's two torches and another
let me let me make that fullscreen their
release I don't need to start a value
review I just want to do the image thank
you
so here's star D value at night right
and again this is you know it's a XM a
game I think if I'm not very much
mistaken it doesn't have it really any
concept of what's going on in 3d so it
has to do something to give you the
sense of lighting at nighttime so what's
going to do and what you can see here is
all they do is they just take a region
around the right of the light and they
color that region and any region that is
not around the light is darker right it
darkens and this is pretty effective
right it works and it doesn't require
anything special now it has obvious
problems with it in terms of what you
might want as a nice effect and what you
can see is there's clearly reflections
painted into the bitmap part of the
light you can see that the light is
brighter here for example and that is
completely wrong so you can see that's
this light like this is the light source
right here the reflection is as if the
light was coming from here it's
completely wrong here is the closest
light here the reflections came from up
here there isn't even a light coming
from up there right so it's I guess
maybe the moonlight but you know that's
much weaker than this so you can kind of
see that like it just it's completely
wrong like objects don't respond to the
light correctly at all and if the player
was trying to use the light sources as a
way of determining the shapes of these
objects it would completely fail right
but fortunately that's not what humans
do humans understand approximations like
this so this works just fine and they
understand that this is a rock shape
because it's representatively shaded
this way even though that's not the way
it would have been shaded and yeah it
doesn't add to the sense of atmosphere
and lighting so you get less of an
effect that it doesn't respond in the
right way
me but it still works just fine and so
something like that is probably more of
what we'll have to do on handmade hero
because again we don't have 3d geometry
for most of our stuff they're just
sprites so we don't really have a lot of
information about how they would reflect
again I'll show you another picture here
of the simplest case right and it's just
again everywhere there's a light source
there's just sort of this this flap of
light there and that's it now you can do
something faster than this obviously if
you take a look at say stuff where
you've got a where you have a normal map
and so what that involves is basic thing
we've got a normal map on top of our
sprite then what you can do is you can
sort of relight the sprites to a certain
degree and you know you can see what
this looks like if you take a look at
say something like sprite lamp which is
just a tool that people use for creating
these you can kind of see that you get
right on a 2d surface you can move the
light around and by using the normal map
to relight it you can kind of get
something that sort of maybe looks like
it's getting lit
sort of right now the problem with this
is just that it's not great like you
know it it maybe gives you a better
sense that whether it's artistically
better or not is kind of hard to say
really
it's it's it you know it's a bit of
personal preference I guess I would say
sometimes it looks better sometimes it
looks worse it probably depends it's
probably in the eye of the beholder
whether that's good or bad and again
even that is only talking about inside
particular sprites getting some
curvature information in there for the
lighting but it doesn't really
even help with shadowing and stuff like
that because that's not really you know
again you still don't know like when we
run handmade hero if we want to do some
lighting in here we have the problem of
well what do we do - shadow things if a
lights on one side of somebody how much
shadow - the cast in the other direction
bla bla bla bla all right uh so let's
start with star G Valley style lighting
because it's the easiest pop of the
lighting right the easiest possible
lighting to do is we just have splats of
light and they're completely
indiscriminate so they just light things
in a radius right so how would we do
that
well we would start by saying we need a
light direction and all this hard code
the light Direction directly in this
rate are sorry light position all it's
hard code the light position in the
shader and then we can always just pass
it down later right so let's go ahead
and say that we've got the light in the
shader and that'll be you know a v3
light cause and the light pause is going
to be let's just say it's at zero zero
zero for now of course they don't
actually know where zero zero zero
actually is but I guess we'll find out
and then we're going to need another
thing which is going to be I guess the
light strength because we need some
concept of how strong the light is
because the FIR been a comp computer a
fall off for our light we need to know
how much how strong it is to begin with
right what we need to know we need to
have some notion of how strong it is to
begin with so let's go ahead and say
that we have a light strength I'll set
to 1.0 for now which again is unitless
we don't have any real unless we
actually go and try to simulate physical
lighting at which point we would be
talking about lumens or something like
this we don't really have any way other
than just sort of approximately saying
we're going to come up with a brightness
scheme for our game that's completely
arbitrary right
so we have a light Frank that a light
pause that come in here and then what we
want to do is we want to have a way of
taking the color values that we see and
modulating them properly by whatever
that light strength actually is so the
first step to that is finding out how
far away the light is and so what we
want to do there is say well whatever
our actual position in the real world is
we want to take the distance to the
light source and so we're going to do
that we need to do our 3d position and
we don't really know our 3d position
right all we get here is our fragment
coordinate so if you take a look at what
we actually want to know here we
probably want to go ahead and add a
thing here that's like smooth out v3
world pose or something like that right
and so these in vertices are coming in
here right they're getting transformed
by stuff and that transform is a full
transform that we don't actually want
anything to do with at the moment right
so what we want to do is we want to have
some way of getting the world's position
in here and we can assume I think since
we don't use transforms to move things
around our vertex positions are actually
in world space I'm pretty sure that's
the case it could be wrong about that
we'll have to go back and check but I'm
pretty sure that's the case in fact no I
know that's the case so the transfer
doesn't get set for them so if we were
just to output the world position all we
really need to do here is say ok there's
a world position it just gets written
out directly so the world pose is just
the input pose right it's just whatever
we started with and we just don't care
about the W value right now since our
trees use that the bias thing I guess
really technically what we want to do is
use the V vertex version and I think
about it because we do want to account
for the V bias I guess because we want
lighting to change as it gets higher so
really we want to use with V vertex as X
Y Z I think that's what we actually want
so that's our world position and it
comes out we can then say we've got our
smooth in
Veck three also but now we know where in
the world each pixel actually is
supposed to be and so we can figure out
how far away it is right I don't
remember I have to do this computation
myself but I'm pretty sure it's actually
built in so I'm going to just double
check that it is don't quote me on that
oops that's es I don't want yes and I
don't want yes I want GLSL spec where is
it just it Jeolla so oh you know what I
want quick reference cards that's sorry
I typed the wrong thing that's what I
wanted all right so here's all the
geometric functions we have and look our
thing I believe yet there is I was gonna
say I believe this is something I can
just ask for directly and I can because
you know we could just write it
ourselves but we want to use these
built-ins when we can usually because
the graphic card is presumably going to
insert the code that's most optimal for
it
so there's distance right there so I can
just use the light distance is just
distance the world closed and the light
pose and that's it right now I know how
far away the light is and I can use one
over that to compute the distance so all
I should have to do there is say well
okay my light the lighting value here is
just going to be the light strength
divided by the light distance squared
and that would be inverse all off right
and that's the lighting so if I then
want to darken everything I can just
multiply by that value and iron Theory
should get a thing that lights in
fear around this light don't know if I
will or not but in theory I should where
is my heir fixer compilers oh I'm sorry
I didn't mean say that oops
yeah didn't mean to put that there was
complaining there was a missing can I
call him there didn't quite do it in the
most clear terms but that's what it was
um so what you can see here is we've got
our light sources centered at the origin
and it does exactly what you would
expect right it lights things in a
sphere around it and it looks like a
light all right and like I think before
it's surprising how little your eye uses
the reality of the cue it's it's a
completely incorrect light I mean this
space that's facing directly at the
light versus this face that's facing Oh
perpendicular to the light they don't
respond properly this one should be much
brighter this one should be much darker
because of the way most typical
real-world reflection functions work and
yet that is not at all what we get
instead what we get is something that
the eye still interprets as a light
emanating from that area even though
completely wrong right and this is why I
say you know it's worth understanding
the basics of light because then as you
need more from them you will know how to
get that that mourneth of that's more
but you typically will be very surprised
at how forgiving the viewer is of
complete incorrect results as long as
they have some basis in the properties
of light gamers have been looking at
wrong lighting for so long that they are
very used to it to say the least
um so you know that's a obviously a very
simple light source and a very simple
way to add some lighting to the scene
let's try making that be something
that's a little more systemic so what we
could do right if you think about how if
we wanted more lights we can add more
lights but it starts to get expensive
right if we wanted to sum up the
lighting in this area you could imagine
it would start to look kind of costly as
we start to do this if we created a
second light then we're doing more
distance calculations and we end up with
this sort of thing so here I'm going to
create a brighter light and I'm going to
move it a little bit off to the side it
might not be far enough to the side it's
not
so there you've got two lights right
that you can see and the one of the
center is not as bright as the one on
the side but they sum together properly
in between them and stuff and off we go
now we could do all our lighting this
way if we wanted to we could push all
the lighting into the cosmos door and
you know off we would go however you
know the question is is that the most
efficient way to do it and you know the
it's a difficult question it might be
the most efficient way to do it
certainly for a small number of light
sources it would be the most efficient
way to do that for as that number of
light sources get larger though it
becomes too expensive potentially and
what we might want to do is pre compute
the lighting first into something like a
voxel grid or something like this and
then just sample the lighting where we
actually are in the world at that time
right that tends to be the kind of thing
that might be a little bit easier to do
because then it prevents us from having
to have like you know 20 light sources
summed for every pixel we draw so I
don't know so it's so that of course is
a tough question because it is something
that concerns how we're going to handle
lighting in sort of a structural way I'm
not going to dive into that today maybe
that's something we'll talk about a
little more tomorrow but what I want to
talk about today now is okay so now that
we know that we're going to compute some
lighting this way what else might we do
here to improve the quality of the
lighting a little bit so the first thing
we could do is we could start to take a
look at sort of the facing direction of
these surfaces in in some way that would
allow us to
actually respond to the light
differently depending on how we're
facing right so you know I gotta be
honest I'm not sure I mean I guess for
our cubes it's easy to understand
because our cubes are actually 3d
geometry so we can talk about how the
light should really bei went when it
hits the cube for our for our sprites
it's a little trickier but I suppose
still fine for our sprites since our
sprites are facing only one direction in
a sense and by one direction I mean to
band One Direction
you know just absolutely fabulous some
of some of the best music really
pinnacle of mankind's new school
achievements it's like you know it's
like Mahler and then and then one
direction but that's getting sort of off
into a different situation but anyway so
here you know I wonder what just I'm
just looking at it what should the
lighting do on this and I'm guessing you
know we probably want something where we
want to treat it as just a flat card I
guess and say well if I'm on this side
of the light source I should be
reflecting the light if I'm on this side
of the light source I shouldn't and my
my character should be darker right my
carrot my character should be reflecting
less less light I think
but either way what this basically says
is in order to start treating this
lighting a little bit more reasonably
what we need to do is have some way of
some way of taking that lighting and
testing what direction the you you know
what the the facing direction of the
services versus the light and so what is
what is that transom you light well
there's two separate things or
transferring light there so let's take
the first one
here's my cube here's the eye and here's
the light actually let's make the leg a
little higher okay so if we imagine
hitting this surface here and the light
hitting this surface here what you can
see is there's a reasonable reflection
path for something that's facing you
know this face of that of the cube which
is like sort of the the face of the cube
there right whereas the face of the
qubits facing effort it's a really tough
road to hoe right when both when the the
the light source is so oblique to the
cube like this most of the light for a
normal lighting function is going to
reflect that light out this way and very
literate little of the light is going to
back scatter on a typical surface like
that very little of the light is going
to back scatter back to the eye right so
a perfect mirror you know if it was a
perfect mirror surface nothing comes
back that way basically the only thing
that comes back that way is stuff that
comes in from over here and there's no
light out here the lights come from over
here right for a perfect mirror and as
the surface gets more diffuse it has to
get up to an incredibly high level of
diffusion before it's going to kick much
light out this way and even once it does
now we get into the cosine theta term
problem here that we were talking about
before where it's like as this light
shines in here and as its passes out
this way the actual portion of a light
shaft that can go out in that direction
from something that hits is going to
have the
I'm term in there right because what's
going to happen here is if we imagine
the light shaft coming in however much
light is coming in right if we call this
RL that's going to get spread onto this
big of a surface and then the amount
that's actually going to go out in that
direction same diagram right if we want
to know I guess let's say the outgoing
reflection here same difference right
the amount of light that comes from a
unit of the surface is going to go out
proportional to the cosine of the angle
to that surface right so that means as
you get really oblique this cosine term
right as as that angle gets get steeper
and steeper the amount of light that can
come out from there diminishes to
basically zero right as you get
perfectly down so again really kind of
tricky there there's just a lot at play
so what we would expect though again is
whatever lighting function we come up
with here it's probably going to take
into account the angle there and it's
probably going to want to become dimmer
as you get facing away from the light
source right or rather you know the
surface as the surface becomes that
oblique to the light source especially
if the light source is on the other side
of it there is a weird property of light
where if you happen to be going like
this where the light is perfectly on the
other side as you get to really bleak
angle it tends to just graze off the
surface and it's most services are
actually really bright reflectors in
this way so the light was over here
you'd actually get quite a bit of it if
you don't believe me on that one you can
do something weird if you take a piece
of paper and you look at a light source
really just glancing along the paper
what you can see is you get a very
bright reflection
I can really do this paper consol folded
then I'm going to look at the light
source here you get almost a mirror as
you get to like the perfectly 90-degree
angle it's very very bright along the
paper right whereas if I just bring the
paper down a little bit it's much darker
so like as you get to that perfect
glancing angle it's it's pretty darn
good
it's almost yeah if it's almost like the
surface of water right there if you look
at a piece of paper so a lot of services
they get very reflective right at that
point where the light is just grazing
off them but again we don't really care
about that so we can ignore that for now
so what we would have to do if we want
to start taking into account angular
issues is we need to start passing in
what's called a surface normal and a
surface normal is just a fancy way of
saying that we want to start passing in
information about how the surfaces are
facing what direction they're facing
right and so what we want to do is say
hey this is a flat surface it's facing
that direction right this is the flat
surface was facing that direction so we
just need something a vector that tells
us what direction it's facing so for
every vertex we pass in we can just pass
in a vector that says this is the
direction that the surface is facing
right it's pretty easy to do but it
would it would require us again to sort
of augment how we're doing things
unfortunately we've I think set
ourselves up to make that not be
particularly difficult right so if we
were to take a look at our vertex here
extra vertex if we want to do we can
just add a normal vector in here right
and that normal vector just a
three-dimensional vector
it just is going to say what direction
the surface is pointing it'd be pretty
trivial for us to add that right there's
nothing very difficult about that at all
so if I was to go
find where we're writing these out which
is in our render group what you can see
is we've kind of nicely isolated
everything down the only place we do
anything with it is in this push blog
function here right and so what we would
have to do is augment this push squad
function to somehow figure out what
these normals are right now we can
actually just pass the normals down and
that may well be what we want to do
eventually but if we don't mind spending
a little extra computational multiplying
here we can actually produce normals
without that in the first place right if
we assume all our triangles are supposed
to be coming from flat objects which
they are at the moment right then what
we know is if we're given three vertices
or in this case four vertices because of
the quad then really we actually know
remember the cross product remember that
guy we have this idea that if you cross
a vector a with a vector B you'd get a
vector perpendicular to it right well
all we would have to do is pick three of
these vertices produce the two vectors
and cross them and we would get the
normal right that's all we would have to
do because the cross products gives us a
perpendicular vector if we want a arrow
pointing out of our triangle it's pretty
easy to get so what we could do is say
you know what
[Applause]
let's just go ahead and produce the
cross product of you know two of these
now we want this to be in the direction
you can see the triangle right and
remember we were talking about the right
hand rule so we know that if we if we
have a triangle that's wound
counterclockwise which is how we round
our triangles and we know that this is
going to go like 0 1 2 for example right
then what we want to do is make sure
that we cross in this direction so the
normal comes out pointing us remember
right hand rule curl your fingers from
the vector a to the vector B and your
thumb is pointing out if it use your
right hand your thumb is pointing out
towards the direction the normal the
results the cross product right so we
want P 1 minus p 0 and p 2 minus p 0
right looking at that diagram we want to
do the cross of those true and that will
give us our normal now of course
remember our normal is actually not
quite right yet because one of the
things that we're going to want to do
with this normal probably since we're
going to use it in letting equations
we're going to need to do things like
that product is so on so forth on it so
one of the reasons we want when we're
producing our surface normals one of the
reasons we often call them normals is
because we want them to be normalized so
we want them to be unit length right so
since we know that the cross product
will actually produce something that's
the length of a time's the length of B
right this is not going to be a normal
it's not going to normalize like we knew
unit length but we can just normalize it
that since we have that we can do that
like this I forgot these are four
dimensional
[Applause]
oops so that will actually produce a
normal for us and now that normal will
be correct and I can put it to do here
[Applause]
let me pass down the normal there is
sort of a caveat there I guess to which
is that when we do this subtraction if
we want to compute this correctly
that's device value that's in the W that
gets added to the Z we should probably
add it first right so probably what we
want to do here is we want to do
something a little bit more Safi in a
sense right we probably want to do
something like this which is like edge
one zero is this an edge to zero is this
right so what we probably want to do
here is when we do this subtract we're
going to get an additional Z value out
of it right so we probably want to do
the Z bias here so that we will properly
produce the normal for things that are
four as if the things were actually
there's biased Z right which I think
this will do properly I'd have to think
about it we'll check it a little bit
more carefully later but there you go
right so there's the surface normal and
now that's getting stored right so now
we're writing out that surface normal
and we have it in our vertices what that
means is we can pop back to our OpenGL
now and we can say that that surface
normal is something that we can handle
in our
common set so what we can do here is
take a look at this we do use program
begin we can say there's now an NRA and
there's a normal ID and then we're just
going to use that exact like everything
else so I will say NRA and that's really
all there is to it right I we only three
long one of the things we want to do
here with that normal is we want to like
I said set it up so we also got to take
it down so this will unset it and then
the other thing we got to do is when we
actually get the uniform locations
let's see where that's happening there
it is
[Applause]
so it looks like we did this manually
every time what we do
so why do we do that manually every time
does anybody know why we do that manual
every time like why wouldn't we just do
that in OpenGL create program I feel
like we just should right I mean doesn't
that seem like a more reasonable thing
to do so we can opengl create program
right why don't we just do this like
OpenGL create program and then it takes
one of these things here and so then you
don't return anything you just say get
all the stuff
I don't know why I didn't call that vert
n I probably should have Virtanen but
that seems a lot saner to me so I think
I'm just going to do that okay and then
we found our OpenGL create program here
now and I think we can just get rid of
all of this stuff so basically result
common is now going to be written into
directly and this thing only has to get
the stuff it's actually specific to it
what's the problem cannot convert from
void to why isn't this wrapping anymore
it's weird that from void to gluant yes
that's correct
[Applause]
clog handles yeah all right so that's
just cleaner I think and you know what I
could still return the Frog handle as
well just to make things a little easier
there's no reason not to I guess as so
we can still return program IDs
and this goes away sort of all that code
[Applause]
so now in theory we should have that
array getting submitted but in theory
unless they mess something up and I
obviously did Oh God
I was going to say it shouldn't do
anything because nobody's looking for it
yet right or at least they should not be
looking for it yet I don't even want to
know what just happened there because
nothing should have happened there right
because we're not touching that array at
all so I'm not sure why it would be
upset about it why the class should not
have had any effect on anything at least
not that I could think of
we make sure I mess something up in the
create program there we go so the
program handle is getting set properly
the it's attribute locations are in
theory getting queried here and set I'm
going to step in to use program begin
[Applause]
just to see if anything looks weird
that all looks totally normal
[Applause]
so I have no idea why that's unhappy
it doesn't seem like it should be
I must have mistyped something somewhere
[Applause]
because we always use textured vertex ah
that's the problem right there
[Applause]
one of those reasons I really do wish
that C had a way of bulk initializing
things more cleanly right I would have
liked that to have been able to say
which one of these I was specifying you
know which I think they do in more
modern versions now have but anyway this
doesn't have normals so we need to
insert in here see where's the other
third is you need to insert in here
space for the normals so that we can
still set the other elements there we go
okay so let's go ahead and go to the QA
we have prepared ourselves for tomorrow
where we will have normals for doing a
little bit more with our lighting but
let's go ahead and go to Q&amp;A for now
or the lighting of the sprites do you
need to compensate for the angle offset
if is it using the same light source as
the terrain
I don't think I understand the question
we do for or for the normals right we do
want to take into account the fact that
the sprites are sort of standing upright
and we will we are doing that by using
the WZ bias offset part of that in doing
the normal calculation at the moment so
in theory we are going to be taking that
into account if that's what you mean but
if that's not what you mean I'm not sure
SF Gartner says there seems to be a lot
of banding around the lights actually no
that is not the twitch encoding there
just is a lot of banding around the
lights and I don't know exactly what the
banding is from but I would assume well
I don't know what I would assume there's
a couple different things that can be
from right and I would guess some of it
may have to do with the precision at
which things are computed because that
can change but I don't actually know so
it could actually just be because of the
fact that we don't have enough color
resolution
in theory I would expect that to not be
so banded unless those are actually the
so here's one thing I will say it is at
least theoretically plausible to me that
the internal precision of the buffer
that we store back to is not sufficient
and so when we square an unsquare later
it's a problem let me just test
something really quickly to see if
that's the case but the short answer is
I'm not sure that I've investigated yet
I couldn't tell you what it is
[Applause]
so this right here OpenGL default frame
buffer texture format
in it we set it to RGB a8 and then if we
allow we set to srgb alpha 8 so what we
can do here if we want to is we could
try setting this to an actual higher
depth right so we could try some kind of
a deeper frame buffer to see what
happens to the banding and I don't see I
don't see any improvement to the banding
there
so I mean I would assume that it's some
kind of a math precision problem but I
don't know
we've defined where it is so we can set
it to full a full floating-point frame
buffer which is you know in theory way
more than we could possibly need and see
if we still get the banding but yeah so
I still see the banding there so we've
got some other problem right it's not
that which is you know I just wanted to
double-check but yeah I don't know what
the bandings from it it's possible I
suppose let me also check just to make
sure I'll try to see what the actual
pixel values are there it may be that
the banding is actually just unavoidable
in terms of that's the color that's the
level of color you get an 8-bit and in
order to avoid it we have to differ
right which you might want to do but
let's find out so here is a boundary
between two of them so I'm taking this
this upper one here tonight because that
stay open while I do this no doesn't
seem to actually work so there's the
upper one it's 26 4026 here's the lower
one twenty-five thirty nine twenty five
so it's pretty much that that says much
as that is the color resolution of 8-bit
. right so the only way we could get rid
of that banding unfortunately is to
deter the output which to be honest I
don't remember what you'll turn on we
should have been able to if if we use
the higher resolution back buffer
it should deter on display normally so
I'm not sure why it wasn't we don't
that's not we that's not the good three
I'm talking about all right so I just
don't know
[Applause]
I don't know if this is the case or not
like I just don't know
so yeah I don't know about this let me
just see I'll I'll try turning this on I
know I'm going to have to like spend
more time finding out about exactly how
we get it to get there the final frame
buffer down but assuming we set this to
RGB a 16 so that our you know
intermediate services have more
resolution than eight bits you should be
able to get to disser unresolved I don't
actually know though what the correct
way to do that is I do not remember what
the OpenGL magic sauce is to make that
happen I mean we could implement it
ourselves as well to which maybe we
should do but
so here is our final blitt right it's
right here so right before we do this
we're we're actually drawing to the
final frame buffer I can try just seeing
if telling it to use this in there helps
I don't know that it will yeah it
doesn't so we're going to have to look
up if we want to get rid of that banding
we're going to have to look up how to
force it to differ
let's see flying silences as our hero
does not represent the actual hero that
save our lives every day all over the
world I took the liberty and made some
corrections to the game art that was
what okay miss Kipps that one - yo cat
what kind of rendering pipeline does
this use forward deferred or both well
it's it's forward but it's a desk filled
renderer which is unusual it's pretty
bizarre um we may in the future want to
do something with deferred maybe but
probably not
I don't think we're going to need to so
it's forward with depth feeling at the
moment crammed 7 it's a debug text being
lighted yes at the moment it is use
sampler with Shift key pressed to get
info window Oh in you mean I'll
have to do that I missed a little line
showing the current file name inside for
critter it was easier to follow that way
yeah I don't use that anymore but I
could try to compile a special for coder
custom for that if you want to remind me
if someone want to send me an email to
remind me to do that I'll do that I'll
build one of my other machine
Arif 86 how expensive it will be if the
light source is moving for example
following the torch the hero could be
carrying or the flying light projectile
well right now the lighting doesn't care
where it is so it's no more expensive to
have it move than then to have it be
stationary right so this gives it's free
to have it follow the here around
basically all we do is change that value
in the constant store right and then the
light moves so because we're not using
any pre computed lighting at the moment
I think code or update code Excel it
will not be able to step into the shader
but you should be able to see the open
till state I don't know I think I'm
going to uninstall code Excel because it
makes Visual Studio not work anymore I
will at least need to uninstall the
Visual Studio you're a part of it I
think
uh all right so I think that's it stream
has ended
I will be back here tomorrow for sure
because we got more lighting to do but
for now I think we'll just call it it'd
be interesting yeah we'll have to take a
look at what we can do about the banding
oh I forgot right since those lights are
just absolute they will as we move down
as the world wreath centers since we
always render around the camera in terms
of coordinates as the world.we centers
the light moves that's cool that's
really cool
awesome alright
anyway um alright so I'm going to wind
it down
yeah thank you very much for joining me
for the episode of handmade hero for the
pleasure coating with you as always if
you would like to follow along theories
at home you can always peer to the game
on handmade hero org and it comes with
source code so you could do your own
experimentation with it we also have
forms that you can go to if you want to
ask questions a patreon page if you want
to support the video series a schedule
bot you can go to if you want to know
one we're going to be live and an
episode guide for catching up on old
episodes that's it for today I'll be
back here tomorrow I believe I said it'd
be noon tomorrow noon Pacific Daylight
Time
until then we'll probably be doing just
putting in the normal stuff and maybe
we'll take a look at that death ring as
well if we can figure out a good way to
open Jill together for us that's about
it until then have fun programming and
I'll see you on the Internet take these
everybody