hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero
lighting edition uh we are going to
today take a look at
the last sort of the last thing that i
think is a quality issue with the
lighting we
just kind of have
um a
we we've we've got some pretty good
stuff here uh
it looks really good the lighting i
think is high quality but
when we look at just right around single
bright light sources
it's just not a very high quality um
a high quality result
it's very like squary and also a little
bit uh irregular and this is the best
case scenario when we've cranked up sort
of
uh the bounce level so this is you know
that this is a number that we could
easily do on the on the gpu right now
we're off cpu side only so it's a little
bit slower frame rate than it should be
if we were going to try and roll out
something
like this exactly but
um
you know even even if we want to talk
about just cpu side what we can do right
now
it's actually quite good if we drop this
down
you know to like eight
uh instead of 16
samples
you know raise per per texel there
you can see that we get a really smooth
frame rate here
uh and it actually looks quite good
everywhere else so so just
those small moving light sources right
they're just not
good enough in my opinion
and they definitely have that like made
with unity personal learning edition
kind of vibe to them right
um and it would be nice you know because
the idea here is to do some reasonable
quality engine programming it would be
nice if we could get uh rid of that
because it's it makes the rest of the
lighting not look as good right it's
like a it's a quality
uh it's like a polished quality step
down you know what i'm saying
uh and so i guess i would say what we
want here i think is to look at ways to
mitigate that and we looked at some
uh ways of trying to improve it last
time and they really weren't sufficient
and i don't think they're going to work
long term so i i thought about it over
the week
as i often do kind of just like in the
back of my head while i'm doing regular
work sometimes i think uh about handmade
hero stuff uh because it just pops in
and what i was thinking is that
i originally said maybe once you know
you you probably remember me actually
literally saying this i was like what if
we instead of you know everything right
now
light probes cast rays and they hit
things in this case there's a light
hovering above the hero's head that we
were using for testing right now
uh and the
the rays from the various light probes
they hit that thing
and that's how they know uh that there's
a that there's light that they should
represent
and that works quite nice for diffuse
like gather right
uh
they in all of these scenarios when you
look at where the light's getting
gathered everywhere else um this
actually looks quite good right
and the reason that it looks quite good
is because of the exact inverse of what
normally happens
with forward lighting
like the kind you would see if you just
use light source with shadow maps
what you see is the lighting quality
looks very high looks very convincing
and good
in areas where there's a lot of light
coming from
a lot of different directions
that's what makes indirect like this
global illumination
it's what it does really well what it
doesn't do very well is that part where
you just have the direct light source
shining
right on
a particular thing um
and that is this scenario uh in a
nutshell right what we've got here is a
small fast-moving light source
um and it just doesn't produce the same
kind of like nice results uh that you
would expect
there's also a fair bit of flicker that
comes from these lights because again
since they uh since it is a small light
and it's in a wide area and there's not
much other light around right
you get more of that sampling noise we
could try to take that out with better
sampling uh more focused sampling
various things
but to me that is actually not a problem
so to me that you can just chalk up
um too
effectively like
oh that's just you know
the lights are a little flickery right
it looks atmospheric almost
so to me i'm not really concerned if
that was the problem if that was the
only problem we were looking at i'd call
it done i'm like i'm fine with that as
an artistic thing
i'm not worried about that at all it
does not ruin the look of the game at
all to me what ruins the look of the
game for me is this
this bit right
um
that is just not quite good enough to me
it just looks very square and weird
and more importantly in a way that's not
actually the case
anywhere else so you know when you look
at these kind of larger more diffused
lights over here
um and you know elsewhere in the game
you just don't get like that's not
happening right uh everything else looks
softer it looks nicer it looks cleaner
and then you get into you know to here
and it just looks really ugly and square
so
that's really the thing that concerns me
and so what i said last time
well maybe one thing we could do is we
could try rasterizing light sources
forward like
instead of of strictly you know being uh
um
you know you know
instead of exclusively having light
probes cast rays backwards and hit light
sources and sample them
what if we did a forward pass where each
light source would walk through
uh the squares it overlapped
and it would write its lighting directly
in
so it wouldn't have to
uh actually
it wouldn't need to do that part of the
process
where it you know
we wouldn't need to worry about the fact
that it's hard to sample a small light
source
because that's basically what's going on
here it's like this light is like
missing
entirely like none of you know we're not
getting any light contribution here
not because this light might wouldn't
necessarily contribute here
but just because this light source
itself
is probably never getting hit by any of
the rays just accidentally right
so even though uh that light source and
i can make that a little bit more
explicit like if i go in here um
and
we
you know
turn on the spatial grid
um
drawing
uh and then wait for it to like the
compiler to finish and there you go
um we should be able to turn on drawing
of light sources and see them you know
what i'm saying and uh
honestly i guess i don't know
not sure like exactly what we're drawing
here um
[Music]
so i think that's actually the emitter
right that light i think is actually the
emitter uh it's it's quite low to the
ground that's probably another reason
why these things are not seeing it
easily if it was up higher uh that might
not be a problem i wonder what it would
look like up higher this is not really
what i was expecting to see
um
but i guess that's where we placed it
maybe we should fix that first because
that's also maybe a little misleading
since i thought
it was a little higher up but either way
still i think we're going to have the
same problem it's just that's
interesting i wonder if that's why it's
a little bit more exaggerated uh than
the other light sources
maybe it is i don't know let's find out
um so in here when we add the the light
this is us adding the light here
and um
yeah i guess you know normally you would
probably expect to have seen something
elevating it off the ground like like
here
uh and and we didn't so when the player
got added it didn't it didn't actually
do that um so that's interesting uh so
so now
uh it should be a little higher up i
think yeah there we go it's like you
know on the on the hero's head right
uh and we could we could put it even
maybe a little higher than that
um hmm
so that is a bit interesting i
i guess that was somewhat surprising i
wasn't necessarily expecting that
um
that's interesting so if we now look
actually you can see that that the fact
that it was lower to the ground was
actually a pretty big deal with the in
terms of
how square the lighting was uh which is
interesting
and so i guess maybe that was a bit
misleading
like uh i didn't quite realize that that
we had
um
i didn't quite realize that that was
contributing as much as it was it
actually looks a lot better
uh in in this way
maybe you know if that was it you
wouldn't really be that concerned so
um
gosh i don't know does that mean we
should just move on like that would be
fine developing the game that way and
then maybe i still do a little bit of
fixing at the end but that's
that's surprisingly good i guess is what
i would say compared to what we thought
we had which was not as good um
and and uh yeah i i don't really know
what to make of that i guess that's just
because when it's sitting on the ground
like that
uh you have a lot of
there's quite a difference in how it's
going to be hit it's it's a bit strange
but you know i guess i could believe
that
i
all right let's
hmm okay
well
um huh
uh
i don't know
yeah all right
so so
do we just say that's good enough for
now then i don't know
uh it's still a bit square right i mean
it's not it's not fabulous right um but
but it's a lot better than it was so hmm
well
that's a tough one
uh i i would i would classify that
as a tough one
and i'm not sure what to make of it um
maybe we just
gosh
i mean maybe we just call that good
enough for now
i mean i feel like that's more than good
enough to do the rest of the game with
uh and then we could you know we could
do
before shipping maybe some more cleanup
of it um
i added a light to the glove here
you still get a fair bit of lag on the
glove but
well
yeah and it still is a bit square right
i mean it's not great
so you know there is that
um
so i guess i'm a little bit torn i i
don't know now should i pursue this a
little bit further or is that good
enough
and
uh yeah this is there's no tone mapping
um on right now tone mapping i think in
theory when we add tone mapping i think
it will actually improve
the perception of how the lighting is i
think i don't know that that's true but
it might so that might give us a little
more i don't know that it will
fundamentally fix the squariness
um
it might uh
i don't know i mean we could try it it's
certainly not that
difficult to try
but yeah wow okay well i'm just i'm just
not sure that wasn't what i was
expecting to find uh i do wonder so if
the the glove
floats above the ground a little bit uh
if we added the light if we push the
light of the glove up what does that do
to it because i don't know
um what that does either so i'm going to
take a look but yeah gosh i just i i
don't know i i really couldn't tell you
um
uh
that's really a tough call
um
i guess i would say like i don't know
it's still a open question to me like if
some of that squareness
can be uh
repaired
and
you know i don't know
um
all right i guess here's what here's
what i'll say since i don't really know
maybe what we should do is
actually go ahead and do the tone
mapping
uh
and put in some
put in some semblance of like
what we would expect to have happen is
sort of like a final
rendering pass like something that's
going to take
and
you know produce an output
um
yeah you know i mean
that seems like maybe the best idea is
to just go ahead and do that um
i mean the reason i say that is just
because we know we need to probably do
that
you know we we know that tone mapping is
not a huge deal and it will improve the
look of the game so we probably would
want to do it
and
i guess i don't can't think of a reason
not to do that
so maybe we just do that um and
you know i i guess i don't know which
tone mapping i want to do uh i don't not
being someone who
really does this
part of stuff for a living um
you know there's a fair number of
different ways that we could use the
use our outputs on on
yeah on tone mapping
so anyway uh you know the the way you
typically do
tone mapping is is uh
it looks like this i mean it always
looks like this basically what you're
doing is
uh you take some kind of an incoming
light level
and and this is the aces which is like
this kind of standardized curve i don't
think i've ever used this one but you
know i know about it so i'm you know
effectively what this is doing is it
produces a curve
that approximates some kind of a of a
film like like a literally like a piece
of film how it will respond to incoming
light and it's just a piecewise
polynomial
uh in this case it's irrational
um
it is a rational not irrational
uh it is a rational um and if we drop
this into like desmos or something you
can see what it looks like i mean that
blog entry probably had that uh as well
um
but like here so
uh if we graph like y equals x with this
nonsense here
uh and then we put in these
these numbers uh in response to it in
fact uh we could leave them as sliders
so that we can play with them later as
well
so if we take a look
at a
b
c d
uh
it said that a was 2.51 and that b
is
0.03
and 2.43 for c
uh and
0.59 for
uh where is e
what happened to e
oh you know what it thinks e is e it
probably thinks that's euler's number
and i can understand that
um am i allowed to say in this case e is
not e
i don't know if i am or not
um
well you know what let's call it um
z
how do i add a slider for something in
this program i don't know desmos very
well there we'll do it that way
at least it works
so z which is e in this case i just
wanted to get a slider for it
okay so now we've got our abcd
and z which is actually e in in this
and so x comes in and it's a brightness
level and here is the parameters on it
here's the the curve that they drew but
we've got our own one here i guess so
you know here's what this looks like
uh and you can kind of see like in their
drawing of this it's a little
exaggerated uh at that point
you know they're sort of showing
a
a flatter version of it
um perhaps
than are we they go out to 10. i don't
know ours doesn't look quite like theirs
looks that i put something in
um
incorrectly
251.003
243 059
and it's x
ax plus b
over x times
c times x plus z
i don't know looks like it's right but
does you know am i wrong
they're going from one to oh
i see why this is a log scale
um so in order to get ours to look like
there's uh we would have to make this be
a log axis i don't actually know
if this program does this it might um
not seeing it though
so i don't know we might not quite be
able to get it
to match but that's just because right
it's a log scale so you would expect it
to be yeah i don't i don't see
i don't really see any way we can do
that
so
i don't think we can get a log scale but
point being they've elongated this part
down here right
this is plotted on a log scale uh so for
them right they're basically looking at
one that goes from zero to ten
like so
but they've stretched it so that like
the part from here to here is like as
long as the part from here to here right
they've
they've kind of uh
log stepped it right
fox yeah
uh
does anyone know sorry i guess i'll just
ask does anyone know if you can get a
log scale i don't know if you can
i don't see it
that's what i was looking for
but
i mean it doesn't really matter because
like if we wanted to
we could do something like
right uh maybe um i guess it's
but it's the wrong way around uh so just
log that like log of the whole thing
sorry
that will not work
it almost worked
um
yeah because we want to be able to say
like well what would the output be if
you were to
plot the output so so i guess you would
do like like
yeah
like i don't know
uh this won't work i don't think but i
could be wrong about that because that's
that's a different
um way to do it right log of this whole
thing is not gonna do it because we
don't want the output plotted log we
want the input plotted log
if they had out if the output if they
had done a log on y then sure but they
didn't
so i don't know i guess we can't quite
get a match
of that
but
um
otherwise yes you can see what this
curve is attempting to do uh either way
yeah as i was gonna say like we could do
10 to the x
in there um
yeah exactly right i am bad as matt at
math as well but like uh
we wanted the opposite of what that was
doing we wanted to do
um
probably shouldn't deleted that
uh so you know
if we did
10 to the x
that's the opposite of log i actually
put in log which is not what we wanted
um so if i maybe do this
we can get it to simulate what would
happen if you brought it on a long scale
um
maybe
uh and then we put
in our constants again
right
copied in backwards order
i should have clicked on the uh add
slider buttons in the opposite order
right
um
so like in theory now yeah like you can
see now it looks a lot more like theirs
right it kind of goes slow right slow up
and over you know what i'm saying
um and you can also see here that like
what the effect of these dials actually
is
right so you can see like
a kind of controls like where we're
headed
right
um
b is that knee
that that top knee
um
c is is the angle like that that exit
angle there right
um
d is the other part of that top knee
and uh z is the where the like where the
inflection point like how you roll it
forward right
um so like you could you know just
intuitively as you play with them you
can see what they affect and you could
tweak it
we don't really care about that so much
the point is just that this is sort of
the kind of curve that you want
for film
when you're trying to do like what does
it look like to expose film
you want something that
has this sort of natural asymptotic like
going down towards black going up
towards white
that's you know
gradual and in the middle is somewhat
linear
that way no matter how bright things get
they always sort of fall somewhere in
your mappable range no matter how bright
it gets right
um
and so more importantly you can see that
this
even though this is like an official acs
um
like tone mapping curve
you can kind of see that it's very
simple like this is not particularly
complicated
it is rational
uh which is not fabulous
and you know um
[Music]
i think i remember this
oh is this gone
that's unfortunate all right can we get
that this was a good article
is that gone
no one's ever really gone
can i uh
can i get it back
um
did i do that wrong
yes so was this the one
um
so you know this one's still rational i
i could be
very wrong
but i could have sworn the last time i
worked on something like this
i did one that
that was basically
that did wasn't actually rational so it
didn't have a a divide but that
basically did what i wanted
um
and it's
i guess i don't remember where i got it
from maybe i worked it out myself
i don't
know uh it's been a long time
so anyway the point is a divide is
somewhat expensive
but these days it's not that bad so you
might and since you only really do it at
the end you know you're only going to do
one of these for a pixel right
well possibly more if you're doing
multi-sampling but you're not doing very
many
uh you know i guess people just don't
care these days but
it is true that it divides a lot more
expensive than like you know
uh just a
straight ahead multiply add the rest of
this stuff is all f mads which is the
cheapest possible thing but then you got
this divided in here and that's somewhat
expensive now i don't think it really
matters because like i said we're not
doing it that it's not a heavy lifting
kind of a thing
um it's not happening like many times
per pixel
so you know it's probably fine but in
general uh this curve
i guess we start with
maybe let's start with this curve
because hey it's well known
it's a standard
uh and we can tweak it pretty easily if
we want to
uh so maybe this is this is where we
start um like i said a little less
comfortable
with it uh
be just because of the fact that i
don't know that you really need a divide
i don't know that this has to be so
precise as to need a rational
in it um and that just feels off to me
it doesn't feel like something you would
need
but you know i guess apparently
that's how they did this so
[Music]
yeah um
you know i don't care enough to go to go
further i suppose
so this is just literally their curve
and
you know
we've got our params we have f32 defined
here right yeah
i you can't put f's
if i remember correctly in the version
we're using here
so it's going to look a little bit
different
but otherwise it's the same
and so basically we pass in an x which
is the incoming light and it just
returns the tone mapped version of it so
that would be a basic filmic tone map
and we literally can just drop that in i
think uh at when we're done
so you know in here
you've got
lighting
summation
i
[Music]
what the heck
what is
what is that
here for
uh anytime we go spelunking in this
nonsense shader that we wrote um it's
always a bit of a
an absurd
like what
i i don't know what the heck that's
supposed to be
why is it being clamped
um
i don't know we don't need the light
floor anymore i don't think uh because
it's not defined to be anything anyway
right it's just zero um
so all right we're gonna get rid of this
and this
and we're gonna start here
um
so we're just simplifying things a
little bit
uh
is anyone calling this function
yeah this is just old old stuff so we've
we've excised all of that stuff out it's
gone
uh
what is this open just like
saturate oh uh right that would be a d
that's that's a
a d 3d kind of a thing
um
an hl sl
so
we don't want that uh that's just a
clamp01 is all that is saturate is just
their term for clamping between zero and
one
uh and i think we already defined our
own clamp01
right yeah
so
we can just just use the standard thing
that we would do and that will do the
correct thing uh
it's just you know
it's just a nomenclature difference
between glsl and
hlsl which i assume that the code that
they were talking about
was hlsl there so that's why it had a
saturated in it right
which is totally reasonable
okay
uh that's about it i think um
[Music]
so here's us doing our thing hopping
around and
having a party and hopping party
uh and so now we need to put in this
tone mapping and i don't think there's
gonna be a huge difference between what
we see i don't think it's going to be
huge
but again at least now this way it will
be
roughly correct and you can see in here
so we've got our surface reflect
i we have a fogging factor but i i can't
really say why
uh
anymore because we don't use the fog
maybe we leave that in because we want
to use fog in the future
um
i guess i don't know
anyway uh so we've got some other
garbage here we've got like a lerp
between this and a frag emission value
uh and that that frag emission thing is
here i don't know
who actually sets the fragments and
stuff we're going to have to look
at that stuff because we're going to
need it later we're probably going to
want to render light sources that are
emitters right
and then when they are emitting you can
see here they would then flow through
and they would uh do a like a boost
basically
and this clamp01 now i think we just
want to replace this right here
with our asus film map
uh so rather than just clamping between
zero and one we wanna feed this into
uh the tone mapper
um so here's what that looks like
and you know you can already see it
looks a lot better right it looks a lot
more dramatic
being fed through the tone mapper
um
it's just nice
right uh
a lot more just a lot more dramatic a
lot more
uh
stark and interesting right
um so but i would say the squariness
right still totally there uh it doesn't
really help um
if anything it sort of exacerbates that
and uh so while everything else looks
really good like any area that has a lot
of light looks ten times better
uh areas of low light have that
squareness problem but but yeah i mean
it just it's a nice response curve it
looks a lot better there's no question
about that right
it definitely looks a lot better
so uh yeah i guess i would say
um
i mean based on that i'd say i might
still want to do the light rasterization
because yeah this looks good the tone
mapping is definitely an improvement um
we would want to keep that
but
the squariness persists it doesn't
really help
with the squariness very much
um and
i guess we also don't know so if i
if i switch these to spheres
i don't know what that does if anything
um
but basically no change the squariness
kind of remains they get dimmer because
they're smaller
right um
but
not really
a dramatic difference i wouldn't say
um
yeah
so
gosh
i think that kind of argues for still
doing the rasterization step
i think that i think that argues
for doing the rasterization step
because
obviously we could change the way we're
doing interpolation and maybe that would
help it's true
but
i also don't know
that
i i feel like we probably have some a
lot of mileage we could get out of just
more
accurate
light source
placement
into the into the the voxel
so
you
i guess i don't know what what to do
next
uh my guess is we should just try
rasterization direct direct
rasterization i think
that feels like what you would want
um
uh dr zul the light prepositions are
already jittered
um
if you would like to see
uh what i mean
by that
here is
one of the ray samples
this is just the first one taken
uh and you can see that it's already
jittered right
so
you know
so uh yeah i don't have a lot else to
say about that
um i guess i'm i'm not really sure what
i think i should do for the next step
here
what i will say is the lighting looks
awesome i'm very happy with it
uh so i really have no complaints about
it and i think you could ship a game
this way i just think that that
squariness
i think i can probably fix it if i do
direct rasterization of the light
sources and because the lighting looks
so good
and you know it kind of brings it down
like when you're out here like for
example and you get that squariness it
just kind of brings the quality down um
i think i should probably just try it
because if it did fix it then that would
be like the lighting would basically be
perfect i mean everywhere else the
lighting is
spectacular
um
to the point where stuff now just looks
so freaking good uh
it just looks so damn good that i i feel
like if
it's a shame to let one thing
uh bring it down like that and it's just
because i think uh we don't have a good
way of handling when you're close to a
light source so you get a
that drastic almost a step function when
all the rays then miss or a large number
of rays miss and you don't so you don't
have a proper interpolant you end up
getting that sort of square
fall off i
i mean like yeah because it just it just
looks really good
now and i feel like uh we
would really be doing a disservice uh if
we didn't at least try to get it perfect
because it's
it's really good looking
um
so um and like here's an example of of
playing the game with only one light
source and just i mean look at how good
that looks right
like
the indirect lighting is just awesome
um
it's just so much better than what i'm
used to seeing in a lot of cases it just
looks great
i mean that's just amazing
um
and if we did move this to the gpu it
would look even better because like
don't forget on the gpu it's going to be
rather than you know eight samples
uh it's gonna be like
it would be like 64 samples or something
you know we could do so you know it'd be
the quality level would be like that
um
so very little flicker as well
right
um
and that that would just be like really
really really
hard to argue with at that point right
um
so i don't know
i feel like we should do the
rasterization just to see if it helps if
i knew for sure it would definitely fix
it i would say it's it's absolutely what
we do
um
but i you know there's a possibility
that it simply won't fix it and then
we've done
um
[Music]
we've done that work for no reason right
but i mean you know that's that's engine
programming engine programming is about
trying stuff and finding something that
works
that's your job as an engine programmer
it's the game designer's job then to
have this nice situation where
everything just works right we build
this for them
so that they can go make a game that's
the whole point uh we do the
experimentation
on the engine so that they can do
experimentation on the game design right
i mean that's how that works
so so i don't mind at all uh but it is
the case that you know we may go do the
rasterization and it doesn't matter
right like it doesn't actually fix it uh
so you know
um so anyway
uh
i guess we just try it
uh and we
see what we can do
um
if you look at what's going on here it's
pretty clear so you know like if i go
and
if you take a look at the light probe
locations
that are implicated by you know this
this thing
what we would be looking at is basically
a five by five
square
right uh and the question would be
i mean i guess i don't even really know
that maybe it's only a three by three
square
so you know for a given light it's gonna
be we'd rasterize it into the three by
three
i mean technically it's a stack because
we would do both you know be the bottom
and the top there
um
i'm gonna hop out into an area where
it's more pronounced and and try to take
a look at what's happening with the
light prep see if i can get a better
feel for why
you know why we're seeing that
and i gotta be honest with you i
i
don't
you know looking at this i'm starting to
think maybe interpolation
really would be
sort of more of it
because those look about right
and i'm just i'm wondering are we doing
something wrong
um
because
i even linear interpolation should not
really be having such a hard
edge
i mean linear interpolation is capable
of reproducing a literally an exact
circle
uh
linear interpolation just is is not
does not really explain
uh
why we're getting that hard edge
um
so i'm a little nervous about this
because i think
i think we're seeing something else
uh i wonder if this has to do with
mixing specular let's turn off the
specular out off because right now we
have those both on which is not
necessarily great
so this material parameter uh i'm going
to turn it down to zero
so that the
uh it's only looking at the diffuse map
uh so that is kind of what i thought
so if you look at just the diffuse map
you actually don't quite have that same
problem do you
i mean it still has more of a square
aspect than you would like
but it's not nearly like the same as
with the spec map where it's very hard
edged
right
that's the spec map
all right so hold on a second here folks
everyone hold on a second
i'm going to look at debugger octahedral
values
and we're going to turn on the values
and we're going to use the spec atlas
instead of the diffuse atlas so we can
see what we actually have
i mean no
like it still doesn't
something just does not add up here
some something weird
something feels off because when you
look at what's happening with the actual
light probes
you know they
there's still a fair bit of light being
collected
by this
and maybe that's not really true because
maybe what we're seeing there
is
it really does feel like it
maybe what we're seeing there is
like well yeah if you look like this
it is pretty smooth right so what you're
seeing there is just the transition from
a reflection vector that looks up into
the part that does have the light source
versus one that doesn't have the light
source you're just seeing that
you know that difference
um
so that seems pretty weird let's go take
a look um at what we're doing there
because i don't actually know
well i don't actually know what we're
doing there
let's be completely honest we just don't
know
so uh when we sample the lighting
which you can see us doing here
we pull out you know from the octahedral
map a particular lighting sample and we
merge them together here we've asked for
just the specular so that we could look
at it
because the diffuse map is obviously a
blur
um a cosine weighted blur of the spec
map which is you know what you expect
um
so we sample the lighting each time and
we do it
we sample at each of the eight
corn you know the the eight corners of
the the the voxel you know cage you
would be in
uh and we
use those to do a standard tri-linear
interpolation right here is this lurping
z you know between the up the up and the
down basically
uh using the the z we then lerp the y
uh and then finally the x uh to produce
the final result
that you know that's what you would
expect to see um that's the standard
trilinear
right um not a lot of
anything particularly weird going on
there
um
so it's hard to say that that you know
that doesn't look particularly odd now
it's possible that there's some bugs in
here though right like
you know suppose we were computing vox r
wrong
you know what i mean like that could
lead to you having
you know a harder
you know
fall off than you should
um
light look up voxel dimension
minus one
times vox uvw
uh
i can't say that makes a huge amount of
sense to me
like why
are we sending down the total dimension
as being one less than it should be
i guess
because that's a little weird
um
right that's not
i mean
am i the only one who thinks this is
strange
uh you know maybe i am but
like what are we sending down for the
vox imf total dim in the first place
what do we send down for vox in
this value
voxel in turtle dim
what does that get set to
i mean someone must set that right
so who
so it's in set light bounds
and it's it's here
so this feels a little sloppy
um
this this is
making me a little nervous so
this
doesn't
make sense exactly
i mean it sort of does don't get me
wrong
um
but i think it's interpolating off by
0.5 in a way
right
i don't know what to make of that
so let's take a look at what this looks
like with and without it it's because
it's really confusing and i'm not sure
how to process that it's it's very odd
and
i want to understand it better so if i
delete this
um so that we don't have the minus one
it should shift we should see the
lighting shift yeah like that
um
and presumably it should be
more
wrong
or otherwise i don't know why we had it
shifted like that
um
right i mean
but why you would one that i'm not quite
sure
because it's sort of like it feels more
it feels like we're correcting for
something that we did wrong in the first
place
and so i'm not sure about that minus one
i'm not sure i can justify that minus
one very well
now granted this has nothing to do with
what we were actually looking at
i'm also not sure how us changing our
orientation here should have any effect
because i thought we turned off
the specular
oh no we're looking entirely at specular
never mind
um
so i i
don't
love that
and
i feel that's i don't know i really just
kind of that feels suspicious to me
and furthermore so if you take a look
you know let's suppose i was correct
that there should be a minus one there
well
is there a minus one in here because
these are the same code path like one's
on the gpu side
and one's on the cpu side
and you can see here like we've got like
all right you know
i
we're doing the same stuff
we
do like um
[Music]
an f chord and a b chord right that's
this this stuff right here
uh inverse cell dimension times p minus
total bounds right
um
it's a very similar computation
in this case we're trying to actually
get a number that we index into because
this one's you know in zero to one land
and this one's in zero to count so
that's why you know it's a little bit
different
uh
so i mean this is this is just getting
the exact cell count
and so you would think this would too
i guess there is a difference in that
the zero to one uv scale thing is kind
of messed up the way that opengl does
textures is really bizarre and strange i
mean the way all 3d graphics cards do
them i've never understood it it's very
weird and
unnatural
um
it's just kind of wrong like like i
think it's just objectively wrong the
way they do texture lookups personally
um
it's just
and it doesn't work with almost anything
like it's why they had to struggle so
long with weird things they tried to add
like texture borders and all the stuff
it's just wrong
uh the way that they decided to do
texture mapping so you know maybe it
could be that i'm not thinking through
the weird like okay zero
is actually like
half a pixel back from the center of the
first pixel and one is actually half a
pixel forward from the last you know
pixel
and if you actually internalize that
there's that's the extra one that you're
removing when you do this
right
so maybe i could believe that
um i'll let it go for now with just the
to-do because
you know it doesn't have anything to do
with
what i'm looking at
i'm looking at the squariness
um
but
yeah that was a bit disquieting as well
um
so i think you can also see when we look
at the specular map right
you can see that i can make the falloff
either be hard or soft based on what the
reflection angle is and i guess that's
just yeah that all that's doing
is it's because you have that blur
uh from the spec map to the diffuse map
the spec map just immediately falls off
when you no longer are targeting the
light source the texels on that side
won't have
um
any contribution at all
right
so i guess what i'm trying to say
is this whole thing might
might
um implicate the part of the code that i
sort of said we would get rid of
but maybe we actually secretly need it
um which is actually not so much better
interpolation on the voxel
because maybe we don't really need that
maybe our main problem is better
interpolation
in the octahedral map um
i really don't want that to be true
uh because it would be really nice if
that wasn't the case
you
well okay
so here's what i'll say because i'm not
really sure
uh
maybe we just
try some different things like maybe we
try a different interpolator
i've had multiple people write in asking
for me to do this
and so you know maybe now is a good time
to say let's experiment let's answer the
question of would an interpolator make
any difference here anyway
um and i think someone sent me one and
it's been i i've been delinquent in not
trying it i said i would try it
and i just haven't gotten around to it
so i will i will bring it up here
and uh i will will mention it and uh
we'll see if there's if it if it really
helps
um or not and it was uh
okay so it was from sebastian mester
uh i'm sure i'm like pronouncing that
wrong because it's like probably
sebastian master or something like this
but uh they said hey casey i just looked
at your most recent youtube video if
you're looking at a different blending
function for handmade heroes raytrace
voxels here's a cool one
uh and he says float f float x return x
times x times three minus two times x
um float g is return f u v dot u times f
u v dot v
and it says it's hat shaped
uh continuous with the continuous
derivative and the four samples always
add up to one the derivatives are also
zero at the edges which makes it really
nice for blending light values at the
far edges of the square
um so it was probably hard for you to
understand what i was reading exactly
because i read some equations there that
you know probably were hard to see but
it's actually very simple um so let me
just show you
show you
um soy sauce let me just soy sauce this
uh
in here what he was suggesting so that
you can see what i can see uh as well so
uh what they were saying is i don't know
what we're gonna call this uh we'll call
this a mester
um in honor of the the fellow who wrote
in
i so what
he was saying was that look you pass in
um an x value
and it returns x times x times three
minus 2 x
right so just a like a
cubic
right
um and you know what since we were
having the decimals party today
there's no reason we can't uh decimals
this up
right so if we
if we put that in there
uh you can see that it's actually not
that dissimilar
uh to the lighting one right it's
another one of these little sigmoid guys
uh and it just kind of goes like a
little smoother up and then a little
smoother out
so rather than just a harsh line it's
got like a little bend
right
um
and uh
yeah so that's the first part of it but
he had a second part
uh which he said that was when you
actually look up
uh the value
like where you're going to look up the
value i guess
so i think what he was saying is that
when you actually do like uh the
coordinates
you do you pass in the coordinates that
you're going to look up
i guess
you know what i don't really understand
this part
i don't really understand this part so
here's another one that this is the
other part of it and i guess i'm just
not sure where it comes from so like
here's the uv
uh and he said
uh
that we would do the first one
uh so basically like doing this falloff
function on the u times the fall
function on the v
and
so i guess
this is just a way to produce the
interpolant
in 2d
i'm not sure how that really helps us
though because we're doing 3d i don't
really know so i'm not sure how this was
meant to be applied
is i guess what i would say
uh you could do three of them
um
[Music]
so like
this
right um
so so
you could do that and
but i don't know if that's really what
the person intended so you know i guess
i apologize i probably should have asked
um
some clarifying questions at the time
um and so
yeah maybe that's
less good so maybe this is not what they
so i apologize to the the viewer because
i don't actually know
if this is what they were recommending
i assume this is for the lerp uh
preconditioning the lerp
uh but i really don't know
so we could try this and see but it may
not actually be what they were
suggesting so i apologize so here is our
vox r uh and so basically what we would
be doing here is just i think the
intention of this would be before we in
combine the values using uh trilinear we
would first precondition this
uh
value to sort of conform to that sigmoid
function and
i i think that's what they wanted but
honestly i i just don't really know
oops i've i've made a horrible error
um
mester three
must be broken what did i screw up
um
oh wait but that only gives you back one
value
yeah now that like like this doesn't
actually return a v3
so
how does that help you
again i don't really see
i don't really quite see how the
blending's supposed to work because you
need to be able to produce a three you
need to be able to produce three blend
coefficients right
um
and i i don't understand what this g
value is i could just call this on each
dimension separately
um
but i just don't get what the uv parts
for
right because i it's trilinear so i need
three linear interpolation values i
could feed each of them into the first
mester
but the second mester what would it be
for
i just don't know where i would bother
where would that go
right
so like you know this function it's
pretty easy for me to take this and just
feed all of them into that
um you know that's the most
straightforward thing to do
so
where we had the vox r before right
um
right here
we would just say like okay yeah each of
these
you know what i'm saying
so each of these we could feed through
that interpolant that's not hard right
but i just don't see how that uses i
don't see how the second function gets
used um i'm not sure oops
uh
so that mester two and three
[Music]
these two or well the three he didn't
say but this two this one
i don't get
right
um so this is not going to be useful
tests um i apologize
i guess i'll just need to get
clarification
on what was supposed to happen there
um because i don't know
i do not know
what they wanted me to do
[Music]
so
so i can do it to each of the axes
independently but what that other one
was supposed to be i don't know
um so here's what that looks like
uh
and you know it's
it's better you can still see what it's
doing but it it turns the squares into
sort of rounder
versions of of themselves i'll turn off
the
um
octahedral values so that you can see it
a little bit better
um
and it's nicer
right i mean to be sure it's definitely
a little bit nicer uh but i don't know
that it really solves the problem like
it it hides the problem but
i don't know like the i still think
there's some kind of core problem with
the fact that we're not really capturing
that lighting well enough i don't know
maybe it's fine
um it i think it does help a little
uh but it's not
it's not quite right um
so
yeah
i'm gonna go ahead and turn back on our
other lights also so i can see how that
affected
um
you know just if the if the interior is
lit again
what does that look like uh just so we
can get a better sense of it
um
i would say it doesn't really affect
those lights in any particular way like
they don't look better or worse they
just look fine either one
so i would say it's pretty low cost to
keep this uh
if we didn't make any other improvements
we would probably want to keep it
because it it looks better than the
alternative i think
um
you know i would i would say it probably
does look better than the alternative
it's still not great though
um
so yeah i'm still not completely
thrilled with that and
i kind of want to do a little bit of
testing i guess is what i would say
so so i might do that um
now yeah so so like in the chat
frisio9 said i still believe this might
just be an artifact of too low voxel
resolution
and what we see is actually expected
given the current constraints um
i'm pretty sure that is not true
so
a linearly interpolated voxel can
capture
spherical falloff perfectly
at any
resolution
um
the only thing it can't do
is
capture the
uh the
if if
two
it can't capture an interior curve so if
you're curving from
like
uh
like if you think of quartering a circle
if two quarters of the circle have to
happen inside the same voxel cell it
wouldn't
right
um
and so uh it's it's i think a problem
not
with
um
with the fact that we are using a voxel
and and more a problem that just we are
not producing the right function in our
voxel
and let me try to substantiate that
slash debug this
so let's suppose that we um take out
the
uh this this particular this
sort of
interpolant here
uh and go back to standard linear uh
which again i think looks great honestly
i i think it looks good
and really my only complaint is
this sort of
we're getting things are too blocky you
know out here
right
i so
what i would like to do is say well what
would happen
just to just to sort of motivate this a
little bit what would happen if i
literally just set
uh the values in the voxel
to be
uh
directly
the falloff function from a point
and again this is just me trying to kind
of like convince you and or for my
debugging purposes so that i can have a
known function that i can put in there
and validate which again is also
would be really handy right
um
let's make sure that that actually would
look okay and look correct uh and then
you can also see it so that you know
that i'm not lying
and or it doesn't work and then i know
we have a bug because i'm quite certain
that this works
in math uh
maybe not in our code
so let's suppose we go into the internal
lighting core i if you look at what
happens right we set up these work units
uh and they all go and do their little
uh happy dance
uh and that happy dance is is full cast
right uh so full cast is the is the work
function
uh what we do is we loop over all of the
voxels assigned to a particular thread
and uh we
so like each thread takes a an xz
cross section
right of of the atlas each each thread
does
um
which by the way we probably have to fix
to doing a
a more
discrete partic partition than that
because if you had something that was
more threads they would not be able to
effectively work on it we probably need
to split x up because before we were
assuming like oh well okay
um
you know there's going to be a lot of
these
and blah blah now there's only really
like there's only two sheets in z
so
yeah you know maybe that is not the
smartest thing and maybe we should
partition it so that we have like more
like z is split for each one as well so
there's just more granularity there like
because like let's suppose you ran this
on like a thread ripper or something
you know what i'm saying
um
you know like
you're not gonna get uh
you're not gonna get any acceleration
because there aren't 64 different pieces
to work on
so you know
um
so yeah
yeah yeah
so let's go ahead and and uh take a look
and if i just go ahead what i was going
to do is to say like what if we just put
in a hard-coded light value here
so instead of doing full cast we just
did something that wrote
specifically to the octahedral map like
a thing
that was a circular pattern so we could
verify that the falloff
you know was
was roughly correct
right that it that
we would reconstruct it properly
um and and what we could do is say
i mean i'm not sure exactly how you
would want to how you'd want to do this
like do we want to just write them all
into the same
into the same one
um
like the transfer pps value here
so what i'm saying is like look we would
say okay
transfer pps
i
so we're going to have to produce eight
values here so maybe what we do is we
just set them all the same thing
temporarily
uh and then we set you know this fall
off funk this is what we're actually
gonna do here we would lerp between
you know zero
uh and one i guess we don't really need
to do that because we know we can just
produce that value so
maybe the falloff funk is just gonna be
fall off
like three times and then fall off
uh is gonna be like clamp clamp01 some
distance function
right
uh you know one minus some distance
between
so i guess we just do length
uh
you know the the length of
between some light location
which we'll just put at the origin for
now
uh and we'll just say that it's going to
be the length of the light location to
wherever we're at
it's not the ray origin it's the center
of the thing so it's
whatever that light probe p
um so that should be a radial falloff
um
what is the complaint compiler
i agree that should not be a parentheses
um
so i guess what i would say is like that
to me
looks just wrong
so i think there's something else going
on bad here right because that should
not
that should not really be the case
of course it's inside one so maybe not i
don't know we'll find out
we'll find out in a second
okay so i'm
pretty sure that is completely wrong
um
that interpolation is broken
i'm pretty sure
um
and so if that's
maybe i filled this out wrong but if i
did actually fill this out correctly
this would be why we're getting so such
squarey stuff because that should not it
should not look anything like that um
well okay that's not actually true
so you have to do the subtraction you do
have to have a light floor in order for
that to work
so
i guess i would say well
not exactly
um
so let me keep going on that front
because you do need to not have it
ever hit actual zero
so you have to be able to do the floor
the thing that i removed before
you need to have so in other words right
here where we do this lerp
and we produce this light value
uh at the end of it
we do have to basically floor like drop
this down
further
first
so
um
in other words
some value here
that we agree on is our floor value has
to be removed prior to the rest of the
process right
and we're going to have to clamp it as
well
so so that's gonna be
an issue um
like it's gotta get clamped to zero
which
it's clamp zero inf yeah that's the one
oops
let's do it this way
okay
so basically like after we sort of
you know do this whatever random fog
thing which we should probably just
remove for now because if we're gonna do
fog we would do it differently
um
and hey look there's our exact circle
which is what we would expect
right
um
something's a bit odd about that though
like
i guess i'm not sure why it creates such
a stark
uh is it because this is too much light
to be removing i don't actually know
is it because the clamp zero infinity is
broken what's happening there
i'm not really sure why that's happening
right like like uh
i will say that that part was was
confusing
that was legit confusing
um but here you can see that the proper
reconstruction of a circle once you
remove a floor value from it so that the
the function doesn't get confused
outside of there
um i don't know what to expect if you
were to remove a slight floor value
prior to feeding it through that
function in general
um
so
that's
i don't know
what that will do um
[Music]
so
yeah
and and i don't know why there's no
other lighting like where is all the
lighting i don't know what's going on
right now did i break something else
when i was
messing with that
because if i take this
out if i take this out of the equation
the rest of it should run pro the same
right this was all i changed i thought
what am i missing
what horror hath i
inflicted upon thy world
like all i added i added literally just
that right
how is it possible is all of the
lighting happening literally between 0
and 0.05
that doesn't seem possible is clamp zero
inf actually busted
or am i misunderstanding something
i mean that looks right
so is it just like so let's suppose i
said i subtract nothing
don't subtract anything
all good
and now let's suppose i i
100 like one hundredth of the total
light value
what happens then
so subtracting
only just that much
is like where all of our light is how
about one one thousandth of the light
that is just crazy
it's crazy right
don't you think
how small that is all right so suppose
we um
were to
to subtract a larger amount i'm just
curious what this does
uh to our interpolator
i mean
it's very circular
right
i mean it is right so it does seem like
it's a function reconstruction problem
do you know what i'm saying
um
uh this is not specular by the way
whoever said that in chat uh this is
just the diffuse map right
at this point
right
so we're only looking at diffuse uh
specular would be this
that's that's specular
right
so um
[Music]
gosh
i am
uh well that both confirms and surprises
me
it confirms what i was thinking before
but also it surprises me that so much of
the light is down in the lower
end of the range
[Music]
alrighty then
um
yeah
well anyway
um so
that confirms my suspicion though right
so
if you look at what happens when you try
to interpolate the linear function
you can see pretty clearly that where
you get the square artifacts are where
you lose the ability to interpolate
because you no longer have a sample
anymore of that function the function
that you were trying to
reproduce
you don't have a sample of that function
in the next cell over the function is
just has gone straight to zero
um
and so
if you capture the light and you say
well we're just going to use
like a natural floor function that we
remove out
after we do the interpolation you get
your correct circles back
but the problem is you also get
incorrect light levels
so how do you fix that
hmm
i say
is is the thing that i'm saying so i
don't know
i mean i don't really know how you would
fix that
and
you know if you crank it down to
whatever level would be necessary to
actually
uh deal with the light levels as they
are
um
it doesn't help you right so like this
level of flooring doesn't do anything
right
um whereas this level of flooring does
but it removes so much light
that it doesn't help you reproduce the
circles that you want
i mean you get nice circles but
you've removed so much light that you
can't see anything
although it is kind of a nice effect
it's not one we can really use
is the acs film functioning trading the
venice um
no
not particularly it's it's pretty
neutral
um
[Music]
you can actually see like okay so that's
what it looks like with the acs film
function
and
oops if i just
remove it
uh you can watch the change
you know
that's it
uh if anything i'd say it's slightly
better
right let's go back this is without it
and there's with it uh
you know neither is great but it seems
like the acs one's actually a little bit
better
to me
so i don't
know um i don't have a strong opinion
about it i would say this looks good
enough probably now um with the film in
there
i don't know
uh it's pretty reasonable
like i feel like you could ship this and
maybe what you do is you just don't you
don't make a lot of regions
that have this kind of feel to them
right like don't do exactly this
because you you know whenever you're in
a region that actually has any kind of a
lighting scheme at all it looks totally
good right everything looks great
um
and even this area looks like okay
it's not great
it's only really the grasses
that look pretty bad uh for whatever
reason they're you know
we have hopped out of the game
so
so i guess what i will say is it does
kind of answer the question of like look
if you don't have the floor flooring
then linear interpolation is not going
to cut it
right i mean that's just kind of
true
uh
so
so i guess there's not a lot we can
really do because you know
would be practical to up the voxel
resolution
uh yeah i mean i guess
i don't know
i don't know that we can really it'll
just make the square be
smaller i don't know that that's really
going to help but i mean yeah like we
could because maybe
maybe if we move this to the gpu we can
increase the voxel resolution to the
point where it's fine
um
yeah i don't think that's a realistic
option right now but like with
you know with the with moving it to the
gpu we would get a massive speed
increase
uh or even just to a more modern cpu
we'd get a massive speed increase we'd
get like
four x or something moving to a zen
three right so
you know you could pretty easily double
both
uh your voxel
uh
dimensions for sure so yeah i mean
that's definitely true
um
so
let's give that a shot i guess so the
the problem we're gonna have is that i
don't actually remember how the vauxhall
look up dim stuff even really works
but so let's suppose that i i double it
here
like so
and i think we might have to introduce a
corresponding scale because i don't know
that we actually divide up i think we
actually just use
they're they're always placed so that
would just do a larger
uh region
right it's not going to actually
like that's just going to produce a
larger lighting region like you can see
uh that it's actually totally messed up
right like this
this part right now is is going to be
like indexing out of
out of bounds right because it's too
large
so we would need like a way to shrink
that down and
uh so the
the part that actually like uh starts
the lighting
that would have to
[Music]
have
uh that resolution so so
this
um would have to be like
a point
five thing
i don't know why that's
producing a
uh difference there why we're getting an
out of bounds actually look at that
um don't
think we sh should
what is the spatial cell dim
[Music]
two times the voxel cell dim
atlas cell count
is a specialist size yeah so i think
we should probably look at why why i
don't know why that's having
a weird
effect on anything
um
i guess technically that should be
a 1.0 there but
um
yeah we might have to switch into debug
mode and find out what's the problem
there
like who what is what is going on here
in the grid to build spatial partition
it's like
it's getting like an out of bounds
uh look up here for some reason but i
don't actually know why that would be
happening
doesn't make a lot of sense
you
yeah i'm not sure that's that's a bit
disquieting so i don't know why that
would happen so let's take a quick look
at why that is maybe it's something
obvious that we should be thinking about
so i'm going to switch this to d and i'm
going to let it crash and then i'm going
to look at what's going on there
because i would like to be able to
change that resolution
even though i don't think we can afford
it at the moment like i agree that we
should run that test
just so we have a better idea
uh so give this a second
um
to
to put
poot itself
it's it's gonna have to put forth
don't seem to be getting a lot of
crashiness here
probably just because it's not running
fast enough
this is riveting
okay
so we finally after much waiting get to
the part that we are looking for here
which is in flat index
uh from
and the index that it's asking for is
out of bounds of the grid so you know
the grid
uh has a cell count 30 22 1
and you know it's asking for 18 9 1
uh
and
you know
that that is
it's the z
value there
that's actually incorrect so
[Music]
not sure i
know what's going on there because
i would have expected it to be another
one of the
i guess yeah i wouldn't expect a z to
ever be a problem
and in fact when we were doing these
insertions since there are not multiple
levels of z
uh the min max node here uh this part
doesn't i don't even know why we're
getting
that
happening in the first place
the spatial grid itself what it does
good index for p
yeah like i guess our z is just not
clamped to the correct amount we can fix
that pretty easily by just removing this
iterator because we don't allow there to
be multiple z's anyway so the z is
always zero and we don't actually need
to loop over it
um
and i guess in the reason that we were
having this problem is because
the get index for p it's just on the
outside of where those bounds should be
so i guess changing the resolution i
don't know why that would actually cause
that problem though because we're not
changing the z part of this so it is a
little bit concerning
um
but i guess i will say that you know we
probably should simplify this because we
did remove z
so we don't have
like there isn't multiple z now it's
it's literally just that
um so that entire thing should never be
a problem
but you know
i
i don't really know
we didn't like optimize this code path
for the non-z case that we ended up
switching to
uh where you know the spatial index for
z is just always going to be zero
uh
no matter what happens in this case
right
same with this
so let me take a quick look and just
make sure that all these things yeah
like we even had an assertion there for
it
uh and i don't know what's going on
there i guess the problem is somehow our
z bounds are not
as high as they should be
i'm not sure exactly what was going on
with that let's see if this fixes it
because i don't really want to
investigate that right now
but you know again we took z out of
everything and we did it pretty quickly
so we probably don't quite have it right
um but i don't know
this may not be enough to fix it let's
let it freak out again with the stupid
glove
so i would say it definitely looks
better
right i mean
i mean i could convince myself
that that was better
you do see the sampling error more right
you can see like the shining
it's interesting
so let's
let's
take a look
and if we increase that one more time
uh we've got to yeah that's going to be
too dense for it because remember we're
sending down floats for these things so
i mean it's not
yet you're not wrong like it definitely
does improve the situation
um so maybe it is just not
sufficient sampling levels
for what we need
and if that's the case and i guess we're
just kind of screwed like use bigger
light sources
is your pretty much your only option at
that point
um
so i don't know
i don't know
i do not know
yeah bigger and slightly weaker light
source right um
all right well
i don't know
i'm not feeling particularly inspired
today so i can't say that i have any
really great ideas about what we would
do after this
[Music]
um it's not quite as good as i would
like but it's also still pretty good um
we could just try like you know playing
to the strengths of the system
and you know using light sources that
are going to be
like larger than
what we're currently making
uh
that's certainly one option
like here you know we've got these are
you know maybe we we update these to be
more like
larger lights
maybe like 0.7 or whatever and then we
drop the brightness down
and maybe that's fine i don't know uh
because again like we can make the light
itself the thing itself be bright
um and so maybe we just use larger light
sources and we call it a day uh because
i don't know how squary those would look
um
like i don't know it's still a bit
squarey
um
but it's not that bad like i can live
with that
um
we do have the ability to change the
interpolator again i'm not sure we want
to
uh but we do have the ability to change
it and we don't really know also to try
other interpolators
um but i don't really think that's going
to solve our problem to be completely
honest with you
i
i don't know any amount of interpolation
is really going to fix that
i mean maybe it does
i don't know
um
like it still just kind of looks
like it looks it just looks
a little bit more radial but oh well
um
so i don't know so maybe you just have
to make sure maybe there's like a
certain nyquist maybe we try to like
move it to the gpu and get
um
and make it
go faster so that we can have a denser
sampling i don't know
right
um
i don't know
is it trivial to move to the gpu i mean
yes and no
it's trivial in the sense that there's
no log there's be like the exact same
logic basically it's very very time
consuming and annoying because
programming sucks like the way that
these things are written
has to be completely different and you
know the
gpus suck to program in general because
the environment for debugging is
super lousy
um
so yeah so maybe i mean let's put it
this way looking at this
you might say that like you could
believe if you just cranked up the um
if you just cranked up the actual like
resolution that maybe that's enough but
i don't know i mean it still also kind
of looks very squarey
in here it doesn't and i think part of
that is just
again when you get out here the reason
is there's no there's nothing else
you're only seeing just that fall off
right
um
because there's basically no bounce
lighting there's no nothing
there right whereas everywhere else you
get more
there's more that's filling it in and
you know
so i don't know
what is the right solution to this
problem
so let's ask
a question
let's ask the following question
suppose we were to increase the power of
the light source
right
so let's say that i increase the power
of this light source to a very high
level it's at five now or something
right
um
again i'm just
trying to think about how you would go
about fixing this problem
so suppose we change this so that the
lights are larger uh you know than they
should be or whatever and then they're
super powerful like here's my blown out
light source gonna come get you
uh and then i remove the light floor
from the very powerful light so you know
we're we're gonna try the light floor
removal trick again
so i say like okay clamp zero in
um
surface reflect rgb minus v3
and it's like gonna remove
[Music]
um
you know some amount i don't remember
how much
we need to remove uh oops
um
i forgot the semicolon
the entire world crashed because i
forgot the semicolon isn't that the
programming way
not in python it's not
so right like you can kind of see now
that
if you just increase the power of the
light source you can still get that
that same trick
and now it looks right
i feel like i feel like there's a way to
do this
i feel like there's a way to do this
and i just don't quite understand
it enough
to do it
um
on a second
let's change the way we're writing this
just so it's a little easier to see so
we're a hundred times in our light
uh and then that would mean you just
subtract one
from it for now
okay
and and here's
us
in our room doing stuff
right
uh
then we go and say
okay we want
we want the fall off
to be smoother to zero though
right so when we subtract the one away
well i guess i'm not sure exactly why
that produces i'm still not quite sure
why it produces exactly what we're
seeing now so that is a little bit tough
but let's say i 10x these lights
so they're in the mix again
i feel like i don't understand quite why
we are getting
so i'm doing something wrong we
shouldn't actually be getting what i'm
seeing right now
um
after the flooring trick it's
doesn't quite make sense to me
why that would be happening
i'm a little bit confused as to why that
would be happening
oops i'm going to
power these lights up even more i'm
going to make these full bright
so i just want to see what's going on
because i don't quite understand it
yes something's a little bit off about
this
because all that should be happening is
things should be getting a little bit
dimmer as you turn that number up
but that's not
really what's happening right
what if we tried to
like i wonder to what extent this would
work if we just try to sort of clamp
well
i guess it's not really going to work
but i'm saying like is i wonder if
there's a way to really like
sort of smooth out that transition
region
differently
than what we're doing so
[Music]
all right so so let's not do that
and
you know we'll go back to what i was
doing before
all right
um
so
if we don't subtract one
i guess i didn't need to restart it but
i did
if we don't subtract one here is our
world
uh everything looks hunky-dory
but we have our blockiness problem
it's a little too blocky
so if i go
in here and like what happens if i just
say
you know
what happens if i square the light value
more blocky less blocky
like way less blocky
not very much light but way less blocky
right
and i i guess i would say it's for this
for exactly that reason right because
now a lot of that tail those low
the low values in the tail
are now
you can't see where they actually hit
their zero they're spread out further
you know what i'm saying
so i wonder if there's something we can
do um
so let's go back to our desmos here
i wonder if there's something we could
do
where we would be
kind of flattening that bottom part more
heavily
so
like if we were to take this
thing
and um
is that right
all right
so
is that undo yeah
so yeah i'm thinking what if we did more
like that
right
um and now we would need to kind of
adjust potentially the rest of this
thing although maybe not
so what's b normally
vso3
so what if we just said no no no b is
zero
what happens then
more blocky less blocky
kind of hard to say
not really that big of a difference
either way i guess one would
one would argue
so we may want to play with that value
as well let's let's zoom on in there
again
i really wish it didn't i really really
wish it did not reset the
view
that makes it really hard to compare
right
so z at 0.5
i don't know still not really good
enough
oh i did type 0.5 oh whoops okay hold on
a second yeah let me let me take a look
at that really quickly
but i don't think this is gonna work
like
it's not quite a it's not quite a
winning strategy you know what i'm
saying
like it's pretty good
it's pretty good it's just not quite a
winning strategy
uh
it's not quite a winning strategy
so i don't know
i don't know
we may have to perk on this
i
and like i said maybe we just go forward
with this and say look you know we know
roughly like
this is basically like what the game
will then look like right like
like this is good enough that we can you
know maybe add a maybe add like a glow
pass
on there and then and then you're
basically like that's it right that's
what the game looks like
and you know the the squariness is not
maybe fabulous but you just say look it
won't really change the look of the game
it'll just improve the quality if later
we try
doing something where maybe we do it on
the gpu and do a denser sampling or
something right
uh and so maybe we just call it a day
and say okay we can go ahead and
and
pull the 3d out of the collision
detector
and then
you know put in some of the gameplay
rooms
and just see assuming that they all look
fine in this we just say look if the
quality improves later it improves but
we don't
like we know what it looks like now
the lighting you can you can have all of
the game design
rooms
can just assume that the lighting looks
basically like this and if the quality
improves from here it shouldn't like
materially change everything in the
design right like it shouldn't
like break anything at that point i
don't think
um
so i would say like yeah we just add
some bloom
because we need that like add
self-illumination and bloom to our past
because right now i don't even know how
that's specified
um i think we had something random in
there for it but it's like not
i don't really remember exactly how like
that's how these things
it's how this stuff is showing up right
now kind of like a bad self-illumination
thing that's happening
um so i know we've got something in
there that's getting past anyway we
should go clean that up and make sure
we're passing down something sane
uh and the other thing we should
probably do is send these things down to
16 bit or something we are sending these
down as full float right now for no
reason at all
uh and that doesn't need to be happening
either i suppose but you know
so
all right
so let's call it a day i think that's
good enough for now
um
we'll have to think a bit uh
we'll have to think about what we want
to do and maybe the answer is like look
for any further quality we're just going
to go ahead and and do this on the gpu
and try to sample the voxel more densely
and that's that that's how that's going
to
improve the
you know
the look or whatever
else you know is supposed to happen
there
um i also don't know i assume that the
the spheres
doesn't help here either uh
i don't think we tried it with the
latest version necessarily but
uh with the spheres
i don't think it would change anything
but we should double check to make sure
that it wouldn't because i don't
actually know
i don't see any really material
difference there
looks about the same
it also really looks
the other thing too is
at eight samples
it actually also looks great as long as
you're in an area with some reasonable
amount of light
so you really only need the 16 samples
when you're in an area like this
where it's higher and even then you can
get away with it so i may leave it at
eight for now as well
uh
and and we'll go from there
all right i'm happy with this i'm happy
to call this the lighting that we'll use
for now
um
yeah i'm happy with that
we can we can just
we can just make that be that
i don't think we have to go any further
than that for now
all right good work team
i can still punch through walls we'll be
fixing that in a moment but
all right
all right i'm going to call that a day i
think we're good uh next time we'll just
add bloom i think is what we'll do
and then we'll just say that's as good
as it's gonna get until we basically
ship like
you know maybe we put this on the gpu
way way um
go back to
yeah the frame rate's a little too high
okay fair enough
um but i think that's it
so we're gonna we're gonna call it
that's just where it's at
so thank you everyone for joining me
it's been a pleasure coding this always
i think the lighting looks fantastic
unfortunately we do have that blockiness
problem
nothing's perfect um
and
i guess what i would say is
we can probably just lean on the gpu to
solve that for us in the future we can
probably just say you know what
um if you want really amazing
circular-ness on your lights then go buy
an nvidia rtx if you can actually find
one
um steal one from the cryptocurrency
miner next door
uh and
you know we'll do a gpu pass at the end
where where we just put the lighting on
the gpu side and and go buy more
hardware if you want to look cleaner
right
um
so
[Music]
so yeah
so there you go
we did the rtx on comparison yeah
exactly all right thanks er for joining
me
uh i'll be back here next week maybe
we'll do the bloom and then we'll just
call the lighting kind of shelled for
now
and move on to cleaning up some of the
other stuff i
probably need to get the room trend
going try to generate some stuff like
room gen and collection detection so
that we can kind of just like play
through some rooms
um
and get the lighting i want the lighting
to work nicely with like the gameplay
down there uh so just try to make that
stuff
uh
make some more sense so we'll we'll get
that going
uh
that's it for today until next time have
fun program everyone and i'll see you on
the internet take it easy everybody