all righty
hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero sure we code a complete game
live on stream uh i have no idea
what we want to do today um to be
completely honest with you
i'm not sure um we probably
i would guess uh should continue our
why did that not i don't even know how
the new four coder thing works with
builds i i have never been able to
figure it out it's extremely confusing
to me
i have a project and i thought it would
build
when i tried to hit build but it doesn't
build and i don't really know why
and i haven't really bothered to figure
it out so if you just start by
being in a file that's part of the
project and you hit build it does build
i i don't know i don't know only alan
orion could tell me the answer to those
questions um
well that's not true we could go find
out ourselves if we were so motivated
i'm not
so we're just gonna say that's what it
does and then uh we're gonna go in here
and run the game now i'm assuming what i
would want to do today
is work on the pressure plates now
the other thing we might want to do is
is work on combat because at this point
we're kind of just talking
um about things that are involved in
making gameplay stuff happen
like in the dungeon areas and whatever
and another thing that i think i
probably want to do is have a convenient
shortcut switch
that i can use uh in order to start
myself off like in the dungeon
because i don't really want to have to
hop here every time when i'm testing
things
um it's we have hot code reloading so i
can just like
reload code when we're standing around
here but the problem is that reloading
code is not really gonna help
uh when we're when we're looking at like
generator stuff you know
um so so to a first approximation
we're gonna need something that gets us
started faster
so i guess what i would say is we have a
couple things uh we would probably want
to do there
and uh you know i don't have a strong
opinion on any of them so i think maybe
the first thing we should start with
is uh before we start working on tiles
again
right uh we probably want to that was
kind of interesting
it seems like it is that because it
doesn't know what room it's in if you go
down low enough
the camera kind of looks like it went up
higher to above the
the camera like went upward but i don't
know why the camera went upward
it's interesting probably because it
doesn't have a room at that point it's
outside
any room geometry anyway uh that doesn't
really matter
we don't care about that at the moment
but the point is uh
so i should probably just start by doing
a quick startup thing so that we can
make sure that we just start
in like a dungeon room because if we
don't just start in the dungeon room all
the time
we're gonna waste all our time like
hopping down here because we want to be
able to quickly see
like when we work on the room generation
stuff or anything else like that
we want to be able to make sure that we
can quickly go ahead and get ourselves
like re-situated right we want to be
able to
to like restart right in in an area
that's relevant
and you know hot code reloading can't
really help us
if it's world generation stuff because
when we hot reload code
we keep the same the world the way it is
right
um we could add a key that like destroys
the world and creates a new one
um but again that would pop us back to
the beginning of the game so like for
example if i did that
we've created a new world now but the
problem is
we're back at start so we still have to
hop all the way down
right so uh that seems to me like
something we should probably
work on right like something where we're
actually going to have
an easy time showing up in a place that
actually makes
sense uh and you know
i assume that we could just make it so
that the world generator just skips the
generation of the orphanage altogether
that's probably fine um because
i would assume that like you know
we don't need the orphanage to get
generated when we're just working on the
dungeon area
so for example in here well actually you
know we don't skip the
it doesn't even matter we can still
generate the orphanage we'll just place
the hero somewhere else so you can see
here like we do a dungeon
create dungeon like that and if we
look at the dungeon data you can see
that there's an entrance room
so i think that if we just did this
where we said okay there's a start room
equals
dungeon entrance room
we can just do that and now it will
start us
in right where the dungeon is i think
right
um i take it back that does not
look like it worked at all
oh never mind
that is not what that is
that is the room we start laying out at
that's cool so that started laying out
at a totally different place
but it still placed us in the same place
that's interesting okay so actually
it's this that we care about and this
places the camera there
which i guess is what we care about you
can see us even we had one in here for
placing ourselves in the forest so i
guess we can just do this
the same thing um and just say all right
there's a
volume here that we're going to place
the hero at and and off we go
there we go um so this starts us off in
this room here
the the entrance room that we're talking
about which seems good
i feel like the entrance room shouldn't
have a door because it's an entrance way
so i don't know that you should have to
hop on a door to get in there
maybe you do maybe you don't i don't
know but that's something to think about
um but okay so now that we're starting
here we got a lot of stuff we can do now
so the first thing i'd like to do
um probably just looking at it is we
need to actually place these tiles
in actually interesting patterns in the
rooms right
so when you like when you look at one of
these things the idea is that these
those tiles want to be placed
in the room and they want to be placed
in some kind of gameplay
relevant way right uh
so like to be honest i don't
really think that they want to be placed
next to each other even like they don't
really want to be contiguous
like this i think they more want to be
placed kind of randomly
throughout the room um
using some kind of a like you know
scattering
because the idea is you have to hop
on the various tiles to open up the next
door
and we don't really want them to be all
next to each other probably
um i mean maybe sometimes they can be
next to each other
but i don't know that
yeah you know it's it's that's a pretty
tough one i don't really know
um maybe they do kind of want to be more
like in a pattern
because i could see that being kind of
fun like you have to kind of hop through
the pattern so so all right
um so yeah i guess i would say
uh maybe maybe i take it back maybe they
are
supposed to be in a pattern and then
maybe like
how that works is we try to place the
pattern
in the room like we're doing now um
we just need the thing we don't have is
right now the pattern is like
always right
placed the in the it searches you can
imagine it's starting
up here right like if you look at what's
going on in here
um you can kind of see like okay we
start at the upper corner of a room
right and we just go until
ah camera
it'd be nice if there was some way to
like not have the camera do
that thing um
to to have the camera not show these
upper rooms
uh when we're in debug mode they
automatically fade out in game play but
they don't in debug mode anyway point
being
what you can kind of see here if we look
at these rooms
um is that you get all it always puts it
in the top corner and the reason for
that
is just that it just starts in the top
corner and then
uh keeps trying until it can find a
place to put it
and since it pretty much can always put
it in the top corner
like there's no reason it will ever fail
to put it in that top corner
it just always ends up in the top
quarter so even once we make kind of
more interesting patterns
it will really it will be like really
heavily biased towards the top corner of
the room
if we don't do something about that now
one question is do we want it to
actually be biased like do we want it to
just always place the pattern like in
the middle of the room
and then keep trying till it can find a
place to put it
uh that like spirals outward
from the middle of the room for example
because we could do something like that
and you know maybe that's what we want i
don't know
i would say maybe let's try that
just because i can't really think of
any reason not to um
let's let's take a look so if we if we
look
um at one of these like pending entity
things
and you know this might be an
opportunity for us to do
uh
this might be an opportunity for us to
do one of the things that i was
thinking we wanted to do right which was
create
a thing that houses these uh
like bundles them up into bundles
basically
so that rather than getting gen entities
back from things you get like a gen
entity group
right like this thing um
you get one of these back for everything
so everything is an entity group and
then
the thing that was the entity group is
actually a group of groups
right or a list of groups because we now
are pretty much always placing sort of
templates of things that have multiple
entities in them and it was kind of a
pain in the butt to use this thing
so i think we might want to do that as
well and this would give us an
opportunity to do that because you would
end up with something more like this
where you say like all right there's a
gen entity group
um you you have
you know and it could be like a genetic
list maybe is a better way to do it
or or pattern you know something like
that and
you have that
and these are actually what you
stack up so instead of this
it's actually a pattern you know
and that way you would just say these
we build the pattern itself could store
some information
like about uh you know
where it wants to start so you know
there would be something like
a uh like a starting
you know like a flag that says where in
the
where in the room you want to start
roughly
it could even be like a uv kind of like
a bias sort of a thing
it could be something like you know
start p
bias where we basically say or start p
u v or something like that where we say
okay
given the room zero zero you know point
five point five would be the center zero
zero be upper or lower left corner or
something you know whatever it is
and we would just say that's gonna be
our
[Music]
the way in which we go about laying
these things out
they're gonna they're gonna follow that
pattern
right so if we assume that's the case
you could see making these entity
patterns and saying i want to place this
starting in the middle starting in the
upper corner starting the other corner
you know something like that um
and and the rest of this would just
remain the same you know there
we wouldn't have to do anything else i
don't think
and so maybe that works okay
um and the only problem that i have
here is just that like
you sort of have a boundary
like this this template sort of has a
size to it
and it's a little confusing because if
you allow
the thing to be a little bit flexible
with how the pattern is generated
it's tough to sort of see how it gets
placed
if if the pattern is always rigid
which i'll be honest seems like it might
need to be
um
so you can sort of see maybe why i'm
not sure what to do about this and and
this may just be a case
of us over complicating things like
maybe i just need to change
this stuff and so instead of doing this
where you do like
ins it could be that i've done this one
level too
low right so maybe the answer is
look we should not have entity creators
that was just a bad idea
what we have is pattern creators and
pattern creators are just custom written
right
because the more i think about this i'm
just like how are we ever going to get
this to work we basically have to encode
so much smarts into this thing you know
what i mean
that it just doesn't make a whole lot of
sense how that's ever gonna work
you know so i feel like what we want is
instead of doing what we did here where
we're sort of saying look
let's buffer up all the stuff that's
going to get created and then have this
thing try to create it in the room
maybe what we'd rather do is say all
right for every
thing that's a collection that's a call
into a function that knows how to create
that thing and it
does its own probing to figure out like
where to put stuff
you know um
and the reason i say that is just
because thinking about how complicated
this would get
once you're trying to do gameplay stuff
you have so many metrics you might want
to take account in there
it just feels like we're going to have
to create our own kind of hacky code
to do some of these things because
there's not going to be like a good
formal way to describe
what we're trying to accomplish there
without just making a whole programming
language inside this pattern generator
thing
you know so it kind of seems to me
like maybe this was just a bad idea so
maybe that's the goal for today
convert this to something that does not
work that way right
so convert this into something where
instead of gen entity group and this
being gen entity
um i mean maybe we leave these names
because that's
still fine but maybe what we do here
instead
is this gen entity thing actually just
has
uh it has a call that's like
pattern creator and it it
takes all that it takes like what kind
of pattern you were trying to create
using a bunch of parameters or something
and then it creates that and this stuff
doesn't really exist anymore
so you know uh if we look at all the
places that are
actually doing this right so if we if we
then go
into the room generator where this stuff
is actually called
uh and you can see like there's a couple
places where you know we're doing sort
of
uh generating trees and stuff like this
right
these would just turn into calls
directly to those things
so like add inanimate or whatever would
just get called directly and that's
better
that seems just better period right
and then this stuff here where we're
generating things
um the the door stuff
would just call that obstacle but then
this thing where we
where we loop through the group this
rather than calling
find place to put entity group would
just call the function
it just straight up calls the function
right there
you know what i'm saying um
so let's try that
that seems
that seems like what i want
that seems like what i want so i'm going
to go into gen entity
um or sorry entity gen
and right here we've got the gen create
entity thing that wraps
these calls and i'm gonna say that
that's not a thing anymore
so uh well okay i don't even have to do
that i can just say
that there's a gen create entity uh
like pattern uh
something like that right or gen create
pattern
and uh it probably should be an indie
pad
and we say the name and in here what
happens is
we call this function which is like you
know whatever it is
and it gets past basically just
the region and then the thing
so
the spec i guess whatever you want to
call it and it will get
all of the data that this thing needed
so when it was
coming through here all of the stuff
that this was using
it will receive so for example it will
take
uh the grid
i don't know what this thing was called
there's like this weird grid thing we
made to help with construction
edit grid so it'll take the edit grid
um and the sim region the
the edit grid probably has the sim
region
in it yeah so actually it just needs the
edit grid
um it needs the spec that it was given
so the thing that the the entity like
pattern you know maybe this is called
the pattern
uh so you do gen pattern you call this
thing
with the pattern it creates all of the
entities that it needs
and hopefully that's kind of it
so then in here at the bottom of this
we just have some of these right
so in like in here
uh we would have one for each of the
things that we're currently creating
so all of the places that we're doing
stuff
in like world gen now that created those
just become calls to these rather than
what they were doing before
so for example uh when
we go down to
where's like it's like this stuff
yeah so when we look at this like from
now on
like there wouldn't be like anything
happening
inside place cat right
um so instead and this would also i
guess get us out of this iterate options
stuff
as well um so the options thing that
looks for places to put things that
probably doesn't have to happen anymore
because now we can just look at the time
so this might simplify things i don't
really know
um so we'll see but you can see here
we've got
four of these that we would do
right so i think what happens
is we just say yeah okay
there's the cat placement thing
which just literally does this i think
okay so no i take it back the option
thing is fine because that's just
picking which room it is
right so that's actually fine
so uh this right here uh
is probably all we really need to do so
it's it's it's like this
right
so when we do
place cat it just says cr
you know i don't know what this is this
is the cat
function or whatever um
we would just say add pattern
um add cat
right and then the thing that actually
adds the cat
because it's it would just get welded in
right
so it would just be this
i think
right and the nice part about this is a
lot of the stuff gets simpler because
now it's actually just creating an
entity and we don't have to duplicate
all of that stuff
so we can just create the entity um
using the region that comes in on the
grid
we can add the flags that we want for
the cat
we can use the um
the base asset can just come from that
pattern structure
so we can preserve that concept because
that still works well
like um this tags thing
i guess would be it so
i guess in here
i guess in there i'm not really sure
how much
i don't want to change too much at once
but i feel like that stuff can be really
simplified now as well because we have
sort of those more convenient things for
working
with the with the um classes and all
that
but you know oh oh well
so let me take it one step at a time but
anyway so we're going to add an entity
here we'll do this work we'll pretend we
have one of these base asset things
which we don't really have
uh it would come from from this uh and
then we would just create it in here
uh and that would just be things that
you specify on the cat that you actually
want
um and we know that it has to be a cat
so that tag thing could also be
specified there
i suppose
and it's a little annoying that you have
to do you still have to do this
thing you know what i mean
i don't know it has to loop over that
gen thing but it seems like it's a
little annoying
we could pr it seems like we should be
able to get rid of this you know what
i'm saying
like i feel like this should be able to
go away
um so we'll see i'm just gonna go slowly
for a little while and we'll see what
ends up happening
so uh
this can just go away now
these are actually now i think just
straight up calls right so
we don't really need them to be yeah we
don't really need them to be
uh function pointers anymore i don't
think
we'll leave them that way for now
because there's no reason not to
but we don't actually need to do that so
when you create one of these you just
have the entity piece asset
base asset thing um entity piece asset
is a tag hash and a variant so you can
see why this doesn't really make
much sense to me um an asset tag hash
is just one of these things and you can
you know you can munch them however you
want
so i'm not sure we care about that
either so
i kind of feel like this gennady tag
builder thing should go away
it doesn't really make any sense anymore
and
i don't think we really need it for
anything so
i would suspect that we can we can
eliminate that too
um just by thinking it through a little
bit better
so yeah um
[Music]
let's just go whole hog
let's just go whole hog so let's just
get rid of all this stuff
so we have asset tag hash here
and the thing with asset tag hash is
we want to be able to generate that
thing
um conveniently
and and modify it right and i'm pretty
sure
that we have uh hash stuff for that so
like
you can see us doing stuff like getting
tag ashes here and you can extract
things from it
it's just an it just it just builds
these things up right you can see it's
like category plus some
some hash stuff there right it's it's
pretty straightforward what's happening
so i feel like you know we can just
we can just do that so i think what
we'll do is we'll just say okay entity
tag hash is what we're storing
it's just what's going on um and we'll
leave it like that
when we go through here this is going to
be the pattern creator thing now so this
is a type def
gen create pattern
and that oops
so that's the pattern and all the rest
of this stuff can probably stay the same
um facing direction
probably shouldn't be there anymore
i mean
i'm going to leave that out because i
don't know that we care about that
at the moment so we've got gennady flag
with the gen flags allow directions for
next
that's just you know not necessary
anymore at all
i don't think so this would go away
that would go away um
i think all of this stuff goes away so i
think we're really just looking at this
so there's stuff here where you say like
what the tags are coming in as
and we may want to change this a little
bit to something that's like
you know this could even be something
more like asset tag id
you know id or like
tags like that where we just say
these are used by the caller however
they want
and we don't really know uh so the
creator just uses these tags
for something you know what i mean and
we'll see
we may not even need that but but i
think we might just in terms of knowing
which particular assets supposed to go
where
i don't know we'll find out so it'd be
more like this
and uh so the pattern creator thing
would just get called here
and these would all just be functions
right so these just take region
take the region and they add the thing
and that's it
um so they're literally just
they're back to what they used to be
right they're back to just
calls that add entities which again is
just about
simplifying life it's trying to make
this less complicated because it was
just getting
it was it was putting too much stuff on
top that didn't really need to be there
and so i think it would be fine so this
isn't takes an asset tag hash for base
asset so these all look like that and
now we can just make these regular
function calls so that they can actually
take
other things as well depending on what
they are so they're just more flexible
as well if that makes sense
so i think that should be fine
um
that all looks fine
i think we said we wanted to be able to
steal heads from orphans so this should
probably
change
while we're at it
we said we want to be able to steal
heads from orphans or swap heads with
orphans
um so so that should probably change
uh
you know do you swap heads or do you
swap bodies
in this game it would make more sense
thematically if you swap bodies
so like you hop you do the swap and you
swap
your head with
with their body and then you hop around
on their body would probably make more
sense
you know
[Music]
that would probably make more sense but
i don't know doesn't matter either way
you're going to be swapping something
so yeah so you know in here where we add
orphan it should really probably be two
entities
right and those entities should be just
linked together
like the hero is so at some point we
should do that it's just something to
remember to do
all right so
back to our story so yeah these are just
gonna be
like this now
and
now we've got all of our creation code
looking a little bit better uh this
stuff
gen entity at p is just setting the
result p
to something which doesn't seem super
useful but
you know whatever um so i think
that probably doesn't really need to be
here none of this stuff does
these probably would rather just be a
call that places something somewhere
so you can say like place and then you
do whatever the thing is what you're
going to
be placing so you know
maybe this is just place entity at p
you know what i mean uh and it
presumably
doesn't need anything but that
you know what i'm saying um and we could
even do this as
an operator if you wanted i don't think
i want to go that far because we don't
really do that in handmade hero but we
could
uh same thing here so if you do like nd
and we say
i guess we don't care about
about that part because we would just
not call this so we do something more
like
um place entity at traversable
and place entity on traversible
so this would just be a traversal
reference standing on
so something like this
and the difference between and on would
just be whether or not they occupy it
right so you put it there and you either
occupy it or you don't right so
here's that this would just be
exactly what it looks like
right
that sort of thing um so we've got
monstar and familiar here
which we're not really using at the
moment
so we'll just leave those up at the top
because maybe we want to add monstar
and familiar at some point um
that all looks fine and then we just
have the actual pattern
generation stuff right so now where you
do play snake
or whatever it is this stuff right
this just goes away because the play
snake thing
is just gonna be inside the gen the
entity creator
part right
so literally you would just say
this whole thing
goes in here
right uh and this would create
everything
and
we would just call stuff like add
snakehead directly
so the and then we just
we just need to start thinking about how
we want to try to create these patterns
but they can be
a lot smarter now than they used to be
uh and we can start hacking them and
it's just it's a lot of code
unfortunately like that we'll have to
write but i don't know really any way
around it
because we need something that's pretty
flexible right
that makes sense um so anyway
uh that all looks fine
that all looks fine
[Music]
um this could probably be simplified to
just say use the brain id
of the head so this would just be add
brain
here um
undead and bones is just what the tag is
right and so
we can i think do this
and skip this whole ad tag thing you can
see why
i want to do this because this this code
is just too much
there's too much code that's not doing
anything other than bookkeeping
and so i'm just going to try to keep
collapsing this down until it's smoother
that's the real goal here is to smooth
it out
you know what i'm saying um
so yeah in add snakehead um
in this case you can see that it's just
gonna do
all of the basic stuff we needed it to
do
and then we're gonna set the brain up
here then we're gonna place the entity
at
a p um actually this is going to be a
non-traversable kind of a thing right
and this is the part that's going to be
hard
and then we will just try to create
these segments
and we will go through and
do add snake body for each segment
and
and i think that gets rid of that code
this stays the same
[Music]
we don't know what that will do
we don't care about this anymore that
goes away
so i think now we're yeah so you can see
like basically
this stuff now is more what we wanted to
write
and furthermore we can probably just
collapse these
we can snake heads and bodies are
presumably all getting generated by the
snake pattern generator anyway
we could even collapse those down right
so now basically what we're doing is
we're regressing the code
now that we've got a new routing in
place we're trying to get the code back
to the simplicity that it was at
originally
where you just kind of created this
stuff in
line right um
and that's the goal so yeah you can see
here like where we added the head
so here we would just say okay the head
is there
um
like so
um we made a collision volume for it
for whatever reason we add this piece to
it
which is the body piece we add the light
to it we connect this to the world
and we give it some hit point oops
um we will call this headlight
and that uh lets us just create
this thing in line right then for each
segment
we would say take the snake body and put
that in here
i don't know why those have lights so i
might suggest that we just don't do that
anymore
um so then in here we would say okay
snake segments
does what it does um
this collision volume and that collision
volume
are like the same collision volume so
maybe we just use the same one for now
and then uh when we're actually
making the visual piece here which
actually no that's not true so it's this
visual piece that gets connected to the
world here this
this part uh
this is just the head the headpiece it's
not the headlight
this is the headlight okay um so this is
just the body piece
or the seg piece it's kind of annoying
how you have to make both those calls
i feel like these should be a little bit
more condensed like it's just too much
work
right but anyway there's a segment
this goes away that stays in
[Music]
um and so there's our snake creator and
we could do better i think we can
collapse some of these down a little bit
they're a little bit too verbose in my
opinion
um but now it's nicely condensed it's
not strewn all over the place like it
was before
so i think that's better
um i guess that's an on the cat does
take up a square
so i think that's better i'm happier
with that
and so then
yeah if okay so if we look at the base
asset now
then probably what we would do is say
tag zero
goes here and that was undead
and uh and then bones right
so you can see that would pull the base
asset out and then switch it each time
which
maybe means yeah maybe we do maybe we
can just make that be
um locked in there
where this can just be an asset tag hash
um and maybe there are multiple of these
eventually
i don't know so maybe we do do that and
we just say
okay uh you pass in
what kind of a snake you wanted right
and then we pull that out of the pattern
like so
so then when you say that you wanted a
snake
which somebody does
yeah so then when you when you wanted a
snake
we could say something like uh place
pattern
or add pattern
um and it would be something like this
right
you see what i'm saying so you'd go like
okay add this pattern we want a snake
pattern in this room
uh we want it to be we want to have this
these tags um it goes in this room
something like that and if i need my
four coder
indentation to get better i need like
somebody needs to remind me off stream
to go talk to ryan and alan
and update to the newest stuff because
i'm behind and i think they fixed this
stuff
i just am behind unfortunately
um so that is what we're talking about
right um
and maybe
maybe it's something like
this
actually you know
um
[Music]
maybe that's maybe that's what we're
talking about
and then similarly like
this would be would actually be more
like
that
seems like a plan
okay
wait so which one is which the previous
room
the snake goes in this room the priest
room yeah okay so that we don't really
we don't care about what
how that we can deal with that later
okay
so this is going to be a tile pattern
um for a switch pattern
tile switch pattern i don't know
so we just do something like this where
we add these things
and then we you know we make them do
whatever it is that they
do or something it's fine doesn't matter
point being
uh we create those and then we can set
these things which get passed through as
parameters
and then they get called later when we
actually need to
add those things to the room
um and you know the only thing i would
say
is that i i suspect we're probably going
to end up wanting to put
this stuff in a more like
my suspicion is that this is all just a
gigantic waste of our time
um i'm gonna do it in these steps anyway
to take it slower but i'm guessing that
what we're actually going to want to do
is get rid of this entirely and they'll
eventually
this thing will eventually just be a
giant flags field or something
that just says here's all the stuff
that's supposed to be in this room
because we're probably going to want to
do stuff that goes oh if there's snakes
and switches then do this
right so it's probably going to have to
be like you call
gen room and gen room is this giant
function that's like does all this crazy
stuff
right but we're gonna wanna do that
checking so i think this was probably
just a bad idea because
although the world um can probably get a
you know maybe can get away with how we
did it i think
rooms can't be cannot because of
their they're like the central aspect of
the gameplay they have to be
sort of knowledgeable about all the
things that are going on
in them so i really don't know that this
makes sense as a thing
right but we'll see
so anyway i think that's all of the
things that have that sort of pattern
like thing happening
so in here then when i when i make one
of those
gen create entity pattern
tile switch pattern i can now take this
out and dump it in
and
uh we've got this place orphan thing and
that's really a gen
create entity pattern uh this is like a
it's it's not really an orphan pattern
per se um it's sort of
it's sort of more like a
it's it's sort of more like a npc
pattern so like this doesn't probably
need to be
specific in that way
um it can probably be
more like
where does orphan name tag go in this
by the way
it's here
okay um so if we make this pattern
the orphan name tag thing i guess
goes at the beginning of the orphan so i
guess
it's like gen entity
pattern or canonity
orphan or i don't even know what's the
result i guess
result equals add
pattern um
we call these patterns so npc pattern
so we're going to add an npc pattern
here and then i think we just do result
base asset equals get tag hash and it's
going to be orphan
name tag uh and asset none
probably
i mean i don't really know i'm not sure
how this thing was supposed to work and
i don't care
so anyway uh it's gonna be something
like this where you
where you have just that first pat part
of it there
um and then this that's literally all
this thing does
and you can see that this is kind of
stupid like these are not
these really make any sense and they're
kind of dumb
so uh if we move on from there
and and this is probably this is extra
stupid
like all this stuff is really stupid and
we should probably
change it um whatever point being
if we look at this these are the same
you know these
are these are the same the same code
so it's it's just this
it's it's something like that right and
we'll work on that later
so when we do place cat and place orphan
these are actually just place npc you
know what i'm saying
oops
and i don't think we want uh this stuff
because you know this this should just
be tag hannah
tag fred and tag molly
you know this this should not be none of
this stuff
should be the way it is so placing npcs
in the world should just be like
you know i don't know
why we did it this way but you know it's
not not necessarily bad but there's
the you know the people
and the cats and so those are all placed
around
and we should
then say i don't know
uh here's the place npc
pattern
and
it wouldn't be add orphan
it would just be like add this npc
um
and and i don't know we're just gonna
we're just gonna dump this crap
directly in here is what we're actually
gonna do
like that um so here we create the
actual orphan
tag orphan should really be in there on
the npc pattern
so this like npc should be like tag
orphan probably although is orphan even
in there i don't know
let's look at what the tags are because
we probably want to update those
as well
like where is tag orphan is that even in
here
so it's orphan and then the thing and
then what are the cats
yeah so like this like this stuff i
don't know
that doesn't really make any sense so i
think this should be more like that's
fred
you know that's hannah um
and that's molly and when you look at
these i don't know
if they really need like cat
put in front of them
you know it doesn't really make much
sense because it's just
that that's just the character same with
these like i don't know
that you actually need these to say
orphan because it's just
whoever the person is you know
and putting i don't know what putting
orphan in front of it
does for you other than just make
matters more complicated for no reason
so i do wonder if we want to just do
something more like this
um right because i'm not sure what the
point is
of over complicating the tags because i
think the tags were just kind of dumb
and we only really need them
we only really need them to do stuff for
us that we actually care about
so if we want to say like here is
the body of the thing and the head of
the thing then it makes sense to have a
separate tag that's like what part is it
so it's dylan
head dylan body or whatever right
that stuff makes a lot of sense the
other stuff doesn't and
furthermore the fact that there's asset
type
with base like that stuff is dumb we
should get rid of that as well
it should just be the tags here are like
layered body or body layered those are
the two tags we needed
the rest of this stuff was just a waste
of time right
um so yeah we just we have a tremendous
amount of work to do
uh to clean all this stuff up that's
just the nature of the beast
like it's fine you know i don't mind uh
but when you actually can start to see
how things should be working
you want to do it right you don't want
to just go oh we didn't do it that way
before so we're not going to do it that
way now
you know what i mean um
that's just a bad excuse
so we have molly fred and hannah now um
and they're gonna be in there and i
don't remember
uh where do we have our there it is i'm
like wait no we've got a
so let's do molly
fred hannah
and
there we go now these are all
capitalized but in the game ht they're
lower case so i guess these tags are
case insensitive
i guess
not sure why but that's what we did so
it is
okay um so
getting rid of like orphan in here
because it's not
useful oops
i'm just going to remove it just looking
i'm just going to remove it manually
because i don't
really want to remove it automatically
right now because i
want to see where this is actually being
done
why would that ever be the default i'm
so confused about why
the default is to delete up to the thing
and then if you hit it again it deletes
the rest of it like that makes it
impossible to ever delete
one thing using that hotkey it kind of
makes the hotkey
worthless but somehow that's the default
it's really weird
at least it seems like it is i don't
know maybe it's not
um so i think that's
fine uh for now we don't have to look at
the rest of this stuff
that's all is what it is
yeah um okay so
let's keep going here so let's
do a structs
like so um
[Music]
and the recursive open tile search thing
like i said i don't really know
um that we want to keep doing this
so i'm just going to say that that goes
away like that's going away
as is this um well
so i guess i don't know no because i
don't even want to go in that order
anyway
so those are all going away goodbye um
i don't care about any of this i don't
think
let me look at where that's used
yeah so so all of that stuff i can
i think i can just do directly now so i
probably
will do all that stuff directly
now yeah what's this stuff
yeah so all of this stuff is pointless
and we can get rid of it so lots of code
can go away
which is great um so get piece asset can
get
can get removed goodbye
and goodbye
alrighty so in here where we're doing
entity visible piece and we do the chain
testing
all we have to do here is just say oh
well just call get tag hash
because now you can build the tags uh
directly
right and
we should be able to make that work
right
[Music]
um
and i thought we had one of these
that specifically works
nope yeah
i thought we had one of these that
specifically did the changing of the
hash
from the actual hash
did we not
oh weird so it's just called get tag
hash
there you go
um
what does ad piece take
oh weird and any visible pieces take
those this is so crazy what we're
looking at here
so so this is all and that's just an
asset tag hash plus a variant
okay
this is crazy
this is so crazy because you're looking
it's like the entity visible piece
already has a variant
in it right here
right
so that's all really kind of nuts um
yeah we need to simplify this stuff this
is my this is just two nuts
all right so we're going to have to take
this slow because there's way too much
crap
in here right so when we add these
these don't have any variants anyway
right
so anytime you do an ad piece call you
should be fine
to just not pass that right and i have
no idea what's going on with the variant
stuff
because why would you need an additional
variant
right like it doesn't make any sense so
we must have done that and kind of only
half finished it
because there's a variant value right
here and then there's one right here
as well you know what i mean and so
maybe that was meant to be welded in
or maybe it wasn't i don't know but it
doesn't really make a lot of sense
why you would need to do that
i think it was probably just because we
had such a long conduit we thought we
would save ourselves time by doing that
right
but forget that
because now that we're actually creating
these things directly where they're
actually spec'd
we shouldn't need to do that anymore
right
so we can grab the variant here
and
[Music]
we can get the bitmap match there
and be done uh okay
so get tag hash add piece
blah blah blah blah um
here's a bunch of ad piece nonsense with
assets
uh i don't know what these other ad
piece calls are okay so they're these
so it's just
that and i think we're probably good now
so kind of just a pain in the butt
but you know it's always seems obvious
once you do stuff
this goes away
um gen create
entity pattern
we've got to get rid of the semicolon
and we're back so change hash just isn't
a thing anymore it's just get hash
uh
i don't know what that is complaining
about
oh it doesn't know what the base asset
is
so that's actually in the
gen in the pattern
so it's it's just the pattern right
is where that is so that's pretty easy
so here's the thing we don't know
when we add the cat we're not really
sure where it's gonna go
um here's the snake pattern and
i guess this is technically like the cat
pattern
right um
and really i guess it's npc pattern now
so i guess we don't even need cat
pattern maybe
i mean maybe we do maybe we don't we'll
we'll look at that
i guess later but i'm gonna remove that
for now
so okay uh
[Music]
should be kind of okay here except for
the placement part i would think that
would be the only
real thing that's broken um
because everything else should be okay
and so really we should just be left
with the placement calls
in red which is exactly what we have
um these don't return anything so that
doesn't need to happen
um same here
so the tile switch pattern now
uh we can just do exactly what this is
doing
uh this none of this
has to happen so so now all we're really
going to be doing
is looking at that particular element of
the grid
so so the code that used to have to
happen
in here uh happens
outside of here now right so basically
this code
um is now what's happening
it's what's happening uh none of that
happens anymore
in fact this and this code will be going
away right
so this is the actual code that we need
to to now
call in here we get the content
structural
thing so this part it's it's this right
we are going to look through uh the area
that we're at
which is like the part we don't know is
where it is but we're gonna get it
we don't need that um
we're going to take the brain slot of
that thing
so you know
uh this part will be coming from the
pattern
whatever it told us the brain was and
then the slot keeps going i
suspect i'm just going to say
that this is probably not in there
it's probably just that now um
we don't care about that
we don't care about this or that because
that's all fixed now
this is the part we need to set for this
thing
we don't need any of this
we do need any of this
no no right
so all of that is fine and
this is just the entity that we're going
to edit so
this is i think all we need uh
and and that just works right
that seems good
um then we get down to here so now we're
into
placing we got to do the stuff for
placing the npcs we're almost done with
these so that's good so again
not too bad a pretty major code
reorganization but but really not too
bad
you know not not super horrible
probably finish it next weekend right
not not not too long of a thing
it's probably like a three hour three
hour reorg roughly
something like that
all right so then we get into here and
uh yeah
later this will become fancier because
we'll probably have like actual edit
like actual tag stuff we'll set but for
now again we don't we just modify the
places
and so in here we say npc pattern okay
we've got the orphan
we don't really need that uh we
we don't really need any of this so
now we have like what's our facing
direction going to be well we'll just
store that in a variable
and then we'll try to put this entity
in in places so there's one entity with
a body and a head
looks like how that works the pieces
for their facing direction um
need to have that set so
i assume that the entity just sets its
facing direction i think that we don't
need to set it on individual pieces they
all inherit it right
it's just like a transform hierarchy so
they get it from their parent
so that's all fine uh this should just
work i think
right all that's fine
yeah actually i think all that just
works
right
the base asset comes from the pattern
so that's done and then
yeah we're we're where we are
and inside this uh
append entity thing like this none of
this has to happen so
we just need the the part where we
actually place this stuff
in the world so like this stuff here
um is is what we would be talking about
and it's like
this kind of a thing so we would place
uh the entity
on a traversible and we don't know how
to do that yet
and we would place this one at a
traversible and we don't know how to do
that yet
so those are the two parts we don't we
don't know
as far as ad conversation is concerned
i don't know that we need that to really
be
a uh callable thing but we might
so i'm gonna leave it that way i don't
think there's a base asset for that
in fact it doesn't use it right so
so it's just that
oops and obviously we don't need
any of this so it's literally just
placing that thing
somewhere and we just don't know where
so the dialog gets placed there and so
yeah i'm going to think we're pretty
much we've pretty much ported all of
that code now and the
main thing we need to do now is start
thinking about how those patterns will
actually work
so let's go ahead and clean up some of
this stuff
before we do that um and then you know
then at that point i think we'll
probably call it a day so
this ad entity call is really now an ad
pattern call
and it takes the gen entity pattern
thing
or whatever it is uh i don't
even remember what's called gen crate
pattern
um
so it's like that and
add tag is not a thing
and
append entity is also not a thing
uh place entity is
also not a thing
um
right so
hold on
yeah so it's really that
yeah and so really this thing doesn't
need to look like this
either so
so why why are there even two of these
what what even is the point of that
anyone want to tell me because i don't
really see it
so like when we place one of these
things
why are we not just saying look the add
the pattern to this room
like that's what we're doing right so
when we say add pattern
it should just be like you add it to the
room
because where else are you gonna put it
right um and you always know
which one you're doing really
i mean i guess we could stratify it
out but like
so so i don't know like this this
doesn't
like i think i could be really wrong
about this but i feel like
you're adding these groups and the
groups are now
all you need you don't need another
level down
right because a room has a set of these
and there aren't multiple of these
so i'm pretty sure really what we're
looking at is this
right um
so let's just do it
let's just finish it off
damn i gotta fix this thing
um
it's the weirdest thing like i wish i
knew what the logic was for that
it makes no sense to me you go back one
token
it thinks that was a token but in no
universe could that possibly be a token
but then if you have like this
and you delete it deletes the comma and
the token
it's so weird it's like it's it's
on underscores it's super conservative
and on
commas it's super aggressive and i have
no idea where that
why that's happening or why you would
ever want that more importantly
like i mean i guess there must be some
reason but
i i'm just i'm not sure why that why
that would be a thing
you would ever do
okay so we've got our little patterns
here and
i'm just going to say that that's what
happens so you do add pattern
and you give it the room that you're
adding the pattern on
like so it does this garbage
here like so and it just says
okay like here's the pattern
that you asked for that's really
annoying
um and then you just go like okay
results
result results this goes away
and we do
first pattern first
pattern and
that okay so we create one of these
we set the next we make the room oops
we make the room by tommy wiseau
uh
add that on and now i think we are good
to
go okay okay so what else we got
um
okay that all looks fine
uh place nbc looks like the only thing
that's actually doing the search
that way so that's probably fine um
that all looks fine here's the ad
pattern uh this is the room so we need
to pass
past the room with tom erwiseau
and then i think those are the placement
things which we know we need to
fix anyway uh this is just a genetic
pattern
otherwise i think it's what it
should be that all looks right
um
that's just a spelling error so
looks good
and
looks like we added like a chair at some
point i don't
who cares about that at all
um
all right so
here's the part that we actually were um
this is where we actually had the
variant stuff so let's try and clean
this up now so we can
we can figure out what the heck we want
to do because it's all going to be
inside generate room like
that's where all of the garbage is going
to be
so uh forget tree tags
you can see already we've got the piece
here we're creating
i don't even really know like that's not
in the cube this is adding
the tree entity so i'm pretty sure we
just change all this
and just say we just call add tree right
is what actually happens here so i think
this
this should all be simplified quite a
bit right it's just because this code
like you know we've never really spent
any time we just dump stuff into it
and never spend any time looking at
going like how should this actually work
so uh get tree tags is fine
um but i don't know that we really need
it i think what we can do instead
is just have a thing that's like add
tree or whatever it needs to be
yeah um so let's try that i'm gonna go
over into energy gen here
and i'm just gonna have up here like an
ad tree call for now
where we do an internal thing where
we're just like okay
add the tree here's the thing that you
know does
whatever random randomization we were
doing before
so i don't have to think about it and
this is just like
add tree and
you know it it adds the tree uh
for right now we're just gonna we're not
even gonna pass anything in because we
don't even
pass in data about what kind of tree it
should be i guess although
you know we'll see if we actually did
have some of that in here we can pass it
through but for now we're gonna assume
we don't because i don't know that we
did
um and then we're just gonna say like
okay
you can see here like the way that we're
adding this stuff on here
we we just need to change the way that
we're looking at this because
we we don't just stack up tags randomly
and throw it into a tag matcher anymore
there's like specific tags that go with
specific things
so we're going to want to fix the way
this thing is doing what it's doing and
that's fine
but first things first let's deal with
the tree part
so you can see here this is the tree
thing so
what we would do here is just do add
tree right
so we would do add tree and
we would place the tree so
we do that and then like place tree
on traversible or sorry place entity on
traversible
and that's the traversible i don't
really know what that is about or why we
care
um but it'd be something like this and
when we add the tree
uh
it would i mean that would be it right
it just adds the tree
and and there's the tree so i think
uh it's something like this
uh where this
where we do add uh inanimate that
creates
uh one of these things so the first
piece
uh wants to have a variant set for it
um and so we could even just have it so
that if this is just you know this is
just a variant
comes in here and it's normally set to
zero we can even just do that
if we want to select body variants
equals variance
something like that so that in here
where we do
add tree we can say
add obstacle
the variant is some random number
whatever it is uh and then the
asset tag hash is just
i you know this this thing
and that's it so i mean man like
so much sort of crazy bookkeeping
gets eliminated which i think is just a
good sign
um we we
don't know what we're doing with this
stuff yet i mean to be sure
so we're pretty far from out of the
woods on the placement side of things
but that's the part that we know is
going to be hard anyway because we just
have to write code that does
intelligent stuff for that which is
going to be tough
um but anyway so if we go ahead and do
add obstacle here again
rather than having to make these calls
we just do the actual thing
in place which i think is way better
so we do it uh the tag hash here uh the
ref
part of this is is it the placement call
right so this would just be
uh place unity on traversible
i mean i'm just gonna call it lamp
and uh you know
that's it that's that's all we're doing
um
so yeah let's fix this up uh asset hash
random choice tag winter tag none uh
what's the complaint is you don't know
who jen is
ah so it needs the entropy um so this
needs
a way to get entropy uh for the
randomization
so i'm going to have it pass the
like jen whatever those
world gen
the i don't even know what what's that
thing called
world generator
so i'm going to have the thing take the
world generator because it needs
entropy and we're just going to say that
that's fine but it needs that
um for add obstacle asset hash
unilateral
gen hp
that seems okay though
uh oh whoops
there we go
and we don't really need to do that like
we could just go in and set the variance
ourselves but i felt like yeah just pass
it through i mean who cares
i don't know that may be a mistake we
may just want to
to set it after the fact but
anyway okay so now we've got tags where
we're doing like
wall or floor which one we're doing
right so what i'd rather do here is just
say like okay
there's an asset tag uh
for the type like what the actual
like squ like tile is like
tile type or something right and
we're gonna assume i suppose that it's a
floor
um but we'll set it in both cases so
tile type
equals wall here and tile material
equals wood or whatever right
because these have to go in order or
they at least have to be
like sane now they're not as just random
as they used to be so you kind of have
to
actually um
specify them in a particular way
so that seems fine
and then uh and these could actually be
things that are specified a little bit
in a little bit more interesting a way
as well but uh it doesn't matter
point being we go through here and then
when we actually
create the thing which would happen
here right
um piece variance is going to be
the unilateral there and the
when we do this add piece this would
just be like get tag
hash um from
our tile type and tile material right
so it actually reads better too like you
can even
even just with that you can now see
what's going on there's like two
tags that you're setting and you're
setting them based on some you know
parameters you had
and now you could pass one in as well so
like you know we had this thing
uh in here where we were like gen room
and it was like what was the type
of the room or something like that uh
where it was like stone
floor that could now that could now
actually just be like what's the type of
tile you want on the floor
right or something so you could see how
you could like it makes things better
too
in a way but anyway it is it actually
makes more flexible i should say
easier to make like parameterized
so when we do add tree
we need to send down the generator thing
there because we don't it can't get the
entropy that it needs
i don't know what this is complaining
about this add obstacle call
um it looks like it doesn't
like the oh that's why there you go
uh so other than the placement stuff
what else we got
uh so generated first of all so this at
when you're creating the door now we can
literally
just do this directly um where we do an
ad obstacle
i don't know why we're adding a tree for
doors uh but we are maybe that
can change now like since we can add an
obstacle much more easily
maybe we do a get tag hash
here and where we were doing the
uh asset block thing with the materials
like maybe in here we say
like okay uh it's a it's a it's a
um a wall
uh made of stone i don't know
don't look at me i look at program games
to you
no uh so anyway when we do add obstacle
uh we would just pass the
the region that we're using
and then we just need to place it on
this location so we just oops so we just
need to do a place
entity on traversible
and
and it goes like on top of the thing i
think that's how we decided to do it
so we would just say place the door
on that on that traversible and that's
it
yep so then
uh we just loop through the patterns now
and we let each pattern generator uh
there we go uh we let each pattern do
its thing
and this is the part that we need to
still do but you know this gets a lot
simpler
as well um so this stuff here
you know we probably want to keep a
little bit of it just so we can see
like what we were doing um
when we go to to like implement the
search code
uh but basically what we're really gonna
do now
is is just call it's just a dispatch
list
we're just saying look everyone in this
list gets a chance to do something to
the room
but that's all right so it's it's
literally just that
um and you pass like the construction
grid
and the pattern you were trying to make
um and off it goes right
um so yeah like i think we're basically
done
uh with all of the porting at that point
um and we now just need a way
of of actually placing these things
which is like i said the hard part but
we've organized it so now that's like in
more control
a more controlled thing that's happening
when replacing the apron here you can
see that we want to place
tiles uh that's really easy for us to do
when we do this add piece this is just a
get tag hash
right um and
i think that's literally all we need to
do to that code um
and then that last bit there where we're
adding a tree
would again just just create the tree
uh by calling it add tree call and then
a like place
entity on traversible where
it's oh and it's it's actually not it's
just a place entity
at p because that that is actually not a
traversable
so uh again pretty simple
um
much simpler than it was before
and so that all seems good
so now we are just left with the problem
did i do something wrong here um
oh so it doesn't even need the region
right
so i think that's it um
pretty much everything else is now just
the fact that we don't
know where the things are in
the room because we've gutted that piece
of the code which was the entire point
of that whole
epic adventure and what we'd like to do
here is find a way to
uh you know we'd like to find a way to
sort of
have some utility code that subsequently
does the same stuff like the greedy
search stuff for example
was a crappy version of it we'd like to
find some stuff that we can use to
quickly build
pattern finding like that
and that's going to be a topic for a
different day because we don't have time
for that
obviously um but what we can do here
is we could just make a thing that like
searches like spirals outward
or something from from where we are
try some things um and you know
we just if we can't find a place to put
something we fail
you know so you could imagine something
that was like
okay we want to place
entities on traversibles here
um and
you know like
you can imagine the crappy stuff
that just kind of does the same thing it
used to do
uh but now maybe it places it more
towards the center of the room or
whatever so we can we can even
make it a little bit better already but
in general we would just say like
you know find random
open tile or something like that and we
would just say
here's the construction grid and that
would give us back
you know one of those uh edit tile
placement things or i don't
quite remember exactly but it's like
you know there's like a relative
this this thing you know
so
this
is is like what we would do i guess
and we would just say can you please
place that
um place the thing
on there you know and i'm pretty sure we
have an is valid
on those so we can just do
like
this kind of thing
so i think that's fine i mean it's it's
not the best thing
but at the moment we'll just try it like
this and then we'll try to just expand
this code
and see what we can do because you know
i don't know i don't have a strong
opinion
i don't have an idea right now about how
we will go about doing this
but
so we'll do something like this
um yeah
maybe like that and we'll just do the
head tile where we
start is where we look from
you know something like that
uh and we then
just do
this each time
and so that is like the super duper
crappy
version um and this maybe takes one of
those
like box mass planer things
uh and this maybe takes a like where did
you want to start from
kind of thing something like that
uh oop no no no
i meant
there and like that's
just what happens
you know what i'm saying and uh
and then we'll just go from there and
and we'll see if we can make things that
allow you to look for little patterns
and you can test like some locations
or something um but we like i said we
may even have to move
it out one more level above that into
the room stuff that will like
actually carve up the space in an
intelligent way
so this is just step one and step two
will probably be
like creating more of a unified thing um
just because i think it's going to have
to be that way i don't know why i didn't
think of that originally
when i started breaking it up like this
was probably just dumb but
you know you program on a project only
once a week or twice a week or something
your brain is not
like super with it you know it doesn't
doesn't think of all the
um pieces as well as
you would like you know what i mean
uh so you know we just go all right
this thing needs to create a
uh
this thing needs to create a a place for
the mpc
to live and you know maybe npcs are kind
of supposed to be up more towards the
top
i don't it felt like our it feels like
our grid is
like backwards or something because i'm
not sure why it was
going the other way oh maybe it goes
though
you know normally i would say that is
higher like like y
goes into the screen so i don't know i'm
going to leave it like that we'll we'll
deal with it
let's go make sure what we know what the
coordinate system is first but
that'll be a different thing uh anyway i
would then say okay let's
let's do oh you know um
yeah i could see this getting cool yeah
so i i think we're in we're okay
[Music]
don't worry everything's fine um so
we'll have the the care tile and
we'll have the um the tactile
uh and
this is like south i guess
i guess um
right and assuming they're both valid we
place the thing down
oops
and then we just say yeah man
uh and stuff
bro and we say
keratile and tactile like that
and those both come through here and
everyone loves it
it's freaking great
um and off you go and
[Music]
i think that's everything
that we need there
this one is the same as this so
that's just going to go like that
and it will do like
like well actually no i don't know what
this is gonna do yet
because we haven't thought about that so
actually this is just gonna do that
you know like find me a random open tile
just do it please
uh and then i don't actually know oh
uh and then i can just do this
um i don't know that
how is this supposed to work like if you
can't get the tile
from the tile what kind of tile are we
even talking about
like if you have the concept of an edit
tile
aren't you supposed to be able to use
that somehow
like that doesn't make a lot of sense
does it folks
like you can see this was being used as
a loop but how do you actually get the
tile
out of it it's kind of dumb right um
because you're supposed to be able to
get the tile contents you would think
this is
oh wait no you can oh okay
it's just it takes a pointer
that's fine i'm not going to complain
about that
that's fine um
so at that point i don't know what we
want to do but i'm just going to throw
these in there for now because why not
so if we have both of these and then
we go take the place entity at
traversable and on traversable and
and that kind of stuff right um
then what we can do is just create
facsimiles
of these two things like so
uh and you know i guess we only need on
at the moment uh where what we would do
is we'd say okay
you know this takes the edit grid
uh the entity you're trying to place and
then it takes the uh the tile
you know and then what you would do
is you would call place entity on
traversible
and you would pass the grid region the
entity
and then the traversable reference that
actually
goes there right
um and and that
is the code that we had in room gen
right that is just this code and so
i think we just do this for now
um
right so we say okay
you know we get the tile
uh contents which we get directly from
this instead you know
uh we get the structural reference
garbage
out of that and then we place it using
the
the information we extract i think
that's it
then these are just functions
that try to pick tiles
and you know uh
i mean maybe this is even just like hey
it starts from the center by default
um and
and we're gonna do this in like the
dumbest possible crappiest
work most worthless way uh
and
and i probably shouldn't have deleted
that code because we probably actually
could have just cut and pasted it
so that was dumb and i admit that
that was really stupid um
because we actually already had the code
for this it was just the interior of
those recursive loops that we were doing
so that's pretty stupid uh but you know
what are you gonna do we could go back
to source could we could
go back to source code control
and grab it but i'm not sure that it's
worth it
especially because we're not logged in
i don't think
although
actually i guess we are i mean we're not
you know what i mean so
actually we do have it here don't we
because
if we look at
[Music]
i don't even know where that code was
but if we look at the get
version since i haven't pushed anything
to it
it still has it there now i don't know
where the heck that code was
so i don't actually know where we're
even looking
but if we look for what was it like um
i was like find place to put entity or
whatever well it's not gonna find it in
there obviously um
yeah so i don't know where that code
even was
but uh if we look in there we can pull
it back out so maybe we do that uh i'll
look for a second
and then if it takes me too long to find
it i'll just write it again
so yeah uh it was like find place to put
entity or something like that
i don't even know um
so this is all for room placement
and it doesn't look like it's in there
right so it's not in there
uh it's presumably it could be in the
edit grid i guess
or it could be in the room no oh no
no no no
oh please stop no no no
no no don't do that the worst thing in
the world
is if visual studio opens that's like
when you know you're having a really bad
day
when visual studio it's like when an
artist accidentally hits the thing that
says
open in bridge and they just scream you
can hear them
it's like adobe bridge opens up and it's
like the worst thing that happens in
their day
that's like when visual studio opens
right
uh when visual studio opens it's just
the work it's just the worst
and it's like the same is true of of you
know
of adobe bridge they're like these these
products that you know
if you accidentally click the thing that
opens them
you're just really unhappy right because
it's going to take forever to load and
then you're not going to actually want
it to be there
okay so it's this thing um
so we can just copy and paste this code
out
because this is actually all we need and
we can just
use a very simplified version of it
right
so in here all we're doing is no
copy okay um
so in
in this where we have uh you know find
place to put blah blah or whatever it is
find random open tile you know
uh what we can do here is just say all
right do exactly what you were doing
before
um but you know take take a distance
metric uh and and
figure out uh whether or not the thing
that you're looking
at is um
it is closer to the starting area you
were asked to produce
you know what i'm saying just take the
distance
and that's all we really need to do
i think so that's fine
so we'll do that uh and then
for find adjacent tile oops
um we want this code here where we're
doing like
um
where really it's just this
right so we're still using more or less
the same
code to a certain extent
you know but we're just not calling it
in the same way
so we loop over all of the tiles in the
region that we're asked to
we would get the tile here and we would
see if it's open
so what we really need is like
we need the thing that says whether this
thing is open or not
is the problem and
i guess the way we were
doing that is by setting it
is that what we were doing
yeah so in the edit tile contents thing
we have like a b32 open
and that probably we just don't want
anymore
so probably what we want to do here
is something more like put the
traversible reference directly into the
edit tile
you know what i mean um
because we're just going to place these
things in in waves we're not going to
try to do rip up and replace
because i just don't think it's
plausible right
so for edit tile contents yeah this b32
open thing
i think we just want to do a like is
open so
for each one of these we would do
something like if you know is open
uh or or traversible
is open or whatever and
this tile p thing here where we do the
gen v3
i think what we actually want to do is
just be able to pass an edit tile for
that
so there'd basically there'd just be a
thing that's like you know b32
is open and
and that would take the edit tile
so assuming that we have that this
really just wants to be a thing that
creates the edit tile from that
and uh this is a relative
it's relative it's it's a relative uh
one right so you can see it here i think
is how it would work and um
the only thing i'm not certain about
it's always relative right
it looks like it's always relative so
i'm pretty sure all we
have to do is
is loop over all of the tiles
precisely that way
yeah so i'm pretty sure this is
where's the thing that bundles this up
uh
[Music]
i guess it's here and i guess this is
you know
why did i even bother with this that's
kind of dumb so i didn't even need to
cut and paste that out this is just
iterate as planar tiles
right
so so actually this
thing here does what we want already
um this is what we actually want
so we can just do this
right and that's that's actually what we
want
and then we just say if it's open
um then we do something if it's not
it's not uh and
the result here is like nothing
and what we probably want to do is say
there's a best distance
like that and what we'll do is we'll
check the distance here
like how far is this thing from whatever
the person
uh gave us as a start right
and we know um because we have this tile
count stuff
what we can do is we can say
we don't care about z distance at the
moment
so we just have grid tile count y
and grid tile count x
yeah which i think is just that
oops
and what we should be able to do is if
we take that tile count
we should be able to produce like a
center point or an inverse like a
scaling factor
that can produce things in the same
space as the start from thing
right barry centric coordinates for the
room
if you will the room being the room by
tommy wiseau
so if we just say what's the inverse of
this thing
right um
like that that's the room scale
and so from there i should just be able
to say whatever the tile's relative
index is
that x y times the inverse room scale
is the uv and then i can just do
a
a distance
so
the vector from the starting the place
that it told me to start to where
this particular tile is in barycentric
coordinates
i can then just take that and
you know it's
it's hard to say whether you want what
distance measure you want do you want a
very centric distance
which is what this is or do you want a
distance
that's in the room in in real world
and i just don't know which one you
would want so i'm just going to use this
i'll put it to do
but we could do it the other way around
if we wanted to
you know um in fact you know what let's
yeah i'm sorry i'm just i'm fascinating
a little bit
we could just do it the other way around
there um so
the start p is is just the hadamard
product of the
you know start uv
um and the and the the tile count right
so that now we've got a physical
placement that just felt a little bit
better i don't know i don't have
i don't have any reason why i'm picking
this i'm literally just going like hey
yeah that seems okay right because i
don't i don't have an idea for why
um uh i don't have an idea for why
why i would want that or not so you know
it is what it is
so i think that gives us a distance
um and then we would just do oops and
then we would
oh do we not have a xy pick out of these
things
what's up with that somebody tell me why
we don't have that
um gen v3 where is that
oh it's just a v3s
oh my
really
i see
anyway uh so yeah there's a v2
s oh well that's why
never mind because we don't have v2s's
so we wouldn't be able to slice them out
that way okay that's fine
i don't have a problem with that so
here we can just do
this then right convert it to a v3 and
then take the xy out of it
uh that's fine uh same thing here
right uh and and that should be fine
so let's see traversible is open we
don't have yet uh
no overlord upper tile i agree
wholeheartedly
and then we just need to do like look if
the best distance squared is greater
than this distance squared then this is
the tile for
us sir um
and uh and we should capture the the
particular tile in question
um as the results right
so i think that's all we need um and
and then the find adjacent part of
things just needs to be modified a
little bit
uh i don't know why this is taking an
edit grid
because it wouldn't do that it would
take the
base tile right
and then it would say all right uh the
dur mask comes in here we would do
get direction from that we would then
say
uh we want to step
that in like one tile in that direction
so this
is the tile to look for or to look at
rather
uh and we would see whether we we got it
or not so we
would say okay there's no tile that
starts
we would say that we
would look to see um if it's open
if it's open then we use it
right
[Music]
and and this is probably wants to be
biased so
we probably want to change that dur mask
at some point to say like look
you know
either we do these in a random order
or uh we pass in an array
so that you know it's not always picking
one preferably so
so that's just a separate thing but
that's neither here nor there
so then what we would do is say all
right we're going to go ahead and
get this tile out
so
[Music]
that would literally just be the base
tile
so edit tile check tile equals base tile
check tile rail index
is is just going to change like that
and then it's going to be like
traversible is open this check tile
or something and then
if that's true the result is the check
tile and you're done
yep uh this doesn't have a plus equals
operator it looks like so maybe we'll
just do this
um the grid is not something we got
passed in but it
is like oh and that has the grid in it
so we wouldn't need that we would just
say that
um so then
uh the only
thing we're missing is this call
is that true
not quite um
i don't really like the fact that this
takes a pointer
um
that doesn't make a whole lot of sense
uh to me furthermore
why does it even have to do that
like this is dumb because what you would
actually do
is in here where you do advance you just
null
the thing probably
so that doesn't feel super good
um
like i don't i don't like anything about
this uh at all
that just seems it just seems bad
um
yeah so i don't know i don't know how i
feel about that but probably not great
if we're honest about it uh probably
what i would want this to do
is say if tile rail index
z is greater than or equal to grid tile
count
z then tile
you know grid equals zero
right like it's just null
at that point and so that way when you
say
uh is valid you would just
say that
if it has a grid it's valid
um right
oops
so i would like that to be
you know zeroable basically and so
i just want to say like if the tile that
you pass in
has a grid you know
um
then it's valid
in fact it's just this
you know what i'm saying um
i feel like that's
like that's what i actually wanted
and
and then these things here
that iterate over the tiles
those are all fine what is this
complaining about does not take
find adjacent open tile that doesn't
need the grid
is the difference there
um place unity on traversible
what's wrong with that oh it takes a
grid not
that find adjacent tile
that's from the care tile
um
so that actually has to happen
here as well so this
place entity at traversible
is just a shim right so it takes the
grid
um and the tile
uh this part here
it just calls a different thing right we
really shouldn't have done it this way
this was dumb
so we should fix this because the better
way to do it is to just say whether it
occupies the thing or not
um so like you know
that way you don't have two of these
it's like the inverse bob martin
you know like if you heard advice in a
talk by bob martin just
think what is the opposite of that
advice and do that you know he says make
a separate function for everything don't
pass flags the opposite's the true thing
you
pass flags because that's what collapses
the code down and makes it the most
flexible so you can pass
information through streams without
having the intermediaries be aware of it
right which is what you want
so we kind of bob martin that but oh
well uh
let's go ahead and and uh finish it this
way and
we should probably just just go clean
that code up so it does it's not garbage
um if we look it is valid here uh i just
want to take a look and see how this is
working and clean it up a little bit
uh but i think it's mostly just handles
itself
right and yeah so i think we're good
i think all that's fine and
now i think we're just down to debugging
which i probably don't want to do today
because we've already gone over
time um so you know
maybe i'll just step through it and
clean up any immediate
crashes and things like clean up any
like kind of garbage
that i just forgot to wire up or
whatever let's also close this
notepad thing out um
so what we want to do is
run this and
uh like see where we stop
so
this is trying to get okay so
that looks like i just messed up that
tile thing there um
what's the tile count
179 z
and that returns zero wait so hmm
did i mess up the iteration a little bit
there looks like i did
somehow
oh and also we have to finish this sorry
so this does have to
that has to happen otherwise
everything's going to to fall apart
uh so yeah so what was i saying uh if
the relative z is greater than the
tripod z then the grid is done
we're not going to iterate over it
anymore so
but that seems fine like why would that
change that doesn't make a lot of sense
so i'm not sure why that got messed up
there
um
[Music]
this is actually false that should be an
and
that's a separate issue like it should
only be you should only be able to
iterate
over things that have some volume
right um which we might even have
a thing for for already i don't know
um
yeah so like this this is
is that exact thing we want
right so it'd be like it'd be that uh of
course we don't
i guess we don't really pass that but
you could just do get total volume
right and say you know it's got to be
bigger so you know
we probably should have uh loaded that
in there because that that makes some
sense but
let's actually go see what's going on
here because i'm not sure why we're
getting this
this failure so um
so if we look at this we see we're
trying to get the tile that we're
iterating over and it's not working for
some reason
so if we look at the tile itself here's
the grid
and here's the relative index it's
looking for tiles 0 9
0 which doesn't make any sense
because it shouldn't be trying to
get that tile like that's not a tile so
something about the advance call didn't
work and i'm not sure why because i
don't think i broke
it um but i guess i did you know i mean
you know you may not think you broke it
but you broke it
so it looks like these things reset to
zero
um
oh this only does planar right now
okay
that's actually what we needed sorry
um i was thinking this iterated over all
three dimensions but it doesn't it only
does planar at the moment
um so that makes more sense okay uh
so let's let's do our traversable as
open call
uh and so what this has to do is this
has to get out that
structural piece right the thing
uh so the same code that's that's at
work here
this
this has to get has to access the
traversible
and see whether or not it's open
wherever that is
so what we really want is trans is the
transactional occupy
you know what i mean um
we're just we're just calling this thing
so
when we have the reference once we have
the reference i think we're done
you know what i mean so traversable open
is just going to call is occupied
on the traversal reference for the thing
and in a sense it just looks like this
edit tile contents
when you actually do the get tile
on on that
right what it probably should do there
is
say this
like so so we can say get the tile
that will give us back the contents if
there's anything there
uh we'll just say if it's not occupied
it's good
and i think that's all we need because
we already had the call that asks if the
thing is occupied so
i guess that's just it um
okay so it looks like here we're calling
that
on an entity
that doesn't actually have
traversibles
which doesn't really make a lot of sense
because presumably
uh the structural entity always
does so let's take a look at who's
calling that
and why look at the call stack
so on here
i guess we would need to see if it had
one because i guess maybe there are
structural things that don't have
traversibles
so so maybe like actually we want to say
does it have one at all so is occupied
i mean
i guess here we would want to do like
this
this is really pretty clumsy but
you know
like we did today eventually we collapse
code down into things that are good
but not before it's time
unfortunately n
oh well i don't know
why that's happening that's not a good
sign but
it's fine all right so surprisingly
enough
we still generated like a lot of actual
stuff which was i was expecting it to
kind of crash and burn there
um but actually you know looks like it
still generated the world
after all of that um
so that looks pretty good our only
problem is our hero looks like he's got
the wrong tags
uh on at the moment so that we want to
fix
and also it looks like the thing that
tries to pick more
tiles isn't working it looks like it the
the find adjacent tile isn't working
so let's try to fix those up real quick
um because that's less good and i that
shouldn't take very long
i can maybe fix the tags thing too so it
looks like we mostly
mostly everything just worked um so
that's good
so in here this is the part that doesn't
look like it's working so find adjacent
open tile starts out with an
invalid tile it loops over all of the
directions you could go from a from a
base tile that you pass it
it tries to figure out what direction
that thing would go
in for for a mask you pass in
and then it says all right i'm going to
take wherever i was
at i'm going to move
the relative index by whatever the delta
is i'm going to look to see
if that place is open and if it is i'm
going to return the tile
right it looks like that's never working
i mean i could be wrong about that and
it was just not
working most of the time but since it
looks like it's never working
i'm guessing i should be able to just
kind of step in here
and watch it not work
rather than have to guess right
that's my assumption so let's take a
look here so this is trying to make the
snake
uh if we look at what the directional
mask says
uh it's 15 which probably is all four
planar directions
right so here we go
uh and hey it looks like we're going to
try one
let's see where it thinks we're going to
go and let's also look at the base tile
um so we have some idea of where we're
going so
it's 8 4 0 we
are going negative 1 in x so that should
produce a check tile that's like one off
yes seven four zero right um
and then we say okay we've got one
we we and then have have a valid
check tile so that worked um
so this looks like it is actually just
placing the thing
on it right um
hmm
so i guess i don't
know why that's failing
it looked like it was failing before
um
hmm so that's not what i expected to see
uh i'm not sure
what's happening
because clearly like
at least for here there's only one of
those things
um only one of those like switches
uh and
so at least the switch code is bad
maybe the switch code is just maybe just
the switch code is broken
it could be maybe we forgot to set the
pre-tile
or something um
oh that's just constantly asking find
random open tile
oh
right that doesn't that makes sense
it's always gonna find that because it's
always open
so yeah um
so i guess really what we want there is
just find
random tile with
traversable and then we
just want to put the pattern
in so okay so that's
fine that's yeah all right so that code
is fine
so it looks like the only actual problem
we're having
is when we add the player um
we we aren't properly setting up the tag
hashes for the player
and that makes perfect sense because we
got rid of this orphan tag
right so i'm pretty sure it's just tag
hero now
so wow we we really didn't screw up very
much did we
um that's that's pretty wild
all right well whatever um
let's go ahead and just just check uh so
our other orphans are all gonna be
borked
right uh it looks like that stone wall
we try to put in place is invisible like
i couldn't walk through it but it wasn't
there
so that's a little bit broken as well um
and i'd like to figure out why that's
the case
uh unfortunately these snakes are so
good at
they hop all over the there's never
going to be a switch that
isn't pressed because of these stupid
snakes um
so anyway uh that's all good let's start
at the orphanage real quick
and just take a look at uh the orphans
because they're gonna have to have
different tag settings as well
uh so let's just make sure that we get
those right
uh and so that we're not sitting around
going like what happened
to the thing
this code can just go away so this is
now just a trivial loop
which is great uh room connections blah
blah blah blah so all yeah all this is
good
and this just
needs
wherever that is that thing this just
needs to be um
all right i don't know why i did that
why not just use the comment out i don't
know
i just didn't so there we go
and now we can go see if any of the
orphans work or
change their tags because we might need
to
um okay there they are
and oh so it looks like the that
thing is still blocking so so right
uh place entity on traversible
um this is supposed to be place entity
at traversable and i
think we're good now
it's like bob barker and
there we go uh that's fine
and the baby is here hello baby
um handmade baby that doesn't sound good
uh all right there's the orphans
there's oh there's a puss even
oh dear the puss doesn't have no head
though um
i don't know if we ever set up the puss
heads
so uh it
could it could be i don't remember how
we did this
exactly but uh it could actually just be
that like it could be that we just never
set those
right um
yeah it looks like we just never set
those actually
so like
i don't know
um
i guess that goes like something like
there
uh and then the
the weird head thing that
goes
like that probably
um
i don't know if these should have scale
on them or not
and i don't know which one would have
scale on it either
um so
[Music]
i don't i don't know like
i don't know there's a cat it's not my
problem
so
so there's a cat and um
and everyone loves cats or they're not
allowed on the stream
we have another cat here so we should
probably set
it it is
oops it is fred
and
looks like that bitmap is actually out
of alignment to be completely honest
uh
isn't there how do you set like the
default alignment position or you can't
yeah you can so i think we actually want
this one to be set to there because it
was kind of like
off off-center so i feel like that
bitmap just wanted to be re-centered
first
and then we can place the head on it and
then we can edit the head
and where that goes uh
as a separate situation and
you know i don't know i don't know
fred's kind of kind of overweight the
cat was
um his owner
you know let him let him eat a lot more
than probably he should have so he's
he's a bit overweight
he's he's still alive that's a that's a
real cat fred and he's a little bit
he's a little bit heavy so that's that's
why he looks bigger than the other cat
which was molly who you've seen on
stream
um so yeah like everything is
looking pretty good um
i feel like
i don't have a lot of complaints here
let's take a quick second and fix molly
i mean hannah
cause hannah looks like she's in the
wrong place as well
so let's go ahead and add
some tag giving some alignment points
in here like so hannah was a very small
cat she was she was really tiny
um never ate much
you know um
she was a good puss she's a ghost now
that's why she looks
ghostly because she was a she was she
died a few years ago
all right so i think all that's good
and uh
you know who knows we can set those
differently later but at least now all
of our
sprites have some have some basic
settings um
and that seems good uh so so i'm happy
with that and the only thing i might say
is like the lamp stuff
just for now i don't really want to put
lamps
in there quite so much potentially
um
so i was kind of thinking of of maybe
just changing this a little bit uh
and going like all right like let's add
a uh a light uh
that's an inanimate object and has no
tags it's invisible
um in fact i think actually not even
that i think it's just add entity
right we just want an entity we're going
to place it
at a location um
and
and we'll add a light and the light will
be
fairly large i don't i don't know what
these parameters are because i haven't
called this function in forever
it's radius so maybe it's like a large
radius
light um that's like kind of floating
up above the ground which it looks like
that would be
with a lamp light and it has like some
fairly high emission
right and maybe what we do here is
is we get rid of this on lamp garbage
um and we just have a lighting pattern
generator
i'm sorry like this is going wicked long
um
i'm not even paying attention thing it's
just like this stuff is so easy
like we might as well do it um
you know there's no reason not to so uh
and it's kind of fun to place things in
the world right it's
it's you know it feels creative
even though it's not um so
what we might do is is get rid of this
stuff get rid of the on
lamp nonsense and and just have like a
lighting pattern
right um or like standard lighting
pattern or something i don't know uh
but we'll have like a standard lighting
pattern we'll get rid of this stuff the
on lamp stuff is gone
you know forget that um you know that's
out of here
uh and then you know when we add rooms
we'll just add lighting or we won't
right and so when we come through one of
these things we'll just say add ran
you know find random open tile and
the only thing about this is like uh
maybe we just want to say like find
random tile right and not have random
open tile
because we don't actually care if it's
open um
but uh you know
we'll just have that for now with a
to-do
for next time this shouldn't actually
look for
open tiles uh
so we'll get one and if it's valid
i will just would place one of those on
there like i said i don't
i don't care about the lamp at the
moment um i don't think i want that so
we're just going to place a regular old
light
and we're going to place it at wherever
the
the tile is that we got back
and we we've
we've have it all
and you know
we get we get back our our lamp and
everyone and everyone loves it
uh and this is just a way of placing
lights around for
for mood right uh it's
it's not um
let me go ahead and just get the
entropy out of this
right and so now if we ran this like the
world would have no lighting in it
whatsoever because
nobody adds the standard lighting
pattern to their rooms
right so it'd just be the hero walking
around with like a little tiny light
you know like so
and so then if we wanted to uh
we could then start saying look let's
add lights to rooms
and to do that we would just say when we
create these rooms
so like create dungeon um
and create orphanage or whatever we
would just add
uh lighting to these rooms
right and
so like in here for example
every time we made a room uh
we would create the standard lighting
for that room so like here
we would say you know ad pattern
gen room standard lighting pattern
you know what i mean uh and i think that
would add
like lighting to a bunch of the dungeon
rooms using that lighting pattern
um and then for the orphanage we would
probably need to like be more specific
because we probably want to like
talk about the lighting more
and like what kind of lighting should be
in each room i mean we want to do that
with the dungeon too but like
i think that adds
uh lighting to the dungeon right uh
[Music]
so you can kind of see there's light in
the room now
um of course the the little hoppy snake
person
also has lights attached um
but i'll be honest it looks like the
light is weirdly skewed towards the top
like i wonder if that's because it had
to find an open
tile so it had to avoid the snake
that might have been there i think
that's probably what happened
so you know it needs to not do that
obviously but
so that's fine um
so that's all fine um so i think we're
good
uh and and then if i do the orphanage
one you know i don't really know
um i guess we'll just add the standard
lighting pattern to all these rooms
right now although it would it'll be it
would be cooler if we actually did
something real here and had different
rooms have different lightings so you
know that's the idea is that we would
not
do this you know the entire time or
whatever but
uh so for lights
um here you know i guess what i'm saying
is i would like to have
a uh
i would like to have a way where we
customize the lighting for these rooms
or something
and we'll have to look maybe it goes in
the room spec
uh and and then the room spec when you
gen the room automatically adds one of
these
i don't know um but
i i feel like that's just something we
can deal with later
i don't know there's a lot of text
messages i normally turn my phone off
and i guess i forgot to turn it off and
i don't normally get a lot of text
messages
because i don't really use messaging
much
but apparently
i'm getting a lot of messages now and i
don't know what those messages say
but they probably say something that
doesn't need
for me to look at it at this immediate
moment so i'm not going to
and that's all i have to say um
so that just adds lights and in a really
uninteresting way
right it just adds lights to rooms and
so they have lights now
right um
and no one cares but you know there you
go
and as we make the lighting system
better
uh presumably
uh yeah presumably it will be better um
so i guess
the other thing i would point out here
is that you know
so we could when we talk about the
standard lighting pattern thing
um we probably want that to be smart
or so if you think about what's going to
happen
you want to place lights you know more
lights in larger rooms
and less lights and smaller rooms and
crap like that
you know so what you're probably gonna
do is
have something that's like a gen
v3 uh that's like your light spacing
you know and you're gonna say like okay
you know we we roughly want to place a
light every
you know five steps or something
you know i don't know but you're gonna
have some kind of rule where you're like
you know this is this is what the
spacing is that we expect for lights
uh in 2d or whatever you know who cares
and then you could do a thing where you
were like
okay i want to loop over
it take the room figure out how many of
these are going to be
and space them correctly so i can step
over them that way right so
in other words you would get a thing
where you're like uh
iterate as planar tiles you can do like
an iterate
equally spaced
you know
so you'd be something like this
you know what i'm saying so
if you uh if you pass in like a spacing
you get like you get like steppings uh
that that are like aligned properly for
that thing
and i don't know exactly how i would
want to do that
per se but it would it would really just
it would be more like this
because we're not trying to look for
tiles we're trying to like strewn
we're trying to like place lights in the
world
you know um and so you know i wouldn't
actually want
it to look like that it would be this
sort of thing
and the light would be placed
on the tiles that we iterate so if you
imagine
what the planar tile iterator looks like
it's already set up to do
what we want and we can already do this
striation really easily
actually if we want to by saying
okay if we do iterate as planar tiles
we there's no reason why the edit tile
thing
can't have a step
associated with it right so we could do
something
like this
you know what i'm saying where you know
you're going to step by that much
so inside this where you have
um the step you're going to take
instead of these like plus equals is all
over the place
you would just do this and
go by the step amount rather than one
all the rest of the code still works
and uh you could even
you know
you could do this right so you have your
your step which defaults to one one one
and in this case
the the final one isn't used and your
base which defaults to zero zero
zero and then your iterator can actually
iterate
any kind of grid like pattern and you
didn't actually have to do any more work
you know what i mean it's the same code
for all intents and purposes but you can
call it in like
a bunch of different ways and you get
like more mileage out of that
you know what i'm saying so this would
allow us to do
that quite easily and
i guess this is really just iterate as
planar tiles and then we would have
um the base p here
um like that
and all we would need to do is say uh
calculate you know um
calc spacing offset right or something
like this
and this would give us if we passed it
the spacing
um calculate you know base p for
offset and you know you'd give it the
grid
um or something like this and then when
it looked at the grid it would just
figure out where the first one would be
and then you know that you step by that
many each time and then we pass that
spacing
in you know um
each time yeah
pretty pretty straightforward and so i
think that would just work
and the only thing that you would need
to do is
that when you do iterate as planar tiles
that just takes the base p and
so when it initializes the thing instead
of the relative index
um you know it's base rail index
whatever
and similarly this is you know space
real index it's just the same thing you
passed
you know now we can still make that work
for everybody else
by just doing 0 0 0 because that's what
it would have been anyway
when they initialize and they'll just
work and then if we do calc
base p for offset and we just shove that
in here
just to make it start working before we
look at what that calculation actually
is
we can just put d step in here
and the edit grid you know
okay uh and at that point
i think this would actually work but it
wouldn't be centered so the pattern
would not be centered in the room like
we would want it to be
um but it will do
something like that i think right
okay now uh yeah so
one problem we get here is
we also when we're doing placenta
traversable we don't actually want to
place this at traversable we just want
to do
at p um
right and so
when we get the tile contents thing
here we really don't care about that
what we care about is
is where this thing is in the world you
know
so i'm assuming that
assuming that we just want to use the
structural entity
so here we probably want to do
the same thing we were doing before
where we just have one of these
but it works off of the edit tile
and we just say get the contents
of this tile and then instead of this
content structural thing
you know you would just do that
um
something like that
so i think that's what we would do
uh and i don't really know
but i think that's what we do and then
in theory
you know that places lights regularly
spaced throughout the room and you can
kind of see that that's happening now
right um you know what i mean
we've got too much light in the world
now the intensity of these lights should
probably be
less because there's so much light
but uh you know that's easy
just take the light level down a little
bit
and so then all we need to do is center
them and that's pretty easy
but you can see now we sort of have a
better light distribution
in the world
and seems okay
i don't really know how high up these
lights are
that's a little confusing so the fact
that we don't draw
lights is is a little
not good um
you could imagine wanting to draw the
lights
and that we probably have done this
so um
in here where we draw the light you
could just also push a volume outline
right
so if you did
push light you could just do push volume
outline and say
okay if this is where that thing
is um
it's going to be a rectangle with that
shape
i guess
yeah so we're gonna do so this would be
a rectangle three
oops wrecked
uh center dim i guess is how this works
um so it would look like that oops
and i think that would draw where the
lights are just so we can see them
and so you can see how they're hovering
around uh
and you know
uh and that seems
is maybe sort of sensible um
it does seem with that many lights we
get a little bit of to we get a little
bit of feedback
which maybe means our we've got a bug
somewhere in our lighting well you know
we've probably got a lot of bugs in our
lighting
um but uh
i don't know why this room seems to not
have any
light except for what's coming from in
from the ceiling
but i don't see any i don't see any
lights in there i guess the entry room
didn't get any lights
don't know why
um so yeah but these rooms all did
so i'm not sure why that is but i guess
that room the entrance room
at the end of the forest there didn't
get a light
these rooms all have them and they look
fine
and maybe so i can take the snake it's
not really supposed to have a light on
it so maybe i'll take the
snake and
[Music]
remove the light from the snake
because i don't really want the snake to
have a light um
so add piece light it's there's like way
too many of these
maybe the head could still have one but
just
you know not the not the body segments
that's just too much
okay so there we go um
those are being drawn now i think those
are roughly as high as they should be i
don't know maybe they should be slightly
higher up
um it's hard to say
i'll put i'll leave that in there so
that we can turn it on anytime we want
to draw
the lights um and and i guess that's it
i don't know is there anything else
uh centering these so when we do this
you know um we're gonna have the grid
tile tile count
and if you imagine the tile count x
and you take the d step x and you say
here's how many they're going to be
so there's like an x count right
and these are going to be the same thing
you'll we can collapse them you'll see
in a second
but we know how many we're going to have
so like if you say that they need to be
faced five apart
and the room is like six long then we
know we're just going to only be able to
put one
right so we know how many we would have
and then uh after after we know how many
we would have
uh we just need to figure out like how
much
extra there would be so in a sense we
could just say well okay
so however much the steps are we know
that there's like an
off like like an amount if we take that
remainder when we divide this thing
we know there's going to be a remainder
to the d step so if the d step
is three and the room size is seven
we know we're gonna have like um
this is probably something better done
on the on the light board or something
but you know
um we know we're gonna have like two
spans
like the span that goes from the wall
from the first wall to the light
then from the light to the next wall
there's two spans and we want those to
be equally spaced
so however many of these are going to be
we want
one more than that right
is the size that we're trying to divide
up i don't i don't know if this is
making any sense you know what
we'll do it next weekend so i can
actually draw it out
we're done we're done now we finished
uh
and um there was that one other thing
which was that for some reason we
weren't seeing the
trees so when we did the door like
the only other thing i noticed was when
we did the door it wasn't there
we tried to put a door like this
right so asset block
tag wall tag stone or something
didn't work um
and i think the reason for that is
obstacle
is not is not adding a block
right it's actually a block that we need
to add
um so you know this should probably be
something like an
ad block call
because it's not an obstacle right
actually i guess i guess it should be
this
and so there should be a way to say like
okay there's a block
and the block is the blocks i don't
think do
connections do they um
well let's take a look let's see what we
do
here because this is what we want right
um so we're just doing this
it's it's it's literally just this
so so i think it'd be okay we would just
you know add one of these we'd add this
block
um with whatever the base asset was
that you told us to use right
um and we would add
the thing for whatever the volume was so
you'd have to
you'd have to give us a volume is the
only thing
and
i guess i don't know i guess i don't
know
how that would work right i'm not sure
where we get those volumes from
so we would call ad block we would just
need the volume that you were going to
use
and i guess you just have to pass that
in
because i'm not sure any other way to do
it
so you're going to have to do that you
know
and then the uh
the variant is passed in
here and yeah
i guess this is actually a rectangle
three
for the piece
um
[Music]
all right and
i guess that's it
entity tag hash
you know dim offset
color
and off we go okay so
[Music]
when we actually create that door um
the door should be a
ad block
and we would pass you know
the hash and then we need the other
stuff
for now um oops
we have a color that's just white and
we need to know what the volume is
of the thing which i guess we'll
get because
we can look at the tile contents for
that
because we're getting
we're getting this crap already like
this stuff
get volume from minzy
right so we're already doing this
for the tile
um so we know which tile it is
um
right and so we really just need
this thing
and it's a little annoying that there's
so many of these
i don't know what that's going to do um
it's kind of annoying that there's so
many of these though
like we gotta condense this down this
should probably just be something that
you get
directly out of here and you're always
working with one of these
that's what it should really be
um so i don't really know about that
okay so the volume
is really the thing that we don't have
here and so
um
you know this is exactly what we want we
just don't actually want it to be
i mean can't can't this just be like
get volume from minzy right um
we want this to be relative so we really
just want the thing that's like get
total volume
this is kind of just a waste of our time
because this entire thing
is just placing it it's just the tile
dim
is is like
all we actually needed right so the
volume is just that
and we don't need to do the rest of the
stuff all we need to do is make sure the
wall height is correct
you know what i'm saying so that whole
thing
is kind of stupid because it doesn't
really matter
so i think what we want is to just say
okay
you know you know we would change the
height of this thing
or set dim or something we would want to
be able to change the dimension
of it but only the only the z
right and to to make it be the wall
height but we'll deal with that in one
second
if we just take the tile dim for now we
should be able to pass this
and when we do add block add block is
taking the volume
as the input so that would be the end of
it
right so we would just say okay pass the
volume
pass pass the volume
uh right which is that and we just want
to center it
so can we do this
pass the tile dim in add block
we base this around the center point so
um this is actually just the dimensions
of the thing
uh so this is the v3 dim
and so in here if we want the radius it
would just be half times the dim
and then the center point of it is just
going to be
like play you know centered at the z
base
so it would presumably just be like uh
you know um zero
zero 0.5 times dim z
you know so it's just like a block
that's placed at its base wherever you
happen to actually put the thing
you know um
okay so i don't know what that's going
to do but i feel like we should at least
hack that in there for now
and then
[Music]
that way we can have doors that actually
look like doors we can get some art done
to
to have a door on it or something i
don't know
um and so oh you know what and i don't
have to hop down there every time to
debug this
because i can just set up
the um initial camera
right
okay so uh our goal now is just to make
there be a door right there uh hopefully
and we can also look to see there might
be doors there that are actually just
sunk into the geometry so i just wanted
to check first to make sure that it
wasn't a placement
issue but it doesn't look like it right
so
let's go ahead and get that working so
in ad block and let me just
like it's an ad blocker um
let me also check how we do it we do
place entity
on traversable door reference here's the
door
uh it's block tag wall stone
yup and tile dim
is that this is where we're placing it
there's the color
the color is just one one one and it's a
piece type cube
here's the variant to do region
flags collide so i feel like that
actually
should have worked i'm not actually sure
why it didn't
we place its position here
and presumably it is there quote unquote
meaning
i can't go through it yeah so it is
placed there
i just don't see it for some reason so
that's the question is why
right
if we look in here you can see
us adding the other one this is how this
one's added
and we can look at how the entity is
placed
uh and just see if there's any does
anyone even touch
that nope it's just ads like ground
cover and traversibles
um
it should probably have an occluder so
you can't see light from the other side
but again since we can't actually see
the thing to begin with i'm not sure
that matters
um the entity p will be set
when it gets placed on the traversible
so i don't know that should work
is there some kind of tag thing i don't
understand
that like we didn't set the tags right
like
is there no stone wall
that could be it actually you know what
that
may well be it it might be that there's
only a stone floor
um we should probably have a thing that
if it can't find an
asset it like draws bright pink or
something
that's probably going to be useful like
so that we know the difference between
those two things
probably something to put on the to-do
list it's probably just that we don't
have
stone walls
that's my guess and i'm right
so here's our like
you know our door piece you can see that
it's too high because this is the thing
where we didn't set the wall height
so we'd like that to now have its z
changed
i don't know like i feel like we should
have a math function
that does that that like sets the
dimensions of a rectangle you know what
i mean
but um
[Music]
i don't know that we do
yeah i don't know that we do um
i don't know that i want to think too
hard about it right now
so what i'll probably do is just say
uh yeah you know we we got the tile dim
and we'll just we'll just say
okay if that's the the dimensions of the
door
the door dim you know max c equals door
dim
min z plus the wall height
you know it's not real exciting
um
it's not oh
that's even easier
uh so wall height
is specified in here right
and i don't know that it
it gets set depending on the situation
right
and so i guess we kind of have to say
well the wall height quote-unquote is
this thing
like full wall height
and the full wall height is two
that way everybody uses the same
arbitrary numbers that we just decided
or how high the walls are
you know what i'm saying
all right and i think that's it for
today
um
because i don't want to do anything
fancy uh since we're so far over time
so you know there's that the wall um
and you know it looks like
maybe the centering the positioning of
the wall might be slightly wrong
as well uh which again i don't know that
i care about right now either
um but you know you
you can clear it out now at least uh
and so yeah for doors
um again we we don't really know
what we're gonna do with those long term
but
you know for now we're just moving them
out of the way
and
it's going to be a problem because if
they go down that far they might block
things in the other room like we're
going to need an actual solution for
what happens with doors because that's
not going to cut it right
but that's where we're at okay so
i think we're good that'll be it for
today
and
seems good
all reasonable
all reasonable okay
oh that was funny it put the yeah that's
interesting it put the switch down the
stairs so you would have had to hit it
down there
um
i think that's it
maybe it could actually be a gameplay
feature for the door moved to the house
i mean it could be but i doubt it
right like
when plopping down furniture props do
you want to allow for pattern variations
e
example desk above chair below desk lamp
on the right
another pattern outside wall would
require completely different arrangement
um yeah i mean i would assume that
when we actually plan plop down
furniture we'll have some
decision about how we want to do that
but
at the moment i don't really care about
furniture so i just haven't bothered
right
can you explain why only one switch is
being added to room uh yeah so
the problem with the switches is just
that what we want to do is just look for
a pattern that we can play
that we can like sort of stamp down
and what's happening at the moment is
that those those switch patterns
um they they don't actually
take up any placement right
they don't you can walk on the switches
so when you say find random open tile it
always returns the same tile because
when you place this down
you don't actually occupy it
right so that's really it
that's the only reason and so we want to
actually go code this up next weekend
probably to like place down interesting
tile patterns
as a starting thing
you're talking about switching bodies
and switching heads would you be able to
switch to have a snake body
that would be pretty cool especially as
required to accomplish something later
in the game like using the snake body to
press down
on multiple adjacent buttons at the same
time
um so we
i guess the answer is i don't know i
mean
i'm not a game designer so i don't know
but it seems like it would be fun
the problem is we don't have a really
solid understanding of
what it would mean because you
like we don't really have a solid
understanding of what it means
to be able to swap heads
so you know we could come up with a game
design way that that works
and then yeah because like you can't
just swap heads with any arbitrary
monster otherwise then you don't have to
really fight the monster
right i mean i guess you have to fight
your body
with that monster which might be hard if
you had a good
i i don't i don't know i don't know how
to
like
think about that but i think yeah if you
keep your
head and you can switch to certain
monsters like maybe
maybe monsters before they
die or something before they disappear
if you beat them they're in a dazed
state temporarily where you can swap
to their body instead of yours
for a limited amount of time i don't
know like sure we can try it
but i don't know
will you add normal maps to sprites for
lighting effects
um probably not because
i don't know where i would get the
normal maps from right
are you interested for it to be a mix of
hand authored rooms oh yeah
i i probably want there to be some hand
authoring
and gender like it's there wouldn't be
like hand authoring like
where we specifically create a room but
we're going to create i think
generators that are fairly specific so
it's kind of hand authored
with a limited amount of stuff right
oh gameplay-wise no the gameplay-wise is
that the tiles you hop on the tiles
while fighting the monsters so it gives
you something constructive you have to
do in the room
it's not about trying to get monsters to
jump on them
there probably will be some things like
that in the game because why not but
that's not like the main
thing you would do the main thing you do
is try to hop on the tiles yourself
while fighting
i've heard you say before it you don't
believe it's good or necessary to know
many programming languages because in
your words program it works from first
principles
i do hear all the time though that you
shouldn't be married to your programming
language and you should always use the
best science to the problem
um i would say i just i mean i say i
don't disagree with that actually
um what i would say is that
programming is basically the same no
matter what language you do it in
the mental process is and understanding
what the computer does is all you really
need to know
so most of the time
it really doesn't matter what language
you use in my opinion
as long as that language isn't like
really um
hamstrung so like you know i wouldn't
program in javascript most of the time
because
you can't really do much with it it
doesn't really work
like you can't really do threading and
you can't really do
cmd very well like like you just can't
really use it
it forces you to go through a garbage
collector you don't have a choice
so like you know there's some languages
like javascript that you just never use
unless you have to right
but other than that
as long as you know a language that's
fairly capable that you can do most
things with
you know c d rust now seems okay
probably
although i haven't actually verified
that myself um
you know java probably not because it's
kind of limited like java is kind of
like javascript in some ways it's it's
not very good
at letting you express things like
probably not python
again very limited um in what it can
express
so there are some languages that i would
probably stay away from because
you're very limited if you use them but
any language that's like generally
capable
um it doesn't really matter
which one you're using right um so
so i would say i kind of agree
where i might disagree with the people
that you're talking about
is that they think there's these huge
differences between how good it is to
program in language a versus b
and i think they're wrong about that i
think they drastically overestimate
the actual benefits you get from these
different languages
which is not to say that i don't think
there could be languages
that were like so good that
you really do get a huge benefit program
i think in the future we'll have those
right now like people who think that
like python is way better than
you know c sharp or something it just
it's like
they're just kind of delusional you know
as to thinking about
what they've never done any measurements
to prove that i think is usually what i
would say
because it's just not true
do you find it hard to design the engine
without the concrete requirements of a
civic game design
not really um
you know engine code is engine code it
needs to be flexible
because even if you think you know the
game design it always changes so you
can't really
you know you can't really hard code
stuff that way anyway
starco galaxies were shooting for may
so starco galaxy hopefully will be out
the very early versions of it will be
out sometime in may
is the hope definitely by june something
will be shipped
but it's very early so it will be
updated substantially
um after that so that's
it won't be anywhere close to final
that'll be like the earliest of early
access for people who want to start in
the beginner's stuff
so
how do you avoid overcomplication i
don't i don't over
avoid it you watched that today what i
do is
as when it gets over complicated we then
[Music]
we then work on condensing it right
like it
not putting in things that you don't
need you know you you always want to be
sensible when you're programming but
you're always going to make mistakes
about thinking something should go one
way and you start going and you realize
it's just too unwieldy
just stop condense it right like when
you see it happening just condense it
it's
nobody knows like
the um nobody knows
ahead of time the right architecture
ever unless they've already done it
and so you don't really want to come at
it from the standpoint of how do i not
over complicate my code
you want to come out from the standpoint
of how do i identify complexity that
doesn't need to be there and remove it
and again it's like what we were doing
today it's like oh why are we storing
all this stuff only to unpack it later
like can we just condense that down and
do it directly
can we move that stuff closer to where
it's actually happening you're
asking yourself questions like that all
the time and when you see opportunities
you take them
and over time that compacts the code
back down to something usable
when you've done something wrong you
know what i mean
so it's it's usually less about not
making mistakes because
everyone makes mistakes no matter how
good you get you're going to over
complicate your code
sometimes so the important part is to
recognize when it's got over complicated
and then condense back down right
pull out that complexity find better
ways to like
you know attack that complexity
when you see it happening
if i like a low level language like c
but a syntax feature like member
function
what's the solution well i mean
for the literal thing you just said the
solution is c plus plus
because you can take c and
just program and c exclusively and then
when you want member functions you just
use them right
so
you need a feature that doesn't exist
yeah i mean meta program is really your
only choice
right because if the feature doesn't
exist in the language that you're using
you know you've got to figure out a way
to implement it yourself right
if that's what you want you know ideally
ideally you luck out and there's a
language that has the feature set that
you want
but you know it's true that a lot of
times these days most languages don't
have most features you would want so
you're usually left unhappy because
you know you have to make compromises
that's just programming someday we'll
have better languages hopefully
you know
if you have questions about star code
galaxy um i would highly recommend
just going to the discord um
so this this right here um
discord.com invite molly rocket just
just go to this discord
um and there's a star code galaxy forum
it's got pinned messages that have
stuff like that um
so you know
when someone notes slash slash to do
casey does that means to do casey
noted or to do four cases to do um
so i don't think there's a standard for
that
so i don't know but
everywhere i've ever done anything like
that
and the people that i see who do it we
all
tend to mean that it's something we
noted
so it's not assigning someone a task
it's saying casey thought this
right and then someone else knows
when they look at that to do they're
like oh casey thought this should be
fixed
they don't think casey's going to fix it
now probably if casey thought it should
be fixed casey is going to fix it
because he's the one who wanted it fixed
but that's not usually the implication
i think
um following up on the question about
programming languages a lot of people
seem to think that dynamic languages are
way more expressive than non-dynamic
ones in the sense that you can
accomplish a lot with very little code
when you say these languages are limited
do you mostly mean they don't allow you
to
okay so so that's nonsense it's just
complete nonsense
uh people who think that that you know
dynamic
languages are more expressed in
non-dynamic languages and accomplishing
a lot of code they're they're just
you know completely wrong it's full stop
and
um you know the
the reason they think that is because
they've never actually looked at how
much code they are i mean
ask yourself a very simple question
if i go
somewhere on the internet okay
ask yourself how much code it would take
to produce this in c
assuming that you're using some kind of
render library or something
you know um because
presumably you know or even if you had
to implement opengl yourself
and the message loop and everything it'd
be like a couple thousand lines of code
right well if i actually go
uh in here you know and
we look at sources and we say like well
all right well where's all the code like
let's take a look
at all the code that's in here
right this is a dynamic language
and it's not only a dynamic language but
it's a dynamic language that like
was used as an output format right
i'm sorry i haven't looked at facebook's
javascript code in a while i'm also not
familiar with how to do this in
edge but i just want to pull up some
some code right uh that's in here
i suppose i also need to go to an actual
i suppose i probably should look i mean
you look at how much stuff is in here
but this is all stuff that they
generated so
it's probably not as useful because it's
tons of tiny little files
um let me take somebody who maybe didn't
compress their stuff or maybe shipped it
more directly
i don't know let's see if we can find
somebody
so let's take a look at
you know i mean you know i can't even
really
assess it because it's all been
compressed down i can't even look at how
big it actually
is because they you know in the old days
it used to be easier
to take a look at some of this stuff
because they don't
uh smush it all down like this so it's a
little bit harder to see
but just look at this
there are literally like thousands and
thousands of lines of smushed down code
in this website and it all it has
is this it's two buttons
right um
yeah i should look for you're right i
should you know what someone just
mentioned the chat use the pretty print
so that's a very good idea thank you so
look at the code there is
thousands and thousands of lines of code
and this is what they got
so i mean if this were
20 lines of code in javascript i'd agree
with you
and to a certain extent i'm
i'm beating up on them a little unfairly
because i could probably do this
in you know a couple hundred lines of
javascript code
soup to nuts actually as a library that
worked or whatever
right but
if you look at how these people actually
ship code
before they can ever make that statement
where they have to be like look at how
easy it is to program diamond clearance
everything they ship should be trivial
it should be like 50 lines of code for
everything for the like you know
for the stupid ad cookie for the
you know the button layout whatever if
these languages were so much more
powerful
why are they thousands and thousands of
lines of code to do almost nothing
right so and the answer is because
no like architecture is what determines
how few code
lines you have it's not the language
really
and the architectures that they choose
are so bad you know
you end up with things like you know
that this page is probably made in you
know angular react.js or
one of these things and it's like yeah
here's you know 50 000 lines of code
that we just shove down your face and
all it can do is like put up a couple
buttons or something
right and then they're like well we
program in
dynamic languages because look at how
convenient and easy they are and there's
so many cuz like no they're not
it's this huge like debugging these
things
must take forever trying to find out
what's going on right
and so in general
it's how sensible you code is how
concise the code is you can write a c
program
that does a lot of stuff in a thousand
lines of code
you can write a javascript program that
does a lot of stuff in a thousand lines
of code
the people who sit around saying stuff
like javascript is
takes less lines of code to do stuff
where's the proof
where is the proof that they're doing so
much with so little because they
always seem to take drastically more
to do drastically less so i think people
should
stop making claims without metrics
you want to claim that javascript like
languages let you be much more compact
than c
show me this web page in less than like
50 000 lines of code or whatever the
hell it's doing right now right
so i mean and it gets tiresome because
it's like you know people have these
arguments but what are they arguing
about they have nothing they have no leg
to stand on
their stuff is terrible it's slow it's
buggy it's bloated
and it takes tens of thousands of lines
of code to do simple things
they shouldn't be saying anything they
should be saying the only thing that
people who ship stuff like this should
be saying
is we have a lot to learn that's what
they should be saying
right they should never be advocating
for anything that they're doing
because it's obviously not good right
yeah i'm sorry is another thing they
could say
but you should do x or this is better
than c
is a stupid thing to say because
obviously it's not
like you know you obviously didn't
succeed
in whatever the thing is that you said
you were doing you failed
so maybe maybe it is true
that javascript is better than c for
something right
but you didn't demonstrate that so you
should stop
talking like that until you actually go
figure it out
your intuition is worthless because this
is what we got
right so
you know put up or shut up is another
way to say it like
you want to make big claims like dynamic
languages are better than static
languages
show me right
you should be if it's so obvious it
should be easy to prove and this
is the opposite this proves the opposite
if anything right
so you're starting from you got to go
uphill
you're shipping real crappy stuff so
if you want to make claims that there's
something better about it
the burden's on you because your output
sucks right like what you're what you're
accomplishing is terrible
so you need to you've got you need to
start making excuses for yourself
not claiming that somehow other people
are making bad choices
because because it looks like you're the
one who's making the bad choices right
so you should start from a place of like
if you want to explain that away
go ahead explain it away for me right um
but
you know you got to do it with metrics
you got to prove that what you're saying
is not hand waving that you're really
right
you know
500 it took me 400 lines of code to
write a 2d plotting calculator in
javascript
i don't know why it takes so much for a
simple crud website though
yeah i mean and like um the starco
galaxy front end is web front end
so that's written in javascript and it's
you know i use the same principles i use
when i'm programming c and it's very
small compact and very reliable
unlike the web pages i use which is why
i say i think
how much utility how much reliability
you get out of a piece of code is almost
always about
your sensible architecture and not about
like
what you're programming in because as
far as i can tell
you know if you give twitter any
language it doesn't matter what the
language is
they will give you a thing that's
terrible right
it doesn't matter if you hand them
javascript or rust
or c or d or c sharp or
java the thing that will come out will
be garbage
right so i don't think it matters
whether you're using javascript or c
it doesn't really make a difference
right
when you pick a particular task you
usually just
have you know a limited set of options
that are things that you could use you
know
you obviously can't use c on a web front
end because javascript's the only thing
that it will execute
although you know soon you might be able
to right with webassembly you might be
able to use c
but basically you should just pick the
thing that you're most comfortable in
that has the capabilities that
you need and then it's the sensible
architecture that will keep the code
good it has nothing to do with the
language that's just language fetishism
that doesn't really pay off these days
because most languages
at the end of the day are just too
similar and they really don't get much
leverage
you know
all right
you everyone for joining me for the
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
uh
you can always pre-order the game on
handmadehero.org and it comes with a
source code
so that you can play around with it uh
we will be back no
well that's not true i will be giving a
lecture
uh for the university of i don't know
how to say the name
t-w-e-n-t-e it's in the netherlands and
i'm sure i will
butcher their pronunciation um so i
won't do it
but i'm giving a lecture on wednesday
and you can see it's on the schedule
here
right there so if you're interested in
that
it's going to be about taking a look
at some work i did on optimizing
a sort of distribution a grass
plant and grass distribution system uh
in the witness
and it was the thing where i i had
something
that i was supposed to take a look at
that took you know a minute or two
minutes or something to to complete and
i was able to optimize it down to real
time
and so it was it's just going to be a
talk about like looking at
a thing that someone has created that's
very slow
and figuring out why it's very slow and
how when you actually remove all of the
things that make it slow it's
it's like you know potentially like a
thousand times faster right
than it was because you know a lot of
times we don't really go
over stuff like that so i figured it
would be fun to to sort of go over what
that looked like
um so that's what's going to be and
it's uh it's it's at this time
and at this it'll be a light board
it'll be on the light board uh
so so you know it's it's like a stand-up
kind of
thing so that's it that'll be wednesday
uh hope to be back here for that and
then next weekend
uh on saturday again we'll we'll be back
to programming handmade hero so that's
it
have fun pranking everyone and i maybe
i'll see you wednesday for the lecture
if not i'll see you next weekend
take it easy everybody