hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero sure we code a complete game
live on stream uh folks actually
found a bug for us um
i'll be completely honest with you i
don't know that we are logged in in fact
we aren't logged into github here but
um
suffice to say if you are on the
handmade hero private github
then you may have seen there is an issue
that someone had found
a bug in math code it's a mistake i've
made twice i can't seem to get it
through uh my my thick skull
on this particular issue i don't know
why
i have it in my head that a particular
command works a particular way and it
doesn't work that way
and i've literally made this mistake two
times on exactly the same thing
right uh and let me show you uh where it
is
first of all thank you for the folks who
who tracked this bug down it saves us
a lot of of headaches of ever finding it
which we probably would have had to do
eventually but we probably would have
had no idea where it was
uh and it would have been bad but
um like we probably only would have
found it when it comes time to like
do like specific testing on the math
library or something like that which you
know
is the only time we probably ever ever
would have even found it
but anyway uh so if you take a look at
our
intrinsics i believe is where they are
um so we have a sign of function
that we were using for f32s
and you can see here that we have a
blend vps
right um and so
in my mind for some reason
blend v works by doing
a bit-wise combine of the source and the
input
using the mask so it goes through the
bits of
the uh source and the two sources
it goes through the bits the two sources
and it just uses the mask
bit in that location to pick which one
which bit it's going to pull
so in my mind it's like an or
between an and of the mask and an and
not of the mask
of the two inputs right that's in my
mind what it does in actuality that is
not what it does so if you look at the
intra intrinsics guide for example
uh which i think we can
and then blend vps yeah
um so if you actually look at what this
does
you can see that it actually doesn't
do it per bit right it
only does it per lane
see what i'm saying
i do not i do not know
why this fails to
be in my head like this is not what the
function does
in my head and i'm gonna have to re
i'm gonna keep making mistakes about it
uh until i
internalize this i've literally made
exactly this mistake before
at least one other case i can remember
and so
this doesn't work for sine of
right so we can look and we can see
where our blend v
ps is at uh and oops i should probably
search the whole project
mm blendvps
so we can look here at where this uh
value actually is and you can see we've
got one in cmd
here where we do sine of there and we've
got one
um in 70 here where we do it's the same
function
right uh just one for scalar and one for
four wide
and they're both the same wrong
now i don't actually know where we use
this
if we search probably not in a lot of
places because we would have seen this
bug
uh show up more often if you know
uh if we'd used it a lot so you can see
here
inside the lighting code where we're
doing our like actual probe stuff here
you can see that we do a sign of there
um and that's gonna be wrong so so this
is probably wrong
uh then we've got inside the other the
octahedral like from unit vector stuff
i don't really know who's still calling
that because i think we may have like in
line most of that but
um and then that's not real these are
these are uh
from the shaders so those are those are
different uh
they are using the shaders version not
ours right
so at least i think that's true let me
just verify but it wouldn't matter
because this wouldn't use a blend b
anyway right there in shaders
so you can see like this will be
adversely
affecting our lighting i don't know that
it has anything to do with the lighting
bug that we had but you know because i
can't think of any
i can't think of a lot of ways that that
would actually
be the case um
i i i can't think of of a lot of ways
that that would be
the the case
yeah i don't know um i also don't know
if this would have
uh if this would have affected our
octahedral lighting pattern right uh
because if you look at generate
octahedral lighting pattern
uh i don't know if this direction from
txty
right that's the direction from txty and
get octahedral offset
uh those could be implicated with this
as well in which case we'd have to rerun
the generator so you can see
uh yeah in fact they are right
so we've got in both cases we've got
uh we just have this sign problem here
and so what i want to do
is go ahead and fix that code just so we
don't have this issue
it might also be nice at some point to
merge these two like it would be nice if
we didn't have two sino functions
because
you know we probably could get away with
one
there are some issues because you kind
of want to do ps versus ss
in these cases um and so i don't know to
what extent we want to
you know try and go down that route but
um
like this should really be an ss uh
if unless they don't have one of those
do we not have one of those is that why
that's doing that yeah okay
um but the and and stuff and the or
would do that
so anyway this is what we need to do we
would like to take the sign of this
value and
what we want to do here is we want to
basically
keep the uh entirety
of the input but we want to
[Music]
we want to just replace the top bit
right that's all we wanted to do so
we're trying to take this mask u32 here
and we're trying to basically do an mm
like and
uh and not probably right so we're gonna
try and take do an and not to clear it
out and then we're gonna do
an mm or right to knock it back in
so we want to to
we want to just knock that into a value
that's all ones
which we already have and so this
doesn't need to get
masked out right so we can take
the value that's all ones and then we
can
make something called sign only right
that we produce here
that that only has the sign bit and when
we or the sign bit into the ones
it will flip their sign as necessary
right
so that's all we really needed to do and
so what we need to do here is just
uh pull out the the sine value and so we
have to look up
i never remember who gets knotted in the
and not
i don't remember if it's the second
parameter or the first parameter
right so so somebody gets nodded and i
don't remember
who it is but we can take a look
yes you can see the and not here
actually that's
huh
so
i i'm a little confused
is there a reason why lake
is no longer listed on here
it's there
did they just never update these for
skylake i guess i've never looked
anyway i'm assuming that it's 0.33 on
skylake although maybe not because this
is 1-1-1 for throughput
so so actually based on that
this looks maybe like a bad idea um
oh no that's right never mind we don't
need to end not that that's the correct
thing
right i take it back we only need to and
it out
correct because if we and this out
uh then it will just be the sign bit so
we don't need to and not it because we
don't have to process this
uh at all otherwise so if we load that
in
and we we mask off just the high bit and
then we merge it in
we should be good to go in fact we can
just do this right
uh so that seems that seems good
um
that all seems good to me uh and so
let's just go ahead
and finish this off we need to extract
the result
obviously so there we go um i might make
this
be a two-step process because that line
is getting a little long
in the tooth so
maybe i'll just grab this out there
and we could do this just to make it a
little easier to read
right
just helping helping peeps out
so if we look at what this does now we
basically say we need
one because we're trying to get a sign
here this is not
sign or zero which i thought we needed
so now i'm a little weirded out because
i don't know
where that went um
because we had that didn't we like what
happened to signer zero
i'm kind of weirded out about that
because i thought
for sure that you needed to have
the sign for that octahedral where you
did a sine or zero
and maybe we like reorganized the code
did did we
like did we do something else here
because i really just don't
remember
i guess is what we did just say that
sign of is always signer zero
like meaning this just always produces
sine or zero
or something because if that's the case
then this is also wrong
so i'm just i'm just a little confused
like i don't i thought i
i recall the sign of having to be
uh negative one positive one or
zero if the input was actually zero and
i thought that was a requirement
for the octahedral stuff
but maybe i'm misremembering that right
um but but i seem to recall that that
was a thing that happened
right uh
so i i don't i don't love that right um
i i i don't really know what's going on
there
so it would be nice to know uh what was
happening
that's one to go back to the episode
because i know we like we should go back
and watch the video
because i know that that was something
uh that was an issue
and
i just don't really remember
does anyone chat remember
yeah probably no one remembers that's
all right so so this part is weird
and i think we kind of need to take a
look at that so i'm just going to put a
to-do in here which says to
do look
at octahedral code and figure out
if we're actually using sine or
zero uh or sine
of four sine or zero in places
because i don't see a sine or zero and i
feel like i feel like there should be
one um
so yeah
[Music]
what else do we need to do okay so
it looks like these are only in ps land
okay so in this case we've now
got a sign of that should probably be
more correct let's take a look at it
really carefully to make sure
and we can also step through it to see
if we've got it uh working a little bit
better than it was before
so in here we have the mask which
is just this like mask u32 with the high
bit
set right we then have a one that we
load
we and the mask with
the value that you pass in which the
mask is all zeros except for the sign
bit so that should leave us with just
the sign bit
that was passed in right so just the
sign bit of whatever this is
we then combine that by oring it in to
the one
so we flip the signs of the one
basically based on where they were
flipped
in here and of course we're only doing
this for one lane right now but we're
going to have it for the four lanes as
well
and then we like extract the value back
out now there's another sign of function
there's one uh
uh it would be nice if these showed the
where they are in the files
yeah um so here's the same function
right and so we can if we want to uh
just
change this one to basically be the
exact same thing
only instead of ever there being a ss
it's just a ps everywhere um
and i think
that is the whole of it i think
sign bit and ps and i'm set ss
value dot p
um what is the problem cannot convert
argument 1
from mn128 to float
there we go so
i think this should be the equivalent
for it in four wide for our little
f32s4x
there so this will do the the
correct sign i believe um
and here's sign bit from
i don't know why synov isn't just using
those those were written correctly
um as you can see here so
anyway so we could just have this call
sign bit from
in fact maybe that's more sensible right
like right here we could just say
well we just need the sign bit so we
just say
sign bit from like so
and that gives us the sign bit so we
just order the sign bit
with one
right
and that's the result
probably i also don't know
like do we just have an operator or
anyway
we do so really you could just write
this
just directly so the other thing we
could do is just say
oh like actually the result is just
this
and i don't know what we have for set
calls in this particular world
but um yeah so it's just this right
oops so we could just
do that um where we load a one and then
we or
the sign bit um
oops i gotta work on the
the new four coder thing doesn't do
tokens the way i expect
i have to go figure out how to fix that
not sure how
anyway um so i think that would
basically do it
and in theory if we run this now we
presumably
won't really get because since we
weren't
super able to perceive that error to
begin with um running it or not running
it is not really going to tell us
anything um anyway
uh but you know we can at least verify
that things didn't completely destroy
themselves
right um
so that all seems fine
right this looks like it's running the
way that it was before
um unfortunately we don't really
have a way of looking at this code
you know we don't have a way of like
reproducing our our release lighting bug
so um there was some question as to
whether fixing the sign
bit error would actually fix the
lighting bug that we were encountering
and the answer to that
is that we just don't know right i mean
we hadn't tracked down that bug yet so
we don't
actually know um we don't have any
expectation of
whether or not that would fix it uh so
so i'm sorry unfortunately i can't
there's no real way to reliably provoke
that bug
um it's entirely possible that it was
because of that
like there was something that was
writing garbage in somewhere or who
knows what
um as a result of that code being
totally uh wrong
but uh we don't have a way of
specifically provoking that bug at the
moment
so unfortunately we can't release we we
just don't know
so we're gonna have to still look at um
uh at that and see uh
but you know that's just yeah that's
just where we're at
at the moment uh so yeah thank you for
reporting that in i'm going to go take a
quick second to just look through that
code
and make sure that it's now doing
something sensible because we know that
it was wrong
and we just kind of slapped in a fix for
it so i'd like to just make sure
uh that it's actually correct uh at some
point
or at least like step through it at
least once to give myself a little bit
more
uh confidence that we actually fixed it
and yeah so the lighting the retail
lighting bug that we were having before
is not
there at the moment um let me look
so the spec valid diffuse valve thing
though still
is a bit weird it looks like that was
still set to
um bogus values there
see there there's like spec valid
diffuse valid
are both zero and they both knock on to
one as we move
so i think there's probably still issues
there
um like there may be a situation
for example where we're i think we have
a situation where we're not like
clearing the lighting because remember
we're trying to be
pretty minimal here there's not a lot of
safeguards in the lighting code because
it's trying to be performance oriented
and so we don't have the luxury of doing
a lot of like clearing or
you know things where we're spending
extra cpu time to make sure we don't
have stupid errors
we don't really have the luxury of doing
that right everything's got to be kind
of a little bit bare bones
um so given that given that uh
fact uh i i still
i still yeah there we go i'm like i
still suspect the bug is there we just
can't provoke it uh and so there you go
right
and so i think that we still should keep
looking for that
error uh and i think there's uh there's
some issues there right
now we may and i don't know
but we may have gotten a quality
improvement
as well uh oh check that out
look at there's the bug in like a
localized way right
um we may have gotten a quality
improvement from fixing that sign bug
like
probably what happened like we could go
back and compare by like flipping the
sign thing back to
to being wrong but uh
we probably got better like more uniform
lighting
or something you can see that they're
still kind of it kind of feels a little
bit like there might still be some bugs
in there we haven't really done a
careful pass on lighting
but we probably had some asymmetry that
was getting introduced by that sign
being wrong
and by fixing it we presumably got a
more
correct distribution of the light right
so that presumably happened but you know
we
uh like i said we were just trying to
fix that but we weren't really trying to
improve the lighting quality that
may have just been a byproduct that
happened because that bug would have
been making things worse
right would have been making the
lighting look worse um
similarly like we have very boxy
interpolation of the lighting right now
which i
wanted to fix for a while uh but that
sort of separates you i don't know where
it's coming
from is the problem like obviously it's
coming from the fact that we interpolate
uh the lighting based on uh
the like cube boundaries there but
it it probably shouldn't quite look like
that right um and so that's kind of
another thing but that's separate so
we'd
have plenty of lighting quality things
to do for right now i want to look at
that
right you can see you get these weird
artifacts that come in
and we just have no idea where they're
coming from
so what i'd like to do is get a uh just
spend the rest of the day seeing if we
can get a better
uh way of looking at
the state of the light map so that we
can figure out where those values are
coming from
right just just some idea of where
they're coming from and i
think that it only happens in release
mode so
for whatever reason um if this is set to
od
we we don't really see it happen as much
but
uh to be fair that may just be because
we don't run
enough frame like you know the debug
mode is very slow
because the lighting is slow in debug
mode um and so it may just be
like that you it's hard to provoke
because
you need it to run you know fast to run
enough frames to hit the bug
because it's periodic right so
i think that's kind of you know
uh i don't want to put too much stock in
that
uh
i mean you know it's because it looks
like the lighting
basically looks the same in both modes i
i don't see like a lot of difference
between them
which is why i'm not really sure
is the spec valid diffuse valid does
that happen in
in debug mode the same way as well would
be another question
you can see those like spec valid
diffuse valid values
are not wrong um
and like it sure so that it's a bit
troubling because
you know if i if i set it to o2
like yes the the bug uh
isn't immediate like like we don't see
the bug immediately
but like those values start out at zero
right
so i would like to know what's going on
there uh and so i want to take a look
and see like is there something weird
going on that is not what i would expect
to have happen
like how are those how are we getting
those values um
written in their wrong and so
i want to go ahead and look at the light
atlas like here's the code
um in validate atlas
that that tells us when a texel is is
wrong or whatever right
and so what i'd probably like to do here
is just have the validate like like
i'd like to have a thing that validates
texels
this is just checking to see if they're
negative right um
and they really never should be so i'm
just gonna do here
a validate pexel
and i'm going to have a texel that you
pass in here
and i'm going to put this code as
validate texel
um
like so and i'm going to put that
in a way that we can call it on a single
texel
uh elsewhere in the code actually let's
do this why does it do that so the
indentation
in yeah uh i want that may have been
fixed i have to update the four coder as
well i i should i should do that like
after stream today we should like update
our for coder
and the new four quarter flurry and then
send the things that are still not
working to
ryan and alan just to see what the
status is um
on that uh yeah
okay um so let's go ahead and do this
and see what happens here
this is oops
this is more correctly written as suchly
so what i now need to do is this
validate texel call here i want to be
able to do that any time that we're like
writing new texels so like for example
in here you can see this block copy
thing where we do like copy tile or zero
tile right
um we could
put in a stopper here for example uh
in fact that seems like a good idea uh
now that i think about it
so we've got this validate atlas thing
maybe one thing we'll do here
is like i'll put in a uh
some assertions so like when we do
block copy atlas i will do like a
um assert
so this is just going to be an assertion
like in and out
so what this will tell me is just does
the block copy
ever like screw up the atlas
um and so what we can see here is that
like i put one at the top and one at the
bottom and the reason for that was to
see
if it ever screwed up the atlas and what
you can see
is that we're hitting the top one which
means that block copy atlas
was not implicated this time around
somebody else
was the reason why like somebody's
passing it in
uh it had already been mucked up
right block copy atlas didn't muck it up
and if we run this multiple times it's
actually kind of nice because we can see
that it just happens
every time right or well not i guess not
quite every time
it happens often right
so often when we run through there uh
we we will hit that validation fail
that means i can more or less leave this
routine out for now
uh meaning i don't have to worry like if
this thing is
like what's corrupting it because we now
know it's happening
uh before it ever does the block copy
atlas
for whatever frame the first frame is
that
that gets borked we never saw one where
it came in
okay and then left borked right
so that's helpful because it lets me go
all right let's focus on
somebody else then and uh let's see who
else is
is writing to these right um so when we
make the atlas as well
like you can see here where we do make
light atlas
that doesn't actually set the
uh atlas texels when we actually go to
set the light access
texels we could validate the atlas there
um and that is just something we might
as well do
um for you know just to make sure that
it's set to zeros to begin with and you
can see that like that just does not
trigger any problems right so we're
pretty sure we're starting up with valid
we could leave that one in there in fact
if we want to
all right uh and what's going on with
our light atlas assert right now
so the light atlas start is even defined
in in fact i could just go ahead and put
these in there
and then we could define it out right we
have to remember to actually do that so
our light atlas actually has a bunch of
assertions it shouldn't have
all right so we can put in some of these
like we can put in these calls uh
like to just do light atlas asserts that
we'll then turn off
at the end right so here's us doing a
bunch of validation
and we think we should basically
determine you know
from that that the light atlas code
itself is not causing the problem here
and that when we do cause the problem uh
wait how did that not happen
like is this not working or something
that should have
triggered right we just saw it happen
what's going on
okay
[Music]
that should be the exact same code right
very scared right now
okay so it was just the fact that
it just didn't happen to do it that okay
whoo i thought for i'm like what is
going on
okay so in theory that should be fine
now
so now what i want to do is try
to find a uh a i want to try and like
when i look at problems like this where
i just don't have any idea what's going
on right so
so so if i'm approaching a bug
and i don't have a theory like
i'm not testing there's no hypothesis
it's just a bug
i don't know where it comes from i just
know that there's a bogus
value getting in here somehow and i have
no idea how right
it could be a correctly written equation
that was just ill-conceived that
produces bad results
it could be typos in the code it could
be
something like the sign bug where i
thought an instruction did something it
didn't right it could be literally
anything
all i know is that there's a bad value
but i can sort of detect the bad values
by just saying like look
into intuitively speaking i should not
be able to get
negative values into this
uh light atlas but they they clearly are
why don't i just go hunt for negative
values then what i'm doing here is i'm
just thinking of like a set of pincers
basically right and what i'm going to
try and do
is just keep narrowing down the places
where the bug can be by validating the
atlas
in like sections of the code until
i find a place where when i enter the
code
it validates and when i exit the code it
doesn't validate
and i'm going to keep closing those
pincers in until i zero
in on the block of code that actually is
causing the problem
right and so by doing that
i'm hoping that we will be able to
narrow down our search before we start
looking at code
because otherwise it's just like it
completely
like i have no real way of pinpointing
anything in the code because any of the
code
in the entire lighting update could be
wrong and so i want to keep trying to
refine that down as
as small as i can get it because the
smaller i can get those pincers to start
with
the easier time i'll have like debugging
the code
so that's what i'm doing okay so we now
know that if we validate the atlas
we know that we're coming into the block
copy wrong so
we're we're assuming that that means
that like the lighting update itself is
what's writing in the negative values
um and so we can start to look at the
code that actually writes in these
things and you can see here that i
believe
there's only really two places where we
ever
update these things and i can validate
both of them and see
if i get a clean like enter clean exit
dirty
um out of out of those so one of them
is where we update the spec texels right
and the spectexel atlas
uh gets updated in here and i think i
think this is the only place
right so so i think that the only place
the spec atlas gets written to is in
grid rake i mean
other than the block copy we already
looked at the grid raycast
will update the spec texels so every
time we enter
a light atlas texel for spec texel there
so here right
you can see it writing in it loads out
the texel here
and writes the texel here so we should
be able to validate the texel
right there and see very clearly
whether or not the spec texel gets
updated to negative values there
and then even if so we can see if that
enters clean exit sturdy
then we can also look because eve if
that
actually happens there's another thing
we could do is we could validate
the thing we're actually blending
towards right
because it could be that the spectexel
uh that this
the spectexel itself uh is is just
getting blended with like a negative
value and going towards zero
which would mean that it's really just
this code up here that screwed up right
and so on and so forth so we should be
able to validate this code very heavily
now
in addition to that code we also have
um all this other code like here that
does stuff with texels like filling in
the borders of
of places um on the octahedral map
and the thing that takes and blurs out
right the it takes the spec and blurs it
out to produce a diffuse map
so the thing that that basically takes
the spec map and produces a diffuse map
from the spec map
that also uh can be busted
so those are all of our points and we
can really start to narrow this down so
the first thing i'm going to do
is just put in assertions here um
where we're going to do a validate atlas
on the spec atlas and the diffuse atlas
uh and what we should be able to do here
is where we
uh validate these on like the full cast
right this is going to make this code
run very slowly because we keep
uh validating the atlases all the time i
don't care
uh we're just going to validate these
atlases uh multiple times inside here i
should probably also turn off
multithreading to make this a little bit
easier on us
so we'll we'll do that in a second as
well but we'll go ahead and do the full
cast here
and then we'll we'll uh do the blur
update
and uh we'll validate again and then
we'll validate again
right so now we're just validating we're
we're having a validation party
right um konichiwa
validation party sorry i've been
watching a lot of mr yabatan lately
uh
let's see uh so now we're just doing
some stuff
right we're just validating we're
validating a lot
uh and so oh and we're in release mode
right because
we want to be yeah um so we're
validating a lot we're just hoping we
crash somewhere
uh and we do so here you can see us
entering the validation
doing the full cast exiting the
validation
assuming that i didn't screw anything up
here it means that we don't really have
to think about this code
right because we validated the atlas
uh after each of these right
and we know that we entered clean
to full cast and exited dirty
right um so
enter clean exit dirty full cast means
that now i'm just going to assume
for sake of argument that we don't have
to think about
the rest of this code here we can just
focus
on full cast itself and start to look at
problems with that so inside
full cast what i might do since i know
that that
is the case i might just go to full cast
itself
uh full cast is working on a specific
set
of tiles right uh is how this is working
you can see it here as it goes
we assume that since the diffuse atlas
is validated
that it cannot be the source of
incorrect values
our reading from it could be broken so
we could
end up with incorrect values that we're
getting because we screw
up the lookup into the diffuse atlas but
we've validated the atlas itself
so it should not actually be producing
negative values itself it would have to
be
our reading from it that was broken but
let's take a look now at
every place where these atlases are
actually used and go from there
also i don't know why we're passing in
the tile
when we also pass in both atlases
but you know that's just i guess the way
we wrote this routine
oops
i don't know what's going on here
okay um so what i want to do
is try to validate now on a texel by
texa level
so we can catch specifically what piece
of code is causing the problem like we
valid we know that now
or at least we think we know that inside
the full cast someone is producing
negative values right and what we want
to do
is we want to take those uh the the
individual steps as best we can
and start to see like who's producing uh
the garbage
now if we take a look at here you can
see us doing some stuff
like looping through these spatial grids
and so on
none of this stuff should really be
implicated because no matter what it
does
uh it's it it's just going to produce
like ray intersections or something
right so in theory we shouldn't really
care what's happening here because even
if this code is completely broken and
just produces
totally incorrect uh intersection points
the lookup code is still supposed to
work like if you just pass
a 3d position that you're like what's
the lighting at this point it's still
supposed to work no matter what garbage
you did
to generate it so we should be able to
find um
something i'm looking at what is go chat
does nobody on the chat speak japanese
seriously
nobody on the chat speech job we don't
have a single japanese viewer
somebody does somebody does somebody
said
right there
yes excellent
so those of you who are replying right
now
uh who do speak japanese it's 5 30 a.m
okay good point but there would be
there'd be japanese people who don't
necessarily live in japan like or people
who
aren't japanese but speak japanese right
and if you watch mr yabaton you know
what hontoni bikurista means
because he says it like in every single
video
somebody post a link to mr yabatan
how good is my japanese is terrible
absolutely terrible as you could
probably tell from my
pronunciation of hanto nibikirishta
which is probably
very poorly pronounced um
somebody post a link to mr yabaton
like maybe post if someone can while i'm
typing here post a link to the mr
yabaton
where he does a uh he he
he does like a um hot pot
with his dad on the phone
uh
did you know what i'm talking about
if someone could post that link mr
yabaton
if you don't know who mr yabatan is
we'll take care of it after the stream
all right anyway
uh mr yabatan is great
um he's like from norway i think
but he does like japanese videos um
and and like he makes fun of
people trying to speak japanese and
failing actually sometimes i mean
you'll see it's fine um yeah foreigner
meets ramen is great
he in forner meets ramen he actually
does
he says he pretends to have like an
australian accent and does like what it
sounds like
when a person with an australian accent
is speaking japanese
which is pretty funny that's not how mr
yabutan actually sounds mr yabadon
actually has
very good japanese pronunciation from
what i can hear not that i'm a great
judge of that but
um him and dogen who's another streamer
who does that stuff they they sound like
really good uh compared to like what a
foreigner normally
seems to sound like to me when they
speak japanese where i can i can really
tell
even though i'm not very good at
japanese you can hear the difference
between a native japanese speaker
and the average like foreign youtuber
who also speaks japanese
they sound totally different um
but like mr yabatan and dogen
sound like really good uh by comparison
you know i'm sure so sure they probably
still have an accent
because you know it's probably not
possible to be like 100 fluent
um but like it's pretty impressive how
much better they are than a lot of the
people oh yeah nabe party not a party
with my dad
that's the one
uh anyway mr yabaton's catchphrase is
haunto nibikrista which means i'm very
surprised
uh or like or like
that's surprising and i mean i don't
know how you want to translate it but
like that's what
uh he says all the time so uh
i feel like i feel like that's you know
when we find this bug
hontoni bikrishta we're very surprised
we'll be very surprised at what it is
okay so we know that we're inside full
cast we've got issues
uh and so let's try to narrow it down
here we like
i i really don't think that the spatial
partition walk is implicated that seems
unlikely
um so when we go through here and we're
doing like uh
raycasting you can see here
where we uh where we don't care what
happens in here i guess handle lurking
towards zero in case where we
ever have moving occluders
um so what happens in that case actually
uh what do we produce
so nothing okay so we actually like just
don't we just don't do an update
uh in this case so in this case i think
we're fine right like we shouldn't have
we shouldn't really have any problems
there so so maybe
uh let's do this just to make sure that
the problem is actually in this case
uh because it should be now right
okay here we go
and this is just validating around that
block yeah
so again that's what we want to see
remember pincers we're just pincing down
and what we want to see is we want to
see enter clean
exit dirty right now before i go any
further with the pincers i want to turn
off multi-threading
the reason i want to turn off
multi-threading is just because
if we if we don't there's a possibility
that like some piece of code
in some other place is doing it that
hasn't entered yet and we're picking
that up on the exit
so i just want to go ahead and nerf the
multi-threading real quick
just to make sure uh that we don't have
uh
that that particular pathology happening
uh it's not that likely obviously but
you know it certainly could
so what i want to do is where it does
the internal lighting core which is here
um and it passes in uh the lighting
queue
i want to just pass in uh zero there so
maybe we'll do a thing that's like uh
you know
dis disable oh i don't i don't know
maybe i shouldn't do that uh
i was thinking of maybe making a switch
for this right
um so one way to do this would be like
global b32 uh light uh
multi like light disable
threading so there's a thing here that
we could just turn
uh so we can basically like look oops
uh if we disable the threading then you
don't get a lighting queue
uh and and you won't um multithread
and so uh in theory like right if i
set this to true now um then it will
pass a zero there
and and we won't get uh we won't get any
threading
and mind mark 42 yeah i mean that's what
i remember i remember it using assign
not zero
and so i was wondering we have to go
back and see because i know we dealt
with that
on stream when we were doing it so
something's weird about the fact that
we're not doing a sign or zero there
and so i would like to know why
uh and so i want to go back and see why
we didn't
do that uh maybe we had a good reason
but but that seems weird so i don't know
all right anyway remove multi-threading
we've got that
uh busted assertion now and so uh i'm
gonna go ahead
and take that validate atlas stuff uh
that we dropped into the full cast so
here if i go up to full cast
and what i wanna do is now just validate
the actual parts i care about
so you can see here if we go down we've
got like sample direction
reading we run the grid raycast here
right a bunch of times
and then we come back and this is just
debug code so really
you know really we're talking about just
this code um
in grid raycast so uh
like right here is what we think is
the the bug right um
so in theory if we just uh if we just
validate just the texel so
i'm going to get rid of these right
and i want to take just the spec texel
and
if we look at grid raycast
so grid raycast loads one two
three four five six
right um
so i'll be completely honest with you my
memory of how this
is running has completely paged out of
my head
uh and so
i actually don't know
why that would be okay
[Music]
so
so oh well okay so it's we run
through eight rays at a time
six times four is 24 okay so we just do
eight rays at a time
and so that we can write out 24
things at a time so that's fine
so that's looks like all that is right
um so that seems fine and that just
means that we have to
uh we're we're writing one row
right so so we're writing the eight
texels
of one row of this thing oh
um don't let chat do not let me forget
to
re-run the sphere generator because our
sphere generator is also wrong
right um
probably has nothing to do with this bug
but again we want to do that because it
means that our casting is probably wrong
separate issue
okay so when we're doing this casting
what i want to do
is i want to validate all of these
texels so in here
i want to do a validate texel for each
of
these so when we do
um these texels
i think if i look at light atlas texel
it should just be
the row uh in question you can see it
here
right where we have uh the value is just
a pointer
so i should be able to do like validate
texel
like this um and we should be able to
validate
all of the tech the taxels in this row
um on entry and exit so basically that
is the validator right
so that should validate everything and
in theory
we should be able to catch the actual
like specific
uh validation like the thing that failed
um
and and that should that should just
work i think
now again don't actually don't quote me
on that because
i i don't 100
know
i mean i think that should be the case
so i'm gonna try and run it in debug
mode and just see if we can get it
um
or if it only happens in release mode
which it might
which really sucks
because i i you know i don't really know
like
why we would only be getting release
mode here if it has to do with some kind
of optimization that's happening
um like i just don't know you know what
would be
what would be causing this but you can
see pretty clearly like we're not
getting anything there
um but then when i do an o2
oh okay
what
such a weird bug
so we were having a validation fail
right away
and now magically it like it wasn't
happening
so we really have no idea what the
heck's going on here
if we believe this code
um where we're validating the tax holes
um you can see here that like it seems
incontrovertible
at this point that this is blending
towards a zero value
meaning that transfer pps had to be
negative the only reason i say that
is because if you look at the validate
textile calls
even if this is validating garbage
meaning even if this is like
off the end of the array or something
right
it validated here and it didn't validate
here it's the same value
right so
i mean i don't know how else to look at
that
now this is an f32 for x here
so there's something a little wonky if
we're writing 24 values
uh this is too many
right uh is that right no
no that's right so five times yeah so
in theory uh that just means that this
wrote out the last three values of this
f30
f324x the last three values the last rgb
set
that was written out there um
was just is just plain wrong it was
negative
somehow and if you take a look at this
code here
all it's doing is doing a one minus uh
blend value
right from s0 to t0
so the next thing i feel like that we
would want to
validate is that there are no negative
values in transfer pps now transfer bps
may be directly inspectable by us still
at this point i don't actually know
um or it could be complete hogwash so
uh i don't know you know this this is
what it's telling me transfer pps is but
don't know
if it actually is that or not right if i
go up and look at what transfer bps is
uh it's uninitialized right so
like uh one thing i don't know is is it
always
actually processed somehow um because
that
if it wasn't right like if if there's a
way to get out of this routine
without setting transfer pps that would
be a real doozy
right that that would that would do it
presumably
um now there's only really reason
ah there's one real easy way to test
that quickly um which is i could just
initialize transfer pps
right i could just say yeah yeah yeah
it's it's zero now
right um and then we
you know we can just see like does does
it have anything to do with that
uh and and off we go so so no right
so i mean it could that could still be a
separate bug but we know we can produce
it
excuse me regardless of whether that's
initialized or not
now if we look in here and we see where
transfer pps actually gets set
you can see we do a bunch of work here
to produce these values
uh which is i think that's us doing like
blending and such
and we produce down here the transfer
pps for the array index value by
reading out the transmission level of
these things um
and you can see us you know it's a
combination of a bunch of stuff
right now
i mean one of the things that's kind of
weird is how low these values are
um they're all very small
numbers which is a little bit weird
but uh what you can see
is that if like if we pretend
temporarily
that this is actually real like what
we're looking at here is not
fake uh that is just nuts
right like like i have no idea how that
value gets produced it's complete lunacy
the rest of these values are just very
small positive values which in theory
could be correct
right if you're kind of fairly distant
you know what i mean
uh
so i don't know what to make of that uh
i really don't
and we should probably just now try to
track that down
and we know furthermore even more
troubling
we know that this doesn't happen in
debug mode that we can
find um so like
whatever is happening there
is like is bad mojo on a code gen front
right so this code is like busted
somehow uh and and we don't know
we don't know how uh but it's
uh you know somewhere along the lines
it's broken
that suggests to me that we probably
need to start pincing
more because we don't know where in this
code we're at
so let's continue to pinch and let's
just say
look transfer pps should not be negative
so let's go ahead and make sure that
it's not
and now i'm just trying to move this bug
one up this this the spec the stack
basically right
and find a place where we trigger this
before we trigger this and it looks like
that's exactly what happened
right so if transfer pps is actually
negative
that again helps us narrow down the code
here
because it means that we're not like it
means that we kind of now know
uh that the actual culprit is the
computation of the transfer value
not the blend at the end so in theory
right we can now get rid of these
um although well you know i won't get
rid of them yet i suppose
but it means i can push up this transfer
here
and start looking at the transfer values
as they are retired
individually right so i'm going to
validate the transfers at the end i'm
also going to validate the
individual transfer values as they are
computed
right and i i expect that now i can hit
this
right away
oops transfer pps there we go
that i can hit that before hitting the
bottom
right meaning that the actual
computation of transfer pps inside the
loop
is what the heck uh
what
i am very confused about
that
what the heck happened there there was
no assertion
it was just incorrect lighting
this is the weirdest thing
that's so weird all right
so we're now uh able to at least
get at some times this to produce
negative values which we know it
shouldn't do so we can at least narrow
down
that if we look at what's going on here
this is a multiplication uh and so
really all we're doing is multiplying
the transmission by the hit ref
right so what we would expect to see
is that one of those two things
uh is like like if we take a look here
at what these
actually do um
we're taking the reflection level and
the emission level we're taking a max of
those two to produce the transmission
level
and we're extracting the values out of
it right for the r
the g and the b um
why we're doing that i
don't no
um
[Music]
what the heck
so we maybe just stopped because we were
like oh
we're not gonna finish optimizing this
or something right now and that's why
this thing
does a rgb back out because like
it could just do it direct
right um
so that that's i don't know what that's
doing
um
now that you know what it's doing i know
what it's doing i don't know why it's
doing it
right um so that that just seems weird
because you would you would
probably not do that um you'd probably
just do the shuffle then the multiply
wide and leave it
right uh so i think that's just
something we didn't want to
deal with at the moment so uh let's just
change that so we can switch to doing
transfer pbs wide which would be better
um and i think that's probably not very
hard for us to do
uh but you know um whatever
doesn't matter so here
when we're taking these out what i want
to do is say up here
we should be able to validate uh this
stuff right the transmission level
and the hit ref color uh we should be
able to to validate
because in theory i don't think they
should ever be negative anyway
right um like i'm not sure why these
would ever be negative so i just want to
see who
which one of them is right um
in those cases
uh because they shouldn't be they should
just be zero or valid values i think
but i could be wrong about that so i
guess we'll find out
in a second so let's see oh well we
don't have a validator for
those we don't have a validator for
f324xs so i'm gonna have to make one
but let's take a look uh at this a
little bit more carefully here anyway so
transmission level is a max from reflect
from reflect
level and emission level um those are
samples
right so this is a sample from the tile
set
uh as you can see here where we just do
a
um a
trilinear blend of all of the
uh pieces
that should obviously never be negative
because it's supposed to be a convex
blend
over things that are themselves not
negative so nothing in reflect level
should should be
negative uh ever right
um and then we've got the emission level
which is the thing that we produce from
the actual like
hit uh that's how much light is emitted
from the thing that we hit uh so we're
basically taking the two
and and we're taking the max so again
if reflect level should never be
negative and we're taking the max then
we know that transmission level itself
should also never be negative
right um
so i'm gonna make i'm gonna i'm gonna
actually just write this
for f32x in that actual code so
i'm gonna go to validate xl and
i'm gonna do exactly the same thing
uh so we're gonna have a call
like so but it'll take an f32 for x
and validate it as as if it was a texel
right so i believe
uh that if we just pass the four values
that are in
uh the f32x in question that should
validate those
uh and and then we should be okay now
hit ref color
i don't actually know what that is
because we haven't looked at that yet
um so let's try to find that hit ref
color
is where is hit ref color um hit ref
so hit ref color is actually a v3 so
it's got
like actually like multiple components
right um and
so hit ref color we would have to
validate the individual pieces
thereof uh
but that's pretty easy to do
so now like maybe um if we're lucky
we'll be able to see who like which one
of these things is creating the
bogusness
right um and
i just want to make sure because i don't
really trust this
i just want to make sure what i'm seeing
here
yeah so our hit ref color looks like
the culprit here so hit ref color is not
producing the correct thing um
so that seems like it means that our
tile blending
is not really uh implicated there
and
[Music]
our hit ref color is just busted
somehow now we don't actually
know much about that we haven't looked
at that yet so
hit ref color is like being selected in
here
right and so the question is just like
is something weird happening with hit
ref color that we don't understand
i don't know you can see that here
hitreff color is supposed to be
initialized to all ones right
and then when we come through and we do
uh
let's just step through the places where
it's actually used
so there's the first one it should be
set to all ones
uh we then get to
the heck does that mean
so
wait a second
so if you pass three values okay so
that's just initializing it crosswise
so it just assumes that you pass in
wait no that's not the that's the v3
version so
so that just assumes that each of these
gets set to the same
four wide value all right so this is
just
a three by four matrix or a four by
three matrix depending how you want to
think of it
of all ones right
so that's fine uh and if we validate the
texel here
one would assume that that should never
trigger right because it's like we set
the values
they should all be right um so it should
only be
like uh
what
so now transfer pps is
wrong but it wasn't before
or is that just because wait but i took
but uh i didn't mean to take these out
right right sorry these just got removed
i didn't really mean to do that i wanted
to leave those in sorry
so those should hit first
and
uh there we go so when we get the bug
those hit first which is what we'd
expect
so now we have to go find out why that
hit ref color
isn't getting initialized i mean i isn't
getting exercise is getting corrupted
somewhere in here so during this hit ref
color select
um so it's literally just this
like this is what's this is the only
thing that's happening
so the leaf ref color
um
there's only two things that can be
happening here one is that our select
code is broken so that's possible
uh the other is that our our leaf ref
colors
are broken right
now if we take a look at one of these uh
leafs
what you can see is that it's just
another v3 here
of another v3 4x so what i could do here
is just do a validation on the leaf ref
color
is like is one of these things uh
garbage town right because if we hit
that
then that is that would tell us exactly
what what's happening there right
so so that's good in a sense
uh it means that the ref colors that are
coming
in off of the leafs in the actual tree
we built
are wrong um
and and furthermore they're wrong in in
an interesting
way um let's just check something here
what the heck how is that possible
oh well that's just if it's a large
value so never mind no no
we would expect that to be true because
we're not checking for large values so
that's okay
yeah that's okay um so let me see what
leaf ref color looks like right now um
if i can so here's the pointer
here's the ref color uh and and
this is just nuts like what even is
going on here
right uh like like i have no idea
uh what that's supposed to be um
that's just it's just nuts right
isn't there some way to do this
yeah anyway uh so
if we take a look at this uh p oh comma
ps
that's what i wanted that's what i
wanted
i suppose i can't do it here probably um
but
can i do it like
that yeah okay thank you george
so yeah like there's this nice thing
that remedy does where you can see
your um cimd registers
will not register simply data types as
actual
like as what you would actually expect
right uh which is really nice so you can
see this garbage here
um is like very garbagey
and it's the very first one in the ref
color
uh leaf here although i guess i don't
know which leaf index we're on
so that's i guess a separate issue but
that just is not good for obvious
reasons
so maybe and i don't know
but maybe our lighting routine
is actually not the problem here maybe
it's really just the thing that builds
the spatial index that's
busted uh could be
we don't know
so here's grid build spatial partition
um
and if you know if that theory were true
then it would mean that this is the code
that's busted
right so a couple things we can do here
you can see us doing some stuff where we
set the ref color
right to the box refsey and all that
sort of stuff
and you can see that this is a sliced
writing routine
so it's entirely possible
like entirely possible
that that this code is is crap
right um
100 possible
and that seems plausible actually all
right
um so what we're going to try to do here
is we're going to move the validation
into
the well we're not going to move it i
guess we're just going to copy it
so we're going to move the validation
into this box code here and see
if we can catch anybody uh doing
something
scrimpus in here right
so you can see when we get down here to
this cell count thing
and we go through all the cells and for
each node in the spatial grid
we try to figure out what all the leaves
are like you can see that happening here
for example um any time
we don't have this we should be able to
validate
the run so if we look at like
this so we've got a node here and we say
look if if it's not a bug i'm sorry if
it's not
a terminator node so it's not a thing
that we stop on
we should be able to run through uh
the entire set that we just set up so
this thing right here
we should be able to load out all of
those and validate them
and if we can't validate them
something's wrong or i'm
misunderstanding how this is supposed to
work like maybe you're supposed to mask
out part of it or something
we'll have to look and see if there's
something weird like that
but
assuming that we load in these leaves
that are specified here
and we look at each individual leaf now
the leaves are packed
for long right
so is it possible that the entire
problem here is we just don't clear them
so we just have garbage left in there
i think that may be it
um it could just be that we need to
clear those
out because there's garbage left at the
end
and and we we can't like that's not
valid right
so we don't fill the whole thing
yeah so what i would suggest
here is just maybe all we have to do
is like zero this thing
um and if we clear this out first that
may be the entirety of the problem
evidently not um
i just want to make sure i do this right
sorry
that should have a parenthesis around it
and doesn't for some reason
um
okay so that should clear the entire
thing
um and so we should be starting off with
clean values
so when we come through here
uh and we write stuff in
let me just validate so this this
validation here that we're doing
um
we should now be able to verify that
it's clean at the outset
and bogus in here
right we should also be able to assert
that nobody read past the end
right oops
so nobody should be able to read past
the end of it so let's
let's just make sure that's true before
we go any further
good um and then let's try to validate
all of the leaves before we start right
so we start here
we go here
oh actually so no
this is not quite right
is it no no it is okay
um so we're going through all of them
here
and they should all validate because
none of them should have anything in it
they should all be zero
and looks like that's okay and so now i
should be able to verify in theory
that this will now trigger
so when we validate after the fill-in
perfect um and so in
here we are actually writing bogus
values
uh in to this um
like this box refc stuff is
is bogus and we don't actually know why
uh it could be that the input values are
wrong
it could be that the compiler is getting
confused on this lane index right
um but refcolor.x.e is like the only
thing
like there's not a lot else that can be
happening there
right um
[Music]
like if we look uh
we're assuming that this is cabined
yeah uh like this should be
uh this should this should be able to
trigger right
in the right around that actual
code yeah
so we should be able to crash it right
in there
uh and you can you can see it happening
unfortunately box is not available for
us uh
box is the thing that we're actually
getting the data from
so it's like for some reason we can't
get that input boxes
is what can we see that
and
well
i mean that's not reassuring
so it looks like possibly um
we're literally just getting bogus input
if that's the case that means the bug
isn't even
in the lighting code it's in the input
code
right so if we go here and say
all right mr grimbleton
like tell me about your input
code like tell me about tell me about
the actual thing that feeds in
to this routine for box colors what does
that have to say
for itself all right so that is
supremely messed up
that means according to this and this
could still not be the case but
according to our pincing we have
completely exonerated the entire
lighting pipeline
i mean that's what it says right
as far as i can tell that's
that's what happened right um
and i i don't know like it does not look
like that code is implicated here
i so
so there we have it um
so i don't know i i i guess i will
literally just move on to looking
outside
at the actual like place where we push
this stuff down
we will just validate that these color
values are actually correct when they're
getting pushed in here because i don't
know
there's nothing else that i can see here
that
appear to be uh that that
like i don't know where else to track
this bug down to like that that was it
that was all the lighting code did so
like if the renderer is handing it
negative values for real
then that's where they're coming from
right
uh so you know the bugs are coming from
inside
the house at this point um
so i'm going to validate uh those those
texels
all right four coders decided that it
doesn't want to build anymore
and i don't know why
wait uh
why does it not want to build sometimes
i don't understand
there we go um all right let me go back
to
what i was doing before uh so looking at
these refc lines we've got the lighting
refse lines we've got these refse lines
here
um and uh
and these validate texl functions i'm
just going to pull
i'm going to pull them out so everyone
can call them
if it's the kind of thing you would like
to do with your time
you can call them
i guess not that one because that's not
defined
uh and i also want to look for there was
one more
right is it here
there's one more in here somewhere so
we've got here
here here
um oops
validate texel v3 declared but not
defined
really
uh but it's right
there
someone tell me what they mean by
declared and not defined in that case
tell you what since i'm feeling generous
there you go
okay so now we're getting into voodoo
land
because i don't know where else we're
getting these boxes
from i guess we'll find out but i'm just
going to go ahead and check
to see uh if we validate the texels
um at all times
just to make sure
that's in handmade array
surely a bug in handmade ray can not be
affecting us
here
so i literally can't figure out where
that's coming from now
so we're going to have to do this
like we've pushed back to the place
where we think it has to happen
and it turns out that like we don't see
it happening
there at all
um so now we have to figure out how are
we getting
in here right
um how have we managed to get to this
point in the code uh
with a ref c that's bogus but we can't
figure out who put it there
right is someone mucking with the memory
uh do we have like an out of bounds
right bug because again this is in the
performance oriented side of the code
so we don't have a lot of safety net
here right
um you know we're kind of in the place
where things are kind of fast and loose
so we have to look at this
maybe the count is wrong maybe the input
boxes
pointer is off i have no idea
but we now have to kind of look and see
how are we getting this
and what might be happening that would
cause it
to be busted so i'm going to look for
the grid build spatial partition call
point
which is here you can see the input
boxes
uh they just get passed to internal
lighting internal lighting core because
in in theory
these are just going to be passed down
directly so here's internal lighting
core
uh you can see here that it just passes
the occluder count and the occluders
right which is a thing that comes from
the renderer and should just
generally be untouched like i feel like
it's just
it should just be the same right uh
you know and it's it's really not ever
edited so
it the lighting code doesn't care about
this at all
uh and it looks like we're talking about
whoever's calling
update lighting
you know who knows so if we go look at
at the world mode code here right you
can see that it's it's reading it from
the command buffer
um it's doing a safe truncate which
means that this is never allowed to be
greater than 16 bits
uh and we can try and verify that but
this will assert that
to make sure that's true and so the
light occluders array
uh is just coming directly from the
command
structure right um
so let's take a look
so if we look at who's writing to or
setting up or doing stuff with this
particular
array uh you can see that there's like a
you know an array in here you know are
we checking to see
for overwrites there um would be
would be one thing uh like maybe we're
like overwriting the boundary of it
you know like there's more than like
we're writing more than the max
um and you can see a check there
um and a check there the only two things
are occluders and lights that's the only
two things that can write in there
the checks seem to be valid the check's
in the mail
um so
that doesn't seem super likely
right i mean that
that looks about right um
so i guess i'm gonna go ahead and say
i'm gonna actually just put in a
validator for the light occluder set
and we're gonna have to do the same
exact pincing process that we just did
right um we'll have to
you know we will have to do it
uh
oh missing a certain around the validate
texture ah okay
thank you chat um speaking of that
i would like to change that slightly uh
while we're doing that
um although i guess i'll do it this way
for now but i would like to change these
so that this is a
like so that we can leave these in i'd
like to make this a macro
um do you know what i'm saying
so that we just do validate texel as a
like uppercase
and that way i don't have to pull these
out because i'd like to leave these in
this could happen again
right um and if this happens again
we would want to be able to turn it on
again
uh so we'll see whoa uh
all right not what we were expecting
this is a really strange bug
so in this case we we actually now can
hit it because we added that assert
so the color of the occluder in this
case
where we're reading out the cube here uh
is in fact weird
now i don't know that we can actually
look at it unfortunately because we're
in
release mode so we don't know what
we don't know why that would be right
it's just complete garbage
unfortunately as it often is in release
mode so we don't really get to see
what's happening here now why we can't
look at these
i don't know um
[Music]
that is probably the value maybe
um it's hard to say right
but if we take a look at the pieces here
there's supposedly three pieces
here's the first one here's the second
one
and here's the third one yeah
um and if we take a look at at what
these
pieces actually uh refer to we've got
flags
set on these so it's 4 16 16.
uh that's only one flag set for each one
uh and we can take a look at what the
flags actually
reference in here so there's the pieces
and they have the flags set up for them
which is
like um
not it's not that it's this
right and so
this one would say what it was you can
see here
that so occluder is 16 so so these
two are both occluders uh and then the
the
four is a cube so it's like cube uh
occluder occluder
and neither are lights so they're
occluders specifically
and the color on these two
um is correct in both cases
right
so when we get back to
the code that we're actually looking at
here like if i actually go
down to the push occluder call that's
here
um it's pushing on color right
uh what was that so here is color
i mean i suppose that could be a bug
there
um
i'm assuming i can't actually look at
this value right go look at the assembly
and see
we don't know if that i mean that could
be anything in debug mode
um
so match vector
what the heck is tag that just looks
yeah that's just wrong so that's that's
a bug i don't know if it's the bug
uh but that's that's a bug for sure
um so here are the things that you're
allowed to look up into match vector
tag ghost is literally just complete
nonsense so so this right here is
looking up into complete la la land
right um
thanks for no warning on that compiler
like what so this is a this is a fixed
length array
and i'm looking up into it with a with a
constant value right i'm just reading
right the heck off that array this is an
example where
the compiler could easily just tell you
that you were off
and it doesn't
i mean it's my fault because it was dumb
but
you know uh that that's not a case of
like c
not having the information to tell you
that you made a mistake
right uh that's an easy to catch one
so not a huge fan of that
but okay
so this piece of code here uh
is just not allowed
and i guess i don't know why that would
not produce an out of bounds array
access warning
um i i do not know why that would be
uh because that that is a puzzler for
sure
right that is a puzzler
um all right so now we're kind of in a
bad state because we don't have a way to
reproduce this reliably
uh you know what i'm saying
um
since we couldn't we didn't have a way
of
of of like 100 certain
reproduce this this error um
i i'm i'm not quite sure how to
to get it to happen uh uh to to
to validate that that actually fixed it
right um
because it it doesn't 100 repro
and we also know that that i guess that
means that
somebody in here actually um
well yeah i mean i guess we really just
don't know how we would how we would
validate that
i mean how we've we can prove we fixed
it right
um but that may be it um that may be the
whole thing i don't know
uh so i'm gonna do some extra stuff just
really quick before
we finish up here uh and then we'll just
see if we get this bug
back again because there's really no way
to prove that that was it
um it because there could be other
reasons why it was happening that we
don't know about so so we don't really
have a way to say that that was
definitively the only problem
um so what i'm gonna do is i'm gonna go
to validate texel
here uh and what i'm going to do is say
that this is going to become like a
validate text
underscore kind of a thing right and
then i'm going to pound to find validate
texel to be validate texel
like so and then we
are going to change that to an
underscore
and uh
run
uh and then what i would like to do here
is just say
okay so
so this is okay because that's not
supposed to be an assertion so that's
going to call the underscore version
these are all going to change to
validate texel
like so um
uh these i i don't really know if we
should leave these in or not
because none of this code was actually
implicated at all
so i think i may just pull those out
because
they really don't need to be there
like this code was just fine so
i don't think that has to remain for any
particular reason
so then that also begs the question does
that mean this didn't have to be cleared
i think it does still i think that was a
bug
right
i think the only way that's not a bug is
if you clear it
somewhere else as well or something
right
i'm going to leave that assertion in
um okay and
everything seems good
i'm going to re-enable multi-threading
which i guess i could have done live but
i didn't
um and then i'm gonna see if we notice
anything strange happening
um
so it seems pretty good um
it
all right so looks
like we're okay um
i'm gonna call that fixed for now
what a hilarious bug very interesting
um i guess i don't have very much to say
about that
uh other than yeah pincers that's why i
use them because
a lot of times you're totally wrong like
or not even totally wrong but
when you have no idea where the code
what part of the code is causing the bug
oftentimes it turns out to be a
surprising part of the code right
so it behooves you to just figure out a
way to like
branch you know basically like split
where the code could be going wrong
and you just keep pushing that until you
can find like a definitive answer
right um
so yeah i guess i would say that that is
yeah that is that is an effective
very effective debugging technique i
highly recommend it
um
i highly recommend it
so in terms of validating the atlas
[Music]
you know
we probably don't want to have that be
um
we probably want to do something like
this so that we have the light atlas
assert here
and we have ways of of making this stuff
uh all work off of that
so if we define this to be an assert
then it is we can put this a validate
texel
atlas and that'll do basically the same
thing
right
so that way we can do assertions of the
text of the
um of the
texture atlas like anywhere we want in
the code
like this
so what i wanted to be able to do is do
validate texl atlas like that
uh and be able to just put those
anywhere where i feel like
i want them to happen
uh and that way like if we experience
weird lighting artifacts at some point
and we think the atlas might be
implicated i can just turn these back on
and i don't have to uh
think too hard about it right so
i'm just gonna do this
um and get rid of these
okay um so then
i i can run it
uh and there's you know it running
and i can also then now go in and
change this around so
we just don't have any validation
of anything in the in the atlas
and run it again and we should be good
to go
yeah uh so i think that's good
oops
um and so i think you know with the
lighting now
that seems much more stable and i think
mostly the only real thing we
want to do now is probably just like
improve the filtering on it
right so that it's smoother and less
flickery
[Music]
i'd say that's probably about all we
really need to do
um
i wonder at what level it's not
flickering now
because i don't really know um like like
how much blending
uh makes it not flickery at the moment
but oh and we need to rerun the sphere
so we should do that as well uh
so the hh sphere
we need to build
so um
our h8 sphere now
uh we
we have to run this to generate the new
inl that we use
for you know for
all of our light sampling and
i'm not sure what we were passing as
parameters there to be completely honest
but if we look at the inl itself
which is this uh then these should be
the ones right so
assuming that octahedron count is 16
and octahedron dim is eight
uh i'm assuming we can just pass
16 8 here and get the same thing out
so let's see if that's true so i'm going
to say
16 8 and then i'm going to say
um handmade code uh handmade sampling
spheres
like this um and i'm going to
just see if that thing can converge on
a reasonable set of of outputs here
and when it does or if it does then we
will
use those and hopefully that will
provide a improvement right um
okay so in theory now
if i reload this buffer
which i guess i can't do
so let me try and reload that buffer
uh yeah so it's still 8 and 16. so in
theory now if i rebuild
we should have and we don't really know
but we should have
uh fixed like the sign bug in theory was
making that routine worse as well right
we don't know that that's true
and and i don't see any particular
improvement
um in the lighting here uh to be honest
so i don't know that there's really
anything that that did that we care
about
but because it may have been a problem
um
we might as well right and and so
just just trying to do the the due
diligence there to make sure we don't
leave that in the code
and and and leave it in wrong right
all right so what i wanted to say last
was just like hey
what is the t blend value that doesn't
produce the problem
um so in the uh lighting code
when it produces what the t blend value
is
uh which would be like in here
[Music]
um
i'm assuming we can set this to anything
we want so if we set this down
significantly
yeah so you can see like you can get
smoother lighting that just updates more
slowly
um
and you still get a little flickering at
the at the limit right
um which suggests to me that yeah like
just
just if we just do some more sampling
theory in there we should be able to
improve
upon that um you know
i don't know for sure right uh
so i don't want to say that's definitely
the case
but suffice to say
that you know it's
it's not far
it's not far off uh but it should it
should be
um it should be improved and then the
interpolation is really the other thing
that really needs to be improved
uh and also just looks wrong like you
can see it's kind of weirdly
like dark in one direction and not in
the other like there's just
i think there's just other things we've
got going on here right that
are just a case of like lighting like
quality issues so
i think we've got a bunch of stuff we're
going to have to do uh when we want to
really improve the quality but i don't
care about that particularly right now
it's fine for our current purposes
so yeah all right
let's wrap it up any quick questions
no i agree that the lighting does seem
brighter with the blend ps fix
and i mean that was just writing into
the octahedral maps wrong
so you know there's tons of reasons why
it might be the case that that would
would make things appear brighter but
yeah
ah is there a way to test my glsl shader
compilation success failure on
other gpus without actually having to
buy a bunch of gpus
that's a very good question um
gosh no i i don't think so um
one of the things that would be kind of
amazing
uh is if there was a
thing that allowed you to upload
shaders like shader
uh but it ran on a farm and it like ran
them there was one of every graphics
card in that farm
and it could tell you like oh it failed
like here's the image that got produced
from each of these
right and then you could just see like
did it work
right so like god bolt yeah like god
bolt for shaders would be amazing
unfortunately i don't think anyone's
built that and you can tell why
god bolt can just run on a single uh
like it can just install all the
compilers and then just run on that one
machine it doesn't need
hardware whereas the problem with the
idea of god bolt for shaders is you'd
actually have to have
one machine with every single graphics
card in it which is like literally like
thousands like there'd be like a
thousand machines or something right so
i mean so no
you certainly could try renting some
time
on some machines that exist in the cloud
that have known gpus to try other gpus
but you're still only going to get a
small cross-section because
most server farms
have a very narrow range of gpus
installed in them
it sounds like martin's is saying that
there's a thing called shader playground
that at least uses shader
libraries to do some validation
which probably doesn't really help what
you're saying but it might be worth
checking out anyway
i like the thing that just said hello mr
teapot i am here to view your channel as
was previously discussed
who why is there a viewbot that came on
this channel and said hello mr
teapot there is no mr teapot here
is there
stretch all right well good work folks
we were able to fix that bug
um and that was really the only nasty
bug we had
the lighting still needs a bunch of
improvement to it which is really just
like going through and changing some of
the
the math to be better right um
and i think that's probably a good idea
so at some point we should do that but
i'm probably not going to do that right
now because the lighting is good enough
at the moment that i can do most of the
stuff we're going to do
i don't really need it to be better just
for development
um so we can sort of take a look at that
at some
later date also now that we've got all
of the ray tracing and stuff working
you know we may by the time we call
handmade hero done
we may just be move all that ray tracing
the gpu because
that may just be the thing that happens
and we know that it all works so then we
could just have
uh much much much much much much much
faster array tracing
at which point you don't have to really
get better at sampling like if we
[Music]
could send out you know 10 times as many
rays
then we would just be done right
so
so star code galaxy i'm going as fast as
i can i don't have
anything to share i will post an update
as soon as i do
um but basically like
if you sign up for the mailing list you
will get notified so if you go to
starcodegalaxy.com and you put your name
in here and hit subscribe
you will get notified as soon as there
is anything to hear about star code
galaxy but at the moment no
i don't have anything to announce about
that
and yes i am in the tent i'm in the tent
that i use for recording star code
galaxy
it just improves the audio quality once
i'm done with recordings for star code
galaxy i will remove the tent
this is just microsoft edge um it's not
any it's not anything it's just the
browser that's installed by default on
windows machines
so
alrighty folks thank you for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero it
has been a pleasure coding with you
as always if you do want to follow along
with handmade hero at home
you can always pre-order the game on
handmadehero.org and it comes with a
source code
so you can follow along with it and do
your own experiments
um i think we're done with lighting for
a while uh
and we're just gonna put in a bunch of
game stuff now and so that we can test
it
out uh and clean up stuff in the engine
so that we can kind of call it like you
know like here's the game it's done
uh and then we can spend time just like
cleaning stuff up and
and then like really looking at the
lighting and going like okay what's the
shippable quality version of this thing
uh but it's mostly working now so i'm
actually fine with it where it's at i
don't think it needs to be changed much
because it gives us the information that
we actually need
um but if you want to keep on improving
the lighting
now would be a good time to go work on
just the quality of it
uh and you can go see like to what
extent you can improve the quality
with like the same number of raised cast
there's probably ways
to improve the quality that you're
getting back from the lighting there may
also be more bugs like the ones we fixed
today
where if you fix those bugs the lighting
will improve
and so only by actually going through
and putting in like specific test cases
where we where we construct scenes we
think we know like what it should look
like or whatever
without doing that we're never going to
get to the point where we really know
how good the lighting
can be so that's just kind of a separate
thing that has to happen
we'll do that at some point when we want
to like
sort of turn the screw on it that's it
for this week i'll be back next week for
more handmade hero until then have
fun program everyone and i'll see you on
the internet
take it easy everybody