start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show recode
a complete game live on stream you know
I guess now that I've said this multiple
times when we started like all this week
I think I opened with we're going to get
to play around with our debug
visualization today but every day we
were thwarted because we had like some
nasty bug stuff that happened and and
things like this and so here it is
thursday and we have not got to do it
and i think now we can actually do it
because all of our stuff is working and
we actually will get the chance to do
that so i would like to actually do that
because i've been wanting to do it for a
while so i'm looking forward to it so i
have to jump right in today is day 1 88
so if you want to follow along if you
ordered if you pre-order the game on
handmade here org you want to unpack day
187 source code because that's what i'm
starting with today so if you're trying
to follow along at home that's that's
where you're at that's what you're doing
so let's go ahead and open open up the
old give it the old Emacs here and let's
let's just take a look at where we were
so here was our debug sort of you know
our debug output and you know there's a
couple things that you kind of notice
you're there one of the things that that
is clearly true as I kind of look at it
is it gets a lot slower as the game goes
and I think that makes sense because the
number of events remember we're just
kind of piling them up into a buffer
until we get 64 frames worth of debug
events that we're processing through and
when you think about what that means I
feel like that sort of suggests that we
don't want to be processing everything
all together like that right we probably
want to process as soon as we see a
frame boundary kind of like store off
the debug information for that frame in
a processed fashion I would think so
that we can then you know we can
essentially avoid this whole nastiness
so I feel like there's some optimization
that we want to do there but I'm just
gonna instead of doing that I think what
I'd rather do is just set the
number of debug frames down to a low
number so that we can play around the
visualization because I want to do that
first before i try to do any sort of
optimization stuff because I've been
like i said but want to do that for a
while but we kinda had to put it off for
bugs i'd like to do that before we kind
of go back in and look at how do we keep
it performant and keep it from taking
some you know too much of our time or
something like that so the max debug
event array count you know if i were to
set that down from 34 to something like
eight right so that we have a lot less
frames to deal with i strongly suspect
yeah so you can see how the frame rate
is drastically better right so what that
suggests to me is that processing the
frame information like we could easily
test be testing the game in this in this
at this frame rate this is fine and this
is still doing eight frames so it would
be eight faster eight times faster if we
only did one right or I should say it
would take 18 the time so it looks to me
like that's going to be a good solution
for us going forward so we can do that
before we kind of move off this we can
spend a little time making sure that we
kind of do one at a time that way but in
the meantime what I want to do like I
said first I'd like to spend a few days
making the system into something that's
useful to us in terms of visualization
because right now we can sort of start
to see you like we're getting there's
some information that we get from this
we can see we can visualize how our
threads are working like we can see how
long it takes to the thread psychic in
we can see the threads doing their
rendering work here and how much time
they're using to do that we could see
the debug rendering happening up here we
can see what we're doing in terms of
processing the debug information and how
long that takes and then waiting for
frames we can see all that stuff
happening so we we're already getting a
little bit of heads up but it's really
pretty janky right it's pretty ugly it's
hard to see what's going on and more
importantly well two things more
importantly I can't actually like hover
over any of this and find out what the
actual bars correspond to even though
you know we have that information right
so I can't do that and furthermore
there's no way for me to like zoom in on
this or open up one of these bars and
say hey you know show me for this
particular bar right that we got here we
may know a lot more information about
what's actually happening in here like
what it's what child
process what child functions were extra
in there and which ones took time and
that sort of thing but we have no way of
interfacing with that so what I'd like
to do is I'd like to open this up a bit
a try to make a little bit of a UI for
it essentially where we can navigate
through the debug information in a way
that allows us to actually get get out
what's what's already being recorded
because right now we have a tremendous
amount of information we recorded we
just don't have any way of actually
looking at it it's a visualization
problem basically and that's what i want
to start tackling because the only way
this debug information is actually going
to do us the kind of good that i want it
to do is if we can you know quickly get
what we need out of it so the first
thing that I'd like to do is just make a
little something so that I can interact
with these things some way that I could
like click on a bar for example I just
want to start with something like that
so how would we do that right well if
you remember a long time ago we actually
did include and I should probably open
up a my platform here we did include
mouse right so there's the mouse in our
game input we've got Mouse x we've got
mouse why we even have mousey I don't
know if we ever implemented mousey I'm
not sure we actually did that that's the
mouse wheel and I don't know if we ever
sort win32 handmade I don't think we
ever did that but maybe I'm wrong yeah
we don't support mouthfeel yet so we
haven't actually implemented that in the
platform layer so we wouldn't get any of
those but we did implement the the rest
of the stuff so in terms of getting the
mouse the mouse buttons and the XY
position of the mouse that's actually
stuff that we can already do for free it
just comes in and we can use it so what
I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead
and implement just some light you I so
that we can we can browse that debug
information so let's start with the
simplest possible thing I'm gonna do the
simplest possible things r it's just to
show you how we're going to do that and
we'll talk a little about it the
simplest possible thing I think would
just be hover I just want to be able to
hover the mouse over one of those bars
and then I want when I hover over the
bar I want to show me I'll just have it
print out let's say I want it to print
out what the
name of that function was right just
like like what's the function that I'm
hovering over right now so in order to
do that the first thing you have to do
is you have to get the mouse information
to the debug system right because it
comes in and and and it doesn't actually
the cut there's no conduit right there's
no way to actually get that information
down and so what I'd like to do is just
take a look here we've got this debug
overlay it gets past the game memory it
does not get past any game input and so
what I'd like to do there again is just
have some way and we'll do the simplest
way possible you may have to upgrade
this a little bit in the future as we do
more in terms of game input but for
right now it should be sufficient when
we are here in you know our main routine
our land of people who have not kind of
been then sort of cleaned up and moved
out yet our game update and render
that's got the game input here right it
has the game input so all I'm going to
do is I'm going to start passing that
game input directly into the debugger
let's say here you go you can have that
now so then we have game input we've got
that and so in here we now know what the
XY location of the mass is we could just
look it up directly in there and that's
no problem right so now what I'm going
to do is I'm going to say well if we
take a look we've got in here we have
these rectangles right and we're putting
those rectangles you know onto onto the
render stack if we have the rectangle
and we have the mouse x and y there's no
reason we can't just compare those two
and figure out whether or not there's a
particular rectangle that we're over
right that should be a very simple
simple thing to do so what I can do
inside this routine is I can just say
like okay you know if like Mouse in
rectangle or something like that right
and I can just pass it like maybe the
input struct or whatever if I if the
mass is in the rectangle and and then
I'm going to have the rectangle somehow
so I'm just going to say rectangle here
if the mouse is in the rectangle then
what I'd like to do is output a line of
debug texts like because we already have
that going so I'll just use it right
we'll just go ahead and output a line of
debug text again doing the simplest
possible thing here I wanna well you
know what I can even grab the code here
this is the code that actually is
exactly what we want
right so all I'm going to do is when you
mouse in that rectangle I'm just going
to go ahead and say ok if the mouse is
in the rectangle go ahead and output a
debug line of text that happens to be
all of the information that we use to
print out for one of these guys like
cycle counts hit counts that sort of
thing right so how do I get that
information out of this particular thing
in this case when we do the region stuff
you know I've got this these these debug
regions I need some way of having the
region corresponds to something right
because we're not storing that yet and I
need a way of getting that out so inside
handmade platform dot H we've got sort
of what is actually stored you know
right we've got like the debug record
which has kind of the information about
it and then we've got the debug event
which says stuff like what the what the
clock was for the beginning in the end
and that sort of thing so I kind of need
inside this region I want to be able to
act you know I want to be able to get at
this data and you know I don't know that
I want to necessarily point back to the
event because the event the collation
kind of does you know I want the
collation to probably take care of that
but the debug record for the file the
blocking the line number that's probably
more what I'd want right so I want this
region to probably have that in there so
I want to be able to say that there's a
debug record off of the region so that I
can grab it when we happen to mouse over
it like so and when I do that hmm yeah
when I do that I can then use that
record to get at least some of this
information I can get the block name I
can get the line number there and then i
can get sort of this other information i
might make this a little bit more
extended i might do something where we
do like the block name and then you know
maybe I think what might be more
interesting than what we did before is
at the very end i'm thinking i might do
file in line so it will do like the
block name and then at the end it would
do you know the file name of the line
number at the very end so just be like
where you know where this stuff is right
something like that so yeah so there's
there's that we just say ok there's the
block name and
and then here comes the file name and
line number so there's the file name
there's a line number and then inside
here we need to know some stuff we want
to know the cycle count and the hit
count is not relevant for this
particular function I guess you know
these two things are not particularly
relevant because we're talking about a
specific slight we're talking about
specific one of these so for now all i'm
going to say for that region is i'm just
going to say what the cycle count was so
I'd like the region to have the cycle
count in it and that looks roughly right
to me so something like that right for
now okay so if we do that then we can
output it and that's all good so now
what we need to do is upgrade our actual
storage or debug storage to include that
information right so it's got to have a
debug record in it so here's the region
it's got to know what the debug record
is and then it also has to know what the
clock count was right there is a cycle
count in there so that means that every
time when we do a debug frame region
when we do add region we want to record
that information right so I want to
record the cycle count here and I want
to record the debug record you know and
it's pretty easy to do the cycle count
right because that's just the opening
event clock we know and we know the end
you know we know we know the range it's
just that so it's pretty easy for us to
determine what that that is right
there's not a lot of mystery there so
that's pretty simple and then the debug
record we already got probably I'm
guessing is probably already queried up
here yeah it's right there it's called
source so I'll just go ahead and and
drop that in as well and so now we have
all that information right pretty
straightforward a debug overlay debug
overlay debug over
a does not have its thing updated game
input input like so and yeah there we go
so I think that's roughly it fix that
there I think that's roughly it so all
we have to do now is kind of shore up
some of this code here I don't remember
if we ever did anything with rectangles
we did so since we did stuff with
rectangles I'm just going to go ahead
and leverage that that we already wrote
and I'm going to say that we're going to
make a rectangle to here and I feel like
push rec should really take rectangle
tues optionally and so that's I think
would also be nice could fix some of
this absolute nonsense that was going on
here that I think even as i was typing
it in i said i was not super pleased
with it so let me take a look at what we
have for rectangle to it looks like i
can create one with the men in the max
and that's exactly what i want right so
if i create a rectangle here rectangle
to here with the men into max what i
could do is say all right I know the min
X min that the you know I know a bunch
of this stuff right here it is I know
the min and the max the only thing I
need to know now is what the X with the
min and Max XR and I said so that would
just be this stuff here right this is a
that's where the X starts and then the X
runs where is that width it's lane width
the fact you could really just think of
it this way right so it's kind of like
the the lane index it's it's going from
one to the next Lane indexes its its
span you will you know so that's the
rectangle and that's all we really need
there what I would like to do again is
just say okay I want to just be able to
pass those around I should I feel like
it's it's a well within reason to be
able to pass those in so if i had a
rectangle to here where I've got you
know and this is the the region wrecked
something like that I don't really like
the way that's the lining up let's do
that that's fine so if I've got that
then what I'd like to be able to do is
pass that in here so there's a region
wrecked and assuming that it's got a
particular Z you can see that it's z is
0 so what I'd like to do is be able to
just pass the a 2d rectangle and a Z
coordinate and have that expand out into
something that gets caught you know pass
to push wreck so it's basically just
like does whatever fussy map it needs to
but it make sure that that's the
rectangle that actually gets pushed so
then what i can do is i can ask whether
the mouse is in the rectangle and i
think we probably organ also actually
implemented that you can see it's we did
right here right we have is in rectangle
so we could do is in rectangle right
here there's the rectangle and we could
just say whatever the mouse p is right
whatever the point is that represents
where that mouse is and that's again
really really easy because we have that
information so the mouse p if we want to
get it is just the input mass text input
mouse y so we know where it is I and I
think that i implement one of those see
if I did push wrecked so I think that's
really it for the most part that's like
the entirety of the code all we need is
something that actually handles that in
the render group because i'm basically
introducing a new way of pushing a
rectangle that's different from the way
that it was pushing the rectangle before
right so if i go ahead and and say like
there's going to be a different in line
for pushing your rectangle
it's going to be a rectangle too and
here's the rectangle and then there is
an rfid to for the z-coordinate then
what i can do is say alright we can turn
that into one of these for now let the
optimizer deal with it here and if we
ever find that's a problem we can write
it ourselves but all we have to do is
just do a get center on the rectangle
assume that's a call that we have let's
find out if we ever wrote that get
center there it is so we can just get
the center of that and we can say that
we want you know to make something with
that Center and the Z and the dimensions
would just be we actually also have that
for get dim so our rectangle there we go
is that and then we pass the color
straight through and I think that's
actually all we would need now let's
test to see whether that works at all in
terms of drawing because I kind of just
made that up but it does look like that
parts working so now what we have to do
is get our mouse hover thing working
what we want to be able to do is mouse
over these things and have them actually
show up now as you can see if I move the
mouse around we're not actually getting
that so we have to go ahead and work on
that code a little bit there's one thing
that I already know that we're going to
have to do that's why that wouldn't work
but we probably have some other things
to get that working as well so what we
want to do is is now move into figuring
out how to get the hover to work so now
we've added the correct drawing there we
know that we're drawing that rectangle
okay so here is the problem
fundamentally that we are going to face
that is that the mouse p right is not in
the same space as our rendering space
right because we don't we didn't
actually do any work to ensure that that
was true the mouse x mouse why is just
something that windows is outputting in
its coordinate space and we do not
necessarily render in that space so you
can actually see when we do our debug
overlay right when we actually do stuff
here that where is it diva
reset when we actually set up our debug
rendering you can actually see that we
do an orthographic projection and we use
the width and the height that creates a
space where we where we range from like
negative the negative half the width to
positive half the width right and
negative half the height that's re- half
height to positive half the height but
that's not going to be windows of space
at all and so we have some decisions to
make here and i'm not really going to
think too hard about this i'm just going
to make it work here and then later we
can kind of decide whether we want to
push this down to the platform layer and
make it be its responsibility to do this
mapping and in other words the platform
layer is handing us Mouse xmass why
should the platform layer be responsible
for putting it into a canonical thing
like that and the answer may be yes
right but I'm gonna get it working here
for us and then we're going to think
about that and possibly push it down to
the platform layer and say that windows
the platform layer will translate from
windows into our coordinate system and
there's some reasons we might want to do
that namely if all of the platform
layers are responsible for converting
that Mouse coordinates then we know that
no matter what random Mouse coordinate
scheme they use it'll always be able to
be written in the platform layer
something that will convert them into
the ones we want right so what we need
to do here is we can say all right the
mouse X ranges from 0 to the width in
Windows I believe that's typically the
way it goes and we want to do you know
we want to essentially subtract half the
width from that right what we want to do
is something more like this we want to
do Oh point 5 f times with right now we
have to actually know what the width is
which at the moment we don't actually
have a way of telling that I don't
believe you can see that it comes in
here so what we want to do is start
storing that and i think this also is a
good point time to get rid of these
global variables as well so i think
we're going to do that immediately after
we get hover working because again i
said when i first put them here as like
we want to go ahead and move these out
now would be a good time to do that
right so i want to do something like
this
temporarily but then we're going to
change that okay so you know global
width is with global height table sorry
so that's what we're actually getting
past and what we want to do is say well
there's this there's some center right
and I want to offset things in terms of
that Center so we'll do that and then
we'll do the same thing for the height
but the mouse remember in Windows it
probably i believe mask where desert
reported right from the top down we are
bottom up so really this is going to go
the other way it's going to start at
half the height and go down as the mouse
increases so it's going to look a little
bit more like that right so that's
roughly what we're looking at this is
not correct yet just to be clear there's
problems with this still but that's
getting a little bit more towards what
we want to do so let's let's double
check and so i'm also i'll show you a
kind of a little bit of am of a trick we
can do here to to make this a little bit
easier but let's see where we're at
there with that yes so you can kind of
see that now we actually do have hover
working don't ask me why that is down
there i do not know where that why that
is where it is but now we can hover over
any of these guys right and we can see
the actual information i just i do not
understand why oh i know i do you know
what I do understand why where's that at
why yeah it's because it prints it on
the next one that's why so I'm going to
skip that for a minute I'm going to take
that lie there and say that this is
going to be a global height
yeah something like I'm going to start
this at the bottom of the screen and
then I'm going to add well no that is
the chart man so I'm just I'm just gonna
do that oh well or I'm not sharp min Y
is supposed to be negative over there we
go Plus 10 members start from the bottom
I always think top down even though I
try pretty hard to not not do that okay
so there we go yeah so there's reasons
why we're gonna have to fix a little bit
of that that's fine so now we can
actually hover so we're you know again
we've got sort of the basic thing going
we can hover over something and figure
out who it is right and it's what we get
these are what we expect to see or at
least it's what I expected to see right
we can kind of see what's going on in
each of these and you can see that
gigantic bar for debug collation again
really pretty expensive something that
we're going to have to certainly get
down but now we can kind of go go ahead
through here and figure out what these
are and so that's good we've got some
more work that we'd like to do to make
that work out okay but but off we go so
like i said though we're not quite out
of the woods yet and the reason that i
say that is because we have some things
that are a little bit wonky i think in
terms of the way this is working so let
me just see i'm going to also well i
guess i can't expand it passed with the
actual width is so maybe that's not such
a big deal but anyway you get the basic
idea right so that's all good now I do
not know why our last frame time is 0.00
milliseconds that seems like a pretty
odd thing to have happen so I'm if
you'll you'll excuse me for one second I
would like to figure out why that
actually is happening debug state frames
debug state frame cut minus one that's
because that's the last thing that's
open I suppose that frame is not
actually finished yet
so that makes sense that does make some
sense I feel like we probably shouldn't
put that frame into the rotation if it
hasn't actually been closed yet if that
makes sense so I feel like it should be
more like you know when we do the frame
count I don't just notice that but like
when we do the frames the last frame
that we create is never actually it
doesn't actually get closed because the
frame marker hasn't occurred for it yet
since the debug code collation runs
before the frame marker finishes so I
feel like that one should not really be
in there if that makes sense so I feel
like that in terms of how that works I
feel like the frame count stuff should
actually be be a little more
conservative so in here when we get to
this I feel like we should take back one
frame assuming it never gets actually
clear so you know at the end of all this
after we do after we do that stuff we
would do something like taking away one
frame not sure I'm not sure what the
best way to do that is it might be
something like this where we only
increment that frame count when we
actually have a positive frame so we're
like okay we had a frame it completed
now we increment the frame count that
might be reasonable let's find out so
there's that's a little bit better so
all right so now we're hovering over
this stuff and that's good right
everyone likes a little bit of a hover
now and again but like I said I don't
love that and the reason is because you
know cross-platform wise we don't know
what those masks weirdness going coming
and basically what we'd have to do is
all the platform layers would then have
to emulate the way windows does their
mouse which doesn't necessarily make
much sense considering the fact that the
very first thing we're doing with that
data is swapping it over into our
coordinate system it seems like it would
make more sense for the platform layer
to translate the mouse into our
coordinate system instead you know what
I mean which is a center you know why is
up centered coordinate system so that
seems like a little more logical to me
so I think that's where
like to push that I think I'd like to
push it down to that and then we can
move on from there all right so if we go
ahead and move down from there here we
are in been through to handmade there's
the mass x mouse why stuff and so what I
want to do here is I want to perform
this transform at a different time right
so you know instead of doing it here
what I want to do is I want to make it
so I can just do mouse xmass why like so
and that's you know all I would then
have to worry about and so if i look at
mass x mouse why in the platform layer
oops actually spell it right what I'm
going to do is I'm going to change those
two are 32 so that they can be floats
across the boundary which is what I
would think it would prefer and I'm just
going to assume that when we actually
create this this piece of information I
am going to take again and pre do that
sort of transform that I was doing
before so basically the mass p x and y
are going to have themselves sort of
flipped around so how would i do that in
here I've got my game display somewhere
see display it's like buffer or
something right a long times to work
with this code off-screen buffer in 3 2
off-screen oops buffer
win32 off-screen buffer star buffer
where is that in our main loop should be
somewhere should it not its global back
buffer that is what it is all right so
if we got a global valve ever what I
want to do here is say that the global
back buffer is wit right and the global
back buffer is height I'm going to take
those guys and I'm going to do exactly
what I do with them before so we're
going to take negative half the width
which is starting at the left side of
the screen in our coordinate system and
then I'm going to add the mouse p to
that which should move it across right
and I'm going to do the same thing with
the height here right so I'm going to
take start- half and then the mouse
since the mouse actually goes up right
i'm going to subtract it because as the
mouse gets bigger it should go oh sorry
that's not quite right I meant to say
start at the top of the screen and then
as the mass goes down i'm going to
subtract from it right now I think if
I'm not very much an error which of
course I maybe I think that's not quite
correct I think that's off x 1 pixel and
the reason that I say that right if we
take a look here at the blackboard so
here is day 1 88 if you take a look at
what's happening here if the if the
mouse X is actually equal to 0 right
then what we want to do is you want to
be on that first pixel right which is
negative 0 point five times the width /
potentially but when we get over to this
pixel right and again this this kind of
lard is largely about our pixel centers
which we haven't really formally defined
which is probably a bad idea it's
something maybe we should address sooner
than later but anyway what we don't know
what's unclear is what we want the
convention to be for where these pixels
lie so is negative 0 point five times
the width is that lying on this pixel or
at the edge of this pixel and similarly
is plus 0.5 lying on a pixel or on the
edge of the pixel and the reason that
this actually is important is because if
you think about what happens if you
Center your coordinate system then 0 0
is actually in a middle row right it's a
middle column if you will at a middle
row where does that actually lie right
is it off by half a pixel or is it
actually on a pixel if it's on a pixel
remember we have 19 20 on our in a 1080p
resolution that's how many pixels there
are right so 19 20 / 2 yeah is going to
be equal to right sorry 10 for this and
then that's going to be 9 so it's
actually going to have to carry itself
outs it's going to be what like 960
right you got to actually do long
division don't do this much anymore at
least I down so yeah to write x 9 is 18
grab the 120 that's going to be 6 yet I
was right so it's going to be 960 pixels
two sets of 960 pixels which means that
the midline is not on a pixel it's on
the boundary between two pixels it is in
between pixel 959 and pixel 960 so the
middle of the screen is actually pixel
959 point live right so you see the
dilemma right you see what I'm what I'm
saying here at least hopefully you see
what I'm saying here I don't know it's
one of those things that only graphics
programmers get persnickety about not
really that much of a graphics
programmer but you know you could
understand you understand the reason if
you want to get every last little thing
right you can understand
why there's a bit of a problem there in
terms of how this stuff actually works
out because you know you have to think
about kind of what lines up where and
why these things do what they actually
do right and so if this right here if
this is negative 960 and this is
positive 9 60 right then yeah if those
if those are meant to actually be
specific pixels it means that the
midline the 0 is has to be in between
two there's no other way to imprint ER
prett that coordinate system and still
have the right number of pixels you
can't insert a phantom row column of
pixels and have it actually be there
yeah so that's how that works don't know
what else to say other than that that's
just how that works so I assume that if
we were to do that if we were to take
negative 960 and we put it there again I
think what's actually what's actually
going to be true of this coordinate
system right is that if the mouse X is
set to 0 then we will get we would get
the negative 960 right if it was set to
19 19 which is the furthest pixel / can
be it would be at plus 9 59 right so it
actually wouldn't be able to get to that
one extra pixel and so that's kind of
all so that's kind of again the dilemma
that I initially started with it's sort
of like saying well okay do we actually
want this one to line up at negative 9
59.5 right so that we actually do have a
full span so that this one goes so that
the plus and the minus are equivalent
because that way if we take right if you
if you're like how many pixels are there
actually in between these two right how
many are there if I take nine 59.5 and
subtract negative 950 950 9.5 right that
actually gives me the 1920 that I needed
right so yeah right like i said i don't
really know I don't really know how we
want to to think about that I don't
really know what the best way is to do
that I'm not sure this is one of those
things where I feel like being a more
personally graphics programmer would be
helpful because I'd have a stronger
opinion about pixel centers which is
what this kind of thing which is the
domain in which this sort of thing falls
if you will and you know in my in my gut
I feel like I don't like the idea of
having different bounds to the left and
to the right but at the same time I also
don't know if I love the idea of the
mouse always being on half coordinates
right so I don't know I really don't
know since it's only for debug maybe it
doesn't matter that much but point being
if we actually want to do it right if we
actually wanted to do it that way what
it would be is it would be this right it
would be negative with plus half a pixel
then plus the X that would actually give
you the entire span hopefully that makes
some sense like I said it's very
persnickety but right this would be the
other way again starting a point by
starting it than half pixel and going
through it and that would mean like I
said now the center the very center is
is actually going to be on an actual
pixel boundary so you know go figure so
I don't know I don't know I'm gonna
leave it that way for now but but you
know if people if there's a if there's
people who are more personally about
pixel centers I would very much be
interested to hear your opinions on it
it's the kind of thing that I think
through sometimes I'm doing rendering
but I don't have a strong of opinions on
it as I possibly should have if
makes sense so yeah let's see how we're
doing here looks like we're fine yeah so
that's all good okay so now we've got
about 20 minutes left oh go stretch a
little bit gotta stretch it out I so now
we want to do is let's let's try and
have some way that we can we can
interact with this a little bit more
what I'd like to do is I'd like to have
a way of saying stop the collation where
we're at freeze it essentially so that
we're not going to record any more any
more information right we're just going
to stop and in order to do that I guess
what I would want to do is say okay
let's see here I think in order to do
that maybe the best way to go would be
to just say this stuff here where we
kind of do our allocation and our end
temporary sort of stuff I think I could
just make that predicated right so I
could just say you know what can we just
do something like this where we do if
debug state frozen or paused something
like that and so then in the debug state
I could just have something that's like
be 32 pause and then you know whenever
we do this we could do something like at
the end of our overlay here when we're
doing our art debug overlay I could just
do something where we say oh yeah you
know if the mouse buttons and I don't
really remember much about how our mouse
buttons worked completely honest with
you so if our mouse buttons are these
enumerated in any particular way
doesn't look like it this doesn't look
like it to me yeah so I would say that
if the mouse buttons I'm going to go
ahead and add in a numeron ther win32
and made I'm going to go ahead and add
one there I'm going to do something like
you know enum game input mouse button
I'm going to do let's say platform is it
platform should I call out platform do
we have any and numerous here at all we
have like no we knew marincin our
platform layer yeah all right well let's
see here i'm going to call it a platform
mouse button left middle right spended 0
stemmed one and I going to use these in
the platform layer now so we'll just say
yep
and there we have it so that's all good
and now I can actually go in here and
and say by name the one that I want so
i'm going to say whenever we hit maybe
the right button will go ahead and
toggle that and i'm also going to do i
don't know if we have a went down macro
right see for them we don't at least we
don't seem too I'll see one so I'm
assuming that we did have transition
count do not check buttons anywhere half
half transition count well we really
just don't ever use this do we huh
that's a bit odd wouldn't you say that
we use this for something
so we just used whether it ended down or
not that's all we do if it ended down we
we set one of those and off we go so we
never used the half transition camp
which is odd all right well I'm going to
introduce a new thing then because I
don't really like that idea I would like
there to be right for this platform
thing I would like there to be a way
that we can trivially tell whether
something was went down or not we have a
half transition count so we know when it
went down when it went up whatever right
so really what we want to know is
something like was pressed you know so
if we have a game button state right and
then we want to know if it was pressed
oops it's pretty easy to figure out if a
button was pressed right all we have to
do is say hmm so if the state if the
half transition count is greater than
zero meaning there was at least one
transition from up to down or down to up
and it ended down right then we know
that was a kind of press what I'd like
to I'd like to do I'd actually like to
count it so if the half transition count
is actually you can't come to think of
it if it's greater than one then it
definitely had to go down right at some
point because it went from down to up or
up to down twice it's greater than one
so if it's greater than one obviously it
was pressed or if the if the transition
count equals one and it ended down right
that means that it was pressed during
you know this particular time time slice
I think that's what I think that's
roughly what I would like if I'm
understanding that correctly so what I'm
going to do here is say if it was if we
press that button then i would like to
pause the debugging so you know for sort
of chugging along here and i hit the
right mouse button i want that stop of
course that doesn't work at all which is
not good which is bad she's just just I
just don't understand where the code
doesn't work sometimes why does it have
to be so mean so yeah so let me just
double check I probably just did
something stupid there so if the half
transition count is greater than one
then we know that it was pressed if the
hass transition count equals one and it
ended down then we know that it was
pressed as well that seems right Oh
how did that get return true I obviously
just type something really stupid there
hold please the result is that whatever
the state is it has a half transition
count of greater than one which in this
case we know it didn't because I at
least I don't think it did or you know
that a strange count that was one and it
ended down that looks right to me it's
our bar mouse button States busted kind
of interested to see no got a result of
zero ok so that's working now so you
must not clear them or something right
yeah like we don't clear we just got it
we've got a platform bug there we got we
got it we got a platform bug it's what
we got all right where is that book that
bug that bug is is in there somewhere
went through to process keyboard message
let's go see where that's at what's it
doing oh so do we probably just never
cleared these guys did we in fact what's
actually what actually clears these
buttons am I am I just am I yeah I'm a
little bit I'm a little bit nervous
about that code i'm not i'm not thinking
that maybe that was um maybe that was so
good here's the mouse buttons that's the
only place that it ever gets referenced
that's not good right because it's never
going to get cleared ever ever ever
again that's that's a problem that is a
problem and since we're doing it this
way we have to fix this this is bad
people this is this was this was just a
bad this is this is BS this was bad
science right here so bad software so
yeah what we want to do here is say okay
we we get this half transition count and
that's fine but okay so at the start of
the frame we just need to clear the half
transition count right I think that's
probably all we need to do so when we
process the cube our message this will
do it so yes I think what we want to do
here is say set this thing half
transition count we want these all to be
0 right so we want to do like left
middle right extended 0 send one
see if that doesn t better okay
much better
it looks like it's double triggering
though so that's still not quite right
that's still not quite right we set the
half transition count 20 that seems
reasonable and then this stuff should be
oh and also these yeah it needs to copy
this it needs to copy us up so this this
code is just all garbage really because
we need to copy our old state from the
new one to the old one right and we
weren't doing that either so it's just
this is just this is just totally
nonsense this is like the most nonsense
a of nonsense things let's let's see if
we can write something that's not total
garbage I mean it's still kind of
garbage but let's just see if we can
write something better so here's the
mass wetin index we have seven minutes
left on the clock yes I think we started
about 10 minutes late platform mouse
button count mouse button index so what
we want to do is say the mouse button
new buttons you know I could just
shorten that button index so we get to
say that the button index copy the old
one like so and then we can just say
that the half transition capped equals 0
and then we might as well go ahead and
that on in there right and we can just
have that BD word win button' ID and do
that oh yeah and then we can just put
these in here VK m button oops l ro x
yeah oh yeah when button' ID button
index and button index now is all set so
that looks a little better a little
better not the world's best or anything
but that looks a little better and as a
bonus it also actually works which is
nice so now we can come in here and
actually you know sort of look at these
guys a little more carefully we could
also make them a little larger if we
wanted to so they weren't so hard to to
pinpoint that would be nice as well but
we're getting there right we're getting
there so now we have the way to pause
our debug input and to hover over our
debug input as well and then pretty much
the next thing that we should do
tomorrow I'll probably wrap it up next
don't want start a new thing quite yet
is we should have some way of starting
to click and inspect these guys which
should be pretty easy and also we can
clean up this output stuff as well
alright so we're getting there we're
good shakes I'm pretty good shape it's
true it is true alright folks let's do
some Q&amp;A here if you have questions
about what just happened before your
eyes it's what's coming at you what just
came at you please feel free to ask it
now put a cue colon in and I will answer
the question put the pig hat on the owl
know that the owl of shame is not
pigging at the moment i will not do that
I had a love Shaima what was my al of
shame moment what was the where was the
AL of shame moment oh you think the the
mouse code being buggy friend 50 days
trees on the ally that's not an atlas
shame we never used the mouse code we
just put it in there I mean we've never
actually gone and tried to use it I'd I
know that's not an al of shame and Alice
shames when you do something like really
stupid where it's just like oh you know
how did you how are you so dumb it's
like that was just like all right we
choose the mouse go in there it wasn't
good that's fine I'm that I don't
through that knowledge so that's that's
just programming that happens every day
well almond milk make you smarter I do
not know
shorten I three on behalf of all the
people here we love you and you're
awesome i love you guys too you are also
awesome it is pretty darn nice that
people show up every day to watch this
stream because I'll be honest with you
would be pretty lonely programming here
by myself that would not be a fun way to
spend an hour and a half so I thank
everyone for showing up it's been pretty
awesome that there's so many people and
seeing the same faces come back multiple
times and getting to know people is
pretty pretty darn cool too so so thank
you guys for being awesome epica an 00
i'm new here why constrain yourself to
one hour segments isn't ramp up time
every day hard uh you know i think i
think the reason for the one hour
segments is really because programming
is easy to do for long periods of time
you know i can program for eight hours
and that's not a big deal but explaining
programming for eight hours i would be
really dead by the time i did that after
you know a couple days of that right so
keeping it 21 hours one way of just
making sure that even on bad days i
still have a little bit of explanatory
ability because it is really hard to
program and explain at the same time
it's a lot harder than just programming
and it takes it's tough to do so so I
feel like keeping it constrained is it
makes it into little like segments is a
good way to make sure that I don't just
totally fail to explain what I'm doing
how would you go about optimizing the
debug rendering I well first of all we
could optimize a lot of the rectangle
stuff and all that yeah and and you're
right entity basis calculations could be
gotten rid of because we're going
straight through on these guys they're
not they don't need any 3d transforms or
anything so but I don't think that's
most draw rectangle probably optimizing
that would be the way to go
unfortunately right now well not
unfortunately perhaps you can say
fortunately the time is not spent there
right so take a look that stuff right
there that's the debug render time those
those those guys right there this is the
debug collation time so it's really the
collation time that's expensive not the
rendering time and fortunately for us
the collation time is easy to improve
all we have to do right off the bat to
make it eight times faster than it is
right now is to just store collated
frames and only collate new frames as
they come as necessary basically so so
we have a lot of options for making that
faster but as even as it is if we just
left it the way it is now we could leave
it the way it is now and it wouldn't be
the end of the world so that's fine
because remember it's debug code this is
a totally fine speed to play the game at
in testing so you know I'd be okay with
that too and this isn't even an
optimized build right you know like if
you wanted to you could go in here and I
know too that you could 0 to some of
that up get a little 02 going on Yom
same little oxygen little 02 oops of
course you should probably wait till the
build actually finished finishes it's
true so if we owe to tit then it's even
smoother right
yeah wow so our frame wait our frame
wait time is kind of looks just busted
like I said but I've said many many
times so far I think this is going to
tell us a lot of stuff that we don't
know about our code and I'm really
excited about that like look at that
frame wait time like what's going on
there that is just not right so yeah
we're going to learn we're going to
learn good stuff from this I promise you
that
James Woodman you've trained everyone to
listen for whether you're pronounce the
letter T or it's a lephone the glottal
stop where you say the word button it's
true I like saying button just fine in
normal speech but sometimes especially
on the stream I like saying button I
like I like over pronouncing button I
don't know why a chronal dragon should I
wasn't paying attention and use the
mouse button on the pyramid was broken
about I just didn't clear itself from
the new old input thing the mouse the
actual way to read the mouse in Windows
was totally fine it was just how we were
updating our mouse info James would have
been at some point would it makes sense
to pause and redisplay the frame that is
currently moused over uh you know if we
were going to sell this engine or
something yes because we can we have the
really do that does it make sense to
move them on the stream I don't know
that would actually pay off to do so so
I don't know if there's really any
reason to spend the stream time to make
that happen but if you were just going
for the gust oh yeah you could do that
struck 93 by the way I'm from Iraq and
it's 4am right now can you sometime do
an earlier stream I don't mind not
sleeping till 4am but in 2-3 week
university start and be awesome if you
bring back early hours this is the only
time it really fits in my schedule most
of the time at the moment I'm sorry
about that so that's why it is the time
that it is it's not because I don't
because I don't want it to be more
accessible I you know I just I just
can't I'm sorry
quarter on I think you only render top
level debug time functions i play on
drilling down yes that is like like I
said the next we were doing and just
when we get left-click will implant a
left lick where you can drill down
that's what we'll be doing next fire
Jack what is the other long bar some
kind of frame wait should it be that
long oh so if you probably asked that
before I myself ask that and complained
about it disruptor are your name
developer and or is this your
professional job if not what is your day
job yes I am well I most the time I
wasn't in the developer I was just a
regular developer did game technology a
trad game tools that's that was what
most of my professional career was at
the moment I am doing an indie game but
that's a that's a new thing for me toms
toms SAR i forget if the white line is
33 minutes or 60 milliseconds could you
add a green line for 60 hertz or inch or
30 red for 10 or something yeah well
we're gonna make that graph a lot nicer
in over the next few days now that we've
done like the underlying work so we
should we should get that out XOXO
dragon i noticed in task manager all my
seen games or 34 processes is there a
really good reason to compile game 2 30
pitch Rather's before it's just
compatibility microsoft because they
like extracting money out of people
tries to make 64-bit windows an upsell
so 32-bit windows is a cheaper sku than
64 windows so like I've said before
Microsoft just you know they don't care
about developers they don't care about
the fact that it makes developers life
hard to keep having to support 32-bit
for no reason at all they're just like
don't worry about it we're just here for
the money and you guys can can go have
another compatibility nightmare courtesy
of Microsoft so that's the world we live
in unfortunately and until they stop
doing that shipping 32 executables is
the best way to ensure maximum
capability if you don't care you
certainly could get away with shipping a
64-bit only executable because it's true
that it's only like ten percent of the
market or something but again you know
that's just just a game you gotta play
unfortunately
socialist kid the debugger displays for
faster time we're good you any visuals
to remember you said yeah I would like
to after we finish with this ad the same
kind of markup for the memory so so that
that is something that I would like to
do yes
you
alright let's like that's the end of the
questions
would you be willing to do a 12 to our
priests dream haha no I mean maybe once
in a while but but not every day no all
right I'm going to wind it down since it
looks like we're done with the the
queues the queue oh dear I don't touch
the wacom tablet oh my god what happened
I don't know what just happened my pipe
my blackboard like went nuts help what
what happened oh there's all the there
it all is right ah miss chief not a
scalable program apparently we have like
come to the point where it's unable to
let keep up with us look at all that oh
my lord oh my my goodness look oh weird
there's like a parallel it's like
another trail of stuff over there I'm
going to go right in the middle here I'm
going to leave us right here that's what
I'm going to do
all right file save minimize okay all
right thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero it
has been a pleasure coding with you as
always and I'm glad that we are now
having a nicer debug view I'm looking
forward to the next few days of just
like implementing some UI stuff I think
it's going to be kind of cool so we can
kind of look at all that information
that we're capturing I am into that I
think it's going to be pretty nifty so
hopefully you will continue to join me
I'll be back here tomorrow 5 p.m.
pacific daylight time and at that time i
would love to see you here again for
some more good UI upgrades to our debug
system so that's going to be pretty fun
hope see you here for that in the
meantime if you want to follow along at
home with the source code it comes with
the pre-order the game superior hammer
here on ham a dork you can download it
every night right after i'm done with it
i upload it so check that out if you're
interested in playing around and
learning from the source code we also
have a forum site you can go to ask
questions and if you want to to look at
annotated episode guide by some of the
people who are on the chat actually
community members do an anti episode
guide up there it's pretty cool we have
a patreon page you can support the video
series on we have a tweet pipe between
schedule you have to try to catch it
live and so please check out those links
for more information until then or i
should say until tomorrow when we when
we come back for a little more debug you
I fun please have fun coding and i'll
see you guys on the internet take it
easy everyone