Gonna go and hit hit the start record button and I'm gonna minimize OBS here.
And I'm going to welcome everyone to the very first episode of Handmade Hero.
I am super excited about this project
I was thinking that this was going to be basically me on a live programming stream
Making a game for people to sort of learn from
But basically that there were gonna be like five people watching
Because I assumed that it would take a long time to generate any interest.
But actually, the response from people has been completely overwhelming
I was so psyched about it
And it's been so great to see so many people here
Even on the test stream that we did where we were just kind of practicing stuff.
Everyone was awesome, the community was awesome, the questions were awesome.
And, it was just fantastic. I had an absolute blast doing it.
And so I'm really looking forward to this.
Before we get started started
I just wanted to say a couple things
And I'll probably try to, you know, take a minute
At the beginning of every stream just to repeat these for anyone
Who's coming back
Who hasn't necessarily seen
The livestream before.
Basically this is a series where we program an entire game from scratch
With explanations of everything I'm doing.
Now, in order to actually finish an entire game
At some reasonable point in the future
I cannot explain everything  in complete detail
So I have to constantly reference back to things that I've already explained
And, I have to trust that you're gonna be able to keep track of the things that I've explained
And, if you don't understand them
Ask questions, you can use the email link on handmadehero.com
You can basically go there any time you want
And there is a, sorry, handmadehero.org, you can go there any time you want
And there is an Email a Question button, so you can ask there.
You can ask on the twitch chat at the end of the stream
There'll be a time for a Questions and Answers.
Or you can just ask on internet forums, stuff like that
There's been a whole community of people who've been helping out.
So.
I won't be able to drill down into everything,  everytime.
I'll have to reference back to stuff that we've already done.
So please, keep that in mind.
It's ok if you get a little lost
If we blow past something that
We covered earlier on a different stream
And you're like: What was that? It's ok.
All of the videos will be archived.
You can go back and watch them again.
You can go, sort of, look and see if people in the comments have added stuff
And we'll try to have a lot of resources available for you.
You can also, if you preorder the game at any time
You'll get all the source code to it.
Every night you can download the source code, follow along
Play around with it at home, and all that stuff.
So hopefully there'll be plenty of resources for you.
With that said
I am going to get started.
And please keep in mind as we do this
That basically everything that I'm  going to show you here
Is one way
To code a game from scratch.
It is not the only way
And I don't want you to think
That you have to do absolutely everything I do the way I do it.
I'm just showing you the way that I make games
So that you can see one complete  way of doing it and see that...
You know, where there's nothing left out.
But you should develop your own techniques
And you should feel free to experiment with your own styles
And... and try different things and see what works the best for you.
Alright. Let's get going.
So the first thing I wanna do
Is I got to actually build
Something.
I have to get a project started.
And as anyone who's ever actually done a game
Or really probably any computer project knows
Getting a project started is a bit of drudgework.
It's really unfortunate, but it is.
And basically what happens is
You're going to have to create something
That allows you to build the actual text files
That you typed in into the source
You're gonna have to do something that allows us to get built into executable.
And in the intro stream we talked about the basics of that
So if you're unfamilitar with it
You're gonna have to go watch that to
To sort of get you up to speed, but hopefully most people understand
What a compiler is, what a linker is, what an executable is.
A compiler is something that takes the source code that we typed
And it turns it into partially, partially executable code.
And a linker is something that gathers all that executable code
And puts it into an executable
Which is something that we can actually run on our computer.
And what we did in the test stream
Where I was sort of teaching people very, very, very basic things
What we did in the test stream was  we used Visual Studio
Which you can download for free, actually.
This is Visual Studio 2013 Community Edition.
And that's what we'll be using for compiling
And running our code
You can actually go get it at visualstudio.com
Because Microsoft has now made it free for small teams or personal use
Which you are if you're one  person at home, following along.
You can download it here  and install this exact same thing.
It doesn't cost any money.
You can use it for free.
So this tool right here
Is what we're gonna be using to debug and compile.
And what we did in the test stream
Is we actually used this to make our project.
But I never do that in real game development
And most real game developers don't either
Although, some certainly do, so if you want to
You can certainly try to do that.
The way that I do things
Is I actually don't edit in here
And I don't build from in here.
I only run and debug from in here.
I basically use this tool as my debugger
And I access its compilation functions
From the command line.
Now we didn't cover the command line in the intro stream.
So I'm gonna talk a little bit about that here.
Basically what happens is, on your machine, if you're on Windows...
If you're on Linux you already know what a command line is
Because you don't, you don't use Linux without a command line.
But, if you're on Windows, even if you're a programmer
It's possible you may never have even used the command line.
It's possible these days, that can be the case.
So if you go into your All Programs
And you're looking under Accessories
There is a thing here called Command Prompt.
And when you click on it you get this little text window.
And all this text window is, is it's something that allows you to
Basically have a dialog with your computer the old-fashioned way.
You can type a command in, you can hit return
And it spits something back out to you.
Now this is super tiny 'cause the  fonts aren't set.
I have my own over here that I set the fonts to.
But I just wanted to show you the one that comes up when you launch it by default.
And basically we're gonna be using this
To sort of show you how to execute some commands
And I'll show you why you wanna execute commands through it, in a second aswell.
But, if you're like me
You wanna customize that a little bit.
If you right-click on a Command Prompt shortcut
And, I assume you all know how to do shortcuts, but just in case
You can, you know, Control-click and drag this out to the desktop.
You can make a shortcut for it, or anything like that.
If you right-click on a shortcut to a Command Prompt and hit Properties
You can go in here and you can customize a bunch of stuff
Like the fonts, where it is on the screen.
I won't belabor this because it's pretty self-explanatory
But you can basically customize it, and I did that.
I think during the pre, sort of the, the lead-up to the show
People were saying the fonts were a little too dark.
So I'm gonna go ahead and actually just  make them a little brighter in this one.
We made them brighter in Visual Studio and in Emacs and people seemed to think that was good
So I'm just gonna brighten those up a little bit there, and hit OK.
Once you've got have that customized, when you double-click on it, you'll get
Precisely the, you know, precisely the stuff that you said
And then the window will be where you want it, and you can use that.
And like I said I made the fonts a little bigger so they're easier to read, on the stream.
So.
First things first.
What I like to do, and this is unusual.
I don't know many people who do this.
I've heard people tell me that it is
If you used to use an Amiga, the computer from the late eighties.
If you used to use an Amiga computer, then you do this.
And, I don't know if that's true, but that's what I've heard.
I did use an Amiga for a long time, that was one of my favorite computers.
Probably my favorite computer of all time.
What I like to do
Is I like to use a command called subst
And I'll actually go ahead and delete
The subst that I actually already set up in this machine, just so you can see
How it actually works, or at least I'll try to.
Let's see if I can get that to work.
Yeah.
So basically what I like to do is
On Windows, you know, you've got these drives, right?
I've got, you know, I've got drives in this machine that are actually drives
I've got the C drive, I've got the D drive, that's a, you know, whatever.
And you can quickly always refer to those in the File Explorer, whatever
By just hitting, you know, c: or whatever
d:
What I like to do is I like to take
The, the place on my drive that I'm gonna be doing my development
And I like to subst a fake drive letter, so that it points there.
So this command, subst, you can type it in on the command line, subst
It doesn't do anything if you just type it by itself.
But if you type subst with a, like /?
Right? That's the universal symbol for,  well you know what?
Let me go back to the big font version.
If you type subst /? you'll get help on it.
Basically all it is, is a command  that allows you to type subst
And then a drive letter that you want to make.
Basically a fake drive, and I'm gonna use w:
And then give a path on the actual hard drive
Where you want that drive to essentially, exist.
So I made a directory on the J drive, that's an actual drive in this machine
And I made it, called, work, it's what I made it.
And so I'm gonna subst w: to be work.
And now, instead of having to always go to j: and cd to work.
Now that's, that's basically, cd is probably
A new command for people who don't  know the command line.
Basically this is how you move around directories.
So if you remember, up here
You know, when you're working in like a file explorer.
If you look at this thing, this is a path to a file, right?
If you want to move around on an actual command line
You can use the cd command to do that.
So you know, if you start out somewhere like I started on w:
I want to go into the handmade directory, now I'm in the handmade directory
And it always prints out where it is here.
Again that's not really, you should be able  to learn this separate from this stream.
That's stuff you can look up, just how to basically use a command line
So I'm not gonna teach you a ton of stuff.
cd .. goes back and so on.
You should just go learn those if you're totally unfamiliar with command lines.
Anyway, I like to subst a drive to it just  because it's really, makes it more convenient.
It's less typing for me
And it's so that if I ever need to hardcode debug paths into something
It makes them so they're not quite so hardcoded.
I can refer to w: something and then if in the future
I move the drive or, you know, I move where it  actually is on the physical hard drive around
It's no big deal 'cause I can just subst the drive to the new location, right?
So it's totally good.
No big deal.
Alright.
So anyway, I made a directory here, it's the handmade directory.
And what I did, and I'll actually show this in Explorer too
For those of you just who are sort of warming up
To the idea of having command line.
You can see that I've actually, if  you actually go into the Explorer
Um, in the j:&lt;b&gt;\&lt;/b&gt;work&lt;b&gt;\&lt;/b&gt;handmade directory
You can see that the directory listing in here is the same as the directory listing in here.
And dir is what gets me that, right? No big deal.
Again, I'm really not gonna spend a lot of time teaching this stuff
Becuase hopefully this is stuff you can just go read a basic tutorial webpage on.
And so I don't want to spend a lot of time in the stream right now.
But I'll just mention the things I do as I go, so you know.
And basically I made a misc directory here
And the reason I made a misc directory here
Was because I decided to put my .emacs config file in there.
'Cause I'm gonna be using Emacs to edit on the stream
And I figured that anyone who for some reason wants to edit in Emacs
Along with me, instead of editing it in some text editor that they find fun, and nice
They will be able to do that.
So anytime you actually go and, if you download the Handmade Hero source code
It'll have that .emacs file in there in case  you want to just use
The same setup that I'm using.
But other than that you will notice that the directory for handmade is empty.
That is because we are gonna be doing absolutely everything from scratch
So there's nothing in there.
And absolutely everything that it takes to run this game
Will be written in this directory
So it will be full of good code by the end of the series.
Now.
The first thing we're going to do is we are going to launch Emacs.
And we are going to make a simple single cpp file, single source file
That we can use to actually get our build going.
And like I said, this is going to be the drudgework.
In fact tonight will probably be the most drudgeworky night.
It's too bad to start off the series with the drudgework, but hey
This is where projects actually start, there's nothing you can do about it.
So, I am going to go ahead in here
And, inside Emacs, you know, there's all kinds of stuff I can do.
I'm not gonna explain all of these things because, again
I don't even necessarily encourage people to use Emacs, it's just the editor I'm fastest with.
So I think you should all use the text editor you're fastest with
But hey
If you really wanna follow me, you can follow me and use that .emacs file.
So I'm gonna make a directory in here
I'm gonna make a directory called code
And inside that directory called code
I am going to make a handmade...
Actually I'm gonna call it win32_handmade.cpp, right?
Now I have Emacs programmed to insert a little header into each of these.
And what this header actually is, is this is sort of
A little bit anachronistic these days, but I'll tell you what it is.
Basically, you know, inside a comment
What it basically does is it says, hey
I am going to
Actually put little markers in
That some external tool could come along later
And fill in the filename, the date of the file
And the revision it was checked into source code control.
So all of those are actually totally unnecessary
It's just a comment, it has nothing to do with the code, obviously.
But it basically just puts in some boilerplate
Automatically for me any time I create  a source file
And this allows it to play nicely with people's revision control systems
That do this kind of stuff.
So if you happen to check the source code into
A revision control system that you prefer
And it has keyword replacement, you can turn that on
And all the files will get marked cleanly, so that you can see them.
Now.
I'm gonna take one quick second
'Cause I think we didn't do this at the beginning of the stream
I am going to see if I can
Brighten the comments a little bit.
Because I know that people were saying they were having trouble reading some of them.
And I think it will only take a  second here to do that.
So, list-colors-display, let's take a look.
Those of you who were with me at the beginning  of the stream I greatly appreciate your help
Figuring out exactly what the color should be for everything.
So I feel like one of those grays looks good
Maybe a gray50, let's say
gray50 sounds good to me.
We'll try that and we'll see, gray50.
And we will see if that
If that makes it a little bit easier to see, ok.
There we go, so
What I'm going to do in this file is absolutely nothing.
I am just going to insert the entry point for Windows.
Now, those of you who actually were in the intro stream
We covered this a little bit, but basically
What you wanna do whenever you're  programming on windows.
Is you're going to need to use something called MSDN.
So, it is basically the documentation for everything that is on Windows
So if I search for WinMain
Which is the entry point for Windows
You will see that the first hit is msdn.microsoft.com
And that is the documentation for Windows.
Now you may ask me, how do you  know how to search for WinMain?
How do you know what to type  in there when you search?
Well the answer is, WinMain you probably could've figured out.
Because you could go look on some  tutorials for Windows or that sort of stuff.
So that's not that interesting  of a question to answer, but
What is interesting is, for the rest of  programming in Windows and all the minutia
How do you know what to search for?
Yeah there's MSDN and maybe there's a table of contents, but
Trust me, it's huge and it's very hard to find your way around.
The answer is: That's one of the  reasons I'm doing this series.
I don't think there is any way you can know what to search for.
The whole point of this series is basically to give you all those things
That you should search for, to show you
How to make stuff, and I'll go through it quickly
So like I said I can't sit here and explain every last little thing
But, this whole series is supposed to be  that backbone where you can go
How did I know I was supposed to search for this crazy thing in Windows?
It's like, you weren't.
It's just a lot of bad trial and error and years of experience in the industry
That exposes you to these things, so that you know to search for such and such.
And so this series is supposed to actually be that backtone that tells you what to search in.
But, just because I'm gonna show you all those things
It doesn't mean you shouldn't learn  how to use MSDN.
You really need to learn how to use this website, to read these pages
And to understand what they say
Because it's how you're going to be able to fill in all that knowledge.
Because like I said, I can't go into every last little detail
On what every last thing is, I can only give you
You know, a good explanation of each part and then you're gonna have to go, kinda
You know, do more exploring on your own to fully understand
Absolutely everything that I do
If I don't have, you know, if I
Haven't sort of being able to kind of go into like:
Here's why there's an HINSTANCE and here's what the kernel did in 1994, and stuff
You kind of, you know, the stream would go on forever.
So.
This is the entry point  that Windows will be looking for.
And technically, it's actually the entry point that the C Runtime Library
That links with our program will be entering
But we'll see that in just one second.
For now we have to concentrate  on getting our build going
So what I'm gonna do, is I'm gonna cut this out here
And I paste that into our program.
Now what we wanna do, and these _In_s are little markups...
I don't know why the leave them in here, they're kind of annoying actually.
These _In_s are little markups, that you don't actually want to have in code.
They're not actually C code really.
They are basically just something
That lets you know that the parameters are being passed in to you
As opposed... or into the function  whatever the function is.
As opposed to _Out_ parameters which come back out to you.
So.
I am going to include windows.h for now.
Which is the header file on Windows
That has all of the definitions, well
It's not actually all, many of  the definitions
That are functions that we will need to call
In order to get our job done.
To actually get us up and running on Windows.
And again, if you don't know what some of these things are
I highly recommend you go watch  the intro stream that we did
The test stream. I'm kind of assuming that people can sort of read C code.
And if they can't read C code, definitely go back
And watch that intro stream because it will teach you how to read
These things, so that you won't be confused by that.
So.
And it's all, I should also say...
If you go to handmadehero.org
It's on this Archive button
This Archive button right here has all the stuff, Intro to C on Windows
That sort of stuff, so
If you're totally new to programming and totally new to C
You definitely want to start there.  But assuming that you know what this stuff is
And can read C reasonably ok,  or at least a little bit
Basically what we're doing in here is we're including a header file
And that's just a bunch of definitions of functions we can call and types we can use
That Windows wants us to use to  communicate with us.
And this is going to be an entry point where Windows will pass us
A handle to our executable
This hPrevInstance is not something we actually need to use
It's sort of legacy at this point.
Our command line, the command line that got set
When we ran the program, and nCmdShow
Which I'll say what it again is because it's so darn funny.
I said what it is on the intro stream but I'm gonna say it again.
When you actually look at an executable, so
For example if I go out here to
To one of these guys and I hit Properties
You see this little Run dialog box?
It's like Run: and it's got this dropdown, Normal window, Minimized, Maximized.
Well, whatever that gets set to
When Windows calls into us and starts up our code
It's gonna be here, it's that int nCmdShow.
Like it was so important they decided to pass it to you.
So yeah, there you go, anyway
So I'm not gonna do anything here other than return 0 for now.
So I'm just gonna leave this as a stub
We're not gonna do any code, because what we need to do
Is we need to get this building and executing as it is.
Now here's how I like to do builds.
And this is going to shock and horrify
Absolutely everyone out there, and I apologize for that
But you know what? It's how I build stuff.
It's how I build all my stuff these days.
And I'm showing you how I program games, so that's...
That's where it's at.
Here's how I do it.
In the directory, the root directory of the code
For the project, basically wherever I'm going to be doing stuff
I make what is called a build.bat file
And what a bat file is, and the reson that I was talking to you guys
About the command line, which is this thing
Where you can type in commands that do stuff
And I can get printouts back.
A bat file is basically just a script.
It's a script of things that the command line should do.
That's it.
And so what I typically do nowadays
Is I don't actually bother using a makesystem or anything.
What other programmers do
Is they typically have something called a makesystem.
So basically, like for example GNU Make
Would be an example of an original one.
They use things called Ninja, for example.
Build system.
I don't know how to actually search for that
'Cause there are real ninjas in the world.
There you go.
A small build system with a focus on speed.
They use that.
They use something called CMake.
A lot of these things.
People love their build tools, They love their build tools.
They just like to have build tools on top of build tools
And build tools that launch scripts that run other build tools
And build tools for analyzing  their build tools
And build tools for optimizing the build tools that optimize their build tools.
They love it.
I don't love it
'Cause usually what I find is I spend  all my time screwing with the build tools.
Just trying to get stuff to build.
So I just said screw it, there's no more build tools.
It's a batch file.  There's just a batch file
That's all there is.
And the batch file, compiles the code.
Compiles all the code, every time.
And the reason that's gonna shock and horrify a lot of people is 'cause they're gonna be like:
Oh. My. God.  You compile all the code all the time?
The whole point of a makefile
Is that you only compile the code that changed.
And that's what a lot of those utilities do, they try to optimize things
So that they only do the minimal amount of work necessary to rebuild the project.
And when projects get very large, that can get really slow.
But I have found that actually
If you just code sanely
I now compile very large programs
Certainly, larger...
Considerably larger than what we would take to make a good
Full, professional-quality game on this stream.
Much larger, by just using a batch file
And it's only a couple of seconds.
So I think the time has come for people to maybe start re-thinking the way builds work
But, you know, again, like I said, just me.
So what we're gonna do here is we're  gonna start with a line that's @echo off
That is nothing other than
Basically, echo off is a command that says
Don't print the things in this batch file as you do them.
Don't show me every line
That you're about to run when you run it.
And this little @ symbol here
Is basically a thing that says don't echo this particular line.
Because, basically what will happen is
You know, let's say I save that here.
So I got that build.bat
So I go into by code directory and I dir it and the build.bat
You can see it there, it's right here.
And basically I run that build.bat file
And you can see it prints out the line echo off.
So the line that I was trying to use to stop it from
Putting lines out to the console when it did things
It's actually itself echoing.
So the @ is basically a thing that says don't echo that line either.
Because you have to, it hasn't turned off yet, so that's the way
That you do it, yeah.
Windows batch files ladies and gentleman, they're kind of amazing.
And so then the next thing that I need to do
Is I need to compile this program.
And the way you compile programs is you use
Basically, the Microsoft compiler is called cl.
And if you type it in
What you'll get, even after you've installed Visual Studio 2013
Is you'll get this note here
It's like 'cl' is not recognized
As an internal or external command, operable program or batch file.
And the reason that you get that is because
There's a thing called the Path.
In fact if you hit set, you can see it
It's this gigantic thing that's happening here.
Yeah, kinda crazy.
Basically there's this thing  called the Path
And what it is, is anytime  you're in this command line
These are all the actual variables that are set in my command line
They're things called environment variables, that control stuff.
You don't really need to know any of them,  honestly, for what we're doing
But Path is somewhat important.
What Path is, is this thing that says: here are all the places to search.
When I type for a command, look at all these places
In order, and the first time you find it, go, right?
So.
What happens is when I type cl it can't find it because that's not in the Path.
This happens even after you've installed Visual Studio, and you're like, ah
How do I get it to go?
Well, it turns out that Visual Studio is kind of a little janky
And we're gonna work around this a little later on
But at first I don't wanna quite work around it yet
I just wanna show you how to  do the basic maneuver.
And what you have to do, is you have to go find
Where Visual Studio actually is, ok?
So basically, I don't know if you've ever seen this guy
It's called vcvars32, anyone who knows what I'm talking about.
Or I think it's vcvarsall, actually, might be it.
Basically what we're doing is we're going  to look for a particular program that we need
That Visual Studio installs, that will set up our command line for us
To do the compiles from the command line.
So.
Where that is, is you have to first find
Visual Studio itself, right?
So we're gonna type c: to go over to the c: drive, ok?
We're going to cd to what's called the Program Files directory
And this is not... this is a trick.
But we're gonna go over to the Program Files directory
Which is where you would think it is, and we're gonna take a directory, ok?
And here you can see Microsoft Visual Studio 12
Which is the thing we installed.
Now, Microsoft likes to do this sort of stuff.
They like to call their program Microsoft Visual Studio 2013
But then you list it on the drive it's Visual Studio 12
So, you just get to magically find out and know
What version number your thing actually is
As opposed to the like branding thing that marketing decided to name it.
And they constantly do this, like it's never actually named the same thing as it is
When you go to actually look for it.
It's maddening.  It's Microsoft. What you gonna do?
Anyway
If I go into there
There it is.
If I go into there, I can do a directory, and I will see
What is in here, and I can look
And I can start to get nervous
Because there is... where is,  where is all the stuff? Is not here.
I know what should be in here, I'm looking for the compiler
I said there was a cl and as you see it's not there.
Well the reason it's not there is basically a historical accident.
So, what happened long long  long long time ago
When Windows was still only running on 32-bit x86 processors
Is, there was, you know,  a split
And there was a, a sort of a push by Intel to go to something called the Itanium processor
Which was gonna be a 64-bit processor, it was gonna be their new processor line.
And, meanwhile AMD staid with x86
And... because they didn't have the  license for Itanium or any of that stuff.
And they started developing their own 64-bit version of x86
Which of course is the CPU that is in all of these machines.
Well, the Itanium project that Intel had championed did not pan out at all.
I mean, it exists, and it's something that you could run
But nobody wanted to go to a completely new architecture
And switch to this whole new thing so, that didn't work out.
What ended up happening is AMD's  64-bit architecture
Which was just x86 upgraded to basically handle 64 bit
And it still could run x86 code just fine.
That's the thing that won.
And when, you know, everything in  the PC world went from 32-bit to 64-bit
And you had things like Windows 7 64-bit Edition and those sorts of things
When you install those, right?
Those are things that are using the 64-bit capabilities of the CPU.
And, you know, we'll talk a little bit more about
What the differences between 32  and 64-bit CPUs and stuff like that
Later on the stream when it becomes more relevant
But basically what happened at that time
Was Microsoft decided
Probably for reasons of trying to make legacy stuff working
Maybe just because they weren't,  you know, thinking super hard that day
They decided to make two Program Files directories.
So there's Program Files, and there's Program Files (x86)
And basically programs that are compiled
To run under the 32-bit  version of Windows
Go into the x86 one
And things that are designed to run on the x64-bit one
Go into the main Program Files one.
And Visual Studio still hasn't been updated
To run on 64-bit computers.
Now, it's been I don't even know how many years
Since we've all been
Running, I mean, developers especially been running 64-bit things.
But, like, they couldn't figure it out, they're like, that's not where they're at
So heaven knows why that's going on, but, that's the case.
So what you actually have todo is go to Program Files (x86)
And in there, you will see the same directory again
Microsoft Visual Studio 12, or whatever it is
There, yeah, there we go.
And in there
Now we can actually find the  thing that we needed
So when we hit dir inside the Visual Studio 12 directory
You will se all of this stuff, the only one you care about is VC
That stands for Visual C.
And we are using C so that is what we want.
We can go in there and when we do a dir we will see
vcvarsall.bat
And vcvarsall.bat is the thing we actually need to run.
So you'll notice, cl still doesn't work.
vcvarsall.bat, if you run that
It will configure all the stuff, the Path, everything, you run cl
And now it works.
But.
There is a catch ladies and gentleman.
vcvarsall
Only compiles for running a particular version of the compiler
Either the 64-bit one
Or the 32-bit one.
So if we want to run the 64-bit one
We actually have to call vcvars x64.
'Cause you can notice, when I ran it, there is a x86 there at the end.
So that's the 32-bit compiler, which is fine, I think
I think you can compile for...
You may not be able to, I don't even know.
I haven't tried to compile 32-bit with a 64-bit compiler.
I don't know.
We're gonna start off compiling 64-bit code
Because that is the most prevalent PC, CPU kind
Most prevalent PC CPU operating system out there
And it's a more powerful chipset, chip type
'Cause it has more instructions that we might all play with later.
So we are going to go ahead and run that.
And if you put the x64 after it
Then when you run cl, you can see that now you get the compiler for x64
Everything is the same, except for that little guy there, ok?
So what you have to remember
And I know it's a little annoying
Is you have to remember to run this when you start, start off your stuff.
Right?
But, we can do a little bit better.
If we want to we can do a little better, anyway.
What I like to do, 'cause I showed you that subst trick before, right?
What I like to do is I like to go into the Startup folder
See the Startup folder up here?
If I right-click on...
Well, actually I guess you wouldn't have one yet, so I'm gonna right-click on Startup and hit Open.
That basically brings up a folder that will execute anything that you put in it
When the machine starts up.
Wo what I like to do is I like to drop a startup.bat in there, aswell.
And I just edit it with Notepad, I'm not fancy
I don't even bother opening Emacs or anything.
But I like putting a file in there called startup.bat and I put in the subst line
And so while you're in there you might aswell go ahead
And run vcvarsall right from there, right?
Now there's a catch, of course, 'cause there's always a catch.
The catch is, that if you're in a batch file
And you wanna call another batch file
In order to be compatible with the most number of command lines settings that people might use
You have to use the command call.
Do not ask me why.
I really do not know.
I think it's some historical reason about they have to set
Some state in order for the other one to come back to here
After you finished it, and blah blah blah.
But assuming that you want this to actually dispatch to the other batch file
And then actually come back and execute any more lines you might
Put into Startup...
If you didn't put any more lines you'd be fine, you just go execute that, and that'd be it.
But assuming you actually wanted to do this and come back
You can put that in there.
Now, the only thing I'm not sure about
Because I don't always do it this way
Is whether that's sticky for the whole system.
I don't know if it is, it might not be.
And so the other thing that you can do...
I'm just showing that as one option,  you can try that, I'm not gonna spend
Time trying this on the stream.
The other thing that you can do, and this is also pretty cool
Since this definitely does work at startup all the time
subst do always works so I always put that in there.
The other thing you can do and the way that I'm going to do it
Because...
You know? I don't have a because.
I'm not even gonna say because 'cause I don't have one.
And, you know, don't make up a  because if you don't have one.
This is just the way I do it.
So maybe that means it doesn't work in there, I don't know.
This is the way I've always done it, so I'm gonna do it.
So, in here, I've got my misc directory
Where I put stuff that, you know, you don't have to use, you just, you can use it if you want to.
I'm gonna go ahead and I'm gonna create a batch file in here
And I'm just gonna call that shell.bat
Right?
I'm gonna call that shell.bat and I'm gonna edit it
And in there I'm gonna put
The actual thing that I'm gonna call, right?
And so that way, anything that I want to happen
Any sort of configuration for the shell when I start it up
That I want to have happen, I can have happen in there.
If that makes sense, right?
And there's some things that we might wanna do
Actually, I can show you some other tricks that are pretty cool
That me might wanna do in there, for example
We can also make the Path point to something in our directory
So if we wanna put like little tools  that we have, or things like that in there
We can actually make it so that that happens aswell.
So for example, if I wanted to...
Let's say...
So let's say I wanna make the Path point to something in our, in our guy.
So I can do set path=%path%
Which just means insert the old Path in here
Right?
I can do that, set the Path equal to the old Path
Oh well, you know what? Let's put ourselves first.
Why not?
I'm gonna make it so that it looks in
Our handmade directory
And underneath misc.
Right? So anything in the handmade\misc
You know what?  Let's go even further than that.
Let's make it... should we make it bin?
Nah, why complicate things?
So I'm gonna make it look in the  handmade\misc directory
And so that way, anytime we run something from the command line
It can look in there and it can actually just run it if there's something in there.
Right? And so that will be pretty cool.
So.
Now, what happens if we actually go in here
If we actually run this guy, right?
Let's see what happens when we do cl
Yeah, 'cl' is not recognized as an intenal or external command.
So I was right to suspect that we probably can't put it in the startup
'Cause if we put it in the startup
It's only gonna be scoped to that little startup shell
Like, if you noticed, right? Basically what happens is
I go in here to Startup, I run this thing
It kind of flashes, it does the command and goes.
subst is sticky, it works for the whole machine.
You can see even Explorer gets that W drive that I decided to make.
But vcvarsall
Just sets local environment  variables to the shell
And so it has to be local to that shell.
So basically what we wanna do is at shell startup
When we actually start the shell
We want to do those changes, right?
So we want to make sure that we can basically go in here
Right?
Run our shell.bat
Um, oh, that's good.
Already got a typo.
We haven't even started programming yet.
Anything that's got spaces in it
Since spaces are considered delimiting
You gotta enclose them in double quotes.
I forget that all the time
And I suspect you will too.
Anyway, I run that, and that'll run our vcvars
And now we will get our cl back, and we're good to go.
We can go one step further
And, well, you know what?
I may even remember this  command line switch.
I'm not gonna promise it to you, but I think
I may...
Actually remember the command line switch for telling the shell
To actually execute something
On startup, on its own.
So we don't even have to go in  there and run that.
Hmmmmm... Is it /k?
Do we think it's /k?
Does anyone wanna place bets? I think the stream should place bets.
Some poeple on the stream know.
We're gonna look it up in a second but we're just gonna type /k for now.
We're gonna type /k and then we're gonna tell it to go ahead and run
handmade\misc\shell.bat
Like that, and we're gonna see what happens.
Bam.
Did you see that? Did you see that?
That is a useless set of neurons right there, ladies and gentleman
Remembering stuff like that. That's what happens
When you get to be 38 years old now
And have dealt with this stuff for far too long.
Ok so now we are at a position
Where we can double-click on that icon
And we can actually run a compiler.
Congratulations.  That is some big big news right there.
Surely it's not very far to a complete  game from there, right?
Surely.
Ok.
So anyway, if we can do a cl then we can basically build an executable.
That is mostly all we need.
So if we go in here
And, oh, and I guess I did that setting that Path to handmade
I didn't actually show anything that we can do in there
I set the Path to there
So basically obviously we can run shell again.
And that would work because it  found it in the Path.
Now, remember, shell wasn't there but it went and looked in that Path that we set.
If I hit click set again, you can see
That I got right here, it now  inserted me into that Path
So it's looking through each of these, right?
And it's gotta find the stuff that I put there.
So, now that I've got that set
I can put something else in there,
So why don't I, instead of  running Emacs from an icon?
Let's, let's stop doing that, let's, you know, there's no need for that.
What we can actually do instead
Is we can run Emacs directly from our shell.
So basically the only thing we'll start up is this.
Ok.
So, and you know what? I'm gonna close this aswell.
So we're gonna have a little party here.
Ok.  So if I want to
I can basically make another batch file
So inside handmade\misc
I will make notepad...
And I will go ahead and say that  this is going to be
My Emacs launcher. Save.
Why did... Oh, you know what?
I should give it a name so I don't have to actually into..
notepad emacs.bat
And I do want to create a new file.
I'm gonna @echo off
And I'm gonna go over here to the GNU Emacs icon that I had
And I'm gonna copy in what was in there.
So, what's interesting about this
And I'll show you this part aswell 'cause I've customized this icon
And it's good for you to know if you do wanna follow along with Emacs.
When you do this runemacs command to run Emacs
And this has to be wherever you installed it, it comes in like a zip file
So wherever you unzipped it, you're gonna have to find the runemacs command
And you're gonna have to call that.
I unzipped it just into Program Files (x86) where everything else that's x86 goes
Why not? You can put it into  something more sanely named if you wish.
-q -l w:&lt;b&gt;\&lt;/b&gt;handmade\misc\.emacs is just a way of saying
Load this as the config file, I think -q might be
You know, I don't even know what -q is
-l loads this file right here
I believe, which is the one that I created my custom emacs file.
And so that way it will come up with my settings.
So I'm gonna go ahead and save that.
And close it.
And now, no matter where we are, in theory
If we wish to summon our editor
You can type emacs, and bum, there it is.
Close it.  Comes back.  Everyone is happy.
And, we're starting to get a little closer to a machine I can actually use to develop code.
The other thing that is good to know, is devenv.
devenv is the name of the actual Visual Studio IDE
And if I type that in and hit return
It will load it, just like I'd clicked on the icon, and now
We are at the point
Where all we need...
Plew, plew.
Is just our command prompt, ladies and gentleman
So get rid of those icons, they are gone.
So.
That is the drudgework of setting up
A machine to actually develop on.
If you want to have some of the same stuff that I have, obviously
You can go grab GNU Emacs yourself.
You can search for it here, you can go to GNU Emacs
And it willl come up.
You can click through to the various fun locations.
I think, there's an Obtaining, click on Obtaining.
You click on nearby GNU mirror
And after clicking on that there's a windows/ directory that you can click on to go in
And get the correct one, I am using...
Because a lot of stuff has broken in recent Emacses
I am using version 23.4.1
And so you can go in and you can download 23.4
Which is this bin, 23.4-bin-i386.zip
That's what I'm using.
Ok.  So.
We have about 20 minutes left to go
Which is plenty of time to get our code working.
Drudgework done.
Here we go.
So I'm gonna actually go in here to handmade\code
I'm gonna hit emacs
And I'm gonna open up my build.bat
I can now take this win32_handmade thing that I made here
And I'm gonna say
I want to build this code
But I don't want to build it where it actually is right now
I don't want to build it right in its current location.
And the reason that I don't want to do that
Is be... well, you know what?
Why tell you when I can show you?
So, cl is the compiler
If I wanna compile something I can actually just type
cl win32_handmade.cpp hit return.
It will then do the compilation and you can see that it spit it out.
Here is the win32_handmade.exe
Here is the win32_handmade.obj
Now.  I will be getting a little bit ahead of things here
So, you don't have to worry about this too much
Becuase we'll talk about compiler switches in a separate episode.
Later on down the road when we talk about optimizations and stuff like this.
But.
When you do cl, if I put /Zi
That will actually cause it to generate what's called debug info
Which allows us to debug the program more effectively.
When I do that you will notice that  we start getting a lot of crap in here.
There is just a lot of crap in here.
There is this pdb file, which is debug info that it spit out.
There's another pdb file which is a separate thing that it uses
These are both part of the debug info, I believe...
Don't quote me on that.
They change it every version, I don't  know if you can maybe get rid of this
But I don't think you can, I think you need both.
The obj file is the intermediate file that it used when it first compiled this.
This was the thing that it linked with.
I think this is some kind of incremental linker data.
So, it's gonna start spewing stuff into our directory
And I don't want my directory to look like that.
That is not ok, that is not ok.
I am getting rid of those pdbs
And you noticed I did  del *.pdb
Which basically says delete everything that's got a .pdb at the end of it.
I'm gonna delete *.ilk I'm gonna delete *.obj
And I am back to what I actually wanted which is just the exe.
So, I'm even gonna delete that, because
We're gonna try and make that a different way
So what I wanna do is I want to basically
Force all this stuff to go somewhere else, and keep my source directory clean.
So what I'm gonna is I'm gonna use a thing called pushd popd.
pushd and popd means push directory, pop directory.
So I'm going to build this
Back a few, in build, I think.
I'm gonna go back two of these, this is the syntax for back a directory.
So I'm gonna back two directories from where we are.
So, out of code, out of handmade.
And I am going to go into a build directory.
Now of course that may not exist, so I'm  gonna double-check that it's made first
Then, I am going to cl
This file.
I'm going to cl handmade/code/win32_handmade.cpp
Like that.
And then I'm gonna popd back out.
So that will bring me back to where I originally was
Before I ran this build.bat
Now that's not strictly necessary
But basically pushd and popd are sort of like enclosing something you do
In a block
So that when you're done with it, you return to the directory you started from
So that you don't have to remember it.
Right? If I was to just use a cd here, it would change the directory permanently
And that's not going to be very useful. So.
Here's my build.bat I build it, and, oh...
Not off to a good start,  it can not find my, oh...
How about that?
I'm using the wrong... You can tell I use Linux most of the day.
Linux of course uses slashes for directories, that go forward, and Windows uses backwards.
And you can't, you can't mix  and match the two.
Although you should've been able todo that.
You know what I think?
You should've been able to do that, shouldn't you?
Oh, you know, you can do it in the cl, I bet, let's take a look...
No, maybe not.  Alright, what's going on here? Let's take a look...
handmade\code\win32...
Do?
win32_handmade.cpp
What is the complaint?
Syntax for the command is incorrect.
Ohh, wow, well, I'm very glad I decided to show you that
Because I believe, that means...
That we did not actually enable something that we needed to enable.
Windows, ladies and gentleman, it is always fun.
So, I believe...
This may actually be, let's see, pushd
Let's see, pushd
You're gonna have to get used to this, by the way, 'cause this sort of thing is going to happen a lot.
Especially in things that I've done... haven't done for a long time.
So that actually works just fine.
The pushd works fine the way that it appears to be here.
The mkdir works just fine.
So what is it actually complaining about? I don't actually know.
Is this just becuase we don't have command extensions enabled?
That would be starnge.
At least I feel like that would be strange.
But it could actually be true, I always use them
I always have them enabled on my machine.
No, it worked fine.
So there you go, that just works.
Cannot open source file: 'handmade\code\win32_handmade.cpp': No such file or directory.
So I'm gonna actually just go ahead and see... can we do that here?
So that I can see what actual directory
It ends up in when it tries to do the build.
So it ends up in w:\build Oh! doh.
Ok, everything is fine, I'm just not thinking straight tonight.
That's totally fine.
So what I did is I told it to go  to the build directory
And then I told it that this was the path to the thing, but it's not the path to the thing.
Because of course these paths are all relative
I'm using relative paths  instead of absolute paths
So that you can build it in your machine wherever you happen to put it.
So instead of typing w:&lt;b&gt;\&lt;/b&gt;handmade right?
If I'd typed that, it probably would've worked just fine
And you can see that it does.
But since I tried to use a relative path, I forgot I'm inside the build directory
So I have to go back out one to get it, yeah.
Fantastic.  This is the kind of stuff that you love to do when setting up a machine.
So that actually builds, as you can see, it did the build.
It didn't dump anything in our directory.
And so now if I dir that build directory, you can see our win32_handmade executable
There it is, right? It's just sitting there, it's ready to go.
All is well and good.
Now you may ask, where does all the complicated build stuff come in?
Well, the answer is there isn't going to be any complicated build stuff.
That is, what you see right here,  going to be the way we build this project
Right up 'til the day we ship it, and I'm not kidding.
If you think I'm kidding, I'm not kidding.
And we are going to be totally fine, you just have to trust me, on that one.
So that is really all you need to build a project, now, what's gonna happen here
And this will change a little
Is we are going to start putting things on this line, that are options to the compiler
'Cause the compiler has a lot of options
And we are going to do stuff that tells the compiler
That we wanted to produce certain types of executables, and these sorts of things.
We're going to control a bunch of stuff about it
And so, saying it's exactly this isn't quite true.
But this is the entirety of the code that will be happening.
Basically we'll just be adding things
To this line, we'll probably set some variables up here equal to...
Like a set of debug flags and a set of release flags, and then we'll pick which one
We're trying to use at any time.
So the only thing I'm gonna do, is again, I'm gonna jump ahead a litte bit here
And I'm gonna add some compiler flags, I'm just gonna tell it to generate
Debug info, that debug info that we talked about before.
I'm going to build that.
And then back in that build directory, we should be fine.
There it is.  So.
What we can do now, is we can actually go and step into our code.
We actually have a working Win32 program now.
Built by the command line using our own batch file
Which is all good, all good.
If I now want to actually go and step into that, and look it in the debugger
That devenv thing that brings up Visual Studio, we just have to call that
With the actual path to the executable that we are going to run.
So there we go.
Up comes our project.
Now if you click in Solution Explorer, you will see that what happens
You know, we never created a project, right? in here, right? So what happened?
Well basically if you tell devenv  to just load an executable
From the command line like this
If will just make a dummy solution for it with that executable
And you can go in and set the debug properties on it, just the same.
Just as if, it was some project that you had created in here, right?
So, what I do wanna do is, I do want to say where we're going to run from.
Becuase one of the things that's true in any low-level piece of code
Is that you basically have a directory
That the program was launched in, and it's called the current working directory
And basically everything that you do when you reference things in your code
When you try to load files
If you use a relative path, like the kinds I was using here...
And just to be clear about what a relative path is
Again, something you should probably look up on your own, it's very straightforward.
But, a relative path is basically saying
I'm at some place, and you can see  the current working directory for my shell
Right here, w:&lt;b&gt;\&lt;/b&gt;handmade\code Right?
But if I want to reference something
I can use an absolute path by  saying, the whole path
Like dir w:\build says  dir that directory
You know, tells me exactly where it is and it does it.
But I can also use a relative path
Which is go back one, go back two, then go into build
That's relative.
But the question is relative to what?
And so basically just like the shell has a current working directory
We have a current working directory
And that current working directory is important
Because if we want our game to run
Without any external knowledge of where it is
We kind of want it to load things out of wherever it happens to be
And wherever the user happens to run it.
So to set ourselves up for success
I am basically going to say, well
Let's make a directory under handmade
Right?
Called, hmmm, I usually call it data.
To be honest with you, I know it's not a great name.
I'm open to other suggestions.
So I'm gonna make a directory called data
And I'm gonna say that we're gonna put
Basically what we will be  shipping with the game
So the packaged art assets or anything else like that
I'm gonna put those underneath the data directory.
So in order to tell this
That when we debug the program
We want you to run it in that directory.
I'm gonna put that, ups,  I'm gonna put that into the home directory
So that it knows the working directory, so that it knows
That that's where I want it.
So I'm gonna go in here, well I'm just gonna type it in.
See Working Directory?
I'm gonna type in the working directory, I'm sorry that's tiny.
Hopefully this...
We will almost never be editing these project settings
So hopefully you don't even really have to read this.
There's a thing called Working Directory
We're just gonna put in that handmade\data and we're gonna hit return there, right?
So now when we run our code
It will run it as if it was running out of this directory
So we can kind of, always be running
Sort of in a closer configuration to what we will actually ship
To end users who buy the game  and want to play it
So that we won't have surprises down the road.
Ok.
Furthermore, this Arguments field here
Is where we'll put things that we pass to the game
For like, you know, parameters and stuff, debug parameters that we want.
Alright.
So once we've set that, we can hit F11
And F11 will... oops
I gotta close this Properties window.
Well, no, it closed it for me, well thank you.
We're gonna hit F11 which means start our application
And stop on the first line of main
Which is exactly what it did.
And you can see the little thing highlighted here, where it stopped.
This is actually our code.
This is the thing that we built, it's exactly what we hoped for.
So, we can go like this, it ends.
Our first Windows program ladies and gentleman.
But, you may ask what is this all this stuff here.
That's a very good question.
We covered it in the intro stream but I'm gonna mention it a little bit
In this stream aswell because it's kind of important.
So.
Now that we have our build going
We can start to look at actual Win32 code.
When I said this was the entry point for Windows, what does that mean?
You know, what is an entry point?
For those of you who are well familiar with programming or who took the intro...
Who watched the intro stream.
You know that this is a function.
It's something that gets called,  it executes the code inside of it
And it returns to whoever who called it
And that is what it does
But the question is who called us and how did they do it?
Well, the answer is
That in this particular way of compiling which we're doing right now
It's not actually Windows the  operating system that calls into us.
The person who actually calls into us is the C Runtime Library.
Now the C Runtime Library is something that ships with al C compilers
As mandated by the C specification
And if you go online
In fact you can look for  c runtime library
You will find, probably, some documentation somewhere
That talks about what is in it.
So let's see if I can get something for example here.
Yes, here we go, CRT,  C Runtime Library Features.
If I go into something like  Files and Streams
And open that up, you can see that it's basically got a bunch of documentation
That tells me about the sorts of things that this thing can do.
Right? It's like some, you know, here we go, here's some
Functions that are in the C Runtime Library
setlocale, _wsetlocale, who knows, we don't really care about these.
But point being, this is stuff that is not part of Windows.
It is not in the operating system.
It's just part of the standard library that everyone has to support
When they ship a C compiler, because code will be written to expect it to be there.
That's all well and good, we won't really be calling any of that
But, the truth of the matter is
It's actually very very difficult nowadays to build an application
Without the compiler essentially sticking the C Runtime Library in there.
So I'm not really gonna call hardly anything from the C Runtime Library
'Cause I wanna show you how to make basically everything from scratch yourself
But, we will still have to link  with the C Runtime Library
Because if we don't link  with the C Runtime Library
The compiler is going to be very unhappy.
It counts on the C Runtime Library for a number of things
Like stack grows
Like C++ initializer list that happen at startup time.
All sorts of things are actually hardcoded into the compiler to call
Into that C Runtime Library so that if it's not there
You have to implement all that  code yourself, to compensate
For the fact that the compiler was basically doing a lousy job.
I don't think that's particularly useful
And nobody I know actually ships
Without linking to the  C Runtime Library.
So we are not actually going to address that here.
But, what that does mean is
You should be aware, when you get called, it's not Windows who is calling you.
If I hit F11 here
I can bring up something called the Call Stack, right?
And waht the call stack is, oh...
Awesome, is this not set? There we go.  Ok.
So basically you can see it came up
In I guess what you might want to call training-wheels mode.
The call stack is a thing that shows you where you are in your program
Basically by showing all of the functions
That have been called, that called eachother that called eachother, to call to you.
Right? It's the entire stack of functions up to the point where you are.
So, it decided to only show me my actual function
Right? It didn't show me any functions that  were outside of us, in the C Runtime Library.
But, it looks like there's a button here called Show External Code
You can see it right here  there's a checkbox
If you hit Show External Code
All of the sudden you can see this other stuff that happens.
ntdll.dll and kernel32.dll are the actual operating system.
We're gonna talk more about what dlls are and that sort of stuff much later
So don't get too hung up on what those are
But point being that's code that's actually in the operating system.
If we jump out there we're just  gonna see assembly language code
That's basically stuff that's in the operating  system that we don't have source code to
'Cause Microsoft does not release the source code to Windows.
But, after Windows calls into our executable, you'll notice
The first thing that's called is not us, at all.
It is actually...
Some code we didn't write.
It is crt0.c
And you can see that  that, if you hover over it
You'll actually get a tooltip that  shows you were it is, and it's actually
Out in the Visual Studio directory
So this is the code that they shipped with the C Runtime Library.
And they shipped the source code to the C Runtime Library
So even though it's compiled code that we're in right now
We can actually view the source, which is kind of nice of them
To provide that so we can see what's going on.
So as you can see there's a whole host of things that happens.
And this is actually
The place where things start up in Windows.
Right? So if we really really truly  want to see
Where the code starts  when Windows calls us...
When Windows get-loads our executables, does its patching, and gets us ready to go
This is actually where the code starts.
These things all happened first
They're in code we did not write
And they are doing a bunch of things to set up the C Runtime Library
Which unfortunately we're not even going to use, but
It's good to know that it's there just so you don't get confused.
It then will actually dispatch to us
And so you can see if I step into there
That's where we go, right?
So it's all good.
That is what is actually happening.
Alright.
So one more thing I wanna do
Just to get things to a place where we have done all of the drudgework.
So that we can actually do something interesting on tomorrow's stream.
If I hit, let's see...
I want to be able to basically make it so that I can compile
My code from inside Emacs.
But I don't have it set up to do that yet.
What I wanna do is I wanna make it  so that I can hit Alt-M, basically
And I can... I can basically, oh you know what?
I think I can actually just do it right here, does that actually work?
No, I guess it doesn't.
You know what? Maybe I'll save that to next time
'Cause I don't actually wanna kind of complicate things for that matter.
We probably have, maybe 5 minutes left on the stream.
I will show you how to get that stuff working in the next one
But, for right now I guess what we could do
Is we could at least just have our Windows program do something
So that we know that it's actually running and doing something amusing.
So what I'm gonna do, is I'm gonna call a function called MessageBoxEx
Why not? Actually I guess I could just call MessageBox
But I think I wanna call MessageBoxEx
'Cause, you know, it's a little more fun.
MessageBoxEx is just something that pops up a message box.
It's the easiest thing for us to call that we can quickly see
That our code is actually working.
So if we look at it here we can see what it actually calls.
We can look at MessageBox  and see if it's a little simpler
Because they both do basically the same thing, yeah, that's even simpler
So we'll just call MessageBox, it's even simpler.
MessageBox basically takes a bunch of things
That we'll be covering more in detail what they actually are.
But the HWND is basically a handle to a window
And we haven't open a window yet so we're just gonna pass 0 there.
It then takes a string, just a regular old string
ANSI string
That's basically what you want to... excuse me
What you want to display  in the message box.
This is Handmade Hero.
And it has a caption
Which is the thing that appears sort of as the title
I believe of it, so let's make that Handmade Hero.
Right? And then it has like a little, sort of a
I wanna say a predefined value here
That basically says what kind  of like icon it is and...
What you want it to be, well we don't really have anything to ask the user
So we're gonna to pass MB_OK
And we don't really have a...
I guess anything in particular we want to...
Warn about anything so we are going  to pass MB_ICONINFORMATION
So, for those of you who were with me
In the intro stream
This is a bitwise operator, it ors things together.
If you're uncomfortable with that I highly recommend watching the intro stream
Because it will tell you about that operator and how it works.
But in that stream people were asking, do you do much bitwise manipulation in real coding?
And I said something like:
I bet we'll do some in the first stream, you do it all the time.
And ladies and gentleman,  even though I was not planning that
You can see right here
That it actually happens and the reason that it happens
Is because the way that people often likes to do flags
Like when you just wanna set some flags
Like ok, I'm calling this function and I wanna set some things like:
Do this, do that, don't do this, don't do that.
Some little booleans like toggles.
A lot of times what they'll do is is they'll use a bitfield
Which is basically saying that each bit
In a particular sized thing like in a 32-bit value
Each bit means a specific thing
And what you'll do is you'll or the bits together
To set the things that you want set.
So in this case we want MB_OK
To say that it's a dialog box that has an OK button.
And in this case we want MB_ICONINFORMATION to say we want to have a little
Information symbol next to it.
And we're gonna or those two together
To basically say that that is what our dialog box is going to do.
Now if I go ahead and do our build...
Oops, if I actually go to the right directory and do our build
It will rebuild our thing, oh...
And, we get to the other part of our build
So...
When we actually call something
And this is a little bit confusing, I, I...
This is one of those things that you wish the compiler didn't do for you
But it does do it for you and so it's kind of a little confusing.
But.
When you compile a program, as we did here
And you can see our command to compile our program
Did not actually include anything other than our code
Right? It's handmade.cpp
And when I built it you saw me run it and everything worked properly
So you're like: oh ok, that makes sense.
I build the cpp file, right?  It compiles the code, it links it together
It builds that executable, all the stuff we covered in the intro stream
If you're unfamiliar with it you can take a look at that, again, for more detail.
It builds our executable and  then we run it and it's all good, right?
That's all that had to happen, but that's not actually entirely true.
What actually happens is
Windows needs to basically bind to us
And we did talk about this in  the stream a little bit too
But Windows basically needs to find the  places in our executable where we try to call it.
And it needs to be able to go in there, reach in there
And patch those locations
To point to its own code that's running at that time in memory, right?
And in order to do that it uses what's called an import library.
What happens is when you link
When you actually build your program in here
And it links together the obj files and makes an executable
What it has to do is it has to  have a library that says
Here are the functions that Windows  actually is going to call...
Here are the functions you're going to call that are in Windows
And I'm going to put little markers in
This library tells me how to put little markers in
Where they should go
So that they can actually be found  by Windows when it loads it
And off you go.
And in the intro stream I drew a little diagram that shows like how that works
Where Windows loads it, it looks at that table of fixups
It goes through, patches your executable
And that sort of stuff, so if you're interested about that
I highly recommend watching the episode of the intro stream that talks about that.
Anyway, the problem is, we didn't specify any import libraries
So technicaly we should not actually have been able to call anything in Windows
At all.
And I don't actually know if it's true because I think they may sneak kernel32 in there
I'm not actually sure if they do, you know what?  I'm just gonna go ahead and test it
Since I know how to test it.
Let's actually just call... Well, you know what?
I'll call GetModuleHandle, let's see...
Yeah, so they do. They actually do sneak it in there.
So basically what happens is they sneak in
One import library or at least one import library.
The import library that they sneak in is the import library for the kernel.
So basically you're allowed to call things that happen to call into the kernel.
You can call those.
We'll see a bunch of them when we actually  start programming Windows for real tomorrow.
We'll see a bunch of calls.
But when you call into the kernel
You're actually fine because they snuck it in there for you.
If you call into something else
For example the UI system
Which exists in something called user32.dll
It doesn't include it.
So basically what I have to do
Is I have to go in here
And I have to specify, and I'm...
Totally doing this by memory, I'm assuming this is correct.
Is it /LINKER or /LINK?
/LINKER... let's, I don't even remember what it is.
What is the option for the linker?
In fact do I even  need to specify the option for the linker?
No I don't, nevermind.
So, anyway...
If I go in there and give it the import library
That I actually need to call the function
And where that function is actually mentioned so that Windows knows where it is
Then all of the sudden my code compiles, right?
If I don't do that
If I don't specify the import libraries that I need
Right? And I compile it
Then I'll get what's called an  unresolved external symbol.
Again, covered in the stream if you don't know what that is
They happen in other languages aswell so I hope that you were familiar with them.
But basically what it says is
I can't find the actual, sort of...
Actual call that I need to make
That you're saying that windows.h defined
I can't actually find where that  function actually is.
And it makes sense that it can't find it because we didn't define it
And neither did windows.h, all it did was say that there was one.
So what the library does is it actually gives it
The information it needs
To actually sort of insert
The placeholder that says: When Windows loads this
Patch this up to call into Windows code
'Cause this doesn't exist in our executable, it exists in Windows.
Now, the question is, how did I know that it was user32?
I mean, I knew 'cause it was memory, but what would you do if you didn't know that?
Well the anser is: I said, you gotta get used to using MSDN, and I meant it.
What you wanna do is you wanna scroll down to the bottom
Of MSDN's documentation on the function you're trying to call.
And down there you will find...
Explanations of that particular function.
Now you will see...
What the minimum client is  that you can call it.
And if you care about server then you  actually can find that aswell, but we don't.
We only ship to basic client OSs.
We're not gonna ship to people running servers, certainly.
The minimum supported client  so you can find out
If that function is callable by you
On your target platform.
So if I'm targeting Windows 95, let's say
I can't call this function.
I have to call some other function, let's say.
Now I actually think this function was in Windows 95
So I think this might be a little agressive
When it says Windows 2000 Professional, but point being...
Certainly antyhing after that it's fine, Windows XP...
Windows XP will probably be  our minimum platform
Right? So we can, we're, we're scot-free.
It tells you what header it's in
Basically it says: Well it's in Winuser but include Windows.h which includes Winuser.
It tells you what dll it's in, so that's actually what will get loaded at runtime
To actually support you.
And we'll talk about what dlls are later 'cause we'll be manually loading them
For things like the gamepad support.
And it tells you what library  you will need to link with.
So all I did, right?
Essentially was, I'm short-circuiting this process 'cause I knew
But all you actually have to do when you call something
Is go find the documentation for the function
Go down to the bottom
And right there it will tell you
What the lib is that you need, now there's one other thing
We covered this on the other stream but I'm gonna mention it again.
A lot of functions, if they take strings in Windows
They have an ANSI and a wide character version.
The wide character version is  if you have UTF-16-encoded stuff
And the ANSI version is if you have
Just regular ASCII that you're going to try and pass it.
Now you may wonder, why it has these two
And I called this MessageBox function
Like, what's going on there? Like, that doesn't make any sense, right?
Well the answer is because in all of Windows
Everything that takes a string is actually not
The function that you actually call.
You actually call a macro
So inside windows.h there's actually a #define
Which is how you do macros in C, how you replace text in c.
It is actually a #define that #defines MessageBox
To MessageBoxA or MessageBoxW
Depending on whether or not you're compiling in UTF-8 mode or ANSI mode.
By default, if you just call cl
The compiler is set to compile without being in Unicode mode
So it's gonna compile in ANSI mode
Which means that we're gonna call MessageBoxA, which is what we wanted
Because this is an ANSI string.
But if we were trying to pass UTF-16 to it
We wouldn't have to switch the  compiler to compiling in Unicode mode.
Which is, basically
Putting in a #define or anything like that to switch it
We don't have to do anything like that.
We could just go ahead and stop using the macro.
The macro is just something Windows did for backwards compatibility a long time ago.
So we can actually just actually short-circuit that process entirely
And call the actual function that we actually wanted.
And that'll work just fine as you can see.
Again, we need that user32.lib
To make sure that it can find it
But other than that we're good to go.
So now, if we go to our program and we run it...
Take out the breakpoint that I set there
You can see that our app now actually prints
Something on the screen. This is Handmade Hero.  Handmade Hero.
Now that is completely uninteresting to me.
I would much rather see some  sprites flying around the screen.
But.
Like I said, there is a lot of drudgework in getting a project up and running.
And we had to do that all tonight.
So in order to keep this stream
To only an hour I will...
Even though I would love to go spend the next hour so we can actually put
Some graphics on the screen
I am not going to do that, I am going to stop.
We will do that tomorrow.
And honestly, I guess I would say that went pretty well
Because we got everything out of the way
That we need to get out of the way to build, run, and have fun on Windows.
So from here, tomorrow
At 8:00 pm, pacific time, again
We will, probably be able to, I think
Open a Window and draw some stuff to it.
We may not get to user input yet
But I think we'll be able to draw, open a Window, draw stuff to it
And the day after that, we'll get user input for sure.
Basic user input but user input nonetheless.
So.
With that
I'd like to thank everyone for joining us for the first edition
The very first episode of Handmade Hero.
It has been delightful, even though it was drudgework today.
Which is what happens at the beginning of every project, I'm afraid.
Even though it was drudgework today
I still enjoyed going through it with you, and I hope
That you will come back tomorrow when we will do something
Frankly, a lot more exciting.
But
We will still be dealing with Windows a little bit
So we're still not quite out of the drudgework.
It will be more exciting because at least we'll actually see things happenning, but
The real excitement will probably pick up
In a week or so when we're off Windows and actually just dealing
With all fun game code
And rendering code which is just so much more exciting.
It's why I like to do it, instead of sitting around programming Windows all day.
If you would like to  be on the source tree
Or if you already are on the source tree
You can preorder the game here and you will get it.
It will give you an email
So for those of you who got that email, there's a link in there.
And what I will do is tonight I will  upload this code, this setup that we made
I will upload that
And so you can go back to that email that you got, with that link in it
Which you should bookmark because you can go back to it all the time and download the code.
You can go there, you can download that code and you can be setup just like this
So that you can see everything that we did.
I know I went fast through everything today
And we're gonna be going fast  through things.
That's just what we're gonna have to do
To actually get through  a meaningful amount of stuff
In a reasonable amount of time.
But
While we're going fast I think
It's easy if you can go back to the source code, look through it yourself
Think about each individual thing, what did he say about this?
Make sure that you're comforable with it, if you're not comforable with it, ask questions
Go read that MSDN, get comfortable there, play around with it
Call some other stuff, change this MessageBoxEx
Play with the build, play with the compiler, do all that stuff
Because really, the way that you're gonna learn is not just by watching me.
What I do here on the stream is  basically showing you sort of the backbone
Showing you how to make the game sort of like by example.
But what's really gonna solidify it for you is you trying it yourself
And you doing these things yourself.
So you should go back now and try all of the things that I just did.
All of that stuff.
Try it yourself, play around with it yourself.
Make the mistakes, make the same mistakes that I did, make different mistakes.
And really get comfortable with that stuff.
And if you do that every day, just spend an hour or two redoing this stuff that I did
And learning about them, that's really gonna be what solidifies it for you.
'Cause if you just watch me
I mean if you're just entertained by watching me code a game, that's great
There's no problem with that.
But if you really wanna learn  how to do this stuff
Definitely go through.
Do it yourself.
Ask questions, go on the interntet, find resources, just do some reading
Really soak that stuff in
Because that's what's really gonna make the difference
When you actually go and do it yourself
And sort of struggle through it a little bit and go:
Oh, what did he do there? Oh, right he did this, go back to the video, see what's going on.
That process is what's gonna really drill it into your brain and then you're just gonna know it
And you're gonna have it down cold.
So that's really the thing to do and I encourage everyone to do it.
So, that's it for this stream.
There will now be about 30 minutes of Q&amp;A.
And I will stop the recording now so that we can have two separate streams on youtube
And so people can sort of jump between Q&amp;A and the regular.
So, I will see you back here  in just a few seconds for the Q&amp;A.