hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream today we actually left ourselves
in a pretty obvious situation from last
week we implemented some explicit room
placement code and we just didn't get a
chance to really use it we typed it all
in but we haven't debugged it yet and so
what we want to do today is just debug
that code that's it that's that's what
we want to do and then we can start
expanding on it and seeing where how we
want to move forward with how rooms get
placed in the generative part of the
engine at the moment today date is day
449 so start with day 440 it's code if
you're following along at home I'm sure
everyone knows that by now so probably
don't need to say it but so if we go
ahead and build the game we actually
don't crash or anything or crashes I
don't know that why we would crash but
we don't assert in the placement code or
anything like that but you can see that
we don't for some reason the camera gets
placed sort of as if there was nothing
to place it on or as if we don't know
where the hero should go or something
like that which is weird because if you
look you can see that some things got
placed so there is something strange
going on I'm not sure what and that is
our job for today is to debug this and
figure out why we're getting this sort
of strange situation occurring so I'm
just gonna go ahead and start with that
and that's gonna be our job for today
and then based on how long it takes us
to get everything working we'll see we
may end up with some time to do
something additional
we don't really know though so we'll see
about that a little bit later on um so
if you remember how this code works
we set up went in sort of the end of the
code here we return a result code which
is basically saying here's where this
stuff is that you may want to use in the
outside code and the way that works is
you know we call okay so nevermind this
this obviously now makes perfect sense
so we just never implemented that it's
just still sitting here with a
hard-coded placement so that's that's
why that's got to be why we we
actually put the camera anywhere where
the game could successfully start up
probably right this initial camera P is
just wrong so what we want to do is when
we get this orphanage back we want to
use that information to actually put the
camera in like the middle of the room
right that's what we that's what we
would like to do and so to set the
initial camera P there what we'd want to
do is use the information that we've got
on the room which is the we've got the
volume of the room right there so what
we want to do is is set that initial
camera P to something in a more sensible
way so what I can do here is just say
all right let's take a look at the gen
William of the heroes room so that is
here a bedroom ticket set so once we
have that we should be able to come up
with those chunk positions really easily
right we can just say that this this
where do we put that in here there you
go so we can just say that like we've
got the min and the max here if we want
to we can just use like the min plus the
max over to or something like that
right so we just start the camera in the
middle like this so in terms of
tile-based positions that should just do
it right in Africa so that if that
actually was the only problem will be he
fairly uninteresting so we will be doing
other stuff today but we don't know if
there might be more to it than that
anyway so let me grab out the volume
here like I said oh no I didn't grab the
volume and then the hero rooms min and
Max there should be oh these are not
actually gen VIII's we should probably
fix that I don't know if now is the time
to do it
but it seems like we want to sort of
consolidate those two anyway that should
start the camera now actually looking at
at the actual room where the hero is
supposed to be in theory anyway so let's
see if we can get that working and so
the hero is there actually and again I'm
not sure why we're lower down that
should set the Z to something correct I
would think not sure what the rest of
the stuff here is doing we don't use any
of this could probably get rid of most
of it now in fact this stuff can kind of
go away we really don't need most of
that but I messed up in there because I
don't really know why that wouldn't work
it we should be able to set it to the
center and have it work but the initial
camera P I'm not really sure much about
how it gets handled anymore we haven't
looked at that code in a while so I
don't know if maybe there's something
weird about that that doesn't actually
work properly why don't I just trace
that through and then we can see I'm
gonna go ahead and set to a debug build
so I can step through the code and see
all the variables easily so let's stop
at create world and we'll just see here
in create worlds that's not the great
world I meant I meant this one when we
get this back right here I'm gonna just
inspect it really quickly just to make
sure it all makes sense and we're not
passing anything silly but it looked
like it was putting us in the right
place so I think we're okay here's where
I put that room that's that's the the
basic idea there and so we can sort of
see if we place ourselves somewhere
sensible relative that so our max of one
there well these are chunk indices
actually so to be honest it's a little
bit harder to look at let me go ahead
and and verify that they're correct on a
on a tile basis because that we actually
know more about
okay sue if I jump in here I should now
be able to see what we actually passed
12 negative 56 0 so that's what we
actually said we were gonna that's where
we wanted everything to be right and so
let's make sure that that actually makes
sense with the hero room so if the min
and the max is 10 to 14 then 12 does
make a lot of sense right that's right
in the middle
that's SEC what we expect negative 56 is
right in the middle from negative 59
tonight of 54 there so that's actually
quite good 2 and 0 is exactly what we
would have expected for Minzy so it
looks like we're placing the camera in
the correct place relative to the hero's
bedroom that seems correct to me
so given that I'm gonna go ahead and say
I want to then look at the world crease
I've been the room creation code because
we still sort of have and we don't
really know whether we want to keep this
long term but we still have this idea
over here of the sort of room area right
like a volume that the room looks at to
figure out where to place the camera and
so what I would like to do is make sure
that that is still getting set in a
sensible fashion because I don't know
that it is we set the X count wide count
and Z count to be how big the room was
and we know these things here Z count
being two is a little bit weird
I'm not really sure how we ended up with
a room with a dimension of two I would
like to know ah so we're still doing it
looks it looks like so quickly I would
like to just address this because I
don't really want that it looks like the
way that we're making these rooms at the
moment when we set the size it looks
like we're setting the size so that they
actually have like the Minzy and the
Maxie are set apart right so I don't
know why that is exactly I guess our
room placement code is doing something a
little wonky there so it's not a problem
that they're too too high like too tall
because we allow rooms to do that but it
shouldn't be doing that
so I would like to fix that because that
is erroneous so something's messed up
there so if we take a look at place room
a long edge this code when it actually
goes to deal with the the max on - you
can see it just copies from the original
room all the time so when we do our
initial room placement yeah so required
dimensions this just looks like we
messed up it looks like because the this
is we said that our dimensions don't
include the fact that the min and the
max see ours are equal to each other if
they encounter encompass a single tile
so this really should have looked like
this is basically what it boils down to
our initial room placement was not
correct there so now we should have a z
count that's properly set to one which
we do and now that's a little bit better
okay so it must be that we don't
properly handle that aspect
of of we with the camera for some reason
if something's too high we must be
messing it up so we're gonna have to
deal with that and look at why that's
not working properly because something
is not working properly there so I'm
gonna put it to doing here that once
we're done with what working on now
we've got some issue where the camera
gets confused about that or we're
creating it wrong we should go fix that
because there's just something not
working there and it should be working
we we don't we don't have any reason to
believe that that should occur it should
have just handled that room just fine
there's nothing illegal about doing that
in our name okay so if we look at what
we've created now this is our orphanage
and I think what's kind of interesting
about this again we have to give
ourselves a bit of a high-five so
remember we told this thing just about
which rooms we wanted and what sides
they were on of the other rooms and what
you could see is it laid it out exactly
like my diagram so we did a good job
congratulations right I don't know if
you remember my diagram here here it is
right we decided to not do the side
alley yet and to just do this sort of
structure for things and that's exactly
what it made right it made exactly the
orphanage that I wanted main room to
side rooms four bedrooms here three hero
bedrooms here the hallways the garden
out back the the forest area and whatnot
up there so it actually laid all that
out properly so really all we have to do
at this point now is we need to make the
doorways in between the rooms be placed
because what we did at the end of the
last stream is we placed all the rooms
but we never actually put any code to
put in the doors so
unlike the original code here which put
in the doors this doesn't put in the
tourist and when I say doors I mean the
classic rock group with Jimmy Morrison
alright so if we want to avoid a drug
overdose but still want to have doors in
in the room and play on The Tonight Show
or get banned from The Tonight Show for
saying lyrics that the public at large
at that time felt were untoward we can
go ahead and look at this piece of code
and place the actual doors in when we
place connections so remember this code
here it loops over the connections that
a room has and places those connections
places rooms to match those connections
so we're already at the point where we
know exactly what we would do the only
problem is we never put in the code here
to set this connections actual spacing
now we did that in the other test layout
routine it's this code right here so you
see how we intersect the two rooms and
then do it that way so in theory I think
that should work the same we should be
able to just use this code or a modified
variant thereof to create our apertures
between rooms and then sort of tweak it
from there so let's just take a look and
see what happens if we drop this in here
once we've placed these rooms we can
create a volume that is the intersection
of this room and the other room that
it's being connected to at that point we
know exactly where they overlap and we
can try to figure out where we want to
put the door so in order to put the door
in what we want to do is use what was
the edge that actually abutted these two
together right so we know that the edge
axis that we're talking about here the
edge axis is the one that we're moving
along I believe right is that correct
yeah so the edge access is
axis we're moving along that's the axis
along which we want to shrink the door
so that it doesn't take up the entire
room now
we could take up the entire room right
so we could say we could just say the
door is the entire aperture between them
right and that's just seeing look we're
it's a completely what's the oh it's
sorry it's base room and room so what
that says it's just intersect these two
volumes put the door like in their
entire intersection and what that would
do is they will be less like doors at
that point well of course didn't work so
that's your relevant I guess um oh it
didn't work because we don't overlap our
rooms in this placement scheme that's
actually why
okay so so first question do we want to
overlap the room walls or not I don't
think we do so why were we doing that
before so never mind because yeah this
intersection we need to expand those two
volumes first in order to actually
compute that intersection so that's not
gonna help us at all ah I know why it
worked so this intersection we were
doing it right before this intersection
does the intersection one of the axes
will not intersect that's the one where
they abut right and so what we were
doing before is we then broaden that
notion here right we took that place
where they wouldn't have overlapped and
we made we gave it some volume there so
never mind it makes perfect sense
I don't yeah I don't know why I didn't
remember that we did this correctly
actually so this intersection will
produce no actual intersected volume but
it will produce the correct bounds for
that non intersection right it'll
basically prove
a zero volume rectangle right at the
aperture between the two rooms so all we
have to do is expand that one in either
direction in order to make the room we
want now the axis that it's going to use
again the edge access is the one running
in the direction we actually placed the
rooms along so that's not the one we
want so what we want instead is that
alternate access now we know what the l2
next is we its access a we already
determined what that other actions axis
was right and you can see us placing the
room that sort of abutment there so we
know here we can actually do in this set
up here we can actually take the axis a
and grab out what those two values are
now I don't want to do it this way I
think this was a stupid way to do it
what I want to do instead is I want to
just take the door and I want to take
its minimum access because what I know
about that is that's actually right at
the aperture the min and the max will be
set counter to each other so the max
will be like one smaller and the min in
fact we can actually just look at this
directly just you can see what I'm
talking about
after this intersection takes place I
just want to show you what I mean
because I'm saying a lot of things here
and you know they're pseudo clear in my
head but they might not be in your head
I say pseudo clear because I messed it
up the first time so obviously I did not
remember how we were actually doing this
so clear may be a bit of a exaggeration
all right so if I go ahead and just
write this code here so you can look at
what I mean when we get these min min
door max door things out here I just got
out what that axis was that's not
actually being laid out I'm gonna go
ahead and step into here this is what
place room is a long edge so if we come
to to place rooms a long edge and we
kind of hop through here what we can see
is that I need to compile debug mode or
probably Visual Studio will have no idea
where those values are where are they I
don't
I'll never know I can't possibly find
them since Visual Studio alright so
coming here and I look at my two values
along that axis and what I should see is
like I said they're just one past each
other right so that's the way that the
intersection tells us there is no
overlap right there right at the edge so
the men of this door in the max apt or
if they were if they both were zero then
it would be one long right along zero it
would be one long but it's not
overlapping so that's why it's zero
negative one right so all we really need
to do here is just flip these right we
just need to switch which ones we're
thinking about here so we can basically
say okay if the min door that was the
lowest value that was actually being
included there so we can do like the min
door and the min door plus one would
give us a two wide aperture now I have
to think about how the intersection code
works to see which one of those we want
but either we use the min door or the
max door let me let's let's take a look
at which one we want right here's the
room ball here's the base Rimbaud so
we're coming from the base room and
which axis are we talking about which
one did was it placing on this time oops
why so look 8 y we have 0 2 7 on the
base room and negative 16 2 negative 1
right so we want negative 1 to 0 okay so
what we want to do is we want to say we
just want to use the max to the min so
we just want to flip them right that's
all we need to do we just need to flip
them and then we've covered the the
swath right and that's all we need to do
so if I come in here to the world
gencode and just do that what I just
said
we're just say okay the min becomes the
max the max becomes the min for now that
should be sufficient now we should be
placing doors down like right in in the
area where rooms overlap right and and
that's what we want so now when I look
at it we have one more thing to do
right we're almost there but what you
can see is I don't think we're we didn't
switch the door placement code because
remember we made a change to a big
change last time last episode where we
switched to doing inclusive bounds I
don't think we ever changed this
gentleman right here so I don't know if
we did if we didn't so we'll have to see
but it looks like even though this think
clearly net oh nope maybe we did I typed
it in wrong typo so either we either
this will then work or we still have to
go update is in volume to handle it so
we'll see which one it is alright so it
was just a typo so we must have updated
is in volume last time as well right so
if I go ahead and switch the build there
to optimized I can go ahead and hop
around now and and go through the
various rooms so if I want to come out
here this is the hallway write this out
back this would be the garden and now
would be a good time to to start looking
at that camera code remember I said one
of the reason I want to do this so we
can start work on the camera code you
can see now the camera code is should it
should be zooming out right so we want
to start working on that code so we can
we can do that properly so we come up
here we can go to this other hallway
that we made right and and yeah so you
can see now this is doing essentially
exactly what I wanted the camera and the
lighting are up you know you can see how
they're off they're not doing the right
things and that's why I wanted to get
these maps working so now we can once we
sort of are a little bit further along
with the map building we can go just
make the lighting so it properly
encompasses the visible area and make
the camera so it properly zooms to
whichever part of a room we're trying
do you can also see there's like a bit
of a confusion right there the camera
can't decide right because we're right
on the edge you can actually see that we
need to adjust those volumes a little
bit right because the camera can't
decide where to be at that point and you
get that bug so you can see this is
doing it is basically doing exactly what
I wanted right as this starts to come
together we can start to finalize those
various systems that we're talking about
but we're in the middle of the
generation code right now I say we push
a little bit further on that because we
don't need to play the game right now we
can build little worlds and not actually
have be able to have like the lighting
work properly and that's fine right
although we probably will need a way to
zoom around a little bit more quickly so
we can look at other things here but
that's sort of a separate issue so we'll
have to adjust our zoom out zoom ins
about camera code so we can get a little
bit better sense of that in the meantime
anyway so if we keep going on this what
we want to do now is say well okay yeah
that's nice but that's not how we
actually probably want doors to be we
don't want doors to be the entire
aperture of where two rooms intersect we
want to maybe just use like the center
one so you're hopping out through a one
wide door the way you might expect a
regular that you know game to be right
you know something a little bit more
like what you would expect at the moment
for from a standard game so in order to
do that what we want to do is make those
room setups should be right here what we
want to do here is make this so that in
addition to setting the min and Max to
encompass the to wide swath where they
were they we want the rooms to connect
we need to adjust the edge axis now so
that edge access is too wide as the
problem we're using the entire length of
the rooms where we're using the entirety
of where the two rooms overlap to
produce that value and we don't really
want to do that right what we'd rather
do is just take like say the center one
so in order to do that what we could do
is say you know door edge equals the
centroids so we could say like you know
oops the doors
min of the edge access plus the doors
max of the edge access / - right so the
mid the midpoint would be where the door
would start and then what we can do is
reset these so like the edge access this
min will be the drawer edge and the max
will also be the door edge so we just
get a one wide door running down the
middle of where they overlap and if they
if there's not an even point in the
middle of just pick one of the other
right it'll pick the lesser of the two
so you know if it's not if it's not an
odd number of tiles it can't be right in
the middle it'll just pick something to
either side and that's fine right um so
now you can see what happens when we've
just got one wide doors in here right
and so when we hop through here now
we've got what would you know sort of be
more traditionally thought of as a door
to a room right so there's a single one
one wide thing and we hop through it and
that's what we get right now one of the
things that I'm noticing too while I'm
looking at this is the eccentricity of
that perspective projection is maybe a
little bit high I like having that
perspective feel to the game it's kind
of nice and it gives it a little bit of
an additional Flair than a normal 2d
game doesn't have but it may be a little
bit much because it starts to become and
I'll show you what was making me think
that it starts to become a little bit
problematic in cases like this where
like that door is very hard to see here
right so in terms of where we set up our
perspective projection there we may want
to go ahead and tune that down a little
bit so what I'm talking about is you
know I believe that's over in world mode
where we set up the camera we've got
sort of a particular opinion about that
focal length right and you can see here
we've got that set up that we're saying
something particularly specific about
and if I was to change what that focal
length is that that would be something
that we might want to be more specific
about so here you can see a set it for
the cuts
I'm not sure where we set it for I'm not
sure where we set it otherwise looks
like right here so it looks like we're
just setting it to that right um so if I
look at what we're looking at here I
don't know where are we here it's active
MSP I don't know if we can just change
this value yeah we can um so it may be
that we can just go ahead and change
this value and then set the camera to be
closer down so you know if we take a
focal length and and change it to some
different values we will get different
amounts of eccentricity when we zoom in
so maybe we want to just zoom out the
camera a little bit from here let me go
ahead and see about that so distance
above
so focus on room looks like it's not
even used at the moment so if we take a
look at how far above the camera we're
placing I'm sorry how far above the
target replacing what you can sort of
see here about how we do that is there's
a certain degree of of manhandling that
we allowed to be done to the camera here
right so you could set the camera to
special locations that you want to be
and I think it generally just sets the
target and then the target offset Z it
looks like it was just hard coded to 8
right again
like I said this code so if I set that
to 4 we should zoom in right yeah so let
me set it to something higher right so
what you can see based on what I did
there and and we've got some other
things we'd have to fix like the fog
distances and stuff like that but what
you can see what I did there do you see
how it reduces the eccentricity of like
I can now see that door more clearly
because of how the focal length changes
how much perspective there is at in any
given piece right so when you set it
like this you end up setting that
eccentricity down quite a bit compared
to what it would have been with with a
different focal length the focal length
of the lens it basically controls that
eccentricity to a large extent right and
so that's something that that we want to
sort of be aware of
and I don't know maybe I tuned it down a
little bit too much maybe I didn't I
don't know I want this game to be fairly
top-down because I want you to be able
to see pretty clearly what you're
hitting and what you're not one of my
big complaints actually with Binding of
Isaac a game which I quite like a lot is
just it's kind of hard to see what your
bullets hit because it's so up and down
I'm so so lateral in terms of the way
that it draws the characters that your
brain gets a little confused sometimes
about that I find and so that's kind of
something that I was hoping to maybe get
more towards the hotline Miami
perspective right which is straight
top-down so I want to kind of have a bit
of a mix between those two I want to try
and find a happy medium between those
two again not super care I don't super
care about that that much because I am
NOT a game designer so you know that's
more of a game designers argument to
have I'm just talking about my personal
preference there and I think that would
be better right
for what I what I was wanted to see so
that's that's all I'm talking about so
here we now have pretty much everything
working the way that I would expect I do
think that eccentricity is good dial
down a little bit so I think I will
leave it that way for now just dialing
it down again just that little bit and
now we've got room layout code that
works so what we can do too is we can we
can't expand on this now to produce a
fairly large world if we wanted to write
like even just right off the bat we
could just generate an entirely you know
a dungeon area and all that kind of
stuff
so maybe we can go ahead and do that and
play around that a little bit and then
what I want to do is start looking at
how we want to do more complex
replacement right and we can choose how
we want to do this like I saying it's
interesting that the camera doesn't
doesn't move there did you notice that
like you can't hop back through this
this thing yeah
so camera really wants Cochran so I'm a
ping back to the camera lighting stuff
first and get it to a place where it's a
little bit more playable to explore and
maybe we want to put some of the
graphics into at that point so we can
differentiate our rooms a little bit
better things like that so you know at
this point I'm not gonna promise about
any sort of order we're doing things and
I might bounce around quite a bit
because I just want to bring things up
to a playable state and how we do that
is really usually best left up to
intuition right whatever seems to be the
most annoying thing at that time is
usually the best thing to focus on right
so yeah I think we kind of want to move
move intuitively from here at the moment
I'm thinking that I might want to just
generate some more stuff and the other
thing I might want to do is produce some
way that we can view the world more
intelligently than this so right right
now I can't do anything with the debug
camera even to let go look at other
regions of the world and that's kind of
annoying so being able to like click and
teleport somewhere to inspect it or I
don't know what putting in a debug
camera system is probably gonna be
important all right let's keep going
here so if I want to to sort of continue
along this theme in my world gencode now
like I've got an orphanage layout piece
right and what you can see from the
orphanage layout stuff the way I it's
important to sort of mention the reason
I did this way this is a modular
component actually at this point right
so if you wanted multiple orphanages you
just could have them okay and so for
example let's suppose I just want to
show you the power of doing things in
this in this
where I create something and then it
gets laid out in a secondary pass what I
can now do is say oh you know maybe I
want to orphanages all right so I have
orphanage 1 &amp; 2 well if I if all I did
was that then what's gonna happen is I'm
only gonna get like one of them right so
when I actually lay this out I'm only
gonna get one of these orphanages and
the other orphanage is not going to be
there and furthermore depending on which
one gets laid out the hero room might be
non-existent right which i think is what
probably happened there if that makes
sense so when it goes to place the
camera it's gonna be like a bunkie in
whatever because if you remember the way
that our layout code worked in Gen is it
starts and it crawls out from a room
it's whatever this room first room is
right now you know maybe we want to be
more specific about that
maybe we want to do this so maybe I
wanna do something like this and then I
could at least guarantee it of course we
need to do it here yeah when we actually
do the work here we could pass it in so
we say oh you know what I know I'm gonna
place people in the heros bedroom so
that's where I want you to start laying
out the world right because we know we
want a seed from there and if I did that
then we would always get that room
placed properly right and and off we
would go although that looks like we
placed looks like we placed multiple
[Music]
it's a little bit odd so we're getting
some z-fighting there
did it actually place both of them
somehow
it should not have right cuz the crawler
should not have laid the other one out
hold on a second I'm freaking out right
now it should have had no way to lay out
that first orphanage I wanna make sure
I'm not Oh
so that's just happening why are we
getting why are we getting z-fighting
stuff happening there I think I made do
I have a bug in the did it oh did it
just place the I did nevermind it just
decided to place two rooms on top of
each other there okay so we have a bug
we should address first I'm glad I
looked at that because that's like
that's wrong so we do have one bug you
can notice there should be three
bedrooms there's only two why is that
it's because one of them was already
placed so what we need to do here as
well right because this initial room
just gets seated down and then this room
got placed and then when it went to
place things along this edge it just
started at the top of the edge and it
never checks for overlap right so
another thing we're gonna have to do is
checking for overlap right we need to
figure out whether there's already a
room in a place so that we don't place
another room there so that's something
we need to be able to do to avoid this
so I'm gonna put a to-do in for that as
well
I'll ignore it for now because that's
not gonna affect what I was about to do
either way but I want to be aware of it
so anyway back to our story so if I have
two orphanages well I only get one
orphanage anyway because I only started
laying out at one and they're not
connected but I could just connect these
two right I could just say all right
look you know I know that orphanages
have a forest entrance and a hero
bedroom let me just connect the forest
entrance of one with the hero's bedroom
of the other and I'll say which
direction I want that to go in right
we've got this idea of directions I'll
just say that it's a northbound
connection secure out the top of the
forest entrance and you come in the
bottom of the heroes bedroom of the
other orphanage right I believe we all
said passage in there right yeah so now
if I run this code and I start walking
right what I should find is that when I
get out to the forest path area which is
right here the other orphanage in there
you can see it is just attached right I
really wish I knew why we can't lie it
doesn't detect those sometimes that's
going to be something we're gonna have
to fix sooner rather than later but
anyway point being so I like the the way
that we've set up this system because I
feel like it gives us a really good way
to create pieces that can then just be
thrown together and it means that you
know once we create a thing that
produces a useable like piece of a
dungeon for example we can just call
that right and be done with it
okay that's really weird I don't know
why those changeovers don't seem to
happen properly right like why the
camera thing doesn't seem to think that
that was a point that it needed to to
deal with I have no idea but anyway
that's neither here nor there we'll be
looking at the camera a little bit later
on so anyway I really like that aspect
of it because now you can just like plop
down orphanages as often as you want to
plop them down and you know there's it
just all kind of works I also think I
may want to let me see what happens if I
reduce the size of these rooms to make
them not quite so big it might create
all kinds of problems for us here but
I could also make the default distance
there be a little higher just as a
stopgap so now you may wonder why BQ at
this wall that's because there's
actually two rooms on top of each other
right that's the problem we have one we
can travel through and one we can
thankfully it always picks the one it
can travel through with the can so that
was good but now you can see there's a
second orphanage up here right and we
can you know this can go on all day we
can have as many of those as we want we
can have lots and lots and lots of
orphanages in fact we could try
stressing our rest of our systems out if
we want to just to see what happens by
just making a ton of them right and
again this is the nice part about
procedural stuff it's it's free to do
right there's really no cost to like
stressing the system or testing the
system so one thing I can do is just say
like okay well how many orphanages do
you want we'll just say I don't know
let's try 64 orphanages and then all we
really need to do is just say there's
such a thing as an orphanage
we create one we create I guess a
previous one like so so we basically
just track whichever that one is and we
just do this every time so each time we
create an orphanage we just like tack it
on right and off we go so if I run one
of those in theory we know what happened
there can you tell me what that crash
was Oh hmm all right so our debug system
runs out of space to record the timings
for this which I guess I can understand
looks like add entity to hash let me get
rid of that because we really don't need
to mark that
basically we will run out of space in
our debug log because our debug log is
only so big use chunk space don't really
know why we were timing all these we
must have been looking for something
they don't need to be timed for any
particular reason we must have been
trying to figure out if something why
something was slow ah I see because
there's a ticket mutex in there that's
why for multiple sim regions to work at
the same time that's what that was for
so anyway in theory now we just have
like infinite orphanages going you know
a lot of warfare interests uh and in
theory they all just work right and now
the world is actually quite large so
large that without something
constructive to do in it you would never
walk through it all right if I've sat
here and walked through it all we would
get really really bored and so we can
just keep going on and on and on right
but the point about the programming
aspect of this which is the part that
I'm actually you know trying to show you
is just that once you construct things
out of functional pieces like this and I
mean function should say procedural
pieces not functional I don't mean
functional programming like that kind of
functional but once you construct things
out of procedural pieces like this it's
free to sort of and you have a then
essential routine that then tries to lay
them all out based on what you said you
can just start jamming stuff together
and it works right there's nothing
stopping you then you can just kind of
go nuts with it
right and so now out of just one call
that makes an orphanage we can make
infinite orphanages and you can walk
around them all the time and more
importantly as we add random variability
to our orphanage then each orphanage
would be different right because it's
going to roll different random numbers
for it and this is the back
Buon of making a proper procedural world
is exactly that kind of a system so now
we can start making functions that
generate other things things that we
actually want to make that reflect
gameplay elements in the world and then
those things will just be calls that we
can make when we decide in the world
needs one of those things we just make
the call and connect it up and we're
done right and so that's the kind of
backbone we're looking for and that
should give you an idea of how we want
to proceed as we go through this
procedural generation portion of the
game right okay
uh so moving on if we actually go into
the world gen park here and you'll also
notice how irrelevant the time for that
was so 64 orphanages we maybe walk
through three or four of them there so
in terms of just even if you're walking
straight through not having to do any
play or beating any enemies or anything
you know you're talking about something
like probably what ten minutes or twenty
minutes even just a walk from one side
of the other you can see that it's
trivial to create arbitrarily large
things now without costing like there's
no there was no loading waiting thing
happening there it's just there right so
we're not even in danger of costing too
much time we don't have to put place a
little like reticulating splines thing
up on the screen yet either
we're not in danger that at all even
creating as much of a world as we
probably ever will you know I don't know
how big an individual playthrough of
handmade hero is going to be but it's
supposed to be the kind of game where
you play multiple runs of it not where
one run takes an infinity of time so
it's supposed to be more like a binding
of issac sort of style or spelunky or
something like that where an individual
run through the game takes a couple
hours at most
so at that whatwhat's what we're seeing
now you can kind of see hopefully even
if we crank this number very high we're
just not in a lot of danger right and
really the only thing that's giving us
trouble is
our the fact that our debug code runs
out of space to record everything we did
I'm gonna get rid of that in begin
ticket mutex there as well
um so the other thing that I think is
really good and I think we should pat
ourselves on the back for this as well
is you can already see our architecture
is pre useful at this point as well
because you can sort of see that we're
not having any trouble managing the fact
that the number of entities in the world
right now is incredibly large right so
each one of these orphanages is several
thousand entities because every floor
tile is an entity right and we've got
now you know somewhere on the order of
probably half a million entities in the
game and nobody cares right the speed is
totally fine and we could just crank
that number all day long and it won't
matter why because we were smart about
how we set up our worlds so that we only
consider a portions of them at the time
and so we don't have to worry about the
fact that once we start dumping millions
of entities into the system it doesn't
roll over and die it's just like fine I
don't care put as many of these as you
want if you've got memory to store them
I'll be happy to use them furthermore we
actually even made our system even more
robust than that our system actually
could support swapped at disk which
nowadays is irrelevant
I mean machines have 16 gigabytes of
memory how much entities you're really
gonna have right so it's kind of
irrelevant but it's it's worth noting
that even before we've even optimized
our any system at all remember any
system is this giant fatty thing that
just and these are huge right we haven't
even looked at making those efficient in
any way doesn't matter the system just
handles it it's it's it's not an issue
right such that if we were to count how
many entities we actually have I bet we
would be surprised at what the number
was right I don't know how high it is
but you know let's say we looked at it
there it is create and see or allocate
entity ID so if we just looked at
allocate entity ID what we can see is
the world has a running counter so if I
just stop the game in the middle
somewhere right so here we are and I say
all right just let's you know let's stop
here
then if I come out and just look for
something that'll have the world in it
so here's the world node here's the
world we should in here be able to look
at what the entity storage ID is you can
see it here so it's a quarter of a
million entities in the system right now
and again it just doesn't care right
it's it's like a complete non-issue and
so again I think that's really nice
like we architected our system well and
we anticipated some of those needs
because we knew we want to be a big game
potentially where could have lots of
rooms and lots of entities and lots of
people doing things in the game and
whatever else so good on us for that we
now know that's actually true and I'm
assuming we could crank this number
fairly high and really not be in that
much danger I don't know that we need to
crank it any higher than it is right now
but we can certainly see what that ends
up being and I think if we turn off the
debug system so we don't have to worry
about that overflowing which again that
is set up just for debug it's not ever
summon skyship we could see so if we
wanted a million entities we'd do
something like that I think and just see
whether a million entities costs any
problems again I don't know whether the
debug system needs to have some of its
recording taken out of there it still
does right and so I don't know how we
really want to look at that maybe what
I'll do because I don't really feel like
taking too much more of that out maybe
I'll just set
internal to zero so it just won't they
just won't look at that anymore debug
string and HUD timed function look like
they don't have it looks like we never
goes in there you just go ahead and add
those so we want those to go away right
in this mode because they are no longer
functional so if I run it without the
debug system I think we should be fine
and oh and I guess we get full screen at
that point as well
I'm gonna do the exact same thing I did
before which is I'm gonna look in here
and see what that what the value is it
should be something like a million yeah
uh so I think you know we did what I
wanted to do when I was showing how to
build that system which is that even
though currently our entity system is
complete nonsense right we have not done
anything to it I mean look at this thing
we just stuffed wit every wand in there
it's got a raise of stuff in here it's
got the lighting storage for every
entity in the world
even people who are nowhere near the
visible area right we have done nothing
to this it's huge and unnecessary
doesn't matter we can still make a ton
of them because hey computers are fast
to have lots of memory these days so as
long as we make a system that only
considers a small number at a time it's
free to just have a ton of them that we
don't see right that we don't deal with
it just works and so we take a little
bit of a startup hit here when they're
all being created when a million of
these are being made but it's not that
big of a hit and once we're ready to go
we're ready to go right and now we can
walk through a thousand orphanages if or
if each orphanage takes ten seconds to
walk through I don't know it probably
took a little more intense I guess five
more like 20
and scoops don't use that use the real
calculator right if we figure 20 seconds
times 10,000 24 orphanages so we say
that's how many minutes that takes
that's when the hours it takes it would
take five and a half hours walking from
end to end to just cover all of those
right so that to me is a totally
reasonable proof of concept there it
just says look we did it right we're
good to go
we can make any world we want in this
thing and it's never gonna roll over and
die on us so awesome right very very
good and I think you could probably just
keep cranking this number on and on and
on and your startup time would just be
bad right because then you would at some
point we that uh noctem eyes entity
thing is gonna cause a problem right oh
and our and we do have this weird world
structure we added here once we add too
many rooms we didn't actually make that
that's not a real thing yet so that
would hold us back right this thing here
[Music]
so eventually we don't really want a fix
two rooms right we want to handle that
properly but that was just some test
code we were putting in there so we can
outline rooms and stuff like that but
anyway so in theory you know again this
number just cranks as high as we want
and probably we just won't have much
trouble with it I don't know because
again we never really need to get up to
this high but just it's fun to play
around with it and just make sure so we
can kind of see did we break anything
did we do anything stupid and it looks
like the answer is we really didn't like
it seems like we did it pretty
reasonably well and if we look at how
many enemies are in the world now I yeah
so now we've got four and a half million
entities in this world and it's just
fine with that right so I think I think
that's great I think we did what we
needed to do and now I think we've got a
good solid system that we can just keep
building on and
it's never gonna it's never going to
come back and invite us like it would if
you know if we hadn't thought through
those things okay so now that we've got
that sort of testing out of the way I
don't want to create an infinity of
orphanages that is nobody's idea of a
good time so let's just go ahead and and
get back to the basics here single
orphanage and instead of creating more
rooms today which I think we might want
to do tomorrow I think I'll do that
we've got about 20 minutes left and I
would like to address the bug that we
have or one of them right off the bat
because it's going to become important
pretty soon and that is this bug of two
rooms getting place on top of each other
right so you can see right here we've
got two rows placed on top of each other
that's what does e Fighting's coming
from there's supposed to be three rooms
right so there's supposed to be a hot
second let me get our mouse pointer back
here
so there supposed to be three rooms also
you know it's interesting but we haven't
looked at the profile here have we yeah
so out of these rooms we know that we've
messed up because there's supposed to be
another hero's bedroom right there
should have been a third heroes bedroom
here somewhere it's not there why isn't
it there what happened well what
happened was is once we place a hero a
bedroom there at the outset as our seed
room and say generate the rest of the
world from here it then does exactly
what we told it to do it looks at the
rooms connected to the hero's bedroom it
finds one room which is this hallway it
places that hallway relative to the
hero's bedroom right so it looks and
goes okay walk along that edge place
eros bedroom there's no other things to
place there so we're done then it goes
let me place all the rooms connected to
the hallway which is exactly what we
want to do right that's fine but then
immediately after there after it we'll
look back and go oh there's other rooms
I haven't placed along this edge right I
haven't placed like this room so I need
to place the rooms along the edge of
this hallway it then starts placing
those rooms it goes one two three it
won't move the existing hero's bedroom
that's placed here right it won't try to
place that so it's already placed
it'll only place the other two bedrooms
and it will place them starting at the
head end and moving backwards that
places the second here of bedroom right
on top of the first one
why because nothing in that routine ever
looks to see if there's already room
there now this would be a problem even
if we didn't do the ping-pong even if we
didn't place a room go to a new room and
then come back and skip that room and
place two other rooms and happen to
place over it would be problem in
general why would be a problem general
well think about what would happen if
let's say there were some rooms off of
this room like a room here and then a
room here and here and here or something
that curve
well that may create a little tail that
would like intersect the rooms that are
here and so we would need to know that
we can't put a room there because
there's already something there and we
should try to shift the rooms somewhere
else right so a very minor modification
we can make to the strategy to begin
with to start getting our room placement
code to be a little bit smarter and do a
little bit better work is to look at
what rooms are already there and not put
something in a place that would
intersect an existing room all right so
let's go ahead and try that what I want
to do is do exactly what I was just
saying actually I would like to start to
look at this bit here and I think we
want to sort of have a two-tiered
structure here right so we have the
chunk cash and the chunk cash is a
really great way of storing all of our
entities as you just saw it allows us to
scale to arbitrarily many entities and
be fine
so you can plug for a million eight
billion I don't care how many things you
put in there eventually you'll run on a
memory but you won't run out of
performance because we will just go
ahead and handle that nice and clean
however that chunk cache is not
particularly useful for talking about
things at room granularity and there are
times when we want to talk about things
that room granularity two times one time
is we want to be able to check for room
based abutment and collision really
quickly as part of the room generation
so that's one thing we want to have in
there and the other thing we want to
have in there is we want to have a way
of being able to show things like a map
right of the game to the player at
runtime so not just for our debugging
person but we may want to have a mini
map or a world map right because you
know
most games like the kind we're talking
about here Legend of Zelda binding of
issac these sorts of games tend to now
have mini maps or world maps that you
can switch to view and so if we want to
do something like that it's gonna be
really expensive if the only way that we
can produce that map at a high level of
zoom so like a little where look each
room is like a little tiny square or
something it's the only way you can
produce that map is by looking at all of
the entities and drawing them all that
may just be too expensive so a more
useful potential potentially way to deal
with that used to have a two tiered
structure where all of the entities and
the things that actually affect the
gameplay they're all in the chunk cache
but then we also have this separate data
structure that's just an accelerated
data structure meant to do nothing other
than mapping right so that's all it does
it does not know anything else about
anything it just has room boundaries so
that when we want to draw those it's
very quick and it could even be like
some hierarchical so that if there's two
levels of zoom like oh I'm in the
orphanage so there's an orphanage map
and I can display that very quickly
without having to pull in all of the
orphanage entities to draw the entire
orphanage that's one level and then
there's also a level above that where
the orphanage itself is just one
boundary right um so if you kind of
think about how that might go that's
what we want to start a sort look start
looking at now and we want to look at
that from the perspective of both
generation because we're generating
things in that way and needing to do
those queries that generation time to
find out whether we're overlapping
something and so on but we also want to
keep an eye towards how will we display
this to the player when we need to put
up something like a map screen and both
the mini-map kind that hovers in the
corner we may or may not want that you
don't know if we do but both back
and then the kind where we see more of a
world map like where you're not
necessarily looking at any particular
regions rooms there's just a box that
says orphanage or something right all
right
let's let's look at this a little more
closely here so if I were to imagine
because I think this is a case where we
can write the API first because our
starts the usage code first let's take a
look at what we want just for this one
situation which we now know that we have
and also let's move some of this stuff
out of here because we now have code
that we really just don't need to talk
about anymore like this stuff in here we
may want to use it for reference a
little bit later on but I kind of want
to get it out of my visual field right
so now I can comment that out and it
will be grayed out right and I can move
some of this other stuff down there as
well because I don't want to look at any
of this either because this is not
involved this is the old sort of
placeholder code we were using to just
create rooms for when we were trying to
do the engine right but it wasn't ever
really intended to be real-world gencode
but we might want to look at it at some
point in case we want to see how we did
like the stairs or something when we put
stairs and again to the generator or
something like that so I don't want to
leave it entirely I just want down there
for reference so I don't have to go
pulling through old verses of the code
to find it necessarily but I don't want
it in my way anymore so that's gone
goodbye so now if we come through here I
want to take a look at this layout code
we come through here we do our place
rooms along edge right and our place
rooms along edge is working real good
and the only problem that we're having
with it right is at some point we get to
a place right here where when we place
this volume
we accidentally romp right over an
existing room so what would we do if we
wanted to be a little bit more careful
right if we wanted to sort of place
rooms with the Mort with an eye towards
not screwing that part up well there's a
couple things so first of all we know
that we have some leeway as to where we
place rooms along an edge sometimes so
if an edge is not fully subscribed like
and what do I mean by fully subscribed
if you imagine the parameters let me go
ahead and get Milton going here Milton
by the way really an excellent drawing
package at this point I highly recommend
using Milton for your stream
illustrations really just great Sergio
has done a really nice job getting this
to a good place if you think about what
it's doing right now it has almost every
day of handmade hero is on the same
blackboard right it's nuts I mean look
at this try doing this in Photoshop like
good luck my friend you know I'm saying
to roll over and die so hard so I think
sir - you did a really great job this
thing and it has been rock-solid for me
now he fixed some of the bugs that were
in there at the effort that we're
preventing it from being a pretty smooth
user experience
he's just silky smooth now I highly
recommend it anyway I'm gonna go ahead
and dress draw what I was talking about
with some script edge strips in there so
let's just talk about edge subscription
oops
so I'm borrowing a term there just to
say that look if I've got a room and I
say that three rooms need to be on that
side it could be that those rooms
literally cannot be placed in any other
way than like just like this like if
they need one you know an entryway there
and entryway there and an entryway there
is the maximum you could have stuffed in
there right that's the best you could
have done we could say that that edge
was like fully subscribed was the term I
was sort of using my head there's
nothing you can do there's no freedom
there right so this is like fully
subscribed then there's like under
subscribed so it's like oh yeah I just
got this one thing to put there and that
means it could go anywhere right so
there's like a degree of freedom where
it could go anywhere from here to here
the door could go right and we know it
has to be on that edge so we couldn't
move it to another edge but we can put
it anywhere on the edge that we want and
then there's oversubscribed which is
just an illegal scenario right that
means the generation code announced to
us that it wanted like you know a bunch
of rooms placed here and they don't all
fit right so no matter what you do
they're gonna like overlap so this case
cannot be handled that's just an error
further up the chain like the gameplay
generation code fundamentally asks us to
create a room that cannot exist in
practice at the very least it would have
had to say that this room can stretch
right or something so we're really
talking about these two cases here which
we sort of handle now but not really
right and so try and get more towards
actually really handling these cases
correctly and again like I said we've
only got like 10 minutes or something no
week back no that's not true we've got
25 minutes we started it at 15 after
today right yeah yeah yeah so if we
actually look at this and go so I should
be able to get make make a little
progress on this today so what we want
to do is say if we want start having
these cases correctly what we need to do
is take a look
at a room and when we are going to place
it say look assuming we're
undersubscribed at all we actually could
start here and test a bunch of positions
to see where we can place the room and
if any of them work we can proceed so
what we want to do is we want to take
take this loop have it try a bunch of
positions for a room if it can and
accept anyone that works that way all we
need is a query that says can room be
you know in volume so we just asked look
here's one place we could place room
he's that legal and it's like Matt like
okay can we place it here now right now
that may not end up being the most
efficient way to do it and we may want
to do something that actually says how
far are we should have moved and so we
may make this a little bit more fancy so
we don't have to keep querying
unnecessarily so another way we could
phrase this is a query with direction
right so we could say look here's my
room I want place it here tell me where
is the first place I could place this
room in this direction so when it sees
what overlaps so it does a query to see
what this room overlaps it could go oh
well once you get here you're not
overlapping anymore so you could put it
there right and the reason to do that is
because if you think about what has to
happen one is a blind search and one's a
directed search right so in the blind
search case that is what this would be
it says look I don't know where these
other rooms might be that are
overlapping
I'm gonna try here and you're gonna give
me back a boolean answer that just says
yes or no the problem it's yes or no is
all that tells me is if this exact
location was okay when I get back and
yes from you I'm super happy
down goes the room if I get back to know
well then I don't know anything right so
I have to test literally the next
possible placement one tile over and
asked again now you may have known even
just from a single intersection the code
that's doing the query immediately knows
that's stupid because even if all it did
was exit out on the first overlap it
still knows we shouldn't try again till
here right it still knows where to try
next and that may not work as well so it
is still a search it may be that we need
to do another query to look at what else
might overlap that room but it's a much
more directed search it uses the
information that it gets back on a No to
do avoid other queries that will
obviously be no so I think what we want
to do here is is we want to set up that
API that call to give us back where to
try next it when we move to avoid lots
of little tiny queries looking for that
edge when the thing can just it knows
where the edge is
just tell us where the edges right so I
think we want to kind of go that route
with it that's all I'm trying to say so
that's what we want to start working on
now and we may not get that done before
the end of the stream but that's where
we're going and we've got all tomorrow
to do it and we should be able to have
something nice working for that tomorrow
it's just rectangle overlap testing and
then we need an acceleration structure
that to start with just for the
orphanage there are not enough
rectangles in the orphanage to even
require a spatial hierarchy so that
should allow us to do a brute force
version quickly and get working which is
what we'll try do now but then we want
to do something that's going to be a
little smart in that because
like I said if we do want to do stuff
like crank ourselves up to hundreds of
thousands of rooms which we do because
the rest of our system handles it we
shouldn't make the generator be
something that rolls over and dies at
that point so we can't be linearly
searching through all of our rooms for
overlap every time that's not going to
cut it that's a little dance for you
hope you enjoyed it okay so moving back
what I want to do now is I want to go
through here and and take a look at how
I would want to call this right given
the things that I just explained so what
you can see here is one of the things we
do is we start off at the minimum
position along the edge and that gets
started out right here and then we move
forward now this actually isn't
maximally trying all the places that we
probably should try to place things
there's actually a lot more variability
than that involved and what we may want
to do is change that scheme so in the
future
in the future we probably want to do is
take a more considerate approach where
we say look we we will pre check our
connections we'll see how many things
we're gonna try and place and then we'll
try to choose a strategy that logically
looks for where we might want to connect
rooms up right so we're gonna get more
advanced as we go right now we'll leave
it as it is because we only have one
specific bug we're going to fix but we
want that process of testing where we
want to place rooms along an edge to get
more advanced as we go because this is
pretty weak sauce right here I mean the
whole thing is weak sauce but we just
started it but that in particular is
weak sauce that we could specifically
pinpoint we know what we could do that
would be an improvement so once we get
into the connections here's our tests
for whether or not this room wants to be
placed here in the first place
placed in the first place and when we
find out that it does you can see is we
actually very specifically look at these
volumes here and start setting them
directly I want to do that I want to
start with a test volume so what I want
to do here is say Jen volume test ball
and I want to go from there so all of
these things that talk about room vol I
want to talk about test vol instead so
I'm just going to do a real quick search
or in place here like so oops I don't
want to replace base room though guess
I'm gonna have to be pretty judicious
here no no no
okay when we get to the end then I will
say that room volume equals test volume
and off we go so now I should have a
situation where I can talk about test
volume test volume at the outset can
just be nothing in particular because we
set all of its axes so really we don't
have to worry about that in fact I can
if I want to just not initialize it
because it should have all the rest of
stuff initialized so then when I run
this I should see exact same thing we
saw before and now we're just doing that
on a test volume so now what I want to
do is I want to essentially enter a loop
here where I look for tests what just
happened did I accidentally remove what
that's odd
is this a for coder bug that I have
never seen before correct me if I'm
wrong but it's confused about how to
invent that is it not maybe it's not
what happened here something weirds
going on here well I don't know maybe
that's just a bug in for coder it's one
I've never seen before this is not the
latest version but I've literally never
seen that bug before that's really weird
how would I have not seen it before well
I kind of make a note to myself to
update the four code around this machine
because that is probably a bug that has
probably gotten fixed I haven't I don't
tend to have much problems with for
coders so I sometimes I'm a bit behind
on the stream machine I tend to switch
my dev machine pretty frequently though
to the latest version update page for
coder build send all right so I don't
know what's going on there will that re
do it okay so hopefully we can keep
hopefully this will keep screwed up and
so I can do it to do KC see if new build
of our corner still has the bug here
because we'd want to report that to
Allen so he can fix it but I don't want
to report it to Allen on an old version
of for coder because he may already have
fixed it and then I'm just reporting a
bug that's wasting his time so I'd
rather update the build first and then
see what goes on there okay so if I go
ahead and now start this process
obviously if I actually ran this code
we'd be in trouble cuz gonna loop
forever so what I really want to do here
is essentially say if one break
otherwise loop and then we get
essentially the the sudo setup for what
I want to actually do which is right
here when we've prepared the volume
we're going to test I want to test to
see whether or not that volume would
actually work right and furthermore I
want this
at edge P version here to be a little
bit more careful about how updates
things because in the case where I
actually get a room placed here then
it's actually okay but I don't I don't
know that I want I don't know that I
want to keep it so I just placed the
rooms one after another the reason is
because maybe what I want to do now is
start at the minimum and try to place
the room each time anew
why because if I have two rooms of
different sizes now that I'm testing for
overlap it may be that one of the rooms
can't be placed in like the starting
area the starting you know well let me
just draw it right instead of me waving
my hands around like a maniac so if I'm
doing a search along the edge this way
right and I've got two rooms that I'm
trying to place one that looks like that
and one looks like this this is the
first room I'm trying to place I come in
here if there's another room right there
I try to place this room here it's like
you can't place it there so it ends up
going oh I could place it here so I
place it there if I then assume you know
maybe there's another room let's say
there's another room over here if I then
assume that the next room has to go has
to start looking right here it'll be
like ah can't place the room bro right
bad news well this room actually could
have gone right here but I never tested
it because I started I just tried to
place it after that so I think I want to
do is now what I want to do is just
start the beginning and let the overlap
tester tell me where I can't place rooms
so we can slot rooms into positions
where they could have fit again it's not
quite good enough we you need more
strategies than these but it starts to
make a more robust system right you can
see how it's it's gaining a little bit
more possibility as we do that then just
placing the neighbor wise right it still
doesn't handle all the possibilities
because it may be that you should have
placed the other room first in this one
second because maybe the way you place
the second room ends up allowing you to
place the first room better and bah bah
blah so you know there's there's more to
it than this but again it's getting a
a little bit better right the coffee is
gone the coffee is gone you'll notice
I'm actually drinking a branded coffee
today because the espresso machine is
broken
and that's a very sad time basically
like you know we at Mali rocket if you
actually go buy coffee every time you
want coffee that is fantastically
expensive especially for a little indie
company so we actually have a little
coffee making machine and we needed to
clean out the little grinder piece for
the coffee making machine and it has
this little felt piece and I tried to
clean it and it just kind of shredded it
just disintegrated so we needed to order
a new one and until they come until the
new little felt pieces they're like they
cost like two dollars a piece so they're
pretty cheap to get but we had to wait
for it to come until the comes we have
to actually get coffee at an actual
coffee shop which despite being more
expensive also has the downside of you
actually to go there other instead of
just having infinite coffee on demand
for very cheap which is the best part
about a coffee baking machine so highly
recommend coffee making machines but
unfortunately today not in the cards
very sad anyway don't know why I bother
mentioning that I guess just if you're
if you're an indie you doesn't have a
lot of money you should get a coffee
machine instead of getting coffee out
but that is probably the most obvious
thing that everyone would automatically
do so I don't know why I'm bothering to
tell you that it's kind of the same as
saying don't eat dinner at a restaurant
make it yourself
which everyone knows so there's some
information that Indies should use that
they would just do by necessity because
it's painfully obvious I hope if there's
any indie out there who doesn't already
know that I don't think they're gonna
last very long anyway hmm yeah doesn't
matter point being if I keep moving on
here and looking at the code that's
actually important rather than telling
you tips on not spending you money on
coffee which I hopefully everyone could
on their own I what you want to do here
is say look let's start at the place the
min edge right every time
I and we'll work from there out on every
room placement and before we were
counting on that to keep our room
separate now we're just gonna test to
see if there's anything in the way so
that will keep our room separate and we
don't have to worry about this part
anymore so the at edge P probing piece
will now be something to get updated
much more straightforward so what we'll
say is okay here's where we place the
room it's wherever our probe is to and
it goes to this oops that goes to this
maximum right and then what we want to
do is we want to update our edge first
of all if the room can be placed we
don't have to do anything right if the
room can be placed we're done we move on
to the next room or we're just done if
there are no more rooms on this edge but
if we do have another room on this edge
then what we want to do is update at
edge P it's at this point right and so
what I'd like to do is say okay we know
the direction we're searching because we
go from the min to the max generally
speaking right I that's just how it
works so what we want to do is when we
send down this information we want to
get back the distance we would move from
our location for example in order to fit
right we want we want it to sort of tell
us that piece of information so what we
want to do is we want like some kind of
a check for overlap or like get a room
overlap Delta or something like this
right so we want to say um
yet yet Delta along axis for placement
or something so we wanted for clear
placement clean placement so we want
basically something that's gonna tell us
look how far would we have to move this
thing in order to put it down you know
how far would we have to go in order to
put this thing without it overlapping
some other room in the mix right so I
give you the test volume this is the
thing that we're actually gonna try to
put down and I'll give you the generator
which will have the hierarchy in it that
you can use to query eventually and then
I'll just say look I don't care about
the other axes because I can only move
it along this edge so you got to move it
this way right this is this is the
direction it can go it's along this
dimension so if that Delta equals zero
then we know that we can place the room
if that Delta is not zero then we'll
just try to move it with that amount I
and and see if we can place it after
that right so at that point what we
could say is well you know the Delta
this function can now emulate our
existing code
by just returning zero because if all
the function does is return zero that
just says every room can be placed right
and now this isn't great because we took
out the part where we actually walk
along the edge P so now all of the rooms
will get placed on top of each other
which is not great right you can kind of
see how all the rooms that were
previously a little late arrayed along
an edge have folded in on themselves
right but otherwise all the code is
working fine so now all we should have
to do is in this code actually go
through and test to see whether the
volume overlaps if it does overlap we
can just move as far as that one overlap
and then we're done because the outside
code will continue to try so let's go
ahead and do that and like I said we
don't have a spatial hierarchy so we're
going to do this in a really piggy way I
don't know my pig hats on right now
so we're gonna do that in a really
wasteful way that's very expensive to
compute and so why are we doing that
well the answer is because never give
yourself two things to debug at the same
time when you could just do one and then
the other so what I want to do here is I
want to give myself the brute force
version get that working properly and
then we can do a spatial hierarchy
accelerated version because if I do them
both at the same time we don't know
where the bug is right if I do the brute
force version once then we know the bug
is just with our algorithm if and then
we can fix that and be done then we do
the spatial hierarchy if there's a bug
we know it's in the spatial Harket right
thinking about the same time I don't
know which one's broken
maybe the spatial hierarchies broken
maybe the placement codes broken and now
I have a much more complicated problem
and my debugging has just gotten much
more complicated right and I'll probably
have to end up doing the exact same
thing drop down to just one version
without using the the heart or something
to see if that works right now for right
so you might as well just do it this way
first so piggy is oftentimes better you
want to start with the simplest thing
first get that working and then make it
progressively more complicated because
that just simplifies your debugging and
it helps to clarify what you're doing
anyway so it's just usually the best way
to go all right so once we get to here
we know we can just look at all of our
rooms that we have and so that's pretty
easy we just step over each individual
room starting with the very first room
in the game we then say look for every
one of these if the rooms overlap then
we need to issue a placement
and if none of them do then we're just
fine so we need to do the overlap test
here and then all we need to do is say
look this code can now fail so at some
point we want this to end and the time
when I think we want to end is just say
look if at Edge P ever exceeds the
maximum edge P we we have to stop and we
can't place this room right so at that
point we need to sort of assert right we
need to assert that we have failed and
what I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna make
a little placed and in here I'll say Oh
congratulations we placed it right and
that way out here I can just assert that
we've placed for now and the future we
may take steps if we can't place a room
okay where was my January of global next
so this allows me to loop through all of
my rooms and all I have to do now is see
if these two rooms intersect right now
we have an intersection code that we've
already written you can see it right
here so if we want to we can intersect
these rooms just fine so what I can do
here is say the intersection of these
two rooms
produces an intersected volume if that
has any volume at all then we know that
we're in trouble so when we we don't
actually have a call for that here but
you can see we got get dim and also
Ismet so you know you look at these here
you can sort of see we sort of have the
beginnings of what we want here so we
really just want a similar call to one
of these calls which is like has volume
right and that just says look for each
one of these things I guess it's one
because this will adjust it right if
each of these is greater than one then
this thing has some volume if anything
is zero or less than it doesn't right
and I think that's all we really need
another way to say that would be like
this so if each of the dimensions is
greater than zero then this thing has
some volume so what we can say is look
if this has volume then this thing
intersects unfortunately right and so
we'll just say look at that point
intersects you're gonna have to move
along the axis right here we want to say
actually returned the amount to move
which isn't hard to do but we're just
going to ignore it even that for right
now so we're gonna do the intersection
assuming that that does intersect then
we tell it it's got to keep trying
somewhere else and that's the basic
sketch of the routine and now we just
have to make sure it actually works okay
so the first problem we got here is it
looks like we cannot actually place the
room we started with here let me go
ahead and switch the debug mode so we
could step through and I'll go a little
bit over time here and and see what's up
all right right so we cannot place the
room which rooms were replacing
so we're trying to go from safe aid
to the orphanage back hallway right so
this just looks like me to straight-up
have a bug here I probably am returning
things incorrectly or something like
that because that looks like the first
time through so let's just make oh you
and I forgot to we actually need to do
this because rooms that haven't been
placed yet don't count right so now let
me just go ahead and start here I'm
gonna go ahead and step through
all right so we've got our @hp oh that's
great let's try that one more time
also yeah that's fine that should really
start backwards a little bit all right
so that looked like that actually worked
just fine
so we may be done at that point let's
find out so here's the orphanage
placement and so now you can see
everything did get placed properly now
right so you know you can see we get
those through three rooms placed now and
so now we're in better shape right so
now it won't it won't ever overlay
things on top now it's not great because
if it gets itself into a situation where
it could have placed rooms if it just
had arranged them slightly differently
it's too dumb to know how to try that so
it's always gonna just do this and the
only thing it will do is avoid over
writing its own rooms so it's not really
out of the woods yet right it's still
really basic but at least now it's smart
enough to know it won't ever overlap any
of its existing stuff in like a really
stupid way right and so we can kind of
sort of maybe a little bit possibly not
entirely take some comfort in that fact
and and we won't get any of those weird
problems where the thing overlaps right
I'm gonna go to the Q&amp;A now
[Music]
do you plan on making an in-game editor
similar to the one of the witness no cuz
this game is procedural so unlike the
witness there is no hand authored
content that is not a philosophical
point again because this is not a game
design stream so I don't mean to suggest
that there's something bad about hand
design content on the contrary hand
design content is probably quite good
but more specifically I wanted to focus
on showing the programming aspects of
level design and so I want all of the
things that we create to be created with
generative algorithms so you can see how
those algorithms work so we will not be
doing any editor stuff because that's
sort of a different difference different
situation someone said the four-quarter
thing wasn't a bug we were missing a
bracket oh yeah okay okay okay so that
was the problem a bracket accidentally
got deleted okay
so cool so Allen does not need a bug
report for that that just a bracket got
deleted Jonathan Blow hello are you back
in the United States or not you want to
know how you can get a piggy hat for
yourself I this one was given to me as a
gift actually so I don't even know where
this came from but if I can find one
John I will make sure you have one so
that on your stream when you're doing
something that you know is a little
bloated you can just put it on and have
the fashion to go with it
Gary Johansson I think I know the answer
this question but do you know of some
simple preprocessor library that has a
duration as a feature oh I think any of
you're talking about okay so are you
saying like actually now I don't know
you're talking about are you saying like
you want to write a thing that takes
your C code and allows you to put some
meta code in it that iterates over
something and outputs new code for the C
compiler or I don't I don't know exactly
what you're talking about
okay um so I guess I don't know I don't
know in the old days people used to use
em for but it's awful no not the m4
carbine
so people used to use this thing but it
doesn't understand see so it's not that
useful gosh I don't know there's got to
be one out there it's just like I
wouldn't recommend using m4 but it's
like the only preprocessor alabbar I
could think of there's God I don't I
don't know why there isn't a standard
see professor Lambert probably because
everyone keeps using C++ which they're
told has the features that they need but
of course it doesn't have them so just a
simple C preprocessor would actually be
great because everyone could use it and
it would actually be good and John says
he can vouch for how bad m4 is and so
maybe definitely don't use it since I
just said it was bad and he said it was
bad it's probably pretty bad but I don't
know I don't know where to get a library
for that it would be cool LLVM the clang
toolset has a bunch of stuff in it that
you could maybe sort of massage in to
what you want but man that codebase is
an epic nightmare it's like 17 levels of
inheritance to do like a really basic
simple thing that would have been like
one you know that'll like write to a
variable or something so I don't
necessarily recommend that either but I
don't know if you don't want to write
one yourself I don't know where the good
like C preprocessor is if there is one
out there please someone post it on the
stream that'd be a very useful thing for
people to know about I just don't know I
just don't know
mmm D 966 asks hello sir I just started
creating my first game using STL in C++
can you give me some advice am I going
the right way or should I change my
tools plus I'm looking for a game
programming book do you know a good one
to start with
I worked a little with unity3d I guess
what I would say is I depends on what
your goals are right I usually what I
usually tell people is if their primary
interest is just making a game like they
want to be a game designer I would not
use I would not write your own engine
right and the reason for that is that
it's a lot of work and knowledge and
skills that you have to build up to do
something like that which i think is
really valuable and good and people
should do it if they want to be a game
engine programmer but if all you want to
do is design games you should just use
an existing engine because otherwise you
will find yourself spending a ton of
time learning things you don't care
about that's the problem right game
engine programming is difficult it's a
it's a discipline that requires
knowledge and skill and if you want to
do it it's very rewarding and
interesting and I highly recommend it
but if you don't then you will probably
fail in your attempts to make one
because you won't enjoy what you're
doing right and so that's a really
critical difference to figure out first
what do you want to be do you want to be
a game engine programmer or do you want
to be a game designer if you want to be
a game designer who's very avant-garde
and pushes the boundaries of things you
may also have to be a game designer
that's like what John does right what
John Blow does a lot of stuff he does
you can't do in an existing engine right
when braid came out there was nothing
that could have run that game I don't
even know if there still is anything
that can run that game right like I
don't know what something like unity
would do if you try to make the
x-coordinate of a player be the time
value of the entity system and expect
rewinding to be in the mix right at that
point you're kind of an engine
programmer want whether you want it or
not but if that's not what you're trying
to do if you're
like I just want to make my little JRPG
or whatever right then you know go use
an appropriate tool for that job because
if that's what you're trying to do
you'll be happier focusing on just the
parts that are the design and not the
part just the engine so you have to
figure out which one of those are trying
to do first if you've decided that you
want to be an engine programmer
and like if you were going to go apply
for a job you'd want an engine
programming job maybe you want to go
work unity to make the next edition of
engines or maybe you want to go work at
epic and like and make the next version
of the Unreal Engine or maybe you want
to go work at rockstar and make the next
version of Grand Theft Auto which is
always on a custom engine right
bla bla bla bla bla depending on what
your goals are there you may want to
start doing your own engine programming
and in that case C plus plus plus
SDL is a pretty good way to go a lot of
games use SEL it's it's reasonable you
know not everything in it is something
that I would necessarily think is the
right way to do things but then again
you know that's true of everything right
everyone always has different ways
they're do things so it's using SDL is a
fine way to get started and it abstract
away the platform part that maybe you
don't want to focus on right now for
programming books I don't know I haven't
read any of the ones in recent memory
but you know I've heard good things
about the game engine programming book
that that I think just got revised to
its third edition or is soon being
revised anyway Jason Gregory's engine
book is probably a good bet again I
haven't read any of these books because
it's just been a long time since I've
been looking for intro to architecture
kinds of stuff but I suspect this is
probably a good one Chase is pretty
no-nonsense he tends to be pretty
serious about design and it's probably a
reasonable place to get some information
right so maybe take a look at that one
I don't know what else
see voucher says the current generator
always creates two tile wide walls when
rooms are adjacent will you leave it
like this because it's easier to include
the walls inside the room volume would
you take the same approach of the tile
size we're not tied to the traversal
size which would allowed for thinner
walls for example um we will probably
support both actually so at the moment
I'm just making the room generation code
is really weak right it's just kind of
sitting there waiting for us to go play
with that more so it doesn't know about
the concept that we may want to overlap
rooms and have a shared wall boundary
between them so I would actually say we
might make one tile wide things in some
places as well so I don't know what
we'll do there but the only reason swing
it that way right now is just because
that's sort of the way we had been doing
things our previous rooms were that way
rooms had their own walls to them and
you kind of had to do it that way in the
old days when it was tile mappy because
you had one tiles on one side and one
tile on the other side for the angle of
the wall we don't have to do that
because we have actual 3d now so we
could do a single wall down the middle
whether we want to or not will depend on
some gameplay concerns it I don't know
so I guess what I would say is we
probably will end up having some areas
where we only want one wide and we'll
see how to do that when we get there
but why not one says lid plane can parse
your code and give you the ast it's a
simple C interface so that might be a
place to go if you can maybe boil it
down to that well this can you show the
game I just fell asleep and missed all
the coding I'm sure for you Val bus
absolutely so we just were making the
thing that would create the orphanage
layout so you can see there it is right
and this is the orphans layout we said
we wanted right
what to do if a CS course enforces OOP
well so the thing with object-oriented
programming is it's a common requirement
for our courses or for work so you know
OOP is one of those things I think we'll
be gone in 30 40 years as anything that
anyone ever thought was useful or
interesting right I don't think it's got
any legs on it it's one of those like
fad things that you know once we
actually have metrics people will go oh
yeah this was dumb or whatever so I
think it's got much legs to it but it's
definitely around at the moment and so I
don't think you should look at a CS
course in forcing OOP as a problem you
should know how to program
object-oriented programming because you
may be asked to do it or you may have to
use code that does it and if you don't
understand how it works you're at a
disadvantage there right I know how to
do object oriented programming if you
want me to do an object oriented program
I can do that right I know how to do
template metaprogramming like I can do
all those things I choose not to because
after having used them I know that they
are too limited and I don't find them to
work right especially not in C++ where
the object-oriented programming
constructs are weak there are languages
where the objects programming
object-oriented programming constructs
are stronger and there's more of an
argument to use them in those languages
C++ is not that language right
but either way just because
object-oriented programming is usually a
bad idea doesn't mean you shouldn't know
how to do it especially in today's work
environment you will probably be called
upon to understand at least if not write
object-oriented programming code at your
first job because many places use it
sadly and so you need to be able to do
that you need to be understand what
people are talking about when they talk
about how to transfer code you need to
be under able to understand how people
expect auditory schoo to look and behave
so that you can make it and interface
with it as necessary I would never write
it because I don't think it's useful
that's
different from saying you shouldn't know
how it works not everything that sucks
shouldn't be understood right and
furthermore if you never actually learn
it yourself you wouldn't know that it's
lousy you just have to take my word for
it and what if I'm wrong
tons of people tell you ooop is good and
I'm telling you they're wrong right if
you would always took their advice you'd
never learn how to do things the non OOP
way and it might be that'd be really bad
similarly maybe I'm wrong and if I'm
wrong you need to know that so learning
different programming styles is very
important because if you don't learn
them you cannot make an honest
assessment yourself take a step back and
go which of these things do I think
actually results in more well working
programs in less time etc so don't think
of your OOP class or job as man this is
awful I'm not getting out of this think
of that as your opportunity to
understand object-oriented programming
and assess it and that's valuable even
if you come away thinking the exact same
thing I think which is that it's useless
now you know now you know for for real
you don't know just because I told you
you know because you evaluated it and
that's gonna be really valuable to you
going forwards because I'm not gonna be
there to tell you everything right you
can't just go ask me or some other
person what to do you should be able to
assess every new programming technique
that you're exposed to you should be
able to learn it evaluate it and make a
decision about whether you want some or
all of that in your programming style
right without having to appeal to an
expert on the topic somewhere and trust
that they know what they're talking
about oftentimes they don't or even if
they do it may be true for their
circumstance and not yours
maybe there are certain things that on a
large team are useful programming
practices that when you're a team of one
just don't make any sense which one of
those are you doing
well don't assume that everything they
said then just applies right maybe
you're doing really performance oriented
programming and something else isn't
maybe those two things create very
different programming requirements right
bla bla bla bla bla bla bla so I think
that's really how you should approach
opportunities to learn things like
opportunity programming that you may
kind of know a priori or a waste of time
it's not necessarily a waste of time to
figure that out yourself or go into it
with an open mind and see if you come to
similar conclusions because you may
learn something really valuable there
what do you think about Lua and love 2d
I have not used them what paradigm to
use instead of we just focused on
straightforward procedural programming
like the traditional style of C
programming that was around before OOP
Jonathan Blow adds the problem is that
understanding why OOP is really bad
probably requires five plus years of
experience because it takes that long
deal to build sufficiently complex
programs such that you know what should
be easy or which complications are
unnecessary I guess I would say I do
agree with that but I don't know what
else to say you need to be able to learn
why things are good and bad and I think
building up that experience is useful I
don't know that you want to do five
years of programming exclusively like
like I did for example before I came to
those conclusions but I think you want
to understand it and try to think about
those things at a higher level if
possible so one of the things that I
actually I should mention that's kind of
a programming philosophy point that has
to do with OOP as well is that
fundamentally speaking I also feel like
there
is sort of a true aspect of programming
that's emerging that I become more
certain of every year which is that the
problem with object-oriented programming
is very similar to the problems with
other styles of programming that share
its design philosophy which is that it
is a design philosophy divorced from the
computer so there is literally nothing
that has anything to do with
object-oriented programming in a CPU
right a CPU is procedural that is what
it is so when you start to design
languages whose core tenants do not
respect the fact that the CPU does not
have the things that it is claiming are
central to the design process I think
you have made a fundamental mistake that
doesn't mean you don't want higher level
of language constructs but what it does
mean is those higher level language
constructs must be constructed in such a
way as to respect the fact that the end
product is code that a CPU runs and C++
for example long since forgot that and
most object-oriented design forgets that
fact and that fact is crucial so I think
once you divorce yourself from the
notion that the important thing is
generating CPU code efficiently and how
can you give the programmer the most
ability to have control over the CPU
code that is generated in a clean and
efficient manner when you've lost sight
of that as the goal and you start to
think of the goal as other things that
are unrelated to that then you have
fundamentally lost your way and I think
your language will never be good right I
so I think that is really the core
language design tenant that should be
respected and OOP does not respect it
its core tenants are all things
unrelated to the C
pee-yew and that's a problem again not
even just because of performance or
anything like that it's because the
programmers day-to-day work is to
produce a working piece of CPU code and
when your language starts having most of
its features not be about that that is
when it becomes cumbersome to do real
work with this language and we've seen
that with C++ doing a very simple thing
that you'd think would be very
straightforward to do in terms of CPU
code generation in C++ is like
impossible and the reason is because
they never thought of that is that go as
a goal right that's why it's been so
late to add things that are obvious in
terms of CPUs codes such as
introspection and things like that so I
would just point out that philosophical
problem C++ has it in spades
so do a lot of other object-oriented
programming constructs that's usually
the reasons why I end up not liking them
is because I know what I want to CPU to
do and what I am fundamentally looking
for is the simplest smallest possible
amount of high-level code I can write
that generates that CPU code not some
huge sprawling mess of other CPU code
that happens to reduce the same result
very slowly and with a ton of memory and
that's usually what OOP actually gives
you right if you're lucky a lot of times
doesn't even give you that but you know
that's a separate issue
all right um I'm gonna go ahead and
close down here thank you everyone for
joining me for less than a handmade hero
it's a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade here org it comes
to the source code so you can play
around with it if you want to for
example go try your hand at making some
smarter room layout code you could do
that before I get to it if you'd like
and see how your coding skills have
progressed that's it for today I'll be
back here tomorrow so if you would like
to see some more of the replacement code
that's the place to do it same time same
place
hope you see you back here for that
until then have fun programming I'll see
everyone on the Internet
take these everybody