okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the show where we code a
complete game live on stream we are
gonna do one more day of raycasting
programming just because people seem to
like it from yesterday and so we figured
we'd do one weekend of it and yeah and
that's about it next weekend we will
return to handmade hero as normal unless
something catastrophic happens which I'm
not willing to rule out based on how
much trouble I had getting this
streaming setup to work even though it
should have been simple so let's take a
look at where we left off from yesterday
oops that's for UNIX we're not on UNIX
right now let's go to the handmade ray
directory this is what we wrote
yesterday on stream and you can see if I
open up the project here it's a very
simple to file project there's like an H
file and a CPP file let me go ahead and
show you those and I'm running it right
now you can see it ray casting over
there and what you can see is we just
have a really really simple program very
very straightforward all it does is set
up a little you know world model here
that's got some materials in it with
some planes and some spheres and so on
and then it just has a simple ray
casting loop it goes through and ask
this little ray caster here to trace
some rays for it
the Rays this is really I don't know why
we call this ray count it's really
bounce count it's how many bounces the
Ray has done has nothing to do with rate
count so it's how many bounces ray has
done it just goes through in Casa ray it
looks at all the planes and spheres in
the world sees if it hits them takes the
closest hit and then processes the
material on that hit and that's it right
we write out a bitmap at the end here
just a simple bitmap image that we could
view and we made a batch file that runs
the ray caster which you see running in
the left hand side of the screen and
then outputs the final image which you
can see here right and that's about it
so what I'd like to do probably today I
think is we've got sort of two things we
need to do to this rate caster in order
to make it like a useful rate caster
really technically three but the third
one I don't know that we'd ever do I
mean maybe we will but this is just kind
of a toy project could people wanted me
to make so I made it so I don't know
that we're really gonna try and make it
into something much more than that
but that those those two things are
better material processing right because
right now we don't really do like
transport for real it's not physically
simulated we don't have a real material
model we're not like handling like the
Fornell equations or you know any kind
of of real computation of what happens
with like it's a surface or a transports
along array and so the results while
they look sort of pseudo real like they
have some of the properties that you
might expect from real light there's a
bunch of like errors in there about how
it's been computed so the results just
aren't very good right there they're not
gonna provide that like realistic look
that you can get from a ray tracer
without too much effort as long as you
obey the correct physical equations so
that's something that's worth doing and
some weekend we'll do that in the future
the second thing is just making it
properly
sim D and parallel which is something
that makes the speed work well and
that's something we really want to do
because especially once you start
working on adding better lighting and
that's our stuff and you want to test it
you don't really want to sit around all
the time waiting a long time for the
results to see what worked and what
didn't or any of that sort of stuff so
we'd also like to speed up the ray
tracing considerably if we can and
decrease that turnaround time so
optimization is the other one those are
the two big ones
and I'd like to do both of those I think
I might do optimization today or try
some optimization today like try to get
threading working for example now the
problem that we have with the third one
which is one I probably don't want to do
that would make this a complete ray
tracer you could actually
use for something is some way of loading
real scenes and creating an actual
spatial accelerator right and that one
is a much more complex undertaking so
that involves picking some kind of file
format like you know wavefront obj files
or I don't know some kind of an
interchange format there's a lot of them
out there and reading in the data from
that which is probably gonna be triangle
meshes or displacement meshes or
something and then processing those into
a ray casting format that is bin so that
Ray's don't you know because we're gonna
be loading like at that point
millions of triangles or something you
can't test every one every ray it would
you know you'd be way too slow so you
need an acceleration structure that that
allows Ray's to only test triangles or
seen elements that they may come close
to hitting rather than all the ones in
the scene and if we wanted to increase
the number of spheres we would want to
do that as well like the number of
spheres in here is very tiny if we
wanted to increase the number of spheres
to you know a hundred thousand seers or
something we would have the same concern
right we would need to put in some kind
of spatial hierarchy to reduce the
number of spirit checks we have to do
per rate test in order to make it run
reasonably and that's a whole nother
sort of huge undertaking that is the the
vast vast vast majority of work in a
real ray caster is that that is where
the work is the work is not so much in
the light transport parallelization
stuff because that is just a more well
understood it's usually the that
bounding hierarchy building the bounding
hierarchically you what kind of bounding
Arkadiy is most effective usually KD
trees how to test triangles efficiently
with you know look them up and gather
them quickly the ones you need to test
how you deal with the fact that you're
trying to do sim D but different people
are looking at different triangle lists
and ba-ba-ba-ba-ba it's just it's very
it's just very much
a serious programming undertaking once
you bring that into it so I'll probably
skip that part since this is not the
main focus of handmade hero and will
just focus on the other two which I
think we can do relatively simply and
I'll take the easier of the two today
which is just figuring out how we're
going to do some sort of optimization
for this so if you take a look at what's
going on here in the code you can see
already you know the slowness of it is
largely becoming from this race per
pixel because if we set the Rays per
pixel to one it would finish almost
immediately right and you can see the
problem of having raised per pixel up
being one and that is that we don't get
enough samples to really get a smooth
image now we get roughly a correct image
right I mean we are producing something
that looks reasonable because you know
one ray does produce a reasonable result
but it's just not a smooth nice
continuous image like we would like and
there are a lot of ways of producing
better results even from lower sampling
rates and that's something we can look
into in terms of when we go to start
doing the lighting sampling and stuff
like that there's ways of using better
reconstruction from the samples that you
do take and also in in figure out how
you take your samples
there are ways you can improve the
quality without improving the number of
rays and so again when we start to look
at material stuff that's something we
can look at as well but for right now
what we want to do is just set up the
structure of our program a little bit
better so that we're getting more
performance in terms of just how many
rays we do take so for example if I
raise 4 pixel 1 and I switch to raise 4
pixel being 8 you can see that the
difference in speed is already pretty
dramatic right and you know it's
probably roughly eight times slower now
how much slower is it well it would be
nice if we actually knew how much slower
it was so I think what I'm probably
gonna do here is I'm gonna first
introduce a timer so we can actually see
how long we're taking as we go now
because we're timing an entire ray cast
we don't really have to appeal to
Windows functions yet we can use a low
great timer so we can take a look at the
C runtime library again and look at the
functions involved there and see if
there are any that will be good enough
for us
so for example the time function is one
that's available everywhere and this
returns the number of seconds elapsed
for example so we could get the number
of seconds elapsed pretty easily from
the C runtime library and if since our
things takes it tend to take multiple
seconds that could be enough there's
also other functions that might be
reasonable that could give us a little
bit more resolution unfortunately don't
know how many of them are portable for
example the you time functions I'm not
sure that's not what I wanted the you
time functions are 4 files do we have
anything slightly better time management
clock so clock is clocks per second
which might be reasonable let's just
take a look at what it is that may give
us a little bit better resolution here
we go let's do a printf here per sec I
don't know what clock is per second what
the clock T value is actually defined to
be
so I'm not sure exactly how I would
print it out but what I can do here if
we want to is I could find clocks for a
second and in fact why don't I just go
ahead and do that
so if i open up ms dev actually we have
a project that we had created for this
purpose but i think it's we didn't copy
it to the new machine i'm just gonna
create a Windows desktop application
here using the stupid application wizard
and I don't care where it puts it so
this is in Windows project 1 in some
users KC source repos I don't care I
don't care where the stupid wizard puts
it it doesn't matter all I want to do is
get the Browse info thing working that
this thing builds by default right and
so what I can do here is I can say clock
T in this project right why is it
capitalizing that like so and then if I
take a look at this I should be able to
do a go to definition now it can't
locate it but I assume that's just
because I haven't included the right
file
so if we take a look at what it requires
4 o'clock tea where was that I had that
a minute ago
here it is
I assume yeah it's just in time dot H I
assume that if I just put time dot H in
here right as an include file and and
save that then it should be able to find
this and hey lo and behold it does so if
we take a look at it it's just a long
value which means I can print it out
with a % D just fine so if I come back
here to our Rea program I should be able
to run it and see what the clocks per
second is now I'm getting the same error
here but that's like rather obvious why
I need that was it called time that H I
need that time that H so you can see
that the clocks per second it looks like
there's a thousand clocks per second
that means it's a millisecond clock that
is fine for our purposes right because
we're timing huge loops here so the fact
that this is a fairly low-resolution
timer I don't care I'm totally fine with
that that will be fine for our purposes
and it will remain platform-independent
I'm kind of trying to do on this project
so that we don't have to have additional
libraries or anything involved how we're
gonna do threading that way I don't know
I don't really want to use standard
thread but maybe we might have to that's
gonna be the worst thing that's ever
happened to me but okay so if we take a
look at the start time here it looks
like we could just get this by calling
clock like so and then we can make an
end time by calling clock here and then
we can just sort of go through this as
we start our loop we can just go through
the loop and we'll ignore it like the
right image time so as we get a start
and end and maybe I'll call these start
and end clock
there's our start clock there's our end
clock what I should be able to do is say
okay
here's the number of milliseconds that
this took let me go to the other pane
here so we're not getting up into the
KC's head area if I take the end clock
and the start clock and difference them
together I should get how many
milliseconds it took it to do the rate
casting right and so you know there's
the image it looks like it took two
thousand fifty nine milliseconds so
that's a pretty easy way for us to
determine how long it took and
furthermore what I could do is count the
bounces so if I introduce here some kind
of a global variable I'm just going to
define global variable term they're not
just again so I can see it if I
introduce a global variable here that's
like how many Rays have I cast I'm gonna
say like so well you know what I don't
even have to make it a global I could
just put it in the world actually all
right let's just do that
if I go ahead and accumulate how many
rays are cast then I can have some idea
of what's going on right so if I come in
here and say every time I enter this
loop I'm casting array not so I will go
world raised cast we can say how many or
I should say like bounces computed or
like let's call it that
so I need some way of printing this out
and in general I always forget that I
think it's L LD or ll you I guess for a
long for a you 64 I don't really
remember
let's take a look also let me let me go
ahead and grab from handmade here of the
you 64 definition I think it's standard
def that has these in there well I
forgot about standard def this whole
time I actually defined these myself but
I didn't really need to because we are
using the standard library so I guess I
shouldn't have bothered with that I
guess I could have just done
you win 8 t can I do that now you at 16
T 32 T you are
oops into 8 T in 16 T 15 I forgot about
this so I don't need to change that one
so yeah in theory I can just make 64-bit
types here without having to do anything
fancy and then we can count the total
number of rays even if that number Co
comes very high in theory oops
what is this complaining about doesn't
standard F include these did I mess
something up oh it's standard int my bad
there we go
all right so let's see where we're at
here let me go ahead and finish this up
there we go
so now we should get a thing that says
how many bounces we have don't ask me
why the millisecond number is in there
here's how many bounces we did here's
how many rays we cast put this in here
cleaner so now we can print out the
number of milliseconds per bounce or
something similar right so you know the
performance was you know point something
milliseconds per bounce so if I go ahead
and say all right we've got a a total
time like so
so we've got a time elapsed this is the
number of milliseconds that have elapsed
and then we want to take how many
milliseconds per bounce I just divide
the number of milliseconds by the number
of bounces I'm gonna cast them to double
so that we'll get a fret that's going to
be a fractional number then we should be
good to go so there we go
so now we can sort of see how many
milliseconds for bounce we're taking
right in our goal obviously is to drive
that number as low as possible as well
as the total recasting time as well now
in theory that milliseconds for bounce
numbers should remain relatively
constant I mean it's not going to be
perfect but for example if I was to
crank up the number of rays to pixel 216
you know here's the number of bounces
we've had so far right so you know roll
ups we're looking at this number if I
recompile it and rerun a slower one you
know the total time will change right it
doubled roughly but you can see that the
performance number was pretty darn
consistent right so as I you know
increase the number of rays I can make
the total time slow down but if we just
look at how long it's taking us in
general per bounce that number should be
roughly the same you can see that it
does and that's why I divided those out
was just because we're a little bit
early in the process here but it just
gives me a starting number I can look at
to see you know whether I'm making some
progress or not and driving that number
down
I can fuss with different things here
and change which images we're creating
without having a huge effect on that
number which is good so that way I know
whether you know I have a sort of a
stable version of the performance there
okay
so let's start by taking a look at how
these loops are working here we are
already compiling in release mode to a
certain extent and
way and you know we don't need these
handmade defines in there because
there's no there's none of that that's
happening now so you know we're already
compiling in release mode so we're
already getting some performance the
compiler is already doing some basic
stuff here for us and that's all good
but you know there's a bunch of stuff
that we need to start thinking about now
in terms of what we want to do so the
first thing I'd like to do is I'd like
to break this up into chunk in chunks
right I'd like to be able to in a little
bit hand this off to let's say I think
this machine handles eight threads
simultaneously if I remember correctly
let's take a look
change graph to logical processors so
this is a 777 hundred K it's a four core
machine each core has two hyper threads
that's why you're seeing an eight wide
graph here and hyper threads in our case
may or may not help the performance
significantly to be honest I don't I'm
not super familiar with the 7700 K core
i7 I don't know to what extent
ray-tracing is going to saturate the
arithmetic units on a single core we are
not under memory pressure right now we
are not only not modifying any memory at
all but we have very little memory to
read so all of its gonna pretty much fit
in a very small cache it'll probably
just stay in l1 the entire time would be
my guess the only thing that wouldn't
was is the output image itself so you
know I think we're looking at a
situation where we're probably gonna be
able to get the memory traffic down
quite a bit which means that the hyper
threads are not going to be covering for
latency bubbles one of the things that
hyper threats often do is hyper threads
will allow you to cover long memory
latency bubbles by giving you know one
thread will will execute inside the
other threads memory bubble well it's
waiting for some memory to come in the
other thread could execute and use the
ALUs and whatever during that time we're
probably not gonna get much of that
because we don't have very much to read
from in a ray tracer that actually was
using a real scene we absolutely would
because a lot of that time is pulling in
stuff from the bounding volume hierarchy
and getting new triangles into rate cast
against so that is not necessarily the
case in a flow rate tracer so to take
that the grain of salt but in our case
we're mostly talking about trying to use
the Ale use I think and so I don't know
whether or not we will really be getting
much mileage out of it or not we will
find out as we go so we'll see but
either way even if we weren't gonna get
anything out of hyper threads at all and
determined that they we wouldn't which
is probably not a case but let's say we
completely weren't able to down the high
scratch we still want four threads
operating at the same time right we want
to have four threads doing things at the
same time now there's a couple different
ways that we might want to do this and
again it's a little bit tricky to think
through exactly how we want to do it
because as we go a little further in how
we're gonna do the ray tracing and so on
we don't know whether or not we really
want to separate out into pieces of the
image or not I suspect though that we
probably do so I think what we probably
want to do is just divide the image up
into little chunks and possibly if we're
gonna be operating on those chunks
repeatedly and summing together the
results we may even want to make the
chunks small enough that that the output
stays inside of the cache so for example
the l1 cache is 256 K if we were summing
up samples in there we may want to try
doing if we're out putting them
successively we may want to try to keep
the size small right now we're just
summing we're doing an entire pixel
completely first rather than producing
out intermediate output images as a
preview to the user so right now we
don't really have to care about that and
we know that we're not having any cache
problems at all I think cuz it's really
just nothing to load so I don't know
first things first I'm just gonna divide
us up into some tiles to do so that
basically every CPU core can have its
own tile that's completely separate for
anyone else's tile right so that's what
I'd like to do now and because
I'm gonna do this in a way that's more
like what you would do in a real
raytracer rather than take advantage of
the fact that we don't have a bounding
volume Hart gate normally what you would
do is you use tiles that are square
shaped and the reason for that is
because you assume that the kind of
traversal through the grid the bounding
valve our key will be more coherent in a
square than in a row if I just gave
every CPU a row because you figured that
rays cast in a similar direction will
hit similar things and bounce and
similar ways prohibit entually now
that's only true to a certain extent
when you have a lot of diffuse surfaces
rays tend to bounce in all directions
and that doesn't always happen but you
still will probably get more in a square
than you would otherwise although it
won't be that much more as it is if
everything was perfectly coherent
obviously so anyway sorry to dump too
much information on you there anyway so
what I'm gonna do here is I'm just gonna
break this up into a couple different
tiles so what I want to do here is I
want to introduce a function that I can
do which is sort of like render tile
right and that will take one of these
saucy fellows here where I you know will
sort of grab you know this sort of thing
like this I and we want this render tile
function to take the range for X&amp;Y that
it's actually going to use and it's
going to need to be smarter about how it
writes to the output value because of
that right this line can stay the same
because X outputs will march along it
uniformly but Y outputs will have to do
something different right so we need to
do to make that change as well so for
example where is the output pixels line
here it's somewhere
right here so this line will have to
change but everything else could
probably say the same all right so what
I want to pass in here is like the Y min
and the Y count and the x-men and the X
count something like this
and I might do this maybe I'll do this
like like this and I also want to pass
in the image that we're going to write
to and the world so I'm gonna say
raycast this world into this image and I
want you to just do this tile right so
this Y here is actually going to be like
hey start from Y min or actually I guess
that won't quite do it that way you know
what why don't I just do this fine do Y
min
so do it like this
so this will basically say let's do a
subset of the image again the X will
work just fine inside gets loop but the
outer Y loop is going to have to have
some specificity to it so the first
thing we need to do is we probably want
to do a thing that's like get pixel
pointer and we want to say like hey give
me the pixel pointer at this location
and that'll move the pixel pointer to
the right place for that
x and y min and then what we need to do
is every time we do the Y we got a go
and you know what we we probably don't
need to be to it because the inner loop
is gonna be so costly it's okay we can
probably just use get pixel pointer here
where we say all right get the wat X min
and the Y that we're on right now just
give me that out planar and then I'll
you know increment along it right all of
these equations should in theory now
stay the same there shouldn't be
anything weird going on there at all and
so if I go up here and just implement
this get pixel pointer function
what I should be able to do is just
compute where the pointer would be in
the image so I know I have an image
here's the pixel pointer to the image I
know that I want to go xpick CIL's in
and I know that I want to go Y pixels up
right so I just need to multiply by the
width to move me up Y pixels that number
of rows and then just use the X I'd
probably write it this way just to get
me to the right X right but that should
give me a pixel anywhere in the image
and off we go now sorry what is this
complaining about left two pixels
must have a oops that's what I didn't
want that there there we go in fact I
can just do this and we need some of
these other values to be computed in
here so 1/2 pix w that sort of stuff all
of these sorts of things think all of
this stuff wants to be up in here go and
the camera we need to pass in as well
now the camera at the moment since we
don't care I'm gonna let that happen up
in here as well because we're not really
fussing with that yet in the future we
probably want that to be passed in as
part of the world or something right
but it doesn't really matter
rate cats cannot convert argument -
there we go
let's get that going all right so now we
just have to as you can see we don't get
any image now because we're not calling
this but what I would like to do now is
I'd like to actually call this raycast
function to render the world like so and
I'm just gonna do image width image
height and have it just render the image
as it was rendering before and if we
didn't mess anything up we should just
get the same image right and it looks
like we basically did that looks right
to me
and so now what we want to do is say
okay can we break this up into multiple
tiles now yeah I don't have a way of
getting the number of CPUs here but I
could pretend that I did so let's say I
said core count equals 8 here and maybe
if we wanted to add something in the
future that could query the number of
logical cores by calling Windows since
we're not calling Windows right now I
don't want to do that but you know the
user could say maybe the core count then
that they want to use what I want to do
is I want to break up the image into
that many tiles right and so I guess the
other way we could do it is just use a
tile count I don't know we kind of need
a core count though so let's go ahead
and say that we could specify a core
count and then we might have a tile with
tile height kind of a situation right
and we want to compute what these are
and so maybe what we say is maybe we
want to just take however many cores
there are and we want to kind of break
up every row into that many tiles or
something I don't know I'm making this
up but let's say we took the image width
and we divided it by the core count
right and let's say we wanted to round
up so that we wouldn't have too few we'd
have too many if there if it wasn't an
even divisor so let's say we took the
image width and we added the core count
minus 1 and then we divided by the core
count to give us a number that we knew
would sort of like get us to the end of
a row always and let's say we always use
square tiles so we have tile with M tile
height equaling the same amount let's go
ahead and print that out so here's the
configuration MIT cores with D by D
tiles right so just so we can see what
it is so here's our core count goes our
tile width oops
so we can actually see what that ends up
being and then what I'm going to do is
just render one of those tiles right and
so that's it that's all I wanted but you
can see we do we this is 160 by 160
tiles and you know what maybe I'll
actually also put the the bytes per tile
in here or the Cape or tile and what
that's going to tell me is just how big
the tile is relative to the cache now
again it shouldn't matter because we're
not actually updating tiles in a
particular way but I'm just gonna print
it out anyway so that's tile width times
tile height times 4 or size of you 32
divided by 1024
what is it Oh because of size of all
right fine so now it'll tell us like
okay it's 100k per tile that would be
that would fit in the l1 just fine
because it's 2 and 56 K l1 on this
particular chip so you know there we go
right and we know the world is pretty
tiny as well we could actually print out
the size of that if we wanted to but I
think we're basically good so now let's
just make a loop that will render all of
our tiles for us right like so so here
we go with this render tile function we
just need to go okay we've got tile
index for tile X tile X is less than
well actually I don't know how exactly I
want to do this I guess we could just
say what the tile count was not sure how
I want to do this exactly you'll see
you'll see as I write it
so what I want to do here is say all
right let's suppose that I'm gonna go
over all of the tiles right and what I
want to do here is I want to say that
I'm gonna produce them in Y and that's
going to be the tile Y times the tile
height right so as we go through here
I'm gonna like you know I'm gonna
basically you know I can just I I think
I can just figure this out ahead of time
because I can just do the divide and
round up and then I know that's how many
tiles there are so it should be pretty
straightforward right in fact I don't
really even need to quite do it this way
because I mean I could just do the
straight divide without right rounding
the divide up as well and it wouldn't
matter you just have a fractional at the
end so the rounded up version is just
saying like hey you know 160 times 8 is
1280 it gets the well I'm always going
to get that much even if we had an image
that was slightly bigger it would it
would bump the tile size up so that we'd
only have that many we'd only have the
core count number of tiles there so but
I don't really know that we care about
that so maybe I'll just won't care about
that for now and just say well just do
this and then what I'll say is let's
compute the tile count X and the tile
count Y and just know those at a time
[Applause]
right so the tile count X is just going
to be however big the image width is
divided by the tile width it's gonna
tell us how many of these we have to do
but that would be if we skipped like any
remainder so this is where we want to do
sort of a plus tile with minus one thing
to make sure that we count for the
remainder so we'll get an extra tile
that's like smaller if we need it right
to fill in the gap and the same is true
of the height here so there we go
so this way we can know that that's
going to cover the entire image when we
do the min X min Y those are just going
to be straight multiples so we know that
our minimum Y is going to be however
many tiles we've gone times a tile
height same with the min X the max X on
the other hand is going to be the min
you know we take the min and go one tile
height forward that would be how big it
would be if we didn't ever have
remainder tiles but sometimes we do so
if max X is going is going to be greater
than the image height we need to clamp
it right we don't want to you know if we
have a tile where we need to do a
fractional tile to fill in like the top
row of the image we want to clamp it
down so we don't overwrite the image you
know go go further out of the image then
then there actually exists image don't
ask you why I wrote X there
so here we're computing those values we
now can use those values here's the min
X min Y max X max Y and I really
sometimes I just like to be careful
about this and say it's well it's really
one past the max X because we're not
it's not really the maximum X value X
we'll never take that actual value right
it's one past max X and so sometimes I
just like to say that so that it's clear
because again the loop doesn't actually
use that value so it's important to note
right because it's a fencepost error
otherwise we never compute the actual
image height row that is one passed the
last row the last row is image height
minus one that's the index for it right
so sometimes I just like to say that
anyway let's do that so now we're doing
each of those tiles separately and it
looks like that reassembled properly
which is nice we now have a problem
which is like this printout is kind of
printing out in the wrong place
I don't know how we want to print out
percent done yet that's kind of a tough
one I guess we could just print out how
many tiles we'd done but that might be a
little too granular I don't know I mean
let's try it for now and we'll see how
it goes
something like this maybe even total
tile count equals tile count x times
child count Y and then in here I'll just
say tiles right retired divided by total
tile count right so that'll just print
out that percentage I and let us know
how far we've gone and yeah we'll just
keep track of how many tiles you've
retired retired count zero and so every
time I render a tile I'll do tile
retired count plus plus and off we go
so there you go
that looked a bit strange oh right that
needs to be inside this loop there we go
so there's the tiles as they retire and
they're we're done so that's fine and
dandy now we know we can do this in
tiles and we've got one or two things
that are slightly busted at the moment
here in our world structure where we've
got bounces computed and I'm gonna do a
tile retired count in here as well I'm
just going to go ahead and put that in
the world structure and the reason I
want to do that we'll see you in a
second where we go ahead and do where's
that bounces bit bounce computed will
put tile retired in here I'm gonna move
these to the end so when we complete a
tile we're gonna take the bounces
computed
and put it in here so what I want to do
is locally in here use a local variable
that's not in that structure for bounces
computed and I'm just gonna add in here
every time we do a bounce I'm gonna
increment that I think it would be
sufficient I mean I'll make it a 64 it
would probably be sufficient to do a 32
inside here because it's just in the
tile but who knows maybe it'll overflow
we don't want to guarantee that so we'll
just make it be a 64 and we'll do it
here
at the end we'll sum these two together
for our statistic gathering purposes at
I retired camp and then in here when we
print things out we should be able to
print out the correct values I think
oops
of course I have to actually get them
out here we go piling up preview windows
here and world's is a dot what else we
got what else you got for me uh-oh those
were all from one thing Jesus okay that
is a pretty bogus value what is what's
going on here tile retired count times
100 divided by total tile count total
tile count is valid
child retired count
is a you 64 I mean is you 32 why did
that get grumpy all of a sudden I must
have missed it
let's take a look it slipped by me
here's the red caster no switch real
quick to debug mode so you can see that
this value is highly bogus here let me
go down here and take a look I don't
really want this to keep going I'm gonna
kill it and task okay and I am going to
go ahead and compile oh no I did it
again that I just want to run it from
here all right so when I run it from
here I do not know why this window
consists on continuously coming up this
Diagnostics tools things I think we just
want to kill it because it's bugging me
so I want to look at the world structure
you can see the tile retired count is
zero here I'm gonna go into one of these
and I don't really want any of this
stuff so let's just go to the watch
here's a towel retired count I'm gonna
do rendered tile I'm gonna see what that
actually so tower retired count gets
incremented by a huge number there which
isn't what I intended so I probably just
put that in the wrong place
oh I put it all that would explain it
I put it in raycast
don't ask me why I did that
so yeah inside render tile I really want
it in here is where I would like it to
be
when raycast returns this value what I
would prefer is that I since this bounce
count is like pretty low here I would
like this to be returned as part of the
raycast and really this can be inlined
inside of render tile it doesn't
actually need to be its own function
call because really it's like it's just
this loop here right it's just this
thing so if we want to we don't really
need this to be a separate raycast
function and I don't know that I want to
inline it like that for now but it's
hard to say how I want to do it you know
I sort of do I sort of don't for right
now I'll cheese it i'll go ahead and say
bounce is computed well yeah you know
I'm just gonna inline it it's going in
line that's what's happening
so raycast is going away goodbye
so here we are
so inside contrib here as you can see
we've got kind of our array index
happening we compute all these values
here and we compute our very origin in
ray direction then we go through the
bounces and we'll do our bounce computed
there this will come out to the outside
and we'll do our bounce computed that
way that will go through each of these
computations and in the end we will do
our color sum this way so here's where
we were doing the raycast before so
we'll get rid of it here we have this
contrib value which is the amount that
it will be contributed to so what we can
do is just come in here and say color
equals country times how to Mart there's
that summation that we need to do and
that should give us what we need for
color right
we don't need result there so that
should give us what we want right and if
we needed to we could also sort of
separate those out a little bit more
cleanly so that contrib is multiplied
once at the end rather than every time
here which does kind of seem like a
little bit better so what we could do is
say that when we get the color out it's
it's like as it summed up at the very
end we just do a color of x equals
contribs something like that right so
that way we have sort of two separate
things we've got the you know the result
here and we've got the sample now this
probably shouldn't be called color this
should probably be called like final
color or something like that all right
so let's see what we've got here did I
say that was a v4 it was my mistake all
right so now we've kind of got a closed
loop here which should be about right
bass is computed is now gonna be
accurate I think and we retire both of
those things here with a tile so that's
good let's wait till that finishes up
okay come on mr. ray caster don't make
me kill your task I'll do it
here we go alright so
all right so the sample is summed here
like so and the final color is summed in
here that is how that should work I am
gonna kill you this time ray and now I
think we're good there we go okay so now
we're pretty good to go here most of the
most of most of what we have does what
we needed to do our problem now as you
can see the way I've set it up our
problem now is we want each of these
render tile calls to run on a separate
CPU right that's what we would like it
to do so rather than calling render tile
like this what we would like to do is
basically push these tiles onto a list
and then we would like to DQ them from
the list as we go right so you know
that's that's the goal anyway so what
I'd like to do here is say all right
we've got a total tile count I'm just
gonna record all of the ones that need
to happen into a queue and then I'm just
gonna have that queue sort of ready to
go that can be processed in a multi
processing environment right so I'm
gonna have like a little work you think
here and it's gonna store the stats so
that world is now separate and it's also
gonna have a work order and that work
order is just going to store the things
that we needed to do to render the tile
right I so what we're gonna have here is
essentially all of this this stuff here
here's the output image here's the x-men
the wyman the one pass like all this
stuff is just going to be in there like
that and then the work queue is just
gonna have some number of these and all
of this stuff is gonna become
multi-threaded so I'm gonna label it as
volatile and what that is instructing it
just so we're clear when we went over
the stuff on handmade Hiro for some
reason and I do not know the reason not
only is everyone on the Internet
wrong about what volatile does but
everyone who ever writes in to me about
volatile is also wrong about what it
does and I do not know why it is the
simplest possible thing to understand
please just trust me when I tell you I
am NOT wrong volatile is an instruction
to the compiler that the value may have
been changed by someone other than the
code generated by the compiler that's
all it's doing it is required for
multi-threaded programming because
otherwise the compiler may not reread
the value when it has been changed by
somebody else so it's required it is not
sufficient meaning labeling something
volatile does not make the code work
multi-threaded it's simply required to
make code work multi-threaded so if you
have a value that multiple threads may
touch you probably need to call it
volatile now there are times that you
don't need to call it volatile and the
reason that sometimes you don't need to
call it volatile is sometimes the
functions you use to operate on them
imply volatility so if you use a locked
increment function it may have the
notion of volatility baked into it in
some way that forces the compiler to
treat it that way it can't hurt to add
another volatile however so in this case
I'm going to label these volatile
and the reason that I'm labeling all of
these volatile is because when we go to
make this multi-threaded each of these
values may be touched by multiple
threats none of the other values will
ever be touched by two threads at once
ever right
and when I say touched I mean written
too right
and so as long as you're only ever
reading and writing values from a single
thread even if there's thousands of
threads operating any value that's only
read read and read from and written to
by a single thread that is not volatile
right the only things that need to be
mark volatile are things where inside a
particular operation of a given thread
as far as the compiler is concerned some
other thread may come and touch the
value that needs to be marked volatile
to prevent the compiler from cashing its
value in a register and not reading it
back for example right because that is
something the compiler will do right the
compiler me like let's say we're looking
at next work order index the compiler
may go ahead our bounces computed right
the compiler may go ahead and pull
bounce of computing into a register
operate on at a bunch and then put it
back out again
well if another thread might come along
and also change bounces computed now
that value is wrong even if our
multi-threading is correct and
everything works exactly as it should
the compilers caching of the value in a
register will create a bug in the code
that wouldn't have been there otherwise
and that is what volatile prevents
volatile prevents register caching or
stack caching of a global and it doesn't
have to be global in the CEPA fluff
scheme but in a visible from multiple
threads value that is changing on more
than one thread at a time right
so what cumulate errs are generally
where that happens please just believe
me when I say that I really don't want
to get another 100 emails from people
who don't know what volatile means
telling me that I got it wrong because I
didn't that is what it actually means
for real
that was very annoying the first time we
went over that on handmade hero I don't
mind getting corrected by people who
know what they're talking about but that
one was particularly bad where hundreds
of people were trying to correct me on
something that was correct that and the
locked increment thing you don't know
how many people wrote to me telling me
there was a raised condition in handmade
hero and there wasn't a race condition
and I have to go back and forth on email
like 20 times then be like no that's not
a race condition this is how x64 works
this is how locked increment works this
is not a race condition right like it's
good to get you know I guess I should
take the good with the bad it's good to
get people who actually tell me when
there's a bug in the hand made hero
multi-threading code but the problem is
for every one person who correctly
identifies a problem in the handmade
hero code most of the time people write
in and there's they're just right it's
like oh here's the thing I found out
like oh yeah that's wrong for some
reason multi-threading is like unique in
that tons of people seem to think they
understand it well enough to point out a
bug and some else's code when they
actually don't and there is no bug and I
don't know why that is I guess it's just
poorly understood topic it's weird
anyway so here we go with render tile
I'm marking this volatile now because I
know they will be volatile because
multiple threads will operate from them
my work queue I'm just gonna basically
make an array of work orders I know
exactly how many there are ahead of time
because I know how many tiles we've
broken the scene up into so what I'm
gonna do is when we start we have a
total tile count number here I'm going
to go ahead and set the world I'm sorry
I'm going to go ahead and create a work
queue here's my queue I'm gonna clear it
I'm going to set the work order count
thought to be the total tile count I'm
going to set the work orders to be an
array that will have the correct number
of these so it's going to have the
number of work orders that they're
supposed to be in the queue it's gonna
have those like so and then what I'm
going to do is I'm gonna each each time
through this loop rather than calling
render tile I'm just going to move that
render tile out here into a different
for loop and instead and you know this
is going to print out
status here I and what I'm gonna do here
is for these tiles as we go I'm instead
of actually computing any given tile of
time I'm just gonna take what I would
have done to compute the tile and I'll
put that into the work queue so I'm
gonna say here's a work order right and
in fact you know what I could do this is
just a poops that's good I can do that
just a pointer where we start out here
with just like work order you know
Brooke order equals recorders so and as
we go you know that I could do here just
to make sure - this would be an
interesting way probably to prevent bugs
you know what I'll do I'll do total work
order count or it'll be total tile count
will be the number here so we'll just
say okay
the total tile count is how many of
these we're going to have but the work
order count will leave at zero and then
when I come in here what I'll say is
work order count plus plus will be where
we are we can assert here that the work
order count is always less than the
total town that we attic allocated right
just to just to make sure that that
we're not doing anything weird so we
have a work order we need to fill out so
here's the order it's going to be the
queue work borders plus the record
account we're then going to fill it out
with all of the values that we would
have used to render the tile right so in
fact here they all are right we're just
going to do these world those worlds
image equals image min x equals min X
oops that's I guess it's X min and you
know and I guess these are I named them
differently don't ask me why
right and so all we're doing going to do
here is just copy in these values like
so okay so that's the thing that's going
to go through and get us all of our
tiles that we wanted into the work queue
so we have an array of all of the things
that we need to do to complete the image
like all of the tiles that we need to
render in order to complete the image
and then all I'm gonna do is loop
through them from you know zero to
however many there
turned out to be and at the end here i
could also assert the equivalent that
it's equal all right I'm gonna go ahead
to array dot H I like capitalizing
assert myself and I'm gonna go ahead and
include the default C runtime library
sir there it is okay and so I'm going to
go through each of the work orders here
and I'm gonna grab the correct one out
so work orders like so we're gonna grab
each of the work orders out in series
and then I'm just going to use the
parameters of the work order like so to
render the tile now the work order
itself is the other way round
I don't know why
but it is so there we go and now what we
need to do is now what we need to do is
when we call render tile we want to pass
the work queue here because that has the
accumulators in it now so what I'm going
to do is go up to our render tile call
here it is and when this goes to to
implement stuff to increment stuff in
the world it's really gonna increment
stuff on the world on the queue just
that's where the stats will live and it
looks like I also have to change didn't
print out of course there we go
that'll be here and here and here there
we go and so now we're using the work
queue and looks like everything's good
so you'll notice how I did this right I
took a single-threaded program and I
never made it multi-threaded I just did
a series of steps to transform it into
something that could be multi-threaded
right so now we just have an array and
that array has all of the work that
needs to be done and what that means is
now if I did have a way to launch
multiple threads I could actually make
this work so let's see how I would do
that specifically here is render tile
what if I wanted to get rid of all of
this stuff here right well what I could
do is I could say well let's just do a
while loop here for example that said
while the queue
you know I think I even made a thing for
here next work order index that's gonna
start at 0 while the next work order
index is less than or I could say work
retired or total tiles retired I guess I
could say while the tile retired count
is less than the work order count or
even I could say total tile count right
I know that we're not done so while it's
not done I'm just gonna call render tile
and I'm not gonna do any of this stuff
I'm gonna pull this out into a separate
sort of thing right so out here at the
top of render tile I'm gonna say what if
I just took all of the information that
render tile was previously getting
passed and instead of that I just
actually pretended that I had a work
order here that would tell me what it
was right so I'm gonna say okay let's go
ahead and get you know border world's
let's get image you 32 for the image
let's get X min close border x-men
border Y min boarded one past X Max
order oops
one past y max so if I did something
like this now I have all of the
information that I actually need to get
right and so all I need to know is what
work order index I should use and in
order to know what order I should use I
actually have this next work order index
thing here so what I can do is take next
work order index use that to tell me
which order to use and do the rest from
here so now the render tile call itself
is sort of like a multi-threaded thing
that just isn't multi running on
multiple threads it can just take a
queue figure out which work order it's
supposed to do and it will automatically
tell me when we're done because every
time I do tile retired count less than
total tile count I'll know that you know
it was correct right now the other thing
I can do here is I can be a little bit
more careful with this I can take the
next work order index here and say this
is my work before it or index like so
and I can say if right the work order
index itself is greater than or equal to
the work order count so the total number
to do then I can just return immediately
I can
just say don't don't do the rest of the
thing right don't do the rest of the
function so only if the work order that
I got back so this way even I can just
keep calling it over and over again and
it's not a problem right so now we're
just calling that one function it's
responsible for getting something off
the queue itself and it will work and do
it and you know off we go now you notice
we've got a little my head is in the way
here so we can't really see if we
finished the last tile so I want to just
make sure that we're not missing a tile
there is there some way I can maybe make
this there we go
I want to there we go I want to make
sure we don't miss a tile so there
that's good right okay
I'd also like to print out the number of
tiles
there we go so we're currently doing 40
tiles right which is not quite perfectly
balanced for the number of CPU cores we
have we'd probably like the number of
tiles to be equal to the number of cores
but who cares we don't really know that
that's true because each tile could take
longer shorter or longer so there's that
but hold on one second here what's the
all right so hmm what we would like to
do now is we'd like to actually get
multiple threads hitting that render
tile function right so what I'd like to
do here is say well okay when we start
up here and I do this work queue thing I
want to basically create you know four
core index equals zero core index is
less than blah plus plus core index
right and what I'd like to do here is
actually say well I want to do the court
I guess there's a core count there it is
I want to create threads I want to
create one thread per core to start
doing the work here the problem I have
is that I don't actually want to create
one per core because I still am in the
main loop here I want to have one core
that's the one core is is this extra
miss right so I really want to do I want
to assume that core 0 is doing me and
then the rest of the cores will you know
spin up now right so what I want to do
here is go through the core in each of
the course I want to create threads for
each of these and I want those threads
to basically be able to call render tile
so I want to create a thread and I want
to pass this as the special value to the
thread is going to be this this queue
here right and then the rest of this
code should actually just work the only
thing that we're gonna have to do that
we're gonna have to change is we're
gonna have to go look at these two
functions here these are gonna have to
be functions
that will carefully update these values
because they they need to be told that
these are you know these are basically
have to be locked ads right because now
these values are getting updated for
multiple threads they're actually the
only values that are getting updated for
multiple threads are these ones that
I've mocked about marked volatile so
we'll do this all of those volatiles
have to be behind locked ads the reason
for that again is multiple CPUs you
touching it once the CPUs themselves
therefore need to be told that they
cannot just update what's in their cache
they have to go out and make sure that
they have exclusive access to that cache
line to update it properly without
stepping on someone else's value right
so we have to tell them that it's a lock
that okay so those locked ads have to be
in place and I don't really like to use
the term lock that necessarily because
it doesn't say what's gonna be the
return value and you can see in this
case in the case down here where we do
lock dad I don't have to care too much
about what happens you can see this is
just incrementing these values and
nobody cares what happened to the actual
value right but in the case of here
where I do lock dad
I actually need to know what the value
was and I want to know what the value
was before the ad took place so I want
to do a locked ad and return previous
value right is actually what I want to
call this function so that I know what's
actually coming back from it because the
other thing it could do is do a lock tab
and return the new value after the ad
now I don't care which one it returns me
I could compute either one by just doing
a subtraction after the fact of the
number that I know that I added so
they're really equivalent functions I
just want to make sure we know which one
it is so that you don't get little bugs
where you think that you're calling
locked ad that returns the new value or
lock title value and turns out you
actually have the other one so we're
gonna need one of these for each right
we're gonna need values that increment
you 64's and you know when we look at
this we're like well if we wanted to
make this program simpler we could just
only use you 64's for this right we
could say that we just do that and if we
want to do that I would just end up with
this right that's all there really is to
it and what I can do is I can just cast
these down
let me when we actually use it the one
time we use the tau tau retired and it's
no big deal and the integral promotion
everything else should work fine there I
think so that should just be you know
totally reasonable I'm going to stub
this function out right now and so these
are the two functions that we really
need to create at the moment we can just
do this but you know we're gonna have to
do something better when we actually
want them to work right okay so our work
order index is a 64-bit value now I
think that's the only change we actually
need let me kill these dudes that are
popping up there where's the poops must
return of value right you are sir
so when we actually get the value out
here we want to return the previous
value so we'll grab out the value first
then we'll add to it and return the
result there we go so now we have what I
think at barring any bugs that we may
have here we I have what I think would
be a correctly written program for
multi-threading without the actual
multi-threading and so what we need to
do at this point is we need to have and
there is one thing we probably want to
do here
which is it's really not super necessary
but we probably want to just make sure
after we fill out all the work orders
and start creating the threads
technically we want to say here that
there's a memory fence now you know
technically we might want to do that
here I don't want to introduce a
separate memory fence so what I can do
is I could increment a dummy variable
right what I could do is I could do a
lock dad and return previous value of
one of these volatiles here let's say
next work order index and what I'm doing
curious I just I don't want to introduce
extra complexity program which has I
don't want to find more stuff than I
need to so I don't want to rely on a
fence but I need a fence here and what
do I mean by that well all of these work
orders are getting written by core zero
right whoever's running the main code
and then I'm going to create a bunch of
threads technically core zero is under
no obligation to have flushed those
actual results out and so if another
thread were to come along and look at
the Q net it may not have actually
fleshed out the results that it wrote so
we want a fence there that just says hey
complete all of the rights you were
going to write here before those other
threads start to come because
technically creating a thread is sort of
not really a right now it actually is a
right that will be serious because I
know that Windows has to do rights to
create the thread so really you know
this this fence is probably just not
necessary but I'm just doing it there to
just be complete right because create
thread is almost certainly gonna fence
itself and so you
really don't need an extra fence here
but just to be extra secure I'm just
saying hey technically speaking since
there's no other rights happening
subsequent to this that our multi thread
where you should probably write fence to
make sure that the work orders all got
filled out beforehand that's all so
anyway I all we really need now is to
implement these two functions so I think
we're pretty good to go you know address
there I think we now have a fairly
correctly written program we got a maybe
pig lil closer attention to and make
sure it really is correctly written but
we we should be good for for everything
else in the program now except for the
fact that we don't actually create any
threads and we don't actually have a
lock increment so what I'm gonna do here
is because I don't want to use the C++
runtime libraries thread stuff yet
because I'm not super familiar with it
and I never actually use it I'm gonna
first use the Windows ones and then I
don't think we have time today but in
some future time when I'm feeling like
getting disgusting stru strip all over
me and taking a shower immediately
afterwards we'll try using standard
thread just to make it so that this
compiles on more than just Windows I
really don't want to do that like I
really don't want to do that but I will
do it just for fun so I'm gonna include
Windows here and I'm gonna have create
thread actually do a create thread call
I'm gonna call this like I don't know
great work thread maybe just to not come
conflict with a create thread call for
you want to use the regular create
thread call
although overloading should take care of
it but sometimes they use macros and
things like this so I want to create a
work thread cure so I'm going to go
ahead and use the windows call for
create thread
here's the function so what I need to do
is I just need to call this guy here and
it's relatively straightforward I don't
care about Security Act attributes I can
use the default stack size we need the
starting address here which is going to
be the worker thread function we need
the parameter which is the one that
we've passed here we need the creation
flags which I don't know if there's
anything we actually care about I don't
think we do we can just let it go we
don't need to suspend or anything and we
need to know what the thread ID is we
don't really need to know what the
thread ID is but you know so we'll go
ahead and and grab the thread ID here
like so and I think we can close the
thread handle immediately afterwards but
I don't think we care about it at all
right so in theory that's all fine that
should all work I think and there
shouldn't be anything particularly saucy
going on here yeah so that should create
a work thread we just now need a
function that uses the sort of the
thread start routine right we just need
to go look up what the thread start
routine definition is so we can make a
call back there that Windows will call
us back at that's not what I wanted
there it is this is the thread so as you
can see all it is is just something that
passes that one parameter that we have
there to us as a void star this LP void
is just I don't know why they insist on
defining everything in Windows but
there's the thread callback looks like
that so when we create the thread it
will get called back here with the
parameter we know that parameter is our
work queue
and so all we have to do here is just
call our actual function that we wanted
to have happen which is render tile
right yeah I love jumping around there
so I'm gonna go ahead and put this here
and be like do Casey a twin I feel like
taking a long long shower afterward go
ahead and port this to standard thread
maybe no promises so anyway I we need to
have this called render tile so what we
want to do here is inside the thread
proper you want to call render tile on
the work queue and what we'd like to do
is we want this thread to run for as
long as render tile could potentially do
something right
so render tile right now doesn't return
anything what I'd like to do is make it
so render tile does return something
right so in this case it will return
false in this case it will return true
so what I'll do is I'll just say while
render tile off we go right so we'll
just keep calling render tile until it
returns false which means it couldn't do
any more work and at that point we'll
just return out of thread and say we're
done right and that's all its gonna do
okay
uh so I forgot to name this worker
thread but now it should be correct and
yeah I got to fix this function here so
whenever we succeed in rendering a tile
I'll do the printf because otherwise
it's going to end up at the end when
it's waiting on the last tiles other
threads may have taken those tiles and
we just print out ray casting a ton of
so I only want to print it out if we
actually finish the tile just to gate
that a little bit so off we go and you
can see now that the speed has improved
rather dramatically right if we don't
create work with threads so if we if we
don't want a thread our system we're
we're much slower let's like to take a
look at the total time here right it
took us four thousand sixty three
milliseconds to compute our image so
about four thousand milliseconds or four
seconds right if we do multi thread it
takes 823 milliseconds right it's so if
we look at the speed up there
it's about 5x which isn't bad right
that's not bad
now we don't know that this is working
properly yet it's kind of just
accidentally working properly probably
and the reason for that is I haven't
implemented the lock bad yet right so if
we take a look at locked out a return
previous value this is still not it's
not actually safe it's not actually
doing a lock that so to finish our
program we just need to do interlock to
adhere right so here's our windows
here's the interlocked API what I want
is an interlocked ad
interlock exchange ad that looks good
the value of the strain will replace
with result the operation that's what we
want the function returns a initial
value that appears so this is exactly
what we want is interlocked exchanged ad
we want the 64-bit value version so we
want this one but this is exactly what
we want so inside here what we want to
do is the interlock exchange ad here's
the value that we're actually using they
named these opposite sorry about that
folks
just my bad there and the result comes
out here so now it's an actual interlock
dad looks like cuz yeah we're not a long
64 were au 64 those were going to be
equivalent in terms of behavior so we
can we should be able to cast that just
fine like that and off we go
sooo hey that's pretty good we've got a
five-time speed-up just from
multi-threading which is great it's you
know we might be able to get more out of
that I don't know let's take a look here
so I you can see we got about seven
hundred and ninety milliseconds to
render the whole thing eight hundred and
twenty eight thirty six eight sixteen so
we're hovering around the eight hundred
millisecond mark there right and now I
don't know whether or not having more or
less of these tiles would be better or
worse and I don't know that we've really
got a completely well functioning
program at this point either I also
don't know what the optimal number of
cores is and blah blah blah so we
haven't done a lot of the work that we
might want to do to make sure that all
of this is working properly but that is
neither here nor there
we you know we we've done a reasonable
job for just you know two hours of work
or whatever we're at least in sort of
okay position what I would like to do
here is just say like hey maybe we
should double check some of these tile
counts or core counts here let's try
setting the cork out to only before I
just see what the effect is on the image
so you can see that it definitely got
slower in that case let's try making
like
too many threads and see what happens
that didn't really affect the time oddly
enough and I guess that's just because
Windows just hey it's smart enough to
you know each of our threads is doing as
fast as they can Windows is smart enough
not to start up those other threads I
guess I don't really know but it looks
like there's not a lot of gain to be had
here by fussing with the cork out
specifically it looks like the number
being the number of cores equal to the
number of actual course is about right
it produces about the right number here
now in terms of the tile width and
height here I'm interested to know if I
just kind of fuss with it a little is
there anything you know like let's say I
I change it around kind of arbitrarily
poke at the tile numbers do I get much
of a change there and I don't know it
looks like you know not really it looks
like maybe a smaller tile is a little
bit better the process cannot what file
is being used by another I don't know
what that's complaining about
yeah I have no idea what that was either
complaining about but it looks like
maybe there's a little bit of a win to
be had there were smaller tile sizes I'm
not sure but that looks like on average
it is faster right with a smaller tile
size for whatever reason I have no idea
why
better finer grained multi-threading
perhaps but it does look like you know
if you if you kind of drop that tile
size down a little bit maybe because you
can get more at the end like you know
the the there's the sort of this concept
of drain out right just it just to kind
of give you a perspective some
perspective here so you know we're going
through here and we're doing these tiles
right and we're you know we're retiring
tiles retiring tiles at the end you know
there's some tiles left over if there's
only two tiles left over here but I've
got eight threads well one thread is
gonna pick up this tile one thread is
gonna pick up this out and then six
threads are gonna sit around doing
nothing right so the smaller the tiles
are the smaller the individual work unit
is and the less total drain out time
there is because let's say each tile
takes you know ten milliseconds to
compute right or something like this if
each tile takes eight ten milliseconds
to compute then that means during this
time here I'm gonna wait ten
milliseconds of drain out because the
other six threads are can't do anything
and so we're just waiting for the ten
milliseconds for each of these to
compute if I make the tile smaller right
so that each one of the tiles only takes
like four milliseconds to compute then
even when I eventually get to the end
and end on if there was only two tiles
then the ending is only four
milliseconds that can't be overlapped
right so the total amount of time that
can't be overlap is equal to however
much time it takes to do one work unit
in the worst case because at the end
when you get to the end you can't divide
up that work unit any smaller so even if
there's you know if a tile takes however
long it takes even if there's a ton of
thread sitting around with nothing to do
they can't help on
Tyl at all right so making the tile
smaller makes the worst case time on
overlapped time smaller and smaller and
smaller so as you get to the end you
avoid that drain out however you do have
overhead in the dispatch so that
overhead in the dispatch does get worse
as you go so you can't just make them
arbitrarily small you can't make them
one pixel because the overhead of
dispatching the pixel then becomes you
know that locked increment and all that
stuff starts to get in the way right so
you know just something to be aware of
so we may want to just sort of prescribe
the tile height here like
since we included windows we can also
get the get that quark down in here so
what I can do here is just have a thing
which is like winter you'd get poor
account I can't remember what the that
is this is not what I wanted
PS not what I wanted
let's go to get CPU can we already did
this in Hammett here I should just look
in there it's not get current processor
number
and I don't really know to need to know
about NEMA groups at the moment because
we don't have that kind of Numa groups
or not this that says we're a
non-uniform memory access and the idea
is there as sometimes you have like
processors that have localized memory to
them so like you know one gigabyte of
memory is closer to this processor and
can be activate this processor more
quickly
you know another gigabyte of memory is
more close to this processor and you
want to manage that so you put the
memory and the processors together so
that they're not like split you don't
have this processor using the memory
that's closer to that processor and vice
versa so non-uniform memory access
groups are important in certain services
in this case we just don't have that
because we're not really sharing memory
in that way but you know that's what
that is so I just want to get this
can you just tell me I just want you to
tell me how many processors there are
that's all I wanted
I'm just gonna use this so I'm going to
use VW number of processors and for now
we'll just call that good so here's the
system info get system info because I
don't remember how to get it on Windows
number processors done
oops so let me just take a look at what
that actually gave me because I don't
actually know oh wait we are printing
that out nevermind
so that correctly got the number so hey
that's good enough for now so this way
if we ran it on a you know maybe some of
you at home have saucy err machines than
I do that have like 32 cards or
something that way we would create more
more threads in those circumstances
which is what we would like to do so
that is the multi-threaded version of
the situation and yeah so we're now
pretty well multi-threaded so what we
need to do now is kind of extract this
part out a little bit and and you know
sort of make it clear what's win32 and
what's not so I may do that I might just
say you know because I hate to see
runtime library and I and I strongly
dislike the C Standards Committee and
sort of their bumbling around so I
really don't want to be involved in that
so I might just make a win32 Rea dot cpp
and put these functions in there so and
make it someone else's problem to port
it to their disaster so let's go ahead
and and put these in here and so this is
all we really need to do here and what
we can do is sort of define the
functions that we actually care about
raid on H where is that interlocked guy
ah we're behind my head no okay so in
theory that should be good all we now
need to do is actually use that win32
bit in there and so all we need to do
here is say like alright we need
something here that just tells us which
of these things we're gonna include so
we can say like you know maybe at the
bottom will just say include win32 array
dot cpp and we can even do this in the
build here we could say - d win32 plus 1
or something like this right rate
132-pound if
right uh and then like something like
this so if I don't have one in the build
its if I don't have one in ability it'll
say you need to define a platform if I
do have one in the build
it'll be fine and then people can port
those functions as necessary now the
raven 32 thing here one of the things i
would like this to have a last error
situation i think probably so i'm gonna
go ahead and crib off the handmade hero
build here and do one of those last
arrow jumps so after we do the compile
I'm gonna do a set last error and then
I'm gonna do a jump around it so where's
the last error here I want to do one of
those last error jumps so I'm gonna put
a thing here that like jumps around the
this thing that runs the actual ray
tracer so what I'd like to do is jump
around that last error now it gets it
guess we don't do that in here anywhere
and I forget the syntax that file jump
on last year
oh boy I'm on stackoverflow this may go
poorly uh I just want the if no I don't
want this is not what I wanted
this is not what I wanted all
I just want the jump call I just want
this so I assume I can do if last error
go to no streaming or go to and right I
assume I don't actually know going to
bend in there
ah let's see
I hate batch file syntax so I guess I
can just do equals equals zero I don't
know or not do I have to do that okay so
let me see now if I insert an error that
didn't work at all
[Music]
what does faster equal it equals zero so
why did oh I guess I want not equal to
zero is what I actually want so I'm
assuming I can do a knot there yeah so I
can do an if not
but it does equal zero I don't
understand there we go all right we
finally got the magic so I just wanted
to since we had some extra time I just
wanted to make it so it wouldn't run the
program any more if we weren't actually
using if we weren't actually using a
valid program all right so now we should
be able to crank up the hoop that's not
what I wanted we should be able to crank
up the Rea count here a bit for each of
the tiles so if we want to do raise four
pixel is like something high the
multi-threading should help us here so
you can see it still runs pretty quickly
like it's you know it's certainly a
useable speed with and we never like
that would have taken forever before
because 256 which was you know even half
of it was like barely working right so
just the multi-threading alone gets this
up to a much more usable level which is
nice and that's a pretty smooth image
you know like that's super useable we
haven't put in like actual like we
haven't put in any kind of real light
transfer so it's a little iffy in terms
of how slow that will become but at
least we're you know we're getting
better here right and yeah and so that's
nice it would be nice to put in a better
random number generator certainly but I
think we're basically out of time so I'm
gonna go overhead and go to the
questions and we'll leave it at that
let's verify that our that are sort of
here let's verify that our sort of test
runs well if I if I run it from the
command line like the printout still
works properly so it should like show us
a percentage here cleanly right and
printout properly and all that
off we go
and we should have we can sort of see
here is our first day's one you can see
that it gets a good bit smoother on our
next one right if we were saucy we could
like try to write out as well like what
the what the timing cat was so maybe
we'll do that let's let's just add one
more thing real quick well we can inside
the work you let's parameterize like the
rays per pixel in the bounces right so
let's use Q raised four pixel
what I might do here is actually let's
just do it this way so that way the race
for pixel's set that way and the bounce
count will be the same also sure but to
do it here just so we remember there's a
thing with not with needing to randomly
terminate it's a long story
we'll discuss that some day when we do
better light transport so if we set the
max bounce count and the rays per pixel
both in the queue right q max bounce
count just 8q graze pixel let's go 1024
the reason I wanted to do this was
because I'd like to print it out and I'm
gonna move the clock down to past the
business so we're just gonna do
basically everything after the sync
right so we're just going to time this
part of it
so I'm gonna go ahead here and say
configuration is this quality is raised
for pixel bounces
so now when we run it it should give us
like all the information that we need
right and it does so it's like says 1024
rays per pixel 8 max bounces per ray
maybe I should rephrase that to 8
bounces max and I think we're good I
think that's
that's sufficient
and so now yet we can produce a really
nice and smooth image right I mean it's
pretty good and you know mostly we're
just didn't want of lighting now that
doesn't take very long to do and the
other thing is we haven't sin deed yet
so the next thing we can do is is make
its indie and I think that will improve
it quite a bit so I think that's all
good let me go ahead and we'll save an
image off for this as well yeah all
right so let's go ahead and go to the
Q&amp;A here duratorq could you please make
a portal changing the rate position
orientation upon hitting the portal to
come out of the second portal and that's
I mean if we ever do geometry stuff sure
but that's kind of not really in line of
what we're doing here psionics do you
assume the x86 memory model in your code
I assume x86 arm basically because
there's nothing else to run on anymore
game code or server code doesn't run on
anything other than those two processors
so that's the memory model that I tend
to assume what about Const volatile and
register together in a circular
christian register is ignored register
doesn't doesn't do anything anymore for
most compilers
uh okay let me just get one more thing
done here let's close this down I'm
gonna go ahead and do build array oops
no I'm going to build Rea to 2017 10 22
second day commands text I suppose
standard error should really print out
so that we can capture the output that's
the stats and have standard error still
print out the rest of it you know what I
took it back I'm not quite done let me
do one more thing so let me just print a
standard error the status stuff
like so and that way we can pipe the
results if we want to capture them
configuration and quality and all that
stuff should go to standard print def
all right let me see here
so I assume that will work properly I'm
not 100% certain let's take a look here
so let's go to data now build rated X E
and that and we'll see if we get yeah
there we go
so I just wanted the status to always
print out here and thus all the rest of
the output goes to standard its standard
out what is there between path tracing
and ray tracing so really those are kind
of just like arbitrary terms because
path tracing still does do ray tracing
but they're generally used to
distinguish the difference between a a
ray tracer generally just is forward
doing bounces where it cast out array
sees what it hits casts and other races
what it hits cast another ray right and
it doesn't really consider the whole
path in any particular way path tracers
actually do so what a path tracer
there's a couple different kinds but
what a path tracer might do for example
is take a start the camera and a light
source and do rake casts that try to
connect the two of them together another
way might be to start with a ray tracer
that produces a bounce that goes from a
camera to an emitter but then after it
goes from a camera to an emitter it will
permute the path by taking things in the
middle of the path like bounce of the
middle path and re shooting to try and
connect those two right and so a path
tracer generally implies a ray tracer
that
thinks about the whole path somehow in a
way that an that just straightforward
bouncing wouldn't do so it tries to do
some permutations or some multi-sided
like by directionality you know things
like that it will try to take us an
account right so you know like a very
sophisticated version would be like
metropolis light transport for example
where it finds a stable path and then
does permutations on the path based on
probabilities that it thinks they will
that will create likely contributions to
the lighting equation as proportional to
their value proportional to their likely
contribution there's things like
manifold exploration where they'll try
to use they'll try to take one path from
an emitter to a to the camera and figure
out the boundaries around where the
various paths could work for that
emitter to to hit the camera right so
there's like a bunch of things you can
do there that are like sophisticated
ways of treating the light transport
exploration that don't just randomly
bounce around the scene
now that they're raised for pixel in max
bats count our parameters you could
potentially give different tiles
different settings to compare quality
side by side and say marriage that's
true you could if you wanted to you
could put raised four pics on max that's
count you could put those into the work
order if you wanted the different ones
to be different what do you think about
OpenMP I've never used it
what is Cindy Cindy is SMBs IMD single
instruction multiple data it just means
utilizing the fact that modern
processors both arm and x86 or x64 I
should say although x86 at it as well
they both have the concept of wide
instructions which are instructions that
do for example a floating put multiply
they do eight numbers times eight other
numbers at once or sixteen numbers times
sixteen other numbers at once with a
single instruction and so if you've got
perfect speed up by using those
instructions you could have eight times
faster or sixteen times faster execution
of your code or four times faster of
using the older sse stuff avx2 and
avx-512 are the eight they go 8 and 16
wide um so that's a good way to increase
for entry code you usually don't get the
full 8x or 16x is usually there's a
bunch of stuff that's not expandable to
the full width and there's work that has
to be done there so you don't typically
get a full speed up but you do get a
significant speed up usually and so
that's what Cindy is do you get effects
like bloom or lens there for free if you
implement more realistic camera stuff
yes if you if you leave those scare
quotes on for free you do but it's
important to know what those scare
quotes mean so if you implement a real
lens and film aperture then bloom and
lens flare and things like that will
happen automatically the problem is that
it isn't
in terms of computation right so things
like bloom happened because of halation
on the image plane and you have to that
means you have to actually raycast
hail hail ation raised right you have to
actually penetrate the film back and
bounce back up into the the film
substrate you for things like lens star
you have to be accurately modeling the
optics of the lens through the glass in
multiple places in order to get the
flare to occur so you know it's for free
in the sense that if you model
everything accurately you'll get those
effects but it's in no way free in terms
of sampling cost the same thing cost
goes up dramatically in order to capture
those effects because you have to
actually simulate those things so
oftentimes it will behoove you to not do
them 100% realistically anyway because
you'd get a lot faster image for the
same quality as if you tried to actually
simulate like real halation isn't
uniform random sampling bad I thought
you need to use blue noise or prasanta
sampling or something
yes uniform random sampling is not a
good idea for two reasons one is because
yeah you would like to use sampling
patterns that are more suited to
avoiding ringing artifacts or bar
banding artifacts or things like that so
yes and also the other thing that's bad
about uniform random sampling is right
now we are not doing any work to try and
get the samples to properly sample the
space based on importance or anything so
generally speaking as you go and
implement better material handling
you're gonna want to put good sampling
in there right we are not doing any of
that
sigh knocks our memory model is
extremely relaxed though I don't think
it's extremely relaxed arm has a pretty
reasonable memory model so you mentioned
that hyper threading can schedule
instructions on separate bail use of the
same core did I hear that correctly or
did I miss construe what you said in my
mind I'm not sure exactly how to
interpret the question a core has some
number of ail use on it right so if you
take a single core let's say it has 2
units that can issue a multiply so it's
got 2 multipliers on it or something
right
whatever making this up so let's say
it's got two multiplied units on it then
what that means is that if I'm looking
at the instruction window for one of my
threads and I see two multiplies that I
can issue I can issue them both and
they'll just go start doing the work but
then if I need to issue a third multiply
that multiply can't issue into one of
those other multiplies completes because
there are no more arithmetic logic units
available so if the instruction window
is large enough and there's enough
multiply stacked up without other things
happening that might block them then a
single thread can utilize all the
multiply units of a core and you don't
have to worry about it right however if
there's stuff in between there that
would stall it so there aren't enough
multiplies to feed the number of
multiply units that are there then what
hyper threading could do is it can look
to the other thread on that core because
hyper threading remember there's two
threads on a core right it can look at
the instruction window from the other
thread and if that one has a multiply it
can issue that multiply on the ALU that
is that is currently fallow so what you
can think of hyper threading is doing is
hyper threading is basically a way of
pulling instructions
from two threads at once based on what
is available on the chip to execute and
this is true for things that are not L
use as well basically any execution port
on the CPU that can do something if they
can find and available ready to execute
instruction on either of the two hyper
threads it can start utilizing that
instruction port that otherwise would
have gone fallow because the other core
just doesn't have a need for it right
and so that's what hyper threading does
would you change anything if you're
using a Rison thread Ripper CPU that has
four core core complexes um no but only
because I have never programmed their
eyes and thread Ripper before so I don't
know what its behavior is like when I
get more experience with that CPU
architecture I may have more opinions on
it but at the moment I wouldn't suspect
you need to do anything really much
because this is a pretty simple
multi-threaded program in that the cores
are completely that the threads are
completely disagree today don't share
memory almost at all so in theory you
should shouldn't have to worry too much
about the underlying architecture
because this is a very simple program
typically you only need to start
thinking about other architectures
really hard when you have a lot of
memory sharing or complicated stuff
happening can you give a quick overview
of how important Symphony works
no because it's very complicated why
were you trying to kill me I was working
very hard from Ray caster because I
needed to make changes to you could you
maybe do a GTA information on test rooms
sometime maybe in the future but that
that'd be a ways off is avx2 khan enough
to use it in a game probably not at this
point
it's common enough that you might want
to use it in advanced features in a game
so for example if you have an ability to
test you you could just look at the CPU
doesn't have a DX to use this fast path
for X some extra bonus feature like
better blah or whatever like faster
physics more physics I don't
no but whatever you're doing if it's an
optional feature you can turn on and off
that might be a reason to use a VX - I
wouldn't require it unless you're just a
strictly unless your game already
requires a CPU so powerful that you know
it will always have it right what you
might you might already be doing that so
you have to kind of make that call there
well the ratio HR program in the future
use GPU does rate races nope where can
we find the code the next time I update
the handmade hero code so next weekend
when I up load the next day of handmade
hero code it will be in the repository
and the downloadable would it be more
sufficient to make an entry for each ray
to split up the work more evenly and
also this could work on the GPU no you
never want to go per ray that's too
granular so the amount of overhead and
dispatching per ray is is not good right
you need to have a much bigger bundle
than a single ray because otherwise the
overhead of work management and dispatch
becomes dominant and you don't really
want that how much different is this ray
tracer to those that with live previews
where you see the image get better
starting low res and go higher and
higher I assume they don't render line
by line so the way you would do that is
you just do one ray per pixel for all
pixels and then go back and do another
pass right so you're constantly doing
one ray per pixel over and over and over
and so right now right like you can see
the way that we're doing that in in here
we've got a loop raised per pixel right
and we just accumulate the Rays for
pixel and then output a single value
what you do instead is you save this
final color plus config sample what you
actually do is you make final color be
you basically make an image that's a
float image and you do this contribute a
s--t
you do that accumulation right and then
you just every time you finish one pass
for the image one ray per pixel which is
relatively quick right you output a new
preview
that's what that's the only difference
are there any things that you need to do
take advantage of hyper-threading CPUs
or do you treat threading the same as a
non hyper threading CPU yeah you don't
really need to do anything specific for
this usage case because of the memory
pattern is very simple if you have more
complex memory patterns you do have to
think about it because since cores two
hyper threads on one core share a cache
they share that least the l1 cache and
probably the l2 cache so what that means
is that in that scenario you want to
make sure that those two hyper threads
as much as possible are using the same
memory areas so if you have a more
complex memory layout and usage then we
have in this example where you're
actually caring about how cache
utilization is working meaning if you
have a work set that's bigger than the
cache then you want to try and keep
things that use similar memory access
patterns on the same core so those two
hyper threads should be similar memory
access patterns
all right so someone was asking about
that memory writer was posting a thing
for our memory model let me take me open
that up real quick here and then I'm
gonna end the stream here we go
doot doot doot doot doot
there's a lot of this is a bit big you
said page 20 so hopefully I can skip to
just page 20 here where is that
this is not a very concise summary
where am I supposed to be looking this
is way too big I don't really need this
the only thing you care about is whether
or not it Rio doors around a locked
increment right that's it
if it doesn't reorder around a locked
increment that's all you need to know or
I'm sorry like a like a locked
instruction right so whatever it's
compare exchange a stretch instruction
is if it doesn't reorder around the
compare exchange you're pretty much done
right if it does reorder around the
compare exchange then you have
additional issues to worry about and so
that's most of what I would say you care
about if arms memory model is relaxed
enough that it reorder is around a
compare exchange then I would just which
I don't think it does but if it does you
just include a barrier you include a
fence when you call that function and
then you're done so that's really all
you need to know about the memory model
because I'm pretty sure arm will not do
that right it will not reorder it's
trivial to just fence your mutex and
then you're done so the only CPUs that
we're really weird is like the power pcs
and things like that where you had all
kinds of weird sorts of read things you
had to manage and just strange things
going on and those were just yeah
nowadays you really just don't have to
worry about that particularly much I
don't think
page 349
okay I'll take a quick look 349 is where
is 349 nope nope ah let's see
dependent those rear atomic instructions
reordered with stores here we go
so armed 64 AR is the one we're looking
at here I assume the rest of these we
don't care about right like MIPS
whatever so it looks like with atomic
instructions reordered with stores is
the one you care about so I would say
all you have to do yeah
like literally all you have to do is
just put in the fence put in a store
fence and I probably put in a load fence
to a low defense in a store fence right
next to your atomic increment your
atomic exchange and then that's it right
you don't have to worry about it
assuming that they allow you to do that
that's really the only thing you have to
do and then you're pretty much done
because that's what you worry about on
x64 as well or AMD 64 is what they call
it on this on this list right and then
and then you're good to go
yeah and in like I saying you just want
to make sure that your interlock
function does that that's all you need
to do and then off you go
I generally yeah I generally don't I I
try not to write code that cleverly
works without an interlock function if
that makes sense
not so much I guess because I'm worried
about arm or something but more because
or you know a weaker memory model the
NEX 64 but more just because I don't
want I find that I may miss something in
that case if that's you know like I feel
like it's too easy to be overly clever
and then make some change the code and
forget that that will break it or
something so I you generally try to make
my stuff work around work with a compare
exchange and have that be a sync point
where I just assume everything
synchronized at that point and I don't
assume anything in particular happens
outside that point because I find that
if I try to be more clever than that
which you can be right
especially on x64 you could be way more
clever than that because it almost it
basically has extremely enforced memory
ordering most of the time like it's the
most enforced you can pretty much be you
can be way cleverer than that I just
don't tend to do that because I feel
like it's too easy to make a mistake and
think that you did it right but you
really didn't so I don't really tend to
do that code and I tend to assume that
my lock increment will include a barrier
which it automatically will on Intel in
all cases but yeah it looks like maybe
arm doesn't I didn't think that was true
of harm but it's been a while
so I'm actually surprised at that I
didn't think they did do that reordering
but maybe they do now so you know
next time I program an arm I'll take a
look alright so you know what we also
should I guess I'll notate that as well
so there we go
all right I think oops did I not save
that there we go I think that's it for
today
I'm gonna save off our second day image
here as well so our first day's image
and our second day's image are really no
different other than the fact that we
sped it up quite a bit and I also saved
here what the configuration was we used
so we know we have eight cores see far
so tiles we did 1024 rays per pixel with
eight maximum bounces the total number
of bounces that we ended up recording
was this many and here's our performance
per bounce right and so we think we did
all that correctly hopefully and you
know someday when we decide to do a
little bit more work on the Ray tracer
we can implement better lighting
calculations and we'll see how that
effects it we could also sim the eyes it
at some point when we're in the mood to
make it Cindy and then we can make it
again maybe four times faster or
something like that hopefully so we get
another speed boost there before laying
in a bunch of gnarly math computations
for doing our images right anyway that's
it for handmade Hiro for today thanks
everyone for joining me - next weekend I
think we'll go back to doing regular
handmade Hiro programming where we'll
try to get some lighting again actually
working in the game now which we wanted
to do GPU accelerated which does a
little bit of red casting actually just
not for the entire image so we'll be
back on that next weekend hopefully I'd
be here
for that till then keep in mind if you
would like to play around with handmade
hero source code and I will next weekend
when the source code gets updated I will
also include the raycasting source so
that if you want play around that you
can always pro2 the game on handmade
hero dot oregon it will come with all
that good stuff for you we also have a
forum site if you want to ask questions
we have a patreon page you want support
the video series a schedule bot it tells
you where we're gonna be live and an
episode guide you can use to catch up on
old editions of the series that's it for
me I will be back next week till then
take care everyone and I'll see you on
the Internet
thank you everybody