and start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show recode
a complete game live on stream we have
well yesterday we sort of added doing
sort of a fog blend versus alpha
blending and we're sort of doing part of
our render or Z clean up right now and
what I wanted to do is I want it to go
in today I think and actually make sort
of slices a first class citizen so
that's the really big change that needs
to happen and you know it's it's going
to take a little bit of work and I think
today would be the right day to get
started on that we kind of you know
we're kind of all set up for it now we
just have to cut go in there and
actually get it done here's the day
today is 297 so use 296 source code if
you want to follow along at home in the
meantime I'm going to load up that sweet
sweet project here it is all right so
I'm going to run the game as it stands
currently so you can kind of see where
we're at and so we did this test where
we place the tiles that kind of fade out
up into the distance right and we we
sort of did this testing and you can
kind of see that we have some z's
sorting problems there of the kind that
I discussed yesterday but then we also
have some issues where for example right
now we're not treating these slices of
separate things all objects are kind of
being fed in uniformly and so we get
some problems such as if I am to go do
the Alpha fade out so for example like
here see right it's kind of a
little bit tricky to see because there's
not a lot of it going on but any
overlapping objects that we have alpha
fade out together separately right so
basically like if you look what we would
want to have happen here and I can slow
this down
oh you know what we have a thing for us
I can slow this transition down
considerably to show you what I'm
talking about so let's say we throw it
slow it down to ten percent of its
original speed right so i can see
everyone is moving very slowly so take a
look right here at Monstar torso who's
hopping around as i hopped down to the
level below take a look at what happens
to him and to the thing below him right
and we've talked about this before by
just want refresh your memory do you see
how he fades out in addition to the tile
fading out and you can see the tile
behind him while he's fading out right
and that's not really what we want we
don't want the objects that are sitting
on tiles above us to fade out as well as
the tiles fade out in sort of a separate
per object fade what we want is that
whole coherent image that whole piece to
fade out as one image so it still looks
like a coherent thing that we're just
sort of moving through it's becoming
more ethereal as a whole right so that
is what I want to get to and we have
another issue that we need to address
coming down the pipe a little later on
which is lighting that we did some work
on earlier and we'll do a little bit
more work on before we're done and that
also wants to have an understanding of
these slices because our lighting is
going to be very much US based on an
understanding of a 2d slice and how the
light in it is working right so we need
this this understanding of the slices
and I want to start putting information
into the renderer so that it can decide
to render each slice as a separate thing
and in order to do that we need some
kind of communication regarding that now
I have an idea about how we might do
this and it's a little while
ki but I'm just going to throw it out
there and you'd see what you think my
idea was we already have the notion of a
clip wrecked and so I was thinking why
not have clip Rex have the information
on them about slices since every entry
knows that it goes with a particular
clip wrecked it seems only fitting that
we go ahead and throw all of our
information about what goes into a slice
into the clip wrecked that way we just
set up a series of clip Rex one for each
slice which don't actually do any
additional clipping right they can all
have the same clip rectangle but each
one of those would have with it in the
the information about what to do with
that slice like should it be fog should
it be faded what order should it be
drawing anything we want to do like that
right so that seems to me like a pretty
reasonable thing to do I don't know
that's just my gut instinct and so I'm
you know just thinking that would be the
easiest way to go because if we don't do
that we would need to introduce a sec
like a separate concept really right
that's about these Z slices and yet you
know because we need to be able to
gather things up into these slices and
draw the slices as separate things
because if we didn't do that then what
would happen is that when we do our
rendering we couldn't do stuff like put
them in a render buffer by themselves so
that they could be alpha faded out
separately the other thing that I'm what
the other thing we could do as another
potential option is to duplicate the
render group right so we could have
multiple render groups one for each
slice and just you know sort of render
render render render and put the slices
in sort of separately I don't know if
that's a particularly good idea
but that's another thing we could do
right and I don't know which of these is
the smartest thing I I really don't and
so we should just sort of take a look
and see what's going to be involved each
of them or you know maybe there's a sort
of a thing that's separate from all of
those that we want to do as well alright
so we already know some information
about how these things should be moved
into slices potentially right and that
is we know the Z sort of taught the the
Z packing address of each of our of each
individual entity right and at the
moment we have a little bit of an odd
pneus in that those I I don't know that
those are particularly aligned to
Flora's exactly yet and that is a little
bit of an issue like we don't have a
solid of an idea of what it means to be
on this floor or that floor right we
just sort of have a 3d spatial query
that allows you to place things
arbitrarily in 3d so even though it's a
2-d game right it's actually free to
kind of place things arbitrarily in 3d
so the question is you know how do we
start by even knowing what sliced
something's in and it seems to me that
you know when we're we kind of want
those slices to be represented in the
world storage since we know that the
world is evenly sliced up into them so
it seems to me that we could easily say
that whatever our sort of packing
tranche is going to be that would be a
good indication of where we should get
drawn or which slice we should get drawn
in now it's a little tricky because we
haven't typically after you know when we
when we go to do our rendering we
haven't typically figured out where a
particular entity is going to be packed
right but we certainly could meaning
after we do our move entity call we
could do the the packing here where we
say okay let's determine
we're in packing space you would be
right similarly we could also just take
just that z value and figure out what
that Z value implies because we only
need to really do basically a flooring
operation on Z and then we could assume
that you were in that tranch just from
that piece of information right so if we
have that piece of information then we
should be able to assign numbers to
these things and I feel like we just
wanted to sign numbers in a very
straightforward ways such as 0 is the
floor that the player is looking at
right and then negative numbers go down
floors so floors that are you know two
floors behind below us is floor negative
2 and floors that are above us would be
for like 1 2 3 4 and really we only
track one floor above us before it alpha
fades out so we really only need to
worry about there's floor one is the one
above us that's alpha fading out there's
40 which is the one we're on and there's
floral ex- one two three four that we
can kind of see off below us in the
distance if we look down any kind of
holes in the floor so if I if I want to
go that route then here in the entity
transform right I've already got this
notion of the offset p which has a
z-value baked into it right I can also
say okay well you know entity transforms
can certainly also have that notion of
what the floor is right so I could have
something like you know a slice index in
here and the slice index could get set
now similarly you know we've got this
u16 here that's a type I could easily
slip that into a you ate for the type
right something like this where wherever
you wait for the type and I have a you
wait for the slice index and that way we
can you know sort of keep again that
header to be very minimal if we want to
be it's still only 32 bytes long but it
would store which clip wrecked we were
using in which
slice index are using so if we want to
we could assign the slices i purely
without the clip Rex at all right and we
could have them be a separate thing the
other option like i said before would be
to go and do it more this way where we
say all right inside the render entry
clip wrecked that itself would have the
information about like the global color
and all those sorts of things right and
it would have what its slice index was
right yeah so something like this and
you know that that clip record also keep
in in it the information that this is a
proper slice it wants to be rendered as
a separate piece and then composited in
potentially blah blah blah blah blah
okay so yeah so who knows where we're
going to pack that if we wanted to do
something like where we would have the
clip Rex be that piece of information
then what we would do at the outset is
we would figure out how many things deep
we want to draw and we would just create
that many clip Rex so if we look at the
clip wreck that we've got here you can
see well that's not the one I'm talking
about risk my clip wrecked so I guess I
guess we're just using the default clip
wrecked at the moment in fact we're not
even assigning any clip Rex so yep so
this would be the first time we'd be
doing it but at the top we would just
say all right how many of these are we
going to do how many clip Rex are we
going to have and that's what we would
make so let's take a look at what that
would look like so what wrecked
so here is our push clip rock so up here
at the top before well I don't even know
before I guess it could be after that we
would do something where we'd say okay
how many of these clip Rex do we want to
have and we would push them all on onto
the render group that we're working with
and each one of these would get stored
in some array that we could look up into
later right so we'd say something like
okay there's our cliff Brecht indices
clip brick index or something like this
and each clip wrecked index is going to
be based on the maximum number of levels
we want to draw right so we'd say
something like I don't know minimum
level index and maybe the minimal level
indexes for and the maximum level index
is one look I sang before and so if we
wanted to know how many of these slices
we would need right we'd have the
maximum or you know total level index is
going to be the maximum level index
minus the minimum level index right and
so then we'd have something like this
now of course I'm not allowed to use
that value even though the compiler
could trivially tell that it's known at
compile time I would have to put a
concert why you would have to put a
Const to specify that an obviously
constant value is constant I have no
idea that's just the minds of the C++
people they are unfathomable to a normal
programmer certainly but I could do this
or something similar if I wanted to
right and that would give me the correct
information so oak like I said you need
to do plus one
so that's how many levels we would need
and so if we want to initialize those
levels right we can just say like level
index equals zero level index is less
than however many there were in here and
you'll notice that I could have used
total level index but I don't really
want to in fact I might even say let's
do that because I don't really want to i
always like to just refer to the actual
thing I'm iterating if possible rather
than use the constant that I know it was
set to so I think it just it it reduces
the possibility for error so if I loop
through each of these level indices I
could then say like oh let's get a clip
direct index for each of these levels
and what I'm going to push on here for
the the 0 Y and then width and the
height is just whatever we started our
our render group doing right so we're
getting a render group passed into us
obviously but when we do our perspective
you know we know the draw buffer width
and height so we pretty much know what
the clip region is going to be for this
thing it's going to be passed in
directly as as that width height and
we're not because we're not sub clipping
it at all so we would just generate that
miniclip regions and then we would just
set each of our clip Rex to be whenever
we're sort of rendering any individual
entity we would just make sure that the
clip wreck that we were going to use is
is the one that corresponds to the slice
that entity goes into so you can see
that we have the clip wrecked here the
current clip wrecked index and right now
if I remember correctly current clip
wrecked index we just set that directly
right so current clip wreck index is
just something reset so we would say
like okay the render group current clip
wrecked index
we just save whatever that was and then
later we would restore it and that's
probably something we should have a
utility for and I don't know that we do
I don't see one do you I don't see one
so I'm just going to say okay let's make
one so we don't do this all over the
place for no reason anytime we need to
put your clip rep we could use this so
we could say like a temporary clip
wrecked or something like this or click
direct restore I don't know what it
should be called I don't really care
what it's called but here we have a
constructor and destructor pair for it
and we'll just say that okay this thing
stores the render group
and we're just going to do exactly this
so there's that old flip wrecked we save
it maybe you know what i'll call it
transient flip correct that seems
reasonable so here's what would happen
on transient clip entry we would take a
new clip wrecked index and that new clip
repped index is what we would set and
then when we close will reset it and of
course because you can't refer to outer
scopes again the majesty of c++ i have
to copy this in for no reason it's
fabulous isn't it anyway so here we go
we'll just say there's a transient clip
wrecked and we can also say here that if
you don't specify anything then all it's
doing essentially is saving whatever the
clip wrecked was and it's assuming
you're going to set it in here to
whatever you want to set it to right and
in fact we could even do something a
little bit snappier here not a real word
where we say oh yeah if you wanted to
you could just do the exact same thing
right but make it so that you don't ever
actually execute that override right
don't ask me why I put team next there
make sense so here I can just say well
I'm going to make a transient clip
wrecked it's going to restore the old to
pick for me so now i can kind of you
know with reckless abandon i can go in
and say oh let's just let's just assign
whatever clip brecht we want to whomever
we want and so what i could do here is
say well alright temporarily let's just
see if this works at all by picking
three different clip wrecks up here
alright so I'll do clip wrecked zero
printer group alright collecting next I
will just say ok there's clip bricks
there's a clip wrecked one what are
these called is a clip back to index or
click click right click something clip
clip clip clip rectangle x yeah so I can
just say ok there's clip acting necks
and each of these will go into a
different one right ok
sup oops we need to pass the render
project so in this particular case right
we come into the trip we come into the
stranding typically will save the old
one for us so that anyone who's on the
outside of this will have the clip
breakfast toward which is you know
something we would obviously want to
have happen and you know in order to
make this work I need to make sure that
there's nothing here that needs that
clip wrecked so this is kind of
something that probably wants to be part
you know of of this sort of entire
render operation right meaning this
block is where this wants to happen
since simulate entities is relatively
heavy weight here as well and you know
we go through those and do this the
simulation render kind of a thing in a
in one batch air that I think probably
wants to be broken out to a new function
now that's just my my gut feeling so I'm
going to go ahead and move that here
that's going to take a bunch of
parameters so we're going to have to
figure out what all those are and so I'm
going to go ahead and just call that
here update and render entities and grab
all this stuff okay so you know first
things first obviously we're going to
need a render group we're going to need
sim region probably need a lot else time
function we're going to need the camera
key is that so where is the canopy
so just who does anyone actually use
this piece of information anywhere so
sort of is the answer it gets used by
this dude here so i guess for now we
could say let's pass it fade top starts
z so those guys i guess are specified in
the world mode somewhere else slicked up
in here world mode i think that is
actually called like game mode world and
then these clip Rex can be generated in
here for now we might want to move them
out later but we'll see for now we can
actually just us in here while we get
this working so here's that clip rekt
information and then of course we need
that draw buffer width and height now
actually I suppose technically we don't
because we could just say that we want
to clone the existing clip wrecked that
we were using right and that's kind of
something that we would like to have
happen anyway so if you take a look at
current clip rekt index that is actually
something that in the game render
commands we could look up what that
actual clip rekt was and push it right
so in platform
you can see in here that we've kind of
got this array of clip Rex right and I
assume that that hasn't been filled out
yet and that that will only get filled
out later but maybe that's not true like
I said I don't really remember how that
code was going does it know what the
clip rekt is normally ooh I'll down
three key there let's find out let's
find out so let's say I do a push clip
group clip right push clip rep says okay
here's the commands we're going to push
when I here and we daisy chain them
looks like right
you can see the like first wreck last
wrecked so they just get kind of daisy
chained daisy chain through so that
means it's not really that easy for us
if we want to look up a clip wrecked
right we so whatever the current clip
wrecked is is actually relatively tricky
for us to look up because we haven't
linearized those anywhere right so
whatever the current clip wrecked index
thing is you know it would probably be
who've us to save what they save with
that clip wreck was so that we could use
it again I don't know that all seems to
add up to me to be a little bit too much
so I think what I would rather do is
just say okay let's go ahead and just
pass this piece of information in so
i'll pass the draw buffer and just let
that continue working the way it was
working because i don't really want to
go down that particular rat hole at the
moment and i feel like there's a lot of
stuff we could potentially do there
right alright so let's see loaded bitmap
draw buffer so in this case we'll just
pass that in there and then background
color is what we cleared to and we do
need to know that as well although
that'll probably come from a more you
know reasonable place in the future
so dt4 frame is already being passed
here it doesn't need to be passed that
way and translate assets is definitely
necessary draw hit points can be moved
in here as well and mouse the mouse p we
can pass but we're not really using that
at the moment that was really a
debugging thing right alright so we'll
go ahead and pass that here and these
are all named exactly the same things as
they were named so in theory if we just
literally delete the definition of the
variable type we've got the right call
presumably oops don't know why that's
still there all right so now in theory
we're actually we are actually doing
that clipping and we could test this
potentially as well by actually
shrinking one of the clip Rex so for
example if we go into the bush clip
wrecked stuff in entity now see here
we could choose to say well all right
you know here's the code for the normal
one but if you're on the zeroeth level
which is actually in this case because
we're going you know it's it's negative
4 negative 3 negative 2 negative 1 0 1
right it's actually going to be the
maximum level index minus the minimum
level index right it's kind of really
think about it it's actually going to be
this right it's going to be this minus 1
because it's going to be this span which
is like I want to be the maximum but I
want to be back by one another way to
think of it would just be you know we
could actually even just hard code it
where we just say like okay so these
correspond this way well the night I
think about it we were kind of at the
moment we're shoving them in this way so
I should probably use this temporarily
since that's what we actually care about
so here is the the default is to that's
stuff that's completely in view so I'm
just going to say like if level index
equals to do one thing otherwise do the
other so here you know when we've got
the width I'm just going to say like
okay just let's let's pretend that we
only had half the screen and since this
one since we'll just divide by two
and so now we should get a thing where
yeah you can kind of see we're entirely
clipped to that lower part of the screen
but because we're only doing it to one
you can see the layer above us doesn't
have that restriction right so if I take
it back you can even make this a little
bit more explicit so if I kind of come
up here oops
if I jump up to a level where things
start to fog fade those wouldn't be
clipped either I know why I continue
jumping there it was not smart
there we go so those guys are starting
to fog fog fade out so if i restore that
clipping you can now see like nothing
gets clipped that's on the fogging out
layers nothing gets clipped it's on the
Alpha layers but that mid ground stuff
is clipped so we do know that these are
sorting into the correct buckets now if
we were just bucketing based on whether
or not you were going to get fogged
right alright so now we have to kind of
think this through a little bit more
carefully right now we have to actually
start assigning floor numbers to these
things and obviously we don't actually
want to do any kind of different
clipping we want the clipping to stay
the same but this information here where
we sort of have the camera relative
ground PZ and all that stuff that
information now kind of wants to be with
the clip wrecked right or you know if
again or if we create a non clip rec
thing for storing it it wants to be with
whatever that other thing is so we want
to say something like camera relative
ground p is now going to be computed per
level right / like individual slice and
in order to figure out where those
slices are we're going to start to need
to be more rigorous about the rules
about where a slices in the Z range
right so let's pause for a second and
just if0 this out and just make sure
that no one cares right what that value
is and they don't right so if we run it
now everyone just going through the
default clip wrecked and you can also
see that of course we've got the issue
of if we aren't going to run through
that then nobody gets alpha blended out
at all right so there's that
so coming back to this let's say that we
wanted to do this computation but we
want to do this computation per level
index well then what we would need is we
would still need to know what the camera
relative ground point is right so we
would need to know camera relative
ground Z and that's not something we
really would know how to compute just
yet that's okay we can figure it out and
what we would do here is just use
exactly the same logic that we were
using before but now instead of setting
it per item we would just set it per
clip wrecked and then whatever clip
rector you went into that would be what
would determine what was going on right
so when we do push clip wrecked here we
would now be able to specify this
additional color info and maybe we would
call this like you know this year would
be like a clip wrecked blending or
something like this or clip clip direct
effects I don't know something like this
and that clip rep wrecked effects clip
wrecked F X would be the thing that
stores this information so we would
basically say that that global color
goes away and we just have a color and a
tee color for the effects the moment
and oh and we got to do this one here so
and then when we do push clip rekt we
would say oh and by the way we want you
to use this special effects thing that
we set up right so that's really all I'm
thinking and I guess this one doesn't
have to be initialized at all it's just
the null effect same with here so that's
really all I'm talking about right this
would be the entirety of it we just have
to know with the relative camera see
what you know what that was but
otherwise this would all work just fine
provided that we were able to figure out
where the entity actually went so what
we would have to do here is we have to
figure out for any given Z what level
index it was actually in right and
that's a you know again easier said than
done because we have to do sort of a
careful analysis of how to truncate Z
values down to the correct sort of
bucket if you will but hey nobody said
it was easy so you just gotta just gotta
you know bite the bullet okay so for
every entity we know what its Z value is
relative to the camera right so we can
still use this part which we're not
using up there anymore you can still use
this down here and camera relative
ground pz gives us the information that
we would need to create those buckets
now what I don't know is why we would
still do it up at the top right because
that's the wrong place to do it we
should move the end we can now fix the
bug we had before basically and I think
we even had to do there at one point
where what we would like to do is do it
here when we're about to render so that
the objects been transformed already
right that would be much preferable
so here our camera left of ground p get
ground point right Kim relative pz is
the information we need we're not gonna
set that equal to anything so what i
need to do now is figure out what is the
z layer that this thing is in in our
system right so i want to say something
like you know clip rekt index and i
probably wanna do something like if get
clip rec for something uh although now i
think about it i may want to phrase this
a little bit differently i may want to
phrase this more like well let's take
the camera relative ground PZ and do
whatever the truncation thing is or
whatever to it so relative layer from
kind of a thing right so that would
produce one of those numbers negative 4
21 or whatever and then we could say
well alright if the relative layer is
and I don't know I called those levels
up at the top and calling the layers now
can you tell I can tell I'm overworked
it's true you know it's weird I don't
mind being overworked programming wise
at all it's really only the stress of
not having the time to do things right
and worrying about what will happen that
ever really gets to me I kind of really
like having lots of programming to do
it's very nice probably when I'm a
programmer anyway so yeah I don't even
know why I did that it's really just
this that I want I want to say that this
thing has to be between those two I
don't want to render anything that's not
because if it's not between those two
why clog up the renderer why even bother
looking for the bitmaps when we know
that they're simply not relevant right
so all of this stuff doesn't have to
happen really because it's not on the
screen so we can just go ahead and
kind of truncate that part off right
yeah so let's go ahead and move to sort
of the the money part of this here which
is that when we oh hey look the offset p
is already computing this exact value so
really all we needed to do here with say
well whatever the offset p was that
offset pz is the piece of information we
actually needed right uh and that's
going to need to get broken up into two
pieces basically that right because
we're now going to be trying to
bifurcate the concept of z into two
things one is what slice it goes into
and the other is is the Z in that slice
and the reason that we need those to be
two separate pieces of information is
because one of them is going to displace
the object and why but not produce any
scaling or perspective artifacts whereas
the other one which is what slice it's
in is going to do those things so we
need to know that information right we
need to have that sort of additional
data if you will and so we want to kind
of be aware of that so when we do entity
transform offset p what we're going to
want to do is something probably like
this we're probably going to want to say
hey here's a z-value i want to get back
the relative layer and i want you to
take out the layer part and just leave
me the remainder you know I'm saying so
we'd say like a you know
convert to layer relative something like
that and then when it does that it's
going to give me back the layer in terms
that I understand here and it will
update this Z value that it gets passed
so that that Z value can then be used as
a proper y offset which is the thing
that we really wanted to get to
eventually can sort it can you see how
this is sort of starting to come
together finally right the the you know
because we've had it in there a long
time we were never really sure and now
we kind of finally have a path towards
handling Z in a way that I think will be
mostly constructive most of the time
which is that we have this notion of
slices which can do the scaling and then
we have Z inside the slices that does
the displacement and I'm hoping that
that will be the best sort of compromise
since we're not since our artwork is 2d
and we want to and we don't want to do
3d stuff because we don't have actual
solid geometry started to back that up
right we need everything to be sort of a
little faux mmm all right so really
that's all we would need because if we
had that magic function we could do a
lot of good stuff with it and and we
would just in here set the current clip
rekt index equal to our clip breath
index looked up by that relative layer
right the relative layer needs to be
rebased to fit into this array but
that's not particularly difficult
because we know that if we just subtract
the minimum from it we will get one
that's relatively indexed into it right
so that's it
not a lot of confusion there so now
let's get to the what I said I said it
was going to be tricky obviously that's
not tricky the tricky part is in here
making sure anytime discrete math rears
its ugly head you know that it's going
to get a little finicky right it's just
going to get a little tweaky because you
got to be rut you got to be just right
and whenever you got to be just right
it's a lot harder than just having to be
sort of right so here we go there's our
convert layer to relative and I think
before we write it we want to start
thinking about this part right here
which is to say that these floor levels
the camera relative ground Z is going to
have to have some kind of a notion of
where the camera is relative to where
the absolute ground slices are right and
so what that would actually mean is you
gyming if we were to take the cameras
location we would want the cameras
location in world in the actual world
space right so if i go into sim region
here i think we have the origin in as a
world position right now that origin as
a world position tells us
two things it has the absolute tiles II
and it has the offset from that absolute
tiles II right and the camera relative
ground Z is just going to be whatever
that Z offset is right because the
closest ground round tile would it be it
offset 0 right so the relative ground Z
is going to be displaced by whatever the
offset is it gets like that right all
right we gotta go do this part as well
but it's going to be displaced by
whatever this offset is and then it's
going to be displaced by one entire
floor height for every one I go up or
down right so what I'm looking at like
minimum level index or that sort of
stuff right if I'm down four levels well
that's minus four entire floor heights
so typical floor height for example and
that sort of stuff is what we would want
to know here so I'm going to go ahead
and look to see ya and you can see that
right there that's our world div
invaders so basically we can just say
well our typical floor height is where
we're making these slices at so we would
say that the typical floor height is
just going to be multiplied by the floor
index
and our relative layer index is you know
whatever the level index is it's plus
that minimum level index so it starts at
negative 4 runs up to 1 and that's how
we would know how much typical floor
height to add in right so that's pretty
straightforward when we do convert to
layer relative here we have this notion
that the same thing should be happening
we want to bucket into the exact same
set of possibilities here right and so
this is essentially we can do this exact
thing using the code we already have in
world I believe right so if we want to
we could say like well all right let's
just where is that guy let's just use
map into chunks face right or something
similar we can use that to do the
operation that we actually wanted to do
right because if we get a z-value that's
relative to the camera we know that we
could just use the cameras base pose
base position and that offset to give us
back as e value that's the exact same
kind that we were doing here right so it
would have it would have an ABS tiles e
right that would tell us what that what
that slice should be what that actual
index is relative to to the camera that
makes sense so yeah so what I'm saying
is if we were to call this it would give
us the the right thing but map in the
trunk space obviously just calls rican
annika lies coordinate right and so what
we could say here is well let's just use
the Wrekin Annika lies coordinate call
directly since we only have to do this
on z now we know the chunk dimension
that
talking about right it's this typical
floor height and that typical floor
height is going to have to be renamed
because that's actually a literal thing
now that's like how high is one floor
they're always the same so if you wanted
to make things that were skipped to
floor you could do that but you can't
change the floor arbitrarily anymore and
the reason for that of course is that
our concept of how we slice things into
layers is based entirely on this piece
of information right so when we reach a
comic canonicalize the coordinates we
need to specify that game world mode and
then for our tile and our tile relative
well we want to know what we are
relative to where the camera was right
and furthermore we kind of want to know
here is not just relative to where the
camera was but relative to where the
floor that we would be looking at was
if that makes sense uh yeah I'm gonna
have to think this through a little more
carefully but you get the basic idea so
here's the relative index here's the
tile relative value we're going to
return that relative index and it will
truncate the Z value for us right and
only thing I'm not 100% sure about
is whether those two things line up
exactly but no matter we'll tackle that
in a second because we're going to debug
this anyway so let's finish the other
part here which is giving these render
groups a piece of important information
right which is the clip rekt effects so
there's the render unto clip wrecked and
here's the clip rekt affects the clip
rectify really just a removal of these
global values from the render group and
a placing of them into the clip wrecked
now this is going to cause some
consternation for us in the renderer
we're going to have to do a little bit
of extra work here and the reason for
that is because the clip wrecked now has
to have that information merged in at
the end right but that's okay we can
handle it we're professionals ostensibly
so you can see here when we do store
color right we're producing you know we
sort of did this nicely so that it gets
stored the pepperoni do it and
unfortunately now what we're fact it
going to have to do is undo this right
we're going to have to say don't when
you start color just throw them directly
and then what we'll do is when we
actually use these things in the
renderer at that time when you look up
the clip wrecked you'll you'll do the
operation and now you may say isn't this
a bad idea because the whole point of
this was we were supposed to be you know
having these things alpha out or we're
supposed to be like doing this
efficiently well what we're going to
have to do is probably render at least
the Alpha fading one has to be rendered
as a separate plate anyway so the this
effect has to be applied separate from
the entities the enemies would get
rendered themselves and then this effect
would get applied after the fact right
now for fog
we can put everything in the same clip
rekt eventually so to be honest we
probably don't have to be as fancy as I
was being because I don't think for fog
layers we really need to separate things
into those layers we really just need
three layers or possibly even just to
just the one above us and the one that's
below the one that's like everything
going out into the distance that's not
being alpha faded right so actually
storing it in each one and separate
thing is really just an exercise at this
point and we can probably get it simpler
afterwards yeah and and really it's just
to make sure like I guess the way I
would say it is I need to make sure that
I actually can do this operation
accurately like I need to make sure that
we verify that i can put them into
slices because the offset Z needs to
make sure that you've put it into the
right slice correctly so the reason I'm
doing all of them first pass through
which I didn't quite explain originally
is I want to then color by slice to
guarantee that everything is getting
assigned to the right slice and then
later I think we can actually back out
the number of slices and probably just
have to because I think we're only going
to need the Alpha fade slice and then
the other slices so even though we will
know what flights things are right we
won't actually have to assign it to a
slice because all that is going to
matter is that that slice index is used
for the perspective effect and we can do
that in line we don't have to wait till
at render correlation if that makes
sense so so yeah so it's it's a little
dicey like it's a little hat six of one
half dozen the other I'm not sure what
we want to do with that global color
thing in some sense because you know we
may still want the notion that you're
going to use this this
store color to do fogging effects on
people that are all in the same layer
that are getting different fog values
you know that that is plausible it's not
entirely out of the question but at the
same time I don't know that might not be
the most efficient way to do the fog
anyway it might be that we want to do Z
based fog or who knows what else instead
of doing it per slice anyway so I'm just
not sure but what I do know is that the
store color definitely has to at least
be flexible enough to allow us to store
stuff in the FX as well right and so
that probably means we could make this
be a fogging only kind of effect store
color but I guess now that I think about
it we probably should leave it in the
global because as I talk that through I
was remembering yeah we we can go back
to having those other layers can fog
themselves just just fine and they don't
need to be broken up into slices as far
as the render is concerned so all right
so I'll leave these two in here for the
moment but then eventually we might get
rid of them oops all right so let's see
here these values just need to get moved
up there we go push flip wrecked
obviously we haven't modified to take
one of these you know calls so let's
take a look here's push clip wrecked and
I'll just say that you know push clip
wrecked can take a clip direct effects
and that can be a pointer there and so
what we'll do is when we actually do
this push we can just say well the
effects will either be 0 for the push
and you know what I could just do it
this way I suppose
convert to layer relative needs to take
the world mode and so nothing in
particular should be happening now
although you can see that we do have a
problem with how we're drawing these and
I guess I shouldn't say we have a
problem we're doing what we wanted to do
which is to say that we are taking the
indices and we're flooring them but
since we now aren't actually obeying the
perspective since we don't put the
prospective transform anywhere we aren't
drawing the world that those slices
aren't actually doing their sort of
perspective duty if that makes sense but
we're out of time so i will go to QA and
we'll tackle that tomorrow
huh
and by the way while i'm waiting for Q&amp;A
i would i would ask the question in so
far as is in sabah ready to to be made a
moderator yet or not I didn't know when
that was supposed to happen because I
need to remember to go do that on a
machine that where I can assign mod ops
in fact let me rephrase that insofar s
when you are ready for in so bot to have
moderator privileges email me and when I
see that email i will add mod privileges
looks like there are no questions I can
do to bed early
pig in a it's been a while did I see you
programming without wrist braces are you
not affected anymore um so you know uh
it's it's been an ongoing issue and it's
been a little weird I have I have a lot
to say on that topic but i don't know
that i have anything particularly
definitive to say my physical therapist
who i trust she's one of the only
medical professionals I know who is very
very like I don't want to say smart
because obviously I knew plenty of smart
medical professionals but she has that
sort of a functional approach like like
sort of mechanical approach to problem
solving that's like she really does
actual debugging work to a certain
degree which I almost never see in
medical professionals like like I have
no idea where to go to a doctor in
seattle where they're actually like a
good debugger you know for a hard
medical problem and she said that she
doesn't think the wrist braces are a
good idea so I tried not using them and
what I found in general is that with and
without the wrist braces tend to have
different sorts of like wrist or or i
should say hand problems and i don't so
i don't know that they really are
necessary at least not for me i don't
know if they really helped or hurt what
i have found that is like perhaps not
that surprising but it's a little early
to tell is i started rock climbing again
because i felt like in you know Emily
the physical therapist I was talking
about you know would say the same thing
I felt like I just don't get enough arm
exercise that's you know regular arm
exercise and like
the building and stuff like that in a
given day anyway I get like almost none
and so I started doing rock climbing
again and I like my wrists and hands
feel much better than they have for a
long time like much much better and so I
don't know that's just you know take it
with a grain of salt so far but I would
say that I would say that it's kind of
like been the most improvement I've seen
in terms of how my arms and hands feel
is is just rock climbing he's Jeff
Atwood a good programmer like I have no
idea I don't even think I know who Jeff
Atwood is I think I maybe I mean I know
I've heard the name but I have no idea
and I said never worked with them so I
have no idea how I would even know I
mean maybe if he says something
obviously stupid or something we're just
like wow this person was really not
another program you know then you could
say that someone's probably not a good
programmer just from you know cursory
glance but most of the time if you
really want to know if someone's a good
program right now you kind of have to
work with them and you know see how they
attack problems how much work they get
done or how are they handle new things
are they efficient and how maintainable
zar code and blah blah blah and that's
not you know I mean you read someone's
blog or something and you can't you
don't know some people may come across
is not particularly good but they're
actually very effective in practice some
people may come across as very very
smart you think they're great but
actually getting a work done and they're
very bad the actual like act of getting
code together and working and
maintaining it right and so I feel like
it's really hard to ever say whether you
think someone is a good program or not
honestly and have any kind of a chance
of being right if you haven't worked
with them
hmm even looking at their code isn't a
good example right because you know I
have plenty of things I've written that
are just awful right and if you happen
to look at that or something you know
maybe you think I program really poorly
or maybe you pick something really good
that I did and you look and you think oh
my God he's amazing right and the truth
is that you're neither of those things
it's like you know you have high points
and you have low points and so you kind
of got to see you kind of got to see
what happens when you were working on
switching between the software and
hardware under yesterday why did it look
like there was a skill a very slight
color difference um so we don't know
specifically why there is a very slight
color difference because we have not
investigated that exactly but we expect
to see a very slight color difference
and the reason for that is we are just
using an approximation to gamma which is
squaring and square rooting the values
whereas OpenGL is using an exact gamma
or at least a very close to exact gamma
in the hardware so they're like a 2.2
curve or something close to it right and
we're a 2 point 0 curve and so we know
that our software renderer will have a
slight color difference from open jail
and that's expected so if we wanted to
verify that that was what the color
difference is we'd still have to do some
more work but since that really wasn't
what I was doing I didn't feel it was
necessary but I knew when the color
difference was drastic I knew there was
no way that was right because the
difference between a gamma 2 curve in a
game a 2.2 curve while it's visible is
not all that visible right it's not
drastic and it was clearly drastic right
in that in that context so I wanted to
make sure that that we found what the
real bug was and we did now that doesn't
mean that there isn't some other bug in
there but the slight color difference is
absolutely expected
what would you say are the top three
things that have made Molly rocket
successful in your eyes from a startup
business perspective Molly rocket isn't
successful we don't make money right
we're working on to game projects right
now and we have nothing to sell so we're
definitely not successful whether or not
we're successful will basically be
determined by when we finish handmade
hero which is obviously kind of not
really a product as much because I have
to do it on stream so it's slow and we
can't you know it's a community thing
that can't I can't just go burn you know
hard on it for a month and finish or you
know the game or whatever I have to do
it in piecemeal on specific way but when
handmade hero in 1935 or both you know
out did they make back their investment
right and so you know where we have very
nice financing right which is because
jeff was willing to you know take a bet
on us we probably won't go out of
business because we run out of time
because we can you know take an extra
six months or something if we need to
but you know when we when we actually
put a product out there we're in Seattle
so our costs are high you know we we
don't have the luxury of paying people
you know forty thousand dollars a year
expecting them to be able to get by
right it's not Seattle is a very bad
cost of living town it's very expensive
it costs a lot to run a studio here so
you know when those games come out they
have to make back a substantial amount
of money and if they don't then then we
read just go out of business basically
and and we would try to find some place
that would hire Anna and myself to to do
something for them which I really hope
we don't have hope it doesn't come to
that but you know that's that's the the
truth of the matter so so I definitely
wouldn't call Molly rocket successful I
wouldn't necessarily call it
unsuccessful but it's definitely not
unknown quantity so I feel like it would
be you know really really premature to
suggest that there are our top three
things that make it successful because
got to be successful for you can
identify things that make you successful
piggin 00 do you mind name dropping her
I live in Seattle too and have a new
wrist issue with programming I do not
mind name dropping her at all in fact I
am a spoiler alert probably going to
like it's highly likely but don't take
it as an official announcement but it's
highly likely that i will also be
working with her at handmade con to get
people more information about wrist
issues and talk to people about risk
issues perhaps at the conference and
maybe give like you know a quick
presentation sort of thing or we're
we're probably going to try to do
something at the conference related to
wrist issues because it is so prevalent
I've asked by so many people so often
about wrist pain and hand pain problems
that they have and she's like the only
person I know who seems to be at all
good at trying that stuff out and
actually working through issues that
people have so I do not mind name
dropping her at all and I I will
probably be actively sort of asking her
to to help people in the community get
the resources they need to have a bit
have less pain when they work so I don't
know what the quickest way to do it is
but if you can remember PUREMOTION
physical therapy this is the site and I
you can go to like it's on westlake so
if you know where that is it's it's kind
of there's a giant weird building called
the china harbor which is this weird
like it's half community center and a
half chinese restaurant don't ask me
it's been there forever she's like right
next to that in like this sort of you
know storefront area that's got
like yachts yacht salesman and all sorts
of things in it and you can email oh I
guess you can just use this to submit a
request if you want to be seen and in
the comments just put Casey sent me I'm
a programmer who has risked problems and
she'll know what that means so there you
go and she takes most insurance that's
any good so if you have any reasonable
inference it you'd probably just pay you
know 20 bucks or some copay
as someone back at episode 54 how far
gone am I well you know it's not as bad
as you might think right I mean an
episodes only an hour so although they
say day 54 day 56 whatever it's like oh
my god day 54 today 300 must be forever
but it's like well if it's ours 300
hours is nothing it's like less than 10
weeks of programming time right or
something so you can do it it's not much
need sir do you find that your hands
shake when holding a drinking glass that
is the only time my hands shake at all I
don't find my hands shake that is not
really something that i have have found
so i i i don't i don't know really
anything about that
all right I'm gonna wind it on down uh
yeah and hopefully I mean yeah it'sit's
a long web web web site address but
PUREMOTION physical therapy that's the
place it's just her own it's her own
practice so you don't have to ask for
her it's her and she has her own you
know shop basically so yeah I would I
would just say should be pretty be
pretty easy to to make it happen
alrighty then um I'm going to close it
on down we're going to come back
tomorrow and start working on getting
those z's separated because now we've
kind of got that in place we got to
figure out how that's going to flow
through the pipeline which is a little
tricky so we gotta we're going to have
to to take care of that tomorrow thank
you everyone for joining me further
episode of handmade hero to the pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow along at home you can always p
order the game on handmade hero organic
comes with the source code so that you
can play around with it and learn from
it as you work your way through this
series we also have a forum you can go
to if you have questions we have a
patreon page you can use to support the
video series which is always much
appreciated and it's scheduled about the
tweet the schedule you if you want to
catch a stream live it if you do want to
catch a stream live be back here
tomorrow same time same place Eh p.m.
pacific standard that's right pacific
daylight time tomorrow for the last
stream of the week we also have an
episode guide if you need to catch up
with past episodes so in the meantime be
sure to check that out I will catch you
guys tomorrow until then f on
programming I'll see you guys on the
Internet