okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the show recode complete
games live on Twitch no engines no no
libraries no nothing it's just us and
today we're starting a topic that's
actually unfortunately bad news for
everyone out there unfortunately it's
important yep
and I don't say unfortunately because of
anything like because it's bad to have
important topics on hanbit here
obviously it's great to have important
topics on Hanneman here I say
unfortunately because really there is
nothing inherently inherently
interesting in some sense you might say
when you try to solve problems given
this thing that we're going to talk
about today it is literally just another
layer you have to pile on to the
problems that you already have so it's
not like optimization where you're
talking about taking a problem and
solving it down to a more fine level
this is not what this is what we're
talking about today is is really it just
adds to your to your troubles and in
some sense unfortunately this is the
thing that that really programming
languages and high-level stuff hasn't
really solved that well either it's it's
just relatively nasty and so on handmade
here we'll try to show some ways that
you can make it a lot less nasty and
think about it as a you know in in sort
of a simple way as possible but I won't
lie to you it is one of those things
that has just been sort of creeping up
on programming and it keeps being more
and more important to do and it never
really gets all that much easier I'm
beating around the bush but of course
the subject is multi-threading
multi-threading is the process by which
you have multiple simultaneously
executing CPU cores or separate
processors entirely working on problems
together and if you're lucky you can
separate them out so that
degree to which they have to communicate
with each other is very small if you are
unlucky then you cannot and really that
depends on the problem and sometimes
your own ingenuity let's go to the
blackboard first and I'll talk a little
bit about how this sort of stuff goes
down and then we'll sort of show how to
create some threads and get them doing
some things I don't know how far we'll
get into it today because we'll have to
cover the basics and win32 of how to
actually make these things but will by
tomorrow at least we'll be at the point
where we're actually having things
happen multi-threading it's not that
hard to get there all right so
multi-threading so first of all let's
just say very briefly what this even
means and why this phrase exists the way
it does so you'll notice you have this
thing called threading here which we've
never really talked about that much and
basically that's because there's these
words that have been introduced in
operating system parlance that have to
do with with certain degrees of
execution granularity and they tend to
be processed thread and fiber what what
generally these things refer to are the
degree of sort of logical separation
that an operating system does between
you know lines of execution so let me
just break them down for you very simply
so as you know on handmade hero right
we're writing a bunch of code and that
code looks like assembly language
instructions so there's like a NASM
instruction right followed by another as
of instruction followed by another as an
instruction right and there's a notion
of where in the code we are there's
thing called the instruction pointer we
talked about and it says you know I'm
here and I'm going to do this
instruction I do this instruction the
instruction pointer moves down to the
next one I do the next one right and we
also know there's a bunch of things like
registers that are here and we talked a
little bit about things like translation
lookaside buffer or the address table
and there's all these are the things
that the processor is doing that
basically allow us to map memory and do
all these sorts of things right so what
I want you to think about here is just
the fact that there's CPU state right
there's all the CPU state that says a
whole bunch of things that need
CPU needs to know in order to execute an
assemble damage instruction it needs to
know which instruction is executing for
starters it needs to know what the
memory layout is for the thing that it's
using right because we said everything's
virtual memory right so it needs to know
how addresses in the in the data map or
in the code map to actual addresses on
the physical chip of memory the chip
memory chips it needs to know what the
register states are like we have these
registers right we had those like Cindy
wide registers we were talking about
moving things in and out of those
registers well it's got to have the
registers right it's got to have all
these sorts of things right okay so it's
got that the question is how is this
broken up right how is the operating
system conceptualizing of this because
we know that multiple processes multiple
like logical processes to us as users
multiple applications I should say are
running at any given time and as we
talked about in hand may hero each one
of those has their own virtual address
space right so handmade hero has a
virtual address space that's its memory
layout but like mischeif has its own one
and they're both running on the same
machine okay
and so that is is this is this
granularity that is what we call a
process okay and what a process is is a
process is essentially the state of the
memory layout right the memory layout is
controlled on the process level and what
that's basically saying is okay when you
are running this particular application
on the CPU its memory layout looks like
this right but the rest of this stuff is
not per process right what azzam
instructions are running and and well so
that this the translation lookaside
buffer and the addresses are part of
memory right so this is all process
stuff right process process process the
registers the assembly instructions that
stuff is not per process it is actually
done at a level but
low process because each process may
want to have multiple simultaneous or
not even simultaneous possibly separate
code execution states which is what we
call threads so underneath a process
inside a process you actually have
multiple threads and threads are what
store the rest of this stuff a thread
knows where it is in in terms of what
instructions its executing a thread has
a state of the registers in the
processor right and so what you have to
start to think about is the fact that
these are actually sort of like there's
like two levels right so there's
processes which are sort of memory Maps
and a collection of threads and then
each individual thread stores additional
state that has to do with with the state
of the processor beyond just what the
memory map is okay so handmade hero is a
process that runs right it's an
executable and inside that process there
are many threads that run right now we
have written one of those threads the
main execution thread there are other
threads that are running that the
operating system starts that we have no
control over for example directsound
starts some threads the fact that we're
using direct sound at all starts some
threads in our process space that we
have no control over but that do things
with the audio device well the audio
output should say device so there are
multiple threads already in hand-made
here but only one of them have we have
we actually written okay now in addition
to processes and threads there's also
things called fibers which we won't
really talk about because they're not
super necessary but what a fiber is is a
thread and a fiber are very similar
things the difference is a thread is
something that is actually a first-class
operating system citizen that actually
exists on the hardware and the hardware
actually can run multiple of them at the
same time a fiber is sort of a main
newel version of a thread it's a thing
that lets you save the CPU state for
something but they don't execute
concurrently you basically say like I'm
capturing the state of this thing and
then I'm going to like restart it later
or something like that so we're not
really going to talk about those because
the reason that we're doing
multi-threading is to take advantage of
multiple CPU cores and stuff like this
we don't really need to worry about
fibers they were more things for
overlapping work in the old days when
you wanted to make it easier on yourself
and I read I really all I can say about
this I don't really want to talk about
they're not useful but know that they
did exist and you know you couldn't go
look up more information around if you
care about but this is what we care
about all right so why do we care about
this at all right why can't we just
write everything in one thread well the
reason is because as we've shown before
here in the windows task manager which I
opened by hitting ctrl shift escape
which you can do as well you can see the
number of logical processing units that
this CPU that I'm on has now this is a
Xeon machine it was originally a very
beefy machine so as you can see it has a
ton of these your machine if it's a
modern machine will probably only have
eight of these I think - twelve one two
three four five six seven eight nine ten
twelve thirteen fourteen fifteen sixteen
nevermind it's got sixteen so my
processor setup has roughly twice the
number of logical units as does the
common modern desktop which has four
cores each with two hyper threads or
eight slots right the reason I'm
pointing this out is because each one of
these things is capable of executing a
thread simultaneously effectively right
so what that means is the fact that
we've only written our code in handmade
hero on a single thread means that no
matter what we do effectively there is
you know if there are if there are
sixteen slots for executing things on
the CPU we have filled one of those
slots right so we are effectively
leaving
right fifteen sixteenths if you will of
our performance potentially on the table
because the CPU can only actually fill
one slot of execution with handmade hero
and the other 15 slots just sit around
waiting and maybe live for lucky they do
some work on behalf of the OS or
something right like graphics driver or
who knows what but for the most part
because we only wrote one thread the CPU
can only execute one out of the the
sixteen possible
units can it even fill right so our goal
with multi-threading on handmade hero
well it's actually twofold but the
primary thing that we're talking about
right now is we want to increase the
number of threads that we have available
to the processor to run so that it can
fill up logical processing units with
those threads and do more work on our
behalf
okay so there's two types of sort of
ways of thinking about this there is a
core and there is a hyper thread and
let's talk about what those are we've
mentioned them multiple times before but
just to be concrete a core is a set of
those units that we've talked about a
bunch of times that can do work right so
a core has instruction decoding right it
has arithmetic logic units on it it has
memory units on it right and basically
what a core is is it's a set of units
that can do work like our multiplies
like looking up addresses all of that
stuff is what a core actually has on it
okay now a core as we know can issue
several instructions per clock cycle if
there are instructions available for it
to issue we just got done with two weeks
of talking about stuff like that right
so hopefully that's all fairly
comfortable to you you
basically no in fact we were using that
IACA thing to tell us about how many
ports we could stuff with things and
which instructions went in which ports
all those sorts of stuff right so the
concept of a core the core is that thing
that we were looking at with the ports
that could have stuff filled right but
modern cores the x64 cores that we're
looking at here like the one that's in
this machine the ones that's on your
machine at your that for those of you
watching at home actually have the
ability to issue instructions from more
than one place at the same time so a
core that might have a bunch of Units
here like we saw it have you know like
five ports or whatever right and each of
those ports on any given cycle could
accept something right so you could if
you had a port free and an instruction
that could go into that port you could
issue it right and it could start doing
work for you well a hyper thread right
is basically the same thing as a thread
in terms of what it means right it's got
the CPU state it has a notion of where
it is in an instruction stream it has a
notion of what the register state is but
unlike threads as they were defined
before hyper threading came along what a
hyper thread can do is actually run
concurrently on the same core as another
hyper thread at the same time so in the
past used to have one thread per logical
core right so if I had a processor right
and it had two cores
here's core a and here's core B then the
what would happen is the operating
system would assign one thread to each
core so this core would be running this
thread and this core would be running
this thread and that's the end of it
here's thread a here's thread B they go
on the chorus they operate
simultaneously but that's it if one of
these cores is actually a hyper
threading core then what happens is it
actually assigns more than one thread to
the core and it depends on the hyper
threading counts some things to handle -
hyper threads this processor is - our
threads I believe some
hyper-threading chorus can do like four
hyper threads and basically it's just
how many slots the processor has for
storing things like the registers in the
instruction state and all that stuff
right and what happens here is on any
given clock cycle right so when the
clock cycle you know ticks over it's
like it's time to execute like four
instructions right I can execute like we
were saying up to four instructions on a
clock cycle what it does is it looks at
both threads and sees do either of these
two guys have instructions that can go
into the ports that I have available
right and so now instead of the
situation before like you know like we
were having where we're looking to go oh
okay
here's all the instructions you know
here's these as instructions right
here's thread thread see right and
here's these atom instructions oh they
all go on port one all the instructions
in the instruction window that I'm
looking at go in port one so you know
what I can only execute one in spike and
only issue one instruction this clock
cycle I guess I'll have to waste the
other three instructions that I could
have issued if only they go on two
different ports instead what it will do
is it will go oh well you know what I've
also got thread B right and here's some
asthma instructions there and yeah the
first one goes on port one but the
second one goes on port zero and the
third one goes on I'm sorry on port two
and that's what goes in port zero I'm
going to grab these other two as well
and now I can issue three instructions
on this clock cycle instead of only
having to issue one and so effectively
what you can think of this doing is it's
as if it were sort of free for the core
to switch which thread it was using at
any time and it can just bounce back
between them all the time even inside
one clock cycle right because it can
literally just grab from either of the
threads so it's it's actually much more
efficient than the old style where the
operating system had to manually switch
out these threads right because instead
of having to wait for the operating
system come in and switch out a thread
it can literally feel very tiny
latency bubbles you know on the order of
a few cycles latency bubbles it can fill
those in by picking instructions from
multiple streams which if the two
streams can sort of manage to like slot
into each other nicely where they you
know get into a phase where one guys
doing is memory while the other ones
doing is computations and vice versa
it's this can be really symbiotic and
you can fill in a lot of the bubbles
that way right so okay so let's talk
about the thing I just said which is I
said something like the operating system
comes in and switches right because
that's the next part we have to think
about so all right so on a given cord
whether it's hyper threading or not
there's typically more threads in the
running at any given time then can fit
on the course right so we just said
there are sixteen slots on this
processor but the number of threads
running in this machine are probably
probably like in the hundreds if not the
thousands right and that's because you
know here you go here I open up
processes look at all these processes
there are more processes running on this
computer right now than there are
execution slots right and each of these
processes itself has threads okay so
what that means is the operating system
at any given time really has some giant
set of threads right you know there's a
thousand of these or whatever and it's
only got 16 slots worth on this CPU or
like on your CPU maybe eight or whatever
worth of actual logical right CPUs these
are often called logical CPUs I keep
using that term because like like I said
or or logical cores would be a better
term for it they're usually called
logical cores because again they're not
actual cores a lot of times they're too
high per threads right is are both
executing on one actual physical pour so
there's always this constant between
logical and physical cores this machine
probably has eight physical cores for
sample but it has got 16 logical cores
because each of the physical cores can
have two threads on it so it's as if
there were more now it's not as good as
having a whole nother CPU core because
it doesn't duplicate all those things
like the ALU or the l1 cache or stuff
like that those are shared but it does
allow you to run as many threads as if
you actually had 16 actual course you
just may not run them as fast as you
could if you have 16 actual cores with
all the duplicated stuff but the hope is
that you do run it somewhere near that
fast right so if that was going to be
twice as fast to run them on on 16
physical cores you're hoping maybe you
get 1.4 1.3 X you get something right
you're not going to get it all but
you'll get something and maybe if you're
really lucky you get up close to it 1.8
who knows it depends on the workload
what's going to happen but that's the
goal right because it's relatively cheap
my understanding anyway is it's
relatively cheap for Intel to add hyper
threads to a core as opposed to adding a
whole nother core because they don't
have to duplicate things like the
multiplier circuitry and the memory
circuitry whenever that's the same they
just have to add things that allow
multiple slots in terms of like the
register file and stuff like that now
those things are still expensive they're
not free so it's not like you can just
have a hundred Piper threads it's free
woohoo
it doesn't work that way because the
routing and all that stuff is still
expensive I don't know very much about
it but that's why we don't have like
tons of hyper threads but in order to
get like a certain number of hyper
threads it turns out to usually be a
performance win that's why they do it
it's cheaper to add hyper threads than
it would be to stamp out a whole new
core alright so and just to put a cherry
on top of that so you can imagine what
they do at Intel is they basically look
and go okay how underutilized is this
are the set of things on a core
typically right like the ALU or whatever
how underutilized is that and then they
would want to add as many hyper threads
as would be necessary to utilize it so
you know if it takes two hyper threads
for typical workloads to fully utilize
the actual work units of the core then
that's a good number of hyper threads
right if it takes four of them then they
would do that takes two of them they
would do that what you'll typically see
I believe and this is again me sort of
hand waving here because I'm not a
hardware guy so you know hardware guys
feel free to correct me if I'm wrong but
well you'll typically see is out of
order processors versus in order
processors right the x64 is an out of
order processor which means it has that
big window where it can grab
instructions from right we talked about
that a lot what that means is that the
degree to which it needs hyper threading
is drastically reduced because it's able
to use stuff in the same thread a lot
more efficiently than an inorder
processor which is a processor that has
to execute the next instruction always
right
these stall a lot more on the same code
because even if there were instructions
just even if just the next instruction
that you would have executed wouldn't
have been blocked the fact that you're
the one you're on right now is blocked
means you can't continue and so these
tend to benefit a lot more from more
hyper threads so you might see you know
four hyper threads right on an inorder
processor being common whereas two hyper
threads on an out-of-order processor
might be common and that's because you
don't need as many hyper threads to give
you the options that you need on an out
of order processor wares on an internal
processor you might need quite a few for
might not even be enough right so there
you go
okay so here we go want to wrap this up
so we can go show how to create some
threads and win32 hopefully this gave
you some idea about that but what I want
to talk about one more thing today we're
going to save memory for tomorrow
one more thing today is the OS so what's
the OS doing well honestly these days I
have no idea what the OS is doing I've
never seen a modern OS kernel so I can't
tell you but it works something like
this there's a thing called an interrupt
alright we haven't talked about these at
all on handmade hero because you will
never get to use them probably we the
first time we'll probably ever get to
use one of these for any real purpose is
if we do Raspberry Pi programming or
something like that where we're able to
write sort of all the way down to the
hardware and run as the kernel
effectively but on Windows you probably
will never deal with this so especially
if you're just writing a game so what is
an interrupt well an interrupt is
something where the processor itself
decides to replace the thing that's
currently running with something else
right so basically what happens is you
have that azzam code right and you've
got an instruction pointer and it's
going right so we're on some core here's
the core we're running this stuff and
we're and that's all fine and dandy and
then what happens is at some point you
get an interrupt and that interrupt
might be like the scheduling timer for
example in this case so it might be an
interrupt that just happens periodically
right and what that interrupt does is it
says all right hold on I know you were
going to you were going to execute
something don't execute that instead I
want you to execute this other code over
here right and that code happens to be
some operating system code so when the
operating system started up back when
you like booted Windows right it
installed this interrupt it installed
the thing called an interrupt handler
which is this code and it basically told
the processor every so often every
millisecond or whatever I
want you to stop what you are doing I
want you to run my code okay and my code
is going to do some stuff now what this
code will do is this code will see
whether it wants to change which thread
is running on this core so for example
what this this code could do is it could
issue a thing that says save the state
of the processor right save those
registers write that register state and
the registers by the way includes this
instruction pointer right because that's
actually a register in the processor so
save out all this stuff to a piece of
memory somewhere okay save it out load
in somebody else's right go grab some
other state from some other thread and
move it in here and then resume what you
were doing jump back in there right so
effectively what the OS does is it has a
thing which every so often will
interrupt what's running on a processor
possibly decide you know doesn't have to
do this but possibly decide that what
should really be running on the
processor is some other thread possibly
from some other process in which case
it'll also have the TLB like travel and
not patil v but it'll have the the
virtual addressing table it'll pull in
that memory mapping table as well it
will swap that out right so it'll
possibly do a whole bunch of work to
change over the state and then it will
resume execution of some totally other
thread possibly from some totally other
process okay so the operating system is
the guy who's actually doing this work
it's doing it on an interrupt that
interrupts is allowing the optical
system to come in and interrupt what
someone's doing to let someone else do
it now this is called preemption and
operating systems that work this way are
called pre-emptive multitasking
operating systems
okay a pre-emptive multitasking
operating system is one that preempts
the the execution of a thread without
that thread giving the operating system
permission okay this is how modern
operating multitasking operating systems
work there are other styles called
cooperative multitasking okay
and what those are are ones where the
operand system does not have this
interrupts instead what they have is
every uh every chain of execution every
thread when it was written has to have a
thing in there that basically looks like
yield
it basically says like okay I'm gonna do
a bunch of work and then I'm going to
call yield and yield actually physically
calls out to the scheduler right so
basically these are much more efficient
actually because they never have these
interrupts popping up ever so that's
kind of Handy but they are much less
reliable for the user because what it
means is that if one of these pieces of
code is behaving badly or has a bug in
it or just doesn't care and it never
calls yield
you can never that's you can never
switch what's running on that core right
once that launches it's gone forever
right so the reason that most monitoring
system operating systems are preempted
multitasking now is because it no longer
requires the people who program these
things to be good citizens and it gets
much more even load balancing because it
can guarantee that it doesn't matter how
this code was written it can always
preempt it at predefined intervals right
whereas with the cooperative when it
couldn't do that so whereas this one can
be made more efficient because you're
never having these things happen at
inopportune times they can always be
planned they are much more reliable if
they're pre-emptive because they can
spread the work evenly that's guaranteed
and they can make sure that bad actors
don't suck up all the cpu time
okay so what do we have to do on
handmade here oh right like I said but
we want to do right now our goal for
today or our goal for this week I should
say is we want to fill all 16 slots
worth of cores of logical cores on the
processor we want to fill those all with
threads that the CPUs could be executing
and right now when we have one right so
what we need to do is we need to give
the operating system some threads it can
start filling right it can start
assigning to these processors right
because the operating system is the
thing that assigns these the operating
is the thing that that schedules them
right and so right now basically what's
happening is on all 16 slots right you
know we've got these 16 slots worth of
processing that are happening right most
of them are just sitting there right
most of them are doing nothing they're
just waiting right and so the operating
system is like running all of handmade
hero basically on like one thread and
the rest of these guys are sitting
around waiting what we want to do is
have it so that there's things in all
the slots so the processor can kick them
all off and get them all doing things
that's all we're trying to do here right
and so when we look at this when we look
at this graph what you can see here is
you can see that this number hovers
around 11 percent right and we can see
if we look at processes you can see
what's going on on there it's it's the
its OBS that's that's taken that that
time right but we could get we could
probably get a little bit more explicit
well you know we'll do first of all
let's just run handmade hero
right now so if I run handmade hero and
we just have it running right um you
know if you can see that there but you
know this is going you know handmade
heroes is going here here it goes and
right now it's using like three percent
of the CPU right and I guess we that may
actually be less than even a full single
thread performance because there's just
enough not enough rendering to do so we
may have to actually start making that
we have to increase the render workload
but what I wanted to point out is we're
hovering around three percent when we're
doing our rendering right now of
processor usage and what we want to do
is we want to be using like a tremendous
amount right we want to be using
basically 90 percent because that's
what's left over from after OBS is
running we want to make sure that we're
actually using all that and so if we
take a look at what that value actually
means right one sixteenth of a processor
right is six percent right so right now
we're are we've optimized our render
enough that with the current amount of
work that we're asking it to do we're
not even using all of one cores worth
right so the first thing we may have to
do once we start doing our
multi-threading is we may have to
increase the graphics work well because
we did a little bit too good of a job
optimizing it but that that amount that
1/16 that point oh six there 6% if we
did not increase the number of threads
that handmade here are used for
rendering that would be the maximum
amount of the CPU we'd ever see used by
us because even if we fully max it out
so we add enough rendering work that
it's just it's in the renderer the whole
time right and you know it's it's
working the entire time does the blitt
two windows and then goes right back to
rendering we would never see it get
above 6% because without
more cores going we can't ever use more
than 6% of the processor right so when
you see this in the task manager and you
wonder my why isn't my application
running faster it's only using 10% of
the CPU and like it was dog slow or
whatever right and I mean we can even do
this in fact I can do this pretty easily
and this would be a problem maybe even a
good way to illustrate it first off if I
go back and switch it to the super slow
version right where we do draw rectangle
quickly in our render group thing where
we were actually calling that if I
switched it back to calling draw
rectangle slowly right then our game is
super slow and crappy right you know
here we go right and here's our here's
our game it's like barely functioning
right so that's super slow if we if we
go look again at this this is super slow
framerate we can see that we're just
it's the CPU isn't pegged at all right
and if we go back here and look at how
much hand may is taking advantage of hey
look it's the exact number that I
calculated six percent right and so
again the threading what we're trying to
do now is we're trying to say okay you
know modern processors they just they
count on this multi-threading a lot and
so we're never going to get all of the
horsepower out of the processor if all
we do is write the single tiptoe we've
got to push it into multi-threading in
order to get above that amount and if
you think about how much processing is
left on the table if it actually worked
out perfectly and again it never does
but if it actually worked out perfectly
right using 60 percent of the processor
would be 10 times faster right that's
how much is left on the table there and
60 percent 800 does even you know after
sixty percent there's like another 2x or
right so we're talking about something
in the order of like 617 percent or
something like this 1600 sorry 16x
because we know we're only filling one
slot and we've got 16 processors so
we're talking about 16 times the
performance we could get if we filled
those out now you won't get actually all
16 for like I said because you know
some of those are logical cores not
actual course and then there's memory
issues and all these other sorts of
things and handshaking blah blah blah
blah blah so we probably won't get 16x
but you know 10x totally plausible right
and 10x is huge so that's again why it's
so important and again the reason why
this is the case you may wonder who's
really bad idea it was to make these
processors require this because why do
we have to care why can't we just write
the code single-threaded and widen just
make a processor that excuse a single
threaded code is very fast
the answer is heat unfortunately
so basically like heat is bad is is is
basically the problem so what they found
out there is an architecture it was
called the Pentium 6 or the P 6 or
whatever it was the thing after the
Pentium right so there's the Pentium and
then they made the P 6 and the P 6 was
designed to scale to very high clock
rates so they were like ah yeah you know
like we're going to make this run eight
gigahertz or something right what they
found is when they got up to 4 gigahertz
the chip melted basically right and they
just did not anticipate how much heat
these things would generate and how much
the heat would be a problem and to my
knowledge to this day they pretty much
never solved this problem like the heat
just is flat-out not solvable at the
moment I don't know chip design so I
can't speak to that again that may be
not quite true but basically what
happened is right around this period
they hit a heat barrier and the heat
barrier has never been breached it's
basically just a hard limit so you will
never see the 8 gigahertz CPU well
someday you might but you didn't see an
8 gigahertz CPU in the last decade
specifically because of this otherwise
you would have and so what they quickly
found was that they cannot increase the
clock rate any more than they already
have
and what that
means is they've had to do other things
and what were those other things well
number one is wide execution right and
we saw that that's like alright if we
can't go any faster maybe we can go the
same speed but do the operation on four
times as many things and that was Cindy
right that was four times many things
eight times many things sixteen times
many things in five to pay maybe X 512
right and we already took advantage of
that that was the first set of
optimizations we did right we didn't
really have to optimize much really all
we did was just make the routine wide
and hey it got done faster right so
that's what that is and that's a way of
getting for extra performance 8x
performance 60 pips worth right through
the the CPU just by saying okay
instructions instead of operating on one
thing now operate on way more things
right so that's a way to make the speed
not change but the work amount change so
that's the first thing they did number
two was more more execution right and
that's what threads are they were just
like alright if we can't go any faster
let's just execute more different
programs at once right and we'll just
hope that the programmers can figure out
ways of breaking their work up into
multiple simultaneous programs and so
that's where we're at today and that's
why optimization today largely boils
down to how well you can do these two
things because at the end of the day
this is where all of the processor
horsepower now goes it's getting wider
and getting more execution at the same
time right and so we've already looked
at how to do this and you kind of have
an idea of how to write routines to do
this now and so this is the second thing
that we're trying to do now we've got
about 1518 minutes left and so what I
want to do is pop back to win32 and show
you how to do the basics okay so
hopefully everyone's kind of clear on
that there's not a lot of mystery there
it's at its core again it's a very
simple concept it's just saying hey
before you could execute one thing now
you can have
multiple things like shooting at the
same time but other than that they're
basically the same right and there's a
bunch of nuance to it that will start
going into over the next couple days but
that's that's really about it and really
gets down memory the way you deal with
memory and synchronization issues tends
to be the the part that's really hard
about multi-threading you'll already see
there's there's already one thing we'll
have to change in the way that we're
filling our rectangles because of the
way cache line boundaries work and stuff
like this so there's one thing left to
do there and then there's another thing
that we'll have to do in terms of
letting people know what which threads
are supposed to do what but that's
basically like you know where the where
the actual difficulty comes in so here
we are in win32 handmade right and what
you can see here is you know when we
wrote this code we never really talked
about threading at all and the reason
for that is because by default things
were set up the same way they were in
the old days right like Windows still
launches your app exactly the way they
used to be in the old days which is to
say that in the old days there was only
one thread execution anyway so you
called in to win main and it was just a
given that that was the one thread and
this was the thread of execution so
everything pretty much happened on that
thread and here it is happening on that
thread so if we want more threads and we
want to start control more threads we
need a way of telling the operating
system hey I need to start making more
threads give me more execution context
please and so as you might expect the
way to do that is with a function called
create thread it's actually fairly
straightforward as some things in
Windows actually are oftentimes the
things in the Windows kernel are
actually pretty well thought out because
honestly the guys who originally wrote
the Windows kernel were pretty darn
smart and actually unlike people who
write a lot of the windows API they were
very experienced as well which makes a
huge difference and so some of the
things that they do are really actually
pretty well thought out and I'm not
going to say that create thread is
perfect or anything like that but I'll
just say that a lot of the Windows
kernel stuff is is done in a very nice
way I Oh completion ports for example IO
completion ports which will
use a little later on or probably one of
the best api's that exists in window
actually in windows actually it's it's
almost perfect and that's not something
that you pretty much ever say about a
windows API or anyone elses API for that
matter all right
so we have a function here that we're
going to call and I'll just call it
right at the top for now we'll worry
about where we're going to call it a
little bit later I just want to show you
how it works we have a function here
called create thread okay and what that
does is it returns us to handle to the
thread this is our thread oops our
thread handle okay and it takes a bunch
of things in first of all it takes these
LP security attributes and what those
are is we don't really care very much
about those we I think we bumped into
them once before we said we didn't care
about them there we also don't care
about them here what those are is these
things that you can do if you wanted a
thread that you were creating to not
have the same permissions that you have
right and so we don't really care about
that so we're just going to passion
though which basically says that you
know the thread that I'm creating should
be able to do anything that I can do but
you can imagine in other security
scenarios where you wanted a thread to
have restricted ability to call when
win32 calls like oh I'm going to I don't
know I'm trying to protect against some
kind of hack soaring so I just don't
want this thread to be able to call some
stuff I don't know whatever you can
imagine maybe some cases where you want
to do that in games you rarely have that
case but you know maybe a web browser or
somebody else wants to do stuff like
that okay
so then we've got the actual meat of the
thing here we've got the stack size
right you can see what this is what we
can do here is we can basically say we
want to use whatever one we were using
for all the other threads right which is
if we pass 0 so again we can just pass
essentially default values for these two
and nothing will change that stack size
is whatever we specified when we built
the executable so in the build bat file
right we didn't actually put one in here
but if later on we wanted to we can
control the stack size in here we played
around with that a little in early
handmade hero but so we're just going to
use the default again but we could we
could change it then we get down to the
meat of it which is the start address in
the LP
ammeter and basically what these are is
just saying okay what's the actual code
for this thread what's actually going to
happen right and so what you do is you
create one of these guys it's this this
is what it looks like right we create
one of these guys called a thread proc
and this is the actual parameter I'm so
going to leave it like that it doesn't
actually matter in 164 but that's
separate issue this is actually what the
code is going to be for this thread
right it's the entry point for the
thread so just like when main was where
we get started calling although
technically it was in the CRT that first
call but point being we basically have
an entry point where this thread is
going to start executing and then it's
going to do something in here and then
it's going to you know when it's done
it'll exit out and that'll be the end of
the thread right so we want to we can do
output debug string you know thread
started or something like this and
that's fine and this would be the code
for the thread that's all the thread
would do and what we do is we pass that
address to create thread and say that's
where I want you to start executing
right and then what we can do is we can
also pass a parameter to the thread and
that parameter is what comes in right
here right so whatever we pass is the
next thing is the thing that comes in
here so right now we don't actually have
anything but you know we have a pram
equals 0 we'll just put it there and
leave it there for right now that's what
and then later we'll actually worry
about what we're going to pass it and
that's what will come in here in fact we
could do something like this just to
show it thread started like so we could
do it this way where we just say a
string to print equals whatever this LP
parameter was casted oops and then we
print it right like so and this way
we're passing in that right so we call
that almost like that not really
anything particularly too weird there we
then have two more things which is the
creation flags and you can see those
again always using MSDN you can see
those here and basically what these are
is special ways that we won't want to do
stuff so normally if we just pass a 0
which is what we're going to do here the
thread just starts executing right away
right but if we'd want to
- we could create it so that the thread
gets created but doesn't actually start
executing until we call an additional
function so if we want to create a bunch
of threads that are just waiting like
courses at the start of a race until
like you know the the gates open in the
air loud and start running basically
like that resume thread would be the
thing that actually starts them going
right so if we wanted to we can create
the threads and not have them run yet
but we don't really care about that so
we don't wanna do that this guy I've
never even I don't even remember this
guy being in here but you can see here
this is basically a thing which says
whether you want to do reserves or
commits on the stack memory I mean I
don't know there must be that must have
been something that they needed to do at
some point so they had to flag for it
we're definitely not going to ever look
at that okay so then finally and this is
the part that's a little bit weird in
Windows threads are identified both by a
handle and by an identifier okay and I
feel like this was kind of a mistake but
I don't know maybe they had a really
good reason for it I've never really
grok tweye they thought this was a good
idea but so they basically have a thread
ID that identifies the thread and it
will give you that as a return value as
well so not only do you get back a
handle which you can use to operate on
the thread you also get back an ID which
you can also use to operate on thread in
different ways right so you basically
have the thread ID here and we pass the
address of that thread ID d-word and it
will fill it out it's a return value
essentially it will fill it out with the
value so if we actually do this so we
actually run this code that's actually
all we need to start multi-threaded for
the most part oops I got a rest return
something here right this actually
returns a d-word
that's actually all we need to actually
get multi-threading started and if we
actually run the code here and I just
run the code in then and then exit or
try to exit anyway stop in theory we
should be able to see that work now of
course I didn't actually see it here I'm
not sure why we didn't see it oh yes we
did there it is it's up here so you can
see it right here right so here's the
thread started call and you can see
immediately after it that thread exited
right and so
this is just something that happened
totally separate execution paths than
the rest of the code and it's just that
was it right and again we'll be able to
demonstrate this a little bit more
explicitly a little bit later on but you
know that is literally the the entirety
of how you get multi-threading started
and so you can create as many of these
as you want
right you can imagine us creating lots
of these threads if that's what we
wanted to do we could do that like so we
can just keep on creating threads all
day long and and no one's going to stop
us right and so if we want to do that we
can do that off we go
that just creates a bunch of threads all
of which call that initial thing and you
can see them all happening here right
and they happen in exit right so that's
really about it however there's some
additional work that we probably want to
do here just to sort of solidify things
a little bit which is that when we call
this create thread we get back this
thread handle ok and the thread handle
like I said is something that allows us
to do operations on that thread right so
once we have a thread handle like for
example we could destroy the thread or
we can like that resume thread call that
you saw if you were to create the thread
suspended the resume thread call you can
see that basically what they do is they
take that thread handle and that's a way
that you can refer to this particular
thread right now when we don't want it
anymore if we don't want that handle
anymore we can call closed handle which
basically says to Windows we're not
going to talk about this thread anymore
right we're just not it's not going to
happen
right and so we can actually do that we
can actually say we don't care about
this anymore and say closed handle right
thread handle but what's important to
remember is that doesn't kill the thread
the thread is still going it just says
closing the handle says you know what I
don't need to talk about this story
anymore it's off doing its thing I'm not
going to explicitly manhandle it and so
you can just release that handle back to
the operating system just by doing that
right
and what we can see here if I add in
something like to say I did something
like this oops
where I was just going to print the
string out over and over and over and
over again ad infinitum right and maybe
I introduced a sleep here so it doesn't
spam it too much so this thing is just
going to every second it's going to
print this out right what we can see
here if I do this is yeah I know it's
unreachable code what do you want me to
do I got a return a value oh is this one
of those kept 22s no okay so off we go I
run this code and what you can see here
is that even though I've you know closed
that handle the thread started message
is still getting printed right and
that's just going to keep on going that
threads just going to keep on doing that
thing because the closed handle is just
releasing the handle back to the
operation the sing act I don't need to
talk about this thread anymore right but
you should but it's still going to be
running is still going to be doing its
execution path right so whether we want
to or not I don't know whether we need
to talk about it later we'll see but for
now you can just seal okay we created it
it's off it's running we're done right
and that's about it
that's that's really the end of it so
what we would need to do here right is
we would need to have some way for this
thing to eventually exit right because
otherwise whatever it's doing is still
going to keep on going even after our
game is like you know our game is
supposed to exit and this thread is
still running right and so let's take a
look at what happens there actually I'll
show you what I mean by that so our game
I'm going to actually go stop that draw
rectangle slowly from eating up all of
our time I'm going to put it back to the
fast mode just so we're in a in a more
well-functioning system so here we go
here's the game and if I remember
quickly I believe F alt f4 closes our
application right so when we do alt f4
right and it closes the application I
believe what happens is we do an exit
process right if I well you know I don't
actually remember what we did so let's
actually go take a look at what we did
there we go 1:32 handmade so I don't
actually remember what happens here to
be honest with you I do not know so
let's take a look exit process do be
colleagues and pubs makes a process
anywhere we do not so what happens
within our WM close handle handler right
because like we're doing alt f4 global
running equals false all right let's
take a look yeah so that code gets
optimized out oh this is an optimized
build all right so never mind I will go
into the build and change back there we
go alright because I want to see what
happens when we do that so we hit alt f4
there we go global running equals false
and so now we should fall out of our of
our loop up here right because we've got
this wild global running situation here
oops that's not it that's the simple one
where is our actual wild global running
hello there it is that's the one so when
we get here right global running is now
going to be false so when we actually
come through here we're going to return
zero right and if we actually step
through what happens here we pop out
right and this is in the C runtime
library right and I imagine that's
probably what's going to happen is it's
going to call the exit process for us
I'm not actually sure we'll find out
let's take a look man oh man I assume
we're going through trying to call C++
destructors here yeah so much fun oh the
C++ of it all okay exit process zero to
exit process get module handle there it
is so what you can see here is
eventually the C runtime library calls
exit process for us right here in there
lovely C++ cleanup code that's going
through and trying to claw global
destructors and God knows what else is
doing here is the exit process call and
that exit process call is actually what
kills our other thread right because
that other thread is just right it's
just going right and it would just keep
on running and our process would never
exit because we have that thread running
but exit process basically terminates
all the threads right
so right here you can see the very first
thing that happens all of these threads
just get terminated basically without
any regard to where they were okay so
that is what actually allows our
application to exit if exit process were
not being called by the C runtime
library that thread would just keep on
running and so it's worth the reason I
bring that up is because for example one
thing we have not done yet in handmade
hero but what we might do in the future
is build without the C runtime library
at all in fact we probably will do that
sometime in the future when we're in the
mood to do so because again we like to
do things from scratch here so it'd be
nice to get that out of there it's worth
noting we would have to call exit
process in order to actually kill this
thread because once we get rid of the
handle and if we're not actually looking
up at a thread ID or anything like that
and trying to kill the thread we would
have to do that now there's another way
we could do that right we could say that
in there in win32 hand-made we could
actually make this guy also look at that
right we could say that this guy also
looks at well global running and he will
exit when global running a signal as
well right
because again threads share all the same
memory they're not separate processes
they're separate threads so what that
means is that any piece of information
that we want to look at we can actually
look at right now there's a catch and
this gets into what we start talking
about tomorrow probably although maybe
not we might get into this we might not
get into still Wednesday is that the
compiler doesn't unfortunately know
about these sorts of things it doesn't
know about threading so actually doing
this may or may not work right it
depends and what it depends on is
whether the compiler tries to reload
this value or not right because remember
the optimising compiler how the
optimizing compiler worked where it
would you know the optimizing compiler
would basically say oh well global
running maybe I know that that never
changes so I don't
have to actually reload it from memory
every time it might do something like
that not realizing that some other
thread right unbeknownst to us is what's
actually going to go change global
running so there's things like markup
like volatile and stuff that we might
need to use to make this sort of stuff
work right so for now we'll leave that I
just want to point that out and then
it's time to wrap up anyway so we'll go
ahead and go to the QA that is a very
brief introduction to threading tomorrow
what we'll do is we'll create a bunch of
these threads and figure out how to
start pointing them at the renderer if
that makes sense but hopefully that was
a reasonable introduction to threading
and and now I will take questions on
that it's type Q and a there we go
what does closing the handle of a thread
do for you when you release the handle
to the OS does it open up resources and
increase performance so in our case
nothing really I mean the way that we're
going to do stuff is we're going to
create 16 threads basically we're 15
threads include and then we'll have the
16th from the one we have here whatever
and we don't really have to close those
handles it doesn't matter but the reason
I pointed it out was because it is
creating a handle so what it means is
that there's only a certain number of
handles and so on so closing them might
free up some slots for the operation so
you get it doesn't matter honestly it
really doesn't matter I just wanted to
point it out it's sort of good
housekeeping to say ok if I'm not going
to use the handle anymore I'll free it
but really in the way we're using it now
you could just you could just go ahead
and let the handle leak and it wouldn't
matter at all so in practice nothing
there's no difference doesn't increasing
the number of threads to match the hyper
threads count increase cross core across
context switches thus making it less
efficient for small operations well it
depends so basically what you have to
keep in mind is how much overhead are
you introducing for your multiple
threads right and that's something that
we haven't really talked about yet
because we haven't started actually
doing work on these threads but there's
a question of how much overhead are you
introducing to have the secondary thread
if that overhead in terms of like how it
communicates and how the work has to be
done differently to partition it if that
overhead is very small then it's
unlikely that you will then that it's
unlikely that you'll ever going to lose
from using the same number of threads as
there are hyper thread slots available
in the machine but if you are actually
creating more work and more like if
you're creating a lot of extra stuff
that happens there in
terms of getting the hyper-threading
getting up to the number of threads that
you need then that can definitely be the
case it may be the case that you really
only want to increase it to the number
of actual cores not to the number of
hyper cores but again the only real way
you can know that is by testing it so
you probably want to if you really care
about the formants try it at least first
before deciding ahead of time that you
think it's one way or the other because
you probably aren't going to guess right
is there any advantage to creating a
separate process to render the graphics
in the context of game development
probably not the only reason you would
want to create a separate process is if
you were worried about security but
there isn't really much reason to create
a separate process to render graphics
otherwise because I mean okay so there's
one other reason it would be if you were
on 32-bit windows instead of 64-bit
windows which is becoming increasingly
rare so I doubt that anyone would do
this anymore
but if you were on 32-bit windows you
would get more memory because remember
each process has its own virtual memory
space which on 32 at Windows is 2
gigabytes of memory for the for the
process memory and 2 gigabytes of memory
for kernel mapped memory and other
things right so if you needed more than
a 2 gig to Gig split then you wanted
your game to say have a four gig 4 gig
split if you broke the game into two
processes each process gets its own two
gigabytes right so I mean in some real
crazy scenario maybe but on 64-bit
Windows I don't think there's really any
reason you would want to do it if you
weren't if it wasn't first for making a
security partition because in 64-bit
windows you have way more memory
addressing space than you could possibly
need and so there wouldn't be any reason
to go breaking it up into multiple oxys
like that is it still a while yet before
we look at other platform layers other
than win32 yeah so just to be clear on
that I've said it a couple times I'll
say it again we won't be doing multiple
platform layers until we're ready to
ship because otherwise we're just
wasting work because we want one
platform layer that has all the stuff in
it that we know we need so we want the
game to basically be done and having all
the platform support that we know that
we need and then we just port just that
instead of trying to maintain multiple
platform layers at a time which just
wastes a lot of work right
why just 15 threads why not future-proof
so when I say 16 threads I'm talking
about on this particular machine what we
will be doing is not creating 16 magical
threads and saying that's good because
that would actually be too many threads
for people who have only a fork or two
hyper thread processor right so what we
will actually be doing is we'll be
calling a function that asks the
operating system how many processors
there actually are and that's how many
threads we'll be creating
you
will we be creating the system for its
CPU count determine how many threads to
use yes and we will also try to out in
the fact this is the next question do
you have control over on which cord the
thread excuse from the program itself
and the answer is to some degree yes and
so what we will be doing is we'll be
using operating system calls to
basically say how many processors are
there to what extent can you tell me mr.
operating system which of these
processor logical processors share
resources like caches right and that's
the hyper thread thing right because two
hyper threads share resources on a core
and then we will be using that
information to as best as we can create
the right number of threads and hint to
the operating system which cores we want
those threads to run on so that we will
try to make it so that if the thing has
you know eight cores with two hyper
threads each we actually create two
threads per core to run and know which
two they are so that they can work on
the correct workloads to try to maximize
the caster's cache usage so we will try
to do that and Windows does give you
calls that get get that allow you to do
those sorts of things
do you plan to make pathfinding
multi-threaded so I don't think we will
probably multi-thread pathfinding
specifically itself what I suspect we
will do is multi thread simulation in
general and so that all of the
simulation stuff can happen while they
thread it if we want it to we'll see I'm
not sure but we'll see Jonathan Blow had
created 10,000 threads on his compiler
demo some people wondered how in the
world that could happen well a thread is
just a CPU State so you can create
hundreds of thousands of them you could
create a million of them if you wanted
to it's only limited by the amount of
storage space the operating system will
allow you to use for storing thread
State that's it because remember there's
only 16 of them like on this processor
that are happening on the processor so
the rest of it is just memory that the
operating system is reserving to store
the state of a thread that it might swap
in at some point right that's it so
creating a thread is not a big deal
right you you wouldn't ever want to
create 10,000 threads because you're
just wasting a bunch of resources and
slowing things down because the
operation has to swap them in so
typically you only want as many threads
as can actually execute on the processor
right but you can create as many as you
want up to the limit that the operating
system until the operating system just
says I'm out of space right
I think all the rest of the questions
were not on topic do we have any other
on topic questions first let me make
sure
and by the way Carl and Oh bloom is
totally right obviously no one will ever
need more than 16 threads or two
gigabytes of RAM clearly Andy Seven
Samurai it's also correct that no one
will ever need more than 20 56 colors we
just know these limits there of it
they're so high how could you ever use
more than 26 colors I don't even know
like how many colors can you name red
green blue cyan magenta I mean that's it
right I mean you probably only need like
16 colors really okay I dare you there
aren't even 200 colors in one of those
big boxes of Crayola so clearly these
limits are totally fine
all right so it doesn't look like
there's any more on topic questions so
I'll address a couple of the off-topic
ones why you see over C++
I would note we do use some C++ features
occasionally operator overloading
function overloading and declare
anywhere our C++ features that we use
now granted declare anywhere I think now
is in c99
so that's not really a C++ feature I
guess but just point being when I
started using it it was a C++ feature
back in the 90s but the reason that I
don't use C++ is because almost all the
features of C++ are bad they're they're
poorly implemented they don't work very
well they end up wasting a lot of code
and producing lousy output code they're
just they're just really bad C++ is a
lousy language and most of its features
are lousy so I don't use them C is a
pretty good language and most of its
features are good I wish it had other
features they're a bunch of features I
wish C had that it doesn't unfortunately
C++ doesn't add those features it adds
other lousy features and you know what
do you do
can we stay on stream after I end the
episode recording for another try on the
story yes I will stay on and we can try
that again two other questions which
programmers code you'd recommend reading
I don't know I don't spend a lot of time
reading other people's code and I'm not
sure what you mean by that
if you mean like to pick up good habits
in coding or to learn about how to
implement algorithms like it would
depend right and that stuff's pretty
preference oriented so I don't really
know into when are we covering patching
or a couple of words on brief basics of
patching so you're talking about you
want an asset list and you want to
update the asset list so I don't know
that we'll ever cover patching because I
don't know that we have a lot of options
in terms of doing patching right like my
understanding and again this is not
something that I normally deal with my
understanding is like Steam does the
patching the way it does the patching
right so like when we put our game up
there or whatever we're going to do in
terms of getting of releasing the game
we don't get to do patching right so you
know I don't I don't know that there's
really anything we're going to do with
patching because the patching is
determined to a large extent by the
distribution service you know if we put
it on GOG galaxy or something like they
have their own patching as far as I know
so I don't actually know to what extent
we are allowed to do anything with
patching so we may never cover that but
in terms of how to deal with it like you
know it's a pretty straightforward
problem you can go read about our sink
you can go read about standard you know
diffing systems and you know if you want
to go those routes you can go those
routes there isn't something special
about game assets that makes any
different from other people's
synchronization really
so what was the reason for dismissing
the use of fibers early on so the reason
is because fibers don't give us what we
actually wanted out of threading like
our problem right now is not that we
need to interleave work on the same cpu
core our problem is we need more work
available for the processor and fibers
don't do that right so we don't actually
have a use case for fibers at the moment
and I don't think we ever will I don't
anticipate us ever needing them we want
actual real threads
have you made any progress on the
license text reports for other program
to other programming languages
unfortunately not I tried multiple times
to do this
unfortunately the liability is a little
bit difficult so like what I was trying
to figure out is how I would get it so
that Mali rocket isn't liable if someone
like basically ships a virus as part of
their port to some other language and we
include that with our zip file I don't
know what happens there right and I
haven't been able to find anything
definitive that says how we deal with
that so I've been considering other
options for how to do the licensing
which is basically saying maybe
something like you have to stay a
hundred days behind the mainstream but
other than that you're allowed to post
it or something I was trying to figure
out things where we could basically just
allow people to post it and just have
some restriction on there so that we
still get some of the exclusivity out of
it in you know just short-term I I don't
know it's a very tough problem because
lawyers
would be possible for you to boost the
sound of your voice on stream I've
always found that it is barely high
enough even with all mixers at maximum
volume possible so I think you've got
something weird going on because
actually it's at the maximum volume
right like if you actually look at
what's happening here it is actually at
the maximum volume it doesn't really go
any higher than that without just
straight-up clipping if that makes sense
alright I think that's it for today so
I'm going to go ahead and wrap things up
close this down
exit make sure we've saved our
blackboard alright thank you everyone
for joining me for another episode of
hand made here oh it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always it was a good
blackboard session today we covered
threading and we created our threads but
we haven't actually done anything with
them that will be tomorrow's job to
actually start pointing our threads for
something useful and in order to do that
we will have start talking about
synchronization which is the next big
topic in multi-threading so we'll have
to do quite a bit of Blackboard work
this week because there's a whole bunch
of topics in need to be introduced but
slowly but surely we will get to the
point where we are running
multi-threaded in the renderer and that
will be a good thing so thank you
everyone for joining me if you would
like to follow along at home with a
source code you can do so by going to
handmade hero org and pre-ordering the
game it comes with all the source code
you can download it every night after
I'm done you'll get a link that you can
just keep using to reap download the
source code anytime you want
we also have a forum site you can go to
ask questions or to get coding resources
like ports to Mac or Linux or an
eight-episode guide that the community
maintains stuff like that it's really
handy we have a patreon page where you
can support the video series if you'd
like which is very appreciated and we
have a tweet bot that tweets the
schedule at you we also thanks to some
donations by folks who helped write the
JavaScript and in fact I do not know how
to pronounce either of their names so I
will simply point you at the thing that
says their names I'm going to say
like Remy rock kitsch let's see
and maybe Jakob Munk Anderson I don't
know how to pronounce these names they
are names whose pronunciations I
probably butchered but thanks to them we
also have the live button now actually
does a reasonable job at telling you
when it's actually going to be live so
you can also just check this guy and
I'll do it but the tweet bot tells you
the schedule in advance so if you want
to know kind of what the schedules will
be for the week and to get a reminder in
the morning or stuff like that that's
the place to go for that it's pretty
handy so thanks everyone I hope to see
you back here tomorrow tomorrow will be
regularly scheduled timeslot 5 p.m.
Pacific Daylight Time hope to see you
all here for that we will go over how to
get those threads actually doing some
work for us which i think will be good
so see you there for that until then
have fun coding and I will see you next
time I'm going to stay on the stream
just for a few seconds because
apparently there's some story I'm
supposed to check out so we'll take a
look at that ok thanks everyone