hello everyone and welcome back to
handmade hero it has been well I suppose
it hasn't really been any time for
people who are watching this video on
demand because they'll just see these in
order but if you watched the series live
then you know that we've been on break
for a couple weeks and we're back now
right before we went on break what we
did is we actually isolated and
optimized our renderer so it's actually
a standalone component now you can use
to make really anything you want that's
a sprite renderer and we also went
through the work of making it use sprite
a rate well texture arrays to represent
sprites which we did because it's a
fairly widely supported feature that
allows you to get a off of the single
draw call per sprite kind of an issue
that we had before when we just
literally translated the renderer from a
Safa renderer to a hardware render one
of the problems you get is that you end
up changing textures every drop call
because every sprite is its own texture
and that's just not really something
that all video cards can support now
like I said before there actually are
plenty of cards that can changing
textures per draw per quod issues
actually pretty easy on higher-end cards
the problem is that doesn't scale to all
sorts of stuff so there's like intel
chips that don't support it that are
pretty common in the wild there's
probably phone style hardware out there
that you'd have trouble with so texture
arrays is one way to kind of almost get
the same benefits as being able to
quickly change the texture pointer every
primitive without actually using that
feature which is not ubiquitous so just
to refresh everyone's memory we ended up
with some pretty nice results here and
we've got like one more thing I think to
do in the renderer before we're done but
if we take again see I was working on
the meow
this is the only machine I have with a
VX on it so I had to do some now hash or
a cons particular machine yeah
if for those of you don't know I posted
meow hash on Friday as well which is
pretty fun
now hash is our the hash we now use at
Molly rocket that I developed well
handmade here it was off actually I just
developed at this past week because I
was looking for something to fix our
slow hashing
it's the fastest hash I think that there
is right now I don't know that there's a
faster hash out there that actually can
pass all of a like all of the current
hash tests like a SM hasher and
practical collision tests like large
datasets and verifying they don't
collide it's pretty cool so check it out
the source code is is licensed
permissively and it's upon there's
github for it here the entire thing is
justin now hashed out h so if you're
interested in fast hashing it's not
cryptographic it's designed for data
comparison so it's not the kind of thing
you use for security it's the kind of
thing used for like data deduplication
but it's designed to hash huge blocks of
data extremely quickly and it actually
hashes it's one of the only hashes I'm
aware of that hash is well higher than
memory speed so if the data is in cache
it actually hashes significantly faster
than the speed of main memory whereas
main memory is usually like an upper
bound for most hashes they'll if things
are in cache they don't hatch any faster
meowww hash actually hashes even faster
in cache than it does normally and it
beats all the hashes that I've seen even
at memory speeds because a lot of hashes
can't quite hit memory speed but meow
hash does it fully saturates anyway so
what I was going to say is when we we
left off we were we may look a little
render or test here and this thing is
just a oh all right well that's not a
very good sign do we leave
bug what's going on here did we I
thought we left everything in a
reasonable state did we did we totally
cheese out or something
what am I forgetting
well I guess we've got some work to do
apparently we made a change that we
didn't run before we left last week is
that true hmm well let's take a look all
right never mind forget the recap we've
got work to do folks that's weird we
don't usually do that or at least I
don't think we do let's compile and now
it looks like we crash in this route oh
hey someone wanna tell me what's going
on here
you know Visual Studio was updated in
between the time we left and came back
is this some kind of what's what's going
on here someone tell me this is this is
someone tell me there's an explanation
for what just happened mm-hmm very
grumpy right now very grumpy right now
why were we crashing in OpenGL managed
textures people what what's going on I
mean I'm assuming the only way you could
really have a crash here is if this
OpenGL managed textures I mean all it's
doing here is just passing two things in
I'm not sure what really could have been
the problem there
I mean OpenGL managed textures is just a
function right maybe it got well no I
just looked at it didn't get in mind did
it get in line
yeah it looks like maybe it did all
right hold on one second I mean it's
really weird that we would crash like
that and if you recompile it doesn't
crash does not make a lot of sense I
probably should have run that executable
outside the debugger to see if it was
the debugger that was doing something
nasty there so this is the entirety of
what OpenGL managed textures does right
it just does a DQ OpenGL allocate and
then in Q free that's the entirety of
that process right so if we actually set
a breakpoint in this line here and run
to it
yeah I'm not sure what's going on there
cuz in theory that should just be
calling up with genetics but it looks
like it actually went ahead and
rearranged this probably because of just
being compiled with optimizations right
so I'm guessing that if I compiled
without optimizations on so it won't
inline that code when I actually go here
I'll actually jump into it yeah so so
I'm not sure I'm not sure what we could
have done wrong there that's gonna bug
me
I shouldn't destroy the executable I
guess because we probably can't produce
that particular executable again would
be my guess well and this isn't
multi-threaded at this point right I
mean I don't think the initialization
the initialization code just processes
messages and doesn't ever call the
render so it's really there are not two
actually active threads as far as I know
well all right I guess we'll have to
postpone that till we see that crash
happen again or assume that the debugger
was doing something weird there I really
don't know what that is and it was
reliable it happened in both programs
it happened in both handmade Hiro and in
the standalone renderer
you know I'm saying to you
hmm well all right we're just gonna have
to leave that for now anyway what I was
going to say before we got really
interrupted by that crash which I guess
we don't really know why that would be
happening because a fresh compile does
not produce the bug and presumably these
were the same build before all I was
going to say is we got some pretty good
results here there's only really one
thing that's a little ugly about it but
I think that's something we can leave
for a little later on if you look at the
render tests in handmade hero they both
now get very good throughput so you can
have lots and lots and lots of sprites
well very good is not probably the right
term adequate throughput for our needs
rather than being held back so now we
can just spam tons of grass out if we
want to or do you know who knows what
we're gonna want to do but here you can
just see a test of just throwing a bunch
of grass sprites and there's like
hundreds and hundreds and hundreds them
all over the place and it's fine that's
what we want to make sure we can achieve
right we don't want to be in situations
where we have to worry about we put too
many grass sprites out there or
something so that was good results I'm
glad we got that now handmade here us
have to think about it so hard there are
a few things left we probably want to do
on the renderer that don't have much to
do with the pulling it out part that
part's pretty much done I don't think we
have to really do anything else we got
what we wanted out of that but now what
we would like to do moving back over to
handmade hero there are a couple of
things that would be nice to do that we
just haven't done in the renderer yet
because we only just finished the that
sort of using texture as part of it and
that is first of all we no longer
support large textures because
everything has to fit inside the texture
array so for example if we switch back
to the cutscene which I've done here
what will happen is that all of those
textures we were going to use will all
be trying to draw
extras that are much too large or who
knows what happened right and so yeah we
can look here and see when we go to
allocate the texture the problem that
we're going to have is that the texture
itself will not actually fit inside the
texture array so what's going to happen
here and I probably should compile in
debug mode so we can step through this a
little bit more cleanly but what's going
to happen here is when we get down into
the code that would put the texture into
a texture array it can't because the
texture is too large so what ends up
happening is right here it's going to
come into this routine it's going to ask
for well it's gonna ask for you know oh
I'll put it in texture index 45 like
that's the slot in the texture array but
the width and height are these big
cutscene plates and so what's gonna
happen is open gels gonna be like I
can't put that into here because it's
only 512 by 512 I can't put something
that's 2345 by 1152 right
so what we need is we need to have some
way well okay there's a couple different
ways you could approach this problem if
our goal was to primarily be about
drawing large textures so let's say that
a cutscene was not the only time we were
gonna do that and we had lots and lots
and lots of things in the game they're
all about drawing arbitrarily big stuff
right if that were the case we'd
probably want to do something where we
break large images up into tiles and
then reassemble the tiles right because
we wouldn't want to break our nice clean
render path that doesn't have to switch
textures for that purpose right we would
want to be able to just keep drawing the
tiles everywhere and that would be much
more powerful but we already know that
the only times you really care about
this there's like five or six textures
total in five or six plates total being
drawn on the screen so really we'd be
creating an entire system to deal with
something that really only happens once
in a while and certainly isn't a
performance bottleneck because there's
only like six things on the screen so
changing texture six times in the render
is is free right it's not something we
care about so what we should probably do
here instead is just have a path that
when we see large textures we handle
them specially and let the card do its
standard change over each time with
those large texture calls right because
we don't even have to detect it really
we know when that's happening right we
know that our cutscenes are the things
that use them in our game does it so we
don't even have to detect it we could
because of the texture width and height
are packed into the texture handle the
way we did it so it's a nice convenient
way for anyone who wants you to switch
either way right but we don't even
really have to do that if we wanted to
we could just make a special call called
cutscene plate that's a separate kind of
render state
and that could switch textures every
primitive the way that we used to do it
so we can just by forget the path and I
think that's a much smarter option here
because that's gonna let the card do the
work for us in a more efficient way than
if we were do it ourselves and so we
just be slowing things down by going the
other route I think and actually being
counterproductive that's my assumption
anyway so I think that's thing one we
want to do there's one other thing we
want to do and you can't really see it
much here but if you look at what we're
doing behind the scenes
we are not mipmapping our sprites and we
probably will want to MIT map our
sprites what this means is that as the
sprites scale up and down right the
graphics card can only do by linear
filtering I mean that's not true we
could have it do much better filtering
if you want to but in terms of the
fastest possible drawing bilinear
filtering is the thing that's on the
fast path it can do that basically for
free for us like bilinear filtering is
more or less free bilinear filtering
gets you a scale factor of two okay so
if our sprites are 512 by 512 at maximum
and when they render we could shrink
them down to two by two to six anywhere
between 512 by 512 and 26 by 26 the
bilinear filtering because remember it
blends between two pixels that's the
having factor that would get down to
every pixel represents two pixels in the
original every pixel drawn is two pixels
right there are 512 by 512 pixels 256 by
256 as the size we're rendering so every
single pixel we render corresponds to
two texels
or four texels right in x and y but in
terms of what we're blending between
right
so for texels - left - - left - right -
top to bottom
so at that scale we would produce clean
usable results what happens when we
shrink below 256 by 36 is now every
pixel we draw represents three or more
texels worth of area in the original
image because we will only filter by
linearly we are missing some of the data
and that's why you get that sparkly like
weirdness going on when you shrink
things down below that size now it's
hard to see
unfortunately because our renderer is
actually pretty good and oh I should
probably turn the rotation back on here
our renderer is pretty darn good and so
what ends up happening is that because
we've done a lot of work to carefully
use things like multi sampling and
because you know we're very conscience
it's about depth peeling and all this
stuff what ends up happening is it's
really hard to see that this is
happening because we've got other things
helping to eliminate those sort of
jagged pieces but they're still there
and if we turn off the multi sampling we
would see it for sure and so we get into
a situation where yet if we shrink
things down enough they probably will
start to show some objectionable
artifacting and so because doing MIT
maps is relatively free we probably
should just do even at least a crappy
version something that just does
bilinear filtering when we submit the
texture so that we can have reasonable
quality for down scaling right and yeah
again I don't it's it's hard to motivate
because thanks to the fact that we have
multi sampling turned on we may just
never see it I mean
I can motivate a different way which is
that if you down sample then they'll be
less texture footprint used when you in
the texture cache when you actually go
to draw those things and that could be a
speed win for us I don't know it's hard
to say so yeah sixth one that doesn't
the other the much more pressing thing
in case you can't tell is the cutscene
issue because that one actually prevents
our cutscene from rendering at all
whereas this is a quality issue and as
you saw it's a pretty hard quality issue
to motivate because once you turn on
because you have bilinear sampling you
can shrink down by half and then because
you have multi sampling you get an
additional factor below that probably
right because the multi sampling will
clean a lot of that up to be honest with
you i don't think it should be really
cleaning it up that much so as i'm
saying that i'm not sure why that's
happening it's just the edges probably
really that it would clean up but that's
probably what you would mostly see i
don't know i actually would have thought
we would have seen it a little bit more
so who knows hard to say i mean another
thing that could be happening is maybe
the car is just generating it maps for
us because they can do that actually
like for example
let me see here sometimes there's things
you can turn on that will just do that
yeah like that for Schmitt Maps I'm not
seeing it on here so maybe that doesn't
happen anymore in the old days it did so
I don't know we can do some tests to see
so maybe we don't even really care about
min maps which is kind of crazy that
it's that high quality sampling and
maybe the I mean the other thing I guess
is maybe we're just not drawing things
large enough so maybe a lot of them
aren't being shrank past past double and
if you don't shrink past double then
you're okay right so yeah I don't know
we'll go from there okay so let's start
with the thing that actually we know
makes a difference and then we can
debate the other part of it a little bit
later so if we go into handmade renderer
OpenGL and we look at where we're
actually submitting all of our draw
calls right so we look at the the part
here where we're actually doing like
this
render entry textured quads you can see
the way this works is you know it sets
the scissor rect up it looks whether or
not means you death peeling and then
once it's ready to go
it just says all right go ahead and draw
all the elements this is how we used to
do it right and now we're gonna be like
nad do it this way because we want to be
able to just have everything drawn
without the without the texture handles
right because we're just going to use
the indices that are baked in there so
all I'm saying is that look because it's
probably free for us to do so why don't
we just make it so that we can still do
this this texture switching each time
and there's a pretty easy way we could
probably do that right if we wanted to
be max
we piggy we could actually just use this
and have the texture array be specified
each time right so that way the texture
that we're using to draw from would just
be specified and then we could just
issue multiples of these and and go from
there now the reason that that's a
little bit risky is because there's so
much stuff here that you don't really
need to do right like ideally we would
want it set up the same way we had it
before where we change textures each
time so I'm a little reticent to do that
and I think what might be better is if
we just look at the renderer itself the
way that it specifies this stuff you can
see that the like the textured claws
that we send down we're sending down
this set up that we're setting down this
information what we could do is just say
look why don't we still specify a
texture array like let's just still send
down an array of textures and we'll just
set that pointer to either zero in the
case that we currently have where we
just want to use the texture array and
draw a batch or we set it to non zero
and point to one texture per primitive
and then draw the primitives the way we
used to be drawing them that seems
compelling to me because that allows us
to then have all of the set up be
amortized so the cut scene can still
draw everything in one batch it just has
to issue multiple draw calls but it can
amortize a set-up cost and then the
sprite path can do it is it's doing now
where not only is it amortized a setup
but it actually does a single dispatch
for the entire batch without having to
do multiple dispatches right so that
seems pretty good to me
I think that's the way I would like to
go with it so yeah so what I'm gonna do
here is say alright let's say that
there's something here like
texture pointer we've got the concept of
a renderer texture pointer and if I
remember correctly that's sort of
something that we have in here right
this renderer texture and so we can just
use this stuff that's here again and say
look there's renderer textures that are
special we'll deal with that somehow but
basically all you really need to know is
look there can be a renderer texture
specified in here which is texture array
and this let's just be look texture
array is zero if and I just let me call
it textures textures is zero if using
the default texture array single batch
render textures points to one texture
per quad if not right
and so then we could do here is say well
let's go ahead and do an if and see
which one we actually have so when we
come in here and we get the and we get
the entry out that will have this
pointer and we can just switch on it so
we can say look if this looks like it's
felt textures properly if we have one of
these pointers then we need to do the
old-school dispatch right and if not
then we can do the faster nice dispatch
right
so something like this so all we need to
do now is figure out a good way to
communicate those textures through and
special case them so when someone asks
for a texture that's going to be large
they get back a special handle that's
you know in some little pool that we
reuse and those are for large textures
only in the cutscenes and then we've
gone a separate case where we handle the
texture of a fast path and we just
switch between those as necessary so I
think that's a good way to go now we
need to make sure we can draw the same
way with both of these so you can kind
of see here like we want to do the same
sort of stuff here since we're looking
at indices we need to make sure that all
this it looks like we did it looks like
we updated this routine actually to use
indices so it seems like everything's
actually set so really the only thing we
have to do is just look here at what's
going on maybe I'll call it the same
thing that we were sort of client before
like that and that way we can just say
all right whichever one we're going to
do we'll grab it out of here and then
we'll bind it and go now when we grab
this rendered texture out there's going
to be an index in it and that index in
this case we could just we can just pack
the actual texture handle from OpenGL
into that index that should just work I
think I can't think of a reason why it
wouldn't and so I think we can just go
with that
I think that will be sufficient so
really you can see very simple here it's
really easy for us to handle this to Bay
dispatch so I think this is again just
getting good feeling about that decision
it seems like a really simple way to
handle this one special case
again it's not the bulk of our rendering
we don't want to contort our render path
a bunch to deal with it so you want to
kind of have the easiest possible way to
just shunt those special large texture
calls off to the side and try not to
make them ruin any of the sort of
mainstream high-throughput rendering
that we need for the in-game stuff
because it's just for the cutscenes and
they're very simple they're just a few
layers alright alright so what we need
to do now is actually figure out how to
get this array set up and ready in the
case where we need it right so there's
two parts to that one is detecting these
textures that need special treatment and
doing something with them and two is
actually having space to put this array
so that we actually can use it right we
need some way of dealing with it there
so there's a couple ways we can do this
I'm not sure exactly how we want to do
it I'll kind of just start feeling my
way through it and we'll let it shake
out to wherever it's going to shake out
since we know this is always going to be
a small number of textures we're talking
about like eight 16 textures tops I mean
I think let's let's actually get a bead
on that
I mean it looks like if these are all of
our cutscenes that we sort of threw in
there right one two three four five six
seven eight is the highest so we're
talking about 8 texture handles total
right so what we could very easily do is
allocate a small pool let's say 16
texture handles or something and we
could just go through them in like a
wrap almost a round robin fashion or
something equally crappy
would probably get us by possibly even
just to ship like it may never get more
complicated than that because again like
we only care about this in this specific
case so maybe we'll care about it more
later and wouldn't have to do a better
scheme if it turns out that we do
something else
at some point where we need to think
harder about it but as far as I know
like the cutscene is it and it is what
it is like we're done with it basically
like you know we'll be playing some
audio over it but other than that there
it's not like we did a fake version of
the cutscene and then really the real
version later it's like it is the real
version already so I think it's just
done and really would only be tweaked so
I think we could safely say that a 16
texture round robin scheme or something
where we just overwrite textures in that
order or something would probably be
sufficient and so it's just the asset
system that really has to be aware of
that so that sounds right to me yeah
so I think we may also want to well all
right let me just do it and I'll show
you I was gonna say something about how
we may want to actually use an index
into a array inside the renderer for
other reasons so actually let me well
since I went ahead and blurted out
anyway
so this is probably not quite right it's
probably gonna be something more like
that right so we're probably gonna do
something more like hey I need the
special texture handle for this special
texture and you know that's it'll use
the index in a way that makes sense
there or something right so we'll we'll
deal with that a little bit later but
that's that's probably actually what we
will do so let's go ahead and and push a
little bit further down that path so if
we wanted to make this render texture
stuff a little bit cleaner here so let's
take a look inside the renderer where we
actually push on the quads and figure
out how we would deal with this so
inside push quad you can see here that
we sort of do a kick you know a current
quads thing here and what we want to do
is take a look at that and figure out
whether we need to specify special quad
textures or not for something and so I
think what we want to do is make that
again be something that we do probably
especially it's a little bit hard to say
but probably especially so when you
actually do like a push cube or
something like that you can see here
that we do we you know we do a get
current quad and when we do something
like a push sprite or a push rect you
know we do that get current quads and
and it makes sure we get one
that's Fitz you know a particular size
right and so I think all we really have
to do is make sure that the get current
quads call is smart enough to go hey if
you're switching from rendering
something that's using the fast path the
sounds doing the slow path I need to
create another batch because it already
sort of does that right when it looks at
max quads per batch and it just goes
like I all right
you know you've exceeded them so stop
and so that I think is what we would
really need to do in here where we do
get current quads what we could do is
say look you've got to pass the texture
handle down to us so we can check to
make sure that it's not gonna conflict
or something as we start to worry about
how expensive it is to do these current
quad calls we may need to do more than
that but you know let's just assume
we're gonna do that here so we'll say
that you pass a renderer texture here so
you say a quad count and the texture
that you're planning to use and then we
can do is say well okay if there were
current quads and the grip current quads
has quad textures I guess I should say
and it doesn't match like we sort of
need a thing which says that the quad
textures is either on or off based on
whether we want it to be on or offering
as well right so we might just I guess
be a little more explicit about that say
current quad current textures and we
could just say current quads quad
textures so you know if that's not
to zero then the current currently we
have textures and we need textures for
this one we could say like this textures
is something like needs quad textures
right we could ask if this one needs it
and then we could say if current
textures is not equal to this textures
then we also have to flush right so
basically that's just a way of us saying
look we've got a batch we always Jam
things into the current batch as far as
we can go but anytime we hit a blocking
condition that's like we can't do any
more on this batch then we flush and
make a new batch so we're just adding a
new check here to make sure that if we
need to switch between texture arrays
and large textures or vice-versa that we
flush that batch and go from there now
this is actually out here because it
doesn't depend on whether there's
current quads or not and we do need to
know this because we're then going to
have to create one of those arrays here
if we need it right so ups so we're
going to have to go all right the
current quads needs to get a quad
textures here for whatever the quad
count is that you're actually going to
output right and so that becomes again a
little bit more persnickety now what I'd
like to do because I like the way we
were setting up before I think I might
want to do it kind of think here
I mean I think I might want to do it
kind of the same way we were doing it
before where we just used the vertex
buffer an index buffer that are that are
kind of inside the the render group
there right so like I'm sorry the render
commands where's it out there it is so
you know this game render command struct
has all that stuff in it like the push
buffer and so on and so it feels like
that's probably a natural place to put
it where we just have an array there for
that purpose
you know what I mean so we would have in
here sort of a texture array that's like
you know max texture count and inside
the render or texture stuff we just have
I don't like using the word texture
right even though that's what it is
because it makes it sound like the
texture array that's inside the renderer
which it's not so this would allow us to
sort of append those on
and I think that's how I want to do it
so if we just make one more right here
that's the same as we used to have so
really we're just restoring the old
feature we're not even really
implementing something new I'm kind of
saying look let's it's a little bit
different but it's mostly the same we
just have a back band array it's got
some information in it for textures it's
small you know this is maybe 64 to t6
something really tiny because we know
we're only gonna have like eight nine
ten of them so you know we're just it's
not gonna be a large number of these
things and so I think that's really all
we will be talking about here so we just
say all right you know the quad textures
is really just gonna be a pointer into
that into that array so we would say all
right the quad textures is whatever the
commands quads textures is oops plus
whatever the offset was at that point so
it'd be like commands quad texture count
right it's just gonna point in there and
then people can stack those up in there
and similarly in here we would have to
double check like that the quad texture
count plus the quad count here is not
going to exceed the max cloud texture
cap because if it does then you can't
render right you've you've run out of
steam so you've got to double check that
you know when we look at the quads we're
actually going to return they better
actually be valid for the number that
people are saying they're going to draw
so this also is predicated on the fact
that you're going to actually use it so
in here right we know that this is going
to be if this textures I mean well
actually do this way
right it's a little ugly so maybe I'll
leave it like this so if you need
textures then you will get them if you
don't need textures you won't so by
default it's zero and then if you
actually want the textures then we'll
give you that will give you the textures
and similarly here either
you don't need textures right so if this
is 0 ox I used to say if this is true
and you would exceed then it's bad but
if this was false then it's ok right so
we won't shrink because if you're not
using textures we don't care if you
would exceed right so then we just need
to answer this question which is does a
particular texture need quad textures
and we can make a call that does that
check pretty easily so we'll deal with
that in a second in the meantime here we
could just say and same with get special
texture for a right so now let's take a
look at what else stopping here so in
this case we need to be able to I
certainly have a null texture do we yes
we do
um so I don't actually know if we know
well I don't actually need that there we
actually pass the texture there so I
don't remember if there's places that we
pass and millet extra we probably do and
so we may need to deal with that a
second but we'll across the picture come
to it so here you go is an example right
there's no texture here so we need like
in the military for these circumstances
which seems fine in most cases we should
probably have one is just the wrecked
like the sort of debug drawing tools
that don't use that oh well you know
what they use group white texture anyway
so in theory we could just pass that
because that is correct
so actually that seems fine but everyone
else will have a texture and so most of
the time anything that we actually care
about will act we'll be using an actual
texture here
get current quads does not - yes that's
true where is the texture handle bitmap
texture handle and get kind of quads for
the white texture
oops just be here so I think almost good
all right so I think that's all good we
just now need to have an understanding
of when those get created right when
they're larger so needs quad texture is
probably not the best name for it so I
think we probably want to have something
more like special texture handle like is
special texture right is probably more
what we're talking about here and inside
the renderer this is something that
we're gonna want to be able to answer
really easily right so if you ask if a
renderer texture is a special texture
it's gonna be something like you know if
the width and height are different than
the dimensions of the texture right so
this right here is really what we're
talking about so we we probably want to
have this be past the render group just
in case in the future it becomes a
parameter that we don't necessarily know
at compile time so right now we won't
actually use this but we would
potentially use it in the future right
so the results here is just gonna be if
the textures width is greater than the
array dim or the textures height is
greater than the array dim then that's
all we need to know it's gonna be
special at that point right and so we
could do other ways of deterring it but
right now that's dispositive so we can
probably just say done we could do other
fancy things there so for example we
could have a break in our indices we
could say that indices like above the
high bit set are special and below the
bit aren't or something but I'm just not
gonna bother with that I'm just gonna
say look it's based on the width and
height for now
and we could change that right we could
we could change the the indexing scheme
in the future well ok you know what no
now that I say it I'm gonna take that
back and the reason I'm going to take
that fact is because if we do it with
the index we wouldn't get we would
guarantee ibly never have to pass a
group here or look anything up so if we
did something more like this that would
allow us to say oh there's a special
textured bit here that you know
determines whether or not the texture is
a special texture we never need to know
anything about where it came from or
compare it to anything we can just do a
quick bit check and off we go
that does seem kind of compelling for a
lot of reasons right so if we look here
we've got two u16s and a u-32 so like
yeah we could just say hey there's a
special texture bit and it's you know
that or something right
and that would allow us to really
quickly determine it and go from there
so yeah I mean I guess the only thing we
really need to do at that point is when
we do get special text or handle for we
now need some way of resolving those
textures and and when we go to submit
textures we need a special way of saying
that those textures were ones that we're
gonna go down the special pipe so that
seems good to me and there's a couple
different ways we could do this but
we'll talk about that a little bit later
all right
but I'm reasonably happy with that so
okay so if we take get special texture
handy for and we throw that in here just
real quick so this is not really
implemented yet when we actually send a
render or texture damn it should be able
to return us that handle we're gonna
need to pass it probably the OpenGL
context stuff because it's probably
going to look into an array of some kind
but other than that should be pretty
straightforward
let me do this here so we can see it as
well if and when we step into this code
to debug it so we'll do it a little bit
more like this see good that all seems
reasonable
so I think that should be pretty much it
for the binds for the user side in terms
of like outputting these textures and
hopefully if I have to screw anything up
everything just works when you're not
using textures of that size so basically
you know the render test suite the game
as it currently exists should be fine
and so they're just still running
through the same path and that other
path is just sitting in there not being
used when we switch to the cutscene now
of course we'll still get the exact same
error that we got before because we now
have to actually take the step to create
our large textures as special textures
which we have not done so now we just
need to do the last part of this which
is to make the asset system aware of
situations where it's loading a texture
above the texture or a size that it
specifies so inside the asset system
that's really where this stuff now gets
a little complicated is we just have to
have when we load the assets we have to
have the texture understand when it's
special and when it's not right and so
when we do all of this stuff it can just
pass through because the texture handle
itself says whether or not it's special
so it's really the point where we refer
to the texture that it makes it that it
becomes relevant right so right here
when we do our refer to texture and we
use next free texture handle that part
right here this right here
here's the part that's gonna need to
understand that it has to use a separate
texture pool for large textures and so
what I want to do is expand the renderer
out or expand the asset system
understanding a little bit and don't
forget one of the things that's
interesting about the way we're doing
the asset system here is we can now
massively simplify most of what's
happening in the asset system because
almost all of our textures in it now are
fixed size for the most part in terms of
how we're actually handling them and
they're being backed by storage in the
renderer so we really don't need to have
most of the code that's me asset system
anymore it can just back be backed by
texture handles and be done so this to
do is very much correct and that's sort
of a separate issue but what we need to
do here is have some way of saying all
right there's going to be two ways that
this is going to happen really this call
can be the same but what we want to do
here is say that there's a free texture
Anil I don't know why that's a u16
because I thought that it was actually
u32 I think that may be old news at this
point because there's no reason it has
to be you 16 now you could never use 32
bits because there's no way the graphics
card has enough memory to have a texture
array that's 32 bits worth of indices so
you can kind of forget that in this day
and age maybe someday in the distant
future that will be possible but
certainly not right now so if we look at
an actual renderer texture here I'm
pretty sure yeah
so right at least right now we're not
doing that now in the future maybe we
want to use the 16-bit index and use the
other 16 bits for something more useful
because we're also not going to have
65,000 textures load
any more than we were gonna have four
billion textures loaded both of those
are ridiculous for our current hardware
specs so that's not an issue but at the
moment in history two bits so there's no
reason to be casting we should save the
casting for when we actually need to do
that so let's do this here
we'll start by saying that in the case
where the texture is not special we will
do this and in the case where the
texture is special we will do the will
get it from a round-robin scheme so in
here we would just say next special
texture handle and we will want to mod
that value by the texture
we'll want it to wrap right so what
we'll do when we assign this is we'll
say well you know use the next special
texturing handle plus plus and we want
to say if the next special texture that
you would have used is outside the range
then we would reset it back to zero
right
sueing here we'd say something like max
special texture handle count or
something like this or just special
texture handle count and so we just
assign and wrap and so it will reuse the
textures as it goes in that way okay now
again this is not really correct yet
because we still haven't dealt with sort
of how the asset system as a whole is
thinking about these and that's because
the asset system still stores these
textures itself which we don't really
want it to do and so we're gonna
probably fuss with that a little bit in
the not-too-distant future but that's a
separate issue so we've got the texture
handle here and the texturing handle is
going to be a sign in one of two ways
now and what we're gonna do is now is
the finally the time that we might want
to do a dimensions require special
texture handle or something like this
right and so what we can do here is say
look let's pass the width and height in
and we'll ask does this texture need
special handling according to the system
and you know now I think about it this
is probably a termination fest made by
the asset system and so the asset system
itself can say when it starts up it'll
maybe create the texture array with a
specific size and that's how it will do
it so in the future we could make that
more flexible where we create different
sizes of texture array based on for
example what resolution we're running at
so we probably want that feature to be
something that's internal to the asset
system itself not something that the
renderer cares about and really doesn't
care what size you make the texture
array as long as it fits in memory so
it's probably something better done sort
of out here so if we pass the width and
height in this
here like so
then what we can do is we can compare
those exactly like we were going to do
before now what we will say here is in
the future probably make this dynamic
but for right now we don't have to and
so all we really do here is exactly the
thing I was gonna write before in the
other part of half that I decided now
let's make it to the handle nose and so
all we're gonna do here say look if the
width is greater than whatever the
texture Tim is that we've sort of
hard-coded now I guess why I say let's
make it dynamic maybe in the future
because there's really not a lot of
reason for it to be hard-coded it'd be
pretty easy modification for us to make
it so that you pass it when you start
the renderer up you know so anyway we'll
just say look there's a width and height
here and the texture array dimensions
we're gonna test against them if you
exceed them in either case then you will
need special texture handling so you go
through the special texture path
otherwise you don't right so I think
that's really all there is to it and off
you go so here where we do refer to
texture we're going to go ahead and put
the texture handle in here and what we
need to do now is the texture handle
itself needs to get the special bit Ord
in there so that everybody knows that
it's a special texture and not one of
the ones that goes through the random
the regular packing path so in here when
we know that it was a special texture we
could do something like this texture
handle
we'll make special texture like that or
something something like that and then
inside the renderer it's got a way of
tagging that out so you say okay pass me
in the index and I'll pass you back the
thing that says that it's special while
we're at it we will assert that the
index doesn't already have that bit set
because obviously if someone actually
was trying to use those bits somehow
that's bad because that's reserved for
our use we need to make sure that it's
not there and so we're going to keep
that like masked off right so we need
the asset system itself to have this
special texture concept now in it so in
addition to next free texture handle
this is going to have next special
texture handle and it's also going to
have special texture handle count and
these are going to be things that are at
the start you know when we initialize
that we have to just know right they
have to be created in the renderer and
we have to just know exactly how it's
going to work so when we go to allocate
the game assets we need to set up the
special texture handle count and
presumably our renderer texture cue for
example could have that on it
since that's something that it knows
about and it'll just say look this is
how many special textures you're gonna
get so deal with it right
I'm not sure if that's the best way I
mean really handmade here itself
probably wants to to specify that at
startup how many special textures it
wants and this information kind of has
to get get trickled down here so I feel
like to a certain extent it's like this
is largely sort of a communication thing
that has to happen if we take a look at
the texture op queue here since that's
the thing that people would be looking
at and would have a handle tube in here
I think it might make some sense to put
the information about how the textures
are set up because then everyone knows
what that is so I might say look let's
say that in addition to the texture
queue operation in here you can also get
a thing that says your texture handled
count like your normal texture handle
count and your special texture handle
count and so in here you just know what
those two are you know I'm saying
furthermore since the texture op q is
there I guess that means I could just
get rid of that and I could just say
alright let's make that be something
that happens in here so when we actually
do the the load bitmap function we could
do that now one of the things that I'm
not sure about is because this I believe
that this is always load bitmap is
always called synchronously
it's not inside a task so I think it's
safe to just use regular increments here
meaning these things are not hit by
multiple threads at once we don't have
to be careful about whether or not
they're like actually gonna get out of
sync incremented and gets some kind of
bad over-allocation situation happening
cuz I'm pretty sure that basically the
only thing that happens on the deferred
thread is just the load decompress you
know or the load prepare stuff right
it's all that happens so I think that
probably is irrelevant alright so what
I'm gonna do here is just say okay this
is actually going to be texture op cube
special texture handle camp and so
that's just fine
and off it goes so really all we need to
do now to make this work I think
everybody is treating it reasonably also
I can put this assertion here like
assert that the next free texture
handled the one that we're about to use
is less than the assets texture normal
texture handle count and so we can also
now check to see when we overrun if that
makes sense so now all we need to do to
actually bring the scheme together and
start debugging it and testing it is we
need to have a way of when we start up
OpenGL allocating some of those special
texture handles so that there actually
is some thing there to use we're
handling them all up and down the
pipeline now but that doesn't really
make any difference if nobody ever
allocates any of these to begin with you
can't very well render with the texture
you've never allocated now where do we
do that well we kind of know because
remember we ran this before and crashed
well we didn't crash we hit an open GL
error that said hey you're trying to put
a texture in a texture array that
doesn't fit and so insight allocate
texture here where we're putting this in
what we can do now
is actually control this very cleanly
right so we can take back this core code
here where we specify the GL text image
and we can say look this is now going to
be predicated on whether or not you're
using a special texture handle or a
regular texture handle so the same thing
would happen here like so and we could
maybe get these off of the op queue as
well depending on whether or not we have
that here we can look at that to sort of
collapse those down into something a
little bit more usable there but again
here the way that we would do that is we
would just now instead of trying to
generate a texture handle at this point
we'd actually just reuse the texture
Nano and and over bind it so we'd
replace the image that was in there with
the new image that we were getting and
so I think that's pretty much it this
stuff here can actually happen I don't
know why I feel like buying texture 0
should probably just happen out here to
clear out that just in case I'm gonna
leave it like that for now um so really
what we want to do is accent thing we're
doing here so we want to move this gen
textures out right into something we're
gonna deal with a little bit later and
similarly these text parameters the text
image is separate from the text
parameter it's in OpenGL so especially
the recess on the image shouldn't clear
these out so we probably don't need to
specify them again either we can
probably specify them once when we
create those textures and then just run
with it so really I think all we need to
do is this path here so what we can do
is say test the texture for a special
miss right so in here we can just say
alright is it a special texture that
you're trying to bind if it is then what
we need to do is create the index from
it so
here where we were just getting the
index out raw what we can do now is say
that we're gonna take and mask off that
texture special bit I feel like that
should just be an X or probably huh you
know my brain is just not one of those
brains that does algebra well like just
period so like really basic stuff that
you would think I would have known
because I've done it so many times I
still often times have to think about
for some reason things like geometric
things I don't so a lot of times I'll
just be like oh yeah well it's just like
the cross-product daunted with this and
like my brain just like works out the
entire geometric construction I can just
say the whole thing because the practice
has built up the ability to jump several
steps forward even with fairly complex
geometric things like quaternions
sometimes I can do that
algebraic things it's like the opposite
the simplest stupidest thing like is an
X or the same as an and not he is
something that someone who's been
programming for 30 years would probably
just know but I don't I have to actually
sit there every time and go like okay so
an X or right lifts to it an X or if
it's zero zero it equals one right cause
excluse its exclusive I'm sorry if zero
zero equals zero so it's exclusively or
right if it's 0 and 1 its 1 if it's 1
and 0 its 1 and if it's 1 in 1 its 0
right
because it has to be exclusively Ord
with the thing meaning you can't have
the same value in any one Lane right
whereas an end that not an end with a
knotted second parameter well an end
with anything that's 0 is going to be 0
right so and and
in this case yes so that's this one's
different right so and not in this case
like if I'm not that that will become a
zero so this would still be zero right
if I X or the I'm sorry if I am not the
one in the zero that will actually give
me a one and if I and not this one I
would get a zero as well right
again when I say I'm bad at this I'm not
kidding so correct truth table so no
they're not they're not saying they're
right
you get one difference in them which is
that the so in this case we're doing
like this was the original value and
what we're trying to do is clear out
where it's a 1 so if the 1 is set here I
want to clear it which is what's
happening whereas if I don't have it set
I don't clear it and so you can see the
case where it's wrong is that if I was
trying to clear this I will accidentally
set it so it's almost what I want right
but not quite so that comports with my
recollection which was sort of that no
you can't do that because I always write
it like this and I don't write it like
this but I just wanted to underscore
that because sometimes you know one of
the things I say a lot on handmade hero
is that I like to show the actual act of
programming 2d mythologize a lot of the
stuff about how good people actually are
or aren't because most programmers I
know or probably all are bad at some
things and make mistakes and struggle
with stuff all the time even the very
best people and I think it's usually
good to show that that's true because I
feel like some people may get
unrealistic expectations about how good
people are and they're almost always
inflating the their opinion of how good
another person actually is yes there are
great programmers there's no question
about that but even great programmers
struggle all the time and I get to see
that because I've gotten to work with
great programmers I think that's one of
the nicest things about handmade hero
style streaming is that now there's so
many people like you can go watch John
Blow stream who you know I mean like if
anyone deserves credit it's him in the
game industry I mean of people who have
done game programming he's like the top
right
you can just watch them make a mistake
and I feel like that's really good
because every time you can watch someone
make a mistake you're like oh okay it's
okay like I'm not like bad at this or
something this is just how it goes and
so I feel like the more of that we get
there it's like yeah you know like I've
been programming forever and I still
there's just parts of my brain they're
just like yep it's never gonna learn
that you know who knows why just isn't
it's gonna have to draw out a truth
table sometimes for stuff that you
should just know like you should just be
able to just do it and so when people
are just starting out and they're like
wow this stuff is hard it's like yeah it
it does get easier but it always is a
little hard right like even with a lot
of experience or even if you're a very
successful program or anything else
[Music]
there's always some things because it's
such a complicated discipline you're
never going to be perfect like it's just
not gonna happen no matter who you are I
don't think maybe I'm wrong about that
but I've never seen anybody who can
write so anyway long digression but it's
I just think that's great about
streaming programming because that's one
of the things I don't think people see
enough you know when you post finished
code on a blog or something it's just
you feel like it just came out of
nowhere and that person must be awesome
but no they probably made all kinds of
screw-ups on the way to that but you
just didn't see and so the streaming
formats so much nicer because you can
see the mistakes and I feel like that's
just really important for beginners to
see so they know that's not them that's
just programming right so anyway okay so
what I want to do here is I want to be
able to get the texture out of thing so
I'm going to make a texture index I'm
just gonna get the
index out of it right out of the
textures that we're talking about and so
then instead of using text or dot index
I'm just gonna use texture index
directly and that way I can know that
it's been masked off and it doesn't have
the flag on there anymore because I
don't really want that in there anymore
so now the question is well where do I
get the handle from right and the answer
is I get the handle from the get special
right the where is that guy the get
special texture handle for this guy
right here is where that would come from
right and it's actually this this code
right here I is what that means to start
with now in this case this kind of
becomes redundant I don't like the
construction that I've kind of chosen
there because I'm gonna end up having a
double call this in a kind of stupid way
you see what I mean in a second but when
I call a texture image from here that
strips off the index here now I need to
look that up I want to assert then it's
less than a special texture handle count
right which will gonna look at a little
bit later and then I want to just grab
it like so and so all I'm doing here is
saying all right peel it off look up
into an array this is the array that I
will allocate later and we'll go from
there
all right so let's keep going with that
so the reason I was saying I didn't
really love this is because the texture
index from thing here doesn't really
need to happen in that case so oh well I
guess maybe I'll do it like this and
like this
okay that's not so bad
seems reasonable so here we can
bifurcate the paths we checks you with a
special texture if it is a special
texture we will handle it by letting the
graphics card do whatever crazy
ideations wants to handle an unusually
sized texture that's not even power to
and it's a disaster and everyone's
unhappy but then most of the time it
will not be special texture so we could
pack it nicely into a texture array and
the grabs car will be pleased
I don't won't get mad at us right so
we'll do that and then what we need to
do is when we are actually allocating
our texture array in the first place
which is down here so when we do this GL
gem texture is for our texture array
that we need to actually create the
special textures as well so what we want
to do in this case is right here we want
to do the same sort of path right we
want to do a deal gem textures we want
to say say that we're going to generate
opengl special textual special texture
handles there we go
and we want to do the special texture
handle count which is going to be
parameterize Abul right there is so ever
many of these we wanted we're going to
generate an array of them to use and
then what we're going to do is for each
one of those we're going to set the
texture parameters parameters on it
upfront so that we don't have to set
them later because otherwise we'd just
be sitting around setting them all the
time
so what we're going to do here is bind
that texture up right here and inside
here we'll just say all right
loop through all of them and for each
one get those parameters initialized for
us right and that just saves us from
spewing unnecessary traffic down the bus
I mean it doesn't matter because the
number of textures that we're talking
about is so small here as you recall the
whole point of it is we're only gonna
have a few of them we certainly could
send them down on allocate it's not a
big deal but why do something
unnecessary when it's unnecessary and
it's trivial to do the right way right
it you know if it was some big deal I'd
be like yeah it's probably not worth it
but in this case it's so simple to do it
this way that it's you know what can I
say
so let's go ahead and get that stuff set
up so I gotta actually access the index
there properly so this doesn't need to
happen anymore because that's gonna be
handled and get special texture handle
for that needs to be moved up so that it
can be seen here but otherwise that's
easy enough and then we need to actually
be aware of those special texture handle
situations so in here we've got or I
think we should have there it is our
texture array and we've got a texture
handled count that we're recording I
think we're talking about this right
here right and that max texture count is
now needs to be augmented with also a
one for special textures you know what I
mean so in addition to the GL you meant
texture array here
we need sort of one for special textures
and so for right now again I don't know
that I necessarily care too much well
and trying to think of how we want to do
it so you know we we we do have startup
code that sets the texture handle count
I believe right I mean you can pass that
in I think so you write because there's
a max there's a max texture count here
so it seems like we should probably let
you say the maximum number of quads you
want to handle the maximum number of
textures and the maximum number of
special textures I can't think of a
reason not to do this so yeah so that's
gonna say let's say that you get to pass
that max special texture count so when
you create one of these you can say max
special texture count equals max special
texture count right and that'll get
allocated up for you
I guess one question I have is in terms
of the texture op q do we yeah I mean
seems reasonable so let's just go with
that and we'll see if I had any
nastiness is so that seems reasonable we
can also say max quad texture count max
quad count the frame and the mascot
proper frame here it's just literally
that this will also let us
allocate the array that we need to for
storing the open gel arrays here oh we
still do it this is actually still here
right so that didn't appareil we never
stopped allocating it it's still there
so we can just use that right we just
don't need as many yeah that's too many
we don't actually need that many so I
might I'm not totally sure I feel about
that I'm gonna can note about that so
I'll just leave it this way for now
and we'll deal with that a little bit
later so the other thing that I do need
to do here though is since we don't know
how many of those they've asked for we
do still need to be because we are going
to have a max special texture right we
need to have an array here for those
I also these are not actually these
actually don't change when the say so
these really shouldn't be in the dynamic
resources section because these don't
change they're actually the same right
this is kind of not true the push buffer
memory and the vertex are a bitmap array
index array all that stuff gets
allocated actually one time
so I think that's a little bit more
accurate right so what we need to do
here is specify one of these texture
arrays for the special textures and we
also need to have some way of saying how
many there are so once we have those
then in here we can also do sort of the
exact same thing we did here which is
say alright special texture handles
equals do you in Star Max special
texture count times size of and that way
you can have as many as you want and we
will allocate those specifically for you
and they don't have to be a fixed number
so when that comes in that'll just kind
of work right and we should be good to
go
that this is one line up and okay so
let's see here
special Dijkstra handle count this is
actually Mac's special texture count but
I think that's otherwise good that is
not that that's just a pointer and so
now we're allocating those the render
commands themselves though when we do
begin frame is going to need to have the
new settings properly accounted for so
we do need to do a couple of things here
we need to set this stuff up so the max
quad texture count the quad texture
count and the quad textures have to be
set properly so the max quad texture
count is really just the same as the
number of actual quads you can stuff
down I don't know if we saved that
anywhere I hope we did it didn't so
we'll have to just save that
what I could do is say max quad texture
count is actually a thing and we're
gonna use it and then I'll just set that
when we actually set the rest of our
stuff kind of the way that I was going
to do it there so like that so that kind
of sets up the aperture and gets
everything ready to go and so now really
what we need to do is make sure we can
actually get that from somewhere we do
have sort of a renderer definition here
[Music]
don't remember where this is actually
specified we've got some kind of a
platform layer specification for it but
let me go ahead and look here so
renderer where do we specify this stuff
so it's so it is just in here I guess or
seen it stuff not in here
alright so it's in Windsor two-handed
okay so it is just it's just this
specification here yeah so we can just
say max special texture count as
additional parameter that you have to
provide and then everybody who was
previously calling something there
so this doesn't use one so it wouldn't
care whereas handmade here oh it does
use one so it needs to say hey we're
going to use up to 16 of these
in terms of the texture up cube I really
want the texture up queue to have that
information in it but it seems like that
maybe not that likely right because it's
separate it's just a cue that's separate
from the renderer and so it's like
someone would just have to let copy it
in there and I just don't know if that
makes much sense you know i'm santi so I
kind of feel like
I kind of feel like these should just be
separate from it so I think I'm gonna
have to not do it that way because it
just doesn't just feels like I'm shoving
sort of stuff through where it shouldn't
really go so I do feel like maybe you
know maybe that stuff has to be put into
a better location so if the game assets
we're gonna have that stored separately
right then I just need to pass those
down and I think the way I could do that
is right now it could just be a pound of
fine because handmade Hiro is gonna use
however many it's going to use and it
really won't change so I think that can
just be a pound to find that's sort of
used at initialization time in both
places and that would be fine so I think
that's probably fine and wouldn't really
cause a problem so inside here where we
actually do the initialization I feel
like that's okay so you know
yeah I mean I think that's what I would
go with for now don't really see much
point in doing it a different way so
here you just say look the normal
texture NACA handmade we could just set
those those that way maybe in the future
we make them be more dynamic than that
but the important part to me is that the
renderer can be started up in either way
I just need to make sure those are the
same across each one's because then in
the future we could do it a different
way if we want to and make that into a
more parameterised thing right so that's
probably fine so inside handmade H I'll
just make some pound of fines for this
at the moment
see what I include inside when teaching
handmade because that's where it's gonna
have to get used right so much went
through to code
so yeah I mean I'm not really sure
exactly where they should live it's
something that we're probably gonna want
to fix I just don't have a clear idea of
how that would get past you at the
moment it could be something that comes
in and in the game input or something
like this or in the game sort of the way
the game gets started up I'm just not
sure
so I think this will probably be changed
eventually but that's roughly what it
would be currently so alright there's a
quite a bit of stuff that has to happen
there and so we kind of got a look
through this a little bit more carefully
here but that's basically what's going
on what did we what happened here
I should hole a second sorry I just want
to switch to debug mode so we can have
an easier time
so let's just take a look here what's
our max special texture cap 16
what's our special handles like oh so
did that not get allocated I thought I
did I probably just made a slight
mistake there and didn't even though I
thought I did ah this is in the wrong
place
that is the problem there so these
probably should happen before the open
jail in it right I should probably do
them here so we can have everything
allocated up that might get used
so there that now can operate properly
so it looks like you know nominally
working right like it didn't crash and
it's showing textures but we don't
really know to what extent it's actually
working right we haven't like looked at
any of that stuff so we probably want to
do now is start like stepping through
some of that code and make sure that we
like we're kind of out of time for days
so maybe I'll do it tomorrow but it
looks like it's not correctly picking
special texture here because you can see
that index does not have the high bit
set so yeah
looks like that's our primary problem
here let me just quickly fix that since
we know it's a problem and then we'll
wrap it up for today and we'll do the
debugging work tomorrow since everything
still runs just not the cutscenes which
is the same way we started the day so
it's not like we're breaking anything
we just haven't finished fixing it so
yeah special textures dimensions of cry
switch textures takes the width and the
height looks to see whether or not it
needs to use a dynamic one generates a
special texture handle here based on
that
so I don't see anything obviously wrong
there let's take a look in the debugger
real quick just to see what's going on
with that so let's go into load bitmap
here and just take a look at what
happens when it goes through this code
path so you know we're looking in here
and we've got a width of 144 or height
of yeah I mean you see what's going on
there
and so you know all of these for the
initial set of textures are all going to
be you know they're gonna be small this
is fonts and junk probably right so that
does its thing and then when we go to
the cutscenes we need to take a look and
see what's happening on the large ones
is something not tagging those textures
properly or what so here's our bitmap
the width and height are obviously too
large up well that's initial screw-up
that should be an or right not an and
you know what Allen Webster was talking
about this very bug maybe not this one
but a closely related book in this case
though it doesn't matter because they
are both larger than 512 so the result
is true so it comes in here I it says
look let's get a special texture for a
texture handle 0 it says all right let's
compute a result by Oregon the texture
bit there it is out pops the texture
handle it's that right so then we're
going to do refer to texture
and it sure seems right so I wonder if
it's just the and let's see where what
is the dimension we actually crash on
because maybe it is just the end yes
it's just because the height was lower
so it was just because of this and
should have been or there right
yeah so it did look like the other parts
we're working okay no I don't know that
they actually are but you know what is
this why are we still you 16 in that so
that's not right that oh wait a minute
that is probably because we pack it into
16 bits instead of 32 for setting it
down so that's actually fine
this assert doesn't actually catch the
bug any particular bug so it's actually
fine what we want to do here is sort of
say like this so once you peel off the
special handle like right because if you
do want to pack it into 16 you totally
can it's just you have to have peeled
off a special handle otherwise you'll
think that it doesn't match anymore
because hey a 16-bit number can't equal
the 32-bit number right so that is not
good
so index array offset is boat so I said
we were gonna bug this tomorrow I guess
I lied I'm just debugging it now
probably because these have all been
really obvious bugs so you just tend to
want to fix them
we've probably changed the meaning of
this
although I can't say that it looks like
we did hmm so
the entry just looks straight-up bogus
whereas nothing else does well that kind
of does that's not a special texture
so we does kind of look bogus actually
this on the other hand looks fine so
it's not total garbage
but it's kind of garbage II let's take a
look here what is going on real quick I
would just like to see so we set this up
to be the quad texture count and zero
and Max Tucker's all that stuff makes
sense indexed array and all that it's
good stuff looks good get current quads
looks at the batching here if you can't
fit the number of quads it'll reset if
it needs a special texture it will reset
and if it has to allocate Oh
why is it not setting the index array
offset there so this may have just been
in a bug we had before that didn't rear
its head till now because it looks like
we never use index array offset actually
and it was probably just getting set to
zero by happenstance I'm guessing I
don't know if that's exactly correct but
it certainly seems like we should be
doing that ie
and if you look at how we're using it
here right we are doing that now this
needs to be changed slightly so we do
need to we do need to have that routine
work a little bit because now the those
arrays don't line up one-to-one right
and so we do kind of need to say well
alright let's just do the index arrayed
directly over the quad count and we'll
take the index array offset and add it
in right so right here we'll do that
because this needs to be able to do the
diff by 6 there
furthermore it's unclear that we really
want to do that I mean why not do this
right so let's loop over the quad count
the index is just going to be the offset
of the clawed index times six right so
we just say look start where we're going
to start and for every quad we go six
forward then that way this is just a
direct index into quad texture is no
divide and then the draw elements call
just works using the same stuff we were
using before right so we just say yeah
like that seemed saner to me it was a
little bit contorted before so that must
have just been a bug we just overlooked
it when we finished last time a month
ago on our last stream before a break we
probably just overlooked that because we
were only ever doing one dispatch
because the entire game was being drawn
with a single dispatch right and so now
that we're drawing multiple dispatches
we need to do that now unfortunately we
aren't seeing anything which is not
great but we're not crashing so now we
know we are actually at least using the
textures a little bit more correctly my
assumption is that probably we just have
a slight few issues with how where's
maybe submitting the textures or
something pretty basic it probably won't
be too hard to finish this off and get
to a point where this is working
but now I probably should save it for
another day because I suspect this will
now be somewhere we got to kind of look
at the open jail a little bit more
carefully which as you know is always a
little bit of a adventure so probably
don't want to do too much more let me
just take a quick look
where we set these up where is my there
it is
yeah so I mean it seems reasonable so
yeah I don't see anything obviously
wrong so I'm suspecting we'll have to do
a little bit more hardcore checking on
that just to make sure
I must set a breakpoint in here real
quick just to take a look at what it
looks like and again that path never
gets hit it's just it's only in the
cutscenes
all right so we take a look here at the
index that we're drawing it's zero take
a look at the texture it's zero that's
width and height of zero I'm not sure
doesn't quite sound correct here oh hey
one thing we might want to do is when
you actually push a quad on there you
might want to push one onto the you
might want to actually record the
texture that you're using which we did
not do oops I so yeah what we could do
here is say look we get the current
quads we can say if it's special push it
on there
I think we can just do this I think I do
not want anyone to quote me on that
because it's sort of a vague feeling I
have that I can do that it's sort of a
premonition rather than a actually
scientifically thought through thing
that looks a lot better
well it looked a lot better in the code
it doesn't look any better in the game I
said I was gonna stop programming and I
didn't did I I lied I completely it was
like a bald-faced lie
so I really will stop now I just I
sometimes it's a little obsessive you
know what I'm saying so this is binding
texture drawing elements once I short
off the index index of zero and we did
bind those right so they should be
correct all right so I'll I'll leave it
there I'll leave it there let's go to a
brief Q&amp;A and I will leave it there we
will come back to it I keep saying I was
gonna stop I didn't stop we will come
back to it tomorrow and we'll debug why
we're not getting think we've done
everything else but we did make a lot of
changes
commands should be entry online where it
breaks commands with left / right you
are I still don't think that helps us
because it's it's probably the first one
but so I think we're still probably
broken but that step you're you're right
yeah we shall sit me still I think
should have seen one bitmap if so I
think we probably still have another bug
unfortunately I wish that were the only
one but I don't I don't think it's
enough good caps though yeah because we
would have seen one bitmap is what would
have happened in that case we would have
always drawn with bitmap zero right
probably would have seen more actually
now I think about it yeah just not quite
not quite it was it was a bug row just
not the only bug
all right are we so if we have no
questions then we're done we will be
back tomorrow for more fun and James
how do you know activate some variants
for your GLSL um so we aren't really
doing much in the way of parametrized
shading so we don't really have much in
the way of what you're talking about
really all we do is we just have a
couple shaders I think we have like four
or five of them that we actually use and
we just set up the parameters manually
in the code right so we don't we don't
really have like if you had like a
hundred shaders or whatever you wouldn't
be able to do what we're doing I don't
think because we're doing something much
more simplistic so you can see here like
we just grabbed these out and then we
later just set them when we go to
actually do that dispatch uh and that's
because we're fundamentally not a GLSL
party like we we only use GLSL to
replicate the things we would want to do
in our software renderer it's pretty
basic stuff right like so if you were
like really shade or heavy and had tons
of stuff happening in shaders you would
need more than what we're doing and yeah
and it's ugly
believe me it's ugly it's one of the
things that C does worst is that kind of
thing C and C++ one of the great
failings of C and C++ you can see it
right in there where it's like oh we
have this other thing that wants to be
able to take some text that also uses
Struck's
and we should be able to just like use
the meta programming features of a
language to make it so we define the
struck once and then just call it and it
all just works but instead it's this
whole ridiculousness of like having to
do like some tricks with includes if you
want to do that or you have to define it
in two places
or you make a preprocessor it's like
again a real language for games which we
will get someday will not have any of
these problems when we leave C++ behind
maybe we're on ji j I can already do
this
if it wanted to right because it's
gotten at a protein can it can
introspect it could generate the shaders
as part of the compile step J I can
already do all of this stuff if you
wanted it to right and that's just the
beginnings of John's language I you know
it's not even publicly out yet and it
can already do this stuff so you can
already see like if somebody who knows
what they're doing
goes and makes a language for what we
want to do it it's not that difficult to
see where it goes to but the C C++
people they don't think about like what
you actually do when you're programming
like they don't think about how to make
programming work better they think about
weird esoteric things that they like to
argue about that have no bearing on
programming efficiency right so you end
up with a language that has aspect
eighty miles long and can't even do
basic stuff that J I could do like the
first day it was you know a language
right and that's just it's where your
priorities are it's what you focus on
right
so did insu bot just say domo arigato
mr. compiler because if so that is the
new high-water mark for artificial
intelligence what are the stats on your
glasses the stats are that they were
like the only pair of expensive glasses
I ever bought and it was my first pair
of glasses and I've never gotten a new
pair of glasses I tried to buy like a
cheap pair one time and they were so
much worse that I just I've always kept
using these it's just like some kind of
titanium frame or something just little
wire that just connects and they're
great they also have like because
they're bendy like that they never like
you can go rock climbing with them and
they will not fall off because they're
like looped almost like a sport glasses
are looped so you know I mean maybe
there's certain things you could do like
boxing or something where they would
come off although you but
we're than boxing but you know even
stuff where you're hanging upside down
they never come off which is great all
right I'm gonna wrap it up thank you
everyone for joining me for those sort
of handmade here it's what a pleasure
coating with you as always if you want
to follow along the series at home you
can always go to handmade hero org and
pier to the game because it comes to the
source code so that you can follow along
with what we do here every day and play
around the source yourself we also have
some other stuff there's a watch page
you can go to watch old versions of the
series like old episodes and stuff it's
got a great search page too so you can
find stuff we also have an FAQ if you're
just have basic questions and we also
have the handmade fun refused to fund
community projects so if you're
interested in supporting things like our
episode guide or handmade Network that's
a good way to funnel money to those
projects that's it for today I'll be
back tomorrow when we'll finish to
bugging that until then have fun
programming and I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody