hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream let's go ahead and take a look we
were doing lighting last weekend and I
think we have I want to say we actually
made some good progress we just did some
tight fitting of the actual sort of
lighting bounds to where we were
actually looking so basically we all we
really did we didn't even optimize it at
all all we did is just fit the lighting
bounds to the the total viewable area
more accurately and and I believe you
can actually see if I pull out you can
sort of see what's happening here so
only like the region that was actually
visible plus a little like apron so that
we make sure you don't see it kind of
page in the lighting because you know
the lighting needs 10 frames the startup
time or so something along those lines
right you can see it kind of just like
follows you around pretty pretty
carefully now and so when you're
actually in the game we more or less got
rid of any weird lighting anomalies that
were due to the fact that we you know
we're not properly aligning the visual
region and we also improve the speed
dramatically because we could use at
that now we can at this point we can use
a much tighter bound on the lighting
region which means a lot less lighting
samples have to get sent out and again
that really helps us keep the frame rate
up so even though we've done like
literally no work to optimize our full
cast here we've already gotten our speed
within striking distance of 30 frames a
second which is pretty great because
that just makes our work load that much
easier it gives us a running start if
you will towards making the lighting be
something that we don't have to worry
too much about and again we haven't even
put it on the GPU or anything this is
actually just running entirely CPU side
so we can probably start I think to
upgrade the like lighting
rate caster now to try and make it a
little bit faster and I'd like to do
that today and tomorrow and we'll see
how far we can get with that but then I
think our last big push is gonna have to
be like you know working on the lighting
equations and the perhaps some tone
mapping to get the lighting looking
really good it already looks okay but
you can see we got some there's some
rectangular interpolation that still
kind of is in there I don't like I'd
like to fuzz that out a little bit more
the actual bounce equations and what
we're putting in for reflectors isn't
actually right at the moment so we want
to kind of clean that up we want to put
in reflectors for large objects like
trees for example too so that those
collect light right now they're not
collecting any light you know there
should be some light reflecting off of
here and onto the ground and that sort
of stuff and that's really just a world
Jen issue so that we can control what
we're pushing down there so a lot of
things like that that was in a quality
pass on the lighting but for right now
what I'd like to do is again focus on on
that bottom line number so I'd like to
focus on getting this full cast down and
what I'd like to do is basically say
look let's try to get it down to like 60
frames a second on like a beefy machine
like this one this machine isn't like
the fastest machine out there anything
but it's you know it's a pretty fast
machine so I'd like it to run at 60
frames a second so that worse machines
like machines that aren't as good as
this one could run it the game at a
reasonable 30 frames a second just you
know as a baseline there and again
another thing is you can also drop the
resolution down a little bit too but
that won't help the lighting
particularly I mean we could drop the
resolution of the lighting down
obviously as well and that would help it
but I don't know that we really want to
go that route so what I want to do today
is just look at what we've got for that
lighting routine and and I want to go
ahead and and in handmade prj here I
want to go ahead and look what we've
what what was that about
did I not switch projects oh I didn't
switch projects sorry somebody go ahead
and switch projects there to handmade
here him just go ahead and run the build
I'm gonna jump over to the lighting and
what I want to do is we just want to
start looking again and re familiarize
itself with what
we're doing in the raycast take some
statistics I believe we had a little
lighting statistics dump and I I don't
know that we're still drawing that but
what we should do is like reenable that
in case we don't have it actually we do
so you can see here we have a bunch of
information now I think now is a good
time to say look lighting probes are out
we're just not going to use them because
we've gotten really good baseline
example running with no light probes and
that'll save me a bunch of code so maybe
the first thing that we'll do oh that's
nice maybe the first thing we'll do is
just pull that out completely cuz we're
done with that I'm just not going to try
and do it we're gonna accept whatever
quality we can do without them because
it looks like using the Vox directly is
just better right it's simpler and we
know that we're always aligned so let me
go ahead and pull that out of everywhere
that it existed so for example in the
world we have this notion here of light
probe slots and this was just a huge
pain in the butt and what I want to do
is get rid of that entirely so
everywhere we were doing light probe
assignment is just gonna go away
so it just makes it easier for us to
work with so everywhere we were doing
like an is light probe that sort of
thing that's just gonna get out of out
of here entirely and so this idea of
assigning indices and removing indices
can just go away and so again just
really simplifies our code and gets rid
of an entire unnecessary pass and which
could cause like you know bugs as well
because this this whole are the thing
that had to happen and had to happen
properly and so again it just
simplifying the entity system getting
rid of stuff that we don't need that was
just you know we thought we needed to
try it and then we tried it and it turns
out it wasn't really necessary so at
that point I don't want to leave it
lying around because it's way better if
we just don't have it so let's go ahead
and keep going with this just pull all
of this stuff out of there you can see
that we had a few places where that was
sort of tied in and I'm just gonna get
rid of any place that was talking about
that because we just don't need it
anymore
let's go ahead and take a look there's
our light probe index check to actually
push the light probes on and we can get
rid of those now and I believe that also
means that the entire push light probe
system there can go away as well so
basically the and you know here's the
thing though
I might leave global lighting show
probes in there because we actually
could still draw the voxel and so that
might still be worth it at some point so
maybe I'll leave the control in there
and we can try to wire that up at some
point if we are so inclined so I'm going
to go ahead and get rid of any more
mentions of the the lighting here and
I'm also gonna get rid of push light
probe this code right here so this whole
thing where we've got commands light
probe position again gonna go ahead and
and nerf all of that stuff so every
place that was previously using like
light probe buffer and all that stuff
again just really making it easier to
you know just getting rid of complexity
in the code and making the code more
flexible as well because now you don't
have to worry about a light limit or
anything like that a light probe limit
you just get the lighting that is the
voxel and off you go so I think that's
great and I'm psyched about that again
just really helps us in a lot of a lot
of places so let's go ahead and and get
rid of any mention of these light probes
just so they're gone this is great it
takes out a lot of ugly code that really
we just didn't want to have right
there's there's no reason for it we
don't actually want that where was that
coming from
max light probe count I don't even know
where that specified maybe we've already
got rid of it
so anyway create world yeah you could
see this was getting like passed through
a bunch of people which again so really
nice that it goes away because it's just
nasty it's just it's just ugly and
there's no point to it so I'm also gonna
search for light probe here and I'm
gonna go ahead and just look to see if
there's anywhere where we're still doing
that and try to get rid of that so
there's some here's an is light probe
call I'm gonna get rid of that looks
like there's a brain light probe I'll
get that on the second pass through
here's some light probes that we're
adding here let's get rid of that
because we don't want those let's get
rid of these light probe positions let's
get rid of these add light probes and
now I'm also gonna do a search for light
underscore probe just so we can see
anywhere that was doing we're gonna get
rid of the light probe counter and the
light probe brain so that pulls light
probes out of the system entirely and
now we don't do any of that bookkeeping
or any of that work and we just get the
exact same result right and that's
really great because I don't really want
to have to deal with any of that stuff
right it's just extra work that I don't
want to do so you can see here what
we're doing in the sort of in the I
don't know how look at this but if you
look at the costs here there's a lot of
stuff now that I think that we want to
start working our way through to
simplify this code and so what I might
do to start with today before actually
trying to optimize it I might just try
to simplify it so in other words it's
you know it's been through a lot we've
done so many experiments with lighting
trying to figure out like a good system
and we finally kind of I think got to a
place where I'm really happy with how
it's turning out
so I'm ready to start turning the crank
on it and I think this is actually like
something we can ship right so what I
want to do is say can we go through here
and simplify everything that's happening
so that we're down to like the bare
minimum of stuff so we can focus on just
what we need and so you know before
looking at these numbers and I'm glad
that I have them now before looking at
these numbers what I want to do is go
and for example
we changed the way that we're generating
like our sphere tests and stuff like
that
and the reason I want to change that is
because if you look at how we're picking
our Rea directions we were picking our
Rea directions before we knew about our
octahedral map right so we didn't
actually have an octahedral map when we
did our light relaxation stuff and it I
think probably at least my guess is that
now that we know that we're doing an
octahedral map and it's 8 by 8 we might
just want to say look we do 64 ray casts
per light probe or something and that's
just how it goes we send one out of each
Texel each time or something like that
right and then what we would know is
when we load up the Rays we could load
them up in such a way that we know we're
loading up a specific like set that gets
used exactly in a specific way right so
we could actually make the so we don't
have to do like oh we're we're in the
octahedral map is this ray or let's make
sure that these are evenly distribute
across the sphere because we know like
each time we're just updating one of our
octahedral positions and we know which
one it is because it's always the same
one since the probes don't rotate right
so I think I'd like to kind of go
through and and start that process and
again just to simplify sort of the way
that that full cast process is working
so if we go into the lighting system and
I go to the full cast you can see the
function here that we're talking about
and what I mean to say is so you can see
here we do our ray bundle count right
and I think our a bundle count actually
I think we actually are doing 64 casts
currently I'm not sure so let's go ahead
and print that out in the the actual
system here so if we want to we can
actually print out our array bundle
count because we know the rate bundle
count is always equal to the array count
of
it's this value right so when we
actually do the dump at the end where we
print out our statistics which is right
here what I can do here is say like
raise per probe or something like this
right I can go ahead and compute that by
saying that the Ray bundle count is it's
just gonna be four cuz that's how wide
that's how many is in each bundle times
however big the sandbox here is right
and the sampling sphere I think is just
in the solution if I'm not mistaken
so like the sampling sphere excuse me
it's just one of these things so I
should be able to say like all right
like you know that so however many there
are oops in there and off we go
okay so if I take a look at what that's
printing out there are ways for probe
currently says 72 so basically I pretty
much want that value I think to be 64 so
each frame I want to send out 64 raised
one out of each of the 8x8 voxels and I
think that's basically what I want to do
so that's effectively going to be a
stratified sampling and we can just
generate like lots of like sort of
fairly even coverages in there now
one thing I don't know is if we did a
stratified sampling so that we're
basically just always casting out of a
particular piece of the act of the
Octagon there of the octagonal map what
I don't exactly know is I don't exactly
know where how the Rays should be
distributed inside that stratified
sample so from frame to frame I don't
actually know if what we want to do is
just pure rant pure white noise out of
each individual voxel each individual
Texel or whether we still want blue
noise out of each individual Texel
because I would my gut says blue noise
but since it's already confined to the
bounds of the voxel itself I'm not sure
what that actually means and
I mean I guess I guess what I was what I
would think gosh I guess my thinking
there is like you walk blue noise over
the sphere and then you want to have
bucket the blue noise into like you want
like something that's blue noise but
constrained so that only each one is
only in the Texel of the octahedral map
and I'm not sure exactly how to get that
right that seems kind of confusing so
maybe I don't know maybe we'll start
with some randomness like maybe we'll
start with just white noise and we'll
try to figure out how to work with that
later as we go because I really like my
in my brain I'm I'm not coming upon like
the instant answer to how we would want
those sampling spheres to go we know
that like we want to modify the sampling
sphere slightly from what it actually is
right now so if you look like the
sampling spheres you can see that
there's a sample Direction that's like
here's how many of these bundles purse
fear there are and in this case like you
know 18 is not what we want we want less
you know if we're doing four times this
number then we want this to be 16 so
that we have 64 of them oh so we already
computed this value too so you know what
I want to do is I want to in addition to
this also have which indices you write
into with each of the results here
so what I want to do is inside the full
cast you can see that when it goes to
update the voxel it has to do the get
octahedral offset for the incoming light
direction but I don't actually want to
do that I want to be able to just sort
of sum the voxel directly right so I
almost don't even want to do it this way
I want to just it I don't even want to
be random access I want to basically
just do a thing where like load up
whatever was currently in the in the
texels do the raycast and add it back
right so it's like it's a very
straightforward procedure yeah that I
want that I want to be able to do there
so yeah
so I think what I want is this would
change a little bit and what we would
actually do here is we'd actually just
[Music]
we'd actually just go ahead and walk the
texels so in much the same way that we
were previously doing like our you know
our weight updates here like this sort
of stuff right it would be more or less
this sort of code so in here we would
say like let's walk the texels that
we're looking at right and for each one
of those in the thing we're actually
updating and in this case it's going to
be the spec atlas not that a few setlist
so for each one of these I'm then going
to go ahead and get like the I'm gonna
go ahead and do two ray casts right and
so instead of ray bundles we'd actually
do this right so we'd step through the
spec atlas tile each time we would go
ahead and keep the Ray bundle index as
something that just kind of increments
along right and you know we don't even
really need it we could just reconstruct
it from the TTX 40y right so we could do
that too but we'll look at that in a
second we do the ray cast
we update the voxels but here instead of
like doing this stuff where the update
voxel call was we can actually just grab
this directly and do it to the Texel in
question right so because we'd already
know what this is so it would be
something like you know like this and we
wouldn't probably we wouldn't even
really need this part of it and we could
probably step that Texel yeah more
directly so basically the T update blend
I think I would just say is a variable
we pull out at the top and boobs and we
know that we've got like the transfer
PPS here and that's it so it would be
something like this where we just always
know what the desk Texel is because we
just have that information right and so
you know would just be this
probably again we probably want to do
this a little bit more cleanly because
this is not the best but something like
that and then what we would require is
that for each of these when we pull out
this Ray bundle we want each ray
direction for the sphere to know that it
goes out that particular Texel right so
then when we go through our subarrays
again we know that each so we know that
each sub right should go by four
actually so in this particular case I
guess I take it back that cuz we yeah we
would want to do that right as for
rights as well so really like you'd
probably want to pack that down anyway
mmm so hmm yeah here's what I'd say
about this I think we want to do this
even more explicitly because if we know
that we've got a bundle of four rays
that we cast that's four different
texels we can update right at the same
time and so really all we need to do is
make a V 3 for X here that's our
transfer PPS right and so instead of
doing that each time what we would do
here instead is in the slow part here
the part that's non sended we would grab
the transfer PPS
for each one of our subarrays like this
you know I'm saying and then the update
could happen fully wide like we don't
actually need the update to do anything
slowly because we know we're doing four
times three we know we're doing 12 ads
here and those can be done entirely
linearly like entirely SIM need right so
what we would want to do is like load
the all the stuff up and romp all this
stuff out you know I'm saying and so
let's go ahead and structure the loop
more that way I think that's just better
so in here like where we were previously
doing our sort of updates right so I
think what we want to do is something
more like this
so you know here you can see us pulling
out these spec Texel sets and what we
want to do is just update those spec
Texel sets right so we want to be able
to just load the T update blend in there
and then romp the blend so it's just
gonna be like a replicated T update
blend and then we're just gonna go ahead
and do it fully wide so I think what we
want is literally this like we want
exactly this load behavior here and so
we can we can actually I think just copy
this so I think maybe I started with
like sort of the wrong template loop so
maybe let's just not do that let's do
this instead like this where we load
each of these up right like this and so
what I want to do here is say let's do
the loads then let's do the stores and
write them back here and I'm saying
and looking at that looking at that we
probably only want to do four of these
at a time which would be three because
we probably don't want to do eight wide
ray casting although we could and that
would also probably a lot well yeah
maybe we do want to do that
so another way to look at that would ya
be like look don't do this just do this
one loop of why I kind of like the sound
of that so if we just did one loop of Y
and then we did and then we just pulled
out two ray directions did - ray casts
and then rode everything back that seems
better because again if we wanted to
switch to a VX eventually you'd want the
eight wide path to happen here
so I'm actually I'm actually fine with
that
so what we want to do here is we want to
do a store f/32 for X you know so what
we'd want to do here is basically this
so after we like update these variables
which we have to do we would want to do
a store which I assume we have yeah so
we have a load F 32 X but we don't have
a store after new 2x so we're gonna have
to add that guy
so there's that address and we just want
to know like what's the actual f32 Forex
that we have and that's just gonna be a
store you and it's literally just gonna
be like whatever this a dot p-value is
right all right so if I want to do a
store there these would just be store F
32x I'm gonna get rid of this and we
would basically like look right s 0 back
to the zero location and so on right so
it would just be something like this
right so we do a loads we do stores so
at the end after we update everything so
like after the lerp s-- we would just do
the stores and the lips in this case i
think we could just do yeah i mean i
think we could just do this as like you
know s0 equals lerp from from s 0 to
whatever the transfer PPS was kind of a
thing the problem we're gonna have here
is that when we've loaded these up right
it's RGB r g b RG right so these are
like strided across so the transfer PPS
is that we get are actually gonna have
to be strided in the same way right like
we're gonna have to actually have those
come across lined up so you know it's
gonna be something like this you know
i'm saying to you
which makes it a little bit harder for
us to work with but that's how it has to
be packed to do the load to do the
storage eventually
so we're gonna have to make sure that we
put things in here correctly and again
I'm not really sure how we want to do
that we might do that the cheesy way
first and then you know cuz the cheesy
way to do it would just be like look
we've got you know a certain number of F
32s here and then what we're gonna do in
each of these cases is just we're gonna
just load up out of that so you know
it'd be it'd be this right you'd go
through and load them up and then you
would load out of that array to get your
transfer PPS like so right so you know
you just do that and here's that
transfer PPS and that's gonna load you
know six times four values which is
which is how many this would have to
have in it right so here's the RGB we
know that I sorry it's eight of these
right so three times eight is the same
as 6 times four so that would load
correctly across the top this T update
blend now we need to be able to do this
wide and again that's not particularly
difficult so what we do here is we'd
make our basically our blend value and
our inverse blend value so we'd have our
blend and our in blends right and this
would just be load F 32 I guess I don't
know load F 3/2
this so this would just be something
where we you know replicate the value
across so in this case we'd have a blend
and an inverse blend and the inverse
blend is just you know 1.0 - the the
blend value so in order to do our lerp
it's pretty simple so for each of these
it's just going to be like blend times
the T zero plus I'm sorry in the blend
times the T zero plus blend times the no
sorry was s zero so T update blend I
don't know what T update blend actually
represented so let me just make sure
we've got that right T update blend all
right so T update blend is how much
we're going towards so that means the
inverse blend should be on whatever the
old value would just is that and the new
value should get the T zero right so
that's the entirety of our update right
one two three four five and so that
updates are our sort of lighting
template there and I think this would do
everything that we needed right now this
will not be correct because we haven't
changed our spheres to be sorted the way
that I just said right so it's not
actually correct let me go ahead and say
oh also this this spec atlas here we
don't actually want offset from textile
respect I'll probably well actually
maybe we do
it's just tile right so so I think
that's what we would need here so when
we go through and we're trying to set up
our PBS here we now have like sort of a
double loop if we do want to load all of
these at once eight wide where we
basically say like okay we're doing a
ray cast here's our you know our ray
cast it's only going to return four
things you know rather than eight and
like I said we may want to go ahead and
start just doing it eight wide
the problem we would have here too is I
don't actually know if we want to split
this into two halves because the other
thing that's a little bit ugly is when
we do our ray cast we probably want to
do the ray cast for we want those four
to be as close as possible and if we
actually ray cast four in a row those
are going to be spread out more than if
we did four like right in a little
square pattern right so that part's kind
of annoying and that's just because
again the like the hierarchy what you
load out of the hierarchy is different
and so it's hard to say usually if you
trace ray bundles that are near each
other I mean that's usually more
coherent but you know you can't really
guarantee it so it's hard to say but
anyway if we were to do it this way then
we would essentially do two ray cast
right and then we would do this for each
of the ray casts so for example when
we're pulling out the sub braze here and
we're doing like the getcomponent calls
and all this garbage what we need to be
able to do here is actually have this
code be sort of usable if we're going to
do eight of these and the only thing
that I would say here is I'm not sure
I'm not sure if that shouldn't maybe be
done let me take a look here I'm not
sure if maybe that shouldn't just be
done at the end of this routine you know
I'm saying because rather than return
this information back it seems like you
would just it seems like you would just
want to have this be handled rather than
returning the result this way because
since we don't ever do a ray cast for
any other reason you might as well just
compute the diffuse irradiance
right there
and just allow the optimizer Morse to
see more stuff so I'm not actually sure
that that is the right thing to do there
either because it just seems like it's
kind of just wasting effort to a certain
degree and again that way it would just
it wouldn't have to return anything it
would just literally return the emission
information and that seems maybe it may
be better to me yeah that seems maybe
better so so I actually don't know if
maybe this should just be welded right
in here you and I'm Sam
we're basically we're just saying we
just have the transfers what gets
computed here so that all can be welded
together so when it does that raycast
you get back the transmission that you
want and then the outer code can do the
blend for you that seems more sane to me
probably yeah so I'm going to go ahead
and say that that that's what we're
going to do here and I'll go ahead and
throw this debug code in here as well
like so
just because I don't know if we're gonna
need that someday but we'll believe it
in there in case we need it
so this is more what I'd like this to
look like we just loop over you know
just going over each one and then you
know I won't even bother with the
transfer people yes here what we'll say
is that raycast results we just get back
a transmission right maybe something
like sorry I'm just trying to think this
through what I want here but I think I
do want just this so you know it's just
this stuff doesn't really get get used
that way anymore I guess what I'm
thinking is maybe you just give it I
mean another way to do this would be we
don't even do that we just we just weld
this whole thing in you know I mean the
reason the Ray caster is separate at the
moment is because I like to be able to
call it for debug purposes you know but
it may be that it just wants to work on
the size of a tile anyway and this stuff
just gets welded in
so it's like you just sample a sphere
that's just what happens you know what I
mean hmm we don't care about Rea weight
or any of this stuff yeah I'm thinking
that smite might be what I want actually
so if that were the case here's what
that would look like essentially you
would pass the raycast routine here and
I don't know what debugging was doing
looks like it pushed the debug box on
there yeah so essentially what you do is
you tell the raycast routine and the
raycast routine would not return things
so that's out of here right so raycast
result just kind of goes away and so
then what you would do is you'd say the
raycast routine you actually tell the
raycast routine what to update and the
raycast just does the update in place
right so essentially you know you don't
get to just get Rea information back
instead what happens is it does it does
the load and store and you just give it
like here's the Rea bundle and here's
the taxol to update and it would do like
this code right so that's at the opening
you know it would do this it was loaded
up you would pass in this value and the
spec Texel right so the sampling sphere
this part would still be up to you like
here but you know you would pass in that
which you already are so you would pass
recast work the Ray origin here is just
you know whatever whatever the light
probe P is I believe so
ray origin and Ray direction and then
you would pass the speck Texel
then it would actually update the
lighting in place for that thing so
really we're just calling this thing a
few times and it's doing its its
business right yeah so I think that's
more what I want
so then what it does is it right it does
the load up of the the samples and then
it does the right back of the samples
and I think I like that better because
now I can sort of see what's happening
easier and I can start to optimize this
routine as a whole which I like better
and Jimmy and so this stuff here where
we're using like hit normal and all that
stuff I can also then you know make that
be more coherent with what's going on so
yeah that that seems more thing to me
that seems more saying to me when we're
actually doing this and we're doing it
for why though if we're loading up these
again doing eight at a time seems good
but maybe again like maybe we'll just to
make it a little easier on ourselves
because everything was written for a
wire to begin with we will just only do
four so we'll call this twice
essentially like that so we'll do one
through four and then five through nine
I'm sorry five
one two and three and then four right
five six seven eight nine yes no sorry
that's correct
five six seven eight five through eight
one through four and five through eight
like this that seems reasonable to me
and that way yeah we just know that the
spheres are set up correctly we have a
nice little simple loop here that goes
through each individual place we want to
cast from does the cast and off we go
right that seems fine and then we just
have to make sure this routine can work
that way right so it's gonna go ahead
and load up those I guess it doesn't
really need them till the end so we
might as well just put them down here so
it loads up the s zeroes it loads up the
T zeroes it does the blend and then it
writes them back out right that seems
totally reasonable
I don't know
yeah so I guess for now we'll just go
ahead and do the four I loop here on the
sub-array and then we'll go ahead and
try to make that better later because
this code is terrible right not entirely
our fault lookups like compute Vox
already and syrup are bad for that but
anyway so here's our little cheat sheet
here so for each ray we want tea ray and
that's just this apparently so that's
good
t raise T ray emission direction this we
already know right let's see hit we're
pulling out their probe sample P R a dot
P that's just hit P this is it normal
ref color is hit ref color and emission
is hit emission
so looking at here I assume that the
problem is we don't have the solution
pulled out how do we do what's the
problem there diffuse Atlas so we're
gonna have to pull out the diffuse Atlas
as well which we can do here
I assume oh you know what though I guess
we just can pass those down let's just
do that for now there we go
so probe sample P probe sample and
emission direction where is emission
direction is up here so what's the
problem compute Vox right oh it's we
just jumped we jumped over it now just
grab these and put them up above here so
in this case we need to write back the
transfer PPS correctly and I think if we
just do it this way we will so again
this just loads them out in the opposite
format so I think that's all fine and
then we just need to do our hard-coded
moondoor nonsense we just have to move
that in there and we want to figure out
what our long term strategy is for that
I don't actually know what we're gonna
do but eventually we want the moon to
only affect outdoor areas and stuff like
that so we're gonna have to do something
with that eventually anyway but if we go
ahead here and grab that out for now
we can just go ahead and put that in the
raycast for now all right so T update
blend is again just something we
probably want to pull out of the
solution here so when we actually are
doing the raycast we just grab RT update
blend then we don't need to do the extra
blends for stuff we didn't load and then
I think we're good so here in our test
caster we can't actually do this one
anymore which is fine that's that's no
biggie but I think I may just remove the
test caster entirely
should this wait what happened there
okay
so we actually want here is this right
there yeah all right so now we've got
the Ray caster going and this is going
to be a complete disaster because what's
happening now is we're casting off of
spheres that are not correctly put that
they're not correctly aligned to those
octahedral maps but we're writing them
as if they were right so we're casting
raised in arbitrary directions and then
writing to anywhere in the map so
obviously that's wrong but otherwise
we're fine and this this will allow us
to just look at this one routine and
simplify it down exactly however it
needs to be so the other thing that I
would note is if we take a look at
what's going on here and we look at why
we need for example the like some of the
most expensive stuff we're doing here is
for computing the normal like you can
see how simple it is to compute
everything else but computing the normal
is a huge pain in the butt right and our
compute voxel irradiance at like that's
the thing that uses it right our compute
voxel irradiance at is doing the lerp
based on what we're using that value
that that hit normal right to look up
into the octahedral map and the
octahedral map is a txt why we're only
ever going to be sampling from certain
of those tx2 eyes right because our
normal our surface normals there's only
six of them
that there can be right and so another
way to look at this would just be look
we don't actually have to do all this
work instead what we can do is just know
that there's only four lookups we could
possibly do and let's just load
whichever of those four lookups is the
one we need right
so the T X and T Y values we can just
get we can just get back directly from
that I think and avoid doing this so I'm
not gonna change it now but you know
probably the short end of the stick
because it only happens at the end but
I'm just you know going to note all of
the places where we can improve things
because we don't know how hardcore we're
gonna have to get on this thing all
right
so I think this should roughly do
exactly the same thing as we were doing
before the only difference like I said
is that we're not actually sending
things out the octahedral map at the
moment so what I might suggest is look
let's just actually generate noise
temporarily or not even noise let's just
generate exact outcasts out from the
Centers let's say and use that just to
verify that that we can get everything
working right so in here instead of
grabbing these out so I'm gonna go ahead
temporarily and say we've got a 33 for X
it's like sampled er a and it's this
oops and then a V 3 for X that's sampled
Derbe and it's this
what I want to do here is just let's
overwrite those right let's just
overwrite those entirely so what I'd
like to do is overwrite sample dirt a
and sample their B with actually with
voxels that with with with direct output
directions from the voxel right so we
want to do like this kind of thing where
we just say like alright whatever the s
y-value is we're gonna use that and then
we're gonna get the directions here you
know like this right and we're gonna
stuff these in to the the v3 for X like
so so we're gonna we're gonna basically
do like sample dirt a gets overwritten
by a direct load and sampled your B gets
overwritten by a direct load so now we
know that these things are going
directly out the texels in question
right and if we do direction from
consuming mmm if we do direction from
text Y what I'd like to do here is we
need to pass the X Y coefficient I think
we can get that directly from the Atlas
right so we shouldn't have to do any
work there there we go
and so now hopefully we're at least
sending things out the correct direction
I don't know so it's close it's at least
looking sort of right we may still have
some bugs in there but remember remember
currently there's no jitter right so
it's now not picking up any light that
it doesn't just happen to hit with that
one
rection right but of course yeah it's
nice and stable and everything else is
fine
what I don't know however is if we're
missing anything like with the right
back right we may be missing something
there it's hard to say
so without the jitter to get us back to
our previous lighting solution I don't
actually know if this is correct or not
we'll see so what I'd like to do now is
maybe let's pong back to the nuts of the
actual sphere code and what we can do is
we can make our spheres always go out
the correct voxels now right and these
this code here where we've got direction
from T X Y and get octahedral offset I
think that can go in the math now the
layer two because now that we've got
octahedral from unit vector and unit
vector from octahedral these could also
be the these also would work because
these coefficients are now just regular
variables right they don't require you
to have like an Atlas pointer or
anything like that so if we want to
update our sphere generator that would
allow us in theory to make this work
properly because now we would just make
sure that the sphere data that we're
outputting happens to have things
aligned with those voxels properly let's
go ahead and try that so if I go ahead
and and nerf this and go to our HH
sphere code what you can see here is
when we do our output sphere you can see
it outputting the sampling sphere here I
don't know where we got the idea that
there was going to be 18 I guess that's
just how many we were using before or
something because like like 18 times 4
is 72 and I don't know why 72 was the
number that we were doing
it's confusing but I guess that's what
we typed in right we typed in an 18 here
for some reason I don't know so when you
look at what output sphere INL does that
outputs everything that we wanted and it
does it exactly the way that we want we
don't need to change that at all so I
think we can keep this exactly the same
what we will have to do is for generate
lighting pattern we're gonna need to do
something different so in here what I
would say is this can be generated like
Hasaan lighting pattern and then we'll
have another generate lighting pattern
that's that's a different thing
so we'll have generate octahedral
lighting pattern and so we want to do
here is be able to output the sample
directions exactly as we were doing
before and you can see here we've got a
thing that like produces the bundles
from the directions right
so we probably want to make that be just
a utility because we're gonna want to do
that in both cases so in this case here
where we're doing Durr from directions
I'm assuming what we want to do is
generate all the directions the same way
we were direct generating directions
before and then use this piece of code
right so this is like something like
this so you pass the sphere count you
pass the directions and you pass the
sphere you're trying to write to right
of the sphere array and it just goes
through and copies the directions into
the series for you right and we would
need Ray bundles purse fear as well in
this case like so but otherwise that
would do it I think
yeah
so that seems fine and this would do the
same thing right Jimmy and so all we
need here is that the directions like
this stuff we would want to do the exact
same thing I don't know what the used
thing is for I probably don't care about
this at all at the moment but we would
say all right that's total directions
here's the directions we don't care
about this and we don't care about that
so we would just go through and for each
sphere we would just like we'll just use
noise for now right so what we'll do is
we'll say the I guess in this case to
the these two values are kind of
hard-coded right meaning you don't
actually get to choose them so really
what happens here hmm oh sorry not the
severe account the severe account is
it's the Ray bundles purse fear that you
don't get to choose right it has to
basically be well no you know what
that's not true so we can't leave it
like this what we would do is we'll just
keep wrapping around right so that seems
fine so then what we would say is okay
for each sphere right because we've got
to initialize all of our spheres right
also why
okay so this pulled the spheres out of
that alright I don't think we care about
a lot of the stuff but anyway so what we
want to do is for each sphere so you
know what I'm starting to get a sense
for how this would work in fact I think
I see exactly how this would work so
what we would want to do is we'd want to
do exactly the same thing as we were
doing in the other one meaning this
routine actually I think is more or less
correct now I think about it
it's just it would get a little more
complicated right so what we want to do
I think we do want to generate a blue
noise fear but what we want to do is we
want the blue noise to be evaluated only
inside each individual tile now the
ultimate thing to do and unfortunately I
just don't know anyway you would
actually do this
I'm not sure how you would actually
write the algorithm to do this I'm
trying to think but so what you would
want is you would want to be able to
generate a light you'd want to be able
to generate a sphere that was a plus on
distribution exactly like we were doing
so you could literally run the exact
same code generator Poisson sphere and
then you would just want to pull out for
each sphere that you write out you'd
pull out one point from the evenly
distributed Poisson sphere one point per
octahedral tile now the problem because
I could just write that and that'd be it
the problem is you how do you guarantee
that you always have you know however
many spheres let's say you want to
generate 64 spheres
how do you generate a plus on
distribution that guarantees that each
octahedral tile always has 64 points in
it I don't think you can so my
suggestion would be maybe what we do is
we generate the Poisson sphere then we
pull out one per tile right and we just
use white noise to fill in the gaps you
know i'm santi
I mean right I mean that seems like the
same as thing to me so yeah I think
that's correct so I guess what I would
say is we probably want to do the
generate plus on lighting pattern as a
thing you call and what that does is it
just returns you like the district you
know the distribution so the direct like
this thing right so you call it and you
know it does whatever random crap it's
going to do here and what does it care
about does it care about just total
Direction count probably yeah so what we
do here is we'd pull out this total
Direction count and we just say all
right so in each case you compute the
total direction count but then you know
you don't do any of this stuff right you
just call this routine which does the
Poisson distribution so you you pass
total direction count to it it just does
whatever it's gonna do to generate the
sphere and that's fine and everyone
loves it in this great and like
everyone's dancing in the streets and
having a party and you know getting
coronavirus so then we just get the
directions back by calling that function
and then in the case where we want to
actually just generate the simple plus
on lighting pattern we do the
interleaved directions call which I was
totally wrong that's not the thing we
probably actually want to call here but
you know whatever it's fine so in there
we would call it really
directions after calling whatever this
is generate Poisson distribution with
the total direction count and then for
our generate octahedral lighting pattern
what we would do is we would go through
right and now what we want to do is
split out we'd want to split out by
basically using this used again probably
right we would want to split out the I
guess we don't really need that we can
just set the things to 0 0 0 actually we
would we would gather essentially each
individual thing by grabbing one point
from the octahedral region we were
talking about so we would effectively do
like all right we go through each sphere
we still do want to do this probably do
we probably not probably we just do this
and so what we need to do is we need to
like write these things out purse fear
and so when we do this we would have to
go through the Ray bundles and what we'd
want to do is just kind of loop through
the octagonal sets pulling out ones that
we find so how we can do this well what
we want to do here is instead of instead
of just thinking this strictly as bun
ray bundles for sphere what we want to
do is think of it in terms of like txt Y
right and so you know these I guess are
going to be well they're gonna be
whatever they are but as we step through
here what we do is we'd say after each
time we record a direction we're gonna
plus plus the TX if the TX is greater
than and we could you need to have the
like the dimension in here right if the
TX gets up to be too high it goes back
to
and the T Y increments right and the
same thing happens with T Y like if the
t y is greater than however much the max
is it goes back to 1 so we just say like
look the the the the maps here and maybe
we just put in the offset separately so
maybe we just say it's an 8 by 8 and we
use 0 based here just to be a little bit
fancier right so we loop through we go
through pulling out bundles and each
bundle goes into subsequent slots in the
map dimension generating the octahedral
lighting pattern and so all we then need
to do is figure out whether or not a
particular thing falls into that region
right and so in order to do that we
already have the function which is like
the get octahedral offset right so if we
call get octahedral offset is that the
right thing yeah so if we call get
octahedral offset got get octahedral
offset tells us the like the because the
the XY of this thing whatever sample
we're gonna look at here right so you
have to blow my nose
and so each one of those that we pull
out we need to match against the txt Y
that we have so this is going to be a
loop over all the directions we're gonna
go ahead and get the octahedral offset
of the direction and we could cache if
we cared about how fast this thing run
which we don't we could cache it but
we're gonna loop over each of them we're
gonna get the octahedral offset and see
if it maps to anywhere we actually care
about assuming that it does we would
then go ahead and use this so if the o
XY x equals the TX and the o XY y equals
the T Y then what we would do is we
would say all right we've found to match
and in this case like the derp is going
to be this would be some random thing
that goes off in that direction so you
know something like this I might call
this the match X Y because this has to
sort of be updated so the match X Y is
is actually this right so the direction
that we actually want to pick or maybe
we'll just call this pick so we loop
through each thing and we check them
assuming that we found one that matched
we'd pick it right and what we'd also
want to do there I think is we would
want to say that you know maybe we do it
like this and so that way we could also
say look if the if the check value if
all of the check values is 0 right
then we know that that we're not going
to use it in fact we could do that even
simpler we could just say look there's a
magic value you know called used and
that's just something that can never
happen right you can't have a normal
with a with a 10x value we're just going
to go ahead and say that when we do that
right the the check X is going to get
set to used so we we can only use each
point once when we grab it out and off
we go
and here what we're gonna do is say look
we're gonna just feel we're gonna have a
fill in direction here so when we run
out of points in that particular
octahedral region we'll just fill them
in with direction here and I might say
like to do perturbed this right so get
give me you know give me something
that's a little bit off from there right
but for now we'll we'll actually leave
it so this would be what we're talking
about we would loop through all of the
directions we have so it would be like
the derp index less than total Direction
count
oops and then our directions plus stir
index would be our check vector so this
loops through every direction that we
have it looks to see whether we've used
it or not it gets where it would be in
the octahedron it looks to see whether
it matches the octahedron if it does we
use it if it doesn't we don't and if we
don't find anything to use meaning we
went through this entire thing and we
had a break if this is in the wrong part
of thing we would drop out of the dirt
check loop but and just use whatever the
pick the random pick was right does that
make sense yeah so we need to do this
for you know to produce our bundles and
just looking at it I think what we would
probably want to do here is say okay I
will go ahead and use the interleave
because I already wrote it and we'll
just make an output directions
so here where we have directions I'm
going to do two things I'm going to do
like input directions and output
directions and I output directions is
going to be allocated exactly the same
way so these directions here that we've
got we now have an input and an output
and so as we go through I just want to I
just want to write to that output
direction so I'm gonna call this outdoor
and that's just gonna start at output
directions as we go through this we're
not gonna be doing this at all so as we
go through each individual sphere we're
gonna actually go through four times the
rate bundles for sphere for each one of
these we're gonna write out an outdoor
right so each time through here when we
get to this we're gonna do like you know
outdoor plus plus equals pick like so
right then at the end we're gonna take
the output directions we're gonna
interleave those out and I think that's
roughly what I want now I don't think we
build this anymore we remand it but I'm
gonna go ahead and start building it and
we now need our atlases we need those
capri computed Atlas values so I'm gonna
go ahead and do that but in the meantime
let me just finish the other things we
can do there there we go so I'm going to
call this generate octahedral lighting
pattern here and then I think we're good
so let me go ahead and grab the light
Atlas and what we're gonna do here is
we're gonna call that make Atlas call
because that computes the values we
actually need
and our voxel dim in this case I don't
actually know how we call this there we
go
we don't care what that is but our tile
dim we do
so the tyldum has to be 10 10 I believe
yep so we just pass in the 10 10 tiled
in there and then we can do in the dupes
direction from CX CY the XY coefficient
and in here we can do the ops dim
coefficient oh no wow I'd seen that in a
while don't know what we did wrong there
to be fair this is like an interim I
really have to switch to the new for
coder it's been a long time
just having gotten around to it alright
so I think we now have our generator I
think that's roughly what I want again
not 100% sure but let's give it a shot
if I call build h8 sphere we should be
able to just try it so let's say we want
you know 16 spheres we want 16 ray
bundles is that true no so we know we're
going to do 2 ray bundles per row and
there's 8 rows yeah no it is 6 exactly
16 ray bundles right yeah so it's 16 ray
bundles and then like I don't know
feared tests I know yeah so this goes
ahead and tries to get down to the
minimum error there and presumably this
will actually output a sphere test we
can actually use now we probably we're
gonna have to actually print like the
we're gonna have to to print like draw
the sphere or something just so we can
make sure I mean hey it works but we
don't actually know if it's doing the
right thing
so we're gonna have to go ahead and copy
that in if I look
so I should be able to do a copy right
on to that handmade code handmade
sampling spheres and now we should
actually be able to build handmade Hira
with those new sampling spheres and we
just need a way to like now inspect them
which we sort of have but not to inspect
them quite the way that we want right
now if I go into the lighting code we'll
have to turn on some inspection I can
also try using the spheres which happens
in here oh wait that is using the
spheres so something must be wrong with
the way we're out putting those spheres
because that means the spheres are 100%
stable like it's not changing the
spheres at all right so I must have had
a bug in there like I'm not maybe I'm
not like I must be picking the same
things for every sphere does that make
sense
hmm that's all
all right um let's go ahead and real
quick rerun this so build HH sphere 1616
and we want to do handmade sampling
spheres so I'm gonna go ahead and rerun
this that was a mistake
obviously we we were previously just
literally just using this so now it
should hopefully actually pick some
spheres some of the samples and we
should get noise now and then what we
need to do is inspect these spheres by
drawing them to see if they're correct
all right so if we now recompile this
like so what I hope to see I don't know
is we should now see noise reappear
although I'm not
if check not to use our see if accident
check x equals used pic equals check and
I mean that should work right we're
looking through all of the directions
that we have which I think should work
we're looking at any one that hasn't
been used yet we're looking to see if it
equals the thing the place we're trying
to find and if it is we should write it
yeah seems right anyway
all right so that's much better because
now we're getting like a complete
disaster there which is what I would
have expected so or not what I would
have expected but at least it means okay
we're getting closer to what we actually
wanted here all right so let's take a
look at those fears so what I want to do
now is rien a below the thing where we
drew the spheres which I believe we
still have and the only question is we
yeah I guess we I guess we even did have
a way to look at the different pieces of
them as well lo so let me go ahead and
try and resurrect that code hopefully we
didn't delete it entirely but we may
have in which case bad on us because we
would like to draw it so let's take a
look see if we've still got it here that
draws our debug lines not really gonna
help us yeah unfortunately it looks like
we got rid of that's maybe
not sure why but I'm not seeing it
tests fear yeah I said when I just kind
of saved that you know lying around but
doesn't look like I did looks like we
got rid of it well that's alright so if
we want to draw it's pretty easy to do
inside and lightning computation I guess
would be the best way to do it where we
can just go ahead and push debug boxes
at the very end that seems like the best
thing to do so in here what I can do is
I can go through each sphere do we have
a way to push points I don't know if we
actually have a way to push points on
there although I could actually just
push them directly so maybe I'll do this
hmmm so if I just push one of these on
here this should be fairly
straightforward actually so I'll get
debug color for the sphere index and
actually guess that's all we need so if
I was to push cubes on here what I
should be able to do is push on cubes
for each one so for each sphere index
and we'll go through like however many
spheres there are so if we go to that
and made lighting spheres we know that
they'll be a your account here like so
and when we go through rate bundles this
should be can I revert this buffer
let me load that again so when we go
through here and we do the Ray bundles
first fear here's the bundle index and
for each bundle I'm gonna go for each
ray so that would draw all of our
learning spheres and all we need to do
now is extract the P and the radius the
radius is just a known quantity it's how
big we want the points to be when we're
drawing them so that's not a
particularly big deal so all we really
need to do is extract that P so what we
want to do here is say like alright
whatever the sampling spheres are for a
particular sphere index I then need to
get the sampling Direction for whatever
bundle I'm on right
oops sorry sample Direction for
whichever bundle I'm on and then I just
used the Ray index as the component if I
use that I should be able to draw all of
the spheres and I just need that white
texture cuz we're not gonna we don't
actually want it putting a texture on
that we just want to be solid where's
the if oops
thank you compiler alright
and so now what we need is we need to
place that somewhere and size that you
can see it's there right I mean that's
that's the actual thing so what we now
need to do is place that somewhere and
make it a little larger just so we can
see it easily so I think this those
radii are that's a little bit too much
so we'll go ahead and drop that down a
little bit and then what I want to do is
just take the Z and I'm just gonna lift
it up a few meters so it's in a place
that's easier to see right all right so
there's our sampling spheres I don't
know that I'm drawing it correctly yet
but whoa what the heck wow that's total
nonsense alright so now that we've got
that I should be able to go debug our HH
sphere because we should be able to
figure out what we're doing wrong and
you know make the stuff work properly oh
that's good we slammed that 10 in there
[Laughter]
do you think that might have something
to do with it yeah before we actually
before we overwrite the X component with
10 we may want to copy the value out
that was a bit of a mistake all right
so hopefully now we can we can take a
look at these spheres see if they make
any sense I don't know if they will or
not but we'll see and then we can we can
try and go from there so let's go ahead
and generate our sphere let's recompile
the game so that now it's using that
sphere data set that we just generated
hopefully without the weird bug in it
and now I'll run the game and now we can
inspect like our sphere so it at least
looks like a sphere so you know I think
that's a plus
the only question I have now is we kind
of need to now have some way of seeing
whether or not these things are
correctly like lined up right because we
don't actually know right now if they're
if they're actually in the octahedrons
that we think they should be so what I
want to do you can see you know from the
cars that the cars look reasonably
distributed but you know that's telling
us for each sphere so what I want to do
now is say look let's actually look at
the bundle index ray index and let's see
if we can make the debug color line up
with that instead so what I'm going to
do is I'm going to say look for the
debug color I want to get the bundle
index plus the Ray index so like four
times bundle index plus Ray index right
and now I should see colors clustering
around the sphere right so if we look at
where each cluster is each color should
sort of be a region of the sphere and
that does look like what's happening
right so that does look pretty good like
I think that's probably you know you
could make a good argument that that's
correct so I think we're in good shape
now right now it looks like we still got
some bugs here so I think our ray cast
routine is still a little bit buggy but
I'm gonna go ahead and go and turn off
the sphere render temporarily and I'm
gonna go look at the ray caster scene
and see if I can clean that up a little
bit now although maybe we should save
that for tomorrow alright so here is us
hopping around and you can see the
lighting sort of works but it looks like
there's still some bugs right it's it
looks like maybe there's some bugs in
the way that it's working at the moment
right
in other news if we take a look at the
profile we can see we're hovering around
our 30 frames a second pretty easily
there right not able to get down into
the 60 frames a second but we're you
know we're in much better shape so
all right so now we got to figure out
what exactly is going on there why are
we getting that weird behavior so here's
our sphere indices bundle as we drew
those those look to correct so we know
we should be able to loop over these
things pretty much the way that they're
being looped over now we just take a
quick look and then we'll save any heavy
debugging for tomorrow so I won't dive
too far into it but I just want to take
a look so yeah after we're doing our ray
cast here you can see us doing our
transfer PPS let's see where do we pull
out the sampling sphere so let's make
sure where do we get that sphere so this
seems right we're masking out there
we're taking sample directions here I
guess are we making sure we're filled as
much as we think we should be so I might
say a double check that the the light
sampling rate bundles Purse fear assert
that this never goes above that right
because we don't ever want that - yeah
we don't want that to overwrite that
buffer right so we want to make sure
that that's in bounds and similarly we
should have started this one as well and
that just means you know let's make sure
we're not sampling off of the array or
something like that it's just just basic
bounds checking and get in place there
okay so assuming we have the basic
bounds checking in place now let's just
make sure okay our spec texels we're
going in X which is what we would expect
we're looping over the tiled my and that
seems right so that this here was wrong
incidentally because that +1 oh no it
wasn't it was that was right that's fine
um so yeah I don't see anything
obviously busted there so I think that's
fine I do think my transfer PPS code may
be wrong and we should look at that real
quick because that was another big
change we made so looking at the raycast
here well that's probably fine right
this looks like sample ders would
probably come out of the right place
they're the ones for this particular row
and spec texels probably right there so
let's take a look at the raycast part of
things here
so really it's this part here that we're
looking at so if you look at what
happens for our transfer PPS we're
producing RGB RGB RGB RGB and I think
this should work properly like we're
loading the spec texels that's RGB RGB
RGB so that's loading 3 oh that's
just wrong no it's not no it's not
that's really RGB r g b r g b RGB right
and so is this so those should both load
for wide times three or three times four
worth of ops we load in the blends
values and we blend them together oh and
we never change those variables um so
yeah I mean that could have been our
only bug but it's doubtful all right but
that looks much more like it right all
right
um so that's a good place to end it for
today again we're not really done at all
with what we want to do to this routine
but at least now we're at least now
we're operating in order and we're not
like calling a bunch of random crap we
don't need to because since we compute
the sampling spheres there's no reason
for us not to know exactly where to
write for each sampling sphere and this
way we also know we update the map
relatively uniformly which also I think
is a good idea so every Texel gets a
refresh value once per frame which I
like right so I think that's good I
think that's good let's go go ahead and
go to brief Q&amp;A
when programming returned um I don't
know like at some point I may do a real
one I just need to rehearse one first at
some point and so I can it's hard to do
it and not make mistakes in the code and
remember to say weird stuff so at some
point I'll try to record one and put it
up
uh so you don't have to use static so
here's what happens when you don't mark
a function as static because that's what
we're talking about because I don't
really use static much otherwise cuz the
only other time you would use it is for
like a global variable maybe I don't use
static for pretty much ever inside like
inside actual to have local persistent
variables I don't ever use it for that
cuz it doesn't really work very well
with multi-threading usually so it's
just I'm out of the habit right but the
reason that I use static is because
anytime you don't use static the
function is by default external so it
goes into the linker at that point and
the linker is notoriously like the
slowest part of the compilation process
typically especially if you're not doing
random crap like weird templates and
huge amounts of header files so the
problem is like I just don't ever want
to put more stuff in the linker than I
have to so it's only for optimizing
build times you don't need to do it to
make your code work because it doesn't
matter right so that's what I would say
I would heavily encourage you to use it
because it does help build times but I
would say if you don't use it
there's nothing oh the only thing that's
the problem is the linker can get slower
largely because linkers seem to be
written very poorly
he's a 3d shear transformation useful in
graphics programming for games how do
you construct a 4x4 shear matrix so the
second part of your question is easy the
first part of your question is hard let
me try to take the hard part first is it
useful um I mean it's hard to say it can
be uh it can sometimes help your artists
get squash and stretch you know it's
just the problem with it is it causes a
lot of headaches you can no longer treat
things as just a position in a
quaternion right so it's no longer v3
before you now have to actually have a
scale shear addenda to that and so you
know it's it's hard to say whether it's
useful it may or may not be useful as
but probably the best answer I can give
it really depends on what you're doing
and what your animation system has for
support for like mesh morphing and
whether or not you can attack those kind
of squash and stretch animation problems
in a different way right so I really
just couldn't tell you it can be useful
but it really depends on what you're
doing it may just be over complicating
things and you don't need it so I'm like
that's just a really hard question the
easy part of your question which is how
to construct it is well you all you have
to do is just make the when you make the
matrix don't try to make the basis
vectors be orthogonal that's it so if
you imagine we just draw up for you here
so the important thing to remember and
we've talked about this a lot on
handmade hero so go back and look at
matrix stuff if you don't understand
what I'm saying here but again if you
just always remember the fundamental
construction for an object placement
matrix it should be obvious how you
create a shear matrix so I'm just going
to reiterate that again
here's your matrix
and if you're a longtime handmade hero
viewer you should be able to look at
this bag of numbers which is a four by
four matrix here right and you should be
able to say if this is something that
takes a object and places it in the
world which is where you'd be doing your
shears or whatever you should be able to
pull out for me exactly what that
objects XY and z axes are and what its
origin is right and so what you would
expect to see is this down here MN o P
would be and if I I'll draw it over here
would be 0 0 0 1 right because this is
the part of the matrix that deals with
the W parameter of your input and so
it's not really participating in placing
this object unless you're doing things
like trying to move things into the
output W which is for you know
perspective transforms and things like
that so you're looking at this bag of
twelve numbers right here where's the
position all right everyone who watches
handmade here regularly you should be
able to pull this out if you don't I'm
gonna have to go programming on you
again so it's right here right this is
the position this right here is the
vector that is the position of the
object that you're placing so it's a px
py PZ right is these three and then
where's the XY and z axes of this object
okay it's here here and here so that
means we have our x axis x or x axis y
our x axis Z our Y axis X our Y axis Y
and our y axis Z our z axis X or z axis
Y our z axis Z okay and so now we can
see that for any bag of four by four
numbers you've given us if you're
telling us hey this is an object
transform we can immediately tell you
that these are the parameters for it
right so that tells us exactly like
exact
just by pulling the numbers out no work
on the numbers exactly this here's the
origin here's the y axis x axis z axis
they are literally these right here all
right so if you know that now you should
be able to make your sheer matrix
trivially all you have to do is well
assure matrix doesn't move anybody right
so the p values are just 0 0 0 and the
bottom obviously is 0 0 1 right so we
can start off there because we're not
trying to place the thing anywhere we're
just trying to share it so then we could
say well what kind of shear are we
trying to do right and I guess I don't
know what kind of sure you're trying to
do but let's say you were trying to
shear the y axis so what you want to do
is you want it to kind of look more like
that right so you're shearing this over
so what you're going to do there is just
say okay my z axis and my x axis are not
going to change so I'm gonna put my x
axis in here right which is 1 0 0 that's
just you know the x axis unchanged my Y
axis I'm gonna shear so I'll leave that
out for now and the z axis is also gonna
be unchanged right so now I want my
sheared Y axis well what would a sheared
y axis look like well if I wanted to
produce a thing that you know sheared
like that then my Y axis should just be
set to I don't know 1 1 let's say that
would be that point there right that
would shear me over by 1 okay and again
you can just conceptualize it by saying
what did you want these to do right
maybe you wanted to shear and why as
well in which case maybe you would put a
1 you know I'm sorry a 1 there right I
don't know I don't know what kind of
steer you're trying to do right but
however much for this for example if you
just want to do a Y shear however much Y
sure you wanted would go right there
right and we know that because this is
the y axis so if you want to do an X
here on the y axis right or Y shear I
don't know why you describe these things
but if you want to share your Y in the X
direction then that's just that value
and we know that because
that's where the y-axis goes right so
does that make sense
okay cool a couple other questions you
may see which kind of light does
hand-made hero support did I assume
right it support any as long as you put
like correctly maybe moonlight can be a
planar light put over rooms marked as
outside yes we certainly can we pretty
much don't have any restrictions on the
light at the moment we could just put
any anything we can evaluate for a ray
cast can be in there so if we want to
like you say we could totally just put a
fake light that's like a roof over
outdoor rooms and it just says if you
hit this thing computer moonlight we
could totally do that
and that may very well be what we do we
just haven't we don't really have any
need to do that until we actually have
everything else correct but putting in
types of lights yet is pretty much free
because since we're using Ray casting it
means that anything you can compute a
ray cast for which is literally all
lights that exist period pretty much we
can do could you check how much slower
the build is if you define internal to
nothing I can although it's probably not
a particularly good check
because handmade Heroes codebase is
fairly small so I wouldn't really expect
it to save that much time on a very
small codebase right because there's
just not that many functions so we
certainly can take a look at it if I go
here and run the builds we can take a
look at how long that takes and you know
see if that's a consistent number four
point eight eight seven and and you know
we may want to do two is say look the
debug build is the one that's gonna be
fastest and would you know possibly be
the one to look at there so if I do a
build for debug and look at how much
time is that's two point two oh three
two point four oh six two point zero
three right so it's gonna be kind of
hard to measure something that small but
it's in the two point three two
two point two two two point three area
right yeah
so I can go and take a look at internal
and I can try I don't know if we'll
compile without that but we can try so
it looks like yeah the problem there is
we're getting some unresolved externals
there that's really only cut at h8
sphere so I could get rid of that but it
looks like like I said they're hand
meters cuz isn't that big so I wouldn't
expect this to really make a difference
here and I don't think it really does
let's try that again so that's you know
roughly two seconds
and now I'll put it in and my assumption
is you know it'll basically be the same
I mean it you know we're not even
measuring I think it so yeah I mean even
there I guess it is slightly faster
looks like it's fairly consistently
slightly faster but again like not in a
meaningful way so you know again with a
code base of this size I don't know that
you'd really care about it but it does
look like it's slightly slower
oddly enough I wouldn't necessarily have
thought that but it does look like it's
pretty consistently slightly slower
right looking at the release build my
assumption is that the percentage of the
time that it would take there would be
even less I could be wrong about that
but you know if we take a look at that's
just because release bills tend to be
longer so the amount of time it's doing
resolving the names would take up less
of the time but again so looking at a
like a 4.3 to 4.4 range in there and
then if I go ahead and get rid of that
and I do a build we can see if it's any
different and
looks like we're failing there though
with it with an unresolved symbol men
copied their so hold on a second so not
really sure why we're getting that mem
copy we don't call mem copy so I'm not
sure why that would actually mmmm that's
just in the preprocessor mm-hmm so it
looks like checksum of for whatever
reason if we call checksum of here we're
getting
that's actually generating a mem copy
for this I would assume and I don't know
why it may just be because okay so it
may just be because since it can't see
it or thin since it thinks it's external
gosh I don't I don't really know why
it's doing that though let me just see
what happens
I don't really know I don't know why
it's why it's happening that you got me
the compiler is putting in like we're
not calling it but for some reason and
and I I would have to investigate more
closely so so I don't know exactly why
it's doing that
but for some reason it looks like in the
optimized build if you don't include
that it can't actually do the build
because it inserts a spurious mem copy
and and I don't know why so I guess
that's another reason to always use it
no it's not going to be REM something
out the that's just the sphere build and
we don't need to do that so so I don't
know
that's not a reason I would think it so
as you can see it does actually even get
slower even for our code base which is a
little bit surprising but that's the
case and so yeah I don't know how much
lower the release build gets though
because it was hard for to tell since it
can't complete it
alright let's go ahead and wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me for
those that a handmade hero it's when I
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow on the series
at home you can always go to handmade
hero org and pre-order the game and it
comes to the source code so you can do
your own experiments with it maybe you'd
like to try optimizing our lighting code
which is what we're gonna start on
tomorrow you can see if you can make a
dent in it I think there's a lot of fat
in there we can start to trim so we'll
go ahead and do that
hope to see you back here tomorrow for
that till then have fun programming
everyone and I'll see you on the
Internet take it easy everybody