okay hello everyone and welcome to hand
made here on the show Rico to complete
gain live on twitch no engines no
libraries just us even our renderer
rewrote by hand and not like GPU render
but I mean literally we wrote the whole
thing by hand every last pixel is put
there by us on the cpu if you can
believe it and we still run at 60 frames
per second how do you like that just a
little bit of old-fashioned elbow grease
you never know what's possible you
really don't anyway we're in the middle
of doing some asset work and I want to
sort of get right back into that because
we kind of ended at a good place last
last week and this week is going to kind
of be about actually exploring the
system that we set up and hopefully
coming up with a definition of what our
asset pack file will be so that I can
make one some time off the stream and
have a new asset pack file for us that
will you know conform to the standard
that we want it to to conform to I okay
before I get started to let me just say
it's day 1 36 aren't handmade hero so if
you have pre-ordered the game and want
to follow along at home unpacked day 135
source code that is the source code that
I am starting with today and so that is
the source code that you will want to
start with if you want to match what I'm
doing I have an itch on my back can we
just say that my allowed to say that I'm
stream my back is itchy I need one of
those little like hand scratcher thing
is that they sell those weird things
really like why would anyone want this
will now is right now is literally the
time that I actually do want that thing
okay so we have everything running
through our new asset system which we
worked on last week and it all streams
in assets progressively and all that
other kind of good stuff but there is a
separate aspect of the asset system that
was not just about streaming that we've
been working on lately and what we want
to do is we want to explore that now
because that's a pretty important part a
pretty important thing that we were
trying to accomplish and so we want to
kind of look at that and and see if we
can start to define it a little more
rigorously
so if you remember what we were talking
about was how we could go about and I
sort of proposed this tag system that we
put in there how we could go about
classifying assets in ways and where the
engine could use those assets without
really knowing the specifics of what it
was doing and the reason that that's
interesting is because what we'd like to
be able to do is have the engine just
sort of talk in a general way about what
it is looking for in terms of a
particular asset like i need a hero you
know sprite here and I need them to be
like pointing upwards or something
because the hero's moving upwards or
something like this right it'd be nice
to be able to say that from the engine
into the asset system and then the asset
system go and get whatever the most
appropriate asset is for that thing and
there's a lot of reasons why you might
want to do it this way one of the big
reasons is because you can add assets
after the fact and not have to do any
additional work in the code to make the
game a little bit richer so for example
let's say that we had some way of
telling the asset system which direction
the hero was facing and it would return
the sprite that most closely matched
that direction well once you do that in
the future you can always put in more
facing directions for the hero and
everything will just magically work
right the game just gets a little more
fidelity at that point and you didn't
have to do any more work in the engine
right and so rather than have to write
that code everywhere in the engine where
every place in the engine where we might
be doing something where there could be
lots of there could be different numbers
of art assets depending on how much art
we have finished and all those other
sorts of things rather than have to do
to get all the time if we can just put
that into the asset system it's a lot
more useful there because then everybody
who ever asks for an asset can ask for
it in a way where it's not talking about
specific asset but rather a family of
assets and it can trust the asset system
to return back to it whatever asset is
most appropriate then as the pack file
gets more assets in it the game just
gets richer and you don't really have to
do any additional work right so that's
kind of handy it also helps during
development because for example let's
say that yangshin hasn't drawn a
particular thing yet
but I need to test that thing I can
always have a way of asking the asset
system for it and having the asset
system just return me something close
that's like some other thing that hasn't
you know that that's any asset pack file
but isn't exactly the right thing and
then I can still test out everything
with that and then later when she
actually delivers whatever the stuff is
that was for that that new thing that
was added it just goes into the asset
system and then suddenly you know the
game has the right graphics right and
there isn't like this huge stall of me
having to wait for her to give me back
the thing before I can implant it or any
of this sort of sort of stuff right so
it helps kind of like with that
pipelining that's really important
because you never want the artist to be
waiting on you or you to be waiting on
the artist that you can avoid it you'd
always rather just be able to develop at
full speed and as things come together
they just get used and you don't have to
really worry about those sort of
dependency as much so what I kind of
proposed for this was an asset tag
system where basically we have any given
asset in the game does have a primary
type and that is just whatever the ass
the asset generally is to the engine so
if the engine tends to think about
things in terms of like oh there's a
hero and there's this and there's that
then those are representing the types
and those are the things where we know
specifically we want to get back a thing
of this type right so if we ask for hero
we want to get back a hero right but
then everything else underneath there
are is kind of saying maybe we could get
that out of the concept of a bunch of
tags which are like IDs paired with
values and those IDs would be things
like oh this is you know a thing that
says you know for a lack of an example
like say the gender of the hero like
leisa you wanted to have like a male and
female versions of the hero right well
maybe you have an asset tag ID that's
like gender and then you would just put
in there you know you'd assign number
values to them like you know zeros mayl
one is female or something like this I
don't know and hey then you could even
represent as you know anything in
between genders if you wanted to write
maybe maybe not all the creatures in
this game have a binary gender right
maybe it's a more progressive game and
and creatures in this game can have
mixed genders or transition between
genders or do all sorts of other things
right well then the engine only has to
know about that and it can just go ahead
and say that and then
nobody's drawn a female hero yet then it
would just return a male hero if that
was what we had in there like the one
that's in there currently although I'll
be honest with you are I feel like our
guy's a little kid he's cut you no he's
not he's somewhat of androgynous you
know he's not strongly Mia but he sees
you know sort of mail so we have you
know that in there I've it asked for a
female protagonist there wouldn't be one
yet so it would return anything I'm
sorry but it so we return the closest
match which would be the male 1 but that
if in the future you drop in a female
hero now you have that ability for the
asset system to pick that so when
someone picks female hero as their hero
they will get back the right set of art
assets right and so that's kind of the
idea right and the same goes for other
properties like if I have grass and I
want you know tall grass and short grass
I can have an ID that's like the
tallness of something and then I could
put in like zero for the shortest one
for the highest and everything in
between and it'll just you know at first
that there's only one type of grass I
always get that asset back but then as
more grasses go in I'll start to get
back different grasses based on that
number that I put in right and so that
all seems pretty reasonable but you know
is it enough do we have to do more i
don't know let's let's so you know I
feel like what we're supposed to do this
week I start playing with this see what
we can represent with it and try to play
around with some of those sort of some
of those characters characteristics that
I think we might want to have of the
asset system and see if we can make it
work now we already made it work with
arrays which was the simple case you
notice that we don't have any of the Ray
types in here anymore we just ask them
directly from the asset system and so
you could always dump more of something
in and that just works currently but now
what we want to do is start to talk
about some of the more structural
aspects and so we do have one example of
that which is our hero bitmaps and
that's the thing that we want to start
looking at today so here is our hero
bitmaps thing and you can see that the
way that this typically works currently
is there's three parts to a hero there's
the head the cape and the torso and so
there's two things that we might want to
try and tackle here and I'm not one
hundred percent certain which
you know which of these two we actually
necessarily want to use and I'm not sure
how far we want to go down one of the
past necessarily but I'll just sort of
briefly discuss them so you can get an
idea of what I'm talking about so
there's two ways we can go about doing
this there is one way which is that the
asset system itself has the capability
of exposing information such as what
constitutes a hero right in other words
it's entirely possible for us to say the
engine doesn't really know specifically
what makes up a hero and in fact it asks
the asset system give me back a hero and
tell me what parts it has right so
that's like doesn't have a head doesn't
have a cape does neva torso that sort of
stuff right the other way of doing
things is the engine is always the thing
that nose and it asks the asset system
to give it back the individual pieces
right and so these two ways of doing
things obviously have different benefits
and trade-offs and stuff like this what
I'm thinking as I say it I feel like our
game is probably going to be the kind of
one where the game engine decides and
just ask the asset system directly
because since it's a procedurally
generated game what that means is we
probably don't want to be asking the
asset system what constitutes a hero we
will probably randomly roll what
constitutes a hero or have different
unlocks that determine what constitutes
a hero and then that hero is dictated to
the asset system which is required to
give back the assets that will form that
procedurally generated entity not the
other way around so what I suspect would
happen here is that what we would want
to do is say that maybe the parts of the
hero are additional things that that
sort of get gets specified right okay
so here's the problem that we have for
every one of these things we have sort
of an additional we have a choice of
whether we put the asset type you know
whether the heroes head is an asset type
or whether it's a tag right underneath
the that hero type and what I think
would be relatively straightforward is
if we make sure that everything that the
engine thinks about specifically is
typically going to be in a type ID right
and the reason I say that is because if
I asked for a hero head you can you can
give me any number of heads from the
asset pool like a male or female head or
a you know a skinny head or a wide head
a fat head all those sorts of things
right but you need to give me back ahead
you can't really substitute the head
with something that's not a head like
you can't give me the torso in place of
the head it doesn't really make any
sense so that to me seems like it's not
really a tag situation that seems to me
that it's more of a specificity
situation right so it seems to me that
we want like asset head asset cape asset
torso right that seems to me like
probably what I want right and then when
I asked and these are probably like well
you know what honestly I suppose now
that I think about it I don't even know
if they're they're necessarily specific
to the hero like pretty much you know
anything could have a cape right I mean
at some level I don't know that we need
to split hairs about what kind of cape
it is so I might just say that we've got
you know maybe even child head for human
head I don't even know what to say about
that maybe it's just head yeah I don't
know I'm just going to leave it as just
head for now so those are new asset
types that we could ask about and then
the other question is well with the way
we did hero bitmaps right we've got
those hero bitmaps for four different
facing directions that's why there are
four of them here and the facing
direction to me that does seem like a
tag ID thing right because what
direction it's facing you could give me
back something facing the wrong
direction
as a stand-in for the direction that I
actually want and furthermore if my
directions are very precise I don't
really need you to give me back a head
that's pointing exactly like say 63
degrees off off right or something like
that you could give me back a head that
was pointing just somewhere anywhere
close to there and that would be
sufficient so I feel like for our asset
tags we can now start to think about
what that might be we've got this asset
tag here for example we could have a
facing direction and that's something
that seems pretty clear about what that
would be right that would be something
and I guess I could put a note here that
this is like the angle in radians off of
do right you know right so like like the
you know the mathematical sort of
circular Sam and facing direction so now
let's try you know given just that very
simple experiment let's try to encode
our hero into the asset system so that
it's no longer a special purpose thing
that sort of happens out here that you
know in a sort of way that we had a
special case for heroes let's see if we
can do it in a way that doesn't require
any of that special casing at all and so
what I want to do now is I want to
introduce some way of course of actually
passing what you want for the asset tags
and the way that I think that I'm going
to do that is probably with large with
wide vectors at first maybe we won't do
this later but you know we're going to
say so what I'm going to I'm going to
call this here an asset vector and an
asset vector is just going to be a giant
set of real 32s right that's all of the
possible asset tag types that we had in
here like so right and so when you
create one of these asset vectors you
can essentially go ahead and make it an
asset vector full of all these reels
whether this gets a little bit too
unwieldy and whether we need to store
them sparsely I will worry about later
and so for right now I'm just going to
the simplest possible thing and
introduce that and this will basically
be a way of me saying that I want to
pick an asset type based on something
that isn't random right and so let's go
ahead like I said
try to write the rusev code first I had
already put in that sort of pic asset
function I don't know where that guy
ended up actually being I think he's in
here here we go pick best so what I want
to do is I want to go ahead and write
that you can see right here that we've
got this random asset from and so what I
want to do is make this basically be the
same thing where I've got a sort of a
random essa friend but now I want to do
something that's like a match asset from
or something like this right or best
match asset right and so what I'll do is
I'll pass something like one of these
asset tag vectors right we go and this
is like the desired characteristics so
this is the you know the match but in
fact I guess I already got it laid out
here right so we have an asset vector
like so an asset vector here so I pass
in what I want to match how I want to
wait those matches and then I can just
say well we've got the game assets I've
got the type of the asset that I want
and instead of passing that random
series I'm going to pass those match
vectors and then let's see if we can
implement that with our asset system
right and so any cuz you can see we like
I said remember when we wrote this what
we do is we just loop through the assets
that we have and we see which one of
them has tags that matches the closest
is possible to our match vector weighted
by whatever the weights are and i'll
talk about that maybe a little bit more
after we implement this for those of you
who don't really understand how that
works i'll try to give you a little bit
more information about that since we
never really talked about in detail when
i wrote that sort of as an exploratory
function okay so basically we want to do
exactly the same stuff here right this
is exactly the startup that we're going
to use we want to grab out whatever that
asset is and then assuming that there
are some assets we're going to take a
look at all of the assets and serious
own so instead of doing it like this we
actually want to do is do a for I loop
here now where I'll go ahead and do
Asset index equals whatever the first
one is and I guess we don't even need
that that for loop anymore because we're
just going to loop you know sort of
between the the balance here so there we
go I'm going to start with this asset
index I'm going to loop until the the
end of this particular asset and off we
go now every time I encounter one of
these assets right I'm going to take a
look at that asset and I'm going to loop
through the flags and I'm going to do
that exactly how we did it here right
and so what I need to do is find out
where those flags are and i believe the
asset itself tells me right that's the
way it should work we've got the asset
type which told us all the assets we
should consider and then breathe asset
we have all the tags week should
consider so there's our first tag index
excuse me there's that first tag index
there's the one passed the last tag
index so and for each one of those we're
going to grab out that asset tag which
again is just off of our our global tags
array so for each one of those tanks in
the asset system we're going to take a
look at the match vector we're going to
subtract it from the actual value that
the tag has and that's basically the
difference between what we wanted and
what this particular asset prescribes
and then we're going to wait that by
multiplying it by whatever the the
weight vector is for that that
particular tag that gives us total
weighted diff and so each time through
the asset every time we check an asset
if the diff that we come up with here is
better than whatever our current best is
then we will go ahead and save that as
as the resulting asset right and i think
that's basically all we need to do i'm
going to go ahead and make this look
like that there we go we don't really
need best index we only need to save
best if because the result itself will
carry
the return value so let's go ahead and
compile that and see if I did anything
stupid there oh I forgot these are now
Dottie's there we go I should say arrow
ease and that is a best match routine
that loops through all the assets now
it's not particularly smart it's not
accelerated very well so it's got to do
a lot of work to check all these and
that may be a problem for us so that's
something that we definitely have to
think about and when we start to do a
little bit more profiling and stuff like
that in the future we may have to start
to think about how we want to make this
stuff run faster but again we're not
going to worry about that until we
actually have some indication that it's
going to be a problem because otherwise
we're just spending time in the wrong
place potentially so there we go that's
something that does what we needed to do
and so now let's take a look at actually
calling that best match asset from you
know some code that was actually using
the hero bitmaps right so let's let's
assume just start off with go handing
and turning off those here a bit maps
entirely so that we just don't have them
anymore right and so we can see everyone
who's trying to use them and here you go
you can see us grabbing the hero bitmaps
out here and if we take a look at what
happens with those here a bit maps you
can see that they they get I guess they
get used here both by the the familiars
and here by the by the hero it looks
like yeah the familiar and the Monstar
are only drawing the torso and the head
what I might do just for the moment I
might go ahead and disable the familiar
and the Monstar so that we only have to
work with one person which is this guy
right and and see how we would go about
specifying this stuff here well you know
what actually now that I think about it
no we don't really have to do that
that's actually probably premature what
I could do instead there's a pretty easy
way to port this now that I think about
it all we really have to do is take this
out
and you know make this back into
something that only i think it was
originally in handmade dot H anyway I'm
just going to go ahead and make one of
those there and instead I'm just going
to say that there's a bitmap ID in each
of these right and we'll call this hero
bitmap IVs right then in here what i can
do is where we were getting them before
where we do here a bit maps and we we
look up that facing direction right i'm
just going to say okay here's our hero
bitmap IDs right and that i will
actually set each of these members to be
the appropriate what the ID should be
for the facing direction by calling the
asset system right here so i can
basically emulate exactly the way that
we were doing this before right and so
what i want to do here is call that new
function that we made and you know like
i said write the usage code first i want
to make sure before i go down this path
any further I want to make sure that
it's convenient to use this function so
let's take a look and see if it actually
does things the way that I want it to do
it so we've got our trans state assets
we have our asset type ID which in this
case is going to be you know like the
head and so on so there's our asset head
then we have our match vector in our
weight vector and those are going to be
basically the same for the head decay
from the torso at the moment so i'll
just go ahead and make those and then
use them in each case right so let's go
ahead and do best match asset go best
match asset best match asset so we have
head cape or so and that's really all we
need let's take a look here set top down
a line we don't really want that anymore
that is not at all what we want let's go
ahead and keep that let's see and so
asset vector match vector so ass
effector weight vector so what I want to
do here I want I'm not sure
how exactly I want to set these it's a
little bit confusing because I haven't
really thought it through too much I'm
going to do this in a very simplistic
way at the moment so we're going to kind
of want to work with these guys a little
bit more to figure out exactly what we
want to do but for now yeah we're just
going to do the simplest possible thing
and and just directly set the values but
i think i'm going to want some helper
functions for this eventually is it
empty facing direction is that the is
not the appropriate and i'm actually
even know let's see the military to yet
so that's fine alright so I want the
weight right now oops I've got these
backwards I want the wait to just be one
point ammo for right now and and I want
the facing direction to be the only
thing that we're matching against so
there we go and when I'm calling these
guys here I need to pass the address
because that's a pointer based value so
there we go oops and let's see and these
are now dots so there we go and none of
the two overloads right because that's
not address anymore it's just a bitmap
ID so let's do that and that and now we
should be ported ok perfect so now what
I'm expecting to happen now is is
absolutely nothing like we shouldn't see
anything because of course we haven't
actually set up any of those asset
tables so what we want to do now is go
ahead and set up those asset tables and
see how they work so here we are in the
part where we would have to start
setting those up right and you can see
that we've kind of got this stuff
happening here so what we'd want to do
is we want to go ahead and do a begin
asset type and we'd want to say that
we're going to set you know like for
example the cape and then we do an end
asset type and you know I could go ahead
and grab the right Cape in here right
and just add that in there oops add
bitmap asset
assets like so and now we'd have the
cape in there and it would just always
pick the right word facing cape right so
anytime you ask for a cape you're going
to get the right word facing kate right
because that's the only asset that's in
there so it doesn't matter what tags you
specify you'll always get that one and
similarly I could do the exact same
thing for everything else on the Kiro
right we've got the head and asset type
assets and again this code I don't care
about it all really because this is not
code will ever actually use in the real
game this code right here is just to
build the asset list as if it had
already been built in an asset pack file
so this is really just whatever it takes
to get something in there because it's
really all the query code and stuff that
we care about we don't care about at all
the building code here because that will
never run at runtime at all that'll be
something that's done it is an offline
process so there we go so let's see if I
specify these now we should get a
complete hero facing to the right like
so oh and hey we also get the familiar
head which is also good right now we
have a problem here which is that we
have not done our top down alignment
stuff for these guys yet and so we need
to pass in that and as well as like a
sort of a v2 thing there right as a
thing that specifies that and I'm not
sure how we want to do that exactly I
guess I can just do the divide I guess I
could what I did before if i remember
correctly as i went in and actually
inspected what they all were seems a
little bit tedious maybe we'll leave
that for a little bit later and focus on
so what we're doing here and then I'll
deal with that a little bit later on all
right so now what I want to do is I want
to be able to start adding in the
different types of assets for the head
here are the different facing direction
so I'd like to do is make the head go
different directions so I don't want to
do is I want to be able to make the head
go right I want to make the head be able
to go up or i guess i should say back
and in front right to represent that
sort of rotational
that rotation right and if i add all
those to the system then what we get
right is it just picks whatever the
first asset is because none of the other
assets will ever be a higher math in it
so what i need to do now is set those
assets to have some tags that are
actually going to distinguish them from
other things okay and so what I want to
do there is I want to be able to set
that asset tag for the facing direction
like so right I don't know that should
say asset tag or not but we'll just say
tag facing direction right I want to be
able to say tag facing direction and I
want to be able to set that basing
direction to something right now I don't
know what these are actually you know
these aren't actually angles yet because
i think the facing direction stuff is
still set to be integers in the ones
will have to line those up but this will
basically give me something that will
start to differentiate these assets by
adding these tags all right so i'm going
to go ahead and put that tag in here if
i do add tag add tag game assets this
right here is going to be the tag ID
that lets us know what type of tag we're
adding then we have the value which is
what it should be set to and what that
has to do is that has to insert a tag
into the tag table right and it's going
to have to know which particular asset
it was talking about right so since we
haven't ever done anything like this
before you'll notice we don't have the
right pointer in here we need a debug
asset in there for building and what
that's going to be is just the thing
that remembers whatever the last asset
was it whoa that we that we created
right like so and so as we do that I
will do an assert here right cert assets
this guy debug asset and whenever we
sort of end an asset type obviously
we'll also set that debug asset to 0 so
and that's all fine so when we go to add
a tag what we need to do is we need to
make sure that this axe
we get set in the proper way so what we
have here is we've got a you know much
like we had all that other stuff we want
a debug used tag count right and we want
that debug used CAD count to allow us to
continue to add tags right so we're
going to have an asset tag here where we
basically do assets tags Plus debug used
tag count + + right and that allocates a
new tag and again we would also want to
assert here it looks like I didn't
assert this one for some reason I would
I don't know why I'd like to assert but
we're actually in the reasonable range
right make sure that that one passed
last asset index is actually less than
the asset count total just again it's
not like this is really an issue at all
because this is stuff again that will
all be done offline but you know just
well we're it helps in debugging to
double-check that way you don't spend a
lot of time trying to debug something
that an assert could very easily have
caught right so sometimes it pays to
just throw in a few extra asserts in
there even if you don't think they're
particularly useful or even if you don't
think it's very important for the code
to be robust it's you know sometimes
you're just doing it to save yourself a
little bit of time right so let's go
ahead and do that we set this up now the
first tag index much like we were doing
here this sort of stuff we want this to
work exactly the same way so we set this
up to to initialize itself with
essentially a mill range right and then
every time we add a tag what we would
want to do is we would want to sort of
advanced that debug used tag count and
we also probably want to to take that
that debug asset and increase its one
pass last tag index right so we want to
increment both of those both the total
number of tags that we have written so
far and then also the you know for the
asset that we're actually adding them to
we want to expand its range as well so
that it knows that it has another tag
now once we have that tag we just set
the ID and the value and that's really
all that we need to do they're just
really nothing else that we're going to
do with the tags
so now that we've got that if we go
ahead and you know we really this end
asset type could probably is really
superfluous it's mostly just for error
checking now so we could actually get
rid of that if you want to doesn't
really do anything but that's separate
issue so in here you'll notice we don't
act we don't allocate any tags at the
moment you can see that the tag array is
totally not allocated so we would crash
pretty much immediately well we wouldn't
crash we desert that there's no room
left in the tag table so what I need to
do again is just allocate some room the
tag table for this test stuff so I don't
know how many of those going to be let's
just say that there is a bunch of them I
don't know how many there are but
doesn't really matter a lot the moment
and again we'll know the exact number
normally because we'll be loading enough
disk so that's really not an issue going
forwards so let's go ahead and set that
up and compile now we should probably
step through this and see that
everything's going this one run it ah
there we go so you can kind of see now
that we got exactly what we wanted right
you know those tags are now allowing the
asset system to match properly so now we
no longer specifically code anything
about how the facing direction stuff
works we just ask the asset system and
it returns one for us and as you can see
since we haven't added any other assets
for that cape and the torso they just
stay giving us back the one bitmap that
actually is added and so now without
again changing any other code this is
this kind of nice thing about the system
I can just kind of come in here and
pretend that you know if this was the
asset system I can just pretend that
what we did is we loaded you know the
new asset pack file that has this more
stuff in it right and and off we go so
if I if I actually define these guys so
that now all the directions of all the
stuff is in there you can see we've got
our hero back and now the other nice
thing too is our heroes going through
the asset system which means he's delay
loaded and all that other stuff so
that's all good news as well okay so
that's all cool tag matching is working
nicely
I do think however that this is not a
particularly good way of doing facing
direction I feel like facing direction
should be more you know more general
than that it just just doesn't seem like
a very good idea so what I want to do is
I want to take a look at where that
facing direction stuff is actually set I
want to maybe change that to something
that makes a little more sense so let's
take a look here we are in sim region
you can see that what we're doing here
is we're sort of taking a look at
whether we're you know where we're
moving in X or Y and we're encoding that
in there and I feel like maybe what we
would want to do here is just like an
atan two or something to figure out what
angle the hero is pointing and actually
use that as the facing direction that
way we could introduce diagonal sprites
if we wanted to in the future if we
decided that those were good idea or
other stuff like that it would just give
us a little bit more as you know
fidelity there in our in our you know in
our character sprites if that makes
sense now there is a there is something
that's a little bit nasty about that so
we do have to think about this a little
and this is I'm kind of glad that I
decided to do this because this brings
up a thing that we'd probably have to
support in our tag system that right now
we really aren't supporting right so
let's go ahead and talk about that
because it's it's a very interesting
point I think and and probably will have
some ramifications right in fact I think
someone actually mentioned this they
were like what you need to have
different matching functions and I said
well we don't know yet right and so
here's an example of where we might need
to have one I don't know this is exactly
what they meant but you know I think
they were asking along these lines
anyway so let's say that what I want to
do is I want to match bitmaps against
the facing directions so here's like an
example of a facing direction right
here's another example of a facing
direction here's another direction
example of a facing direction right and
so in here what I do is I have you know
the different drawings of the guy and so
you know here he is facing that
direction
and here he is you know facing that
direction he's some kind of a fish mouth
thing I don't know what he is but that's
just what he is and here he is facing
that direction okay now if I encode
these by the angle right this is maybe 0
degrees this is something like you know
smay be 80 degrees don't actually know
and that's maybe something like I don't
know if that's 180 and that's 90 that's
going to be like you know ones let's
let's say that's 150 I don't really know
maybe 160 probably more like 160 degrees
so if I encode these by the angle and I
pull them out I'm going to get what I
want put in you know let's say 10
degrees and I'll get 0 properly it'll
match the closest i put in 75 degrees
that will match the closest i put in 125
degrees this will match the closest and
it's going to do roughly what i want to
do and that's good but i have a problem
and that is what happens when i go here
and i put in this angle right which is i
don't know exactly what it is but it's
something like 300 degrees what am I
going to get back right I want to get
back this guy because of the three
things that I put in the asset system
he's clearly the closest but the problem
is he's actually going to match this guy
because 300 is closest to 150 not zero
right and that's because this parameter
is periodic right not monotonic right it
does not just keep increasing it wraps
around and in order to correctly obey
you know in order to correctly encode
that notion that this thing is wrapping
around I don't really have any way to to
do that with something that just matches
about based on the value the matching
code needs to do some logic to handle
the fact that it's periodic and match on
a periodic basis does that make sense
hopefully that makes some sense so yeah
that complicates matters a bit for us
right that makes things a little bit
more difficult because what we'd have to
do here is what we'd have to do is say
all right let's assume that you're going
to take these these things together we
would need to for every value pair that
you put in we'd first have to see
whether they were a greater than 180
degrees apart and if they were we have
to like flip one of them right so in
other words flip is probably the wrong
word but basically what we need to say
is okay this is more than 180 degrees
apart so really this guy should not be
whatever angle he is he should be a 300
do you know he should be 360 degrees
plus whatever he was right so let's say
he was you know 10 degrees or something
like this but these guys are more than
360 degrees apart well I should go ahead
and map him by adding right that 360
degrees in there right or the other way
I could do that is say the input when it
comes in if it's more than I'm going to
go ahead and subtract 360 degrees from
it which would bring it to be this would
be negative 60 degrees which would make
him mad zero closer again right so we
need a little comparator in there and
the only way that we would know how to
do that comparison is if we knew / ID
which ones are periodic and which ones
weren't and that is kind of what I mean
when I say we might need different
comparison functions now at the moment
it's totally fine because what we're
doing is we're just matching on a single
value that kind of is set to something
or it isn't but when we start talking
about those values that are going to be
sort of periodic like that that's
something that we have to think about in
I don't know how many of these we would
have but at the very least we know that
many things will probably have a facing
direction and that facing direction is
definitely periodic right there's no
question about that so
that suggests to me that this is
something that we would want to add
that's just seems like what we would
need right so I don't know let's go
ahead and let's go ahead and try that
let's get let's go ahead and play around
with that a little and see where we
where we end up right so what I'm going
to do here is I'm going to say okay
let's go to handmade intrinsics I don't
know if we have any tan too we do so the
ATM to would let me get back with that
angle actually is so what I could do
here is say change to using the
acceleration vector what i could do is
say all right if that's what we wanted
to do we can go ahead and say you know
entity facing direction equals a tan too
and it's going to be dpy DPX like so
that's going to be that facing direction
and I'm going to change that to now be a
floating point value and this is just
going to be else right so yeah something
like that right so if I do that I need
to go grab that facing direction and
make that into something that's that's
actually going to be a floating point
value like so and now the facing
direction is actually an angle and so
what I'd want to do is is actually
specify these guys in the asset when I
in the asset system when I actually and
I won't need this cast anymore as well
so so in the asset system what I want to
do now is I want to change these to be a
you know basically like you know angle
right angle back
angle left oops angle front something
like that right so you know 0.0 F with
angle right one point of F with angled
back a two-pointer left with angle left
and three point i left with angle front
and so then i can just go ahead and
define these angle right is I was 200
angle back is going to be a half pie
right angle left is going to be just pie
in fact I could just make these all in
terms of pies so on or do people like
tau better I know a lot of people liked
a better do we have a pie 32 or tau does
anyone know do we have a tau what do we
have do we have any of these at all can
we seriously not even have a pie there
it is there's our pie all right one
point omf pie 32 + 1.5 f pi 32 all right
so there's our angles they're in radians
that's why it's a nope I half pi 1 pi
1.5 pie as we go around the circle those
specified now and so in theory this
should probably maybe it will work I
don't know so
almost but not for down down does not
work which is interesting to say the
least I'm not entirely sure I know why
yeah yeah I don't know why that would be
messed up necessarily but it definitely
likes to pick the the wrong facing
direction there for our front guys and I
am not exactly sure why that would be
that is something because I you know I
discussed the matching bug there but
that's matching that bug would only
affect things that were sort of closer
calls but down should match pretty much
exactly and we that's not really a
periodic issue or anything like that so
yeah that's that's very weird and it
looks like left is not working properly
at the moment either so we got some
weird got some weird stuff happening
here
yeah so I want to take a look at what's
going on there to die so i'm going to
take a look at first the entity facing
direction stuff to see what that is
actually going to be equal to velocity
wise i guess i could also yeah that's
what i'm going to do first I just want
to take a look and see why it doesn't
change at all so let's go ahead and take
a look at that first I want to see what
we're actually getting here so let's
take let's go ahead and open up file we
want handmade sim region and I want to
see see here I want to see you know what
I don't even care i'm just going to
search for a tattoo because that's got
to find it there we go um alright I kind
of was not expecting my aunt any
entities to have a velocity at the
moment oh man and their d normals oh
well we're still in debug build so let's
go ahead and turn that off first of all
so we can view everything appropriately
like so okay it's so much slower in in
debug mode it's crazy alright so here we
go right I'm moving downwards now I flip
over break in here let's take a look
entity our DP is this the hero it is
negative e so there's really no xcountry
large y component negative 1.4 so that's
that's a pretty huge negative Y so I
would expect the entity facing direction
to come out to be something reasonable
here let's actually see if it does
negative 1.57 and so let's see what that
what 1.5 f times 3.14 5 is
like so that is not what I would have
expected maybe my math is so rusty that
I just am totally forgetting how to use
my a tan to properly do I actually need
to normalize these guys first I didn't
think that would have been the case so
why would we come out so this is what
actually would be facing downwards oh
duh right so this is actually the
periodic matching problem that I was
just talking about never mind these are
just right it just gave us the negative
angle duh cuz 8 am-2 doesn't do 0 to 360
it does- 182 positive 180 so that's this
actually is exactly the bug all right so
yeah this is exactly the bug I guess I'm
glad that I'm glad that it was what I
said we were going to have to do but I'm
not glad that I was too dumb to
immediately know that that would happen
so yeah if we wanted to fix this right
we could also go ahead and and right
afterwards do like an empty you know if
nad facing direction is less than zero
entity facing direction equal you know
plus equals 360 right so pi 32 2.5 32
something like this and that would you
know correct it back down i believe so
that we could just verify that it's
working still in the janky ur way I'll
have to turn that off alright so there
we go
yeah so yeah so we do have the bug and
that's good because now we would like to
go ahead and fix that right we'd like to
make it so that that can match on the
periodic boundary and that everything is
fine and you can kind of see even right
there I get a nice bug where it's not
quite matching with zero properly like
he's still gonna until I give him a
little bit of upwards velocity he still
matches more closely with the down value
because his velocity is probably still
pretty small in terms of upwards
velocity right yeah alright so we have
exactly that problem I think we can
probably wrap it up for today because I
feel like we've done basically
everything that I want to do and so
talking about how we want to handle
those variable types will be the thing
that will do will start on tomorrow like
meaning how we want to add the tag types
so that'll be that'll be our goal for
tomorrow we'll be adding the tactic so
i'll put that bug back in there unfix
now so that it's more blatant and that's
exactly what we'll do tomorrow as well
go ahead and work on getting that
correct because it shouldn't be too much
work but I don't want to start a lot to
take this it's kind of a new system all
right so that sounds good let me go
ahead and go over to the Q&amp;A here see
there we go so if you have any questions
on what we did please make sure you
prefix your colon question with two
colon and then I will be able to see it
and answer it
Abner cumbre says it's a bit delayed so
bear with us very well I will bear with
you
repeating the question for the pre
stream or that's not on topic let's see
robot chocolate Dino could all tag
matching be periodic and then we just
make the period really large when we
don't want it to wrap you know I like
the sound of that i you may be onto
something there
I need to think about that a little more
I'll think about that and tomorrow we
will talk about that when we go to
implement it we might be able to do
something like that where all the tags
are handled uniformly but they have sort
of parameters that let a single set of
quick math functions give us a bunch of
options to play with along those lines
that's a good idea robot chocolate Dino
the hero has separate bit mess for your
sprites will this be a recurring thing
for other kinds of sprites in the game
yes lots of the sprites will have
different pieces so that they can kind
of be animated like bouncy and I mean
obviously you know just like every game
you're going to be able to like get
different capes or stuff right and so
you want to be able to swap out
different capes if you get like a new
Cape that's you know magical or
something right so you want to always
have the ability to to have more
granular control over what you're
drawing
you
from a scale of 1 to 10 how dumb do you
think windows API is the answer is you
can't assign a single number because it
depends which AP are talking about some
of the colonel AP is are very well
designed you know so are you talking
about those are you talking about
Windows Event tracing which is probably
the worst API ever designed like ever
you know and so I think the answer could
be a one or it could be a 9 or a 10
depending on which part of the windows
api you're talking about so I think it's
impossible to sign a single number and
that is not surprising because it wasn't
like the windows api was written by one
dude right the windows api is written by
many people over many years and some of
those people were very very good at what
they did and their api is probably are
the ones that we look at and go okay
that's pretty good api and then other
people who had no idea what they were
doing wrote stuff and you know those
aren't and so that's just the way it
goes for the getting the angle you want
couldn't you just divide the angle by 45
giving you a number to switch on you
could go go a step further and take the
modulus of the number of angles you want
uh no I don't want to do that anymore
because the idea here is now the engine
should ask for things directly without
doing that it should just say here's the
actual angle and then whatever the art
asset pack happens to have in it it will
get back the closest match that way if
you you know add more art sprites to it
it just gets smoother tau is clearly the
superior constant please remove every
instance of Pi in the code I guess you
feel very strongly about that if you if
you really want the the PI stuff to go
away do we have a good where is a good
tau out too many digits give me a good I
don't want to do 2 times pi because then
I'll lose a bit of precision potentially
so give me give me the value of tab how
come Google doesn't have the value of
tau
just should not just come up you know
they have all those little drop downs
and things that come up let's see so do
we think we trust this source see here
there's some towel that's more tail than
we need so handmade dot cpp h platform
whatever so here we go time to fine I'll
32 six-point some like so so
there's some tau and if you want to we
can go ahead and replace the places
where it makes sense let's see so here's
tau tau tau tau so you cleaned up a
bunch of two point I was there right Hey
look Tahoe that's why tau is better
sometimes it's just because a lot of
times you're talking about 30 60 degrees
so it's just cleaner oh and look at that
we already were doing one of those
reentry sort of things to burn train
right so there's that tau and then
here's this Taos so we have tau 32
tattoo right now 32 to 32 and that's
probably it
so yeah there you go
what is your opinion on people who use
spaces instead of tabs i think spaces
are good I don't think tabs are a very
good idea they're kind of a half
implemented feature and usually when you
try to use a half infinite feature it
goes poorly
why did you use a tangent of the angle
for determining the asset so the reason
is because what I need to do right what
I have is I have a direction vector
right and so this is my velocity right
or DP as we call it right the Delta of
my position so i know that vector and
what I want to do is I want to be able
to look up based on that I want to be
able to look up at aren't asset now I
don't want to look up the artists at by
two independent numbers like I don't
want to look it up by a DP DX and a DP
dot why because I really only care about
the direction this vector is heading I
don't care about its actual magnitude or
anything like that right so what I
wanted to do is I want to encode this
into one float right one floating point
value and so the way I can encode the
direction of vector and flowing x value
is using an angle right obviously an
angle is a really easy way I can just
say okay wherever this vector was I just
wanted you to give me an angle that says
how far off of you know off of the sort
of the x axis that is right so the way
that you convert a vector into an angle
is by using the arctangent right because
if you look at what happens if i draw in
some arbitrary vector here i know that
the vector has an X component right and
it has a y component and what I want to
do is I want to find this theta right I
want to find find out what theta is I
want to know what that angle is well as
you know from grade scroll trigonometry
right tangent of theta is actually equal
to this Y over this X right it's the
sign over the cosine of that angle right
and so what I want to do is I want to do
the inverse of that right I know the Y
in the X and I want the theta so instead
of tan what I want to do is do the
inverse tangent right you could think of
applying the inverse tangent function to
both sides of this equation I
get inverse tangent of tangent equals
inverse tangent of Y over X right so
inverse tangent and tangent cancel and I
just get theta equals tangent inverse of
Y over X right and so what I could do is
I could call 8am right I could say give
me the a tan of Y over X I could I could
do that right that's one way I could
have done it but what happens there if i
call a tan of the quantity y over x the
problem is the signs disappear so i end
up with you know if it was negative Y
over negative x right and think about
what these mean let me just draw them
out for you just so you're totally clear
on this right here's something with
positive x positive Y right here's
something with negative x negative
positive Y right here's something with
positive x negative Y and here's
something with negative x negative Y
okay all of these have exactly the same
x and y values other than their sign
okay all of these could be like you know
this could be 1 comma 1 and this could
be negative 1 comma 1 right and this
could be negative 1 negative 1 and this
could be one negative one okay so now
when I asked for the tangent well I
wanted two very different values here I
wanted that value for this vector I
wanted that value for this vector right
I wanted that value or negative this
value for that vector etc etc right but
with a tan it would have no idea which
one of those I met right if I passed it
X a positive x over positive Y or
negative x over negative why it's the
same result the division is the same
right negative 1 over negative 1 is 1
and 1 over 1 is 1 they're the same so it
has no idea which of these two vectors
I'm talking about right so it just gives
me back a representative angle that's
what could have had that tangent and
it's the wrong actual angle for our
purposes because we care about what
quadrant the vector was in not just how
much the deflection was off of
access right because basically what
that's doing is it saying well you know
what I don't care whether you're talking
about this deflection off the negative
access or this deflection of the
positive axis I'm just going to give you
back what the theta would have been in
either case that's not what i want i
want you to differentiate between those
right so ATM two is a much more powerful
and useful function for computer
graphics because what it does is it
takes both the why and the x and it uses
their respective signs to properly give
you the angle that relates to the vector
that you actually passed in and not just
a example theta that would have worked
for a deflection off of the closest
access rather than the universal x axis
x positive axis
how many spaces two three or four I use
four spaces for my indentations but you
know you should use whatever you want to
use we implement asset loading priority
for example the player should probably
load first that you're not invisible in
the beginning I don't know that will
implement asset loading priority but
what we will do is will pre will
prefetch stuff so what we'll do is we'll
like try to start the asset loading
happening long enough before we need
assets to make it so that they don't
they aren't missing when we need them
would it be a good idea to switch to
using matrices for rotation so further
down the line it's easier to implement
scale and transform um so I'm not sure
what you mean by that right now we
basically do use matrices we just never
called them that like we have an x-axis
and y-axis and they can be scaled and
that's how we're doing rotations so
we're not actually using angles for
rotation if that makes sense if you're
just talking about this encoding this is
just encoding for the asset lookup
system and no I definitely don't think
we should use matrices for the asset
lookup system because then you're trying
to match on four tags instead of one tag
just to figure out what direction
something's going which doesn't really
make much sense especially because you
probably want the scale and the rotation
to be separate matching which means you
don't want them to be miscible if you
don't want them representing the same
point you want separate quantities for
how big something is versus what
direction is facing
maybe this is something I missed out on
but are using CMOS 8 into yes right now
we have not replaced the sea runtime
libraries math functions that's kind of
a topic that I'm not sure what exactly
will do there I'll do it on stream but
that's nothing going to be something
that not everyone probably cares about
but basically what we'll do is we'll go
ahead for our 8am two will actually
implement a little mathematical guy who
does the atan2 in simdi right so
probably you know it'll do a four wide
atan2 probably as well I don't know if
we'll ever actually care about that but
really like our 8 am-2 will probably
operate on four values at once as well
all right so due to e3 looks like it's
probably a slow day I'm guessing at what
happened why does my weird my hex chat
says there are no operators on the
channel and there's only one person the
channel which is me and yet I see stuff
streaming by so yeah anyway so I think
now would be a good time to call it and
yeah we'll be back tomorrow still in the
middle of III madness I'm sure but we'll
be back tomorrow to go ahead and talk
about how we want to do periodic
matching asset tags but it looks like
things are going pretty well here that
was pretty easy and now we've got a
system where we can dump assets in that
have properties and those properties we
properly obeyed so that's a good thing
so thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with a source code at home you could
always pure to the game and it comes
with the source code you can do that at
handmade here org and then you can go
ahead and download it every night after
I'm done if you want to ask questions we
do have a place for that there's a forum
site which has a place to ask questions
i answer and other people answer on
there it's also got ports to mac and
linux from the members of the community
so if you're trying to do that follow
along an anon window
platform that's a good good thing to
start with there's also a patreon page
you want to support this video series
that's a very nice thing to do and we
have a subscription there you can you
can pledge to and we also have a tweet
bought that tweet the schedule do so if
you want to catch the series live that's
the thing to check out for now have fun
with all of the e3 craziest that's going
on I hope see you guys back here
tomorrow same time same place 5 Pacific
5 p.m. pacific daylight time on twitch
and and yeah we'll be right back with
our asset stuff which seems to be going
pretty well so I feel like we should
probably be able to wrap it up fairly
quickly and maybe we can spend the rest
of the week just looking at how we want
our asset files to be structured and
stuff like that so thanks everyone for
tuning in and I will catch you tomorrow