hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero show where we could a complete-game
live on stream I kind of realized after
yesterday's stream I was like you know
what I'm I'm putting the cart before the
horse here and I realized that like we
had already optimized that part of the
code that we were looking at the
specular to diffuse transform we'd
already kind of gotten that down to a
fairly low amount of work and although
we could lower it further to be certain
I think it was probably the wrong time
to do it so if you take a look at where
we're at currently in our lighting
experiments here you can see we've
gotten this down to 12% of the total
time and the cast is still at 80% so I
was thinking like you know probably at
this point we're gonna have to start
looking at the casting a little bit more
aggressively and that's probably what we
should be focusing on rather than what
we were focusing on which was further
optimizing that particular piece of the
spec diffuse transform there so we
should probably do that and that's what
we should probably start looking at
today because that's gonna be the more
important thing to look at now the other
thing I realized is that if we go into
one of our largest rooms which is here I
also think probably at the very least
you know if we if we kind of pull back
on this and take a look at where we wrap
we probably have a lighting box that is
maybe also still a little too big we
could probably shrink the lighting
bounds down because this is the largest
kind of view will ever have is like this
and you know this is still probably
larger than we need it to be especially
if we slide it along and so we may also
be able to say look you know in terms of
the total amount of space that we need
here we might also be able to even at
the same resolution drop the total
amount of lighting region down a little
bit right that or we can change the size
right and so maybe the thing is you know
maybe this is something we should still
strive to do about this much but we
could make the size smaller so for
example
if we go into the lining code and we
look at how this is being aligned so we
look at like how we're actually building
up the the region where this is going to
be then in here you know we can sort of
say well we could make it you know we
could shrink this down by two or
something like that because it does have
to currently be aligned to the world so
it could be some other multiple of the
world you know or we could also just
make it be less and I don't know which
one we want to do but you know for
example I could imagine dropping this
town or even dropping like just the Y so
you could imagine doing something like
this and if we did something like this
where we were like 32 24 16 so where the
Y is actually a little bit different and
I don't actually know we've never tested
changing those two so we don't actually
know if there's bugs in that as well but
if you look at the effects of that on
runtime you can see that the more we
drop that down the closer we get to 30
frames a second and the closer we get to
30 frames a second that's a shippable
frame rate and it also gives us a lot
better chance of optimizing 260 right so
if we take a look at how that fits the
region it fits the region still pretty
good right and so you know we can
continue to shrink this down and have a
you know we can continue to make this
fairly we can continue to make this
fairly tight as a bound on the world and
I don't think that there's much of a
problem with that so we may want to just
like keep that bound as tight as we can
because again that just improves our
chances of getting a good frame rate
with quality lighting because the less
lighting we're computing every frame the
better and off we go
so what I might want to do now is say
all right how let's try to actually
position this thing around the actual
view right because right now you can see
the view sliding around like this is
what we'd be seeing in-game and like the
as the view would be sliding around here
this is not moving at all right so what
I might want to do is go in here and say
inside the world mode like let's try and
draw the camera like focus point like
where we're actually you know let's try
and figure out like what are we actually
looking at here frustum
and see if we can figure out how to
bound the lighting
you know align the lighting as closely
as possible to what we're actually going
to see because that's pretty important
right so if we take a look at how this
is going you can actually see here that
there's some stuff that's if zeroed out
regarding that right like here's some
like light bound nonsense right you can
see here us we were doing some things
here right so at the moment we're doing
the light bound stuff inside the begin
letting computation entirely but before
we had done some things here that was
related to it right and you can see we
have a world camera wreck that's being
sort of get-get out here which is the
get camera rectangle at Target and so
what I'd like to do is resurrect at
least just that one part of it there so
that we can maybe start to see about
where are we actually looking so I'm
gonna try and get this function working
better because I don't think we ever
really got it working and so I'd like to
do is pull out what we think this camera
rectangle actually is and just draw it
and then I'm gonna try and get the
lighting bounds to chase that visual
rectangle more closely so if we take a
look at the push volume outline clock
here right you can see that we're
drawing one the hot voxel rect in here
I'm gonna also draw at the same time I
want to draw the visible rectangle so we
can see that one two right okay so in
here right before we do the lightning
computation and again these colors don't
actually work cuz we don't have a way to
turn off lighting at the moment
eventually we will we haven't gotten
there yet so we're gonna go ahead and
push a volume outline here the hot voxel
rect is not what we want to draw
obviously what we want to draw is that
world camera rect and what we want to do
is take the world camera rectangle oh
wait we need the focus see there and you
can see this is this is probably garbage
I don't know maybe it's not but we'll
see you in a second
so what we want to do is take that that
camera figure out where it's looking and
try to actually get an accurate picture
of what we're actually seeing
so here's me drawing that right and now
you can see like as I move around you
can see those bounds moving with me and
the problem that we have now is I don't
know that these bounds are particularly
accurate right and so what we need to do
now is figure out what you know how to
make that be really closely tied to
where the screen is
so let's actually see if we can do that
so you see right now you can see how
it's it's actually like it's sort of
correct in a sense but it's a little bit
under like it's it's a little bit not
concerned we need some conservative I
guess is the word here we need something
that we can never actually see this part
of it so it's not giving us a large
enough screen rectangle it is now
correctly moving with us so we've got
that part right
it is like it does appear to be locked
to the camera position and that's great
but what it doesn't seem to do at the
moment is actually kind of give us the
size now one thing I guess now that I
think about it is since we can't change
the size of the lighting thing maybe I
actually don't care I guess we only
really need the centroid of this thing
right
so I guess actually now I think about I
don't have to really modify that what I
could do is say look we know that the
world camera rect actually does give us
a center okay so maybe that's all we
need
seems likely so I'm gonna go ahead and
say all right in here we've got a world
position for the origin P and then we've
got this camera offset from origin that
we're passing down and I guess when we
get this world camera rect here that is
giving us a good enough a good enough
piece of information there so I guess we
don't really need to pass this down the
camera offset from origins not being
used at the moment right yeah so we
could say like a camera center
[Music]
from origin someone I don't know camera
Center offset something like that and
then we can do is just pass down the
center of this thing so we can just say
all right we'll pass simulation center
get rid of the delta from sim and we'll
say get center like so and we can just
pass the center of that bounding box and
that could give us where we want our
lighting to be centered so now one thing
we could do is just use that Center
immediately right we can do that but the
problem is if we do that we don't
actually have include me we're not
actually aligned to the world and what
you could see here is we need to be able
or I shouldn't say align throat we're
not aligned to light chunks we need this
thing to be aligned because otherwise as
it slides you would see the lighting
kind of slide across the cells in the
world so we want it to move by like
entire voxel cells you know I'm saying
and I guess to a certain extent I'm not
really sure why we cared that it was
aligned to the world per se but we might
want to keep that for some reasons about
like light leaking and so on we might
want to make it so that we're always
sort of snapped to the world grid as
well so I think we probably do want to
keep that but what we don't want to do
here is the this sort of stuff here
where we do the center moved thing I
think that now this whole thing has to
get unfortunately a lot more complicated
so we do need to know like all of this
information and we do need to do all of
this work but we have to take our inputs
where we're actually going to be moving
we have to be a lot more granular about
how we're moving we need to move by
world tiles probably not world chunks
that would be my assumption so we need
to actually be like very specific about
how we do this that's my thinking so
probably what we want to do here is just
say all right we've got the origin P and
we know that that's going to give us a
an offset and we probably need to do the
center moved stuff basically every frame
now not every
but anytime the camera moves so we it
has to be a per frame thing it means
that there's a lot more pressure on
block copy Atlas certainly and we're
gonna have to make sure that that
routine is nice and quick but hopefully
we can make sure that that's the case so
what we need to do here is say alright
this this idea where the center like
this part here is now not sufficient
this is actually going to be something
different which is like chunk moved
right and chunk moved is going to be
some one way in which we can have a
displacement but another way that we can
have a displacement is if the camera
Center offset changes enough as well
right so the first thing we want to do
is say all right voxels per chunk is
always on the table because we're gonna
need to know that piece of inference
that's not actually true I tell you back
I suppose we only need to know that if
this happened so all right so if we have
an origin change like before we do need
to adjust for that so that's fine and we
do have like a you know a or you know D
origin chunk sort of operation that's
happening here right and so we're going
to want to do some kind of a summation
where we say all right we've got a D you
know something like D voxel right and it
starts off at nothing and in this
particular case we then know that we're
going to have to take our D voxel and
add to it however much the offset would
have been for this right so we we need
the chunk moved to occur properly and we
need that to do you know to do this
right and I guess I don't know that we
need to save this variable either so we
could probably just make this a little
simpler by saying look let's go ahead
and just make this path happen whenever
this is not true and then once that's
done once this has finished then we need
to say that from there we need to adjust
for the camera center offset right
and at the end here where we have D
voxel really what I want to do here is
just check to see if any of these are
nonzero so all I'm doing here is saying
all right let's break this up into two
stages one that does the offset for the
center and one that does a check to see
if there is any changes and then does
the block copy and that will set me up
in here for adding an additional way of
sliding the voxel around that's based on
the camera position so let's take a look
at what we need to do here for D voxel
um this is the origin chunk and it looks
like we don't have a + equals that you
yeah it's true
and so that should just work the same
way you know there shouldn't be any
difference so if we take a look at what
happens now that hopefully nothing like
broke right and it looks looks about
right
you know those copies like the lighting
there say it's stable as it moved right
so that seems fine and then what I need
is I need to be able to and you know I
may have been pretty mature about this
because we may need to do the second
part as well but either way sorry my
eyes itchy
allergy season this is why I can't go
outside I have such a eyes I definitely
get the corona virus anyway so basically
what I need to do here is I need to say
if the camera Center offset was
different I'm going to have to also
account for that so we need to take a
look at the camera offset center and see
if that meaningfully changed one way or
the other now I don't actually know
how we should do this exactly because we
kind of also need to track what this
offset would be so I think I guess what
so I guess what we'd probably want to do
yeah I think I was pretty mature with
this I guess what we probably want to do
the easiest way I think to do this and
maybe we'll see an easier way to do it
in a second but we probably want to do
an if Center changed and then process
the center change and then do as if
Center changed like or kind of a thing
where we compute a voxel offset if the
camera Center offset changed right and
then we do something like this where we
account for the change here so let's see
what we would need to do there if the
previous voxel was centered around a
particular camera Center offset all we
really need to do is figure out like how
many voxels we need to offset to get to
the current camera center and that
should be pretty simple right it's just
yet another you know flooring function
probably or we can do a rounding
function doesn't really matter but
basically what we would say is like you
know the camera you know the the camera
offset or chunk or you know voxel camera
offset something like this it's gonna be
the camera center offset and it's gonna
be using the sort of inverse of the
voxel seldom so whatever the voxel
seldom was and I thought we had an
influx seldom here am I wrong about that
so we have an inbox seldom why is this a
divided instead of a multiple why not
use in box seldom here so this is I
don't know what's going on here we
probably just didn't have the time or
got or I don't know what but we can just
multiply by the inverse cell dim and
then basically the round of that right
and I assume we have
no we don't actually all right so I'm
gonna go ahead and see if we can't just
add something that rounds a whole vector
at once because if we have some that
rounds a whole vector at once then these
equations get easier for people to read
right so like for example if I want to
compute a a V scope there it is so we
have a floor 2 V 3 s right so we should
also just have a round 2 V 3 s like this
and then then we can just go ahead and
call that on moss so this can just be
you know a simple rounding function
round real 32 in 32
oops nope sorry round 2 yes so once we
reduce this and say okay how many cells
is it we can then round it to an offset
and now we have however much the offset
should be and in this case we would then
add that to the total offset we need to
compute and we this is the amount of
movement that would be required because
of that offset and I guess now that I
think about it so I got a slate back on
the back and forth on this I guess if we
just saved the previous offset we could
change we could did look to see what the
difference between the two values
actually ends up being and only produce
a change if necessary
so I guess actually we we really don't
need this so I guess we would just say
look here's the voxel camera offset we'd
look at voxel camera offset here and say
you know if not are equal then we
actually do the difference so in here
the D voxel in this case is just the
difference between these two and off we
go now I think that also means we
probably want to news 0 so we could be
like a DVR camera offset something like
this I guess where we just say oh ok
what we really could just say
if is not is zero right and that would
just allow us to do a direct ad so we
could say okay here's the old one here's
the new one that's the Delta and then
after we're done we just save it and
then we could just say look if there's
any difference here then we need to do
the block copy otherwise we don't need
to do the block copy right yet another
way to look at it would be is we always
do the block copy if the you know we
could actually put in if here you know
if nonzero but it doesn't seem worth it
so hmm all I really need to do there is
save whatever the voxel camera offset
actually is and then I think we're okay
um yeah that seems rights
yeah this has to be a Hadamard product
obviously cuz it's you know it's a
vector product and we don't actually
assume that that vector product is a
particular thing we don't know if it's a
dot product or Hadamard product or cross
product so we make you say which one it
is it's not the same as in shaders but
you know what do you do um so yeah I
don't know that I thought that through
properly right in fact I think I
probably didn't cuz I saw some flickery
in this there but let's just take a look
at what happens first just to get a
sense of it you can kind of see there's
a little bit too much jerking around
there so it looks like it's not quite it
looks like it's going like rather than
then copying forward it almost looks
like it's copying backwards like it
maybe I had like I did the math wrong or
something so I'm not sure exactly what's
going on there so if you take a look at
what I'm doing maybe we can see if
there's a bug in there in theory this
part of the code is not happening right
so you know in other words if I just
look at what's happening in well I guess
that's big enough that the simulation
center changes so but if I go to like
say a scrolling room so let's go over to
here right so the simulation center now
is not changing right the only thing
that's happening is the scrolling is
occurring right see and so in theory the
first part of the code this part of the
code is not involved so the only thing
that's happening now is just this and
you can see here that this camera offset
here is basically saying like all right
hold on a second I mean take a drink
here
so here we're basically saying look
let's figure out how many of these there
are and we'll do a round and that's
where we'll put this thing so the inbox
seldom should tell us how many cells we
want to get to the camera Center and
then the Delta between those we're just
subtracting like what that desired
amount is versus what the amount we last
applied was right and I can't I mean I
can't see what the flaws in that logic
I'm trying to think seems about right
we then have the D voxel which is saying
look this is the amount we're gonna sum
so if we had any of that that we needed
to do we're gonna do it now right we
then save whatever it was that we
thought the offset should be so that we
won't do it again on the next frame
right and again I can't really see why
that's creating sort of the weirdness
that I'm seeing because it should I
would think just as it slides if it's
doing the correct copy you wouldn't see
any change at all except around the
edges right because all it's doing is
moving one cell forward and then copying
one cell but maybe I'm misunderstanding
like what this actually means right like
oh you know what though here's the
problem is that the Vox min corner is
never actually okay is not itself moving
right so what we actually need to do
here is take whatever the voxel camera
offset is like floored basically and use
that amount so this voxel camera offset
here has to actually be factored in here
right meaning we have to have
this this voxel camera offset here
however much removing has to be taken
into account so hmm
so I guess what we want to say is that
the actual starting location right is
you know the negative of the origin here
plus the voxel camera offset times the
cell dim right and I think that's
correct
could be wrong about that what's the
problem here no acceptable conversion
app keep living in shader land there we
go all right
so again not quite what we would expect
let me see am I thinking about this
wrong
let me also I'm gonna pull this out so
this is the origin offset for camera
oops yeah and so yeah the center we've
moved by that much so it should be as it
should be negative as well right and so
I think wherever the min corner hot is
it's it's gonna be whatever that you
know value actually is right because
that's the amount of of Delta that we
applied so let me just take a look at
what movement is happening if I actually
run this and zoom out I should be able
to see like
so it's actually going the wrong way so
I'm I have this backwards in my head
somehow I guess meaning that this value
should actually be positive on the
outside and I'm to be honest I'm not
really sure I understand why I'll have
to think that through but basically what
that implies is that it's actually going
the other way let me just see if that's
actually true yeah hmm
so why we need to go draw this out on
the blackboard because I don't really
get that like I'm these sorts of origin
things are always very Squinkie so I'm
not surprised I don't get it but at the
same time I want to make sure that I'm
not missing some other thing because if
something goes the opposite direction I
think it means my mental models wrong
and that's not great right okay so now
if we actually go in here and look at
the view I'm hoping that we won't see a
lot of lighting errors visible lighting
errors and we'll see you know I don't
know to what extent that'll be true but
we'll check it out so we do see some
weirdness here we're seeing some like
weird beat frequency out there what's
what's going on with that so this is
still like totally broken though to a
certain extent if this is if this is the
camera center why is this so far over
here like that's just not the way that
the lighting should be aligned right so
you can see there's some other bug as
well like yes it's moving but it's not
moving correctly
so yeah it's still not centering the
lighting region so what am I doing wrong
there because I'm obviously doing
something wrong there what's the deal
with that something's wrong so there's a
couple things that could be wrong now
about it in addition to the fact that
this is not the sign that I thought it
was there's also the fact that I guess
I'm not sure what happens when this
changes you know and now we don't know
what this offset should necessarily be
so I don't know like if it makes more
sense to say like I'm onna I'm curious
again just exploring this if I set this
to zero so that now it reapplies the
Delta like whole cloth basically mm-hmm
that shouldn't be right so again this is
kind of me just looking to see oops this
is me looking to see whether I'm just
like totally floating out in space with
my conception how this works because
this should be worse right and if this
is better then that's yet another thing
I don't understand
yeah so that's not that's not better
okay good
so I only have one thing I understand
all right so yeah fundamentally right
now we're just getting some weird like I
don't really understand where that why
we're not getting more of an offset on
the lighting like why is the X Y is the
lighting not sliding over in X right
because we want this to be the center
and this was the center so we need Oh
so the sign is wrong here we want this
to be the center don't we so let me
think about how this is working here so
first of all block copy of Atlas I don't
know what the D yeah so we here okay
let's start from the beginning I need to
document what this means because D voxel
doesn't really make any sense what does
that mean it's like is it gonna move it
in that direction or backwards right and
I don't know all right so if we look at
what's happening here and we want to do
a copy tile we copy from the D voxel to
where we are so I think now we're sort
of getting to the point where which
which is what I didn't understand so if
we look at what's going on there the
devoxx hole is actually telling us how
far to grab the next tile from that
means that the entire voxel will
actually shift by the opposite of D
voxel right so yeah we got to start with
that understanding so block copy atlas
really needs to document what this is so
this value should probably not be called
D voxel it should probably be like fetch
offset or something like that so it's
where you will fetch the the voxel from
when you're actually doing your Delta
right and that's why the copy tile here
right is look I'm fetching from whatever
this Delta tells me to fetch
and I'm getting this putting that in the
destination that means if you looked at
the Vauxhall and you were just like
visualizing just the voxel then if it if
you gave it a plus X you would actually
see a negative X translation because
it's fetching from the negative of of
that thing
right so it's important to understand
what this is and I think we just want to
make that clear something like that and
that way we now have a comment in there
that says blah copy Atlas does this
particular operation so we're not
confused about what it should be right
so D voxel is basically you know inverse
D voxel I mean I don't know how you want
to look at that but it's kind of a
little bit you know it's Squinkie and I
suppose calling it D voxel is maybe a
good idea at that point because it's
like kind of an ambiguous term and so it
encourages you to actually read about
what it's going to be used for all right
so if we look here and we say we know
that the origin is getting you displaced
a certain amount you can see that's why
we're doing the subtraction in this
order it's because D voxel itself is
sort of inverted as to the direction the
voxel slide so this has to be talking
about the place you want to put the
origin which are going to invert the
direction you would slide things I don't
know that that makes a lot of sense to
do it that way but that is how we were
doing it right so then if we look at box
I'll camera offset
we're saying well in addition to the
location of the origin we're also going
to have to move around a thing that says
where the camera is relative to the
origin right and in theory we could
actually I suppose we could make it so
that we recompute you know it and now
that I think about it so here's a
question for everyone do I even need to
do this so here's a question if we go
look at the world position we have a way
to canonicalize things right so if we
actually just used that so we could just
say look here's our world position and
we want to reckon annika lies it right
couldn't we just do that
so like this call here like this
couldn't we just call that and not do a
secondary one of these I think I may
have just done something stupid so let's
suppose we just don't do this any of
this
right so let's suppose we actually did
this so we actually don't care about any
of this stuff right would this actually
be sufficient if we just used the chunk
space map and maybe it won't be like
we'll check it out in a second but
suppose that that was all I did so begin
lighting computation actually when we
call it we just move the thing into
chunk space first so we say get the
center of the world rect and we
basically say like you know world
position lighting Center equals whatever
the current simulation center is we then
say lighting Center offset plus equals
get center world camera rect and then we
just say or actually I guess we don't do
that nevermind we just say map into
chunk space and in here we put the get
center world camera rect so we just
produce the lighting center as its own
world position and let that flow through
this I don't know if that's resolute
enough but it might be and then we
wouldn't have to even have a secondary
code path there right so I think that
needs the world probably I'm guessing I
don't actually know yeah so I'm curious
if that just solves the problem it might
not really know let's take a look whoa
so again really strange I don't
understand why that motion is happening
counter so we've got we've got issues
here I also don't see why that whatever
I just changed should have created that
like making things brighter right like
what happened there you you saw what I
was talking about so if in here if I
literally just do this right
lighting is normal if now I do this
lighting is nuts right so again like
something weird is happening here I
don't really know what and so we've got
a lot of issues now and we need to
figure out like what the heck is
happening at this point that doesn't
need to still be there but we've got
some really weird stuff happening here
so we've got bugs and I guess this is
good we have a pretty obvious like a
test case where we can take a look at
what's happening but so in here in begin
lighting computation I want to go ahead
and see like what's happening here
because I guess this must be triggering
more often I mean that's the only thing
I can think of meaning if this is not
happening I'm assuming what this is
crazy so just the act of passing down a
slightly different Center made that
happen so we're in like nonsense Ville
at this point so we've got issues and it
could be this is well actually no I
don't really know so this is going to be
interesting and I guess we'll see so
here let's go ahead and investigate
further
so that's fascinating and I have no idea
what's going on so I guess we'll learn
something in a minute here so if we have
the lighting offs that getting passed
down on each frame like so light fills
up the entire area almost like there's a
copy bug or something also we can get
rid of this let's suppose I turn this
off I'm assuming that now that it's done
it will never undo itself but I don't
even know that
and so the weird part about that is it
doesn't even look like it's a different
materially different Lighting's scenario
either right so let me just see what
happens if I move this now does this
shift at all I mean barely that's a
puzzler wow that's just a real puzzler I
have a literally no idea what's going on
there at all all right so we're gonna
have to kind of dig in here and do some
sleuthing cuz that's just totally
bizarre I have no idea what that's doing
even a little bit I don't know why those
two things would be related because
again it doesn't really look like
there's any particular way that that
would affect the lighting so something
is super weird probably just a bug
somewhere that we are not catching right
so let's just take a quick look here and
see what's going on when we look at like
the cell count you know all this stuff
makes reasonable sense right we're just
looking at how big the the voxel itself
is going to be and when we're creating
the rectangle itself we're just you know
we're just producing exactly what you
would expect and then we're drawing it
here right when we set the lighting
bounds we're just saying the region in
which the lighting would occur that
doesn't really make much sense anyway
[Music]
and I don't see anything weird going on
there
so yeah that's totally I mean I again I
really don't see what's what's
particularly weird about that I don't
really see what's particularly worried
about that
so again just trying to get clues about
even where to look for what we have for
bugs here if I pull out and we look at
what happens when I for example jump up
there you can see too that it definitely
it basically like counter it counter
moves the direction you would think it
should move right the center of the
lighting region should be around this
and it actually goes the opposite way it
would need to go to get there right and
if you look at what's happening in here
for chasing the chunk origin I don't see
why that would actually be the case you
know what I mean
in here for the voxel cells perch uncle
we're just producing how many voxel
cells you move for every world chunk in
here we're saying when the origin moved
it moved from here to here so this is
the number of chunks you would go if you
were walking in that direction now
granted that kind of seems backwards to
me like I said so that's if I was
standing on one and I wanted to walk to
the next one that's where I would go
right and that seems backwards because
actually when you're going to shift for
the origin you want to invert that but I
guess because this was inverted you know
because this is getting inverted that's
what's happening I guess now since I
don't actually know that I want to again
just investigation wise I want to I want
to see what happens if we do an opposite
movement and then I kind of want to walk
this work this out on paper I'll do it
up here we should probably add an
operator negative there but
and again this is just for me to try and
figure out like are we doing this
backwards or aren't we and then I want
to write it out to figure out like what
the heck
and again it's just yeah I'm so confused
I literally have no idea what the heck's
going on I'm I'm totally lost so let's
go ahead and start from square one and
see if we can understand what the heck
is happening so
here's the 588 here's the de 588
blackboard and like this is just like
what is happening so again this is why
origin centers are so difficult to do
you can see why everyone just wants to
throw everything into doubles but I
actually find it's pretty good to work
these through because these are the
kinds of problems you should get
mentally flexible enough to handle plus
doubles are slow anyway so if we
actually look at what's going on here
here's what we have we know that we have
a simulation center and we know that
around this simulation center we have a
world that's been constructed somehow
right so you know we've got various
pieces of the world that are out here
and you know maybe we have a chunk and
the chunk has some offset from the
simulation center and inside that chunk
there's you know some floor tiles or who
knows what's in there and one of these
floor tiles has lighting you know all of
them do and that lighting is lined up
with our voxel so our voxel is somewhere
in the world right and its location is
also based on the simulation center it's
some offset from the simulation center
okay
so now what's gonna happen is the
simulation center itself is going to
move right it's going to move somewhere
so like it moves you know off to some
location right and what's gonna happen
is the simulation center moves the
offset of the chunk is going to change
relative to the simulation center in
world space right because this this
offset and this offset are different so
you know we want
to appear to be like in the same place
or something
so the actual practical offset for
rendering is different because in one
case you know let's say this was s0 and
this is s1 and this is the chunk
position so chunk zeroes position on in
the actual like rendering pipeline is
going to be s 0 plus or I should say c0
prime is s 0 plus C 0 and C 1 prime is s
1 plus C 1 right there are like totally
different equations here because as you
move the simulation center the offset is
going to change completely to render
this thing whatever you're rendering
even if the camera position is the same
in terms of what you see you've changed
the coordinates out from under yourself
right so they're completely different
alright so if we want the voxel right to
be positioned in the same place as it
used to be positioned when the camera
changes or I should say when the
simulation center changes we previously
had something like well you know the
voxel and I guess we should say
something else here so this is actually
constructing the answer in an absolute
space what we actually render is just
these right so this is the basis and the
basis goes away because it's just
assumed to be 0 you know I'm saying
this is so hard to even write down
what's going on all right so if we now
want this to slide properly right and we
want this to align itself properly we
want the voxel to align itself properly
then when we change one of these we're
effectively asking the same question
we're basically saying like okay we have
a V zero Prime somewhere and that was
the s zero plus the V zero and now we
want to produce a new one and that's
going to be like some new offset that
gets us to the same apparent visual
location right in in both cases and so
if we want like if we want these two
things to be the same at the end of the
day we would have to solve this right
we'd say we want these two things to be
equal and so solving for like V one it
would have to be like s 0 minus s 1 plus
V 0 equals V 1 right so the change in
coordinates here plus the old offset is
what we would now have as a new offset
it would seem and that's like where the
voxel would end up that's where the
voxels you know Corner would be and so
what we're trying to do here
fundamentally is we're trying to just
account for this space has changed right
and furthermore like when I look at this
when we do this basis change
[Music]
I mean even just thinking about this it
doesn't really make much sense the way
I'm doing this even now so hmm
let's take this one step further now I
think about it
so this origin P here is just like where
I want to build the thing around so when
we pass in this value this simulation
center value what I don't totally
understand is why can't we get we need
this this hot voxel rect to start being
centered around the actual origin here
so this origin P that comes in this
origin P offset right minus 305 hot dim
that we should be able to focus on that
and that should always track whatever
we're drawing out here right this
lighting center bit right because the
lighting center if we take the
simulation center and we get whatever
the world camera wrecks location should
be for its its center and we base
something around that that should always
be drawing in the correct place so what
that's the first thing we need to figure
out what has gone wrong because
something has definitely gone wrong here
right this value when we look at
whatever the render offset is that
that's what's screwing us up here right
so yeah let's figure out what's going on
so if we always did if we always do this
where we're just passing the simulation
center what we would expect to see is we
would expect to see the lighting region
which is that to be centered around
wherever the simulation center is and
let's draw that - so where is that that
thing sim bounds right so I'm gonna push
the sim bounds on here as well and just
look at them
all right so what we would expect to see
now and I don't actually know if we will
see it okay so we don't okay so
basically we're doing this wrong even
before we start so there's the
simulation bounds right and here's the
lighting bounds it's just totally wrong
because this should always be centered
the lighting band should always always
be centered around the simulation center
it's not so somebody needs to explain to
me how the heck that's happening right
so so our problem extends well beyond
what I thought it did we're just like
we're often no-man's land here so when
we do begin learning computation and we
push the box that we push the hot voxel
rectangle you know out here so this is
somehow garbage right and I I don't
understand why I literally have no idea
why this is wrong because in theory that
should be centered about the same
location that the simulation center is
because it should just be drawn at the
same location right so how is this
possible
what what is happening it doesn't make
any sense
so in this case it's interesting our rec
center Tim this is actually not using
the offset of the sim bounds is that
actually wrong for starters because in
theory the sim bounds like yeah you know
in theory the sim bounds would take the
similar occasion offset right it's not
ever supposed to be at least I don't
think it's ever supposed to be anything
other than zero but we should verify
that at the very least right oh well to
be fair what is the why is it camera dot
simulation center so yeah maybe we've
just got too many variables in here
meaning different things because when we
come through this code here we create a
simulation center that we actually use
for the world sim what are we passing to
that right
so here's begin sim and it is passing
world mode camera simulation center so I
mean that's the right thing right I mean
if you actually look at what's happening
so we just double check but that should
be zero anyway so I don't think that
should have done anything yeah and it
didn't so if this wrecked centre dim is
if they're centered around here we know
that we're passing that literal value
like that is literally the value that is
getting passed down exactly right
is there an offset applied to this
render group perhaps that we're not
understanding I mean I guess that could
be but if there was it would be the same
it would be applied here as well
right so that doesn't really make a
whole lot of sense either so if we then
move and say all right here's the sim
bounce we know the sim Bonds is just a
rec centre dim where it does you know it
picks the center this should be zero
huh I mean I got nothing
those should be exactly the same the
Centers of these two rectangles should
be exactly the same right so let's try
one other thing just to see if we're
just off in this like I mean I don't
know what's good no idea what's going on
right now
might as well be someone else's code
base at this point so let's just try a
rec center dim em and we'll say all
right the rec center dam is just going
to be the negative P or so the center
point we're doing here
and then we just are gonna make a
something that's just like one by one by
one so we're just drawing like a little
cube right at the center that we think
we are I'm gonna have to make it a
little bigger I guess
okay so there's my center cube
it's totally garbage right it is not
even remotely centered around the
simulation center even a little bit so
now I'm gonna take the exact same piece
of code right like literally the exact
same piece of code that's the hot voxel
rector right I'm going to take the exact
same piece of code and I'm gonna move it
out here so and do push volume outline
I'm gonna pass the negative simulation
center and yeah I'm just gonna literally
call that code and we're gonna see where
that ends up
all right so that is actually in the
wrong place as well yeah yeah okay so
basically the problem is the this
negation I think that's all there is to
it this is supposed to be putting you at
the correct offset from the camera
we're negating it for no real reason I
guess we just threw a negative in there
I don't know why so if we draw the
symbols and then we draw I don't need
this anymore
we draw the rec center gym at this
offset which is actually putting us into
the correct location that should draw it
in the center would be my argument in
theory assuming I actually draw it okay
at least now we're back to sanity so
that's fine so that means the Vox mid
corner hot was always incorrect this was
not supposed to be there which I don't
think really necessarily should have
made a difference but the weird part is
I guess I hadn't been considering the
fact that it would actually contain some
content and I guess it does right what
I'm not sure about is that we actually
want to use that though because if we
use that that's sliding continuously and
we'll be wrong but I'm gonna put that in
for a second anyway right so if we get
rid of this and change this to not
having the negative I'm going to go
ahead and draw all our rectangles again
I think we have found the rogue negative
that was causing us problems
okay so now when I move around at least
in theory we should have things more
centered at the moment and let's see if
we actually do so yes there's the
lighting voxel there's the sim region
and they are basically the same now I'm
noticing that actually the sim region is
narrower here then the lighting voxel so
I guess that doesn't really make any
sense and we should probably trim that
down I don't really know why or how
that's happening but you know we maybe
that we should actually widen the same
region I'm not sure doesn't really
matter anyway if you take a look at
what's happening here as I'm moving
around those two are now nicely in
lockstep so thank God that was just a
momentary like you know errant negative
ruining our day so now if we actually
want to figure out where the Vox min
corner is going to be we should be okay
to now pass down a moving value right so
now as we move I think we should allow
be able to allow this to slide yeah and
we can right so you see how the
Lightning voxel is now sliding along it
seems like it is right and that's good
however it's weird to you that we get
that weird like sampling error but
however you'll notice we also do still
have a weirdness here which is that
which is that our lighting voxel is
still not centered the way I would think
it should be right it's not centered
around this so what's happening so let's
narrow down to that now because that's
the next part of this problem so now if
we say look we want to Center ourselves
around the world camera rect instead
this should allow us to do that right by
figuring out where that actual center is
I would think and I guess the problem is
in order to draw this we need to know
what the offset is from the actual
simulation center right so I guess this
is mostly a drawing offset problem so if
we then say here's the lighting bounds
like this what we want to now do is this
needs to kind of be drawn out here right
and it needs to be offset it needs to it
needs to be subtracted so we know where
it actually is right so the hot voxel
rectangle in this case now yeah well I
guess we get still drawn in here because
I guess this is where it's being set so
I guess we do need one additional piece
of information which is like the sim
origin P which we were getting past
before right so this is the thing that
determines what we're actually storing
as we move around but then where this
actually is in world space if we want to
place it in world space actually has to
be a subtract right
so it actually has to be this
to place us relative to the world space
in order to draw the thing and send it
to the graphics card so we just didn't
have actually the information we needed
to begin with I guess that was just like
yeah not thinking it through so we need
to pass down both of these the sim
origin P and like where were actually
want the lighting to be solved and then
we can do the rest of the work that we
needed to do I don't actually remember
what this is called ah so this requires
a world but we have that doesn't it call
subtract I guess this is not exposed at
the moment no user defined conversion
available sorry about that I will pass
addresses alright so now let's get this
thing drawing in the right place which
hopefully it will looks correct
so that looks correct to me now
again the copying looks totally messed
up but at least now the voxel is moving
the way that I would expect the voxel to
be moving right so you can see the
camera bounds in the center there and
like the voxel is locked to it so that's
good so now we just have to figure out
how to copy these properly and then also
why we're getting the weird light
explosion that doesn't really make a
whole lot of sense to me so something's
busted there if we now move throughout
the world though other than that like
sort of bug
it seemed which is the copying bug it
seems like at least we're seeing the
right stuff I would point out that we
still have some kind of weirdness going
on with a simulation region like the
fact that I don't see like when you move
back here like the fact that the
simulation region doesn't slide forwards
as fast as or maybe the simulations just
isn't large as large as it should be you
know what I mean so it feels like the
simulation engine region needs to be
expanded a little bit like one more room
in that direction if we take a look at
the where we do this in bounds
in here it feels like this or something
is not quite right and I don't really
know the best way to fix that but maybe
this
so now the symbols are expanded a little
bit there and I just wanted to do that
to make sure that like we have enough of
the simulation region always loaded in
around the player which seems good right
so there we go
all right so now we have the question of
why are we getting this weird like copy
error and it seems like at the moment
the primary problem again is the like
the the copy seems to be mostly having
well actually seems like it's always
wrong
it seems like it's not copying for this
camera slide at all right all right
so anyway let's go ahead and finish up
what we're doing here so this camera
slide now has to be actually prevented
from doing a full slide meaning this
subtract has to actually only happen on
it has to be zeroed out to the chunk
boundary now that doesn't seem
particularly hard to do because in
theory the origin P here now can just be
truncated down so for example we could
just say like the origin P offset is 0
or something right
and I think that would lock this to
moving only per chunk so now as this
moves right I think
yeah you can see now it moves kind of
discreetly right the problem with that
is again so now we've gotten to the
point that I was wondering about before
and it looks like the answer is yeah it
doesn't really work and that's that like
the the chunk granularity is probably
too low like we probably need it to do
the lighting on something tighter than
that you know I'm saying so that gets us
back in the business now of saying all
right now we actually have to look at
voxel centers as well which is pretty
annoying right but that's what we're
gonna have to do so what we're gonna
have to have here is like a secondary
offset that tells us how much because it
looks like actually that now is working
properly right to a certain extent I
mean it's hard to say but looks roughly
correct those I'm not seeing those I'm
not seeing any lighting bugs other than
when we're catching up to the lighting
region right like the rest of the
lighting doesn't doesn't freak out you
know I'm saying
so I think all we really need to do now
is just track that offset correctly and
then I think we're in good shape
so it seems like we have like weird
light leaking bugs though just yeah we
there's interesting things that happen
with the lighting word like it gets over
bright so we've got plenty of stuff to
debug here but at least the copy you
know the copying seems okay we can sort
of narrow in on all the bugs as we go
alright so that seems pretty good and so
the question now is how do we get the
something more granular so basically we
don't really want this offset to
actually drop to zero here that's not
good so what we need to do is we do need
to do the thing we were talking about
before where we need to say like okay
whatever this origin P is that we're
getting in here if this actually needs
to be sort of truncated down to
something some other thing whatever that
other thing is and we need to do this
more often than just when they're in the
same chunk so it's true that we need to
do it when they you know it's true that
we need to do it whenever the center
does move but we also need to do it
whenever the origin offset part changes
sufficiently to produce a different
offset there right and I'm not sure I'm
not sure exactly how to make this work
out properly so we need to do the base
the same thing we were doing before
which is to say that like the origin P
offset should drop to zero and we should
just save whatever it was probably right
so we probably just want to keep this
and then remove it from further
consideration entirely the camera offset
then needs to go through like the d
camera offset bit so this is actually
going to be you know the Hadamard
product of the m seldom so we're gonna
say look how many of these are we
actually going to do and then we would
do our round so this is how far the
camera is offset based on what we got
told we then want to do our delta from
there so again we would probably just do
this and we would have our d voxel up
here so in theory this should not do
anything different now because we're
really not changing anything so if we
just some in the change for the center
we should be okay
yeah so that all looks fine and so now
we just need a way of accounting for
this camera offset and this is what we
were doing before it now this camera
offset is again like how far in addition
we would have to move besides just
accounting for the change in where the
chunks actually are right so we need to
move this far we need to slide the voxel
this much over as well so if that's our
camera offset in voxels I guess are this
is like I'm gonna call this box camera
offset I guess and then I'm gonna
actually produce a camera offset which
is the Vox camera offset times the cell
dim so basically just getting the exact
same value back but truncated to the
nearest voxel cell so now if I say where
the min corner actually is we would say
it's at this location plus the Vox
camera offset minus the centering right
what is the problem
all right and that's not Vox camera
offset that's just regular camera offset
and we're good all right so now we're
not actually sliding the voxel we're
just drawing it in a different place but
we're gonna see if we're drawing it in
the place we would want to draw it right
yeah so it looks like now it's properly
following but we're not actually moving
it right so we're not doing the devoxx
'el stuff properly at all like the d
voxels totally busted
so it's not copying the lighting but at
least now we're not off in like you know
no-man's land where we are not even sure
why the rectangles we're seeing on the
screen or where they are like we've
actually like got that down right all
right so now we need to like okay if
we're going like forward with this
camera offset we need to slide the voxel
so we need to slide the voxel back one
right so we need to when we do this we
need to know that we've changed this
camera offset now I don't I have to
think about how that interacts with this
because I don't really know but I feel
like it should just be the same all the
time right I feel like we should just be
able to do this and say if the so if the
camera off set went forward we need to
go backward would be the way I would
think of it think about it right so I
think that just means we can use the
same solution we were doing before
although I need to think about this so
again it's fetching from the plus so if
we are moving forward we need it to go
backward
so we know that block copy voxel it
let's just take the X direction so if
block copy voxel is going to be fed a
value of 1 then what we will see happen
in the voxel is a movement to the left
right because each cell will grab the
one one to the right of it which will
look like everything is moving to the
left so an output value of positive x
produces a negative X motion right so we
are going to move our camera offset
let's say it was it's self moving in the
positive x-direction so it's moving to
the right so the new one is higher than
the old one meaning subtraction you
would normally do would produce a
positive value as it slides to the left
we need it's moving it's I'm sorry as it
slides to the right it's moving the
voxels with it to the right so they need
to be slid back and to they need to be
slit slid back in the left direction to
count for that so I think it's right
I think that's all I got who knows um so
I think that slides the voxel to account
for the motion that's occurring there
but no promises this is just too many
things to keep in your head yeah
and in that worked properly right
alright so it took us a long time to get
there because man that was confusing but
I think this is right now I'm gonna go
turn off the debug drawing of those
light Maps
and also I guess I'll turn off some of
these volumes alright so this is now
what we would expect to sort of see
in-game in terms of the lighting and I
just want to see if I see any you know
weird errors or stuff like that with the
region
so that's looking pretty good now you
know and basically our lighting accuracy
and the computation of the lighting is
probably not super great at the moment
but now like you don't see any like bugs
with the fact that we have a roving
lighting region anymore like it looks
pretty reasonable as you're hopping
around like I'm not seeing any of those
cracks the lighting cracks anymore right
it just kind of looks really fluid and
so mostly I think what we've got now is
just light transmission equation
problems so like why is that light so
bright and things like that so I think
mostly what we need to look at now is
how to stabilize and make accurate those
lighting computations because everything
else now seems pretty good right but
this sort of lighting feedback weirdness
that seems like there's some weird
errors going on there and I don't know
what that's about
feels pretty good I'm liking it
all right so I don't know where we are
on time probably about ten minutes left
I guess but this is feeling pretty good
to me
and again this also is completely flat
cost now which is nice
meaning at the moment there is no cost
for light sources because we actually
don't even we can actually turn off the
build of the light volume hierarchy
thing because we don't even use it so
actually this means you can have
infinite lights or do it doesn't matter
but its main light sources as you want
you won't pay any additional costs for
them the the lighting is a flat fee if
you will and you can dump as many lights
as you want into the scene which is good
because I want a lot of that all right
[Music]
so I think basically I'm gonna end that
for now and then next weekend we'll
start to look at optimization of the ray
caster get that to as good as we can and
then we'll move from there to light
quality and that you know we're narrow
this is getting good
like I'm liking the look of this we need
to start putting in light collectors for
trees like right now we don't put any
actual light collector in there like we
need to to basically say like hey
there's a light collector there which is
pretty easy for us to do and right now
we don't so like like light can't bounce
off trees at all at the moment you know
what I mean
which it would you probably should
also we're not properly setting the
color of like walls and stuff so we got
some work to do on on what we feed in to
the lighting system that would make a
pretty big difference in quality as well
looking really great though I mean I'm
loving look at this I would like to
smooth out the way like I I would like
to make this look a little bit more
radial which I also think we probably
can do if we want to using a little bit
more the way that we're blending voxels
together could probably be changed to
produce a more pleasant look there so we
probably want but that's a pixel shader
thing that doesn't really have anything
to do with the lighting scheme also we
now have specular as well so we probably
want to find a way to take advantage of
that meaning we can have surfaces that
appear kind of shiny and we probably
want to have some way of getting that
into the game but anyway let's do Q&amp;A
how can we disable lighting for the
debug UI oh well it sort of is at the
moment but only because someone
requested a hack for it
so like at the moment it actually is but
it the reason that it is is because
someone just was like well since the Z
is weird you know just use the Z it's
not a particularly good solution but but
it already is doing that I think the
better way to do it is just have that
pass turn it off so there should just be
a thing in the render that's like this
is the the you know the lighting is only
on for this pass and it just uses a
differentiator
Wow really OBS is skipping frames due to
encoding lag are you sure about that how
sure are you of that
like at least on OBS it does not list
any dropped frames
so it I don't know like is it possible
that OBS is just doing something like
stupid like it's you know it's we're not
stupid
possibly intentional even is it possible
that like OBS is sending out like a
lower quality stream to twitch but
recording a good one locally or
something like this
okay so basically you're saying go to
view stats
oh yeah yeah skip frames due to encoding
lag 4.4%
hmm
I'm not sure how to fix that no the game
is not fighting OBS for the GPU because
it's running on a different machine
there are two separate machines this
this streaming machine is actually it's
just that it's the only thing that's
it's doing so
I mean that you know what the problem
might be here is that it has to do to
encoding z' like there's a streaming one
and like a recording one and I wonder if
there's a way to tell it just do one
thing and send them both out I actually
don't know how to tell it to do that to
be honest
yeah you know I don't even really know
how to tell it to not do that we'll have
to look at that a little more carefully
[Music]
so I don't really know how I would get
OBS to not drop frames I mean the other
thing too is I probably it's the thing
is I'm doing it at 60 frames a second
which I wasn't doing before so it's
recording at 60 frames a second and
streaming at 30 and maybe you just can't
maybe you can only record and stream
both at 30 and otherwise it's not fast
enough or something
I read a Twitter conversation from an
engine program rated software about the
engine for a new doom game not having a
main thread or render thread only tasks
and queues could you comment on this
architecture yeah that's kind of more or
less the standard architecture I would
say that like so you do need to like you
can't use OpenGL for example if you want
to do that it doesn't work you can use
d3 D or I think they use Vulcan they
might use both D 3d and Vulcan I don't
know which ones they use but OpenGL
doesn't really work if that makes sense
and so I guess what I would say is you
know as long as you have the ability to
do things like allocate graphics memory
for more than one thread this works ok
if you don't have that ability then
you're just kind of screwed and OpenGL
multi-threaded just doesn't work they
it's not it's not because it couldn't
it's because it doesn't if that makes
sense
like the drivers just are too buggy
well no but like so Valles the thing is
like looking at the stats on looking at
the stats on the actual OBS it says skip
frames due to encoding lag is 4.3
percent so it's just not fast enough at
encoding this video it's just I don't
know why what's weird though
is that like if I watched this if I
watched the number it's at 26 1 7 right
now and if I start hopping around like
so you can see it goes up only when the
screen goes up so it's it's literally
just the act of having too many Delta's
per frame is the thing that causes it to
miss and again I really don't know what
to do about that
let me see what's going on GPU I mean
CPU wise I think the problem is this
machine doesn't have a dedicated GPU
that could really be used for this so
it's entirely CPU based and if I look at
the CPU usage it is pegged like like OBS
studio is basically just using like 100
percent of the CPU and thirty percent of
the GPU at all times
[Music]
so like I don't know I don't know what
it's having trouble with but again like
video encoding is kind of expensive like
mo comp specifically checks are
expensive so I don't know if I look at
the
yeah if I look at it it's probably the
recording I don't know I also don't know
why like is there a reason that there
isn't a framerate on here it looks like
like you can't set to different frame
rates so there's only 60 so I think the
problem is it's happening to do to 60
Pietra streams at to 60 1080p streams
probably too much for a core i7 you know
one would probably be okay but I don't
know how to tell it to just stream the
one like I don't know how to tell it
like just just do one and stream it
isn't that like wouldn't that be a
button here somewhere I don't know maybe
there's a way to do that but I don't see
it so
[Music]
I got nothing so it might be possible
that you can do that it might not be and
I'll just have to I mean I don't know or
we just live with it I guess another
question is I don't know if I go look at
the recorded video does is the recorded
video actually okay like this is not
really telling me much about like like
it's this isn't really telling me much
about the difference between those two
things so I don't know
that there are two types of GPU tiled
and non tiled and mobiles use tiled
method but why what are the benefits
removals using it well actually kind of
everyone use tiles is uses tiled to a
certain extent it just depends on how
tiled you are right but the idea behind
tiled rendering is just that if you
don't have a I mean you could think of
it as being exactly the same as why you
do it on the CPU if you have a very
strong caching architecture that allows
the cache to kind of suck up any kind of
weird access pattern problems that you
might have and everything this works
fine then you don't have to really worry
about a lot of locality stuff but if you
have a limited ability to do things like
caching or limited ways of accessing the
cache or limited amount of memory to use
for stuff etc etc the reason that you
want to move to tiled rendering is
because if you keep everything in one
tile local to like one processing unit
on the GPU then there's just a lot less
communication that has to happen and a
lot less cash missing that has to happen
right think about a pretty simple case
where you want to rasterize two
different triangles right and I hand one
of those triangles to one processing
unit on a GPU and another triangle to
another processing unit on the GPU this
is not how it actually works but I'm
just giving you an example well if those
two triangles are actually in completely
separate locations this works just fine
right if these two triangles are in the
same location we have an issue because
one GPU processing unit is trying to
write to stuff that another GPU
processing unit needs to write to first
because the triangles go in order right
and so if I know that all of my
triangles that are in a particular
location as bound by a tile on the
screen are all being handled by this
same processing unit I don't need to
worry about that data dependency anymore
at all right so you can see why at the
very least you want to break things up
into bins on the screen because if you
can do that you then can eliminate a
whole like series of inter core
communication problems you might have
with people wanting to fill stuff right
in order now in reality GPUs have lots
of strategies for doing these things
tiling is one way of reducing the
communication that you need and the
amount that you have to move memory
between different parts of the chip or
Core caches right another way that they
often do it is by producing intermediate
results and then combining those
intermediate results later now if you've
ever wondered for example why blending
is not programmable this is why on a
tiled part where one core is doing all
of the rendering for a small region of
the screen programming the blend
operation is free right you can just do
it and it will work because you can just
execute code and be done exactly like it
executes all the rest of the code on the
other hand if you are doing something
where you have a triangle being
rasterized by somebody who doesn't yet
have the ability to know if someone else
who needed to rasterize a different
triangle had already done so right then
in that case you need to wait for a
special purpose unit to combine those
two results in order later and that unit
isn't programmable see what I'm saying
so you definitely have situations where
tiling makes things a lot simpler for
you and the degree to which you want can
leverage a tiling architecture is like
everything else in GPU design it's kind
of just a magic hey we keep trying to
work out the fastest way to take giant
sets of triangles and move them through
this chip to produce an output frame and
sometimes the
cost of the chip plus the die area plus
the caching plus the power consumption
rules mean that tiling everything
completely is the fastest way to render
triangles at this price point and other
times it isn't no I'm saying
so why chips use tiling or don't use
tiling is beyond me
you know it's it's a GPU design question
but hopefully you can appreciate why
tiling changes how things behave because
the degree to which a particular
architecture needs to have handling of
things like order dependency or needs to
understand things like how to move
things between caches efficiently and
stuff like that can change dramatically
depending on how it is ever going to
partition work between the elements of
the chip and so if you can make a chip
that just knows that all of the things
that happen to a particular 4x4 pixel
block somewhere always happen on one
core of the GPU well that's a lot easier
than saying you can happen on multiple
ones right so they make those decisions
based on how their architecture can most
leverage the cost at the power and the
silicon cost that they're going to have
right
yes so Fabien is totally Fabien is like
totally describing what's going on for a
GPU right if you think about the way a
GPU works a GPU is what a GPU is knows
ahead of time what has to go out to the
display it is handed literally a
complete package that is like here is
everything that has to happen to draw
this frame so latency is not
particularly relevant to a GPU because
it doesn't care when any particular
thing comes back it just wants the total
amount of time taken to produce a frame
to be as small as possible so even if
there's something at the beginning of
the frame that takes all the way till
the end of the frame to finish nobody
cares
as long as the total frame time was
minimized right so as a result and I
think this is presumably what Fabian is
talking about I don't know because I'm
not sure what you're referring to but as
a result everything in the actual excuse
me
everything in the actual GPU pipeline is
designed strictly around one thing
really and that is never let an F mad go
to waste right so a GPU is a giant set
of floating multiply floating point
multiply add circuitries right and these
ALU units that can do that we just have
a crap ton of them and we need to in so
much as possible ensure that at no time
is one of these F Mads not producing a
value we will actually use in the final
frame like the
fastest possible GPU performance is 100%
of the f mad circuits RF matting for
something that we actually will use in
the frame all the time for the entire
duration of the frame because that means
you literally did the maximum amount of
computation work for the visual that you
could write so as a result a GPU doesn't
think about things as trying to get the
fastest turnaround time for things like
a memory access what it wants to do is
just make sure that it can have enough
memory accesses in-flight at a time so
that it can be doing F Mads and by the
time it finishes doing the F Mads is
currently doing enough memory has come
back to start the next batch of F Mads
right so the entire pipeline is in the
GPU is not set up to render one triangle
as fast as possible it never cares how
fast a single triangle renders in fact a
single triangle could take the entire
frame to render and no one would care
all that matters is that at no time is
some actual multiplier unit sitting
around doing nothing and so they go
through extraordinary lengths to make
sure that they can pipeline everything
so that there's always work coming in
and so forward fetching that work is
incredibly important like you always
want to make sure that they've got tons
of things queued up to do because if
those queues ever run dry then an F mad
will go to fetch the next thing to do
and it will find nothing and that is
when you have now lost the battle right
to keep the GPU math pipe stuffed
why are desktops using non tiled method
well so there's a lot of reasons that
tiling might not be the best decision
depending on how complex your
architecture is right so let's take a
couple examples one is that you have to
reprocess things so on every tile
boundary any triangle that spans those
two tiles to people now process that
triangle right one on the one side one
on the other a triangle could span
several tiles many people are now doing
work on that triangle right
another reason is well some things can
be sawed tiled but some things can't for
example unordered access views well
these things are now writing to
arbitrary pieces so we don't really know
where they're targeting and so some
feature sets just don't lend themselves
to tiling right ray-tracing not tiled at
all like that feature is just a pure
like geometry walk right and so the more
general purpose the GPU work the GPU is
actually doing the less amenable it is
to tiling now the rasterizer is always
going to be somewhat tile based right
because we always know that when we
rasterize something eventually it gets
down to something we can bin into tiles
if we want to and in fact we need to do
that to determine what actually gets
drawn at all so there's always some
concept of a tile to a certain extent
but the degree to which it's really
tiled as a rendering architecture again
more heavyweight high-end superpower
GPUs that are designed for arbitrary
processing the amount to which they can
really rely on tiling to be efficient
goes down not to mention the fact that
tiling makes it so that you are only as
fast as your slowest tile is a way to
look at it
so things that expect to have really
concentrated areas of detail and then
less area of detail everywhere else that
all
so won't work very well with tiling
because tiling requires you have a
fairly flat equal level of detail across
the whole screen to a certain extent I
mean it's not exactly that but sort of
so tiling isn't a panacea it's just a
strategy and the degree to which that
strategy has payoffs for you depend a
lot on what your workloads look like and
what your GPU architecture is going to
be the new co D Battle Royale install
shader for better game performance when
being in the game
can you imagine what my I'm sorry I
don't really know what that means
it might not be installing the shaders
so we have to understand is a shader is
a program much like an executable as a
program yes but it can't ship
pre-compiled and the reason it can't
quite ship precompiled I shouldn't say
pre compiled but pre compiled and linked
and the reason it can't be shipped that
way is because the shader itself doesn't
know which hardware it's going to run on
so it might run on this particular piece
of Intel hardware might run on this
particular Nvidia hardware right so the
shaders have to actually be compiled for
the card the chip on which those shaders
are running if you have an engine that
has a you know a festival of shaders so
there's like a thousand shaders using
this game because that's the way they
did it right what normally happens when
you're playing the game is every time
one of these shaders needs to get
activated it has to get compiled first
right and that can actually cause your
machine to suffer a performance
degradation because now the like
compilation of that shader is actually
taking machine resources right so what
you can do if you care a lot about this
problem and have it is during your
install you can say Oh what is the GPU
that's currently there and let's go
ahead and ask the GPU driver that's
installed the machine right now to
compile these shaders now during install
and we'll just save what it produces as
the binary blob of the of the shader
right
and then at runtime when we need to
actor that shader we can just literally
hand it the precompiled optimized
version that it already had plenty of
time to chew on right and so I don't
know cuz I don't know anything about
Call of Duty I don't know anything about
the team I have no idea about the engine
and I've never even played it but one
thing that might be happening if someone
says it's installing shaders is that
might not be installing the shaders so
much as they are compiling the shaders
for you so that that doesn't have to
happen when the games actually running
but that's just a guess I have no idea
so if Albus no there are actually no
current ways of compiling shaders on any
API period what actually happens is that
you can pre-process a shader into an ir
and there's two of those so one is SP ir
v which is Vulcan in OpenGL and one is
like d 3d assembly language
quote-unquote right so you can do the
first phase of compilation which is like
the text processing and turning it into
like an intermediate representation but
there is no way to pre compile it all
the way and so what then has to happen
is say it even on OpenGL this is the way
it works when you're actually on the
machine in question when you're on the
actual GPU you're running on right now
then you can ask that compile this for
you and you can hand it the intermediate
rep or just the raw shader code it will
compile it for that card and then you
get back a binary blob that binary blob
will only work on literally that card
like yes it may work on another very
similar card maybe but the driver is
under no obligation to do that and it
certainly won't work on like a different
manufacturers card or anything right
does that make sense so OpenGL does have
a way to say pre compile this shader but
it pre compiles it for a card the card
you're running the opengl thing on right
now so you can't ship that shader it
wouldn't work it would fail on most
people's machines so that's why you need
to do it at install time now if you know
exactly what you're installing on so you
know like a PlayStation 4 well there you
can pre compile your shaders because
there's only one thing it could be right
but that's the minority of the cases
almost everything you ship on these days
you have to compile at the time you're
actually on the platform
Oh team R&amp;B I'm not sure what our frame
rate is right now it's it's you know we
still I'm still you know some thing we
have to do some pretty hard optimization
work based on where we're at because
we'd like to get that down to at least
30 milliseconds and you know for feeling
really saucy we want to get all the way
down to 15 so we're gonna have our work
cut out for us to be sure however you
know like I don't know that it's
impossible I think we you know I think
we've got a good shot at it so I also
don't know if we need the lighting
region to be this big it seems like
based on what I'm seeing that we could
shrink the region a bit and bias it
forward slightly and and probably narrow
the the region quite a bit like if we're
looking at this you know this whole area
back here is never visible right so we
could probably shift the area forward a
few voxels in Y and reduce it just in
general the total size because you know
looking at it it's just it's lighting a
lot more than it needs to so you know
could we get away with with a much
tighter voxel I think we probably could
and I don't know exactly what the you
know the tightness of that is and where
the artifacts would start coming in but
I could see something maybe even that
aggressively small as being
theoretically feasible if we tighten the
bounds up you know so looking at
something like this right and how that
Scrolls around again we would probably
want it to be biased forwards a little
bit rather than backwards so you know in
inside the Vox Minh corner in in the
shift here what we would generally want
to do is say like look whatever we're
getting for the camera offset here we're
gonna have a Y bias where the bias for
the look like where the the Y is
actually located relative to the camera
center it's always been a shifted like
up a little bit
so you know we're gonna go like two
cells forward or something like this so
it's always just a little bit up and so
that it has a little bit more look ahead
but that's just because of the way the
perspective is shifted right and if we
did something like that then I'm not
convinced we couldn't get away with
something like this small again it's
it's hard to say exactly but you know it
doesn't feel like it would be a stretch
to say that that's a tight enough bounds
on the voxel right and and and who knows
we'll see I guess right and if you look
at how fast that's going that's already
at 30 frames a second basically and so
if we figure we maybe can squeeze some
more performance out of the way that
it's working I could see I could see us
getting to to a reasonable 30 frames a
second or 60 frames a second hit there
without a lot of stress
could you recommend some resources about
GP architectural strategies to dig
deeper not really I don't know where
those would be you'd probably have to go
look at fob Ian's blog I don't know
could be easier to not have the
submission - fine well the problem is I
don't want the framerate to vary based
on where you are so I'd rather have the
lighting be a fairly fixed cost what do
you think about the new kind of pipeline
that Nvidia is pushing with mess mesh
and tasked shaders I think it makes a
lot of sense because I think GPUs and
CPUs are kind of converging to a certain
extent so I think moving to something
more like a CPU models probably where
that has to go long term
Chimere and B if we had a major light
source from behind and we had say large
treehouse behind us if this light box is
too small would it mean we would not get
the shadow of whatever is behind us hmm
no so the lighting as it exists now it
computes probes in certain locations but
the lights can be wherever you want them
to be and the shadows can cast from
wherever you want them to be so all it
would mean is you wouldn't get secondary
lighting from over there because the
secondary lighting is only produced when
you grab something from a when you grab
something from a secondary bounce that
requires you to be inside the voxel so
secondary bounce lighting from outside
the region will not contribute however I
don't know to what extent that would
ever affect us because secondary bounce
lighting is fairly weak so the chances
that you could actually have a
significant difference there it seems
pretty low
is it possible to make 2d the 2d trees
cast shadows in the shape of a tree on
the ground so I guess the answer is like
the answer is like yes and no it's
possible to cast to have the 2d tree
cast a shadow on the ground that will
look exactly like the tree actually is a
2d cut out card right so it will not
look right at all and there's literally
nothing you can do to make it look right
because the place where the tree and its
shadow meet you can't really orient that
to look proper probably you could try to
warp the tree a little bit right but the
problem that you fundamentally have is
like the same problem that we have in
rendering like you know when you look at
what would happen if I started to try
and look at these trees from a different
angle you see what they look like right
there just cards sitting there and so
we're orienting them at the camera to
make them look okay but the light isn't
gonna come from a different angle mm-hmm
and so if you want to cast a shadow
you'd have to like fly the sprite down
on the shadow and then you'd have the
kind of like figure out what to do at
the base so that it didn't produce a
nossa I mean it's it's ugly so is why we
don't do hard shadows that's why we're
not doing hard shadows in this game is
because hard shadows on sprites I don't
think they look very good so with
solving the lighting wrapping in X
reduced CPU load to stiffening sent I
don't think light wrapping in X has
anything to do with CPU load we consider
using computers for some of these
lighting calculations not really because
we're trying to keep it
fairly straightforward and not using
compute shaders compute shaders almost
never work also they're extremely buggy
and error-prone so you invite a lot of
compatibility issues if you use compute
shaders and try to ship that so if we
were going to accelerate the lighting
mm-hmm I would try to phrase it as a
straightforward shader meaning something
that can be done as a pixel shader not
as a as a compute trader and to be clear
I don't think you would need a computer
shader because in order to do generation
of the voxel I shouldn't really need to
use a computer because you know you're
updating each individual voxel piece at
a time you shouldn't need art the
arbitrary nature of the computer really
so if we were gonna move this to the GPU
I wouldn't use a computer unless I found
I really somehow couldn't do it
otherwise all right I'm gonna wrap it up
okay thank you for joining me for in the
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you want to following series at home you
can always peer to the game on handmade
hero org and it comes to source code so
you can try out your own stuff if you
want to experiment with it I'll be back
here next week when we'll look at
optimizing the raycasting engine and
trying to get it up to a faster speed
and maybe more raised per second and
just in general so even if you want to
stay at something like 30 frames a
second we can at least improve the
quality of the lighting and so on using
more rays and then from there we'll just
move into lighting quality territory and
try to figure out how to make sure that
our lighting is always making sense and
that'll require some analysis of all the
things we're computing to make sure
we're not doing anything that adds
energy to the system in the wrong way
and things like that that's it for now
hope see you back here next week until
then have fun program everyone and I'll
see you on the Internet techies
everybody