alright hello everyone and thank you for
joining me for a very special episode of
handmade hero as you know one of the
things that we have put off for a very
long time in handmade here and that I
intimated recently that we would
probably not want to put off much longer
is getting rid of the few I think
there's only three functions that we
still call from the C standard library
because right now handmade here pretty
much doesn't use any external code at
all but it does still link with a c
runtime library and the only reason
we're doing that right now is because of
cosine sine and a tan two are the only
things that we actually call and so at
some point we really want to get rid of
those for a whole number of reasons some
of which will actually be going into in
a moment I think as well but one of the
big problems was replacing those is I am
NOT a numerical programming person it's
not something that I spend a lot of time
doing and so when I go to replace sine
or cosine typically what I do is I just
look up somebody who's already figured
out how to do a good replacement for
sine or cosine and just do some version
of that code and that is not a very good
explanation and it's certainly not
something that's going to help anyone
watching the stream know about what goes
into this sorts of replacement and this
sort of mathematical coding so it's kind
of hoping that someone could give us a
better explanation of that and kind of
give us more of the details about how
one goes about truly replacing sine or
cosine or a tan to a tan to my
understanding evilly harder and so
thankfully as you know way back in the
early days of handmade hero on the chat
sudonym 73 who you haven't seen much
because unfortunately in the in the
recent days the stream time has moved
was always kind of our guardian angel of
math and would would kind of jump in to
to help us anytime we were when I was
like and I think there's probably some
math thing here but I don't know what it
is so I knew that he was into this sort
of programming had a lot more experience
than I did so I asked him his actual
name is Andrew Brahmaji I now know how
to pronounce that correctly and he lives
in Howell you do yeah there you go and
and he lives in Australia so we set up a
stream time we were trying to work out
stream he'd come on explain this to us
so I'm I'm honored to have him on the
stream and although our connections not
great because we're going all the way
from Australia to me to twitch which is
probably not the best thing in the world
he's gonna try and walk us through this
first of all what this kind of
programming is is all about and how one
goes about doing something like sine and
cosine replacements so with with that
introduction Andrew over to you okay so
will will try and do this as a I think
we'll try and do it as a conversation
I've got I've got a whole bunch of notes
here which I will dump on the hand mate
wiki at some point soon it just needs a
little bit of editing awesome so right
so the basic idea is what you have to
understand first is how numbers are
represented by the computer and
floating-point numbers in particular so
this is all covered in this wonderful
document which you probably can't get
access to which is the I Triple E
standard for floating-point arithmetic
2008 edition this is this is kind of
expensive I think it's like 50 euros or
something ridiculous like that but if
you haven't had a fusion that will pay
for access for you all a bit up like me
the I Triple E standard grew out of a
bunch of incompatible computer
arithmetic systems from the 70s and 80s
but thankfully for for the PC industry
it was largely based around they base
this on Intel standard the basic so okay
let's let's let's step back for a minute
and talk about how you would represent a
number by the way I'm going to assume
that everyone can kind of read binary
and hexadecimal because if you can't
you're going to get lost very quickly
here because we're going to go into
actual binary representations and I will
scold them thoroughly if they do think I
miss you you know this many episodes of
handmade
exactly we will not assume octal okay
okay those who used who uses octal right
okay need to know is some basic high
school maths and the first thing we're
going to look at is scientific notation
scientific notation is we represent a
number like say 1,024 is 1 point 0 to 4
times 10 to the 3 or as we say in c
notation 1.0 243 if you understand what
that means the rest should be easy
well straightforward anyway so in
scientific notation what we do is we
take a number and we represent it in two
parts one of them is a number between 1
and 10 including 9 not including 10 and
then times 10 to the power of something
and that's what shifts this decimal
point you can shift this decimal point
backwards and forwards by changing this
over here this is the terms for this is
this is the mantissa I'm going to spell
it out here because that's a an equal
term and this number here is 3 is called
the exponent and these are kind of the
two important numbers in a
floating-point representation the way
that I Triple E 754 represents numbers
is exactly the same as this except of
course it's not in decimal it's in
binary so if you have a number like 1
point 1 1 1 0 in binary right so this is
a binary number this is not a decimal
point this is a binary point in
scientific notation of me times 2 to the
right
maybe not 53 that's a big number
and this is equivalent through the
number
oops the way this is a MacBook Pro I
anyone who has a a modern MacBook Pro
knows what I mean about the keyboard on
this it's absolutely terrible everyone
complains the lack of them Escape key is
though is the least of your problems
although it is a big problem Weaver V I
use myself they say no oh my punch bar
like my goodness okay oh we seem to have
lost Andrew oh no I wonder if the
MacBook has has decided to take revenge
on us here I shouldn't have said
anything
is it dead hmm hmm let me see here oh
there it goes
well that's a problem because we've only
just begun our replacement for sine and
cosine so I'm not sure I'm not sure how
to get it back okay the link between
here in Australia is not that bad though
Google come on surely it can't be this
bad unless the MacBook really did well
we will wait for a second and see if we
can get a get it back in the meantime I
will take another bite of this
Oh mm-hmm Oh is your coming back
hello are we on now yes but only your
voice excellent no okay
Oh Leon now just your voice not your
screen no I
okay alright ladies and gentlemen of the
audience you have to understand a little
thing called Australian home internet we
I don't I don't indian yet not in yes it
is we this will probably happen again
over the course of this show we will
struggle we will figure out a way all
right so I got rid of my I got rid of
the video of me down the bottom left
because I think that's probably just
increasing the bandwidth unnecessary
just my face you probably see my face we
might bring it back up again for the Q&amp;A
sounds good okay okay good so what I was
saying is that this number is kind of
equivalent to this number two to the
zero is of course one and this is the
idea of the name floating point is that
this binary point can float around by
altering the exponent what's important
for us though is this number this
representation most numbers can be
represented let's make this a let's make
this a negative number just to just to
make this absolutely clear most flirting
point numbers can be or most most
numbers that we want to deal with can be
represented represented in three parts
one of them is this which is the sign
whether it's positive or negative
the
second part is the mantissa which is
this part which is a number between 1
and 2 including 1 not including 2 and
this number which is the number that you
aides to ^
and that part is called the exponent and
the obvious number that you may think
can't be represented in this way and
you'd be right is 0 and that's a very
important number and we'll deal with
that in a minute but most numbers can be
represented this way and the way we do
it in I Triple E floating point is we
pack these into bits in the following
way
I've actually got standing here so I can
show you some with you it's decimal we
don't care about decimal the I Triple E
standard covers a lot of ground and I'm
going to introduce you to some of the
really weird parts later not in detail
because you really don't want to know
but no you really don't
but I have an exact I here we go this is
what I'm looking for right here so this
is the format we have one bit with
ripper time it's 0 of the numbers
positive and 1 if the numbers negative
this is the exponent field and the way
we represent that is we represent this
in in a field that's W bits in size now
in the case of binary 32 which is what
handmade Eirik all's real 32 and by the
way this is a finite set of numbers
there are two 232 possible binary thirty
twos they are not real numbers it's
finite anyway that's neither he nor
that's an argument for another time
the way we the way we represent this as
we take this number six and then we add
to it 127 which is two to the okay so
this this field in binary so view is
eight bits in size 127 is
I hang on 27 let me let me just check
that because I I have it here yes one
bias bias 7f yes that's so that's that's
127 so we add a hundred and twenty-seven
and then we store that number in the
field
that's what 133 now those of you who of
course know about binary representation
may wonder why we don't just use the
two's complement here there is a good
reason for this and we'll get to that in
a minute but anyway that's the number we
store 133 which is the exponent plus
this number which is called the BIOS the
bias and we'll go through all of this in
a minute so that's how we that's that's
so we have one bit which is the sign bit
and eight bits which is the biased
exponent the exponent plus a bias the
final thing is how we represent the
mantissa in this case this is the
mantissa one of the interesting things
about scientific notation is for any
number other than zero this leftmost
digit is always a 1 it's it's never a
zero because that's what we mean by this
kind of normalized scientific notation
so we don't actually need to store that
so we strip that off and we stored that
bit better and that is called the
significand the trailing significant
field as it's called in the standard and
with that you can store any what we call
normal number now there is a useful
little tool here we go flirt toy oh hey
look toys little little thing that
someone has stuck on on github which
lets you actually play with this so you
can you can flip the sign bits and it'll
make a negative number you can play with
the experiment you can play with this
and
and have a lot of fun with this with
various bit patterns and see what
floating-point number it corresponds to
it has 32-bit and 64-bit sir
if you want to work with this in a
little more detail and get a bit
familiar with this I use this a lot
writing the notes very useful little
little thing to know that and it's got
links to the Wikipedia pages on single
precision double precision if you want
to explain better than I can
alright so that's how what we call
normal numbers are represented by my use
of the word normal number suggests this
some other kind of number that's not
normal and the main other kind you need
to know is what's called sub normal
numbers now this is this word was
introduced in the 2008 standard before
that people called them d normal numbers
or denormalized numbers but I'm going to
use the you know the current terminology
even though sub normal sounds I think
quite totalitarian nonetheless
nonetheless so the idea is that for the
exponent field we reserved two bit
battens in this case there are eight
bits we reserved one which is all zeros
and this one which is all ones so these
do not represent the normal exponents
you know you don't subtract 127 and
that's what it is 0 is interesting on
from our point of view because what 0
means is it is a sub normal number and
what that means to the floating-point
implementation is it means that the
exponent is set to minus 126 and the
mantissa the significant field is
interpreted as a mantissa without a
leading one so it's with a leading zero
so if you were to see for example
Paton whoops
how do I hit this keyboard writte what
that means is this
this means that number times two to the
power of minus 126 and what this does is
this gives us a representation for very
small numbers very small numbers are
sometimes important in floating-point
but more importantly gives us a
representation for zero by simply making
it all zeros it's I think there are 23
of them and there's that that is the
representation of zero and the reason
for that is that we that we use the the
reason why we use the all zeros in the
exponent field for this is because
programmers really really like it if
when you have a block of memory and you
fill it with zero bytes that that means
the number zero it means when it's an
integer and it now it means that when
it's a floating point value as well this
is a very highly desirable feature of
the number system okay so there's a
there's a really all of the finite
numbers that we have to that we have to
worry about this bit pattern one is
reserved for two other things they're
infinity and a special value called not
a number you will see these if you've
ever worked with floating-point you will
be well familiar with not a number and
infinity not a number more so these are
there to make the system algebraically
closed now what that means is that any
operation gives you a meaningful answer
so for example if you divide one by zero
what you get is infinity that's not a
finite number and in fact you can
usually set in fact no you can set your
floating-point unit to give you an
exception if that ever happens
we really don't want that in a program
like I'm a hero but it least gives it to
me and so for that and if you divide or
you get negative infinity not a number
is for situate is for situations where
the answer really isn't a real number
like the square root of negative 1 or 0
divided by 0 oh one thing I didn't
mention by the way is that that is also
a possibility and what that means is
negative now you may wonder what why
what's negative 0 why would you need it
and you're right that doesn't make any
mathematical sense but it does there are
some some uses for it because often what
will happen is you do some calculations
calculations calculations and the number
just gets to your small to represent and
by making this a negative 0 is at least
it tells you which way that that's
called an underflow by the way and what
that does is at least tells you which
direction it under flowed from and so
that's a sometimes useful feature of the
system again it's they're mostly for
algebraic closure reasons not because it
necessarily makes any mathematical sense
to Heather negative 0 but it's useful in
practice so that in a nutshell is I
Triple E phone point up
that's just so we're absolutely certain
what we know this so there's a sign bit
all one's infinity is if this field is
all zeros that's that that's that's a
representation for infinity the sign bit
whether it's possibly made in finding
this the sign field is currently ignored
at the moment one you have that
that's where non-zero pattern that is
the representation for not a number and
by the way there are two kinds of not a
number one is if there's a one bit here
and one if there's a zero bit here but
really this part here has to be nonzero
if that zero this is called a quiet
difficult to quiet nan quiet not a
number and this is called a signalling
name signaling not a number and the
difference is that quiet is just
probably the three calculus it was
basically view try and doing anything
was not enough yet not a number as an
answer and if signalling not a number is
one that always raises an exception no
matter what so that's that's something
that you may have to know but that's
that's basically all of there all of the
tricky cases so you've got normal
numbers sub normal numbers and then
these special cases infinity quiet man
signaling man and that's everything
uh once again this sign bit here is is
currently not interpreted by the under
standard I'm sure that some future
standard will will take a liking to that
and use it for some reason all right so
that's that ly that's the basic idea of
of how floating point numbers are
represented so what we have one bit here
eight bits here and 23 bits here and
that should add up to 32 so that's the
the binary 30 presentation binary 60 aim
the sign bits the same size this is a
bit wider this is a bit wider but
otherwise it's it's it's the same idea
any questions about any of that
so I don't think I had any I'll look
briefly at the chat to see if there are
any questions about that that are coming
through if anyone wants to put a Q :
I will yeah double check it but that
that was pretty clear I had one question
while I'm waiting to see if anyone
didn't anyone had something they didn't
understand I did have one question
which was so I with the let me look back
over here I should have written it down
at the time but I I thought I had oh yes
so it's just a peculiarities of binary
as a number system that you can skip
encoding the leading digit because any
other number scheme it's always just the
the base of the number minus one that
you would have to encode there probably
and just since two minus one happens to
be just one you can skip the encoding
but it seems like that's just like we
got lucky with binary in a sense is that
well yes you're kind of you're kind of
right on the other hand you know that's
it's a it's it's the it's one of the
reasons why we use a binary yes yeah so
so but yes if you are encoding decimal
and you know the standard has a way to
incur decimal in here you have to store
a number between one and nine yep okay
oh yes this is why this is why these
these formats are called binary
thirty-two and binary 64 once again new
this is new language in 2008 new in 2008
I know yeah before that they were called
single precision and double precision
got it we still mostly use those terms
but it's binary as opposed to decimal
okay so we had one question from the
stream on that so very good explanation
by the way because I think everyone got
it including me thank you
is there a representation for under
flowing numbers I think that was just a
question regarding like so when you do
have an underflow there you you lose all
information about the sign bit it was I
correct understanding you there so when
there's an underflow you it'll go all
the way down to subnormal and then it'll
just be left with just the sign bit and
zeroes eventually that is that is
correct of course there are the the
standard and your floating-point unit as
well has a way to turn an underflow
condition into an exception okay
if that's what you really want
sometimes that is what you want it's uh
it's called uh what's called loss of
significance I think yeah yes exactly
it's it's it is very very very extension
yes or loss of precision or something
like that
anytime you go from normal to some of
your significand you you know you you
you don't have as many bits available to
represent your mantissa as you might
want yes oh hey if I got binary 16 by 32
binary 64 binary heads so about half
precision as well interesting decimal 34
decimal 64 decimal 128 those are the
main versions that are in the standard I
accidentally landed on that page okay so
yeah I don't think we're any real
questions then other than that one so
you take it away all right yeah we will
go on so let me have a look let's have a
look at a little header file over Q
which is it's nu 10 made numerix so I
put it under an MIT license so anyone
anyone can have a copy of this and this
this defines a lot of the constants that
we need floating point numbers at the
bit level there's colors all right by
the way you know look fine to me okay
cool I mind you it's not available for
the Mac anyway so that wasn't okay I
didn't I didn't mean that as I didn't
mean that as a hint yeah so so the main
the main things here are the number of
bits in the exponent the bias for the
exponent which by the way is always two
to the number of exponent bits minus one
for any for any floating-point format
that's what it is
the significant bits that's not the
mantissa it's the significant and
mantissa is the number of bits in this
one this is one point something the
significand is yeah
all right the minimum maximum exponent
these of course - not symmetric around
zero and the reason is because we
reserved two values one for the
subnormal and one for all of the other
special case the things that aren't
finite numbers then we've got a bunch of
a bunch of constants here now these by
the way the C standard library does
define something very like these and let
me just show you what they are they're
they're in defined in float that H
whoops no I don't want to enable cereal
that's unfortunately right next to the
Delete key and it's on the cut bar on
this method so I keep I know it's it's
it's crazy absolutely crazy all right so
we don't do that
here we go that's probably good enough
you see how long this is taking by the
way while I'm while I'm yeah screen
sharing okay yeah yeah I'm into it I'm
telling you all right so it this defines
a bunch of a bunch of constants that are
very similar to the ones that I've
defined here but they differ in one
slightly subtle way so we've got minimum
exponent maximum exponent this is for
flirt the maximum value the minimum
value which by the way is not actually
the minimum value for a flirt it is the
minimum positive normal number for a
flirt a lot of people hate this that
this this you you flirt max is the
largest flirt flirt min should be this
the smallest plug well but it isn't
that's why I've actually called it max
normal min normal and min subnormal in
this I think that that's probably less
confusing that notation
the this is just some the sign mass the
exponent mask the amount by which you
shift the exponent right the significant
mask and finally this number epsilon and
this is probably the most useful number
of them all unless you're actually
packing and unpacking flirts if all
you're doing is working with flirts
using the values that you're the the
Machine epsilon is probably the most
useful number that you'll see and you'll
find we use this in a few places in the
cups Alana is not equal to one could you
could you go back about fifteen seconds
with nothing she likes for a split
second there okay and it was the most
important thing yeah okay
all right epsilon is the smallest number
such that 1 plus epsilon is not equal to
1 so what this done what this value does
this is actually 2 to the minus 23 if
you work it out that's tuna minus 23
because that's the number of bits in the
significant what this does is this gives
you a measure of how granular the number
system is it's the smallest relative
difference between two adjacent and so
this is actually a really important
number because this will this this is
this is how you kind of this is this
this number if you like is the
difference between a real number and a
floating-point number in some sense and
this this number will will turn up a lot
of the time in what we're doing so so
remember this number epsilon I will
explain it again when we see it in when
we see it in the future but that's that
this is that this of all of the of all
of these constants here these are
important for unpacking and unpacking
floats a bit level but this is the
number that you need the most for
actually working with them
all right what I finally got here is a
union of real 32 aun 32 and that's back
could do it with the Union could do it
with pointer hackery and C either way I
checked with a couple of compilers and
it does seem to compile this Union away
which is what you want because in in
modern Intel F peers in sse sse2 it's
what you have is on 128 register that
you can pick that you can fit four
binary 32 s in for single precision
floats or for you in thirty twos and all
you have to do is decide that that value
is something different you don't
actually need to convert from one to the
other to do bit hackery on it and you
want a representation where that is
compiled away by the compiler and I
think most compilers are pretty good
about this because people who are doing
low-level hacking with floating-point
numbers they need a consistent way to
just have some somewhere interpreted as
a flirt and now I want to win
interpreters unity too so I can extract
some bits from it and so the Union way
seems to work on everything I've tried I
have not tried Visual Studio so might
have to do some disassembly later just
to see how that's happening all right so
I've got a little enum here because this
is this is useful for some of the basic
operations to work out number zero
normal subnormal infinity or nem we'll
see an example of that in a minute just
just just to be clear what I'm heading
towards I've got I've got a real worked
example here of floating point division
um in all of its glory you'll see what I
mean by that in a minute anyway so this
is to test if it's a positive infinity
negative infinity this is a sort of note
these are values this returns positive
infinity returns negative infinity this
returns a quiet man
which is I just set the significant to
all ones it has to be at least the first
bit has the most significant bit has to
be one I just sit into all ones that's a
fairly standard way of doing it
and now finally some queries this is the
first one these is a number a finite
number that means it's anything other
than infinity or not a number
normal or sub normal this is true of
it's an infinity this is all fairly
straightforward but you you take the
number X you store it in this Union as a
flirt as a flirt
you read it out as an integer and then
do whatever bit masking and and mucking
around you want to do again this is for
infinity it's infinity if the exponent
field is the special or one's pattern
and the significant field is zero this
is true if the number is positive
according to its sign bit of course if
it's not a number then the sign bit
doesn't mean anything but that's alright
so here's the first useful operation if
you like it take the value of the number
and all we do for that is we take this
Union we store X in it we mask off the
sign bit so we force the sign bit to be
zero and then just read the value as a
floating point number again and that
gives us the absolute value of a number
of course there's a there's a there are
functions to do this in the C standard
library but this this should this is
this is and also you can use you know
comparison and negative and so forth but
this should this should compile down to
like one instruction I think maybe maybe
a load of this of this sign mask so
maybe two instructions but it's a lot of
code to get two instructions right this
is a function which sets the sign bit so
you take a number you mask off
everything sign bit you then set it yeah
we few ways you could do that anyway we
either either set the bit if we want it
to be negative or we clear the bit if we
want it to be
all right this is the this is the
function that takes this this enum up
here takes a number and categorizes it
as to what kind it is
so we extract the exponent field listing
event field experiment field of zero
then it's either zero or sub normal zero
is is special kind of sub normal but the
difference between that and between zero
and a sub normal number is the sub
normal number in theory could be
normalized if we had enough if we had
enough experiment and we'll see why we
might want to do this in the future so
that we can deal with most normal and
sub normal numbers in a uniform way and
that's a sometimes a useful feature then
we've got infinity and then and those
cases don't apply that's um I think I
think this is fairly straightforward
because what this really does is this
just implements the the patterns that we
looked at earlier alright now this is
this is where the where the work starts
getting interesting extract --ax now
again there is a function in the c
standard library that does this it is
called if our exp here we go it's the
c++ c library function okay we've got
microsoft let's look at microsoft Joey
so if our axp takes a there's a there's
a double version and a float version
here the flat version takes a flirt
returns a float and also takes a pointer
to an integer into which the exponent is
stored so what this does is this
separates a number into its mantissa and
its exponent this is one of the most
useful operations for very low-level
this page helpful yes it is go away
no I'm not giving you feedback on
this and and the reason why this is one
of the most useful operations is that it
helps you reduce the size of your
problem down now let me give you an
example of that let's suppose you're
implanting square root I want one
endpoint square root so we or the zero
case we know the negative negative
number is not a number infinity and then
we don't care about those for the moment
we'll just we'll just look at positive
numbers whether they're normal or
subnormal we know that a number can-can
is M times two to the eighth where where
m is a number between one and two and E
is some integer if the exponent is even
that is if this is actually to the to P
in the square root of that number is the
square root of M times to the P because
the square root of 2 to the 2 P is P if
it's an odd number through P plus one
then it's the square root of M times the
square root of two times two to the P in
either way we've reduced the problem of
computing the square root of an
arbitrary number normal or sub normal
down to the problem of computing the
square root of a number in the range
between one and two reduce the size of
the problem down so far for just a
little bit of a bit hackery and of
course this is what your FPU does
because the bits are just there and so
that that reduces as it reduces the size
of the problem down this is this is what
a concept that we're going to come back
to which is range reduction the the
range of values that you have to feed to
this to this to this function can be
reduced dramatically to a numbers in a
very small range
so that's the reason why this is a very
useful operation to have around and
we'll have a look at it in a minute when
we look at division because so let's
actually look at the implementation of
that extract exponent so there's a lot
of code here some of its comments of
course so in the case of zero infinity
or nan we just said the exponent to zero
and set the mantissa to that so there's
not a lot you can do in that case I
think this is what kind of what the C
library does by convention anyway for a
normal number all we do is we extract
the exponent field we extract these
front field read the mask shift it by
the amount that needs to be shifted to
bring the least significant bit to the
least significant bit of this you in 32
we convert it to a signed integer and
then subtract the bias and that gives it
to get the mantissa all we have to do is
set the exponent to zero which means we
really set it to the exponent bias
because to represent two to the power of
zero we add the exponent bias to that
and so all we need to do is just force
that field as if it was two to the power
of zero and that is the representation
of a mantissa so is that is that that I
does everyone kind of understand that it
makes perfect sense to me I said I can
I'll kind of eye the chat to make sure
yeah so if you have basically you have
this e is fine this is what we do is we
ask to find out what the exponent should
be and then to return the mantissa all
we do is we just set this to what is it
it's it's this bit pen we just force it
to be that yes
we force it to be that and then that
gives us another bird that is where the
exponent has just been forced to be zero
okay um for the subnormal case this is a
little tricky
now we could find the exponent by
extracting the mantissa using like bits
can reverse in people know what bits can
use bits can reverse yeah some people
may have forgotten but in the handmade
intrinsics there is a bits can we used
it actually for doing bitmap extraction
because the way that they store the
bitmap code in a Microsoft BMP format is
to actually just put the mask in there
so to figure out what you have to shift
write it like the read out or whatever
you have a bit scan yeah okay so what
bits can reverse would do is if in the
subnormal case we should be we're
storing the exponent isn't 32 so we're
not constrained by the size of the field
and you could do that by extracting the
mantissa and using bits can reverse to
find the most significant one bit
the mantissa but the way I'm actually
doing it here is by multiple just by
multiplying them by two to the power of
25 and this is you can you can believe
me that that number is to the power of
25 calculate it yourself I've only
memorized my powers of two up to about
17 or so and and of course I know 32 and
I know anyway
most programmers have memorized their
powers of two up to a fairly modest
number around the 16 or 17 mark most of
them have not memorized to the 25 but
that is 2/3 for multiplying a number by
2 to the power of 25 if it is a
subnormal number is a lossless operation
and this is another thing that will come
up as we go on with this which is that
some floating-point operations are
lossless that they do not they don't
involve any rounding the result is exact
and multiplying by 2 to the power of 25
is one of those operations because he's
just many people
the experiment and and the FPU doesn't
optimize that case but it knows that if
you multiply a mantissa by one you get a
mantissa you get the same mantissa back
it is in that sense it's a lossless
operation
so all we do here is we do pretty much
exactly the same thing here except we
multiply it by to the power of 25 first
and then when we extract the exponent
field we just subtract off the 25 and
then we set the experiment of this
scaled number to zero and that's how we
deal with subnormal numbers in this case
does that make sense to everyone I have
one question yeah I have one question
about that actually yes so assuming that
a number is subnormal it means that it's
binary pattern in the mantissa is
implicit zero then the debt well binary
point and then some number of zeroes and
then weights then the actual 1 0 pattern
that that we have for it right
when you Joe you cut out there for just
a second yes so if you've got a
subnormal number you've got bits at the
end you know you got the low order bit
set some number of zeros at the top when
you multiply by a power of two
does the floating-point unit first shift
those numbers up it's to actually move
them into the normal range then start
incrementing the exponent or what
happens exactly probably what is going
on and you have to look at the actual
circuit to find out what's going on it
probably does something very similar to
what we're saying here it probably uses
something like like a bit scam reverse
so it probably operation done thing like
this it basically turns a number into
its normal form to do work on it in fact
of course for those of you who are old
enough to remember
x87 oh yes
this is yes this is this is pretty much
exactly what happens x8 780 bit floating
point numbers the Intel extended
precision as its as it's known now hmm
doesn't have sub normal numbers it
doesn't have normal numbers i that the
one is always explicit hmm in the
significand
of an 80 bit flow as I as I as I recall
I think that is the case vague memory of
that and probably in turn using some
kind of extended precision like this to
do all the intermediate calculations so
it probably is turning into some kind of
representation without a Miss it one so
perhaps one thing it might do is when
when a floating-point number comes in it
will turn it back into a normal number
right there then it will do the
operation turn it back into a sub normal
number if it had to if it doesn't have
to because it got multiplied up then it
just stays normal something like this
perhaps exactly exactly or another thing
it perhaps or another thing it could do
it could have an internal representation
that just includes another beating in
the in the in the exponent field and
that's in okay thank you I didn't see
any questions in the chat by the way so
you are good to go yeah so the converse
of this operation is scaled by exponent
which doesn't necessarily have to be a
number between one and two will relax
that and an exponent and then puts it
back together
there are a few more cases you have to
deal with here because we could cause an
overflow or underflow overflow being and
we can represent and underflow if it's
smaller than number we can represent and
I just picked a number 500 which is kind
of roughly it then if it's less than
zero then it's a then we return a 0 with
the
same sign as X that is we preserve the
sign bit so this this is true flow
correctly according to the standard if
you under flow a negative number you get
negative 0 sorry handmade here our users
you're going to get negative zeros if
you try this
but dart an underflow is probably a
mistake anyway unless unless you don't
care that it's close enough to 0 and
again for an overflow we return infinity
so and then now this is all the code
that does the rest of it and this is
this is a bit nasty here so for now nor
infinity we just return X that's that's
fine and to handle the normal inside
normal cases basically what I did here
was exactly the same as above I used to
the power of 25 got to the 25 and to the
minus 25 so if we trying to scale a sub
normal number we turn it back into the
normal range this is this this again
turns it into a kind of a normal number
X field is what is X field that's yep so
we pretend that that we've got more bits
of precision in this is me in 32 for the
sub normal case we do that and subtract
off 25 so that's if we're scaling a sub
normal number but there's also the
possibility that when we scale by the
exponent we get a sub normal and for
that what we do is we just basically
check it against the maxixe burnham in
exponent it was greater than max
exponent we were to infinity if it's
less than the min exponent then this is
a sub normal or underflow case in which
case we may be like this by 25 we do
that so this is definitely under flow
here just return sine 0 otherwise we add
25 to the X field heck that was a number
and then return that value times 2 to
the minus 25 so it's a case of unpacking
subnormal number packing the subnormal
number we just manipulate the X field
and then multiply the value by to the
minus 25
you um but that's it's this just just an
illustration of the kind of to to deal
with the case between no one side not
long and for the normal case it's fairly
is you you know you just add the X field
exponent bias shift it and pack it all
back together so we can just use this as
a box now now this is a probably where a
food talk about the difference between
this and the C standard because you have
a look at the thing at the definition of
our X P it says it splits it interment
history parent such the absolute value
of M is greater than or equal to 0.5 and
less than 1.0 so the C standard doesn't
isn't talking point in textbooks do it
talks about a number between zero point
this I a it's probably too much time
actually trying to decide whether I
should follow the see that the sea
Convention on this or I should follow
the the the more usual floating point
thing on this and I decided to follow
the more useful starting point thing the
as a result what what the other thing
that this affects is it is effects sorry
it effects mean exponent and Max
exponent if you have a look at the value
of min exponent and Max exponent
according to your C standard library
these numbers are different by one I
think it's minus 127 to 126 or something
so that's that's the if you like the
flip side of using this convention I
don't know should I have used the CC
convention because Murphy will be using
I tend to not care at all what's in the
C specification and double that for the
C++
vacation just because I find that a lot
of times their decisions are usually
motivated by things that well in the C++
case they're just motivated by lunacy
but in the C case yes
they're probably they probably had a
reason for doing it but that reason is
probably not particularly applicable to
game programming necessarily and
probably had more to do with like some
case in scientific computing that was
legitimate but is not really what you
want in the case of performance oriented
code that typically you know flush
subnormal to zero is a typical thing for
a game to do it's probably not a typical
thing for us exactly the computation to
do exactly and and look to be fair right
the see this part of the C standard
probably predates the I Triple E 754
standard by ten years yes yes yes you
know it's it's because the first version
of the I Triple E standard was 1985 yeah
and and this probably is ten years
before that yes so yeah it's yeah so you
know it dates from the days when all of
the vendors had their had their own
different floating point standards and
and and they're all mutually
incompatible and quirky yes there's a
little there's a little quote here that
I'm actually going to put is Jenny
that's Wilkinson not Wilson I think it
was like a cheering award speech or
something it was like it was called like
confessions of a numeric analyst or
something like this well this is
basically a rant about the state of
computer or if metic in 1971 that you
know that one of the main virtues of an
electronic computer from the point of
view of the miracle analyst is its
ability to do arithmetic fast need the
year be sir bad so that's the state of
computer arithmetic at the time that the
C standard that C was invented I like
the fact that he may be said about it in
1971 if if he had anyway if he could see
it today I think he would probably just
die immediately of shock but Easter we
have a standard that's true
you know that the I Triple E standard is
at least predictable and there's
something to be said for that
I mean the the C standard doesn't even
depend on on these being binary one of
the things that that you'll find me is
right is the float radix and it'll be
different from a double radix at least
in theory and that is I mean you can
assume that it's two one because it's a
binary number on everything you care
about but even so right yes anyway
anyway all right now for that okay so
that's the that's the if you like the
the basic operations or at least the
ones they needed so far so I'm not this
is this is the right set of basic
operations but it's it's probably good
enough for what we're doing here sorry
let me walk you through division is
floating point division without doing
the slash operator that divides two
numbers anywhere and the reason why I
wanted to show people this is because
when you step inside like any debugger
you step inside your c-stand library's
implantation of sine or cosine or
something there's a lot of stuff in
there and it doesn't look like
calculation quite a lot of it and so the
reason why I wrote this out is to kind
of show you what all that stuff is now
I'm not going to go through that stuff
in detail all I'm going to do is show
you that it is there and how much of it
there is and then this will give you an
idea of then you may want to use the
standard library if you're not doing an
all-purpose computing the special
purpose computing like handmade hero
where you can assume some things about
the values that you're going to give to
your functions you know you can assume
that it's saying if you try and take
this you know if you try and take the
sine of ten thousand radians that's
probably a bug in hand right here
yes whereas the standard library has to
return a correct answer in that case for
some definition of correct and so it's
it's to deal with things like that and
to deal with negative 0 correctly it's
to deal with positive negative phineus
to deal with not a number you know if
you're if you've got a library function
that computes e to the X if you give
that negative infinity that actually
returns a reasonable and say return 0 e
to the negative infinity is 0 because
that's you know if your number overflows
in that direction imagine that it's just
a number that's less less than the
largest representable number in that
direction that's sensible answer so
anyway so let's look at the division so
this if you like is the finite number K
is the case where X is a finite number
and Y is a far which is really the case
that we're interesting so that's normal
and subnormal including 0 we do have to
deal with division by 0 that's that's
something we probably can't get away
with 0 divided by 0 is not a number
anything else divided by 0 is infinity
and it is an infinity of the same sign
as X so if X is a well or no actually no
it's the sine of X exclusive odd with
the sine of Y so if we take negative 100
and divide it by negative 0 we get
positive infinity this is this is laid
out in the spec let me let me show you
let me let me see if I can find this
here so the sine of the divide still
proceeds as if it were just a regular
number yes number part becomes infinity
yes shall be a an infinity correctly
signed here we go correctly signed
according to the operation the division
when the divisor is 0 and the dividend
is a finite nonzero number the sign of
the Infinity is the
exclusive or of the operand signs so
there you know got it
we follow this there let's go to that
section this section yeah there's the
thing that explains all the sign bit
yeah all right so that's so if you like
that's division by zero so that's an
exception case and imagine that there's
a little bit of code here this here is
the code that does division it is mostly
comments and I'll go through the
algorithm in a little bit cuz I think
that's a that's actually it's kind of an
interesting algorithm and and it
illustrates from other points that we're
talking about but what I want to show
you is this this down here is at least
as much code as this this stuff is the
stuff that does division this stuff down
here is the stuff does all of the I
Triple E compliance so this is the case
where either zero is not a where either
X is not a finite number or what a
finite number so we look at the category
of why something divided by zero that's
got to be either infinity divided by
zero and then divided by zero and so
those are the cases we have to do
different things in each case if we're
dividing by nan you're turnin n if we're
returning by infinity well a number
divided by infinity is zero that makes
sense
but we do have to worry about the sign I
think yes no that's it should be
negative is the is the yes that's where
we do the XOR of the two signs so we XOR
the true signs and do that quickly
return negative zero or positive zero
and the VAIO me infinitive and then
number divided by infinity number
divided by nan the point of that I
wanted it doesn't matter what all this
is I just looked at the spec and I think
I got her all right and and look to be
honest I'm because I didn't spend a
whole lot of time on this but the point
that I wanted I want to from in here is
that this is division it is really I
mean it's that line of code it's those
lines of code it's this which I'll
explain later because this is very
interesting and it's that so that is
division and this stuff down here is
all right so that stuff is division and
this stuff is compliance now this isn't
very much circuitry in an FPU but you
know a software library it's a lot of
code and it's just to get all of these
cases correct and if you have a look at
the standard that they often have lists
here like this is a 10/2 which we'll
come to in a moment here are all the
cases that I tend to has to cover that's
you know that's what it means to be
compliant with the standard is you need
to get all these cases correctly you
need to get a 10 to positive zero
negative 0 and a 10 to negative 0
negative 0 has to return different
values it's just the way the spec is
written and what can you know that's
that's what it means to be compliant and
your C standard library or your C++
standard library has to be compliant
otherwise it's not implementing the I
Triple E standard and that means it's
got to get all of these edge cases right
and that's that's really what I wanted
to show everyone with is is that I wrote
this so you don't have to so you won't
you unless you you get the job of
writing compilers standard library you
will not have to worry about any of this
because for kind of handmade hero kind
of code this is you know this is why
behind numerical analysts I'm not an
American host but this is kind of why we
hire them misty it is partly to get
these cases correct as well as to get
the normal case all right so I'm not
going to ask you there any questions
about this because I don't want any
questions about this let's talk about
the actual division okay
so to divide X by Y we do now I'm using
doubles and the reason is this is
actually the algorithm which is which is
this part here but that's that's I did
this so that I didn't have to do it the
way that real life
you use do it and how the reason why
women want to do this is so you can
actually this is a real algorithm this
is what your FPU does when you ask the
when you ask for one floating-point
number divided by another floating-point
so the first obvious case here is
extract exponent because once again if
you have M 1 M 1 times 2 to the he he 1
divided by M 2 times 2 and that equals
m1 divided by m2 times 2 to the power of
B 1 minus e 2 once again reduction we're
doing it so that now we only have to
deal with numbers in the range from 1 to
2 everything else is taken care of by
this exponent extraction so that's the
first step
here we go the result ok now what this
is and I will explain how we get these
in a minute this is an approximation to
one on why it's a polynomial this is
using Horner's rule so this is if you
like it's you know for some your one
times X this X plus T 3 times X etc etc
only goes up to be for anyway I could
have just included that but the way we
do it is by factoring out X in if you
like there's a fact there's a common
factor of X here so we just multiplied
this next time
and and then do the same there this is
the way we usually evaluate polynomials
because it's usually it causes the
fewest numeric problems it's not the and
one thing that people especially you
know being Triple A game programmers or
people who write the sine and cosine
library for console platforms which are
often different from the ones that you
see in mercy standard libraries they
don't like this because this is very
serial you've got the the result of like
you have to vet I shouldn't be do that
multiplication before you can do this
addition and so on
and so do the long chain of data
dependencies here and a lot of kind of
the big Triple A game programmers do not
like this there is a related method that
we may talk about if we have time
otherwise we might have to do this again
and we'll we'll talk about one way to
get around that serial that that being
serial calculation anyway so what this
is is these are these are the
coefficients of the polynomial and this
is a polynomial approximation to one on
Y in the range 1 to 2 these numbers look
magic they're not magic they're just
sufficiently advanced technology but it
gives about 11 bits of accuracy within
0.01 try it if you don't believe me I'll
hold on there I'll put it on the wiki or
something and and you can try it for
yourself but I will explain how we get
these numbers sir this 11 bits of
accuracy
I didn't pick that at random let me show
you how I picked that whoops okay let me
show you how I picked that this is a
document we've seen before
No
this one that one this is document we've
seen before which is the UM the Intel
software developer's manual I'm sure
that this has turned up on the stream
before I seem to remember it oh yes if
you search for reciprocal what you find
is there is an instruction here here we
go
an instruction called compute reciprocal
of scalar single precision flow which is
a slight light isn't what is is an
approximate reciprocal which is good to
around 1.5 times to the minus 12 so now
I did not pick this 11 bits at random
this is what this instruction gives and
what this actually does is what the FPU
is actually doing is it's actually used
a lookup table because you know modern
CPUs we can waste lots of transistors on
a ROM and so inside the FPU it doesn't
use a polynomial approximation like this
for the division operation it uses this
approximation that's based on the table
available until very kindly gave us a or
me where of which is it's the
approximate square root you may have to
back in 15 seconds there intel gave us
what it gave us basically an instruction
which accesses that lookup table ah okay
yes because it needs it anyway
sometimes you need a reciprocal to
eleven bits of precision computing a
lighting calculation even in high
definition
oh sorry oh it was a high dynamic range
then actually only about 12 bits I think
so I reciprocal it's less than 1.5 x to
the minus 12 might be good enough
so it is a handy instruction to have
around and same with reciprocal of
square root once again the the mere
existence of this instruction actually
gives you a clue to how it's being
implemented inside the fact that it
gives you an approximate reciprocal
square root instead of an approximate
square root over to what algorithm the
FPU is using to calculate square roots
I'm not gonna go into do happen to know
what it is this is also this is gold
from its division algorithm that's
called Schmidt's square root algorithm
and the one of the nice things about
this is that the inner loop of the
square root algorithm uses is three uses
of the same circuit so you only have to
invent one kind of circuit to implement
square root that's its key advantage
there
similarly here all we do is
multiplication as we will see I know
that that looks like a subtraction but
wait I will show you okay so what what
we have here is we have an a number so
we've we've now decided that where we've
got n divided by D numerator divided by
denominator where we know denominator is
in the range between 1 and 2 so we can
use this to get 11 bits of precision on
an approximation to 1 on D in this case
and so we can multiply both the
numerator and the denominator by this
number and what that will give us is it
will give us a new numerator we'll call
it n 0 divided by D 0 where D 0 is 1
plus all number 11 you know point 0 0 1
now if we multiply this number by 2
minus D 0 or 2 minus T 0 times T 0 is 1
+ x - -1 + e equals 1 + e times
- which equals 1 minus e squared we know
that E is a small number less than point
zero zero one good - a battle
probably good - about 11 bits so this is
within 20 so this is one in a thousand
this is within one and a million of one
if we do this twice and this is what
we're doing here we actually do that
twice we want both the numerator to -
the denominator from the previous step
we get a number that's close enough to
one that it's it's it's one and so
that's that's how that's how division
works is you you multiply both the
numerator and the denominator by 2 - the
denominator twice we don't actually have
to do the second one because we care
about nominator we know that's close to
one and so the numerator is is an X
divided by Y and then we just put the
exponent back set the sign bit so we did
some some sign hackery up there so that
so that we know it's between one we're
not negative one negative two and that
division works so straightforward or do
it or do I need to go over that again
that seems pretty straightforward
at least to me I will double check for
questions but again like I think yeah
the only part that is is it's needs
explanation its part you were going to
go into about how the magic constants
are picked the final thing that I'll
talk about and this is just really
really quick is this - - the denominator
the the FPU doesn't actually do that
what it does is it has a trick you can
do if you've got lots of extra precision
like you're using a double to calculate
floats you don't actually need to do 2 -
denominator and the reason is if you
have a number like let's let's suppose
that the nominators listens your let's
say zero point one one okay something
like that we want to minus that so
that's 2 - right that's 2 in binary
- that now I I just picked this number
at random but I can tell you exactly
what it is it's 1.2 I I didn't I didn't
have to I didn't have to think very hard
about that for reasons that won't come
clear at the moment what this number is
is this is this number with all its bits
flipped and then adding a 1 to the last
place so that's the two's complement to
- to - that number is the two's
complement of that number
this little last little add a 1
operation is so small that we don't care
we're using lots of extra bits of
precision to calculate this so all
rather than 2-0 what it actually uses is
not d0 so that we can't really do I mean
I guess we could but anyway anyway
they're division operations so it's
alright okay so that's so now we're not
gonna worry about all of this from now
on
we're just going to we're just going to
look at actually how we how with how we
do things like approximations like this
let me just make sure that that is in
fact the next thing on the agenda yes
okay so that is how to come up with
polynomial nations for things and this
is I think where we start getting out of
big bit hackery and start talking maths
so I'm on firm ground here so the one
you may be familiar in from high school
maths with Taylor series and Maclaurin
series where - Maclaurin series is that
f of X
F of 0 plus X F X times I'm a zero where
this is the derivative x squared on 2
factorial second derivative 0 and this
is a this is an equality this is
actually for if for any sufficiently
well behaved function X this is actually
equality this is equal if you add up all
the infinite number of terms on the
right you get a function that is f at
least around the point you can also do
it around a different point by saying X
minus X plus a yeah I think it's X plus
a is a or is it X minus a I can never
remember it doesn't matter anyway
because we're not going to use this
important point is that it's like minus
I so the thing is that this is actually
a good way to approximate a function at
point but we don't actually want to
approximate a function at a point we
want to approximate it over a range so
in this case for example we want our
approximation to one on Y that's good in
the range from 1 to 2 not at the point 1
point 5 what we really want is a a
polynomial that gives that's known as
the minimax polynomial that it minimizes
the maximum error over that range and
there's a mathematician named chebyshev
he's a 19th century russian
mathematician who is in this problem and
he came up with a very interesting
theory about this most of Witten is not
important but one of the things that he
showed is that the minimax polynomial
even exists has some very interesting
properties now I'm gonna use Mathematica
here because I have a copy so so
it's gonna be easier than trying to
write at maths and and also do some
these calculations sir let's no that's
not my Mathematica syntax is so rusty
I cannot remember anything it's been
like 10 years since I've you get it yeah
yeah exactly
all right what do we got here here we go
there we go this is this is why we have
Google so we don't have to remember
things right okay this is the this is
the verbose way of saying it that's
right now let me so in this case we plot
one on X all right we will have to we'll
have to deal with a small font I think
from X from one that's that's what the
function looks like in that room I think
there's that that's big enough I assume
yes sorry to anyone who's streaming from
Australia in load F as I often have to
do sorry about that
okay so so that's it that's what it
looks like in that range calculate the
minimax approximation have to remember
the in taxi this way from X 1/2 and an
order what did I say that's what ik
you're the reason for this zero is that
this will actually calculate rash can
you say that I think all tabbing
of course made it so that we couldn't
possibly hear the explanation
it only had business there's one or the
other so the reason for this is zero
here is that is that this will calculate
a rational approximations a polynomial
divided by polynomial sometimes that's a
better approximation even for an
American all but ever phone lists very
well approximated by use a rational
approximation and pay for the division
alright so we have this now there's our
there's our approximation there and what
you'll find is that that is exactly that
so that's how I got that I just used
Mathematica I will explain the algorithm
to do this in a minute but I just want
to show you because this isn't minimax
approximation I want to show you a very
interesting property of it which is that
now minimax approximation actually
approximate actually minimizes the
relative error rather than the absolute
error so I'm slightly cheating a little
bit here so but if we plot you relative
versus absolute error okay so so the
absolute error is if you like a minus B
whereas the relative error is a minus B
divided by the two today or B so if you
like it's the absolute error it might be
it's good to within point zero zero one
whereas an absolute error might be it's
good to within point ma the relative
error the reason why relative error is
sometimes a more useful thing is because
these floating point numbers really are
kind of relative yes that value epsilon
is the smallest number such that 1 plus
epsilon is not equal to Epsilon
similarly to
epsilon is the smallest number such that
2 plus 2 epsilon is not equal to 2 and
so the the relative errors in
floating-point arithmetic like that so
that's the that's so this is the
relative error between this polynomial
and one on X in the range 1 to what the
error function looks like as you can see
it's it's okay it's within point zero
zero three so maybe I was lying about it
being good to within point zero zero one
yeah I'll change it oh no what zero zero
zero so this is the difference a between
the approximation or approximate okay
and this oscillation theorem behind this
is the chebyshev's equal function
theorem well it's usually known as and
the point of it is that this function
oscillates around zero but also that the
peaks have the same magnitude that is it
hits this somewhere around it's it's
actually here it is it's point zero zero
zero two nine seven three five four
that's the actual number that it's
calculated there that it hits that
number there then negative that number
then that number then negative that
number then then that number there
negative that number and certainly
errors same magnitude and they alternate
in sign and this is this is a really
interesting property it kind of makes
sense when you think about it if one of
these Peaks was a little higher or a
little lower that would probably mean we
haven't quite optimized it correctly
mm-hmm but this is this this it's this
equius elation
property that actually it turns out
helps us to find the minimax polynomial
because instead of trying
find the minimax polynomial what we do
is we try and look for an error function
that looks like this now just as a
little aside the the named chebyshev may
be familiar to some people you may have
heard of chebyshev polynomials chebyshev
approximation and so forth he worked a
lot on this one of the things that's
gonna come up in a minute is what I'm
gonna call the chebyshev nodes and I'm
just gonna briefly explain what what
that is the other because there's
another little feature of this that's
that he's not part of the equity
oscillation theorem but it is kind of
important and that's that the places
where this crosses the zero axis across
across this axis they get closer
together the further towards the ends of
the interval you see so these two roots
the places where it crosses the the
x-axis are closer together than nerves
so if you and this extends further so if
I come up with a degree 15 approximation
no working precision - there we go 100
digits there we go
so there we go are this in order 15
polynomial that's that's it's good
hundred hundred decimal places and if I
say P to X I'm probably not using
mathematical will here and now if I plot
the difference there between that and p2
and maybe that was not a good example
let's let's use something you can say
I'm very well prepared for this let's
come up with a twin order seven people
have to work through things on the
stream so absolutely okay so this
approximation is good 1.5 times 10 minus
6 awesome and now
will flop that there and we'll see okay
so there you go
so once again you can see the distance
between these two routes here is larger
than distance between these which is
lives in distance he owns larger than
the difference here but this crosses the
the axis and also of course the distance
between these Peaks it gets smaller as
you as you get to all the ones of the
range
now if explained they are artists that
he came up with they're helping his
approximation Theory make sure there's
something a lunatic so this is this is
this is the area curve between a
function that's a polynomial and the
function that's that's not a polynomial
one on X is not a polynomial of finite
degree I'm going to plot it says the
average of functions built-in magically
so that's one two three four five six
seven eight so I'm going to use the
whoops the the order eight polynomial X
in the range 1 to 1 but this is a polyp
this is a set of polynomials that
chebyshev came up with they have nothing
to do with one on X whatsoever this is
the polynomial go back about 15 seconds
there I missed that last part it was
show up an out so this is a set of
polynomials that he came up with there's
one for every order so this is the
eighth degree polynomial I'll see how
they defined there there's one it's the
first one that see auto zero polynomial
second one is X so that's if you like t
0x that's one of X is 1 then T n plus 1
of X is 2 T in minus P of n minus 1 know
but these are how to find they are also
equals a cause in cause X doesn't look
like a polynomial trust me at the
polynomial at Z this is I'm bringing
this up so that you so that this art
cause doesn't seem like it doesn't seem
like med come up to in the middle and
these polynomials as it turns out tend
to approximate these error curves very
well this is in the range negative one
to one that's just standard range
whereas this in the range 1 to 2 which
is the range we care about and so we can
start looking for an error function of
this kind by starting with the
polynomial that looks like this and
that's that is kind of that get assessed
looking but the way that works is an
algorithm school and the idea is I
missed the name rim is right I kicked it
is rim is it's not rim if or something
like that
now let me let me just see if I can I've
got the example here yeah here we go so
if we have an initial guess as to where
these peaks are right let's say they're
at X 0 X 1 X 2 X 3 blah blah blah blah
blah and what we can do and set up a
linear system a system equations that
looks like this
here we go so a 0 plus a 1 X 0 plus a 2
a 2 X Y plus e equals f of X 0 F is the
function that we're trying to find an
approximation to so what we're saying is
that this polynomial let's let looking
for cubic plus a 3
but the error between this polynomial
and the actual function is equal to e at
that point right that we've found this
point we'll say we've found this point
x0 which is this point where the extrema
and and the air are between sorry this
one here they look so similar that the
distant that the difference between the
function that we're trying to calculate
and the polynomial approximation is
exactly equal to and then at the next
point x1 the error is minus because it's
the same magnitude and the opposite sign
and then we just keep going for the next
one and that's plus e because the next
one is the next sign and I'm sorry they
say x1 x2 and then this gives us a
linear system because we know what these
are these x0 x1 x2 are our initial
guesses right and then we this gives and
this is this is this is so x0 we know x0
x0 to the three is just a number so this
gives us an a system of linear equations
that are unknown in a 0 a 1 a 2 a 3 and
E and if we solve that system we get an
approximate polynomial because these are
the coefficients of the polynomial and
an estimate of the error and if you have
a look at minimax polynomial here one of
the things that it does is this what the
outputs are I'll give you a smaller one
yeah
these are the points where it thought
that the extrema were these points here
here's the polynomial and he is e so
this matter is giving you your Z and
it's giving you the the points where the
extrema are notice what one of them is
one and one of them is two they are
typically the ends of the range extrema
points it's giving you the polynomial
and it's also giving you the error
because that is the maximum error no it
gives you the polynomial it also gives
you the the
in the approximation so once you've done
that that gives you a polynomial then
what you can do is you can say okay
let's assume that that is the minimax
polynomial and we'll find the extrema
points so we'll we'll actually subtract
that polynomial from from F and find
point that differs the most and then use
that as a next approximation to go
through the loop again and solve the
system again and for behaved functions
this gives you the minimax polynomial if
you iterate enough times
now this is a very tricky e a very
tricky thing to get your head around I
think should we stop here and get some
questions on this I think so my question
is just starting with your initial
guesses I have seen that sort of thing
before obviously where you know it's
like okay so you try to make some Ischl
guesses and if it's an algorithm that's
about convergence then typically you
know there's ways of trying to do good
initial guesses and stuff like this but
so that part is not sure is a sort of a
separate issue but once you start this
process I so I put the initial guesses
in for my my locations of the extremum
so that's x0 x1 x2 correct okay you
timed out it you lagged out at just the
wrong point but you need to repeat that
question I'm sorry so my initial guesses
are the limit are the are the zero
crossings x0 x1 x2 are zero crossings
yes but no it's actually for extremum
okay it's exist yeah but but yeah but
let me let me okay so that does require
that that does require a little
explanation okay device shortened so
that's the that's the eighth order
chebyshev polynomial let me show you
what the ninth order polynomial looks
like places the place where this crosses
the zero axis is the extremum of this
polynomial and the place where this
process the x axis is the next
extremely spicy and it's it's really not
obvious here yeah but if you have one
nice property of these polynomials
chebyshev define and theory and it
actually does quite well to just not
bother with this iterative thing and
just trying to proximate with a backrub
chebyshev polynomials added together and
that actually a lot of older numerical
analysis textbooks just tell you to do
that okay and then they tell you okay
now let's just add the next order of
oxidation and then but a property with
operation this this link is awful I'm so
surprised at how tough it is to talk to
Australia I'm sorry it's perilously
different hemisphere
I could rant about this at length that
you probably wouldn't he immersed of it
so let's not well also the thing is
ridiculous that Google's like I'd ever
understand why chat programs don't just
buffer up what you say and then send it
losslessly with error correction like I
can wait to hear what you have to say
yeah if I could hear it correctly but
instead they prioritize real game which
I don't care about that
you know exactly exactly I guess the
video conferencing or something like
that it makes even so what would what is
it where it's not worth it if I can't
understand you right it's you failed at
the primary task in service of some
secondary thing okay I'd like to point
out by the way that this is home
internet we're talking about here when
I'm actually at work I work at a
university in the University of
Melbourne the internet there is fabulous
okay because it's designed for you know
I been with research and so this is why
I this is why you never see me stream
this is why my streams have been
historically silent for those who
remember the few times I stream is
because it's just not worth it so okay
let me ask my other question now that
because I think want to get that
clarified because I was wasn't sure
which one it was I so my other question
for the iteration I'm not sure I quite
understand so yes you're saying that you
switch so once I do one initial guess I
linearly solve for a and then I plug the
A's back in as my new X's no no I didn't
get okay all right what you need to do
then is you need to find the real points
where this polynomial get okay so so
you've done that if you've done one
iteration you've now got this yes you've
now got you've now got this he of X
you've now got this polynomial
approximation to F yes but of course
it's not it's not it's not equal to even
if it's an approximation it's not equal
to so there's some error function X
equals P of X minus f of X right where
this is again it's a real function not a
polynomial this is your polynomial what
you now do is you search along is you
search this function experiment now that
requires typically some kind of search
on F the easiest way to do it is to find
the places where it crosses the the
x-axis again because it's just the roots
of this function you know you can use
like newton raphson okay method or
something to find the zeros and then
between those zeros you're going to find
a maximum or a minimum yes okay okay if
it's well-behaved you can do it by
fitting pull a network by fitting
parabolas there's a really nice
algorithm which I'm going to introduce
everyone to now which is called golden
section search which is a very high
precision high-quality one and lots of
people do this for when they do videos
explaining it but golden section
searches and as a technique for finding
the minimum or maximum of a strictly
unimodal function so
this error function is going to be
unimodal it's going to be you know it's
gonna be like shaped like a loop like
this or loop like this between two roots
of the function so it is unimodal in
that right and so you can use golden
section search if you want to do
something really really principle look
there's even code in Python there if you
want to code in Python there we go okay
so they are golden section search is is
is a good way of doing that or you can
use the other way you can do it is by
fitting parabolas right you can fit a
parabola to this function find the
extremum and then say okay use that as a
refinement to fit another parabola I'm
not gonna okay section search is a
really nice function to know about okay
quite a lot especially if you've got
like a weird golden section search all
right so that's the that's the that's
the basic idea it's their image remiz
exchange algorithm and by iterating on
enough times you do get a minimax
approximation and that is pretty much
but as I said I just used Mathematica
because I'm lazy I have actually Remos
exchange algorithm I've got the source
code sitting around using the new multi
precision library and reason why I'm not
showing you the source code is the new
new multi version library is pretty
horrible actually no yeah it's it's ugly
work but someone's got to do with it
okay
I wouldn't deploy I wouldn't deploy card
using it but to calculate constants that
you deploy I I'm very happy okay all
right all right
so that's that's an army all
approximation there's a lot more that
can be said about that and we're not
going to say it here the important thing
that I wanted to show you is that
there's number come from yes there's the
advanced technology all right
so that's that and now it's signing yeah
so we're actually Wiggy to the actual
replacing the functions that we've got
now let me just have a look at my notes
just track Lee what we want to do the
sine function you know you know what's
and you know it looks like sine X in the
rain it looks like it repeats itself and
the the the period of the repeat the
distance between that and that when you
get another copy of it is 2 so what we
kind of want to do is we want to divide
by 2 pi and take the remainder and that
reduces the range from there to there so
we only have to deal with numbers in
that range
or maybe from negative PI to PI be a
useful range as well and in fact
negative PI to PI is the one that I
chose the trouble is that pi is is a
transit little number it does not exact
operation it so it doesn't represent in
in floating-point but conceptually what
we want to do with this we want to take
X multiply it by 1 over 2 pi whatever
number that is truncate it to an integer
and that gives us like the X divided by
2 pi and then we want to take the
remainder we take X subtract n times 2
pi and that gives us a number in the
range 0 to PI so that's that's that's
alright but the problem is that there
are a couple problems one of them is
wave X is large
now obviously a real implementation of
sine and cosine near one for one for the
this Israel but one for the C standard
library will have to deal with numbers
up to the range 2 to the 1 e6 or
whatever it is and we can deal with X
you know in a much more limited range
than that we've got this this truncation
to an integer which is actually more
expensive operation than you might think
and there are ways around that but we've
also got the problem that where you've
got X where X is close to a multiple of
2 pi
let's say it's it's somewhere around 2
pi what you're subtracting is two
numbers that are almost and this traffic
cancellation which that's but it's not
gonna actually it's not actually it's
it's what happens is that you've got two
mantises that are almost equal and when
you subtract them what you end up with
is the way around and to get off to get
a number that that's that's higher
precision is we can actually split 2 pi
up now again I have x again I've got
some constants here let me tell you
there is two constants oops
Sixpoint so 2 pi is what's 2 pi 2 times
pi whoops
expresses okay let me just in that
[Music]
there we go okay so at six point two
eight three one nine ish what I've done
is I split this up into two numbers one
of those six point two three eight two
and the other one is negative that is
this this number is not special this is
two pi minus this number but this number
is special because it it looks like it's
close to two pi but it has this
representation in its bit pattern and
the thing that I want you to see is all
these euros at the end I do we designed
this constant has twelve zeros at the
end of the significant field and that
means that we can multiply this by a
number to jar up to 320 it's a power of
two multiplied this missed that last
part thanks to the internet we can
multiply this by a number by two 1024
because 1,024 is just manipulating
exponent anything lower than that we've
got these boo and to work with any
number up to 1000 any integer up to 1024
this multiplication gives an exact
result okay okay so okay so you can
multiply this number by 999 and the
number that you get is exact you could
write it by 100 and 999 again and you'll
get exactly this number okay okay this
number is 2pi minus k1 and it's and this
gives you what this is under 12 yeah
this is 23 bits of precision on the on
the on the number two pi okay which is
more than one small serving point number
yeah single precision okay and then what
we do is we just do
roost x equals x minus n times K 1 minus
n times and that gives you X reduced
into this range 0 to PI or whatever it
is to to a higher precision then you
would get bison by 2 pi at the cost of
another multiply in a subtract and we
are going to find and using a divide at
some point or something
we are not going to use it ok so what
we're doing here is we're multiplying it
by 1 over 2 pi moles or something you'll
you'll see multiplication divisions are
slower but of course we saw the division
algorithm it uses a lot of
multiplications yes so so you shouldn't
you shouldn't run away from divisions
screaming but if we can do it without
divisions a little better ok ok now
here's the next thing which is how we
actually find in because first thing is
I've got this number which is one point
five two via Knight Epsilon this is a
large number
Ramar are 32 epsilon is a small number
it's 10 to the minus an or something so
1 point 5 divided by that is a large
this is an exact number of course this
is to the minus 23 so this is 1.5 times
2 to the power of 23 so it's a
reasonably big number but it's a number
that has this really interesting feature
that if you take a number like x times 1
over 2 pi add that number and then
subtract that number it has the effect
of rounding acts rounding this value to
an integer as long as this addition and
subtraction fit so this will only worked
for X in a certain range but you know
where we're saying this this work up
doesn't as it
C standard library implantation has to
look over the whole range of numbers and
so special case this a lot but up to a
thousand is probably good enough it's
probably not good enough for the the
audio thing you did really really early
on that same wave right right right
probably not going to use it because it
runs too long enough it's real earnest
but but yeah so don't do that but four
rotations really a thousand radians is
it's it's like three hundred rotations
you should not be out in not for games
no yeah okay and so this has the effect
of of but using the floating-point unit
to round this number to an integer but
it's an edit an integer that's
represented as a floating point number
yes and so that's and so that's how we
do it now the actual current is a little
bit more complicated than that so let's
let's actually have a look at the
implementation wait I keep I keep
opening new editors every time I need
something
I alt tabbed so I'm going to be quiet
for a second some people on the stream
were asking if you could turn the video
bitrate down but I don't know if that's
actually possible anymore than it
already is
yeah sorry I can't okay so this is the
actual code in the the sine cosine table
version that I implemented so this said
the the signatures it takes an X a
pointer to a sine X and a pointer to a
closed set cosine X and it stores sine
cosine in there so here's that round two
integer here's the range reduction which
I've actually used three constants for
and I will explain that minute it turned
out that actually got a little bit more
precision by splitting this in by
splitting two pi into three constants
this K to again has that property that
if you multiply it by a number up to
about a thousand it's it's an exact
representation and there's that X times
1 over 2 pi plus R and n minus R and
danger and then it does this down of
range reduction using only k1 and k2 and
then I use k3 here to adjust the answer
so you've got so this is x times okay so
this is that this is the table lookup
heart which will talk because this would
be the other I think
thing about about this this code is that
so this this basically does that
rounding it to rounding it to an integer
here and then we can use sorry this here
in in is a floating point number and we
don't have to need to turn back again
all right now let's take a quick - a
quick a quick look at trigonometric
identities because this so again this is
probably high school maths no it wasn't
a high school maths for me strangely
enough when I was in high school we
didn't really do a trigonometric
identities very much but I understand it
curriculum yeah no really which is
interesting but the thing is I never
remember them anyway and usually yeah
and you shouldn't because whenever I
need a trigonometric identity I derived
and let me tell you how I derive it
there are two identities and I remember
one of them is this one sine squared X
plus cosine squared X and I remember
because it's Pythagoras T yep
you have a right-angled triangle with
one on the hypotenuse base power so he
should be memorize that one please
memorize that one yep
the other one that I memorize is this
one is that x pi x equals cosine X plus
I sine X where ice is negative one not
the square root of negative one please
don't make that mistake it annoys people
then e to the power of I X is cosine X
plus I sine of X and this is Euler Euler
EUL ER Euler and Euler and Gauss have so
many things named after them you can be
forgiven for their saying oh yes you're
probably 50% chance of being right if
you name one of those two in this kind
of entry function arithmetic especially
all right so other way this is suppose
you want to know what cosine of a plus B
is or because if I do this plus I times
sine of a plus B and this is equal to e
to the power of I a plus B hey that's
just that identity applied let's expose
e to the power of yet let me let me do
that for that sir everyone knows that
expose e to the power of right yes but
he is Euler's concept people when
7-1-8-2 when they
well hello Bob yeah basis natural
logarithms okay
this is equal to e to the I a times e to
the I be hey that's the index laws here
distributive law of that which is equal
to cosine of a plus I sine of a times
cosine of B plus I sine B equals B
[Music]
because that's I signed I sine B is
negative I plus I times a sine a and I'm
gonna put parentheses around here
because now we can match up the real and
imaginary parts of that line and that
line and what we find is that sine of a
plus B equals that and sine of a plus B
equals that now we go there there there
and this memorize another another
trigonometric identity again so that's
that's it for anyone who's doing high
school American high school maths okay
what this that's these formulas is it
gives us if we can calculate cosine a at
a point a cosine a and Sinai at a point
then we can calculate values of cosine
around a so if we if instead of B we
think of it as this is epsilon small
number right then if we've got cosine of
a and sine of a of a point then just
then this cosine of e and sine of the if
we can come up with a nice polynomial
approximation that's good in a small
around this formula gives us a way to
calculate cosine at a point around that
belt
so we're using here and by the way the
reason why I'm using this approach is
that this code is branch free and this
is since I read between the lines of the
requirements it is even what on a
calculator it's going to be much easy to
calculate force can you say the part
from read between the lines again that
was like for some reason it dropped out
it's pretty severely there couldn't
quite reconstruct it I read between the
line and the requirements here for
example stuff and I figured probably
want ease you probably want a version
that you can do for signs and for
persons yes yes you know vector
instructions yes pretty much anything
that you're gonna do in a math library
in a game these days wants to be able to
be done wide and it can have branches
but you have to factor in the cost of
those branches both branches will be
taken so usually it doesn't help you if
if one of you know if you're doing a
branch to save time that really doesn't
help you that's right now I am trying a
different approach down here and I'm a
ridge eventually going to get rid of
these branches down here but will will
well just have a quick look at that mode
this is experimental code it does not
work it's buggy you do not use it okay
the only catch here is these dependent
loads is that this table lookup does
require taking a number converting it to
an integer and then reading a table now
the table is only that and this in a
couple of cars so it's a small table I'm
not concerned about the cost of the load
you know getting riddle getting rid of a
floating point square root even and if
it what if you want square root because
it's it's expensive and you're replacing
with
Kashmir's that's actually a bad right so
if you are using tables you want to make
them small but this still is a dependent
load here yeah
so I did defer to your rent the thing is
on making this into a vector with it if
you want but but you know something for
okay so what we've got here is this -
outland this table is this is a value of
x this is sine of X and this is cosine
of X at various sample points what I
decided to do was I originally tried
using these sample points so what we do
is we sample cosine sine and cosine it
at bunch of points and then we use a
polynomial approximation for sine and
cosine using done using Mathematica
using exactly what we've discussed to
calculate sine and cosine in a smaller
range so I originally used integer we're
now using 1/2 in this because it
improves things enormous ly the table
features fits in a cache line which is
very nice fits into cache lines
I think it's an acceptable trade if we
sample them we're sampling in there in
the range negative pi to pi because this
range reduction algorithm gives us a
value in that range so I'm sampling it
at negative 3 negative 3 point 5 sorry
2.5 2.5 on I've but these are the points
that I'm blinging that and I say sort of
because it's actually not quite the
reasons that will become clear in a
moment so we this is that's the reason
for this x 2 here is we multi-is we're
taking this value that we've done here
we've got here which is X range reduced
from negative pi to pi multiplying it by
2 rounding it to an integer again
probably don't need to round it to an
integer actually we can probably just do
this
yeah in fact let's do that let's keep
that in case that's probably fine this
six is just to do with the fact that
arrays start at zero in C counting
starts at zero as always started at zero
even before zero was invented counting
started it's true this table has a
wonderful talk on this that explaining
how counting is always started at zero
he's one of them probably the most cited
computer scientist of all time
and he has wonderful paper titles like
theorems from think paper titles but yes
it's wonderful talk on on things it's in
retrospect and one of them things that's
obvious in reading starts at zero yeah
just a little okay but what you might
notice here is this is this is the value
of x plus yeah and it's not exactly and
this is between negative two point five
I've this in scientific notation
that's not exactly negative two and
that's not exactly negative one point
offset them slightly yes and you can do
this once you're thinking in terms of
these tables you know there's there's no
reason why you can't we have to sample
at that point and there are two reasons
well there's a good reason for putting X
in here and that means and that's so
that this calculation doesn't have to be
exact
if we if if this if there's some round
of error in here all that means is that
we were close to one point five and we
went slightly high instead of slightly
but that's okay if we just make these
polynomials nations just a little wider
so they work over a slightly range the
negative five point five two point five
we can weaken comments
for that first reason that's a good
reason to put it in the table but the
other reason is is once you've decided
that you've put X in the table it
doesn't have to be exactly under the
range and again I do not numbers at
random I picked them for it through very
careful reason let me just run it I have
actually got code and this is will be
part of the thing which calculates these
tables about sine curves tables where we
find a line somewhere around negative 3
somewhere around negative two point five
somewhere around negative and now well
let me so let me give you the example
here this is this is an actual result
this is this is 0.5 so this is what we
get for 0.5 so instead of 0.5 actually
years that number which is a few
floating-point numbers away from from
0.5 and the reason why is that one the
difference is 2 times 10 to the minus 6
so that's a very very small number of
radians but the reason why is because
sine and cosine property here
this is a double precision okay and
stuff we did earlier to this sine of
that number in all these zeros at the
end yep yeah I picked that number
because it's close to that but also it's
got all easy rows at the end and in
particular this number fits in a single
precision float in a binary 32 so this
is a double double precision and so that
fit you know good double precision and
so this number here is pretty close to
exact as is this one as is this one as
is this one these numbers are very close
to it I see
and one little more precision out of the
head of the value
so okay so this involves searching
floating-point numbers and again I did
not implement this in a handmade kind of
way I used the c standard library for
this but there's a little function that
not many people know about it's in
method age there actually there's
actually a family of functions well one
of them is next after and the other one
is next toward and what is next after f
of X of x plus hundred this gives you
the next floating-point number after X
in the direction of X plus 100 okay so
using this technique what we can do is
we can search adjacent floating-point
numbers so in this case what I've done
is I've said we'll search a hundred
floating-point numbers in each direction
and what we want is the best one that is
we want one with the most zeros after
the little 32 mantissa
so so if you like we we go up to the end
of the to the mentis of a single
precision float then we count the zeros
following and we want the one with the
most and in the case of ties we want the
one that's closest that that's closest
but these these loops do they calculate
sine and cosine in double precision
using the library because high quality B
and it's slow as well it's not what we
want for handmade here oh but it's fine
for and then we calculate that we count
the zeros after it so I've replicated
some of this real 32 stuff in real 64
here this but and there's there's the
union for it that because I need to work
with doubles and then here's the thing
that counts the zeros after real don't
do that I just did it as a I think I
just did it as a loop yeah just in his
loop you know again if this was speed we
cared about we use its can reverse or
something and again to handle the
subnormal case we use two two
fifty-five instead of to the 23 which we
used in there in the previous example we
don't adjust the exponent for that
because we don't care about the exponent
we're just looking for zeros in the
mantissa and and and that's basically
all we do the code is is actually quite
straightforward once you understand the
bit hackery that's going on here and so
that's how we calculate there's sine and
cosine tables and then the only thing
left is this is a polynomial
approximation to cosine this is a
polynomial first equation to sign and
this is a slightly rearranged polynomial
evaluation with some you know we share
some of it here but it is essentially
the same thing that's going on it's just
rearranged a little bit further for
precision so that the most important
terms are added on at the end yeah and
the other thing is of course this third
constant k3 that we split to Paynter we
just added on to XD here and that way it
doesn't have to go through this
rigmarole we've preserved these very
small error compensation term and we
just added in the XT here and that's the
argument of the poem um that was a long
that was a long speech familiar is there
anything that anyone did not live so I
have a couple questions asked I can ask
so my first question is can you go back
to the table there because so so the
thing that I'm sure if I looked at the
code more carefully I would probably
understand but yeah you've got two terms
coming out of the table but then you've
got a bunch of terms that are the same
no matter where you are in the table how
can you add a little more exposition
there to why part of it looks up the
table part of it's the same no matter
where you are do you mean do you sorry
do you mean like that that do you mean
do you mean that some of these title
entries are the same
the question you're asking no no what I
meant was so to look up into the table
you're getting back some part of the
computation going forward but then no
matter where you were when you looked up
your base point in the table the
polynomial terms don't have to get
looked over those are the same
everywhere and that was just that's
quite until I look at work everybody I I
wouldn't be able to figure out why that
was only if you could explain that at
part a little bit okay sure so what
you're doing is you're looking up cosine
of a plus T where a is a point that's
sampled in the table right so cosine a
and curse and Sinai are stored in the
table write cosine E and sign e are the
polynomial approximation okay right and
they're gonna be the same because you're
always around zero at that point around
zero at that point right we take to work
out the Oakland area we take X prime
which is X that's been range reduced
subtract X in the table and that makes
it between roughly negative 0.5 and 0.5
yeah and then this little arrow
compensation to that and so the reason
why X it's XD here he's always in the
range somewhere around negative 0.5 to
somewhere around positive 0.5 it is
slightly wider because I did actually I
put the difference between X and the
sample point here and I took the maximum
of those and expanded the range of that
the polynomial is good at and by that a
little bit and then I expanded it again
by by a number that's related to K 3
don't close that era compensation to him
so I I was very very careful about this
again these numbers are not magic it's
just
that's that's the that's the reason for
that it's an XD - because these are the
East polynomials this this is things
there's the zero to zero X to the six
this is always X to the 1 X - 3 X 5 X to
the 7 these are all odd values because
it centered around zero makes sense
we pre calculate x squared as well
calculation later on these are the
right-hand sides of cosine and sine from
c2 to c6 so that's a Horner's rule
calculation there you can actually see
that looks like a polynomial valuation
we just plug those in but we take the
first couple of polynomial evaluations
and add them on at the end just so that
you you sometimes can get an exposition
again it's not magic it's just a little
tricky yes sorry so my other question
would be so yet for if trying to do wide
versions of these it's very hard to do
table lookups because each Lane has to
look up a different entry and in the
table typically so what sort of stuff
would you end up doing if you couldn't
use the table so this is this is where
this this version comes in okay so this
is this is as I said this is
experimental code where where what I'm
doing here is doing range reducing
instead of from the range negative if hi
I'm Ranger adducing range from zero that
part of it okay so the sine of a X from
zero to
hmm is that and the curse sign is that
and these are just mirror images of a
yes a because this and that are mirror
images of each other we should be able
to evaluate it by simply using a
different X pi on to - X yes and then
evaluating the same approximation there
again for this part of the range here
that shape there is the same as that
shape there only its negative yes this
shape here is the same as this shape
here only it's a mirror image around
that line so so the other way of doing
it and this is a common we'll find is to
is to use this kind of quadrant analysis
you decide which which part of this you
know which you know that's a polynomial
it looks so much like a side yeah it's
that's kind of shockingly the same it
yeah yeah exactly so this is this is the
sine curve you know this is like is one
whole period you split into quadrants
there's one quadrant here one quadrant
here one quadrant here and one quadrant
here and this is the they only differ by
flipping the sign of the answer and also
kind of mirror imaging around kind of a
line imagine a line drawn down there yes
so that's that's what I'm trying to do
here
at the moment I'm doing it with case
analysis and in this case is buggy at
the moment I and you know is these
negative sign adjusts yeah what I
eventually want to do is I want to turn
this into bit hackery so that we can do
that path branch free and then just do
two polynomial evaluations they use the
same approximation because you know one
of them is just the mirror image of each
other so that's okay in theory you could
do both of these in power in using
vector instructions or maybe you don't
want to if you want to calculate
you know for sines and cosines in
parallel maybe just don't want to bother
with that and just through theirs in
parallel that's usually how it's these
are completely independent usually you
yeah impute them in parallel because
typically if you're in a
performance-oriented scenario packing
and unpacking is just do you lose too
much time so they typically try to go
like all right look let's just process
things in bulk so we're gonna try and
take four angles in and spit for but
also of course this is a this is a
sequential computation it's data
dependent right this see depends on that
this see depends on that and so
interleaving these two computations yes
would probably look quite a lot as well
well the CPU will do that for you
automatically these days of course yeah
so okay so but you said this routine
wasn't working yet
you you have a big do not use on the top
of it so what's what haven't you done
yet here I'm curious okay I haven't
fully debugged this quadrant calculation
here there's I mean I can I can I can
show you I can I can show you so this is
this is so this is here we've got a
start here at the quadrant number so in
quadrant one well look the difference is
five times ten to the minus eight zero
zero the difference between sine X is
calculated by the C standard library and
is calculated by this routine the
difference is zero ten to the minus food
in that quadrant but when you get to
quadrant three you find that the
difference is negative three times ten
to the minus three negative one point
four times ten to the minus one so yes
sign looks correct but bug in her sign
and I I've just got that wrong or maybe
I need to I'm not sure I'm not sure what
I need to do there it was it was like 11
o'clock so I will and then my next step
after that we'll beat
turn this branch into in tuba Thackeray
so we'll try and do it with with with
you know the compare instructions that
are built into SSE and masking and and
whatever we need to do and and also of
course this this sign adjust here we'll
be extracting the sign bit and then
we'll put the sign bit back on the
answer instead of them all as well so
that's that's that's my theory with this
because I want to see which one performs
better basically this is going to
involve this will be bit hackery it will
be single line it will be single thread
branch free code but my feeling is that
it's going to be a lot of code and
probably comparable with one of these
that there'll be about as much code to
calculate this as there will be to a
calculate one of these polynomials I say
and I don't know if that is better than
a table lookup or not and there's a way
to find out table lookups do tend to be
pretty expensive just because you have
to it's it's really if to extract lookup
and repack but yeah it's yeah it's hard
to say so one of the thing I think
Fabien has often said is that he's he's
often surprised at how often table
lookup still win though um cuz like yeah
yeah yeah the conventional wisdom is
that like oh don't do a table lookup
just compute the value but then he says
when he often times when he tries it he
finds that that is not true
yes yeah exactly so who knows and that
that's why I thought that for handmade
here oh I think the right thing to do
was was to try plays yeah he's yeah the
two floating-point your C standard
library doesn't you know the
implementation of of X for example yes
or 2 to the X it will use table lookup
whereas the implantation of sine and
cosine probably doesn't it probably uses
this quadrant analysis in a high degree
polynomial probably even higher than
double precision you know might be
degree 15 or something I don't know
yes sir Oh your library does a birth
place so it's it's worth it it's worth
it's worth try both ways too you know
and and you know we'll probably be
surprised because you know our
requirements are very different from
from ceased library you've got yeah and
and tribal licensing awesome yeah
there's the audacity bugging like a
pretty select okay so that's something
look somebody has probably already
worked out the bug in this Oh probably
not yet all right all right so that's so
that's that
now the next so before we go on to
arctangent maybe you can just what it's
been two and a half hours if you want to
we can save a attend to for a separate
time it's really up to you the only
questions that I see on here were about
C 0 C 2 C 4 C 6 etc those constants that
worries for yeah so I was asking do they
have more precision than can fit in a
float oh yes that you're only well I've
written them here in more precision than
will fit in the float because this is
what came straight out of Mathematica
and I decided I'll just dump it all here
and the compiler will we'll round that
pretty much you only have about you only
have about seven digits of decimal
precision in a floating-point I mean
these are these are bigger than they are
as well but you know if you just dump
more and dump more digits than you need
in there you know calculate it with a
double and put it in and stick a little
F on the end yeah the compiler will
round it to a float for you yeah yeah
compilers are smart about that thing
okay so we'll have a quick look at I
tear into I there is really two I tend
to it this is mostly G
a tree now that this is this is I'm not
claiming that I tend to is good one of
the things that we that I did I did a
little secret stream a couple weeks ago
where I was riding a tan - if we had a
look at how handmade hero uses a ten -
do you know how handmade hero uses I
tend to so to be honest I don't think we
really use it yet in any meaningful way
I was only assuming we would eventually
use it we could get rid of it right now
it is just for like joystick direction
or something stupid like that yeah but
it's even worse than that
it's not even joystick direction it only
returns one it's only called with one of
four arguments the north south east west
okay so maybe we don't need to do a tan
- maybe we don't need to do a ten - and
maybe we'll talk about this as a few 0.2
prove again most of a 10 - is quadrant
analysis and there is a certain amount
of quadrant analysis that I do here I'm
using this is a via stress
transformation maybe maybe maybe we will
leave this for another time because
that's server load yeah - for now and we
can we can do another stream if I put it
back for a legitimate purpose in the
future so I will say one thing I tend to
a 10 he is using the techniques that
we've been talking about is it is a
water 15 polynomial here because that's
as much as I needed to get a good result
and and there's also a reduction so the
the range reduction that we that we need
to know here is if you look at arc if we
plot that out can looks like this okay
so it it it maxes maxes out at pi on to
here and negative PI on to on here but
what's interesting is that is what
happens in the range from negative one
one okay it's it's it's not it looks
like it's reasonably well behaved it
actually isn't and one of the nasty
things about a ten is that when you just
try the rim as exchange algorithm
well I rely on it the look really
doesn't work so well on a tan hmm
a tennis is behaves really weirdly like
this so yeah so once again I just use
Mathematica but I have try my
implementation of the Rimmer's exchange
algorithm on a 10 and it really doesn't
work that well it it it's very hard to
get it to converge so got you there yes
sir approximate so it is magic now that
outside one-to-one what you can use this
you can use use little identity which is
a tan of 1 on x equals negative or where
x is no no it's no it is it's high on
high on 2 minus 8 10 of X and that's
pretty much what we do here we use the
absolute X is greater than case here
where we just do and then and then
adjust that so that's that's how we get
a 10 over the whole range yeah
plantations once again standard library
orientation split the domain up into
more bucks than that because this 15
gree polynomial is kind of X but this
however the other thing I want to point
out is for the cases that handmade hero
uses a 10 to
that's that code there I can pretty much
guarantee because those I've had to
special case there's once okay the other
hypotenuse and the reason why I use a
special function for that is that you
know Pythagoras theorem it's the square
root of you know x squared plus y
squared except that x and y can overflow
value of x and so this is the hypotenuse
function up here again I'll come up with
a better one later but all right sir I
don't want to explain a 10-2 any further
right the moment because I said hand me
here it doesn't really use it at the
moment but the cases where it does use
it are dealt with in this so I should
probably go remove atan2 from the source
code then but sine and cosine we will
definitely want so yeah we'll have to
start taking a look at that based on
what you've done so far which I thank
you so much for coming and explaining
all that that was very clear actually I
feel like I have a pretty good idea
about how that sort of stuff goes now
much more so than I did certainly good
that's here so let me just um let me
just load up my Czechia and maybe we can
go to Q and I know all right let's take
a look I will put Q and I on here
hello everyone
anyone completely lost
mmm
too much maths sorry who said that that
was me okay okay if the values are
normal they will run away slow that will
run way slower sorry it 0 B 0 0 which is
a de normal number thank you for having
it to normal number as your username by
the way which cases are you talking for
which for which for which function okay
what was the reason we couldn't do two's
complement in the opponent ah the reason
why we don't do two's complement is the
exponent is B is to give is so that if
you have a bunch of zeros zero you feel
a block of memory with zero bytes and
then you read that as a floating-point
number you get the number zero if you
used to complement is complement then
that would be an exponent of 2 to the 0
which is 1 and that is a very common
case so that's that's the reason why we
don't use that's the reason why we use
the biased representation for the
exponent
it's because program is really really
like it if 0 then read is a number it's
0 ok sine and cosine all right
so mr. om is normal number for your for
your username sine and cosine yes this
is true when the cosine it's okay if
this is the question here is essentially
what happens if you are calculating the
sine or cosine of a normal number the
cursive line of a sub normal number is
all right it's it's close enough to 1/4
sine of X yes you're right you can just
use X but the reason why I don't want to
do that is I don't want to introduce a
branch
this is branch free code by design and
we want to keep it that way for all of
the reasons we've talked about and yes
that means it's sly
imprecise around that range we can check
to see they're going to be too bad this
is a wonderful book I read one this is
let me see if I can find its basic
animation stand techniques and this is a
book from way way back in the day of
traditional animation yeah it's the one
from 1977 and it was about using these
these multi playing
animation cameras it's basically a guy
Bates camera for a traditional animation
and stuff that these animation stands 2x
animation and it's got all of these
knobs down here I don't know if you can
see these knobs that do things like
rotate the camera and rotate the stand
that it's on a flat sort of thing and
these really only give you a precision
to about point zero one of a degree and
when you had to do pans and zooms and
rotates and so forth the animation stand
operator would actually have to
calculate all the sines and cosines
probably using tables or a slide rule or
some combination thereof and would
calculate and see a rotation of less
than point zero one degrees it's it's at
24 frames a second and it's it's
impossible
anything that's calculated two point
zero one degrees of precision looks so I
guess I'm slightly confused as to the
question in the first place because I
mean at least in my experience usually D
normals you want to flush to zero anyway
like a game never wants to be running
with D normal so it should never be
asking for the cosine a sine of a D
normal I think that yes so so that was
just kind of I just want to throw that
out there is that that these routines
shouldn't ever take D normals as inputs
it
we should have been flushed to zero long
before it would ever get to this routine
and so just the specification for what
these routines should do should not
include de normals in general it should
neither accept nor doubt put them
generally right right cool and and and
the thing is right and an angle of 2 to
the minus 126 radians is not perceivable
as a rotation
I guess that's that's my point and and
that's a the rule of thumb that they
used to use here and this is a knock
spree animation stand the Disney yet
multi-plane camera was similar they
really only work 2.0 one over degree
anything smaller than that is not really
perceivable as a rotation yes yeah okay
alright unless you explicitly run slash
although one super slow sorry
or do you mean okay so the question here
saying that if you actually supply a sub
normal number to these routines
it will run slower yes and this is what
I was able to get this across though
what I was saying is that in games we
always turn on flush to zero so you
don't get D normal numbers yeah in
general that that's what I was kind of
trying to get across but I think I
failed to do so yeah sure and and this
by the way to anyone watching along this
is this is the difference between a
numeric analyst and a game programmer
right yes I'm pretending to be a numeric
analyst and Casey is actually a game
programmer and and this is the this is
the difference in thinking and you're
absolutely right for it for if we were
implementing the C runtime libraries
version of cosine and sine we would we
would deal with the submittal case
separately absolutely
is there a version of this math source
code anywhere will be including the
handmade project eventually both so I'm
releasing this under the MIT license so
that handmade hero can use it and I'm
not sure how I'm going to release it
maybe on github but the explanation is
going on the wiki but yeah at the very
least I mean people people who have
access to the handmade hero source code
of obviously going to get it first
because Casey's probably going to
incorporate it filly sir well and also
again this is just for educational
purposes if you
there are many math libraries out there
you can go get implementations of sine
and cosine and so on the point of this
was we wanted one that we had gone
through so we can know how it works and
everyone's seen how you do one of them
the idea is not to give you a library
that you're supposed to use for sine and
cosine it's you know because there are
many out there you could you could find
yes this is exactly right you know the
the inner standard library is open
source the ethel is x at least all the
trouble is of course you will never
understand them if you look at them and
this is really a look into how the
sausage is made
yeah and hopefully you know if you can
if you followed that and you know on
stream I'm gonna basically go and do an
SSE implementation of you know
equivalent routines now that we've gone
through one of them the idea is that
once you know that then if you do go use
a library or if you do want to make your
own versions of sine and cosine for
specific purposes or try to make them
faster now you have sort of a basic
understanding of what's going on so
you've got your footing there as opposed
to if we just grabbed something out of
one of those math libraries we would
have no idea we just like I don't know
like who knows how they did it because
you know again if you haven't gone
through it you wouldn't yeah exactly
it's these constants are a case in point
right these these the these are
reduction constants that we use in sine
and cosine here they they you would
never know where these came from if not
only explain them to you I mean maybe
you know it's a it's a it's called a
herd herd herd II white reduction if you
want to look it up that's its that's its
official name I don't know who these
guys were
I think it's from a textbook rather than
a paper but everyone who's who's done
research like there are papers that
formally prove these correct if you have
a fused multiplied add instruction and
so forth and it's all very fun and very
important and you don't really need to
care about but yes curly white reduction
is will you go through yeah are the
inverse cosine functions are not really
useful to us that I know of in handmade
hero so we probably wouldn't be going
over those you didn't 73 that that is
that is me I forgetting pretty much I
think I skipped most of the first week
which was introduction to see but I've
I've been here every time that it's the
stream all times I don't and I've been
around so I've if you've been around you
probably know who I am by my username
looks like that's it and I guess I'll
try to bring up one thing really quickly
here on my end if I can find a quick
reference to it but otherwise we can go
in there and so basically if you I'll
look this up on a different stream but
for the questioning about the D normal
numbers in terms of the actual cindy
unit in the x64 processor that we're
actually talking about I just again want
to emphasize the fact that this sort of
the concern about D normal numbers is
more of an ex 87 FPU kind of a concern
like when you're programming an SSE it's
pretty easy to just make sure that you
don't have to deal with d normal numbers
that's not something that's really a
problem with that not not sure how to
show that other than just to go over the
architecture guide but we can do that on
another stream I could show you in their
connection guide D normal numbers are
not really an issue in that way like
they did the SLO do you normal numbers
thing used to be a problem on x87 it was
something you had to think about more
but it's not loosen me up think about as
much anymore okay okay
um and and binary zero I don't know how
to pronounce you use thank if I can show
you asked I can show you some versions
that are completely branches for that
tables you're interested sure absolutely
very interested once again this is not
necessarily I'm not necessarily telling
you how to do it I'm just telling you
how I did it and you know I do not claim
in that this is industrial-strength for
all applications because yeah and once
again this quadrant version I intend to
make this branch free without tables so
that will happen but yes if you've got
versions branches that tables by all
means sure there's there on the end made
network there'll be
Aurum entry for this stream uncial and
also some was asking have we done
speaking prayers versus the sea versions
also again that was not really the point
here this is not an optimization if that
makes sense so the reason that I wanted
to have these gone over was because I
wanted to show how to implement them at
all not how to beat a particular
implementation speed wise because again
that wasn't really the goal in fact in
handy here right now we have no
bottleneck on something like sine and
cosine so we're not specifically
concerned about producing the fastest
possible versions there are cases where
you have sine and cosine in your
critical path and you really do care
about making sure that they're very fast
that's not really something that we have
a problem with on handmade hero so this
was more because we just wanted to stop
using the C runtime versions show you
how you know the code actually works
because when there is no magic sine and
cosine function you have to have some
way of actually doing it with just you
know adds subtracts multiplies divides
and so on and so that was all this was
for so we don't really even care it
could be slower than the C version for
all we care and we still wouldn't care
that would be something that we would
look at further on down the line if we
then determined that some problem with
our frame rate was related back to our
sine and cosines chances are these won't
be slower than C runtime libraries
though because C runtime errors do a lot
of that a lot of extra checking if you
ever looking into them yeah I mean I
just have a look at this division
algorithm again right again
this is slow division do not use this
you know if you use this in your code
you deserve the code you get all right
just making that clear but the point
here is not that this is fast because it
isn't the point is to show you the stuff
that the C standard library the sort of
stuff it has to do to implement things
in a compliant way this is the
industrial-strength part here because
industry cares about this and so that is
you know that's that's really the reason
why I went
that in not in any detail but justice
for you and so simply getting rid of
that is already a win yeah this happens
in well this is also why we early on in
handmade hero much earlier than we would
have had to in terms of getting rid of
the runtime library thing we replaced
square root using the SSE square root
was specifically it was not because
there's all this much calculation
involved in doing the square root but
it's because if you call the C runtime
square root it does a huge amount of
preamble work to handle all of these
additional cases that have to do with
taking square roots of values that we
will never take square roots of in
handmade hero and so that you know is is
again one of the big reasons to get rid
of the C runtime library just to get rid
of all that cruft
you're already probably starting out
ahead even if you haven't made it
particularly a well optimized version
just not having to deal with all of the
sort of I Triple E compliance is a huge
win in and of itself and and just just
to just to just rub it in this point
again this is not that it's fast the
point of this is that its branch free
and that's I think the basis on which it
might be more useful in in handmade hero
the fact that you've fact that you can
turn this into a four-way sine and
cosine might actually be where the real
win is it might not it might not be the
numerical method itself
[Music]
well strength why am I here ah you're
here because yes I don't know why you're
here well it's very industrial strength
does not really handmade heroes thing
right I mean
industrial strength on these young guys
this is this is artisanal if you want
factory produced you know where to find
it sure it means the Symbian transistor
not standard compliant so I don't know
so it depends on I don't know how well
the square
intrinsic is eventually you know they
probably yeah it might just not be
seeked like this was the thing that
Andrew was talking about a little
earlier in the stream is that there's
actually a difference between the C
runtime library standard and the I
Triple E standard so it's entirely
possible to have something like oh the
Intel square-root instruction is
compliant with the I Triple E standard
but not compliant with the C runtime
library standard like that's an actual
thing that can happen right so I don't
know the specifics of that but you know
that's that's just part of the course it
probably is okay the square root that's
probably okay but x87 be the old on has
these it actually has a southern
implementation yes incidentally and
there's something that there's something
here in the software development manual
that I want to read out to you because
this is very very important and that is
not it there I will just and and this
this if you like is is the reason is
another way a thing it's said there
there are the instructions there it's
got a tan and sine cosine and on all of
that its accuracy let me see if I can
find this because this is wonderful cord
in here that it that I think kind of
does I can add one thing to the question
to be sure it means to be in choice or
not sir also the other thing that Andrew
mentioned is going on for those
functions is also true which is that
just because it takes a lot of
instructions to implement something like
standards compliance doesn't mean that
you can't make circuitry that's very
efficient to do so like we may have to
do a bunch of shifting and fiddling and
extraction and all these other non
senses and they may be able to make a
circuit that's quite efficient that does
all those things in
of the time right so I you know don't
don't necessarily take it to mean that
something that requires a lot of
instructions when there isn't a CPU
version of it means that the C fusion
version CPU version will be slow that's
not actually always the case in fact it
may be unrelated okay it might be in the
optimisation reference manual I might be
thinking of the different manual I don't
think I know the past be talking about
I'm interested to see yeah um you know
that there are now more pages of
documentation for a model Intel chip
than there were transistors in Intel's
first CPU ah here we go here we go this
is the pet this is the quorum after this
is from the authorization you although
x87 supports transcendental instructions
software library implementation that's
that that's incorrect remove
transcendental function can be faster in
many cases so there you go that's why
we're doing it I don't remember that
being the case I wonder if yeah well I
suppose it depends if what you were
taking yeah yes so there you go they
said there's a little life lesson there
that's pretty great which is that
sometimes you can do better in software
than you can in hardware all right I
think that we will let you get back to
your evening Andrew it's actually eat
he's back to midday but thank you so
much for taking the time to walk us
through that that was great and I will
thank you thank you I will go over those
routines myself on stream and and we'll
work through him again so that was that
was excellent and yeah very educational
so thank you so much for taking the time
to talk to us all right no thank you all
right have a good one yeah okay thanks
man all right so that was sort of a
brief introduction to numerical approach
summation sorts of stuff again it's the
sort of thing that you can spend a
tremendous amount of time doing and
there's people who specialize in this
and it's it's all they do is numerical
methods for doing things on computers so
you know you can take this to the nth
degree and there's people who are
probably spending a tremendous amount of
time doing nothing other than figuring
out how to make say for example the
fastest sine and cosine on various chips
Intel for example does releases
libraries of mathematical operations for
their SSE chips where they're trying to
work out fast ways to do it and so on
and so forth and you know this this is
basically a whole sort of area of itself
unhand me and here we're fortunate
enough that we don't really have to
worry too much about getting the very
fastest sine and cosine or anything like
that but like I said for completeness I
really do think we want to go take a
look at it and that's why I wanted to
have somebody who kind of knew how to
make one from scratch show us how to
make one from scratch and that was
really good I think I understand it
pretty well now too and I was always a
little hazy on that sort of stuff
because I've never really gone and dug
into that sort of thing myself the only
times I've ever used functional
approximations they were pretty
straightforward and I never really tried
to do something more complicated like
atan2 or sine and cosine which are you
know more more sort of the real sorts of
stuff you would be doing for basic math
library things so what we'll probably do
is we'll take a look at those again
because I'm gonna want to kind of go
through them line by line myself on the
stream make sure we really do understand
them and have internalized them and then
we can go ahead and make SSE versions of
them actually because there's yeah
there's a little bit of fun in doing
that as well just figuring out how we're
gonna implement those in SSE which is a
pretty straight translation but again
you know do we want to try and do the
quadrant hacking version do we want to
try and do the lookup table version and
you know figuring out which ones going
on maybe we time them see which one's
faster just for fun anything like that
so we'll be taking a look more of those
in the future but again thank you very
much to Andrew for taking time out of
his day to show us how you go about
building those things if you're the kind
of person who wants to investigate that
path a little bit more hopefully now
you've got some some footholds earned
you can go alright that's it for today
we will be back next week on handmade
hero when yeah we will pick back up with
our lighting code and when Andrews ready
with that code he said he was going to
be posting that online as well and so
we'll pick that up and we'll start
playing with it with our own version of
it at that time so thanks everyone for
joining me and we'll see you next
weekend until then have fun programming
and I'll see everyone on the Internet
take it easy everybody