start recording all right hello everyone
and welcome to handmade here the show
recode a complete game live on stream we
are still in our sort situation which
you know like i said is a little bit of
a dicey thing because we're doing a 2-d
game but it's got some 3d elements in it
and whenever you kind of mix those two
things you kind of have to fall back to
some touchy sort of touchy-feely
semantics rules for how things get
sorted and we've been sort of trying to
work through how we think that will work
out and you know what's the minimum
amount of markup we can do on our
rendering to make sure that it will sort
in some way that we feel is reasonable
and plausible for the kinds of scenes
and the kinds of entities that we know
that we'll have now we just finished
getting our sorting working yesterday
but we haven't really debugged it and we
we also don't really technically know
whether our sort rule is going to work
right so we're kind of still in a little
bit of an investigative phase I gotta
jump right into it though so we'll have
time to kind of pick around there it's
day 30 too so if you would like to
follow along at home just open up day
301 source code that's what we're
looking at here that's what I'm starting
with on stream so what I wanted to do
first of all someone pointed out that I
made a really bad typo at the end of
last last night's dream which is to say
that inside the render group when I push
when I was sort of doing the code for
creating the sort keys that we needed I
instead of doing a plus equals I did
like an equals and that's obviously not
good at all so you can kind of see here
where is that code get bound for you can
kind of see your where the code was
probably supposed to be looking like
this one where you know we had the plus
equals here and so these were actually
supposed to look like that and in fact I
guess you could say you might do it like
this so it was supposed to be taking the
wyman and spreading it out by the height
and instead it was just setting it to
that which meant that all of our Y
bounds were just wrong so that was
obviously wrong but I don't I I don't
actually think that's the only problem
we've got you know I suspect we're going
to have a bunch of problems here and
you also have a you know we have more
stuff that we have to do as well so
we've got we've got a lot of work to do
you know there's a bunch of stuff that
we're going to have to do so you know
for starters I'd say that the the first
thing I would point out if you take a
look at what we're seeing on the screen
is just that there's a little bit of a
there's some twitchiness right to the
sorting that you can see happening and
some of its explicable and some of it is
indicative I think potentially of
problems but we'll see and so I'm just
kind of going through I just want to
kind of like articulate what I'm seeing
on screen so that you can kind of get a
little bit of a feel for for how I was
thinking through this so first of all if
you take a look at what's happening here
with these sort of flashing these bits
that were kind of flashing and you know
as I mouse over it of course the decided
to stop doing it but there you go so you
see that's that flashing there I what I
wanted to point out about that flashing
there is that well that's a flashing
that wouldn't necessarily concern me
because these are debug things anyway
and the reason that that doesn't really
concern me is because these are a bunch
of rectangles which are overlapping and
which have the same essentially Z plane
in which overlap and we never did as a
rule to try to differentiate those
because we want we aren't really going
to have that case right so that's not a
case that worries me at all and if we
had wanted to make this work we would
have just increased the Z of the border
by just a slight bit to make sure that
it's sorted above it and that would have
been a fine solution in my opinion I
wouldn't have problem with that so the
fact that that's twitchy doesn't worry
me at all what worries me uh quite a bit
is this situation down here so you can
see that these guys which are definitely
below these sort of upper tier people
you can see that they're sorting above
this tier and what's more concerning
than that is that they're sorting above
it only some of the time right so what
that says to me or suggests to me anyway
and again we haven't really looked into
this in any particular detail but what
that suggests to me is that the
the rule that we defined as I suspected
sort of mentioned as like we're gonna
have to be able to worry about this that
suggests to me that my my fears about it
not being a straightforward sortable
criteria are perhaps well-founded
because what very well might be
happening there is depending on the
order in which we hand these things off
to the renderer the sort may produce
different results and again that's just
because of the way that our criteria
happens to work so you know we have a
sort of a question there that we can
sort of think about and it's really the
question is should we try to extend the
sort rule so that it works all the time
like is there a way to extend it to be a
little bit smarter so that the sort rule
can produce complete ordering so it
doesn't have that if basically and part
of that is just if you have an if
statement inside a sort rule then you
know chances are it's not going to be
something that produces a correct it's
not going to produce a correct total
ordering for these things and the reason
that I say that is because well it's
unless you did specific work to ensure
that the two halves of the if always
produce consistent results no matter
which route you take through things then
then depending on which items you end up
comparing as part of the merge sort
you'll get different merges right so
it's not unusual that that would happen
which is why i said i was a little bit
afraid of it it also is sort of in line
with what andrew russell was talking
about on River City Rampage underground
we're sorry River City ransom
underground where he was talking about
the fact that he had to use a more
topological approach to actually do the
sorting which we might have to to for
all we know right we don't know we don't
know the answer to that question yet so
the first thing I would say is that
seems like a likely thing to me I want
to spend a few minutes on the blackboard
looking into what we would do if we want
to extend this out a little bit is there
a way to make it more consistent without
the if and if there's not then I'm going
to go in and try to verify that that's
what's actually happening
and actually you know because it's easy
to verify maybe I'll just do that first
just to prove to myself at least that
that's happening because it's not that
hard for me to too sorry I want to go in
here actually to to know that that's
happening it just it requires a little
bit of slowness here essentially what
you can see is after we perform our sort
here's the sort happening here we've got
this check if handmade slow is true
we'll go through and we check our sort
of all the things that we sorted to make
sure that they're still in sorted order
and we do that by checking entry a
against entry b4 every pair of entries
all the way down the list right and but
when I say every pair what I mean is
adjacent pairs right so we do 0 &amp; 1 1 &amp;
2 2 &amp; 3 3 &amp; 4 or 4 and 5 and what that
lets us know is that our partial
ordering was correct right it means that
we never compared two items and got the
wrong you know our sort never did
something like insert two items that
obviously failed their sort test next to
each other that never happened so that's
good but what we don't know is if we
were to check each entry against every
other entry would we ever find a pair
that was Miss sorted right and that's
what we don't know so what I'd like to
do is sort of make two versions of this
one that is like a note Casey this is
the partial ordering check only
neighbors are verified and the benefit
to this is it's 0 n right we only have
to loop through that list once and so
it's it's relatively speedy we can just
always turn it on it's never going to be
too slow to use on the other hand if I
actually expand this out to check every
pair well that's going to be 0 N squared
so we're not going to want to leave that
on during regular usage I wouldn't think
unless we have a very low number of
sprites that's going to kind of come
back to to haunt us when we have higher
numbers of sprites because the number of
is going to be absurdly high so this is
something we only want to do during an
active debugging scenario in my opinion
so I want to make both cases so we can
pick which one they use so this is the 0
N squared oops a total ordering check
all Paris verified so if we go ahead
through here and you know we could also
do I suppose we could save ourselves one
repetitive loop right and do something
kind of absurd like this yes I'm getting
a little crazy here it's true but what I
could do here radius like it say like oh
okay you know give me a second loop here
and I guess in this case technically I'm
not doing a second loop but for the N
squared case what I'm going to do is say
well I've got you know this index here
and then I'm going to have an index b
which is going to be this guy and so
then up here when we do the partial
check I could just say well oh all right
you know index be can just be hard-coded
to do this and then we'll open a block
that isn't a loop and then we'll close
the block here right so that way when
we're in here we do the partial a big
check by just grabbing okay you know
we'll just compare against this one for
index be in the case where we want to do
the N squared check we can just say like
oh well we'll start at the index plus 1
right and then we'll go all the way
until we hit the very end of the array
and just test all of them right so that
would check every pair against every
other pair and make sure that in front
over
earns the answer that we think that it
should right now this is a little weird
though I'm a little confused by this and
I'm wondering if this check is actually
executing at the moment because
shouldn't this be giving us the opposite
results like take a look at this if if
after we do the merge sort when we go to
check all these we do index you know
from 02 count minus 1 and and let's say
we're still in this case like let's say
we're still doing the o/n partial
ordering check we come in here and we
say okay from you know from in x equals
0 to index count minus 1 let's check
entry a which is you know whichever one
we're on plus whichever one came after
it right which is that index plus 1 and
then I want you to tell me if at the the
one the first entry is in front of the
second entry and okay no cuz we don't
have a not there's alright so that's
okay nevermind faster narrowly averted
alright so assuming that we that I
didn't mess anything up there if we run
this now we have this is sort of the old
check we know that nothing is is failing
in the old check if I rerun it now with
with the new check which i guess is not
in the hot code reloaded so we're going
to go I'm hoping we get an assertion its
and so there we go we did get an
assertion and so you know we got an
assertion on index nine and index 40
right and so let's take a look at what
those two are entry a entry fee and we
can sort of see here what those two look
like now we can see that both of these
have a wyman wimax range and so what
that means is there are both sort of z
sprites right they're both they're both
in the Z plane and we can see that the
zmax of one of them is zero the zmax of
the other one is 1.25 now what we know
is that the 1.25 one in this scenario
right should be drawing
above the the I'm sorry yeah should be
drawing above the 01 so in this case we
should have we should have entry be
being above entry a but you know that
looks correct right why are we getting
that assertion because in this case
entry a is not above entry be how did we
get in here am I missing something uh
let's let's step in there so here we go
I backed the run you know the
instruction pointer back up so I could
have the code executes a second time so
I'm going to go in here and say you know
are they both sea sprites that should
return true and it doesn't so why
doesn't it return true ah ok nevermind
this guy isn't as East right that was
the problem I was too hasty in that I
guess yeah so never mind that guy isn't
disease right so that makes sense so if
that guy isn't as East right then we
have to see uh right what the what the
sort criteria would be here he is not
contained and so since he's not
contained I think well that should still
sort by Z shouldn't it or I guess it
sorts by why in that case yeah so if it
starts by why that's that's going to put
me yeah be should have been behind a
because it's why was was greater and
obviously it wasn't so that's definitely
a case where yeah that didn't come out
the way that we would have expected to
so so not fabulous right and I would
like to see that update more is it
really the case that that's the only
error
I'm a little confused by that let's take
a look here I think it I think what I'd
like to do is change this from an
assertion temporarily to something where
I can just set a breakpoint all right so
i just want to see how many different
ones of these there are right so I just
kind of wanted to know how many sort
errors there were if that makes sense it
looks like there's a lot of them but
they're all kind of very similar very
similar sort keys probably because
they're rows of things in why let's also
do this here let me take a look here so
let's also do do a count
sorry my knees been bothering me lately
make it a little more comfortable for
myself probably not that I can try all
right so if I have let's see if I have
all my sword eres here and I can go in
here and let me go ahead and sort of
compile that in and now I should be able
to break at the end and just see how
many sorter as I have
let's see
okay so break here sorters should tell
me I of course that's em so I guess that
doesn't really tell me that much about
how many sorters there were hmm all
right but point being I think that at
least verifies what I wanted to know in
the first place which is just how many
of these particular guys were actually
in you know how many how likely was it
that we needed to a pelagic assort and
weren't getting one it seems very likely
that that's the case so the problem with
that just to sort of give a little bit
more of a specific kind of move this out
of the way just to give sort of a more
specific description of what's going on
here and I don't actually remember so
stayed a 301 right sit here do too so
day 30 to sort partial ordering problem
so the problem that we're having here is
just that when we compare if we have
three items right so we've got a B and C
then the problem that we're having here
is that we may compare these guys
together right we may compare a and b
and b and c and we may never compare say
a and C right because the way in merge
sort works this doesn't compare every
pair with every other pair obviously
because that would be incredibly
inefficient right and so what ends up
happening is if we compare a and B and
we say like oh okay a should be in front
of B and then you compare B and C and
say oh well be should be in front of C
then we're going to think that the
ordering is a B and C right but if we
compare a and C we may have found that C
should have been in front of a and so in
depending on which order these came in
if instead it had gone ACB when we fed
it to the renderer we then would have
come up and said oh well the correct
ordering was actually see a B now
neither of these is technically a
correct ordering because since we've
written a sort rule which doesn't
necessarily always produce transitive
results properly right then there is no
such thing as the one total ordering and
that's the thing that we were that sort
of andrew russell was getting at when he
was talking about his River City ransom
stuff it's just saying hey in this
scenario you're going to have to sort of
decide well when you sort things you
have to look at which things are
actually overlapping and only sort those
and hope that you don't produce any
complicated cycles in those and if you
do you have to do something clever to
break them right and so you know that's
certainly wrap we could go by we could
first check to see whether two sprites
overlap and sort those you know and then
draw them in sort of overlapping chains
that's certainly something we could do
but the other thing we can do is say can
we turn our partial ordering into a
total ordering right and the way that we
would do that is again we would have to
come up with something that sort of
represent you know does the 3d check a
little bit more thoroughly remember
people were asking about this yesterday
like why don't we just do a whole 3d
check and my answer to that is
always been well we are right the
question is just how little of a 3d
check can we get away with because the
more 3d the more 3d of a check we put in
the more 3d data we have to associate
with all our stuff so we're good
classically making more work for
ourselves as we go so we want to verify
at each step of the way that in order to
that that we actually need the data that
were requiring of the sort of the input
phase right if that makes sense um so
anyway if we take a look at what happens
here right now we're talking about
sorting objects where we either talk
about you know a Z sprite which is kind
of like the top face of a cube kind of a
thing or we talk about a why sprite
which is sort of the the front facing
part of that cube assuming that we're
viewing things from here right although
one might argue that the Z is the more
front facing one since we're top down so
I guess you might say the Z is front
facing for our purposes and why is kind
of facing out the bottom of the screen
sort of in a limited sense so if that's
the way we're looking at our sorting
then we have to ask the question well
you know if we start sorting things by
why you know let's say we were sorting
two things x y and so we put one thing
on this side and one thing on the other
side the problem that we rapidly would
run into is this thing might be higher
in Z than this thing is but because we
sorted them by why because there was
some interceding object that pushed one
to the side and one to the side and the
sort order this is never going to sort
above this in Z so later when somebody
else who's below this guy in Z sorts
against this guy it puts him in a place
that's below this guy which will always
draw in the wrong order for this guy
right so the question is is there any
way that we could get a round up by
saying well we need to sort these guys
in in some you know other way that's
that's more consistent and I think you
know my smite my assumption is there is
no way to do a 3d sort that will
actually produce that but you know we
might be able to uh you know if we
actually sort of these as actual sort of
as the actual planes you know maybe we
could do something there and I don't
think about exactly what that would be
if we want to compare two elements
together and you know one of them is a
plane like this and what we could do is
we could potentially try to sort them by
Z first I guess since we know what the
upper bound of this guy actually is and
then only if we can't sort by Z could we
sort by Y if they overlap or something
you know maybe that would be a better
sort rule and I'm not sure we can
certainly try it easily enough you know
stuff like that is not particularly
difficult to try in our sort rule now
that we sort of have it to play around
with we can leave this in here and I'll
just leave this as the assertion because
now we don't really need that sword
arrest thing I just kind of playing
around that anyway we can certainly
leave our slow verifier in there as well
the is in front of rule this was our old
one and what we could do here is just
sort of change the the sort criteria
selector right so what we could do is
say well previously what we were doing
to determine whether or not we were
going to sort this thing by Z is we were
looking to see whether the Y ranges of
something overlapped right so if both
things resist rights we would sort them
by Z if if the things were overlapping
and why we would also sort them by Z
because then we would know they wouldn't
be able to be sort of that way but in
the case where none of that was true we
wouldn't actually sort by the z values
so what that means is the case where we
weren't sorting by Z values would have
been cases like so let's say both things
were y sprites that overlapped the
problem that we were having there is
just because we want to sort those
things and why we then wouldn't I guess
once we sort those things and why they
create sort of a problem space yeah you
know I
I'll be honest I don't really see a way
of fixing that particular problem I mean
obviously we could try to sort them by
the clip their closest point to the
camera
you know it's plausible that something
like that could work right where you'd
have something where we would say well
what's the closest point to the camera
technically given that we sort of know
what the what the kind of movement is in
Y for the transform that we're trying to
apply we could try to do that I'm trying
to think if that has any particularly
problematic applications untangle this
cord is getting a little tangled here so
let's see I guess what I was saying is
so if we imagine these as always being
sprites that look sort of like this and
we're sort of sorting down here we could
sort of figure out what's your closest
point to the camera right and the
closest point to the camera is going to
have a certain distance that maybe tells
us the answer to that question and I
don't actually know how true that is in
the cases that we're looking at before
the interval seem to not be particularly
what we would want but I suppose when we
actually think about what these actually
are in 3d space it's possible that being
close to the camera would be how close
they are to the camera would be enough
to go on yeah i don't i don't really
know I don't necessarily think that
that's true either but it's hard to say
one of the things that's a little
problematic is because we sort of did a
relatively hockey you know we don't do a
standard orthographic transform is that
it's a little bit tricky to figure out
how far our way things actually are from
the camera and the reason for that is we
haven't really defined what exactly
happens when things kind of raise up on
the Y plane you know for based on Z
right like right now we're not only
think we're really even doing that but
that's you know that's kind of the thing
that would would be important for us to
know there is sort of like how that how
much how much closer to the camera you
that when you go up or down on a on like
a facing card and stuff like that but if
we were going to do that well let's just
take a look because like I say I don't I
certainly don't know the correct answer
to any of these particular problems like
I said I've never really done a 2d sort
of thing like this before so it's hard
for me to really know in advance what's
going to be a good answer versus what's
going to be a bad answer if that makes
sense so let's take a look here so if I
do if we do the get render entity basis
p and we look at what's happening to our
transform then we can sort of see that
once we actually add once we actually
put the Z value in here we would know
whatever that percentage was would be
what we would multiply the height by
order to get the closest point to the
camera in Z uh so I would say and since
Y itself doesn't actually change the
sorting in that sense like
you think about this since we're sort of
saying that things are sort of tilted at
an angle here right we're sort of saying
that you know here's the here's the
ground and we're looking down at it
we're never really actually constructing
this space explicitly at the moment
right and I wonder if that's sort of
something that we've done incorrectly
like I wonder if we want to actually do
the transform that this implies with the
actual camera looking down on it with an
actual orthographic transform because if
we actually did that then all of this
would sort of be a little bit more
academic in the sense that like oh ok
then it would be really trivial to just
go well what's the closest point to the
camera because it goes way to the camera
is just the subtraction of whatever your
top your maximum point in Z is you know
to here and you don't have to really
think about the y at all because that's
going to be automatic as you get closer
this way you just will get closer to the
camera in that sense right and I guess I
shouldn't say that because it really
looks it looks like this right in an
orthographic sense
so yeah if you have an orthographic
camera looking at the scene like so then
effectively what we have is we have
these kind of lines coming at it and so
that should mean that we would always
get lower distances as things move
closer to the camera right using the
orthographic you know distance to that
plane so effectively what we're doing is
saying what's the distance to this plane
that is the camera plane you know I'm
saying and when we have things that are
Z height so I guess we could just take
the distance to the camera plane that's
actually relatively straightforward
right because if we want to know the
distance of something to a plane you
know all we need to do is measure its
distance along along the planes normal
right so we know what that normal would
be because we're going to define how we
define how sloped down the projection is
going to be once we define that normal
all we would have to do is take the dot
product of whatever this normal is right
we take the top rope whatever that
normal is with the the three-dimensional
point we're trying to measure and that's
how we would get a you know the distance
along it now obviously we need to know
where this plane is but we know the
camera is at zero so we kind of already
know what that that plane is so we just
take the straight dot product would give
us how far along how far we would go
from the plane out to the point we're
talking about so if we were to do that
for each card and we always just take
the topmost point you know would that be
sufficient uh
and I'm not sure I know the answer to
that question so let's think about it
for one second suppose I have this dude
here right and I want to take his top
most point and maybe he looks like this
in this case you can certainly see that
that would not work this is why we
discarded these cases before because
this long piece here is is always going
to appear to sort closer to the camera
than this one at fact I think that's the
way we can convince ourselves that the
3d sort doesn't work right because it
requires a point-by-point sort to know
that this part of this guy is a behind
this one so that's why we need the sort
of weird rules about about sprites sort
of coming together in order to resolve
those things because in order to resolve
something like this we would not we
would have to do a point-by-point
comparison in order to know that this
part should be drawn behind this part
because otherwise you'd say well this is
the closest point right to the camera so
this whole sprite would have to be drawn
first and that's not correct this is
actually the one that would be drawn
first right so I think again that sort
of suggests that that either you need to
do sort of a fully 3d position Z buffer
thing or you need to go with something
that's going to handle the topological
sort properly so I think I've relatively
convinced myself just by looking at that
it does seem to me that that means if
you know if we want to try and go this
route then we're going to need something
that's going to take a look at sprites
that overlap and when it finds sprites
that overlap it's going to have to
perform those sorts specifically that at
least seems like the case to me and
that's relatively tricky right because
now we have to actually think a little
bit more about whether these sprites you
know kind of there whether they're
actual screen space bounds line them up
or not so yeah how do I want to approach
that it seems like that's not something
that wants to get sent down through
renderer and so that seems to me like
again that's going to require now
thinking about this as something that's
built outside as sort of the sprite list
that then is walked as a tree and I'm
sorry as a graph and then we actually
sort of try to sort that graph more
intelligently right so yeah uh let's try
and I guess I you know like i said i'm
not really sure what's going to happen
here but let's try to start building
something like that and i'm gonna i
think we might have to try to do this
sort of impasses because gonna be relied
to the complicated so i'll start doing
it now but this is probably going to be
a thing for next week let's go ahead and
take a look so let's let's just make I
guess we can make this in here but what
would we actually need and let's say I
did this in the least like we won't try
to accelerate it for us i'll do it in
the dumbest possible way so let's say we
had a thing a function here that's like
you know resolved sprite graph or
something you know and so we're just
going to go full pull oops so what do i
need to do to or i should i guess i
should really say like build sprite
graph at least first because we have to
actually make one of these things first
so in order to build a sprite graph i
would need a list of sprites so i would
need something here that would have
information like okay here's the sprite
and i would need to have essentially
this the sort of sort key information i
have here but i would need also some
more information about whether the
things overlap in screen space right so
if I think about this I'm going to need
the original sort of screen space
positions of these guys so we need like
min p or like screen mimpi and screen
max p something like this so i can tell
if these two things overlap and then i
would need the stuff that we actually
would use like i said for the sort which
would probably be that z mac
set the very least so I don't know if we
would want the Y min Y max because we
can probably use the screen ones for
that I'm guessing but we'll find out in
a second so we would have something like
this where we've got you know a sprite
note or something like this and each one
of these things we would have a list and
we have to then build a graph out of the
list right we'd have to sort of have a
have a idea of the edges in there that
sort of connect these sprite nodes to
each other and say you know this sprite
nodes in front of this sprite note or
something like that so let's suppose I
had a list of these things here's the
input nodes and maybe I have an input
node count to me so if i take this input
node count and I've got the input nodes
and here I go and I say okay let's go
through a you know node index a at
equals something note index a is less
than input node count and node indexes
go like this like so so if I was to
compare every node with every other node
right so I'm just I'm just doing the
absolute stupidest thing possible here I
could then say you know a good dias in
the exact same way I was doing it before
and also I guess this would be minus one
so if i go through every possible
combination of these guys and I should
also probably check make sure we
actually have some
I do not know what that just did all
right so if I go through all of these
index indexes so that I can have both my
nodes what I could do here say you know
let me compare these two nodes with each
other to see whether they overlap in
screen space so I'm gonna say input
nodes plus mode index a and put nodes
just note index be so I grabbed out two
of these sprite notes and then I want to
know like if overlap the screen overlap
for a and B then I know that I have a
case where I need to determine which one
of these two would appear in front of
which other one right so then I would
have a notion of a sprite edge and the
sprite edge would just be in this graph
a connectivity between two sprite nodes
right so it would have like a you know
index a and an index be of the sprites
and it would say like oh okay this index
is in front of this other index or
whatever and so you know maybe I could
do this in front and behind so basically
i can add an edge and say that this
sprite is in front of this right or this
right is behind the sprite so it's a
directed edge for those of you who don't
know any graft your i suppose i should
mention this really briefly so there is
such a thing as graph theory we don't
really cover it on handmade here we
haven't really got to do much with it I
don't know how much we will do with it
there might be a little bit more but we
do world Jen I definitely something that
you need to know if you're doing game
programming in a broad sense it comes up
in various places so it is relevant and
I wouldn't discourage anyone from going
from reading more about it but basically
there's you know in graph theory we
essentially have the concept of you know
nodes and edges and what we're talking
about is building
graph where we've got some number of
nodes and these nodes you know have
something in them and then we have some
number of edges between them right and
the edges might also have data
associated with them you know maybe I've
got some data associated with these
edges as well for some reason who knows
why I have no idea why they would but
you know maybe they do I don't know that
many Greek symbols but let's say there's
some of those uh so anyway you you know
you get a situation where you construct
some meaning out of this usually in the
context of your program and so for the
cases that I'm talking about I was sort
of saying that the nodes of this are
going to be sprites and the edges of
this are going to be information that
says that one sprite is in front of
another sprite right and the reason we
want to do this is again harkening back
to the river city ransom underground
case we want to kind of say well we're
going to define some semantic
information where we say that this is
supposed to be in front of this this is
supposed to be behind this whatever we
want to define that and then allowed the
have the game have a solver that will go
in and figure out what the order is that
you can draw these sprites in in order
to satisfy as much as possible as what
the graph said to do right okay so graph
theory is basically algorithms that
study these sorts of things and how you
can determine stuff about them for
example in this case you know you might
say oh maybe I want to you know ask some
simple questions about the graph like
what's you know what's the maximum
number of edges that emanate from a node
or how many times could I get to this
node by a different paths or you know
stuff like this and specifically the
kind of graph that we're talking about
here we have what's called a directed
graph and the reason it's a directed
graph is because of the way that I
talked about my edges we didn't say
sprite a is connected to stripe be if we
did that would be an undirected graph
because we're just saying that there's
an edge between a and B and we don't
have any other
thing we want to say about it but in our
case we're trying to specify a
directionality to that connection so not
just some data but an actual meaning in
the graph and what that means is that
our edges are directed they have the
notion that say like a is in front of B
so there's a natural order to it C is in
front of a or something right and we
would then say well the base of the
arrow is in front of the target of the
arrow maybe or who knows what right and
so once we assign that meaning we then
create a specific type of graph that's a
directed graph which is to say that its
edges have direction to them and
furthermore we would want to have one
step up from that which is a directed
acyclic graph now directed acyclic graph
is a graph that doesn't have any cycles
in it so for example this right here is
a cycle if I started see I can go to a I
can go to d I can go back to see and I
can just keep going around and around
and around right because the edges flow
in that direction right on the other
hand if I was to create a slightly
different graph one that looked like for
example this now I no longer have in a
cyclic I'm sorry now I no longer have a
cyclic graph I have an acyclic graph
because no matter where you go you
always end up at be right there's no way
to go i can't cycle no matter where I go
I always end up getting forced into be
right I always end up getting forced out
to a leaf and so directed acyclic graphs
or dags as they're often called are
super nice because we know there's sort
of that total ordering to them right and
that's exactly what we want for our sort
so we want this because if we have this
we would know we could always draw
everything because we always know
there's a chain for every set of sprites
that we can follow to draw them in the
correct order we probably won't be so
lucky we'll probably end up having
something like this where we can create
a cycle and so this is again getting
back to what andrew russell was talking
about in his blog post if we got that
cycle we have to break it somehow
because if a is supposed to be in front
of B&amp;B is hosted in front of c and c is
for us in front of a
there's no way to ever draw them in
order you've created a cycle and so if
we're saying that we're still we're
never going to split sprites you know we
don't want to solve it that way so if we
never want to split sprites then what we
have to do is acknowledge that fact that
we have a cycle and just kill one of the
edges arbitrarily right and we can sort
of make that determination about which
edge to kill in a number of ways like
which rights have the least overlap
might be a good way of doing it which
brights are closest to being together I
don't know but there's a number of
metrics we could employ to figure out
which of the edges would be the best one
to kill in a cycle and we would just
kill edges in a cycle until we got a
directed graph that didn't have any a
directed acyclic graph that so it didn't
have any cycles so that's you know
that's the part of the graph theory that
we're talking about here so basically
what we'd say is well okay if they if
these two things overlap on the screen
then what we're going to do is we're
going to add an edge here right we would
add an edge so we'd add a sprite edge
and the sprite edge would say if these
two things overlap we just want to know
which ones in front of and which ones
behind you know each other well we
already have that ability so we can go
up here and take our our in front of
code and we can just call that right so
we can just do this right here so we can
say like if is in front of bound a and
bound be like so and if a you know in
this case if a is in front of B then we
would add an you know an a B edge and
the other in the other case we'd add the
BA edge right in the case where they
don't overlap we just wouldn't add an
edge at all because we don't care if two
sprites don't overlap in screens place
we don't care what order they draw in
because they're never going to include
each other so that doesn't matter all
right so in this case we've got sort of
the sprite bound a sprite Bambi
situation what
like to do here probably is well i don't
know i guess i'll leave it like this for
the time being because we don't really
care about it too much I'll just
construct these two directly but we're
ventually we're going to want to
regularize the data format anyway so
that we don't have to do that so it's
why min why me why min wimax zmax so the
zmax is transferred directly but the
wise i think we would do a sort of like
this so there I've created the bounds
and then we can use ours in front of we
add the edges and off we go and so
really all we would need to know is is
this you know is there a screen overlap
and you know what we could do here we
could even lean on if we wanted to our
rectangle concept right so we could even
say you know we've got we have to have a
rectangle area here and if we did that
then we would just actually say like if
they intersect so I'm going to take a
look at our math here
so we have a two I intersect but we
don't have a to regular intersect which
we would need right and I don't see I
don't see you there so I'm going to go
ahead and grab this guy and make one for
our two case and let's see is inside
oops and so in this case we just not
gonna check the Z but otherwise it's
exactly the same so there's our
rectangles and so all i would say here
is like okay if our rectangles intersect
and for a area or a screen area and B
screen area then I would know that these
are two people that have to have edge is
constructed between them so in the case
of I guess the other thing we could
check is if there's these were equal we
wouldn't necessarily have to do anything
if they yeah there's some things we
could do there but anyway so point being
if we you know if we construct something
like this then I and of course I have to
change this to a screen area I don't
remember what our convention was for
rectangle tues here met take a look
rectangle to where is that defined is
that in the platform good it is such min
max
so you know that would that would
basically be what would construct the
graph for us and then we just need a way
of recording those edges right so we
just need you know we would just have
some temporary memory where we just put
all those edges in there and off we go
now unfortunately for us this is
actually going to be a little bit dicey
because as we're constructing this graph
we also have to figure out how we're
going to sort of more quickly access it
right so we're probably gonna I'm going
to leave this unimplemented because
until I know a little bit more about how
we need to walk the graph I until I know
more about how we're going to walk the
graph I don't feel like I'm going to be
too comfortable with that right because
we're probably going to do something
like for each bright node have a list of
the edges that come off it so that we
can quickly get to them rather than
having to sort of check through that
list the whole time but at least this is
the code that we know that we would be
executing up to the point where we
actually have to add the edge so that is
how the sprite graph would be built and
you can see that this is an N squared
problem so what we would need to do
shortly after doing this part of it is
we have to do something that partitions
the screen up into sub rectangles for
purposes of building this graph probably
so that we would not have to check
everyone against every other one right
in terms of the screen area overlap so
that's also something that we'd have to
do at the outset because basically
looping over every node for node index a
is not acceptable this would have to
loop over only ones that we knew were
roughly within a similar screen bound if
that makes sense uh so yeah that looks
like how we would pretty much handle the
sprite graph and then we'd have to do
sort of our our testing on it
now the other thing that's sort of
questionable here is if you look at how
much work that's going to go into this
the other thing that we can't have to
IRS ourselves at this point is like do
you know would we rather figure out a
way to break our stuff up into Z buffer
roll pieces right because that's the
other route we can go with it we can
just say like well let's actually try to
put these cards in actual 3d and I don't
really know but you can see how much
works gonna be involved here we're going
to have to do a spatial partition for
this we're going to have to do it is in
front of then we're going to have to
walk the graph and we're going to have
to figure out which cycles we want to
remove it is a lot of work and it's kind
of I'm wondering whether that's going to
just be it's going to bog us down in
terms of performance when we want to run
on GPUs which are already going to be
capable of doing Z buffers fast enough
you know at that point it's like well
should we just use the Z buffer and be
done with it because that will be faster
than trying to run the sorts on the cpu
probably if we push the sprite count up
high enough you know I'm saying
and I don't really know right you know
for transparent things obviously we have
the problem where we would have to sort
anyway and so part of its just saying
well you know if you actually just bite
the bullet and have your sorting be a
primary thing in a sprite engine it
means that you can lean on that for
transparency as well and then you can do
whatever con transparent effects you
want because you know throw is going to
sort into the scene of the right order
but I don't know so we'll see that's
probably yet for today because I don't
really want to actually start going into
that into more detail because I feel
like you know we're going to be at a
time in like two minutes anyway so I'm
going to go to the Q&amp;A but that's that's
basically what we're looking at and i'll
leave 0 this out so that it won't cause
any code problems but there we go one
thing we could also do you know in that
case as well is for these sprites we
also have the option certainly of you
know if we ever went to optimize our
software renderer the fact that we're
bucketing sprites by which by part of
the screen that would also we could
leverage that in the software renderer
to only consider sprites that overlap a
tile for tiled rendering right so we
could also get dual use out of that sort
if we wanted to anyway so I'm going to
wind it down and will redress this in in
next week streams
room 0 0 1 0 0 1 1 how much more work
would you have to do to get a full 3d
sorting I I feel like I'm not explaining
this properly because this question has
kind of so many times and I don't I feel
like I'm not communicating it well full
3d sorting is really easy the problem is
we don't have 3d data that's the problem
right you can sort 3d points trivially
you just use the distance from the
camera and you're dumb right but the
problem is if you don't have 3d data you
can't sort 3d data and so in our
situation you know we have the problem
of here's a sprite it represents a
fairly complex 3d object but it's just a
flat plane there is no way to really you
know sort it into a scene correctly
because it's a card and that card
doesn't have the meaning that you're I
thinks that it has right and so we have
to decide how much 3d construction we're
going to make for our actual objects if
that makes sense and so and I don't know
the answer to that question right
I really don't and you know obviously we
won't get we won't ever be able to get
full 3d data because the things don't
exist as 3d objects they've only been
painted as images nobody knows what they
look like in 3d right Rome's or is it or
10 11 I mean use fake 3d data since our
cards are essentially flat we can give
an epsilon width to it for the sorting
yes so in order to do that like I said I
I really just don't know how to explain
this sorry um I'll try one more time and
you can tell me if this helps suppose I
have two 3d objects here's one here's
another right here is the camera looking
at them and I want to know which one I'm
going to draw first there is no way to
sort these two 3d objects by which one
the camera hits first because there's no
such thing as which one the camera hits
first right that's that's not really a
thing being humans we happen to know
that because of the shapes of these two
objects in the places where they happen
to overlap we could always draw this one
first and it would always be correct
from this perspective right so that's
good that's the kind of rules we were
trying to think of when we were talking
about our sprites which were like kind
of fake cards they're okay but if we
actually wanted to sort these properly
in 3d using actual 3d data so suppose we
actually have these 3d objects then the
answer is for every ray that comes out
of the camera we must see which object
gets hit first for that ray for that
pixel right that's why you use Z
buffering and 3d rendering because let's
say for example that what these things
actually look like is something like
this
and now I ask you which one of these
should be drawn first well the answer is
which part if I'm looking at this part
of this object then this one should be
drawn first if I'm looking at this part
drawn first right and that's because
their shape is complicated in 3d it's
not straightforward so once you start
approximating things by cards you know
you're into a case that's more like this
which is to say you know there probably
is a rule that would allow you to draw
one thing first and then the other thing
without having to do per pixel
comparison and the reason for that is
because you know that you don't have any
particularly weird like you know shapes
that can be represented so once you've
flatten them down two cards are actually
in better shape in some sense because
now you know you don't have any sort of
weirdness here but you still don't
really know how you should sort these
things because when you're actually
drawing the sprites they're sort of only
approximations to wear these things
actually were in 3d and what they looked
like right so at that point we have to
ask well ok let's say that we know that
we have you know these these sprites and
we're sort of talking about them as the
Y cards the Z cards and we have the full
bounds of them and then we look at these
two things and we know that we want to
do a sort of these of these objects
right well like I said before we can
trivially come up with rule and this is
what we did that does a correct 3d sort
for any two of these things but in order
to actually sort all of the objects in a
single total ordering that isn't a graph
but an actual linear total ordering then
we end up with the problem that we don't
know how each individual split here will
affect the total sort so let's suppose
for example that we have you know two
objects come out drug draw a casar that
would make sense
let's suppose we have two objects that
were on the same plane right or better
yet let's draw one slightly higher okay
and now we've got an object that's here
and we're looking at it from the camera
just want to illustrate you how
difficult this problem is right so I'm
looking at the screen and I'm saying
between these two which one should I
draw first right well okay the first
answer is it doesn't matter because if
the screen looks like this they don't
project onto the same area right so it
doesn't actually matter which one I draw
first but now you're telling me well I
need to do a full sort of all the
objects in the scene that's
topologically correct that they always
drawn the correct order well okay if
that's the case what I need to do is I
need to make a decision about these two
such that my decision about these two
and my decision about these two will
actually yield a correct sort order for
these two which may interfere with each
other and let's make sure that they do
just for fun right so I'm going to move
this one up a little bit right so let's
pretend that one was there
then I move this one down a bit so they
project onto the same area in fact you
know what I'll make this one a little
longer as well
okay so now you can kind of see that
these would project on to the same place
right they overlap so it's incredibly
important that i know that this one come
first and this one comes second right so
if this is a and this is B and this is C
then I know that my order has to be that
a gets drawn first right B or C don't
really matter what order they get drawn
in now so it could be a B C or it could
be AC be but they both put a has to go
first right that makes sense so if I
look down here and I say okay I want to
make a comparison between these two guys
well I don't have any information to go
on but I could pick some rule about
which one I would would draw first
potentially right similarly if I look at
some of these other guys I could make
the same thing they don't actually
overlap right but I could make a
determined about Asian about which one
of these should go first like I could so
let's actually look at some of those
cases and see what happens so let's say
I take a look at a and C and I go well a
should certainly be drawn first and then
a second and then see second because you
know a is overlapping here right that
would always give me the correct results
and then when i start be later I know
that I'm okay but if I start to move a
to the side let's say I move a all the
way over so that now it's here well now
when I look at how these draw right I
could certainly create circumstances
depending on where the camera was right
I could tilt the camera little bit where
c is definitely the thing that's in
front right and so depending on whether
i want to sort a in front of c or not
depending on its motion here right i'm
going to end up with a circumstance
where I either going to see a see if the
head or CA at the head and book in in
different cases depending on how i draw
this it one or the other could be
correct now I come to be and I'm like
what am I going to do with be well if I
was you know looking at be relative to
see before i knew about a right so i
don't know i haven't looked at a yet i'm
just going to compare be
and see together I might say well okay
see clearly klum's in front of be right
I know that that's definitely true so in
this case right I know that I would go
like CB in this case or something like
that right or furthermore maybe I make
the opposite of determination I could
say you know be clearly comes in front
of see because maybe i'm looking more
like at it like this and so I see the
sea at the be in the front and the sea
separately right so if you do these
determinations where I'm just sort of
looking at them in individual pairings
then what happens is depending on how
you picked those pairings even though it
might have been correct for the two as
that you that you looked at when you
then go to insert the third one in
depending on who you were comparing
against right you may insert it into the
wrong place for somebody else it may be
the case that AC is a totally fine order
for where you were looking at right but
be actually needed to be in front of a
so the correct place to put it would
have been here but you never would have
known that because you never looked at a
and B together because that just net
wasn't what you came up with in this
order right so what you end up doing
when you're in a situation like this is
you really have no choice if you're
trying to produce a single total
ordering you really have no choice but
to actually do basically what amounts to
spatial partitions you would have to
essentially build a BSP tree of the
scene I believe because anytime anything
straddle one of these separating plane
lines I have to split it into two pieces
at least in order to be make sure that I
always considered it against everything
else on the side of this guy so the only
things that I could really know that I
don't have to consider are ones that
don't break the plane of one of the
existing sorts that I've already done
and that's a complete like binary space
partition of the thing I don't think
there's I mean I could be wrong but I
don't think there's any other way to
actually do those sorts and guarantee
that they'll come out correctly so
because of that there really is no such
thing I don't think as a complete 3d
sort unless you go into a full spatial
partition so what you're talking about
instead is a partial sort where you only
sort the guys who care about
and prevent yourself from having to do
all of these separate splits to to sort
of deal with people who are sorting
otherwise so that's why you never
actually do this in reality right this
is why you always do as a busy before in
real 3d you would never try to sort the
3d objects in the scene it's like a
fool's errand right because you can't
actually do it for any sort of
complicated objects and even if you have
out it's that you know you could sort
you then have to worry about well how do
I figure out right which one's of these
go in front of which other ones without
actually splitting everyone every time I
kind of go down to which ones are on you
know on which side of which plane right
so we could try I don't know if this
would actually work we could try
splitting people are not swinging people
but we could try always sorting by which
side of the plane you know whoever
whichever side of one of these guys you
were from the camera we could try is
doing a sort like that which I mentioned
before which is to say you know for any
given plane you know am I am I in front
of the camera behind the camera relative
to that plane the problem with that like
I was saying before is that it doesn't
really produce correct results in the
case where two things overlap right if I
have two things that look like this you
know versus two things that look like
this right it's pretty hard to know
without actually looking at the bounds
really explicitly which ones are in
front of which which other ones too
right so I need to kind of know like
exactly where the planes stop and all
other sorts of information like this and
again I don't know you know we can we
can try to do more complicated things
that will hopefully produce a total
ordering and we'd have to worry again
about those splits where we have things
that are on either side I just I mean I
just don't know that we can get any
further than where we got because a very
common case for us would be a Z sprite
with a why sprite standing on it
right that's the standard case of a
ground tile and like a like a monster or
something right that's what we're going
to have and in that case you have a
situation where these planes split each
other in two halves potentially right
half of this guy is on this side of the
monster and half of this guy's on the
other side of the monster right so while
we can definitively perhaps write a sort
rule that always puts the monster on
this side of the plane what we don't
know is what actually happens to which
piece here and like I said it kind of
matters in that sense because if we then
have another sprite and we're comparing
it to this it's critically important or
I guess maybe we'll put it up here it's
critically important that this sprite be
compared to this right and found to be
in front of but if we were in some
scenario where we only were comparing it
to this one and we never got there that
would be that would be a problem right
and so let me give you a scenario where
I think that would happen in a very sort
of clear case so here's an upright
sprite and here's another upright sprite
and here are some grounds so two
monsters and two grounds ok so it's
critically important that this be sorted
in front of this if the cameras here but
and you know what let me make it even
clearer
right but it's also very clear that this
is below this so if this guy got sorted
on this side of him we know that this
guy is in front of this guy right but
this guy is in front of this guy I mean
that's just that's just how that
actually is working for all intents and
purposes right he's he's if he was
extended upward he would be in front of
this guy right so really what we would
need to do in order to know for sure how
these sort orders were supposed to go
again is you kind of have to sort of
think about them in terms of how they
might get bifurcated right so looking at
it this way I'm trying to think of what
the best way to illustrate this case is
once you split somebody by you know once
you have somebody who extends above
where another person sort was it's not
possible to insert this person into the
list in a correct place because this
part of him is above this but this part
of him is below this right and that
makes a difference not only for how he
would draw relative to this but how he
would draw for everyone who's been
sorted relative to this guy already and
I feel like there's really just no
getting around that problem No No maybe
that makes some sense
and so far our sorry this is already
answered but what was the issue with a Z
is not equal to B Z a Z minus B Z else a
y minus B well style total ring so
you're talking about basically sort by Z
first and then by why I think is what
you're saying and the problem of that
with that is that you have so let's say
I've got to two tiles here let me see if
I can do it sometimes it's kind of hard
to draw these things so here is a Z tile
right and then I've got a you know
somebody standing in front of it or
whatever right and you know what I guess
probably a better example for that would
be
see if I can construct this case again
kind of need a 3d program should
probably have one
alright so I believe that this was the
problem that we were having with that
with that situation right so first of
all we kind of have this problem where
let's suppose that these guys are
I've done this so many times now I
forget like what all the cases are and
we probably should have a little thing
that we like keep open which is like
here's you know all the different
problems that we have come across or
thought about so we need a couple
different things to happen first of all
we have the notion that you know there's
going to be Y sprites stacked on top of
each other right so we have the notion
that things you know and I mean I guess
to draw it all in one scene here you
know there's going to be something like
this that's going to include something
like this right and the problem with
that is what are the z values of these
two guys right because if the answer is
I sort by Z first and then by Y then if
this guy is taller than this guy kill
always appear in front but that's not
correct right because this guy although
shorter is supposed to draw in front of
this guy if the camera is coming from
over here so you can't just sort by Z
value okay that's certainly not okay so
let me ask well maybe I could sort by
the base point Z value well alright but
if I sort by the base point Z value uh
then we kind of have the question of
well alright what does it mean to have a
base point Z value and what happens at
that base point Z body just slightly
below where it should be for something
else so for example let's say I have a
step that looks like this so this is
like kind of coming down here and then
I've got my guy here well now his top Z
value right is above this top Z value so
he should draw first and that's correct
but now let's suppose I have the exact
opposite case where he's on the other
side now his top C value is the same as
it was before and he'll draw in front of
this but he clearly should be drawn
behind it right so you can't just
compare one or the other because
whichever one you pick is going to be
wrong sometimes in this case the y
ordering would have told us but you know
in the other cases the other case the Y
ordering would have been wrong so you
have to have a rule that takes both into
account you can't just go let's sort by
one and then the other does that make
sense
and so for us with the wide and z sort
work if z is quantized to room layers
and sprites are split where they cross
layers and maybe the ground a special
case no I think even just even just a
single set of tiles doesn't work
so I don't know and yes like I said I'm
not think about over the weekend my
answer might be we just want to use the
z-buffer because since we know the
z-buffer is fast it may be that
topological sorting is just going to
take too much time and I don't just mean
stream coding time but I mean like
actual CPU time that we don't want to
spend and so we could decide to draw
them as cards where we actually place
the cards in 3d and then we let the Z
before actually do the per pixel
determination if who's in front of who
again not a great solution for certain
cases because of you know a number of
other issues but it might be the right
thing to do so all right I'm going to
wind it down
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for the nurse of a handmade here it's
been a pleasure coating with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home you can always pre-order the
game on handmade hero or if it comes to
the source code which you can play
around with at home we also have a forum
site you can go to ask questions a
patreon page you can you support the
video series we have a a wonderful
little schedule about eight weeks
schedule at you and we have an episode
guide if you want to catch up on old
episodes that's about it for today I
suspect we'll be back next week but
check the schedule bot for more
information on that for whether the next
will be scheduled until then have a good
coding weekend and I'll see you guys on
the Internet take these everyone