hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show Rico to complete-game live on
stream we're just starting in on level
layout stuff laying out rooms in our
game today we're just getting started we
don't really know much about how this
stuff's gonna work or what we're gonna
be able to do here but we wrote some
code that just does some simple stuff
with level layouts and we're kind of get
trying to get to the point where we can
see what we can reasonably do with
procedural generation of how rooms are
laid out and so on
much like the lighting algorithm we're
not going to this with any preconceived
notions we're just trying some things
and we're gonna see what happens and
later on we may take a look at the
literature as well and see what we can
learn from that and integrate that into
what we're doing but at the moment we're
just trying to get our feet wet and see
like what we like what seems to be the
right set of utilities for something and
how it goes alright so let's go ahead
and see where we left off if you
remember from yesterday we had gotten to
the point where we actually had a sort
of full system sketched out for doing
some size computations and we just
finished it at the end of the last
stream so and we were overtime because
you know I didn't want to keep dragging
it on make the stream too long we didn't
actually get a chance to run it so where
we're at right now is we're at the same
place we were yesterday because we if
zero that code out but we changed the
the way that rooms are defined to match
the way that we think we're going to
want to so again same place starting
places yesterday but now we've got all
this code in there that we can now turn
on and so what we want to do is turn
that code on and then try to get it to
the place where it's sort of working and
we can start playing around with it so
I'm going to go ahead and remove our if
zeroes here's our code and there's a
couple things we have to implement the
there's a stack thing that we made that
we were using to sort of track rooms as
we crawl out along the network of rooms
and we want that to to sort of be our
little utility we can use whenever we
want to crawl rooms so that we didn't
implement
never quite got there so we've got a
couple of things like that that we want
to implement so for example this push
room call is the thing that puts
something on to that stack right and so
what that wants to do is that's just
gonna take a room and if you remember
correctly this stack is just real simple
right it's just a thing that says oh
I've got a point nurses in memory arena
that I can just dump things onto and I'm
just trying to keep you know track of
what the stock is we also know right
that we had the pop room version so we
know we've got both the push and the pop
that we want to do and so let's just put
those both in here and write the both at
the same time these are just crazy
simple right there's nothing interesting
about them we're literally just making a
simple little stack here and so if we
want to write the straightforward
version we just say well we know that
there's a room stack entry that gets
generated every time we push so we just
say all right we want one of those of
course we have a free list so we can
just do first free if it turns out that
there is something on the free list but
we take it and we're pretty much done we
just say okay the first free is now the
whatever comes after this one in the
free list and off we go and that's all
we have to do to get one but if we don't
have one then we need to allocate one so
then we would end up in a situation
where we're not going now what I can do
here is sometimes when I like to I don't
like to write it this way sometimes what
I'd rather do is make it so it always
succeeds I think this is just a little
more fun and a little easier to read if
I just say look if there isn't one let's
just put one on right so if there isn't
something on the free list but then I'll
just do a push truck using the memory
that I've got and I know that I want one
of these Jen room stack entries right
and that gets me something on the free
list so basically saying look let's just
say we always get it out of the free
list that we just know and so we always
do this exact thing every time that we
do it but instead we're just gonna you
know seed the free list with a with the
free with a available thing if there
wasn't went on there to begin with right
and so that's just an easier way to
write that in my opinion so I tend to
write it that way fairly often all right
so now once we get on once we actually
have the thing we're gonna fill out we
know we've got entries here and we want
to basically put a room on that that's
the thing we're trying to store and then
the previous entry is whatever was
behind us in the stack right and so we
know what's behind us in the stack
because we've got the stack top pointer
so we know that the top is what was
there and so we just want to go ahead
and replace the top with ourselves and
so this is just creating a backwards
pointing list that just as the stack
grows I just push your stuff back there
so then once we wouldn't need to pop a
room again really really simple here if
you've been watching handmade here at
all hopefully this is just a no-brainer
to you and it's very simple if you don't
watch him you hear that often maybe this
is just like whoa I don't know I just
you know doubt I just use something from
the the STL I don't know what a stack is
okay no big deal
it is not scary right all this thing is
it's just just a chain of pointers
that's it right it's a pointer to the
top and each one has a pointer to the
one that was before it so if we want to
find out what the thing is on top of the
stack we know we can get that really
easy we just say okay the top comes from
stack top right and right now we don't
really need to do it this way if in the
future I'm gonna leave it like this just
cuz it's in the future you want to get
multiple things out of it we may want to
do that but really all we need is the
result here and so we can really just
say that and get all that we were you
know all we're gonna do is pull that
room out and then return it but you can
imagine if there was more data in here
eventually we would want to maybe snap a
pointer to it so you know six of one
half dozen the other but that's true for
the way we want do it now well you know
what here so I think probably we should
just assert on failure when you try to
pop the room because we have a like a
check for it oh you know what let's do
it this way and I'll let you try to pop
an empty stack I'll just let that happen
okay and then there's there's a good
reason why we put the top on
right because now we're gonna check the
top and then if the top has something in
it then we get it right and so that
seems reasonable because then you know
off we go
so anyway once we get one of these
things off the stack we're not quite
done because while we have given you
what the the room was there's on top
stock we have not popped the stack and
this is called pop room which means it
should take the top thing off the stack
so the next time someone looks at the
top of stack they're gonna get something
different right so what I want to do
here is save okay
we know that now whatever the top
pointer is should be the next thing
right we want to move it down the chain
and furthermore we don't want to lose
that piece that we've got we'd like to
recycle that memory the next time you
try to push a room so in addition we can
just take the first free and remember
that by saying oh whatever the first
three thing was that was on there its
previous I'm sorry whatever the first
three thing that was on there that can
be our previous right so basically
whatever the thing was at the top or the
first free list which again is just this
big long list of pointers are gonna
freed ones of these let's just remember
what that was and then stick ourselves
on top of the free list right so this
basically really what pop room ends up
doing at the end of the day is this just
managing two lifts it's taking off one
and putting on the other and push room
is the exact opposite it's it's just
we're just cycling between we're just
moving things from one list to another
right so this way we never take more
memory then we absolutely need to
because we're always gonna just recycle
something if we had a free one available
right we're gonna stick it back in there
all right so again let's just go over
those really quickly now that you've
seen him so we do push through and we
say look is there anything on the free
list if there is then great if there
isn't what we need to do is add a new
one so we use the memory point the the
memory arena that we know we're supposed
to use we just make a new one and again
this will clear to zero so we know that
it comes to is all zeros here not that
it matters we can tell it not to clear
in fact
if we were carried about the speed you
know you could do this I think we've got
right we can just say don't clear and
that way we won't waste the time because
we know we're gonna fill out everything
in here so we could do that too it's up
to us so we come in here and we say all
right let's add to it for this we don't
have one but we then get the thing off
the free list which would either be the
one that's just been there or it's the
one we just put and it depends on
whether there were any free available
right so then we say okay after we grab
that one we want to advance the free
list one forward if we just added one
right oh well I guess you know what that
is a reason why we would want to clear
it right because we need this free
pointer to be zero so we might as well
let it clear if that's what we wanted
anyway and hey we're clearing this a
little bit much but romping zeros is is
probably best in this case anyway all
right so off we go we look at the the
first three we grab it we move the first
free to the next pointer we've got the
room here we record which room it is we
got the preacher we say all right the
previous thing is whatever was on the
top of the stack and now we're the top
of stack done for popping room same
thing in Reverse we say all right what's
at the top of the stack if there wasn't
in the top of stack we do it otherwise
we don't now notice the structural
difference here why is there a
structural difference here the structure
difference is because push room must
succeed right anytime you push a room we
must succeed so if we need more memory
we'll get it pop room just doesn't do
anything if there wasn't anything on
stack right so we want an actual if
around the whole operation because if
there were something to have attack we
don't do anything so that's the
difference everything else is the same
we take the thing off the off the top
right we say all right let's take
whatever the thing was that was right
before this one that had previously been
the top of stack that's now the top of
the stack and then we also say all right
whatever the the whatever the thing is
that we pulled off which is this top
right I don't like you know what
I don't like the fact that it's called
top because it's not the top anymore
how does that look better so we pop this
guy that we're gonna you know we're
gonna remove off we say okay get the
popped room that's the result the stack
top is now whatever we popped previous
so the one that used to be on the top is
now on the top again our previous
becomes whatever the free list is and
the free list points to us done right
now if we wanted to we could also fill
the room with an invalid pointer right
so like if we wanted to we could do this
and that way if somehow you tried to use
it accidentally you would know you'd
fault because we'd be like trying to
look at zero memory so we could do that
as well
it's ineffectual because in any well
working version of the program the only
person who ever writes to it is here and
this is always nonzero in fact we could
ensure that's true
and you know we could ensure that's true
here as well so you know we can add a
little layer of carefulness there if we
want to don't have to but we can so
that's our pushing pop rooms and how
those work and now we can finish the
rest of the stuff that needs to be there
so let's see we have the room stack
there that's fine all right and so now
we get down into the place room stuff
that we were looking at before and seem
to have some parentheses problems here
and there was two men
okay there we go we also got some news
for us to be pointers it looks like and
we did not do that yeah
alright and so now we're back down to
like I said just a couple things we need
to do here it looks like stack probably
needs address up there
so now we're back down to the we're back
down to the functions that we wanted
that we hadn't actually typed in yet and
so what I'm gonna do is actually break
those out here so can be Direction is
gonna be stubbed at the moment so and we
could actually just go put this in for
real
I suppose which is originally when we
wrote the stub code when we said here's
the rooms here's how the rooms are
connected what we didn't specify is why
which directions those rooms were
allowed to be connected so for example
all connections would Allah would be
allowed to be staircases up and down in
the current system because all you say
is this room has to be connected to this
other room but that's realistically now
we probably want for game design for
game design it makes a big difference
whether something is connected up or
down or not because they feel different
and they have different implications to
us in terms of our mental understanding
of the world for example a forest cannot
stack on top of a forest not in most
cases anyway right so the player would
perceive something odd if you had a
forest with a stairwell and a forest on
top of it right so depending on the type
of room that it is and the way that
connection is supposed to be played out
we oftentimes want to restrict
connections to either up and down only
if it's like a bunch of rooms they're
supposed to stacked on top of each other
or sideways only so most connections are
probably going to say either I can be
north south east west or I can be
up down most will not be both and so
that was the thing that we sort of
realized when we were typing in the
actual room connection code and so
that's why we want to be more specific
here right so we want this
directionality to be respected in that
sense right now what we're going to do
is just kind of leave it blank I think
and then we'll take a look at that in a
second but we also have to deal with has
entries which is the way you tell
whether or not the room stack anything
in it and we already really know exactly
what that's going to look like right
because it's the wrong key there if you
don't get the wrong key
then what you can see is that the stack
already has the code for whether it
could pop it's this right here right if
the stack top pointer points to
something then it's got entries if it
doesn't it doesn't so the answer to
whether a stack has anything on it
accomplished is pretty darn simple it's
just whether or not this is a valid
pointer that's it makes sense okay
so now we've got everything in there and
we just need to deal with our concept of
direction now what I want to do to deal
with this constant direction it's gonna
pull this function up a little bit and
I'm just gonna talk about this in terms
of how we actually connect rooms so if
we go over here and we take a look at
room connection what I want to do is
introduce a mask here or a direction
mask I guess I should say and I'm going
to sort of have a an idea of what these
directions should be and I'm gonna kind
of talk about them semantically as well
now if I remember correctly we've done
exactly this thing for exactly this
thing and where we did it was we had
this we had this notion and I don't
remember exactly what it was called but
it was basically like a thing that lets
you get a box sides it was for the
lighting surface index that's what it is
it's this thing right here so if you
remember this thing it had like a
surface index right and the surface
index was decrypted in this fashion and
so what you ended up saying was like
okay I pass in a surface index the axis
and the positive or negative are like
interpreted this way well I'm a big fan
of just once we have a way to do
something let's keep doing it that way
unless we have a real reason not to
because chances are if there was a
reason we did it that way the first time
they'll probably be reason to do it that
way this time so what I'd like to do is
come up with a way of sort of
abstracting this this exact behavior and
then we'll just use it in both cases
right so we'll have this notion of what
direction is like a box you know surface
mask or something like that and we'll
we'll grab this out and we'll make this
be sort of our definition of that right
and that way we and what you know what
else do it like this
all right uh so this will tell us
essentially what we mean by these things
the axis in this case is the x y&amp;z and
it's positive or negative which way it's
pointing right and so we might want to
give a little more I don't know anyway
point being if we just stay consistent
with this then this is the information
that we actually want to know which is
axis index and positive and so what we
can do is make something that translates
to and from that we can basically make a
struct here which encapsulate those two
things for example and we can return
those when you actually want to know
what they are so for example I can say
box surface parameters something like
that right and what we can do is say Fox
service parameters
and you just pass the index and back
come these two so that's a way to go
Jimmy that's a way to go sort of in and
we need a way to go out right
so well maybe we'll call this out and we
need to wait to go in if you will so
what I want to do is make a way to do
get surface index and pass the params
right but really we probably don't need
to bundle them you can probably just do
it like that and then it's why I type I
then what we can do here is just say we
know how to produce one of these we just
say that we do the opposite of what's
going on here so positive we assert
positive is less than or equal to one
right I mean another way to say that
would just be that it's equal to zero or
one and that acts as index has to be
less than or equal to 2 because we 0 1
or 2 right and then the result is just
going to be the surface index shifted up
and a word
so that's a way to go in and out of this
thing
and for what it's worth you're right I
can do this and now that's using the
same code so I know that it's consistent
right so that's really all I'm talking
about there I'm gonna go ahead and pull
these in here I don't know really where
we want to put that we could choose to
put stuff sort of wrap it up into its
own thing at some point if we want to
but I don't know
anyway the box surface mass that you
have here we could call these names as
well so if we think about what these are
x-axis negative is like west x-axis
positive is east y-axis positive and
negative are like north and south right
and ZX is positive and negative are like
down and up so if we want to we can
think about these in that way and these
are the these are sort of the individual
in the indexes that make up what we're
talking about right now the problem with
them is we have two ways that we want to
refer to them and so we have to kind of
think about how they will end up in a
mask these produce indexes where zero
one two three four five are the six
directions we're talking about but if we
wanted to order them together we would
need to generate
asks out of them this is Ike I just want
both so let me put it let me do it this
way something like this and the reason
that I'm doing this is just because I
want to be able to refer to both of
these things quickly and easily and
they're two different things right so
one is the surface index and those are
the actual values the other is the mask
and that's just the index whatever it is
right I in mask for so you see what I'm
doing there one is just zero one two
three four five
the other is one shifted up that many
places so that I can order them in write
very very straightforward but it allows
me to kind of like play with that and
figure out what's going on there right
so what I want to hear is say all right
west east south north down
and at this point this is getting
ridiculous enough that I think I may
just go ahead and make handmade box you
know what let's just go ahead treat
yourself to a fresh file and then I can
just put all this stuff in there
oops yeah and I can put those worlds in
functions in there as well there we go
and now we can look at lightbox surface
and pull that in and now this stuff is
kind of all just in one place and we can
start to build up more things about this
as we want as well right all right thank
you so hopefully this all makes
reasonable sense now we've got the
ability to talk about all these things
and I will go ahead and add them to the
handmade hero list of being food files
that we use and it's probably a pretty
easy generic thing so it probably should
be pretty high up on the list
what is it saying oh semicolon all right
so now that we've consolidated that
stuff in there and that's all pulled out
into a nice little box file that we can
use to do stuff with boxes and we
probably will want to do some other
things with boxes in the future right
but this is just a nice way of like
summarizing our notation so if anyone
wants to know how we're talking about
boxes in any part of the code they can
just look in here and it's pretty clear
how it works and what it does and why
right and furthermore here are the
functions that you can use on it nice
and easy to read right and I do like
that stuff so you notice on handmade
Hiro
I don't fetishize any of those sorts of
things and we never do it earlier than
necessary but once I'm obviously at a
point where I'm like this is how we're
talking about stuff I do like to bring
things out and sort of pretty them up
and make it so that it's nice and like
alright we know that's how that happens
now off we go
so let's go ahead and take a look stir
mask so here's the derp mask what I want
to do is say all right the connection
derp mask needs to be set for whatever
the surface index is what's the surface
index for this thing right well now we
know we can just say get surface index
and here we go we pass the axis and
whether it's positive so there's Tim
inside and then that tells us and we're
done right so that's pretty handy and
it's really that's it yeah not much not
much else to it
so that's all good this of course
doesn't actually need to be any specific
size I suppose so in here our can be
Direction now works unfortunately our
code would not work at all now even if
we didn't have any bugs in the stuff
that we've wrote and never tested which
we kind of need to start testing
certainly but this basically means we
could never lay out any rooms at all the
reason for that is our connect function
has no idea what to do right it's
putting in a 0 for that der mask and
because it'll just be cleared so that
means the direction can't exist in any
way and so what we need to do here is
start actually specifying what the der
mask is when we connect rooms together
now what we can do is by default we can
say a particular thing that should be
the general mask which is whether we
want planar or I guess vertical motion I
don't know but we can see that we've got
a planar box mask which is just gonna be
you know boss Bach's mass west east
south and north combined together and
that's our planar mask and then we've
got an up and bound version and I guess
one thing that's a little confusing
about this is really the direction mask
has to be stated relative to somebody so
suppose you wanted a connection where a
was on the bottom and B was on top well
if I just say box mask up that's not
really what that means because how did
you know which one was supposed to be
the up right so we probably want now
that I'm thinking about it to make the
name of this more explicit
so mask on direction from a or like
direction from a mask
because you can it's always symmetric so
when you specify one mask we know what
the other person's mask is right because
if you say that this can be west or east
then that by default means that the
other one could be west or east
whichever the opposite is if you say
it's only west then that means the other
one had the only East right so we kind
of know that they correspond so we don't
need to specify both but we do need to
say specifically which one we were
specifying it for because otherwise it's
very ambiguous to someone coming along
and looking this code what do you mean
direction mask a thing goes in two
directions right so in a sense we need
to be able to specify and again we don't
want to specify bilaterally directions
because we do want to say did you mean
upward you mean down we need to know
relative to a room though first right it
goes up from a so I think it is roughly
what we want in that case but we do kind
of need to be able to obey it a little
bit more specifically there now there is
another way we could have done that and
that is to just have three different
bits one for up-down one for east-west
and one for north-south right we could
have done that and if we did that then
we would just specify one of those and
we wouldn't need to know
there's pros and cons to each but I
think this way probably ends up being
better because it doesn't introduce
another set of ways of talking about the
directions we already know that plenty
of our code wants to talk about specific
surface indices so just having this code
also use that anomic nature I think
probably will prove to be right because
I think both ways are a little messy
neither solution is perfect and so I
think that just picking the one that can
be used in more places more often is
probably the better choice when faced
with two imperfect solutions and so
unless we find something a little bit
further down the road that really makes
us go wait a minute no it should be the
other way I think we wanted to stay with
something that's more explicit so yeah I
don't know what we want to call this
like what do you what are up and down
you know the problem one of the real
problems is that in the real world be
used terms like vertical to mean things
that go up and down but in the game
world when you're looking at a screen
oftentimes horizontal and vertical
neither of them are up and down right
they're both used to describe lateral
motions that are in the plane so I don't
know
yeah I don't know we're gonna leave like
that for now cuz that's just it's what I
can think of so there's our mask and
here's our indices those are all nice
and tidy now and now we have a direction
mask from a and what I'm gonna say is
that the direction mask from a and I
suppose I can just call this entire mask
from a don't need to get too verbose
there what I could see there is when we
connect two rooms together and you can
kind of see where I'm going with this
99.9% of the time the way that we're
gonna connect rooms probably I'm
guessing is to just say look it's gonna
be planar right so and in fact all of
the connections we did so far were all
planar connections we didn't have any
other specialty but they weren't in
America so I think that that's a
reasonable way to do it because most of
the time that's what it's gonna be
so all of our code right now is now
implicitly saying these two have to be
plain early laid out right so now I
think we're good but can be direction
because of that sort of realization that
der masks kind of has to be relative to
something if we want to be using
specific directions when we specify it
can be Direction is not really
sufficient right the reason is not
sufficient is because when we're talking
about a connection we don't know whether
we're a or B if all we specified was the
connection so what we need to do here is
say alright we need to talk about can be
direction from a particular room and so
when we say could we go this direction
we need to know which we're talking
about here now can be direction for this
particular thing which which one are we
talking about right and that's crucial
here are we talking about you know how
are these rooms getting placed and so
what we're doing is we're placing this
room and so what we want to do is look
at how we wrote this code if we come in
here on axis 0 positive false
essentially right so dim 0 sy
zero if the side parameter was one came
in here if the side primeros zero it
came in here and so that's saying that
well we're we're gonna try and place
ourselves in the case of a negative axis
means our minimum has to be less than
the maximum value of the other room
right which means we're sort of to the
min side of it in the case where we're
negative so that to me suggests that
we're talking about this sort of
backwards if you will because can be
Direction is sort of saying oh if I've
got can be Direction is saying here is
the side in axis I want you to tell me
whether I could place the room in that
direction right so that means that a has
to be the room that's plate that's
that's given here in a sense so probably
what I just need to do is
probably what I need to do is allow you
to ask either one right
I'm pretty I'm pretty sure of that and
so if we take a look actually how that
works I'm just going to go back here to
action box so what's interesting about
this is these are all sort of like
complementary so basically if you just
switch which ones you're talking about I
think at that point you're fine
so I think we can bitwise do this let me
go ahead and sketch that out for you so
if I want to ask if I can go from A to B
that I just used the mask as it is if I
want to ask whether I can go from B to a
I have to do an inversion of the mask
right that flips these directions but
that's actually pretty easy to do I
don't know what to call this getfox mask
compliment maybe
so in this case I need to construct a
result and what I want the result to be
is I want it to be East if it was west
or west it was east north of it was
south south it was north right I just
want to flip those and what you can see
is they're lined up right I've got two
bits for West and East the next two bits
for North and South next two bits are up
and down right so what I can do is I can
mask off half the bits and half the bits
right by being creative so I can make a
thing called a half bit mask here which
is box matte oops and I suppose I could
really just do it this way
right so I'm just taking one in the
bottom zero one zero one right which is
west south and down and what I can do is
mask those out right and then mass the
other ones out
so just west south down just east north
up right space what we're doing here
otherwise like I could also say just
odds just evens right and I can call
this the odd bit mask you know I'm
saying I guess if we wanted to say bit
zero bit one bit maybe you would call
this thing it depends what you want the
one bit to be called 1 or 0 and the
uh here's here's what we'll say how's
that now there's no anomic nature so
what I want to do is say all right let's
take the Box mask and end it with the
bit mask and let's take the box max and
end it with the bit mask shifted up by
one right so when I end it with this bit
mask what I'm going to get is just a
zero two and four bits and when I end it
with the bit master fit up I want I'm
gonna get just the one in the three and
the five right and all I do now just
swap them out again really easy so all
I'm doing is saying okay once I've
masked out the high bit in each pair I
can shift this up and or it in and have
moves a little bit to the high bit in
each pair the same is true for the
opposite if I have the high bit in each
pair I can shift it down and or it in
and now I've swapped the high bit with
the low bit right so this just moves the
ones to where this moves the low bits
where the high bits was and the Hybris
where the world it's just a Swizzle just
a two-bit Swizzle well that's it right
and yeah that's all I wanted to do so to
get the Box mask complement all you have
to do is just this bit pattern here it's
very simple right
so what I can do in terms of going back
to my world Jen I can now ask either way
whichever one I want so I can say Jen
room from so I can say can go direction
or something like that or can or maybe
like could go direction from this room
over this connection and then what I can
say is well we need to compute adder
mask it could be this one which is the
one that's already in there
but if if the connection isn't a so if
it's actually B or something right then
I need to do the complement of it to
flip it all the way around and that's it
so now I think I can ask that question
however I want and that's good because
that way all the rest of the code
doesn't have to think about it anymore
which is pretty important right I
thought I did change it to der mask from
a did I not
oh dear mask from a there we go and so
now we can just call it go direction now
we can pass whichever room we want here
and then pass the other things so what I
want to know I think I wrote this like I
said the other way round so what I was
saying is we're placing this room so I
want to know if I could go the direction
from the other room so what I'm actually
saying I think is this can I go from the
other room to the room I'm placing in
that direction that I'm saying here
right
and so now I can just ask that question
the way I wanted to and I think this
falls out so we'll we'll verify that
later
just to make sure side is correct there
I think it is but yeah you know don't
quote me on that
so all that stuff it's fine when we get
down here and we're gonna do our max
aloud dimension one of the things that
this
I think fails to take into account and I
wish that it would so far is this
doesn't really handle the first room
very well so when we get to the first
room you could put it anywhere you want
you know and maybe it's fine to stick it
all the way at the very earliest part of
the you know at negative two billion or
whatever maybe that's fine but it seems
like we maybe want to place it more
centrally around zero you know what I'm
saying so I think in some sense we may
want to special case that first room so
that it starts out more towards the
center and we actually can do that I
think without really doing much else
what I could do is just here have
something like place room in volume
it's just sort of an understanding of
what's happening there and what I could
do is say look let's just place the
first room wherever we're gonna place
the first room as a seed point and then
we'll go from there so when we actually
this is not the room Tina I wanted so
when we actually put the first room on
the stack let's actually place the room
in some volume that we want and let's
also set its yeah let's do this let's
not push that room let's push the
connected rooms instead and we'll set
its generation index right
and that's just so I can sort of say
where I want layout to start and I
realized that that's not maybe actually
necessary but I just want to do it so
that I can control where the first one
goes for now we may undo that assumption
a little later on but for now I just
want to do it I don't know what we want
this initial room to be quite yet and
again we're gonna kind of play around
with that a little bit later on but for
the moment I just kind of want to do
this manually
yeah we're gonna have some problems with
this but I just want to do it manually
for now so that room goes from negative
4 to 5 maybe well maybe 4 to 4
let's just do that and that's where the
rooms gonna be for now and we'll
consider that placed and we'll push it's
connected rooms on and that'll be bad
so that's all folks that's not what I
wanted so that's all fine and and dandy
and I think that should give us the
ability to start debugging the code now
so let's go ahead and step in what I
want to do is start debugging at the
place where we do the layout and I'm
sorry that that oh you know why we're
compiling in release mode which I don't
wanna do
so let's go through here and let's take
a look at our stack you know I just
thought of two before we start I want to
do something even more ridiculous
actually now I think about it when we
talk about the rooms here what we're
doing this is gonna be real pain in the
butt because we have no idea what we're
looking at right and so what I might do
here is something like this I'm just
gonna stick a debug label in there you
know and then when we do our actual room
creation so you know when we're down
here in the Jen room sort of phase of
things I'm just gonna pass what the what
the room was right
and you know we can be as descriptive as
we want here because these things don't
get
maybe I'll go caps and this way because
the first thing we're gonna do is we're
gonna see a stack of stuff I want to see
what they are right what's in that stack
and we're gonna have no idea there's
gonna be a bunch of bundles of volumes
and we're gonna have no idea what they
are
this way I'll actually be able to see
what they are so then what I can do is
go up to the general function and I'll
just define the general function to
actually be a macro and so that way what
I can do is say well in there's actually
going to be two versions of this thing
and
when you call Jen room either you are
gonna call the version that has the Jen
the spot and I guess this will be the
internal version spec and the name and
the label I should say or you're going
to call the version that doesn't have
that and that way it'll just get
stripped off so when we're not compiling
the internal version it'll just go away
and that'll be the end of it right no
big deal so then all we need to do is in
the case where we did actually have one
let's assign it
and who knows maybe we'll decide this
isn't a debug label and eventually we'll
just print the name of the room like
maybe that comes up in the game and then
I'll just get rid of that and we'll
always have that good do oops okay
so now we can be a little bit more
introspective here so the side alley is
the thing that's getting placed first
and then if you look at the spec I'm in
stack what we should see is justice you
know we we can predict what we want to
see on the stack if the code is working
properly
the orphanage specifically says that the
side alley right is connected to the
forest entrance and the backdoor path so
the two things that should have been
passed there are two things that should
have been pushed on the stack those two
rooms Hey look we have nothing on our
stack so obviously we have a bug
so first place things first we can go
ahead and go here and take a look at
what happened if we look at the first
room here and we look at the connections
you can actually see that there are
connections so it does seem like the bug
is just in push connected rooms right
oh well that's the problem we're looking
at the wrong so as you can see here
we're pushing the other room but for
some reason testing this one well
obviously this one has it set duh like
we're working on this one right now so
that's a pretty simple book maybe that
was the only book we'll see in a second
so let's do this the stock top now here
are the two things that are on the stack
Orphanage backdoor path at orphanage
forest entrance that's what we wanted
well had it up here before let's get it
back that's what we wanted right back to
our paths and Forests entrance that's
the two things clicked to the side alley
so that's exactly what we want and let's
go ahead and see what happens next so we
grab a room off the stack and it turns
out the room that we get should be one
of those right our furnish backdoor path
so now what we need to do is push all
the connected rooms onto the stack that
are from that room right and so let's go
ahead and do that again we can look at
the stack and see what's on there
if we look at the top prove I've got two
rooms and so what we have here is we
have the forest entrance and the
orphanage main room as well that's
exactly right
the orphanage forest entrance is
connected to both the side alley and
lure fridge main room again walking just
right let's go ahead and grab our mid
max vols here so our minimum volume and
our maximum volume start out they should
have the entire universe enclosed in
them and you can see that they do write
negative maximum to positive maximum all
well and good so now we need to figure
out whether we can place this room this
should succeed if we have no bugs
because there's only one constraint on
where we place this room so it should
work right now probably won't cuz you
probably do have a book but point being
this one should work eventually we'll
get to a placement that should fail
because our
current code is not good enough to
handle loops and stuff like that and
there's all other kinds of bugs it has
it's not checking for overlap so our
current code is not good enough at all
to do the right layout but for this
particular part of the layout it should
work so here we go
we step down into the place room
function and we're talking about
connections that this room has to have
right so we start with the first
connection that it has to have and again
thanks to that handy little debug label
like I said this becomes a lot easier
conceptually for us because we can kind
of tell what we're talking about here if
you look at the connections we can see
what's connected to what or what's
supposed to be connected to what by
looking and seeing that we're talking
about a connection from the back door to
the side alley right and we're trying to
place the backdoor path so we're
basically saying well let's look at
where the side alley is which i think
was the first thing we placed right so
we can see that that already got place
because it's got a generation index of
one and so we're talking about these two
getting placed now this one that we're
on right now getting placed so we look
at these two we should see again that
that should be the side alley and it is
so we're talking about the side alley
and again the backdoor path right and
then we go through and we're now gonna
try placing it on one of the sides so
the first thing we do is say well if we
were going to use the x-axis negative
right and against that West you know if
we were gonna place it west could we go
west so let's go in there and see so we
look at what the direction mask from a
is the direction max from a is 15 that
is what we'd expect right because all
bottom bits are set east west north and
south all set so that's going to be
everything up to the 16th bit set or the
16 bit set right not the 16th bit 5th
bit so all bottom 4 is set which is 15
it's what we expect so now we say look
which one of these are we right it turns
out that we are actually the B
connection so we
to flip it so we need to do that
compliment so let's see if that code
works right we've got a bit mascara you
can see that bit mask is set to 21
because it's every other we mask out the
the two halves of this right so we get
the five and the ten sweat it up right
and then we flip it around and as you
can see we get the exact same result
that's what we wanted because if you
have north and south set and east and
west set but not up and down set then
the complement of that should still be
north south east west
because again you can be any of those
right so there we go
now we want to look and see okay for
this dimension inside which index is
that well that's index 0 exactly right
is that allowed in here right oh we have
a bug could be found a book that's wrong
this is the surface index not the
surface mask now that was pretty obvious
and pretty obviously a bug because this
says get service index not good source
mask to avoid that problem in the future
or to make it easier for us to be more
likely to do the right thing let's also
make a get surface mask right and that
way we can call either of those two
things and I feel like that would make
it a little easier
[Music]
and that's just again really really
really really straightforward there's
nothing interesting about it all we're
gonna do is say that we take whatever
the surface index is and make a mask out
of it right okay let's jump right back
in there as the first time you ever call
that function so let's jump right back
in there and make sure we do it right
test mask is 1 now that's what it should
have been not zero result is one which
is true we can go that direction so
that's good so then what we're gonna do
is say all right let's make a new volume
here and let's clip it so this is where
we're going to place the new room we
tested whether we could go in the
negative direction from other room this
means we need this to be placed to the
west right so let's take a look we've
got new min vol new max wall this is
where the minimum can be placed so let's
go ahead and see where that clips to and
this basically says that the maximum for
our volume can be placed at for the
minimum for our volume can be placed no
further than four now
I feel like we got the sense backwards
so the thing that I was afraid of I
think is true right that's that's not
correct these should be the other way
around the reason I say that is because
this should be placed to the west this
placed it to the east you know I'm
saying
so we've got the sense of that flipped
so if we come in here and we're placing
it in the positive direction we're
setting the max2 clip downward so and
that's wrong so this is this should be
the other way is what was messed up
about that right oops
and perhaps if we wanted to be more
specific about it we could also use the
minimum room dimension in that direction
so this is our max we also have a min we
could actually pre constrain it well
I'll just leave it like this for now but
we may want to just pre constrain that
part as well all right let's keep going
all right so we it could go direction
now we're gonna clip it and we should
clip it properly this time I believe and
here you can see yeah this is right so
now we're saying the maximum right that
the both the minimum and the maximum
could have been would be at negative for
now right it can't go any further than
that if that makes sense so I think
that's that's what should have happened
let's keep going so if I look at how its
flipping the other dims here's the
y-axis so now what we should see is it
has to be overlapping that room somehow
right so what we should see now is the
Y's should be set up so that between
negative 4 &amp; 4 you're gonna get those
for your other dimensions right
so that why max can't go any higher than
three for the minimum of the room and
that's correct because if it went any
further you wouldn't be able make a door
and for the maximum volume you can't go
any lower than negative three because
then you wouldn't include negative four
so you couldn't make a door I think
that's right so that all seems saying
what I will say is I think that I
probably want the starting room to just
be one high though oops not quite want
to get there yet I was trying to step
through this code okay
so after we've done one clip and we've
got it in here right then what we want
to do is get the maximum volume we could
fit in here and so what that's going to
be is is massive right it's it's
something that could be really large
really huge right if we wanted it to be
and okay so is minimum dimensions for a
room
so this is a case where we're gonna have
overflow right our problem here is that
this subtraction is going to produce a
signed result which is bad for us
because we need to have another way to
do this
so what we want to see is if these are
greater than four away from each other
and the problem that we're having here
is when you subtract the max from the
men that number may be higher than is
representative all in a nest thirty-two
right so there's a couple ways we can do
that you know one way is just
restricting the range to be smaller than
that so what we could do you know the
trivial way of avoiding the overflow is
to just say that our infinity volume
isn't such an infinity after all right
and then we would be fine I think if
that makes sense so when we now go
through is minimum dimensions we should
be able make it work although the fact
that it's not maybe that code is buggy
in some other way let me actually also
do this
so
if I compute these dimensions first then
we can inspect them pretty easily and I
should be able to see what's what so
so that is actually backward so okay
so no overflow problem there that is
actually just busted so that's okay
let's go ahead and see what's up with
that
so if we look at our min volume
yeah our max our max X can only go up to
negative 4 for some reason so it looks
like maybe we've got a bug in that
clipping routine
yeah let's take a look at that
so here's my Neumann volume that was not
causing the problem yet here's my new
max volume this was causing the problem
right so what I'm saying here is if the
maximum value that the maximum could
have taken was greater than the minimum
that this room is then I need to back it
up to there right
so I guess I see what the problem is the
problem is that the minimum volume well
no I I guess I don't see what the
problem is there
so that's still right so what I'm I'm
just getting confused because there are
so many values here it's hard to think
all through that's still correct
you can't the maximum value can't go
higher than that and the same would be
true of the men right they're both going
to be clipped there so that seems fine
so when I get down here yeah having the
max the minimum volumes maximum is
negative 4 and it's minimum so that's
the actual value that's wrong is the
mins are now non-negative
right
so that's the problem is that divide is
too sloppy
right so the minimum value divided by
four is not able to actually do the
divided by four is it actually because
of that I don't want to say why cuz I'm
not sure why so let me just make sure
this is just C doing its thing
yeah so what was happening there and
maybe so what we should do I guess to
maybe prevent that from happening in the
future is just when we define those
maybe we have to force them to be the
values that they are the types that they
are because what it was doing is it was
converting that value to unsigned
integer and dividing it instead of
leaving it signed through C's magic fun
internal promotion rules I'm sure so now
that should be correct right
and we still have a breakpoint set there
I hope let's see yes we do so now when
we do is minimum dimensions it should
work and it did so now we can go in here
and call place room on the next
connection I don't know if there was an
X connection was there there was but it
doesn't have the generation set so we
don't have to consider it oh but we
don't keep chaining so we're gonna need
one more thing here right we're gonna
need a thing which continues to change
the room chain the room so here when we
went through and we said if room con
else right but what we actually need to
also do is we need to continue placing
the room in the case where the
generation index doesn't happen right so
if we're skipping this connection we
need to keep going so now I think about
it probably this is just a dumb way to
do this we could just speed this up a
bit by just assuming that that's always
the case and spinning on the room con
afterward right
something like this
so basically say look let's just walk
let's just walk this thing until we find
one you know I'm saying so we'll come in
if we have a rim con
we'll grab out what the other room is
from that connection
if the generation index matches ours
[Music]
then we can process it otherwise we keep
going right I think that's all we need
to do
okay so this is correct because the
first room connection is one we can
actually process so we go through we do
our clipping as we wanted to and then we
continue down recursively in this case
we know that this other room hasn't been
placed yet so we skip it and then the
room con is null so and then we can come
down here and actually place our room
which is what we want so we have a min
and a max here that we create we know
that they're going to be very oddly
placed rooms here
yeah because that first one is it should
violate where we placed it
oh this still seems wrong you take a
look at min ball max ball so here's the
min ball and the min Vall says it can be
anywhere from here to here right here's
the maximum volume and that's just that
doesn't make any sense does it
yeah so there's one additional element
of the clipping here yeah yeah yeah when
we say that this thing has to abut the
other room we're not saying that the
maximum can any be anything less than it
we're saying that the maximum has to be
exactly that right so effectively what
we're saying here that's that was just
nonsense what we just said right there
right that that wasn't not correct what
we're actually saying is okay if you're
connecting on the positive side right
then the minimum must line up with this
right so we have to be able to move the
minimum here right otherwise it wouldn't
be able to connect now this means we
could fail and that's one thing that we
weren't really accepting here but yeah
so basically what we need to do here is
say all right
the maximum can still do whatever it
wants it can be as far out as it wants
but it would have to be at least this
far so that's still fine the minimum
volume on the other hand has to be
exactly here and if I can't move it
exactly here then we have a problem
right
so if
No so I think this time so that's all we
have to say so if the minimum could not
have been placed exactly here then we
have an issue so we need to basically
say if the minimum value is greater than
the place that we needed to put it right
if it can't if it already can't be there
then we have a bug otherwise the minimum
has to be there does that make sense
we're basically saying this thing has to
be placed literally exactly here there's
nowhere else it can go
and I think that's what we actually want
and so if for some reason you weren't
able to do that so if the if the minimum
value that we would have accepted before
for where it was going to go doesn't
allow us to actually get here in the
first place it's already further that
way then we're we're toast and I guess
we don't really have to do anything
about that now that I think about it
that we can just do like Newman Vall you
know
or something like this so we can't just
say like clear it out like it's it's
over at that point the same would be
true on the other end so when we needed
to connect the other way round we need
to do the same thing so we need to say
something like well okay if I'm going to
compare the mins here I just need to
make sure that the min can't be any
worse than this but the same thing that
happened to the men up here has to
happen to the max which is to say that I
actually need to be able to set it to be
exactly this value
so whatever the minimum value was on the
other room that has to be the maximum
value on this room now it can't be
anything other than that so I think
that's right and then again if for some
reason we can't do that we have to
invalidate this volume and so it won't
actually work later and it does anything
the new max the test here is going to be
similar to the test here which is to say
that if the maximum value was already
lower than this right meaning it could
not have been placed here then we're
done there's nothing we can do about it
right because we can't move it out to
here at that point
right
so I think that's right and then we just
need a way to basically make one of
these and I think I can just do
all right so now we should be able to
step back through that and I have it
work more like what I want it to do as
opposed to what I wrote before which was
not what I wanted to do let's just take
a quick gander here what we actually end
up with now that we're here so if we
take a look at the minimum placement
here's the the minimum for everything we
take a look at the max placement and you
can see the difference now the max has
to be basically exactly here right it
can't be placed anywhere else so let's
see what we get for each of these
dimensions
and that looks about right again we have
we're not doing anything special here to
try and keep ourselves from creating
large rooms it's just going to create
the largest room it can in the space
which is not good I mean it's not what
we want
although it looks like it still wasn't
quite able to place it let's try that
one more time well I see when that
happened result is true so if this must
be this one no
so the mean is zero and the men volume
max is zero
so I think we just have an off by one
error in that clip on the interior then
it's actually probably just because of
how we're dealing with Z
because the maxi should be won and in
fact the Minzy and maxi should have to
be one there in order for them to line
up right so those look actually a little
bit backwards to me take a look at that
so that's this code here so
so you can see it's setting the maximum
right it's saying if the maximum value
is greater than whatever the apron value
is there right then it has to be equal
to
so I would have thought that this would
have taken care of it if the max was
less than or equal to the minimum of it
it has to be one over that I want to
step in here and see what these come out
to be
yeah but that looks like the only thing
that's misbehaving so I'm gonna go ahead
and get in there I'm gonna skip the Y
for now I'm just gonna look at the Z
value so here we're now on Z and when I
come through here I want to look at what
is gonna happen to these values so you
can see we've got the min Z and Max Z
that these could be are totally wide
open right there's no there's been no
actual clipping of them whatsoever and
you know I'll be honest I don't know why
this part hasn't happened yet
oh whoops because I'm looking at the
wrong ones
so the Z values are not have been not
been changed at all as you can see now
how the X values and the y values 15o
because we were already on that we've
already looped through that so we're
good so that's all good I think that's
what we would expect so we've got
Menzies and Maxie's that are full range
on both right now so as we step through
here and we do our clipping what we
first want to do is say all right then
we're talking about where the minimum
point can be placed and we say if the
maximum Kier is greater than whatever
the maximum of the other room is then we
would no longer overlap so we need to
make sure that it's far enough back
right so that sets the minimum the
maximum point that the minimum Z can be
at zero that's correct because really
well no it's not
so I suppose since in this case we're
talking about these things as not being
inclusive of their maximum it actually
still needs to be plus one
right because that's not the maximum
value that the max could be it's one
more than the maximum value that the max
could be I hate crap like this discrete
math is the worst unfortunately it's
only thin computers can do anyway so
when we actually do that clipping right
if we want to be consistent here then
the maximum always have to be one more
than what they would would otherwise be
so this is actually still this because
the max has to be placed at wherever
that location would be but +1 to include
the room and then like I'm gonna put the
2 min ville updates sort of back to back
here so right to set the minimum value
for where the minimum can be we do move
it back
and that's yes so this is going to have
to be true in the other case as well so
to set the minimum value value here
we need the min plus the interior apron
[Music]
yeah so we've got both problems here as
well so what we need to do we need to do
a couple things first of all we need to
make this line up right gap wise but the
other thing we need to do is we need to
do the same thing we were doing here
which is to say when we actually find
one of these it has to be updated we
have to also make sure that the update
is legal right but I guess since we're
only checking for the greater-than
that's already gonna happen but we need
to cut like this needs to include
failure as well I guess is what I'm
saying so in both of these cases we kind
of want to be able to set an inverted
infinity volume in the case where we
find that we've failed right we don't
ever want to set something in a way that
makes something legal again that was
illegal previously because we always
need to make sure that there's no way to
on do a person's constraint so when the
box the boxes are only ever allowed to
get smaller right we're never allowed to
like push something out that would make
something bigger than it could have
otherwise been so I guess anytime you
see this where you're taking a minimum
and you're pushing it out it's fine but
I have to make sure that we're never
doing anything worse than that right so
basically like this needs to always look
I guess like this so so you know it's
okay because we're always saying look if
the minimum was greater we're pushing it
back that's probably okay but if the
minimum if the maximum was already on
the other side of it we need to
fail so I suppose right I mean that this
is alls I'm trying to trying to say here
like this is we need to fail out here if
we don't overlap I guess if that makes
sense like we need to say oh it's
minus-- greater than that then put it
here but if the max something like this
if the max already says we can't do this
then we're also fail right meaning if
the max was let's say setup such that
the min can't possibly end up in this
range then that's a fail that's the part
that we weren't doing before right so in
addition to this part we yeah we also
need to to nuke it in the other case so
if the maximum place that we would have
put the minimum value before right is
can't reach if it's if it's less than
the place that we needed it to be
I guess we can call that the min min so
if the minimum value before this is
mind-bending I hate writing code this
way this is where you just want the
diagram right because the diagram is
perfectly clear but then when you
actually have to write the code it's so
the names are so obtuse and there's so
many of them that you are always getting
some permutation wrong right where
you're thinking like okay wait this is a
test for greater than the minimums
minimum value you know and it's like
that's just a horrible way to describe
this because not only do you make a ton
of mistakes when you write it but anyone
who has to read it will never be able to
like map it properly whereas if it was
just a diagram you'd be done right it
just feel like oh that's the things this
has to go there that has to go here
right it's like trivial when you draw it
I'm not even bothering drawing it
because we all know what it would look
like when it was drawn but it's trying
to like type in those things that
becomes incredibly difficult and you end
up like having to alt tab back and forth
your diagram all the time and still
getting it wrong right so just yeah it's
maddening anyway so this is the location
at the far end of the room and we're
saying that the minimum the minimum
could be it's got to be less than this
and so if yes so this is just illegal
this is just wrong
I don't think these tests are set up
right I think they're backwards so
here's what we want to say right we want
to say to me that if the minimum value
was passed there already then this is
just illegal right because if you're
seeing that the minimum value couldn't
soak so if this minimum value was
greater than or equal to what what we're
talking about here so the max it's got
to be back one from that and then back
one again right yeah if the minimum was
already greater than or equal to or sir
sir if it was greater than that value
then you can't place this thing because
there you're basically our constraints
say it can't go there right otherwise
we do know now that the minimum minimum
has to still overlap the other bound of
it right
[Music]
and that's really all we can say about
the minimum minimum so I think this
actually looks more like this so the
other rooms volume it has a minimum and
a maximum and so we know that our
minimum and minimum minimum value the
minimum value then it has to fall within
a particular range and that range can be
anywhere prior to the max which is this
guy I suppose we don't need this guy
yeah well I'm a second
so if the minimum goes over that value
then it's illegal if it doesn't go over
that value well in I mean that's really
it that's the only thing we're checking
that value for right
yeah so basically we know that the
minimum value there has to be greater
than whatever this is I'm sorry can't be
greater than whatever this is if it was
we would not be able to overlap the room
and we're done right the next thing we
want to check is the minimum volumes
maximum which is this and so the minimum
in this case I may describe this well
that's that is exactly what we're
talking about here so well no it's not
exactly so the min min here this is
where that is the maximum value the min
can be has to be greater than this now
this is just wrong I don't know why we
wrote this I think that was part of the
bug right so the minimum minimum value
is just whatever the interior apron is
here so then whatever the maximum value
or minimum can take meaning the farthest
we are allowed to slide our minimum
right that's right
the furthest that we're allowed to slide
the minimum now has to be here
here's a question can't we just do this
in a simpler way because they look at
how much time getting spent on their and
I think it's mostly because I'm hand
coding the intervals effectively if we
just did the interval properly I wonder
if this would just work so if we think
about what has to happen here so what
are we saying in the case where we know
we have to clip it to one side of this
volume right we're saying that that this
right the the maximum value here we're
saying that that the this thing has to
be
we're saying that this thing has to be
starting there and it can end anywhere
on the other side of it right that's why
we have to do this inverted infinity
volume stuff here is to peg the value to
a specific location in this case names
trying to think maybe it's okay the way
we were doing before because since we're
always updating the values they should
just cross in the case where they can't
have happened so we shouldn't actually
have to check it right so let me just
see if that's the case here
okay so in this case since we're talking
about and let's just again move these so
that they're in the same place here sooo
if we're looking at these and talking
about always sliding them if we always
slide them the other direction we should
be okay I think because in this case
we're only ever clipping - we're not
having to peg we're just talking about
the range so we should be okay with that
right and if we wanted to hear I suppose
we could even do this the other way
round I mean you just need both checks
that the problem was we were only doing
one of the checks right but in theory
you could actually do that so you could
say like this
if the Newman ball
right so if the minimum was less than
this it becomes this right so we're
moving it forwards and if the new
monville
max is greater than other room Vall
right so I think that's more like it
right the way that I should have been
writing this was you always just adjust
the bounds
towards the direction they're only
allowed to move one direction and then
the bounds just cross each other when
you get an invalid volume right so I
think that's I think that's it
again so writing this other one the same
way then we're just saying okay if the
max is greater than the max slides back
if the min is less than the middle moves
forward right and so probably what we
should do is just make these be an
actual routine we can call that would
clarify this a little bit better and
make it so that it was less verbose
right where you're updating one of these
things and you can imagine what that
would look like right
so this would be what that would look
like meaning clip the minimum to this
and that that slides it forward if it's
less right here's a way to clip the max
right and so that seems probably like
what I want and that way we can just say
like okay there's the function here it
looks like this it has volume it takes a
dimension and it takes a value and then
it just looks like this
so now we've done a clip min and
equipped max they operate inversely
comparison - right and what we couldn't
furthermore do I don't know if we really
want to do this or not but what we could
do is incorporate the max version into
this so basically saying that like if
the max is supposed to clip Q this value
it actually clips to the next value
because we know that max whispy includes
this way if you clip the min and the max
to a value it would move one over right
I don't think I want to do it that way
[Music]
but you could didn't understand why
someone might write so there's that oops
so here we have clipping the min and the
max to that value that just looks a lot
more straightforward now see now how
these are sort of split out so in one
case you clip the min and the max of the
min and you just put them in of the max
and the other ones you clip the max of
the min and the min and the max of a of
right the other two so one of them
always gets pegged and the other one
doesn't
so again it's still really hard to read
like I say you you really want this to
look like a diagram because it's just
you know I mean now it's a lot more
condensed and it's easier to see what's
happening but it's still really
confusing and the reason is because you
have mins and maxes of mins and maxes
you're computing intervals of intervals
right and that's just very easy to see
in a diagram and very hard to see in
code because you just got all these
names flying around that's the only way
to really refer to anything so then when
we come in here though now we should be
able to simplify this a little bit more
and think about what needs to happen
here so we've got two things operating
the min vault with two things I forgot
the maxval so what we want to do is we
want to in both cases clip the min and
the max of both things the question is
just what do we want to clip them to
right
so what we want to see here is that the
lowest value the low can go right
should still be anything probably am I
wrong about that it's really just that
the maximum can't push past oh and the
minimum can't push past so the minimum
minimum value it just can't be past the
location that we want to be before so
the maximum minute so we just have to
set we only have to set the maximum
minimum value and say that the maximum
minimum value or I should say the
minimum well no
the minimum value and the maximum value
of the minimum should in theory be able
to be anywhere you want but the maximum
value of so yeah okay so now I'm
starting to see why this is is confusing
so really it doesn't really matter where
the minimum maximum values are it just
matters that they overlap so if the
maximum value you just care where the
maximum value of this thing is hostel I
somewhere within this if the minimum
doesn't and that's not representable by
an interval right so I think actually
the the nasty part about this that first
parts nice and clean now but the nasty
part about this is actually that we
can't really propagate this information
forwards can we
so the fundamental problem that I'm
talking about is we know that we need to
overlap this or the two rooms won't
touch right so you know this is a room
that's already been placed if we need to
overlap this the definition of
overlapping is just if the minimum lies
within it or to this direction then it
then it's in right well the minimum
value has to be such that its maximum
never passes this right and the maximum
has to be such that its minimum never
passes this and that we can represent
but once you have that satisfied you
still don't know if you actually overlap
because let's say this is the region
that you actually end up with right here
are the values plausible values for the
minimum and here are the plausible
values for the maximum or something
right it will always it'll always
overlap if you instead say well here's
the plausible values for the minimum and
or let's say here are the plausible
values for the minimum and here are the
plausible values for the maximum yeah I
mean I guess what I can say is we can
always ensure that you would include
this but you'd have to ensure that you
include all of it is the problem meaning
a room that just looked like that would
never be allowed right because if you
allow the
[Music]
like if you allow I should say a room
that looks like that would never be
allowed and the reason is because if you
allow the minimum to be down here once
it can go fairly far this way then you
no longer know if the maximum say could
be anywhere in this range or something
like that then you no longer know do you
whether you could place that room
yeah I don't know so let's let's think
this through let's actually just try it
because I'm I find this very confusing
and I think I just need to work it
through a little bit more carefully so
in terms of the minimum minimum it
doesn't matter where it is right because
any it as long as the room was long
enough right you could put it as far
minimum as you wanted right so really
the minimums it's just the maximum is
the only thing that's clipped and the
maximum has to be the the the maximum
has to be such that excuse me when
you're moving the minimum you cannot
move it past the room so in this
situation like that it that's as far as
it can go and it can't go any further
than that the maximum on the other hand
is the other way round
the maximum value it can be as high as
it wants right so we don't care how far
it goes the other way but when we're
actually moving it back we can't move it
back past where it would still over
overlap the room right I think that's
right
so that location would be at the minimum
plus the entire apron plus one right
so those two things are true right now
once once we now the question is what
about the other bounds because we're
talking about the region in which the
maximum could lie and so when we're
maximum could lie we know that the
minimum value for the maximum cannot go
past there but the maximum value for the
maximum could be as far away as we want
right I just don't think there's any
limitation on that unless I'm thinking
about the problem wrong because that
that box that includes it can be
arbitrarily large I think and the same
is true of the of the of the minimum
right it can be arbitrarily small on the
other direction so I think that's about
right that's what I'm going to say
so let me just see where we're at with
that in terms of the rectangle we now
come up with
so let's see here
yeah looking at this again seems still
slightly off because I want it so I
think that's the interior apron problem
again which is to say that the interior
apron actually needs to be zero on Z
because we don't have the same
requirements on Z so I guess we would
say that so let me just try that more
time there right because we don't want
to like do the interior apron on Z's so
the min/max Z's are now set roughly
correctly I think because the Minzy it
will overlap if it's anywhere negative
anywhere to infinity but it can't go any
higher than zero right because it's got
a line up there and the same is true in
the other direction right the the rest
of the values here I guess I think
that's all saying min X min Y yeah so
that looks relatively saying let's see
what room we come up with here
the minimum value for the Z is zero the
minimize maximum value for the dimension
two is wait that's not true oh it is
true so that's actually again that's to
be inclusive that has to actually be one
so how do we not get that so when we're
clipping in here to the maximum value
than the minimum value since it can be
just trying to think it through here we
know that the we know what these values
are so the minimum value in case of the
other mentioned is zero right so then
we're gonna add the interior apron which
is also zero and they're gonna add one
so it seems like that should just
produce one shouldn't it have
oh and the min volume of course is
getting clipped to the interpret minus
minus 1 which in this case I guess yeah
is not what we were well okay but
looking at this so when we clip the
maximum of the minimum moving it to
whatever the max was we know we go back
the interpret and the reason we're
subtracting one there is because we're
setting the max and the max we know is
one past where we want to be so we have
to go back one more further from that
right
but this is clipping the maximum value
itself which already has that one built
in that's a mind bender so it really
does end up being bad then when you clip
the max volumes minimum you're looking
at a minimum and you're clipping a
minimum so you don't need the plus one I
don't think because you're starting with
a minimum and you're saying you need to
be there right
[Music]
but I suppose you kind of have the other
thing which is that you also are talking
about 2 mins man this is nasty
so so when you actually are talking
about clipping these two you've got a
max value that is having these values
where community might might be the
better way to go here just looking at
how many crazy things you have to keep
in your head cuz so it is the max value
but it's also the min volume that you're
clipping so it's where the minimum is
gonna be placed so if you assume that
you placed the minimum you need to allow
the room for the minimum to be placed
there so I guess that's okay the minimum
value has to be between there and when
it's the max of it which it takes it so
I think that's okay this is just
mind-bending there's too many flip-flops
there in my opinion so I think we're
gonna need to look for an easier way to
talk about these I think it's just way
too mind-bending to think about that way
so maybe they need to be uniform values
it's really the only way to look at it I
don't know if that'll introduce other
problems there as well
but we'll see
so that's right that's right
[Music]
well no it's not
so technically that would not be
overlapping right so I do think it's
asymmetric in that sense let me just
double-check that yes so I think that's
correct because it has to be that if it
was zero that would no longer overlap
the other room but hey we placed that
room now and I think we place it in the
right location this will not will
eventually get to room it can't place
like so and I'm interested to now see
what we end up with with our kind of
ridiculous room sir
so I guess one thing and I neglected to
think about is we also have to figure
out where we want to place our our
sausage gentlemen there what I'd like to
do now is simplify this down to just
making two rooms that are connected to
each other so if I got rid of all of
this
and maybe actually I want to do this I'm
not sure where we place the camera
currently let's do this well actually I
can still leave it there
so this will just create two rooms that
are connected to each other the main
room in the Harris bedroom right so now
we should only place two rooms total and
we can actually step through those and
make sure the x/z are right so we got
the main room the hero's bedroom those
two are connected we've created those
two rooms and that's all we have to do
so now we can go ahead and and see what
actually happens there so when we come
down here and you know figure out how
we're gonna place this room the first
room is already placed and we don't know
which one that is let's see so that's
the hero's bedroom so that's already
placed so then we have to just place
whatever this other room is and this
should be the only other room right
there shouldn't be anything else on the
stack and there's not and now we can go
ahead and actually start placing them so
we come through here and we place them
there is no other connection to deal
with than this one so we go ahead and
clip it and we verify that it actually
is about volume so they come through
here now we try to place the room let's
see what the room actually says
seems pretty reasonable it has to be
between there and there
that all seems pretty good so we take a
look at the min and the max we know
roughly where those have to be so let's
go ahead and compute those so then we
end up with a min of negative 53 and a
max of negative 5 that makes sense
the next dimension we can place it
anywhere
and then we get down to Z negative to
positive
so that got placed so the room is now
placed and we're good so I think that's
all fine
the only problem that we have here is
that for reasons unknown to me probably
just because there was so much stuff for
us to think about there
I just never finished the exit path of
this right so what we want to do here is
say well look if you place the room at
some point then you're done right
so we want all of these to sort of be
predicated on the result and we want to
stop looping right so if at this point
we could even return outside from
outside from inside there if you want to
but I'll just make it so these loops are
predicated on it so as soon as you get
one of those you're done right you stop
looking
when you find one of these results and
off you go we could also turn this into
one loop
and we'll see
all right so now we ostensibly are
placing two rooms and you can see that
we actually did place two rooms there
here's the first room so right because
we know because of its dimension and
then here's the second room that got
placed now it doesn't quite look like we
did it right because they don't quite
overlap right you can see that there's a
gap here so we can see that we're off by
one it's but otherwise it's correct it's
not probably great like it's not what we
want but it's okay and we also need to
record the actual connection between
those rooms which is to say we need to
place the connection at the location
where the rooms actually overlap so as
we unwind out of that we need to
actually do that right and I think
that's something we probably need to do
right here so if the room got placed
then we know that the connection that
we're looking at here needs to actually
be put in the place where the two rooms
overlap because that's where you can
walk right
so that's fine as well but we yeah like
I said we still have a problem with the
abutment so the abutment is going to be
coming from here I believe because if
you looked at how it was erroneously
placed it was this one that was wrong so
I suspect that the problem there is just
that like well we're placing the minimum
here and we're saying the minimum has to
be exactly
starting at the maximum and then here
replacing the maximum we're saying this
has to be starting at the minimum back
one but okay so it looks like this case
is wrong to me
you want the maximum value to actually
be literally this value so I think
that's what you're actually looking for
yeah and that's correct now so now you
can see these two rooms join up and they
join up in the minimal way possible
right probably now we want to push this
in the way that I said we wanted to push
it in so maybe you want something more
like that and now when the rooms are
joined they should have to adjoin in a
way that affords more space you can see
that and finally you know let's say we
maybe reduce this at the moment to more
sensibly sized rooms so now we've got
that
why am I not there we go
so now we've got that and so now we
should in theory also be able to extend
the number of them that we do
oops I don't know if this will actually
work probably won't but actually you
know what we know it won't work cuz we
don't do overlap testing so this will
like place rooms on top of each other
right or something crazy like that
so actually we probably don't want to do
that just yet
because we know that won't work what we
want to do instead is probably do
something like the forest path so that
we've got something that comes then out
of the main room you know what I you
know I've never mind I'm just not even
gonna bother because we need to first do
overlap testing before any of that makes
sense because there's no reason why it
couldn't just stick it right on top of
the existing room that would just be
totally illegal right yeah and that'd be
totally fine
so what we really need to do now to
finish up and then all in the stream is
we need to place the connection and we
need to place it in the region where the
two rooms are actually abutting
somewhere in there and so if we knew
that door sizes are like two wide or
something like that or however one wide
even then all we need to do is we need
to look at which direction we were
trying to go and what the actual clip
region now is for the two rooms so we
know we have other room ball and room
all right and what we want to do is we
want to intersect these two
in a sense right like that's sort of
what we want to do but the two are sort
of distinct they're not actually
overlapping they're just a budding so
what we need to do is we need to just
talk about the one intersecting the one
dimension that they that we're actually
trying to use right and we know that
they'll be separated by the dimension of
the connection right so we know that the
dimension that we picked here we know
that they are distinct in that dimension
but they should be overlapping in the
other ones so when we get this door
volume here we know that it doesn't have
any actual volume but it does tell us
the overlap right so the first thing we
need to do to fix that is we know that
the door in the dimension in question
right I think
there we go so in the dimension in
question we now know that the the door
should actually sort of take one from
each one into either side so it should
cut one into the room the middle side
and one into room on the Mac side right
so what we want to do here is say well
we know which side we were doing so if
we were talking about going in the
positive direction so this thing is to
the to the east if you will then we know
that the minimum value of the door is
going to basically be the maximum value
of the source door of the source room
right and furthermore
we know that's actually one pass we want
to recent want to back it up one right
and then the minimum value of that we
want to back that up one oops
when I say we wanted to back that up
when I actually mean we wanted to push
it one forward right so I believe what
we want to say there right is that the
minimum for this door no no I was right
yeah so that's correct so the other room
we've got it to minimum we're pushing it
one forwards and I guess now that I
think about it we don't even really need
to look at the other one at all right
it's just that we're just going on
either side of it on the other hand we
would want to do the opposite thing
or I mean I guess you could look at it
this way so we could actually say maybe
this does that make sense so basically
we know that one of the rooms is minimum
will be where it is but we just don't
know which one right so we just have to
figure out which one it is and then at
that point we can just set this directly
so now we have placed it there the
question is what do we want to do about
the rest of the overlap region right
when we intersect these two things which
sort of says what they are now what I'll
probably say is let's just leave that as
an intersection for now and we'll let
the whole space between them be
intersected there let's just do that
temporarily I'm gonna write doing a
section routine so if we have to
intersect two volumes basically what we
want to do here is just start with one
of them and then we just need to check
each of the each of the dimensions so
what we want to do now is say well okay
we know we've got each of these things
as a span and we want to sort of move
each one up to the other ones mins and
maxes right so what we want to do is say
if the I guess I can even do it this way
right
I can just say my results minimum for
this dimension is going to be whichever
one is less right so if a ZEM is less
than B's minimum and I mean we can just
say you know we just want the minimum
no no if we have an s 32 minimum that
was the only problem looks like we do
all right so all we need to do is do
this for the minimum and the maximum
right now this would be a union because
you'll be taking the minimum minimum and
the maximum maximum and that's not
actually the intersection the extra
intersection after that but I'll go
ahead and make that as well since I
already checked it in right so if the
intersection I actually want whichever
one is higher right I want to squish
these two so I'm taking the lowest
maximum and the highest minimum that
makes sense and we'll step through that
in a second so the other thing I just
realized is we never actually recorded
this value so we need to actually take
the connection now so when we're looking
at this particular connection we need to
set the connections volume equal to this
tour sorry if I'm behind my head there
all right so now that should be right
although it doesn't it looks like we've
got that backwards you can see it's
clipping out there which is wrong so
we're close all right so let me move to
the other side here so I thought I had
this right if the site is positive then
it's the other room minimum that were at
because we're going this way
right otherwise it's ours because we're
going the other way right
Oh nope that that is backwards yeah okay
that is backwards is we're going
positive that's our minimum since it was
going that yeah yeah so this stuff is
just begs to be flipped all the time
accidentally so there you can see the
door being placed right and you can see
where the door actually got got put in
and that's all well and good and we can
go between the rooms as well and of
course our lighting being slow as it is
unfortunately means if we're in debug
mode the lighting just takes up way too
much time to run that's speed but I can
compile in release mode and then we can
hop around properly right so you know
once we're set with that we now have the
ability to sort of correctly solve for
the daisy-chaining of these rooms
together and what we probably want to do
is narrow the door down right because we
don't want the door to take the whole
overlap space we want to just be a
narrow passageway that you go between
right so we can work on that a little
bit later I mean for now we can just
throw something in if we want which is
to say that the dimension of the door in
whatever the other dimension is well I
don't even bother because that's just
gonna take a bunch more time so we can
go ahead and Q&amp;A now I would say the big
thing that I want to think about going
forwards is I don't like how Phoenix I
don't like the max and minimums being
treated differently like that it just
the inclusive exclusive rule is just a
little too mind-bending and I feel like
it's just gonna be annoying and we're
gonna a maybe once you have the basics
worked out it's fine
[Music]
but yeah
it would be nice to deal with there's a
little bit more a little bit more
succinctly
we've now make you like low hi width be
helpful you mean so that you would have
min and Max and low and high so you
could remember which one you were
talking about maybe or something weird
using a range of low values at a range
of high values for dimensions be easier
than having two volumes
I'm not sure what you mean you know can
you be more specific there
why are you pending x2 those types
that's just if I'm making a notation
that it doesn't matter if they're 32
bits just they have to be at least 32
bits right so if I say something is a
you 32 I mean ask me exactly 32 bits if
I say something to you 32 X I just mean
well anything 32 bits or above is fine
and technically I could I could be more
precise about that sometimes too I could
say like actually this only needs to be
16 bits so it's a you 16 X or something
like that and sometimes I go through and
actually do that in the code sometimes
you got to did you want to avoid a
Christian uh in the mean the crawler I
did I didn't want this thing to recurse
and the reason I didn't want it to
recurse is because it's gonna have to do
first of all it'll be deep sometimes
potentially and the other because of
it'll just you know if you have long
change with lots of branching you'll end
up with very large stacks and I just
kind of wanted to not worry about that
but the other reason is rip up and
replace is gonna have to go in here
somewhere and I feel like it's probably
gonna end up going in here and so I
don't really want recursion sitting in
there it's gonna be kind of nasty this
thing is just to get us started so it
may want to become non recursive as well
but at the moment I don't care although
now that I think about it it doesn't
really need to be recursive for any
particular reason
so it could easily just use a stack as
well pretty easy pretty pretty simple
stock but again I don't know we're gonna
have to see how we want to start doing
the harder parts of this first the hero
walk outside the rooms in this setup no
so the way that we do movement is very
specific right now you can only stand on
a legal square so you know if you tried
to walk outside anywhere you just
wouldn't be able to even though this is
just kind of preliminary stuff here I
suppose it still forces you to only do
the right things like you can't ever
stand on something that wasn't mark
stand a bowl which i think is generally
better because it means even even when
we're just in the simple phases of
laying out some rooms here and just have
a little debug hero hopping around you
still can't break the game in that way
which is nice as opposed to you know
player unknown battlegrounds where a
year after supposedly shipping the game
people fall through the world all the
time right Neil said lo can be between
negative 30 and 5 and high can be
negative 40 and 20 as opposed to a
minion volume of negative 4 and 5 and a
max volume of negative 30 and 20
Neal I think that is what we're doing
though unless I'm misunderstanding you
we are doing the min volume is the min
and Max of the minimum so it's the what
the low value can be and the max volume
is the high volume it's but where the
high value can fall so isn't that what
you were saying or is maybe that in that
what you're saying okay do you think
that languages that interact with a GPU
directly like Nvidia CUDA or AMD h IP
would be useful for game programming
yeah I mean some there's some reasons
why it's hard to use things like CUDA
potentially in game programming and
sometimes that's just because they
haven't optimized it for being like
frame coherent so we can say like we
gotta get this frame out on time sort of
stuff because you know a scientific
computing stuff doesn't care if they're
hitting a frame budget they just want to
compute as fast as possible and so on
right so sometimes the systems aren't
set up for that but at least CUDA is now
kind of set up so that you can do frames
on time I don't know about h IP but so
you can use them for game programming
unfortunately they're kind of specific
right and so they're not maybe what you
really want but you can use them or at
least CUDA you could I mean I don't know
what you do on Intel I don't know if
that runs CUDA at all right like I don't
know how you would necessarily ship a
game that way unless you just had one
for each so it's like oh we shipped CUDA
on NVIDIA and H IP on AMD and something
like that the jim-jams 40 off topic do
you miss some features that exist in C
but are absent in C++ no because I
there weren't any of those really when I
learned C so no I mean there is one the
void star treatment in C++ is really bad
that's the only thing that was true in
the original see that they messed up in
C++ pretty bad which is like you kind of
got you were supposed to you needed a
thing that was
a pointer that can convert to any other
pointer type once right
so in see a void star used to mean this
could be anything so if I assign it to a
foo star it will work C++ failed to
introduce when they got rid of void star
as that they failed to introduce
something to take its place and that was
a mistake so when they first did that
change I do miss that I wish that was
not the case
let's hear thoughts on DXR I already
talked about that in a previous episode
we ever get back to the nicely aligned
grass rock bitmaps not exactly there is
something that will happen there but
I'll save that for a little bit later
but we won't be doing quite exactly that
but will we do something simple some
that simply similar
so I could not exactly follow you but
can you guess at what makes the interval
computations tiresome yeah I mean the
thing that's the problem with them is
that there's too many components to them
right and this is like a common source
of problems and a common source of bugs
and it's because whenever you're dealing
with something that has a lot of
components so in this case we have a
minimum and maximum value for the room
location which itself has a minimum and
maximum value each of which is on three
different dimensions right programming
does not make it easy to clearly
articulate which of those you're talking
about any given time in a way a brain
works brains don't think about things in
terms of words when those things are non
semantic right so a brain doesn't like
think about this in terms of like a min
and a max and a radius and whatever
right it just looks at this and it's
like oh yeah the cylinder so the chance
that I hand this to somebody else and
they don't understand what the bottom
the top are is like zero right you have
to be a fantastically stupid human being
to not immediately know what I'm talking
about
on the other hand when you translate
this into code there are so many
variables for all of the parameters here
the width of each of these individual
squares and the height of it and which
direction they're going and how it's
wrapped around here the fact that the
cylinder and the thing are on the
opposite sides of this and this thing
has a joint level right and whatever
when you just look at hundreds of words
in code it's easy to accidentally forget
which one of those real-world things
you're talking about is mapped to the
word because there none of them are
words you would ever use in daily use
you would never talk about the cylinder
that way you just Intuit what it is and
you point to it or you do things like
that right and very rarely do you have
to come up with words that specifically
locate anything on here other than like
top bottom or something right
and so that's just a fundamental problem
with the way we do programming and
people don't appreciate it we've known
it for a long long time and just nobody
bothers to fix it right so people spend
all their time doing stupid stuff like
arguing over ridiculous things in the
C++ standard if they just deleted 90% of
the C++ standard and it says put all of
that effort into specking some visual
representation thing you could do with
your programming it would have paid back
thousands of times versus anything
they've ever done in the language right
and that's just because they
fundamentally don't understand that the
hard parts of programming aren't the
things that they're looking at right of
all the time they've spent looking at
things like pointer lifetimes and stuff
like that which are so simple and never
really cause problems and are just
uninteresting this is the stuff that's
actually hard right this is stuff it's
hard for good programmers anyway maybe
they'd like to spend their time focusing
on stuff that's hard for bad programmers
I don't know right but if you actually
want to talk about what's hard for
everybody that it's just tends to be
difficult it's things with lots of
indices lots of names lots of different
parts many dimensions all these sorts of
things they're just really difficult to
program because you just have all of
this mapping you're costly doing in your
head if you ever do one of those
mappings in your head wrong you've got a
bug right hopefully it's a bug that
shows up but you know if you're unlucky
it's not
do you feel it'd be worth to abstract
away subsystems input audio life psycho
with an event system well I mean I guess
I would sort of answer the question with
a question which is what do you think
the bonus of that abstraction why why
would you add events to them like is
there something in particular you think
you want to achieve can we try all the
rooms now uh no because they can't
possibly be set it's our thing isn't
satisfied isn't smart enough yet to be
able to satisfy them right and it will
just place rooms on top of each other
which will create a huge disaster right
so if you come in here and actually do
this you're in trouble right we've got
it first of all it should just assert
that it can't satisfy once it gets to a
point where it needs to connect to rooms
and it can't connect them it's just
gonna fail right I don't know how many
rooms had actually got to so I guess we
can sort of make that happen here but at
some point right it's gonna it's gonna
hit that limit so you know I don't know
what it did it laid out some rooms here
and and hey they were placed and
connected properly so that's good but
again it can't that's weird
we have too many light points
hmm we must this must be like a very big
room or something you get that or
there's something bugging there let me
actually also take a look at this here
but anyway eventually it can't it
shouldn't be able to place some rooms
right so you can see exactly what it's
doing it's always just going ahead and
using the first direction it finds its
placing placing placing placing
eventually it has to place a room which
connects back to one of these other
rooms and it can't do it right and so
it's just like fails what it needs to do
is actually be smarter right and either
try other permutations or have a
strategy for actually achieving that
otherwise it's just always gonna connect
them this way ad infinitum right so it's
not really a it's not really at the
point yet where we can try to create the
world the way we actually want to and
probably won't be for a little while
right because we're still just getting
into the generative part of it so two
rooms connected each others all we can
really do at this point in terms of what
the algorithms written for it's just the
basics of that and then we have to kind
of go from there
Jim zero have you ever made a
visualisation tool for working stuff
like this out I'm thinking of something
like live could end in combined with
showing values on screen and lurking
between previous values and new values
showing how the changes affect the seam
of the code reloads I yeah I would just
like that to be part of the programming
language though or part of the debugger
right I can only dream of that you know
I have never had time to make one myself
after all of this code on rendering in
this is code reloading still working
yeah sure it depends which code you want
to reload cuz the room the stuff that
generates the world doesn't get run
again so you can't change that code I
mean you can change it but it won't do
anything but the other code you can
change just fine
so you know for example if you just
didn't want the lighting to run or
something like that you could just say
[Music]
let's see
right here inside lighting test I could
just return right so here's the lighting
running and I can recompile and then
when it's finished
syntax error when it's finished how do I
convince you to compile I if the
compiler ever would produce an actual
result there we go
then now we're just not outputting any
lighting at all right and there's just
garbage getting out getting output to
the textures and then if I recompile it
right we're back so code reloading still
works just fine
garbage your awesomeness dead lucky are
you doing custom memory management yes
we do we do do custom memory management
in fact you will note that in the actual
code there are no calls to malloc or new
there's only some in the like
preprocessor so nothing with a handmaid
underscore in front of it is in there
right and we have two modes one of which
grows on demand that's the mode we're
using right now so it actually can't run
out of memory unless the system runs out
of memory there's another way we can run
it and we're not really doing that right
now which is where you fix it's a fixed
size and if you over flat fixed size it
stops and that did you know we haven't
really done much with that in a long
time just kind of is that way
so I'm gonna go ahead and wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me for an
episode of handmade hero sort of
pleasure coating with you as always if
you would like to follow along with a
series at home you can always go to
handmade hero org and you can pre-order
the game which comes with a source code
so you can play around with it yourself
and yeah so if you're interested in
learning C and stuff it's a great place
to play around with it that's it for
today I'll be back next week same time
same place
probably but if you're wondering you can
always check the schedule bot it'll tell
you when we're gonna be live until then
have fun partner everyone I'll see you
on the Internet