start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero show where we
code a complete game live on stream
except not these past two weeks because
I am an RSI break but I'm kind of hoping
that will be a fireside break maybe next
week I don't know so I was kind of
hoping this might be the last week for
it but no promises because well nobody
really knows very much about RS I part
of the problem and so you never really
know what the deal is and getting
diagnosis is pretty tricky so so who
knows but point being in the meantime
instead of just not streaming I decided
to still do essentially q and A's
because I can draw with my right hand
just fine and so there really isn't a
whole lot of issue with taking basic
questions from the audience like we
normally do so we had some questions for
some reason and i'm not going to
probably spell this right but let's say
that it's called brezin ham but i feel
like there's maybe some other letters in
here so let's just put quotes around
that and say that like spelling may vary
but people were asking sort of about
brezin ham in terms of how you do a
breast and ham line drawing or present
ham I I feel like probably the easiest
way to address it is to say that in
general there's a sort of a conceptual
thing here instead of calling it a
present ham drawing scheme or whatever
we could instead just call it error
based rasterization and i think there's
probably a correct term for it but it's
been so long since I've studies so I
don't even remember what the term is but
I think there is it's not digital
differential analyzer because that's
only if you if you add EDA is when you
actually transform it into a slightly
different format so I think it's
actually called something else but point
thing I'm going to explain the technique
they're based on and you can use it to
draw anything you don't have to use it
to just draw lines you can use it to
draw really any shape that has an
implicit formalization of some kind but
first I'm going to bite my fingernail
because I have OCD tendencies it's fine
all right so let's talk about this let's
talk about this this method so I don't
really know why people wanted to know
this I have no idea I just know that
they did and i think it was Charlotte 93
who asked about it originally but I saw
other people mentioning it as well so
apparently multiple people wanted to
know I have no idea point being what is
a breath and ham algorithm what does
that even mean what does the president
lighter why do we care why did anyone
ever care well in the old old old old
old days and I mean old days way back in
the dawn of history when people rode
around on mastodons and all these other
sorts of things you used to try to draw
things a pixel at a time directly to the
actual buffer that was on the screen
most of the time right so we're talking
about the days when like literally there
was like a frame buffer and this frame
buffer was literally being drawn out to
the monitor and it was you know it was a
CRT it was a cathode ray tube right it's
kind of like doing a soul scan out and
literally this frame buffer here was
getting drawn directly out and drawing
graphics was incredibly expensive like
processors were super slow and like you
drew things like one pixel at a time and
you hoped you could sort of draw it fast
enough that the user didn't get bored
watching it and I mean watching it like
the user would literally watch your
program draw the graphics on the screen
and if you don't believe me go watch
some like original capture videos of
like the original say King's Quest you
could literally watch it fill in the
shapes of the graphics on the screen as
you SAT there I'm not kidding so yeah
like we're talking old old days old days
so in those days the performance
characteristics of algorithms looked a
lot different than they look now it was
about minimizing cash effects it wasn't
about trying to keep him like a certain
memory footprint it wasn't about
paralyzing instructions it wasn't about
multithreading you literally had the CPU
was the total gating factor so you were
just trying to minimize the number of
operations it had to do to draw a line
that's what you were trying to do and
furthermore you were also trying to make
sure that those operations were very
cheap because you didn't have things
like fast floating-point multiplies you
didn't have things like floating point
multiplies at all if you wanted to
multiply two floating point numbers
together you probably were going to have
to write code yourself to do it so
everything was in fixed point or integer
math okay and that's sort of the state
of the world where these sorts of
algorithms came about at least as far as
I know I wasn't there I I wasn't present
ham I think invented his line drawing
algorithm before I was born I think
probably as born in 76 I suspected dates
before then because people were doing
raster display stuff before I was born
so I'm assuming I don't know we could
look it up so anyway in that in that
context a line drawing algorithm that
may seem a little bit silly now makes
potentially a lot of sense which is to
say that thinking about a line in terms
of starting at a particular pixel and
literally moving along each individual
pixel until the line is drawn like this
and even if that line goes all the way
down the entire screen doing it that way
today would be kind of a laughable idea
right because what we want to do is we
want to break up things into lots of
pieces where oh my goodness what just
happened okay I didn't want that to
happen but that's fine that was my
drawing tablet helping me we want to
break things into lots of little tiny
pieces we want to do parallelizable
operations and so on so the concept that
we would start out at a particular point
and then draw the whole line it doesn't
make any sense we would never do that
right which is not to say that brezin
hands algorithm can't have applications
in a modern day not saying that at all
because you could imagine maybe adapting
it and clipping the line in doing us
just saying in those things they weren't
thinking about any of those things
they're thinking about literally
starting at a point and then you know
drawing the line pixel by pixel and
that's what they're trying to accomplish
okay so how do we do this right how do
we actually construct an algorithm that
does this well obviously if you're
trying to draw a point from p0 to p1
okay if you're trying to do that you
obviously know two points that are on
the line p0 and p1 right so you have a
starting point if you will you could
choose to start at say p 0 you know one
point that's on the line so the concept
of an algorithm that wants to start at
the start of the line and go towards the
end of the line you immediately have
something you can start doing which is
you can fill whatever pixel you're at
right at that moment right so if you
imagine us trying to create a present
hands line drawing routine you could
imagine us saying okay well we're trying
to create this thing and I want to start
by drawing pixels I want to start by
placing myself in the pixel that the
line starts at right and maybe that's
here maybe that's p 0 so the first step
of a president lime drawing algorithm is
pretty trivial you would just draw this
in right but now where the present hands
line drawing part comes in is the
obvious question of what do you do next
right because I've got this line and I
want to know that it fills in these
pixels right I want to know what pixels
it fills in I want to know that it fills
in that pixel and that pixel and that
pixel and that pixel and so on right I
want to be able to draw this line by
filling in the appropriate pixels so the
question is what is and this is what
sort of i assume brezin ham was asking
himself when he came up with this
assuming that that's a dude I don't even
know to be honest with you that I that I
don't even know normally I know more
about people who made algorithms this I
have no idea I know it's called it I
assume this named after him who knows
anyway the question that the algorithm
designer would sit down and ask
themselves at this point was well what's
the simplest possible what's with the
fewest number of basic operations I
could
to figure out the next pixel I need to
fill because I'm going to sit in some
loop here right I'm going to do like a
while loop ok and I'm going to fill a
pixel each time through this loop and
what I want to do is no okay which of
the pixels am I going to fill because
that pixel fill operation is some fixed
costs and I can't get away from that
I've got to actually fill the pixel
right but then however much work it
takes me to figure out what the next
pixel is to fill that's basically the
whole speed of my line drawing routine
ok so the less work i can do to figure
out what pixel it is the better for me
makes sense okay uh so what the breaths
and ham family of functions do because
you can imagine that's kind of kind of
crazy right it's like oh well what am I
going to do with I got no floating point
like maybe I have no floating point mass
right how do and so this line like I
don't even know I can't normalize its
slope or anything I can't I can't
compute how far it takes me to step to
here cuz that'd be like a divided I got
a guy you know it's like everything you
might start thinking of that would be
trivial for you to do today and you
wouldn't even care is actually like
maybe crazy back then when you only have
integer units and they're very basic and
you know a multiply even an integer
multiplies expensive and blah blah blah
right okay so the concept of these
algorithms is to say well let's think of
it this way okay if I'm drawing this
line I'm going to do one of two possible
things okay I'm either going to move one
pixel sideways or I'm going to move one
pixel down and no matter what kind of
line I'm drawing I could always phrase
it in these terms because no line ever
goes both down and up and no lie either
goes both right and left so no matter
where the line goes I could always start
with just a little bit of preamble and
know that in my while loop I will always
be choosing between one of two possible
motions either a sideways motion whether
it's left or right but
always be one of those for that for that
given line or up or down and so the
present look the key thing to present
ham is to turn line drawing right into a
choice a binary decision basically it's
to say instead of thinking about what
pixel I need to go to next and trying to
calculate that pixel let's acknowledge
the fact that I know the only two
possible pixels it could be and let me
figure out how to choose between them
right so that is how a breath and hand
rolling algorithm works what it does is
it says while you know i'm not at p1
right I say let you know it's the wrong
direction I say like you know start at
p0 while I'm not at p1 ok I'm going to
fill the pixel I'm on right Phil p or
actually I should probably do this the
other way should probably this is a do
loop because I always want to fill even
if it's a zero-length line I'd probably
want to fill it depends on what your
fill rule is whether you're going to
fill p1 or not let's say we're always
going to fill both ends ok so we'll say
p equals p 0 will say do fill p right so
that's just puts a pic you know fills
the pixel with the color or whatever
whatever that has to do and then we
basically make a decision we say like
decide you know up or sorry we say
decide vertical or horizontal right and
then you know p equals you know new pity
or whatever then whatever that move is
okay and so the entirety of the loop the
entirety of the present and part is just
this part right here it's saying we're
going to decide whether to move
vertically or horizontally at each step
and you might say that the probably the
important part of present hams is just
that is literally the fact that it turns
into a decision problem do I move up or
down I just do one of the other right
and I maybe should i maybe should write
this a little more clearly let
say I read it like this right it's more
like if you know horizontal is better
than my PX you know plus equals Delta X
right so whether I'm going forwards or
backwards this will either be a positive
1 or negative 1 otherwise then we assume
that vertical was better and we move
vertically right so that's basically the
entire thing we're going to we're going
to talk about for a present and I
enjoyed routine we're going to fill a
pixel we're gonna say if we should move
horizontally move for a Zaun tily if we
shoot more vertically or or if sorry
should say otherwise the only other
choice is we've replaced so move
vertically and then before we do
anything else you know up here we could
pre initialize this to saying you know
is DX positive or negative right is is
dy positive or negative and that would
just be a check it would just be which
direction does this thing go so for
example if we want to do this really
trivial you could just say whatever the
sign is of p 1 minus p 0 right is is the
Delta for either one so the DX would be
that way and dy would also be that way
right so you can imagine saying okay i'm
going to subtract these i'm going to get
the vector right so here's my p 1 here's
my p0 i'm gonna get the vector whatever
the sign is of the y component that's
the direction I will move the Y and
whatever the sign is of the X but that's
the direction I will move the X make
sense right so it's literally just
saying hey at before i start figure out
whether this is an up line or a downline
and figure out whether this is a left
right or left line or a right line
that's it and then from then on the loop
is the same right I just either it i'm
either like incrementing to the left or
incremental to the right or whatever
right so that's it that's the entirety
of the present game loop so the question
is just how do we compute this how do we
know whether a horizontal movement or a
vertical movement is better
like which one is it and that's why I
use the term error based drawing before
remember I said I use this term I sort
of described it i said error based well
the other sort of interesting part of
resin has besides that turning into a
decision problem is the cleverness of
how you determine this and the reason I
say that is because well it's a kind of
clever idea it's sort of second nature
today because we've sort of had such a
long time of thinking about problems in
this way but if you think about it and
we if we want to decide whether this or
this would be a better choice if I'm
here do I move here or do I move here
well all we really have to do is say
what is the the error at this pixel
center what's the what's the distance
from the actual line right how far away
would I be from the line here okay
versus how far away from the line would
I be here right like which one of these
more closely approximates of the line
and as you can kind of see even just
from this drawing since this is this is
obviously the better move this is a
closer point to the line than this is
and so what these routines essentially
do is they say let me compute an error
term which tells me which movement would
have actually been better okay now in a
modern context the way that we would
probably want to do this right is
because we might want this to be
completely paralyzed and not have any
dependencies on previous iterations of
the loop or who knows what else you can
imagine us computing this whole thing
from whole cloth every time so we might
say oh we have the equation of the line
we know what this point is so let's just
do that entire thing right and we can do
that right so if this is a prospective
point right this is like one point we
might be considering let's see what what
I might call
what do I want to call that let's call
that I don't know let's call this a and
B so I have two choices right I have my
a choice and my B choice alright so what
I know here is I essentially know that
I've got this this you know I've got
this this line and I have to figure out
some way of computing this this sort of
separation right I want to know what
this thing is and similarly I want to
know what this thing is well you know
like i said modern days we could do this
pre simply in fact just looking at the
diagram this is not something I've ever
actually thought about before I think
the last time I implemented in present
hams line drawing routine I was like
reading a present hams thing and just
did what it said to do it was like oh
yeah that makes sense but just looking
at the diagram I can tell you right now
we could solve this ourselves right we
don't eat you know put setting aside the
more clever way that the resident hand
stuff works just looking at this by
itself I can sort of see well okay if i
took p 1 minus p 0 right then if they're
on top of each other then i only have
one pixel to fill and I don't need to
draw a line anyway but if they aren't
then what that's going to give me is
that's going to give me some you know
some line vector here right that's going
to give me a V that's basically the
vector that goes from p0 to p1 okay and
if i were to normalize that remember
we've talked about all of this on hammer
hero we know how to normalize right we
divide a vector by its length we
normalize it right so if i were to get
some kind of a normalized vector here by
saying ok take p and divide it by its
length right I would have a vector of
unit length that points along the line
and now if I want to know which of these
two is closer to the line right well I
don't know if you guys remember again
I'm hoping everyone just has like all of
that handmade here and it's in their
brain right now how do we figure out
this distance right how do I figure out
that distance quickly if I have an A or
a B well remember this guy right here
right triangle right that's a right
angle right there that's perpendicular
that distance right so if I'm looking at
this and I've got this guy out here I've
got this guy here how would I take and
find this distance well remember our
friend the dot product remember this
remember all this stuff we talked about
this guy so the inner product or dot
product which we spent a bunch of time
talking about in handmade heroic is very
very valuable extremely important
function the dot product if this is a
unit vector which we know we have we
have a unit vector that points along
there right then we know that if we dot
the vector to a right if we dot the
vector from p0 to a which is just a
minus p0 if we were to dot that with v1
what would we get right what we would
get from that well we would get whatever
the length of a is right and we would
get that x cosine theta right so this
this right here this cosine theta term
would be would be this right I'm not my
brains a little addled right now for
some reason let me try saying that one
more time
because we are multiplying by the cosine
of theta right and because this is the
hypotenuse right this is this is the
length of a right here if we want to
know this this part we are getting it
for free because we're getting the
length of a time's the cosine of theta
which is the proportionality to this so
this term is literally this length we
are getting the length of that of that
side right because again sine theta
times the hypotenuse is this side right
and cosine theta times the hypothenuse
hypotenuse is this side right just basic
trig and we're getting that from the dot
product already so literally just the
dot product alone tells us this so
without any actual state at all we can
literally just take our dot product a
minus p0 TV one and we can just compare
this we can say if that is less than B
minus p0 TV one right whichever one of
these is less is the one that's closer
to the line and we should pick it make
sense hopefully that makes some sense so
what I'm basically saying is hey just
stop product this this vector here right
dot product this vector with the unit
vector dot product this vector with the
unit vector and we get these two lengths
we compare the two and whichever one was
the shorter that's where we go and then
we repeat the algorithm from there right
and whichever one you know just keep
going whichever one is closer whichever
one's closer whichever one's closer
that's it and that is basically a
present man's line drawing routine
that's exactly what that is now this is
not the actual construction they use if
I remember correctly because again
saying something like normalizing the
vector is not something you ever would
have wanted to do and the reason for
that is because it requires floating
point math right so while we actually in
fact what I just wrote down might be
better
than the present an algorithm for today
for all I know because it involves
floating-point math and 20-point math is
faster and this requires no state so who
knows I don't know but if you put on
your hat of i only have integer
operations there is no floating point so
i need something cleverer here than that
i need something that's not going to
just do the mathematical construction i
got to start thinking in terms of
integers right then you get more what
brezin ham actually did if that makes
sense which to be completely honest I
don't even remember four lines what it
actually is I remember four circles what
it is because it's just an implicit line
evaluate it's an implicit function
evaluation I'm trying to remember if
that's what it is for lines as well so
let me think about that so if it was
going to be an implicit evaluation for a
line then you're going to get something
like uh it would have to be sort of a
cross product would it hmm what would be
the I don't actually know I really
couldn't tell you I guess so so maybe
yeah to be honest I really don't
remember I'll show you the one for
circles and then we'll look up the one
for lions cuz I don't remember how they
did it it's how did they do it this is
the way my brain just did it and I feel
like that's me because I'm a
floating-point math guy and so sometimes
I have a hard time looking at something
when I like when I know how I would
solve it and then I'm like no wait but
that's not the solution they used I
don't remember i'll show you the circle
one that i do remember and then we can
look up the line one it's very simple
it's just like how did they do it I just
don't remember I think it's basically
like they precompute the
they pre compute the slope and see which
one is closer because ok I will simply
say that the way they do it has
something to do with the fact that you
record an error term that you keep
throughout the loop so you don't
evaluate the pixels in a vacuum every
time you step in a direction you
accumulate the error term if I remember
correctly and so that avoids the
floating-point math pneus of it because
they just have an accumulator so they
don't have to worry about that part if I
remember correctly yeah I'm pretty sure
so let me just go ahead and show you the
circle one first because that's when I
actually do remember and then we'll come
back to the line one in a second
hopefully everyone understands this like
I said it's pretty straightforward if
you remember the dot product you can
pretty quickly come up with a very easy
way of determining which one would be
closer and stepping to that one but that
is just not how brezin have did it
because even though this is incredibly
simple calculation I it wouldn't have
been simple for them at the time this
would have been very expensive at the
time all right so superior I draw a
circle right same constraints apply and
maybe when I'm doing this because I
happen to remember how this is all
remember enough about the line that I
can go back and remember how they did
their line one but I don't know probably
not all right so let's say I've got a
center and I've got a radius well again
just like the line case it's trivial for
me to figure out a point that would
start things out right if this is the
center and this were the radius right so
like I centers here wow that's really
bad I centers here and my radius is like
one two three or whatever right then I
know that this is a pixel that's on the
circle so I know I know that that's not
hard so now that I've already told you
how bressingham style things work you
know what we're going to do and that is
we're going to turn this drawing problem
into just a decision problem of from any
pixel which direction do i go right and
so from here I've got two choices i
could go cure or I could go here and the
question is which one do i pick okay
so this one's pretty straightforward
because the circle already has a
parameterization that you know is
perfect for what we're going to do which
makes me think again like if I just go
back and look at the line when I can
probably just come up with the way the
parameterization of the line works
probably you would just use y equals
that my sweet you know what that's
probably what they did now that i think
about it probably what they did is they
probably used y equals MX plus B and you
had a special case the drawing of a
vertical line which I in my head was
avoiding using y x equals that's because
I'm like well then you could draw over
line I bet they couldn't see they're
here to there we'll go back there in one
moment and we'll see okay so you know
one point that's not a circle so you
know you can start there so the question
is which direction do you go you go to a
or do you go to be well we know the
equation for a circle the equation for
the circle is x squared plus y squared
minus R squared equals 0 right very very
straightforward nothing weird about this
at all now that assumes that the circle
is centered around the origin which we
could trivially do but you know if we
wanted to make a fancy right we can just
say X minus Center X right I should
probably do p x minus center x squared
plus py- sentir y squared minus R
squared equals 0 okay very very simple
so now we have the center we can say
where the center is we can say what the
radius is there's our circle equation
well what we know is this is actually an
implicit why why drawing tablet I got a
disabled that there's like it's got this
little weird thing I can like it's like
a scratches like a record scratch pad
protector which are way too real right
it's like I don't want that I don't want
to be at the club right this is not
dance time this is not a rave I did not
drop X we need to just like not have
that happen anyway point being this
equation is the implicit equation for a
circle and we talked about implicit
equations right oops implicit equations
versus explicit equations earlier in
handmade hero so again you might have
put on your rewind cap but an X listen
equation is an equation like our classic
interpolation one or whatever it's it's
one of the form you know p equals one
minus T p0 plus tp1 remember I've said
this many many times I said it was my
desert island equation even if I could
only have one equation i take this one
right this is an example of explicit
equation i say a tea that I want to put
in right I say I've got to put in a tea
and then I get out a particular point on
a line okay it's literally like an
equation that I put in a value between 0
and 1 and I get out points on my line
line segment if I put on points above
one I go off the law I continue the line
pass the end of the line segment if I
put in negative 1 right that's the
example of an explicit equation for a
line similarly would be in the case of a
circle right if I wanted to say that
i've got a P of T for my circle and
probably we might say theta because
right we'd probably / impress as an
angle but you could imagine it being a
tea as well I put in a tea what's the
equation for a circle well I know what
that is to write that equation is just
going to be you know my radius times
cosine T right if I want t to go between
zero and one it would be it would be a 2
pi t right right but i can i can write
an explicit equation for a circle as
well and this is one where i put in a
value between 0 and 1 let's say and by
the way explicit has nothing do is zero
and one that's just how we tend to do
things in math obviously so it could be
anything we could have said theta and
had it range from 0 to 2pi whatever
doesn't matter point being I can draw a
circle by saying I'm going to give you a
series of T values and you're going to
give me back points on a circle right
this is explicit but this is not
explicit there is no single parameter
that I put in and I get out points on
the circle in fact from this equation I
have no idea where the circle even is
okay it's implicit the circle is and the
way that I find it is by testing points
and this equation tells me how far from
the circle they are when it equals
as the equation demands the point is on
the circle when it is greater than zero
or less than zero it is on or I'm sorry
is off the circle in one or two
directions either inside it or outside
it right and hopefully what you can see
is that an implicit parameterization of
a circle is very helpful for doing
something like a president if I have two
candidate points and I want to know
which one to pick well I don't have a
problem anymore I just use the implicit
equation for the circle I evaluate each
point and whichever one comes back with
a lower absolute value is closer to the
circle this is effectively a distance
function that tells me how far I am from
the circle very very handy right and so
that is all we would have to do now you
may ask you already have a function an
explicit function that tells you points
in the circle why do you care about this
why would you ever have done this well
think about it there's a number of
problems with this explicit version if
I'm trying to draw pixels right first of
all I don't know how far in T to advance
to get to the next pixel if I implement
in chromatic salai go way around the
circle and so I have no idea how much to
step by to feel individual pixels so if
my goal is to fill a bunch of pixels
this doesn't help me hardly at all this
only helps me if I knew I wanted to draw
a circle with a certain number of
segments like if I was creating lines
around the circle like maybe drawing it
by passing it to a graphics card to draw
as line segments or something like this
well yeah then i could say i want to
draw it with three two segments so I
step T by 1 30 second every time and
those are my points around the circle
works great right good for you
congratulations explicit function does
not help me in this choice situation at
all because I want to go exactly 1 pixel
well I know how far one pixel is I just
don't know which one of those pixels is
on the circle but now I do implicit
function that's all I need to do so
literally I will plug in as the p I will
do you know ax minus CX squared plus
coops plus a plus a y minus C why
squared minus R squared and I will just
say if the absolute value because i want
the total distance right i don't care if
it's inside or outside the circle
preferentially whichever one of these
two guys is going to be less that's the
one I pick and I can just keep doing
that to like it all the way around my
circle right pretty easy with that in
mind I'd also point out there's actually
a ton of other things you do here so if
you're actually doing brezin hands on a
circle some other things you do is you
say well hey guess what a circle is
symmetric so every time you plot x comma
y also plot y comma X right to think
about it so r example i'm going to plot
this I always plot that right and if I'm
going to plot this I always flop that
but hey guess what anytime you plot x
comma y you also plot negative x comma y
right because I'm going to plot this I
definitely plot that similarly anytime
i'm going to plat x comma y i also plot
x comma negative y right so you keep
doing all these you do you can do all
the different symmetries and you can
draw your circle extremely quickly by
taking advantage of the fact that it's
literally n way symmetric right so all
you actually have to do is just draw
these three pixels and then you do like
x y y x- y x- x y blah blah blah right
so you draw all eight quadrants at once
by just starting here going to there and
that's it you don't as soon as you cross
into the next quadrant you're done
that's neither here nor there and
probably not anything anyone needs to
know any more about point being when you
actually did present ham circle drawing
in the old days since computing the new
points with the expensive part and
there's no such thing as like cash
locality for the frame buffer any of
these other things what you always did
is you computed the point and you drew
all 8 quad that's at the same time so
you only had to compute 18 of the points
obviously a big time saver
congratulations yet bv geograph
it's all fun all right so let's go back
here and let's assume that what they did
was use y equals MX plus B something I
would never use today because obviously
it can't handle vertical lines but what
you gonna do okay the bonus of y equals
MX plus B obviously is that it is an
implicit equation for the line if we
want to be right because we can
basically transform this equation that
into one that looks exactly like our
circle equation right what we can do is
say the equation for our line is you
know MX plus B minus y equals zero right
we just take this and we move it over
the other side looks exactly like a
circle equation right exactly like when
in fact let me write it even closer to
the circle equation MX minus y plus B
equals zero make sense so if we just do
that well now we can evaluate those
points on the line pretty trivially
right all we do is exactly what we did
for the circle we plug in x and y for
you know our test pixel a we plug in the
x and y for Texas will be and we see
which one of them is closer to zero
that's it right same exact thing no
problem I'm assuming that's what brezin
ham did don't remember I'm assuming
that's what he did and i'm assuming
furthermore that what they did is they
basically special case lyon such that
for example one thing you could do is
this equation for a line can exchange x
and y right I couldn't say say that the
I could instead say that the equation
for my line was I was not y equals MX
plus B but something else entirely right
which should not have that that problem
of the M on the X I could say instead
well in fact I could say something like
I have MX minus y plus B equals 0 or X
minus my plus B equals 0 right and all
I'd have to do is just flip which one
you know which
which one I was using I could even
include another multiplier in there if I
wanted to so I could basically write my
line drawing routine twice which again
was very common back then 14 lines that
are vertical ish and ones for ones that
are horizontal ish pick which one of
them they were based on the initial
points that i got and then just use
whichever equation this would be
slope-intercept form for the y axis this
would be for the slope-intercept form
for the x axis right or I should say
about the other way around this is slope
intercept form where B is wearing a sex
the y-axis this is slope intercept form
where it intersects the x-axis right
because every line has to intersect one
or the other you can't have a line which
intersects neither the xnor the y-axis
right it's not a line in that case so
that's probably exactly what present ham
did I'm guessing let's let's see let's
see if I'm right
let's find out okay Hey look look
familiar yeah that's exactly what they
did so they just yep they just do y
equals MX plus B you can see this right
here there's your why there's your be
right and they just chose to make the
y-axis coincide with the the first point
makes perfect sense right and then
here's that slope change in Y over
change in X right yep there you go so I
guess it didn't fall completely out of
my brain up in fact there's the actual
line equation right there uh so yeah now
I don't know if this gets into it and
we're out of time so I'm not going to
get into it but I will simply point out
some additional things about this that I
remember hopefully you know what I
should probably check the chat do you
guys uh did you guys did that make sense
to the people who actually were asking
about brezin ham wanted to know how it
worked did that all make sense like is
that did that get you where you need to
be in a headspace so that you can go
read about it on your own or implement
it on your own
elvin I remember reading that brezin ham
works for the first octant and they had
two cases to handle slope greater than
equal to 1 and slope less than one will
this DX equals sine X 1 minus X ur
address both of these concerns um so the
way that I said to do it would work in
all orientations this this not really
brezin hams thing that I constructed
this guy where you do the dot products I
think that one will just work always
because that's totally generic and does
that's a implicit function for the
distance from a line that does not
actually involve any directionality in
fact you could you could even get rid of
if you didn't care about the performance
at all or weren't thinking about that so
much this sign part you wouldn't even
have to care about that sign part what
you could actually do instead is test
all four points every time through the
loop right if you wanted to I mean yeah
I it doesn't but you know I think you
would rather do like what i said is do
the sign here and yes that addresses all
them because that it doesn't matter what
direction the line is going once you got
those signs in there you're done you're
good to go but this is not like i said
this is not traditional present hams
and no we don't ever drew line drawing
on handmade here really I mean if we may
be weak I don't know we we don't even
ask the GPU to draw it but Alvin I'm
still not a hundred sure president how
President figured out if horizontal is
better you mentioned they use the line
equation how does that help them in
knowing if horizontals better because
it's the it's it's just you test both
points right so let's say I've got I'm
here right this is P and this is a and
this is B so here's my pixel grid right
so if I want to know which of these is
better a or b I just need an equation
that gives me back a distance from a
line and y equals MX plus B is exactly
that equation right so 0 equals MX minus
y plus B okay the further away you are
from the line the higher the actual
evaluation of this will be because if
you're 0 you're on the line and anything
higher or lower than 0 the absolute
value of that is what tells you so all I
need to do is plug both a and B into
here and compare the results so what I
would say is what's the absolute value
right of ma X minus a y plus B right or
I should say yeah plus B if that is less
than m bx minus B Y and I guess beith
having 2 b's is not good so let's call
this let's not call this B let's call
this a and M D for some reason so there
we go so that's magical pointy so let's
say m DX minus dy plus B right so this
is what tells you which is better and it
has nothing to do with telling you
horizontal or vertical is better it's
just a or b and i happen to call those
horizontal cuz the horizontal movement
and vertical because the vertical
movement but you could have picked any
two points in the world and this will
still tell you which one is a better
choice we're just
opening to use it to figure out which
direction to move and we know we only
have two places we can go you know
vertical or horizontal so you plug it
into both and that equation for the line
tells you which one is better and so if
it's less than right then I want this
one if it turned out to be greater than
I would want this one I would want to go
to be instead that make sense
elvin there were multiple extensions
observations done present him like
drawing only half the line and mirroring
it and run slicing by a brash and
symmetric double step by whoo any
thoughts on those yeah those were the
things that I was about to say when I
turned to the chat and said you have any
questions that I was like before I go
any further I was going to mention that
one of the things that turns out to
happen really quickly that you notice
when you draw a line is that it always
does basically the same stuff as it
moves so typically if you know if you
have something where you're drawing the
line what people noticed is like oh you
know no matter what the line is it
always ends up doing something like
going to then going three then going to
then going three or whatever right so
why don't we just pre-compute whatever
that is and then replicate that pattern
right and similarly like you said there
are other things where they were sort of
figuring out like oh we could you know
we could draw from the back in the front
at the same time or blah blah blah so
there's plenty of our stuff there's also
anti-alias present hams which are ones
that tell you to fill more pixels than
just these and to give them darker or
lighter weights depending on their
distance so there's lots of surroundings
of brezin hands but they're all really
not that interesting they're not super
interesting the more interesting part is
just the implicit function part to me
that's the part that's more relevant
today because remember implicit
functions is how we filled our triangles
so that part is always true it's a day
if you were going to draw a line you'd
still use an implicit function
formalization but you wouldn't care
about all these other things like like
the doublet slicing or the sort of those
optimizations right pseudonym 73 little
known fact brezin hams method predates
frame buffers by about five years it was
actually designed for a drum plotter
that's insane but again like I said when
you think about going that far back it
makes sense why they did things these
way because even when I was in high
school this was the fastest way to draw
a line right so like all the way from
probably the 80s back
you you didn't think about things in the
same way that you think about them now
when you're trying to draw stuff so
that's just the way it is
oh and for people who said like they
feel like it should be deciding between
move right and move diagonally right and
down instead of either left or down as I
presented it depends on what kind of
line you're trying to draw so there's
two ways you can do it right and one way
is that you don't want to overfill so
you're only going to do like a line that
looks like this let's say and you don't
want to fill in this and if that's the
case then yet you need to do whether you
move what you well my saves you always
move in the primary direction and then
you're just deciding whether you want to
move down but if you do want to fill
this one in then you do what I was
saying so it depends on which way you
want to fill and there are brezin hams
for both right because he because it
again the concept doesn't change the
concept of deciding which one to go to
doesn't matter it's just whether or not
you want to whether you want to include
those or exclude them that makes sense
elvin can that method be used to draw
wireframe triangles or is there a faster
way to draw wireframe triangles like
flat bottom flat top triggs again when
you say faster what do you mean you know
faster in 1985 no like President ham
line drawing with optimizations with you
know like operations like a brush
straight or whatever nothing was faster
than that nowadays yeah of course you're
never no one would ever draw them this
way I don't think I mean maybe I'm wrong
about that but you'd want to do simdi
evaluation of a bunch of pixels at the
same time so you would be doing more of
an implicit rasterization which again is
related to present hands but it's not
the same expansion pack is this ever
used for uniform grid pathfinding uh I
don't know probably not I mean because
it's a little bit limited it doesn't
really find a path it just goes straight
you know
nixie for tomorrow given an entity with
a position and a current velocity and
maximum acceleration and a target
position how do you determine the
correct acceleration each frame so that
you stop on the target point that's
probably pretty involved so basically
that's like I mean you gotta basically
you're basically solving a quadratic
right and I don't know that the
direction I think I don't think there's
that much I don't know that there's
really any directionality to it because
that they're separable right so I think
you'd solve it in x and y the same so do
you mean do you mean to say that your
acceleration is constrained in some way
because otherwise it's it's a 1d problem
still right nixie would that be am I am
I correct in in interpreting the problem
you're saving to say that it is
separable and therefore the 1d solution
applies to to all dimensions or are you
asking a different question
let's see pseudonym this is how I used
to derive brezin hams algorithm and
there's a paste bid what's on the
pastebin
floating point later we will assume that
X simplicity oh that's kind of neat well
hopefully people will click on that
should click on you should click on
pseudonym 73 to paste bin let's see
Elvin was the cast from float to int
really expensive at the time versus
nowadays Elvin you're asking the wrong
question there was no floating point at
all the processor didn't do it it had
nothing to do with the cast there was
literally no floating point operations
very few processors had floating-point
units in them
let's see nixie acceleration is
constrained to a maximum amount uh but
again it doesn't matter right like that
eat does that make sense like it's still
separable whether it's constrained to a
maximum oh you're talking about it's
constrained to a maximum out in a
combined not like I said an x and y oh I
see that's pretty tricky that sounds
tricky to me wouldn't you agree look I
feel like that's not something I'm going
to drive on stream because I got to
think about it
long billion was this also used for
bezier curves uh hmm I don't think so
because busy acres don't have an
implicit parameterization I don't think
I mean that's not true I should probably
say it'd be very complicated implicit
parameterization
so I think they usually tried to do
stuff like figure like calculate how
much would move them to the next pixel
as a step in T and actually did that I
think but I don't know Kubica off topic
but still on the topic of math during
these RSI streams you think you could go
over the math for replacing see math
specifically the trig functions I'd
probably rather do that when we actually
replace them captain craft just opens
you'll have this stuff implanted already
what stuff it has line drawing elleven
if you were to implement a line during
function in handmade hear what algorithm
would you go for I mean I'd probably do
something that tried to fill four pixels
at a time and evaluated them all filled
them all at that time would be my guess
so it would just be an implicit it would
just be an implicit test probably it
would probably be very much like the one
I described where you did the dot
product and that if the dot product is
less than 1 or whatever then you fill it
alright think it is time to wrap things
up it is time
yeah hands feel good today hope that
keeps up let's go ahead and close things
down here all right everybody thanks for
joining me for another episode of
handmade hero chat addition I have been
uploading these to youtube so you can't
actually get them now if you want to
view the chats the the ones from last
week in the ones for this week will be
up there they're just under chat instead
of under day so if you want to check
those out there in the video archive as
for everything else if you want to hang
out for another chat tomorrow you could
go ahead and look at the tweet bot
because the tweet pot tells you and it
will say what schedule is but I believe
we're back here in fact you know what I
don't even know is schedule is I think
it's 530 yeah we'll be back here at
five-thirty tomorrow 530 PSD so if you
would like to come back for more
chatting I'd love to see it until then
everyone take it easy do some
programming see you on the internets hi
everybody