hello everyone and welcome to handmade
heroes show recode a complete game live
on stream we have some more lighting
work to do today yesterday we finished
changing it so that you sent light boxes
directly down to the lighting system and
it blew them out into surfaces for
lighting and that appears to be working
properly now so if we run the game we
are getting the standard lighting the
slow lighting running now with light
boxes community communicated directly to
the lighting system what we want to do
today is to now change it so that when
we do our lighting computations rather
than doing our letting computations on
services at all we're going to do our
lighting computation on actual boxes so
as we go right at the moment what's
happening is these boxes are getting
computed down all right getting
transmitted down to the lighting system
as boxes but then they still get broken
out into flat polygons for the lighting
system and what I want to do now is
change it so that instead of doing that
they actually get changed over to being
hit tested against as actual boxes never
getting blown out into surfaces at all
this is mostly a bookkeeping change but
there is one algorithmic change we have
to make and that algorithmic change is
we need to do our ray cast checking
against an actual right you know an
actual axis aligned bounding box which
is to say that we have a more
complicated task to do than we would
have if all we were doing was test
against a single polygon now what we can
do at first is change the raycast to
just be 6 ray casts one against each of
the faces but we can quickly make that
faster by only using faces that are back
face I was that our front facing to the
Ray and then we can probably do even
better than that by may be doing
intersection testing that's directly
against the box instead of against the
pieces of the box and so on so we have a
lot of options here that we can pursue
and that's basically what we want to
start doing now
in an attempt to get this down to
something nice and concise and that we
can start using to do multi-resolution
work which is sort of the the end goal
of switching to the box in the first
place although in general even if we
weren't switching to multi-resolution it
would still be a much better idea to do
raycasting against the boxes because the
raycasting itself would just be faster
so this change is good no matter what we
were doing if you know that you're not
taking advantage of the ability to
specify polygons by actually using lots
of things that aren't directly related
to a box then you know whatever but
since we are only ever really concerned
with boxes here at that point it really
makes no sense whatsoever not to just
have the letting system work on them
directly because it will always be able
to get a speed improvement based on that
so what I want to do now is I guess just
do the literal translation of this so
here in the lighting test function right
here is where we blow out the box
services and all I really need to do
here is just move this into this this
part right here that goes over the box
services well I really need to do is
move that over into the actual ray
casting test so if you take a look at
the Ray casting test the ray cast test
goes over these source indices here and
so what I want to do is right inside
where we decide that you know this is
one of the boxes that we're going to
test what I want to do is just move this
this thing right here that does the
actual ray cast I just want to move the
part that generates the box services
right above that and what I can do is
like literally take this lighting
surface information here and instead of
having the lighting surface be something
that's actually stored I can just make a
temporary lighting surface like so and
create that lighting surface on-demand
now obviously this is pretty slow right
we're doing a ton of work here for no
real reason because a lot of this
information we don't actually need
and you know there's all sorts of
reasons why we don't really want to do
it like this in the end but again when
you're making code changes like this
that involve a lot of bookkeeping and a
lot of information
it usually benefits you to make them
slowly one step at a time to reduce your
debugging especially in things like
lighting where the results can be
complicated to interpret it's a lot
easier to do slow changes and make sure
that they're working okay rather than
make some giant changes and then I spend
a ton of time trying to debug why you're
getting a black screen and so on okay so
this is what we effectively want to do
now and we'll take a look at that in a
second but what we want to do first is
get rid of the code that was actually
doing any of the the blowing out here so
this stuff can all basically go away
right so we don't really need any of
this what we're going to do instead is
change the solution to have the box
count specified in it directly and
similarly it will also will have the
boxes specified in it directly so then
when we go back to the lighting solution
oops that's in rolled mode still not a
great place for it but yeah we'll fix
that someday these surfaces here that
used to be here these are going to go
away and these are just going to be
replaced with light box
you know box count go so we're no longer
gonna be having our own services in here
we're never really going to have that
instead what we're gonna have is just
the light boxes in here that can be
directly accessed and the this can just
be a pointer we're not storing them that
you can just point to the one that we
were getting before so now when we come
back through here right we're gonna be
able to go okay let's just go through
the boxes themselves and we'll do each
of these surfaces and that'll be fine
we'll have to fix some bugs in there but
otherwise it should be good and also
this right comes from the solution now
all right so the source index think here
was only really getting used as well for
the you know the result index sort of
stuff so what we want to do here is this
this piece of information that flows out
is now gonna have to be a little bit
more complicated right because once we
do our raycast we're going to need to
give some of this in the the relevant
part of this information we're going to
need to give to the routine that
actually has to process this
intersection on the way out so if we
take a look at what happens here you can
see we have like these ray indices we're
looping over here we're doing the
sampling and whatnot and what happens is
once we get that closest point index
right we've got this the hit surface
which is which is this the piece of
information that I'm talking about that
gets returned from the Ray which surface
got hit that hit surface needs to be
used in a couple different places right
so we need some way of taking care of
the hit surface in a way that doesn't
require returning an index to a surface
that we don't have now in order to do
that I'm gonna have to think through
what we actually use so in accumulate
sample you can see that the lighting
surface here is you know it's getting
past when we look at the reason that
it's getting past the only thing that's
it actually needs is the surface normal
for the angular fall-off okay
so that surface normal is actually also
present in the point itself right points
themselves have their surface normals
included in them and so we could just
use that directly so when we actually
come through here and we're passing the
hit surface we don't really have to do
that what we could do instead is just
take whatever the hit point was and pass
its normal right this part here could be
could be that and if we take a look
if we take a look at what's happening
here and then give us a little more room
were kind of getting so closest point
index is the actual thing that we would
need to get that piece of information
out so if we wanted to say solution
points closest point index and that
would give us that normal that we
actually need so it turns out for
acumulate sample we really don't need
the surface so that's a good thing so
the only place we're really using the
hit surface oops the only place that
we're really using the hit surface which
is the thing we would need that index
for is this part right here where we
loop over the lights themselves so what
we could do instead is just have it so
that this index that comes back could
just be array it could it could be
something that just tells us what the
point count is right so just be whatever
the first point index is we start with
that assuming that it's within range
then when we come through here we're
gonna loop over rate point count ramp
rate first point index and that would be
it
that would be all we'd have to do so in
order to make this routine continue
working the way it was working again not
necessarily the most efficient way to do
things yet we're gonna have to start
pairing this down as we try to make it
more and more efficient certainly but we
can start to see how this routine could
still communicate the same information
back that was actually necessary so what
we would have here is a first point
index and a point count like so and when
we've got those pieces of information
flowing back what we would need to do is
just set them here so in the result
first point index and the results point
count what we need to specify is these
two pieces of information here there's
that light index and there's that light
count so those those
the pieces of information that we would
actually need to pass back to do the
iteration on the outside that needs to
get done and similarly when we
initialize this instead of setting it to
the surface count we're just setting it
to the point count so now at the end
here remember we don't have services
anymore so anywhere that was referring
to service this has to be changed to box
there's two places where that has to
occur actually there's more than two so
there's here where we need to loop over
the boxes which now we will do and I
guess we can still use source index for
this so as we're going over the boxes we
need to do that but then the other thing
place we need to do it in the immediate
vicinity is when we're looping over the
emissions that that is we don't that's
not true
nevermind so there is really only one
other place that we have to loop over it
I guess and that's an output so here we
were going over the surfaces and we
don't want to go the services anymore we
need to go over the box count so this
right here is basically a box index oops
so the box index that comes out is also
going to have to again loop over each of
the phases of this thing I then loop
over the points of those faces again not
really a huge problem because we have
the ability to generate those on demand
so we can just do that and be done with
it right this right here is the code
that will do that and we only really
need a very little bit of that code
anyway so in here when we do this and
get the box surface the only things we
were using it for is the x-axis and
y-axis so this actually doesn't really
have to happen where we translate the
thing out all we really need is these
two pieces of information here so that
we can go okay here's the light index
right and furthermore we don't even need
to do this addition because we can just
read out what that actual maximum value
was to begin with and just skip the
subtraction which gives us exactly what
we would have wanted then inside the
this
some call we go get the x-axis y-axis
that can be read directly out of the box
surface itself
so again just we end up in a situation
where most of the work we were doing
could collapse down pretty easily into
something that just operates directly on
generated services rather than storage
services and there's no real issue here
oops so let's go ahead and clean it up
where is that point count yeah all right
uh so this is actually boxes not light
boxes this is not source it is surface
Oh actually I I disagree is source go
ahead and change that and all of these
that are doing source arrow need to be
source dot there we go
and it's over zealous there actually I
suppose why not
so the box surface index
lighting service does not have member
operator you're correct
doesn't and so did we actually even use
that information that hidden X no no no
so this is points this is not even we're
not even getting that information so we
don't even care about that anymore no
object what is the question point
commands like point count so is this a
you 32 in here I guess and that is not
something we actually want to print
light boxes are just boxes all right so
now effectively we've changed the code
over to doing well to doing exactly what
it's doing so what we're doing now is
we're going through and we're blowing
these things out just when we need them
as you can see not particularly fast so
we're gonna have to go through and now
make this a little bit more sane with
how it's working
I can also probably do a little bit of
work to sort of make sure we're to make
sure we know where our timings are being
spent I guess is what I would say so you
can see we're still compiling in Oh too
so we would expect to have reasonable
optimizations here but there's a bunch
of stuff that's going pretty slowly and
the question is well why and so we're
not we don't necessarily know exactly
but one would assume that the blowing
out
doing this every time there's just too
much actual work in generating these box
sources from the indices and that sort
of stuff one would act would just assume
that that is the majority of the problem
there but since we don't really know
that I'd like to go ahead and actually
time it to make sure that this routine
is where all of our time is being spent
B just to make sure I didn't
accidentally introduce something crazier
here where I you know made some mistake
that causes us to do like way more
iterations or something like this
because I want to make sure that the
thing that's taking the time is the
thing that I was expecting to take the
time and not something else right okay
so what I want to do here is just do a
time function so that it'll so I'm just
gonna put a time function in there and
so hopefully what'll happen now is every
time we go to do a raycast it'll get
counted in the profiler so if I need to
go in now and just verify what is
actually happening I can verify that all
the times we've spent in the raycast it
is so that's great and so what we really
just need to do is focus on making sure
that we can hit tests against these
boxes in some efficient fashion the
number of rays being cast here is not
unusually high 30,000 rays seems
reasonable for the number of iterations
and number of services and stuff we have
I'm not verifying it in any particular
way in my head or anything I'm just
saying that's not usually high if that
had come back is like a million or
something I would have suspected that I
made an accidental iteration change
somewhere else so our goal here is just
to drive down this functions doing all
the work and it was definitely running
faster before so the question is how do
we make it run back at that normal speed
right okay
so let's talk about how we are going to
how we can go about doing this a few
things we can do and so on so the very
first thing that we can do is we can we
can use half the surfaces right go ahead
and Milton here
it is day 422 right did I get that right
yes just wanna double-check sometimes
that I forget all right so for recasting
against boxes or in this case let's just
say a a B B's so axis aligned bounding
boxes what we want to think about first
is just the obvious fact that let's just
draw it in 2d because it's a little bit
simpler and doesn't really change the
principle that whatever direction the
Ray is coming from we know that that Ray
only is going to intersect front faces
right so if the Ray is pointing in this
direction it's never going to be tested
against things that are pointing in the
same direction as the Ray is going
because we only we don't allow ray
casting from inside of the cube right we
or the box we only allow ray casting
from outside the box and when we are
coming from outside the box we only want
to intersect faces that could bounce us
off right so the first thing we could do
is we can eliminate half of the faces
pretty much immediately so if we take a
look at how much time is being spent in
here inside the profiler you can see
that it's well it's pretty huge right I
don't even know we should probably some
commas in here 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 so it's
like a billion cycles right and hey
isn't that nice this is a 4 gigahertz
processor I think and a billion cycles
our amount of time is around a quarter
of a second so hey that works out just
about that works that just about correct
anyway so we're taking about a billion
cycles to do that here so we should
expect to see maybe that number drop not
in half but it should should be
something a fairly significant if we
were to just test that now that's not
going to get us even close to where we
want to be because we want to be if
anything faster than the old version and
that's not gonna get us even in the
ballpark so this is by no means
the majority of the change we want to
make but we should still be able to say
hey only test those those particular
boxes I guess this is too late to do it
there's the dot this test right here is
the test for that but what we want to be
able to do is we want to be able to do
that earlier right so here in the box
source call where we're getting this
this information out for the box surface
what we want to do is we want to test
before we ever generate all this
information and we can do that because
we know the sign of the REA Direction is
going to be the thing that gives us all
of the information we actually need
right because this is access aligned
whatever my Rea direction is what I know
is that the instant I would need to
start testing say the Y positive right
that's Y positive this is Y negative the
incident I would have to start testing
the Y positive plane is precisely when
my ray Direction has a negative Y right
so I don't really need to generate any
of the information I don't even need to
do this test because I know these are
boxes I know their access aligned and so
at that point I can just make the
assumption that the sign of the
components of the normal the Ray normal
are all I really need to figure out
whether I'm gonna test this box surface
or not right so what I can say ahead of
time is rather than doing the ray source
end test and of course I still need to
compute the inner product as you can see
here that the inner product is used for
a piece of information but I can pretty
much say okay this can become an
assertion that doesn't actually
predicating because I pretty much know
that it's always going to be true what I
can do instead is do an if statement
here that will test the sign of the
thing that I actually care about which
is to say the
this index which again is the box
surface index shifted down by one right
that's the axis index whatever the axis
index is like so and we know the
positive right so we know that we have
the axis index which is this and we have
the positive yes or no which is this we
know that our test for whether or not
this thing ever needs to enter this
routine is just going to be all right if
the box if the axis that I'm testing
right if the rain normal what I'm going
to be shooting so the the Ray direction
if the elements of that is greater than
zero that lets me know that I'm testing
the negative right if it's less than
zero that means I'm testing the positive
so I can do something that tells me
whether my normal is positive which is
this and I can do something that tells
me whether my Ray is positive right
which is this and I guess you know test
against positive it's really what this
is because this thing whether the rate
is negative right so if I want to test
against positive and this is positive
then I should do it otherwise I
shouldn't that makes sense so all I'm
doing is seeing whether or not the signs
of these things line up and I should be
able to after debugging it make sure
that that always is true
now this assertion should catch cases
where it's not so to get the code okay
like we go through and step through this
here we got to kind of get this yeah so
what we need to do is make it so this
actually does work correctly let's just
double-check what's going on here
because this could also just be a
threshold problem as well oh we've just
got the assertion backwards I was gonna
say that seems like a plenty of
Tolerance and really want here is that
there we go all right so what we want to
do here is make sure that we're always
up
it's slow morning let me say that again
we want to do here is make sure that the
inner product is sufficiently negative
so the tolerance is going to swap
directions if that makes sense
we want the racehorse normal we want to
assert that it is negative now this is
probably too much tolerance here I don't
know but I'm just guessing that it
should probably be something lower than
that we'll find out in a second but I'm
pretty sure that that is what what
should be happening of course I'm not
seeing anything so that's bad just in
case anyone was wondering what is going
on
okay oh I'm like why is it so slow
because I didn't change it back to I
didn't change back to retail there we go
so now we're only testing a third of the
phases and we're not doing all of the
work necessary to generate those phases
and so now we can see that that hey that
number did actually drop roughly in half
and that's exactly what we expected and
it's exactly what we got right so that's
pretty happy but like I was saying we're
not really even close yet to where we
need to be in terms of getting this to
be fast enough so that's great
you know we're happy campers we can
remove our assertion because now we're
only doing stuff that that we would
expect to be doing right and that's good
now what we want to do as well is start
to break out what we actually need out
of the box for us and what we don't need
right so what you can see here is we
need the width and the height right so
we need these values for sure we need
these values but we only actually need
them in this case right so we don't need
to actually pull these out unless we're
we're getting to this point
right this is the only time we actually
need this information so we can avoid
ever actually doing that sort of pull
out until here now the compiler was
probably smart enough to do that for us
but we don't really want to stress the
compiler any more than we have to on a
critical path like this we want to do as
much work as we can for it to give it
the simplest possible thing to optimize
just so it has the best chance of doing
a good job in this stuff here you can
see that we do a 2.0 times these and
then check against the width so rather
than doing that what we could easily do
here is just stop doing this redundant
work since we have the half-width right
so now we don't really need any of that
in there for the x-axis and y-axis
obviously these are there we go
obviously these are done directly here
so we don't we're not really doing
anything here other than just renaming
some variables but I'm just gonna make
it clear which ones we're doing here
like so transparency isn't necessary the
box source P oops and n are here
here and so now at least we can see a
little bit clearer what's going on all
right
so we just cleaned up some of the
business there shouldn't have really
sped up the code at all and hey it
didn't so again like those are all
things the compiler could have done for
us so it looks roughly the same so now
what we're gonna do is weld this routine
in here so the get box surface call
which does you know a tremendous amount
of work here I'm just gonna grab this
out directly and we're gonna start to
work with it go we're gonna start to
work with it in a more specific way
where's my red cast so I if we drop this
in here instead of calling function
let's start by just taking that exactly
as it is I'll call this box source
source
okay so we've got a couple things we
need to do this it needs to be blocks
min corner well I guess we need to like
pull these out first right all right so
now we should be able to run this
directly now and still get the same
lighting which we do and if you take a
look at what happened is just we didn't
do anything right I mean we did
literally nothing that doubled the speed
of the function right so again now we're
starting it down we're about to xoa
again from where we were before which is
weird right but all we did was drop it
in there and now the compiler can see it
better or some other nonsense who knows
we suddenly get much faster right so
okay that's good news
let's go ahead and push this a little
further though so if you take a look at
what's happening here there's some stuff
right off the bat that we can do let's
let's first of all before I go I guess
any further let's just let's just see
about whether all the things that we're
using are actually necessary and whether
or not we could be doing something
smarter here because obviously there's
there's there's possibilities for
improvement certainly tons of
possibilities for improvements but let's
take take some of the simpler ones so
for starters let me just rename these
variables so that we're not accessing
off of a box source for any particular
reason
right and
there we go all right so now we're not
like putting them into a structure and
taking them out now again shouldn't
change anything Kapow should be smart
enough to have done that and it did but
again remember putting that function in
there in line should have been something
the compiler was smart enough to do and
didn't so you can't always assume that
the compiler is gonna do something
because compilers are very complicated
and the optimization is a difficult
problem especially for a language like C
so it's important to you know actually
make each individual change carefully
and test to make sure that you can't get
that you don't get speed ups when you
change things because a lot of times may
be something that you're not thinking of
is preventing the compiler from doing an
optimization that it should be able to
do or that you think it might be able to
do so you don't really want to make
those assumptions anyway so let's now
start making some structural changes to
this if you look at what I'm doing here
I'm looping over the box services and
then I'm seeing whether or not I'm gonna
test against them by seeing whether
they're equivalent whether the direction
is equivalent the question is why bother
right why not just loop over the three
axes directly like so and if I have the
ability to generate any of the services
I want which I did why not just loop
over the three axes and say whichever
what which did you want me to do right
you want me to test against this one
great that's the one I'm going to test
against forget the if statement just I
know I'm only going to test one of the
faces in each for each axis I'm going to
test one let's just pull out which one
it is
it's going to be whichever one whichever
one is positive there right so we can
get rid of some of the business that's
happening there in a pretty
straightforward way and the only thing
we have to do now is actually be able to
reconstruct this box service index so
that I can pull the light indices out as
necessary right
so that's not even true because we
already have it right here so even
that's not you know that is true
so the box service index I have to pull
out which one of these we're talking
about so in order to create the Box
surface in next year I just need to be
able to take whatever my access index
was rank and add whether I was positive
that's all I need to do so really I
could put that up here because that's
just something that we just know as soon
as we compute whether or not it's
positive we know what the box service
indices as well right so again running
it and what we can see now is we're
basically we're really getting down to
the same speed that we were before hand
in fact I think now we might even be a
little bit faster than we were
originally oh but of course we're not
actually working well that could be why
um yeah it turns out if you don't
actually work you you get faster uh so
let's debug that for a second um so I I
need to figure out whether or not I'm
trying to test against the positive
surface and so what or the negative
surface so what I'm doing here is I'm
tech checking which direction the Ray
goes for this particular axis index I
feel like that should have been correct
trying to take a look at now why that
wasn't correct
[Music]
let me just back this up a bit here
let me just make sure that that was the
change yeah so let's just take that a
little bit slower here because obviously
I was just going a little bit too fast
parently um so what we want to do now is
let's loop over the axes and generate
the box index that we would expect so if
we take a look at what's going on here
we grab the axis index from the box
service index shifted down by one and
let me grab the positive this the
positive based on the and advanced oh
the question is well we know that we
want the positive and the test against
positive to be the same so we're only
going to enter this loop when they're
equivalent right so what I should be
able to do here is say oh well okay
that's pretty straightforward all I
should have to do is create the box
surface index in the opposite way right
I should be able to say take the axis
index shift it up by one and then or in
you know the positive value right that's
the thing that tells me whether thing is
positive along this axis I should be
able to just or in that value you know I
can even be 100% explicit here if the ax
index is greater than zero then it
should be one otherwise it should be
zero right then the box service index is
just whatever the Exynos was shifted up
by one orden with the positive value and
off we go right so I should be able to
to make that work
let's start with that
there we go
and so now we should be able to flatten
this out like I had it so I'm not sure
what I accessed a messed up this part
down here or something I'm not exactly
sure what I did there wrong I made it
maybe messed up the calculation of box
surface index not really sure so anyway
we can just come through here now let me
let me double check this let me see if
what happens when I do this that's still
okay so I'm not sure what I must have
had typos in there but anyway so we can
now look where were the axes directly so
we just do the three different axes and
then do the positive test based on
whatever the rate erection is and then
we can go ahead and compute the rest of
the stuff based on those values so now
we're not even doing that if anymore
we're just directly pulling the values
out all right so let's keep going now in
and continue to think more about what's
what's happening here so there's a
couple of pieces of information that we
know now so one of the things that we
know now that we didn't know before is
the normal is always going to be a it's
always going to look like a zero one
zero zero zero one zero zero negative
one so there's only ever going to be one
element of the normal that actually is
filled right and that's pretty important
because the fact that we know that only
one element of the normal is ever filled
kind of lets us it lets us know that a
bunch of the work that we're going to be
doing down here
is probably easy to simplify in a lot of
ways so for example let's take ray
source n the inner product of the raid
erection and the normal eye we know that
the normal can only have one component
right and if we take a look at all the
places that the normal is used here
let's see where it's being used we've
got here and here and that's it right we
don't use the normal anywhere else so
what we can see is this these two pieces
of information and in fact I can
reorganize this slightly here with no
particular cost if we take a look at
what's what's going on here you can see
that the Ray source direction I started
the race source N and the D value are
both doing full inner products for no
reason because all these two things are
gonna do is they're gonna pick out based
on an access index and positive they're
gonna pick out and then optionally
negate one of the elements of these two
of these two of these two vectors right
so ray D and rel origin are both just
getting extracted they're not really you
don't have to do any of the multiplies
but that one and it doesn't really have
to be a multiply it's just a sign flip
right so what we can do is we can take a
look at what's happening here we can
loft this stuff up a little bit right
and say these pieces of information
should be able to compute it in that way
so for starters let's take racehorses n
right and let's just go in here and put
in what racehorse n would be so in both
these cases it's the raid erection which
we know inner product ad by the N which
we know right after this line right and
so if we're going to and and similarly
we've kind of got a couple situations
where they're a little bit more
confusing but if you take a look at what
happens here with the min corner Plus
this fan this can be computed a little
bit earlier as well right so the span
and the p value we could have put those
right here right because all they
require is that um so
again the devalue the relative origin
can be computed immediately thereafter
and that means the D value can also be
computed inside here as well right now
again I haven't done anything right I
just reorganized the code the order in
which the code was happening so when we
run this we should get exactly the same
result as we got before and we do right
so off we go so now what we want to do
is we just want to go okay let's change
these because we really don't need to do
inner products here there's no point to
it right it doesn't really do anything
for us so what we can do instead is say
alright this computation for D this
inner product we know that the we know
that the normals value is 1 right we
know that that's what it's going to be
and we know that it's going to be in
this access index location right we know
that's the element now the other two
elements going to be zero so the inner
product of anything with n is really
just going to pick out that value does
that make sense so all we're really
doing is this does that make sense and
similarly down here all we're really
doing is the same operation but negated
that's it so that's all the normal
really does for us in this whole routine
we don't ever really need to compute
with it because we're just picking out a
very simple piece of information from it
and you can see the dart you know our
lighting is exactly the same as it was
before so what that means is the normal
as a value just isn't even relevant
anymore right we don't even care about
it it doesn't even function you know
factored into this routine in any way
that's all we that's all we've got right
very very straightforward so furthermore
what we can do here is just have a
signed value and do these with a
multiply if we wanted to and then we
wouldn't even have to have two branches
here either so
oh whoops you know what this is not
quite true these do have to be done
after here because min corner max corner
still has to do its thing that's weird
that it that's weird that that worked
like that lighting was still pretty much
right visually looking even though this
has an incorrect displacement of the
position of the face
I guess cuz if move them yeah that's
interesting right this this is supposed
to be modified first well I'll fix that
in a second all I was gonna say is all
we really need here is a sign value
right so we just need a sign value
that's gonna be 1.0 or or negative 1.0
right that's all we really needed and
then these pieces of information can be
computed down here like so so they don't
really need to be predicated they can
just be handled directly so it's really
just a sign value there so anyway that
allows us to fix the bug which I
introduced there I'm just it's it's
interesting how much you can get away
with and still have a visually correct
looking result I'm sure it would have
shown up in other places but you know
so anyway point being all we really need
is that sign value and then we can
continue going here so let's start
taking a look at some of the other
things that we can be doing that we're
not doing yet so this positive value
here we needed to know because we need
to know whether we do the min corner max
corner thing instantly that's where we
get our sign from but we've got our sort
of our other stuff here which is our
x-axis y-axis stuff let's see
let's put that down there you don't need
that for anything right yeah there we go
so similarly here we've got sine X we
don't really need to be doing a test on
that because we already have a sine
value the sine value is exactly this
right
it's 1.0 or negative 1.0 based on the
positive value so we can just do that
right and then we can switch it the way
we were switching it before so that's
also I suppose something that doesn't
really need to to be predicated either
right so again getting back towards
running as fast as we were before and
not storing any of that information so
let's go ahead and you know I again
continue forwards with what we're doing
so now if we take a look at what we're
doing a lot of this work to create these
axes I guess one question is do we
really need to do it you know and what
you can see here is we don't really care
which direction the axes go right we
don't care
so getting the sine right on the axis
which is something we're doing a lot
isn't really necessary because we don't
care which way it went
we're checking for essentially an
absolute value here right we're looking
to see whether it's in between this the
same thing on either side so if what
we're doing is checking for an absolute
value then the X check and the Y check
values really we don't care what the
sign of the x-axis even is so when we do
this sine X thing it doesn't matter
right it just doesn't matter which one
this was so we can just replace this in
set instead with this and it would be
exactly the same
right so we don't need that piece of
information at all we we could just get
rid of it
and again eliminate a lot of the work
that we're doing there so now the
question is well how far can we take
that right I mean what else can we do
here so the first thing to note is we
already had a way of handling here that
this the fact that we didn't really need
the half-width
either so we could also say well the
probably the better way to do this would
again be would be to return to what we
were doing before where we just multiply
these values by two right and then use
the width and height that's what we were
originally doing so now that we see that
the width and height is actually what we
have we can also get rid of that right
so continuing on just simplifying these
things down but again having to multiply
by two is kind of annoying here so it
probably would have been nice to not
have to do that either maybe we can get
rid of that as well like we'll find out
right so let's keep going
down exactly the same exactly same path
so if we take a look at what's happening
here the same logic applies to our inner
product that applied to the one with the
normal this Ray position thing here is
really just getting selected by the x
axis or the y axis and what we can see
is the x axis and the y axis are really
just used to pull out pieces of
information they're not really used for
a full dot product because we know
they're always access aligned and a dot
product that's axis aligned and unit
just plucks out a value so now we know
the sign never changes so we know that
these are just selections so really what
we could do is again we can just say hey
all so this can be computed down here
right um so we can just say hey why not
just take the
values out directly that are the values
that we want and so what I can do is say
all right
the x-axis was predicated on this so
what it was saying was if the x-axis was
zero then I'm sorry if the accident is
was zero then the x-axis is that
otherwise the x-axis is this that's what
we were saying so what we could do
instead is just say well all right if
that's what the x-axis is can we just go
ahead and predicate these directly on
that instead of doing a bunch of fussing
to make that happen and the answer is
hopefully yes so here we could just say
all right well the width then is just
the spans x-axis right but we don't want
it signed that's all it is similarly
here it would just be the y-axis so
again converting that back it's just
this
so there's that wit and of course we can
do the exact same thing for the height
right yeah where'd my oh I'm like
where'd my access truck go it's right
here so the sack same thing we can do
for the height
there's my access index so I want to
pick out the Y value in the case of the
axis is 2 and I want to pit up pick out
the Z value in the case where the axis
is not so that's all I really need to do
there to get my width and my height
right that gives me that value directly
and similarly in my X chicken Y check I
just need to be able to do the same
thing with the Ray position and so I
again I can just say the exact same
thing the only difference is it's going
to come from the rapey instead of this
fan right pretty straightforward I guess
I should keep this probably rolled out
because it's doing the exact same check
but I'm just gonna leave that for for a
second instead
there we go
so again inner products not necessary in
this case
we're just sort of getting the value out
directly if we want to but again we're
sort of a little bit sloppy here like we
maybe could do better than this we'll
have to see in a second just in terms of
how we're organizing all of our of our
information but again we should still
get the same result here hopefully with
no issues and we do so that's good
there we go
and so if we just keep pressing this and
you know again we keep sort of wringing
it out more and more you can see kind of
how we're continuing to go down so and
we don't need that anymore
so there's still more we can do here
obviously you know looking at sort of
the way that we're computing this stuff
with the min corner and Max corner and
all that and the side and so on so in
terms of the sine or sorry in terms of
the span what you can see here is that
the place that we use the span is for
two pieces of information we use it for
the width and height right but and and
so we're subtracting these two things in
order to figure out that test but if you
think about it we really don't need to
do all of that work because that work is
just we already know the bounds of the X
and the y they're exactly the min and
Max corner right so we could the way
that we're doing this relative to the
box here we could instead have just had
the min and Max corner be relative to
the position and go from there I have to
look here
I guess what I'm trying to say is the
relative origin right where we subtract
the Ray origin - minus P there it gives
us an intersection that is centered
around the the box's position but it
doesn't have to be centered around the
box's position I guess is the way I
would say it we can do this computation
relative to any point on the plane so
what we could choose to do instead is
just do this relative to the min corner
because take a look at what happens here
P is a totally arbitrary choice of a
point on the plane and there is no place
where we actually use it other than as
that point on the plane right so we
could just say don't bother with the
span addition here at all and this would
still be the exact same set of equations
because as long as we pick any point on
the plane we're done right the only
difference is now when we check our
coordinates for the bounds check our
gonna be different but hey guess what
one of the really nice things about this
is now instead of negative width to
width it's just zero on one side it's as
long as it's higher than zero right on
one side and less than or equal to the
width on the other side so that means we
no longer have to multiply we would no
longer have to we would no longer have
to check against we do a subtraction on
the other side to do that check now the
only question I have there is if I shift
it to the min corner and I do the
intersection it should just be regular
width that I'm testing still as well
yeah I think that's fine but the
negative width and height on either side
this this should just you should just
not have to multiply it by two anymore
right because you're just taking
whatever it is it should be between zero
and the width that that's it
right um yeah I mean I think I think
that basically just works for the exact
same equations or not it should have
relative origins reminds P the X check
is no longer x - if it's greater than 3
or less than the height
so I guess the problem there is the sign
does matter at that point so if the sign
of the axis is wrong so I really do have
to kind of do this as the bounds check
the way that I originally was sort of
going to finish doing it so I guess I
can just finish doing it hopefully all
right so let me explain that
oops so doing it around the center
allows me to not care which direction
the axis goes if I wanted to do it the
other way I would have to care which
direction the axis goes and that's why
that that chain didn't work but let me
explain to you what I wanted to be doing
as the next step because it wouldn't
depend on that exactly and then we'll
see how we can get there so what I
wanted to do was when you do the raycast
you're gonna get a point right and right
now what I'm doing is I'm taking
whatever we're calling the min corner
here I'm taking that and saying well
okay I'm gonna displace that and make a
point value here then the axes are
pointing whatever direction they are
look maybe they're left-handed maybe
they're right-handed we don't know
they're whatever they are because we
don't want to actually spend the time to
generate one facing a particular
direction so they're pointing some
either in one of these directions right
we've got one pointing up or down and
one pointing left or right we don't know
which but then we can test against
positive or negative width and we're
fine because at that point we just kind
of know that whichever way the axis was
going we're checking for either side of
the axis anyway so it's fine the problem
is this causes us to have to do extra
work to create like this p-value and so
on and so at that point it is just it's
it's a little bit of extra work that we
probably shouldn't have to do but what I
was going to say is well with the min
quarter max corner we already know how
to test the bounds
this thing anyway so do we really need
to do that work because we already know
what the bounds are even just in world
space right but what I'm thinking now is
well okay but when we store these boxes
we could have distorted the boxes in the
other way anyway
right we could just store the boxes as a
P plus a radius instead of having to do
a min corner and if we just store them
that way then this would be a non-issue
right we'd read the P out and the span
would already be what we what we would
know just ahead of time right so instead
we could do is say like oh okay
if we imagined doing this it's the same
same thing right it doesn't matter which
those we do
if we imagine doing this then we could
just say well let how did I make that
same mistake again
is there something weird about doing it
the way that I'm doing it here I must be
missing something subtle oh there's some
there we go uh so I must be missing
something subtle here because you should
be able to do Oh slow day huh got to
make sure you actually put that in
parentheses that's great so I can flip
the meaning of these two things around
right and if I did that then I wouldn't
have to actually compute these values
right because I could just store the box
as these two pieces of information that
p-value and the span value right and
then I can just check these in this way
I can also just do absolute value here
which would be a direct operation I can
do on the floating point flyer it's just
knocking out the high bit so I can do
that in one check right I could do
something like if absolute value is less
than or equal to width right I just
don't know how that's gonna pan out
speed wise here it's a good question
actually let's go ahead and just double
check to see just vaguely so you know
we're somewhere around the 52 well okay
so depending on your depending where
that guy hops we kind of need him to
stop hopping I suppose let's let's go
ahead and make it more stable test case
here so I'm going to go into world mode
and when we do the the snake
so here is us running and it's around 26
milliseconds I believe it's stable yeah
so I'm just curious to know if this has
any effect on it at all so if I was to
do absolute value absolute value I about
the same about the same so I'm gonna
leave it like that it's a little bit
more concise didn't it didn't really
introduce a dilatory effects there so
yeah if we take a look at what's going
on here
what we want to do is is again continue
to sort of collapse this stuff down into
something that's you know as as concise
as we can possibly make it so this
information here is all this information
could just have been stored directly and
one of the interesting parts about that
is if we take a look at the work we're
doing here min corner max corner are
only used for that value right so what
we could do is just store the boxes that
way and then we'd never have to do this
sort of fairly laborious access
information check here which is probably
pretty costly so if we go ahead and did
that let's just see how that would
affect things I'm gonna go into platform
and I'm gonna take that lighting box
thing and let's just say we've got a P
and a radius that's just how we're going
to store it from now on instead
so in here where we've got sort of the
span value where we picked out this 0.5
instead we're not gonna multiply by 0.5
we're just gonna pick the span out
directly from that box radius like so
and the P values is going to be the
p-value like so and then the min corner
and Max corner oops
are just they're just not gonna get used
right so all we have to do now is when
we actually produce these pieces of
information instead of doing min corner
Max corner we can just compute these
values which we do anyway right in here
and this is not the slow part of things
so really whatever we do here is fine
for the moment so all we have to do is
subtract the min corner in the max
corner to get the radius and to get the
p value which is the center value of of
them in general we just have to find the
midpoint right so that's the center of
the cube and the radius of the cube and
that's all there is to it so once we
have that now everyone who's doing the
the get box surface stuff right has to
switch over to doing it the other way
they have to pass the P and the radius
and that's fine
okay
but the getfox surface call has to be
fixed now that's the wrong place
to take the p-value and the radius so
now we can look and see like okay so
kickbox surface it doesn't really need
to do this part anymore because min
corner and Max corner aren't relevant
obviously right so oh you know what
that's not entirely true though so it
does still need to do that test I I was
a little bit aggressive there it does
still need to pick out the correct value
of that let me just go back and
double-check that just want to make sure
we know where P how P is being used in
that I think I may be wrong about that
yeah so the problem with that is that's
not entirely true for the span it is
true for the Box P the problem is we
still do need to do one piece of work
which is to move it to the place where
it was going to go right so for the p
value whichever axis index index were on
we still do have to do one piece of work
which is whichever element that were on
we have to add that piece of the span in
right so if we're going to positive
x-axis we have to we have to move P to
wherever the face of the cube is that
we're actually working on it's all I was
trying to say there right okay
so yeah so this routine here now we can
sort of make all of this
with that as well with with P and the
radius so if we take a look at what
we're actually computing here the span
we don't really care about anymore the
width and height of the cube we don't
care about anymore either right because
all we really need to do is take the
radius here and this produces the half
width and the half height directly same
again is true of P so the p value just
directly gets added to P there so really
all we have to do is is exactly what I
was suggesting we do here right and we
can make we can change that routine to
also working off of sine so it's a
little bit more efficient than it was so
yeah that was basically gonna say we're
bringing it up with a black screen here
cuz I made too many changes at once
which again I specifically said not to
do but then of course I went ahead and
did it so we have to kind of go through
now and validate all the stuff but you
know that's the price you pay for doing
that all right so if it's positive the p
value again is just going to be equal to
whatever whatever the center of the box
actually was and we're then we're going
to either move to the you know we're
gonna move forward along the normal in
that direction right the other way we
could state this actually and maybe this
is cleaner because in this routine we
don't really care well you know ellis
leave it this way so we're just gonna
you know in there we're just saying okay
the radius elements we're going to go
ahead and
how should I say this we are going to
move from the center of the Box to the
centre of the face by adding however far
we have to go radius wise in that
direction I also want to hold on a
second let me want to make sure this is
being done yeah yeah so this is also a
0.5 so I messed that up the radius of
the box is only half of the dimension of
the box right obviously that's what
makes it a radius and not a diameter
effectually of the box so sorry that was
a that was a mistake
so anyway this should again all be fine
so once we have our radius value passed
into us directly we should be able to
take the half width and half light very
trivially like all we have to do is just
say okay let's get a product them with
the x-axis and off we go right and that
information is now available to anyone
who wants to use it I think so I feel
like that's roughly correct and then
going back to the raycast just to make
sure and then we'll go to plug this in
here again all we're doing is saying
well whichever direction we're going
we're capias sine value the span is just
gonna be the box radius right and so
let's go ahead and change that to to be
radius and so we're gonna say is all
right we need to go in whatever
direction if we're negative normal we
need to go down or up if we're positive
normal right
so whatever axis whichever positive or
negative or testing we need to move on
that axis we need to move from the
center of the box up to the face or down
to the face then all of this stuff is
the same as it was this didn't change at
all and then when we pick out values of
the span here this is going to give us
the half width right
and one of the things you can see here
is the X check and the Y check here I
don't know why we're even still doing
absolute values on these because we're
doing an absolute value of them down
here already so I guess what we could
say here is first of all we know that
the radius itself is always going to be
positive in that way so this really
shouldn't have to be an absolute value
at all right and this shouldn't have to
be an absolute value because we're doing
the absolute value down there so why we
have that I don't know just me failing
to notice it at the time when I typed it
in so yeah really all this has to do is
pick out one of these two things right
here
same with here right and these are just
picking out those those radius and r AP
values and then we do the absolute value
on the check because we don't really
know what that is but the half that the
half-light they should always be
positive anyway so I think that's all of
that information that even needs to
happen to really happen here that makes
sense
all right so now we got to figure out
why this is going wrong right like why
are we getting a black screen and I'm
not really 100% sure how we ended up
with that so something busted is
happening here
we just don't know what it is so now we
have to figure out yeah is that is it
something in here that we did in
switching to it my guess is you know
probably not I don't really know but
probably not because we should just be
seeing some we would be seeing erroneous
lighting but we'd be seeing lighting
just the same so my suspicion is I
messed up the box get box surface call
right so in here when I change to be
using the p-value instead and the radius
instead of using them in quarter in the
max corner my suspicion is that I messed
that up not not that I messed up the
raycast routine but again don't really
know that that's true but that's just my
my rough guess of probably who is who
got screwed up here right okay so let's
go ahead and meant to do that rebuild on
debug so let's go ahead and rebuild
debug here and let me run the program
make sure it's all good
and let's just validate our gift get box
surface call revalidate our get box
service calls so I'm gonna go ahead and
start inspecting this so what we get
here is we've got a p-value inner groups
p-value and a radius value and then we
need to see what axis index and the
positive value are and the result so
taking a look at these
the p-value that comes in you know
doesn't doesn't get changed it should
it's supposed to make correctly if I'm
wrong but those are exactly the same so
the axis index here is zero
so this this operation should have taken
place right
this this should have been added and it
wasn't
all right so I I don't pretend to know
why that happens so let's take a look at
that in in detail oh no no okay right
this is initially past it no no so that
was correct I'm sorry yeah I was looking
at the wrong thing there so here's the
radius value for starters the radius is
negative so that's just wrong so I'm
gonna take a step out and see I must
have done the subtraction incorrectly
there in the thing that passes in the
Box surface so that's a obvious mistake
and would obviously account for the
black screen so that you know is needs
to get fixed immediately
oops okay so in here where we have our
subtraction yeah this is supposed to be
Mac's corner let's make this a little
more consistent so we'll do max corner
min corner yeah okay so let's try that
again our radius is now positive that's
exactly what we want half width half
height all right normal it's negative
one okay much better all right so that's
looking better now let's see what our
visuals look like here okay so we're
back so it looks like the old it was
just that I had accidentally set the
radius is to negative so that was a bit
of a mistake there let's go ahead and
change this back - OH - and see where
we're at
okay all right so again continuing to
get better pretty nice and smooth there
we can go back in now and add our little
our little friend just to increase the
number of light things bouncing around
become and so I think we're now actually
also getting in the range of what we
were originally running at I think we're
fairly close I don't remember exactly
where we are cuz again I'm not really in
an optimization mode right now I'm kind
of more just in a like let's make this
algorithmically relatively correct first
because we need to use boxes one way or
the other
uh so again pretty good right not not
too shabby so far so now again let's
just take a look at that rate cast again
and see where we're at in terms of
simplification of it so yeah looking
here at looking here at what we've got I
mean this is you know pretty drastically
simplified from where it was box surface
index is kind of something that's
annoying to have to compute here because
it's really only used for this readout
but you know yeah hard to say I'm gonna
go ahead and turn off this time function
by the way cuz that's actually taking
some time in there I want to see how
we're doing without it quite a bit
better actually right so I think we're
back down to roughly where we were
before right I think we're getting right
we're in we're in better shape than
probably even better shape than we were
in before potentially
so yeah you know this is looking pretty
good
it's possible I don't actually know but
it's possible that that the fact that
this is still in a four loop and this
can't be optimized is pretty bad right
so I am tempted as well to sort of macro
eyes this a little bit and just actually
do this check unrolls does that make
sense so you know I don't necessarily
think that's a great idea but I am
curious about it so I'm just because we
only have five minutes left I'm just
gonna do that because I just want to see
so here's what would happen if we were
to unroll it so if it were the x-axis
then you know it's just X and we pretty
much know exactly what those values are
makes sense
e axis index is just always X and all of
these like so and and yeah all of this
stuff we know that the access index is
equal to zero so it's just rapey Y and
radius Y and then the Exynos equals two
is not true so we know we do those two
and that's pretty much it right that's
just all we need to do there for the y
axis do that we know that this is just
going to be two because that's what one
shifted up by one is and then again the
rest of this stuff just becomes y ax e Y
access is we know the access is not
equal to zero so it's not and we know
that it's also not equal to two so it's
that and off we go
and finally the z axis again what we're
going to be shifting up here is two so
that's gonna become equal to four
right I'm not mistaken I think because
Eagle would be four or five depending on
whether positive is zero so I think
that's right and again just a few places
where we actually access that
information goes away it's not zero it's
not snowflake it is access to so this
applies
so let's just see how that goes I think
we did it right and we'll see
so there's no question that that helped
us I think just not a whole lot so it's
not clear that we really would want to
do that necessarily off the bat but you
know you can kind of see how unrolling
that loop can simplify things right can
definitely simplify things and you know
we can start to look at this as being
even more simplified if we start to pull
out you know terms maybe we can look at
collapsing some of this stuff as well
you know who knows let's let's we could
just take a little closer look here at
that part so so here's another example
so ray source n doesn't depend on
anything but the positive or negative
sign here so that's interesting well I
guess that doesn't really matter
yeah there's there's more there
significantly more we can do here I
guess it's all I can say we can keep
looking at this
but yeah there's definitely more we can
do here so also if we take a look at
what happens here so the X check
becoming Ray P X radius X that is
actually common for these two so that
can be switched here and similarly these
can be switched here that was not I went
too far
it's not what I meant to do I meant to
switch the other half what I meant was
these right so if I go ahead and pull
out these there's really not much point
in what I'm doing right now I just
wanted to kind of mentally have a feel
for what is actually happening in the
routine as it flows down so that this
will not really improve the speed but
it's just something to kind of be aware
of so you can see it starts at Y Z it
doesn't really change here so the X this
changes the other one doesn't change and
then similarly the same is true here so
only the half height changes here right
so I'm just kind of looking at the way
that flows through the code yeah it's
just worth noting
oh you know what and this is not
actually true this does have to be
redone every time so I think that's
still substantively the exact same thing
and so again looking at this I just
think there's still a fair bit of slop
in here that we could that we could
optimize away we have to think it
through a little bit more but I'm pretty
sure that we're not done getting rid of
a lot of this information one thing
that's interesting here is resource N
and D if you take a look at where that's
being used so resource n is only used
once and D is only used once as well I
want to say so unless I'm mistaken this
multiplication by the sign is just
irrelevant right
like it just isn't necessary I don't
think because we're multiplying two
things by the sign but those things just
get divided so I think you can even get
rid of that multiplication entirely
since no one cares what the sign of
those two things are so again still kind
of just an arbitrary just an you know an
arbitrary sort of aspect of the math
that just kind of falls out we just
really don't need to do it
so yeah keeping going along that line of
reasoning what you can see here is now
sign is only used in one place right so
in a sense all we really the only reason
we even need to know whether we're the
positive or they are the negative
anymore is is strictly because we need
to have an opinion about how to displace
the point so that's really it
it'd be nice if we could get rid of that
because that's the only reason we need
to compute that but I think we have to
unfortunately so anyway that's just kind
of nice
and this is starting to look relatively
respectable you know within reason
all right I'm gonna go ahead and go to
Q&amp;A but what I can also do now is I can
also switch back here to this version of
the routine and make that same
optimization because that's true
regardless of whether it's unrolled so
for example in here where I do the sign
multiplication that's just not necessary
anymore
right because those that piece of
information is is never used D and
racehorses n are only ever used in that
context that's that's the only place
they're actually used so you can even
you could even just get rid of them
right it's just that oops
that and no one ever needs to do that
particular operation of the sign so
that's a pretty meaningful speed saving
is even just there because it just
eliminates multiplies that we're
completely superfluous and unnecessary
let's see
that did not work there it goes
gee Princip is the letting done after
this after what the lighting is not even
close to done we've got several more
things we have to do to it you may now
start the episode guide entries from new
to old oh really oh wow check that out
that's pretty sweet that's cool my bow
stuck panda which headers do you include
for working with OpenGL we included GL
dot H
how long until you'll move all this to
the GPU I don't know I also don't know
for sure that we will so one of the
things is once we do it Multi res if we
wanted to we could also just do it on
the CPU multi-threaded and probably be
fine
so it's it's gonna be an interesting
call when we're done with it we'll have
to see just how likely we think it is to
be able to run efficiently on the GPU
versus CPU so it's hard to say right
because it would get four times faster
than it is right now if we ran it
multi-threaded probably well that's not
really true
but let's for this way if we simply
optimize it in multi-threaded it would
be massively faster than it is right now
probably and so you know we could be
looking at at a pretty dramatic speed-up
right from where it is right now on CPU
and then plus with multi res it would
scale really well and so on so it's
possible possible that we could prefer
doing it on the CPU because the CPU just
faster at random access kinds of things
like rate tracing
if traversal is a big deal but
and might also not be I don't know so
who knows why did inlining get box to
raycast result in such an improvement
without looking at the generated
assembly we don't know exactly why but
the general case is because the compiler
doesn't have that much logic in it right
it's running in a fairly short amount of
time
it doesn't spend like you know it's a
what does it take four seconds to build
the game
it just doesn't spend a lot of time
thinking about how to optimize the code
I know we think of optimizing compilers
as being pretty advanced or something
but they're actually really primitive
especially ones that run in line like
this so it's got a bunch of heuristics
that it uses to determine how much of an
improvement is gonna get if it in line
something it depends on can power
switches like maybe we could set some
faster still it'd be more aggressive
with inlining than it would right that's
etc and so you know when you start
stacking things on top like oh you'd
have to inline this and then you'd have
to realize that once you inline it you
could get rid of this array access
because now you know what it is and you
could unroll the loop and bla bla bla
bla bla right the number of steps you're
requiring the compiler to take before it
gets to code that's fast just reduces
the chances that it figures out it
should do that thing you know
and so when you care about when you have
a particular like thing that actually
needs to be fast you typically have to
massage it pretty well to get it into a
place where the compiler really knows
exactly what it should do it doesn't
have to think too hard that's all well
the lighting boxes remain sort of
separate from the rest of the render
commands flow yes they will just be
pushed on in a separate stream
grapes cream by the way in the legend
let's rate the lighting is gonna look
insanely good once we actually start
using it right now we're not even right
like right now we're doing the worst
possible thing which is we're just
lighting individual services but we
actually have interpolation capability
in there now so once I actually peg
lights to light samples for
interpolation across the faces of
surfaces more it's gonna look a lot
better so it will it will improve
dramatically we'll get there
you'll see in my engine I have 3d models
that contain a buffer of un8 which is
cast into a struct which contains OpenGL
handles for the model my instinct is to
hide the OpenGL stuff from the game
engine itself is this a good idea or
should I just give it into the OpenGL
overlords and foot-pound including GL in
my game code maybe just beyond dogmatic
I would never put pound include GL in
your game code because you might want a
port to came to saying that's not GL and
now you've got to deal with that right
so I always say platform doesn't go in
the game code right
sometimes you have to inline certain
platform things into the game code like
Cindy for example hat you know you may
have to have like things that switch on
it but you still want to make sure that
it's not actually ever touched by the
game code so it's less about whether you
pound include GLH in the game code or
not it's whether the game code ever
refers to anything in there if the game
code is ever gonna actually be using GL
that H somehow it has to be doing it
through some opaque thing where it
doesn't actually rely on that so that if
you were trying to port to Vulcan
direct3d whatever PlayStation 4 Xbox one
blah-blah-blah-blah-blah Nintendo switch
you would always be able to use a
different graphics layer and the game
code doesn't have to change that's the
important part
right
skyvolt games from the JI programming
language stabilizers will you be
considering using it for future handmade
projects of course yes definitely I
don't know what the situation will be
like or when I would have a chance to
really start to learn it and move over
to it in a serious way but obviously I
will be considering it because C++ is a
giant steaming pile of dog turd so I
would greatly welcome the possibility of
programming a language designed by
people who I think are more sane right
is there an episode that explains some
generalities about what open jail
shaders are yes there are some episodes
about that if you go to the annotated
episode guide here that woops and put in
shader you would probably get some
information about that so let's see this
is probably something that might be
worth listening to to start with
here is when we actually implement
compiling and linking shaders so maybe
starting on day 368 would be good
introduction of vertex and fragment
shaders on day 369 that sounds pretty
good right all right no more Q :
so I will wrap it up alright thank you
everyone for joining me for the episode
of hey I made here oh it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series you could always pre-order the
game on handmade hero org and it comes
to the source code so you can play
around with it if you would like to
catch up on past episodes we do have an
episode guide that I was just showing
it's a great place to do that if you're
missed old stuff we have a schedule bot
that says when we're gonna be live you
want to catch a stream we also have a
contribution page if you want to
contribute to things like the episode
guide which are made by people in the
community and so we try to funnel money
to them to support their work that's a
good place to check that out that's what
it for today I will be back next week
when we will continue to optimize our
lending code at this point our rate cast
is probably good enough for now we
probably don't need to spend a lot of
time optimizing it there's a lot more we
could be doing but we're probably not
going to do that because the more
important optimization which is the one
that I want to get to first before we go
any further is starting to deal with
things multi-resolution and that's just
so we can scale the lighting so what
we're gonna do next week is we're going
to go ahead and blow out the scene to
some huge number of entities and lights
and everything and then we're gonna
start focusing on methods that will
allow us to still light those scenes
without tanking our performance so
that's what I'll be doing hopefully see
everyone here for that next week until
then have fun programming and I'll see
everyone in a minute take it easy
everybody