hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero i wanted to take a look well you
know there's there's two things we could
do today and and i think i'm just gonna
pick um
one of them
uh because i don't actually have a lot
of experience with the other and i was
going to be yeah i mean
let me show you what what we're doing
here so if you take a look at the
currently running version of this game
uh
which is oh uh i should probably put it
in release mode because we don't
actually care right now um
uh about debugging anything and i think
i had it in debug mode because i was
doing that remedy bg
um
a lot of people saw that remedy bg uh
video i don't know how many people were
actually convinced to give it a try i
hope
a fair number of people were but like i
did this video if you didn't see it on
the molly rocket channel
um but there's like basically a a video
up here that i did where i i put yeah it
had like 15 000 views which is a you
know it's not a huge number of views but
it's pretty good for like a weird you
know niche programming channel like mine
is
that's still a lot you know the average
videos maybe only get about half of that
you know what i mean
so uh
hopefully like some people maybe got
interested in remedy out of that but i i
did a video where i basically said
here's a bunch of stuff that i think is
cool about remedy that's like stuff you
you know maybe aren't going to do in in
visual studio or whatever and that was
kind of cool
but
in general
back to handmade hero
uh we are at a stage where uh at some
point i would like a glow shader uh when
when you get these like little like uh
panels that are gonna light up on the
floor
um i want them to kind of glow and so
when we do the final resolve we're gonna
need like a pass uh over that that does
some bloom
um probably no halation
because
[Music]
you know there's two things that cause
the
light to
appear outside of the region where the
light actually is so if you have a
bright thing like this right
in a darker area
uh there's two things that people are
used to seeing and they come from film
they're not really real things that
happen in
i mean one of them sort of maybe is the
other definitely isn't
uh that happen in the real world with
your eye but film when you film things
that are bright
uh you get two effects that happen one
is a thing that's very specific to film
it's called halation
and what halation is is film is like a
stack of
sheets
uh that respond to color
uh wavelength of light there's a blue a
green and then a red sheet from the top
to bottom
and then there's a thing called an
antihilation layer and then there's the
actual like film substrate the back like
the back piece
and what happens is when you have a lot
of photons striking the film
not all of them actually get absorbed
not all of them strike the silver halide
particles in the actual like
uh layers that are supposed to receive
them
and get it that would get exposed like
the negative you know that would get
exposed
and those photons hit this thing called
an antihilation layer which tries to
absorb as many photons as it can it's
like as pure black as it could be in a
way like it doesn't reflect anything but
even that isn't perfect so if you have a
really bright exposure on a film what
happens is some of those photons bounce
back up
and expose the red layer sometimes the
green layer rarely ever the blue
layer of film
and so what you'll see in film is
there's like a orange red
because you know the blue layer is not
really getting affected a
orange at the brightest to red dark red
at the outside
fringe around things and that's called
halation
that's one of the effects and it's very
specific to film and wouldn't really be
appropriate in this game like i'm
probably not going to add like film
grain to this game because it's kind of
cartoony looking i probably wouldn't add
vignetting which is something that you
see sometimes i also wouldn't
add red green blue distortion which is a
lens distortion thing these are lots of
things you see in indie games now that
try to make things look better for low
end art or whatever
um
i wouldn't add most of those and i
wouldn't add hilation either because
those are all very film specific effects
and i don't think they're very
appropriate here so really what we'll be
talking about adding is what's called a
bloom
filter although it's a really bad name
because there's another thing called a
bloom filter that has nothing to do with
visuals
uh what it actually is simulating is
light
scattering errantly in the lens
apertures in the in the actual like uh
camera assembly
so what happens is photons when you have
a lot of them
like a very bright layer
or if you're just shooting in the sun i
don't know if you've ever seen
one of those uh things where you put
like a
you know cameras have these snouts
that like there's a thing after the lens
that's just like a hood that goes over
it that's long
really what all that kind of stuff is is
it's to prevent
stray photons from bouncing around
inside the lens assembly and hitting
random places on the film back right
but even if you do that so that you have
a narrow channel and you're just
receiving light from the thing you're
actually pointing at very bright light
can still hit imperfections
in the lens
uh aperture and the camera assembly
and scatter when it scatters it will go
outside of where it's actually supposed
to be exposing the film because it has
it's you know the lens
is not perfect curvature there might be
particles in it that will deflect the
photons there might be just like
imperfections in how in its radius right
and all of those things combine to
scatter a little bit of light outside of
the actual place that the light is
supposed to be focused even when
something is in focus what that means is
that very bright light sources will
produce you'll see some of that haloing
and that's what a bloom filter is meant
to uh you know basically
uh simulate right
so
the
while not really appropriate in a way
because it's not real
um
it doesn't really exist it's it's
something that only happens when you
take a picture of something
um
it's not really there in the real world
right
uh
it's it's a way that we currently now
have grim it's a it's a semantic thing
that we have accepted in our brains from
watching movies
um
and looking at photographs
in our
lives
that we know that something is bright if
it has that halo around it like we've
now like kind of like internalized that
as like a grammar for this thing is
bright
and so what we're really doing when we
introduce a filter like that in a video
game that isn't photorealistic right
that that's not doing all those other
things what we're doing is borrowing a
shorthand mentally that humans have now
grown up to understand because of their
exposure to mass media
is just saying this is very bright and
so when you light these up right
right now they don't look as bright as
they should because we don't have any
other of those signals in there and so
eventually what i'd like to do is put
those signals in
so a bloom filter would be nice to add
and the other thing that would be nice
to add would be some participating media
which means like some dust
in here right
uh so that you will see the light
uh so basically some particles
so uh that's the thing i said there's
two things i might do today that's the
thing i think i'm going to
delay till later
um the main reason for that is that i
don't really think i need it anytime
soon it's just going to sell these
scenes a lot better but it's not
actually going to change anything
material about what i'm doing right so i
think we can safely postpone that the
lighting looks great currently
um and and i really have no need for
anything better for most of the
development of this game so i think i
can safely postpone those two features
even though they are going to be pretty
important to making the game look cool
uh and should happen right
so the thing i'd like to focus on today
is just building some basic interactions
here like you know this is what happens
currently if you try to do anything in
handmade hero you get wedged between
some enemies and because we don't
actually have any combat mechanics in
there i can't kill them and they can't
kill me so we don't really have a way to
particularly do anything like play-wise
uh in the game right and similarly we'd
like to work on the hopping mechanics
like we have these pressure plates
because so we you know proved that we
can put those in there
but they don't actually work right and
also they're kind of buggy like they you
can keep pressing them down further and
further and they go right into the earth
right
um
so we definitely have a bunch of work
that we would want to do here and so
what i think we might do for a little
while is just go clean up some of this
code uh put a little bit of like combat
stuff in there clean up the glove i i
haven't thought hard about how we want
like the glove is just on this like
physics spring right here
and i need to think about how i want the
glove to work or like what it's supposed
to do
um this is largely game design stuff
uh so it's not really something that i'm
going to be talking much about or
pretending that we actually are going to
really solve it's more just like me
putting in something that's vaguely okay
right
um and i'm just gonna assume that those
who out there who are game designers uh
would if you were working on um
your own handmade hero code base i'm
just gonna assume that you're gonna go
ahead and do something
uh more intelligent here than whatever
it is that i'm gonna do uh but that's
your problem and if you have a problem
with it go talk to jonathan blower
somebody who knows game design i don't
want to hear about it because it's not
my job
um so basically like like i said
everything looks good to me i'm really
liking moving around in this world so i
think it's good enough now that i'm
happy to just say i'll just go like make
a world that i can walk around in and i
can do some stuff in and there's a bunch
of code that i have to write to support
that anyway because we decided to do
basically just keeping everything in
flat 2d
like it is now without things stacked on
top of each other so i would also like
um to you know i i'd like to go ahead
and make something where i can um
you know hop into like a dungeon to go
like down dungeon levels right
sort of like uh
you know like just
i don't know i mean basically what i'm
saying is i'm to start just doing some
random stuff here to try and build out
the world because i don't really know
uh what we're going to do there exactly
and i just want to start to just like
polish that stuff up
because now things look pretty good and
i would like to sort of like have some
experiences in the world because it
looks cool
um and also generate some art asset
lists because we also you know at some
point we'll need some more art for the
game uh and without knowing what's going
on there's really not a lot of ways for
us to request art assets because we
don't know what our assets we would
actually need furthermore we can also do
stuff like we actually have the ability
to talk to npcs and stuff now but
there's no reason to talk to npcs and no
reason for them to tell you anything or
to do anything with them and so again we
just we have a lot more features in this
engine that were used than we are using
and so at this point it just seems like
uh logical to build that out again why
hasn't that already been done because
i'm not a game designer and don't really
know what to do so i don't have um you
know one of the things that you'll see
uh if you watch john stream or something
or someone who is a great game designer
there aren't very many of them but you
know uh john at least streams and he's
very good uh he you know he has ideas
about what's going to happen there right
like he one of the things that drives
him forwards when he's working on things
is not the technical excellence of the
thing that he's working on but rather
like some end goal that is a game design
goal that he has right and that's very
valuable when you're working on games if
you're working on them
as a sole practitioner
that's extremely valuable and what you
would love to have if you were such a
person uh i don't really have to do this
in my day-to-day life thankfully most of
the time
but like on handmade hero i'm in the
unfortunate position of having to do it
what you would like there like i said is
some strong idea i mean you know i i'm
able to do this for code like i have a
strong idea of like what
uh i want
to accomplish code wise when i'm working
on technical things and i think what you
want to have right if you're a game
designer is you want to have that strong
motivation
of what you're trying to
uh move towards right
uh because it's the same you know it's
the same with game design as it is with
technology and so you know i'm at a
disadvantage there
but uh what i'm not at a disadvantage as
is just wanting to like do basic stuff
in the world and move around it so what
i'm gonna do is basically just let that
guide me like what i want to see in here
just as an experience i'm just going to
make and i'm just going to assume that
the game itself will not be particularly
good because i don't really have that
kind of a skill
set
but we can make an interesting world
and we can make like some interesting
experiences in it
again and just kind of let that drive us
so
uh the biggest thing that i would say uh
just to start with is i'd like to sort
of work on the glove stuff a little bit
um and maybe like i
you know
i i'd like to figure out how i want this
thing to feel
and you can see
with what's in there currently um i did
a little bit of work on this so
uh right now you can kind of see if you
if you hop around the world
we did this a long time ago just kind of
like basic control stuff when we put it
in
um the idea
basically behind this quote-unquote game
design
is that if you had a bunch of tiles in
the world not probably like the ones
here because these are just randomly
generated as a test uh but if you had a
certain pattern that you had to like do
in order to open the doors to uh in the
room that you're in so maybe like you
hop into the room and the door is closed
like i said very standard legend of
zelda binding of isaac um it's just a
trope at this point it's a very standard
game design thing
that you go into a dungeon room and the
doors close and in order to open the
doors again you have to hop on a series
of tiles that's just the central conceit
of the game it's very simple it
shouldn't be that complicated to
produce something reasonable there right
um and so
one of the things that i wanted to do
was make it so that when you hop that's
very important that's why this game is
grid based and you hop is because it's
important where you're hopping
now the
uh when you hop and you land on
something um what i would like to do
is i would like to make it so that you
can also potentially dodge
and so i i was one of the things you can
do right currently is you hit the space
bar and then you can still push in a
direction you can see that represented
by the movement of the head here right
and i don't really again super know
exactly how i want that to work but
that's like part of it so you come you
come on here look at i i can dodge and
we'll have to make it so that you move
more than this right um
that's not enough of a dodge right uh
and you can see the glove is just this
weird stupid spring and i don't really
like that i thought maybe there'd be
some interesting things with that but
the more i see it the more i think
you know it's out of place in this game
um
a little bit
maybe what i really want is the glove to
be very procedural so that you just you
push you know you push a strike and it
does that strike and and that's it right
um
and again i i don't really know all
these things i'm saying are just like
not real thoughts they're just kind of
like that's basically the idea
so the glove originally was more of a
procedural thing and i wonder if that's
more what we want here i don't know i
don't know that this game really wants
any
um dynamic stuff in it like that
we may just want everything to be based
on the fact that you are going to
[Music]
um
be standing on squares and stepping on
squares and maybe when you strike
like the strike pattern just
you know one way to think about the way
that strikes work is to make them to be
very concrete
and so for example one way that this
might be concrete is saying look
it could be that a glove has a
particular attack pattern and of course
you know there can be glove upgrades and
downgrades and things like that in the
game that you find
was kind of expected to be something
that would happen
and so if you took for example a glove
strike pattern and the glove strike
pattern is like it goes out through
there comes over here back and then in
right like it's like that kind of a
thing
um it could be that like you know
that
pattern is
is fixed so when you do a strike the
glove does that pattern and returns
and the reason that that's sort of
interesting to me is because if the game
is sort of about these geometries that
are formed by tiles in the world
then different glove patterns would have
different ways that you had to approach
different rooms in the game right
and different enemies would be harder or
easier for different glove patterns and
things like that right
and so i don't really know at the end of
the day that i want it to be really uh
like the reason that i think it's kind
of interesting to be able to manipulate
the glove like i'm doing now where it
can kind of go in these sort of fanciful
um dynamic physics based patterns
i just don't know that that makes any
sense in this game
one way to look at that would be to say
that it does make a lot of sense in this
game because the game is going to be
about movement being very discreet but
punching being very fluid and physics
based
um that's totally valid i don't know
that there's any way you could argue
that that was like arbitrarily
wrong
but
uh
i question whether that's the game
that i would want to be making like like
thinking about it i don't know that that
is what i really want um
[Music]
you know because
i feel like what i want is more
something that's that's more about those
tiles that's more akin to like a tactics
game that's just it's not a tactics game
right but it has a little bit of that
sort of i understand what's going on
because i can see where the tiles are
kind of feel
so my sense is that like that might be
more what i want to see happen and so
you know um
it could be that really like we just
don't have
like like one thing that i that i might
one thing that i think could be a valid
path forward in this game and maybe it's
just good enough for now because you
know i don't
i don't know how to do anything
particularly smart here
um
one thing that might be a good path
forward is just to say okay what's gonna
happen here is
everything is about tiles
always
so
there's no such thing like these heads
can't float like they're floating here
they have to move along actual grid
things
there won't be projectiles that can go
like diagonally
projectiles are only horizontal and
vertical right
um
and that is both limiting meaning that
okay so you know that that cuts out a
bunch of possibilities but um
uh
it it makes a space for design
that
guarantees that we'll be exploring
something
sort of interesting and unique right
because
rather than just always falling back to
the same
things that you would normally see in
this kind of game like just projectiles
and other stuff
we would be forcing ourselves to look
specifically at a subset of game design
that's about
cardinal directions
and that at least seems more interesting
so that maybe we would compensate for
our lack of design skill
by at least being in a space that's not
maybe as well tread so we might come up
with a few things that are interesting
uh that aren't just totally trite you
know that aren't just totally the same
as as everyone else right
um so that's kind of my thinking like
maybe that's just how that is and so
that we just don't have
um
like we just don't have things that are
like we almost just don't have a
collision system the collision system is
entirely transactional right
it's it's always about tiles and so when
you resolve collisions the collisions
are on tiles and only on tiles right
um
and to me that just seems like the
smartest way to go like at some point
especially if you're weak at game design
i think at some point you just have to
pick something and say this is what the
game is because if you're not super
skilled at game design you're just you
can't
you can't
give yourself a complete freedom because
freedom is too difficult like
for for unskilled people right you you
need to arb
if you don't have
gay it's the same in programming right
if you're an expert programmer you can
give yourself complete freedom to do
whatever you want because you will
quickly be able to identify the proper
set of constraints based on the problem
that you're trying to solve because
you're really good right
and you just know how to make those
decisions
but if you're not
a very good programmer giving yourself
complete freedom is a disaster because
you just spiral out of control and make
all this stuff and you get nowhere right
and so
based on your skill level i think you
need to be willing to like narrow in and
give yourself artificial constraints
constraints that you don't know if they
were even the right constraints
and the reason for that is just because
like you need to be able to finish the
thing and
and uh
and it's too hard a problem without the
constraints for you to be able to solve
right
you've you've given yourself a problem
that is outside of your ability space
and you need you need those constraints
to give you an easier problem and you
know like in this case i'm saying up
front it probably won't therefore be the
best game design you could have done
with this game but we already knew that
was true because of our skill level so i
think that that
i guess i'm willing to just go ahead and
say let's just do it this way
because i know you could make a good
game that way like i'm sure jon could
make a good game with these constraints
so i don't think we're designing
ourselves out of a good game by making
them
and by picking them arbitrarily it's
sort of saying look this is just going
to be we're
we're putting training wheels on this
design because that's how good we are at
riding a bike right
sure we'd love to ride a 10 speed
you know
um
but if you can't even stay on the bike
like what are you doing on it what what
why are you trying to like do the tour
de france right
so i think that's what i'll say is like
look we're just not gonna do that
entities are gonna have to have move
patterns and we're just gonna say that
like we'll make the best game design we
can within those constraints but those
are the constraints there's no other
options that you get
so figure out how to make the best game
design you can given the constraint that
everything has to be a transactional
movement exactly like it would normally
be in a tactics game however unlike a
regular tactics game this game happens
in real time so it's kind of like
borrowing the ideas from a tactics game
about tiles but not actually having um
any like you know
not actually having
uh
the turn-based nature
you can still move around and do things
as fast as you can figure out how to do
them
and the enemies will as well uh and
that's how that goes so i think what
that means is like effectively we have
sort of this move entity call right
and basically what we want to do is we
looked at this and and this was going to
be a bunch of work that we would have to
do too to like finish up collision
detection
we had some in there but it wasn't as
good as it should be
again it reduces the work for us we
already did the work of having a
transactional movement system
and so by removing this we would also
save ourselves some time because now we
don't have to go down this rat hole of
how do we want to handle our collision
and how do we get that up to
a particularly good level so what we
could do is say all right let's just
remove this stuff
entirely uh and then we don't have to do
you know the movement displacement or
any of this stuff right we would just
have transactional occupy and we will
have to like improve that
system a little bit because right now it
it it's
we need to get like the leading the the
edge transitions uh working correctly
um
i've done a lot of programming in these
kind of systems before and just just
give you a little bit of a perspective
on it
when we look at the edge transitions
here there's like
transactional occupy is basically saying
okay if we were doing a move based game
like a tactics game like you would
normally do
um
what would happen
on the move when entity x makes this
move right
but in this it's not going to be a
tactics game it's going to be a real
time game
and so we have this notion of a movement
edges what that means is for example
let's suppose we already see in fact let
me let me just show you because i don't
have to tell you we've already got it
watch very carefully what happens in
fact i'll help you you don't even have
to watch very carefully because we have
a time step adjustment here let me set
it down to one tenth speed watch what
happens when i hop from this square onto
the tile
do you notice how it lit up immediately
which is totally not what we want to see
right it feels wrong
what was happening there well what
happens there is currently our system
just all works on the leading edge of a
transaction when you decide that you're
going to move from one square to another
square all of the events that would
happen from you landing on that square
happen
one of those events is that you will
light up a floor switch right
so
we don't want that
we now be if if we're going to go down
this route right and we're saying
everything's going to be transactional
we need to add like basically three
stages if you will to the transactional
system it will still work basically like
it currently does but there needs to be
a notion of a leading edge
a sustaining action and then a trailing
edge kind of attack sustain and release
if you will from music nomenclature and
what i mean by that is we have events
that will take place at the leading edge
we will have events that take place
during and events that will take place
at the trailing edge
for
the example of someone hopping onto a
switch that is a trailing edge event
meaning even though the event is more or
less going to be inevitable because we
know that the hopper is going to land
there
we don't want to trigger it until he
actually lands and furthermore it's
still not quite true that is inevitable
because maybe this person for example
gets shot right like suppose there is a
projectile that comes to hit me or or
maybe this is an enemy that's hopping on
there my glove like punches them
in the middle of the sustain then the
trailing edge part wouldn't actually
take place so our system will be a
little bit different than what you would
think of when you normally think of a
transactional movement game such as a
tactics game because
unlike a tactics game where the move is
a foregone conclusion when the initiator
initiates it
and really the only concern you have is
how do you wish to draw it in our game
we really will probably have basically
the equivalent of like what magic the
gathering for example calls an interrupt
where somebody can interrupt the flow of
what's actually going to happen we will
be having that because it's going to be
an action game um which sounds great i
mean to me that just sounds interesting
so i think
again i'm very i'm fine with this uh
approach i think it will yield
reasonable game design results right
so i'm going to get rid of this voxel
stuff that's in here currently and the
shape collision uh things that are there
uh and like the voxel stack stuff like
we don't really need that anymore i
don't believe uh and so we're just gonna
get rid of it i
believe like we've got just a bunch of
yeah like all of this stuff we just
don't really need anymore
um and also this align to movement voxel
i don't think we need either
so we can eliminate a bunch of code and
that at least is good from a technical
standpoint because it means that
again we're reducing the workload and
reduce reducing the variability uh
the the sort of like degree that we have
to bulletproof this stuff
uh and so hopefully uh this is like a
plus
in in that respect right
um
[Music]
i think that's all of it right and so uh
all we would really be doing here for
the most part is for starting we would
just say look there's no such thing as a
floating entity
um that just cuts out that entire
movement mode
now these movement modes are kind of
stupid and we probably now want to clean
those up and regularize them now that we
know what's going on but really that was
it right so that's all it takes to
remove that code from the game and now
we can see that like the glove and also
um like the floating heads are now
basically just dead in the water because
they're set to
have that floating moving movement mode
um which we've now said doesn't exist so
uh they
need to
now have some code for how they're
actually going to move
but otherwise this isn't
you know there's no real uh
there's no real magic to it right it's
not uh
it's not rocket surgery
so let's take a look at
yeah you know like this stuff right um
this stuff is
is is where we're gonna be living for a
little while right um we kind of need
like some ideas about what's supposed to
happen here
uh and
you know
we're gonna need some
we're gonna need to like basically redo
this whole thing i like
how we're conceptualizing of like the
glove and that sort of stuff
now there are some
issues here like
i mean i guess one thing we could say
uh is
is is any of this stuff
really what we want so if you look at
how this stuff is working right you've
got this idea of this movement mode
and i think maybe what we're sort of
going to say is look there's like no
such thing as a movement mode anymore
there's just tile to tile movement right
so really these are animations
like that's really all we're talking
about here is like how do i animate the
fact that you're moving you know what i
mean
and so it may be the case that really
what we can do is is
spread
is sort of break this up into just an
animation of how you move from one tile
to another which is sort of what these
actually are now
i think these got
removed by the way let me put this back
in for just one quick second
um and see because i think these are not
actual things anymore
um
so yeah
when i look at that that's what i'm
thinking right so in my head what i
would want to say is
this is more like
we will still want these codes
for the the animation mode like look
what kind of animation is this thing
playing basically we we have pretty much
just procedural animation in this game
and so when you see somebody says i'm
hopping from this square to this square
that's going to be like a particular
animation that's being played
that's that's more like what this enum
is right
so it's not a movement mode it's an
animation it's just entity animation
that's all it's going to really be
and then movement will no longer have a
mode associated with it at all there's
just you're going from this tile to this
tile that's it
and some entities will go from one tile
to the next tile meaning like we we move
directly
they can only go to tiles next to them
is what i'm trying to say poorly
other entities that maybe hop big jumps
could go differently like you know think
of a knight on a chessboard maybe they
can go you know with a big hop um sort
of from one place to another without
touching the tiles in between right
um so there's going to be sort of like
there's going to be two ideas there
right one is just here's the cells that
i'm going to touch here's the square's
going to touch that now can just i think
be regularized that's just there's just
basically like
this is the sequence of squares i'm
going to hit right
and everyone can share that same code
because it's literally just the like
transactional thing and that's it right
um
then this is just the animation style if
you want to see a hop
right because this is a hopping entity
then it sets the animation to hop when
it hops right
if you want to see it just float along
then it sets it to float right so this
becomes not a movement mode but rather
just a
you know
it's just a
an animation trigger just like you would
in any other game normally you'd just be
loading like an animation off disc in
this case we're we don't have animations
off this but we have like procedural
stuff so really all we're doing is like
picking what that procedural animation
is
right
um and that to me seems like very sane
uh
so
you know
i think we can just kind of go forwards
with that and say like maybe let's start
by renaming this so it's a little
clearer and we just say this is entity
animation
um and we have like animation planted
right animation hopping
and animation floating
and so we just preserve pre preserve
nice
we just preserve what we have right now
but we're going to name it something
else and move it kind of into a
different
place in the code kind of conceptually
so that now we know that that all this
is doing
is driving like that the visual of it
but it but it has
no like what you set this to
will have literally no bearing on the
game
at all right like it's literally just
going to be about what you see
when you
look at the game
right
um
i apologize
for the allergies
um and then the movement will be totally
different uh so so we won't have yeah
like we're not gonna have like any of
this stuff or any of that stuff the
movement's just gonna be a list of cells
and the transition speeds that you go
through so basically like
how long does it take you to
uh begin your transition how long does
it take to transition and then how long
does it take to end right so basically
those like edges that i was talking
about
um like starting hopping hopping and
then finishing hopping or whatever
right
okay so if we go ahead and start
changing these up uh and we just
basically go through and and
uh change movement mode here to
animation
in fact we could change
the literal
word
movement mode
and now i just go through and change
that so
uh
i think we can do like a
a replace i don't remember how to do a
replace i basically never do a replace
is there a place uh query replace
i guess
replacing all buffers
movement mode
with animation
um
and think that's really all we did yeah
so i replaced that
and now it's it's you know called
animation
and so now what we would want to do is
uh go through and
sort of separate out those two
pieces right
uh and if you remember
which you don't i mean
who am i kidding
if you remember uh
when we're doing like
update and render entities there's
basically like this code that does that
sort of breakout
not the video game breakout but
basically like this animation loop so
you can see it right in there
uh this right here is sort of the thing
that handles like how some how something
is supposed to animate right
and
what i'd like to do here is
i would like to make the animation be
something that's just driven off of a tv
variable which it currently is that's
controllable directly by the game
[Music]
i and that just the transactional
movement system will just drive that t
variable
right
um and so i'd like to basically move i'd
like to move this out
i don't remember that um
i guess
you can stomp the enemy
uh i i do remember vaguely adding that
um
i should change internal to function one
of these days i now just type function
there like i now just use that
there are reasons why that's not as good
but
you know
mainly the reason is because it's a
it's actually a
pragma
for
visual studio to define like
um intrinsics like memset
so
you know
so if i want to have this animation
stuff uh now that we kind of know that
it
or not no but i believe i sort of know
how it's going to break down a little
bit better here what i'm going to do is
i'm going to grab the animation stuff
you can actually see like
yeah there's a bunch of things about
this but um if i just go ahead and grab
this animation stuff here and
grab it out to here
in this sort of separated function what
i'm going to do is now just have like a
a
an idea a place here where we say
uh how this stuff is supposed to go and
we'll probably
uh not do this anymore
so
what you can see is the way that this is
li the way that this
code is written
is it effectively assumes
you can see a lot of stuff that's
happening here right
but what you can see is that this
animation stuff
is basically structured
so that the animation itself controls
how fast like this is actually occurring
um
sorry there was a question from a
simulator right now and i just want to
see could you please at some point
explain what internal external function
and static
uh sure yes i can um
so this is what is the actual
uh
c code
internal or function is just a pound
defined to be static
the reason for that is that static
itself is used in multiple places
and it can mean very different things
so
here are the three ways you can have
static
one is in front of a global variable
one is in front of a function
and
one is inside a function
the primary reason for pound defining
static to something else is i don't ever
like to type it in
because
it does not let me search
conveniently for this usage specifically
this one
this usage is generally you should never
use for any reason
this is a usage which says that this ver
value persists inside this function
as a
persistent value when the function
when you were inside the function right
and it persists to the next call of the
function as well right it's a global
variable but that's local to this
function
um these are extremely dangerous
and they're dangerous for a number of
reasons
the first reason they're extremely
dangerous
is because the definition of the sea
spec and seas plus specs is full banana
cakes and says that this variable will
not actually get initialized until you
call the function
the reason that's full banana cakes is
that because it means that depending on
what the compiler that you're using
happens to decide to do
it might introduce code that's
completely nuts and bad to guarantee
that that happens
and you end up in a situation where you
have weird multi-threaded race
conditions about who updates the very
who uh starts
the initialization of the variable or
you add extra code to prevent that
because the compiler's adding code to
make sure that that works properly and
that code is bad or like slow or at the
very least locks up your threads
uh similarly once you have it here if
you're calling this from multiple
threads now you don't really have any
guarantee that this line of code for
example in here what's going to happen
it's not going to yield an atomic so it
means that your increments of this
variable are wrong if multiple threads
call the function
so this is a very bad thing to have
happen and you really don't ever want to
do it unless you were very very
intentional about it and you'd want to
know everywhere in your code that did it
so the goal of pound defining static is
to make sure that you no longer use it
and you use something like
this
which is our pound defined for static
that we would use in this scenario so
that we could search for it anywhere
that it actually happens right
now
why do we need to put static in front of
either of these because otherwise you
really wouldn't need to right i mean
what's the difference between that and
that like for our purposes very little
right
well the answer is that
when you are compiling something
the c and c
spec again being bad uh
they have really bad problems with
linking
most programs take forever to link if
you were to look at something like the
unreal engine or
you know
some large code base
like llvm
or something like this
they have massive link times
like
it takes forever to link
and a lot of the work that's being done
is in exporting a crap ton of symbol
names
out from the compilation process to the
linker
gathering those up in the linker
merging comdats like doing stuff like
link time code generation or or you know
inlining
and just processing all this garbage
it's complete waste of everyone's time
none of it should have happened it's
just because the spec is bad and
continues to be bad and nobody really
knows what they're doing so it never
gets fixed as a result putting static in
front of these
is a fast way to tell the compiler not
to export any of these symbols
because we use a single translation unit
build for the most part it means that we
don't need to export basically any of
our symbols so we can quickly alleviate
that burden on the compiler of producing
the symbol table that it's going to
export to a linker
because we can tell it that we're not
exporting anything to a linker right
and so it just helps keep compile times
down
by ensuring that you don't actually have
this problem
uh if that makes sense
so really all of this stuff is just to
make sure that all that stuff goes well
and really it's all about managing
arbitrary compiler stuff
um
because
just the history of c and c plus plus is
such that you should never ever trust
the compiler
you can never trust the people who write
the spec or the compiler ever
even if they happen to be doing
something okay now they probably will
screw it up next time right
so really what you're trying to do is
just make sure
[Music]
um
that you are in a position to work
around whatever latest garbage they end
up doing
right
so that's what we do here and again it's
just to make sure that we're doing the
best possible thing that we can
to try and help the compiler know that
it doesn't need to send anything to the
linker
so martin's what does c plus plus 11 and
up do with multiple threads that go into
a static variable
like what do they do
what did they expect would happen now
i'm i shudder to ask
yeah but putting locks around it's
terrible
right
or that like just putting locks into
your code that you don't know what kind
of locks they even were right
i mean that's kind of what i was saying
like it's really bad if they put locks
in there
well it works in one sense but it
doesn't work in another sense right like
again describing something as working
doesn't really
it's not really true
just because it produces the correct
result if
if part of the thing was how fast this
thing was supposed to run or whether it
would have any weird behaviors you know
having locks suddenly in there is not
you know what you would want
that said it's not impossible for
you know
it's not impossible for it to do a
reasonable thing because since you can
just do a
check that doesn't take a lock first and
only take the lock if the check fails
then it's unlikely to be particularly
bad but still it's just
in general you should never have
anything that has anything to do with
threads happen that you don't control
it's just a bad bad idea and so i would
still stand by my original statement of
like you don't ever do that
if you want those things you should
write them yourself so that you know
what was happening and when
um
so
uh
let me go ahead and
um
i always imagine local static variables
as being the same as global static
lifetime wise only difference is the
variable's only available
yeah that's not how it works
um
so
it's basically like
there it says that it won't actually get
initialized until you enter the function
i believe
or at least that's how it was so it's
not quite the same
right it introduces code that wouldn't
ordinarily be there it's not
automatically hoisted
right meaning it's not the same
that is not the same as that even if x
is only used inside this function
uh because of the fact that you know
i well i don't know why i don't that's
how i would have defined it right
i think it's because in c plus they want
you to be able to do this
right
um
i mean technically it'd be that right
they want to be able to do this and they
want this to only be called when you get
here so that this thing that does like
17 000 things in the middle of its
constructor
it has to be
like only happen when you go in there
it's all stupid you know
it doesn't matter
here's what i'll say don't use statics
inside functions is the best rule of
thumb you never need them for anything
so i sometimes throw they're in there
for debugging purposes like if i'm doing
something quickly and that's totally
fine other than that just stay away from
them you never need them for anything
there's no point to them just make a
global variable if you need it
that's it it doesn't do anything
it just causes problems so i would just
stay away from it um
it's fine right
so
yeah and martin's that's what i would
exp that's what should have probably
been the definition of this thing like
they probably should have only had that
where it's just a scoped global variable
that can't really call any function
stuff and if it does call stuff it
happens at startup that's how i would
have done it i wouldn't have done what
they did
i know why they did it that way but as
usual i think they don't really know
what they're doing
all right so let's go ahead and finish
up what we're working on here
so we need to pass in a sim region so
that we can do queries uh that's
probably true in general uh i would say
so i don't know that i need to remove
that maybe we should i don't know
oh stomp on entities
so we we actually preserved even the
call to stomp on entity we just don't
let you stomp on an entity yet
i mean because you can't really stomp on
an entity
because you're not allowed to hop into a
square that has an entity in it but i
guess
maybe that was a thing that's kind of
cool
[Music]
i mean that's really kind of neat
uh
so hey maybe that's gonna be a thing
like i don't know it doesn't matter at
the moment but that's kind of neat um i
do i do like that
uh
i don't think we really want this
bit here but
like we do probably want this to happen
but i don't think we would want to
actually like
have to call phil unpacked entity at
this particular time
so i don't know about that uh that
that's probably a bit of a bridge too
far so i'm gonna go ahead and say that
we don't probably pass assets there it
seems like that's maybe a bit
far-fetched
uh but we'll see so anyway
um the same is kind of true of particle
cache like that part's a little bit
strange
um
i don't know like spawning particles
like i don't know to what extent we want
this to happen here maybe we do
um
because this is animation and that's
what particles are so you know uh yeah
um
so yeah what i was trying to say before
is basically this like this idea of like
t movement
i think that wants to be outside
because i think animations just want to
be driven off of the t value and i don't
think they should ever actually have
uh
you know even this yeah like this is not
really in the right place you're gonna
see it this is not you know it should
just be basically about this uh edge
transition that's happening here
and
we want that to kind of be handled
outside in like the
closing edge of what's happening in this
particular
uh entity
um so that's yeah we're kind of gonna
have to like think through
um how we want that to happen
and so yeah i mean we'll we'll get there
it's gonna be a little bit of a
reorganization as we kind of go through
and figure out how we want all these
things to sort of weave together uh but
for the most part it's like you know
we're just trying to make it so that
these things make reasonable sense
uh as they uh you know
as as animation versus event
uh we would rather separate the
animations and events a little bit uh
again to make it easier on ourselves to
to write sort of the animations and use
them more broadly across many different
circumstances that might have different
events happening
and that sort of thing
okay
so
oh i gotta stretch it out as far as i
can stretch okay
um
kwmr like that's really bad if that's
what they're doing if local static
variables use thread local storage to
execute that's like terrible right
thread local storage is like very slow
it's like a double indirect lookup first
you have to look up the gs segment value
for the table and then you have to look
up the index off of that table so like
you would never ever want to use thread
local storage for anything
that you don't absolutely have to right
um
so like if that's actually how they
implemented it that sounds terrible
um
so that would be yet another reason not
to use static variables if if that's
really how it's being done because
that's a terrible terrible idea in my
opinion
um
just absolutely horrible
all right uh so
if we look up uh this update animation i
guess what i'm trying to say is like all
right so if the animation hopping stuff
like you can see like we could just say
oh well so there's the animation
floating stuff and maybe we just do
exactly the same thing
so we just say like all right if there's
a two and a from
uh place that we're going here
then all we really have to do is just
uh do the movement two and the movement
from
it's just floating so it just it's just
a linear interpolation or whatever right
and maybe we want like
you know some better stuff than that in
the future but for now we don't really
care till we look a little bit
um
more closely like what
we want to do you know what i mean um
so
here we could just say
[Music]
clamp01
uh and just use the t movement variable
to
move us you know float us between the
places that we're going
uh just
you know
not in a particularly
interesting way or anything
uh
and now we just need these oops
uh now we just need these guys as like
like these guys could now move i think
um
well no that's not quite true so
we need to regularize this a little bit
more
but what it's going to say is now these
guys could move as long as we go to the
brain controller and just say okay the
brain now picks like
somewhere for them to go
right
um
so yeah so really
oh boy
there's so much stuff to do here i mean
it's like yeah i mean we just really
haven't spent any time on this code and
just there's so many things we can do
and we should probably just start doing
them all because they're all kind of
interesting and
uh
game like
so
you like the floating head things
wouldn't
step on buttons right and so if we
basically have the button stepping code
be in here yeah i mean
right there's just so much stuff we can
do now so let's start to try and work
through this slowly uh we have a
tremendous amount of stuff what time do
i have to start
my dinner stuff i gotta i got at least
an hour of programming i can do here
um
so anyway uh looking at at what's going
on here uh
let's ignore the glove for now because
that's kind of a new thing let's just
look at the um
whatever those floating head things are
called
i i don't actually know um what they're
uh i think they might be one of these
uh
i mean they're not the familiar anymore
but i think that is
what they're
doing
um
yeah and so so these
oh boy
there's so much cleanup to do here right
um
you can still swap your head with ground
towels uh yeah you can swap your head
with
what did we do there was something that
we did that was just a joke that you
could swap your head with
what even was that uh i know what you're
talking about there's like a whole we
added a thing where you could hit a
button and swap your head out with
something
do you guys even remember i don't
remember anything about that other than
like that we did it
uh
it was with the enemy but i don't what
was do you just hit return
i don't even remember like what you hit
but yeah there was something like that
there we go
basically any
uh nearby entity that's not
a
static tile you can just grab as the
head
can you get a tree probably not because
that's not an nd
um
you may be can you get like an orphan
so you can't get an orphan
so i don't know what our check was our
check must have been something like
that prevented you from getting a like i
can't get a cat head
which seems ridiculous if you're going
to have this feature you should be able
to get a cat head right
i mean do we want to target the furry
demographic or don't we here dude you
should be able to get a cat head on
um
so
yeah i don't know what what we're
actually checking for
i don't even know i don't know what this
code is doing i have no idea
um
so that code will just be removed though
uh like that's not gonna stay right i
don't even know what we put that in for
it was just something for fun i guess i
don't know
i don't know what the what the heck we
were doing
um yeah so like basically i grabbed that
thing
i can grab the other thing too looks
like
like now i've got like
a rib cage
as my
head
which doesn't seem particularly good
uh so anyway i don't know what the heck
that code is for
uh it's funny
i guess there's that um
but i don't know that it's particularly
good
thank you for opening the door for us
that was very nice of it
oh i'm also now lighting up the world
because these guys have a light attached
to them i forgot about that
enough substitution no there's only 766
subscribers i said i wouldn't do a react
streamless or 2 000 subscribers there's
no way that will ever have that many
subscribers
by design i picked a number we will
never have so that there's no chance i
have to do a react.js stream so
don't even think about it it's
impossible it was picked to be
impossible
yeah so i guess that code
uh must just like pick
it must just pick like the
the closest thing
gosh i don't even know like the closest
thing that
uh
[Music]
that is a head that is marked as a head
but those ground tiles wouldn't be
um
so it looks like you can swap it with
anything that has a brain
right
so it looks like as long as the thing
has a brain you can swap with it i guess
the reason you can't swap with the npcs
is right now they just don't have a
brain assigned
so
yeah i don't know i i would assume that
probably we just want to turn this off
it's not really something that should be
happening right
um
so we'll we'll nerf that from now
um but who knows if it will come back
right so now you can't you can't grab
arbitrary crap
all right so what i was trying to say
before is just that like
you know we now have to start thinking
how we're going to do the actual
movement transactions and we want those
movement transactions to have like
more consistency and more logic to them
and so let's start trying to make this
happen so
effectively any given entity is going to
have a movement
uh operation that they're currently
doing and that movement operation is
going to have some you know
some rules to it right i
and there's also like kind of
there's some kind of interesting
questions here too about like what do we
actually want how do we want to
represent things like a glove strike
that happens across multiple squares
do we want to just have that be a
movement that like basically cues up
like here are the squares that are going
to be
you know
i need to think about this for a second
because like if we want this thing to be
about like patterns like that
then i do wonder if you want to do
things like when you hit the strike
when you do something like execute a
punch
what it's really saying is we're going
to cue
this
pattern right
of
cell to cell movements
and the same would be true for like
enemy attacks
and like once you commit to one of them
it like has to follow through
right
um and like maybe there are ways for you
to interrupt that
sometimes and maybe there are times when
it cannot be interrupted right like
like maybe sometimes
maybe certain glove attacks
if it turns out that the attack if if
like the attack is fairly lengthy like
it you know it spans nine cells that it
does or something
maybe like certain kinds of attacks you
can't interrupt in the middle if they're
going poorly and you don't and you want
to recall the glove to do something
maybe you can do that
and maybe other times you can't and so
it's like a big deal like
if this glove is an interruptible glove
that's like potentially like a big deal
because it means that you can start an
attack and then not finish it
it turns out to be going poorly
whereas other gloves maybe you know and
there's like trade-offs like oh there's
a more powerful glove but it cannot be
interrupted so once you start an attack
that attack will go through i kind of
like the sound of that so i feel like
maybe what we do is we say like there's
like a move cue
where
you know there's like this
like this move
that you've queued up and it's getting
executed and it sort of
has properties that are gameplay related
right
um
like to me that sounds good and so i'm
just gonna maybe do that because i don't
see a reason not to so like maybe what
we do is basically say look you queue up
you
create a cue
of
tiles that will get occupied by this
thing or attempt you it will attempt to
occupy these squares
and then the system just tries to do
that and they are marked as whether or
not you might may or may not be able to
like
interrupt them
i guess my only question now is where
does that live do we have a move cue
that's basically
separate from entities so like moves go
into the move queue
and they are
generally dealt with
um
uh tin spin yes of course you can
i mean you can make a thing that runs on
xp and windows 10 if you want to
just make sure you don't link with
anything from windows 10 that isn't in
windows xp
and anything that you want to use in
windows 10 you do a get proc address
load library get proc address and only
use if you find it
right that's how you would do it
um
so yeah my my feeling on this is like i
think this all sounds good my only
question is where does that move cue go
and there's two ways you could do it one
way is each entity keeps its own move
queue i think that's kind of wasteful
because most entities in the system
don't move like they're like ground
tiles that don't move
so that seems stupid so what i would say
is probably there's sort of this
separate idea of move cues the move cue
there's just you know some bunch of
64 move cues or whatever like the brains
the brains hold the move cues or
whatever and so brains have the move
cues in them and you only get assigned
to move queue if you actually have an
active thing at that time right
so my guess is it's more like you know
there's this brain thing
and these brains
if i remember correctly the brains kind
of like
do
they get assembled
like over time right like they
they
they get assembled at you as you start a
particular simulation
you basically get like a brain
slot assigned to anybody who's doing
you know active stuff which is the only
people who would need to move q anyway
because if you don't have
an ai attached to you how you wouldn't
know to move
anyway
um so i'm assuming that that would be
fairly safe and so if you look at the
sim region
i believe what happens is that inside
the sim region itself uh why can i not
jump to sim region
i hate the way this works i wish that it
someone would fix it i don't i can
probably try to fix it myself but like
why would you ever want to jump
like this thing needs to say which one
is which right like it needs to say
whether this is the forward declaration
of a type
or the actual type and it should
severely pessimize the forward
declaration because you basically never
want to go there right
it don't make no sense
yeah it's just really inefficient
anyway so the sim region here
what we have is this um entity hash
and brain ash that get built up and i
believe that the only place that brains
ever actually exist
is like in here
you know what i'm saying
they
therefore like we the problem that we
would have is
you can't store these move cues anywhere
because they don't really exist there's
nothing that persists from frame to
frame right
which is kind of
not super useful
so like the question is like where do
you want that stuff to live and of
course like it can live in the entity
like we said
um but it just seems wasteful to put in
the entity
i mean i guess we could put it in the
entity and say well the entities are
going to get compressed anyway
and that stuff gets thrown out when the
entity is packed
so
as long as it stays unpacked it's in the
active set and would need the move queue
if it gets packed then it's not going to
move anyway
so it doesn't need to move anymore i
mean that's
a thing you could say
but what i would really prefer is just a
coherent notion of a move cue that just
exists over time
it's pretty hard to know though
like the handmade hero code does this
nice thing where like you can basically
have worlds be as large as you want
which almost nothing
ever supports
and so
one of the downsides of doing something
like that
is you would have to decide what happens
to a move cue when you are not really
simulating that part of the world
presumably you just throw it out right
and so that kind of suggests one of two
things either the move cues
are just in the entities
and then when they get
packed they just get tossed i mean you
ca right so
um
so when you look at handmade entity
right you can you can see like there's
this thing at the bottom which is just
like crap that doesn't get stored
and so really like maybe that's just the
answer to how most of this stuff works
and you just don't bother overthinking
it right you just say look
there's a move cue the move queue is
like
um
where you're gonna go these these entity
traversal points which at this point now
we could actually get rid of these
so these are totally not necessary
anymore
because we basically are just on a grid
now
you know what i mean
and so while we're on a grid we don't
need the flexibility of traversable
points we could just use the grid index
index
right
uh so the traversable points are not
really interesting and we can simplify
this code tremendously and probably
should
but for now
let's just say that we're not going to
do that and so
what we would say i guess
is
the traversible point id so the this
right
um
there's just some like big old list of
these
32 is probably not
something we would want um
but so let maybe like 16 or whatever but
um there's just a list of those and
anytime you're going to do a movement
um
you push it onto the queue and that is
what that is right
and
you know if we were going to be
the kind of people who do things
that are things that you do when you're
this kind of person
you might also say that there's like a
move cue entry
uh struct and that has the traversable
entry in it
um
that's like the destination
and then also like some crap in here
like
is it interruptible
you know what i mean
so you'd have like these move q entries
you said like okay are we allowed to
interrupt this particular
move or not
and
then when you have like control input
that comes in
you can look to see whether or not
you're actually able to interrupt the
thing
that you're currently doing and if you
can then you do you clear the move queue
and at and change the movement request
um
but
but like otherwise you
you just have to keep doing it right
yeah so i don't know i'm just gonna go
ahead and say like that's fine and maybe
that's just what happens
um
is john still streaming counter-strike
by the way
does anybody know
no
it's over
who won
or is there only one match today how
does counter-strike work
how did the finals work do they are
like is it multiple days of stuff or
whatever
multiple days of playoffs final best of
three today
so like are they going to play another
match later on today
or
okay so so it's already over and like
phase one
won the the thing
i see
all right
yeah well simulator i i that that that
thought had crossed my mind as well
so uh back to our program so if we add
this move cue thing in here also what
the heck does move spec
do now nothing right
um so we should be able to get rid of
that
and just like
you know sort of
squanch that away
and then
we don't use introspection anymore so i
don't know why that's there
let's get rid of all that
oh
all right
um
okay back to our show
so what we want here is we want a way to
yeah like you know okay
so you know you're doing this stuff and
you're hopping around
and all that good stuff
and i assume
although i don't really know that pretty
much what you would do here is
when you don't
uh
like the glove needs to sort of not
really occupy the squares that the glove
moves through because it's not supposed
to block motion
in those squares
probably like the glove is sort of like
ethereal
right
so like
again this is just this is really game
design unfortunately but you know it is
what it is so like if we imagine what's
got to happen here like this glove kind
of has to be like just kind of floating
next to the hero sort of tucked in there
more or less
probably like that's
it's too high up right now as well and
probably needs to be like right there
basically
just sort of in there
and
when you hop from one square to the
other
the glove has to just be like wherever
you are and it can't really
uh
occupy
[Music]
these
squares
which is probably fine
so again
i apologize i'm really just trying to
think this through for the first time so
i don't really know what's supposed to
happen here like i'm just kind of making
this up right
but for
you know
for the most part here what we're
talking about
is
when you do stuff
in here
and you hop from one place to another
um
this pdc nonsense has to be replaced
with something that actually has an idea
of where the heck this thing is going to
go
furthermore entity
ddp like wouldn't be a thing
because all of the animation would have
to be procedural now like maybe we would
have a ddp
um
in there somewhere
for like
matching visual consistency stuff it's
not like we would totally not have that
right
um
but in general
in general like we would just be saying
you move from one square to the other or
whatever
so
my guess is that what should happen here
is that whenever you hop from one place
to another your gloves should hop to
where toward wherever you are
at right
so if we look at the glove
um
and we say okay if the glove
move q count
equals zero
that means there's nothing that it's
like trying to do right now
and so it can have
the place where the hero currently is
we can just push that on as the place
it's going to snap back to
and like in the future we probably want
that snapback to be to have to actually
traverse but for now maybe i'll just
have it go direct
um
for whatever reason
like
i don't know
um
i also don't know why this glove thing
is inside the part where you have to
have a head and a body because it seems
to me
uh like that's not necessary so i'm
assuming that you could really just do
like as long as there's a body and a
glove
um
then
you
do something
or something
so here you would say
the glove
like
place that it's
trying to go
um
yeah all of this stuff would go away god
we just there's so much cleanup we have
to do now
um
the glove place that's trying to go
needs to be set here basically so if the
move queue count is zero
um then it would push one onto there
um
this is all nonsense
okay
so i think we need to sort of
fundamentally change a little bit of the
stuff to put us in a position to be able
to write this kind of code quickly and
like the way that we want to do it right
um
this code should look something like
if the move q if the move
q count is zero
then
if
yeah and i don't know like maybe this is
kind of like well no i don't know
um this stuff probably needs to be like
more about how we execute the move cue
um
and and honestly that move cue might
need
more
like the actual move cue en tree
might be the thing that you
uh
put the animation type in right
um
i
so we kind of have two separate issues
here and i don't really know one of
them's pretty straightforward so what
we'd want to do here is basically say
look we put a move on the m move cue
that's if you know if you are not if the
glove is not
where the player is then it moves to
where the player is right
the harder part is saying what does that
actually mean
because
the glove
[Music]
in addition to moving
needs to know that it should be like
relative to the player's position
so we also want to set like a relative
like relative to the square
gosh i don't know about that
the part about the
glove like where it should appear on the
tile is a little more complicated to me
but i guess
maybe what you say there is
that it is sort of that is like a
separate thing that happens with the
facing direction or something
do we have sound effects at the moment
um
[Music]
yes
but i think they may be turned off
at the immediate moment like if that's
what you mean
let me see
so
i'm pretty sure that there should be a
sound uh in this play sound thing here
so uh
let me see if
that's actually turned off at the moment
because it might be
uh
we probably do want that to be on
at the moment
just
because
uh we're gonna want to start like having
that be in there right so
this thing output playing sounds
i don't know like we may have
we may have basically like nerfed this
somehow i just don't remember like
because you know when we were doing
development before we may have wanted to
turn it off
uh
you know i i again i really just don't
remember like what we did there but it
looks like it's still hooked up so get
sounds game get sound samples
uh is still being called
right
um and so i think
i think all of this stuff should still
be working now the thing that i don't
actually know is
whether we actually
have this
baked in this blue
sound right i don't actually know
if that's
um
if that's actually being built it looks
like it is right there's a bloop
uh wave file that you know maybe is in
here i assume it is
so we could look and see
like there's this play sound right
um so we could look and see if that's
actually happening but it looks like it
should sort of
be happening at least a little bit right
um so let me take a look
and i can see if if this is working or
not because i don't really know
so i'm gonna set a breakpoint at play
sound
so yeah we call this function uh it puts
a sound
uh onto the
it does it does like place a sound
onto the
[Music]
list here although that
that is not finding a sound so
i take it back like
basically this
get best match
uh asset that is actually not
working
so that's wrong um
it may be that asset audio isn't a thing
anymore
to be honest it's like the
i guess that part i don't really
remember
so it looks like sounds currently aren't
playing because we no longer look them
up
that's what it appears to be anyway
so in here like this
um
that
with tag bloop doesn't appear to
actually find anything
for whatever it's worth i
we
could look at the asset processor nope
um
so you can see here there's like this
hha asset sound that's coming in here
and you know
when it processes this audio import you
get
well i mean you get whatever you get and
presumably the tags
presumably the tags on it are set okay
but it doesn't look like it finds it so
so i'm not sure
why we don't get a sound there
but that's why so basically this right
here that tries to
find the sound effect
never finds it
um
and that's why there's no sound at the
moment
so if we go into this
uh this is the tag hash here right
um
so here's like assets by tag
uh and it's like trying to look this up
and
here's the
asset values that it's looking through
i and
this type value here
uh if i add a watch to it i can cast it
to
[Music]
what it thinks it is so that's a bitmap
so that's obviously
not gonna work
right
so basically like it's just not there
um
[Music]
it's just not the tag hash doesn't match
so
the reason that this is not playing is
because
that
was never
added to the import apparently
so
if we look for
in
the
envy system here
if we look for
the
way that we're getting these from other
stuff right so i guess the better place
to look probably would be an entity gen
um when you do the
hashes you can see like
what sort of hashes look like they're
just like
a thing and then the the tag right
um
you would think that that would be
correct so like asset body base asset or
whatever is how those normally are so
presumably
um
presumably that would work now as i look
at this
those are legacy categories supposedly
but yeah
um
as i look at this like the audio
tag right i mean that is what that
should do
and then you know bloop is up here
so it it looks to me like that should
have worked
you know
um and so that's why i said like i'm not
really sure the asset processor when it
presses an audio import and it goes to
do like what are the tags on this thing
you can see it sort of doing that
bit here
it sets the type to hha asset sound
but i guess i don't know if it inserts a
tag
for that right
um
so that's part
might be more interesting so let's look
like this is going to pass in the tags
here right
uh that it parsed out
so yeah like i do wonder
i just maybe no one's ever actually
passing that in
like it could be that
like there's that asset audio right
that's in end tags
um
and that tag is going to be in the
opposite order right so
it looks like it would happen the same
way though so i'm not sure why this
works
either i guess maybe because tags go in
the opposite order but if you look and
it's like okay it's gonna add
this basic category tag with whatever
the category is
you would think that would work so i
don't know it looks you know that code
is terrible like most of the asset
system is absolutely horrible right um
but it honestly doesn't look like as bad
as it is it doesn't look like it's
really doing anything all that
strange
um
so that's a bit
so that's a bit confusing as to why that
didn't work
right um
so so let's take a look here and see if
maybe there's
uh a little bit of a better
explanation for that because it doesn't
really look like it's doing anything too
stupid
but maybe it actually is
um
so you can see here like yeah
it would appear to be doing the thing
for the basic category right like it
doesn't seem
like it's doing anything weird there
um
so you would think
that that would probably work correctly
you know what i mean
um
it doesn't seem particularly
strange right doesn't seem particularly
strange
and by the way nomad pixel yet i really
like the the razer keyboards razer the
orange
[Music]
mechanical switches
they're like my favorite switches by far
but the build quality on razer
keyboards and the software is freaking
terrible i don't install their their
driver
and i have to buy new keyboards fairly
frequently because their build quality
is so terrible
so like if razer would just
stop being a terrible company and
actually just like produce high quality
versions of their orange switches that
work in a keyboard that doesn't require
a
freaking terrible piece of software to
use
they would be by far the recommended
keyboard that i would recommend but as
it is i can't really recommend their
keyboards because everything else about
their
company sucks
so i would actually say don't buy razer
even though i buy razer because their
company is literally that bad
um all right so
uh
yeah and please someday if anyone can
produce a keyboard that's like a high
build quality
non-driver based keyboard
that has something similar to a razer
orange switch in it
please
tell me
i will switch to your keyboards and i
will tell everyone else to switch to
your keyboards
mx brown is not even remotely similar to
a razer orange switch
it's not similar in any way
i have mx brown switch keyboards here
they are literally nothing like razer
orange switches even a little bit
uh i wouldn't even consider them
as
as related they're completely different
uh
mx brown and razer orange they are
nothing alike to type on
whatsoever
what's the difference is that they feel
literally nothing alike uh i don't know
what an actuation profile would actually
tell you because you know i can only say
what happens when you try to type on the
actual keyboard but
razer orange switches and cherry mx
browns do not feel anything alike
at all
um like you would never mistake one for
the other ever
unless you just don't
like have any perception of what's
happening with a keyboard for example
right
um
so
but basically like yeah razer orange
switches uh are the best switches by far
for like feel in my opinion
um
but they just don't like
the keyboard just kind of sucks
so what are you gonna do
zelio purple switches huh
um i would try that
like there's a lot of switches out there
right so for all i know there's like
like maybe those feel the same as razor
orange right
and if they do maybe i could find you
know
so so uh i haven't tried enough switches
i've tried some i one time try bought
one of those like
switch testing packs and none of the
switches felt like a razer orange in
that pack but it was still only like 10
different types of switches and there's
a lot more switches than 10.
so
yeah if somebody tries
uh if somebody who really likes razer
orange switches
tries
some other switches and ever finds one
that's close please tell me because i
would want to try it as well that's what
i would say so if someone does try the
zelio purples and finds that they are
feel the same or some quite similar to a
razer orange switch
that would be really nice to know
because i would love to be able to buy
a better keyboard than this keyboard
but have the same kind of
feel
so yeah please keep me posted if anyone
really does find one that feels like
razor orange don't just tell me to buy
some random switch because i don't
believe you like i want to know that you
actually tested them and feel like you
can't really tell the difference between
a razor orange and whatever this new
switch is
and then i would try it but only if
you've actually done that and can't tell
the difference like you blind taste
tested right
all right so
uh
yeah let's find out why our sounds
aren't launching because that's a good
thing to do at the end of the stream
today and the next week we can pick up
on animation or whatever
so here's the thing that like feeds
these into the asset tag hash uh this
whole system is just garbage now because
it's been through so many iterations and
we can't change the way we're doing
things but just because it's garbage
doesn't mean it doesn't work or
shouldn't work so it'd be nice to know
why like whatever is happening there
that's not actually working
um and so let's see if we can get some
kind of an explanation here
uh as to what's actually going on
so
we've got a
yeah i mean we've got a pretty
straightforward thing it's gonna stick
the type id in here which should be
you know asset audio
and maybe we should go in and just
verify that so like you know we can do
a thing where we base say when you see
an asset audio yo let's go ahead and
stop
right there we could even go one further
and say
you know if tag zero equals tag bloop
um
stop here as well and that way we can
just set breakpoints to see do we
actually ever
register these sounds that we're looking
for do they ever actually get loaded um
because if they don't then well you know
that would give us a clue right there to
what's gone wrong
so
inside here we've got some stuff
um
and i'll go ahead and set a break point
at these little little darlings
i don't think that's the right thing
it's not
that's not what i meant um
so what i actually want is
like
this
so here we can see that you know we've
got our asset audio
um and then we've got tag 0
and it looks like channel index
so maybe that's most of what's going on
here is that we just forgot that channel
index comes through first
right
and the sound comes in next
uh so we don't care about channel index
so that pretty much tells us everything
we needed to know
i
i don't know how exactly we want to
handle that
like what we want to do with channel
indexes
one thing we could do is strip them for
now
uh
the other thing we could do is sort them
to the end
i don't know
um
i feel like it should kind of go into
the match vector is what it really
should do
so that's kind of a tougher question but
like
so in here where we've got this you know
facing direction and variant
um you know i don't know if maybe like
this needs to have one more thing in it
that's
you know that's going to be the channel
or maybe the channel is sort of like
duplicative of that
uh like you know facing direction
and channel
are overlaid
i don't really know
um but you know you would basically say
that
for now anyway
we just do this
and that way you don't put the channel
index in anywhere you just kind of have
you know
um
what is it complaining about
there's an access violation reading the
tag
what
what are you talking about
show me that again
that makes no sense to me what is the
problem here
how did this end up being out of bounds
this should not have altered
the size of anything
right
like this should not have changed
this
uh any of this stuff
so i don't quite see why we would have
like i don't see why that would have
caused a problem just taking
channel index out of
i mean literally all we did was this
right
as far as i know because that's a
non-thing
i mean i'll verify that it's a non-thing
just in case
but because i want to make sure maybe
i'm missing something
so if i rebuild and
uh oops that was still running
so if i rebuild
and we don't have that extra define
presumably we still get get the error
and so what you're telling me is
literally it's just this
i am so confused now so what did we
touch i must have accidentally done
something
but how did we break that because
there's nothing here we didn't change
anything did we
did i accidentally typo something when i
was
not paying attention like this
can be restored to its
previous state right
and this
can be restored to us previously and now
there's no changes
so
explain to me what's going on
how is that possible
we didn't touch anything
this is the problem with programming on
stream like none of this stuff should be
happening but programming on stream is
just so incredibly difficult
and the code comes out so much worse
it's really kind of hard to
convey
just how much harder it is
than when you get to program
on your actual own
um
so all right
fine
whatever you say
so basically what we're saying is here
inside the hha when we actually iterate
over these we've got uh an you know a uh
a bogus
like
uh hha
tag overlay right like like the series
of tags
that we get is somehow
you know grotesquely incorrect right
um and so
you know when we uh step in here
i guess what we would expect to see
is that the assets
hha eventually gets these two values are
garbage right
so what happens is this
in here right we're gonna see this
become somehow
totally wrong
so this is what we expect to see just
like uniform
yeah so eventually we just get to one
that's just complete garbage like the
asset
that we're asked to process is just
complete nonsense
um
so like asset 173 is the garbage in this
case if we look at the assets
um we can see that that's not a
particularly high valued
thing right it's not like that's
somehow totally ridiculous
you know what i mean
um
so it's it's weird
that uh we would be having that problem
that early on in when we loaded you know
when we loaded the asset out
so it does seem a bit strange
and it when we're actually doing this
merge here when we load through these
files like something has gone horribly
wrong and somehow we did that by like
touching
this thing
just lightly right like we didn't do
anything
um
which is absurd but that's what happened
so you just have to deal with it right
um
so
what is going on here
what is happening in the chat do i need
to step in here
yeah it looks like you guys can handle
this on your own
anyway what i will say is that the
reason that open source software is bad
has nothing to do with the quality of
the software the reason open source
software is bad is because it exploits
workers
it's ridiculous that people who claim to
be like you know
uh pro
like pro worker or pro whatever would
ever support open source software
because all it does
is basically allow other people to
profit off of work they didn't pay for
that's literally the only thing that
open source has done as far as i can
tell like entire corporations that now
effectively control
most of the digital world
google facebook twitter whatever
they were all built off of work they did
not pay for
like 90 of the software at those
companies was done by workers who were
completely exploited in like the
traditional
like way that
karl marx would have been very upset
about right
they did a bunch of work
other people came and
basically took control of large swaths
of the economy using their work and paid
them either nothing or almost nothing
versus how much money they extracted out
of those pieces of software
that's what happened right and there's
no alternate read to open source than
that
period
that is just literally what occurred
so
that's really the only thing people
should be talking about with open source
right now as far as i'm concerned is how
to figure out how to stop workers from
being exploited because that is the only
thing happening in open source right now
that
that i can see at all
is people doing work
and getting completely exploited by
effectively like a managerial class that
takes their work for free and builds
adds very small amount of value to it
and takes all the money
right
so
that's what that's what open source
looks like to me that's what the story
of the world is right
um
so
so like solve that
that's the thing you should be talking
about not the software quality yet
because if as far as open source is
closed because i don't think open source
versus closed source is really
necessarily i don't think the the big
issue there has anything to do with code
quality that's that's a separate issue
that we could talk about and whether
open or closed source is better or worse
for that is kind of more of a thing
uh more of a subtle discussion
the fact that open source is massively
exploitative of of the working class is
undisputable in my opinion
like like there's no way you could
possibly make an argument that that's
not what happened because it's like so
overwhelmingly obvious
that people who did not do the majority
of the work now has the majority of the
money and power
and it was all thanks to open source
software right
so so you're going to have to figure
that out before we can have any other
discussion about open source in my
opinion because it's a huge problem and
completely
exploitative and unfair as it currently
stands
all right so
uh
so how the heck did this happen
what we need like a good
forensics that's like how did that how
did what i did
knock this like fairly precarious stuff
into a bad state right
like how did that happen that's a
strange it's a strange beast
right
um it's a strange beast there
whatever just occurred it doesn't really
make
um a whole lot of sense
right
so
i
so i guess i would say like
are we
is this something where we've where i
accidentally typed in some kind of a
weird like override bug or something
or did this
actually write some garbage to it i
don't actually know
again because this is a bit
um
yeah it's a bit weird here
right
so as the files
go
they've already been loaded so
you know the
this part here
so
i suppose that makes sense let's look at
what this is doing
so here we're just reading data from
file
here's the header
not sure i understand what that means
are those like
like
encoded in some ways that's kind of
weird right
uh keep it deeper is always the next uh
once early uh i just wanted to before we
get to that point i wanted to try and
find out
whether it was an actual change or
whether this is actually what's in the
file right because i don't actually know
what kind of bug i'm looking for at the
moment
um
so what does the file info say
all right so i guess that all is
actually what it actually
that all is just what it is right that's
all actually accurate
in theory
it's the intro cut scene
yeah like this stuff is just like way
too complicated right and that's what
happens this is why i say like stream
programming is terrible because like
this stuff should just be simplified
massively and if you were working on
this sort of thing full time you just
these kind of things get
resolved
they do not get resolved when you have
to program on stream and it's very
unsatisfying
uh so if we look at what all these files
actually are
once they've been loaded right
so now we're gonna
we're gonna like
make the merge thing we have the
internal one that pushes the size out
for that's just for adding stuff at run
time but we don't like that's not
actually
that wouldn't be happening if the game
was actually running as it normally does
right
so now we loop through these and we're
going to like
read the tags out of the files into
their final like destinations
right
um
and then we're going to read the assets
out
and adjust
the tags
uh which maybe is broken
[Music]
right
so it's after the it's this first file
does not have any errors in it right
because the asset count
we get through up to like asset 173 or
whatever
is just fine
so the file asset count for the first
you know for the first one here
um
this just is just fine there's no
right
like this will just work and it's only
once we get to the next file that's the
one that that would that is busted right
so in other words this part of the code
here we actually
like we can get down to this temp memory
block in theory right and it's just fine
and we have 170 assets all of which are
fine so it's only when we get to this
next part of the
shenanigans
right
that things go pear-shaped
and
we're loading like a bunch of assets
and a bunch of tags in here and we're
loading them
[Music]
out of this like tag base
uh which we guess i don't care
about that because really it's the asset
that's garbage
so we don't really care about the tag
loading now that i think about it it's
really just this at the moment
um so we look at file asset count and
we're like we're going to load
3113 or whatever out of this thing
uh so we
load it in
like so
um we load in the annotations
and then we loop through the assets like
one at a time
uh and
right there's a bunch of them
and we can see which global one we're
going to be on here
uh
at each time and we can look
at the source asset and the destination
asset right
um
it'd be this is what we were copying
so the hha asset is
what we've loaded out of the file and
it's this
uh
which is garbage
for sure
right so this this is just garbage
so for some reason this file it's just
it just has pure garbage in it i believe
um
so for whatever reason this particular
file is just is just messed up is there
any like which file is this this is the
base game file so somehow the base game
file got
totally borked
i mean
right
how is that possible we didn't do
anything
like we must have done something that
caused our file to get screwed up
somehow
but i don't know what we did that could
possibly have done that
so yeah i don't know that's that's a a
real strange one
although like apparently that one was
okay like am i misreading this
somehow
what is going on here folks
like how is that not
i guess the way this is working is that
you don't see the crash yet
or you don't get a crash yet because
since these two tags are the same you
don't process anything
because you'd loop between them
if you ever went to load the data it
would completely fail
right
so something has gone horribly horribly
wrong
with like our our
loading of
the hha file
the
the base game hha is somehow completely
destroyed
but we don't really have any idea why
that would be
right
meanwhile our cutscene hha file is like
fine
right
so did we actually like
so i don't know how we did that and i
don't
yeah
i don't know how we did that and i also
don't know like i mean
it doesn't make a lot of sense so i
guess my next question would be
so if we rebuilt it
does this problem go away meaning is
this did we just corrupt the file
somehow or is this nothing to do with
that right
so we run it and oops
we run it and we crash here and the data
looks like garbage that we're loading
out of the file
right um if we delete the base game hha
file so it's gone oops
uh and then we rerun the program
what happens
like because now it's just going to like
rebuild that h file
from scratch by loading all of the like
source assets and like smooshing them
together into a file
did we just break that at some point and
since we never bothered to like rebuild
these data files we just didn't see
that it was messed up because that's
very plausible right
um or is that not what happened so
there's it re it rebuilt the game asset
data right
um
and now if i go
i don't quite remember how any of this
stuff worked but basically i think you
just say
um
do i have to hit save or does it just
automatically save
i think it's just automatically saves
that
i'm not quite sure
looks like it automatically saves the
base game aj
so
um
so now we run it and it's right again so
like somebody corrupted that
so probably just bugs the incremental
update i guess we probably need to clean
that system up right i mean we've been
cleaning up all the other systems at
some point that one's going to be on the
table certainly
but it looks like that was the problem
so now the question is well if that was
the problem does that mean now that this
can be
restored so like if i do this again
and put back in the part that i
previously had to remove because
everything seemed to be totally borked
can we now
just include this
thing again
where'd it go
this
so this exact code that i wrote before
right
like so which should not have had any
deleterious effects
um it is
that
um
can we just run it and
expect to now
be back where we started with without
the weird bug
the answer appears to be yes
oh god
so there seems to be some audio tearing
and stuff in there there's also the fact
that apparently there's no actual stop
gap on that attack code
so that's a bit bad
um
but
now we're back to square one so that's
all fine
that was like launching like hundreds of
sounds which is not a good thing
to say the least
uh but
uh so yeah like if we want to
where is attacked
um
yeah you can kind of see like this is
just not
what you would want at all um to say the
least so you would want to do a thing
where you look to see if you were
weren't attacking previously so
this you can't really leave
like that
but otherwise it's fine
so we do have sound effects in there
currently we would need a way of uh
being a little bit more selective about
triggering them um but otherwise
you know no big deal
uh so i'll i'll take this out
temporarily because until we would have
a way to just do a single trigger we
probably wouldn't want
something like that to happen
uh
but
that's fine and then if we
go to like
i want to say
i want to say that the music
is a thing
um
[Music]
and we could restore that as well uh now
if we wanted to uh
again just to double check that this
stuff works at all which you know
some of it's kind of rotted
so we don't really need the
uh
match vector stuff quite exactly the way
it was here this is again not actually
necessary
uh but
if we've have it all so if we just go
like this
and say the
channel
[Music]
so
the channel zero id
and the channel one id are really just
gonna be tag uh
yeah i don't
know what we called this music or did we
even
include this music
um
[Music]
that
maybe we don't even have the music do we
is that even still in here
um
we may have to add
like a sound
we may have to add a thing for the music
because i don't actually know if it's
here at all
uh it kind of looks like it's not
so we might have to
look into
the
sources directory and just see if we've
got any music we don't
um
okay so we do have a music test web
there
and the music test web is an intro
cutscene so maybe we did put it in to
one of these hht's as just into yeah we
did
so it's tagged title screen
i don't know why but it is
um so we can do this
where we ask for
the
best match sound
and the asset match vector
we can pull out individual
channels
pretty trivially
we would just do
match element channel
equals zero
uh and then one and that would be how we
would pull out a stereo sound
right and all this stuff goes away
entirely uh and like it's much cleaner
now like we did clean up that part quite
a bit compared to what it was
uh so in theory that's the music
uh
why we're pulling out both channels i
don't know because we only play one of
them but i guess we were just
i mean i don't know
we're just playing around i guess
so you can see we're getting
a lot of tearing there
right
and i'm guessing that's because in fact
you know what i know it's because we
don't have sound on a separate thread
currently
right
so when the
uh
speed when the
when this speed is off then you're just
going to get tearing
so we probably will have to move sound
to its own thread soon if we want
to start playing with sound which we
probably do right
so for example if you take a look in
win32
so in here write this get sound samples
fill sound buffer you can see that it's
synchronous with the frame update
right
and so because we now don't hit 60 hertz
locked and probably won't
uh
during development at least
um
we would want to move this out
and that's a nice thing to do anyway
we are kind of already prepared to do it
because you can kind of see
like
while not entirely ready
well while we're not like really quite
there yet
um you can see in the audio stuff
when we're doing the sound that we do
have a separate call right so we've sort
of prepared
roughly for this eventuality you know
what i mean
um
but we're just not quite doing that yet
right so it doesn't like we can ask the
game for sound samples on a separate
function but
we don't
do that threaded and we have to do a
little bit of work here because
at the moment
this code would not be thread safe
uh because
of this loop
right
so like if you look at how this this
loop is working here you've got these
playing sounds right this is not you
know
gonna cut it
because if someone comes along and tries
to play a sound while you're in the
middle of iterating this would break
um
just one of the reasons why you don't
write things this way
but keep in mind you know this was old
code it was written
you know when i didn't really do very
much multi-threaded programming so it's
not what i would write today but you
know
that's just to be expected
multi-threaded programming is much
bigger now so i write most of my code
multi-threaded when i started handmade
hero that was not true right
um
so
so uh
we'll probably have to take
that
up soon
maybe let's leave this on
so that we'll maybe do that first thing
um
and that way we can have some sound
effects because we'd like to sort of get
that
part of the loop working and while we're
kind of doing the stuff of like okay
let's put in movement cues and
some sound effects and you know some
reactions that just sort of stuff we
probably just want all that stuff to mix
together so we'll just kind of do like
basic threading of the audio layer um
and uh
[Music]
and basic sort of like movement
resolution stuff and we'll call that
like our next kind of goal right like
sort of making it feel more gamey doing
game like things
and cleaning up the code
uh
in the places that we need to to make
that reasonable
um i'm gonna call it
there
and i mean yeah i'm gonna call it there
so i don't have anything else to say
besides that's the end of it
if one wanted to spawn a second window
how would one go about tackling it
um
i i mean i don't really know what you
mean obviously you can just
create
call create window twice
uh
i don't really understand the question
there's some nasty stuff that opengl
just kind of sucks for stuff like that
so opengl is really annoying
because it's hard to do things like
render to multiple windows
um
unnecessarily
i so you ha
you can do opengl with two windows it's
just it's just ugly you have to unbind
and bind to the different htc but it
works i do it all the time um
directx is easier because you can just
target a specific window right it's not
difficult
um but either way there's not a lot to
it you just open a new window and then
whatever you're going to do to render
you do it to one window and then you do
it to the other window that's it
it's really there really isn't much to
it
i mean if it helps you can even think of
it as not really being two separate
windows you can think of it as rendering
one big thing and then just putting part
of it to one window and part of it to
another right
so
um
so anyway
let's
yeah let's call that a day
i'll be back here next weekend to look
at that
uh but i think we're good to go right
um i think we are
good to go
oh
what's the problem with exploitation of
the working class really an open source
problem you still can have a commercial
licensing on an open source code right
uh well no let me be clear
i'm just telling you what happened
right you can hypothesize if there might
be solutions to the problem but who
cares i mean
so if you can solve the problem then
great go solve the problem but the
problem currently is that's what
happened
so
it's really no good saying well you
could have done open source differently
and this wouldn't be a problem well okay
great but you didn't right
so anything that someone says about open
source being able to work properly so
that people don't get exploited
is purely speculative
right
so if you can go demonstrate it great go
go ahead and do that
uh and then we're great
but so far nobody
period has
done this
the only thing that's happening in open
source right now is like massive
exploitation of working programmers
to this day that is all that's happening
in open source anywhere as far as i can
see even the people who are getting paid
to work on open source are getting
massively
underpaid to do it compared to how much
the people who are using their code are
making right
so you can say that there are solutions
and great i hope there are
but until someone actually demonstrates
that those solutions work it's kind of
the it's the standard like real
communism has never been tried argument
well i don't really care about something
that you say hypothetically works but
that you haven't demonstrated actually
does so someone has to actually prove to
me that open source can work and thrive
while still properly allocating the
correct amount of payment to the people
doing the work in my opinion before i'm
willing to say that it's any good
because so far
all it seems to do to me is a massive
transfer from labor
to management
that's all i see
right
um and i have seen nothing else happen
economically with open source other than
basically like a massive transfer of
wealth from programmers to managers
so
that's that's what happened
can it be fixed i mean i don't know
probably i mean anything can be fixed if
you
work hard at it but will it be fixed i
doubt it
certainly there's no indications that it
will change at all in the near future
it's going exactly as it was going
right
so i am not optimistic about the
prospects of open source as a
fair economic model because the only
thing it's currently doing is
transferring wealth from programmers to
managers and i see
the only thing i see is that trend
accelerating if anything
um because as a generation of
programmers has basically been duped
into thinking that their hard work
should just be given away for free
it becomes increasingly difficult
for people
to
argue that you shouldn't release your
code open source right
so until somebody actually is able to
turn this around i would say i think
open source is very very bad
it is currently like the very worst
thing currently going
because it is so incredibly exploitative
it's far more exploitative than any
actual company is right now of the
workers who work at the company
um
open source is way more exploitative
than that right now
uh and that it should be considered a
great cause for concern
for basically all
um
you know of
for anyone who wants to see people
fairly compensated for their labor and
not
have their labor exploited to produce
power centers that they then are subject
to themselves right
because that's what's currently going on
like working programmers are creating
code they're releasing it for free use
on the internet and then people use that
code without really compensating them
almost at all sometimes they compensate
them a little bit usually it's not very
much
certainly it's nothing compared to the
power that then is accreted by the
people who have co-opted that work
thanks to the open source model
and then basically then what you get is
you know
you just get mark zuckerberg gets to
define how the internet works despite
having paid for almost none of the
software that his company actually
needed to make that work right
um
so that's just that's the situation
and
i
until i see someone proving that there's
a solution in practice
i i just don't endorse open source
anymore
right
i
would like there to be ways like like
for example models more like
uh you people who pay for the software
get to get a license to the source code
but all they are not allowed to do
anything with it
outside of
other people who have paid for it or
something things like that i could see
being useful
but like i really just don't see
we post stuff on github bed under a gpl
ii or lgpl or apache or mit license
that's just all that is is now it's just
exploitation that's all it is to me
um
because it's so obvious
like how
many very bad things have happened on
the back of these
workers who
basically produced the code necessary
for all of these companies to exist at
all they would none of them been able to
get started
facebook doesn't exist without php
apache linux
facebook would never even have gotten
day one without those people and now
those people who built all those things
i mean whether you think php sucks or
not facebook doesn't exist without it
the people who made php have no say in
what happens on facebook
they have no power at all they get no
decision-making authority they do not
share in the profits they basically just
get handouts that facebook decides to
give them if they choose to give them to
them at all and that to me is completely
unacceptable
it's just completely unacceptable
the people who do the work should have
the
just compensation for what they did and
they should have a fair voice in what
happens with their labor and
i don't necessarily go as far as
like a full marxist view of something
like that where
i think that
you can't have like a capital class and
investment and stuff like that
but my point here is this was done
without even the capitalism model
meaning nobody paid up front for those
people to make php
facebook did not pay them right so it's
not even like
it's it's
it's much more like feudalism or
serfdom than anything else open source
is these people just did the work and
got nothing for it they weren't even
paid upfront by the people who ended up
using it which is one of the rationales
for like the capitalist approach is that
well these people are providing you a
salary before you did the work so to me
that's a lot more fair here that didn't
even happen they are not getting a
salary they got nothing they did the
work for free originally and then were
completely exploited at the end of it
it's kind of like
if you took the worst of socialism and
the worst of capitalism and combined
them that's open source
right
it it like that's the only real way i
can think to define it it's like if you
took the worst aspects of capitalism for
workers and the worst aspects of
socialism for workers
and you put them together
you that's what you you get open source
it's it's the you get no power and you
get no money that's what it is right so
it's like the worst of both things
i i just don't know any way to say it
it's very very upsetting to me
right
greg inc i disagree uh just because
someone chooses to let you exploit them
does not mean you didn't exploit them
exploitation is true
objectively
it is not have anything to do with
whether someone was okay with it right
um
so it's exploitative period it doesn't
matter whether the people chose to be
exploited right
because you can't you can choose to be
exploited you can choose to be
submissive you can choose all those
things
nobody said it was coercive
but it's very exploitative
right
and for the record that's how most
exploitation works
most exploitation is about convincing
people that they're doing something that
they should you know convincing them to
do something that turns out to be very
bad for them and very good for you and
that's exactly what the open source
movement has turned out to be
right
so
so fix it
stop doing that
i i think there's some people who've
been trying different licenses like
there's a gpl license now right
um
that
you know you uh
requires basically it to maintain open
source even if it's used on like a
server or something like that
you know what i'm saying
cage betas uh yeah i mean i think there
is like there was a new gpl license
that's designed to fix the problem of
facebook right uh there's a new gpl
license that's like look if you use this
source code even if you run it privately
you have to release all your source code
as well
right that goes with it
agpl yeah um
and and that's really like
it's gonna you're gonna have to do
something like that if you want open
source to survive or you do the opposite
thing which is you have to pay a
reasonable payment for your open source
um or something
but but yeah the agpl is really the only
thing that i've seen so far that's an
attempt to fix these fundamentally
unfair compensation practices
because um
you know
it really just requires
a certain amount of legal enforcement if
you want the source code to be open
there has to be licenses
right
so
anyway i see it as a very bad situation
and people need to
really rethink how this is structured
it's not acceptable currently
it should be fixed
and the people who
who create these foundational pieces of
software that other
companies choose to use to build their
businesses on
they should be getting percentage
ownerships of these companies or
percentages of their earnings just like
a shareholder
right
um
because
the company simply could not have
existed without this open source
software
uh greg yes so so in uh well two things
first of all handmade hero is closed
source
um for starters right
so you have to pay to get the source
code and you cannot use it uh in your
own stuff
right
but
uh
the handmade hero
eventual thing was at some point after
the game is out i will eventually allow
the source code to be reused
i would not have made that decision
today right
uh and we certainly will never do that
with another one of our products but no
even handmade hero was not is not open
source currently
and again that's to try and strike that
balance is to say look this is like
actual
if you think this is useful you should
have to pay for it right because that's
the only real fair way to go
that said handmade hero is not really a
foundational technology so it's not
really similar the level of exploitation
that can happen based off of handmade
hero is not very
large
right
um it's not a fundamental technology
like something like a web server
so
um
the
the chances that i will get fairly
compensated for handmade hero are much
higher
right uh than the chances that you'll
get fairly
compensated for something like linux
if that makes sense
so
you know
even though handmade hero does have an
eventual source code release component
to it
it's also even though i wasn't
as concerned about source open source
then i still did think that it being
open source was not appropriate so
that's why i didn't do that
but yeah but like i said the the the
degree to which someone else can profit
off of handmade heroes source code is
very low anyway so it's not really it's
not a problem compared to something like
you know uh
open ssl or something right like
whatever things are that are like you
know if you're working in that kind of
space you know what i mean
uh arkandos there's generally uh the
the general rule for
stuff like that is it depends on the
license sometimes but in general
restraint of trade laws basically says
that like
people can't control your learning per
se
so like if you're not literally copying
code from one place to another you're
usually okay
right
um
restraint of trade laws basically say
that you know stuff that you learn while
you're working on something
you know absent very specific language
barring you from
employing that education elsewhere
um
you're really not liable
for
you know copyright infringement or
whatever it might be
uh so long as what you were doing was
you learned something and then you you
know repeated that learning somewhere
else legitimately right you weren't just
making an excuse you know what i mean
are you using any open source code in
your private card no we use literally
zero open source code currently
um
i was thinking of using bear ssl and
maybe at some point i might use bear ssl
in something but it turned out we ended
up not
no we do not use shawn's libraries
uh currently no we don't use opengl
um
but opengl also isn't open source
right
so
like the degree if you use opengl on
windows you're using closed source
no we don't use stb for fonts
i have my own font stuff
opengl also isn't an open spec
it is neither open source nor an open
spec
opengl has a lot of
very like contractual restriction things
there's
opengl is its own whole thing
it doesn't matter anyway because you
don't really need to use it anymore but
so basically it's fine if i learn from
your stream then close the stream and
implement something like you for example
downloading architecture but if i say
yeah i mean that's generally the idea
right is that like education you can't
really like
stop
and you know there's obvious good
reasons for that right like you know
otherwise there it would just be too
difficult
to police if people could claim that you
like learned to do something from them
and you weren't like allowed to do that
or whatever right it's pretty tough
so generally speaking the law tends to
expect that like
look if you don't want someone to learn
how to do something then you have to
keep it secret or you have to sign an
agreement with them that they won't go
do something like if if it was like some
kind of thing where like you know you
were working with me specifically and we
basically had a non-compete agreement
that like for five years afterwards you
couldn't go work on games or something
right so so that's tends to be more how
those things are
in general you don't have you know
protection for things
um
like learning if someone learns to do
something and they weren't copying you
they were just they learned to do stuff
and then they went and wrote their own
that's you know that's not considered
copyright infringement
um
right it can be patent infringement
certainly because if things are patented
then they're patented and there is no
defense
you just if you did the same thing then
you're liable
it's one of the reasons i don't like
patents because
that just seems too much but
um there are a lot of practical
drawbacks to opengl it's not as well
supported on windows it doesn't have as
good of like um
just general operating system support
for it uh like things like
multi-threading are harder etc etc so
you know for a very simple game like av
racer isn't asking a whole lot
um of the graphics subsystem so it's
totally fine but as you want to do more
complex stuff you probably really don't
want to use opengl
how to calculate how much to go to open
source project if i make profits in
percent let's say i mean we can't right
now that's kind of the point is there
like currently the answer is zero
percent you don't have to give anything
to them
um and i think that's just a very bad
economic model and so
you know it's not really up to you to
figure that out it was up to the
industry to like come up with a less
stupid model for how power and
uh money which are very intimately
related right like money kind of is
power in modern society to a large
extent
um
[Music]
because money fundamentally is a thing
that allows you to allocate resources
and that's sort of what power is right
so it's really kind of up to the
industry to fix it it's not up to you
it's not up to you to be charitable it's
up to the industry to
wake up and stop using this as a
fundamental model because it's
completely broken
so
um
and that's uh that's that
let's see what's going on
in raid land