hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream today I wanted to take a
second to show how to do something with
our memory system now that we have made
it so that the memory Rena's allocate
memory to the platform layer rather than
being passed the memory in through the
platform layer there is an additional
thing we can do now which we weren't
able to really do before that's kind of
a bonus so I thought I'd show you what
it was it is not a feature that really
is particularly relevant to the shipping
version of the game but it is a feature
that's relevant to debugging the game
and it's a feature that potentially
could have caught errors that we've
already had on handmade hero so in
general I think it's a worthwhile kind
of thing it's the kind of thing that
doesn't catch bugs all that often but
when a Dutch cat does catch bugs they
are bugs that would have taken you
probably a little while to find and so
it's kind of a valuable thing and it
doesn't take too much you can implement
it once and have it forever so it's not
like a thing that particularly difficult
either so let me go ahead and explain
what we're going to do here and it'll
take me a couple a couple minutes to
kind of get around to it but basically
what we're going to do today is day
330-345 so if you want to follow along i
used a 344 source code what you want to
do when you're programming obviously is
you want to have some ways when you're
doing low-level programming like this
where you can catch the kind of bugs
that might take you a while to find and
one of the most sort of insidious
versions here right is you know buffer
overruns right we all know that these
are particularly a you know problematic
i don't i spelled that right overruns
thing is where we sort of you know we
allocate this much memory and then
someone's like writing into it and
somebody writes over here right but
there happens to be more stuff here
because the actual allocated block let's
say was that big so something else is
here and this person who was trying to
write into here got some pointer math
wrong and wrote into here right it's the
kind of its wits one of the kinds of
bugs that people even created
higher-level languages to solve to a
certain extent
right people don't like having buffer
overrun bugs they're tricky to find
tricky to know if you have them because
they typically depend on the actual
runtime parameters of the code they're
not usually catchable at compile time
always so you know static analysis tools
can't always find them for you love
habla and so you know it's the kind of
thing that is a little bit problematic
and see when you're doing this kind of
code but you would like some way of
being able to sell program and see you
don't want to have to switch to
something else just to find them so the
question is how can you find them maybe
more effectively in C well one of the
nice things about the way that we're
working with our code now is since we're
in control of the platform layer we can
do basically our own buffer overrun
detection so if you remember we use a
function called virtual a lock right and
what virtual a lock does is virtual a
lock is essentially you know we think of
it as an alligator because conceptually
that's what it's doing in our program so
when we think about allocating memory we
kind of think about this idea that when
we allocate memory we are getting this
memory we're like acquiring it from the
system and when we free memory we're
releasing it back to the system right
that's kind of how we look at it because
that's what it semantically means to our
program but technically speaking that's
not really exactly that's that's not the
entirety of what it's doing right yes it
is doing the sort of allocation and
freeing operations as we would think of
them semantically but we've also as we
talked about in the past it also does
memory mapping and what that means is
that if we have a you know some kind of
physical memory here right here is our
physical memory you know and this is
however much it is I don't remember how
much is on this machine physical memory
wise performance what do we have
physical memory 12 gigabytes I guess
something like this so you know if we
have 12 gigs of physical memory right
then obviously that's all the memory
that we're operating with that's
actually real but our programs might be
allocating drastically more than 12
gigabytes if we wanted to write and even
if it wasn't even if let's say we're
only allocating a little bit of memory
there's nothing to say
that two programs might not be
allocating memory in effectively the
same place right so how does this work
well as we've talked about before in
addition to physical memory there is the
concept of virtual memory or virtual
addressing space and what that is is
what memory looks like to your program
so in a virtual address space I may
think that this block of memory right is
is right here and maybe I said I
allocated 8k of memory right and this is
where it was in my address space and so
I just think of it as I'm just you know
I've got a pointer in here and I do some
stuff with it and as far as I know you
know it's just whatever the pointer was
is where it is in virtual address space
right but in physical memory the
operating system has mapped this memory
that i'm using into some place
ville-marie may have nothing to do with
these addresses first of all the
operating system works on 4k pages so in
theoretically if this might not even be
in the same place it might be that
there's some up here and some down here
like here's 4k of it the first 4k and
here's the second 4k or this could be
this this could be the first 4k and that
could be the second 4k right it could be
mapped like this so essentially there is
page table and all sorts of things that
happen that translate these virtual
addresses into physical addresses and
the processor has a little table a
translation lookaside buffer and all
these are the things that there's just a
whole bunch of mechanics that go into
making this work smoothly the end result
of course being that our CPU when we are
executing our process as far as we know
it looks like we've just got all this
memory that just belongs to us and then
it's it's we're talking about in our
terms but really the operating system
may be moving things around they may be
in various places of physical memory
they may be evicted out to the disk when
our process is suspended all sorts of
things could happen right so again we've
talked about this on handmade here I'd
encourage you to go back and watch the
original episodes on that if you're
uncomfortable with it but that's the
basic idea of what happens with virtual
and physical memory so what this means
is that we can actually play a bit with
how this this memory works because we
know that these pages are really part of
a scheme that that translates addresses
into physical memory it
not like the old days before memory
management units when a pointer actually
meant the physical like place in RAM
where this thing was that is not what
we're dealing with we're dealing with a
virtual address space so if you think
about what happens when we allocate
something right we call virtual a lock
and we're going to get a pointer to the
beginning of of whatever this is and
that buffer is going to be 64k aligned
the reason it's going to be 64 Kaline is
because when you allocate something with
virtual alec it always gives you back
things on 64k page granular that's the
granularity of empties allocation of
windows is allocation that's the Opera
it's an operating system specific
implementation detail and then what it's
going to do is it's going to allocate
some number of 4k pages the operating
system works in these 4k pages so if we
said we wanted 16 k it would not give us
a single 16 k block what it actually
gives us is a set of blocks that are
each 4k that just happened to be
contiguous ok so if we ask for 16 k
we're actually at 44 k blocks that all
just happen to be mapped contiguously in
in memory but when we go through this
memory make no mistake if our pointer is
the pointer or anything up to the
pointer plus 4 K minus 1 write a plus
4095 right we are writing into this
memory page but as soon as we go to 4096
right now we're pointing into this
memory page and they are actually
different to the operating system
everything inside this 4k page is the
same everything inside this 4k page to
be the same but between the two they are
not the same what that means is we have
the ability to actually allocate memory
in such a way that would create what's
called a guard page and I mean
technically a guard page is usually used
for something slightly different but it
doesn't matter point being we can use
something where we allocate an extra
page of memory so that lets say we did
want 16 k worth of memory we could then
allocate an additional 4k page on the
end so actually 16 k plus 4 case over
20k total and we could then do something
using a new function which we have not
used called virtual protect and what we
can do with virtual protect is say do
not allow anyone to write to this page
if anyone writes to this page I want you
too hard fault right there okay so what
will happen is people can write write
write write write write write write
write write write write write as soon as
somebody writes over this page BAM it's
over right it will fault as if we had
written to a null pointer so now you may
be saying well that's all great how are
we going to deal with the fact that the
16k buffer may actually have been much
much more unaligned than that right what
happens if the person only wants to
allocate let's say they allocated I
don't know 73 bites that was the
allocation size they asked for well 73
bytes is going to end up being like this
little tiny part of the 4k page right so
now yes we could allocate an additional
4k page here and mark it as something
that cannot be written to but they're
still all of this buffer overrun space
what that means is that there's still
plenty of room for error that we won't
catch and since buffer overruns often
tend to be only by a little bit like
it's very common for example to maybe
have an off by one error it's not so
common to have an off by 1734 or
whatever right so it's definitely the
case that we would like to have the very
last little piece here whatever you know
whatever the one closest the delegation
is we like that default and the answer
here is that's actually not that big of
a deal if we want to do that all we have
to do is when we allocate memory if we
want to put our memory allocator in a
mode that guards for buffer overruns off
the beginning of a buffer then we always
just take and we align ourselves such
that whatever the pointer is that we
return from our aliquet
right is aligned at the beginning and we
mark this the page you know the 4k page
before it here are the 2 4get pages as
unrideable on the other hand if what we
wanted to do was catch buffer overruns
that co off the far end of the buffer
then we just move the pointer up to the
end of the page that we get so that it
ends right on the page boundary right
and then we mark it now we can't quite
do this always because if the person who
allocated the memory asked for alignment
of a certain kind we may not be able to
move it all the way to the end for
example if they ask for 73 bites but
they wanted it 16 byte aligned right
well then there's nothing we can do
about it because 64 bytes would be the
previous 16 boundary right and then 80
bytes would be the next one and so we're
going to have a seven bite overhang
there regardless there's nothing we can
do about that that you could overwrite
do but fortunately usually when people
ask for aligned memory they typically
also specify a size that happens to be
aligned to that that's just the way
programming typically works I'm
operating on simdi you know so I'm
allocating M 128 typically I'm going to
have an even multiple event M 128 which
are 16 bytes right so it all works out
in the in the end so previously we
didn't really have any way to implement
anything like this and the reason we
didn't is because we were never actually
asking the operating system for memory
except for just the very beginning the
program where we asked her one big block
and one big block doesn't really help us
because every time the user doesn't
allocation they were out sub alka out of
the block we had no ability to align and
protect memory for them in that
circumstance but now that we do have the
ability to have our allocator go down
through the system and allocate its
memory directly from us if we should
choose to do so we can effectively
implement bounds checking by forcing it
to do that and let me show you what I
mean
again just a reminder we're starting
with day 344 is code here good I'm going
to load up the handmade project build it
here is memory and so what I want to do
here is say alright here's my memory
arena and I have these allocation flags
that I that I'm passing down to the
operating system and what I might want
to do is just say okay those allocation
flags that I have what if i were to
specify another type of flag that says
that we want to do that kind of overrun
checking right so if i do that should be
platform em right yeah if i say platform
memory you know overflow checked or plat
for a memory like underflow check then I
should be able to specify / arena that I
want this now you know now that think
about it this is probably just a thing
that we'd turn on at runtime and not for
any particular arena well I'll do it
poor arena for now anyway why not all
right so all I want to do now say hey
those allocation Flyers could be set to
underflow check or overflow Chuck and so
if those flags are set then we know that
that's something that we want to have
happening on this arena that debug
option we want to have that on the arena
and so what I'm going to do is in here
where we have pushed sighs all I want to
do inside the push size is I just want
to go ahead and say hey let's assume
that if this arena has the allocation
flag set such that it wants some kind of
bounds checking
right so we just go ahead and say let's
see what the allocation flag say if
their overflow check or under flip check
is on then what I want to do is instead
of doing any of this and I guess
technically some of this i do want to do
for example i do want to do that right i
do want to be able to do my zero size so
that should happen regardless of what's
happening but here what i want to do is
say okay if we're going to underflow
over check instead of doing all of this
stuff that we were doing before i want
to instead use essentially a new block
for every single one of my allocations
right so I want to effectively pass
every allocation down to the system
every time if that makes sense so what I
can do here is just say like okay
normally we're calling this only when we
need a new block instead I'm just going
to call it any time that I have anything
happening at all and so I'm going to
declare the result up here like so I'm
going to get it like this and then I'm
going to keep that path working the way
that it was and so when we in dere said
like all right we've got these
allocation flags we want to do overflow
or underflow checking in that case let's
just allocate the memory and we'll pass
the allocation flags down to the system
as is and that's it and now everything
that we do would actually go through an
individual allocation right now this is
going to be incredibly inefficient right
this is definitely not something that we
would ever ever ever want to do in
practice when we were running the game
but it's certainly something we could do
for working on the game so I'm going to
go ahead and and furthermore pass the
the size in it down there we go and we
also need the alignment here but I'll
this will always be aligned to a 16-byte
boundary at the moment so we shouldn't
actually have a problem with that ok so
now if i run it nothing in
ticular is going to happen obviously
because we don't actually have that flag
set anywhere so in theory we just get
the exact same thing but if i am to now
go and say hey let's by default set
those allocation flags so you know let's
just say we're going to have a little
weight here where we just say let's or
it in i'm going to put overflow checking
on this arena all on every arena
basically then you can kind of see
things are super slow right and they're
because they're allocating allocating
allocating and it can't ever free right
and so eventually we'll just use up all
the memory in the system and just crash
right in fact this is probably a bad
idea because now our thing is going to
crash that's not good stop everyone stop
no make it stop please
you
that were the internet worm I don't
understand how we have operating system
still in this day and age when something
just allocates a bunch of memory it's
basically a distributed
denial-of-service attack right it's like
how did that happen and I have no idea
Oh computer it's just like in the old
days when you didn't actually have
memory protection and you'd write a
program and it would just crash your
computer and that would be the end of it
for the love of God man just close the
application how hard is it you're an
operating system have some self-respect
windows how are you not yeah
ladies and gentlemen is 2016 and all you
have to do to kill Windows is just
allocate some memory well that was fun
are we still recording even I have no
idea and we dropped quite a few frames
to say the least but hey that's fine
anyway I was just trying to show that we
could pass all of our allocations down
to the system oops Wow alright anyway so
the problem that will have here if we
want to run in this mode for sended
period of time as you saw is we do need
a way of freeing this memory when the
time comes and so in order to do that we
do need to have sort of a way of keeping
our block footer and that sort of stuff
which is these things here and so what I
need to do is I need to have some way
that I can still do the like freeze you
know as we go so in order to do that
what I want to try and do is I want to
try and use the same path because you
can see like I could go here and try to
put in the block header and do all that
sort of stuff and and you know try I
don't know monkey around with it and
whatever but as you can imagine if I do
that stuff I gotta kind of reimplement
all the stuff that I had here before
because I already had the concept of
sticking your foot around the end and
knowing that i freed it and that sort of
stuff so the question is can I do
anything here that would force me to
always allocate a block and make that be
the default thing that happens and the
answer is yes I can because you can see
here that previously we were checking to
see whether the arena had a particular
size or not and we had this sort of
minimum block size and all that sort of
stuff what I could do instead is when I
detect that the arena has this
particular piece this particular flag
set what i could do is just change the
way that this particular thing works to
ensure that arenas never actually keep
any
eyes other than the exact size they need
for their it for the allocation they
just did if that makes sense so what I
want to do here is say like oh ok if I
am I have to think about whether this
getting effective size for here is a
problem or not but if I am detecting
that I have the overflow or underflow
checking enabled then what I want to do
is I want to say ok let's instead of
trying to reimplement exactly the same
thing we have there let's just make sure
that we never try to allocate more than
exactly the size that's going to give us
what we want right and in fact we can
still leave this code in there that
won't really make any difference but
what I want to do is you can see here we
do this maximum size for Mary black
fighter arena minimum block size so what
we could do is just say like hey always
zero out that minimum block size in fact
maybe I can put it like this i could say
just make the minimum block size always
be zero
typing is hard for this like a fun
tomorrow there we go let's just always
make the arena block size zero if we're
going to do an underfloor over to check
that way the amount we allocate is going
to be exactly the right amount and never
any different right that way we'll
always sort of chain the blocks together
still and off we go so let's give that a
shot let's see if we're going to hose
the system again hopefully we should be
freeing things now although we don't
appear to be
looks like we have stabilized
alright so that looks fairly stable now
and that again is calling strictly
through the operating systems allocator
for every single allocation and you can
see that we get kind of sluggish
performance as a result because again
even the debug system is going through
all of those allocations which is not
great right but that's that's it right
so now we're getting allocations on
every call and so now what we need to do
is say well okay depending on whether we
want to check for overflows or under
flows we're going to want to put the
memory block footer on different sides
depending on which one we're checking
for right if we're checking for
overflows we would want to put the
marriott footer at the beginning if
we're checking for under flows we want
to put the memory block footer at the
end right because we don't we need the
memory lock footer to to be out of the
way so we can line up the thing with the
page exactly where it should be now I
need to double-check the memory block
footer is not going to change our
alignment it looks like it would looks
like our memory lock foot are currently
would because you can see this is going
to be a three instead of four of these
so I'm going to put a pad in here that's
what the memory block footer should
probably look like if we're going to
move it and I feel like calling this the
footer is probably not right because we
might move it around now so i'm going to
call us a memory block chain there you
go
alright so what I'd like to do now is
say okay let's allow ourselves well
first of all what we can do is let's try
to catch overruns off the beginning of a
buffer because that one will work
automatically that one we don't have to
do anything really to to change because
we've already put our footer at we
already put our memory block chain
information at the end of our thing of
at the end of our allocation so you know
if you take a look at when we allocate
this oh I killed Milton I'm sorry Milton
I allocated too much memory and now
Milton is unhappy you can go you can
close Milton go ahead go go it's okay
Milton Milton What's Wrong Milton
and process there we go let's just go
ahead and get our milton back
there we go all right so what we are
doing right now is just saying well okay
we know that we have a footer on the end
right now right there's our mr. footer
and so since we've got a footer that
means that if we wanted to the easiest
thing to do would be to men protect the
part before our allocation so that we'd
catch over rights that go before the
buffer in question right so if I want to
do that what would I have to do at the
operating system level right and so
let's take a look at that because that's
the actual interesting part of the
implementation here so where we when we
do platform allocate oops went to do
allocate memory here it is when we do
win through to allocate memory then here
you can see the virtual Alec hall that
we're making and like I said before what
we want to do here is we want to make
sure that we have 14 K page at the
beginning of our memory block so that
when we go to do overwrite checking
what's at the beginning will be a blank
page that we control right so if we
wanted to do that it's pretty easy let's
say I just wanted to do that without
checking the flag although I could even
do it which I going to flock here I
would just say the total size is going
to be that and then I could say well if
the flags are are including underflow
checking then what I want to do is I
want to add 4k write one page and I'm
probably going to just make that a
constant
maybe I'll make even make that to do so
I'm going to add one page worth to the
total size so that when i allocate it i
will actually get that extra page that i
wanted so i'll get one page plus however
much we actually wanted to have happen
and then you can kind of see here where
we do our get base pointer off of block
or whatever what did we do do we
actually put this at the beginning i
guess it looks like we did so yeah so
we've kind of got this it looks like
we've got counter reading problems here
right we put the memory information that
we needed on this guy sort of the loops
for the chain for our saving to disk
these are actually placed in kind of an
inconvenient location if that makes
sense it's on the wrong side of it and
it also strikes me again and this you
see this pretty often I prefer it when
we don't actually have this problem so I
don't know if we're going to want to try
and get rid of it a little bit there we
go I prefer to not have so many people
sticking things on to allocations so
like it's kind of annoying to have both
of these things on there and we can talk
about that a little bit separately but
so what I want to do here is I want to
say okay how do we you know how do I
deal with this particular thing being in
the way and one thing you know now that
I think about it maybe that would be an
easier way for us to deal with this is I
could make it so that I I suppose I
could make it so that you just get back
you just get back kind of that chain
because both people basically want to
know the same thing right the arena is
only tracking those blocks because it
wants to be able to unwind memory and
the win32 allocate memory call is
exactly doing the same thing right it's
just trying to keep a linked list of all
the memory that's in the system so
really if we wanted to we could just
make it so that the arena and the memory
allocator on the win32 side actually
could just have the same data structure
being used for that process if that
makes sense I kind of feel like we're
going to want to do that possibly before
this had I've thought about that I would
have said let's do that before this I'm
kind of right in the middle of this now
but what I'm gonna do alright so let's
let me just finish the basics of what
we're doing and we'll go talk about that
so anyway when we actually do this
allocation here you can see what happens
is once i get back this memory block I'm
sort of treating that as the actual
block and what I would rather do at this
point is I want to kind of move that
block upwards a little bit right I want
to move that block up to I want it to
start thinking of the rubber block as
being after the additional size that I
sort of said here so you know I if if
I'm in this underflow checking scenario
I want to do that adjustment where block
is going to be equal to you know one
page past wherever virtual Alec gave me
back right that makes sense okay so that
just allocates an additional page at the
beginning of things that's all it's
doing nothing particularly fancy so
again the game runs exactly the same
except it's just allocating an extra
page of memory every time it was doing
an allocation and so then all we have to
do is when we want the underflow
checking to occur we just need to be
able to take this block this original
pointer that's that original page and we
just need to virtual protect
the page right so let's take a look at
that call I talked about it already but
it's it's the one that we need to use if
we call virtual protect here is virtual
protect if we call virtual protect in
this case and we say all right we're
here is the address that we want to
protect here is the size right we know
those two pieces of information we know
we want to protect one page we know it
starts at block then all we need to know
here is what we want to do to this page
and you can see in
here we go in this list of constants
what are the things we are what what the
things that we can do are to the page so
every memory page in Windows and
generally speaking this is sort of like
a function of the like processor and the
operating system depending on what sorts
of things they both support but any
given memory page 1 of those 4k page
pages in memory can have any number of
bits set that say what's allowed to
happen on it so you can see we've got
page execute here and what that means is
that if the instruction pointer for your
code we're inside this page trying to
read code bites from it it would be
allowed right oops and that's all that
means right you can't write to it you
can only execute code out of it page
execute read means that you could
execute code in it or read like the data
out of it but still not right to it
execute read/write means you can do
everything you can read it from the page
right to the page or execute code that's
in the page page execute right copy is a
bizarre kind of thing this is like for
unix fork and stuff like this it
basically says that when you are going
to use a particular page if you were
going to execute that page if you're
going to actually run something in that
page or write to that page it would go
ahead and duplicate that page to a new
page if that makes sense this is for
stuff I believe like fork you don't
typically use it that much outside of
that but you could imagine why you might
want it right page no access is what
we're looking for more it just means
like if anyone touches this page it
immediately should fault page read-only
is that you could read from the page but
just never write to it page read/write
is exactly what it sounds like anything
except executing code in the page is
fine page right copy is the copy on
write version that does not allow
executing out of it so again for the
unix fort command kinds of style stuff
you clone all of the ad
space of a process and then anytime you
write to one of them it's going to clone
to a new page page targets invalid and
page targets no update I have never seen
before I have no idea what they do set
all locations of the pages that invalid
targets for CFG use along with any
ex--you page CFG is what what is CFG I
don't know page of the region will not
have their CFG haven't updated well the
protection changes for richer protect
simple the pages read I have no idea no
idea what that is you're on your own
page guard these are basically like the
things that are used to you know grow
the stack or do other things with guard
pages basically what they do is when you
touch them they fire off an alarm right
they basically are things when for
example the way that the stack
oftentimes works the program stack works
is you will take a piece of memory that
is the initial part let me go ahead and
this is why said back I was like it's
not technically a guard page I said
guard page because it's guarding us but
it's not really garbage so what actually
happens to the guard page is like
typically what will happen is maybe you
have the program stack here and then
what happens is you want the program
stack to grow as the program uses more
of the stack so the program is touching
touching touching touching and then when
it touches this you don't really want it
to fault what you want it to do is call
a handler that's going to commit this
page right and then let you know what
you would then do is go allocate some
more memory for the stack and guard
another page right so it can kind of
grow out like this what you don't want
to do is actually stop the process from
executing and consider in error so
basically what happens when you hit the
page guard is it will raise the
violation exception so that you can
handle it but then immediately turns off
that status so that things that we're
touching that page can still continue to
touch that page right and you can resume
executing as normal
oops again we don't care about that we
don't have to implement that page no
cash is probably exactly what it sounds
like but honestly I've never used it and
Paige right combined same thing page
right combined typically you don't set
that's something that's set for Hardware
access and so that would turn on right
combining for these page to memory which
is the thing that makes it so that when
you you know do rights to it it doesn't
flush all the rights in order
necessarily they may be flushed
aggregated if rights are expensive blah
blah blah all right and then these
Enclave ones are the things we talked
about with SSG X that's that weird like
Intel thing where you lose control of
your own computer it's basically the
thing that allows you to have encrypted
memory that you can't touch so that's
yeah that's what that is anyway so all
we really care about here is page no
access right all I really wanted was
page no access so what I want to do here
is I want a virtual protect this thing
as page no access so that there's no way
for anyone ever touch the page it's just
going to be a problem if they do and we
need to pass one more parameter which is
what the old protect was so we're just
have old protect and now in theory we
are protecting the page now I'm going to
check the return value just so we can
ensure that it's actually working
because maybe we passed some parameters
wrong and we don't want to mess it up
right so now those we have those guard
pages happening there and we can verify
that those are happening properly
because now when we get this block back
what we should be able to do right if I
if I didn't call this virtual protect
then in theory what I should have been
able to do is say the part that I'm
talking about right now if I was to set
the the next pointer to say 0 or
something it should be fine because we
allocated that memory and we're just
touching it and setting it to 0 but if
instead I was to set virtual protect to
say that page is no access now if i
touch the page we should crash right or
not
I said we should crash apparently we
don't crash apparently because we don't
have underflow check on let's try that
again alright one more time let's not
protect the page no problem and protect
the page and we crash right so now we
have everything we need to create a
bounced check ur right we have
everything we need to make sure that the
instant that anyone touches any piece of
memory outside of a valid allocation
location we will fault right we'll just
felt right there so I feel like I want
to be a little bit more efficient
potentially than I'm being right now but
I'm just not going to do that this time
around so I'm just going to do the
simpler thing here and say okay if we're
doing platform underflow checking than
we need what essentially amounts to be
two extra pages right is what I'm going
to do I'm going to say two times page
size and I'm going to do that that is
actually what I'm going to do in both
cases right so I'm going to do I'm going
to do well I got to add a little bit
more to ago so let me just do this one
first and then we'll go from there so
I'm going to add two extra pages I'm
going to take the Jews me I'm going to
take the block here that I was going to
use I'm going to put that in the first
page and then protect the second page
and I'm gonna make the third page and up
be the stuff that's actually protected
right so it's just super super piggy not
not good at all but that's just what I'm
going to do temporarily just to sort of
get this working the way the
I want it to work first and then
tomorrow I think I want to try and sit
down and figure out can we work out a
nice way to make it so that all these
things kind of collapse down into one
and we'll go from there so anyway if we
were going to do underflow checking we
know we have two extra pages that beans
that we have the block being where the
block actually is and that's all fine
and so the thing we want to protect is
actually the block plus the page size
and we're going to start that that's
protectable we then have the block
itself being where it was originally but
i'm going to introduce the notion that
the win32
there it is result so I'm going to
introduce the notion here that again the
get base pointer for a block thing this
is not really going to work anymore and
the reason that this is not really going
to work anymore is because if you ask
for the base point of a block your
problem is that you're going to not know
whether this extra padding was happening
or not now we could make it a global the
juice is set for underflow checking or
not and then you would always know
throughout all the places but in this
case you wouldn't really know because we
want to allow different arenas to have
the overflow or underflow checking on or
off separately right so what I want to
do here is say okay inside the memory
block let's just go ahead since we also
have we have plenty of extra padding in
there I'm just going to say that we have
a base pointer so that basically you can
always get from the block to the result
without calling get base pointer it's
just is the base pointer right and so
I'm going to say here that the base
pointer in most cases is just going to
be the the block plus one but in the
case where we actually have some kind of
checking turned on it's going to be
something else right so in this case
it's going to be 2 times the block size
and off we go so then we know we always
return the base pointer and we can also
get rid of get block probes get base
pointer for the block because now it is
just a thing that's off of it directly
right okay so moving on
what are you unhappy about I did say two
times page size right yes so ah got a
little sloppy there at the point
arithmetic where's my blog virtual
protect I actually meant to only go the
page size up not the page size Simon's
the size of a block but my bad so yeah
so now what we have to do is we have to
figure out when we're virtual freeing
things well we've got a couple things we
have to do but first of all when we
virtual free things we can no longer
assume that the block itself is the
actual pointer that were virtually
freeing right and the reason for that is
because now we may have put the Block in
some location that has nothing to do
with the memory that we're actually
returning to you so we do now need to
lean on the thing that I was talking
about before where you know like we've
got this thing here where we r d like
adding memory we're expected to get back
to the block we actually need to get
down to the base of our allocation again
and in order to get down to the base of
our allocation we need to do the virtual
query call that I was talking about
before and the virtual query call I
believe should give us the piece of
information that we actually needed
where are you do not type that in right
right I thought I typed in virtual query
maybe I didn't that's right it's right
there and so in this case what I can do
is say okay
hmm alright maybe not so that won't help
us either because this has to be the
base address of the region of pages so I
can't actually round it down hmm this is
tricky I guess I'm just going to have to
I guess I'm just going to have to pass
that information to free as well because
it won't know it really wouldn't know
which one it really wouldn't know which
one it would have no idea how to get
back to what it needs to get back to you
know I'm saying so yeah it's just come
tough but anyway again not the end of
the world because we can figure this out
by just passing that in and I'll show
you what I'll show you that it is
relatively easy to make sure that as
long as we always know what we're doing
we can always back out the pointer to
something which will be correct if we
know which one we're doing so let's go
ahead and say platform here needs to
take symmetric flags so that we can work
backwards then when we go to win through
to memory we can do the reverse
operation so here we are with with block
and in this case what we want to do is
say oh well if what we were actually
doing is we were in an underflow
checking scenario then for underflow
checking we would like to say that the
block if we assume that it was say au8
we would like to say that whatever the
block is that we gave that we're getting
in here or rather whatever the memory is
that you're telling us to free we know
that that's two pages up from what it
should be right
so and I what I might do here is because
I would like to make this actual thing
little bit through to her okay sighs um
variable okay i know that i just have to
subtract two x the page size and i will
get back to where i'm supposed to be now
I still should be able to do all the
rest of my operations because I should
be able to always find it when we know
we're in underflip jacketing scenario i
should be able to go back and find the
Block in the location that it now is
right and so in theory now we're all
good and remember tech ting those pages
so if anyone tries to underflow even
just a little bit they would immediately
fault right and so previously if we
wanted to try and catch one of these for
example let's say we went into handmade
memory and turn this off so we're not
underflow chucking anymore we're just
doing the regular kind of running that
we normally would here's our 16 frames a
second and so let's say I went into
someplace kind of touchy trying to think
of what the best place to do this would
be but let's say that I went in
somewhere to maybe like world dot cpp
and let's see so we have a thing where
we're taking where we get a first free
chunk here and that we're allocating one
of these like world chunks and let's
suppose that I was just to touch
something right before the first free
chunk so let's say that I have my my
first free trunk on here and I you know
cast that to a you ate or something like
this and I'm going to go ahead and set
like
you know a few things back from it to be
zero so I'm just I'm just writing off
the end of that buffer right so that's
like plainly illegal right and it's
definitely a bug and could easily be
over writing something important we'll
never know until we see some really
weird behavior and are totally mystified
right but in theory if we've done our
underflow checking right now when we do
that it immediate it's like it's not
only does it catch it immediately with
no debugging effort but it also puts us
right on the line that that was the bug
right so again really really powerful
because who knows how long a bug like
that could sit in the code base without
us ever knowing it's there then we see
it we see a problem later on we're never
going to suspect that part of the code
because it's we haven't touched it in
forever right so when you're doing that
kind of low-level programming it helps
to have tools that allow you to catch
problems like that so if I remove the
offending line of code now we can run
through our chucker and it works okay
right so let's try exactly the same
thing now when we do the first free
chunk push there let's try we only
pushed on just this world chunk let's go
ahead and try going just one after it
right so I'm going to say writing one
after it
and you can see again now we're we're
over writing memory and again nothing is
nothing is happening right we're not
getting any kind of an error there it's
just fine so we would never know that
that was happening until we actually see
a symptom of the overwrite so what we
want to do now is say like okay we want
now want to be able to implement our
overflow checking overflow checking
would work exactly the same way it's
trivial fresh to implement at the win32
side of things unfortunately down here a
little bit it's a little bit nastier the
reason it's a little bit nastier over
here is just because now we've got a
situation where we need to move the
block chain that we're actually using
here we need to you move that out of the
way and so this is again why I say you
know what I think we want to do in this
scenario is we would like to make it so
that these two things work in concert a
little bit more I almost just feel like
we should be able to get the block chain
stuff back from like like that block
chain is a very simple thing it's just
this right and if you take a look at
what's going on in the lower level code
it's the same stuff right it's exactly
the same things we just have to add the
used right we just have to add that used
value and so I kind of feel like almost
what we want to do is just elevate this
construct up but I don't want to start
that now because we're almost out of
time so i think what i'm going to do is
I'm going to say let's go ahead and say
consolidate win through to and platform
nonspecific memory headers and then I
think we'll be all set
all right I'm going to go ahead and go
to QA
weight is in savate now able to
understand that I start the Q&amp;A in
another chat and then it starts the QA
in in the twitch chat did that just
happened
insofar as skin so bot is seriously the
greatest artificial intelligence that
mankind has ever known when can we get
it to the point where in so bot can just
do the programming on the stream and I
can just go home like when will we
actually just have in sohbat just does
handmade hero by itself and we don't
even need a human in the loop that is
really the future that we need
I'm following on linux with sdl because
I'm not sure it's worth building on X 11
or if Whelan is ready yet have you
thought about building on X 11 Whelan or
both know basically on linux I don't
really know linux very well so I don't
really have strong opinions about that
like probably on linux i'll just use sdl
or something or you know ask more lynn
eccentric people which one to use and
will write that I don't like on Windows
I knew a lot of stuff you know I'm not
and the the windows expert or anything
but like you know I know a lot of stuff
about how to structure the platform
layers and things like that so I have
opinions about it but I don't have
opinions about it on when x 11 platforms
at all or Wayland I've never even used
Wayland I know nothing about it other
than like it's one of those things are
like it's going to replace that
eventually or something but I don't
really yeah that's like not really my
area of expertise I don't ship games on
linux I don't have a lot of expertise
there before when you had fixed
allocation you could do a between run
save state kind of thing if I call
quickly how would you make that happen
with the dynamic blocks well we that's
what we did yesterday
so HR do you have any insight into if
you are developing this game in a
similar time flow to major devs example
you spent some time today working on
underflow overflow before such a thing
came into play is it just because of the
format of the show actually no that's
not true we have had overflow and
underflow bugs already well I don't know
if we ever had an underflow one but we
had an overflow bug already just
normally I would do that day one look
normally I'd have overflow checking in
there just day one but you know I try to
structure things based on when we kind
of naturally get to them in terms of
what we're doing when it makes sense and
now is when it made sense
in fact we don't know that we don't
right now have some overflow bugs in the
code right for all we know when we turn
on overflow detection tomorrow it'll
crash somewhere and we'll be like oh hey
look we've gotten over right look we
don't even know if we don't have an
overflow bug right now because we could
just have like a very subtle overflow
bug somewhere why do you look so
different from handmade here at day one
well it's been like two years almost two
years I it's deceptive because it says
345 but I don't stream every night so
it's it's you know it's only it makes it
seem like it's less days than it has
been
oh I see what you're asking sorry dr.
cheats I didn't understand the question
you're saying could we do it if across
different runs of the program wouldn't
you need to muck with the bass pointers
yeah if you wanted to make it work
across different runs of the program
it's that's really not that hard either
we don't really do that ever I on
handmade hero so I haven't felt the need
but yes you can totally do that all you
have to do is just when you call virtual
a lock pass in a base pointer and make
that base pointer just increment itself
as you do your allocations that's really
it
we just save you know we just have to
save that out actually now that I think
about it we wouldn't even have to do
that all you have to do is when you're
reloading you just you just reload one
of those things when you're streaming
out the blocks you just stream out the
base pointer and then when you reload
them you do do virtual Alec and pass the
base pointer you load it off the disk
I know this isn't relevant to the code
but does it seem strange to me in a
different location no not really because
it's the same computer and the same
monitor I just moved them
enemy mouse seems that arena start out
as a fast stack style allocator and I'm
leaving towards I'm going to keep you've
demonstrated the benefits of virtual
Ellicott cetera but can you comment on
the performance it and why you chose it
over Malik know so I just to be clear
I'm not necessarily saying that we'll
ever run in any of these modes probably
will set the initial allocation sizes of
our you know five or six arenas to just
be one allocation and they'll in at the
beginning and that'll be it so we
probably won't really do we will
probably leave it as running in its
stack mode because remember we haven't
changed that at all the only thing we
added was the fact that when you
overflow we will allocate a new page so
basically right now we're just running
in modes like I'm playing around with
like for example here's the debug mode
we can use or whatever but you never
want to take this branch like this
branch just doesn't ever want to be
taken and most of the time it's not
right so it still ends up being a very
fast stack style allocator provided that
you seed it with a good default page
size for the arena William Bundy it is
James Horner's a main theme from The
Rocketeer
window are any days missing from the
YouTube archive not that I know of as
far as i know all day all days are on
the youtube archive
was men protect the primary motivation
for moving to dynamic memory or were
there other reasons um like I said I
don't really have any motivation for
moving to dynamic memory I just wanted
to show how you could do it the game
will run in either mode right you can if
you would like to just get rid of this
path and then go back to having arenas
allocate a big chunk at the beginning
and that would be fine so I don't I
don't want to suggest that that one is
like good or bad it's just whichever one
you want and I wanted to show how you
that can be done like the game doesn't
really have to change at all right they
as long as the game just uses a push
style set up for its own purposes then
you can pretty much just choose whether
you're doing dynamic allocation or
non-dynamic right down to individual
structures if you want to do protected
pages but again that's really only for
debugging you don't ever want to do that
you don't want to protect allocate and
protect extra pages if you're not in a
debug scenario because it it's just
allocates way more memory and it's much
lower too because it has to actually do
a memory allocation every time we do a
push struct whereas normally every time
you push truck just just incrementing
the pointer over
all right looks like no more q Cohen so
I'm going to wrap it up
alright thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with stories at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade here org or go
to the forums to ask questions the
patreon page support the video series
schedule bot which tweets a schedule at
you or our past episode guide where the
old episodes are I'll be back here
tomorrow for the last stream of the week
not streaming on Friday I'll be back
here for 5 p.m. pacific daylight time
oak see you there for that I'm till then
if I programming it and i'll see you
guys on the internet take it easy
everyone