hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we today are just gonna
pick up where we left off yesterday and
it was actually kind of very fortuitous
day to be completely honest with you we
are starting to do the final performance
pass over our grid raytracer and I had
planned on yesterday doing some changes
to the way we're doing good ray casting
which I think will speed up the grid ray
caster quite a bit but in so doing we
discovered that actually our voxel
sampling was a lot slower than I thought
I thought I had tested the voxel
sampling because I assumed that it was
slow before and found that it wasn't
really affecting the performance that
much maybe that was erroneous because
we've tested it now and when we test the
full cycle but just don't do the ray
cast and we let it fall through to just
the sampling it turns out it actually
takes quite a bit of time that's great
news because that was sort of a piece of
code we'd left to optimize for later and
so what that means is we're probably
gonna get a big free speed boost here
probably I mean we don't know for sure
but it's entirely possible that we're
gonna get a bunch of performance here
that I wasn't anticipating getting and
so it's really nice sometimes when you
start to profile a piece of code and
you're anticipating having to work on a
particular piece of it and then you find
out that another piece of it that you
hadn't optimized yet or even looked at
yet is taking a significant chunk of the
time because again it just makes your
job easier since optimizing something
you've literally never touched before
there's always so much more fat in it
that you could potentially remove it's
always easier to do that low-hanging
first-pass than it is to do like the
subsequent passes where you really have
to sort of buckle down right and so it's
really good for us because this means
that we have the potential here to maybe
do to get a good speed win for not that
much creativity so that's kind of a nice
a nice side bonus we don't know that we
will but we might and so that potential
is nice what we did yesterday is we
started rewriting this part of the code
you can see here how it works
it's getting the relative position for a
particular sample point it figures that
where it is in the grid it gets the
tiles that surround that particular
sample point so this is an octave this
is this is a an eight-way so a trilinear
sample and then it produces some weights
and blends them together via the weights
and this was just the main line written
out code there's you know there's
nothing up we didn't try to optimize
this in any way right so this was just
us writing literally exactly what the
code should do in the most
straightforward possible way with no
attempt at optimization and so all I
started doing yesterday was saying okay
look if we wanted to go ahead and try to
improve this piece of code what could we
do to it and what I'd like to do here is
maybe since we have the opportunity to
do so
what I might want to do is because this
code is fairly subtle and we don't
really have a good way of testing it I'd
like to go ahead and just run these two
pieces of code against each other I
think I think that's going to be the
sane astray to kind of do what I want to
do so I basically just want to say look
is there some way that I can run this
code twice so every time we ask for a
sample
you know I'll run this side of it and
rather than an if/else until I actually
want to test the performance of it I'm
actually just going to run both both
sides right so want to run both sides of
the code and what I'll do is we'll have
a result here so we'll say look there's
going to be a result value and the
result value will get assigned by the
first piece of code like this right and
then all I really want to do is for this
new piece of code I just want to check
to see that the result that we compute
is very close to the original
so what we really want to do here is we
just want to have a we just want to have
some idea of whether we've got bugs in
our optimized routine and so as I go
finish this top part because you can see
we actually wrote most of the routine we
actually now just have this sort of top
part where we're gonna have to do that
the tile fetching which will be the
slowest part because it cannot be done
wide unless you have like a V X cat or
gather or something an Intel chips uh
cats cat or gather anyway but in here we
basically have the ability to to do that
we'll have to get optimized slightly
because this get clamped we could do a
lot better you don't really need to
clamp each one of these we could do one
or two quick checks and then know all of
the offsets so get tile clamped is much
slower than it needs to be so we can fix
that part for sure then in here this C
computation this C computation we should
be able to do very cleanly as well you
can see here that basically what we've
got when we're working through this here
is we just assume we have C 0 3 and C 4
7 and we don't have either of those so
that's the thing the main thing we've
got to produce now is that this part
here we could even use the slow part
first just so we can debug the second
half of the routine and that may be what
I do because I'd like to debug this in
waves
I'd like to basically do something where
we can get in fact you know you can see
how I would do this I would like to do
something where I stuck each part so for
example at any given time here I could I
could keep any of these pieces of
information in fact you know I could
even do something more like this so
instead of having the v3 result be the
only thing that persists I could just
you know make the entire thing right and
then oops
and then here
I can do is since I've done the entire
computation here in the original scalar
version I can then at each point in here
where I want to do like sort of a check
I can check my intermediate results to
ensure that they line up with the
existing answers right and so that'll
give me a much faster way of verifying
this routine against the previous code
not that the previous code is special in
any way but we ran a bunch of stuff with
the previous code and we liked the
results we got so at the very least we
know it's not broken to the point of not
actually producing usable like shippable
results at some point we may want to try
a way to you know figure out a good
stress test for this like create scenes
that have very specific lights reading
behavior so you know there's stuff we
could do there but at the moment all I
want to do is make sure that I'm not
making the situation worse with my
optimization so that's really the only
thing I want to make sure of because
again we don't really know that this
routine is working as well as it could
because we have no real testing for it
and in fact I don't really even know
exactly how we would test it but if we
sat down and tried I'm sure we could
find a way to sort of bulletproof this
routine more even if that just meant
plugging in some values that some cases
that we think should do something and me
stepping through them to verify that
they do right so you know at the very
least we could and you know another
example would be like if we if we took
the voxels and flooded them with
structured light so we basically said
like okay this one's full red this one's
full green this one's full blue and we
put sample points and sample normals in
there and looked at what came came out
we could look at those channels and
verify that like okay if the normals
pointed away from the red light it
doesn't sample the red light and if it's
pointed towards the blue light samples
the blue light you know so we certainly
can do more and so at some point we may
want to do some better testing here and
that's just part of like improving
letting quality ensuring that there
aren't
obvious bugs in the sampling routines
that's something we can do so I don't
want to tackle that part yet I just want
to be able to verify it so I know that
I'm doing the same algorithm in either
case and so in order to do that we're
just gonna put in some structured checks
here and I'm gonna do those once we're
ready for the moment all I want to do is
finish this part of the code so if you
take a look at what we haven't done yet
it's this C right here so we have to
recreate the C values here and these C
values are again fairly highly
structured you can see the way that they
work and what we want to try and produce
here just because this is the way we
decided to make it work at first is what
we want to produce Jimmy man I
definitely have Kobe 19 let's just face
it
I am the plague bear all right so what I
want to do here is I want to go ahead
and recreate each of these things with
the end goal of having the first three
so these here are gonna come through as
C 0 3 and again that's because the
inputs are here in here so C 0 3 and C 4
7 so we have C 0 3 and C 4 7 and what I
want to do is produce these answers here
so the inner product of each of these
right and so again I'm the best way to
do this routine if you really knew that
it was like the most important thing and
we were gonna try and do the best
possible job is we would analyze all the
scalar dependency flows and all the
operations that were in them and then we
would try to arrange our lanes so that
they minimize the number of shuffles
we're not doing that okay we're just
doing a first pass simple implementation
of this routine wide to get what we can
get out of it and to reduce the amount
of compiler craft because when I looked
at this routine the compiler was doing
absolutely bonkers stuff for no reason
and so I think we can speed it up just
by doing something basic and so that's
all we're doing here we're not trying to
do the fastest possible version of this
routine
so I'm just gonna do a straight ahead
implementation to try and get these two
pieces of information here and so if you
take a look at what we would need what
we want to achieve here you can see that
in here I've got some things that look
like this this is how we want to load
these up right so these are not you know
this is not really this is not actual
code right this is Nayan this is nothing
so these right here are things that we
actually have to prepare and in fact
those can kind of float to the top where
this sort of thing is happening because
you know it's totally fine but the rest
of this is actual code right the rest of
this is actual code we intend to
implement and it might not be quite
written as actual code yet but most of
it actually is there's a couple things
like we didn't define a one vector and
we we want to make that a floor or
function and so on but for the most part
it's all fine so if I then go through
and take a look at what's happening here
what you can see is I I want to know
what these C values should actually look
like and what you can see is all of them
end in a clamp zero one so one of the
interviews is things I can do here is I
can just make sure that we do well in
fact I think do we actually have a clamp
zero one for these we should I don't
know if we do yeah so we don't actually
even have a clamp zero one for these we
should because it's a very simple
function so I think I might just go
ahead and implement that so in here
where we've got you know all of these
pieces of code that we were writing to
handle our various math ops right in
here where we have all these I don't
know if we have them in max we do so you
can see we have like a min Max here
right we've got these values so it's
pretty straightforward for us to do once
you have a min and the max clamp zero
one's really easy because it's just a
min file
by a max or vice-versa right so if we
just do a clamp 0 1 and we pass in some
value then the result here is just gonna
be the min max of a where the min is
with 0 and the max is with 1 right I'm
sorry the other way around so this needs
to be a 0 vector and this needs to be a
1 vector right so we would just have
something like this I don't know if we
have a 0 here so I guess I'll just do
this
we'll see what if this actually does the
right thing let's look at the code so if
we have a clamp 0 1 here all this is
going to do right is this going to say
look if I take the maximum value between
0 and this thing then if it's less than
0 that will bring it up to 0 if I take
the minimum of this thing in 1 that
means if it's over 1 it'll come down to
1 so in just two instructions I can do a
clamp 0 1 and there's no test right and
so there's no control flow here it just
works and you can contrast that with
what would happen if the compiler
literally interpret interpreted you know
rather than doing a seamoth which you
know I don't know whether I miss VC will
actually generate a seam out for this
but if you look at what actually has to
happen here
you know this less than min result
equals manual greater than max values
max if you actually wrote this code out
that's actually two jumps right and
that's really expensive because they're
not going to be predictable so basically
this is I mean yeah this is incredibly
expensive and this is basically free is
I guess what I'm trying to say and so
it's worth understanding like the
difference between those two things of
why I care about them the compiler could
generate this pretty efficiently in
scaler and in fact could even use the
min and Max
use the minimax operations to do it if
it was smart enough to analyze that
piece of code but it's just usually a
bad idea to rely on the compiler to do
something smart cuz often times it
doesn't that's just you know writing
optimizers is hard and especially the
way that compilers do it where they do
it in a you know in line with the actual
compilation pass where you're like you
know it can't take an hour right well
missus tensorflow but can't take an hour
to like analyze that this little piece
of code right so that can't do like
super optimization or sorts of things
that would make it fairly easy to write
a compiler right it's just because it's
structured wrong and the way we
currently have tools made is wrong and
everything's wrong right so the way they
currently make optimizer is if you want
it actually ship one the way that they
do it is actually pretty hard and so I
don't blame them for not getting stuff
right and so my opinion I should just
write the code right in the first place
so that they can produce reasonable code
from it without having to you know do
anything crazy
so anyway assuming that we just clamp
these two then what we really are
talking about now if I peel away the
part of C that's actually now been done
we're left with this part okay and what
you can see here is all of these are
just inner products with n right and so
we could actually keep the control flow
fairly similar if you look at what's
happening in each of these channels
because it's not that complicated as to
what's going on in the result at the end
so if we take a look at what we would
produce for each of these you can sort
of imagine expanding one of these out
and because in each case it's minus zero
or one there's never anything else
that's - so it's always fairly
straightforward as to what's actually
happening there right so if we look at
the series of operation that's
operations that's going to happen each
one of these is actually doing
effectively the same thing it's taking
uvw X right UVW Y you
you see in each case right and it's
subtracting from them something right so
it's either subtracting zero or it's
subtracting one in each case for each of
these then it's doing four for after
we've done that it's doing various
products with those in occlusion n right
so after it does that in each case we're
doing times the corresponding member of
occlusion n right and then we're just
summing those up so each one of these is
like a plus so that's really very
straightforward for us to actually
implement in fact right because we can
literally just do that as like a series
of steps one right after the other and
we probably don't have to really do much
else to be completely honest with you
let's take a look here so like you can
see that the X is a 0 1 0 pattern and
that's pretty easy for us to make right
so we can do something like this where
we just try to load that up so it's like
that right
I don't know it seems pretty easy and so
we know we have 0 1 0 pattern of 0 0 1 1
pattern you know what
how about that little easier to read
right so we have a 0 0 1 1 pattern and
then we have a well we just have 0 &amp; 1
which we kind of already know we wanted
because we actually use those for
clamping and it should be able to do the
basic common sub-expression elimination
for that so I don't anticipate us having
to go out of our way to make sure that
the thing knows that doesn't have to
produce those values like it should know
in general that zero can just be an X or
register free clear
I hope Microsoft's optimizer at this
point is really just struggles a lot
with sim D code doesn't really
understand it doesn't know some of the
basic things that you would want it to
know and so because we're on like clang
does a much better job with this with
SSE code Visual Studio really struggles
with it it really has a hard time so you
know like I'm saying that but it's not
necessarily true but anyway so in this
case we have 0 &amp; 1 we don't really need
the 0 we might need it for other things
later but we don't need to run a
subtraction pass for 0 right because
that doesn't do anything so we only
really need the 1 here so these are the
three things that we actually needed and
then if we go ahead and create like I
said exactly what we actually wanted to
do here it's actually not that hard
right if we assume that UVW has been
broadcasted out so you know this is this
is that part of the code that we would
actually need we have a 1 - u VW but we
don't have a u VW minus 1 unfortunately
they're you know not quite the same so
if we start up here and we say here's
the code that we need to do to produce
the UVW and then we just do the
broadcast so that the u VW's are kind of
out again i don't really know if there's
something we can do here to make this
stuff go cleaner I don't think there is
because it seems like you really want to
do these here but it's possible that you
could untwist your you VW's in some way
I don't know we can think about the
bottom half of the routine later someone
asked yesterday whether it makes more
sense to do the bottom half with you
VW's replicated and I just don't know we
could just look and see if it does
because I don't know if it does or not
so anyway so up here you can see if we
wanted to do a replication pass now then
basically what we would have is uvw X
right but we can just call those UV and
W because that's what they are so these
would just be what are they broadcast
works yeah so these are just broadcast
for X instructions that broadcast the
various values out so here we've
extracted the different components and
then all we need to do is actually do
this computation so for c03 if we take a
look at what we're doing we want to
subtract 0 1 0 from X so we have 0 1 0
so we want you - right that's the X part
and the X part is then going to get
multiplied by occlusion NX right so here
I probably need something that's called
you know o n X right or something like
this because again that's going to be a
we need to replicate that value out if
we want that to work right so we're
gonna have to multiply by that and then
we do the Y pass next so that's the
Pat's 0 0 1 1 times ony
and then the final one is the W and this
would be minus zero but in this case we
don't actually have to do that
so it's literally just gonna be W times
the onz right and I think that should
get us what we want right because here's
the zero one zero so we're - in that
part apiece this C zero three and then
here we're doing the V - to produce zero
one one and then times the collision and
right so you can see it's it's pretty
straightforward the next one is exactly
the same actually and so when we look at
what's happening here we should be able
to just factor this out right because
you can see that this it's either gonna
add that where is the value it's just 1
so it's either gonna add that or that
right that's all that's gonna happen and
if you take a look at what this
expression would presumably produce at
that point at least unless I'm sorely
mistaken if you multiple if you're just
distributive property this sausage
gentlemen here it should just be that
right which is the same as that yeah I
mean at least that's what it looks like
to me so I I don't see anything else
there that's particularly interesting I
mean that just looks fine so I think
these two values are actually the same
right and all we have to do is say well
in order to get the c-47 one you just do
the you know it's just the same as this
and before you clamp it you just do an
offset of the onz value right so I think
that's fine
and again like just a lot of broadcasts
here and it's not great but one of the
things you have to remember is the not
greatness of this may be mitigated by
the fact that this may already actually
exist so if you take a look this
broadcast oh well but if you take a look
at what happens with the other broadcast
well down here where we actually process
the hit what you can kind of see is that
where we do the compute values at the
occlusion D and the probe sample ends
single here one of the things you can
see is they're actually coming from
things that probably were already
duplicated and spread because we
probably already P shift B some of these
things anyway and if you already P chef
to be them they're already in order so
we may actually be able to do eliminate
some of the pressure on port five on
skylake by just recognizing that we
already freaking did it right so some of
these may be duplicated and I'll just
make a note of that
and so it's entirely possible that we
can do you know like I said a much
faster sample by just eliminating a ton
of the port 5 pressure here because we
may already have those things replicated
in their own channels right so so again
you can see why I think there's gonna be
a lot of a speed wind to be had here
because the compiler wasn't doing a
particularly good job on it and if you
look at you know with the exception of
maybe the broadcast instructions which
are kind of annoying in line up behind
port 5 if you look at what else is
happening here these are just constants
they can be done with memory ops even so
if you look at this it's like one two
three four five six seven operations
seven total like instructions there
right
to replicate this entire thing and this
entire thing like this alone just
calling that would have probably been
about seven instructions right just
welding in that part of the equation and
so you know we're talking about you know
could be as much as eight times faster
just doing this here and that's before
the Clint wiet the clamp was in here too
so this could be this could be many
times faster right
so again just writing it sensibly giving
the compiler a chance to do okay
all right hmm what is going on chat over
there everyone calm down
um all right so in here I think I now
have just about all of the computation
stuff done let me get rid of this stuff
for a moment and all of this code is
actually real with the exception of the
MM floor that I stuck in there that
actually probably wants to go into an
actual function right because I don't
think we ever put an mm floor PS in here
and we should have but we just didn't
right it looks like we have a set zero
in here so I probably should do that one
actually let me just drop that in and
that's just because again I don't know
how done the compiler is I don't know if
this if it reliably detects loads of
zero and replaces them with X source or
other reasonable ways of clearing the
register so yeah so we're good also by
the way chat no I did not delete from
the original code this is the original
code right all right so anyway if we go
ahead and look at what we've got here we
just never added a floor function to
this for reasons that I don't actually
know what they are so yeah I don't know
we haven't really done a particularly
good attempt at assembly library here it
was just kind of whatever we needed at
the time so that's fine but if we want
to make this a little bit more complete
here we should have a floor for sure
because we use it all the time and so if
we want to do that it's pretty
straightforward again it's literally
just the same as any one of these there
we're just proxying you
the floor function right and I don't
know so if we look I don't remember this
is an ssa whoa hello
so if you look at mm floor PS it is a
higher end function but I think we
already decided we are using the later
SSC stuff at least at the moment and if
we have to downgrade it later I guess we
will but you can see here that you know
this just does the basic floor operation
it's what you want so you know we can
just use it directly and and it's pretty
much available on just about everything
that we'll probably ever ship on at
least that could possibly run this
lighting right because this is a pretty
heavyweight thing so you're not gonna be
running this lighting on like 15 year
old machines that's not gonna fly
okay I don't know why C is still here
that okay so now we've got a couple
things we got to do so first of all
these loads don't actually really exist
at all so we're gonna have to actually
fix we're gonna have to eventually fix
those I don't know what's it complaining
about for this the question of W oh I've
already got a W up here I guess that
somebody's using is that true yes we
were using that for the weights so maybe
UVW was not the best choice thing even
though that's what those actually were
that's a little bit of an issue so you
know oops
but I guess I can just use lowercase for
now
here we come and so if we take a look at
what we've got here it looks like
occlusion and he is not a member of what
is it complaining about you Oh cuz
occlusion and is actually just a regular
v3 okay so yeah in this case we don't
actually have an F and F 3 v4 for this
it's actually just a regular v3 so at
the moment I guess what we would
probably want to do is actually just use
our load function it's not a broadcast
it's an actual load because this is not
coming from like the to do says it's not
coming from the actual correct place you
can see here we've got a set one PS in
there so we should be able to just do
like f3 load on that like so and that's
fine so that'll do and so let's take a
look down here so what's the problem
undeclared identifier good point didn't
tell the compiler about that one my bad
so again problem with just the fact that
we called this some I was trying to have
these line up and so I'll just call this
some zero because it's fine and I'll
call this inves some zero and again
that's really just normally we wouldn't
have the same code twice but it's just
for verification purposes I would prefer
that so I'm going to leave it that way
for now we don't have any of the tile
samples that we need so that's fine and
then at the end here it looks like we
just probably want to do because we're
gonna use this for testing so this is
really just going to be called check
probably because we're just gonna use it
to check our answer so the only thing
we're really missing is we have to load
in the initial values this by the way
needs to be the floor function that I
just implemented and this UVW here again
we have that that hiding problem which
is kind of annoying but yeah I'm not
sure what I want to do about that
I'm just kind of hacking this in right
now because I don't I don't really want
to change the names of these I want them
to stay the same but
there's not a lot I can really do about
it right now because I I want them you
know I would just turn that error off
but I like that error normally so I'm
just going to hide their names real
quick and then we can restore the names
later once I pull out the older teen
because we're not going to run them both
in place you know forever so now we just
have loading which we have to do right I
actually don't know what's wrong with
this one though Oh inva seldom is not
supposed to be off of grid it's supposed
to be using these so we just have to
load in our initial values now and then
we have to figure out a way to get our
tile information in here right and like
I said getting the tile information in
here is probably going to be the worst
part you can see that now this has been
streamlined to at least a first
approximation there's actually not very
many instructions in here compared to
how many there were
could we do better than what we've got
here absolutely you know there's a lot
of broadcasting in here and there's no
question that we could improve how this
is actually working so I mean just to
give a simple example you know this is
this is also kind of why program stream
was kind of hard so I would probably
never have written this if I wasn't
programming on stream it's just it's
hard for my brain to keep up sometimes
when trying to explain things and do
them your that part of your brain that
would be a little bit more creative and
a little bit more observant is not
really capable of delivering what it
normally would but you can see that this
is really stupid right because what's
what do we do here well we broadcast out
these things 8 wide and then we
immediately send them together it
doesn't really make any sense because
why wouldn't you just add them together
first right so you know the sensible
thing to do here would be just to do
like you know that or something and and
add these to write some kind of a
composite because that takes care of
this first round of pluses right away
you and I'm saying so it don't make no
sense like I don't know why you would
ever do that
there's there's no point there's no
point to it right because you might as
well start with just one with one vector
instead of two I mean I did you know
what I'm saying like this doesn't make
any sense so this is is silly and I'm
not sure why we were broadcasting out
instead of just adding first because
since you know you're gonna add all of
these things together that's what you
would do um so at that point we we
actually probably want to look at a
different broadcast seem right and we
could still broadcast this way meaning
we could just broadcast these out like
this and then sum them right but again
you would only need to do just you would
only need to do this one step right so
it would be first you'd sum to 0 1 and
then you would sum the zero one and the
two three together and and that would
that would be it right there isn't a
there isn't another sum because now
you've added everything that you needed
to add right so again just tons of fat
in here these are not the kinds of
routines you can really write on stream
bro
that general thing so I'll just sort of
say a sort of a separate philosophical
point here so one of the reasons that
sim D is a crap instruction set is all
of this crap that I'm doing here right
so in order to create good sim decode
you actually need to be thinking and
when a human being needs to be thinking
that also means the compiler needs to be
thinking and both of those things are
expensive it costs to have a human being
spend time thinking about this routine
it costs to have compiler vendors have
to try and figure out how to do that
sort of thinking in code and as a result
the the binary is produced by modern
compilers have a hard time taking
advantage of sim D with the SSE
instruction set
if you compare that to something like
avx-512 one of the reasons that a lot of
programmers like the avx-512 instruction
set is because it's actually complete
instruction set
it has scatter gather so it can bind and
unbind stuff to the right lanes without
having ridiculous pattern shuffle
questions abound
it has masking so it can do branching
properly without having to worry too
much about what's going on and without
costing registers it's just easy to like
if you have a piece of code and if in
you had a full performance avx-512
pipeline it's actually really
straightforward to change the code into
that format right whereas getting
optimal SSE for code from a routine is
actually something that requires a
trained professional to a certain degree
and we're doing a basic job of
transforming this routine right now but
I guarantee you it is a far cry from
what I probably could do if I sat down
and thought about this code exclusively
for a weekend I could do a much better
job and so that's just not a good
instruction set right because the more
like the more Rockstar assembly language
jockey you have to be to get maximum
performance out of an instruction set
the worse it is because only so many
people are capable of doing that and
even the people who are capable of doing
that can only afford to do it on so many
pieces of code right and so it's just
SSE is a very bad instruction set it's
one of the worst wide instruction sets
I've seen avx-512 is significantly
better unfortunately it doesn't
currently exist really in most CPUs that
anyone has and neon is much better as
well so neon did this stuff much closer
to like how avx-512 sort of does it and
so if you're using an arm neon chip and
modern our neon chip it doesn't have
these problems either so it's just worth
noting that we happen
programming on the worst instruction set
designed the most poorly an SSC as far
as I can tell was mostly just designed
to make Intel's engineering job easier
and not really designed to have
programmers actually be able to output
code which was unfortunate and the
results speak for themselves
very few programs are actually able to
take advantage of the actual power
behind sse because in order to do so you
have to like restructure your entire
frickin codebase anyway that rant aside
let's move on so assuming that we
finished the some stuff here which like
I said was just kind of done stupidly so
let's just we can leave it sort of semi
stupid but at least we remove the one
absolutely absurd thing that we
definitely shouldn't have done so at
that point what we really want to do
here is just say well you know and just
just to keep going if you think about
all the opportunities we ever since all
this stuff gets some together you can
basically reorganize any of the lanes
for free to so you know there's stuff we
could pull out here that would be more
efficient blah blah blah blah blah right
so you can kind of tell that there's a
plenty of things here that can be done
we're not going to do them we're just
gonna leave it for now because it's
already gonna be massively better than
what we had before so we'll just ignore
that part but so may come through here
we then have this problem that really
what we need is we need the tiles here
right we need these values and so that's
the one missing part of the equation so
basically if you add that to these
simple parts up here what you basically
have is just like our loading process
loading the data into this routine is
really what we haven't done yet and so
what we need to do is start to take a
look at this part
these ones are trivial like those are
not hard to load but these are going to
be substantially more difficult so if
you take a look at what has to happen
forget clamped you can see here that
what we're doing is we're basically
making sure that we never sample outside
of where the voxel is actually legal
right
and so what we want to do here is say
okay we probably want to call
exclusively this like right look what we
basically need to do is this and we need
to do it a bunch of times right now
because we know the dimensions of this
voxel we actually know the values that
we need to add for each of these offsets
so what we can do is we can compute one
pointer hmm and then we can just take
that pointer and offset it eight times
right so we shouldn't actually have to
do what we're doing here we should be
able to actually load this stuff up in a
much more direct fashion sampling these
tile locations is is just fundamentally
much easier than that right now what I'm
not sure about yes so you can see 60y
here too right now the other nice thing
about this is that we don't have to
worry about being offset in ways that
would cause us to fault because we know
that we're that we have a one pixel
apron around the whole thing
so we're also in a really good state
where we don't have to worry we can
actually do a flat load of this thing
and when we do the load we don't have to
worry about that extra part so if you
look at what's gonna happen here we're
basically blowing a lane like there's
one lane just not used we don't care
what garbage goes in that lane so we can
actually do these flat loads we don't
have to worry so you know basically we
can do you know load ups is on these and
load off the the pointers I don't know
we probably have that right cuz yeah so
we can just do load f/32 for X here and
I think what we want to do is just load
these tiles right so we just want to
load them dry
and so we're gonna have like a Texel
pointer here and what we're gonna do is
we're gonna have sort of like a series
of things we want to load out the Texel
pointer with like various offsets right
so in each of these cases we've got like
an X offset a Y offset and a Z offset
you can sort of see what's going on
there right so I think we just want to
do something like this
nope probably don't want to write it
that laughs there we go
nope okay so what you can see here is
I'm just recreating this exact pattern
so you can see we have the Z offset here
and you know honestly if I was writing
this a little bit more sanely
let's actually not do that if I was
writing this a little bit more sanely
let's just do it in reverse order so we
know that we're doing it sort of this
way right and so if you look at that Z
offset probably the smartest thing to do
here is this right and then each of
these is just going to be is it the X
the Y or the X Y right so it's like the
first one is nothing the next one is X
the next one is Y and the next one is Y
X right and so that would in theory
allow me to load these in a fairly
straightforward fashion but yeah I mean
but nothing that's really all there is
to it
so we just need to produce one texel
pointer and then we can do these loads
very straightforward so you can see we
can get rid of like 99% of the work
that's
actually go out of here but there's a
couple of edge cases we need to be able
to take into account for example if
you're sampling off the voxel we want to
make sure we're sampling in the voxel so
there's a couple things that we want to
be able to do there so the first thing
we want to be able to do right is the
offsets here we want these offsets to by
default just not be things and then if
we're in bounds to the voxel then we'll
actually set them to stuff right but
otherwise we won't and so when we
actually produce this Texel pointer here
we're going to produce the Texel pointer
for the base voxel which we will clamp
in bounds and if we've determined that
it is in bounds then we will set these
offset values otherwise we will not
right
so that's that's sort of the way we're
gonna do this and this actually probably
will happen like here I would assume is
probably what's actually gonna happen
but kind of take a look at that later so
really this whole thing is is not super
important right the txt Y can already be
baked in so when we do this initial
thing we don't because we're sampling
from the same octahedral map slot we
don't ever have to permute that so that
extra work can just be done once it
doesn't have to be done eight times
right so again just massive savings we
can clean out I don't know how much of
this the compiler was doing but based on
that spot check of the code that I did
like I didn't even bother because it was
such a mess but I was just like we got a
we got to write this in a way the
compiler can do something clean with it
because it was already a disaster so how
many things compiler actually spotted I
don't know but not enough was the answer
and so I'm just trying to clean the
whole thing out and just write a
sensible routine that I think the
compiler will have an easy time with
right okay so again we're just trying to
produce base offsets here so that you
know we can basically do offset you know
register with with base register plus
offset register kind of addressing here
and so we just need to produce these
values
and the X offset Y offset X Y offset so
in here I'll just produce the X I'll
clear all these registers out and then
if this thing is in bounds
we'll just produce those offset values
and then we'll address off them after
that right so let's start by actually
trying to decrypt some of the stuff and
we're gonna have to do the actual
clamping here I don't actually know how
I would want to do this but I suspect
that I can just again rather than trying
to do an incredibly fancy version of
this routine if we just lose one lane we
probably can just do the straightforward
thing of taking the X Y Z's directly
loaded I would imagine so if we did
something like this I don't remember how
we do our u3 two loads here but we've
got yeah so we can do this right and the
problem that we'll have here is that
these are actually signed values so we
probably want to have a separate routine
for loading these up I don't really know
why we're doing it this way
III don't know that that makes a lot of
sense but it's okay doesn't really
matter but point being these are
probably signed value so I would imagine
when they come in here right am I wrong
about that yeah cuz we've already well
actually you know what I guess now I
think about it we don't even have to
load them I don't need that because
we're actually just well no you know
what we yeah no we don't so what we
fundamentally we need to do here is we
need to load the bounds the that we're
clamping against I guess is the way to
look at it so if we if we come back here
to get tuck clamped right you can see
that we're doing clamp where we have two
lewd voxel dim minus one right so we
want to do there is we want to be able
to load in these values and we need to
then clamp against them so if we wanted
to do that we could do that wide the
only problem is you know as I'm thinking
about it I'm like well but then we're
just gonna have to transit it out anyway
like is that really the smartest thing
to do I mean maybe I'm just I'm kind of
conflicted like I don't know what to
make of it I'm not sure how I want to do
that front part
so I think I'm just gonna do it wide
because because wide wide not so yeah if
I want to do this wide we can load the
voxel dim indirectly right so what I
would do here is just say let's load the
axis voxel dim so we're gonna have
something like this right where we've
got the x y&amp;z loaded into the voxel dim
and so whatever Atlas we're sampling
here which is diffuse setlists right and
I don't know why we said diffuse
setlists because it doesn't have to be
the diffuse Atlas but you know it's
whatever Atlas you wanted a sample from
we just don't ever sample from any other
Atlas at the moment but you know so in
here we would just say look we've got
the diffuse that lists dimension here
we've got some various constant values
like 1 and then we probably want 0 as
well so up here we would say well
there's 0 what is it like 0 for X yeah
so we start off with a couple of values
here and if we want to we can subtract 1
from this so we can say voxel dem minus
1 and we also have 0 so if you want to
do a clamp we just can write so we can
say like the clamp X Y Z equals clamp
you know and I should probably just do
like f/32 voxel max or something and
store this value because I'm gonna need
it twice at least I think I will
so if we do the voxel max and zero that
would clamp the incoming XYZ coordinates
right so we've got our X Y Z here and I
guess I I knew where that is because
that actually comes out of the first
computation that we do so like if we
look down here the UVW coordinates we
don't need to later but I might just
grab them all and put them at the top
just because they're kind of things we
actually care about so the B chord value
here that's our X Y Z so we already have
the B chord value and what I want to do
with the B chord value is I just want to
clamp it right now the nice thing about
this is so once I've done the floor on
the B chord value the really interesting
thing I can do here is I can also just
say well actually why don't I just
produce a simple location from this
where I can just say oh well when we're
actually doing this clamping I can clamp
two things I can clamp so I can say like
the min XYZ and the max XYZ right which
are just the two sides of the cube that
I want to sample on so what I can do
here is I can just literally do a plus 1
and a minus 1 to some priest abuse the
Max's way and a plus 1 on the B chord to
get the far one if I clamp both of these
now I don't have to do any testing so
this if statement doesn't have to occur
right so now what I can do is I can
produce these by just doing extracts
right it's pretty straightforward
so so actually I can just do this these
can just be extracts where I extract you
32s from these things right so I can get
the 0 the 1 and the 2 out of these and
all these are going to be is the the
Delta right so the Delta X Y Z is just
going to be the max XYZ minus the min
XYZ right
and so if both values were out of bounds
and they both clamped down in either
direction then I will just have an on
Delta and we'll just sample all from the
same tile right which will be fine
but if they weren't then I'll sample
from you know the eight corners as I
should so I think that just works and it
works for all the different kinds of
clamping so if only one thing is out of
bounds it'll still clamp properly so I
think that's kind of a nicer way to do
it so if we just like were to extract
you 32s from this thing and I don't know
exactly how we would want to do that
like this is really like a cast of this
thing you know the SSE code for this is
very straightforward but I just don't
know what we wrote in our library so I'm
gonna have to look that up and we'll you
know it's not really a cast it's a
convert you know again it's just one
simple instruction and then then the
extract but you know doesn't matter well
we'll get to that later so this is very
streamlined right we can do that with no
ifs and we can immediately produce this
XYZ coordinates really very trivially
and then we pretty much know exactly
what we need and so now we're just down
to the fact that these here need to get
multiplied by their appropriate values
right so we really want an X Y Z stride
because we can do that wide as well
right so in here we can just say like
well whatever the and in fact I guess
it's not stride X Y Z it's the leg it's
the actual computed Delta so we probably
want the stride X Y Z to be a thing that
we load but this is just going to be the
stride X Y Z times the Delta right so
we'll be able to produce this very
straightforward
these values will just come straight out
of it we will have a base Texel pointer
cure we'll have to do
movement on the pointer and we need to
go grab this light Atlas offset nonsense
which is a huge disaster and basically
we just need to reproduce this equation
now so for each one of the things
involved here there's obviously stride
values that we need to take into account
and you can actually see what they are
so you can see here what all of these
actually what well these values actually
are I don't know why it's done quite
exactly this way but it's all done in F
32 so it's all multiplied out by I'm
sorry V 3s so it's all multi-tap by that
sort of stride value which seems fine I
mean I don't really care I suppose at
the end of the day and so what that
means is like these values for each of
the strides this if we're going to make
this be a load thing that we do here the
load is going to in it's going to have
these particular values this one's that
we're looking at right here so the Z
value stride is this so that's the Z the
x value stride is this
and the y-value stride is this it looks
like right so for every x value it's
gonna go by one tile now for every Y
value it's gonna go by one voxel x Rho
times the tiles right because the Y's
are packed after the x's and then for
the Z's it's gonna go down by however
much it is so you can see it's pretty
straightforward there and so really all
we've got left after you look at those
is we've got this sort of residual
concept of inside the Texel there so
it's it's gonna have to have in addition
to the XYZ offset it's gonna need this
right that makes sense so this is
something that just has to be done
separately because you know we just have
this extra thing that's gonna get added
on there and there's no point in doing
that wide because it's only there isn't
any clamping or anything done to it it
would just waste time transiting in and
out of the wide registers it's just a
complete it's just complete waste so we
really should probably just do it in
scaler and so the base textile value
that we're actually going to be looking
at here is going to look like that right
and that's where we're actually starting
for our textile pointer and from there
we should be able to just load these
things directly right that makes sense
so we're almost done actually there's
not a lot left so if you take a look at
what's going on here we just need to
produce this initial pointer and we do
all the loads off of them we have the
the delta and so if you look here the
final thing we need is like the base
offset of this thing because this is the
deltas right but we haven't actually
produced the initial XYZ and so we're
going to need one more offset value here
or whatever you want to call it
and and that's just gonna come from this
stride we already have being multiplied
by the B chord right well then me an X Y
Z right so the base X Y Z value here
these are obviously all vectors so the
base X Y Z value is just whatever the
mineus times that stride that's how much
of an offset we actually need so then
those just get summed together because
now they've been correct they've been
correctly look multiplied by their
actual offset numbers so all we really
need to do now is for the like base
offset value we just need you know
whatever these are we need to do them
right
so that's it and now our primary thing
to think about is how we want to extract
integer values from this stuff all of
this I think would just work but the
problem so this is not actually correct
because we actually do want to do these
in F these are actually float we can
just do them in float we could do them
binary but 32 I mean we could do them
integer but multiplying integers 32-bit
on SSE is a bit dicey if I remember
correctly in fact
so no it's not I took it back so we
could just do multi cues on these
I'm a little bit torn so if I was just
writing this myself I might actually use
multi cue on it then because you know
you can see here it's really not
different I mean the latency is a little
bit better on the floating-point
multiply I don't know so here's I'm
going to do I'm gonna leave it in float
just because that's what we were using
is our little library that we're using
here and our library is kind of crap so
I'm just gonna say look we're gonna cast
these and that's just how it is so just
get used to it folks and you know don't
don't whine to me about it because
that's just what we're doing so then we
would be able to use everything exactly
the way that it was and all of this
stuff should in theory just work these
might have to have castes in front of
them in order for the compiler to not
complain but other than that it would be
fine
all of this stuff therefore is just
operating entirely in float and the only
thing we actually need to do here is we
need to figure out a way to get these
values out so if we produce 32s for all
of this we need a way to get you 32 s
out of all this so if we take a look at
how the Simbi code is structured here
you can see we have extracts for
extracting floating point values and we
don't really have anything else what is
this
is that really it produces an int for
mmx4 mmx2 act PS
why the heck does it do that we heard so
what do you suppose the point of that
was gosh that's odd huh well it is what
it is
so when Intel extracts those values they
already come out as integers anyway so I
guess if we do a cat convert on that and
then yeah I mean well you know yeah I
don't know what to tell you it is what
it is it's a little strange anyway so I
don't think we have anything for doing
that kind of extraction so we're gonna
want to actually produce that right we
want we want to have a thing here that
allows to get that out and I don't think
I have not seen anything here where we
where we do that right yeah I don't see
anything so I wanna I want something
there that will do that and so I want
something probably that does both of
these together I'm guessing so I
probably want something like this where
we just do like I'm gonna call it
convert s 32 for now because I know
that's I don't know that Intel actually
has a I don't know that they have a
convert you 32 and we don't need one so
I'm not gonna force the issue so the way
this would work is convert s 3 - it
probably has to be unfortunately a macro
I'm guessing because these probably have
to be immediate and C++ is too crappy
you have to make a template I guess if
you want to do that for no frickin
reason so if I want to do an extract
here probably just do an extract epi32
with whatever the immediate you asked
for is and then on the inside it would
be a convert of the input and the input
in this case we want an mm convert of a
nope none of this I always get the so
there's like which one it's on and which
one it's going to I never there is a
rhyme or reason to this naming scheme
however it's one that always confuses me
like my brain doesn't think of it the
way that they do
so like the PS that this interior part
is the thing that it operates on and
this underscore part is the thing it
produces so convert PS epi32 is take a
floating-point pacts scalar packed
single precision sorry and convert it to
a integer 32 return that right
whereas if convert if the epi32 or the
pi32 was on the inside right then and
the PS was on the outside it would do
the opposite conversion does that make
sense and I think the e is like extended
because it's like if you don't have the
e it's it's the S it's the old MMX
registers or something anyway there is a
rhyme or reason to the scheme I always
forget it and hey look it does have an
convert for unsigned so there you go um
so anyway this is what we actually want
convert PS epi32 you'll notice I wrote
it wrong instinctively like I said
and so now we can actually get those
values out so let's ignore this for now
we don't want any of these now and let's
take a look at actually yeah so these
need to be cast a cast and so did I
would assume these we don't have a clamp
and we probably want one right so the
clamp 0 1 that we made now what we
probably want here is this
so in here I just want to have what the
min V and the max V are so here I would
say look here is the max value and
here's the min value oops right and so
this can now just do a clamp kind of
equivalent to its other the other
routine so clamp between 0 and 1 right
and now anyone can use that clamp and it
makes just a little easier for this is
simpler for people to use okay
so I think we're mostly done now hmm
oh crap so yeah oops forgot about the
fact that we need these anyway so
nevermind my original thing wasn't as
stupid as I thought it was because hey
guess what we already had to do that
that's a bummer so because we need these
w's to still be around this shortcut is
not not really as feasible
I mean we can do it but because we have
to broadcast all these anyway yeah
alright so so much for being clever
there's really not much we can do there
right
least I don't see one which is a bummer
so I also wonder about this so because
these two I guess none of these really
matter what order you do them in but so
that's the zero one some two three some
so this is going to be zero two and four
six so I think that's all we need there
two four five six seven all right so so
much for being clever not gonna happen
unfortunately oops that's some so I
think we're down to just loading those
initial values so we're almost
completely done with the routine so
that's good and then we can take a look
at it so this load here again it depends
on how we want to do it we could just
flat load it directly I'm not going to
bother with that
because we don't really need to it this
particular moment we're not at that kind
of performance level where we're
worrying about you know did you do a
little bit of extra work to get the
stuff into the registers then maybe you
should have so we're going to ignore
that for now
and so those could be done much more
efficiently but we're just not going to
bother at the moment these pieces of
information have to come from the Atlas
grid so it would be this right and so I
might just make just so it's easier on
me I might just make I just might make a
alias for that so that I don't have to
keep typing it right so we'll just do
that up here and leave it at that okay
so in here we have the world P
apparently is not unknown thing but I
thought that came in
oh so it's actually it's sample P so
there's that okay so now we should be
able to run this code and in theory
unless we really screwed something up
which we probably did we should be able
to just it shouldn't do anything right
because we're not actually we're not
actually using it it's just running in a
pair it's like running in parallel right
with our with our existing code so what
that should allow me to do in theory is
take a look to see if the compiler well
you know the compiler probably
eliminated it it's probably the problem
I was gonna say we kind of want to look
to see if it generated any better code
but I don't know that we can't because
it probably doesn't actually exist Yeah
right it probably stops here so we'd
like to do is see what the compiler
generates for this code so I'm gonna
have to start using it which is not
really great because
we kind of know that it's wrong but
we'll try it anyway okay and so I'm
gonna do the exact same thing I just did
and I just want to look at the code
right so now we're actually are using
this code or we should be right and so I
just want to take a look and see what
this code actually looks like and so you
can see here the code for the routine
let's take a look at what happens when
we move in here first so a reason I
can't do we never get here show me
somewhere where you get
okay oh I forgot this probably cause of
threading right all right so with
compute Foxhall radiance that here's
where this routine starts right and so
just looking at what it's doing for code
my hope would be and of course the
problem is multiple threads are banging
on this at the same time so we really
kind of need this to be single threaded
if I actually want to look at it but
after it finishes with this SS stuff we
should go down to code that's more not
you know I can't even do this I got a I
got to do thread that first I can't deal
with that so let me just do thread this
first so where is internal lightning
core called so here's internal lighting
core I'm just gonna know if it real
quick and then I'm gonna run so now if
we take a look at the code you can see
it running through here real quick to
produce like the txt Y values and it's
doing that in just you know to get the
octahedral offset or whatever it's
there's the divide and all that crap
right and then hopefully does it is it
actually still doing all this crap I
think it is all right hold on a second
I should also just real quick so here's
the threading I just want to turn the
threading off like that basically um so
what I'm gonna do here is just get rid
of all this code because I don't know
even know it shouldn't be doing most of
this stuff but it looks like it actually
is it should only really compute that
txt Y value and then it shouldn't do any
of this like this is all not not good so
I'm just gonna try that and see what
happens because I just want to look at
the code I just want to see what it
should generate is it's pretty hard for
me to actually see alright so here we go
so you can see us starting to do some
loads in there what is going on I think
remedy might be busted here which
version are we on oh man
okay so we're on a hmm we're on a really
old version which is less good hold on
one second I kind of forgot to update
this machine that's like incredibly old
hold on one second it's just it's remedy
is you know it's good so a lot of times
I don't notice that I'm still using a
really old version but there are bugs
and it does the bugs do get fixed so
kind of gotta just make sure somebody
see ya it's 3:05 the latest version
what's the latest version let me just
make sure I even have the latest version
so
remedy BG that itch what's the latest
version anyone anyone we're just like
download now there's like a 307 looks
like all right so hold please
I'm just really quickly gonna actually
download the latest one because I didn't
realize that I was so far behind on
remedy for reasons I don't actually know
what they are so
let's take a look here remedy
and over I'm gonna close this sure save
it
watch the incredibly complicated install
process for remedy like let me launch
the Installer and download the updates
and the package manager it's just that
it's the executable in a zip file this
is how everything should be and
everything could be if people were
sensible when they made programs but
they're not so that was it that was
updating remedy and here's the update
right Microsoft did you see that did you
see how that works can you fathom it
alright so sorry about that I forgot
that I was using a very old version I
think there were some bugs in assembly
stepping I remember that being a thing
so let me try it yeah so you see how I'm
able to step through the assembly
correctly now so I forgot that in the
baseline 3 0 there was some sembly
stepping bugs I think and they got fixed
a long time ago but I just hadn't
updated the program all right so here we
are stepping through it unfortunately
the little overlay is kind of in the way
there but this is a bunch of singles
stuff so that's probably this code
happening here that's actually a lot of
code to do that we should probably try
and fix that code as well at some point
because that's not great um so at some
point here actually don't yeah it's just
a lot of code for no real reason I'm not
sure where that a lot of that's coming
from might be these weird like loads
that we're doing here so these are all
the converts you can see them loading up
so we could we could try to do that a
lot more efficiently so that's pretty
ugly here's the actual code we care
about starting to happen so now you can
see like this part's actually pretty
reasonable right it's a little ugly
because we have to do all these pee
extracts to actually start computing the
offsets and stuff right but otherwise
it's fine
once we're done with that this stuff
looks totally fine right just very
simple chefs moles ads right straight
line code no spilling there well you
know a little bit of loads in but no
spills look at that very nice remember
how much spilling there was before very
very clean here totally reasonable yeah
that looks fine okay so the top part
still sucks a little and maybe could
stand it but but now we don't have all
that there was just a lot of ridiculous
garbage going on this all looks pretty
reasonable okay so we're good there I'm
happy with that
honestly it looks like it just worked
this is single threaded by the way it
looks like it actually just worked it
could we should probably still do the
comparison but that's that's kind of
nuts what are the chances that we got
the whole thing right the first time or
that doesn't seem likely but but it
actually looks good so it's not too far
off right I mean it looks like it looked
before so we may still be kind of wrong
there I don't know but it looks pretty
good right
so let's lick end there for today we
probably want to do the testing of this
next weekend I would like now to just to
see what the actual performance ended up
being so if I go to handmade debug and I
run this build of HH light prof what are
we getting because remember we were
taking a look at these values here we
can try turning off the cast again we
can also compare against these values so
I'm just curious what we ended up with
if there was a speed difference from
that first pass over the routine which
there might have been I don't know if we
did enough because that top part still
looks really crappy so we're probably to
fix that but let's just see what we got
because I don't know
so actually if you look at that speed
difference its massive actually so grid
with optimized compute irradiance that's
2.3 seconds faster right just from that
so that's kind of nuts right if you look
at what kind of a speeding increase we
got from that that's kind of ridiculous
right that's a massive speed boost and
by the way that would happen here too
right so if we went back to the AABB
tester that's also calling this routine
so if we do this and do a test of a be
walk that one should have been
accelerated to
so yeah since this one so now we can out
so one of the really interesting things
that this uncovers too so there's some
interesting things here right so the
other thing you can see here is notice
that this one did get about a second
faster but this one got 2 seconds faster
what you can see here is that's because
I think our grid ray caster is like way
faster than the AABB ray caster but you
can't tell as much because the grid ray
caster does more sampling because it
does early-out pulls which the AABB
sampler never did right so this one's
calling computer radiance much more than
this one is and so it was making our
grid look worse than it was now mind you
I still think I can take quite a bit of
time off the grid ray caster by doing a
few things to it but anyway point being
really good work there I think we should
be really proud of that haven't verified
it yet so we should probably go in and
actually do some better testing on it
but that's looking really good right
so anyway oops let's get rid of that I
don't know why the ABS why did the a BB
test or not produce any light is it
calling the radians caster wrong or
something I was weird let's go look at
what's going on there because I don't
actually know so anyway that might still
be wrong but if you take a look at this
number keeps going down quite a bit
right and so I think we're making a lot
of progress here just on in terms of
like what's actually happening and if we
take a look at our threads view here you
can also see that like you know I think
we probably if we if we just turned the
debug system off we're already at 60
frames a second because we're really
close to it right 16 if that number 16
which that kind of looks like it would
be I think we'd kind of be there already
so I think we're pretty much zeroing in
on our on our goal here like
think we're getting there but I also
think that there may be some bugs in
that routine so we got to fix that first
right
so anyway point being looking good
quality is up next but the optimization
is looking really good and we have more
we can do so we'll do a little bit more
of that and then we'll switch over to
quality all right we can do a brief Q&amp;A
let me should I guess I don't need to
eject that just now
[Music]
do you plan on bringing your editor on
stream no can you run light prof without
any days can't you run light prof
without any days o light prof without
any rays yes you just want the bookend
value right is that what you're talking
about you want to know what grid book
ends only looks like now so basically
like this and yes we can
so all we needed to do for that was was
this so basically if we just force it to
early out every time it's basically
doing 100% of the work but it just
doesn't actually do this the grid walk
right so if you take a look at that mmm
there you go and unsurprisingly it's
it's sort of similar to this number
right so basically what's happening
there is you know we're down to two
point five four just doing the the read
right there right so
can we time the function with the debug
system so we see how the top part of
that function takes not really because
it gets called too many times why is
frame time stability such a rare
impossible thing without leaving
Headroom yeah I mean you know the answer
is because modern computer architectures
simply aren't structured around
repeatability that's not really what
they do CPUs are currently designed to
just extract the most amount of compute
that can out of their computation units
and that is just an inherently noisy
process it depends entirely on the cache
and on you know the order in which
things have happened so far and it's
just there they're not like the old in
order processors that were just very
lockstep and 100% predictable right so
the way you have to think of it is that
the underlying performance of a modern
algorithm on modern hardware is just
always inherently noisy because it's
never the same exact cash setup and the
exact port fills every time cache
occupancy port status like what's in the
pipeline branch predictor or state Trant
TLB so address mappings all of these
things even if you took the operating
system out of the equation and we're
just running raw all of that stuff
changes the performance right so it's
just you can't no you can't no you have
to treat it as noisy in what you're
trying to do is figure out what the
bounds on that noise are so
do we activate threading in for
benchmark yeah I'm pretty sure we did
first of all the threading is always on
in the benchmark
I sent you an email regarding this to
see stuff you did in today's stream you
might get a smile out of it okay I will
check it out
so as I'm off stream naysayer mentioned
you discussed with him my programming
languages shouldn't have unsigned
integers no I I said they shouldn't have
signed and unsigned integers they should
just have integers and the reason is
because those don't exist in the CPU so
there's just a few operations that
actually differentiate between them
comparison multiplication and division
right some have assigned shift does
theirs are called arithmetic shifts and
like that's what I kind of want to talk
about when I'm programming I don't
really want to talk about this thing as
signed or unsigned because it's really
just most of the time it doesn't matter
like if you add if you do an addition or
subtraction of numbers it doesn't matter
which one you're doing right like you
don't care about those things usually
because most operations that you're
going to do don't care that the thing is
signed or unsigned right and so I'd
rather just talk about it when I
actually want to know which one it is
you know what I mean
that's all
can you compile all files in all
subdirectories with CL recursively you
mean like using the just the command CL
no it doesn't have it doesn't have that
as far as I know can you use some of the
lighting work you do on Hamid here on
different projects I mean it's probably
applicable to low geometry complexity
scenarios so it depends if that's you
have or not when do we add special sauce
I would say that we are kind of always
adding a little bit of a special sauce
alright we good
couldn't the v3 XYZ be loaded with a
single load if we pad them some can some
can't I mean they both can but we so the
ones that are floats we can load
directly the ones that aren't floats we
would have to load and convert which
what we can that's why I said like I
wasn't remember I said I wasn't gonna do
anything with them at the moment I was
gonna leave them but we could write and
so it really depends on how much we
think that's costing us and we could
certainly try it what do we probably do
is not bother patting them first
just try loading them and see what
performance we get and if we got a
significant boost then maybe like oh
okay
we can go ahead and pad them cuz only
some of them have to be padded right
because like if you take a look at
what's actually going on there what you
can see is that in here where we're
doing these loads so if you take a look
at what is in one of those Atlas voxel
grid things right you can see here that
like there's like a cell count thing and
stuff or whatever and so we know that
actually these are just loadable right
we could just load them because they
already have the padding off the end we
don't need this to be zero
we never care what it is it could be
anything and we could always mask it off
even if we did right so we could just
load this could be a flat load and that
could be a flat load this is less of a
flat load because really what you'd want
to do is just pass it in that way which
is what I think we would do in fact this
applies here as well
because we could probably have the outer
code be smarter about how it produces
that sample value so that one could
probably says what can't really be done
that way exactly is these while while
they sort of could be done you can see
they're a little bit more complicated so
this one would have to be loaded and
converted but that's not a huge deal we
could do that and also it's that value
so we could choose to store this as a v3
instead because you know it's free for
us to do so so we could put a F because
it doesn't change right so we could put
that here and do a single load out of it
as well so there's a ton of stuff we
could do I can mark that for you if you
want um so it's really just this that's
a little more complicated you can see
this one is the thing but we could also
store this
right so in a lot of ways we could
choose to weld these values directly in
there and just have them be f/32 for X's
that we just load out because they're
constants right so you know that's
something we could totally do and maybe
next weekend we can look at it right
it's because doing you know mind as well
it's pretty much free to do it are there
any fundamental differences between game
engines that use low poly models versus
this one yeah
yeah I think there would be so the
primary difference that I would say that
you would need to do is our renderer
assumes you're just gonna be pushing
quads because most of the things on the
screen are quads if you were using low
poly models you would need so you know
how our texture system like pushes
things to the card and has like a cache
there for that and whatever you probably
need that for model data right because
you'd want even low poly models get
large quickly so you don't really want
to send those down as quads like that so
I would say you probably want a cache
that's the same as our texture system
but you know for models basically you'd
want something like that so
yeah I don't use emacs anymore used for
coder on stream which I need to update I
need to update to the latest for Carter
this is ancient actually so I was gonna
update to Ryan Flurry's public custom
layer and integrate anything that wasn't
already in there from mine into his so
that it's just in a github somewhere I
just haven't had time but that's what I
would like to do all right shut it down
loop oops
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for an episode of hand made here at Sona
pleasure coding with you as always if
you'd like to follow on series at home
you can always peer to the game at
handmade hero organic comes to the
source code so you can follow along with
it the optimization works going actually
really well so it looks like we're
totally gonna hit our goals we may have
actually already hit them but I have a
bunch of other stuff that I wanted to do
so I'm going to finish doing those
because I think our grid red caster can
get dramatically faster than it is
without a whole lot of extra work there
so I just want to try out some of those
things and and verify that and then of
course also that routine that we just
found was actually a pretty big deal for
us we can improve that a little bit too
without too much work by just finishing
off so in the opportunities we were
doing so actually there's just a lot of
stuff we can do and so since there's so
many low-hanging fruits here to pick now
that we've kind of got things structured
well we might as let's go picking and so
next weekend that's what we'll do we'll
do a bunch of those and see how it goes
that's it for today I'll probably be
back here next weekend for that I
haven't posted schedule yet but I'll try
to get scheduled up relatively soon
hopes you back for that till then have
from putting everyone I'll see on the
Internet piggies everybody