all right we have started the recording
so it should be recording hello everyone
and welcome to handmade Hiro the show
where we code a complete game live on
stream we if you remember correctly at
the end of last week's streams I said
that I kind of came upon the fact that I
really didn't feel like I had a solid
understanding of exactly what the right
sorting rule would be for our game and
you know this is kind of a aspect of my
inexperience with 2d games I'm really
more of a 3d game person I've never
really worked on 2d games or 2d game
technology I've only ever worked on 3d
stuff so I just don't have a lot of sort
of like tips and tricks for like oh
here's probably how you want to sort
sprites or here's the best way to sort
of like if you're trying to fake a 3d
effect here's you know maybe the the
most efficacious way to do that and so
you know I just don't feel comfortable
yet specifically saying this is the way
that this should work and so what I
wanted to do today because I just at the
end of last dream I was kind of playing
with and I was like I just don't feel
comfortable here I don't feel like I
really understand what the trade-offs
are I don't feel like I understand what
what the rules should be or what would
produce the best outcome for us in in
most circumstances and lead to the
fewest hack hacks so I decided that I
just want to spend today's stream
figuring out what I think about Z
sorting for a game of this fashion and
so that's really all we're gonna do
today and I mean you know if we've come
up with something relatively quickly
then we'll just try and start putting
that into code but if we don't then we
don't so it's really just a case of
trying to work that through and giving
ourselves enough time to get to a point
where it's like okay this seems pretty
reasonable so here's day 299 and we are
talking about tile Z sorting
now for the moment the part that I'm
concerned about is only sorting within a
layer so I'm gonna go ahead and assume
that layers can be sorted separately and
you know our rooms are kind of in those
slices that you saw where they're kind
of you know discrete sort of pieces that
that are faded in separately and of the
sort stuff like this but inside a given
room I want to think about how the tiles
the sorting should work and the way that
I started thinking about this what
because I was kind of thinking about it
a little bit today was just that we
could say very clearly that if we were
looking directly top-down on something
right so let's say that we were 100%
top-down so here is like our tiles right
if we were directly top-down then what
we would know is that you know looking
at it here's our sort of our camera and
here's the the tiles right so we're
looking kind of this way down at them
what we would know is that the z-value
would be all we would sort on right
basically we would know that whatever
the the topmost z value is of a
character or a sprites whatever its
highest z point is that is the point
that we would sort on because since no
two tiles will ever overlap each other
and they will only be like higher or
lower we only care about sorting things
that are stacked on top of each other
and obviously when things are stacked on
top of each other the highest possible z
point is the point that tells us what
would be viewed right so then we get to
sort of the second stage of that which
is what happens now when we tilt that
slightly so here was previously you know
the way we were looking at things here
is sort of a you know an example of
something that we might be seeing from
the top down and so in this circumstance
if the hero is standing here then what I
see when I'm looking top down is that
well the kurios highest point is here
the cloaks last point is here the torsos
highest point is there we can sort all
those by Z here's the highest one in the
ground if we sort the highest points by
Z we will immediately get the correct
answer and since we never really care
about any other aspects of it we don't
have a problem now is that 100% true no
it's not 100% true and why is it 100%
true
well it's not 100% true because we don't
really have the opportunity to do this
sorting in a way that is partial right
because if you think about what's gonna
happen we're really not gonna get a
perfect set of tile like this we're
gonna get sprites that kind of overlap a
bunch of tiles right and so we don't
necessarily always have the luxury of
you know of doing sort of whatever might
be the most sensible thing to do here
well you know now I think about though I
don't know that might also be kind of
correct most of the time right if this
thing was higher than the thing we were
sorting then it would clip it and so on
so I don't know if that that actually
might also be fine right so I take that
back
I think it we might always be fine
because it'll sort separately for each
of those right because we're sorting
each of those four tiles plus the guy
separately right and furthermore there
are some cases that people brought up
like let's say we have a rug that went
across all of these well again exact
same things should work properly here
the rug would sort relative to these
tiles any tiles that were higher than
the rug in Z would draw in front of it
in any that were lower than Z would drop
behind it and although that may seem
nonsensical because like hey what you
don't really want a rug having be
clipping into a top well that's what
should happen if you know if you created
in a not really possible world where a
rug is sticking directly into a tile
that's sticking up well that's you know
that's not the renderers fault so I feel
like top-down is very straightforward
top-down is just sort by highest Z point
so where does the complication come in
right the complication comes in here and
I guess you know what let me let me go
ahead and and draw this maybe a little
bit so just slightly differently and
maybe you know what I could do it by I
could do it by going like this
so the complication comes in just when
we're doing this sort of thing right so
now when I'm drawing this I get a
situation where the the sorting by the
highest Z is unfortunately not going to
always give me the right answer and the
reason that sorting by the highest e is
not going to give me the right answer is
because this guy is obviously the
highest but he would actually be drawn
last in this scenario and the reason
that he would be drawn last is because
this angle that I've taken on the world
allows the viewing ray to encounter
these things here right before it
encounters these things back here and
you can just sort of see that that would
always be the case right there's really
nothing there's no way - - there's
there's really no way to sort by just Z
and see that that's happening because
the activity that you're concerned about
is happening in a different dimension
right it's not happening in the Z
dimension it's happening in the Y
dimension assuming again that this is
kind of rotating here around X right so
it's rotating kind of into the into the
Y plane but the the sort of the the
trick that I was hoping to rely on
before and maybe we still can but I'm
just gonna try and sort of elaborate on
what it kind of was the fix that I tried
hoping to to sort of work with before
was the fact that we can know that
because we've tilted the camera in this
way that there's a strict ordering of
things where the closest things are
going to be the lowest things in Y right
so this is going to be closest and this
is going to be furthest right so in
theory it would seem that if we sorted
by Y first and then by Z that might
actually solve our problem and I would
go a little bit further and say that the
closest to furthest sorting we could
also and this is I think something that
I missed when we were thinking about it
on Thursday one of the things that was
tripping me up is well when you have
these continuous moving pieces like
entities
right then it gets kind of confusing
because you end up with these sorting
problems where it's like well how does
this guy sort relative to you know this
thing and what I realized is we could
actually get around that fact
potentially by quantizing you to the
tile that you're in right and so in
other words we could say well there's a
sort and the sort quantizes you to a
tile so you're always considered to be
at a tile center when we do the sort so
no matter where this person moves on
here it will always sort inside this
column and then inside this column we
could still sort by ascending Z and I
don't know why I thought of that I
thought of that today when actually Anna
and I were taking a look at some of the
art stuff I just kind of popped into my
head like huh
and so I think there's something to that
I think what may be the part was that I
was missing is since it does appear to
be true that absent any other
information you know that you can always
draw in this order right we know that
that we're always going to encounter
these things before we're gonna
encounter these other things maybe
really what we need to do is just say
okay we need to quantize people into
tiles and sort them inside the tiles
because that's really the only way that
we can you know that we can make sense
of what should be happening right and
the other part that's kind of
interesting about this right is that we
you know if we if we assume that
everything was contained within a tile I
think that would work so I think that if
everything was quantized down to a tile
and everything was roughly tile size
then we would have pretty reasonable
sorting so the part where that starts to
break down is the case that we were
talking about sort of someone brought it
up on the on the on the post stream QA
the problem with doing that is what do
you what happens when you have objects
that don't really do that so let's
suppose you know we have a table or
something like this where I guess a
better example that was brought up
before was like a rug so that someone
could actually more plausibly be on on
top of it right I mean maybe you know
characters don't generally stand on
tables unless everyone's drunk but you
know assuming that we have something
that's like a floor covering well the
problem that we get there is we could
easily still write the quantization rule
that probably makes this work correctly
and that quantization rule is just to
say that it should be sorted along with
its front most tile whatever that
whatever that tile might be it doesn't
really matter which one we pick because
X's are relevant here so as long as a
frontmost tile and Y that's fine and we
can quantize it to like that row but the
problem that we run into there is then
it will draw in front of anything that's
in this back row and that's not actually
what we want we still want this thing to
be sorted relative to these other tiles
right we just want it to be sorted such
that we want it to be sorted such that
it covers over those tiles but allows
other people on those tiles to be
standing on top of it right so that's a
little bit confusing and that I think is
the part where I'm a little bit hung up
and I think that's because once you
start linking those stacks together now
you have a case where you have to say
well now I really can't say that
everything that's here is always drawn
in front of everything that's here
because really this thing is sort of
kind of goes across all of them and
creates this sort of weird cross-cutting
concern
so I don't really know what we do about
that right I mean one thing we can do
about it obviously is we can try to
create some kind of a special sort
system that you know takes these things
into account but what would be nice is
if there was some way to sort of you
know if there'd be nice there's some way
to create a rule that would be
intelligent about how these things are
picked up so let's suppose for for
amusements sake let's suppose that we
want to start taking this into account
in a more systematic way what I was
thinking is somewhat plausible is we
could start to think of the sort as a
little bit more painters algorithm right
we could sort of we could think of the
sort as something that was going to
what's the best way to what's the best
way to say this we could think about the
sort that was something that was going
to take into account sort of the way
things extend like the actual planes and
look at which one should be the correct
one right which which order of drawing
these things should be the correct order
so if we have something that's you know
a flat piece like this and then we have
another thing that's sort of standing
upright on it and we know that here's
the Z of this guy and we know that
here's the Z of this guy you know we
know that he doesn't get higher as it
kind of goes further up because we have
the information about sort of whether
it's you know what kind of a plane it is
and so that kind of gets us back to the
upright versus not upright sorting I
don't really know if you know and we
could generalize a little bit to say
like well we give it a plane equation or
something like this but I don't really
know if that's a profitable route to go
down right it's it's it's sort of in the
back of my mind it's like well you know
we could start sorting these things more
more real but I kind of feel like we
should be able to come up with more of a
tricky
I'm we're a clever sort of way of of
doing this right but I'm just not sure
what that is so you can see if we
enumerate the cases of this particular
of the rug situation right
so here is the problem that we have
suppose that we take those four floor
tiles and now we place this rug on if
the rug is obviously an entity right and
then standing on here is a hero element
right this is this is a hero so what we
would want to see right when we actually
draw this thing and let's say that we
will be more specific here so let's say
we give each of these things a letter so
there's well I guess I can't quite do it
so a maybe I'll draw this a little bit
bigger so I can actually label it so
here's a there's be there see there's D
and then we put on here an e which is
the rug and then we put the hero which
is the F okay so what we want to see
happen in this case is the sort order we
would like to produce always is we don't
really care too much about the order of
C and D relative to each other or a and
B relative to each other but otherwise
we have a pretty much complete ordering
of how we would like to draw these
things back to front right we would like
to draw a first we'd like to draw B
second or these are interchangeable
right we don't really care about those
then we have C and D also
interchangeable then we have E and then
we have F that's the order we would like
to draw them in and with thinking about
sorting things inside columns with
quantization obviously inside if we just
considered the tile B and we sorted it
with that rule everything would work
fine right we would produce the the sort
of sort be e F which is the correct
subsequence for inside this tile the
problem comes when we're trying to
figure out what happens in a C and D
right and you know there is a single
sort order for how these things have to
be drawn but each individual tile sort
could have in theory produced something
different so although this tile sort is
AE which is you know and see e and d e
right inside each of these it does
happen
that sort is all ken can all be
represented here right so I guess that's
the part that's that's really kind of
tricky is it's like if we were to
produce a sort for every tile and then
somehow merge those into a single
drawing list then in theory it would
work right in theory that that works you
obviously have the possibility for
ambiguity here or rather the possibility
for a conflict which is to say let's say
that the way this looked from from a 3d
perspective right was something more
like this
so here is a block this is the block a
we've got C D and B here
right and then in here we've got the rug
that's on here
right and a protrudes straight up
through the rug so the rug is actually
interpenetrating right well if we have
that situation I mean yes it's sort of
illegal but I mean you know in a 3d
rasterizer we use the z-buffer we just
kind of like suck that up right so if we
wanted to produce something reasonable
what we would see here is well in this
one tile even if we produce sorts for
all the tiles we would see that we had e
a here right Electronic Arts registered
trademark you'd say that we'd have e a
there and there is no way to really
produce potentially the the rendering
order that you want because we said
perhaps that we wanted C in front of a
because it comes first and why but then
now we're saying that E which has to be
on top of C is coming behind a so you
have an impossible sort order you can't
you can't have these two things appear
in a particular order and these two
things appear in difficult order if that
order is different right that's just not
going to work and so even if we did do
all the sorts we could still end up in
situations like that and we would have
to have some way of knowing how to
resolve it right and it's unclear how we
would do that so I don't really know
what the right solution is there I mean
one thing we could certainly do is just
break this rights up right you could
just straight up cut this rights into
pieces that get sorted separately and
you know is that a awful idea not
necessarily right that could be a
totally reasonable that could be a
totally reasonable thing to do I don't
know what the right solution is there I
really don't
I mean one thing I guess I would say is
this is why you don't tend to see a lot
of 3d sorts of stuff in 2d games right
typically you actually go ahead and do
regular 3d for this sort of stuff and
you know that's that's the reason why
because there's really not a lot of I
don't know that there's a lot of clarity
that you can really get from something
like this I don't know that there's a
lot of I don't know that there's an
elegant solution to it right and so
typically you end up just not doing
stuff like that right you're like well
we just don't allow like we don't allow
floor coverings to go in that way or you
know we don't allow there to be height
changes in the floor so that way we know
that we always just sort by Z and we're
done
I don't know so yeah it's a little bit
iffy I'm not really sure what I think
about it yet
and I can't say I'm really feeling
particularly enthralled with anything
that I've said so far in terms of like a
key to a good solution what I will say
is that sorting by sorting everything by
Z it purely top-down really does seem
like a very straightforward answer that
does work pretty well right and I do
wonder if perhaps that doesn't generally
work pretty well I wonder if maybe we
can just do something where the Y
component of things maybe we can fold
that into the Z somehow and it just sort
of works I'm I'm curious if there's
maybe something there that I'm
neglecting that's actually a relatively
simple solution and I'm just not sure
but like I said you know if you imagine
kind of looking at this top-down
wherever that was over here I'll draw it
again so if we imagine looking at this
top-down right so here's our and maybe
I'll try to do this in a way that we can
actually draw the actual heights of
things so if you imagine looking at this
top-down you know and here is a hero and
then we sort of look at it more in a 3d
setting and maybe the hero is kind of
down in like a bit of a pit
right and maybe there's like kind of a
very tall one here and it goes down to
like a very short one here so you know
if we were to look at this from here and
the hero you know here's the hero kind
of standing back in here so the hero is
like you know there's like a dotted line
kind of coming well that's not a dotted
line let's try that again so if the
hero's kind of standing over here then
can i erase I don't know if I can erase
the eraser is II the eraser is II
brushes B oh my god it's huge how do I
make tools tinier
brush size let's get that a little
tinier there we go
all right lovely so assuming that the
hero is standing here and this is kind
of what we're looking at right then at
first when were pure top down again
sorting by Z I think just works for most
purposes there might be some artifacts
that that we might worry about a little
bit there but I think for the most part
that's probably what will be acceptable
but what's not good is once we start to
tilt a little in view from the side then
this thing has to occlude here now one
thing that's true about that is that
it's higher in Z so it would actually
sort properly so this one is not really
I guess so much the concern the concern
perhaps is more this one right which
will sort in front of this guy which we
don't want it to and so that's where the
y part of things comes in if we do our
sorting by Y then we you know again I
think we would end up with a reasonable
solution here because we would still
have this you know sort by Y and then
sort by Z this guy is still always above
in Z of whoever he's standing on so
that's not a concern and you know yeah
so it seems like that would really just
not be a problem so I think for the most
part sort by Y a sort by Z works for the
things that are contained in the tiles
so if we then say well now we've got a
situation where we want to extend
something out that that exists kind of
cross tile wise and I guess you know it
seems to me like the only time that can
really work I mean the only time that's
really gonna happen realistically is
when things are flat like when the when
the ground is relatively stable so you
know we're talking about a situation I
think that has to look kind of like this
these Z values all have to be very close
otherwise you can't really put like
you're not gonna be able to put you know
a table or something on top of these
with if they're not fairly flat to begin
with so you're talking about a thing
where they're already pretty flat and
then we're talking about layering on top
of it something like a rug or whatever
we're going to put on top there so in
that circumstance where we layer on top
of it you know a rug or whatever is
going to happen then our problem is that
why sorting is is going to make it
difficult for us because now we have a
situation where the hero who's standing
back here should always sort on top of
this because at the point where the
hero's being sorted the rug is clearly
underneath them but if we were to sort Y
if we're taking the Y into account we
end up in a situation where you know
this would have to be assigned out here
somewhere and why in order to sort in
front of these tiles that it's clearly
on top of so yeah so again really con
tricky what we could maybe do here is
like I said the planar sort of sit thing
does make a little bit of sense what we
might be able to do is say if we were to
say what the plane was of each of these
things don't ask me what that crazy
errant line was if we were to use some
sort of planar math for this then what
we could sort of say is well would this
thing sort in front of this other thing
at the point where they coincide right
so we could say well the point where
they coincide is here would it sort in
front the answer is yes right well there
you know that that is OK in some sense
it's not OK in other senses the the
reason why that's a little bit difficult
is not because we couldn't write the
grater to do it the reason why that's a
little bit difficult is because we also
would have to clip things and the reason
that we'd have to clip things is let's
suppose that we then had some more like
stuff out here this would sort in front
of these which I guess is actually is
that okay I guess
might actually be okay though well no I
mean okay so take this other case right
when we're talking about the tile you
know if you imagine extending this tile
out to sort it against this one or
something as a plane you would see that
this was supposed to draw first but
really we want to draw this one first
right because we don't want these to -
we don't ever want that one - to sort of
intercede right hmm
so I still just I still just don't know
I don't feel like I I don't feel like
I'm getting anywhere on this it feels
like something where I just I I can't
think of what you can do besides
actually start representing the things
in 3d to cover that case now maybe the
right thing to do is just say well we
can't do that then right like we we
don't have the ability to do things like
a rug on the floor that's done that way
like it has to be done in tiles right
but that does seem like kind of an
encumbrance because typically you know
you figure you're gonna want to make a
thing where there's you know a sofa or
something that spans two tiles you know
and you're gonna want that to work
there's my top down sofa
I suppose one thing that maybe would
make sense let's think about this for
one second so suppose that we were to
look at this in a little more like as an
actual three-dimensional problem and
let's suppose that I took what was
happening in that case so I've got two
tiles here's the center point of each of
the tiles I'm looking down on them I
then have a rug that's like you know
stacked on top of it and I've drawn them
a little probably a little more
separated than they would actually be in
reality because I just wanted to be able
to to draw them both you know and I've
kind of got this notion that there's the
highest point on these guys or whatever
and then I've got a Kuro and the hero is
standing here and his high it's got a
highest point so what I actually want to
go and look at these guys if I am to
look at their you know let's take some
examples of like where they project
right so the hero projects on here
you know these got these tile that top
projects like they're this tile projects
like right here and this guy projects
right there right on the line so we
would know what they're sort of z-value
was relative to the camera and the
problem there I guess is that by you
know depending on which point we would
pick on one of these objects right you
know let's say we picked this point it
would sort in front of the hero right
whereas if we picked this point it sorts
behind the hero and you know somewhere
in between it switches so the problem
with that right is that normally when we
want to do some kind of sorting things
we know that we're doing it sort of per
pixel and so we don't have this problem
of well which point do we pick to use
for sorting when we're sorting first of
the camera now what we could do is look
at the minimum and the maximum I suppose
as well so one way to look at to sort of
talk about this problem a little bit
differently I suppose is to look at the
the lowest point right and where does
that project on right and you can see
that if we if we have sort of the
extents I mean the other way like a suit
is like the extents like project the
extents right onto here of the other
thing we would sort of see when objects
sort of encompass other objects we we
actually do know by looking at two
values from them we actually would have
that piece of information right and so I
guess one thing we could say is you know
looking at how this thing projects onto
this other you know onto the line maybe
we can make some determination of that
so you know if we were to take a look at
at sort of the cases that can occur
along this view line for two objects
right you know we've got object a we've
got object B with they're extents
projected onto the view line we have a
couple of different cases we have a case
that looks like this so they're disjoint
and in this case where a and B are
disjoint then it would seem to me that
there'd be probably no way that
projected onto the view line that if a
is always coming if every point in a
comes before every point in B then one
would assume that a always draws in
front of B right because that's the case
where like you know you've got this tile
and it's always here and this tile is
always here so there's never any way
that these you know this tile could
never possibly appear in front of this
one no matter what right we've got the
situation where we have an overlap right
so we've got a is here right and B is
here so they've got some area in common
and so that seems like a more ambiguous
case right and then finally we have the
case where one is inside the other right
so we have like for example here is is a
let's say and B is is is actually the
interior
so be is like sort of wholly contained
in a and so you know looking at these
these cases right when there's a slight
overlap between the two then you know
that again is something that could come
from say you know the rug being
underneath the the person right we could
have that for like let's say here's the
rug here's the rug and here's the human
and here's the view line we would know
that like okay when we project the
extents of this guy onto here and
extends onto here like so
just straight project just looking at
literally just the Z values going down
you know we've got a case like this
where here is our a and here is our B
and in that case we would want to draw
the you know we'd want to draw the guy
first right the guy is standing on top
of this so it should sort of appear over
this but if we were to slide it back so
if we were to put a over here we would
still want to draw but now we've created
exactly the same case right we still
want to draw this guy first but just by
sliding this guy backwards we've shifted
it so that now it's the other way round
so looking at this case it doesn't seem
like there's really a lot of ways we can
tell what was actually supposed to go on
there right I mean it doesn't seem it
doesn't seem like there's really all
that much that we could do
yeah at least not that I can see
so I just I don't know that doing any
kind of slicing in that fashion is
really gonna help us I suppose
you know if we go back to sort of the
concept that there's there there's two
sort of Cardinal things there's things
that are sort of flat and things that
are upright if we look at something more
like that then you could maybe see how
these sorts of cases would get resolved
because we'd have you know here
something where we've got you know a an
upright card and a flat card and the
question is well how do we want to sort
these two together well knowing the
extents of the upright card and the
extents of the flat card I think at that
point it probably isn't so hard to
determine what should happen because
since we know that this is an upright
card all we really need to probably
determine there is is to take a look at
if we projected them out to where they
both would meet which one would be
higher right so meaning you know if we
if we took the intersection of those two
and we looked at and we looked at the is
the is the Z extents of this guy how do
they work when we when we actually look
at the point where they would have in
common that would probably tell us the
sort order I would think
and that seems to get back to our sort
of upright versus not upright you know
what I mean because really all that's
doing is saying that well
what is that saying really
I mean really that's just saying that up
right things have you know are sorted by
via their Z whereas flat things are
sorted via their Y in some sense
mmm I say
I guess there is one more sort of way to
start looking at this that I haven't
really considered yet which is that
there's also just the notion of I mean
for a lack of a better term there's
they're sort of just the let's manually
consider how the sort is supposed to
happen yeah I don't know about this I
don't I don't see a lot of profit in
this this way of looking things yet I
mean without knowing the planes and it
doesn't seem like painters algorithms
are gonna help you there anyway because
since we know that y'see sorting would
work for any I think pretty much just
works for things contained properly
inside cells because you can just sort
the cells by Z and the you sort cells by
Y and things inside the cells by Z I
feel like the only real problem we have
is those things things that span a cell
that's really the only problem that I
that I feel like we keep coming back to
because there really isn't any I don't
think we have any problems with other
with other things so you know one thing
we could say is just oh you know maybe
for those purposes they're just you know
if there's stuff that spans that's a
cell of that size right like the cell is
that size I don't know how well that
works in practice it does seem a little
bit janky I don't know how we would
really pull that off
but then you would be able to do you
know that's that sort of stacking
behavior correctly
well I really ask you don't see a lot of
solutions to this I'm not having the
bright sorting idea I feel like it
really is down to only that case like I
don't feel like there's a lot of other
cases so I feel like sorting cells by
why and then inside cells by Z and then
Y works right I mean I guess it's worth
noting that inside the cell we still do
have the problem of Y right so you know
if we allow you know inside a single
cell here's a cell if there's two things
inside the cell we need to know that the
wat like their placement in Y here this
is looking top-down that this guy draws
second and this guy draws first right so
I guess inside the cell we still do have
a similar problem right which is that we
have to sort things by Y but we don't
really know what to do with things that
are completely flat because things that
are completely flat like that you know
we can use the trick I was talking about
where the sort point is kind of back at
the end of them
or something like that so we can inside
the cell make sure that those are biased
properly in that way or something like
this
but it's not as simple as just sorting
by Z if we also want to take into
account intra cell like things that can
be positioned intra cell which doesn't
happen that much but for things like you
know maybe projectiles flying through
the air right since only one person can
be sitting on a cell at a given time
it's not like there's two people stacked
in the cell but you still do have that
problem of like little floaty things
that float you know flying projectiles
whatever so I'm not sure about that
that's still that does still seem also
kind of come nasty right how to get that
sorting properly because that's that's
why we introduced originally that
concept that there were upright cards
versus non upright cards is like oh okay
we got a deal with that problem at some
point as well
I feel like this is not coming together
I don't love it I don't love it I mean I
guess this is like I said it's it's
maybe why I don't tend to program things
in 2d but I feel like there's got to be
something you can do here with it
doesn't involve having to completely go
all the way down to like a z-buffer I
mean I guess we could just decide to
start using a z-buffer but then of
course we also have to start treating
these as like actually having 3d things
that get rasterized out
not to mention we're wasting all that
bandwidth on the z-buffer that we
wouldn't actually need right because if
we want to do early occlusion we could
do it with the Alpha Channel I think I
mean my understanding of how generally
this stuff works in sort of older things
is that it's much more manual than this
right it doesn't try to be dynamic with
a lot of these things and pretty much
the heights of things were
pre-programmed in and sort of a very
specific way so it wasn't really an
issue if you had something like a rug it
was just known that it was on the floor
in a baked into the bitmaps and so on
and didn't really need to be sorted in
the same sort of way right
so I guess one thing to think about here
let me draw one of those cases again cuz
I'm kind of thinking maybe I might have
messed something up let's see here so
here's the view looking down and we're
looking down on a rug and a hero right
now if we were going to use a z-buffer
then the reason that we know that the
hero sorts in front right because this
is really just an infinitely thin plane
right in in the in the case where we
were doing this with 3d cards we would
just have this right so if we
orthographically are projecting this
against a plane right then you know like
we're gonna actually have the case I
talked about before where we're going to
be projecting these onto here right and
it's gonna look like that and now the
reason why we know that this guy appears
above this guy is because at any given
slice where this guy is where he's gonna
appear on the screen right cuz here's
the area that he appears on the screen
the problem is that's the part that we
need to know if we know where he appears
on the screen he appears on the screen
like right here right here is where he
appears so we only care about the part
of this plane that overlaps that
yes so that might be where we could go
with this painters algorithm wise right
we could say well let's ask the question
where is a point that these two have in
common in this plane right so in the
when when view when we're talking about
viewing them
let's project their extents onto the
x-axis right because we know what their
extents are on the x-axis I'm sorry the
y-axis yeah
it doesn't really matter I guess either
either way is fine so if we were to
reject these on to one of the other axes
not Z right and we found a place where
they overlap so we just say okay we'll
project them on to the x-axis so here
here we go here's here's the proposal
let me know I put the keyword away so
I'm gonna view along this axis so here's
my Z and here's my Y right and this is
my view Z and view why not the world Z
and worldwide but we're talking about
relative to the viewer here if I now
have my rug and I've got my dude and I
guess I'm gonna draw my DS as actual
cards so here's the rug and here's the
dude then if I was to reject these back
on to the the y-axis right so if I'm if
I'm gonna look at just what their Y
points are so the min Y and Max Y of
this guy's card right is here and the
min Y and the max Y of this guy's card
are here
so I know where the sprites are in Y
right like I know what's happening there
so if I know a point that they have in
common which I do if they overlap if
they don't overlap and why they don't
have to be sorted right like I don't
really care how they're sorted in some
sense I don't think well that's not true
if it's a total sort ordering I guess I
do sort of care so they're not
overlapping I guess I have to pick the
closest point in common that they have I
don't know exactly how to do that but
anyway I've think about that
whereas if I have two objects and I need
to know how they're drawn relative to
each other if they don't overlap then
there is no rule for how they draw
related to each other but that would
cause potentially problems I think
because I don't think you could pick
arbitrarily because there may be another
object that overlaps both of them that
would care how you sorted them because
it's going to go in front of our behind
one of them and then if you picked the
wrong way for the other one it doesn't
have the opportunity to get sorted in
there so that's tricky right that's
that's kind of nasty
so I don't know that might that might
also be a deal killer but if we take a
look here and I say well alright I've
got you know in in the the closest point
they have in common which would either
be where they overlap or if they're you
know disjoint then the point in between
the their two closest extents right if
I'm to look at that and I see on that
one where are they z wise each of them
so at this point you know we've got here
and here that would tell me who sorts
where right I mean that's what that
tells me and for that matter I guess
also now that I think about it too you
could think of these as sort of forming
a space partition so I guess really
I wonder
if you actually had everything
categorized as these planes could you
just actually use the planes and test
the planes themselves in fact that's
obviously true isn't it
I mean figure this if I've gotten if
I've got any given plane and I look to
see what side an entity is what which
side of a plane it's on if it's on the
same side as the viewer then it's closer
to the viewer right it's it should be
drawn first so the only case that I end
up having to worry about is if it if
it's actually interpenetrating right so
if part of its on one side and part of
its on the other side and if that's
actually the case then I guess you would
just have to know
well I'm trying thinking what the tight
with what is the tiebreaking rule there
in the case where they actually
interpenetrate there is no way to draw
them correctly so that's not really the
concern the concern is more like where
they don't interpenetrate so let's say
you have this case and in this case I
should be drawn first because I'm closer
to the viewer here so when they don't
intersect I guess maybe you would just
say I mean I'm sorry when they do
intersect but they don't actually
overlap because of their extents but
when there were their planes you know
where this plane would intersect this
other object then how would I know which
one so I've got two cases like one case
is here one case is there and the I
guess in that case where where you don't
have it's not on clearly one side or the
other I guess it's you just go the other
way round
right
so you just test the other plane
I think that might work
I mean like I said it does require all
of the sprites to have a plane equation
and that plane equation I think for our
purposes can always be either the worlds
that the normal to the plane would
always be either the world z axis or the
world y axis so it's not like we ever
have to actually do any work there but
if we're willing to do that I think
that's the sorting rule
what do you guys think about that it's
about time for the the sinks stream to
end anyway
I did what I said I was going to do
which is try to figure it out I think
that's I think that's pretty solid
it would require every sprite to know
its bounds which it does and it would
need to know which plane it was which it
does so I think that would work and I
feel like you could use approximations
like you know if an object is thick you
know if an object looks like this
technically in the world I don't think
you need to represent like it a plane
here and a plane here I think you could
just use one or the other and it would
probably be okay I'm guessing but famous
last words obviously
I suppose it really would depend to a
certain degree on what sorts of objects
you tended to have like
yeah I don't know
I think that's the best guess that I can
come up with at the moment so let me see
what you guys think of that so far that
was my thought process on it some people
who watch the stream might have more
experience with 2d game hacks
let's go to Q&amp;A and see
SSS mcgrath if you're only concerned
about sprites that exist on more than
one cell why not slit the polygons on
cell boundaries there can't be that many
can't be that expensive well I don't
know it's not really necessarily the
expense that I was worried about but
it's more just like they're not really
polygons their upright fake cards so now
you're talking about like splitting the
card in based on the 2d the original 2d
and then redoing it I guess I mean I
guess that would work and then you sort
those separately I don't know that's a
good question
I mean I guess we could yeah we could
always split stuff but then again like
inside a cell you still have to sort
them somehow as well
looks like no Q colons I am assuming
everyone is watching you three
all right well I'm going to wind down
then let me go back here thank you
everyone for joining me for an episode
of hand made here it's my pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always peer to the game on handmade hero
org and it comes to the source code so
you can play around with it and do your
own experimentation we also have a forum
site you go to ask questions a patreon
page and go to if you want support the
video series a schedule bot which treats
the schedule so you know when we're live
and the past episodes archive where you
can go to catch up on old episodes
that's it for today we will be back here
Wednesday for the next stream when I
think we will maybe we'll try the
sorting rule and see if we can make it
work for us that's it for today until
then have fun programming and I'll see
you guys on the Internet take your news
everyone