all righty let's see hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show we
could complete game live on stream you
know I wanted these days have to get a
new I have to get a like a cord that's
long enough so I can actually sit up
straight when I do handmade hero because
I it's like this thing doesn't go far
enough and I'm constantly it's really
annoying I I wish I didn't have this
weird like tether to it's like I barely
can move my head at all what I'm doing
animate here and it really it I don't
like it let's put it that way it's
really really annoying
it's like the annoyingness of things but
yeah that's just the way it goes
sometimes so I should do that that's
what I should do for Christmas I should
get some way of actually having since I
do this every night for two hours I
should have some way of like actually
not hating it the entire time it seems
like it should be pretty easy to do but
who knows maybe it's not of course it
would have been a lot easier if I could
have plugged it into the front
microphone for it but if you remember
way back in the original handmade hero
when I started I had it plugged into the
front microphone port and of course the
front microphone port for whatever
reason when captured through OBS has
like clicks in it how that's even
possible I don't know but that's just
how it was so welcome to Microsoft
Windows in the PC where everything is
unreliable it's always fantastic anyway
doesn't really matter point being we are
here today on day 227 we are going to do
some work on our attract mode basically
getting in and out of the game and some
other things like that that we kind of
wanted to you know just just clean up a
little bit I was sort of pulling things
out and and separating out different
pieces of the game code into places
where they were kind of logically
isolated from each other so that we
could sort of go like okay if I want to
I can start up you know I can start up a
cutscene and that's all self-contained I
can start up you know again
world and that's all self-contained and
I could switch between them and do stuff
like that all of those sorts of things
that's really all I was interested in
doing and we did it mostly but we didn't
quite have time to finish yesterday and
so that's what I'm going to finish today
if you would like to follow along at
home and you pre-order the game at
hammer here org day 226 is the source
code you want to start with here on day
227 so that is what I am doing as well
alright so off we go let's take a look
at what we have left ourselves with and
I believe what we did is we we basically
had everything pulled out but we just
didn't have a chance to sort of finish
the last few things so we don't have any
way of actually starting the game now
because we pulled out that piece so we
come to the cutscene and that actually
works just fine and that starts playing
so that all got pulled out and is
reasonable but if I will on the face bar
which should be starting you know should
launch a hero into the game you know
nothing happens and I can't escape to
quit anymore right all of that stuff all
the interface that would have been
running is now gone and and so I gotta
fix that I also wonder why is this scene
not zooming at all do we know why that
is I noticed that yesterday and I was
wondering if we accidentally like
deleted the zoom from that one scene
right cuz you know we've got it here
where we got our intro shot and that's
this is shot too but it should be
zooming right I mean that's the zooming
right there it goes from 0 0 0 to 5
negative 5 negative 1 right that's
that's how that's set up to zoom but
what's why do we not see anything it's a
little weird right just a little weird
so I don't really know what's going on
there but what I would like to do is I'd
like to figure out what happened to it
and if we take a look here we've got
hero and tree wall and window and
icicles they're all obviously very
different layers levels you know
whatever you want to call that they're
different very different Z depths so I
don't feel like it should be as
stationary as
is and what's weird about that is
basically all the other shots seem to
work exactly correctly right like nobody
else has that problem so I guess one
thing I could do is I could drastically
inflate what the actual DT was just to
just to verify that's not moving or at
least to exacerbate it a little bit and
just see if we can sort of tease it out
at all so there's the zoom in okay so
basically it is still zooming in I guess
it's just so subtle that you don't see
it so I wonder if maybe that's something
we should probably you know just just
exaggerate a little bit you know just
try to make that a little bit more
dramatic as it zooms in because it just
does seem like like maybe that's not
sufficient that's a little bit too slow
for whatever reason so I don't know
let's say I cranked that up to something
where I was actually just gonna double
that that rate for example and this is
probably not worth playing with at the
moment but I'm just curious to see if
that gives a little bit more motion
there and probably what we'll have to do
at some point is maybe you know what
what I'll do is when we actually go back
to sync via stuff up with voice over
with like a soundtrack that goes with
the cutscene when we do that I'll go
back to that second scene and I'll see
if I can make it a little more unjust
you know sort of a little more dramatic
and so you now you can sort of see it
moving but it's still really pretty
pretty darn subtle so I feel like that
I'll probably have to be you know just
just made a little bit more a little bit
more pronounced even than what it is
there so I don't know something like
that not sure but anyway so yeah so
point being what we need to do at this
point
in order to get ourselves back to sort
of where I want us to be is we need to
think about how we're going to handle UI
during these various pieces and I think
what I probably will do is say that you
know I don't really want to handle much
UI during the cutscene
attract mode stuff yeah so it looks like
that's zooming you know K now but I feel
like maybe the boy is is is he's just a
little bit too he has too much motion he
should probably be set back a little bit
more sorry to keep jumping in now here I
don't know why we just bugging me I
don't like it when things are not just
so yeah so anyway I point being I wonder
if the here on the tree need to be a
little bit more pushed to the background
if that makes sense so I don't really
know exactly what the right way to do
that would be but you know something
like this I guess anyway sorry what I
was trying to say was like I don't think
I really want to handle much in the way
of UI during the cutscene attract mode
stuff because the only thing that really
needs to happen is if somebody tries to
start the game it needs to go into the
game mode right but that seems to be
just like the only real I I really don't
feel like there's anything else that has
to happen and once you're in the game
mode then that'll do its thing and it's
all fine okay so that's that's actually
looking better but I think even a little
bit further back than that would be good
but so you know I feel like that's
something that can just be handled
without it being too too much of a deal
where just anything that gets hit we
immediately switch over to the game mode
and the game mode will handle like
player joining and stuff like that
because I want you know if we ever allow
multiple players for real in the shipped
game which I don't know if we will if
we're turned that off or not because
we'll have to see if it makes any sense
to have two players in the game at all
but so if we have two if you have two
different people than what I'd like to
do is I would kind of like to have it so
that you could join it anytime so I the
like fundamental concept that someone
could join the game that needs to like
be in there at all times it's not modal
like you know joining a game can't be
something that's dependent right on
you being in the cutscene it's gotta be
something that's always gonna work right
and so that's that's why I say you know
I really want to make sure that that
part is is handled in the game world so
I think what I want to do is leave all
the interface there and then the only
interface that I'll put inside this you
know the like the cutscene a track mode
is just if anybody hits their Start
button
it immediately pops to the game world
and it lets the game world probably
handle the the UI stuff that it's gonna
do at that point something like that all
right so that looks a lot better to me
by the way I feel like we're getting
much closer now to something usable so
again I don't need to deal with that now
it's fine as it is but now at least you
can kind of see the motion a little bit
better and and it's not you know totally
awful or anything so yeah let's see here
also this needs to be a little bigger
and this might want him yeah sorry so
that's what I'm gonna do and after I
quit fixating on the fact that this is
wrong I probably should have if I wasn't
talking I would have gone and made it so
that we could just optimize that one
scene by itself really quickly but yeah
like I said I'm gonna stop fixating on
it immediately after I see if that made
the size of the dude right here and and
that's that's all that's all you know
just it just once I just want to see
that's all just a little you know I just
want to have a little looky loo at it
all right so he's kind of a little bit
off-center but other than that he's fine
so I'll just say let's just say that we
move him over a little bit like maybe
like that and we'll just leave it like
that okay
so now that we've got our cutscene
fixation out of the way for today let's
suppose that I go ahead in here and I do
a track mode and OH
forgot about this we have a track mode
but we don't actually want it somebody
delete that file forget a track mode
pretend that wasn't there
well we actually want its cutscene here
we go which already in and so when we're
in here and we're doing update and
render cutscene or update and render
title screen really in here I guess the
other thing that we need to do is like
we need to have the title screen right
that's got to be there and we've got to
have the cutscene and the title screen
both when they do their updating check
for input and so I'm just gonna have a
thing since they're both the same I'm
just gonna do a thing that's like check
for start or something like that that's
it and all that's gonna do is it's gonna
do like you know at the end it's gonna
have this sort of thing where it goes
ahead and does the checking so I'm gonna
have a thing that's like check for start
so after it does that it's just gonna
look to see if it needs to do anything
with that so both of these guys would do
it and what that means is that okay we
just have to look for just the subset of
buttons that would do that and so if I
look at handmade I guess its world duct
CVP oops I think it's a world mode
rather if we look at handmade world mode
we we have this whole big block of stuff
right and we've got the part that
actually checks for that start for that
start condition and that's let's see
that is where is that there's a button
for it right or did we leave it in here
it we left in here so here's that code
and you can kind of see that that all
we're really doing is spinning over the
controllers and we're seeing whether or
not anyone push the start button and
there's also the quit button so I should
actually call this check for meta input
or something and that would essentially
just do this this part of it so all its
gonna do is say okay for each of these
guys I just want to know if you pressed
either of these two things whichever one
it was I am going to want to take some
action right I'm going to want to take
some action on that and depending on
what the action is I'm going to do
something
in the case of someone pressing the back
button on the controller we want to quit
we want to exit out and in the case of
somebody pressing start in fact I guess
I can do this as well in the case of
somebody pressing start I want to start
the game and that's really all we need
to do that would check all of the input
that is allowed during the metagame and
so now these two guys can do that so all
we really need to do is figure out what
action we're going to take if somebody
presses the start button then what I'm
going to want to do is in hand-made
world I feel like we've got you know
this sort of like play play world
function what I want to do is do play
worlds so that we actually have a world
that gets started up and then once we do
play world I want to be able to add like
a player right I want to actually
initialize what whoever the player is
that started the game so in here we
would have something like okay you know
we've got play worlds so we'll call that
so it would just be like hey man play
play whatever you're gonna play like do
it and we're gonna need that game state
obviously so TM State game states that
will necessitate that sort of being
passed here like so game state
yeah yeah oops and that way when someone
presses that controller button you know
off you go now
quit requested I don't actually remember
how we were handling that but so I'm
gonna just check really quickly how that
happens so that access is the game
memory and says that you want to quit
the thing so in order to do that I don't
really know I don't really know if I
love that concept I want to see
something about that is quit requested
best put here or is it best put in game
input and I don't know right because we
don't really have a concept of where
that sort of thing should go but it does
kind of seem like might be more
appropriate in here I'm not sure I don't
really know but that way you wouldn't
pass them game memory around for no
reason like that because you know you
would have been dealing with the game
input presumably in order to do it so I
don't I don't know I don't know what I
think about that but I think I might
just just move it there for now and so
then I'm gonna say that quit requested
equals true if anyone tries to quit the
game and that's all we're really gonna
do now as soon as we do one of these
things we're gonna break out of this
loop because only we only want to
process the first piece of input because
that's gonna change the mode immediately
at that point and we don't want to
process any further input I think what
we'd rather do is let somebody else
process the input from there right so
one way to do it in - in fact you know
and I think I might do this I think I
might do it this way directly because
this time it sounds good to me
is hand-made world mode that's got
update and render world I may just go
ahead and say you know what let's just
let you know in the case where this meta
input happens let's just let the other
mode handle the input right
so you know let's let it do one frame of
that or whatever it's gonna do now I
don't really know cuz we're gonna have
rendered the cutscene so what I could do
I don't even know like maybe what we
could do is something like this where we
do like check for a meta input like so
and you know maybe we even do something
where we're like okay we see if we get
anything and if we if we decide to
change the mode then we don't actually
we don't actually do any of our work
right so we check for a meta input and
if there was some meta input and we want
to change the mode we don't do like our
rendering instead maybe we punt and let
the next person render like whoever was
going to render gets to do that right
gets to do that separately so I'm not
sure but like imagine something like
that we're gonna happen so if something
like that we're gonna happen then what I
might say is like okay we want to do
something we're like you know we do play
world and then we would do update and
render world or something like that so
maybe we've got something maybe we even
make this somewhat systemic so it does
something like okay in hand made that
CPP but when we do our little dance here
where we look at what the game mode is
and we do whatever we're going to do
maybe I do something that's like
actually going to loop and it'll like it
can punt during a change in type it can
go ahead and rerun the thing a second
time or whatever so I don't know exactly
how I'd want to do that maybe you know
what I could do is something like this I
could say rerun equals false and then I
could do like rerun you know ills
whatever and so anytime someone wants to
change the mode they can just go ahead
and do that and they don't have to worry
right so that would be like okay update
and
under cutscene update and render title
screen essentially it just says like you
know like this like so on so yeah if we
see that we got some input that would
cause us to change the mode then we let
people know that and off we go
so that should be good I think not sure
okay
and I'm quit requested I guess that
doesn't change the mode so we don't pass
result true in that particular case yes
so imagine if you did something like
this and you're just like okay you know
well rerun something like that seems
reasonable you know it's not the
weirdest thing in the world and so if I
go if I grab this stuff out now this
stuff could all go into handmade world
mode which is I think which is where I
would prefer that that it was I believe
I don't actually know where the best
place for it is but you know maybe it
belongs in here or something like that
and so here in controlled heroes like I
was saying I don't really know where
that should live just yet I don't know
if controlled heroes should only live in
in the game world stuff I don't think so
I feel like controlled heroes should
probably stay in the game stay because
it might persist across different things
so I'm just gonna assume that that's
actually what we want and I want to pass
the game state to this so that it can
sort of play with that alright so let's
take a look here at what we've got do me
add player actually takes the world mode
now so that's how that goes these volume
is changed volume I don't know where
that stuff actually exists I assume
that's in here
I'm not sure let's take a look change
volume it is so if we're calling change
volume on the audio state stuff that
just looks like maybe we need to make
sure that that is included first so
that's just I think that's just an
include order thing the audio should
probably be much higher it should
probably be up with like the assets
because that's a pretty pretty core
function that everyone's gonna call I
would assume
alright so let's keep it going so here
we are with play world play world is
something that we would have to sort of
expose I suspect for people to call so
I'm just going to move that up into the
H file so that everyone can see it
anyone who wants to start a world
playthrough but apparently that's not
working and I don't know why oh I do
know why that is because I don't know
where handmade cutscene is actually
placed again this is the kind of thing
that's just so annoying you know this
this stuff should not actually be
something that anyone ever worries about
it's super annoying to have to manage
dependencies it's like because it's
there's it's literally just busywork
like it's something the compiler should
have always done for you it's really
just stupid anyway point being let me
see here why we can't get to that play
role so here say I made let me just take
a look here Sam a cutscene dot CPP so
hand make up scene dot CPP is right here
and of course that included ham a dot H
so it ham a dot H we know includes a
handmade world right or maybe it doesn't
maybe that's the problem
I mean handmade world meds right there
and isn't that where I put that that
play it's right there so why can't it
why can't it get that what am I missing
play world game state since they're
missing racket before semicolon ah ok so
that wasn't dependencies at all that was
just like closing
the parens alright good good let's see
what else we got here input we don't
actually get in this particular function
but we're gonna need it that makes sense
so let's put that in there and then we
just have to make sure we pass
everything that we actually said we were
going to pass to these guys so they can
run themselves which is always good okay
update and render world is in here date
and render world that takes to be 32 the
P 32 is like I don't really know what
this is gonna be like Rhys Rhys LUT
whatever that is so we gotta have a way
I guess of exiting out return salt it's
which before we were doing with like if
there were no heroes right so there was
like a hero's exist thing and so what we
could do now is say okay when we get
down to the end here you could do a
thing that's like if Heroes exists well
if you're just we don't do anything if
heroes don't exist then what we need to
do is switch back to the cutscene or
whatever so we'd want to do play intro
cutscene for example and we want to you
know we want to kind of switch what
state were in and so in that case the
results well we don't really need to
rerun it for any particular reason
so we should be fine there so play into
a cutscene identify are not found that
again is because we don't now have this
is the dependency thing that I was
actually talking about before but that
turned out not actually the problem is
now actually the problem so we've kind
of got the intro cutscene thing that
we've got a now loft up to the to the
outside which is fine let's go ahead and
find all the things it needs yeah update
and render title screen must return a
value
right you are there is that value
so must you and check for meta input as
well so there we go
mmm quit requested is not a member of
game memory that is true and that is
because I went ahead and moved all right
so now we just got to get this stuff
actually working which of course will
take a bit so let's see where are we at
we are currently kicking off something
with a totally bogus pointer to a world
mode which is not great yeah as you
would expect so when we do feel ground
trunk for some reason it looks like
we're passing a boat passing a bogus
world mode there at least that appears
to be the case so what exactly you know
what I just realized what exactly is
that even who who actually does that
stuff I don't know to be honest with you
don't really know who's in charge of
those those things yeah to be honest the
ground chunk stuff I realized as I was
working on a bunch of design stuff to
send art things to yangshin I realized
that the ground chunk stuff I don't know
if we ever actually need it because
there were some reasons why I don't know
that that's actually ever gonna be used
but we should debug it anyway even
though I may yank it because I don't
know that we actually ever want to do it
so there is that anyway so yeah one of
the one of the things that's a little
bit annoying about about that is we're
gonna have to when we do the mode
switching we're going to have to take
into account the fact that there can be
people using the world mode when we like
exit out right like when you exit world
mode or when you close down a world any
like thread any threaded work that's
still going on on behalf of that world
specifically would have to get shut down
right because you can't delete all of
the memory that's being used to render
the world into the ground chunks you
can't you know that that if those things
are still accessing that memory when you
get rid of it
they will go nuts right I don't know
that that's what we're looking at here
per se because we didn't actually try to
close down a world but it's just
something worth noting right alright so
let's take a look here let me turn off
let's let's start with one thing in time
since we've made a bunch of changes
let's just start by not doing any ground
chunks
well we won't kick off any ground chunk
work at all so instead here when we do
like thrill ground fill ground chunk I'm
just gonna go ahead and get rid of that
right so now we're not doing any of that
at all and so now if I go ahead and run
we can just see like where we're at with
everything else okay so this is a little
bit better because now I can see what's
actually happening which is what I would
I would like okay so this is this is
easy right we've never actually done the
initialization of the World Arena and so
that's obviously got to happen we can't
push this truck before we call
initialized world that's kind of obvious
so yeah so we got to take care of that
so let's go ahead and and and reorganize
that part so yeah world node world that
should actually probably be on the mode
arena right game state so allocates the
world thing and then it initializes it
all right and in some sense it does seem
like maybe that should just be a thing
that does its allocation meaning you
know when we do initialize world instead
of passing it in a world at that point
it seems like maybe since it's going to
have to do a sub arena thing here anyway
it seems like you probably would just do
the actual like you just do the actual
allocation so you know we just call
create worlds like this that seems like
maybe a saner thing to do so then you
would just say oh okay
you know we push struct on the parent
arena to get the new worlds you know we
return it and we initialize its arena as
part of that process obviously so then
that goes away and this is a little bit
more straightforward now that seems a
little bit more sane to me honestly that
that you know that's just a saner thing
all right so let's see create world
identifier not found that is true
because I actually forgot to rename it
from initialize world to create worlds
so now we have a way to create a world
then that's great everyone's happy and
it's fine all right so let's keep going
with the debugging process here so let's
see when we do create worlds we call
Sabrina Sabrina asks for some stuff and
we then say that we can't fit it it was
basically what happened that could be
due to the alignment but I'm not
actually sure so let's take a quick look
and see if that is true let's see if we
have handmade get oops get size
remaining yeah so that's a problem that
was basically a case of us not using our
define everywhere probably because we
added the defined a little bit too late
but yeah we would obviously want to make
it so that they always look for the
correct default alignment there and the
other thing was that looked like it was
set to 16 though so did somebody ask did
handmade world ask for a different
alignment than the normal alignment when
it does it Sabrina like why did that
happen
it looked like it said 16 to me
am I wrong let's try that I'm gonna I
want to see that again
I felt like that said 16 maybe I'm wrong
about that
yeah the alignment 16 so how is the
alignment 16 I don't get it so sub arena
takes a default parameter I must be
going blind didn't I just ah
no okay so I missed one more that's the
problem right there
all right that's what should have
happened didn't happen but should have
happened and so if we want to do a sub
arena of size 16 which you know maybe we
do maybe we don't but if we did want to
do that we would have to ask for its
justice if eclis which is what we want
because we need to ask for that when we
ask the sizes so let me make sure that
that nobody actually really wanted that
specifically that certainly doesn't
matter I don't think neither does that
and I don't think these guys care too
much about this at all yes I'm pretty
sure that nobody actually cares about
that alignment being 16 we could change
the default alignment to 16 if we wanted
to but yeah all right so we're getting a
little further here but you can see that
we're still totally messed up like for
example what happened there I don't know
if you saw it but you know this is the
game I hit the spacebar and we're got
nothing on the screen
in fact it's it restarted the cutscene
which doesn't make any sense so we kind
of want to figure out what's going on
there oh well actually you know what I
know what's going on there
but anyway so what we want to have
happen is we want to when we call update
and render on the world node we want to
create a hero so we need to make sure
that that code path is working properly
and then we can kind of get back to to
whatever we were doing and in fact we
could also see if the ground chunk
updating is actually working now as well
let's just take a look here okay
so that is still busted the world mode
world thing it's still kind of busted
let's see here so the world mode is is
just looks garbage to me so basically
whatever whenever this fill ground chunk
thing gets called so I'm guessing that
what happens is we actually do just
straight-up exit out of the we exit as
soon as we enter which means all of
those field ground chunks do exactly
what I said they would do they crash
because they're accessing memory that's
been freed by the call to play in intro
cutscene right so you can see that
hero's exist is set to zero now I don't
actually know why it's set to zero
because I would have thought that it
would have been set to one so that's a
little confusing to me and I would
probably need to look to see oh there it
is
that's why so what has to actually
happen is this guy has to match right
this has to be was pressed because what
was happening there
was that it would come in here and it
would not have ended down it would ended
up because what was pressed starts
checks for ended up so the check in the
cutscene code was different than the
check in this code and therefore there
was a mismatch right so yeah all right
so still not quite there yet so let's
try looking through what happens during
the controller thing so we can now
actually debug that and figure out why
we're not getting any of this
it looks like cos hero's exist only
happens in this path
that's probably why so this was pressed
adds a player but nobody actually looks
for it yet and so the way we could fix
that is actually pretty easy that is is
really just a matter of saying like okay
just do this again like so yeah so okay
so now at least we're back to something
sensible we could start the game right
and yeah we could exit the game as well
and go back to our intro cutscene which
is what we wanted start again and and so
on hopefully I don't actually know if
that's true looks like we still got bug
here and I also notice that we do have
another bug which is that when I start
the game I I can't move right I can tell
that time is advancing because like the
shadows are bobbing and stuff like that
but I can't actually move my dude around
so that's obviously busted right so I'd
like to see what's wrong there but we're
pretty close now to having things
separated out which means we can sort of
proceed a little bit further so what I
want to do is I want to figure out why
when I'm pushing a button I'm not moving
my dude and it I don't really this may
have been something that again normally
if I was going to make all these changes
I'd make them all in one day where it's
easier to keep
in my head and so it's possible that I
just forgot something that I was like oh
I'm just going to comment this out or
something like this right it's possible
that we just did something like that and
now I'm just forgetting that it needs to
be commented back in again right and so
what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna look
for if zero and see in world mode what
we got rid of wall is not particularly
saying why the hero this this looks like
an obvious thing right it looks like we
just commented out the code for
controlling people which okay is exactly
what I said we might have done we did so
here this game state let's put that back
in there and see what happens
all right hey look so that was all it
was and now we can move her a little
here around and that's all good let's
see here so we also though don't seem to
be tracking the camera meaning the
camera does not actually seem to be
updating and so I do also wonder if we
if we nuked that code which you may have
or the code which sets the camera follow
right who would sets who's getting
getting followed by the camera that
makes sense and I believe the person
who's getting followed by the camera is
handling here I think I can't quite
remember might not be let's see
camera follow ad player can follow two
equals Lindsey low index camera
following entity index is the thing that
I care about and hey there it is so when
we look through these guys and we find
one of them we do our camera stuff here
and we set up the camera so that's seems
like that should all be working so I'm
not sure why it wouldn't be unless
camera following entity index is set
incorrectly and so what I suspect you
know could have happened there for all I
know we could have a situation where
like we never initialized any of those
things in fact now that I think about it
that's another thing we will have to do
because now we
to clear our stuff to zero when we start
up because that's our definition of how
everything is supposed to work
everything is supposed to be cleared to
zero and right now we're not actually
doing that right we're not actually
clearing the stuff to zero when we
allocate it for the first time and it's
expected to be right so what I would
probably suggest here and the way that I
would normally do this is I would
probably say our push truck should just
clear to zero when we do it right so
meaning like as we like as we push
things on those things should be should
be cleared and so in handmade H right
when I do push strecht
what I would do normally is say okay
whenever we do push size we would have
some kind of flag here that says whether
you should clear it to zero or not and
you know the default behavior is that it
does get cleared to zero so let's think
about this for a second how I might want
to do this I'm gonna grip for push
struct and just take a quick check and
how often it's used so it's not really
that common you know we don't do very
much allocation as you can see in
general so it's pretty easy to take a
look at the places that we use it and
decide which ones of these we want to do
clear and which ones of these we don't
right so that's not a particularly
difficult thing to and and not really
something we probably have to worry
about too much okay
so this would be pretty straightforward
right
all we would have to do is after we do
our precise if we want to clear things
out we would just say after we get the
memory clear from the place where we did
the allocation through to its size and I
feel like we actually have a zero thing
somewhere maybe yes so we have the
concept of a zero size so really all we
have to do when we do a push size is we
just call a zero size after it
sit so right here when we do like okay
let's figure out what we're returning we
just do a zero size of the result and
however big that we said that it was you
know and we don't have to clear the
whole thing we only have to clear the
park that it actually that they actually
asked for so we could really just clear
the size in it and off we go
so again the only reason not to just
literally do nothing with that and I'm
gonna have to grab that from down below
and bring it up here right the only
reason not to do that literally exactly
that is because I don't actually know if
there's somebody who does an allocation
of a big block of memory who doesn't
really want to clear it I suspect that
for example the world when it allocates
its you know some of its space for
storage may not ever want to actually
clear it so that could be a performance
problem right and something that we
might want to address so that's that's
all just pointed that out right but yeah
so okay so as you can see that was
exactly the case because we expected
that stuff to be cleared to zero and it
wasn't now we have it clearing to zero
we're back to where we wanted to be and
we can sort of do exactly what we would
hope for which is you know switching
around between different modes of the
game creating worlds and playing in them
and then going back to our meta game and
that all is is nice and happy and fun
now we do have one problem to address
like I said we have the the fact that
the ground chunks are sort of like in
theory I should be able to get the
ground chunks to crash here if I if I
just you know if I
if I just like start things up and I I
like run to get the ground chunks going
and then clear it you know oh well
alright so it's you just have to trust
me
I believe it it is it is I believe it is
possible to crash because the fill
ground chunks are running on a separate
thread they're accessing a world state
that can go away
they won't crash immediately necessarily
but they'll start accessing bogus memory
like memory that's being reused for
something else in theory it might be it
probably isn't getting reused for
something else right now and so that's
why it's still working
because it's just using the old memory
that's there but trust me it's a bug so
we do also want the concept at some
point that whatever our whatever our
modes are if we do decide that we want
these sort of like background tasks key
things like if we want the ground chunks
there we would have to make sure that
when we shut down a mode we don't shut
it down until we can close down all of
its tasks you know that's all we just
need to make sure that multi-threading
stuff is is is shut down right you can
kind of think of it as like you know
like task based garbage collection if
you will right so instead of thinking of
things like like memory we're just
thinking of like actual tasks so this
thing has spawned a bunch of tasks and
we can't actually consider it shut down
until all of those tasks have finished
right it's sort of like reference
counting is probably the right words
that it's not really garbage collection
because garbage collection like searches
through things so sound like that but
like like a reference count right so you
imagine like a reference counted pointer
for memories like that it's sort of like
that sort of thing but with tasks so
we're like okay this thing has started
end tasks and it has to wait for those
end tasks to finish before it can be
considered shut down so you would want
to do that I don't know that we need to
do that yet because
it's I mean it's not really necessarily
the best time to do it we could or we
could we could leave it so I'm not sure
but if we got Phil Gramm chunk here I'm
gonna go ahead and jump over there to
note it because at the very least we got
to make sure that we know so this is
like to do AC important right something
like this I don't know how I want that
maybe like this it's probably fill
ground chunk work will cause a crash if
the mode goes away for the task finishes
this must be shut down properly if we
ship it okay so yeah like I said it's
probably pretty hard to get it to crash
but trust me it could crash if you'd if
you did the stuff correctly if you did
the right set of things I think it could
crash all right uh so yeah I guess what
I would say now is I kind of want that
title screen to happen so what I would
like to do is maybe start to figure out
how that's gonna work I don't really
know how that's going to work but you
know like we just need something where
it's going to show like a title screen
some kind of a track MODY thing right
and I probably should have asked
yangshin to draw one but I haven't
thought of it yet so I didn't but point
being when we have the cutscene when we
do update and render cutscene we're
gonna get to a point where the cutscene
is complete right and that's this thing
right here so if the cutscene is
complete why that was set to if not
cutscene complete render cutscene that
time
this is actually the wrong thing it's
not cutscene complete its cutscene still
running it's it's cutscene incomplete
right because it's set to false and then
it becomes true if we found something
so yeah that's things still running
maybe is the best phrase so that's just
wrong terminology that was the exact
opposite of what it actually was all
right so we've got cutscene still
running and so what we want to do is say
like alright if the cutscene is not
still running then what I'd like to do
is switch to play title screen you know
so at the end of the of the title screen
I'm at the end of the cutscene it'll
switch to the title screen and it'll do
its thing and I'd like to do the same
thing with the title screen which is to
say that the title screen will stay up
for like 10 seconds or something and
then it will go back to the intro
cutscene or something like that right
and so yeah let's say that you know we
go through here we check for meta input
we do some thing where we're like I
don't know what's happening something is
happening and so then we say like okay
you know render cutting the time this
this sort of exact thing happens right
so it basically says like okay
title screen t + equals input DT for
frame so we accumulate time and of
course we will just always check when
we're doing that we'll say if the title
screen T is greater than the 10 second
time that we said that we want it to be
then we'll go and and switch to the
intro cutscene right
something like that so yeah starting to
get a roughly where I want but there's
still one more big change and in fact I
could sort of show you why there's a big
problem that we still have to sort of
address and maybe I'll do that in the
last couple seconds servers got about
five minutes left so let me just do this
part first and then we can we I can show
you the thing that I think we still want
to do before we consider this part of
the game sort of you know in a
reasonable state what I would like to do
first is I'd like to verify that we're
actually making our update and render
tunnel screen thing but that's actually
working so I'm gonna put it clear in
here so that when we are doing this this
thing we just we can see like a Reds a
red screen or something right so we
clear it out and that's all good okay
it's still running so what I'm gonna do
just to make sure that that so we can
kind of test that is I'm gonna go ahead
and and run it and I'm gonna run it in
the reverse order so when we initialize
this first instead of playing intro
cutscene I'm going to do play title
screen so I can see that part of it
working and then we'll kind of go from
there
alright so we fade out and now we've got
this this is our title screen
quote-unquote right and after it's up
for ten seconds it should switch to the
in crow cutscene which it does and so
now we've got both modes going and
hopefully you know we can also we could
speed this up a little bit just to make
sure where's our DT at let's see let's
see right here we could go ahead and
speed that up so it doesn't take so long
if that makes sense
whoa what happened there
I don't know cutscene still running
we're cutting that time I don't know why
that why changing that would have had
that effect oh yes I do so the thing
that I said I would show you in a couple
after are thrown with this I actually
showed you just now so the thing that I
was trying to say that I think is busted
that we want to fix is if you think
about what's happening here
right now because of the way that we
happen to be doing our modes only one
mode exists at any time which means that
inside a particular mode once you switch
to a new mode you can't ever do anything
else right because the instant I try to
access like this cutscene T for example
it's actually wrong there is no more
cutscene right because I might have
gotten rid of the whole cutscene
structure right here that make sense and
so what I would like to do as one more
step in the process is make it so we can
have multiple these existing at once so
that when we create a new one that we're
going to switch to we don't switch to it
immediately we delay until we're done
processing this whole thing so we don't
have to make sure that we only ever do
it at the end right that's what I would
prefer now you know you can still always
structure the code this way and you
wouldn't probably have to worry too much
about it but it's still you know like I
said it's not right that way anyways so
let's see how this goes see if we let's
see if we got more bugs here I don't
actually know that was the bug I was
just noticing the fact I was like up we
have the bug I said I was gonna put in
we actually had it already sorry so
we're exhuming through the cutscene at
10 times 10x speed here which is you
know a nice fast forward way to watch
there we go
there we go and back to the title screen
so good so now we just need a title
screen but once we actually have a title
screen which we'll do I don't know we'll
do something then we're going to go we
can go into the game presumably there it
is
and we can get out of the game
presumably there that is and we can quit
so now we're getting a little further
getting a little further we're not there
yet but we're getting a little further
so that's good so I'm gonna go ahead and
call that for today because now we've
got got sort of more of a a little bit
of a game experience going and so that's
something we can build upon all right so
let's go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
soy sauce the kid could you leverage
your debug code when trying to find the
right values you want for inter cutscene
and real time instead of recompiling yes
we could although we didn't quite get to
the point where the debug code was all
finished right so that's why I'm not
using it is because we still have more
work to do there before we can actually
start employing it for any real purpose
Carlino Bleu has some credits and boom
we're done yeah we could just be like
look that's it you know you know we said
there was going to be a game and what we
meant by that was that there's like an
intro cutscene and some credits it's
fine Danny guac how do you terminate or
end each thread at the end at the end of
at the end of what at the end of the
whole executable do you mean when when
like the game closes this is Atticus
what are your thoughts on twitch asking
you to switch labels to creative do I do
not care it's their service and wherever
they want to put us as it's pretty much
fine with me you know I most people who
come to handmade hero come because they
heard about it from like me on Twitter
or somebody else telling them about if
they don't they don't find it through
twitch so I don't super care where they
put us and so if they think that more
people will find it under creative and
that's what they would prefer that's you
know that's fine with me because they
would know better than I would and
honestly I don't care
will we be re-implemented the profiler
yeah I mean when we when we get to the
point where I want that heads up stuff
which is not probably that far away I
want to go finish the debug code thing
that we have so we could see it
Danny Gregg the end of disputable so
when the executable exits we don't need
to close the threads when the executable
exits we can just immediately close and
we don't really have to do anything
right
so what I believe happens when we do
quick requested right so when we fall
out of this loop the global running loop
what's going to happen is when we come
out through here and we do this return
zero we're gonna dump into the C runtime
library external code and it's gonna
call exit process which will just kill
every threat including ours so we don't
have to do anything to shut down threads
they're just gonna die and that's it
all right so food could you read explain
why you couldn't move the hero after
cutscenes for a while do you mean just
because we had the code commented out I
mean the only reason was just cuz we had
the code commented out because we hadn't
quite ported it over yet was the only
reason that was happening in this
episode no VIN if someone wants to run
your game in full-screen but at a
different resolution than native how
would they change it you said before you
don't like menus so would you use a
launcher instead or something for those
options so I'm not sure I would probably
prefer it if it could be in like the
steam launcher on Steam so that when you
like play the game it has a thing that
just says how do you want to run it and
part of the reason for that is because I
don't really like the I don't really
like switching resolutions in the game
because you might if the game starts up
in a resolution that's actually broken
you can't get to the option menu to
change it because you can't see anything
right and so I usually prefer it if you
can set if there's a setting like that
that could potentially break and click a
completely break then my preference is
to have that be settable outside so that
if the user gets themselves into a
circumstance where they like cannot
recover right then then they can they
can fix it so my preference would be
that would be in like the steam in when
you hit like launch on Steam or you
could right click on it and steam and
you know how steam has those little
things it's like parameters my
preference would be that's in there so
if someone wants to change it they
change it but in general I would like it
to always just run meaning Michael
people like a lot of settings II sort of
stuff and I hate that because I just
want the thing to run and I expect users
to not have to care about things like
the resolution so I want my the game to
like choose the right thing and the only
time that someone the only time that
someone should ever even be thinking
about that stuff is if they're like a
very technical person and want to fuss
with things so like it
my opinion like command line parameter
or like things like that is where that
chef should live that should not be
something that the average person who
doesn't know or care what a resolution
even is should never be seeing that they
should not be seeing those things in a
game in the same way that when you go to
like watch a movie you know on Netflix
you're not you don't see these things
they're not there right you just push
play and it put pics the highest
resolution your stream can handle and
then if you're somebody who really cares
maybe you can go in and tweak some
settings and tell like oh don't do that
or whatever right but but I don't like
that like I think things should just
work and always and then if you are
somebody who is very technical and and
you know wants to tweak things then I'm
all for having tweakable parameters but
they should be completely they should be
in like a very specific technical place
that has nothing to do with what the
normal person will ever see when they
launch the game insofar as could you do
some resolution detection at startup to
avoid starting at a brick resolution no
you can you have no idea why your
resolution might be broken like windows
may be up and running just fine
it may report the monitor is supporting
the resolution you're at but in actually
either monitor doesn't and the user is
seeing nothing right now right so
there's really nothing you can do but
what we're doing on here right now is
obviously the safest thing to do which
is always launch in the desktop
resolution because you know whoever
launched you was looking at a screen
that worked because they had to be here
they couldn't have launched you so
that's why I usually prefer always
launching at that resident whatever the
resolution is that the users running at
you just stay there
don't change it leave it what it is and
then if there's a user who wants you
know to have all this extra extra
control right then that person should go
edit you know what some kind of config
file that is like okay just so you know
if you're touching this file we just
expect you know
doing and we're just going to obey
whatever you put in there so go nuts but
we're not responsible what happens
I prefer that sort of thing
and when even let's see says you say
normal person as if tech-savvy people is
something awful no not really they're
just not the average case maybe I should
say average person meaning the person
who knows what a resolution is is not
the average person anymore like it used
to be that if you were someone who
played games on a computer you
absolutely knew what a resolution was
right I mean like in 1980 it's probably
no one playing a game on a computer that
could switch resolutions that didn't
know what that was maybe but nowadays
people might have absolutely no idea
what resolution they're even running and
you're asking like what's your
resolution that you're running in right
now and they might like I have no idea
right and so that's the average case
like you know if someone's playing on
their phone or whatever it's like what's
the resolution that phone they're like I
don't know maybe they knew when they
picked out the phone cuz they looked in
one unlike the sticker it said like this
is higher resolution than that or
something but you know so yeah so when I
say normal person what I really mean is
average person or person who doesn't
care about technology I mean maybe
they're not maybe they are not actually
average but yeah so the common case
should be person doesn't know or care
what their thing is running in they
forgot what a resolution was after they
went to Best Buy and bought a TV or
whatever happened that was the last time
they thought about resolution and so it
doesn't matter right so that's the goal
is it just works as much as possible it
always just works but you know it would
be nice like I said to have like the
ability to create a start up file or
pass parameters so that people who want
to play around with something like
people who want to force this was every
framerate want to force the specific
resolution want to force whatever you
know we can allow them to have that
ability to tweak but that's not going to
be in a menu that like people would
normally see right
and yeah I would agree that I don't
think people really know much about
resolution other than like oh I should
get 1080p or is that a 1080p thing or
whatever and the fact that like it's
gonna get worse because 4k now like what
does that mean 4k isn't even a
resolution as far as I can tell 4k is
like a family of resolutions that are at
least double 1080p but like I've seen
different things described at described
as 4k that each have a different
resolution right so people say like oh
that's a 4k monitor it's like okay is it
you know is it 1920 times 1920 by 1080
times 4 right so is it like is it for
1920 by 1080 screens or is it one of
these like 5000 by something that's
actually more than then for 1920 by 1080
screens right
so looks like there's no more queue
colons so I think I am done in sohbat is
going nuts by the way steel golem do you
generally do cutscene code before
gameplay code when you're working on a
game so I guess what I would say is I
don't consider cutscene code or game
code to necessarily have any particular
place in the development timeline I
usually try to sort them by what I think
is most appropriate for that project so
for example let's say that the cutscene
art is very labor-intensive and needs to
get overlapped with the development of
the game to a large extent then I may do
the cutscene code very early to make
sure that the cutscene artists know what
they're dealing with and there are no
surprises right but if that was not the
case I may just leave the cutscene code
to the very last because if I don't it
because it doesn't affect the gameplay
and doesn't need to be prototyped or
anything like that then there's no point
in doing it early it doesn't matter
right so I feel like in general as a
programmer when you're thinking about
what to do when you need to make sure
that for whatever projects are working
on you make the best decision for
putting the technology development get
it getting it out of the way of the art
team as much as possible and that may be
doing cutscenes first and maybe doing
cutscenes the middle it may be doing
cutscenes last you know who knows right
and so that's that's really what the way
you should think about it not like do I
not like what's the rule do you know
cutscene code for its gameplay code for
its like that's the wrong way think
about the right way to think about it is
what are the dependencies in this
project and how do I make sure that I
schedule my dev time too
line up as much as possible with with
illuminating those dependencies in the
in the order that benefits the game and
so for handmade hero the reason we did
the cutscene code now was actually
exacts a mentality I was just thinking
to myself well what's the thing we could
do that's like gonna use our renderer
and that we could play with here and
that yangshin could do the art for that
doesn't rely too much on the gameplay so
that she can be working on are
productively before we necessarily know
certain things about our gameplay that
maybe require us to implement them and
so on so forth right because handmade
here is a very odd project because you
know at an hour and night the
programming goes way slower than the art
goes whereas normally like the
programming could go way faster than the
art not a per click on handmade hero it
would it should really be the other way
around probably and so you know I just
sort things more by like what works out
well for the streaming nature of the
show as opposed to how I would sort it
if I knew that I was gonna like okay I'm
gonna do four months of programming and
do all the code for am a hero you know
just by myself how am I gonna stretch
turret
I wouldn't did you know the order in
which I do things might be very
different because I might go like oh
okay like I'm gonna blitz this part of
it out and then do this but like you
know I I really try to make sure that
that we do things in the order that will
make it easiest to learn on the stream
which affects you know some of the
decisions about major components right
and what order they we do or don't do
things in
was there any other cues I missed are we
in a point where we're close to have to
need to implement mix-ins it depends
whether we just push on through to the
gameplay code now which we might and if
we do that then yes if I decide to go
back and finish up a few other things
then possibly not so I don't know primer
script will C++ 17 modules solve the
include dependency problem I just always
assumed that no c++ Committee additions
to the language will solve any problem
because they never do
in fact you witnessed that you witnessed
exactly what I think of the C++
committee happening on the stream quite
literally the one time we tried to use a
new feature which was deckle type it
didn't work and it didn't work because
they expect it so poorly that the case
we want to use it for it can't be used
for right and that's like that's my
entire thing about the C++ therapy all
they ever do is introduce features that
don't actually work right and so I don't
even bother anymore so I don't know
whether the C++ modules solve the
include dependence problem because I
haven't looked at them but I also know
that no they won't because somehow they
will do something that makes it so that
the average case that a smart programmer
would want to use them for it won't work
they will I guarantee you that is what
they'll do because every time they've
ever added a feature to the language
they have managed to do it no matter how
simple that feature should have been
they do it so yes I will be shocked to
find that is not the case for modules
pleasantly shocked I supposed I would
would be what I'd find but basically the
chance of that I think is you know zero
so and with that let's go ahead and yeah
and that deco type thing was hilarious
cuz Italy I'm so glad that that was
captured on stream because it's like I
always say that but you know is maybe
I'm just being
maybe I'm just a dream it's like no it's
like you actually saw it we only tried
to use one C++ feature up from the new
thing on the stream and it didn't work
for this super simple case like all we
wanted to do was get the type of
something so we could find out how big
it was it's like it can't do that
it's like it turns out if you want to
use it for that you have to create like
a template to like force it to map it
right it was like and you're like yep
that's that's the C++ center Committee
don't know how to program and always
create things that that a real
programmer can't actually use without
this huge like you know gigantic
investment in doing something that
should have been like one simple
function that worked right it's
hilarious I mean it it's hilarious
because if you don't laugh at it you'll
cry because it's the language you have
to use and it's you know it's
incompetently managed so anyway enough
about that thank you for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home you can always go to handmade
hero org and pier to the game which
comes with a source code so that you can
play around with it yourself at home we
also have a forum site you can go to if
you want to ask questions it also has an
anti episode guide by some folks in the
community who do a fantastic job
maintaining it I don't know if they've
gotten their patreon listed up there or
not yet here's the episode guide you can
kind of see it here yeah they don't
really know how to do marketing so the
patreon link is like buried in here we
got a some someday I'll go in here and
try to pretty this up so you can see it
there should be like a big ol link to
the patreon but anyway there's an
episode guide that's pretty awesome that
you should check out and you can also
support it financially if you want
there's like I said the members
community who'd do it and I take money
every
out of the handmade hero patreon to
transfer over to that and also you know
if that's something that you want to
contribute to specifically you can do so
as well speaking of that we do have
patreon obviously and then we also have
a tweet bought the tweets scheduled at
you so if you want to know when the
series gonna be live you can always
check that out too and it will be live
for the last time in awhile tomorrow
Friday 5:00 p.m. Pacific Standard Time
unfortunately I will be away over
Christmas break so I will not have
access to the machine and can't stream
so there will be at least a week of
downtime probably a little bit more
until I get back to Seattle and can
actually stream this series so for our
final stream for awhile tomorrow I hope
to see you guys back here for that we
can finish up some of our mood stuff and
then we'll have Christmas break to think
about what it is that we're gonna
implement we come back because I guess
we'll have to sort of think about that a
little bit more anyway that's it for for
this episode and of course I can't
actually ask there we go I got a exit
task bar until tomorrow
half a program everyone and I'll see you
guys on the Internet