all right hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero the show where we
temporarily are not actually coding game
from scratch because I am on RS I leave
at the moment problem hands what can you
do something's got to solve it
unfortunately I don't know enough about
neurological things to fix it but
hopefully it will get better and we'll
see anyway point being while I am on
sort of a no typing hiatus I do however
feel like it's worth streaming because
people have questions and I can answer
those questions so we've got some and
I'm going to do exactly that so here's a
question that comes in from trev Newt
they said what are the pros and cons of
baking assets like images into your
executable rather than shipping them
separately and loading them dynamically
and what I would say about that is
really there's none I guess is what I
would say and so let me go over that
process a little bit for you if it just
to just to give you a little bit of a
feel for it so on the disk right here is
my executable right see if I can there
we go so here's my executable on the
disk so this is you know this is my this
is my hard drive here and on the disk
right I've got this executable and
basically the way this is structured
right is you know it's a bunch of binary
data but at the top there is some
information that says like what the
sections are and what kind of executable
it is and that sort of stuff that
windows it's a specific specific format
that windows uses to store its xq Dolson
and there's actually two of them there's
one for 32-bit X's and there's one for
64-bit xes so actually they kind of
revved the format in a pretty major way
when they went to 64-bit but anyway
that's neither here nor there point
being the XE has some information and
then it's got stuff usually they're
called like segments
they'll be called like the code segment
data segments things like this there's
pieces of this executable and in those
pieces of the executable the this thing
at the top there's often things that say
like what's what's there or you know
there'll be other things that affect it
like a relocation table that does
dynamic link loading that sort of thing
and so really all that we're talking
about here is if I want to store an
image does it go in another file right
so here is you know my image file over
here let's go in another file does it go
in the executable right so what's the
actual difference between these two
things okay one is a you know the
executable is already open right you
don't have to get a new handle to it
there's no chance it could fail there's
no chance that you can't read from it
right so it's sort of a little more
fault tolerant in the sense that it's
already open you know it's there and
it's already you know linked up to you
so getting the image out is you know a
basically a known quantity someone would
have to hack the executable to break
that right and number two is it might be
slightly faster in some cases right
because the the linker pre will pre
insert the offset to the image into your
code assuming that some of you compiled
into your code and so that you know
maybe it saves you a little bit of work
but we're talking like a little little
bit of work right like not probably
something you would ever care about so
okay yeah you know those are some pluses
but that's really about it on the whole
there really isn't much of a difference
so I I don't consider that a
particularly important thing now there
is one fringe benefit which is the user
can't screw up if the user wants to move
an executable and all the data is also
in the executable they can just move the
eggsy around and that works nowadays
users don't tend to do that anymore and
so they don't even really know about
executables you know most users they're
just kind of like running something
through steam or download something
through an app store or whatever so you
know it's even less important now that
it would have been in the past so let's
talk about perhaps a more interesting
issue which is do I want this or this
right so here's my image file right and
this maybe has a bunch of images in it
so maybe I've got a b c d e f or
something my images and then here i've
got the same images but they're in
separate files so let's talk about the
difference between basically like packed
files and separate files right so that's
a perhaps more interesting difference
than the executable one because the
executable one is like there's really
not that it's that there's not a lot of
compelling reasons why you ever would
care to put something a text readable
it's just not that necessary there's not
a lot of pros to it but there are some
pros and cons between these two and
that's actually worth noting and so the
reason for that is that a packed file
requires a lot less negotiation with the
operating system to use and that's
actually somewhat important every time I
want to load an image file from a
separate image every time I want to load
an image from a separate image file I
have to go through the operating system
and it has to do a tremendous amount of
work I'm going to pass you know like
filename dot PNG or something and it's
going to have to go through and figure
out okay what directory structure i'm
going in look for a match for this name
find that match open it up generate a
handle insert a thing into the handle
table you know like blah blah blah blah
blah blah blah there's a tremendous
amount of work that has to go on here
and when you're talking about having
hundreds or thousands of files that
might have to get open that's just a lot
of unnecessary traffic back and forth to
the operating system a lot of
unnecessary work in the operating system
that that really just did not need to
happen right it also limits the number
of options that you potentially have for
overlapping that because you know
something like an open call might not be
very easy to over
lap in terms of multi-threading you may
have to create a separate thread to
babysit the open call blah blah blah
blah blah there's there's a whole bunch
of extra stuff that happens here so
packed files there is a pretty good
argument for a packed file is very nice
because you open it once and then all
you have to ever issue to the operating
system from then on is just offset reads
you just say I want to read this much
from here just like we're doing in
handmade here and so having a small
number of large packed files is usually
a better idea for most operating
circumstances then lots and lots of
separate files and so typically when you
ship you want to go with something more
like this than something like this for
that reason and typically it's not too
hard to patch these if you want to patch
them you can design your pact file
format to allow easier patching or you
can do sort of some of the stuff we
don't have in here where you can just
allow it to drop in another pack file
and then maybe make some rules about how
pack files take precedence over each
other for example so then the things you
want to update or just in here or
whatever so there's a number of ways I
think that you could probably make
packing work just as easily I'm sorry
make patching work fairly easily in a
pack file if you're if you're just a
little smart about it than the
circumstance that you might see here
with the with the separate files we're
obviously patching works as easily as
possible there because you can always
just you know replace a particular file
but there's just a lot of drawbacks so I
would say typically you know you should
be able to sign your pack file format so
that patching isn't too hard so that
basically you know changing one thing
doesn't change the entire file right and
then and then I think pack files are
pretty clear choice
dracut once you return to coding episode
streams would you recommend new
followers tune in even though they
haven't caught up with everything the
archive uh that's really for you to
decide I mean basically people can watch
I would just recommend watching couple
streams seeing whether you get anything
out of it or whether it's just not
useful for you to have you know whether
it's you know not useful for you to see
it if you're not all caught up or
whether it is so I would say it's
something that you probably have to you
know it's funny you'd probably have to
decide for yourself in so first I meant
using the built in windows voice
recognition stuff to primary okay that
would be kind of funny if we tried to
use voice activated programming to
program handmade hero we probably should
try that at some point do you think you
could create an in-depth video post on
iocp at some point in the near future
I'm having a bit of trouble
understanding their amazing us not
really I like I said I'm pretty full up
with work right now and not being able
to be uncertain about the cities of the
hands I I really can't do anything other
than what i'm doing right now
elvin good evening sensei so weird to be
called sensei I hope your hand is
feeling better today I salute your
positiveness in handling the situation I
would totally freak out if that happens
to me without programming I'm
practically useless yeah I mean I could
not agree more it's it really is very
very frustrating to me and it upsets me
because it's really all I need is for my
hands to function well hmm basically
like like you know from here up used to
be functioning well you know I could be
in a wheelchair and I wouldn't really
affect my enjoyment of life hardly very
much but losing use of a hand is pretty
devastating so you know it is hard to
keep a positive to keep a positive
outlook on it it's true and you know I
do what I can but it's it's a it's lame
it's really really lame and I wish
someone would solve these problems
because I feel like you know it's it's a
problem when we have people who are able
to program and want to program and are
slowed down or even stopped because of
stupid biomechanical problems like get
me a better interface to a computer why
am I even using these right it's just
dumb so yeah I wish they would sell hard
up and solve that so I could use
something else um let's see dan golf
after fiction technology what are some
candidates for other problems projects
worth your time um I haven't really
talked very much about anything after
that yet i would say that i'm trying not
to be too forward looking with things
like that because like I said especially
when you think about you know how easy
it is to be taken out of the game
interactive fiction is really the thing
that I would like to make sure that we
solve at Molly and if we do that i'll be
very satisfied and if I could still
program after that time then I'll pick
something else
pragma script will there ever be good
real-time global illumination I don't
know probably because it's a very
separable problem you know at the limit
you can have every you know pixel
rendered by a different computer and
then you can afford to do a full-on you
know ray trace I mean if you imagined
having you know a 64,000 core computer
or something it would scale relatively
well and then you would just basically
have the memory distribution problem
would be mostly what you'd have to deal
with is just how do they all access the
information so you know could it happen
probably i don't know how likely it'll
be aight i don't know but it could
happen it could happen proton gaming why
are companies so hard with junior
developers in the interview process make
it very difficult for unexperienced
coders who got a job probably because
there's just a lot of bad programmers
out there and they're nervous about it
and they don't know what to do to you
know they're misguided in their approach
to finding good programmers you can't
blame them for not wanting bat programs
but programmers are really bad to work
with and they ruin everything so you
know they're they're trying to not have
that happen and then the lowest part is
oftentimes they're actually bad
programmers so now you've got a bad
programmer who's thinking they're
preventing a bad parent for getting
hired but actually they're just a bad
programmer which is always hilarious but
you know what do you do x13 pixels is
Martin still putting the videos up on
BitTorrent sync I don't know what he's
doing I have no idea I still copy
anything i post to the YouTube I copy it
into the shared directory for him
whether he runs a bit torncek I don't
know he was doing that other goodness of
his heart and you know if he doesn't
want to do it anymore you know I don't
blame him but if someone does want to
take over that for him if he doesn't
want to do it anymore I I could get the
video I could set someone up else up so
they could get those videos
a junkie suited for you could try
something like Qigong Chinese health
exercise which could help with RSI and
creating good posture nice thought yeah
I actually I don't know about that
specifically but I do I am going to try
to work on we're trying to do one thing
a time here just for testing purposes
and just to be kind of like a little
more systematic but it but I am going to
try adding some exercise routines just
general exercise routines into my day
because that's something I really need
to do anyway and I'll be trying to do
some of that for sure do you ever wonder
if a game you're playing will turn into
frog fractions to with a crazy twist I
find myself wondering this often no I
probably should be wondering that but no
i have not word one did that yet in
Janeiro for some reason i remember you
saying there were changes coming to
hammer here at org forums that i
remember correctly and do you have any
update on the current status um yes so i
am not making a change the handmade hero
forms it's just that the people who are
doing handmade dev wrote a bunch of
forum stuff that's in testing right now
and when they're happy with it the
handmade hero forums will kind of flip
over to those and they're a lot better
at least i thought they were you know
everyone has their preferences i'm sure
but the they're just they're just better
in my opinion and so it'll switch over
to that when they're ready and that's
not i don't i have nothing to do with
that process I just said it I don't like
running forums I don't like writing web
things period so I just like if you guys
want to run the forums have them and
they were like yeah so they've got some
plan for that and I don't know when
that'll be but that's that's what that
is
Danny wag what is the Intel Architecture
Singh on your desktop oh this is from
earlier in the streams this thing are
you talking about or this one so I can
tell you what they both are they're both
very important and things you should
know so the Intel intrinsics guide is a
website that's awesome we use it on the
stream when we do optimization and
basically what it lets you do is search
for things like its search for the
instructions so if you don't know what
the intrinsic SAR intrinsics are
basically compiler things that tell the
compiler that you'd like it to generate
a specific assembly instruction for you
and so you can use that to access the
simdi instructions and among other
things on on Intel hardware and but
there's a lot of intrinsic SAT this
point and they get hard to remember
what's what and so you can use this is
pretty efficient you can check like I'm
programmed for sse2 that's my target so
I want to see like everything that's
that and below let's say and then you
can search like oh show me the functions
that have ad in them like so that has an
ad or something that has a load that
does right and it just makes it really
easy because there's just a lot of them
and it makes it really easy to kind of
come see what they all are so it's a
really nice it's a really nice resource
it was actually I didn't even know about
someone recommended it on stream when I
was looking them up manually and they
were like hey you know there's a great
web page design yeah there is so that
was pretty cool then the the intel
architecture manual this thing could
download you can download this from
intel's websites free it's a you know
it's a publicly available thing and what
this is is this is their manual for for
the x86 architecture which at this point
is the x64 architecture and what it's
got is basically all the information
that you need to know about how the
instruction set is meant to work so you
can go see like what the rationale for
these things is and how they were meant
to work and what how you know what their
general operating modes are all those
sorts of things there's even simps up in
here about you know like how the cpu
just generally does what it does with
the different the 64 verse 32 bit memory
model all that stuff right and so when
you're curious to learn how the chip
does what it does
um from a specification standpoint not
from a hardware standpoint because it's
not about that but from a specification
standpoint this is a great place and
it's got you know like the system
programming guide in here tells you
about stuff that you might want to know
if your program like an operating system
like how interrupts work those are not
things that users ever really deal with
but the OS programmers deal with so it's
just got a lot of great information and
something that everyone should be
familiar with because it can answer a
lot of questions for you if you have a
specific question about the chip girl
and abloom have you ever been to GDC yes
the first GDC I attended was in 1997 and
I attended it up until about two
thousand two maybe three I don't know if
I went in three and i believe i went in
four and five to just just for hosting
the programmers challenge i didn't
really do anything else but related
bloom why is all your such disaster even
on windows I don't know man people over
complicating things i I don't know the
same region all hardware is a disaster
is because the driver layer gets all
super complicated and people refuse to
keep things simple what you know I've
never been a device manufacturer I never
worked at NIH p I don't know how it gets
out of control i think it's like bad
decisions on microsoft side bad
decisions on the HD side they can pound
they grow and compound and people get
bad ideas and then those bad ideas
become initiatives and you know it's
like suddenly you're looking at a USB
spec that's 700 pages long and there's
like 400 pages of audio spec and there's
like this is what like so i don't know
huber caleb don't install our programs
typically bake information about the
program they are installing into the
eggsy is that how its lawyers are
typically done on the windows yes so
typically what happens and and I could
show you guys how to do this it's it's
not hard in fact that you if you've
watched the series you already pretty
much know house so there's two ways you
can actually approach this this problem
and and that is like okay so you know
that you've got the linker right we've
talked about this way way back the early
days of handmade hero and so what
happens is into the linker you're and
you're shoving a bunch of like obj files
right and the linker is going to output
an executable okay just like the kind we
just talked about and so we've got these
obj files there but it can also grab
resource files right it can grab stuff
like images or whatever and it can link
them in and so like the windows has like
the resource compiler it produces res
files with like of your icons or things
like that so you can get data in there
even if the data wasn't in an object
file you can actually package in other
things and then the linker outputs an
executable that has that stuff in
Microsoft format with tables that say
where it is and blah blah blah blah blah
blah right great whatever however
there's another thing you could do which
is once you have your executable let's
say you just make an executable with
this process you don't put anything else
in it it's just code and now you're like
well is there any way I could put a
bunch of data in there like for example
if this was an installer could I put all
the data all the install packages and
the executable that I'm actually
installing could I just shove all that
stuff in there because the neck see
obviously those installer packages are
just one x z so how does that work and
the answer is yes absolutely trivial
trivial this it's super super stupid
simple the dumbest thing you could have
possibly imagined all you have to do is
just take make a program you make a
little program you can even do this see
runtime library just a straightforward
basic C program doesn't even require any
Windows platform layer nothing just a
basic c program can do it all you do is
you f read your executable right so you
read this into memory
very straightforward you then open a new
file you know some new XE that you
create and UF write it boom okay so now
I've ever written this out I took my old
executable I wrote it here then I F read
my data files that freedom one at a time
and i append them so now my eggsy just
grows and grows i just add on to the end
add on to the end add on to the end
right so I'm just f writing I f read in
a new file I f write it so I just F read
every file on my distribution and I
afraid it to the end until I have a
giant executable where the first part is
my executable and everything that comes
after it are all my data files right
make sense then what I do is at the very
last thing I put a footer and the footer
is just like our header for our asset
tables but at the end then when the
executable loads the executable that I
actually wrote this one here all it
needs to do is when I wrote it it just
needs to have up some code in it that
opens its own self it's just F opens
itself right and looks at the last n
bytes reads the footer out of the last n
bytes that footer just has the whole
directory structure everything it needs
to grab stuff out and then it just uses
that as its asset pack file from now on
right so you can actually just do that
if you want to write and you can build
in the slaughter that way or you can
build a game that way that's just an
executable with a bunch of files you
just totally do that there's no reason
to really what you can and if you're
trying to make an installer then you do
have a very good reason to and you could
uh q colon is making an interesting game
AI considered a very hard problem or are
people just lazy I see most games come
with terrible AI these days why does it
seem we're going backwards um I'm really
the wrong one to answer that question
not because I couldn't say some things
about it game AI but actually because I
just don't play that many games that are
AI centric in that way you know like if
you're talking about why can't I play
a wire the enemy players in like
civilization five stupid or something
I'd be like I don't know because I never
played sinless civilization five so I
I'm afraid I can't give you a whole lot
of I got nothing useful to say I got
nothing garland abloom is there any
difference between xing installers and
msi installers yes I believe there is
eggsy installers are actually code
that's actually running that's it's just
running the code that's at the front of
that file and MSI installer actually
requires windows to do the installation
so it's more like a data file if I
remember correctly it's not actually
it's not self it doesn't contain
everything in and of itself which is why
they often don't work like I've had tons
Emma sighs the judges actually don't
straight up don't work because the
Machine didn't have the right stuff
installed to run the msi which is
hilarious so yeah msi's i think are
actually a lot more error-prone than
eggs ease because they actually aren't
just a self-contained thing that works
they're like this weird microsoft hybrid
thing that requires microsoft's code to
do the right thing with it that's my
recollection anyway that said I don't
really remember this the specifics of it
so maybe that's complete nonsense that's
my recollection
really 91 I'm a doctor but couldn't it
be that the wrist braces you are using
you use actually make your muscles in
that part weaker uh yes it definitely
could be and what I can say is that the
wrist braces were very effective for
most of my life like 10 years or so of
programming and so I know that they were
very good for a certain set of things
but they may not really have been a
great idea and maybe I should stop using
them and that is one thing that we will
be testing I think what I may for all I
know the only thing they really did for
me to was keep my hands warm and so one
thing I was thinking is going to just a
hand warmer thing because sometimes that
helps with like arthritic tens and I see
things is to keep it warm and so we'll
see but yes it is absolutely possible I
don't know if it's likely or probable
but yes Gary Johansson possibly to to
give a question but is there an ideal no
strategy to make a natural language
processing system eg you type english
and that parses into actions that are
enacted by a program um I am NOT up on
the state of the art I used to be about
10 years ago I couldn't told you a
better answer the answer used to be that
the current best stuff was statistical
so the best stuff that they had for
processing natural language was they
would take giant corpuses of language
that had been annotated so example
there's a wall street journal corpus
that has like tons and tons and tons of
wall street journal articles that have
been hand annotated by linguists with
what the parts of speech were and stuff
like this and so they were able to do
statistical using that as sort of like a
date of mine they were able to do
statistical analyses on it to like help
inform the decisions because the problem
with parsing English right is that you
end up with the situation where you kind
of need world knowledge to make the
right decision and programming the world
knowledge in is hard
and so they were using statistics to
kind of overcome that they were saying
well if it usually means this then in
the presence of these other things then
i'll soon then that's the truth blah
blah blah right and so that used to be
whether that's the case now I don't know
I haven't looked at it in a while
caricature Hanson we could do an
experiment where you tell us what to
make a new review we could that's not a
bad idea that's not a bad idea we'll see
what happens like i said i'll try maybe
to you know this week and next week
we'll do you know will do no typing
streets with them well i'll see I'm
hoping maybe at that point I'd be ready
just to start going again but if I'm not
then we'll we'll get more creative sss
McGrath have you spoken to chris
crawford about it i'm assuming that the
it is interactive fiction technology I
don't know and the answer is yes I did
speak to him about it I spoke to him
about it in 1999 I want to say and while
there is a gigantic story there that I
will probably tell someday let's simply
say that key and I share literally zero
of the same opinions about how
interactive fiction technology should
work like literally zero and I'll leave
it at that imminent threat how would you
describe your learning curve over your
decades of program experience for me no
matter how long I do something I always
seem to look back to where I was a year
before and feel like there was much less
competent version of myself um I would
say that's very accurate yes uh yeah I
mean I would agree with that basically
what I have found is that it probably
looks a little something like this for
me
we're like you you sort of grow very
rapidly for a time and then at some
point you hit like a language asymptote
which is like you're never going to get
any better than C++ like forget it C++
is just fundamentally limited and so
it's just a problem right and so to
really like the next time I'll be able
to do this again again soon in my hands
hold out is is one I fully switch over
to my own stuff because right now I have
like a hybrid better programming thing I
feel like when I finally switch over to
something that's completely custom no
more C++ i'll be able to do this again
but until then I think I'm pretty much
just like this is the c++ standards
committee right being basically
preventing me from ever getting any
better because they won't give me
anything useful to use have you played
starship titanic i thought that had
quite a cool interactive conversation
thing especially for a 1998 game I don't
think so insofar as I may have missed
that one because it doesn't ring a bell
and I try to play that's that's maybe a
little late for my time which may be why
I missed it could you send me a link to
that email me a link to that if you get
a chance if it's like on gog or
something i'll go check it out elvin
related to the question about embedded
resources versus external ones I had an
idea of using a meta program to load a
model during a preprocessor step and
spit out the code that assigns of
vertices directly to an array etc do you
think that's useful in any way um not
really because the code necessary to do
that is going to be a lot more uh oh
well if you're just talking about trying
to bake it in then yeah it could be
useful i mean people do that for fonts
right if you're talking about baking it
into the executable by put
in an array yeah if you want that model
to just be in your code for some reason
where you don't want to load it out of a
file ever and you want it to just sort
of get loaded as part of the executable
maybe for reliability purposes so you
know it can never get separated it
always has to be there for some reason
people did with fonts like the font that
you need to use say to print out can't
load asset file for example might need
to be baked into the executable because
what if you can't let the asset file you
can't get a font out of it to display
the error message that says that you
can't load the font right so if you're
not a system like windows where you
could just use a message box or
something and have windows deal with it
if you're on some platform where you
have to do everything yourself you could
see why you might need to bake something
in because if the asset fells not there
how do you report it at that point right
see voucher might be jumping the gun
since we haven't gotten the shaders but
I'm having trouble with them in my
renderer am I supposed to save the
attributes and shader programs across
draw calls or reinitialize each time
seems like you went to a lot of trouble
to remove the transient arena from the
OpenGL renderer so things can't be
pushed from there so i guess i'm not
sure exactly what you're asking in
opengl there's there's more than one way
that it happens there's things called
SSB OS there's things called ubos and
there's things that are just uniforms
and the answer to what your how it's
going to work depends on that if you're
just talking about setting uniform
variables then the shader program oh
wait are you talking about actually
there's the program handle
I'm not sure what you're talking about
but I guess what I would say here is
what you want to do for shaders is they
need to be saved so they are going to be
an asset class and what I would say is
you're going to have to wait till we do
our final pass because we got to go do
our texture download stuff that way that
that works will probably be roughly how
the shaders should work meaning it's
stored it is stored and you only want to
build the shader once attributes you
have to switch often so you can't
necessarily build those in but if you're
talking about just the attribute
locations and yeah all that chefs forget
stored you only want to do it once
because it doesn't change sorry I think
I got confused I wasn't sure what you're
asking I think I know what you're asking
now the answer is yes you want to save
it because it costs compiling costs a
lot so you don't once you want to allow
the GL to compile your shader once you
don't want to do it every frame that's
real bad
so what PDF figure is that that is
sumatra PDF all right only two minutes
left here two minutes left what do we
got elven why is it and c++ that people
always like to do many compilation units
one for each CPP file is it just because
of how vigil to your bill works um I
don't know I really don't I think it's
cuz of a misguided impression that
keeping things separated by file
logically per class has some kind of
conceptual purity to it but really all
they're doing is making their build
times awful so having lots of files is
something you only do if you haven't
actually sat down to do the work of
figuring how to make your turnaround
time low in my opinion and keeping your
build working efficiently because even
if you want to do incremental
compilation you don't want them that
small because you almost always when you
touch a header file end up having to
compile multiples of them right and so
it it's not a very good idea in my
opinion but yeah it's somehow it got
into people's heads and that's what they
do let's see Cuba Caleb won't antivirus
get finicky with you writing to the end
of an exit doesn't that also break code
signing so yeah i mean like i said i'm
not advocating that you do that i'm just
saying that you can antivirus programs
might get finicky with you writing to
the end of an XE but that's okay because
you're doing that or you're dead machine
you could just turn the antivirus off so
it's only the reading that happens on
the client side so that's fine as for
breaking code signing I don't know it
depends on the codes it depends on which
coats on you're talking about
let's see I'll take one more question
keeper caleb is it practical to roll
your own see runtime yes it is from what
I've gathered there seems to be a lot of
problems that sort of thing of course
mms has the audacity of shipping
compatible versions of the CRT on
different versions of Windows anywhere
comes to this ah static linking solves
that problem for you that's why we do it
on Hamid hero but yeah at Molly we ship
without the CRT now so our game our game
runs no no crg and I ship granny granny
had an OCR key option as well when i
shipped out a trad that was always no
CRT for for all that stuff yeah moondog
afford to have you considered guests
program is for the interim if like i
said if i have to if it goes more than a
month of me not be legit than then I'll
will do something i'm not sure what but
we will but i'm still you know
cautiously optimistic because really all
i need to do you know to be honest it
doesn't really bother me if if my hands
are numb or something even so it's
really just verifying that i'm not going
to lose use of the hands by using them
is really all i need to get that's
that's as far as I actually need to get
you know so so we're still working on it
we'll see what happens all right I think
that's it for tonight yeah yeah I think
that's about it
alright alright I'm gonna close it down
for now I'm gonna close it down for now
save this up and all right everybody
thank you very much for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it has
been a pleasure coding with you even
though we were not actually coding so I
guess it's the pleasure chatting with
you as always if you would like to come
back tomorrow for more chatting we will
be here five-thirty p.m. same time same
place so love to see it if you enjoy the
chats it's good hanging out it's great
to see so many people here even though
we're not programming so if you've got
questions bring them tomorrow we'll try
to take one or two pretty serious ones
every day and then otherwise we'll just
chat and I'll start uploading these guys
as well to the YouTube so people want to
catch up on the on the chat streams they
could do that to I won't put them as day
numbers I'll do them it's like chat zero
chat one or something like that so that
you don't get confused with stuff where
we're actually coding and that's about
it I will see you guys tomorrow until
then please have fun programming even if
I can't and I'll see you guys on the
internet take these everyone