alright hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hiro sure we could a complete
game live on stream we are going to try
to do some more useful stuff with our
lighting today if you remember from
yesterday we were taking a look at the
ray caster and we think we've got it a
little cleaner now we just hadn't used
it in a while and we hadn't we had made
a bunch of changes to it so we had to
kind of make sure it was still running
okay and it seems like it's at least
functional now and we probably still
have some more debugging to do because
you know we didn't really do much to
ensure that it was working properly but
we did get it basically to the point
where we think it's it's sort of doing
something reasonable and so before we go
any further we want to try doing the
next thing you can notice we're still
getting all these clock marks here but I
think a lot of that has to do with the
way that we're doing the placement of
the Ray casting and the way we're doing
interpolation so I'm pretty sure that
that's not really a concern at the
moment so what I'd like to do now is
take a look at doing the ray casting
from actual proper locations and then
after that's sort of working more
correctly to my satisfaction then we
will move on to debugging the Ray
casting further assuming that we see
evidence of further errors because at
that point I think we'll be able to see
errors more cleanly so what I'm going to
do I'm gonna start with is I want an
pivot I probably shouldn't close that
because I do want to mention one thing
so what I want to do now is if you look
at these you know these these little
cubes that we've placed throughout the
environment here those cubes are the
light probes they're not placed in any
particularly interesting way at the
moment we're just putting two per for
room cell and all I really want to do
here is I want to take those light
probes and I want to use those as the
source locations for our lighting ray
casts right that's all we're really
trying to do here and the reason I want
to do that is because if you think about
the way that we're actually creating our
lighting we have a voxel grid that we're
interpolating the
results on and we really don't want to
cast like this test program this test
version right here is casting from the
Centers of the voxels and you can see
that if i zoom in here you can actually
see we drew this out you could see those
lines all fall over there right so you
can see like it casting from here and oh
it can hit the light source so over here
it will write like okay there's there's
light here right but in other places it
can't hit the light source so for
example if you look like this one down
here is coming from beneath the floor
right so down here it's gonna say that
it can't hit the light source or
whatever right and the problem that you
have so just thinking about right if
you're if you're looking at how this is
going to work the problem that you have
is that if you place these things such
that they're underneath the floor or
whatever and you have like one above the
floor and one below the floor like is
what will happen in this case then you
will get this irregular pattern and
again if we had actually run the full
lighting bounce stuff this wouldn't be
as bad because you would have things
probably diffusing more but it's still a
problem because basically you're taking
samples from places that are inside
geometry and that will always make our
lighting solution worse because it means
that will be interpolating to black in a
bunch of places where we shouldn't have
been right and there's things that we
can do to try to mitigate that but what
we'd rather do is just never have that
problem so what we want to do instead is
say yes we are interpolating lighting at
voxel centers but we don't actually want
to take the the shadowing and
transmission vectors from those centers
we want to take those from places in the
actual world that we know are valid and
then spread them out to the actual voxel
centers for interpolation later that's
what we actually wanted to have happen
and so that's what we need to start
working with here and we're gonna start
doing that now by by trying to take
these light probe locations and using
those as the places that we cast lights
from so in the lighting solution itself
what we need to start doing is when we
do our compute light propagation well
although I guess it's not technically in
here because we're sort of doing the non
propagation version right now we're just
kind of got a hard-coded one cure that
we're working with and that's because we
don't want to actually have to do
propagation yet we're just trying to do
single single ray check and this is
again for debugging purposes before we
start convecting light around and it
becomes really hard to tell if things
are working we want to get it working in
a more easy to to spot case right so if
we now go to the rate caster and we take
a look at what's happening here you can
see here that we're ray casting from
voxel centers and that's not what we
want to do and so what I'd like to do is
take this right here which is you know
this thing that sort of ray casts from
the voxel Center separately I want that
to sort of go away now that needs to now
be just test code and we need something
that's going to do a loop over the the
actual light probes instead and so if
you take a look at what we've got here I
believe we can just get this this is
just something that we pick up as part
of the initialization procedure so I
believe we do begin lighting computation
I believe we need to store that and I
don't know if we're storing it yet right
I don't know I'm just looking here it
doesn't look like we're actually putting
anything in there yet right so if we go
in here and we look for light probe P or
light probe count I don't actually know
if anyone's doing anything with that so
if I go through and I do light probe
count so we are okay so right here we do
we do grab it so this is what we need
we've got a count of the light trips in
the system we have their locations and
that's all we need eventually we won't
even really need to do it this way
because eventually the light probes but
we'll just be stacked in here because
previously we thought we were gonna have
to save them and actually communicate
about them across frames and to their to
the GPU we don't need that anymore we're
just using them as ray cast locations
and so we're gonna it's gonna get even
nicer than this in the future but it
will still boil down to the same thing
which is account in a P it just they
won't have to come from an expanding
buffer with pre-assigned indices if you
remember correctly back in the worlds
import code we got a bunch of nonsense
going on now that's this this stuff
right this will hopefully if I'm right
and we get the lighting working the way
that we're trying to now if this works
well that can go away which is great
it's a whole bunch of bookkeeping that
goes away less possibility for bugs less
runtime costs and everything so it's
just just a unalloyed win if we can
actually make it work without stable
indices across frames I mean generally
speaking anything you can make work
without stable indices across frames
accelerates it usually usually so anyway
going through here taking a look at this
so what I want to do is I want to loop
over these so we kind of want to take
this out of the equation here and
because we're kind of starting to stock
stack up a little bit too much in here
I'm gonna start pulling these out just
because as you know I like having things
written in line
certainly but I don't like it when I've
got too many things turned off right
because then it's hard for me to read
the code so what I'd like to do here is
just grab this whole bit which is all
stuff we were using to compute that
lighting and I'm just gonna go ahead and
pull that out into a function here and I
don't really care about it at the moment
so I'm just gonna have this be like
something like this big yeah from
building that seems good as opposed
to gobbledygook it's tremble - you
know makes perfect sense so anyway in
here I'm just gonna say look there's
some stuff and we don't care about it
right now but I want to save this
routine in case we ever want to rerun
just that version of it where we're
casting from the voxel centers right so
then I want to do another version of
this where we're gonna sort of do
similar codes I'm going to copy it but
we're gonna gut most of it and and do it
sort of a little bit differently so
we're gonna come through here and
instead of looping over the voxel with
these X Y Z and Z's I'm instead gonna
take this and I'm just gonna loop over
the light probes like this so we're
gonna say for every light probe that we
know is in the system like so we're
gonna do some some stuff right so we're
gonna take our light probe we're gonna
do the the test casting here we don't
care about the Vox Center P anymore
right that's not a thing we do maybe
want to do this stuff still so we'll see
so this will maybe be probe P here right
so we are gonna still do the rest of
this stuff and maybe we even do all of
this the same way right but but
otherwise now and then yeah like in here
our is test cast is probably not really
gonna be able to do quite exactly what
it was doing here but we probably do
want an is test cast thing so I'm gonna
get rid of these for now but I'm gonna
leave that is test cast concept in place
we're just gonna say it's not a test
cast all the time and the future we're
gonna do stuff like maybe isolate by
index or by distance from the light
source or who knows what so we're still
gonna do this but now instead of Vox
Center we're gonna be able to we're
gonna do like probe P and ever gonna go
through and do all this nonsense
exactly the same
and we're still gonna want to do all
this don't ask you I didn't just search
and replace that I didn't so here is our
thing for ray casting the light probe
and then we know you know what what we
actually think the light probe did and
then when we get into here we can still
compute all this stuff effectively the
same way but then the problem that we're
gonna have and the part that's the
actual new code that we have to write
because the probe P will be very easy
for us to compute right we know that the
probe P is really trivial because we
have an array of probe P's so if we look
at what's happening here right it's just
that for whichever one of these things
were looking at so we can pretty much
run the exact same ray casting code to
Ray cast from each one of those probes
and the problem that we're gonna have at
that point is just we don't know what to
do with this so the x y&amp;z locations
inside the voxel that pertained in this
particular probe we have absolutely no
idea what the heck would actually be
here right so we don't know the answer
to this particular question and
furthermore there's a couple other
things that we don't really know so if
you take a look in here there's I mean
not don't really know but there's some
other things that we might not really
want to have happen so for example if
you take a look here there's the light
normal which is this thing but if we're
imagining that these lights have like a
radial fall off or anything else that we
might want to including into the
lighting computation that takes distance
into account when I say lighting of
course here I mean artistic lighting
this has nothing to do with real light
real light doesn't really have distance
fall-off what it has instead is an
inverse square law that has to do with
the diffuse reflection and that's just
based on how the photons spread across
whatever is going to bounce off of
so technically for a specular reflection
there would be no distance fall-off for
a diffuse reflection derby
inverse-square fall-off this game is not
about simulating realistic light so
we're probably gonna want what would
amount to be a programmable fall-off
right we're probably going to want to
have something that an artist Tunes or
in this case we're gonna tune it and so
on and so what we want to do here is we
want to go and we want to basically
produce something usable not something
physical right so we don't care too much
about physical stimulation of the light
here what we care about is us getting
good results out of it so we do want
some fall-off equation in there we don't
necessarily know what it is but what we
do know is that if we're putting an
interpolator down at a particular point
we probably want this distance function
here that we're using to be based
instead on something based on the voxel
center we right - even though we're ray
casting from a different location right
which I realize is a little bit weird
but so things like the light normal
might want to be recomputed
if that makes sense and things like this
light d/f maybe want to be recomputed so
there's that right so I'm going to
change this around a little bit and do
it slightly differently in the future
what we're gonna do here is we're gonna
move this down here right and this stuff
is going to be computed in in probably a
very different way and we're maybe gonna
use the shadow as a boolean to like
modify it or something right so we're
gonna just get yourself in the mindset
of what we output to the voxel maybe
computed at voxel centers to improve our
interpolation quality even though the
Ray casting that we do that controls
whether or not things were shadowed is
not going to work that way right so
these are gonna be separate things and
so if we take a look at light end here I
probably want to separate this stuff out
again like I was saying so this stuff
might
come down here and be computed in a
different way so we would compute the
light end and this probe P here might
actually be Vox entropy still right so
this might happen the same way and this
stuff might be based completely
differently so for example we don't need
to normalize this here because the light
well actually no we do we do
nevermind that's happening here right so
we do want to compute this stuff and
then we want to stuff the voxel here and
this is going to be inside some kind of
a thing that works with the foxhole but
what we're actually gonna do for the
casting is we're gonna have a separate
set of things so here we've got the
probe P which is not going to be about
the voxel Center we're gonna have the
like you know the cast Direction or
something happening here and I don't
actually know if there's any reason why
that have to be normalized or completely
honest with you I don't think that it
does since we're not actually doing
something there I may normalize it here
just to start with but we'll probably
pull that out and the light distance
stuff here is really just to figure out
whether we could anything and we
wouldn't really need the length we could
just take the inner product right so we
can do a lot of stuff here that would
make this cleaner than it's going to be
right now or not cleaner but simpler
faster we just don't care about that at
the moment right so what we want to do
here is say like you know this is
basically a teen max value so when we
take this
when we take all this stuff we're really
producing here as a team maxvalue when
we come through here and we place the
task D in there and maybe these should
be written the other way maybe I should
write this as like that right so this is
the casting location so we have a place
for casting from this is the place for
casting to and this is the direction
that we need to cast in right so then we
come down and we're going to do our ray
casting we have our probe p4 and our
light n for this is going to be cast P
this is going to be cast D and after
we're done with that we get back our
cast result this is going to be our
maximum which is how far it took to get
to the light source that's going to tell
us whether or not we hit anything from
then on out we're using the cast
location to recompute this here this is
if we didn't hit and we want to draw the
thing anyway
in fact this though you could just use
the light piece so I'm not sure why we
did that
exactly but probably just for further
testing the cases right but you can see
that we wouldn't actually have to do
that right
this is not Casspi this is like result P
right or hit P area hit P right so that
produces the hit P that we actually want
to use and then from here we would just
yet this would all be cast P cast pig
casting so that keeps that that keeps
that piece of code is sort of doing
something in a separate way this light
end light c0 stuff that's going to get
computed kind of down here instead so
that's just going to be this stuff
and now I think we've sort of cleaned
ourselves up to the point where we could
call with something right this is gonna
be like test cast from probes right and
we're gonna want to pass the lighting
solution in here like so
and then we're gonna have a few problems
we also need the commands there so this
stuff oh wait no we don't that already
got it signed so all we really need now
is to just to deal with the voxel stuff
which is not going to be correct right
oh and of course the light piece so that
actually is a debug thing that we're
specifying so that kind of has to come
in to the equation I think it's just
debug light P that we don't really
adulterer that at all I don't think yeah
so we don't really change that so I'm
just gonna go ahead and say that that's
just something we pull out here so okay
that's the like test casting direction
and then we have to have the dummy work
order because we're not actually
multi-threading this yet so we're really
just doing sort of a nonsense rate cast
version but because the ray caster is
set up to run on multiple threads
it needs some dummy work value to make
it go all right so now if we clean up
what we've got here this light this
thing here this just Tmax is what I
decided to call that when we actually do
this stuff here this Vox entropy is what
we now need to figure out and
furthermore we actually need you know
this stuff to work as well I think that
though gets us down now to where we
actually want to be the rest of the
stuff is stuff we now have to actually
fix and if we go and call this now we
can insert that call right here where we
were doing it before I also don't think
this needs to be here because no one's
break
anymore so we should be able to just
have now an entirely functional program
that just needs some way of spreading
this information out to nearby voxels
and so that's the next thing that we
have to do so well yeah so in order to
do that we now need some way of figuring
out where one of these things actually
is right and if you look at our spatial
index nonsense that we had before you
know we sort of had ways of doing that
we could say you know this this is
exactly the sort of stuff we need where
it's like tell me for a particular
location you know where it was and we
had a way to index into the voxel and
all that good stuff right and that's
pretty much what we actually need to do
now is wreak you know this code is not
necessary anymore we can delete all of
it pretty much except for the mapping
into the grid part right because this is
exactly what we actually need to do now
so what we want to do is have some way
of reconstructing this part of the code
that we sort of sketched out before but
now using you know just our basic voxel
information that we have and you can see
we've got some information here about it
like the enviros voxel cell dimension
and stuff like that so we should be able
to now have this go directly to the
information that we need so let's say
that we've got a v3 s here I don't know
that we're gonna need that uvw
I just don't think that's gonna be
relevant because what we're gonna want
to do is recompute the solutions at the
voxel centers and just use the raycast
so yeah anyway so what I want to do here
is say look here's a lighting solution
here's the p value that's like some
point in space just any world space
point detect a let's call it world P and
what I want to do now is I want this
thing to produce using this information
right I want this thing to produce we're
in the voxel this raycast
actually is right so when we do that
what we need to do is we need to do
exactly the same steps the first thing
we need to do is get the floating-point
coordinates of this thing and to do that
we need the inverse cell dimension which
we have right and then we need to you
know we've got how big the cells are but
we need the corner to start so that
we're relative to the box in the first
place so we need to take the world
position and we need to take the the the
world corner of our voxel and now we've
mapped it into that space right we
didn't take the floor and that gives us
the actual coordinates we don't care
about this at all right this is just not
relevant to us
not sure what that means exactly that Oh
because yeah sure and so then what we
need to do is we need to clamp the
results so that we're always snapped
into the voxel even for things that are
outside the voxel oh because we don't
want to ever have a bad look up right so
in order to clamp it we take our cell
cords right and these are just going to
be that in fact we could just call it
that and these coordinates that we
actually produce like they can be
negative now so we need to clamp them
and they also could be greater than the
maximum value so we need to clamp these
to what the actual values can be and in
order to do that we need to know like
what the maximum size of our voxel is
and we have that here right it's this
value so we just need to say oh well you
know however big the voxel is that's
what it you know has to clamp to once we
have that information we can look up
into the voxel using this and find out
exactly what's in there at that point
and so we kind of now have the ability
to do exactly what we wanted to do in
the inverse mapping so taking a point
and finding out which voxel it
corresponds to so we've got that what we
don't have is the opposite so some way
of taking a voxel when we're going to
want this right to find out what the
voxel center is so what we want to do is
have some reverse of this which is like
get voxel Center P or something like
that that takes the lighting solution
and one of the indexes and then produces
the center point of the voxel from that
so in order to do that we need to do
exactly the opposite right so this exact
thing has to go in reverse right we have
to take the voxel cell dimension and
multiply it by the index here right and
so this has to get lofted
- a v3 that makes our space out
correctly to be spaced the amount that
the voxel cell dim is right and then we
need to add the minimum corner into it
now that'll give us the corner of the
voxel but if we actually want to know
the center of the voxel we need to add
an offset right so in addition to doing
the Hadamard product on the you know
hole indices we kind of want an offset
here of half of the index value so that
we get to the middle of the voxel
instead of the corner this gives us a
way to go in and out of voxel space
pretty cleanly so this should allow us
to do a basic fill of our voxel grid to
start with right so we're gonna we're
gonna do just some basic work with that
now in here this provides us our ability
to solve this problem here not knowing
with the x y&amp;z are so what I should be
able to do at the start here is say
alright let's find out what the voxel
center is and the coordinates so here's
the voxel let's call this box will index
or box I may be so for the cast P this
is the location we cast from this is the
voxel right and so then the box entropy
it's just to look up on that so now when
we do this we have all the information
we need so this now instead of z Y X is
gonna be just Vox I dot Z right box I
got Y Vox I got X now we can't choose to
do some other things here we can choose
if we want to this get voxel index we
could actually change this and you know
maybe we should I don't know exactly we
want to do this but we can do here is
say if we wanted to we could make this
so that this thing would not record
results for people outside of the usable
area right in other words if we wanted
to we could make it so that only like
the hot region was considered or
whatever else we want so we can pretty
easily put an if in here and limit it at
the moment I'm not gonna do that because
I don't really care but when we actually
started to think about this for real
there's gonna be other things we're
gonna want to do there that are not the
same alright so now we've actually got
this coded it's probably totally wrong
but at least we can start getting things
going here right so let's see what
happens there okay so off we go right
and you can see we've got some weird
stuff happening here but oddly enough
it's not totally wrong so it's sort of
doing something at the moment and it's
actually producing a little bounded
light thing which is pretty great right
so we're we're off to a start if not
particularly good start but that's
totally fine right it's our job to now
kind of get get this get this into some
better shape right so we'd take a look
at like what we're seeing here you know
there's there's enough like curiosity in
any one of these there's enough
weirdness like you can see there's like
kind of weird like hard lines going
through that for no apparent reason like
what's that about I have no idea right
and so we kind of want to start looking
at the actual casting now and figuring
out what we're getting
and why we're seeing what we're seeing
right and the first thing I want to do
is find out like did I do any of this
right at all like are any of these
castes happening properly right so the
first thing I'd like to do is take these
these light probe casts that we're doing
I'd like to go ahead and and just see if
those casts look reasonable at all right
so I'm gonna set is test case two one
will probably need to restrict it more
than we are currently in order to
actually get usable results what I could
do is take the distance from the light
for example so this so I'll say like the
test case is if T max is less than you
know 10 or something then that's a test
case anything greater than that is not
right and so that's just me attempting
to bound the number of things that would
be considered test cases in this case
and if I look now honestly it's a bit
weird it seems like it's doing the
opposite of what I asked for if the
length of the cast is less than 10 how
are these less than 10 but those aren't
did I do something stranger
might turn off that's a bit peculiar
wouldn't you say I would have expected
to see the exact opposite thing happen
so I must be going a little bit crazy
here
oops
I mean that's very strange Oh am I just
not drawing things that don't hit yeah
maybe that's all could be that's all
that's happening all right let's take a
look so it looks like I should be
drawing things even if they don't hit
right because here's hit right and we're
setting the line color based on it but
then I do do this
I guess this part here may be wrong so
hit P is T max times cast D
oh yeah that's totally wrong that's
that's the problem so no I was I was
just coding poorly just coding poorly
all right so here's our casting
information and I'll be honest it looks
great
that looks exactly right to me I mean
you can kind of see it connecting up to
all the points we actually wanted to you
can see that points that appear to be
you know probes pros that are like in
weird positions like I don't know what
the heck that cast is doing down there
if they're actually a light probe down
there like what is that doing there I
don't really want to know
that seems busted I wonder if we have a
bogus light probe that might just be
like zero zero zero and we'll have to
address that later but if you take a
look at what's going on here I mean this
looks great
you can see like as I'm going through
the store wake here you can look at the
visibility of these light probes and you
can see that like these are blocked by
the door these are not right and so
everybody is is very very consistent in
my opinion even this one here who can
just barely see over it you know that
was correct right uh so that all seems
pretty good to me so I'm gonna go ahead
and say it looks like our voxel fill is
really the only problem and they're mean
really be a problem with it made us not
be complete enough yet and I'll explain
what I mean by that in a second
what that means really what I kind of
need to see is not the casting anymore
the casting is not the important part
it's the voxel flood so basically the
thing that that fills this voxel in I
want to know which voxels we're filling
that's the important part now and so we
kind of have to get that going a little
bit more I don't know
to be completely honest with you I also
don't want a hundred percent know if
this so we're using the cast starting
location to produce the index which
seems right to me we're then taking the
the distance the light source distance
from the voxel center and that all seems
right and then we're just saying if we
hit we don't fill it and that all seems
right to me yeah yeah yeah so that all
seems pretty good the only thing that
we're not doing it right is these are
these are need to be kind of weighted
additions right these these need to be
blended together and they're currently
not being blended together right so the
main thing that we're really not
handling at the moment is the fact that
we have multiple things writing into the
same location and we're not doing
anything about that I don't think that
has anything to do with the problem
we're looking at now but that is
something that we're gonna have to do
going forward all right so what I want
to do now is we have in our ray caster a
way of drawing a debug box right using
using debug lines we can draw a debug
box I don't really remember where I put
that here it is so what I want to do is
have that be this push debug line
I want like internal void push debug box
and what I want to do is just take this
code this whole that nonsense here I
want that to be callable elsewhere so
that I can draw debug boxes in the debug
system really easily right so this just
needs the letting solution and then it
needs box min box max and then it just
needs a color value I think is all
and then it draws the box right all
right so the Box min/max in color here
those kind of want to be extracted if
you look at how they're being extracted
here we kind of need to do an extract
component on them so that we don't have
to pass them but they can be passed as
v3s and not as these sort of composite
versions right so we want to do like a
get component on these like that and
then I think that should give us
everything we need now this routine now
needs to be like getting rid of the
Docky
right in fact I guess I can just sort of
I think I can just yeah so I can just
remove that entirely because it should
just do that
so now we can call that from anywhere as
soon as I get rid of the compiler errors
that there aren't any so now instead of
just being able to draw boxes inside the
raycast I can draw boxes anywhere it's
exactly what I actually need now to to
debug the next step which is the voxels
sort of filling which may or may not be
operating correctly right now it may be
correct and just incomplete because we
haven't like bloomed out to neighboring
voxels which is something I need to be
able to do but I want to just get the
simple straightforward version and know
that it's working properly first before
we go down that road so the first thing
I want to do yes just verify that we're
filling the voxels that we think we're
filling and so I'm gonna have an if test
case around here and then I'm gonna draw
it so in here I'm going to say like look
if this is a test case so what are the
ones that we were trying to do here I'm
gonna push debug lines on for the box
and I'm gonna use this right here so
I've got my Vox Center P so I'm just
gonna say like alright
not sure what color I should draw this
in but maybe you like something like
this and if we look at what I'm doing
here right all I'm trying to do is say
when I break a storm eyes light probes
show me which voxels are actually
getting hit right because I want to make
sure that that placement scheme is
actually working so the box radius in
this case is pretty easy for us to
figure out right it's just the voxel dim
/ - right
that's all I have to do because I know
that that's the radius of the box so
that's from the center I would just go
half in either direction and then that
gives me my my box right
it's completing about something that's
true
it's a v4 uh and so now I think we're
good that should draw what I wanted it
to draw and so let's go ahead and run
that see it looks like maybe I'm
overflowing maybe let's make this a
little bit less sprawling I have a
pretty small buffer for debug lines and
not to mention the fact that we don't
draw them particularly quickly so
seriously
is that really true do I have a
different bug I wonder if I have a
different bug here
all right so let's start by saying t max
listen to all right
so somehow that seems to be creating a
overflow really early and I feel like
that means I've done something stupid
because it really shouldn't I don't
think that feels really wrong to me I
feel like we need to take a look at that
we're on my debug lines so I don't feel
like we could possibly be drawing 4096
debug lines there that didn't look that
didn't look plausible to me
I mean it's only like what 12 lines per
box so I should be able to draw like
easily a hundred boxes before anyone
thinks anything weird is going on right
so is there some weird thing happening
there let's let's let me I want to take
a look at this a little more carefully
here oh hey Molly being the puss arrived
she's just mousing around right now
she's not doing nothing she's just like
looking see what the status of the world
is you know how cats like to patrol what
you do in puss mm-hmm you want to help
us debug the lighting you want to help
us to bug the lighting at all do you you
want to play with the paperclip what are
you doing
all right that's coffee you don't want
that caffeine is bad for cats all right
so yeah let me just run this in debug
mode and and I want to see like what
that crash is about because I don't
really understand who is drawing so many
lines here so first of all I wanted to
verify that was a case but you can see
that it is right so it's looking at says
like the debug line count is less than
the size of this thing right so if we
look at the the debug line how many of
these there are it looks like it
actually got to 4096 and my question is
you know how is it getting there given
how little there actually is in theory
of drawing these debug lines the number
of debug lines we should be drawing is
it's just not just not that high right
so I'm a little confused about that and
in theory the debug line count should
have been set to zero here so like if we
actually kind of go through here
I want to see
that value specifically so coming into
this routine we have not drawn anything
and so presumably just just running that
is enough to draw 4,096 lines now what's
weird about that is it just didn't seem
like there were but maybe there actually
are I'm gonna go ahead and up that
number just because that's really true
we just need more of them and yeah maybe
it'll bog down our renderer hugely and
it's a disaster but you know what
not my problem all right
so let's see here is supposedly us
drawing 4096 lines that seems totally
crazy to me I mean I guess each one of
these is three and each one of these is
12 but like seriously what do you do
push debug lines is it somehow like add
more than it should all right I'm gonna
do one more check cuz it just doesn't
look right
doesn't look like there's 4096 lines
even with those multiples in there
doesn't feel right to me I mean to be
fair drawing the same box on top of
itself multiple times would you know
increase the count and we are doing that
but like 12 times
you know what 2 300 would have to be
before we really were able to get up
that high it just doesn't seem right so
much watch check to make sure there's
nothing else weird going on this is me
just being paranoid
but sometimes when programming it pays
to be paranoid
hmm that's a little suspicious don't you
think are we doing something where we
have like a ton of light probes that are
all set to the same value or something
yeah that is exactly what's happening so
this could also be just because the
light probe stuff is putting the things
in there at particular locations so
that's what's happening so here's my
proposal I think that means I would like
to get rid of the usage of the
assignment slots at the moment so here's
what we're gonna do instead I'm gonna go
into the renderer here I want to look at
the light probe stuff
and inset light probe position what
we're gonna do is we're gonna nuke this
out here this is not what's going to
happen here instead we're gonna have
like a push a push golf of that so we
don't want any of this light probe clear
we want none of this stuff right so
we're gonna say no to this and instead
what we're gonna do is we're gonna say
push light probe render group entity P
and all this is the only thing this will
do is basically ensured that there is a
light probe at that location right so
then we're gonna take the set light
probe position and we're gonna leave
that in there in case I end up needing
it you know in case it turns out that
this whole thing doesn't work and
instead what we're going to do here is
instead of all this we're just gonna say
assuming that we have room for it then
it goes in here
and that's good right so now we should
get our light probes
did we not so now we should get our
light probes being like a clean compact
set and we should not be having any two
in the same location anymore right now
unless there's something else screwed up
which for all I know there might be but
I want to yeah
that's what I would have expected so
basically we just had a crap ton of
light probes that really weren't doing
anything and that was kind of to be
expected with the way we're doing it but
now you can sort of see like okay
everything's fine right and what you can
see here too is looking at the way that
this stuff is working you can see how
the lighting information is is getting
placed right so there's a couple things
that are kind of nasty about this our
great is not really centered the way
that I probably would have hoped like so
we probably want to adjust the way our
grid is working so that it's offset a
little bit but that's that's a separate
issue that we can deal with later what
we really want to do here is figure out
why we're getting the weird pockmarking
that we were getting right so when we
look at this
boy you know what are we actually
filling and I kind of want to shrink
these I think what I want to do here is
you see it was hard to see like once you
get enough in an area it's hard to see
which one's getting filled I want to
just use a very simple technique to make
it that visualization easier for us to
understand so inside the lighting when
we draw that box I want to shrink it
just a little so basically what that's
gonna do is let me see which ones are
actually getting filled instead of what
was kind of happening for where it was
very hard to see oh and by the way we
don't really need to be
debug mode anymore but so now what you
can see is we can we can easily see
which boxes are actually getting hit and
which ones aren't right and that's you
know pretty useful right so what you can
see here is it's pretty obvious why our
pockmarking is happening and it's just
because these are right on the boundary
so these middles ones never get filled
with any information now obviously our
sampling scheme is pretty crappy if
that's what's happening but it's okay
because actually we want to solve that
problem anyway for separate reasons
which is that when we actually fill a
voxel we want to fill sort of a you know
a swath of nine probably a swath of nine
around the voxel and that's something
that we kind of want to do is a separate
as a separate pass and that's pretty
crucial for you know just for allowing
this thing to work sort of at edges I
guess is what I would say right where
the light probes stop and so in order to
do that what I'd like to do is just go
in there and add a little loop that
spams out to neighboring areas right and
then we're going to very quickly get
into the fact that this is not properly
handling sort of summation like
contribution right but let's go ahead
and do that that part first so when we
get Molly beam where's that was that was
the sad me house
Molly where are you at
come here come here please come on
what's wrong
come on up come on up what's wrong
do you want to code with us do you want
to cope with this do you wanna say hi to
the camera
come on say hi to the camera hey you
want to see the camera that's the camera
yeah there's a bunch of people there's a
couple hundred people watching you right
now did you know that yeah
what's wrong did you want someone to
play with you and no one was playing
with you is that what happened yeah is
that what happened okay do you wanted to
sit with me or do you want to what do
you want to do I don't know what you're
up to
you were mousing around before so I have
a feeling you don't want to sit I have a
feeling you want to play but I can't
play with you right now when the stream
is over we can play well look okay is
that okay is that all right maybe what
do you think what do you think kiddo
maybe all right well you can decide but
I just can't play right now that's all
but you can say it if you want you can
sit on my lap if you want we got room
for you here we do if you're up for it
you looking at get your in a play mode
though yeah this is the problem you're
not in a sitting mode I know you're not
I can see you looking over there here
you want to play go ahead down go ahead
down there you go and we'll play later
okay all right so anyway what I want to
do is just kind of span this out to
nearby voxels as well so I want this to
kind of be a little bit of a four I loop
right and so I want this to you know do
this kind of thing right so we do want
our kind of like XYZ thing in here and
to be honest I don't know if I really
want it to look like a four I loop
though and the reeds
for that is just because I don't really
want to spin up an entire set of like
loops and jumps and unpredictable
branches and crap like this for no
reason
so what I'd rather do is something more
like this maybe so you know maybe
something that looks a little bit like
this where I do like you know spam voxel
or something like this and that's gonna
take that voxel I do all this garbage on
it and then spam out to the voxel and so
what I need here is I just need I don't
really need this part here because I can
just not do the right so this is
probably fine but what I do need is I
need the light position right and of
course since we have that here I can yes
you know this is test code so we don't
have to be pretty very specific about
where that's coming from
but so we can do this stuff just fine
and the is test case part we can just
sort of inherit from our caller I'm
sorry if test cast and then I really
just need to make this stuff get called
with the correct set of voxel eyes so
the problem that we're gonna have here
is just that we could be outside the
voxel now so we kind of need some
ability to clamp this thing and so we
need this to support that sort of spam
radius in a sense right and when we do
that clamp you know we could just clamp
it to the interior and then do the
spamming I don't know if that's a
particularly good idea but you know I'm
just saying we could do it that way but
point being what we need here is
basically like a set of these so we need
like you know this sort of thing
so all I want to do here is just spam a
predictable set of these like so and
I feel like there should only be oh wait
no there's way more of them so no it's
just three by three by three so there's
actually 27 things that touches
that's too many it feels like we really
do want to not have to do this well in
for a penny in for a pound anyway so
this is gonna be expensive for us we're
gonna probably have to figure out ways
to make this work better to be
completely honest because this is gonna
be pretty nasty in terms of the amount
of work that's involved in in sort of
blooming the voxel so we may have to do
something more clever than what I'm
doing here and yeah so if we look at
like how this works so let's suppose we
did it this way we would have to repeat
this for each one of these right and so
maybe we do have like one four I loop
and then we just spam the nine case so
something like this is basically what
we're looking at and the problem that
we're gonna have is this is gonna be out
of bounds now right and so what we could
do is say well when we do map into voxel
we'll just get rid of the clamp
completely right so this part here will
just be like good luck right so when you
get that Fox index that could be just
totally out of bounds and then when we
do like our offsetting of it you know
this this will actually happen here so
we'll do a like if in large voxel off we
go otherwise don't do anything and then
we just have you know something like
this they can test
for like inside nests and then we'll
just not fill if we're not inside so
then we've got solution sigh and I think
at that point we're good to go
no all right I now want to see like what
I'm actually filling hopefully we're
feeling a lot more stuff and it looks
like we are right and so now I want to
see if that kind of takes care of the
issue we were having with the you know
the fill not not spreading out properly
so if we you know if we do that spamming
to the things around the voxel let's go
ahead and see what the actual Z biased
program result looks like at that point
and so I'm gonna turn off the letting
disabled and turn on the non debug build
there and just see what kind of results
were getting
so now it looks like we're more or less
getting what I would expect
and what you can see is the only issue
now right is that we fill things that
that aren't really visible right so
we're spamming kind of out to things
that aren't quite visible and I think
that that actually can be taken care of
by a slightly different thing we can do
as well although actually you know what
the only thing is that may actually
because there's are some of those are
visible let's let's turn that off for us
to get a fair result so I'm gonna set
the light source to be lower now so if
we so that it'll actually be blocked by
walls because it's kind of clears it
clears over the walls a bunch of times
now I just want to get rid of that while
we're testing this so if we go into what
is it debug light yeah so what I want to
do here is take the camera NDP I want to
drop that light down a significant
amount so that's it's much lower down
maybe even lower down than then plus one
but we'll see in a second so that's like
right about the heroes head level yeah
so now it can't really clear walls so
that flood filling presumably is coming
from well you know I'll be honest I'm
not sure who that's coming from how is
there a like valid light that's hitting
that
so I'm not really sure what what's going
on there
because even that shouldn't quite have
the light leaking bug that I'm thinking
of at the moment um let me hmm
so let me take a look and see because
I'm not really sure what we're what
we're dealing with there before I before
I start mouthing off about what I wanted
to do about it because I'm not really
sure where that's going cuz yeah like if
you look at the like that doesn't
propagate through the wall right like
the the light probe here is not gonna
write into that so I'm not sure why you
would ever be getting any light leaking
through there right I need a way to
visit to see these both at the same time
so we're gonna have to that's not what I
wanted at all so we're gonna have to do
some work on our debug setup maybe
that's what we'll do next weekend in
preparation for like doing the final
white coat as will improve the debug vis
on the lighting because right now it's
crappy I just need a bunch of ways to
switch things on and off so I can see
yeah so so I don't get that like I don't
get who's actually filling that there
I'm gonna set the radius a little higher
so I can see some of those test cases
and what they're actually returning so
if I go into
the front with a routine was the
easiest thing to do there so it's what's
the actual name
it's like test-case castro probes so
what I want to do here is maybe to
spread this out a little more so we can
see like a little more what's going on
in there
Oh duh we never put in the the hip case
so yeah that was all just not even a
thing boy that's that's almost an ALICE
shame thankfully I thought of it right
away
that was that was almost a now of shame
all right so let's now figure out what
the heck is going on here so you can see
here that for some reason well no we're
still getting some weird interpolation
there oh I see why that's because we're
not clearing the voxel that's all right
so you can see we're not actually
updating the voxel in those regions and
that's because we don't actually clear
I'll just all this cleared the voxel we
don't actually want to do that
eventually but I think now we're getting
more more accurate results right what is
this looks like we've got too many too
many quads getting pushed down all right
so I think we're better now I think
we're in in more reasonable shape I'm
not too turned that test caster down so
we're not drawn so many boxes back
okay so what I want to do now is just
clear the voxel before we do anything
else and the reason for that is just
because right now we're not really doing
anything sensible in terms of like
averaging over frames or anything so
stuff that goes into the voxel just
stays in the voxel and it sort of
Bogart's our results right so I want to
loop over the entire voxel which
honestly I don't know if we have code
that does that yeah we do so in in from
the Gok we can go ahead in here and just
clear the voxel first which is not
something we would ordinarily do but
it's going to be something we do now and
so I'm just gonna literally clear
everything in the voxel all of the
lights and turn them off that way if you
don't actually see one on a particular
frame then you don't that doesn't
actually work that should show us a
fairer estimate of the lighting and you
can see like when we hop up sometimes it
clears it so I should probably still
move the light down just a little bit
more right
but as you can see like it's starting to
look pretty good
so I think we're now correctly sort of
doing roughly what we should I still
think it's a little too high to move it
down because when we hop up it's still
kind of
what's going on there oh wow so that's
that's too low then it can't quite clear
the floor
all of this will be not really a huge
issue once we're actually doing bounce
lighting obviously but okay so basically
now we more or less have like fog of war
right like you know you can't really see
until you actually get there I'm curious
to know what happens if we increase the
fall-off right so if I actually change
the fall-off of the light which is you
know just a nonsense thing that's
happening in here right now it's just
this this garbage here right so if I
decided to do this as something more
like that so now the light falls off
more slowly that radius gets larger what
you should see is like you know kind of
just basically fog of war right the Ray
caster is sort of telling us now like
what you can see right so again not
really something we want to use for
lighting per se right because it's not
actually telling us any kind of a good
lighting solution right it's not telling
us anything about like how the light
bounces around and so you know it's it's
it's not what we want for any of that
stuff but if we go ahead and turn off
the test cast thing
then you can see that we basically have
a little fog of war solver right which
is exactly what a red caster does right
it doesn't really give us lighting but
it gives us some you know sort of it's
it's a visibility query right and what
we happen to be asking for is the
visibility from the light source and
since I put the light source at the
player unsurprisingly you know that's
what we get right and see our kind of
weird specular thing that we did they're
having an effect so I'm going to call
that good for today for sure because the
next step is now we have to kind of move
on to kind of a whole nother ballgame of
convecting light sources around and then
merging samples as well which is really
not something that's gonna be simple
right that's gonna be a whole another
sort of set of things we've got to do
and you know what can I use the ground
point of the entity by the way and so it
doesn't where's the debug light key
thing there like a ground point nonsense
this is supposed to be more stable I
think
yeah
so we're getting there slowly but surely
and I think that Rea casters working
pretty reliably now from the light like
that seems all seems pretty good we
still have a ton of problems with the
sort of the I don't like the flicker
that you get I mean the lighting
obviously is making most of the problem
here but the fact that you kind of blend
things in and out based like you want
the ground P to actually be a plane so
when you're hopping over uneven terrain
you want things like the Alpha to stay
the same that's kind of a separate issue
that we're gonna have to do before I
really consider the graphics to be solid
but the lighting is more important at
the moment right so I would consider
that pretty much working and we now have
the other two things we have the
blending and the convection now we got
to start working on but that's fine so I
think we're I think we're pretty good
right I mean that that's working very
well considering how we've really done
nothing but a single ray cast so I think
we're in good shape like I'm not I'm not
too worried about this now I think this
is coming along also unlike before like
this is running completely fine very
stable and per pixel right we're getting
full lighting on everything including
characters and stuff like that that we
can now go in and like tune their
normals and stuff but you can see like
it's even working here like if I because
the normals on that person are just
pointing directly away from me it gets
no light and when I come on the other
side of it does right so we now have
like that ability to sample lighting per
pixel on all the sprites as well so that
that'll give us a lot of flexibility to
I mean we have to decide what we want to
do there because it's kind of confusing
how you want to light stuff like that
but you know it gives us a lot of
flexibility on how we can choose to
light our sprites as well which is nice
okay let's go the QA
isn't there an hour left I don't think
so the stream started at 12:30 right
with the particle system be affected by
the shadows yes
just take care so I believe it already
actually is as well
so I don't really know but everything as
far as I know including the particles go
through the same shaders so it should be
totally yeah you can actually see that
there right
so the normals are probably set wrong on
the particles at the moment so we we'd
have to set the normals but you can see
they are affected by the lighting right
so all we really have to do is make sure
for each particle we set the normal to
something right and then we're good so
so the particles should all work just
fine in fact everything will work just
fine so mostly what we have to do now is
is make like a real lighting convection
and then sample blending right because
all right now and you can kind of see
it's just discrete either you can see
the light source or you can so you
basically it goes on one frame from
being able to see it to not being able
to see it and that's what changes the
lighting so that's not what we want at
all right and also we don't get any
bounces right so that's not what we want
so this is just ray casting testing so
we gotta go and you know actually do
that part which is what we'll start on
next weekend but other than that I think
we're good because now any sprite that
we want can can totally have that happen
I should also take out the like there's
there's no reason for the light probes
to be drawn at the moment
yeah
there's some issues with the smoothness
and that has to do with blending as well
I think I suspect
and I'm I guess I'm not 100% sure of it
though so I'm not 100% sure what a
little of that flicker is coming from so
we may have to investigate that a little
further that may just have to do with
the blending not being in there I'm not
positive
can we enable life the debaters we could
see the impact of the code
again probably don't want to do that
till next dream because I think that's a
fairly big thing am i procrastinate
engine games like I didn't invent
problems to solve yes I mean as I've
said many times I really don't want to
have to do any gameplay code I'm going
to run out of things to do eventually
but I will make that I will make that be
as far away as possible because that is
really not my thing right and I don't
really I'm not looking forward to it
that is why I'm an engine programmer and
not a gameplay programmer I would much
rather sit around and proving lighting
quality than having a code like what
happens when you like punch a dude you
know what I mean
I feel like our lighting is gonna look
really really baller once we get the
bounce in there
it seems you look sweet
yeah I'm excited for that
just if the camp code is an assignment
to John yeah John doesn't have much to
do why are the debug liens of fixed size
buffer just cuz it's throwaway code um
yeah I mean it just doesn't matter right
also kind of for the reason that we just
saw like I want it to complain if I draw
too many debug lines that probably means
something weird is happening and it was
so you know sometimes you want some hard
limits in your code especially if it's
not something that the user interacts
with because it lets you know that
something went wrong
you have any thoughts on the trade us of
making your data structures directly
serializable versus having intermediate
serialize to serialize steps ie data
structures containing pointers being
converted to offsets or indices so I
guess what I would say is I don't
normally think of it that way
serialization it's usually not that big
of a deal to me
because usually if your stuff is working
well in at runtime it is usually trivial
to serialize it is my experience so for
example you know typically you don't
really want pointers anyway in your data
structures like if you have pointers in
your like world code it usually means
something bad is happening right it
usually means that like you're using a
lot more space to store something than
you probably should which is gonna make
it inefficient right and so most of the
time I find it's not really an issue
so the question doesn't usually come up
another way to say it would be that
usually you've already converted things
to offsets or indices for other
performance or compactness reasons
before you even have to worry about the
serialization part of things at least
the way I write things 0l PBM says are
the bounces going to be computed also
with the ray tracer absolutely that is
exactly what's going to be happening
that's why we did it this way first it
so I could verify that direct lighting
worked properly because that's easy for
me to inspect like I can tell that this
is doing what it's supposed to be doing
to the for the most part right and that
the rheya caster isn't you know confused
about something and we can test it some
more using this as an example right you
can see there's some weirdness there
where like we clip off the the
Lighting's getting like clipped off
there
I don't know why maybe because of the
close enough filtering fact I can check
that right now
yes so if inside the raycast we are
still doing that which we are yeah I'm
kind of wondering if this is nonsense
right so the close enough filtering I've
already said it's kind of it to do
because that don't think it's very good
I just want to see if that's what's
happening here yep
so that close enough filtering is like
garbage and that's unfortunate but yeah
that's where we're at so that close
enough filtering probably needs to be
done differently however just increasing
the the total distance was enough to fix
it here so I suppose it's not an
immediate concern but I do think it's
just generally kind of wrong
can we add for a test the second bounce
or would it require more work for a test
we could add a second bounce it would
not be being done the way we will do it
in the future though right I'm trying to
think if really it would even do
anything at all
I mean so if we were literally just
hacking that in right to the way that
it's working currently and the problem
is we don't have blending either so I
really don't think this would be an
interesting test to be completely honest
with you
oops like I don't think this is gonna be
useful but if you needed to hack it in
this way what you would have to do is
basically right here where we find out
that we got a hit we then have to like
recast to see if there is an an on hit
from the other point and then we have to
decide like how much to attenuate which
I don't actually know exactly how we
would do I guess we just take the total
distance or something of travel but yeah
I mean I don't know like this is not at
all right but that's what you would do
you'd go like all right you know if we
hit do it again
where we would basically say like yeah
you know where the hit I don't know why
there's an if one around this anymore
it's just kind of stupid but so we'd say
yeah alright you know the the place that
we actually hit we need to produce a new
caste for that that's gonna come from
like the direction the new direction to
the light source right so you'd have to
do this whole stupid thing again right
so you'd say like alright
the secondary caste direction is like
the direction from the hit P and the
secondary caste Tmax right just this or
that who knows right so you would do
that and then you would have a secondary
caste that would tell you whether or not
you hit if you didn't hit so if like you
did this right
or rather that so if you cast you didn't
hit anything then you could undo the hit
and say like no it's not and the problem
would be that we would need to be
passing to the spam voxel the fact that
that it should be dimmer because it had
to bounce right so I I don't really know
that this is gonna do anything that we
want done why am I not able to build my
code what's going on here
oh no we just building the code so you
know in theory I guess that maybe is
doing a secondary bounce now I mean now
again I don't really know how to even
verify that in any particular way but it
kind of does look like it's doing
something slightly different I mean we
can certainly test at least whether or
not the thing works you know whether it
does anything so if I guess zero this
out here
I can't see anything I if it in and like
those things can see the secondary
bounce right but it's like I mean it
just means like someone you know like
someone over here hit that and then
could like or someone over here like hit
that and was able to get there or
something right for whatever reason but
it's not it's not a true secondary it's
not secondary light distribution because
it doesn't take into account the fact
that like all of these services got some
light like like these services could get
some light or something and then they
could spread it out you know in all
directions so it's it's just a specular
bounce so it doesn't mean anything right
it's just not useful I don't think it
doesn't improve the quality in any
meaningful way
right whereas the distribution system we
have from before when we turn that on I
think that'll be a big difference right
because it actually it actually is
taking account infinite bounces
basically and proper like spreading of
the light around so make sure I didn't
screw anything up there
do you plan any details and have spray
charlet yeah I'm not sure what we want
to do with sprite lighting but once we
have the lighting solution correct for
the 3d geometry since we can sample it
per pixel now I don't think it's gonna
be particularly hard to come up with a
reasonable sort of hacked function that
gives us the lighting we want you know
and we can we can sort of play with what
that means it's not gonna be something
physically realistic at all but it will
be probably something around like
interpolating the normals such that they
capture kind of roughly the lighting we
want it's my second year programming it
feels like there's endless stuff to
catch up before I can be a competent
game programmer what might I do to help
with that yeah I mean that's just that's
just true right it takes a lot of work
before you can be a game engine
programmer and that's okay right it
takes a while when you first start
working in the industry you're not gonna
know everything you know and that's fine
it takes several years to kind of get up
to speed on all that stuff so you just
want to focus on one thing at first you
know you know maybe you start by doing
you know I'm just doing some physics or
I'm just doing some graphics or I'm just
doing some this or that or architecture
stuff or entities work or game play
programming work right and you just
build outward you know you one thing at
a time and take it easy
you know nobody knows everything day one
it takes many many years and that's fine
and you're not gonna expect it to know
everything the first day you show up at
your first game permit job so you know I
wouldn't stress too much about it but
always be programming ABC right always
be coding uh-huh and if you're always
working eventually that knowledge will
just build over time
oops tonight sorry Elvis did I mess
something up there maybe I didn't do a
fair test of that I mean I still don't
it's just not useful but was there
something messed up in here oh yeah I
did
sorry I think that's right now
again I mean not really testing it I
don't know to what extent it's actually
doing it properly but in theory that's a
secondary bounce I don't really know if
it is
doesn't seem to actually be doing
anything oops
so there's without the quote-unquote
secondary bounce kind of does what you
expect here's with the not very good
secondary bounce
and you would want some dimming in there
right I mean so to make it even remotely
an interesting test you would need to
sort of have the total distance so like
you would have to have something that
let it know what the mitigation distance
was like and I don't you'd have to like
basically fake the light information so
this would have to update like the light
P right so you know an example would be
like so inside spam voxel this stuff
here so light P and also light C right
so this these would have to be things
that come in like so we'd have to do
this like v3 light P and B 3 light C so
basically you'd be doing this and then
when you do spam voxel you're actually
passing down like like this and again I
really don't think this is even remotely
related to what we should be doing and
we're not gonna do anything like this
next weekend but just you know for a
sake of completeness if we were gonna
update the light beam the light C right
then what we would do is say okay when
we come through here the light P is
gonna get read out of this right and the
light C is just going to be a generic
light and then when we come through here
we're gonna do is say all right if we
have a secondary hit so we need to like
update this light source it's something
else then we're gonna say the light is
actually now technically coming from a
different location so the actual
location the light is coming from now is
the hit P right so where we actually
bounced off of that's the new light and
the light color is actually going to be
whatever the attenuation would have been
at that point right so that means the
actual like this crap here right this
thing needs to be computed for fall off
like this
based on the distance of the original
cast so this thing right
so the original cast distance that we
actually traveled whatever that was
needs to attenuate the attenuate the
light source first and then that's the
actual color that you get right and
that's a totally hacked in nonsense
thing I don't even know if I typed it in
right but you get the idea right and so
that like that like dimming step wants
to be there as well and and now you can
kind of see what that looks like and
it's quite a bit different right
especially like out here right
so it's probably super buggy right look
I don't like I don't know this is
probably not really correct but it's
something like that
right
how you gonna handle bouncing up
different materials so we have
parameters in there right now that sort
of allow you to say some things about
the trails but what we don't have is any
way of like doing multi textured stuff
and I think I'm not going to do that
just for Speed purposes so probably what
we'll do is cubes will just have a color
per face and we'll just use whatever
color face you bump off of or we may
even not do that we may just say look
cubes have a general attenuation and
that's all you get so you basically just
have you know here's the rough
attenuation is brown is it green or
whatever we're not gonna really do
anything more than that
which type of engine programming do you
think the industry needs the most boy I
mean I don't know I couldn't say for
like the industry as a whole I would say
based on what I see the need for
definitely need graphics programmers you
pretty much never run out of need for
graphics programmers there's always so
much fricking graphics work to do
pipeline programmers so people who know
how to like do like processing of assets
and world
elodie generation chunking things ups
constructive solid geometry so base like
people who geometry processing people
tools construction people so people who
can make like little tools to do stuff
or like user interfaces for things need
a lot of that there's just so much stuff
optimizer people are typically very
useful you know who can analyze the
system find out what's causing the
problems and go in and fix them so that
the thing runs smoothly
everyone needs those people generalists
are useful everywhere I mean there's
just there's so much any-anything if you
can do any game programming game engine
programming there's probably a place for
you because there's so few there's just
nobody does it
so I mean that's just just how it is
yeah the answer is everything everywhere
yes kind of yeah I mean for example
right now I am trying to fill at least
four requests from friends of mine
looking for low-level I mean you know
engine programmer quality people and so
far I I have failed to to find it
profession our engine programmers really
as in-demand as you say I see the most
Triple A games or releasing with
hundreds of employees but only like four
to six engine programmers um so here's
what I would say I can't tell you
industry-wide because I don't know how
to get that statistic but I'll say two
things one just personally I can never
find enough like is that literally right
now if I had for high-quality engine
programmer people I could place them all
in jobs immediately I have no idea where
to find them none whatsoever
right as for the statistic of like
Triple A games releasing with hundreds
of employees but only like 46 engine
programmers first of all I think that's
not actually accurate but in general I
would suspect that most of the time the
reason there are only four to six engine
programmers anywhere is because that's
all they could find I mean I don't know
where I'd go to find more than six
engine programmers period like to hire
right now I can't even find four right
so I mean I'm just going by what I can't
find whereas if you just want some
random person who can write a script in
unity I mean I think you can just walk
onto the internet and you'll trip over
one right
how much do games he has hurt interns I
don't really know
I feel like Ryan Fleury that the the
person who now runs handmade Network who
took over for Abner I feel like he has
interned at a couple game companies or
at least one Internet insomniac I think
he might you maybe want to post on the
handmade network discord or something I
don't know how you get those set up
exactly but along with the theme what do
you define as the minimum requirement to
be a good engine programmer
so the the requirements for being a you
know someone who's really useful on an
engine programming team I would say I'd
have to think about how to define it
specifically but it probably is sort of
a three-pronged test for me one would be
gets a lot of work done right and this
can fall into one of two categories if
you're an architecture guy it means
getting a lot of code actually done
because like writes and rewrites are
your bread and butter and you need to
get a lot of this done but if you're not
if you're an optimization guy it may be
a lot more targeted so maybe you don't
get a lot of code done but you do do a
lot of work analyzing figuring out
problems and you get through that
cognitive work a lot right and so either
way you're producing a lot of very
usable work frequently either a lot of
analysis or a lot of actual code but
you're producing a lot you're not just
sitting around talking all the time or
hanging out on Twitter right so that's
super important that's the most
important requirement really for any
programmer is you get a lot of work done
every day
number two would be comfortable with
doing programming in C or C++ or
assembly language
routinely and you do it clean and well
without a lot of fuss not a lot of STD :
: nonsense none of this like modern C++
Rai nonsense like none of that right
just actual sensible code that's simple
easy to read you know like you see on
handmade hero just basic stuff does what
it's supposed to do not all this
ridiculous nonsense where somehow it
takes you ten thousand lines of code to
like you know copy you know a field from
one place to another right
and third would be and this is the
biggest difference I suppose between
game engine programmer and just good
programmer because the other two things
were a good programmer part that is
being comfortable researching and
exploring new areas in sort of
technology right so like what you see me
doing with the lighting I need you to be
able to do experimentation and be
comfortable like going reading some
research papers on something like
integrating that knowledge in like right
being comfortable being given tasks you
don't already know how to do right
that's really what I would say defines a
good engine programmer for the most part
would be mostly those three things right
why aren't most studios willing to
compensate a perfectly in spite of the
seemingly short supply of graphics
programmers I guess what do you mean by
compensate appropriately I mean these
are positions where you get paid well
over $100,000 a year I'm not not sure
what you mean by compensate
appropriately but I mean graphics engine
programmers or leak like the positions
that I would be thinking of filling
would be positions where you you know
would that would be paid a lot more
money then you know this is not a
$50,000 a year position that we're
talking about Ray
have you heard about valves ACO Mesa
shader compiler for AMD GPUs apparently
it is replacing LVM it's a great thing
for Linux gaming I have no idea what
that means
LLVM what does that have to do with
shader compilation
an animal relative to other positions on
the team that may not require his
extensive knowledge III mean yeah can I
just say is that true that doesn't sound
right to me I mean at least you know
maybe my knowledge is old but the
difference between like a unityscript ER
and a person who knows how to do
graphics engine programming is like you
know over 2x salary in my experience
right I mean none of this makes I mean
if you're wondering why compensation
doesn't make sense across companies then
that's a sort of a separate issue and
probably the broader question it's
because games don't make enough money
right you can be the you could be the
very stupidest least good person on your
game on your on a game development team
and be like the smartest person best
programmer at like on a Google team
right the you know the the level of
expectation of being able to do stuff is
like not there's an arbitrage thing
there right so those salaries are
definitely not commensurate you can
definitely leave your game job and go
get a Google job and be paid vastly more
money for the same level of skill that's
just true and that's just because I mean
games have to actually compete on
something whereas you know if you're
monopoly and you're unregulated by the
government its unsurprisingly not hard
to extract a lot of money from an
economy right so that's just like
unfortunate sign of the times I don't
think that'll be true in 20 years right
but for now it is
yes so I'm gonna I'm probably gonna wrap
it through now but yeah sorry I don't
understand that ACO ACO thing so I don't
know I mean like yeah I guess what it
what does that have to do with Linux
gaming is that just because the drivers
on Linux are bad so if you have a better
shader compiler like the games get
better or something I just I don't quite
understand the concept that maybe you
you can use LLVM to compile shaders or
you know I mean I don't I don't really
know what you're talking about exactly
but like I just don't have seen what
this has to do with Linux gaming right
that's the part that's throwing me for a
loop is it just because like the drivers
on Linux can't compile shaders well so
they like they perform poorly I guess
maybe an animal as if example take
Bethesda they pay gameplay programmers
80 to 110 K but the graphics engine
programmer is 90 to 130 K obviously
those numbers are from pay scale faster
etc but most like you represent a decent
sample size so I would say two things
about that one is I don't know much
about Bethesda obviously but what I
would say is it also depends on what you
mean by gameplay programmer so if we're
talking about someone who's actually
programming real gameplay code not in
like a scripting language that actually
involves a bunch of like tech stuff
they're not that different from a
graphics programmer so I wouldn't expect
those two things to be really all that
different right so it really depends on
what you're talking about there the
other thing I would say is that salary
range for a good engine programmer seems
pretty low so it may just be that
Bethesda doesn't care much about engines
for all I know or maybe that's not
really what that means right so you have
to kind of be careful about looking at
those numbers and what do they actually
mean similarly if you look at that range
if you if gameplay programmers are
making 80k if they're scripters and
engine programmers are making 130 K if
they're good
that actually is a very large difference
right that's a 50% salary increase
between the it's more like a 60% one
right so again don't really know what
that even means it's hard to compare but
I would say like good engine programmers
can make a lot more than 130 K depending
on where you go and Bethesda may be a
bad place to go for that because maybe
they just don't care about getting more
people with those skills I don't know I
don't really have much insight into
their process right
all right I'm gonna wrap it up
[Music]
and also just to give some more data in
there like I said before I mean I've had
people who are trying to staff up
studios right now literally tell me that
you know engine programmers they have
tried to hire end up getting jobs at
Google which is their biggest problem
right now or Facebook and they get paid
absurd amounts of money apparently like
a hundred and thirty thousand dollars is
a laughable amount compared to the
mounts that I heard quoted and like I
said I don't know I don't study this
stuff but I guess I would say I would I
would think of it more as a problem in
that direction it does seem like there's
gonna be some leaching going on there
because apparently game programmers are
somewhat in demand because they know how
to actually write stuff instead of just
like writing in PHP or something or
Python I should say if it's Google all
right thank you everyone for joining me
for those sort of handmade hero its what
a pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow in the series
you can always pre-order the game on
handmade hero org and it comes with a
source code so you can follow along with
it I will be back here next week
next weekend to try putting in a more
real lighting solution we already kind
of have code that does that but we
haven't really gone the extra step and
made that code sort of run on top of our
new voxel system so now that we sort of
have some confidence that our voxel
system is interpolating properly and we
have some confidence that our ray
casting is working properly we can now
combine those two things together and
start to produce a system that will
actually give us more subtle more
interesting lighting and there's two
steps to that well I don't know which
order we'll do them in one is we got to
come up with a good blending solution
for how do we actually output the
lighting in a reasonable way but the
other thing that we're gonna have to do
is then re-enable the bounce and caching
of the results over frames both of those
things we have to do so we'll take a
crack at one of the next weekend and
we'll go from there that's it for this
week
hopes everyone has fun programming this
week and I'll see you on the Internet
take it easy everybody
you