all righty let's do this
let us do this ladies and gentlemen it
is my distinct pleasure my singular
honor to welcome you to this edition of
handmade hero this is the show and
ladies gentlemen this is the show not a
show but the show where we code a
complete game live on stream on Twitch
no engines no libraries no extraneous
animals like ferret for example it is
just us in the code and we are you know
I want to say it we were kind of
crushing it on the asset system we kind
of did a pretty good pretty darn good
job so far
and I don't see any reason for us to sit
on our collective arrest I should say on
our collective laurels when we should
forward forward and make things even
awesomer so today let's see if we can
wrap up what we were doing with the
asset file merging and then we would be
in some pretty sweet territory I think
setting ourselves up for a good next
week thanks to what we've done today
sort of like when the basketball player
puts like the you know sends the ball up
and another one comes in like dunks it
right that's like what we're doing only
instead of basketball players it's this
week and next week and the ball is the
game right do you see how that analogy
works I don't know who the opposing
players are in this analogy hmm you know
could be like the visual studio compiler
or something like this or the C++
Standards Committee they could be in
there like blocking us right that could
happen I don't know who the refs are
probably like you know the the Intel
chip because obviously everything has to
run like according to their rules or
something but I think what you know I'm
trying to get across here if nothing
else
is that if you make an analogy you
should probably stop trying to extend
that analogy somewhere after the point
where you say who the two players in the
ball are because after that it starts to
get really confusing and hard to figure
out and then the analogy actually works
against you because you actually get
confused so the people who are trying to
communicate with are only going to be
even more confused so these are the
types of important lessons you know when
we talk about learning programming
obviously one of those things is
learning how to make analogies to
basketball and so I hope everyone has
sort of gained a little bit from that I
know I have so if you are the type of
person who would like to follow along
with my basketball analogies at home
today is day 151 by the way I also don't
watch basketball or know anything about
it so that makes it extra hard so
another pro tip might be try to use
analogies in a sport that you actually
know so anyway today is day 151 if you
would like to follow along with your own
basketball analogies at home and you
have pre-ordered the game on handmade
hero org you want to unpack day 150
source code into a directory because
that is the source code I will be
starting with today all right let's see
what we have in store for today let us
see where we are at I see that I never
actually deleted this somebody asked a
question about when you pass pointers it
looks like we've still got that in there
so maybe our first thing that we'll do
today is delete the little code that we
put in there that was sort of designed
to show people who asked the question
something about why you pass pointers
versus when you would wait a min to pass
things by value hopefully everyone got
that yesterday no need for that code to
stick around all right so we were in the
middle yesterday of making something
that would open a set of asset files
merge their data together and then be
able to run with them and the reason we
were doing that is because I wanted to
take a look at what I might reasonably
believed to be the shipping code that
starts up the game in terms of pulling
in the asset file and in order to do
that I need kind of a map
what that would look like the reason we
were doing that is so that we could
define the platform layer API that we
want for sort of our final file API like
the thing that we're actually going to
support on all of the platforms that
handmade hero ships on so this would not
be Tesco this would actually be like the
API that we want to run the final game
so in order to do that I always say
write the test code first this is an
example of trying to write the test code
first so we're trying to put together
here basically a piece of code that
shows what we would really be doing for
the real final thing where we load the
actual asset files and merge them
together so that we can see what those
data a reading api's would look like
right so let's go ahead and get back to
that all right so what we were
suggesting is that we would have
something called a platform file handle
and the platform file handle would allow
us to basically hold open references to
the asset files in the game right so we
would start up we would look at what
asset files were in the directory we
would load them all well sorry we would
open handles to all of them right and
you can see that I wrote the code there
for that right let's uh this guy out
there we go so this was the code block
that I was working on a base so I said
it's alright we're gonna suppose that
the platform can return to us
sort of a group of files that all have
the same extension that we can iterate
over them that we can then open them and
hold a file handle to them so we can
talk about that file for the rest of the
game while it's running and then that we
can go ahead and read singular chunks
like little little individual chunks out
of that file I also said that I want the
file handle itself to remember whether
it has encountered an error and to be
able to say that there has been an error
on that file handle so that later I can
just do you know I can do a bunch of
operations and then later just check a
single check do a single check to say
were there any errors and if there were
shut down gracefully if there weren't
continue right and so
what we're gonna do you know eventually
will hopefully have some way in here of
notifying users in the game that
something's going wrong maybe like a
little dialog box something like that
it's a little tricky
how we might do that because we'll
probably have to like bake in a debug
font to the executable or something
because if the asset files not there
we can't very well notify someone
without a font right we need a font at
least so we may have to bake a little
debug font in just for the emergency
scenario where we can't even load our
fonts in at all but we'll cross that
bridge when we come to it
that's a little further down the line
all we know is that we need some way of
detecting it so I wanted to make sure
that we had a code path in there that
was where we would note that this error
occurred so that it could be reported
once we have a system so once we do that
we would allocate space to store all of
the assets that we were going to load in
and again we're only talking about the
sort of the metadata for those assets
because the acetate itself is too big
and we want to stream that in so we're
just talking about like you know making
room for if there's you know 30,000
different things in the game we make an
array of 30,000 that holds the metadata
so that we can quickly access that and
know where we need to start loading it
we could even go one step further and
stream that in but honestly it's only
gonna probably be a megabyte or two and
you know especially on PC it would be
actually more inefficient of us to
constantly be loading it so we probably
don't want to do that unless we're on
some much more memory constrained
platform than hammer here ever may ever
actually even run on so that's that's
kind of a separate issue so once we go
ahead and do that what we would like to
do is load all of those assets actually
in and so what we're looking at here is
that code we're gonna have to loop over
and I said this was a very inefficient
way to do it but I don't know that we'll
ever matter we'll cross that bridge when
we come to it but what I would do is
loop over all the files and see if those
files have assets of the particular type
in them right so when we look through
here we find that a you know an asset
that the sort of that main asset array
that tells us how many of each type
there are when we see a particular type
what we wanted
is read out of the file that portion of
the of that asset array so that and put
it in the right place right and then we
will increment the asset count by
however many there were right asset
account for type something like that we
would read like that many in here so
what we need to do first obviously is
compute that asset count for type and
the way that we do that again is taking
the one pass last asset index for
whatever the array says and subtracting
it from the the first asset index right
because that is how many there actually
would be that's how many we would want
to load in to you know we'd have to load
them into obviously the right position
so we'll take care of that in a second
but then we would advance by that many
assets and continue going right so
that's all we would really need to do
there but once we have loaded these guys
in I alluded to this yesterday another
thing that we have to be able to do is
we have to be able to rebase the tag
indices and so let's do that first
before we talk about you know any of the
other stuff here so let's talk about
that so what we have is we have a set of
tag arrays right we have a set of these
asset tags right oops and they're in the
file formats right so we have the HHA
tag right and in the hh8 tag we have ID
and the value now that is what we need
to identify our assets but the way the
assets reference those right if you look
down here is it says the first tag index
and one passed last I guess those are
absolute indices so the HHA asset says
well my first tag is tag five in the tag
table and then my last tag is you know
or one path the last tag is like seven
so I would go five and six or my two
tags right so if there's only one file
that works fine right because those
those will just be correct but if
there's two files then the first files
tag indices will be correct but the
second files would be wrong right if we
can catenate with them on to each other
right so the tag arrays get concatenated
on so tag zero of the second file is
actually one
past the last tag of the first file so
if there's a hundred tags in the first
file right then the hundred and first
tag is actually tagged zero of the
second file so all of the assets in the
second file are pointing essentially are
their indices are wrong and they need to
be rebased by the number of tags right
that came before them so that's what I
want to do first I want to go ahead and
take care of that that's a pretty
straightforward thing to do so we'll go
ahead and we will do it right okay so
what we need to do there once we've
looked at sort of this this stuff here
right I've said that in the asset file
I've already made a tag based thing but
we don't actually set it to anything so
what I want to do is when we read in a
new file right I want to set the files
tag base right to be whatever the
current tag count actually is okay so
the first one will start at zero and
then whatever however made tags are in
that file the next one right will will
actually start at one pass the last one
for for the previous file so they little
like set what that what that rebasing
guy is going to be so then then here
what I can do is I can loop through all
of the files right and I can load out
their tag arrays right
so what I can do is say ok for each file
and put a note here what we're doing no
load tags so when I come in here what I
want to do is say all right assuming
that this was a file that hasn't had any
errors on the file yet what I'm going to
do is is read in that tag array right so
I'm going to read in tag array size like
so and I'm going to read in that tag
array wherever that was right tags oops
that's not where it's gonna be gonna be
somewhere else right so where am I gonna
rotate read it in right I'm gonna read
it in at the asset tags right that I
just allocated a big thing for asset
tags I'm gonna add it I'm gonna load it
in at the tag basis offset so the first
one I'll read in you know I'll just
quickly draw this on the way forward for
you just in case it's it's a little
too confusing I know if you're not a
programmer who's been programming for a
long time so it's hard I think of these
things in my head and it's hard
sometimes if you haven't done it much to
think of them in your head that way but
basically we're really talking about
something real simple when you get down
to it it's just it's just a bunch of
fussing but basically we've got file 0 1
2 right here's their tag arrays these
are the tiger Ray's what we want is we
want all of these guys right to come
into one big array so I want to put this
tag array here I want to put this tag
array right in here and I want to put
this tag array in here right so when I
load them I want to load the first one
at tags 0 right but I want to road the
next one at like whatever file what
zeros tag count was I want to load it at
that tag count right I want to move down
and load the next one in there and then
the next one in there right so that's
all I'm doing here is I made that tag
base so that I know and that's just a
rolling number that kind of incremented
for each one just like I said and then
when we do this platform read data from
file we're gonna read it in at whatever
that tag base offset would be so they
get stacked on top of each other nicely
right so all I really need to do is
compute that tag array size and
obviously that's just going to be the
size of the HHA tag times however many
there actually were in this thing right
but that's really all we're talking
about so we're just gonna read that out
and now we've got the tag array there
and we're good to go right ok so that's
us loading in the tags and we don't
really have to touch the tag so the tags
don't reference anything so they don't
have any values that need to be moved
right they don't have to anything that
has to happen there so we load in the
tags and then I guess we could put here
note allocate all metadata space right
so we load in those tags and that's all
good and then what we need to do is we
need to do those assets rebased
right we need to rebase those assets so
what we need to do here right is we need
to loop through the assets that are
involved in this particular file and we
need to offset the tags by whatever this
files tag base is so they point
into the right part of that tag array
right so inside here we're gonna do is
loop over however many assets there were
in this in this sort of group here right
and we know that when we load it in it's
gonna be loaded in at asset count right
because that's how many assets have been
filled so far right so what we want to
do is say at well and you know what we
could even do it if we wanted the
absolute asset index here we could even
do it by just saying start an asset
count and go to asset count plus asset
count plus asset count for type right so
we could go through there and then we
can get the pointer to the asset really
trivially right all we do is say that
the asset is whatever the assets array
is plus the index that we're looking at
that particular asset we now know that
all we have to do is take those tag
offsets right which is right here and
here all we have to do is take those
guys and rebase them right now you know
like I said it's a little bit janky that
we you know we're kind of using these
things flat loaded HHA asset looks like
something that maybe we shouldn't have
flat loaded because it's got extra stuff
in here and we're having to rebase it so
you know six of one half dozen the other
the tag array looks like something we
definitely it was definitely good to
flat load cuz we can just load it in
chunk and it's done whereas the asset
still we got a lot of fussing and so who
knows so maybe that's not such a good
idea and maybe we should just do these
as temporary loads and you know who
knows it's not gonna matter either way
for this game at all it's only done it
startup and it's not gonna take a huge
amount of memory either way because it's
just the metadata but you know I'm just
trying to call things out like that so
you kind of know roughly sort of all the
things that might be stuff that you
would think about when you're when
you're looking at these sorts of things
because maybe you know you're on a
project that has a ton of individual
assets
millions of assets and then you start
caring or something about that how much
data are stored per asset and how much
work you do on load so anyway when we do
that that would rebase the tags for
these assets the assets that were that
we just loaded in and then we would
advance by the number of the asset count
number now what we also need to do is we
need to widen the desk type right but I
think we've already done that right yeah
we have right so if you look here our
desk type R is is already sort of
setting up the asset type bounds for
this particular asset and we set it here
when we're done so that's kind of
already done for us as well so I think
really the only thing left to do here is
to make sure that we actually read in
the data right we have to actually do
that computation so we want to do
platform read data from file we give it
the file handle that we were trying to
do there we know that we're going to
read this many assets in so it's just
gonna be however many assets there are
to read times the size right so that's
all we have to do there that's how big
of a thing we're reading in we know
we're reading in at a particular offset
right as well that offset is a little
bit complicated if we think about it we
have to start by taking the header and
get the assets array offset that's where
that array starts right in the file we
then have to move forwards from the
start of the asset array to the location
where the first asset in this asset type
array is right we have to move forward
by that much so we need to move forward
by that many assets right that jumps to
the correct place and then we know we
have to read however many we're going to
try and read times the size of the asset
so that's all good and then I finally
last but not least we need a place to
put them and we actually already just
sort of said where we would put them we
would put them at the end of the asset
array as it currently exists right
during all of this we might as well
assert that we never go over the asset
count that we said that we should have
and furthermore at the end of this we
should assert that we have the right
number but looks like we already did
that right so that's also fine so that
seems all good and
tag count think here is not really
relevant we didn't end up loading them
that way so that ends up not really
being that big of a deal either so there
we go
and now what we kind of have to do is
start to actually define these these
functions that we are saying that we
want the platform library to support for
us we need to actually go ahead and make
those a reality right we have to
actually do the work of having those
exists because we were writing these
Scotia risk so we were imagining the
best of all possible worlds for the
thing that we were doing here and of
course that's not actually true anymore
so let's see there's a couple different
ways we could do that so I'm trying to
think of how I want to best approach
that so I think I'm gonna first if zero
out this stuff right and I might I we
there's a couple of different ways we
could do I think I'm just gonna avoid
doing baby steps on this one I think I'm
just gonna go full pull on it because I
think it'll be code that that I can step
through and see if that turns out not to
be the case as we get a little further
in it I might do take switched axe and
load through the original file IO
routine and then mock up the API to work
into that but I think that that might
just end up being more work so unless we
hit some debugging snags I don't think
that's what I'm actually going to want
to do so I think we're gonna leave it
this way for now and I'm going to go
ahead and start defining these actual
things in here so those are going to be
in hand may platform right because these
are going to be actual platform API
things that we want to have exist for us
so in here I'm going to go ahead and
define a new struct oops and of course
since we're trying to remain backwards
compatible with C so that other people
who are using the you are not using C++
who
trying to link with our platform layers
or do other stuff like that can can do
it so let's go ahead and make sure that
we support that still so what I'm going
to do here is I'm gonna say that we've
got a platform file handle I guess and I
don't know you know I wonder if it looks
like yeah it looks like for some reason
we kind of have two different naming
schemes so there's like game underscore
and there's also platform underscore but
I guess anything that like reference to
the platform directly as a platform
underscore things so that's fine so we
have a platform file handle right we
don't really know what's gonna go in
there at the moment but we know we're
gonna have one I think also it may be
the case that it's really a four word
declaration right I think we probably
won't ever show what the platform handle
actually is you know so it's probably
something like that where it's actually
a pointer you know so we've got
something like that we also have and I
suppose we could even make it just be a
pointer here right the platform handle
could just be a pointer and then it
would literally be something like this
right something like that so let's see
let's go a little further here so yeah
inside our loading code when we do our
platform work callback stuff they're
inside our loading code we do have the
problem here where we don't actually we
don't really have we don't really have
things set up to to comment this out so
I guess you know while we're compiling
here I don't know if lobsters nor those
errors or if 0 the map maybe just if 0
them out because we're no longer being
able to point directly into the HHA
contents oh well you know what
interestingly enough I guess well no
ever might I take it back I was gonna
say something but but something isn't
true all right so here we go we've got
platform file group so that's another
thing that's got to go into our platform
file right
so we've got a type def struct platform
file group and that's also going to be a
struct that's that's here but I think
this one's actually going to have actual
data I feel like we're going to have
like file count in it like so it returns
how many there are and then also maybe a
data thing where you know that data
thing is how do we say we did file no I
guess so that day I think is opaque so
we don't actually expose what what that
is we just say that well the platform's
got some data we're not going to tell
you what it is you can only access it by
saying platform open file and saying
which of the files from here you want to
open right so that's what I'm gonna do
so let's go ahead and do that one if I
go ahead and copy this in now we have
another function here right I've got a
type def here so I want to do
essentially this the same stuff that we
were doing I want to do that right I
want to make a new platform specific
function and I don't know how many of
these were going to have we'll have a
platform get all files of type right and
that would be in here so let's see let's
go ahead
and and put that in here right platform
get all files type again and that would
be the sky so platform get all files
like again there we go
and what does that take it's this point
it looks like it's just taking an
extension right or a type right so
that's all that's gonna do and then we
also have we've got platform open file
we've got platform read data from file
and we have platform get all files of
type end we also have platform no file
errors and the thing about platform no
file errors that's the kind of thing we
would probably want to be inlined
but I don't know realistically if we
really want to force that I think maybe
we do and so what I might say I'm just
gonna throw this out there what I might
say is let's actually do things this way
where there's a preamble essentially for
all platforms where there's a be 32 or
you know something like that which is
like has errors right
so that way Platt no platform no file
errors when it when it takes a platform
file handle that can just be a nice
inline function basically so platform
file handle right handle that can just
be an inline function that actually just
returns you know the result
is get the handle has errors right so
something like that
of course again if we're trying to
maintain compatibility with C we can't
do an inline here so I guess I would say
you know maybe let's just do it as a
macro so that it'll work everywhere for
everyone right so it would be something
like this right where we say we return
whatever the not has errors is so that
way we don't actually have to have a
round trip through the platform layer
just to check to see whether particular
file handle has an error on it right
okay so these are the actual functions
that we need so we've got type again and
type end right and that is going to take
one of these platform file groups and it
takes an actual file group right yeah
because it's pointing data so it just
takes the whole file group not a pointer
to one platform built type in yeah so
we've got the end there we've got
platform Open File to do
and platform open file is just going to
take at the moment one of those file
groups so it's gonna take a file group
and the file index in that group right
and that is platform open file all right
and then we did begin and end so we
already did that one and so the only
other one we have left is this guy which
is platform read data from file and it
is ready to go platform the data from
file that's just platform file handle
handle you 64 offset you 64 size and
void star desk right click save that
goes from the source reads at this
offset for this much and puts it there
yeah so that is that I think that's
everything that we would need pretty
sure so when we get all these in there
these these guys have to all be passed
down now right this is extending our
platform API so in addition to these
guys right we basically have have this
stuff now and these debug platform free
file memory read into our file these two
we can probably actually get rid of now
because we're actually how we will
actually be having a real file API right
so this is get all files of type begin
and then we've got this guy platform get
all files of type end
platform open file and platform read a
different file so um yeah I think that's
basically all we need from those guys
and I think I'm not sure exactly how I
want to deal with these these folks I
think they could just be Global's that's
sort of how we started to treat like
platform at entry and platform like I
don't know if you guys remember when we
did this we kind of just said all right
these guys are going to just exist out
in the wild and that seems like a pretty
good idea I wonder so I mean just you
know thinking about it if this is just
gonna be our dispatch table right this
is basically our dispatch table for hot
loading to reconnect what we could do is
we could just do something like this
so this is like our platform dispatch or
a platform API like that we could just
say okay you know this stuff since it's
all known right at least these we could
just put them here right and then we
could just say okay when you call this
thing you get an API right you get the
platform API and then that platform API
as a whole would just be the global
variable that would get called you know
that would get copied every time right
and that seems pretty safe to me that
seems like a pretty good idea if that
makes sense
oops at the platform API there that just
seems pretty logical to me that way we
kind of get out of the business of
having to pass around that those
callbacks right
so if we did that and we you know want
to do this we could do play oh and you
know what else we could do since it's
called platform API we could do it this
way
get rid of platform at the front of
everything right and then that platform
is just kind of like the variable
creates a clear textual thing as you use
it right
so it's platform you know arrow add
entry right sorry dot so let's see
platform dot complete all work don't
care about those right now platform dot
add entry these are this is like
platform dot open file platform dot get
all files of type platform dot read a
different file right just grabbing it
out of that oh and then we also have
platform file error right and I don't
know how exactly we want that one to
work we'll see but I'm assuming it will
also have to be a call into the platform
layer all right so we're initializing
here platform get all files of type
begin
I cannot curt void Oh does it not denied
I did not declare it as returning a
value tonight that's not gonna be good
of course it needs to return a value
everyone knows that so yeah so if we
want to do that begin here should do it
that way and the same would be true a
platform open file right that should
take a platform file handle right and
return that
all right so what's going on here file
header so this is this is file header
magickal you file header right Jake
contents game assets
HHA header it's not even over the member
you're right
because not yeah and the same would be
true here file header file header there
we go so let's see platform dot read
data from file again just kind of moving
it up to speed there so asset type ID is
actually desk type ID in this case right
I changed the name of its we're just if
the asset type were writing again these
are just platform dot and now we get to
the sort of other stuff that I sort of
legacy back right here is a platform so
here it's nice we just go platform
equals memory platform API right and
then we just delete these guys they go
away permanently right and then these
just have to be sort of moved up to
something like this right and these guys
here see okay so now we're almost there
oops this one so now we're almost there
but we have to actually sort of start
putting some of these guys in right so
in handmade asset I'm sorry handmade
platform th we actually need all of
these guys right so we need to to set up
this whole API here right this whole
thing needs to actually occur so we need
to do platform get all file to type
right so we need to make it win through
to version of that and we need to make a
wind turn 8:32 version of this yeah you
know
and so on and so forth and open file and
so on right so now we've got all that
wired up and we just need if we you know
can now go implement these actual
functions we'd be all set I thought we
had one though that I didn't implement
shouldn't have given me an error about
that
there it is file error that's the one so
I need to also have that one that's
that's called file error right and so
platform file error and so platform file
error is just a thing that allows us to
note that there's been an error right so
file error file error that for the file
error and that's just all that's gonna
take is just what the error handle was
and then some kind of stupid message for
now right and that's it so off we go and
here API on the end and do one for file
edit and so I think that's just about it
for wiring so now I just have to
actually go and write these functions
and then we would be in good shape so we
would need to do a window sorry a
version of each of these guys so we've
got this one all right that we want to
define
and this one time deal and who's next
from open file we go and two more and
last one and if you're wondering if a
real like if programming languages were
actually cool if they would do this for
you if the truth is just they would but
of course as we know see both less is
too busy adding lots of extraneous
features and never fixing basic things
like this that they should so it's a lot
of typing that doesn't have to happen
but that's just how it goes sometimes
so in here if we now recompile will have
some return value problems right because
we are an extra turning I think of these
but otherwise we were all wired up now
and we call into the platform layer in a
way that's rebind able and hot loaded
full and all that sort of stuff right so
that's all good but we have to actually
do this this sort of wiring for now what
I can do is I can just return zeros
right I could just sort of fake it for
now and so you know file platform file
group here group equals whatever we can
just return complete garbage to get
ourselves compiling so the thing that we
have left to do is when we actually go
to load an actual thing in we now should
we now actually have to load it right
because we did before what we did is
just kind of pointed to the thing that
we wanted but that's not what we
actually want to do because we don't
want to load all the assets at startup
we want to only load assets as we need
them that was the whole point of the
streaming system so what we need to do
here is bitmap memory we actually want
bitmap memory to sort of be some space
that's reserved for us so when we're in
here in load bitmap right what we want
to do in load
Mapp is push on space for the eventual
bitmap right so in here when we do work
when we do work err a bitmap we also
want to do work bitmap equals push size
right and we want to reserve a memory
slot for it right and actually if you
look at what happens here all of this
stuff actually can just be done pretty
much you know like the work order for
this thing actually doesn't need to do
this stuff I just want to point this out
because again like if you're new to this
sort of stuff a lot of these things I'm
kind of programming is a very sort of
fluid process obviously and it's easy
for people to forget how things are
going so if you think about why we wrote
the function this way originally back
when we wrote it why were these things
getting filled out in thus in the
threaded asset loading system and the
reason was because we didn't know what
the width of a bitmap was when we went
to load it until we actually pulled in
the bitmap file so if we wanted to do
multi-threaded loading we had to defer
that computation of all the extraneous
bitmap data until we actually loaded the
bitmap file but now that we have an
asset processor right that information
has been pulled out into a metadata
structure that we load at startup that's
very small that we can just load
instantly right so we know we have the
metadata it's only the the payload
that's off in you know in the asset file
that has to get pulled in and so since
we have that data we can actually move
all of this stuff out and our work order
that has to go into the threading system
could actually be the same for both
sounds and and bitmaps probably to a
large extent because we don't actually
have to do anything specific to them
really the only thing I can think of
that we might know there's nothing we
would need to do we just so really all
we have to do now is load a little a
chunk of memory and that's all it has to
do so we can collapse these things
together I guess
what I'm saying so I think I would like
to do that so what I want to do now
again this is kind of a handy little
baby steps sort of a situation here oops
let me get rid of that so let's let's go
ahead and continue our baby stepping
because I realized there's a good one
good thing we could do baby step wise
right move this back up to the top for a
second and so what we could do baby
steps wise is I can if there are this
out again right like so and return us to
the previous asset loading where we just
load the whole asset fowl you know in
its entirety right and all I have to do
that is report this to that thing that
we did there right so if we test to
verify that that's working right
right so that's all good all the assets
are loading properly so all I really
need to do now is go do those changes
that I was about to do of prepping the
bitmaps and using a slightly different
thing for loading when we have something
everything working like it is that gives
us the flexibility to do this and know
that we haven't introduced any bugs in
this change before we go do the other
part of using the new file loading
routines which you know could be their
own set of bugs so again just
partitioning the work into clear passes
so that again it minimizes the amount of
time they have to spend debugging
problems with the code and that's just
always a good time saver right so what
I'm gonna do here is I'm going to try to
try to see if I can say that there's
another thing here instead of load
bitmap work
there's just load asset work right and
all load asset work is it's an offset
right a size to load if you will and in
a destination that's it so the only
thing this thing is going to do is it's
just going to execute that that load up
and that's that's it nothing else right
so if I want to do that all I would have
to do right is take what this routine is
doing here
same exact stuff and now it's gonna do
load asset work like so and it's not
going to think about the asset at all
it's not going to get the loaded bitmaps
and that stuff right doesn't have to do
any of this right all it has to do is
know how to do the completion stuff and
then how to end the tasks right so hmm
let's see
what will I need for just that so I need
the tasks right
and it looks like here I don't quite see
exactly how this thing is working so
work bitmap it's assigning the pointer
but why didn't we just always assign the
pointer first I'm a little confused
about that because I feel like all I
should really have to do is that right
so really all I need here is the asset
slot right I just need the slot that
it's getting set right in fact I could
even make it a little bit more
ridiculous than that and say it's not
even the asset slot it's actually just
you know the assets stake
even but I don't know if we need to go
that far so I'll say that we use the
slot and we could always change that if
we need to but so you know this is what
I'm actually talking about so basically
this routine would look something like
do the platform dot read data from file
right at the work specified offset the
work specified size into the work
specified destination and I guess oh
yeah one other thing we need is a
platform file handle right mmm I just
thought of one way we're not gonna waste
space in a particular place as well
that's pretty good
alright because when we when we need to
get this file handled that will be
interesting all right so taking a look
at this we do this this thing here this
this exactly what we expect and I feel
like you know we might we might have to
do a check here right we might have to
do something like this platform no file
errors right we would need to check to
make sure that whatever the file handle
is didn't peter out on us right didn't
didn't die because we don't want to say
that we loaded it if we didn't write if
we couldn't and there's a couple of ways
we could do that look we could choose to
check that like I could do something
here where I say oh and what is final
state
Oh was loaded or locked so we need that
one as well there we go all right so we
could also choose to fill in some
garbage here like some like make it all
bright pink or something if or you know
all white or something are all zeros if
it doesn't succeed so if the file error
if this turns out to be wrong we could
still set it to its final state but put
garbage in there I don't know if we'd
rather do that or rather try to keep
trying to load it so I don't know well
we can do you know play with that a
little bit later on right as we go and
so there's like a to do to do should we
actually fill in bogus data here and set
to final state anyway right but that's
only in an era scenario so you know as
long as we don't crash it's it's not
clear that we want to do anything in
particular so that's fine
all right so right if I compile that see
if we've got everything here so that's
work slot
state load bitmap work that's because I
named it wrong let's just reload assets
there we go all right so that's not
getting called so what I want to do now
is switch the bitmap loading function to
use load asset work instead of using
load bitmap work and have it do all of
the work right when we called load
bitmap do all of this setup work
directly right so what I want to do is I
want to basically grab this stuff right
and I want to go ahead and and make all
this happen right so up front you know I
want to do all of this right and then
we're going to totally ifs def this guy
out entirely
there we go okay so what's all the stuff
that we need to set up now right so we
come in here and we set you know all the
stuff that was going to be used for the
for the work order right and all that
stuff is we're gonna have to still do
but let's let's take care of this stuff
first so we have our work bitmap here
right and we're initializing all of its
stuff if we grab out the info for the
asset like we would be doing and that's
just be this be doing this right if we
set all this stuff up then we don't have
to do any of it obviously anymore in the
in the in in this part of the code so
all we need to do here is just reserve
space for the bitmap to be loaded so we
can just do a push here right in the
giving assets let me read you know in
the arena we can just do a push sorry
sighs right of how big the how big it's
actually going to be and obviously
that's just gonna be the size that would
actually get read so if you remember up
here we said in the work slot it would
just be this size right here right so
I'm gonna go ahead and do that amount
we're gonna make that room right and so
that's can well I guess you know what
there's kind of a chicken and egg thing
there so I'll just say you know memory
size or something right and we'll do
that up here so I'll just say we have
memory size and the memory size is going
to be the info well it's the pitch right
times the height that's the total memory
size so that's how many how much space
we actually need for the bitmap we go
ahead and reserve that much space for
the bitmap and then we can fill out our
work order right and put that on there
and that will just be in the task arena
so it's just temporary memory right so
we do load asset work and we want to
grab that out so let's take a look oops
and I gotta actually
I said work in the asset work struct I
have to fill out all of this stuff all
right so let's see where was work tasks
being actually filled out you know where
was that actually getting set oh there
it is right there
so we've got to fill out work tasks we
want to fill out work slot right which
is just gonna be this essentially write
a set slots we want to fill out the work
slot really know why these were not
phrased as pluses all right so grab all
that stuff out
we then need the platform file handle
this is the part that I've said Oh we'll
be able to save some space we'll talk
about that in a second we need the
offset in the file so where it actually
was and that is this right
it's that date data offset five-minute
warning cushaw so right I need the
offset there it is
I need the size and we've already
computed that memory size we don't need
the assets we don't need the ID the work
bitmap we do actually need obviously
that's just going to be bitmap yeah so
is all that stuff set then bitmap and
then we got final States so all we need
is destination and the destination is
the bitmap memory right so I think
that's the complete work order right
that's everything that's filled out and
the slot right the work slot I I just
don't see why we can't preset it to be
the bitmap
right I don't really see why we can't do
that because when you do when you when
you get the asset okay as I guess we're
actually kind of using that as the thing
so I feel like that's just sloppy and we
don't really want that what we want to
do is make sure that the asset is
actually loaded right I feel like that's
the cleaner way to do it and I don't
know why we weren't doing that exactly
like it just doesn't does it make sense
to you because it doesn't super make
sense to me why we wouldn't just do
something like asset equals zero and
then do the F here now maybe it's just
cuz we're trying to avoid him if right
but I don't know and so we could just do
that up here right we could set the
pointer but it just feels like why do
extra work in the threaded part why why
put you know sort of set up work up
there when we don't really you know wet
something that could have just been done
clean in line then we know that it
doesn't have to be thread safe and
doesn't have to be all these other
things right like why pile any more
stuff there than we need to because the
less stuff we can have being multi
thread dependent right the better in
that sense unless we really think we
need it for the speed or something so if
we go ahead and do the get bitmap we
could change that to just look to see
whether the state of the thing is in a
state where it could be used and that
seems fairly reasonable I don't know
like I said I'm a little wofully about
it but if you take a look here we could
basically just say you know the result
equals zero or you know what we could
even just do a set slot slot equals
asset slots plus ID value and then we
could just do slot state greater than or
equal to asset loaded if so return the
bitmap otherwise don't write and that
would be a pretty trivial way to make
sure that we were always returning the
right thing all right and so if I do
that then I don't have to worry about
this anymore so I can I can just you
know I can I can not have to do anything
particularly odd there right so that
seems all good and so for the moment
like I said this particular part is is
whoops cannot convert loaded sound
yes that's totally true okay all right
so assets assets that's actually just
assets let's see here loaded bitmap work
that's load asset work alright
assets is just assets let's see anything
else
assets slots is it just slots it is and
bitmap is equal to bitmap yeah it's not
a member of load asset work oh well
that's true it's not it is not and
that's just equal to work slot equals
uh I think I think we're just about done
with that right I think we've basically
finished everything that we need to do
so the only caveat there now that
everything's being taken care of there
is since we are still not quite doing
the file stuff right when we come up in
here so we got to basically do you know
something like this where we would
actually set that data you know we would
actually have to do sort of the data
load here but you know I'm thinking that
what I would like to do is in here
directly when we would have gone ahead
and done that done that task what I want
to do is I'm going to just go to nuke
the task for now you know so make it so
it doesn't actually do anything right
other than do the complete right they
get so it doesn't actually do anything
and I'll just set the I'll actually just
set the correct data value in here right
and that way I'll at least be able to
see if it's it's pseudo working or not
right but it's basically just sort of
cheating it out just saying oh wait
actually we'll just you know point to
the right data
oh yeah well we can't really call that
either yet until we have a valid file
handle so I guess that's another thing
that we have to if zero out all right so
number back to loading so that's good
and I think we have everything in
position now to just as soon as we
implement the win32 side of things that
we need we should be good to go right
and we couldn't do the exact same thing
to audio so we can change the audio over
to do exact you know pull this into the
audio side as well so that's what we'll
do next week but I want to go ahead and
go to QA so let's let's do exactly that
let's go to Q&amp;A if you have any
questions about what we did you ask them
now put a Q : in front of them so I can
see with this system is it possible to
add an updated version of an asset in a
new HHA file without modifying the
original how would the IDs work in this
case yes so what's interesting about
that is yes you actually could you could
in certain circumstances and not in
others we would have to do a little more
work in certain circumstances than
others and the reason I say that is for
tag for tag matched queries it would
just work because what we could do is
just you know if we wanted to say that
certain HHA files had preference over
previous HHA files right then we then
whatever was the last asset that was
concatenated on would be the one that
would be picked or whichever the first
one is whichever way we do it basically
you know if you take a look at in here
we've got those asset queries that that
you can use to that we were using to get
the assets back from like a tag right
from a from a tag vector so when we were
doing that when we do
guess the best match to get best match
bitmap right that calls into here and it
mm-hmm
where is that this one right here it
calls into here and what this is gonna
do is it's gonna pick the first it's
gonna prefer the first thing if a bunch
of different assets in the in that asset
type had the same match amount it's
gonna prefer the one that came first
right because it's a greater than if
it's greater than or equal it would
further one came last so basically if we
just sorted when we load if we sort our
HHA files by newest to oldest then you
would automatically replace any asset
you know with a with with the new one
but for ones where you're in an asset
type right you're just picking a random
one that that wouldn't work right that
would not do it now I don't really know
if I care about that like I'm not
thinking of hhas as our patch system
right which is when you would presumably
do that but I don't know maybe if you
wanted it as a mod as a way to mob
things yeah I'm not sure so if we wanted
to do something where we actually
replaced assets we would have to do
something we would have to have some way
in the HHA file we have to like add
essentially some kind of annotation that
told it to get rid of some asset from a
previous file right that said like don't
use this other asset anymore and to be
honest you know that's not that hard to
add really I feel like that's really not
that bad so if we really wanted to do
that we could write and the way that we
would do that in a in a pretty trivial
way right he is inside here we'd
basically have a thing that was
something like this so we'd say all
right I'm going to have a way of
specifying a table that says I want you
to get rid of some of the assets from
some other file right so it would be
like you know wid something like this
and you would have this in the file
itself and then here you would have
asset index right and then when we
loaded each individual file in we would
take the asset removal table and we
would for any file that matches that
asset removal table as grid we would we
would just not as we were spinning over
the assets we would not grab that
particular asset index right so if we
wanted to do that we could so if we
wanted to allow you to replace certain
assets or even just remove them like you
don't actually have to replace it with
something you could literally just have
a file that that nerfs out a previous
files one of its assets right that would
probably be this proposed trade forward
what will get rid of the initial flicker
of the character at startup so basically
right now we don't try to preload
anything that makes sense so what
happens is the first frame on which an
asset is used is the first time that the
asset system has a as is told that it
needs to load it and so you're never
going to it's not going to be able to
load it instantaneously it's putting it
into a thread to be loaded later so
anytime you encounter a new thing it
will blink right
so the thing that will get rid of that
is just we will introduce some limited
pre-caching stuff its won't be super
complicated but basically all we'll do
is stuff that says ahead of time hey you
know warm up these sprites because like
this monster we know it's you know we
caught it sort of know what's on you
know in our in our region we know more
than what's just on the screen we know
like a fairly big apron around the
screen we'll just say hey precache you
know start loading all those guys
because you're going to need them and
that way they'll always be there in time
we won't have to work that makes sense
as a programmer in putting a game with
fairly simple graphics any suggestions
on finding somebody to commission art
assets from or similar if you don't
happen to know a good digital artist not
really that's sort of a not really a
handmade hero kind of topic if that
makes sense that's that's not a
programming thing anybody else all done
lazy Friday which I am totally fine with
it's looking quiet yeah all right well
that's all good we can wind down for
today I think we've got everything in
place now although I do want to I didn't
quite get time today to move the audio I
like to I'd like to move the audio
system so you know in handmade asset dot
H that's our dot CP what I'd like to do
is I'd like to take a load sound and I'd
like to move load sound to use just that
load asset so instead of having another
work queue callback for sound I'd get
rid of that so they both could go to the
same one both bitmaps and audio would go
for the same one which is this one sorry
which is this one right so I'd like to
move the audio over there get that
working as well so make sure everybody's
happy and then we implement the win32
platform later calls that we expect and
we're good to go
that would be it and then we're moving
on to like the very hardest part of the
asset system because a lot of this stuff
has been pretty easy as you've seen
where we'll move on to the the hard part
which is basically how we want to deal
with if we've got a bigger asset
footprint then we'll fit in memory
eventually right so you know if the
users machine has two gigs of physical
memory and we're using you know half a
gig for game day there or something and
we want to use you know so we want 1.5
gigs to be spent on resources you know
the question is how do we deal with that
you know how do we handle when we don't
have when we have four gigs of art
assets you know we're gonna be loading
them in and eventually manage to a point
where we have to start flushing stuff
out to make room for other things and so
like I said it's kind of like we have to
implement our own virtual memory system
because we want to try and have this
like constant win
if that makes sense so so that will be
pretty challenging but that's really all
that's left in the asset system that's
that's kind of tricky and and so we kind
of saved the worst for last if you will
and so I don't know where that puts us -
on our on our to-do list did we already
do this I don't think we did that yeah
yeah but that's on there so yeah I feel
like I feel like we're kind of gonna eat
all this up I feel like we've I feel
like we've actually done all of those
all you have to do is pretty much right
I mean we'll spend a little more time on
them later on when we do the game stuff
but we are able to play both both types
of sounds now ambient sounds music and
everything we can do and our asset
streaming we've all we really have to do
is this memory management one and so
we'll be able to basically do a huge
chunk checked off here yeah it's getting
good it's gonna be exciting all right
okay let's wind it down close everybody
and I don't know what that's supposed to
be that was me drawing where we're
loading the tags so yeah let's close all
that down and say thank you everyone for
joining me for another episode of hand
made here it has been a pleasure coding
with you as always I am gonna be very
happy to see the asset system all nice
and bundled up so I think next week will
be a fun week it will get us probably up
to the point where we're sort of doing
the memory management but we're not
gonna finish the memory management next
week because there's gonna be some
trickiness there so I think we're
looking at probably two weeks before we
can check that off our list for good
and then yeah audio kind of looked
almost done - will maybe take a quick
peek back at that and see if there's
anything else you want to do engine wise
on the audio before checking that off -
and then we're just down to renderer and
debug code and the renderer we did a lot
of the hard work so we're really man
this is looking good it's looking good
people 200 days may turn out to not have
been such a crazy estimate which is only
like
200 hours I don't know let's say 210 220
hours to account for some of the Mareth
like yes we've done one marathon stream
and we did one two hour stream but man
that is so few hours and we're gonna
have a pretty awesome 2d engine to play
with for such a few number of hours it's
like you know five work weeks starting
from nothing so I don't know it's gonna
be pretty sweet and I'm pretty excited
about it I hope you're excited about too
and yeah so I will go ahead and wind
things down thank you very much for
joining me I will see you hopefully here
back on Monday probably 5 p.m. sir
daylight time again but be sure to check
the tweet bot you can always go to
hammer here oregon check the old tweet
bot to find out when the stream will be
if you want to know also as always if
you want to follow along at home if you
preorder the game on handmade here at
org you can get access to the source
code every night where you can download
it and play around with it at home and
experiment all that good stuff we also
have a forum site where we have
community annotated episode guide to
pass videos if you want to catch up on
older videos we have a forum for you to
ask questions we have community ports to
Mac and Linux that they've got so a lot
of good stuff there we also a patreon
page that you can go to if you want
support the video series so check all
that stuff out on handmade org when you
get a chance there's some good stuff up
there all right thank you everyone and
I'll see you back here on Monday until
then have fun programming and I will see
you guys on the Internet's