buddy welcome to handmade hero the game
where we code a complete show on stream
sure right side and say that backwards
today you could really think of them as
interchangeable I so today is a special
to stream day there's a reason for that
it was not an accident some people
thought the bot malfunction it didn't it
is intentional so today I want to do
something because we have had a I don't
want to necessarily call it a request
but an opportunity it was available to
help someone out who was a friend of
mine and who was actually a programmer I
highly respect and admire but somebody
who doesn't do any 3d programming that's
just not what they do
right and I will keep their identity
private I don't know if they want to
talk about it yet or what's going on but
so we're just gonna say it's someone who
I respect and they have asked me
recently about do you know anyone who's
available to do the 3d back-end for this
like sort of pseudo 2d 3d game it's like
mostly sprite graphics but there's some
stuff I want to do and I was like well
what are you trying to make it look like
and they sent me a screenshot that looks
a lot like our renderer it's like blocks
with with bitmaps on the side of them
and then sprites in it now it's like
well I don't know any good 3d
programmers who are available right now
because as usual all good 3d programmers
are almost always at a job somewhere
they're in very high demand and they're
very hard to find but I said if you want
you can try using the handmade hero
render at least get you going and maybe
if you know maybe that'll be enough it
probably isn't not to ship a whole game
but at least then if you start with that
maybe there will be people who because a
lot of people watch the show maybe it'll
be easier for you to find someone who
could do some contract work on it and
put in features that you might want
because hey one of the nice things about
the handmade hero render is everyone
watching this already knows how it works
you not to learn anything you have to go
into someone else's code not knowing
that's
going on everyone watch the shortino's
how it works so they can just edit it to
their heart's content and off you go
so I said you know I would be totally
willing I know that I said that you know
the games source code is proprietary up
to the point where we actually say it's
in the public domain which we will do
but I was just like we'll just give you
an early license for it if you want to
use it like we'll just sign whatever the
document is it says look it's you know
you can use it early you don't have to
wait for that and so I really what I
want to do today was just go hey let's
spend four hours clean up the renderer
put it in a little isolated package so
that it's easy for our friend to take a
look at and compile into their game
engine there you have one that's just a
2-d game engine and play around with to
see if it's something that can they can
make use of in the short term so that's
what I want to do today and maybe
tomorrow we've got you know the weekend
to do it so I want to get three streams
in six hours isn't a lot of time to do a
good clean like API pass on things
necessarily but we should be able to get
like a reasonable amount done and so I
wanted to do that because I think if I
do that pass on it it'll be a lot easier
to integrate in because you know we have
never had that as a concern of ours we
we don't consider the renderer or never
have considered the renderer or
something that someone else was going to
use we just considered it something that
would just be used by handmade hero I
also felt like this would be a good
opportunity to show what one might do if
one wanted to take a portion of a game
and reuse it in another game because
that is good technique to learn it's
also how you go from a game to an engine
right is learning or a multi-use engine
I should say every game has an engine on
the inside right but a multi-use engine
is learning those skills of how do we
take the parts of this game that can be
reused and turned them into portions
that can be reused without having to
have the whole game right without
without them being
wedded to a particular game so that's
all we're doing today and that's why
there's the double stream so I'm just
gonna go ahead and get started there's
nothing magical about doing this you've
seen me do things sort of like it in the
past so we're just gonna start down that
road and there's a couple pretty easy
things we can do to sort of set
ourselves up for success there what I'm
gonna start with is I'm just gonna say
look let's make a sample program that is
in our imagination what we would like
this thing to look like when you're
using it for the first time by someone
on the outside right now I have talked
about this before and I think we came up
with a name for it on streem it's called
snuffleupagus or oriented programming
snuffleupagus oriented programming is
just when you you know if you've ever
watched Sesame Street there's the
fictional snuffleupagus character that
like no one can see but Big Bird I don't
know if they've changed that now I don't
know nothing is as good as it used to be
so I don't know if people other people
can see snuffleupagus now but the old
days were just like an imaginary friend
of Big Bird's that maybe it existed
maybe it didn't
the idea behind snuffleupagus part
oriented programming is just to say look
let's pretend so I got a friend who
wants to use this renderer or might be
able to use this renderer let's pretend
through them and let's pretend we just
got the best possible thing right what's
the best possible thing what does that
look like let's pretend we just got that
how would we call it what would the
magical API look like that would make us
really happy in that circumstance right
and so I don't know the answer to that
question yet because it's pretty broad
so what I want to do is start by
actually putting myself in that
situation writing a little sample code
and going from there right okay so the
first thing we have to consider let me
go to the build up at here the first
thing that we have to consider is the
fact that there's a bunch of win32
startup code that has to have
to get your OpenGL code initialized I
believe that the target platform for
this on the other side the person's
could be using it is actually on a Mac
so that code we can't really help with
they're gonna have to use like did
they're gonna have to know how to start
up in OpenGL context fortunately I'm a
hammy hero github there already is the
code for starting up an OpenGL context
in that way so for our purposes we can
be a little bit more simplistic about
that right but what I want to do is
start off if you look here you know we
kind of have we have like for example
our HHI edit build so I'm going to start
another built here and that build is
right here I'm gonna actually do a build
of our win32 code I'm gonna make our own
sort of win32 combined sample app thing
that is separate from handmade here as a
test so this is like the renderer test
bed or something right and so what I
want to do there is I'm just gonna call
this like win32 renderer test dot CPP
and then what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
go ahead and when I compile this here
I'm gonna get rid of the new default Lib
stuff the reason that I'm going to get
rid of the no default Lib stuff is
because if I don't get rid of the new
default Lib stuff then I'm just assuming
that the person who's using this is
going to be using the C runtime library
so I want to test it in that sense as
well right so I want kind of all that
stuff to be the way that it is right so
I'm gonna include using the C runtime
library there that's what that is I'm
gonna call I'm gonna compile this render
a test in I don't need it to output a
map file and I don't need it to really
output anything else besides just the
renderer test information so then what
I'm going to do is I'm going to load up
and just kind of clone out our win32
startup stuff and this is just gonna be
strictly for the testbed and again this
is not actually something that he's
actually going to get used on the other
side because
it's the win32 version of it right see
that's fine but it is something that I
want to just yeah I basically just want
to sort of pull this stuff together into
a little test bed that I can at least
verify myself is okay so we don't need
any of the D input or any of that stuff
right we just need the opengl things so
here's a bunch of this code this is
interesting because you know this could
be an opportunity to sort of simplify
this stuff out as well in fact I'm
wondering should we kind of even maybe
do that first because if you look at how
this stuff is is set up if you look at
how this stuff is set up it's possible
that we could share this stuff so I may
actually skip this part for now simplify
that first on the handmade hero side and
then pull it over so all I'm going to do
here is I'm just gonna do the very
basics of the startup that we have
really really straightforward stuff so
I'm just gonna do the very basics get a
window up and then I'm going to go from
there with our render tests on on this
side right all right so here's our win
main you know here's our here's our C
runtime library startup stuff right this
one is without the C runtime library so
we kind of want to turn this into a win
main here this wants to not be win main
series startup anymore if this wants to
be actually just a regular win main that
people can use and we can get rid of
almost all the stuff that we have here
right we don't need any of this stuff
anymore
because it's just not gonna be relevant
so most of the complex code that we're
actually doing to do advanced stuff all
of that stuff is is now not really
relevant right so I can get rid of all
this stuff this stuff is all fine we can
go ahead and and just put this stuff in
here we don't care what the back buffer
sizes or any of that stuff so we can
just set up our main here our main stuff
here so and made hero Ren
window clap render a test window class
so what we want to do now just keep the
same code exactly the way it is we're
gonna register that class we're then
gonna open the window in terms of
opening the window we really don't care
what size it is we also don't care if
it's fullscreen or not so we can just
open any old window again this is not
supposed to be anything like the the
sort of stuff we're doing in hand-made
here where we're actually trying to open
a full screen or mean that stuff this is
just the basic basic stuff we would open
we would in it open jail get rid of all
the multi-threaded stuff get rid of the
sound we don't care about the refresh
rate or any of these things we're just
just testing the render so all this code
just goes straight out the window it's
not relevant at all so okay this stuff
for push buffers on stuff this again is
stuff we're gonna probably be cleaning
up so I'm getting rid of all of that
we'll clean it up and hand made here a
first don't need any of this stuff any
of the game memory platform behind none
of that's going to be in here right it's
just the renderer then we come through
here texture op cues those sorts of
things again not really relevant to us
in this case sample memory not important
so cleaning it all out rid of all these
things we don't care about any of this
either this is base likes mouse position
stuff we may import that in if we want
to play with it again don't really care
about it right now just want to open the
window so really all this stuff is just
not necessary we don't care about
directional pads or any of those sorts
of things at all all right so this stuff
is game update render don't care about
that so this is like our renderer test
frame or whatever or update renderer
test would go here we don't care about
audio updating we don't care about any
of this stuff not necessary again
because we're not doing any of it right
so then we get down to checking for
reload again we're not doing hot code
reloading or any of that stuff it's just
a test bed
so that all goes away as well
let's see here so then we got our frame
wait we don't need to wait we can always
just go at the fastest possible frame
right so that's fine - where do we wait
where's our swap buffers though I don't
think this is it's not in here so here's
the frame display right here so this is
where we call the frame display right
here so we want to actually still do
that right we don't care about any of
this we do kind of want the wall clock
stuff probably just to measure things
but I can do that kind of more manually
here so I think maybe what we'll do is
we'll leave this where we do it end
counter get wall clock and then we sort
of do a last counter so I feel like
maybe my large integer last counter that
can kind of go in here wery performance
counter so we can just sort of have that
initialize itself properly and that
should be fine expected frames for
update is not relevant measured seconds
per frame let's see let's get all this
stuff waste we don't care about this so
performance counter
all right uh so where's our winter to
get seconds elapsed there we go
I'll just put that right in here so I
think that's really all we need to know
here's our global perf frequency bit
here that's a new 64 for the quad part
there and the get wall clock like I said
it's just this function so I just
expanded that out in line and that's
what I really want so we can get this
just gets us our frames our seconds per
frame they're round reel 32 to int 32 is
is just there to yeah to look at our
target frames and I respect your frames
again we don't care about any of that
stuff so our measured seconds per frame
is all we really care about that gives
us basically a millisecond count it's in
seconds but you know it's gonna be point
o something it's gonna give us our count
for each frame which we'll probably want
to do just to see to make sure we're
running in a reasonable frame rate right
um so again looking at this here we're
we're pretty good in terms of of what
we're looking at here I'm just gonna put
WS visible in here so that our window is
actually visible I'm then gonna nerf the
two things that that show up for OpenGL
right like so and I now need if you look
at what's gonna go on here and we can
run we can start running this pretty
soon but we're gonna have some some
things like like I said we have to
process window messages and stuff like
that or nothing's gonna happen so we
gots a few more things to do but I'm
just gonna go ahead and sort of nerf
these things out here and we'll kind of
go it so what kind of take it as we go
so I'm gonna go ahead and put a while
loop in here for global running we're
just making sort of a silly little
program here that will never exit that
opens window we'll just
start there right we'll just start there
and we'll and we'll finish you know as
we go so all right so what do we
actually need to complete this just to
get things going
we need our main window callback right
which is this so there's our main window
callback and when we come in here right
we do have our WM close message and
that's going to set that global running
flag to false I need to actually put
this global running flag out in the
actual Global's well I don't need to say
that
so when we look at what's happening here
you can see all of this stuff is kind of
weird code for maintaining an aspect
ratio we don't care about that at all
right and so this is really not relevant
right we can we can get rid of all this
stuff does not matter set cursor is also
not really relevant to us that can just
pass through activate app not relevant
all of this stuff is correct we do want
to exit in all those cases don't care
about ciske down or any of those things
don't care about paint other than to
just make sure that it updates the recs
doesn't keep sending us the message so
most things can just go straight ahead
to our def window proc and off we go so
I think that's all good there and then
so really all we need is our win main
here I don't remember I don't use win
main very often so I don't really
remember what the win main entry point
signature even is so I'm just going to
grab it we go
oops and if you look here if you're
actually switching back to win main we
don't need to use this get module handle
zero because we just have the H instance
there so I'm just gonna go ahead and set
it up like that turn these into things
that humans can actually read and then
we're good to go all right so let's
start with a few things we need to do
first of all we don't have any of our
types in here so what I would like to do
if you look at handmade platform dot H
one thing I've been wanting to do for a
while is those kinds of just a bunch of
things in here that you might want to
use in a more general sense that I kind
of want to pull out into a handmade sort
of types I kind of want to do this for a
while like something like handmade types
that age right
and what handmade types out H would be
is just something that has you know like
a pretty straightforward understanding
of all of this stuff right so you know
we would imagine just putting it in here
and then all of these things just kind
of come out all of these basic calls
right and then all of these basic math
things like so and they're all gonna be
out there then we have kind of our our
understanding of how we do like asserts
and not implemented and all that stuff
all of this stuff is just kind of our
basic basic information right like
nothing super complicated here right so
I kind of wanted to put that all that
out there so that you can pretty
trivially do just the basic operations
that you might want to do we don't
really need any of this other stuff this
is all specific to handmade hero right
but all this stuff actually isn't it's
just things that you might
want to use so I wanted to kind of put
that out there I may want to put the the
mutexes in as well I'm not 100% sure
about that but we'll see
right so then we've kind of got this way
of just saying all right anytime we want
to build something to that effect we can
just say all right include handmade
types H and then we'll get all of those
types that we normally use now this
stuff was for our introspection we're
not really doing that stuff anymore so
I'm just gonna get rid of it for now and
go from there okay uh so I for some
reason made global variable B the thing
that we use here I nowadays just use
global so I kind of want to say look
global is variable is it's just
redundant all this might say global and
and then what I'll do is I'll just for
now I'll just get rid of that usage you
can see I put it in for coders Auto
highlight even that's the way I used to
talk about it is just as global right
and so that's all I'm doing here
[Music]
nurse that for a second and yeah now I
can just kind of put these out I'll do
this in a search in place just a little
bit faster let's see just like this one
can also be a little faster that way
yeah okay I so now we're good to go
and no we're not quite good to go time
there we go uh so also in theory you
know again I'll just double-check but in
theory we're not changing anything about
the code right our game still runs just
as as normal what I want to do here is I
want to now get that little testbed up
and running
that's totally isolated so we know
exactly what we're using and we can
write the test code the way we want what
I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna do
something slightly different from how
we've done it before this is the way
I've been doing things now it's sort of
a change in the way used to do it what I
used to do and you've seen me do it is I
just open just the bear executable right
and this is good because you know that
way you can just run you don't have to
have a project or solution in Visual
Studio but it ends up creating a
solution on the back end anyway I don't
know if you've noticed that but it does
just to save the state but you can't
actually use any of the features so for
example I can't have multiple different
arguments I might run with and set them
as different configurations because when
you just open executable you can't do
that don't ask me why you just can't so
what I kind of figured out is a better
way to do this is if you actually create
an empty project
so if product has nothing in it what you
can then do is say alright well look in
handmade you know MSB C proj will just
be some temporary directory that that
stores this these kind of projects if I
have win32 renderer tests as one of my
projects right I can just and turn off
great directorate resolution I hit OK
here I get an actual project right and
when we look here it keeps it isolated
in here right
I like how I said don't create a
directory resolution and what does it do
it of course creates a directory for the
solution I did that right right I didn't
I didn't screw it up did I let's just
make sure because we don't need it to
put it in directory but you know
let's just make sure I'm not
hallucinating project empty project do
not create director for solution the
location is here the project name is
win32 renderer test right right we all
see it okay
I hit ok creates the project in its own
directory it's so weird like Microsoft
is in their own special universe where
the checkbox for create directory for a
project when unchecked still creates a
director for the project they're like
hey we'll take that under advisement and
and then just totally ignore it anyway
but this is what I do I delete all of
the stuff that it puts in there right
like basically everything and then I
just use this fake project by saying
properties debugging rather than this I
just say hey I want you to use when
three to render a test as your
executable right then if I step in yes
build my project right then if I step in
it just works exactly the same as it
used to right it's it's the same as what
we had before but now you can actually
make configurations of the project so if
I want to make a bunch of different
configurations here that have different
command lines different execution
directories you can so it's just a
little bit of a way of making Visual
Studio be a little less crappy for
debugging external things now everything
sort of works right anyway here's our
window you can see I can't do anything
with it why because we literally don't
handle any messages because we never
actually process messages now sometimes
we'll get them directly sent to the
window but other than that we'd never
get them so let's finish that up so we
can start actually coding the renderer
test by just actually having a place to
process our messages again we can just
copy this code from the handmade hero
side of things so we've got our peek
message loop right I think we decided
this stuff was kind of just nuts and we
had no idea what Windows was actually
doing here we still don't really know
what Windows is doing here it's kind of
ridiculous but I'm just going to copy
this this process pending messages stuff
out to here so that we can call it and
then I'm just going to delete most of
the stuff that we're doing so we don't
care about keyboard or anything at the
moment so that's gone we don't really
care on anything other than just the
quit message and the dispatch stuff here
right so that should be fine okay so I
think that's all we need we don't need
any of this pretty sure that'll just
work
we don't need a time anything so I'm
gonna go ahead and call this winter to
process messages in our loop here as
well okay so there we go
and now when we run this in theory we
should be able to kind of like size the
window or do the other sorts of things
you would normally do it the window so
now we're ready to actually start
calling the renderer right and what I'd
like to do because then you can notice
it closes as well which is good what I'd
like to do here again is I'd like to
make this sort of easy to use so I'd
perhaps like our win32 init OpenGL I
kind of like that to just be able to I'd
like that too I'd like what I'd like to
be able to do here fundamentally
speaking also I don't know why we need
to get a device context here when we
already have a device context here
seems kind of dumb so I'm just gonna
stop doing that and say that this will
use the OpenGL DC so what I liked it
because remember we have CS own DC here
so when we get that handle we can just
keep it it's not a problem right so
anyway what I'm gonna do in here is I
want this init OpenGL stuff to work kind
of cleanly so that I don't have to copy
and paste all that code in there
so the first thing I want to be able to
do is pull out the OpenGL initialization
stuff into its own separate file so for
example in here we've kind of got if you
look at our OpenGL there's all the
opengl code it's the open Jellico that's
shared across operating systems right so
I want a win32 hand-made open jail
that's what I want and I want to pull
out all of that open GL code oops the
same thing we already have I want to
pull out all that Open GL code so that
we can just reuse it in here and I may
also want to simplify it so it's easier
for people on other platforms I know
it's been a little bit tricky because we
haven't really thought much about that
we haven't done anything to help those
people who are porting and we could
start doing stuff like that right now
that we're taking a couple streams to
clean this up so what I want to do is
I'll pull all this code out we know this
code is just for open gel nothing else
is happening in here right this is all
OpenGL code so it's gonna pull all that
code out here it is I'll put it in here
right and really this is the H file
portion to a certain extent so we may
kind of want to do it that way but you
know six in one half dozen the other
we'll see how we want to how we want
that to be going for it I also should
put our little boilerplate in there so
we're gonna include this obviously right
we're gonna include them to do him and
if we build now we should be able to get
this building again like not the new
code but the old code because we're just
we're not making any serious
modifications to it right we're just
doing straightforward reorganisation of
where the code lives so it can be used
by different people so that's pretty
straightforward I think all right so
where's the rest of the OpenGL code well
we've got these Trig's here right that
we know we might want global array we've
got this set pixel format and load
wiggle extensions in it opengl that's
this whole bit here so all that stuff
kind of wants to be you
the open jail side so let's see what we
have to do to pull that out it may be
nothing it may be something you can see
there's some stuff here that doesn't
like right so what's going on here
wiggle context major version ARB the
problem here with that is those weren't
defined anywhere I think is that because
they're in here know where those went
yeah uh so these really shouldn't be in
here I don't know why they were I guess
we just forgot that they were window
specific because this is where the
window specific stuff goes so let's try
that again
all right um so that all looks decent
let's start here here's our open jail
supports sRGB frame buffer this is a tag
that we're supposed to be getting back
from the open gel layer right and we
don't necessarily know so that's an
issue let's just we can think about that
we've then got some some problems here
where we want to sort of crack this open
this video extension stuff where we look
and look at wiggle extensions and
override some things in our OpenGL
settings right so that's a little bit of
an issue here how are we gonna deal with
it so just keep those in your head we're
not looking at quite yet but we're gonna
very shortly then we got this info
structure where we need to look to see
what what sorts of stuff we actually
need to wiggle get proc address for
right what are we using the frame buffer
object or not those sorts of things
right then it looks like we're kind of
okay OpenGL in it then at that point is
sort of the platform the platform the
part that's that's it doesn't have
anything to do with the wiggle section
of things right okay
so in order to get this working really
all we would have to do is make sure
that that we always install like we
always like include the actual handmade
OpenGL side of things and you can see
that does some things like pulling in
render group and stuff like that so
we've got some stuff we're gonna have to
do as we start to walk down this road
but we'll we'll cross that bridge when
we come to it
you'll see in a second alright so for
starters what I want to do is look
inside win32 handmade I want to see how
that inclusion pattern went so if we
look here you can see we have handmade
OpenGL is included sort of in here and
you can you can kind of see it doing
this like oh then I defined as a global
and then off we go and there's sort of
this weird like sort of alternating
pattern that's going on here and this
like kind of needs that to happen inside
it and all of this stuff kind of has to
play out a little bit more sanely there
what I'm gonna start by doing is I just
want to analyze what we actually do and
don't need in these things
more specifically okay for starters
suppose I were to move this down here
what happens right just to see what the
dependencies are right and what you can
see is actually not much this just needs
these two functions to be provided to it
now once it actually can see those what
that means is we could pretty trivially
to like move forward on this a little
bit in sort of slow baby step fashion
you just take those two functions that
we actually care about here the opengl
in it and get info this one
it's behind my head there and the get
info so I can leave these two modules
talking to other this way and continue
to move forward so what I want to do I
want to simplify how those things come
together so I don't like that yeah but I
don't want to address it yet so you can
see I'm doing this in very specific
steps that move things around so that I
can still run and compile and see how
things are related more easily without
taking a big leap right so that's a very
intentional so now if I go look at this
win32 ended up in GL part what you can
see is that I now could call if I wanted
to the same pattern of includes that's
happening here I could actually do that
like this and be okay now the problem is
hand-made rendered out H and rendered
out cbpr probably not going to work
because of dependencies that we aren't
doing right like well v2 was supposed to
be defined so I'm not sure what's going
on there hold on a second let me double
check that types Ted H did I put that
include in the wrong place I did sorry
where's the wind did I just diced delete
it it was here a minute ago
I know what happened there um so you can
see right like inside handmade render
this stuff is just intermingled with
like the game render commands and all
that sort of stuff right and we don't
really want that to be true
so I don't actually know yet
to what extent I can extricate those
without doing more work so that's kind
of more when I mission like for example
if I get rid of this what do I lose
right and you can see well it's got this
this render settings so what I could
very easily decide to do is move that
render settings more into the renderer
look into an understanding of what the
render a proper actually is and sort of
extricate it there so that's a really
good sign of the first place I need to
start making those changes right and let
me get rid of this as well and see where
we're at there so you can see the
current settings seem to be the really
big hang-up so looking in here you can
see we also rely on sort of a printf
because we're trying to generate there
some basically some versions of this
stuff that use parameters that we don't
know so we're kind of trying to set some
parameters here dynamically so that
format string is kind of also something
that we we need to address now
fortunately we don't really need to do
that much for that we can pretty
trivially just say oh yeah you wanted
format string that's fine format string
is just printf s printf so you know the
size and the string or the size of the
test we just skip the size part put the
dest in there and then put the VAR s on
the end of it right so we can pretty
trivially make that happen we can also
use the size to printf if they want to
so that really doesn't concern me that's
gonna be pretty easy to handle but yeah
so then we've got some of the things
like strings are equal again those
things we can
we can easily nerf for the time being
just to move forward if we want to do
two strings that's just a string compare
of a and B equals zero right and so
again we can kind of keep those pretty
much under control so let's take a look
at what else we've got going on here
that seems problematic it wants us to
use sprint def s I don't know if I want
to use sprint FS but I don't really care
it's fine with me so it that'll take the
size which is fine that's what we that's
what we were doing just takes in the
opposite order so if it wants to do that
go nuts and so it looks like those
settings are really most of it there
right so so we kind of know where we're
at here it's really not that bad
if I don't want to include that render
information if I'm just talking about
these things it's not too bad
I don't know about the sort I don't know
if anyone actually calls that so I'd be
interested to see if any I don't think
anyone probably does so I think we're
probably almost to the point where this
would work and really what we're worried
about here is is some of these things
like the render settings and like that
the loaded white bitmap sort of way of
short-circuiting the fact that when you
want to draw without a bitmap it
substitutes that bad in there okay so
looking at this stuff we've got a few
string things here that we use when
we're analyzing the extension stuff this
is really really ugly and this is OpenGL
fault make no mistake about it this is
in no
in no way an acceptable way to have
people look at extensions I mean it's
just ridiculous that you're parsing
strings to look at extensions so
error-prone it's just absurd right at
the very least just say how many strings
to heart and let me enumerate over them
and thankfully they did do that in
future versions of OpenGL but of course
wiggle is old and and doesn't conform to
that name you have to use extensions if
you want to get things as a set of
strings like that so anyway taking a
look at handmade render group so we've
got some some things here that sort of
use like loaded bitmap so you can kind
of see we look through here and we look
at like what our problems are gonna be
if we want to share if we want render
groups definitions to sort of propagate
through here we look at what problems
we're probably gonna have and what
you'll notice is there's really not a
lot in here besides loaded bitmap that's
really a problem for us right look
loaded bitmaps really the only sticking
point I don't know if anyone uses
environment map I'm gonna look and see
if they do so if we look down here if I
just nurse this and say no no more
environment so I want to see who cares
right
so this yeah so this stuff is just not
used at the moment so I'm I'm gonna just
nurse this as well we just we just
fundamentally don't use any of this
stuff it was some rendering experiment
stuff we use before right
I'm just gonna get rid of it yeah you
can I mean you can just see this this
stuff is just I mean it's just nonsense
right just old stuff
I mean this whole thing it's not
necessary just old stuff that we never
got rid of yeah
all right so I think that's all good
this is just from the renderer test
stuff right so getting rid of that
environment map is just fine right like
nobody cares about that we can remove
that entirely if we want to it's just
not a thing I'm just gonna look through
here and see what other sorts of stuff
we have to deal with rectangle - I I'm
not sure where that's defined but we can
put that into our types because that's
also a type sort of thing so let's grab
that out clean these up eventually -
let's take a look so no no care about
that em 4 by 4 M soon that's also in
math yeah about mmm that's just an M 4x4
with its inverse together for
convenience Jimmy again loaded bitmap is
there what's this illegal use of this
type as an expression oh that's just
yeah no we don't care about that at all
s 32 from Z so s 3 - from Z is our
little parser there that can turn that
can parse numbers again that's just a 2i
so we can also again temporarily we can
make that be something that we're gonna
stub out
okay and so then we've got some like
calls on the rectangle to eye those
would be nice to have we got the safe
ratio so that's just using our math
library now which we want to include and
we want that to be pull out a bowl
that'll probably our next step so then
we've got to start thinking about like
the texture ops for allocating textures
those sorts of things how we want those
to go we can think about those a little
bit more in depth I'm just trying to
look through here so it looks this looks
pretty reasonable right this is all none
of this is particularly scary to me
everything looks looks pretty good in
here
alright so in order to get us back on
track of being able to compile the win
through to render a test without the
rest of handmade hero what I need to
start looking at now is taking the parts
of the renderer that are embedded in
other things in handmade hero and
pulling them out into their own thing
right so if you think about what OpenGL
is open jail is like the back end to our
renderer right and so we want and you
know what I should actually get math in
here as well all right so let's these
are things that people will use with the
renderer we want the type stage right
and you can see that that is now pretty
straightforward right the types of H is
just a very simple file that just has
some very basic things in it in terms of
I could clean up these types or they're
concise as well yeah some very basic
things in it those things are just the
way that we write code so anyone who's
going to use our stuff has to be
familiar with it that's totally fine and
so that all is reasonable I might want
to clean this file up a little bit into
wrist break into sections but it's it's
there's nothing really wrong with it's
fine as it is right so the next thing I
want to do is take a look at math and
see to what extent that is also okay
right um so I'm gonna take a look at the
math here is our math dot H and let's
just look through that it's pretty clean
just just sets of math opps there's
nothing weird in there really so if you
want to use our math I think you're
pretty good to go right
that's all seems pretty pretty fine to
me so let's see how that goes and so
these here are these are the intrinsics
and again that all seems pretty good too
so I think all of that's fine now we may
want to weld some of those things
together we'll have to think about how
we want to do that exactly let me go
ahead and grab this out here where are
those things where do we include X mm in
trim oh here no
it's in here because it turns out um hmm
well what I'm gonna do for that since I
want these to be out here as well I
think what I want to do is kind of get
these pieces here I think I kind of want
those to come out here and I want this
to be inside here right there we go
all right 32 max I'm not sure where we
defined that so we'll have to grab that
somewhere it's in platform oh so we have
the maxes they should all be out in that
type styles well yeah that stuff should
all be in here there we go um so again
that all seems pretty fair so now you
can use all of the mass stuff which we
also want we want to be able to ship the
mass stuff out we want to be able to
ship the types file and yeah all of that
stuff we kind of want to just work and I
think it should relatively good right
yeah um so then like I said I think
we're down at that point just the stuff
that really needs to be like like we're
this is all the errors that there are in
fact we're not even we're not even at
they're like 100 like you know the thing
where it's like more errors than I can
display oh no right so in this case I
think we're in good shape I don't know
how much time I have left in this stream
so I've got another entire hour left so
what I focused on here now is I want to
pull out the render into sort of its own
like more of its own proper defined
thing because that's what we're going
we're trying to extricate it from our
program and say it's no longer
intermingled it can just stand by itself
because it was already kind of
architected that way like we didn't
really make it particularly hard-coded
like it's fairly standalone as it is and
that was because OpenGL was kept to the
side like we don't sprinkle OpenGL code
throughout our apps so we kind of
already did a bunch of that anyway so
now the goal here is to move more more
towards that and so we have a couple
things about our renderer like so we've
got this notion of render group and then
we've also got this notion of render
right and you can see that they're kind
of weirdly like separated and I don't
really like too much about the way these
go there they're sort of they're sort of
flipping things there's just too much
kind of chaos there it's unclear who's
doing what and if you look at how these
are broken down like handmade renderer
is weird because handmade render
actually has like all this it's really
the software renderer that ended up in
here as well as some renderer stuff
right so it's just these two files we
never really cared much about figuring
out how they go so what I want to do is
I might start by like breaking these up
into what was actually the software
renderer should now be its own like file
that's completely isolated
for rendering and so much like we have
handmade OpenGL right what I want to do
there is I want to have handmade like
software renderer ok dot cpp or
something like this right so i want to
specifically say that the software
renderer lives in its own file that's
like a different thing and i'm just
gonna grab anything i see that's just
obviously software renderer i want those
things to go into this file right so we
know that our Ayaka stuff where we were
doing profiling that was obviously meant
for this situation so all this stuff
should have gone in there right I don't
know if global renders your living
samples I think that's a separate thing
so draw rectangle is obviously one of
these right bilinear sample st like all
the stuff sample environment map that we
nerfed
all of this is all software renderer
draw a bitmap right change saturation
was like guess some kind of a post pass
thing for a drum mat yeah you can see
all these things are back tank wickley
these were all saw for render features
that we implemented their blend render
target clear rectangle render commands
to bitmap do top render work software
render commands all this stuff right all
that stuff is actually the software
renderer ok um and what I might do I
might even do some renaming here I
apologize to people who like to count on
the names of files for things I know
it's not great
but like if we do handmade renderer
something handmade renderer or something
handmade renderer or something maybe
that helps to say like what's going on
with them so if I were to say for
example let me just save the stuff that
we just did so what I kind of want to do
here say okay like if I go to a handmade
code maybe what we do is say look the
OpenGL renderer and the software
renderer are kind of like two branches
of the same thing not branches really
but two versions of the same thing so
what I'm going to do is I'm actually
going to name them as such so this is
actually gonna be handmade renderer
software like so this is gonna be
handmade renderer OpenGL like so so then
you can kind of see like we've got the
OpenGL renderer the software renderer
and then here what we can do is say
these things will merge together into
like handmade renderer H so that there's
like the renderer then there's the
OpenGL implementation the renderer
there's the software you know
implication of the renderer and
eventually we can do like a D 3d version
of the renderer and a metal version of
the renderer right this is again some
pretty straightforward stuff right
nothing particularly weird about what's
going on there but just worth
understanding what I was trying to to
accomplish with that right so now what I
want to do is merge these two files
render and render group into a single
file that's just renderer dot H right
so I'm gonna load that up and so
rendered eh I'm gonna grab this whole
thing put it in there then I'm gonna
grab the CPP file and do the same thing
put all that in there
and then what I want to do is grab
render group and again do the same thing
like so and then again same thing here
okay so now I've just got those
completely sort of by themselves I want
to quickly switch just really do a
simple switch here to not compile our
test code now just so I can focus on
making sure other code builds so what
I'm going to do is I'm gonna change
these things that used to refer to the
old files and I'm gonna make sure that
we can include them here right oops like
so I think this is what we want to do I
don't actually know if we want that we
don't nothing yeah maybe we do find out
okay so what I want to do is I want to
get rid of everywhere that ink that
includes render group dot H so render
group dot H don't want it ever it's not
a thing anymore so we've got to deal
with that render dot H also not a thing
anymore so we got to deal with that so
anywhere that was getting included it
needs to stop it included and then we
can go from there right all right uh so
looking at here we just have a I think
this is probably just a case of get
bitmap not being included at the right
place where are we inside went through
handmade why isn't that just in handmade
renderer I thought that's what would
have been in here get bitmap it's not
where is get bitmap that's weird it's an
handmade asset this we will want to
untangle we will definitely want to
disentangle this and we can sort of see
how that's going to happen a little
later on but for now what I'm going to
do is I'm just gonna forward to clear it
same with load bitmap should be like
right here fairness
um and these are let me see that load
font again this is kind of just patching
so I'm I'm not really going to leave it
this way probably but I'm just don't I
don't want to disentangle those things
quite yet well suis got
okay so one problem we're gonna have
here is if we those were for including
specifically the renderer dot cpp so i
don't know to what extent we could just
not do that i'm gonna double check to
see what we actually need from there but
really we just want to disentangle those
things to probably eventually as well so
yeah so it's just it's only aspect ratio
fit so really what i probably want to do
for now is if i can get away with it and
let's see if i can to just not like how
much can i get away with not having
these entirely okay good so aspect ratio
fit we still need to have however so
what i'm going to do is just take aspect
ratio fit and since that's just a math
operation that's all that is i'm just
going to put that into the mass math
library
and then I think we're good to go right
okay oops that's not what I wanted to
run now so I just want to check to make
sure things still running okay and it is
so that's good
close this down oh I don't need to close
that down why did I do that just need to
switch it back to the other one so what
I want to do at this point is I want to
I want to now ping-pong back to the
other test bed and again sort of
progress down that road as I was
beforehand
right okay so here's our renderer opengl
includes we need also the handmade
renderer open field here like that
handmade renderer dot cpp doesn't need
to be included yet so we'll talk about
that a second that this actually should
be in here okay so now we need to start
looking at the things in handmade
renderer that are actually sort of
wedded to
we need to look at the things that are
wedded to the platform layer right and
we need to figure out how those are
gonna get pulled out and how we're gonna
look at them now if you remember
correctly inside the platform layer we
have these game render commands and
these game render settings these texture
artists these are all obviously just
renderer things right
these should actually be defined in the
renderer and as we start to simplify
them we'll take more charge of them so
these are not really in the these
actually should be in renderer dot H now
because that's actually the stuff we're
going to be dealing with right so as we
clean these things up we want to start
cleaning these things up - I don't know
about the game last screen buffer that's
praten that really a thing that's sort
of a separate part for the software
renderer I think so we need to kind of
think about why that is even out here in
the first place kind of a good question
but this stuff here wants to be moved
into the render definition almost
certainly and worked from there now
nothing else in here is particularly
related to that I don't think this is
all like input and memory allocation and
that sort of stuff things we don't care
about in that sense so I don't know like
I'm gonna go ahead and search for what
that off-screen buffer who uses that
still so it's only in win32 hand-made
here for this so I kind of feel like
that where does that get passed through
can't see anything my head's in the way
so that's a win 30th - off-screen buffer
so game last review no I'm just gonna go
ahead and see what happens if I nerf
that thing
I also need game render settings in
there let's do that ah so these actually
need to be defined somewhere and in fact
this is this stuff is not really where I
would like it to be anyway
I feel like this stuff should have been
in here to begin with so I'm gonna move
this out to someplace that's actually
doing comparison calls right and then I
take this hour equal bit for the game
render settings and I'm actually gonna
put that into the renderer because
that's where it belongs right we could
put it out here I don't know where we
want to put it exactly but right ok so
again this is temporarily speaking we
can look at that as a pre death and then
we can kind of go from there
loaded bitmaps we can also look at as a
pre death for the moment I don't know
how long that'll hold up so inside our
render test you can see all this still
works here we've got our light data with
stuff that was in the platform layer as
well should have been moved out
didn't we where's our light data with
where's that stuff to find light data
with ah so that's in handmade lighting
[Music]
hmm hmm I say
so I'm not entirely certain how we want
to deal with that for now I think what
I'll say is that is going to get put out
here temporarily I don't want that to
stick around forever but for now it's
totally fine so now we're mostly down
again to sort of things that we were
using in here I don't know how exactly I
want these to work so we're just going
to kind of wing these for now because I
don't want them to be really something
that we're focusing on but for memory is
equal size a B Y these weren't
capitalized this can just be a mem comp
zero a B sighs believe should do it is
whitespace drink
so string comp we actually I see so
string comp we actually have two
versions of one that takes a size and
one that doesn't right so that's
actually string end comp which I believe
exists
I'm not really allowed to define those
looks like multi define them so what
I'll do is I'm just gonna stub them out
like so so again nothing we just
particularly spectacular happening here
but I just don't want to deal with these
at the moment go yeah that seems what is
the problem
Oh
so this wants stars
well why it's a void star there we go so
we just need is white space and zero
struct again those are pretty easy to to
deal with so I'm just going to go ahead
and do them light buffer this instead of
using zero struct here I think I might
just do this so that we don't have to
worry about that and then is white space
is pretty straightforward as well I
don't know if this exists in the C
runtime library it might it would
probably be in like the care care the
the carrot h or whatever it's called
c type is space what else you got for me
this is the character classification
stuff
so I think that's all we really need
would be if space right it seems pretty
straightforward so what I'm gonna say is
is whitespace is just is space see how
that goes
so now I think we're good the only
problem we have here is this in handmade
lighting
I think this now
oh well that's including render group
that's a pity which is not supposed to
be so that's probably it
where is render group dot H being so
shouldn't that have taken care of it cuz
renderer H is what has it in it right
renderer dot H there's light data with
right there and it's gonna include it
beforehand oh you know what it's
probably just inside the win32 handmade
version just remember this get built
separately that's almost certainly the
problem right there I also don't know if
handmade lighting actually needs to be
in there does it so
this right here needs to allocate
lighting boxes and it needs to know how
big those are right apparently
which is a little weird because the
platform layer doesn't really need to
know that much about those things but
but okay
I mean I'm sort of okay with it so for
now I guess
mmm well I mean the lighting never
actually like this doesn't really need
to be here does it like this doesn't
flow through to the that that doesn't
really flow through to the actual
renderer like isn't that something that
should be done as part of the game side
you know because it kind of feels like
it like it kind of feels like that
really isn't part of the render in that
sense so if we go into the renderer here
and I look to see you know does anyone
ever look at the light box is part of
things I'm pretty sure the answer is no
it's not what's called called flipping
geo renderer right or sorry renderer
OpenGL because it never looks at those
so that's kind of wrong to me and I I
don't love that because it should it
should only really exist during the
portion of time like I think that needs
to get cleaned up I guess is what I'm
saying because at some point the light
data gets set and that's all there is
and you don't really need to look into
it in the way that this is having it
look into it so I think I'm gonna go
ahead and get rid of that so rather than
clean this one up and patch it for now I
think I'm gonna actually focus on
getting rid of that so here's the
renderer and we got to go through and
start cleaning this up but before we do
this light box count light boxes thing I
feel like that's got to go I just don't
feel like that's an appropriate place
for that I feel like the appropriate
place for the light boxes is actually in
the just the standard render group
that's actually having the the push you
know that's actually pushing stuff on
here I feel like this is actually where
that should be because it's only
relevant for the pack all right sorry
about that OBS just crashed fortunately
I noticed so we didn't really lose
anything this is where we were but like
okay so hopefully the recording is
intact I don't know if it is or not but
hopefully it'll actually be salvageable
or at least the most part salvageable
and these two could be welded together
anyway what I was saying is I wanted to
put the light boxes in here because they
really only exist for the amount of time
that the rep they're relevant to the
render group right and so what I'd like
to do is say when you enable lighting
then you can push light boxes and if you
don't enable lighting then you don't and
that's all there is to it right so the
light boxes I just want to have them be
gone so in here where the operating
system previously was out getting light
since for you I don't want it to be
allocating light boxes for you what I
want it to do instead is to have those
come directly from here like so so this
way the light box has come out of the
out of the render group which is where I
wanted them to come out of because they
they are computer to CPU side at the
moment and until we actually know what
we might like if we eventually do
computation of lighting on the GPU side
that's fine but we should figure that
out first before we start sending them
down the card or something we kind of
setup as if we're going to send these
down the car but we're not sending them
down to the card so they really should
not be in that part of the code at the
moment that's my opinion on that so this
right here when we do the the lighting
test stuff that's gonna just use the
group information directly so this group
commands thing it's not gonna have to
deal with that the light point index I
don't remember to what extent that he's
actually used inside the render itself
it might not be I'm not sure let me just
take a quick look at that and see so I
don't actually see that the light point
index
is just an index so that also can just
come out I think right that can just be
done in here and we don't have to deal
with it elsewhere I don't think right so
I believe that just means that this
transfers into a group thing so just
this says that and then that's all
coming out of the right place this is
now just looking at the group
exclusively which is what we want and I
don't even know if it needs that anymore
you just find out all right I so now
what we need to do though is actually
allocate those right so those do have to
really get used so you know we now have
this code when we go to start the render
group up so in here where we actually
initialize a render group so in here
where we actually initialize a render
group what we want to do in this case is
we want to initialize the lighting
information as well because otherwise
we'd never get any right so we can Stern
off with it being point to zero when you
do enable lighting though when you make
that call that's when you actually would
have to allocate memory for it right
when you come in here now you'd have to
set these light boxes to be something
where you actually are going to use the
memory right for them
problem is when we call enable lighting
we haven't passed it anything with which
it can get memory and so that's an
obvious problem that we need to rectify
here and so that's what we're gonna do
now
in world mode which is the only place
where enabled lighting actually gets
called you can see here where we do a
enable lighting then we put push the
Lighting's on and yeah whatever yeah
this is because we put them on the stack
so they're transfer at first and then
yeah it's kind of nuts the way that
happens we can probably make that a
little bit clearer too anyway when we do
enable lighting here and then the push
lighting call happens this should
probably just be one in the same when
you enable lighting it should just push
the lighting that's probably what should
happen because you can't do it any other
way right I mean that's how that has to
work so I think we might want to do
there is just just combine those two so
if we take a look at the push lighting
call which is this this part right here
no I push render element is defined like
only right there but it is so yeah there
you go
so I'm going to just take this whole bit
gonna move that down here I'm gonna say
enable lighting is just gonna be pushed
lighting from now on and so what you're
gonna do is you're gonna pass the bounce
and the light source there this right
here will happen in here and then we'll
get back to the part we were trying to
before where we were talking about the
where we're gonna get the memory
so when we do the push lady here then
what happens is eventually when we're
done we do a lighting test thing that's
sort of like when we retire the lighting
so from here to there that's sort of the
lifetime of it right now in here we
should have a transient arena that we
can use and we shouldn't be able to have
some sort of a temporary way that we can
allocate some some lighting on that and
then move along right so I believe
if I go look where's my begin scent all
yeah so I believe if I go look at my
begin sim call and how that works right
you can see how it just does a temporary
it starts a temporary memory thing
that's really all I want to do here too
so inside where we do our lighting I
want to do the same thing right I I know
that the transient arena is a fine place
to stick the memory for the lighting
because it's just stuff that gets used
temporarily so what I should be able to
do here is where I do a push lighting I
should be able to sort of do a light
memory like so and I should be able to
do an end temporary memory light memory
like so and this can just be trans state
trainer ena or whatever right yeah all
right so what I want to do is when I
push the lighting there then we come
down here and then we've used the
lighting and so we can end the temporary
menu feel lighter in it now this sim
here is actually going to have its own
temporary memory so this is just really
we could just do temporary memory for
this whole thing and we probably should
just unify those two together instead of
having an open and closed the temporary
memory like that for no real reason but
it's fine I thought we just looked and
it was oh it's it's not called bad it's
called rhinorrhea
there we go
so now what we need to do is make push
lighting actually do that allocation it
needs to do that allocation in a
sensible way if we go into the render
group right here we don't want to be
calling wind through to allocate memory
obviously we want to do is call push
array we need to pass the array size and
the thing that we're actually using here
we don't care about the not restored bit
at the moment that's sort of a separate
issue so we can put that in here and we
can put that to temporariness so what
I'm going to do here just say we've got
a memory arena and off we go now we need
to look at the pushed lighting call that
is defined there wait there's another
one
is that a bug that might be a bug we're
not supposed to be calling that twice
are we oh and that's in the wrong one I
now you know what I need to do now now
that we're doing this I need to get rid
of those other files there we go
that seems like a bug hold for one
moment while I remove those other two
files also I'm just gonna get rid of
them real quick so I don't accidentally
edit them again right so we want render
group and render we want these to go
away so it's gonna pop out here I do
this sometimes just gonna make a retired
folder this is where old files go to die
so what I want to do here is I want to
just go ahead and and find out if that
that just seems like a bug we just
didn't notice I don't think we're
supposed to be pushing those on twice
I'm I'm nervous about that that that
does not unless I'm forgetting something
I don't think push lighting is supposed
to happen twice right
yeah I don't I don't know what to say
about that I'm gonna see what happens
here but that just seems real bad and I
don't know what's going on so I'm just
gonna go ahead and pretend that that's
okay and nobody saw it and it's fine
we'll go ahead and debug it and see
what's going on but that was weird
okay so we know we want to analyze to
that flight point indexes light point
index 0 is an unused one I guess light
box count needs to get initialized to 0
it will be because it automatically when
you do a push lighting it automatically
initially it was initialized to 0 just
way back here in the group are rid
already so I'm just gonna assert that
group light box count equals 0 because I
don't want people calling push lighting
twice since obviously that's something
we might do and I don't think we're
supposed to ever push lighting twice
we're only supposed to push the lighting
once now we could do a thing that when
you push the lighting again it just
resets your lighting and that's fine but
at the moment since we're not ever doing
that I would really prefer it if we were
not if no one was allowed to do that
right alright so there's the lighting
it's working just fine
so I think we're good there so that's
all fine
okay so I am now building both things
correct building the renderer testbed
and I'm building the renderer proper
okay yeah okay uh so now we have to
start looking at these and crunching
them down into something that we
actually want because there's still
quite a bit of intermingling here and
the biggest thing that we're gonna have
to do you start is the texture
management side of things for sure the
reason that the biggest thing we have to
do is because for the most part most of
things that we're doing in the render
right now are not game specific like we
just have textured vertices that you
send down and it fills them right so
it's pretty straight forward and that
would just generalize anyone who wants
to call that stuff just canned there's
just not a lot to it so the big place
that right now we're tightly coupled to
the app and what we're gonna spend you
know pretty much all of next stream
doing we're almost done with this first
string
he's texture management because that's
the place where the renderer and the
asset system are linked together and so
that needs to be generalized into
something that will work both outside of
handmade hero and inside of handmade
hero because we don't want the renderer
to care where the textures came from
that's that's the crucial thing
we don't want that so that's we're gonna
spend the next dream doing but the first
thing we're gonna do here is just see
what we've got
in terms of initialization and getting
the render working here I just want to
do a quick spin through this code and
see what's going on so if we if we pop
back over to went through to hand-made I
want to look at that display buffer and
window call that's this call right here
so what I want to do is replace that
with the opengl only version that's this
so it's what calls OpenGL renderer
commands with draw region window with
window height I want to know what all
that should look like so first I'm going
to do is I'm going to look at what that
draw region is you could see that that's
a rectangle tool I so what I want to do
is fill out this rectangle to I with
something sensible let me just see what
we've got there so if I want to I can
kind of just use the rectum in dim
probably to create my rectangle to I
because what I know is that well I've
just really all I need to do is just
make something that's the right size for
my open for my window right that's
that's really all I need at the moment
so what I'm gonna do here is I'm just
gonna say I've got my I don't know
display region well you know what draw
region was fine
well you know don't if it ain't broke
don't fix it so I want to make a draw
region here that I can pass and I'm
gonna actually make it so that the draw
region is just whatever the well you
know what no why even do that why not
just use the aspect ratio it just call
that we're using before like we could do
the aspect ratio fit just to make sure
we're still bleeding properly
we could we could just do that right
because it's a good test so I'm still
gonna say aspect ratio fit and we're
gonna say width and height here in terms
of what the target is I guess and then
we've got the dimension width and height
so what I'm gonna say is look let's
pretend we always want a sixteen by nine
window like so and then let's say that
we've got the dimension wit and height
width and height that's what the window
actually has and I think that'll give us
what we want out the back
don't quote me on that because I don't
actually know if it's true
so here I'm going to go ahead and get my
window width and my window height and
pretend I have those and then I'm going
to call all this stuff so here's the
window width and height how do I get
that well for those of you who remember
I mean I guess I can just go look it up
in here but you know it's just get
client rect and they subtracted two it's
not particularly glamorous you can see
it here pretty straightforward right
not like to it alright um so our main
problem now is just how do I actually
know what you know what commands to
render for my test well that's now where
we start to get into the snuffleupagus
stuff right so what we're gonna do and
it'll probably take us tomorrow till
tomorrow to get there what we want to do
now is actually have a thing where if we
were to allocate these the same way that
we're doing in win32 hand-made where we
sort of say look let's allocate the
memory using went through to allocate or
whatever else we're doing if we go ahead
and do that code then make some things
that just clear the screen or something
let's make sure that that works or who
knows what right so that's all we're
really gonna start doing here and then
tomorrow if we get far enough at the end
of the stream that we do in in ten
minutes from now well we're gonna take a
break and then we're gonna do a stream
at two at two o'clock if we get far
enough getting everything together then
tomorrow we'll do is start figuring out
what we want for easy API access to it
right
but anyway so what I want to do here is
I want to actually make sure that all
the OpenGL stuff allocation stuff works
okay
and start to pull that stuff out into
something that makes reasonable sense
right so let's go ahead and do that I'm
gonna go ahead and look at where the
render cut so here's how we allocated
those render commands originally this is
where we did that right is right here so
what I want to do is is figure out how
to get that going
here's default render commands put
oversized push buffer with hide for
ticks blah blah blah right um so in
order to get that I need to have this
memory right this memory has got to come
from somewhere you know and and so
that's what I'm going to do here
and I need that win32 allocate memory
call to be available it's pretty
straightforward because we don't need to
do any of those things that we're doing
there we can just call virtue a like
ourselves so in here what we need to do
is just call virtual Alec as you can see
and so what I can do is just take this
basic allocation call come down here to
where this is happening and we don't
really have to do all of this shuffling
anymore I can just say hey textured
vertex equals this thing oops
still need the cast though
and we don't care about that so yeah
there's that allocation same thing would
be true here like so and let's just
compile that and get that down into
something oh I didn't do this one here
we go
and so now what I'd like to do is this
is I don't I can just call this every
time if I want to write so I can come
down here and when we do this draw
region nonsense what I can do here is
say oh all right let's you know make the
this stuff work that way
this will require our opengl stuff to
understand a little bit better how large
things are so when you have to actually
when it actually has to go deal with the
settings that's kind of kind of be a
separate issue that we'll have to look
at right but the rest of this stuff
stays the same and doesn't have to be
changed right so this stuff is all just
totally fine so let's go ahead and keep
going here
almost to the five-minute warning oh
that's not what I wanted I wanted to
call like get this okay we got a ramp to
take a little bit of a look at how that
stuff is it's playing out in the side
all right so I just I'm gonna start with
some basic stuff here I'm gonna pop over
to went through to render a test and
we're gonna start stepping through some
of this and taking a look at it and how
we want it to kind of work here right so
we're gonna enter in here we process our
messages to ask me where that came from
was this just something left over from
wait a minute
where was your what on earth did it just
do what was that breakpoint
I'm gonna go ahead and assume that is a
debug build prob that was a really weird
situation is that I didn't like what
that was doing yeah that was just a
release build you know em SVC can't do
bug release builds we know this is true
all right so anyway this is the draw
region of the screen here's the size of
those I have to go look to see how we
want to spec that stuff out so that's
gonna actually be more of a thing later
this all looks fine I'm not sure what
how the settings so the settings are
active the width and height in there and
this change command actually takes care
of that but the thing that's a little
weird about that is why is there another
so why are there two of those it's a
little bit weird and I want that to not
be weird so we kind of want to deal with
that a little bit better than we're
dealing with it now where does that come
from and how does it get retired
so this looks kind of bonkers and I
don't love it specifically what I'm
talking about here is forget all that
stuff get the render group you know
that's sort of our separate issue just
look into these the width and height
here oh okay all right no nevermind I
couldn't tell what was going on why we
had to him I thought there were two in
here it's not it just sets it for us so
this does what I want it this does
exactly what I wanted
everything's fine no need to panic we're
good to go
so my next test is just gonna be can I
actually do something with my render
commands here so I want to take a look
at my render group stuff here's the
renderer and so what I want to do is I
want to put in like something I can see
if it actually works so let's say I put
in a put in a push book clear not sure
to what extent we still support clearing
because it's kind of special-purpose now
the way the renderer works but we will
try I'm gonna clear to a nice wonderful
pink color I'm going to do a begin and
end render group here like so
I'm gonna pass null for the assets
because I'm not actually going to ask it
to load any assets and I'm gonna pass
zero for the generation ID
well we'll pass one because who knows
pixel width and pixel height for the
cliprect there that's just going to be
again these two right and so that should
be good to go and then I should be able
to do an end render group as well okay
right so this is right I think where we
start to run into the having to
extricate things which is what I said
we're gonna have to do next because now
I actually need a way of talking to the
renderer and that requires using this
code and as soon as I do that now we're
bound to the asset system right we're
instantly we instantly run up against
the problem where the asset system
becomes a necessary component since
we're right at the end
that's our miss top we have successfully
pulled everything out into a multi-use
thing and now our our goal is to sort of
make the texture stuff be something you
can use with two different asset systems
because I'm assuming that the person
who's going to use this is using their
own asset system not ours right I will
do a very brief QA probably only like 10
to 15 minutes so we literally we will at
most use the normal queue any time
because then we're gonna all take a
break and go get lunch and come back
after that so very brief Q&amp;A here
are we going to check the recording that
ended in an app crash yeah I can I don't
know if it's if it got trashed or not so
that would be this one here let's take a
look yeah it look it looks like it
worked
thankfully I switched to recording flvs
when I set up the new setup which
actually worked
I don't do mp4 SMR mp4s are just gone
when you crash so thankfully the flvs
are there if we have no questions we can
all go to lunch early and then come back
and take a look but I'll wait just a
little bit to make sure there's no
questions on what we did so far it's
fokin we're off to prison heroes jail I
don't think Vulcans worth well really
for anything but not because it doesn't
offer a performance gain it's because I
think you should just use whatever the
platform layer is now so I think what
you want to do if you're going to switch
away from OpenGL switch 2d 3d or metal
depending which one you're on because
I've been on this a couple times
Vulcan doesn't really have a reason to
exist anymore because since Apple is not
going to support anything but metal that
means you should write a metal layer on
on Mac Oz and iOS
that's just what you should do because
you want to be on the main path they are
not supporting anything else and so that
means if you have to do metal you lost
there's no reason to OpenGL you don't
get a you don't get a porting benefit
anymore so you might as well do metal on
mac us and then d 3d on on windows and
that's that so I don't I don't see any
point to to Vulcan it's now a middleman
so if you write to Vulcan you're
actually just writing on top of someone
else's API you should just written to
that API in the first place right cuz
you don't get a porting win anymore
well we take this opportunity implants
III back-end no we're never gonna
implement a d3d back until the games
done as long as we have one functioning
back-end that's fun you know we're done
and then only when we need to actually
do like finalized shipping stuff would
we would we implement more backends than
just one
lunch break is till about 1:45
are there practical solutions to
reducing the fill rate in a software
renderer yes but I'm not sure
I mean sure there's this all the same
tricks that GPUs use right like early Z
out and like storing blocks that have
their their max Z in them been Mac Z for
like early out testing stuff like that
testing whole blocks of alpha and not
filling them you know all that stuff
isn't every graphs API just a middleman
no metal is actually the lowest level
you can write to on Mac Oz you know
that's what drives the graphics driver
if you use molten v/k you're writing to
an API that then writes to metal so you
literally just introduced a second thing
that can go wrong a second thing that
can slow you down right so if you need
to access the hardware access the
hardware with something that actually
accesses it don't write to another thing
and then to another thing at that point
you might as well just be using a higher
level engine style thing right if you're
treating you it's nuts to think about
writing to Vulcan if it doesn't actually
talk to the hardware the only point in
implementing Vulcan is to talk to the
hardware if you're gonna be going
through a middleman use an API just
better than Vulcan because well gives a
terrible API right you'd never use
Vulcan to make your life easier it's a
terrible API right so the only reason
you would have used Vulcan is if it
actually lets you talk to the hardware
it doesn't now right it's it's only on
Windows would that be true on Mac Oz it
talks to metal which is now it's just a
crappy API you put in between yourself
and the actual API you were trying to
call it literally has no point in
existing I I they should just get rid of
it and save everyone the trouble right
it's just taking driver team time now
it's it's not it adds value for nobody
you know if you want to if you want VOC
and have some reason to exist then just
give the whole Vulcan concept and
project over to the Android Linux people
because they're the only people now who
could really do anything with it it's
it's the only place it would actually
have any use would be for them because
they don't have their own graphics API
right so maybe as a replacement for
OpenGL or something I don't know other
than that you know on an actual actual
consumer game platforms it doesn't it
doesn't really have any point in being
there how do you recommend a beginner
get better at writing platform layers is
the only way to just write a bunch of
them to figure out how the common
patterns work yeah more or less you just
got to practice at it understand you
know sort of the stuff we've been saying
about where you put boundaries you know
you want to watch people who know how to
do it do it and think about it but Ronan
says I'm one of the Linux people please
don't give us Vulcan yeah I'm sorry
I didn't mean to wish it upon you but
yeah I don't know Linux doesn't have
another graphics API really it doesn't
have its own low-level graph say Pat
does it I mean it's got sort of the
Weiland stuff but that's not I I thought
that was just a four window compositing
like it's and I didn't think that was
like a full 3d thing so there isn't like
the equivalent of there's like d3 t12
there's metal and then there's I like
Linux and Android I don't know what
they've got you know if I don't know
what's the native thing on on Linux
really I think largely because Linux
doesn't care like Linux is a compute
server platform you know it's not really
consumer platform so it's not the kind
of question you ask I would guess for
them probably the important things are
like open CL or something
alright that looks like we don't really
have any questions on the on the code
reorganization so I think what we will
do is just close it down for now and I
will be back at 2:00 to do the second
the second stream of the day hopes you
back here for that in the meantime go
have some lunch
or whatever the appropriate meal is for
your time zone