hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show where we code a complete
game live on stream today we are going
to be doing I think I'm gonna play
around with a couple things in the
lighting right now I've gotten the
architecture to a place where I'm pretty
happy with it actually and so now we
just start working on like turning the
crank on variants and speed and so I've
got some ideas about how I want to do
that but we've got a couple of different
things I won't try there so specifically
the two things I want to try today which
I don't know if I'll get to both of them
but we'll get to both of them over the
next two days hopefully is I'd like to
try playing around with not casting the
entire hierarchy basically things that
are far away treating them as more
aggregate elements for example I'd like
to play around with that a little bit
today and then the other thing I'd like
to do is I'd like to put in something
where we can draw our hierarchy because
again right now because we still we were
still trying to lock down how we were
doing our light transport which I think
now I'm pretty happy with what I'd like
to I had never really gotten to the
point of let's look at our spatial harpy
and see if it's actually doing the work
we think it's doing and if we can
improve it etcetera we never did that
right so we just threw one in there and
we're like okay we got to put we know we
need a hierarchy in here so let's put
one in but we haven't actually gone and
really done much with it so that's
another thing that we have to do so
those are two things we're gonna be
doing today is day 429 Sauve 428 source
code is what I'm looking at here alright
and so then as of last week we had
gotten to the point where we were pretty
happy with how the light transport was
stabilizing I think we are still yeah I
think we are still using a high number
of bounces that I remember correctly
because we're in
they count hoops you can see here that
we crank the rate count up to 256 and if
we take a look at what's happening here
so this is a pretty slow running versus
gaming mouses optimized you can kind of
see that the lighting is actually pretty
stable here though with the way things
are going so if this were running at
60fps we would probably just call it
done and so the real problem here that
we're looking at is just the fact that
we can't get that stable of a variance
without the speed hit now we certainly
can just go ahead and crank up the rate
count to something like 286 and then do
like more parallelism and more optimal
calculations that would probably be fine
for this scene but then again once we
start adding more stuff into the mix it
becomes more problematic right so when
we drop the Ray count down to something
more manageable such as this and now you
can see that we are running more at like
we're running at 60 frames a second here
now and this is totally acceptable frame
rate but you can sort of see how we get
this flicker in there now that flicker
you know you could always just say that
all the lights in the game or fire and
they have a natural flicker to them you
can solve problems in tech with fiction
and that's always fine too I don't
discourage people from doing that
because hey man it's all black arts when
we're trying to do things like simulate
lighting or things like this that we
know to be intractable problems at 60
frames per second currently anyway
everything is an approximation so
whatever solution you want to use it's
fine
but at least for the time being I'm not
gonna go ahead and go that route yet
because there's still a lot more we can
do here to try and work out what we're
to try and improve the stability of the
solution and so I'd like to go ahead and
do that and so that's mainly what we're
talking about here is is going ahead and
figuring out how to continue to improve
upon that sort of that stability and
just making it more clean so a couple of
things we can do now let's talk about
what those are and the things that I
want to sort of get underway here
I'm gonna load up Milton which by the
way Milton's been awesome ever since
that they found the bug in in the ape in
the what's that thing called Penn
there's some kind of Penn thing that it
uses I think it was from papaya
originally I'm sorry I don't remember
what it was but ever since they found
the bug in that milton's been super
stable just a pleasure to use it's nuts
to think about how I don't even know can
we look out here it's nice to think
about how big this thing is is there a
way to zoom level one one one one one is
what we're on I guess it's nuts to look
at like how much stuff this thing does
it's like super good and it's very fast
like think about all this stuff that's
in here how much pen strokes there are
and it just kind of handles it all it's
just a good program I think that I don't
know sir if you did a fantastic job
getting this thing going I mean look at
all this stuff and it just kind of runs
right through it
it saves incrementally perfectly -
there's no lag on save anymore he's just
this is a good program you know it's
just a really good program look at look
at that that's great you know very very
well done anyway let's go back here here
we go
so I just want to talk about some
lighting bombs that we could make so
let's talk about a couple of these here
so one thing I talked about is
stratified sampling
let's talk about that too
Multi red sampling and number three I
think I mentioned this before it's
bi-directional so we've got a number of
different things we can be doing here
that again are not these are not
optimizations in the I'm gonna go ahead
and try to save cycles specifically on
some given algorithm sense this is more
about algorithmic optimization just can
we be doing something smarter that works
better you know and and produces a more
stable result just by doing the math
differently right or whatever so let's
talk about stratified sampling so right
now what we're doing is on any given
frame if we imagine the Hemisphere and
I'll draw it in 2d but obviously it's
actually three dimensional z-- right so
it's it's a you know it's actually a
proper hemisphere not a hema circle or a
semicircle so if you imagine we have a
surface with this normal and we go to
sample it I mentioned this briefly the
other day right now we're using pure
white noise and you know I'm gonna even
put that in quotes because we're not
even really using that if you remember
we've never really even gotten a proper
random number generator in here we just
have a table right because I just said
let's deal will deal with random number
generation later cuz we want to kind of
talk about that as a topic so you know
this we're just using this table and
that's not a very good way to do it cuz
the period of this thing is pretty short
right now we don't know that that's
necessarily a problem for us in practice
right now but that could be too so using
a proper random number generator that we
have some work guarantees about and that
has a longer period might be helpful but
even if we had proper pure white noise
that was act that we actually measured
and where nu was good
an input white noise might not be the
best thing for us for sampling the
incoming light now why the answer is
because white noise is a completely
truly random in the semantic sense of
the word so when you say random what
you're thinking about in your head is no
coherence no correlation no properties
at all right you're thinking that that
from one to the next the information
you're getting out of a random source
you can say nothing about it relative to
the previous thing right it's like
cryptographically andum miss in a sense
you're talking about something
unpredictable we can't say anything
about it now a good white noise
generator is something that is very
close to that now we know that we can't
really get true unpredictable stuff out
of a deterministic machine so unless we
use for example the Rd R and instruction
or something like this on the Intel CPU
which maybe produces real randomness I'm
not really sure they I don't think they
will tell anyone how it works so that's
I don't really know but ignoring that
fact anything we're doing that's
pseudo-random is obviously not truly
white noise it's not truly unpredictable
but its goal is to be as close to white
noise as possible as close to completely
unpredictable as possible and what does
that mean well it means that as the
number of samples you take out of the
white noise goes down right you end up
with highly potentially biased placement
on your hemisphere why because let's say
we only take two samples right well
intuitively we know we'd like to take
like one sample this way in one sample
that way ish because if we don't sample
one direction at all then we're very
likely to have variance that goes we're
just if the light source was over here
and we're shooting this way we won't see
it at all
right so coverage is kind of important
to us when we're sampling this
hemisphere we need some coverage a
little bit at least but what we know
about white noise is it's not even
remotely interested in that a truly
random sequence will just as likely pick
two things here as it will pick a thing
here in thing here because the first
first one should have no relationship to
the second one now it's not true that
maybe if you take any two it is more
likely that one will be here than then
two in there slightly more likely in
white noise because once you consider
two at a time it's different right but
once you know that one is here for
example that doesn't increase the
likelihood that one will be here here
right it's like a coin toss just because
you know one came up heads doesn't mean
the next one is now more likely to come
up tails right I know that's a little
confusing but that statistics for you
our probability I should say but the
plane is regardless of how you want to
think about the marginal probabilities
there the overall effect is that the
algorithm does not overwhelmingly prefer
an even distribution across the
hemisphere because by nature a random
distribution is not supposed to
guarantee evenness if it did it would be
much more predictable than white noise
is then randomness is right
so what stratified sampling or other
forms of biased sampling do is they say
look we may want randomness for certain
purposes the purpose we want randomness
for in this scheme is because we know
we're not going to cast an infinity of
raise or close to infinity of raise so
we know that we can't use a complete
coverage so over time we would like to
get a complete coverage by randomly
moving around the space that's what we
want the randomness for but on any given
frame in order to retain a fairly good
pick
sure of what the lighting is we don't
want all of our casts to end up going in
one direction so we want to force the
randomness to work within say
compartments of the hemisphere so that
we know we're not gonna be randomly
clumping on certain frames which will
drastically bias what we think the
lighting is on that frame versus on
another frame where the distribution may
have been more even so stratified
sampling says let's make compartments of
the hemisphere and force the white noise
to be distributed over that atmosphere
more cleanly right in a way that is less
random but perhaps better so we are
reducing the randomness in an attempt to
try and make things more consistent
right now there's two ways we can do
this as stratified sampling isn't maybe
necessarily the only word right so I've
talked about blue noise in the past so
white noise is just dart throwing
randomness I don't know I just get a
bunch of points right some of those
points are very close together some of
those points are very far apart and
that's just how it goes that's white
noise purely random blue noise on the
other hand once I throw down a dart I
restrict the ring around the dart and
say no one can throw a dart anywhere in
here right so what that gives me is it
gives me a distribution where I know
that all the points are somewhat
separated
I cannot cluster around a particular
area right blue noise is not technically
stratified sampling stratified sampling
means random within buckets so you can
still have some clumping here in a
stratified sample right or you might not
have clumping within the buckets but you
may say well I'm gonna pick something
random in this bucket so here in this
bucket and the two things in either
bucket happen to end up very close to
each other because I'm not checking
within the buckets right so stratified
sampling and blue noise are actually a
bit different technically oftentimes
stratified sampling does not indicate a
minimum
distance between points blue noise does
blue noise says no two points can be
closer than this period that's the
definition of it right this is also
called for some reason Plus on disk let
me just get these up for you
know that ya know it's a see there you
go so hmm what you can see here plays
different kinds so blue noise is the
name that's used for this pattern of
sort of random but not if you will that
has points that are required to be a
certain distance from each other and the
reason that this is an interesting
phenomenon for a lot of reasons is
because it actually came from the
retinal cells you can you can see them
saying that here see Oh Tom Mitchell is
here he was the person who originally
taught me about blue noise in fact
anyway he was an 18 to 18 t guy he then
went to UM he then went to Microsoft
Research and he's retired now I haven't
seen him in a while I tried to email him
actually 2-3 years ago and never heard
back I hope he's doing okay anyway he's
a great guy and he was doing originally
taught me about blue noise and anyway he
originally started looking into blue
noise specifically because it's the way
that your eye the cells in your eye are
set up and it helps eliminate regular
patterns because if you imagine setting
up the samples for things in your eye
however getting off-topic here but this
is interesting stuff to me if you
imagine the way that your eye works
right it's essentially like a like a
photograph plane where you've got an
image that's going through a lens like
like light that's going through a lens
and it's hitting this sort of film back
almost and the film back is your retinal
cells right and they're sort of
developing the image if you will they're
taking the light that comes in and then
your optic nerve is like counting it
right
saying like how much of that light is
hitting it if you imagine placing those
cells regularly if they were highly
regularly set up right then what happens
is as a shape moves across it but as the
light moves across it you would see
regular patterns like stair stepping and
stuff like this because you're always
gonna do sort of that that linear
filtering between the two as it moves
from one to the other you're gonna see
these sort of regular stair stepping
patterns as a shape for example but that
looks like that you'll see the sort of
gradual regular pattern of it getting
dimmer dimmer dimmer dimmer across each
row right if instead they're set up in a
blue noise pattern like this sort of
thing then because you now don't have
any particularly regular way because
it's always a little bit random you'll
always get some noise in there that
makes it so you don't see repeating
patterns because there is no way to
construct a repeating pattern unless the
thing that's coming in is the exact blue
noise complement of them of the surf of
the cells themselves right which never
happens not really possible right so
essentially what a blue noise pattern
does is it makes it so that you get the
most pleasing anti-aliasing possible on
your image because nothing can produce a
regular pattern for you to pick out um
so blue noise is in effect the holy
grail of sampling pretty much always
it's always what you would use if you
could now it's much harder to generate
than anything else because it's by
default something that only is defined
by a constraint applied to white noise
effectively it's basically saying take a
white noise pattern and remove all the
points that are too close that's kind of
how it's defined and you can generate
them in quicker ways in fact I talked
about that in my articles on how the
witness grass planting system works
which I always meant to do a second
update too because I actually updated
the witnesses
grass planting system subsequent to that
but that's the whole nother story anyway
sooo what we have here is kind of a an
argument for what we want to do
optimally which is if we could sample
these hemispheres with a nice plus on
disk or blue noise pattern we would be
the happiest possible people because
then we would sort of know that we were
maximizing our samples right maximizing
them from a perspective of not knowing
what we're aiming at now there's this
concepts of concept of important
sampling which is to say that we may not
really want to cover things uniformly it
may be that we know we should cover
things more in one direction or another
that's a separate issue that's sort of
saying that if we have information about
where we're likely to get more signal
maybe we should aim more heavily there
right and that's fine but what we're
talking about is in the absence of the
guidance or even once we have the
guidance how do we then distribute our
samples along the area that the guidance
wants us to use right and the answer is
always blue noise if you could you'd
always use a blue noise pattern in a
sample if you could again blue noise
potentially adjusted by some bias if you
know you want to shoot one area more
heavily you still want blue noise but
you just kind of shrink so they're
closer together towards one and further
away towards the other you would still
use blue noise because it's always
better pretty much you never really want
white noise so given that fact how would
we do this in practice how would we get
something that was gonna do the
stratified sampling well we've got two
options one is we can really do blue
noise and if we want to do blue noise
the cost there is that we can only have
a limited number of patterns the other
is that we can do stratified sampling
then we can do random every frame now
what do I mean by this well let's
suppose we want to do stratified
sampling it's trivial right all we have
to do is define how we're going to you
know talk about quadrants let's say we
divide the hemisphere into four pieces
and we just do white noise in each piece
right to white noise samples in each
piece there's some free stratified
sampling right maybe we think a little
further and we say well we've got a cone
that's facing sort of outwards like the
main cone of interest and then we've got
sort of the the area around the cone so
maybe we shoot you know say eight if we
do sixteen rays maybe we shoot eight out
the cone randomly white noise and then
we do you know four around the the I'm
sorry eight around the cone by just
picking white noise around each of the
octants right so it's pretty easy to
imagine how we would implement
stratified sampling it's not much
different than what we have now you just
throw it in there and go okay rather
than just say pick any random thing on
the hemisphere we're just gonna say pick
something close to a particular
direction on the hemisphere with white
noise and I forget so a stratified
sampling is for you trios how we do it
but blue noise it's very expensive to
create much more expensive to create so
we probably can't create it every frame
but what we can do is say what if we
created let's say 16 different blue
noise patterns maybe and then what we
did is just rotated them or something
right
rotate them randomly per place that
we're sampling you know because a blue
Tomi's pattern you can rotate it all any
way you want
it'll still be blue noise so we could do
something like that right spin it around
the normal those sorts of things and it
doesn't cost as much as you would think
because it's only costs one rotation
like all we have to do is construct the
coordinate frame for the blue noise in a
rotated fashion which would cost us like
one sign in one cosign which is a little
expensive you know but it's not the end
of the world so you know we could
imagine doing blue noise by picking a
random angle of rotation so that part's
white noise and won't destroy our blue
noise pattern and does inject a fair bit
of randomness and then we have a few
patterns if we need more than that we
have you know a couple different
patterns let's say I don't know maybe we
don't and we just have
we just use randomness on it right so
there are ways we can get blue noise
into a real annoy real time algorithm
even though we probably don't want to
actually create the blue noise every
frame because that might introduce too
much overhead into the system we
certainly can still get the benefits of
blue noise that for at least some of
them if we're willing to do some pre
computation and a little bit of setup so
which of those that we want to do I
don't know but you know those are our
options
we could probably try the stratified
sampling one first because it's much
easier and then think about the blue
noise one maybe a little bit later if we
think it's worth it right all right
let's go to multi rate sampling so multi
risk sampling is and unfortunately I
come through ho for the area I would
have used to illustrate it my bad
pretend this isn't here so multi risk
sampling is just saying well okay so you
know I've got these reflectors and I
want to compute the ludie for a point
well okay so I do a raycast and I find
that I missed these reflectors right so
I'm in this part of spatial hierarchy
and now I got a test against all of
these right cuz I missed these two here
if I hit one of these great I could stop
early maybe but now I got to test all
the guys in this thing right well what
if instead of doing that we just said
look when you get far when you get a
certain distance away let's say this is
you know maybe this is the sphere here
or something when you get a certain
distance away like if the center of the
thing is further than a certain amount
from the point just use an aggregate
understanding of the lighting for this
region as your output rather than
testing the things in it right just just
compute an aggregate value I don't know
how just by an average of the light in
the region right not my problem I don't
know how we're gonna do it we're gonna
do something that produces an average
value for each of our bounding boxes and
rather than descend through the spatial
hierarchy we will only
descend into ones that are close enough
and ones that aren't close enough we
just use the aggregate value as the
output done right so that's something we
could consider now I don't know how much
it will affect our results but it's an
example of something we could do
and this improves our variance
potentially in two ways actually the
first thing it does is it reduces
variance because now you're using a
smooth average of a number of reflectors
which means that it doesn't matter
whether I was shooting this ray or this
ray they're both gonna get the same
result back from the sky right and that
reduces variance because now you're not
talking about missing this guy and
hitting this right so that you get two
very different results based on a very
small and angular change again
introducing variance in the system what
we're saying is look we know we're never
gonna shoot enough rays to really
capture what's happening out here
because it's so far away we'd have to
shoot tons of rays a really tight angle
to capture all that lighting let's just
figure out what generally that is
sending back and use that and this is
very similar to the concept of voxel
cone tracing right which we know is used
in high-end engines to do you know
reflection kind of stuff and bounce
lighting it's very similar to that voxel
cone tracing concept it's saying look
when we get further away from things we
don't need to know really specifically
where we were casting because generally
speaking it's a tiny ant part of our
hemisphere just give us the general
light that's coming back that's what we
wanted anyway and we're just never gonna
shoot enough rays to capture it so if we
can just smooth out those regions and
just get the result comes back with one
ray it's pretty good right so that's
what we can do with that bi-directional
sampling finally is just the observation
that right now what we're doing is we're
saying look we find a path to transfer
light between two surfaces right now and
then we only use one direction of that
we just say okay
we know that lights gonna get
transferred from this point to this
point why not just say look it transfers
the other way - right and the reason
again that reduces our variance is
because for the same number of Ray casts
we get twice the amount of light
transport so it's as if we cast twice as
many Ray's effectively right now it's a
little bit cheeky of me to say that
reduces our variance we don't really
know that reduces our variance actually
it could increase our parents for all I
know because there's nothing that says
it's gonna really decrease the variance
because that transport could be an
unlikely path in which case counting it
twice
is worse than counting at once in a
sense right so we don't really know that
I reserved variance but what you can
generally say is that if in general we
have set up the rest of the scheme to
reduce variance in general then using
the paths more efficiently should in
theory over the grand scheme of things
reduce the variance because we're just
getting more Ray casts effectively at
that point so if we generally expect an
individual ray cast to reduce our
variance then we would expect doubling
the number of ray casts we're
effectively getting to reduce our
variance in general as opposed to make
exacerbating right on average again not
an any given ray may do the opposite of
that so it's hard to say definitively
that that's the case right okay
so I think that is most of what I wanted
to talk about and so those are the
things that I'd like to explore now we
don't really necessarily have any way of
predicting how these are going to affect
us because again lighting is one of
those massive problems that's just very
amorphous we don't know anything about
what the solution looks like unless
we're casting you know millions and
millions of rays and so when we're
talking about casting such a small
number of rays it's really more of a
hack at that point and we have to
explore our options in a very
experimental way we don't really know
when you get time to casting so few rays
you don't really know what you're
dealing with in terms of the math right
you can sort of try to do your best to
approximate the real answer but at some
level what you're really aiming for it's
not the real answer anyway it's sort of
the smoothest answer that still has
effects you cared about right so I think
it's best to kind of remember that we're
in that sort of uncharted area so yeah
the other thing I can do right now is
also say if we take a look at world mode
and I'm gonna go to screen index here if
I crank up the number of screens a
little bit just so we have that that
existing slowness you can see that that
in this case where we're running it at a
much slower frame rate here when we get
more of these into the mix and if I take
a look at the profiler right you can see
that we've got 81% of time spent in
compute like propagation right so even
in the case where we're only casting 16
Ray's per per attempt you can see that
this still is pretty costly right once
you get enough stuff in there so the
thing that I'd like to try first I think
is to see what I can do
if the multi-resolution stuff just
coming interested to play without a
little bit I'd like to see if we can get
the multi-resolution stuff working then
from there we'll start looking at the
stratified sampling and then finally
when we're done with everything I think
I'll try to add some bi-directional Ness
to it that's my current thinking anyway
and then once we're done with all of
that we will be able to move on to the
final step of lighting which is
distributing and using our lighting
points effectively which i think will be
a really nice touch because it'll smooth
out things like these walls instead of
them having different lighting across
them they'll have a nice uniform light
across them which I think we want our
games look is supposed to be kind of
averting so at some level I guess I'm
not 100% sure that's what we want but I
do suspect it's what we want because I
think we want the art
to emphasize the blockiness not the
lighting necessarily to emphasize the
blockiness if that makes sense but you
know that's obviously up to us we can
always decide not to smooth it and use
blockier lighting if we decide that that
is a nicer look for the game for
whatever reason so anyway I think that's
where we're at so let's go ahead and
take a look at how we might do that so
the simplest way to do that is to go
ahead and take a look at these lighting
systems here we've got this lighting
block and in it it's kind of got a bunch
of information right it's got a ref C
and an emission and all this stuff right
now
those don't get used if you're an
aggregate lighting block so if you were
one of the lighting blocks that's just
used for sorting what you can see here
is inside raycast recurse then what's
going to happen is as you're testing the
phases of the Ray what you can see here
is that you know in the case where
there's two separate places where this
can happen in the case where you're
inside a particular box then obviously
you
to recurse and that is always gonna be
correct right like if you're casting
from within a box are always gonna go
below it so we don't really need to look
at that case but let's look at this case
in the case where we're ray casting
against the box here then what you can
see is if we find that we hit a
particular one of the Box faces then we
recurse into it if the box has children
now what I'm proposing here is we say
well okay we've got a t-value right what
we could do instead is say if that T
value is greater than a certain distance
away
don't recurse down the box right just
don't do it if the T value is is too far
away let's just pretend we hit a box
here and have that box be have that box
be used in some other fashion right I
that's all I'm saying now the problem
with this that we see is that we sort of
have two different once we have two
different types of boxes it becomes a
little harder to figure out what the
light transport is exactly and there's
two ways that we can do this one way you
can do this is just to set up synthetic
lighting for these lighting boxes and I
think that might be the best way to do
it it's hard to say but it might be
right and and so you know one way we
could do this to just say look let's
just set up synthetic light indices so
much like we add lighting boxes we'll
add lighting points as well maybe one
light point per side of the box right
and then when we build the box we will
set those lighting points to be averages
or something like this that allow us to
send out the right average lighting out
that direction right you know just just
basic basic simple some kind of simple
thing like that
then what we would do is when we return
one of these we just return the we just
returned the box right here it's the
same with this so it's almost instead of
box child count it would just be an and
it's like box child count and we're
close enough to the box then the curse
otherwise just return it right uh and
that seems like a pretty compelling
solution to me because it keeps the
algorithm very simple none of the code
really has to change the only thing we
need to do to some of the other parts of
the system is back where we actually do
the lighting test routines there are
some places where we loop over our point
counts all we really have to do here is
make sure this point count is not
modified so we'll add points as in an
extended sense so we sort of have an
original like we have an original box
count we'd have an original point count
right and we would just know that there
these additional points after it that
we're assuming you're not going to be
involved so I think we can just do that
let me just verify that fact but in here
for example inside compute light
propagation what you can see here is
when we go through this algorithm all we
do is we say look did we get a box back
if we got a box back we just do our
thing right
so really that's all we have to do and
it I mean yeah that would be all there
is to it so I think that's pretty much
it there's nothing there's nothing else
that we would have to do and yeah it
feels pretty straightforward to me so I
feel like that's the right solution to
this when we come in through split box
and what we could do here is just have
you know a you sixteen point count and a
you 16
you know extended point count and so
when we come through here and we set the
point count I could also say all right
the extended point count equals the
point count but then I can add past the
point count as we go so yeah so off we
go you know we do this this point counts
it you know we see the points and do
whatever we want to there and then when
we come in to build spatial partition
for lighting we just
add points so in here for example you
can see us creating boxes you know
here's an example of us creating a box
right where we do add box storage and
what we could do is add points now as
well right so you know we could just add
six points or something like that when
we add one of these boxes right so maybe
inside split box that's what happens
maybe that seems pretty fair I guess
take a look here yeah so you can see
here where we call split box recursively
we basically create the box here and
then we add the two boxes to it and then
in the case otherwise we just record the
box references here right
so either we use the boxes that if we
get passed or we put them in here right
so what we could do for that is I think
just again say alright if the source
count is greater than four then we know
this is going to be a well I guess in
any I guess in any case where we call
split box actually we're gonna want this
so I guess this just happens period
yeah I think this just happens period so
in any case where we called split box
we're gonna need to create these yeah so
inside here we have when we do build
space partition for lighting inside here
where we do our root box you can see us
get the root box here and then we split
the root box so that means every box
that is an on that's not an actual leaf
node that has actual light information
will come through this path and when it
gets down to here I think we just want
to do it right here so at the very end
when we know exactly what our child
stuff is then we can compute the
lighting I think at that point so let's
go ahead and do that
so here what we're gonna do is compute
the aggregate lighting for this
container box right partition box and so
the parent box now you know should have
it should have a light this light index
here should be just garbage there's
nothing in it because never it's never
been used and never gonna get used in
the current version I don't what we're
gonna do is now start using that right
so we want to just set these lighting
indices to sort of be incremental and
this is kind of a dumb thing but it's
just what we have to do so we've got 1 2
3 4 5 6 of them and what we're gonna do
again is just set them like so right in
fact we could do this a little more
efficiently without actually doing the
back reference by just doing this
something like that so we can say our
light index equals the extended point
count something like this and then at
the end
right so we do something like that which
just assigns one light point per you
know per side so one light point on the
top bottom one light point on each of
the four sides east west north south so
there's the entire assignment right
along the parent box so we do something
that then we and I guess this one
technically we don't need one for the
six the six is just the terminators so
we just assign a light zero one two
three four five like so and then we're
done so now this has light points but we
need to actually compute the aggregate
version of each of those right so we
need to seed those with some actual
information because now if we look in
here there's information for each of
those points we haven't set it though to
anything that we don't we don't know any
of these values and we need to know
these values for those points in order
to do anything useful with them right so
if you take a look in here all of the
initial points all got seeded with
something and and our points that we've
added will not have been seeded with
anything and so if you take a look at
this code here we need a way of
replicating that for each of these light
points right but it's not this right we
need to set all these values but we need
to have a different way of setting them
because this is not you know this is not
useful right so we need to figure out a
way to set all these values and luckily
we pretty much know at least one simple
way to do it now there could be more
it's that you could imagine a lot of
different ways of of doing this
particular thing because the way that
I'm gonna propose doing it now is
actually not very accurate and probably
not very good and so we probably want to
investigate ways of doing it better
you know I'm gonna just start with a
simple one so what I would say first is
look here's what's happening we've got
some boxes and now we want to enclose
those boxes in another box we did that
spatial partition wise so that's all
fine but what we have to do now is say
ok we want there to be a point let's say
here and we want it to encapsulate how
much light is generally leaving this box
in this direction so the simplest
possible way to do this is let's just
take all of the surfaces that are facing
that direction and average them together
right really really simple really really
stupid not very accurate but there you
go
right entirely plausible so we can do
that another thing we could do is weight
it by how close they are to this so
things that are really close to this
will contribute more because you have a
higher chance if you're coming in
through here of hitting them before
hitting something else because they're
closer so we could wait by distance as
well both of those two things so I might
do that right I might wait by the
distance but then you know otherwise
it's just an average that's the simplest
way I think it's pretty good way it
doesn't cost us very much to do right it
will not affect the runtime of this
routine hardly at all there is another
way we could do it and this way is much
more involved but if we wanted to be
accurate we could do it and what that is
is let's run the Ray casting recursively
right so let's take the things that are
inside a box which we know is something
around you know 4 to 8 I think I'm not
sure what a requirement is
no it's zero to four so if anything has
more than four things inside it it
splits them right so we come through
here the root box has you know look
whatever it is 100 boxes entered or
something like this says if it's greater
than four then you need to split them
into two halves right and create two
boxes that have each 50 and then those
will get split and so on
so actually it has between 2 &amp; 4 right
it has between 2 &amp; 4 and it at any given
time right and it's a it's a KD tree
here looks like because it takes a dim
dimension index so it basically runs
through and it's gonna split it's gonna
look you know like this
that sort of thing depending on the
distribution of things so if we know
that we only have two things you know or
four things per box you could imagine
running a little ray cast it just cast
an additional safe 64 rays or something
around to see who can see which parts of
the external box and then you just
actually do a ray cast to figure out how
much light generally is hitting this
thing we could do that right totally
possible I'm not going to do it because
it just adds more computation to our
system and we don't know that it's
necessary but if we really wanted to try
and get an accurate estimation of the
light that was leaving that's what we
would want to do and so we may find that
this is just not in that averaging is
just not an adequate substitute for
actual light transport in our game most
of the time in which case we may have to
do something more fancy that does cost
more but still not as much as actually
doing the ray cast entirely on
everything all the time because once
when you subdivide again it's much
cheaper to do a ray cast on four boxes
than it is to do one on hundreds of
boxes okay so let's try the averaging
version first because I think that's the
simplest so we're just going to do that
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
step through the light indices for the
box here so I'm going to start with the
surface index and I'm gonna loop through
all the surfaces of the box like so
right so this is exactly equivalent
really to how we're stepping through it
here and so I do actually also want to
get the surface information out as well
just so that I can correctly set the
location of this point because people
are using that location now it doesn't
really need to be set because since
we're only using that position as an
average it doesn't really matter as much
but again you know there's
there's implications right in terms of
how the normals work out and and that
sort of thing so I just I'm gonna try
and set it accurately anyway all right
so if we come through here we need to
love which lighting point we're setting
and unfortunately for us that's pretty
easy it's just gonna be the light index
for this surface because there's only
one surface so all we have to do is just
pull out whatever that one was what we
assigned up here and that's the one that
we're gonna set we also know what
surface are on but because we know that
we're the parent box here so we can just
use this information directly and then
we've got it
setting the point is pretty trivial all
we have to do is just take the surface P
here and not modify it right because I
believe the surface P is just the
correct P in this case right the
reflected color here is just going to be
the average of the ones underneath us I
believe so we just need to loop through
the boxes and average them oops let's
also get our light index out here I'm
gonna call this a sine light index just
to avoid confusion of what's going on
there and I'm gonna go ahead and get
this light index out here so we can use
it everywhere
that gives us a little bit in there
right so when we go through this what I
want to do now is say okay I've got my
individual lighting system now I want to
average all the rest of the stuff is
just gonna be averaged together now I
don't need to know average I don't need
to know values for any of the other
things because I don't
Wow so I'm not sure what we would want
to do with average direction to light I
think it just doesn't matter cuz it
should never get used really so I think
what I could say is look some of these
things just don't matter so what I'm
gonna do is just set it to be directly
outward from the surface right because I
don't think we care similarly like
accumulated weight and stuff like that I
don't think we ever care what those get
set to an accumulated PPS we don't care
either because I'm pretty sure all we
care about is a mission and initial also
I'll keep these cleared but I don't even
know that they would ever get played
with so we'll look at that a little
later when we're done with things and
see do we care what these get set to but
mostly I think these don't matter
because since we don't ever use the
results of this light and we don't cast
from it it shouldn't really matter right
but these other folks here these need to
be average so the reflected color the
emission and the initial those are the
ones we want to look at people
underneath us and figure out what they
should be based on that so that puts us
into a loop here over our children and
you can see us up here with that
information right
so we have the child index I guess we
know it this way so we know that this is
our first child index we know that our
child index our children run this way
like so so we can go through our child
indices here and just do our summation
over all of our children that may only
be two children but again I'm doing this
in a more general case here because we
haven't investigated this facial Harkey
much yet we may not want only two
children per box we may want more like
eight children per box or something for
all we know so I'd like to have this
routine be flexible and be able to work
no matter how many children are in a box
whether there's four or two or eight or
sixteen or a hundred it should just work
because we're gonna want to play around
the spacial hierarchy a little bit later
as we tune the lighting and I don't want
to have this routine break at that point
so yeah so now what I want to do here
and I guess I can pull this out because
really that's happening at the end when
we assign what I want to do now is
create those averages so we have the ref
see we have the emission PBS and we have
the initial PBS again I don't know that
initial PPS is really going to matter
here I don't think it really gets used
emission PPS has really looked at use so
we may not have to do that one either
but I'm gonna compute it anyway just
because we don't know yet and we - well
it's not gonna cost much to do and we
can always eliminate it later if it
turns out we don't care so what I want
to do is set these based on the average
and we're gonna use the same technique
we've used everywhere else you want to
do something like that which is that we
want to do the reflected the emission
the initial all as weighted sums that we
then undo the weighting you know we we
normalized for the weighting at the end
based on the accumulated weight so we've
got a total weight here and then what
we'll do is compute the inverse weight
at the end to give us our normalization
coefficient right so then once we're in
here we know we want to take all of
those surfaces that are on the same
plane the same direction as ours
and we want to take those services and
and basically we want to take all of
those services and average them together
potentially based on the distance that
we are from them right so we know our
point P is here we know that we're ly
getting other point piece that we're
going to sum and we can take the
distance between them and use that as a
scaling coefficient right so we want all
of these to start out zero
so all these are going to start out zero
then we go through the child indices one
by one and we're gonna sum up the points
that they have on this particular
surface so we need a child point index
here and we're going to loop over that
and then do that summation so again we
need a distance or you know a weight
that we'll compute here we'll add the
total 8 like so and then we will sum
each of these based on that weight so
when we take a look at what these values
are here where we do the various weight
summations here and we do the the total
weight with the summation what we need
to do is we need to have a way of
accessing the correct child points but
after that it should be fairly
straightforward because we know each of
these points
has that information on it so you can
see the lining point here has like the
ref C so I can just say like okay the
child point ref C goes in there
we know this solution emission PP s for
the child point index gives us what we
want there and the initial people yes to
checkpoint index gives us what we want
there so that's pretty straightforward
and then we get the total weight and off
we go
so this is the entire structure of their
teen all we really need to do is know
how to find this point and so in order
to do that we need to get the box that
we're talking about here the child box
so we need a lighting box and for that
we're gonna have to grab the box out of
the box array here right exactly the way
that we were doing it right here
so that gives us the channel box in
question and then once we have the child
box we know which what it's child
indices are by just looking here right
so we know that the child point the
point index that we're going to start
with is going to be the child box light
index for whichever surface we're on
right so if we're on surface three we
get that we start at that weight index
and then we know that the child point
index has to go from there to the one
that's in front of it right so the the
next one in the array we subtract out
the previous one that gives us our count
right oh no what am i this is just this
we know we go until the next one in the
array so that's really all we need to do
there we'll loop over those points now
we can get our actual child point out
this gives us the child point and once
we have the child point we can compute
the weight however we wish I'm gonna use
that same function we used before which
is to say we're just going to take the
distance between the two points and use
that as a divisor so I'm going to take
the point that we're talking about and
the child point and I'll just use the
distance squared right so the the leg
square between those points is how I'll
weight them and that's really it that's
the end of the story
I don't know how Add Box Storage got
deleted there must have been typos we
certainly didn't mean to and these are
you 16 so I believe that now when we run
this we are now computing aggregate box
lighting now again one of the problems
is we don't actually know that we are
and when we look here you know you see
the lighting solution all we see is the
total lighting solution we don't get to
see that spatial hierarchy um so what
I'd like to do is I'd like to go ahead
and see if we can now move to you know
again computing the lighting now using
that our information is going to be
trivial inside here all we're gonna do
is just do a return if T force this case
we're gonna add like one less than here
and that's all we'll have to do to use
the multi-resolution lighting sample so
it's great right but if we do that maybe
it just works brilliantly all of a
sudden and it's fantastic
great yay for us but chances are it
won't work perfectly I mean right we're
dealing with complex stuff with a lot of
inter relations and
we're not even gonna know if we computed
those values right you know and so what
I think we need to do is we just have to
have a way of showing our space
spaceship spatial hierarchy in more
detail and in order to do that we're
gonna need some way of in order to do
that we're gonna need some way of sort
of stepping through it somehow right and
so what I want to do is just add some
simple ways we could do that hopefully
maybe inside out put Lennie points for
example so in output lighting points
that's the thing that gets run when I
hit the f1 key so that's this thing so
what I'm thinking is maybe we can use
this to our advantage here so let's
suppose we did output Lennie points and
we were going to do it this way where we
go through the boxes and you can see
this kind of does a nice it does nice
work that way it goes through each of
the boxes and sort of puts the
information out there now why that's
timed I don't know because it's not
normally called but I guess let's take a
look here you know it doesn't it doesn't
really take any time and it wouldn't be
called normally anyway right output
learning points is it's right here and
it just doesn't get called normally so I
don't really care about this ping of
time function I'm rid of that and what
I'm going to do here is I'm going to go
ahead and say that this is going to have
a recursive function now
and what I want to do is I want to make
it so that inside here where we output
one of these boxes we can actually
choose to or not to descend into the sub
boxes of that box that's my general idea
here so what we're gonna do is we're
gonna say output letting points recurse
on this particular box and then we're
gonna have a depth function here let's
say and what I'm gonna do is say well if
the depth value is zero then I'm going
to do the thing that we were doing
before right
so we'll we'll do the the the push of
the lighting elements if the depth is
zero
but if the depth is not zero then what
I'm gonna do is just call this on the
sub components right so we have one
other problem I wanna deal with which is
that we may not have any sub components
if you don't have any second photos then
I will let this case happen so if the
child count is zero meaning I'm sorry if
the child count yeah if the child count
is zero then I know that we can't
recurse on this box it doesn't have any
sub boxes so we'll do it but if it does
have children and the depth value that
we're passing in is high enough then
what I'm going to do is I'm going to say
okay let's continue down
and so all I'm gonna do here is take the
boxes and I'm gonna do the plus cloud
index here and again we also need to
take into account whatever the first one
is but that's it
and then we're gonna do is a minute past
depth minus 1 so that it will continue
to reduce the depth as we recurse
downwards and that's all right that's it
so then what I'm going to do is I'm
going to call output letting points
recurse you know and I guess I don't
know why I removed time function of this
I guess we can still time the whole
thing you want to I don't know why we
would but we could and so what I'm going
to do here is just pass the things we
need which is the group in the solution
and then I'm gonna pass the root box and
the depth right so we actually I do need
to pass these two things in addition to
our two operative parameters the Box in
the depth so the box in this case is
going to be the root box all right it's
gonna be this one and the depth is going
to be in this case just everything right
we're just gonna let's just just do
everything right so I don't know how
many of these we have but we know it's
not going to be more than that because 2
to the 256 is more than like the memory
in the machine so it doesn't matter so
inside here we just have two things get
the element with that we need that's
just these constants that we had
specified so that needs to go out here
we got the white bitmap that comes out
of the command Q here that again also
come through
[Music]
these I suppose only have to happen and
we're actually outputting as well and
then we need to pass the group here and
the solution and in theory now if I
haven't messed anything up this should
still do exactly what did before it's
just doing it recursively well or it's
not so yeah if I messed anything up part
turns out to be important um so let's
see what's going on here if the depth
equals zero what do we pass for depth
it's very high so that won't happen
or the box trial count equals zero which
should not be the case then we come in
through here otherwise assuming we have
children and we go through each of them
that should be right shouldn't it
I couldn't tell you why that wasn't
working but it's definitely not working
let's take a look at that I'm gonna step
on in there obviously it's something
pretty stupid but sometimes the only way
to tell what you did stupid is to just
go go on into the debugger and see what
you did stupid the debugger or stupid
finder what happened there so reason
that my breakpoint didn't hit oh this is
that okay this is that new thing where
Visual Studio 20 whatever this is 2017
does not do breakpoints in the same
place as it used to it does them there
yeah I do not know what the deal is that
but they decide to change that um so
okay when we break here on this line
output loading points recurse let's take
a look at what's going on here so we're
gonna start at the root box index which
is set to box zero apparently is that
correct
so that doesn't seem right because ad
box reference should have
ah right right right these are in
directed ah yes
hmm always fun so yeah we have to
actually in direct those I never love
that but yeah we don't have any other
really way of doing it right we have to
do everything through the Box table so
both of those routines have to do that
see I told you we would have got
something wrong if we didn't visualize
it and we did I think John Carmack is
the person who said time spent making
visualizations has never wasted
something close to that uh so I believe
we have our utility function for this so
we really just have to use it it's
pretty straightforward it's just that
right so that's pretty easy to do but we
have to do that everywhere so in here we
also have to do that so when we go to
get this one we would have to do the
same thing right so we need to do like a
get box here and then in our building
routine same thing applies right
yep
alright so in the building routine the
same thing applies just making sure
so in here for example where we go to do
our summation when we do a child box we
have to do a get box like so right I
think that's the only thing that we did
stupidly
I probably don't need to be in debug
mode anymore but it's just yeah there we
go
so what I want to do now is besides
turning us back to release mode build
what I'd like to do is I'd like to go
ahead and figure out how to make the
lighting drawn this now that I have a
way of doing this recursively I'd like
to go ahead and allow make there be a
way to control that depth
luck with the keyboard right so I can
sort of step down the depth and step up
the depth to see what our
multi-resolution lighting actually looks
like which you know would give us a
little bit more of an idea of what's
going on so inside the lighting solution
I'm just gonna have a little debug value
here and what I want to do is I want to
make it so that when we do this depth
here I'm gonna use debug box draw depth
and so what should happen now is that
should be set to zero right because we
never initialize it so when I do this we
should just have like the the outer box
basically should be the only thing on
the table right and what you can see
here is the this is the outer box right
and we we ideally want these elements to
be bigger because the box itself is
bigger or we're never gonna see it right
so what I want to do here is I want to
adjust this information this element
with element height to be proportional
to the size of the actual box so that it
makes some sense right so if we want if
we were imagining that it was two five
was the size that was correct for
whatever those box sizes were we want to
make sure that we think about what that
means so it probably meant that those
boxes were one point something long and
not sure how long they were but we want
to sort of have something that's going
to be proportional to the box size so
what I'm going to say here is I'm going
to say all right let's look at the box
itself and how big its surface was and
that's what we'll assign these points to
but that's that's how big the points
will get assigned to be so if we take a
look at the box surface call light box
surface so if we take a look at this guy
right here we've got the half width and
the half height what I'm gonna do is
just take those values and probably just
divide them again by two right just to
make them a little smaller than that and
that'll serve for the moment anyway as
our understanding of how big we want
these things to be now I could also make
it proportional how many lights there
are but at the moment I'm not going to
all right so here's our root box and so
this MMus encapsulate the entire letting
solution and now what I'd like to do is
be able to get sort of lower down into
it again if I wanted to I could make
this a little more accurate potentially
by again using that light point count so
I could say something like you know
point count equals
that which is the number of points on
the surface and then I could say size
ratio equals fair points or 1.0 or
something what do I really want to say
there so maybe Oh 1.8 I don't know
something like that and then I could say
well if the point count is greater than
one so there's more than one point then
we'll just divide the size ratio by that
point count because we don't really know
what else we would do necessarily it's
probably not the best way to do this but
it's good enough for now and then we'll
just say that we have a size ratio that
multiplies these here and that's just
our sort of poor way of getting some
related size and so now when we look at
the box we can actually see here's our
thing the white is not involved in lying
solution because it's too far away from
the visible area there's our lighting
box which is what we would expect right
and there's the sum amount of lighting
now the first thing that I notice here
is the lighting on this box isn't
fabulous I don't know maybe it's not as
bad as I think but there could be some
bugs in here it does correctly seem to
give more weight to here so you can kind
of see that where the light is it
actually is a little bit brighter so I
don't know maybe it's not wrong but it
does seem like over on this side it
should be darker than it is and it's not
so I'm not sure about that maybe we've
got the weighting information incorrect
here or maybe something else is busted
but I think it's probably worth checking
that a little bit and figuring out
what's going on there because it could
be that something's busted now we'll get
a little bit more information about
whether something is busted now as I go
and add the ability for us to adjust
that value so what I'm gonna do here is
along with where we have our F keys
pressed what we can do here is again add
in some F key information maybe f5 and
f6 to allow us to step that lighting in
and out so here on the lighting solution
what we want to do is what's that called
solution
I don't remember test lighting so what I
want to do here is inside that test
lighting I want to take the debug box
draw depth and I want to modify it so if
we hit f5 if this is greater than zero
then I just want to subtract it and in
the other case I just want to add to it
and that's it that's all I want to do
and now in theory what we should be able
to do is use a five and a six so if a to
five nothing should happen because we
should be at the lowest level ready if I
hit a six we should be able to see our
next two boxes down and then so on and
so forth
and so what you can see here is I
definitely think we've got bugs in here
because these don't seem like fair
representations of the lighting right so
if I toggle back and forth and you take
a look at what lighting elements are
being summed here while this does look
like a box that correctly in caps like
this there's definitely some lighting
here and yet the lighting on this well
yeah it's just I mean it just doesn't
seem to make a lot of sense does it I
mean those are the boxes that are
included here and somehow this boxes
says that all of the things inside it
have no light at all but yet you can see
that there's light in them right and so
it seems like maybe we're only getting
the emission value here and no reflected
value at all but we should be accounting
the reflecting value from last frame
right I mean in fact if you look at it
it's very clearly giving us that because
look at where the lights are here's
lights that are emitting and when I go
ahead here and start to put these
together you can see that the boxes that
don't have emitters have nothing right
so I think we've got a bug where we're
only counting emission and we're not
counting secondary emission so
transmitted emission and so let's take a
look at like what's happening there or
why that's happening so that we can
understand a little bit better so when
we're doing our recursive output you can
see we do accumulated PPS and emission
PPS are the two things we add together
here and so what do we need to do I
guess so that that's probably the
problem since we're cold setting that
well I don't know if that's true let's
go ahead and look so we know that
accumulated PPS is going to be nothing
we know that admission PPS is going to
be whatever started out as right so that
explains the results for seeing if
emission PPS never got modified let's
see what happens so here you can see
that we sum our emission PPS we sum our
initial PPS here and then I guess the
problem is that's actually the value
that we want to be drawing right it's
the initial PPS that we actually wanted
so I think what we probably have to do
here and this sort of answers our
question is the accumulated PPS kind of
has to be set to the initial PPS as well
I guess yeah I don't know any other way
to do it and that I guess should draw
more fairly what's happening here
so again here's that initial box here's
what we're looking at in terms of the
lighting solution there so there's the
initial box and let's go ahead and step
down
it does seem a little weird right I mean
doesn't
it doesn't really seem like a fair
average to me
like where is that light coming from
you know why is that suddenly pure
bright
is it because there's a light in there
that's getting averaged all of a sudden
I guess that is why
so let's try it let's just see if it's
fair if we don't draw that because
that's not really relevant I suppose
so I guess what I'll say here is let's
not add that in unless this is a leaf
box does that fix that problem all right
that does not seem to fix that problem I
do that right so we're drawing the
lighting points we start with the
accumulated PPS if the child account of
a box is zero then its emission PPS is
included otherwise the mission PPS is
not included right
so I mean you know I can and I can
double-check this by just saying look we
never at it it's just not even in there
yeah so so in that case we're still
getting sort of the accumulated values
themselves are blown out in that
summation which just seems weird right
cuz these are averages and so especially
when they're not taking into account
that a mission people yes so something
seems busted here let's see why that's
happening so everything that we some is
definitely multiplied by the wait
right the ref see the emission and the
initial they all get normalized so I'm
not sure why we would be getting that
sort of aggressive over-counting there I
guess since I mean given that the value
is so much higher it's possible that it
just is naturally dominating the average
I guess but that doesn't I don't know if
I really believe that you know
it seems a little far-fetched
I suppose part of it could be that maybe
the fall-off is too steep I mean we
could be we could try doing actual
length but again I'm not really sure
not sure what a good way to approach
that would be debugging wise because it
definitely seems wrong to me but it
could be that I'm just misunderstanding
something as well
it could be that they're just so bright
they dominate the average I could be
willing to believe that it's just I
don't really want to assume that that's
true and then have that turn out to be a
bad bug that's in there that we're just
missing right so I don't know so here's
what I'll say we don't know much time of
I want to say that let's just assume we
need to do a little bit more work on
that still some not 100% happy with that
but that's okay so what I'd like to do
here is just go ahead and and finish the
part that I was going to say before
which is let's just go ahead and use
that now
and see what difference that makes so
here where we do if box child count what
we'll do is we'll say okay and close
enough right and so what we can do here
is now introduce an expression - close
enough that we'll make it so that we
don't recurse if something is too far
away okay so here we're doing our
lighting and we're doing it that way
where we always use everything and now
I'm going to just try adding in an
expression that will make it so that we
won't do that right so if we say that
well okay let's suppose that tier a is
less than some value is how we're gonna
do that I don't know what the value
should be I have no idea let's say that
the value has to be six meters or
something like this
in order for us to recurse now we should
get a very different result from the
system in theory although I guess I
don't actually know if that's quite far
enough but you can imagine us playing
with this value now to see what the
difference is
okay so let's see here is our total ray
count it's I'm sorry a ray cast box
count it's
1 million I think want to be able to see
these at the same time I can't do that
multi-monitor all right so it's 1
million ish right here's if it's just 2
meters away there you go so that drops
it down it doesn't drop it down as much
as I would have thought though put it
back up to 10 so the effects are smaller
than I would have thought they were
although that could just be because
we're in not as big of a space like we
you know we're still for whatever reason
this particular creation here did not
really yeah
didn't really create a very wide room I
could I could go through and oh you know
why we can make the room real big
actually can't wait so let's suppose I
just do a screen index of one but I make
the room like 32 by 32 or something does
that work
it's not 2-minute we never really did
the world creation stuff that we need to
do in order to make sure that we can
like the world building stuff is still a
bit busted but okay there we go
there's a much larger room oh that's a
very large room so there's a much larger
room you can see the area that this is
the box that we've just arbitrarily set
up for lighting so the area outside it
doesn't get lighting and off we go
so at the moment there's our raycast box
count I'm gonna turn this off
I just sang oops didn't mean to do that
then to just make it be true
and if I look at the total ray can't
cast box count here which I think that
is the thing that comes through here
right we increment this every time
through yeah
so if I crank that number down quite a
bit we should cast a lot fewer boxes
right well I don't know about a lot here
but so from one point 1 million why are
we getting I don't know why we're
getting that it's really annoying
so that number just doesn't decrease
very much so I feel like something weird
is happening
because
I guess unless our spacial hierarchy is
just maybe our state shark is just
really good
I mean this is incredibly you can even
see the results of how the lighting is
very bucketed here I'm surprised to see
because we know that the well I guess
the fact that solution point count says
what it says maybe has something to do
with it point count should not be that
number let's go look at that where is
that value getting output
so what's happening here are how are we
getting that value solution point count
should be a sane value but it's not
right I want to see what's up at that
that's definitely bad
so the point count is 3457 supposedly
yet we're seeing that value what on
earth is going on there do we have a bug
in how we output you six teens could be
let's find out
looks like it now I don't know why there
because the box count is also a year 16
is it not so that seems a little bit
weird but it could be because it's
padded so it could be that since there's
another thing in fact I guess I can test
that
so let's suppose that we did exactly
that and we said all right we're
outputting the solution point count and
what we see when we go through here so
is this garbage value now we go ahead
and Pat it inside here so we say there's
just a huge gap of zeroes in between
there now what happens yeah so there's
definitely some problem with how we were
doing that we must cast to a u-32
pointer somewhere in the debug interface
for you 16
so we're passing the pointer to the
value
and I guess it must be choosing the u32
version so I'm wondering here suppose I
do this so we don't have a youth 16
version yeah so it looks like it's
because we don't have a 60 version it's
treating it like a u-32 which is you
know completely wrong
so we can make a custom version of one
of these
and that would be like something like
this right oops where we have the like
type of the thing and an AZ type right
and then we said well the type of the
thing is gonna be one of these and then
you know we'll write it back by casting
it and you know your mileage may vary
what was the question macro redefinition
OOP sorry
and when we set the type it's gotta be
that one uh so yeah I mean we can do
that and that's all fine and that would
probably just solve the problem if
anyone cared I don't know that anyone
does but probably we work with u16s now
Hey look
so for three thousand four hundred and
fifty seven points I and we're casting
sixteen raise four point at the moment
right
so that's 55,000 points at 55,000
initial raise so 55,000 is like in this
range here so if I were to heavily
restrict that distance I would actually
have expected it to be quite a bit less
than that value when I do the raycast
and I'm not seeing that which is just a
little bit odd right so let's see I just
force it to always hit the top one what
happens other than the fact that we
crash in that we should probably switch
to using conserved DLLs so we don't have
to worry about string preservation
anymore so how many do we cast now yeah
that just that seems really strange so
that means that we're in enough boxes
[Music]
just by default to have to iterate over
that many children even if I'm all the
way out here in the corner right and I
just don't know what to make of that but
it sure seems like a bug like if we're
never recursing
then I don't see how we get that far
down the down the road no I'm Santa
because in theory this is only happening
if we're actually inside it
maybe this check is wrong is this firing
like way more often than it should
because this should only recurse on
boxes that we actually are inside where
the the thing that's casting the array
is inside the actual box
and so that if I'm out in the corner
that should only be accounting for a
very small number of actual boxes
involved right we could test that if we
wanted to but just like yeah you know if
we look at how many things we'd have to
expand it be like the only box that we'd
be inside of for any given point it just
seems like it would be well we know it
would be four but I guess it's includes
it includes the whole path downward
maybe that's enough to make it like 10
because if it was 10 then I guess that's
where you get that multiplier for
well what am I saying look at the total
array count it's huge hmm yeah okay
let's let's investigate this further
I'm obviously confused about how this is
working which is not good
so let's investigate this a little bit
further and I'll just return it to its
original state so this this is just
doing the same all lighting no changes
how many rays are we casting like how
many rays are getting cast here so when
we look at total array count here is the
number so that should be the ray count
like you know what we would expect to
see or what I'm expecting to see
erroneously obviously is that's the
number of points we have right so the
number of points then needs to each one
of those is going to get cast 16 rays
right so I would expect 55,000 so
obviously I'm thinking of the ray count
wrong why am I thinking of the ray count
wrong so here we are
let's take a look here's our sample set
here's our read count so for each sample
point which is the point count wide
we're gonna do that many Ray's yeah
sample the hemisphere called a ray cast
do this and then we're so is the exit
right so how could we get anything other
than sample point x ray count like how
do we get something else out of that and
I guess the answer is because of the
recursion so we should probably change
this this total ray count is a little
misleading that's really not what that
value means
so recast point count would really be
the thing let's rename these better
all right so here's what we're gonna do
we're going to have a maybe total Ray
initiated let's say so like this is how
many we're going to start or like total
casts initiated then we're going to have
total cast recursions
and then we'll have total box
this is tested why these are - duze
these are notes okay so these are what
let's just clean this up so we're not
confused about the statistics were
actually looking at right
so in recast for curse we're talking
about total recursions right total box
is tested is in here and then we could
further split that actually so we could
call these total partitions tested and
total Leafs tested we could do like
these as two different values so we
could say something like total
partitions used in total leaves used or
something like that Wow
I'm not sure how we want to do this
so in here we could just say well
alright you know if box you know child
count else right so we'll say this is
the total number of partitions we tested
this is the total number of Leafs
probably should say leaves and then we
know the total number Curzon's is the
number of like steps through that I
don't know that we actually do we care
about that value that value seems
irrelevant like who cares I don't know
that we care about that so let's get rid
of that so I think that's mostly what we
want and then in here we'll deuce
solution total cast initiated plus plus
because that's how we know we initiated
a cast this will not have any summations
tonight at all and then we will just
update this to reflect that so inside
lighting test we'll do total cast
initiated total partitions tested and
total leaves tested their total pass
initiated total petitions tested total
we use tested
all right uh I did that wrong sorry
about that
I meant to do this Cass initiated total
partitions tested to the leaves tested
and let's see if I can look at these
stats and make more sense of them now
all right
so fifty-five thousand two hundred and
ninety-six cast initiated now is exactly
what I would have hoped right so at
least we now know that that value is
sane total partitions tested tells us
how many boxes were checking that are
not actual leaf boxes right and that
says that we're doing eight hundred and
fifty seven thousand of those partition
checks which is really high right so
what I would now expect is that if I
were to I would have expected myself to
be able to reduce the number of
partitions tested by doing that early
out check that's saying four right in
other words if we go through here by the
way what's our profile say here's sixty
seven so actually this is still really
fast just kind of surprising but anyway
whatever
so that total partitions tested number
being very high again that just seems
like kind of a bit of a weird scenario
because I would have expected now when I
go through and request a smaller number
of those that we would have seen more of
an effect on the numbers but we weren't
releasing more effect on the numbers and
so that's the part that's a little
confusing but anyway so if we go ahead
and look at red cast or curse now and
come here and actually do force it so
that it's never going to recurse on
anything other than the box that you are
physically inside
right I would have expected total
partitions tested to go down quite a bit
but actually total partition tested
hardly went down at all which suggests
to me that for most people most of the
boxes tested are ones they are inside
and I just don't understand that it
seems almost like there's a bug in this
check or something because it just
doesn't eat you know it doesn't seem
like you could be inside more than half
of the partitions you check I mean if
anything the definition of where you are
at inna for a point it can't be in less
than a half the boxes right I'm sorry in
more than half the boxes how could it be
it can only be in half of them if
they're split binary even the best case
scenario where you only had one split
you can only be in half right but it
should be drastically less than half if
you go down more than two splits worth
so that seems busted and I'm kind of
wondering if like is in rectangle Center
half to him somehow wrong
because that's pretty strange
so let's think about this for a second
so the box radius let's take a look at
that function
I mean it looks pretty sane subtracting
the Ray origin from the center of the
box pretty reasonable and then you're
seeing whether the absolute value of the
result is less than the radius on all
axes so you know if the the distance
some question there is less than each
case or the X Y and the Z then you're
good
certainly seems right so I guess we'll
have to leave this for tomorrow
and that's fine but I I mean again
totally possible it's correct just
doesn't seem plausible to me in that way
so take a look at the number of leaves
tested as well so the number of Leafs
tests that there are right 209,000 in
this case so we go in here and now we
say all right now you can test like way
more leaves right test them all go all
the way down right total number of
leaves tested doesn't even double it
just seems odd and so I feel like I'm
really want to dig into that code a
little bit and find out if there's just
something fundamentally screwed up
happening there that's that is making us
test in a way that isn't you know isn't
congruent or isn't what we would expect
right because you would expect a pretty
large number of leaves to be no longer
tested in that scenario that just seems
real weird
I mean I guess you know what it could be
is just that most of the time the angle
that you're testing just hits the
skylight in which case you just don't
recurse so I guess I could believe that
[Music]
in this case you know and especially I
suppose you know maybe if I go in and
add if I allow it to add another layer
on top see here something we have a lot
of like extraneous part room here so let
me try to make that not so big so if I
hopefully here can add you know I want
room like on top of me so I mean
that looks like it's always sideways so
can I set the direction to always be
like one way
there we go
so now there's like more stuff in there
right and you got people bouncing
between these two you know what I might
want to go the other way so maybe make
it stack on top
so now you've got at least like a lot
less hitting the skylight in this case
and so if we take a look at that value
here I wonder if it changes
significantly now depending on that
piece of information so if in here we
were to say quote for close this and
we're looking at you know I don't know
how many seven hundred thirty thousand
leaves tested there and I say okay let's
stop doing that
does that go down that's really annoying
me
does that go down and it that goes down
quite a bit more right so that's a
little more plausible there I guess when
you when you say like look don't even
really do raycasting sort of do
completely fake so I could believe that
was a little bit more plausible let me
go ahead and see what happens now if I
put in like a fair check of some kind so
I say like okay you know it's five
meters see what happens to the lighting
now
and that actually works pretty well I
think actually in terms of of
compartmentalizing it
all right so it may be that that's okay
I still want to go a little bit more
in-depth on that because I'm just not
100% certain that I'm really getting
what I expect there so you know I would
yeah I would like to get I would like to
get a little more information on that I
also want to know so is this a reliable
crash case now so if I this just crash
it doesn't always crash unfortunately
because I'm gonna say it would be nice
to go fix that crash but it looks like
it's a little bit less reliable than
that
uh all right so let's go ahead and go to
quick Q&amp;A here and then yeah what's
going on
we're get that word
[Music]
Jeff look can you explain why the debug
was oh yeah yes I can
sorry I just since we were in the
lighting I didn't take much time to
explain what I was doing there so um the
way the debug system works obviously
since it's kind of like an annotation
system that sits on top of things what
it does is when you come through the
debug system you announced to the debug
system the data that you wanted it to
look at and it looks at it but we only
have in the debug system a few different
types that it handles and you can see
them here and you can see that there is
no u16 isn't a type it doesn't have 16
bit integer support it only has like
32-bit integers as a thing unsigned and
signed right so what was happening
before was that when you passed a u16 it
would just find the closest match to the
overloaded functions and you can see
there's a macro here actually was this
one that we just used to make a few
different versions of the routine that
picks up a value for the debug system it
would use the u-32 version problem or it
may have used this the sign 32 version
actually based on C's integral promotion
rules but that's neither here or there a
point being it would use a 32-bit
version so what do we do is it would
call one of these routines that had say
s 32 in here which means that when it
went to do the value to pick up the
value right here this line right here or
this line right here so either wrote
back if you were doing modification it
with the debug system or if you just
create keeping it right which would be
this case so if you're keeping the debug
value it would go okay into the event
store the value that I got but change it
to the type that I'm pointing to that I
said I was which would be you 32 or an
s3 2 in this case that meant that it
picked up not only this 16-bit integer
that we're talking about but also the
next 16 bits that were there now in the
case of certain elements of the system
[Music]
like box count that's actually fine
because the next thing is a pointer
which is 8 bytes long and sees padding
rules for structures is that if you have
a thing that's say 2 byte aligned
like a 16-bit integer followed by
something that's eight byte aligned like
a pointer pad out to the next eight byte
boundary so there actually would have
been six bytes worth of zeros following
the box count here so when we output it
we would just get zero and even though
it was taking a 32-bit or a four byte
slice of the Dana it was fine because
was padded with zero so it still looked
like the right value on the other hand
down here what happened was when I had
the point count I then added another you
16 which is the extended point count so
we could track that value that meant
that there were two valid 16-bit values
next to each other which meant that
there was no pad anymore there was a pad
previously when we had this now there's
no pad what that means is the debug
system will take four bytes the next two
bytes after that the first two bytes
actually had data in it which would give
it the wrong 32-bit value right so the
only thing we had to do to fix that was
just to make a version that actually
respected the 16-bit value and you can
see that I did that here so what I did
is I said look let's actually use the
16-bit value correctly and just use have
the processor up convert it inside a
register which is what's happening here
so that it just expands out with zero
padding and does what we wanted to do in
the first place so that's all I did
there was allowed that conversion to
work properly
how likely is a lighting system GPU port
you could definitely run on the GPU I
don't know that we want it to I'm not
sure how to make that decision exactly
it may be smarter for us to just do a
multi-threaded CPU version it might be
that that's just fast enough but I don't
know it's pretty hard to say
gram fie off topic did you ever find out
if it's necessary for CPUs to have name
registers but no I am still really
curious to know if that's true this is
one of those things that's just like I
wish I knew someone who was really
really good at hardware design so I
could ask them because it's the kind of
question that only an expert extremely
good extremely smart hardware designer
could ask could could answer right
because the orthodoxy is one thing and
then knowing whether the orthodoxy is
just because of historical precedent is
another right and it's a very
complicated question with a lot of
details right
and so I don't really know I don't have
a gut feeling either way what I can say
is that it makes obvious sense to me why
named registers came into existence and
why they persisted for a long time what
I don't know is whether they still make
sense now that CPUs are so overly
complicated right and and I don't know
and there were computers way long ago in
the era where I think named registers
were the right decision obviously that
didn't use name registers and at that
point I can understand why those
machines didn't find favor I don't think
was accidental that that wasn't the
preferred method but
nowadays I don't know if the same thing
is true however I also don't see anyone
proposing this so I'm guessing that
either that just means that it's just
stupid right and if you're a really good
hardware designer you know it's dumb in
which case I really just want someone to
walk me through exactly why not curse
orally why but really why because curse
orally I don't think there is a reason
why I think it is only a reason why when
you really get down to the Nitty Gritty
right or they it's just something that's
too far from the current designs and you
don't want to take a risk on doing that
new design right I see some of the chat
brought off the mill CPU mill CPU still
uses named registers they're just named
based on their frequency of use right so
it's it's still basically a named
register machine for all intents and
purposes because you still have a
limited number of names and they still
are specific to what's happening inside
the CPU so they don't correspond to
memory and that's the key difference
that I was talking about
I was basically asking is there a reason
why we don't have register to memory
correspondence in modern CPUs because
everything else does right so nowadays
like every last thing in the CPU
actually does correspond to a memory
location except for the registers right
so like the level 1 cache for example
knows exactly where that thing would
live in memory if it was to be put back
right registers are the only things that
don't know that and I don't know if
that's actually the right decision the
argument for why it's the right decision
makes a lot of sense in the old days I
just don't know if it makes a lot of
sense now and I suspect that the
argument so it may be that it is the
right decision now but the argument
should look totally different than it
used to look right
so that's all long billion do you think
arranging pixels on LCD monitors in a
blue glowing blue image pattern would be
an improvement visually so the answer is
that it would absolutely be and improve
a huge improvement visually probably if
you knew what the pattern was and the
GPU used it for sampling if that makes
sense I don't think you can scatter
pixels in a blue noise pattern and then
render to them as if they're square that
may be a problem now if the monitor is
dense enough it might not matter but
then again if it's dense enough it might
not matter at all right so right
after enough memory is slow yes I know
memory is slow that really doesn't have
anything to do with whether your
registers know where they live in memory
or not right all right I'm gonna go
ahead and COEs down
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for those some handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow
series at home you can always pair to
the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with a source code so you can play
around with it yourself and do your own
experimentation which is a good way to
learn I'll be back here tomorrow to work
on more lighting until then if you want
to play around the lighting yourself you
can let me know what you find hope see
you back here tomorrow for that until
then have fun programming everyone and
I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody