hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream uh we had a sort of I
guess you might say a brainstorming
session on Monday where we were trying
to figure out what we wanted to do with
respect to sorting our sprites and my
sort of cursory conclusion after having
gone through it quite a bit was that it
didn't seem like there was really going
to be a simple straightforward way to
sort sprites and like I said in that
stream I am not really a 2-d game
programmer it's not what I tend to do I
almost always worked on 3d games pretty
much exclusively except for like very
rare occasions and so the idea of having
to sort sprites is not really one that
I've thought through in any particular
way and so we're kind of trying to think
it through now so that we could do
something realistic now I was hoping
that would be a relatively simple
problem but it seems like it's not in
one very interesting thing that happened
over the break yesterday because I did
this dream yesterday was that andrew
russell actually i guess i don't know
how to pronounce his name andrew russell
andrew russell i have no idea but i
tweeted this out he basically made a
blog post for us because it turns out
that he is working on this problem right
now in River City ransom which is I
believe that the sequel to river city
rampage and he had actually been dealing
with this and did a bunch of work to try
and solve this problem and I the way
that he discussed it made it sound like
he did not find an easy solution either
it's actually relatively complicated he
sort of made a blog post it was like
talking about the fact that I was asking
the question how should this be done and
then he was talked showing how he did it
and generally what happens is there's
two fairly complicated elements to it
the first part of what he's doing there
is they have a little bit more
information with their sprites than we
do so for example when you have a
situation that like you're like you
species posted here where we have three
sprites that we might be talking about i
mean there's other sprites back here but
you're just talking about these three
sprites right here clearly we have a
situation where you've got one sprite
that's behind and one sprite that's in
front of and what they were kind of
looking at is when these bounding boxes
overlap they actually have an idea of
what the Vox sort of the
three-dimensional depth of this thing is
and so they know what the bounding box
of the sprite is at various Z levels a
world or whatever you want to call going
back into the screen in this case and so
that's one thing we don't really have I
don't know if we'll need it because even
if we sort of didn't approach similar to
what andrew is talking about but if you
look at this because if you look at this
right here you can see they've got a
sort of a to their isometric view is
skewed twice right it's skewed both in
terms of the tilt that handmade hero has
but then also a sideways tilt and so
that's a little more complicated in
terms of what you have to handle because
on handmade hero you I don't think we
ever really have the case so much where
up which side of a sprite you're on
would determine whether you were in
front of or behind it because you can
see in this situation you could have
these two people at sort of equal layers
in the scene and one would be in front
and one would be behind strictly based
on which side of the sprite it was on
there because of that that isometric
tilt we only have that in one direction
and and Andrews got it in two with the
way that he structured this so that's a
little bit of an issue because we don't
really have much of a cook
conceptualization there but ignoring
that for a second because I'm not sure
we have that problem the second part is
I I i mean i guess i would say he sort
of decided to solve the problem by
saying look this is a semantic problem
there is no real solution so you can't
you can't approach it like a 3d thing
which may very well be true it certainly
seems consistent with the way I was
feeling about it on Monday and so when
he said it's look let's just build the
actual graph of what we think is in
front of what so we take all the sprites
in the scene
and we take what we essentially know
about them right we say you know we know
that this should be in front of this we
know that this should be in front of
that and remember I had sort of
mentioned something like this on Monday
and I saying well that's a little bit
tricky because once you get into that
situation you don't necessarily have a
single sort and it's like that's exactly
what he talks about here and what he
said was that's like okay I let's just
make the graph and even though that
graph does not have a you like a single
Universal way that you could sort it
that's okay we'll just break cycles in
the graph by arbitrarily deleting edges
and if our arbitrary deletion of edges
turns out to be incorrect will start
introducing heuristics to figure out
okay let's be smarter about how we
delete these edges right so he goes
through and he uses Tarzan's algorithm
Tarzan's album I have no idea to
pronounce that either I don't really
know how to pronounce most things well
you know what Wikipedia would probably
tell us nope it won't nevermind and he's
using that algorithm to basically go
through and find out about the cycles in
the graph so that you can remove edges
to produce a single directed graph that
doesn't have cycles in it right it
doesn't have cycles that'll break the
sort so that's how he tackled the
problem and you know I think there's a
certain amount of attractiveness to the
idea of just saying well you know this
is a this is a very semantic thing and
possibly that the way in which we might
want to state how things appear in front
of or behind other things may never
really be all that coherent right it may
not be something that really makes sense
in full three dimensions in a way that
can really be processed and so maybe
what you need is just something that
deals with semantics and then you just
write rules for determining what those
semantics are for any given scene right
that basically says I know this is has
to be in front
this I know this has to be behind this
and you put enough of those out there
and then you can run a sort on it that
will produce the correct sorter for the
script for the scene that you're looking
at and I don't really have a problem
with that that seems like a pretty
reasonable solution it also lets us do
some things that might be interesting
for example let's say that we're going
to output the sprite for the hero you
know maybe we just want to say the heads
always on top of the Cape Cape toys on
top of the body right um before we kind
of had to address that sort of a problem
by specifying Z values that would be
higher than other Z values or playing
with the sort key remember we add the
concept of the sort key and stuff like
that and you know I again being a 3d
graphics memory I haven't really thought
too hard about what I might want to do
in scenarios where I don't have sort of
this more tangible definition of what's
behind and in front of other things but
you know at first blush it seems like a
graph oriented approach is kind of nice
because it does mean that I can just
throw arbitrary semantic constraints
into it that have nothing to do with
where anything is it's just I know that
the Cape should always be over the body
or I know that the head should always be
over the Cape I never want them to be
drawn in any other configuration than
that right so you know there is a
certain attractiveness to that I don't
really know again because like I said I
don't have a lot of experience with this
kind of of an engine I don't have a
strong of a sort of intuition about
whether this is a good route to go down
or not but I did really like the fact
that someone took the time to write in
with a solution that they've been
working on because it's kind of nice to
know that if another person who knew you
know if another smart person basically
looks at a problem and determines that
it needs a relatively complex solution
that's kind of a good hint that probably
you know there isn't some really obvious
simple thing that we're just
right the more smart people look at a
problem and decide that something
complex probably has to be done here the
less likely it is that there is a hidden
sort of simple solution whereas if
you're the only you know if you you're
the only person who's really looked at
this problem you don't know whether you
know something complicated is really
necessary or whether you're just
overthinking it or missing some special
insight that would allow you to some
simple now does this mean that there
isn't just because he and I both looked
at this problem and didn't see an
immediate obvious answer no I mean there
might still be something we're both
missing but again I just feel like it's
kind of nice to know that I'm not the
only person who looked at this problem
and didn't see an immediate obvious
solution to it so I feel like that's you
know kind of a nice it's nice to have
backup as I guess what I would say a
little reassurance that you're not just
being stupid and missing some obvious
thing that you know some anyone else who
came the problem just go like oh you
just do whatever right um so uh you know
I'm I would totally be down for doing a
semantic sort here and I don't really
see a lot of problem with that the main
thing is that if we were to do a
semantic sort you know regardless of
whether we did a similar sort of
resolution to the semantic sort we do
have the problem that we are probably
going to have to build our semantic
sorts a little bit differently from how
from how River City what does it really
ransom underground your city ransom
underground I'm going to call that RC
are you how are C are you is doing it
because again they're they're sort of
tackling a slightly different problem I
feel like in some ways to their their
problem might be a little harder than
our problem because like I saying when
you when you start to have a second you
know the more axes your kind of trying
to fake depth along I feel like the more
complexity that you have to you're going
to have to deal with right so i don't
really know that that's the case but I
feel like that's yeah probably the case
and similarly I think they're trying to
get a lot more sort of variance in kind
of
how much can be sort of contained in a
sprite in terms of height variance
whereas we don't really necessarily have
as much of that so I would suspect that
we can probably get away with something
simpler than what they have which I hope
is true because like I said I was kind
of hoping to not have to augment our
sprites with really any more information
than what they kind of already have
which is an image right so yeah so there
you go so anyway obviously in case I
didn't already say that thank you very
much to andrew russell for writing in
because that was really i thought that
was really great and it was really
interesting to read to and also i kind
of as a separate total aside this game
kind of looked to me a little bit like
Double Dragon and I feel like that would
be kind of fun to play so I I'm also
kind of looking forward to the game so I
hope that's coming along nicely because
I kind of want to play it anyway so
that's the the developments that
happened yesterday so I think I might
try playing around with that now just to
see if I start to code something similar
to that just so I can get a feel for
what it would look like in the code if
that was what we were doing and see if I
can spot any obvious problems or if I if
I think I like the way it feels so I can
get a handle on how that would work and
you know go from there so today's day
300 on handmade hero so you want to
going to want to unpack day 299 source
code if you're trying to follow along
with the programming at home now let's
do a little loading of the project yeah
so here we go all right so let's go
ahead and try to to take a look at some
of this stuff now the first thing that I
might do is push the stack a little bit
and say well let's hold off for just a
second on the topological sort concept
because we sort of have a higher level
sort concept as well which is that we
had those layers and so maybe those
layers as well those
sort of BB sort of packed into this sort
in addition so I might also take a look
at that I guess as we as we kind of go
through this right and so one thing that
I'm kind of curious about and I don't
really know what I think about it yet
but I'm getting the sense is that I feel
like packing this into the render group
might be the wrong way to go right so if
the renderer you know previously the
renderer was doing the sorting and it
was doing the sorting sort of as its own
conceptual thing that it did at the end
of everything getting pushed onto the
render group and what it sort of
suggests uni is that that might want to
be a separate sort of system now right
we might want to have a separate idea of
how that works and only because if you
start to think about how this would work
I don't know that we want to bake all of
that sort of topological information
into the thing that's just supposed to
be how we get things out to the graphics
and so i'm not sure we may sort of have
a case where we've baked too much down
into into a single place I don't really
know that that's a little that's a
little iffy at the moment okay but again
like I said I'm not really sure what I
want to do yet so I'm just going to kind
of start playing with this to see what I
think would happen here so let's go down
and take a pretty simple scenario like
something that's not again like maybe
something very very straightforward that
that I kind of know is the case which is
that you know I've got sort of this
notion of these where are we here of
these pieces that I'm rendering and
maybe I want to start talking about the
the how the pieces why am I not seeing
the iterator for those is it called
something else
oh right I know why I made the same
mistake before the piece iterators
actually on here so when I come through
this this piece in dec stuff right what
i could do is have some idea of for each
one of these pieces how they're supposed
to fit together to in terms of sorting
because that's almost always going to be
the case where like every sort of
creature that I create probably the
pieces are going to want to have a
particular sort if piece of sort
information sort of going with them
right and especially for things like you
know articulated bodies you know we kind
of just know we want you know for these
these 2d sprites to layer on top of each
other the way that they were layered you
know in the photoshop file that came
from or whatever else so if we take a
look at this piece in dec stuff we could
imagine looking at this here and going
well when we were when we do this push
bitmap maybe in addition to just pushing
the bitmap here we would also say hey
this bitmap always has to be in front of
this other bitmap board this bitmap is
you know whatever write something like
this and then we could know that the
people who do the piece things could
just store which peace index they were
in front of and if that piece index is
you know your own index or something
like this then you know that you're not
in front of anybody if it's an other
index in the array then you know you're
in front of that other thing whatever it
is so that's just an example of
something that we probably could do it
would be really simple to do here and so
that I think would solve the problem of
inter piece sorting certainly because we
know that they always go in that order
now the other question that I have here
is all right so let's say I'm out
putting these pieces where how would I
know how these pieces sort relative to
other things right and and that of
course isn't is another question I I
guess entities are sort of output by
themselves and so what we would have to
do is in order to figure out how an
individual piece that doesn't have a
particular piece of information about
you know how it fits into the scene
which I guess normally they wouldn't
because they're only going to have
information about how they fit with each
other I got to go ahead and figure out
what the rules are for what goes in
front of of what right so let me go
ahead and try to enumerate those in as
much as I can here here is day three
hundred these are our like sorting rules
so I guess my thinking on this is we
have a number of cases and we should
just try to enumerate them as best we
can right so I think what I would say is
I we know certain information about
planar so we kind of have this notion
that we've got sort of you know two
types of sprite we have the ones that
are like on the sort of on the Z plane
and when we've got ones that are on the
the Y plane and I think that's basically
all we have the moment so if you think
about those what we would have is here
is like our coordinate system right
oops at the moment so that's what our
coordinate system looks like and so the
sprites that we have our sprites that
are on the Z plane so you know something
that's lying flat and since we're in
orthographic it would look like this in
perspective it would have looked like
that right these are things on the
z-plane their normal easy and they have
like a Z sort right and then we have
things that are in the Y plane so this
plane and their normal is y which faces
kind of right out at the screen right
although it's not quite right at the
screen it's tilted a little bit it'sit's
since you know it's that way right so
we've got those two types of sprites
those are the two kinds of of car of of
sprites that we have and I we really
just don't have any other kinds right a
sprite has to be categorized into one of
those two and I don't anticipate really
allowing at this point anything else so
if we then take a look at these sprites
and we see a you know if two sprites and
this is kind of another thing that I
think we have to admit and looking at
what Andrew posted i think reinforces
this in my mind anyway one thing that I
really wasn't doing before really wasn't
thinking about carefully enough was the
fact that obviously to start with we
only care about sorting sprites if the
sprites overlap each other right meaning
it doesn't matter what order we draw two
sprites who aren't overlapping so to the
extent that we care about what happens
to those sprites it's only in terms of
how our sort order goes right how our
overall sort order goes so in terms of
determining the rules we actually care
about we only need to know what happens
when two sprites are overlapping right
so
okay so let's talk about this for a
second so we have if these are the kinds
of sprites that we are going to support
we're going to support Z planar and why
planar sprites then by definition in
terms of overlaps we have four sort of
nominal cases right but we can simplify
that down to three because one of them
is interchangeable right we have Z
overlaps Z we have Y overlaps y and we
have Z overlaps why right so this is
like Z planar sprites overlapping Z
planner sprites y plena sprites are my
parents flights and then one more its a
mix and technically we have Y overlaps Z
as well but because there isn't really a
meaning to the ordering of who is
overlapping who I mean two things that
overlap since we're talking about
sorting there isn't a concept of who's
like in charge here right so the Z
overlaps why case is the same as the Y
overlap Z case which is why I say we
technically have four cases but really
if there's only three that matter
because Y overlap Z can just be treated
as Z overlaps why you switch the order
of the two things you were checking if
you know if you got that case so these
are the cases that we have now if we
have a Z overlaps Z sprite case in that
case uh so so let me let me brick I
guess I say let's let's break these down
one at a time and figure out what we
want each case to be here right so let's
take our first case which is Z overlaps
Z ok now for zee overlap z we have a
situation that looks something you know
like this let's say ok so both of these
sprites are basically right they are you
know parallel to the concept of the
ground and we need to sort these things
so that they come out properly right now
if we were only talking about things
that were directly on top of each other
then presumably it becomes relatively
straightforward to sort them because we
would just sort them by Z so you know if
to you know looking from the top down if
the answer here was that these things
are right on top of each other we would
only care about sorting them by Z but if
things are sort of offset in Y as well
we have to think about this problem a
little bit harder right so let's talk
about this a little bit more carefully
so in order to get something that looks
like this one thing that I think we
could say is that if we sort if we sort
these by Z and in fact I think I'm
trying to think if this is incorrect or
not
well let me keep talking because I was
kind of trying to jump to a conclusion
there and maybe I shouldn't all right so
we have some we have some different
cases about what's going to happen in
the why and what's going to happen in
the Z so I'm just going to again
enumerate all the cases and we'll just
see how it shakes out right so if we
take Ozzie overlaps Z case then we
obviously have three things that could
happen with their Z coordinates or and
three things that could happen with
their y coordinates or I guess for
technically right so if we take a look
at the coordinates it we just look at
one of the axes right we would have as I
think I drew up before we would have a
disjoint case right so there they look
like this and maybe I should draw these
a little bit offset so you can kind of
see so there's the disjoint case there's
the overlap case right and then there's
the sub zoomed case
right and you can think of this is
happening in either dimension right so
this could be happening along the z-axis
this could be happening along the x axis
as well right because technically these
things can be sort of could could be
considered bounding volumes so you know
the sprite has a certain could have a
certain depth in Z if it wants to write
you can you can sort of have that as a
conceptual z-depth if that makes sense
um so we so kind of think of what that
sort of means you know I guess no that's
not really true so since we're not
really allowing you to have not to think
about that I'm not sure to what extent
we want to allow things to have both as
opposed to just breaking them into two
sprites I think what we would always do
is just break things into two sprites
for the most part right so for example
when if we were to have a block that
looked like this right and here's like
the side of the block and here's the top
of the block I mean I think we would
want to break it into two sprites like
this is the one sprite and this is the
tooth right and this one is the Z sprite
right and this one is a why sprite I
think that's how we would want to do it
if you could you know if you can stand
out if you couldn't stand on it we
wouldn't need the Z sprite part of it at
all so I think we might be able to get
away with not really having the concept
of depth at all there right so for Z
sprites it would seem that since they
are always flat slices for all intents
and purposes you can sort them directly
i think based on their highest z point
like they're just be whatever that
slices it's just constant right so i
think we could say that this is
this is the case for why but for Z
there's really only you know two cases
there's coincident and not coincident
right there's either they're right
together or there you know ask you all
right so let's think about this for a
second so let's say that these two
things are overlapping on the y-axis but
but we're let's talk about this z
sorting here so if something is higher
than something else in Z then that means
that it's sort of on a different plane
and if we assume that it's always going
to be a flat piece like this that would
seem to suggest that you could always
sort those things just sorting them by Z
right it's always sufficient to sort Z
planar things by Z they'll they'll never
be a case where something that's below
something else in Z should be drawn
first I don't think that would ever
actually occur right because no matter
what you did I don't think you could
ever really produce the case where like
I'm trying to think if I can ever
produce the case where something that's
lower in Z actually draws on top because
as things you know it as you tilt and
things kind of go up in why they're
going up and why by getting a higher Z
value it you know if they have a higher
Z value so you could never get lower by
having a higher Z value or go higher
z-value always increases your visibility
on the screen never decreases it as far
as I can think right so I feel like
sorting by Z would always work for Z
sprites I don't know
so it seems to me like maybe sort by Z
just kind of works in that case and you
don't really have to worry about it at
all I don't know that's just my thought
but I'm not sure so I feel like sorting
by z4z overlap sea sprite would be a
fine rule that would just kind of work
for why overlaps why right I feel like
it basically the same thing is is
probably not I feel like we're not going
to get away with something so simple and
the reason for that is that the Z value
of the sprite could influence how it's
supposed to be sorted so let's take a
look at that case a little more
carefully for y overlaps why maybe what
we should do in fact and I'm going to
see if this is true but let's let's take
a look at a why overlaps Z first because
that may be the easier case even so
here's case to this case one all right
so for a while apps Z that's the case
where we have like a Z sprite like this
and then we have a why sprite like this
right and we need to know which one of
these we should be drawing so I would
imagine that in the case where we're
drawing these what we want to know is is
the highest point on the Y sprite right
is the highest point on this Y sprite
going to be above this Z sprite in the
case where the Y sprite is actually
overlaps the Z sprite in Y right so for
example what we would kind of have to
know here is how big is this Z sprite in
Z right so if we were looking at how big
is this sea sprite in why so if we took
a look at the top down right here is the
y-axis here is the x axis z axis is kind
of coming out at us so if we were to
look at this if this if this sprite is
behind this Z sprite in why
I feel like there's no way that the that
this bright should ever be drawn in
front right that's just nonsensical to
me same is true i think for if it's in
front of right so if the why if the if
the sprite that we're talking about if
the Y sprites why is entirely behind the
sea sprite or entirely in front of the
Z's right then you can just sort by why
I think and be done right because
there's really no case i can think of
where that wouldn't be true I it yeah I
think that's always the case right so
the only question comes when there's an
overlap so I think the first thing we
say is if overlaps in Y then we need to
do the complex case else sort by why
right so if we overlap in Y and I
shouldn't say overlap I should say
something a little bit more specific if
Y inside why range of Z right if Y if
the Y sprite is inside the Y range of
the sea sprite if that's the case then
we have to figure out how to sort these
two things more conclusively and I guess
the easiest way to say that would be is
then then we would say sort top of Y
sprite by Z right because if this if
this point is above this sprites plane
we should draw this guy and if it's
below we shouldn't I think it's that
simple right and if we wanted to allow
you to interpenetrate we would have to
split the sprite in half at the point
where was in pendant penetrating but
we're really not gonna allow
interpenetration I don't think so at
least I'm I don't anticipate allowing
that I think if we were gonna do
something like a
a creature that kind of rose up out of
the ground magically that would be a
fact that knew about that so it would
already be clipping I think it could
just know to clip to it where it was
think was coming on the ground so I
don't think we need the sort to
compensate for that I think that can
just be handled manually in the cases
where we want that because we're already
gonna have to manage that as a real
effect so let's talk about number three
which is why overlaps why so if Y
sprites overlap each other then we sort
of have I guess I think this is the most
complicated case I don't know I could be
wrong about that because these two cases
are pretty straightforward but if Y
overlaps why then what we have
essentially looking at it again sort of
from the perspective of top-down we
basically have something that looks like
this right so we've got these two sort
of sprites we're looking at them and
they've got a sort order in Y and you
know on the screen they look something
like this now the question that the only
question that there is is how you know
can we just sort them and why or do we
have to do something more complicated
here and the reason that I don't know if
we need to something more complicated
here is because I feel like there's a Z
component to this sorting that is
relevant and the reason that I think
that's true is because for example let's
say we took the hero so there's the head
there's the torso there's the body in
this configuration head sorts top torsos
sorts middle and body sorts last right
or sorry cape sorts middle of bodies
force last if that's the case then what
that means is we need sort of this this
idea that the Z stacking of Y sprites
makes a difference right so I think uh
what we would need to know
there is how do we interplay the Y and
the Z properly to figure out whether
you're in front of or behind someone
based on that that's e value so because
yeah obviously you know increasing the Z
value of a sprite that's clearly behind
another sprite shouldn't sort it in
front but then at the same time we kind
of have this weird thing where the capes
are you know in front of the here or
whatever the answer might be that you do
what we sort in Y and this is a special
case so things that are assemblies have
to be especially given those rules
specially right and that would be fine
like I said we could just have that be a
thing that happens so I don't know maybe
that's not a problem I don't know
I would say that I don't have a real
case in mind uh
like I wish I had a clear case in my
mind that's like something that'll
happen in the game that involves sort of
not a not unknown assembly right because
because what we're talking about here is
sort of I want this one known assembly
to sort like this but if that's the only
time that this sort of thing ever
happens then that's probably not there's
probably no reason to lean on the
topological sort we just throw these
things into the sort as a unit that just
always goes in the direction it goes
right it's like hey these things are
just sorted together and then make sure
they go on top of each other like this
that would just work right in other
words we could treat them all as just
once front effectively at that point and
not have to think about that too hard so
I don't really know if there's another
case where where I actually wouldn't be
able to sort by Y so it's possible that
the answer here is like you just sort by
Y and then you're done that they just
have to be in front of behind each other
based on their y values and that's
always correct because I think that
might always be correct so yeah so if
you take a look at what actually happens
here if we if we consolidate these cases
and write that down and assume that
we're correct at all which we might not
be we have like Z a Z Z pairing is sort
by Z a YY pairing is sort x y and z y
pairing is a is sort of a question mark
if you will which is why in Z and if it
is then we sort by Z else we would sort
biwi right that's what we said I think
if Y overlaps and z sort by Z and there
we go and z is always the top see so
like Z is always highest Z and Y sorting
by why in this case is always just a
known unknown thing so if we look at
what actually happens here essentially
we always fall into one of two cases a
sort by Z and a sort by why that's
always true so really we just have a
preamble which says how do i pick you
know what I'm sorting by and in this
case we could say that this predicate
here the y and z predicate we could say
that this predicate is really the entire
determiner so the entire thing is we
would say you know if you know y and z
whatever that means we would say sort by
Z else
sort by why right and this function here
is just our cases so the y and z case is
like you know is it z on z if it's z on
zee i guess i'll draw this way in the
case where we have a Zeon z case we want
to sort by Z so it would return true is
it a why on why case then it would
return false right and then we because
if you think about this why on why
sprites can never overlap right that's
not possible because they don't have any
Z depth they can't overlap at Z so that
is actually the case that there that's
always false if they did they would be
in an illegal case where there where we
which we can't resolve anyway right and
if it's a Z if it's a why Anzhi case you
know then in that case we have to check
the actual bounds so really we know
we're always sorting by either the Y or
Z and then we have again that sort of
concept of like we've got to check the
bounds at that point this seems
plausible to me I feel like I feel like
I'm okay with that you know I feel like
that's reasonable and I feel like we
could I feel like there's enough wiggle
room there too that we could basically
say that like okay suppose you know we
came up with some suppose we came up
with some tricky case that we're having
trouble with it feels like we could add
special cases into a system like this
relatively easily and that seems like
kind of what you want because when the
system looks like it does
these two sort of 2d plus some 3d kind
of engines it feels like you want to
have that concept of a sort that can
support weird stuff getting thrown into
it like hey I know it's weird but you
got to use this crazy sort rule I feel
like that's a good thing because that
allows us I think to special case stuff
in in times when it's like clear that
something you know needs to get resolved
that's just kind of semantics and weird
doesn't have a lot of physical physical
analogue to it potentially right uh so
that seems pretty good to me and if we
wanted to I feel like we could do a sort
there I feel like we could do a sort
there where I don't know we could almost
try not having something that does much
conflict resolution whole a second here
like for example if we were to do this
does this produce a total sorting right
would be one question uh and I guess the
problem is that we don't know what would
happen if the things are disjoint
although I guess we do so we are kind of
fully specified here so the only
question is can this produce cycles and
I don't know if it can or if it can
write obviously this is the thing that
would produce the cycles because if we
always sorted Z's on z's or wise unwise
and obviously the sword is complete so
the only question is what happens when
we start to get this in two intersecting
people are there times when we would
pick that one thing sorts on either side
of another right so let's say we've got
two things that overlap
so we've got two Z's and we've got a why
that overlaps them both right this is
the kind of thing where we would have
you know here's to Z tiles and we have a
why that overlaps and them both which is
a pretty common thing that would happen
right so is there ever a case that the
sort would not produce the sort that we
would expect it to produce right and uh
that question seems like it doesn't seem
super plausible I don't know but let's
think about this so let's say that we
raise this sprite up to you know to hear
or whatever well I've got to keep it
overlapping so they're still going to
overlap right in theory even though this
one might be considered a little higher
although I guess strictly speaking
that's not technically possible and
either way in both cases this guy would
sort in front of so I don't think that
affects yeah I don't know this I guess
we should try and figure it out a little
bit more diligently but I don't know if
this always actually for our cases
produces something we could sort on
directly if that makes sense so it may
be that we don't really have to worry
too much about even doing a full
topological sort we could or rather I
guess a graph sort because we may be
able to just still do this by an item
comparison sort that is a partial
ordering that's an that will produce
correct results in all the cases we care
about that would be nice right so let's
say that we were going to do something
like that you know if we were going to
do something like that when we throw
these pieces into the system again like
I said the main question here is should
that'd be in the rendering code or
shouldn't that the inner enter code it
seems to me like maybe that should not
be in the rendering code I don't know
like we maybe want to stop having that
sort of sorting stuff happened the
rendering code and maybe it should
happen kind of as a separate layer that
sits on top of it a little bit I'm not
entirely certain like I said how that
should go because if you think about the
information that has to be stored here
essentially what you need to store is a
y min and Max and a z-value I don't
think you need the minimum Z value for
anything in particular it didn't look
like any of our cases we're going to
matter much about what your minimum Z
value was so it seems like we only
really care as far as I know about
having y min and Max and Z and the Z
would be the maximum so your Mac Z your
minun minun max y and then with that
information you can sort everything
far as I can tell
well let's take a look so if we were
going to do that when we have our
entries here let's see here here's our
headers so when we have our render
entries which I'll get that sort of
entered into here our sort keys which I
think are used separately where where do
those happen where's our swords on the
platform okay there we go no where's our
sword entries
I don't know where they are this is the
problem with having too many code bases
in your head at any given time you start
to forget things there it is so these
these things where we kind of have a
sort key and index the problem is here
right we would not be able to use the
same sort that we were using because it
would need to be more complex than that
now that's not a problem right we can
create another sort here that's that's
you know does it a little bit
differently so let's say we have you
know we take this merge sort here right
because we can't use a radix sort
anymore because there's nothing to radix
sort by right there's no way it can
construct a single value that you would
use to do your sorting but if we wanted
to we could do a merge sort still the
merge sort is fine so we could do a
merge sort and this is for a you know I
guess it's right bound
something like that I don't know what
this is that was kind of an aborted
attempt there we go so if we take a look
at this guy here where we're doing our
merge sort the merge sort is now going
to basically just be the exact same
piece of code here except when there's
two places right here where we do our
basic comparison between two items and
here where we determine whether or not
we need our merged items to be placed in
front of or behind each other these now
have to be sort of these have to be
described in a way that is more
complicated it's not just taking two
values and comparing them we now have to
actually implement the sort rules as we
talked about using more elaborate data
now the first I'm going to do is I'm
just going to swap the sense of this
comparison so that they're both going in
the same direction I don't really know
why I didn't do that to begin with but
you know what can you do so in this
situation you can see here right we've
got the same comparison done both times
with on two different things and so what
I'm going to do is just introduce a
thing here that's like you know here's
my comparator and it's going to return
either true or false whether or not I
should do the case since they're both
the same and so what I want to know here
is you know who should sort in front of
who I guess if that makes sense and in
this case like we're saying we're going
to put entry a and entry be in order and
we swap them if this comes back true for
entry be so this is like in front of so
I'm just going to name it that is in
front of and then we'll have sorts right
round a and source break ground be
so I'm just going to say like okay if is
in front of then we need to swap these
two guys and the same is true here where
we say if is in front of and that's
really all we need to do for our sort
now we just have to implement the rule
which is to say that in here where we do
sort sprite bad we need the things that
I've talked about so this is a y min a
wimax a zmax and then our actual index
so it's still not too big of a thing to
sort so that's good because we don't
want these to be particularly large
since we're moving them around
potentially I so it's still something
that is what is it it's a it's 16 bytes
long so that's not a bad thing that can
be sort of romp written by the CPU in an
easy copy fashion which is I think
probably what we want those things were
going to be sorting a lot of so how do
we determine this well I rode out very
explicitly what we were going to do here
right and so in these cases I think we
might be able to get them down to just
looking at these numbers a little bit
more directly with the wyman wimax v-max
right so because what we would know is
that the wyman in the wimax for a y
sprite are going to be equal to each
other so we would know ahead of time
whether or not something could be inside
of look we can just test for equality
those two without storing which kind of
sprite this is right and we can probably
simplify the math down as well once we
get so i'm going to write out the cases
explicitly without being too clever and
then we're going to probably be able to
collapse them down into something even
better right so all right let's do the
first thing which is to say what are our
cases here right we have if Y against
why else if Z against Z
else our final case right so we know if
we have a why sprite and actually you
know what I could do it this way if sort
by why else not first of all so we know
that there's only two cases that we're
ever going to actually process by sort
by Z sort by Y right I'll do it the same
way I wrote in the code so let's say for
starters that we have that and we're
going to equal that because something
that tells us which one to sort by if
we're going to sort by Z then all we
really need to do is say well whatever
the result is here and in fact I can
even just roll this into a very this is
a very simple ternary I could just say
well if we're supposed to sort by Z then
we'll do the Z comparison if we're
supposed to sort by Y will do the Y
comparison right so for sorting by Z
than what we want to say is we're
comparing the Z Max's we want to see if
I'm going to be in front of you then my
zmax should be higher than your zmax
right and then for sort by why what we
want to say is whatever the the Y again
is kind of going back into the screen
because of the way that we've got that
arranged so I want my Y min to be less
than your wyman right so i want to say
my wyman is less than your wyman that
would determine whether or not i'm
closer than than you to the viewer so
that's a pretty easy way to return the
results here so they're really the only
thing that we have to do is write the
slightly more complicated code that is
how do we determine which one of the
cases were actually in are we in a sort
by Z case or not and so if we take a
look at what happens in our thing here
we said well the cases where this is
true where we're going to do z sort is
if they're both Z sprites right or if
they overlap in why because that's the
you know if they don't overlap and why
the rest sort by why right so if both of
these are Z sprites then
if both of these are z sprites then that
would mean that there Y min and Max's
were equivalent right so one case for
sort by Z is like both Z sprites and
both these sprites would be like a y min
equals a wimax and the wyman equals B Y
max right so if they're both sea sprites
I would do it the other case is a
includes be and the other won't be be
includes a so the sort by Z is just if
they're both sea sprites or a includes B
or B includes a in any other case we're
going to sort by Y so a includes be is
pretty simple a includes be if gets y
min choose me ah and I guess technically
if I wanted to be a little bit more uh
well let's keep going with this if
includes V if if bees y min is greater
than or equal to a is why men and bees
wyman is less than equal to a is why max
similarly the same would be the exact
same thing would be true if these were
reversed
right and so the question that I was
having before it or list the thing that
I was thinking about is in the case
where I have I'm wondering if this can
be kind of just simplified fairly
drastically like I was kind of saying at
the outset if I know that why my Y min
in my MOT and my Y max are the same
value then there's no way that I could
include and in fact I could make this
more dramatic and say okay now there's
literally no way that a why sprite can
ever include anybody else because it has
no actual why range only a Z sprite can
include right so at that point I would
know that if they're both Z sprites I
should sort by Z if a includes B or B
includes a I know these will never be
true in the case of Y sprites they can't
include anybody right they can never
include anybody um so I think uh let me
just think this through here a little
bit further I think we could probably
well no maybe not Tenley it's time for
the QA so I should probably stop but I
have a feeling that if we actually look
at what happens here with the math I
think we can probably get to a point
where this actually simplifies much
further if that makes sense I'm gonna do
a little compile here
what is the thing you're missing
semicolon right you are sir oh wait are
you right there we go and entry a entry
be so op connective rig one from swap
what is swap do here swap so we need
another swamp there's our swap and then
again if you're okay with templates that
was something you could template eyes
they're the same right the swap is the
same in both cases so there we go and
then tomorrow we can take a closer look
at that
the sizing isn't it why vertical sprites
that have why men equal wimax yes it is
oh yes sorry you're totally right there
so this is actually both why sprites not
both z sprites uh so that is my bad
right that's what that should be thank
you you always do equals for flow
comparisons how can you ensure those
will ever return true because of float
precision so this may be something that
I fail to mention a lot of times and
that's probably my bad it's I don't
think about it that often but the reason
that I can do that here is because i
know that i'm setting these values not
computing these values right so if I'm
computing values with a floating point
calculation then that's a case where you
have to be aware of what the tolerances
are for the computation because if the
computation has a spread that it could
produce you can't test for equals and so
your intuition is very correct there and
that's totally true but if this is the
case where I'm setting the Y values
myself then I might know that there's
cases where I set them both to the same
thing so in the case where I record Ozzy
sprite i'm going to set y min and wimax
equal time sorry the case where I record
a wife's right i'm going to set y min
and wimax to the same value that makes
sense so I know that they'll be exactly
equal not approximately equal and
therefore I don't need to think about a
computation epsilon and so yeah when you
see me right actual equals there that
means i feel like i'm setting these two
exact values not as the result of a
computation that could be variable
in the Y overlap Z case what about cliff
sides that are holding up the ground
sprites so elevated ground isn't just
floating there would that cause an issue
with anything so what I was sort of
saying before is I feel like we can
break up sprites that are problematic
into two pieces so for example if I've
got a cliff side here and here's the top
of the cliff and here's the side of the
cliff right um we could break these up
into two sprites if we needed to however
that said I don't know that we actually
need to and the reason that I don't know
if we actually need to is because I
think since no one can stand on the side
of this thing it might actually just
always work right because it's always
going to sort in why behind anything
that's out here I think
right because because anything that's
here it's y value isn't going to be
intersecting this guy right it's going
to be in front of it so I think it's
probably okay uh but like I said I i
don't i'm not too worried about that
case because i know i can split those
sprites very reliably at asset creation
time even so it's not like a thing that
has happened the sort so that special
case i'm not too worried about em and
Evander I literally did the float equals
thing last week and considered it
acceptable for that exact reason because
I was just checking if the value had
just been set by me to exact value on
the previous frame or whatever yes I
mean so the important thing to remember
about floating point numbers is that
floating point numbers are still just
integer numbers right at the end of the
day they're they're not actually magical
they're just they're just a way of
taking an integer and knowing where it
lies on the number line I'm sorry I'm a
decimal point right that's that's all it
does and so they still have concrete
exact values and if you know what your
computations are doing you know whether
those values should be equal or not
certainly on handmade hero and generally
in my programming career I don't tend to
analyze floating-point algorithms to the
degree where I have any idea what their
values will be at that level of
precision if I didn't set them equal to
something myself so typically you treat
them as having epsilons foremost
computations because you haven't
analyzed the computation to the point
where you have any idea about what the
actual range really is right but that
doesn't mean that it doesn't have an
exact value that it does come out to you
do know what it's going to be right you
know where the round is going to happen
you know all that stuff and it will be
an actual value at the end the problem
is just are you ever realistically going
to analyze your things and have opinions
about that stuff at any fine grading
level most of the time no but when you
do set something to an exact value it's
not like it can be some other thing it's
still
an exact bit pattern and you can check
that exact bit pattern on both sides and
know that it's going to be equal
any more q Cowen's
any more cute
alright looks like we've got no more q
Colin's so I am going to go ahead and
close down
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for the sort of handmade here at sort of
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
with the source code you can do so by
pre-ordering the game on hand meteor org
it comes to the source code so you can
go ahead and play with it we also have a
forum site that forum site is a good
place to ask questions we have a patreon
page where you can support our lovely
video series we also have a schedule bot
where you can tweet the schedule or
rather you can have the schedule tweeted
to you so you know where we're gonna be
live and we have enough so guide if you
want to catch up on past episodes check
them all out there great buttons they're
the kinds of buttons that just make you
happy to push them that's about it I
will be back here tomorrow 5 p.m.
pacific daylight time for more
programming where we will see what
happens with our new sort or well that
may be presumptuous we will finish the
coding of our new sort but that will
probably take a while because we have to
sort of get the render pipeline
organized for it which is going to take
a little bit of moving stuff around but
we should have our new sort implemented
we may not get to the point we can
actually that we're actually debugging
it much but we're getting close that is
it i will see you tomorrow for that
until then tickety's everyone and i'll
see on the internet