hello everyone welcome to handmade Hero
show recode a complete game live on
stream we're doing some API stuff today
which i think is good and important I
know it's probably not the most exciting
thing you know everyone would rather
code explosions or something but API
design is probably one of the least well
done things in the entire industry most
api's that people ship are just
absolutely terrible and so spending time
learning about how you would brush
something up and rework parts of it in
order to create a good design for an API
is valuable not just because if you're
ever in the position to release a tool
to the public it's very nice to have
some experience designing API so that
you release something that's usable and
good that's certainly the case but also
just even for your own purposes like
like I kind of said pulling out this
render is good because someone else
might get a chance to use it but the
other part that's really important is
that it just makes it easier for us to
use so when you spend a few hours going
through and cleaning up a piece of the
code surface boundary right like between
the renderer and the game or something
by cleaning that up it gives you a
chance to do that polish work that can
then pay dividends because now
everything is more well thought through
is more well specified right so you've
decided things like do you specify
things from the center outward or do you
specify them from the bottom up and like
by bringing that extra layer of
consistency into the API it just reduces
frustration it reduces simple mistakes
that people might make because now are
things consistent they don't have to
learn lots of different things so it
really does help if it pays dividends in
more than just code reuse when you spend
time improving an API it also helps you
understand how the code works better
what was involved in it you learn it
better and then you also can use it more
easily because you've done the extra
work necessary to make sure
that you're not doing anything stupid
that it is easiest to use as it can be
that the it's efficient all of those
things that you've done will pay you
dividends going forwards so that I feel
like is really important to underscore
here as we go into this it is important
to learn and important to get right for
two different reasons
and I think that is something worth
noting now what I'd like to do is pop
back to our win32 render test for those
of you just joining us let me just show
you what this is this is an outside
handmade hero that just compiles in the
handmade hero renderer it's very small
so let me go ahead and show you the code
here right
I can't because we're in the wrong
project there we go
so really here's just some simple code
that puts together a simple scene again
not using the API at all so all this
stuff is not part of the API here is
where we start using the render API you
can see very simple it just got a few
simple calls cube sprite right that's
all you need to know to use it that
renders the entire scene basically and
then here's what a render loop looks
like again for start-up mostly windows
code here is the initialization for the
OpenGL layer that you need to call for
our renderer that's really it right
there here is the memory allocation so
you and allocate the memory for the you
don't have to call us to do it you
allocate the memory we may change that a
little if we want this buffer to be
something special but that's a separate
issue so there's that so anyway that's
one thing and then this is all just
initialization for the test scene right
again not really late to the API and
then here's the use of the API again
very simple this is just utility
functions you don't really need to use
this this is just giving you a way to
figure out what region to draw on if you
want a sixteen by nine window rights are
very simple something that steps up the
camera again this is not really using
the API per se you could use anything to
generate as long as you can generate a
camera matrix so in terms of our render
API it's really just this very very
straightforward you initialize the
command buffer that's gonna have
everything in it
you say here's a group of render
commands I'm going to issue here is the
camera transforms that I'm going to use
for them here is the def peel marker
here's the scene end of the death -
marker end of the render group and then
you issued it to OpenGL so again very
very simple you're talking about an API
that basically just that is just that
for your entire render loop which i
think is pretty good so I think that's
all good but we can still do better and
we can also make utility functions for
some of these things that will simplify
this so one of the things that I often
like to say
is you want granularity to be something
that the user is in control of of
whatever your API is so for example in
this case you can see we have a very
high level of granularity here so very
very fine granularity where basically
the user is making their own four by
four camera matrix and has control over
all of this stuff right the dolly the
shift the pitch the orbit right they're
creating their own matrix all this stuff
and that's great and you want that never
get rid of the ability in an API for
someone to micromanage what they're
doing however you also want to provide
high level calls that do all those
things together for people who don't
know or don't care about how that thing
works so for example when I look at all
this code I see an opportunity for us to
provide some utility functions that
again don't get rid of this make sure
this code path still works because you
definitely want the person to be able to
make their own matrices and be able to
position the camera very specifically
like that however they want to but we
also should just make some nice camera
utilities that allow you to just do this
automatically because a lot of the times
that's all you're gonna want to do is
just say here's the point I'm looking at
I want to like spin around it this much
and up this much and here's the ship
let's just make something where these
parameters you just feed those
parameters in and it works right so
something like that seems like a really
good addition to what we have made
because at that point we could get rid
of all this code - for people who again
don't want to know how camera code
necessarily works they can they can sort
of take advantage of the fact that we do
know and off we go right
all right so I think that's one thing we
should look at the other thing that I
think we should look at is this depth
field stuff so I don't necessarily know
to what extent we need the depth field
to be as explicitly programmable as it
currently is I think one thing we could
do is just always def appeal and then
just have some things that are outside
the Deaf peel like I don't know that we
need multiple depth peel groups so it
may simplify the renderer as well as the
API if we just said look render groups
are either depth peeled or they're not
and you don't have to use a begin depth
peel and depth peel you just say when
you begin a render group whether it's
def peeled right that seems pretty easy
to do and I feel like we could do that
really simply here by just actually
adding that into the render group
already and not really doing any
optimization around it meaning actually
just call begin depth you end up peel
for you in the render group for example
I think that might make things easier
since the DEF peels are cleared I mean
the way we have the API now because the
depth peels themselves have a clear
involved I feel like that also means you
really couldn't use multiple of them
anyway so we would have to change this
API to support multiple def peels in the
first place
so I kind of feel like we could simplify
that down because our render really
doesn't support multiple def peel passes
so why bother with this part of it right
so I think we want to do that let's go
ahead and start down this path so there
you go I've now said everything I'm
going to do this is not going to be very
complicated we're just gonna basically
start down the path I said and do as
much as we can today that's really it so
if I jump here to the render
Loup I'm gonna start with the DEF peel
stuff because it's pretty basic I'm
gonna hop over here into the rendered
rib code and I'm gonna I'm just gonna
look at that begin def peel stuff
so here's begin def peel and depth peel
I'm gonna jump to the render group and
I'm just gonna put this in here so we
can kind of look at what they do so if
you look at begin render group yer you
can sort of see in the command structure
as we're doing this you can see that
normally we call begin render group this
way I don't know if we're still using
these generation IDs I actually am very
curious about that I don't know to what
extent we care about this stuff anymore
I feel like we should have been able to
actually get rid of that at some point I
feel like those generation IDs can go
and unfortunately I don't quite know if
they can yet because we're sort of still
relying on them the generation ideas
were just there to avoid having assets
being evicted on a frame where they were
getting used and I don't think we
actually really need to do that anymore
because I'm pretty sure we can just make
our asset eviction happen at a specific
time nowadays and I should state that a
little differently
we kind of know already that the assets
are evicted at a specific time anyway so
if you look at the like the OpenGL
renderer for example so here's 1/32
handmade up in jail and what you can see
is if I jump down to the place where we
actually look at a particular texture oh
sorry now I'm in the wrong file I meant
actually render open jail we're not
talking with you we're talking about the
platform nonspecific OpenGL code not
that platform feel good so if we look in
here when we actually render something
what you can see is when we actually
grab it we don't care anymore about the
loaded bitmap right remember we were
passing loading bitmap down here
originally if you look we care not at
all about loaded bitmaps any
more and the reason for that is we now
process are open Jill our textures we
now process those at an own time which
is right when open Jill manage textures
is called now what we could very easily
do and we may actually want to do is say
that that happens actually on render so
meaning textured transfers are it are
started at that time and so for example
let's suppose I did this right this
would be exactly what we want to do mean
we process these at this time
unfortunately there is a one downside to
this that we may not want I'll fix this
now to I might as well so what I'd like
to do you know what I can also do it
this way and then we can do it in two
stages but let me continue what I was
saying first and then we could talk
about that because this is something we
wanted to get to next weekend is going
to texture race anyway but so let's
suppose we just call opengl managed
textures right here so basically at this
time we know that we're gonna manage our
textures so we take the lock get
everything off the cue process at all
and off we go right so if we know we've
done all of those changes at this point
we know that we really don't need to
worry anymore I think about those
generation IDs because we know that
we're never going to do any evictions
except at a very specific time right
before we start the render process now I
think since those evictions happen like
since those evictions are going to
happen when we're rendering they're
gonna reuse a texture slot technically
speaking I don't know if really what you
want to do is put them here meaning we
don't want to evict anything - we're
done rendering that particular frame
right
because any textures we may have used on
this frame we want to use them first and
then we want to evict them right so I
think we may want the code to look more
like that but once it looks more like
that
I think generation IDs become irrelevant
right I don't think you really need them
because I think most of the time the
generation ID is is really not relevant
let's find out what it it gets used for
just in general so let's suppose I get
rid of that what happens so here we
update them whenever we load here we
let's see here we check when we evict
and that's it so really if we just don't
do that right if we just don't check
generation has completed I think we're
done right so I think that's that's
basically it
yeah hold on one second sorry I just
want to close the door there um so let's
take a look at what happens in in the
generation ID stuff if I just remove
this entirely I think we'd be fine and
then we can get rid of that because we
don't really need that anymore because
we do update the textures at a known
time so in theory we should be able to
ignore that but I you know you never
know with with with multi-threaded code
we're gonna have to double check and
make sure everything's kosher first
before we make that kind of a bold
statement so anyway let me go ahead and
and get rid of that stuff here make sure
that it's not involved anywhere anymore
and then we can test it lightly it will
not really be a definitive test for
obvious reasons
where is that generation ID from there's
another one there let me get rid of it
it's from that it's from the render
group let me just get rid of the one in
the render group that'll generate there
we go that'll generate other ones so we
go no sorry
and again not doing anything interesting
here just removing vestige will remain
to make sure that everything is is
kosher now for sounds as far as when
sounds are evicted it looks like we load
them right when we use them so in theory
that should make it impossible to ever
evict enough in time so I think those
don't care and also those were never
checked in the first place
so those generation I needs weren't
doing anything for us anyway all right
let's see generation ID let me take a
look at render group there and make sure
that we don't actually ask for that
anymore
oops hey that's a good to do we got rid
of sorry ice to take it so long
sometimes you gotta do a little
housecleaning and it's kind of mundane
so we don't really yeah in fact these
two do's I'll say pull this out so
that's a pretty good indication that
maybe it should get pulled out
so in flight generations that should go
away
this should go away operation lock so
I'm not 100% sure what that asset lock
was actually bothering to do but we'll
check it out because I don't want to
remove that lock yeah let's take a quick
look here that gets rid of all of the
generation ID code I want to take a look
at the beginner satlok code though
because that we may actually care about
yes so that we need we can eventually
get rid of this I think because I think
we probably would be able to once we
switch to the different texture system
we may be able to keep things more
straightforward there but the asset lock
for updating the memory headers that we
don't want to get rid of that would
cause us issues for sure
so anyway all right so here's that
render test let me go ahead and make
sure our game is working as well because
that's gonna that person puts more
stress on the asset system certainly
because it's actually loading things
all right so debug build the game works
okay I might try the optimized version
of the game too
we don't have any really good way of
testing about by threading we don't have
really severe like burning kind of test
that we would do which is fine we don't
need to do that kind of testing during
this phase of diliman anyway but I'm
just gonna make sure that there's no
obvious hang-ups like that we didn't
break anything that is immediately clear
so anyway back to where we're going
so that begin render group and render
group now that we pulled out that
Generation Next we don't need any more
because we have a specific asset up to
update time I think we want to keep that
especially for OpenGL output we you can
get fancier with other ApS open jail
really hates multi-threaded texture
transfer it's super hard to get it to
work reliably across systems just
multi-threading in general with OpenGL
just doesn't work
not enough drivers support it well
enough you can't do it and if you're on
certain cards it will work just fine but
it's just not it's got issues buyer
beware
anyway so as far as deafness is
concerned sort of what I was suggesting
we might do is just weld these together
with the beginning of the render group
so for example in here if we were to say
look I do want to begin a render group
with a depth peel maybe that's just a
thing we do explicitly I'm gonna I don't
know what the missing resource count is
for here I think that would just say
look we don't want to render this frame
we count missing resources and see if we
want to delay the frame by one frame or
not which we didn't do here we could do
that that's kind of interesting actually
maybe we should look at that later
anyway when we do begin render group
what we could do is have two ways of
beginning render group we could do
basically a def peeled render group and
a non def peeled render group and so I
guess what I'd say here is we could just
say
I mean we could just weld this together
and be like do you want to clear do you
want a depth feel and when you begin the
render group you say which of those you
want I don't know that that that's great
but I'm gonna try it and we're gonna see
what happens so let's suppose that this
begin render group just takes some flags
and it says what you want to do with it
I'm just gonna try that and see if I
like it I don't know if I will I might
not so let's just say I have an enum
rendered group flags and I'll have
render clear do you want to clear guess
candle prints lucency or I guess like
Auto sort sort
something like that
meaning do something that handles the
sort automatically or like handle
overlapping transparency or I don't know
I don't know something like that
I got nothing I don't know what to call
that but we're just gonna go with that
for now so if you want to do a clear you
can specify that if you want to help
transparency you can specify that I and
maybe I'll also say like there's sort of
a third kind of thing that I might want
to do in the future which is that so I
don't know for sure but I may just want
to have the ability to to do like 3d
shapes versus 2d shapes so I feel like
we may also want to do like something
like anti-alias edges because to a
certain extent we don't really need to
run the we don't need to run the multi
sampling path on anything other than the
cubes right so like when we do our
render group we could choose to do no
depth feeling and anti-aliasing on the
cubes and then we could choose to do
anti-aliasing and I'm sorry def peeling
but no anti-aliasing on the things that
aren't the cubes you know what I mean
I don't really know if we want to do
that because it seems like maybe it's
better to just allow everything to maybe
that just gets too complicated you know
I don't know I'll just leave it like
this for now we'll see how it goes all
right so here in the render group I want
one of these to base to say what the
flags are and what I'm gonna do here
again for the benefit of people who
maybe don't necessarily know what's
going on I'm gonna also have a render
like default and that's gonna be one
that does both of these right so it's
this or this and that's what you'll get
if you just so that way if you're just
doing one render group here you would
get the thing that works you know for
just a game scene if you don't know what
you're doing you can just slam
everything through that path and it will
work it may not be the best thing for
later when you're trying to do something
more specific but it will work right so
then what we can do is put this stuff on
here I am trying to think of like for
depth clear and full clear I don't know
to what extent we were actually doing
those I don't know when we do like depth
clear versus full clear but maybe I'll
put here like maybe I could put those in
here
yeah so I'm gonna look at when we're
using that I'm assuming it's for the
debug it is so what would happen is here
we would do that depth clear right and
so I think that's probably just fine
I don't know if we have to make sure
that we push a camera transform first
before the clear in order to make sure
the scissor rect is not messed up but
that's kind of a separate issue as far
as full clear is concerned that's not
really used other than in the same way
yeah so that's just what we would do at
the beginning of that render group for
clearing the screen anyway is not
particularly relevant either way so I
think we're good I think we don't really
have to worry too much about this so I'm
gonna go ahead and say that that'll work
I'm gonna arbitrarily say that and
obviously I don't actually know but
that's fine so then I'm gonna get rid of
those debt to Def peel pieces so those
depth peel part things will go away and
I'm gonna weld those in for now so let's
put these up in here as well as these so
if the render group is a depth filled
render group we need to remember that
and probably the easiest thing to do
here is just store the flags that that
were used for us you know so what I can
do is say when we put this on here the
flags will be remembered and that way we
can test them later as necessary I think
that should do it
yeah so then what I'm going to do is
minitest these flags and I'm gonna see
whether we need to do like a clear color
or a clear depth and I'm gonna see
whether or not we want to do a death
feel
so the way that I want to do this is say
that at the moment if we're doing handle
transparency you have to clear
everything that's just how we require it
to be done I believe at the moment so in
this case I will say like assert that
both of these are true I think that's
what we want to do meaning we want to
say hey right now if you're gonna do a
transparency pass you have you have to
clear and if you didn't specify clear
then that's just an error and you will
have you will be sad panda in the future
we could try to figure out a way to
support that because you could actually
copy the depth buffer or the color
buffer into the first def peel layer so
you could technically do that and
actually have that work I just don't
know that we want to write so again I'm
just experimenting with this I may
decide this is not good we'll see but
I'm gonna at least try it first so
here's my depth heal
so in that case that's all we needed to
do in this case I think we also don't
have and I'm gonna grab these two right
here we currently don't have a way to
clear just the color so we're also going
to assert here and again these are just
to make sure that no one tries to use it
in that way yet because we don't support
it we don't want them to be confused
about why it's not working we could
start to try and support those later for
people who want to do something fancier
right but at the moment we're not gonna
so here's our clear depth and here's our
full clear and I think that's mostly it
this should really be now
okay let's yeah so we got here semicolon
missing flags are off the render groups
drop the render group why this isn't
just about group I don't know cuz I
guess I really like typewriter grip
every time it's like what other group
would be in this function that we would
need to differentiate those two so now
what we want to do is make sure people
aren't calling these manually and so
what we want to do is give them a name
that will make sure that doesn't happen
so I'm just gonna go ahead and
underscore these so that basically
everybody who is calling them cannot
call them and only the internal code
will call them and we may well these
together later on so like I'm
anticipating also kind of sort of
getting rid of those right so I just
want them give them a name that no one
will use and then what I can do is pull
this stuff apart into a you know make
this stuff a little bit more specific
here as to how it's it's working right
so we don't need this anymore
now it's just that and this should be
rendered default actually okay and now
for the game the background color is
just going to be for the render group
and how are we so is this render group
how are we getting this render group who
makes the start of the render group
because I'm not sure what's happening
there let me look at update and render
world so the render group actually gets
created like outside and I don't really
know why
[Music]
that that yeah I don't know what really
is going on there so let's take a look
at a couple of things here first of all
what is draw buffer supposed to be doing
here like what's going on there
what is that for yeah that's that's just
garbage it's it's really just there to
get the width in like one thing like
let's let's that we got to get rid of
that as well like the eliminate this in
these entirely all of this stuff you
know that that couldn't that comment
could not be truer I don't know what
that's doing there let's let's hose that
right away
all right so now as far as depth
clearing is concerned so on here when we
go to do these commands we really want a
depth clear right here and that should
be fine for depth peeling we want that
to be done on the outside we can look at
that in a second in here I feel like
this wants to be its own push-pull like
this should be its own open closed and
the same would be true of here so when
this does rendered layered seen that
clear should have been just at the
outset I don't know why I guess it's
only if the layer count was zero that we
want to but we kind of want to do it at
all times anyway in case there's a
little bit of something missing in there
I don't know or we just don't want to do
it at all so I'm not sure this is a
little bit strange I'm not sure why
that's there yeah it doesn't make a
whole lot of sense let's see here so I'm
gonna get rid of this entirely I'd like
to get rid of draw buffer as well I mean
I'm just gonna start icing that
everywhere I see it I think that's a
vestige will remain from the old days
that's all stuff I wanna update in a
second here's draw buffer I'm just
getting rid of it and I that I think
that was just from the software renderer
we just never got rid of it it's not
necessary anymore but it was still
getting passed through all the time so
let's take a look here at cutscene dot H
update and render title screen well see
where else that draw buffers still still
hanging around like I don't want that in
there anywhere so we need the width
there you know that's true and that's
fine
so I think that's all good and we just
need a way of getting the width in into
here so it's some way of figuring out
how big it is to get this so we can get
the standard camera parameters and let
me just look at what we're doing with
the standard camera parameters to make
sure we even really need to do that soon
that's in the renderer hey not a lot of
using of width in pixels there so I
guess that's the end of that that's
pretty funny I guess
that's again the bonus of cleaning up
the code you're like hey do I need to
pass this it's not even used and then
you can just get rid of it alright so
now I think what I'd like to do is stop
with the passing in of that because I
want people to be able to open their own
render blocks pretty much as necessary
so this code right here that does the
begin render group stuff I kind of want
that to be something that you use
directly and so I feel like these will
now be able to open their own and you
know you're really so now you can really
think of the render commands structure
as really the thing that gets plat
passed around that's the thing you're
actually adding to and render groups are
just things you open and close as you
wish
which is kind of what they were supposed
to be so this I'm just gonna say look we
passed down the render commands and you
do whatever you want to do with that we
don't pass down the render group anymore
you create your own render group as
necessary right
and I think that's all we really need to
do so anyone who wants to make one of
these now can just do it anyone who
wants to do it right can just do this
and the other thing we could do is if we
wanted to we could actually use this as
a pointer in the render group could it
in fact return a pointer the reason
we're not doing that is it's kind of
just easier to put it on the stack and
the compiler probably has an easier time
understanding what's going on so this
code is just written this way so that
you don't have to keep taking the
address of it I don't know how valuable
that really is to be completely honest
but you know all right
so let's go in here and get that going I
don't remember what this is called
render commands okay so what I'd like to
do here is just open up a render group
when I actually need one so right here
is sort of where it starts although I
don't think it really needs to start
here so we can probably actually move
this some are else but point being in
here we want to say is okay we're gonna
do a render handle transparency and we
want to do a render clear color and a
render depth clear so we're gonna do all
three for this render group and we are
gonna pass that background color and
clear this so then whenever we use these
I don't really remember where we use
these what we actually do start right
there so that's fine so then after we
push all the rendering on here
that's pretty much the end of our render
group and I suppose what I might well
we'll we'll take let's take a look at
that in a second so then in here if we
actually wanted to render something else
I think if we wanted to render something
else we would just open the render group
again in here right so what I want to do
is say okay this it's gonna do the same
thing again and this time it's going to
do no transparency probably I don't know
how we want to do this exactly but I
don't really know exactly but we don't
need to do
Yeah right so that seems totally
reasonable and that way you just open
and close render groups as you want them
okay bat and so for the title screen and
then we've also got the cutscenes those
are both things that again can open
their own as they wish and those don't
need to use the duck dealer at all
I don't think so anyway I suppose
actually nice look at it it looks like
we actually only need to open it if
we're gonna do this so there's our
background color we don't have a title
screen yet so really this is sort of
putting the cart before the horse I
suppose there's nothing to render but
hey we're clearing the screen I guess so
we can see that the title screen would
go here we don't need a handle
transparency on this we just need to
clear and that's what we're gonna do and
the same would be true for this although
I think this doesn't need to clear so it
doesn't need to clear and it doesn't
really need to use the death buffer so
we can just clear just the depth buffer
even though we don't really need it to
use the depth buffer which is a little
complicated but yeah we don't really
have multimodal rendering in that sense
so at the moment anyway we don't have a
way of saying just turn we don't have a
way of saying turnoff depth testing we
could actually put that in here and
maybe we should we probably don't need
to
but I'll put it to do so this way at
least we know you know if we want to do
it we can and I don't know that we ever
would care because the title screens
just probably aren't particularly
interesting in that sense but for the
software renderer you know maybe we
would want to put that in there someday
so that it could kind of say like hey
look this thing really would help if we
didn't have to check a z-buffer so let's
tell it that you don't need to check a
z-buffer for putting these right and so
that that could come into play for
hardware rendering no it's no good
hardware won't care at all
hardware's too fast it's gonna render a
layered cutscene no problem right so I
think that's all we really needed to do
I don't know to what extent this is
working so we have to go ahead and make
sure that it actually is I want to test
both projects to make sure that we
haven't broken anything I also don't
know okay so we have broken something
okay so you were wondering spatial
lighting where is my call stack there it
is
[Music]
inside lighting test who calls that Oh
hmm hmm I say um okay okay well let's
think about this a little bit more
because our lighting is a little bit
oops because I know it's a little bit
janky right now so I hadn't really
considered how that might flow through
the pipeline we may have to make a
little bit of a special concession for
that so looking here the root box is
zero I believe that the root box is zero
because there are no boxes and I believe
the reason there are no boxes is because
we started the render group fresh right
here so I believe what actually has to
happen is this begin render group has to
be moved down in a sense right so for
example in here what we would need to do
is when this you know with this stuff
set up the way that it is the lighting
test actually has to be placed sort of
here unfortunately right so we need to
kind of do that it needs to happen as
something that happens before you close
the render group that you were working
with and
for output lighting points and output
lighting textures I guess I don't
remember when the lighting so the
lighting already got pushed on here
yeah the lighting is kind of a bit
broken we really want to clean up how
that's working because as you can see
it's kind of a little janky here so
really an output lighting textures is
always gonna be done as well so I guess
you just want to do like you can see
this this is very messy you want to do
this I think and then for here you want
to say if you were gonna show the
lighting then you clear everything and
just make a render pass that does
nothing to that right something like
this and again I think that the lighting
is not finished yet right the lighting
is kind of a work in progress so it's
not I don't want to make much of a big
deal about that I want just leave it and
I think that will kind of sort itself
out over time also we don't do we
actually have
I want to take a look what what happens
to for our title screen we haven't
really done that in a while so we should
probably look at that too it looks like
we don't have a clean exit path for that
play title screen what's that going to
do
so I might want to clean these up Lily
could see these are kind of ugly too
we're kind of going down a little bit of
a rat hole here but its a rat hole that
has a rat that's been bothering us so I
feel like it's a hole that you want to
go into to get the rat out of to a
certain extent so if you look at the way
that we've got this set up as far as the
transient state is concerned right oh
hey there's still the main generation ID
there I don't really want that if you
look at the way this is set up we have
like game modes here right and you can
kind of see the different game modes
that we've got each one of these and
they have their arena on it
I don't know like why we still even have
this anymore we don't really need that
and so I do wonder a little bit about
this structure to what extent this is
actually relevant anymore I kind of feel
like it doesn't really need to be there
and we can kind of we could collapse it
down just into something more specific I
mean it cuz it gets they'll stay named
transient State if it wants to but like
really it's just going to be these
pointers and not this
so what to think about that a little bit
but a lot of these things again can be
made simpler now that we know how things
work we can simplify things down into
stuff that doesn't actually require as
much fancy footwork so as far as the
game you know you can see here we've got
this arena stuff for the game state I
feel like that stuff can sort of just be
it Systema sized a little bit more and I
feel like these things like the trainer
like let's just do it I I'm in a clean
up mood let's just get rid of that and I
want to see where what's actually going
in there right so we've got the assets
are going in there the Lighting's going
in there
yeah it's just not much stuff I I I'm
gonna I'm gonna nuke that I know this is
a lot of changes at once and I apologize
but it's just like sometimes if you're
in a cleanup mode and you're cleaning up
the code it's just getting rid of stuff
feels really good because you could
simplify things and make it more
reasonable which is just always fun
right
so okay look also do we actually need
the struct here yeah I don't think so
so let's kind of move along and see
what's actually happening so in here we
are allocating our game assets right and
that we get past the transient state and
we use the transient state to allocate
these sort of temporary buffers right we
don't really need to do that because we
can't now our ability to do temporary
ops is actually a lot better than it
used to be we can just make temporary
memory and have it go away in the middle
of a in the middle of a function pretty
easily right especially in an init
function we wouldn't really need to pass
a transient Arena there for any of this
stuff we didn't want to for lighting
memory the game mode which is you know
this stuff here I feel like I feel like
pretty much there should just be a temp
here so we've got the mode arena I don't
really know why we probably we broke
these down a little bit earlier before
right so I feel like you know these
arenas can be segmented pretty easily
here and you could just say look there's
a temporary arena like this
and we could say that this just
automatically gets cleared once per
frame and then you wouldn't even have to
bracket the temporary lighting stuff at
all
right you could just say like oh okay
you know the gamestate a it just uses
the frame arena for that and off you go
I assume we know the game stayed in here
because yeah we would have to the
transient State on the other hand I
don't even know what that's for is it
just for the asset pointer I guess it's
for the queues and stuff so really that
becomes more of a work distribution
thing you know what I mean this this
will probably not be called transient
state eventually is what it's looking
like to me because it won't really be
necessary um so when we do allocate game
assets I'm interested to know is who I
want to skip that for now because I'm
interested to know who calls that and
what what I want to do exactly that but
we can get rid of this now and similarly
like most of this stuff that's that's
being put on that temporary arena like
it can just it doesn't really need to be
doing that anymore right okay let me
just take a look what else we got so in
terms of the world Sims here right same
deal so that transient arena this can
just be the frame arena and similarly
like again it doesn't really have to be
cleared like it could be but doesn't
have to be so you know if you wanted to
have begin sim and sim not really reset
that memory it totally could I also
don't know to what extent it actually
already automatically does that
so the sim arena it doesn't really
bracket that so this does right here
because it knows the can yeah and off
you go
so if we wanted to we could make this
even more aggressive and not even have
that and not even have that clear until
the end of the frame I don't know that
we want to do that but there are reasons
we might want to do that eventually like
if we don't if we want to be able to
access stuff and know that it lasts for
the entire frame we could start actually
just not clearing that arena at all
right and that's kind of interesting
yeah
so let me inspect this a little bit so
what I would like to do here I guess to
is say okay so when we do when we come
in here to game update and render when
we actually have a functioning game
state what I'd like to do is make sure
that we end up with we end up with
something yeah so like the transient
state doesn't really need to be done in
the way that it's being done at the
moment right yeah so what I'd like to do
here is once we actually have the game
mode going whatever the game with
whatever this game state is here I'd
like to go ahead and say all right
that game state arena is just gonna be
like it's gonna be snapped
as a begin temporary right
and then we will clear it at the end
before we conclude and the render memory
is not gonna be a thing like that goes
away and so now anyone who wants to use
the frame arena for rendering should
just go ahead and do so and that's gonna
be cleared every frame I'm also gonna
assert that the frame arena has nothing
in it so like I should be able to do
that right by looking at the memory
arena and seeing if the platform memory
block is there I assume that once we
clear I don't know if we really give
those blocks back we do so basically I
can assert that the frame arena tent I
can assert that the current block has
nothing in it right
so yeah continuing down that road having
the transient thing have an arena is
really now only relevant because it
wants to allocate one of these transient
stay things but I really don't care
about that
and furthermore I don't really like the
way the game mode thing is working here
because we can't have multiple of them
which is a little weird so really yeah
like it's not fabulous I guess is what
I'm saying
I don't I don't love how this ended up
because I feel like we want the game
mode to have its own arenas like this
mode arena should be owned by whoever is
in here so that we can have multiple of
these exist at the same time if we
wanted to you know there's no real
reason not to do that and so you know
the place where these get their memory
from should really be coming from a more
specific place and then this stuff just
gets flattened together right so game
state just has this stuff in it there's
no point to this stuff right like this
would just come down here
and everyone just uses the gamestate for
that and then the game-mode itself it
can have its own arena in there that
would just get cleared out when it's
done you know I'm Sam and we sort of do
that with this but you couldn't keep
both of them at that point so you'd
rather have it so that the game-mode is
like a flushable thing that you can keep
around if you wish like this should go
in there I'm gonna real quick do this we
don't need that I don't know why we need
the task with memory up there but that's
okay maybe cuz gets used in there so I'm
gonna go ahead and say that whenever we
look at you know stuff like this that
operation lock do we even know if the
operation lock should be on there and
not on the assets like I don't know if
we even know that really but maybe we do
but anyway point being inside the assets
structure we can really just store the
gamestate pointer than if that's what we
really need although let's take a look
at everyone who calls on the operation
lock so the operation lock is only
called on is only called on the assets
anyway so that's yeah okay fantastic
so that is just dumb to begin with right
that should not have been in here that's
probably because of again old
architectural things so this is pretty
great like there's a lot of stuff we can
clean up in here and if there is a lot
of stuff you can clean up then you
should right so I'm gonna put this in
here and I'm gonna leave that to do
because I think we may want to get rid
of it entirely but anyway point being
this now can be done thusly I don't know
why this wasn't marked volatile probably
because you only ever use it in an
atomic compare exchange which will treat
it as volatile but I'm just gonna mark
it that way just so everyone know
is that it is so in here I think the low
priority queue needs to be accessible so
the assets would have to be able to get
back to the game State there I can leave
this in here because I am still not
thrilled about it
any chance you're gonna give me begin
tasks with memory probably not huh so
this is just game state and actually
trans State oops trans state and game
state here just the same and really this
is going to be the same everywhere
so this transient estate here in the
memory structure this is just that and
inside handmade H you can see kind of
why this change occurs right the reason
that the change occurs is because we now
have the ability to articulate from the
game to the platform layer what isn't is
not transient before it was the other
way around the platform layer
articulated forwards what that was
whereas now we just say when we create
an arena is it restored or isn't it you
know what I mean so now you don't need
to pass information about what is the
transient state and what is the game
state that's not necessary
right so this is not necessary you only
need that and then the arena's
themselves say whether or not they were
restored per block so yeah you know it's
just again six of one half dozen at the
other but now we got to do some type in
particularly now okay
so put on your track shoes or track
finger tip something and just replace
these as we go eventually we might be
able to figure out what to do with those
low part accuse maybe they get stuck on
the asset system permanently you know
for all I know that's that's entirely
feasible as a potential thing you know
maybe that stuff can be made clearer
will certainly see but oops
for right now I just have to okay so
this is actually as far as the arena's
are concerned here you can see that we
have our non restored memory and then we
we sort of create all of our stuff in
the non restored memory pool for our
assets because it doesn't get saved to
disk right
so for these these are just places where
we temporarily push something on and we
don't do any allocations in here at all
right well we come through here
so these want to be done in a in a
temporary way and so I guess I will just
say these are going to be you know
they're just going to use that frame
arena because we don't care what happens
to them
and I feel like this stuff can be
simplified down quite a bit it's just a
unfortunate thing of untangling a little
bit of how we were doing it originally
that we don't really need to do anymore
right
um create worlds show me create worlds I
don't actually know what create world
needs to do does it actually use this it
doesn't so really create worlds can just
be that looks like
[Music]
okay so this stuff is a lot of pretty
wrote that these can get rid of these
things entirely just again simplifies
things and this is really all I am
literally doing is just getting rid of
that separation because now the arena's
remember that separation internally
which is just a feature we just didn't
have originally right and there's a
couple other things we're gonna have to
do in terms of making sure the code
reloading works but otherwise it should
be pretty simple
what's going on why aren't we jumping
sorry this is kind of just taking a
while and is going to be boring that's
just the nature of pulling something out
it's easy to do but you know not
particularly exciting especially since
most people were past this thing so we
in terms of debug get game assets we can
really just do this yeah and get it that
way that's what I meant to do before I
just didn't change the actual point of
there
so yeah so for this we don't care about
this at all so it should be sufficient
to do this
[Music]
this stuff is all not what we want and
this is just basic very simple basics so
the only thing that's a little annoying
is that when we allocate the game assets
we would like to do so I am gonna go
ahead and just make this do an end
temporary here just to make sure that it
has something it can use basically to
get rid of whatever it's you know
happens to use this temporary memory
although I suppose it's I think about it
I suppose it actually is doing that
itself so I suppose I don't really even
need to do that
now the key game assets presumably also
presumably also this stuff can go now
because since we have grobel arenas we
don't really need to lock a maximum size
on that either
[Music]
yeah there's a lot of stuff we could
simplify now because the arena's are
just a lot more powerful than they used
to be think that should mostly do it
yeah
so I don't actually know yeah I don't
actually know how we want to proceed on
this but we'll kind of play it by ear so
at this point now we have the we sort of
have the transient arena as merged in
now with our frame and the problem that
we're gonna have is that now we just
need to make sure that our sort of coat
our memory flashing will work properly
when we reload things so if we go back
to the win32 side of things when you're
in the platform this game memory stuff
right
we don't really provide anything
specific with game memory anymore on the
win32 side of things so if you look at
game state right we never touch it and
the reason for that is the fat
allocation is something that happens
inside like that's something that
happens inside the game and gets set
there as something that the game you
know cares about right so in terms of
what we need to make sure work when you
do something like loop life code editing
[Music]
in theory what we've got now would kind
of just work but there are some issues
with it like as far as the as far as
anything that's non restored so if we
look here and we look at what's non
restored you can see that it's like only
the asset system that is non restored
memory and so what happened
is anytime this stuff is doing anything
it's going into the non restored pool
what that means is that all of the
things in the game asset structure that
get allocated into the non restored pool
themselves should not actually get
restored either so the game asset
pointer needs to not get restored
it needs to stay the same if that's
actually true which it looks like it is
in most cases then we should be okay
because it won't restore any of this at
all
so the fact that it's all non-responder
stored memory should be fine I don't
know if the tasks cause a problem I
think we shut down all running tasks
before we start so in theory that should
be fine too but I'm not 100% sure so I
want to check so let's start with some
basics to see if we work at all
right so here we are in the the game and
I'm gonna go into the world mode and
just play like I'll change the clear
color or something right just to make
sure that we can reload this background
color here so just to make sure that we
can reload this I'm gonna set the
background color to be like some kind of
red or something and just see whether it
reloads properly and doesn't grind to a
screaming halt
right and it didn't it didn't flash the
screen either so you could tell the
assets were non reloaded I'm gonna do it
again again looks pretty clear I'm gonna
switch to debug from debug to release
there's our framerate jump and that all
seems good I should try a loop I don't
remember how to do a loop but let's try
one
and as far as memory blocks are
concerned I don't really
also remember so one of the things that
we have had a problem with and you could
see it there is our debug system is not
very good at avoiding string usage
that's in the unrelated blocks one thing
that some people do and we could do is
just not unload the DLLs and you get
into a little bit of a problem there
where if you'd never unload dll's maybe
eventually get too many dll's or
something but it would be nice if we
could avoid having to do that right like
so one thing we might consider doing
there is just getting rid of that
because this part this stuff doesn't
really work correctly with that because
specifically we aren't careful enough
about making sure our strings get copied
right anyway that's neither here nor
there I just wanted to make sure that
was okay and it all is looks like at the
moment so that's fine now let's go back
to debugging what I wanted to bug before
which is how those cutscenes are working
if those cutscenes are working so going
in here you can see we get a problem
we've got a render group this oh just to
be clear since you can't see that forgot
you can't see what I'm doing when I hit
escape on the keyboard you end up going
through a code path that puts us out to
cutscene mode which we haven't
maintained and we should it was just
been in there kind of sitting around it
doesn't get used but we should and so
what I wanted to do was if you look here
if we hit escape what's gonna happen is
the it's gonna delete the player who hit
escape and there's only one player in
the game if you know we can put in more
than one player and then it wouldn't but
if we hit escape we get rid of the
player in the game and so then it'll
switch to the title screen here so I can
show you that happening I hit escape
we're gonna go to play title screen and
play title screen is gonna go to set
game mode so what that does right is it
looks here to see if there are tasks
that we're still running that our
opponent of game mode again that's
something we could probably fix by by
striding those things if we need to wait
we look and well okay I probably
shouldn't have hit run because you
jumped over that let's try it again so
there is no work that had to get done so
it comes up here and it's gonna clear
the mode arena for this game mode there
it goes and then it's gonna switch the
game mode to a different game mode right
and the problem with that is again like
when we actually go then to when we go
to render the actual frame so when the
render commands get issued they're bogus
because some of them are pointing into
something that actually exists on the
world mode stack right it's it's
actually here so to be honest fixing
that the way that that should have
happened is the lighting textures should
actually come back from the push so
really that's just kind of a screw up in
general so I don't think I want to fix
this by going down the game mode route
yet I'm happy we got rid of the
transient Arina it wasn't none of that
stuff Ness was needed to be in there
really any more because our arenas are
smarter than they used to be and could
do that themselves
but this is not proper
this should come back from the render
system so these pieces of light data
should be coming back from the render
system and and they're not so what we
want to do is get rid of this like that
should not be there and anyone who was
using that needs to stop what I would
recommend
is that the test textures so the
lighting textures here
those should come back from push
lighting is what should happen right
push lighting should give us back the
police where we write our lighting to
and we might do that a little bit
differently in the future but for the
moment we definitely want the renderer
to tell us where do we put our lighting
textures right push lighting should be
in here summer there is insu in here
right when when we get this stuff out
this going onto the temporary nough is
fine and when we call that push lighting
call here and we passed a frame arena
that would work just fine so what we can
do temporarily is we can just go ahead
and when we push these on this source
here I'm just gonna say that's actually
gonna get allocated itself so that'll
just be push direct lighting textures
and we can then play with this later
but that's exactly what we want there
something more like this so now that
will persist properly throughout the
frame and we just have to do a little
bit more work to make sure that it's
actually valid at render time in fact
yeah I think about this still won't work
because this frame is clean this is
cleared before the render finishes so we
actually want to do that slightly
differently than we were before so I'll
show you how we can do that in a second
alright so I want to return these so
that they can get pushed onto in that
temporary arena
what did I call that light textures like
so
okay so those light textures if I run
out I'm still gonna have the same
problem which is that they will go away
only this time they'll definitely go
away because instead of being allocated
being in the permanent or they get freed
right before we exit and the renderer
hasn't been invoked yet right because
that gets invoked on the platform side
but that's really no big deal what we
can do pretty easily is inside the the
handmade CTP code right we have two
choices we can if we want to make the
frame arena be something who's temporary
actually lasts one round right so that's
one option the other option is we just
get our lighting space passed in to us
which also seems like a good idea right
I don't know which one of those I want
to do let me show you what this would
look like so what we want to do here is
say okay the frame arena
instead of getting cleared here it
doesn't this is not where that happens
so the mode arena gets cleared every
time round but the frame arena actually
gets cleared only when it goes to get
used again right and this is then
something that actually exists in the
game State and it just gets cleared at a
strobe point right so it lasts outside
and we can totally do that
and it just depends which one we want
since we don't really need to use this
for anything else I would lean towards
moving the lighting into the renderer
commands buffer proper that seems like a
better idea but I just want to show how
we would have done it if we wanted to do
it here it's not complicated right so
here what we would do I just realized I
gotta clear this so I can't call this
the first time around
how do I want to you know I probably do
this so the first time we allocate set
it up there and that way from then on it
will always get checked it'll always
have a clue to always be able to clear
itself or however you want to and say
that right so then that structure
doesn't exist in a bogus place right
okay so now let's go ahead and try to
get our title screen stuff working I
yeah I don't actually know how much work
it would be to get all those things
working so I'm gonna take a little look
at them but I don't promise anything
because I got to go on time today
what time is it it's like one o'clock
one twelve yeah I can't be too late
today I have something happening later
today
should be in the title screen here we're
not seeing the clear right and that I'm
not 100% sure if that's just because we
need to be going through the def peeler
to see the clear which is kind of a
slightly slightly different thing I'm
gonna go ahead and just check that part
cuz I don't know if that's render
related or not so this stuff here I'm
just gonna quickly change this to render
defaults and same up here instead of
this I'm gonna change it to render
default and that's just a check because
I don't know to what extent the the
rendering subsystem is doing something
stupid right now
and doesn't let sighs yeah so it's just
that we don't actually support a lack of
depth peels at the moment so that's I
think probably where are where we're at
so yeah the cutscenes seem like they're
working okay otherwise but we really
don't need cutscenes to go through the
depth feeling so I I want to fix that
yeah this all looks pretty good
all right let's go to Q&amp;A
if I use a wrist support while typing
and using a mouse I do for typing I use
this in front of the keyboard it's just
a you know thick sort of foam pad I do
find it helps I don't use one from
mousing but that's probably like I don't
use the mouse that much so I you know
don't really need one can you go through
the rendering pipeline briefly again
what are the render commands and render
groups what are they used for and when
do they get initialized then what
exactly is OpenGL doing with them so
that's a little bit broad I mean that's
you know multiple days worth of stuff
that we've done but briefly render
commands is a structure that is the
thing that you provide to the renderer
whatever it is so it basically gets
initialized in the platform layer and it
can be specific to the platform layer so
you know you can allocate the memory
wherever you want you can allocate the
memory in graphics card memory if you
want you can do whatever you want if the
platform for that platform right that
gets passed to the game and render
groups are then buckets of commands that
go into the render command structure but
the render group is just a utility
struct you use to not have to store
stuff like where in the render commands
you were or what kind of group you're
using at the time things like this right
so render group is just a utility
wrapper around the render commands that
people use and that's it
OpenGL in specifically takes the render
commands that you have built and execute
them in order so it just goes through
and actually C really does them and
right now it's not very efficient and
that's because we haven't done texture
packing
so that's one of the big things we need
to do is is the texture packing sort of
stuff
[Music]
hidden triforces on the orphanage so i
are there I mean I don't really know
that I didn't request any
let's see how can I start in game
development without knowing much about
C++ well it depends what you want to do
right like if you want to be an engine
program or you got to learn that stuff
because that's there are no such things
as engines not written in C++ I mean
there's like maybe one successful one
that I know of which would be minecraft
was written in Java but you know it's
Minecraft it's not a particularly good
looking game and not a particularly
performant game either so it kind of
just is lucky that you happen to be able
to do a world of blocks with a very
short draw distance in Java right but
that's sort of a separate issue um so
yeah I mean if essence you want to do if
you just want to make a game you know I
don't know you can do things of
different degrees of simplicity right
like you can go I want to say like you
could start with something very simple
like RPG Maker or game maker right like
these are things designed for people who
don't on a program and it can get you
started so it really just depends on
what you want to do if you want to
actually work on serious game technology
that is a long learning process and it's
a dedicated field and that's the stuff
we do on handmade hero I don't cover how
to do like simple game like I want to
script a game in unity or whatever
that's there's plenty of tutorials out
there for that sort of thing and you can
go grab them and furthermore like things
like game maker come with example games
you can look at right like you don't
need much to use those tools to make
games of the form that the tools
supports right if you want to make like
a platformer game makers got like the
stuff you need in there for it and it's
pretty straightforward and it works and
people have shipped games with it that
are popular right like I can't think of
what game maker ones would be off the
top of my head but like I think like
chasm probably was gaming or was it I
don't know if that's true
yeah I shouldn't say cuz I yeah I don't
know off the top of my head like what's
made in what but like you know you can
point to popular games that were made
and like game maker and and and you know
it's it's it's not an impediment to
commercial success necessarily what it
is though you know one of the problems
that you do face nowadays is if you just
if you're just someone who doesn't
really know much about programming and
you use you know unity or game maker or
something to make a game one of the
problems that you do have is what's the
difference between your game and
everyone else there's literally 7,000
people a year doing exactly what you're
doing
7,000 teams a year doing exactly what
you're doing so if you can't program
anything new and differentiate yourself
you'd better have good art I guess is
what I would say like you need like
because you can't just be like bad art
and bad programming and hey we just
downloaded unity and used it that you're
just gonna be no one's gonna care right
so you need to have a plan for that and
it's important to understand right
and so you gotta have something that
differentiates you and maybe you're like
an amazing game designer and you you
just have like these ideas that people
haven't had before about how to design
game 99% of the people who think they're
great if that are actually not very good
and you're just gonna design something
exactly like everyone else right and so
again like you know you have to be
realistic and so one of the things you
have to understand is like what are you
trying to build why is anyone gonna care
about that because the number 7,000 was
not arbitrary there literally are 7,000
new games on Steam every year now why is
anyone going to buy your game it can't
just be because you downloaded unity and
put something together because that's
not good enough right you have to have
something else you have to
and what you are bringing to the table
that's one of the reasons I think game
engine programming is a very good
discipline to be involved in because
people always need it
there are very few people who know how
to do it and you can't just download
unity or download error because those
companies themselves need to make the
engine so you can always have a job even
if it's just working on one of those
engines if you are a good engine
programmer if all you know how to do is
script games good luck right I feel like
your employment prospects if that's all
you know how to do are pretty darn
limited because anyone can learn how to
write a script in unity pretty quickly
and if they don't know all the core
fundamentals if they're not really good
with vector math if they don't have all
the things they would need to be like a
really outstanding unity programmer for
example then what's the point like why a
good engine programmer can also make a
big difference on a Unity game or on a
Unreal game because they can write all
this custom code that nobody else can do
right so it's just I feel like there's a
lot to understand there when you're
thinking about it and people who don't
understand the value of learning how to
program games for real I think they're
in for a pretty rude awakening because
your competition is fierce
out there and if you think you're just
gonna download an engine and not know
what you're doing and put together
something that anyone cares about well I
can say is you better have great artists
right because they can they can pull it
out for you right really great artists
can differentiate your game with the art
but if you don't have that you're in a
lot of trouble
can you recommend any game engine the
source code that would be helpful to
look over for general architecture for
example the doom engine etc I feel like
quake is probably good for old school
for new school like the problem with
quake is it's not gonna be
multi-threaded so game architecture in
the new in new days is gonna have at
least some multi-threading and I don't
know what to look for for that I mean
obviously you can look at the Unreal
Engine if you want to but good luck
right because it's massive so I don't
know how realistic that really is in
terms of an educational process but
as reference can you disclose how much
you paid the artist for handmade here no
like generally I wouldn't probably give
out the details of someone else's
contract I would not necessarily be
adverse to them giving out the details
of their contract for a contractor but
like a contractor is their own business
basically and you know if you tell
people what they gave you on their game
or whatever it's maybe a little unfair
to them in terms of negotiating
you know maybe they charged you less
than they should have or you know maybe
they charge you more and it's fine we
try to pay well so we probably paid good
relative to other jobs that person had
done but you know again I don't really
want to do that for an independent
contractor I don't think that's
appropriate for the rest of the art so
that was young-shin
[Music]
for the cutscenes and she was did the
initial concept work and stuff and I
took it over after she was working at
Molly full-time I and so she now you
couldn't it would be hard to say what
the budget would be because she just
does it like part-time as we need stuff
as part of her work here which isn't the
same as like billable hours on a
contractor
I mean one thing I can say is that in
terms of looking at the market I would
say contract art tends to run somewhere
between 35 and 65 dollars an hour
depending on the experience of the
contractor and where they are located
and where you are located for us prices
outside us things can be totally
different right 65 dollars an hour is
probably an insanely high contractor
rate in Argentina right I pick Argentina
because I happen to know some contract
prices there and like the dollar is much
more depressed there in terms of
economics so that would be like a
ludicrously high contract salary if it
was an argentinian company paying an
argentinian contractor right so I guess
what I would say is I can't really give
broad advice on something that but I
would say that from what I've seen when
people quote prices they tend to quote
prices around that range but that's for
2d art and I couldn't tell you much
about 3d art because we don't really use
any
click two is pretty interesting to go
through does it matter that much that it
is not multi-threaded because at least
it is only around 120,000 lines of code
and with Fabian overview is it a pretty
good selling point I mean here's what I
would say multi-threading is very
important and you would you will need to
learn it you'll need to learn probably
even more than anything that we've done
in hand-made here because we've pretty
done pretty simple stuff so if you're
talking about like hard core like full
engine multi-threading stuff we haven't
really done much of that on handmade
hero and probably won't so that's a
little bit of a missing area that you
would have to get into for full triple-a
kind of stuff and that again that's if
you're doing whole engine architecture
or not you wouldn't necessarily need to
know as far as learning goes I would say
definitely look at quick - because you
know some things never get old like the
way that quake was - was architected is
probably relevant to everybody it's
interesting probably to see the
decisions that were made there and how
it looked and how it was rendered and
how it was structured for network play
and everything else right so my opinion
is that like what I was trying to say is
you probably need more than that if
you're really trying to understand a
modern game architecture but it still
would be a great exercise regardless to
go through quake 2
a super off-topic but as someone who's
older and perhaps a lot more experienced
than someone like me is younger do you
have anything to say regarding
interpersonal issues ever encounter
people giving you issues or being rude
yes of course even absolute bullies do
you have any advice for that if what
encounters that even as an adult in a
university or at their job not really I
would say that generally speaking the
reason I like computer programming is
because I don't have to interact with
people and I don't find interacting with
people rewarding and I generally don't
find most people I interact with to be
worth interacting with because I guess I
would how I would put it so I don't have
a lot of advice as far as like how to
interact with people productively that's
something for a person who has a higher
opinion of humanity to answer that makes
sense like like I like programming
specifically because it is a mental
activity that it only matters whether
you are right about what you did and not
about what other people's opinions are
and I find that generally speaking
humans don't form opinions particularly
well they also don't tend to care about
data and they don't tend to care about
validating their opinions so interacting
with them is generally a pretty
disappointing experience unless you just
happen to agree on things or happen to
have a similar outlook on things right
the good news is the better you are at
programming the less you need to do it
if you're a very good programmer you can
get paid just a program you can even get
paid just a program on contract not in
an office so you don't even have to
interact with anybody who isn't your
friend on a daily basis or which is nice
in the mean time yet can't really help
you in terms of advice on that I'll go
ahead and recommend doom 3 as learning
engine since from what I can tell it
meets all the criteria to suggested on a
modern API has multi-threading you know
I didn't know that they released the
source code to doom three that's pretty
cool now that I think about it I
probably did read that and looks like oh
that's cool but I I didn't really
remember that that would be cool I
haven't looked at doom 3 I also think
Doom 3 like you know my feelings on
opportunity programming I don't like it
but the reality is a lot of triple-a
Studios use at least some of it some use
way too much of it
um but I believe Doom 3 has opted rated
program in it because John Carmack
wasn't the only programmer on it so I
think there's C++ in there more C++ than
there used to be in like quake 2 for
example so doom 3 might also be valuable
because you can see the kinds of oop
stuff that starts to come in a little
more it probably doesn't have me like it
you know engines like source 2 or
something are like ooh out into the
disaster zone right but you know so you
don't want to start there because just
be like what is going on whereas I think
doom probably has a little bit of OOP
going on and that would get you warmed
up to that as well which is probably
useful you know
all right I'm gonna wrap it up do you
think the performance of the game would
be fine on the Intel a cheapy or in
general the integrated GPU at the moment
well we do need to fix our texture
dispatch issue so there like I'd like to
put that aside but at the moment we
until our lighting is a little more
flexible probably it's not very like
right now the lighting is kind of does
this weird summation per pixel thing
that we probably don't want to do and
it's a little too scatter gallery like
right now the lighting would I think
prevent it from running particularly
well on an on an i GPU from Intel I
think so I would say in the long term we
will probably be have a good shot at
running reasonably on integrated
graphics part from Intel or for AMD
obviously which tends to have better
integrated graphics parts on at on the
current version the renderer probably I
think you would have problems right now
we have problems with with just with the
lighting you can see that right like in
a cutscene we're spending all of our
time waiting for the graphics card and a
lot of it's like like if we turn off the
debugger all this stuff we almost spend
no time at all right we're just sitting
there waiting for the graphics card
entirely but when we are in the game
right know how we'd get into the game
here we go but when we are in the game
you can also see like I mean we're in I
think we're in debug mode at the moment
so it's a little bit of a of a non test
but when we're running the game right
now our lighting which we run on the CPU
is actually very slow as well so it's
again pretty hard to tell but even that
you can see
in the current situation if you ignore
the light propagation stuff and just
focus on what the GPU has to do you can
see that fill rate is in fact a problem
I'm not sure if we can shrink down the
amount of processing we do and still
read anything not really
oh you know what that's not going to
matter because we did we don't change
the render resolution anyway no if we
have any way to really yeah we don't I
mean you can just see like so there's
the multi sampling if I turn that on up
you can just see like our fill rate is
an issue right it's all I'm trying to
say that will be really bad on Intel
GPUs and so that is I think you know
when we fix that up I think we'd be in
much better position
alright I'm gonna shut it down there
alright thank you everyone for joining
me further episode of handmade hero it's
a pleasure coding me with you as always
if you would like to pre-order the game
on hand me here at org you can get the
source code for it right now and play
around with it if you would like we
didn't quite get to what I wanted to get
to today in terms of finishing the I
wanted to check out those bright push
calls so we'll probably do that next
weekend next weekend we will hopefully
have time to do both things
so sprite push just clean up those calls
and make them a little bit more
understandable and a little more
flexible and probably a little faster
too at the moment I think they're kind
of a little bit too slow but then also
start down the road towards packed
textures and texture arrays because
that's really gonna hold back our
performance a lot and so just getting
that out of the way I feel like for a
lot of those things like ground cover
and things like that that we want we
want to have ways of making those things
work quickly and easily so that we can
put nice effects into the game as
necessary so that's really what I want
to start focusing on is to get that into
position so that we can sort of have a
more realistic picture about where our
render slowness is and I suspect it'll
all end up being in that sort of
lighting summation stuff which we can
then work on and try to figure out how
we're going to mitigate in terms of of
making sure the lighting is efficient
enough so that's it I'll be back next
weekend with that as always if you want
to check out what we've got on the hand
made here at that org page is a bunch of
resources here the watch page will show
the schedule at all times so you know
when we're going to be live-streaming it
also will show the livestream so you can
really just do everything from that page
if you want to it's pretty handy it also
has the episode guide so if you want to
watch old episodes that's it on there
too it has everything you need to watch
this series right there there's also the
handmade fun if you want to support
people who are
doing work related to the series like
the episode guide that gets paid for out
of a handmade fund it's a fun thing to
do if you want to continue the community
and it comes with a bunch of bonus stuff
for me that I put in a little bonus pack
for people who want to support community
efforts obviously if we also have the
special handmade hero head you can click
on if you want to get two of the other
sites from Maya Rocket and check out
what we're doing you can always click on
the handmade here a head or sign up for
our mailing list down here all that
stuff again is on handmade hero dog
works pretty easy to get to if you want
check it out that's it for this week
I'll be back next week when we hopefully
can like I said start down the path of
just cleaning up that render performance
stuff for the texture race that's a
really big thorn in our side right now
in terms of saying that the renderer is
real because it's it's too amateur hour
with a texture change for quad we don't
want to we don't want to be going into
the homestretch of actually developing
the gameplay with that kind of nonsense
in place so it'll be good to get that
out of there thanks for joining me see
you all next week have a good one
everybody