hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recoat a complete game
live on stream yesterday we covered how
to look at camera transitions we
introduced the concept of cubic and how
to design one and parameterize it in a
way that allowed you to do a nice easy
OV and we wrote you know some some code
for that which we you know which we
employed as a test and in order to do
that we just simplified the way the
camera was working really quickly as
something that allows us to sort of do
transitions between rooms using the
function that we designed right and so
what you can see here is that I can do
this transition when I move from room to
room and you know there's there's no
particular tuning to it currently but
it'll we did like implement the function
we wanted and now we can tweak that
cubic as necessary right but we have
another problem that we need to solve
and that's what I said at the end of
last dream we would do today and that is
we want the ability to have the camera
track a moving target so if all we
wanted to do was move from room to room
which is what we're doing now we would
kind of be done there because you could
actually just leave it implemented the
way I implemented it right and you might
have some issues where you like when you
hop from room to room you get some kind
of maybe a little bit like you can see
if I if I hop back and forth maybe
that's not as pleasant of emotion but
even that's really not that bad so you
know if we didn't need a track and
moving target you could call this done
and all you would really want to do is
maybe tweak the function to get the
exact amount of like easing that you
wanted or you know play around play
around with that curve until it was
something that that felt like the curve
that you wanted to feel right but we are
not quite at the point where we can call
it done because we do want to track a
moving target and so like when the
player hops up and down this corridor
for example we want it to follow them
Verta
and so this puts us in an awkward
position because the only technique that
we really developed yesterday for using
that cubic required us to have like a
known start time and a known in time for
the interpolation and if the targets
moving we no longer really know that
okay so let's talk a little bit about
about what I mean by that that is if I
can find the pen and by that I mean like
marine lepen from France let's see here
I guess I don't know if anyone's ever
tried to draw with her on a tablet but
but there you go
alright so let's go ahead and talk about
this moving camera target so if you look
at for lack of a better term the
behavior of the camera that we wanted
what we were seeing is that we want the
camera to move you know from here to
here and in that process we wanted it to
follow a speed curve if you will right
if this is the speed we wanted it to
follow a speed curve that sort of looks
you know something like this right in
other words we want the the rate at
which the camera is moving to look
something like this
so as a result we defined a function
that had that kind of a look to it I
mean I guess you shouldn't say that the
speed of ours is kind of more like that
right but that's what we wanted low high
low and so this is a parabola right and
when we look at the position that's when
we get the cubic that we designed okay
so if you integrate this up you get
something like this slow start fast
middle slow end right and that's exactly
what we would expect here if this is our
speed and this is time so if we want our
speed to look like this and more
importantly I suppose you could say if
we wanted to write any given function
for our speed meaning we want the speed
to be proportional to where we are along
the motion from here to here right then
what we could think about is maybe what
we're really saying is we don't care so
much about the cubic right the cubic is
a way of getting the position by having
previously integrated this parabola
right because we're doing you know a t3
plus B T squared plus C T right this is
our equation for our position right so
like that's you know that's PT so if we
take the derivative of it right if we
say what's the speed of this equation
then we're gonna get we're gonna get a
second-order equation right if you take
the derivative of a third degree
polynomial you get a secondary one right
so you get 380 square plus 2 BT plus C
as our speed right and so really what we
were talking about like we didn't care
about this really what we were trying to
say is this is what we want our speed
curd to look like because remember it's
the easing ease out that we were looking
for we don't really care that much about
the position other than we need to get
it as an answer but other than the fact
that it goes from A to B it was really
the speed that we were talking about
that we wanted to articulate to the math
and all we really use the cubic for was
to get the position out of that
right so the next question is well
alright what can we do then to make our
interpolation work in some way that
doesn't have a fixed start at end
because what we have to know right is
that at the start right you know at T
equals zero right
we want our speed to be zero you know
what I mean and we want it to pick up
over time so that when we're about
halfway you know we want our speed to be
you know one let's say where I don't
really mean the literal value one but I
mean some value I mean we could say max
right
we want our speed to be the maximum
speed whatever we decide that to be and
then we're at T equals one we want it to
be zero again right that's what we
wanted the problem is this and this are
now not really known in a sense we can
remember what T equals zero was because
we know anytime the camera stops moving
so if the camera stops moving completely
we could know that we could detect that
the velocity of the camera had
diminished below some threshold and say
we are now at rest and then we could
remember when we start accelerating out
of that rest and call that T equals zero
and then we could track that T over time
as much as we want it right but if we
don't know when T equals one will be we
still can't construct the curve and why
might we not know what T equals one is
well let's suppose that the camera is at
rest and then you know so we basically
have you know in our parlance we have a
target and we have the camera and it's
moving to the target
when it arrives at the target right
maybe I'll do it this way so when the
camera arrives so the target and the
camera are in sync right then we can
sort of say the camera is at rest and
this is T equals zero and will remain T
equals zero right there's no speed it's
just at rest now the user hops from one
room to another and let's say this is
focusing on like you know the center of
the room the user hops from one room to
another and we're right back in the
situation that we were up here oops
we're right back in the situation that
we were up here where we have the camera
here and the target here and now we know
that this would be T equals zero and
this would be T equals one and we want
that smooth curve from one to the other
right and the crucial thing to remember
here is in a sense we want potentially
that we don't know exactly what we want
to require here but we may actually also
want to say look we want room
transitions to be nice and snappy so we
want them to always take half a second
or one second or something like we may
want room transitions I don't care if
you're going from a small room to a big
room or from down a long corridor we
want those room transitions to be fast
because I don't want the player to you
know have to sit around waiting to see
what's in the next room they're supposed
to get it you know it supposed to be a
nice Pleasant visual effect but that
happens snappy right so pleasing
movement but fast so we don't really
know we may want this T equals one to
just be assumed to be here or we may
want to say well you know look maybe we
want to take how far away it is and say
that we don't really want our function
to ever produce a velocity higher than a
certain amount so we want our our curve
to start at zero go to a maximum
velocity remain at the maximum velocity
and then end right so in other words if
we want our room transitions to tap an
in constant time meaning like you know
once
in all ways or something like that then
our thing can look like this because we
can always make a parabola that gets us
there on time and the height this right
here will just change right so sometimes
the parabola will look like that
sometimes the parabola will look like
that you know what I mean in terms of
what our actual speed ends up being when
measured in the world but we could
always make it there in constant time
just by making the speed bigger and the
way we're doing that right now is we
always use the same parabola but we just
blend between points that are further
away right so we don't actually use the
parabola as speed we use the probably
parabola as a normalized speed and then
we stretch it out over a line which is
also a totally valid way to do it right
but either way point being that always
gets us there the same time so in the
actual game if I'm going from here to
here which is a smaller movement right
the camera can move at a slower speed
than from here to here where it has to
move faster right it has to move much
faster there in order to get because the
points are further apart but we could
instead decide and this is an artistic
decision right that affects the math we
could instead decide that we want a
curve that looks more like this right
so there's a start and end to the
parabola but in the middle there's just
a long linear region so there's a linear
region and there's like an acceleration
and a deceleration right and so this
parabola is really split in two and
there's an intermediate area that's just
a constant speed which is the maximum
speed so it goes up to its maximum speed
stays there and then comes down from its
maximum speed when it's done okay
I can't say that I really have a strong
opinion about what should be happening
in that case you know there's a couple
different ways we could do this keeping
all of those things there is sort of
another thing we could do which is just
making the players location always be be
the target and then if T equals zero
then you just move the target so I don't
know I I just wanted to kind of get all
of that out there and just talk about
what the possibilities are because I
don't know exactly what we want in this
particular case I don't have an editor
open so here we go so I guess it depends
it really depends on what we want to do
but in terms of the way our camera is at
the immediate moment we take a look here
and we just say update camera for entity
movement you know if we wanted to say
that the way that it works is it always
takes a constant amount of time to
switch from run room to another in which
case we have the from P to P
construction and we leave it this way
and then we can make whatever function
we want here for their interpolation if
we did say that then one interesting
aspect of that that what one interesting
thing that comes from that is the fact
that the camera itself could then just
be locked to the user in all other cases
right so yeah like effectively we would
say something like
if the target and the camera are close
enough to each other and T equals one
then we just set them equal to each
other otherwise we update the target I
know this sounds a little bit weird but
that's basically what we would be doing
there so yeah let me see how if I was
gonna just to give some explanation of
that so in here where we set this in
room and and not is equal to right so
what this was doing is this was
preventing us from ever setting a new
camera right so we never update the
camera when we move rooms except for
that first time once you're inside the
room you'll never update the camera
again that means that things like are
tracking the player scrolling we would
never even hit this case right if
instead we said well you know maybe what
we really wanted to do was always update
the target but only update the from and
well only update the T interpolation and
the from P when we actually do a room
change right so only do that
interpolation at that point and if we do
something like that then you know what
you would see is we still have constant
time room transition but once you get
into a room that Scrolls you're just
locked to where the player is right
let's see that now the problem with that
to a certain extent is locking to the
player you can see there's a certain
amount of smoothing that isn't happening
there so you know I don't know to what
extent we wanna we would probably want
to smooth that out because hopping is
kind of jarring right you can kind of
see it being fairly jarring there and
I'm not really sure why could the why is
being changed there instead of the Z
that's probably old like historical
reasons so we can probably fix that part
but
to see that we would want to smooth it
out but other than smoothing it out it's
not immediately clear we couldn't just
use that right because it does track the
player just fine and then our
interpolation you know so really what we
have for the most part is a problem with
smoothing out the player's motion not a
problem with what the camera would do in
this case right so if we imagined doing
something a little bit different here
tracking the cameras in room is probably
would not really be necessary either
right so what we could do here is say
look we don't care about any of this
all we really need to know is if the
front P and the P are like really far
apart you know and I mean I'm sorry if
the if the current location of the
camera and the new location camera are
really far apart and T is less than one
I'm sorry equals one so if we're not
interpolating the camera right so this
means interpolation server and the
difference between these two vectors the
length happens to be larger than our
whatever our maximum is so like distance
between squared something like that from
target P like that so if the distance is
greater than you know some amount that
we consider to be a large movement you
know like a meter then we restart our
interpolation otherwise we just snap
here I mean then we don't really need
the in room I don't know if we've got
that distance between
it don't look like it so we can just say
length squared of the vector in between
so if the amount we wanted to move was
greater than some max distance so like
max distance per frame you know is
something it's probably less than that
if we were going to move more than the
maximum distance per frame then what we
do is we start an interpolation
otherwise we do nothing that would mean
that we don't really have to set anymore
the the in room and that goes away so
then we just have T interpolation and
the target from construction right I
need to make sure we set the from though
yes we did okay so that's all fine I
think
also to me um so let's take a look at
what happens there you can see us now it
looks like we're getting a weird glitch
there so I think our frumpy is not quite
right there yeah so the problem is
that's gonna get Rhian coded so we don't
really want to do that we want that to
be rien coded here like so so we really
want this right we don't ever want to be
copying in the unmapped Bay in the you
know in world space we want to be
mapping it like simulation space so now
we pretty much just would work no matter
what we did we don't need to know about
rooms or anything the camera just works
and so now we're just down to wanting a
more pleasant effect when the character
is hopping because we don't really want
to account for all that motion there
what happened there
something weird happened there
all right so there's something there's
something busted about that let me take
a look at what's going on here
[Music]
I guess that may have been us hitting
the max distance per frame no not sure
what that was
target P target P is always set so that
really shouldn't be an issue and it's
always mapped into the region and out of
so that all looks really good did I mess
up anything else here here's the T
update let me put that down here
actually
these are still kind of doing their own
thing which is fine they could actually
be rewritten this way as well at which I
should do because you know we can just
lurk them in addition so we actually
don't need to do this anymore on them
but I'm not sure why they're getting
that weirdness there where I was seeing
yeah I don't know why we were getting
that hiccup and I'd like to take a look
more closely at that what I do want to
do here there was I would like to make
these be something that goes off of the
bezzie a magic so they they would
interpolate basically the same way that
that they would just interpolate the
same way everything else interpolates
right because once we've we've
interpreted our blend here so I think
this is our you know blend factor once
we computed what that blend factor is I
would like to use it for everything so
you know this would also be alert where
we would take the expected focus Minzy
and the expected focus maxie and we'd
blend between those and that way it's
also stable per frame and doesn't have a
weird like doesn't have like a weird
dependency
I just want to take that out of the mix
so that we're not getting like weird
results due to that or something that
make sense all right so yeah like most
of the things look okay here
it's just not that one particular thing
and so I'm not sure how we want to deal
with that and you can kind of see it
looks it actually looks like we do we
get like a positional hiccup even we
definitely get some hiccups on the blend
I think yeah like that was an actual
positional hiccup so how are we getting
a positional hiccup there what's going
on we do map everything back in right
everything always the front P and from P
target P is always mapped just period
right
target fee is always mapped and the
target of the focuses are always kept
from the from the destination and you
know I wonder if that should just be
based on the camera directly I don't
know that's hard to say
I do wonder if these maybe should be
measured from the camera directly after
we interpolate it so that's a little
hard to say like I don't know how much
blending we really want on those one way
or the other but so something weird is
happening here where if the camera
interpolation needs to hop back
something bad happens now I'm terribly
certain why because if you think of what
would happen here maybe let me just walk
through it in the case where we set the
interpolation here to zero we're going
to set the from value to be the same as
the p value and the t interpolation will
be set to zero so this whole thing will
basically just mean that wheat we're at
the from P which means P will remain
completely unchanged and so you
shouldn't get a hiccup there so I'm
trying to figure out maybe the the way
you get a hiccup though is by changing
the target P to discontinuously so yeah
I guess what you could say is if the
target P was changing too much it would
also need to do this you know what I
mean
because you get you could get a
discontinuity if the target if you
haven't finished an interpolation and
the target P has changed too much then
in a sense you need to like restart the
interpolation you know what I mean and
and so that's like kind of a rude
awakening there and mainly sort of
motivates the thing that I was talking
about before where it's like we need a
thing that allows you to have a moving
target because occasionally you do so I
don't know the way we would do that is I
think all we would say is restart
interpolation is a value that we can
trigger and then when we're here we can
just say look if we move the target too
much and I guess you know another way to
do it would be to say looking at this
right if we make the target P be
something that comes out here so the
target P in this case gets pulled out
early and in fact I guess all of these
can be pulled out early so we would say
grab all of our stuff if we want to
update the target P you know we can
update the target P right but we would
want to say something like new target P
right so in here we would say like okay
target P
so when we get our new target P and then
of course down here we would want to map
everybody back into the trunk space for
storage when we get our new target P we
now know when we get down here how far
you know each of these things moved so
we could say yeah if the amount that you
wanted to move was greater than this you
would just earth you would restart the
interpolation but also if the target P
itself moved enough you would want to
restart the interpolation so it doesn't
really matter how close they are and you
know we probably could have solved that
by just reducing this value but it just
seems you know it just seems sensible
there so if you move the target P or you
move the new target P you know either
way and then after that we set it up so
if either of these moved an appreciable
amount then we swap it over
and if we're not in a room we if we are
in some kind of error condition then we
just don't update it right we just use
whatever the last one was oops I messed
something up there so yeah like we get
all this stuff here camera simulation
center should probably be handled
outside as well but and we'll leave it
leave it there so studying the new
target P I missed one
looks like you can see the target P down
there I don't know what I did there
accidentally when I was replacing that I
just didn't go far enough right so
that's the problem but yeah so let's see
if we are going around here and
that we're still glitching out I'm
really not sure what that's run I'm not
sure where else we'd get that I have to
think of a good way to bug back because
I'm not sure how to look at something
that happens across that frame we'd have
to figure out what was going on
specially there cuz this should never do
it right because from P just gets reset
to P which would not move the camera
if interpolation is set to zero because
that you should come through with P
equal to front P in that case cuz blend
is zero right I mean in theory anyway
look I don't see why we would get that
discontinuous jump I'm curious if it has
to do with that resetting or not
since that's the area that we're having
the bugging also I might say that now
would be a good time to switch so that
we don't have to hop out there since
we're not getting that bug in other
locations you're Mazal just start on the
stairs so we can just hop right up it
seems to mostly be about going down the
stairs and you can see there's just a
little glitchyness it's like things move
it moves to the right a little bit which
doesn't make a lot of sense because that
wouldn't even like I don't even know how
we would get that happening exactly
like that's that's a saucy one that's a
weird one because if we're blending from
you know from this P to this P I'm not
sure how the T interpolation value could
ever be something that would produce a
rightward motion like that unless this
no I don't have an idea about why that
would be happening but it does look like
it has to do right with these two I also
it's not gonna ever reset these up
uh-huh
that is what I had meant to type in I
meant if we move either of those two
things not if we move both of those two
things I don't necessarily know that
that was the problem but that was not
what I meant to test for obvious reasons
so I'm getting it even just there when I
crossed the boundary it's glitchy right
I don't know you may not be able to see
that due to streaming effects but when I
cross the boundary it glitches right so
something's just busted I'm doing it I'm
doing something backwards or stupid that
I'm not understanding there right and
I'm not sure what it is
so again in theory if we map everything
back into chunks face we should not be
having any problems with origin movement
because everything gets encoded in the
same place and then gets decoded in the
same place later
so the sim region shouldn't be able to
affect us here that makes sense it
seemed like in this case we weren't
really having much problems other than
with this particular issue here so in
terms of resetting the interpolator we
didn't see this problem when we reset
the interpolator only on room moves I
would like to do something here where
I'm just curious
what happens if I what happens like am I
ever like not in a room I because I
don't know
doesn't seem like it so that's good so
we know we're always taking this code
path for even when we're having the
glitch so we know we can basically read
this out of it and just say this is
happening this whole thing right so we
know we're looking at what the room
looks like we know we're setting up the
new target P based on the center of the
room right we're gonna move the offset
of that thing out from there somehow
we're gonna reset the camera simulation
center to be based on that simulation
center yeah all that seems pretty normal
and so then the only question here is
like yeah you know I mean one thing is
if you're still in the middle of an
interpolation I guess one thing maybe
you have to say is if if the
interpolation
if the target P changes discontinuously
then I suppose we kind of always have
that problem so I wonder if we yeah
aren't just stuck back in the same
position because now I think about it
this is gonna have that problem period
if we allow the target P to get updated
then it can always get updated out from
under us and if the target interpolation
was 0.9 let's say and the and the new
target moved is continuously this
wouldn't run because of this check and
so really we're just gonna have to deal
with the fact that that new target moves
and yeah and I don't really know what
else we could really do about that so in
terms of this what we would want to say
is look if the interpolation is you
one and the distance we would want to
move is greater than that then we do
right and I think we really don't need
this extra truck I mean that that was
probably a waste of time
I just wasn't thinking of three right
but new target P really shouldn't be
allowed to it's got a very more
continuously right so when we set new
target P this you know this thing here
we got to make that be something that's
at least a linear interpolation or
something right and so I think we do get
back to what I was talking about here
even though it seems like we could have
handled it without that I'm not sure we
really can I think we are gonna have to
do the sort of more fuller featured part
where we deal with the continuously
moving new target as something real
because we always could hop down like in
some way that like we were doing there
where we kind of need it to smooth out
those motions and think about them more
critically right so let me just verify
that that's the case if I was to move
new target piece smoothly would this
work fine meaning if I was to say take
this Delta
[Music]
get the length of it and then say if
that length is less than some you know
epsilon value don't care about then just
set it but otherwise linearly move it
between the two right and so I guess
what I would say here is maybe this is
like the target speed and whatever
that's gonna be it's gonna be like DT
times something
so maybe the target speed actually is
just DT I don't know so in the case
where I would just move it however much
I can move it or less we just set it
directly otherwise I take the d target P
times the max target speed and I add
that right so I'm just moving the target
like slowly kind of
in that case so this would only be
relevant in the case where you know in
terms of moving the target slowly if
we've started a new interpolation that's
not necessary so we really only need to
do this in that case so where we have
where we have done this we can set them
directly so we can just do you know that
but in the other case we have to update
the target continuously so that it
doesn't cause a discontinuity you know
or something like this so now you can
see us having that target move around
continuously right which again is not I
think what we actually want to do but I
just want to make sure that fixes the
glitch bug and it does we do have a
problem with we wanna like I said I
think we want to make those alpha ranges
be set more directly because we really
don't want them interpolating at a
separate rate
um so that was definitely the problem
and so now our question is just well
okay if we know we have to do something
better here what's the something better
like if we know we've got to have some
way that we smooth this out and we have
certain requirements for how we want our
camera to behave and so on you know what
does that look like
so I guess my first inclination is to
say what if we made something where we
look at the distance between where we
would like the camera to be and where
the camera is now and we map the what we
would like the speed to be at that point
we map what we would like the speed to
be at that point and then we map that
versus our current speed and we
basically make those two things match I
mean one way to say that would be right
so we've got three phases the camera
could be in we've got a min speed area
we got a like an acceleration area a
deceleration area and then a max speed
area right and if we're far from the
target and we've gotten into this region
we would just stay here but then once we
get closer to the target we go into our
deceleration region and the speed should
be proportional to this right I think we
also want to try and get the velocity of
the target so we'd like to know how fast
the target is moving as well because we
want to target where it's going to be
not where it is because otherwise we're
always a little bit behind right so
let's see to what extent we can even get
that information to start with so in the
entity I don't actually know you know
we've got the DP value here but I don't
actually know if anyone is setting that
value like the the P DP and DDP I
suspect they're probably not so inside
the entity like
you know we never set that right so you
know we could approximate it by looking
at the difference between last frame and
this frame for an MV and say well we
assume that the motion will be similar
to what it was last frame but that's
still not quite right
you know what we'd rather have is some
notion of the speed that's set by the
actual controllers so I guess I'll
forego that part right now and then
we'll try to get that in later because
that'll be the harder part since we
don't really have a way of getting it
directly okay so and we kind of do know
that because like we have a permanent
placement point for this entity
generally right there are world
locations for each of these I think that
we store at some point maybe not I guess
we only store those in in actual stored
entities but so we'll assume we can do
something about that later
but let's go ahead and look at this
first so if we want to do something more
sensible here then let's start storing
some different parameters the first
thing I want to do is let this let this
thing happen the way that it was
happening currently so meaning maybe
let's switch back to inside a generic
room
and so if inside this room right we can
hop from here not to here and we get our
E's curve the way we wanted
so let's recreate that eaves curve
behavior let's see if we can recreate
that without using the from concept and
instead working mostly with
accelerations you know what I mean
so inside the world mode if I was to
store instead of a frumpy and a target P
if I was to for example not store the
target P at all perhaps and I'm gonna
get rid of the frumpy and the T
interpolation but the target PE the
target P I'm gonna say I'm gonna keep
for now because I don't know if we're
gonna need to track whether we're doing
big Newt movements or small movements at
any given time so I'm gonna say we keep
that but from P is gonna go away so
let's suppose we got rid of from piece
we don't know anymore where we're coming
from and let's suppose we got rid of
this so we don't know this stuff for the
T interpolation right we don't know any
of that and we have to still do
something relating to a an update of
this form okay
how will we how would we do it
right so this is what we've got to work
with we're just getting a target P in
here
and the only thing that we know that we
can remember is basically like our speed
right so our we're not we want we're not
going to store our speed as a vector
we're just going to store it as like a
single value that we say like how fast
like what's the throttle right and it'll
start at zero and go up some max value
so then I'll see you like max camera
speed something here right or maybe I'll
just say DP Max and you know the DP max
is whatever it is and that's that that's
so that's the maximum DP we could get up
to you know and we'll set this value of
something else later or maybe you want
to now I think about it let's not do
that
let's say the DP let's say this is
between zero and one always and then
we'll just multiply it out right so
we'll say one is maximum speed and we
multiply that by a speed coefficient
later but we always just consider it
going between zero and one
okay so now let's look and get some
information about our our behavior here
so we know that we're going to target P
and we know we're coming from P so this
is the Delta P meaning it's not the
derivative of P but it's the it's the
total Delta right it's how far we would
need to go you might even call it the
desired Delta P or total Delta P right
so that's the amount that we would need
to move to get the full to just go
directly where the camera system wants
to view the world from at this
particular time so we know that length
of that vector and we can now consider
mapping that into a space that looks
like this potentially right meaning we
know how we know how
we could go and so we could say well if
we were at this location where would we
be ideally on this curve meaning what do
we want our deceleration region to look
like in terms of something spatial you
know what's a what's the distance out at
which we would start slowing down and
what's the distance here where we would
start accelerating right in this curve
here and I mean it's basically like oh
you know maybe we we do this over the
course of like one meter or something
you know what I mean so what we could
say here is like let let's map into that
space where we expect that fall-off
curve to actually be in terms of taking
Delta steps along it and then we could
you know make that total work out seems
plausible anyway seems plausible um so
if we wanted to do that then what we
could say is we could almost make like a
fictional construction of of where we
are on this curve and solve for that in
a sense I know that sounds kind of weird
but we could still update as if we were
going to always lurk from you know from
a location to another location along
that curve and we would just reconstruct
what the location should actually be you
know what I mean
yeah
that all seems pretty plausible to me so
let's skip that what that would look
like if the total length here is greater
than the the cooldown distance right so
whatever we want that like I guess we
whatever we call that
acceleration/deceleration so we'd call
this the D cell range right so this is
the range over which we decelerate and
who knows what that is right so maybe we
say we've got an AK cell range of 1
meter a deceleration range of 1 meter
right and then we've got a total Delta P
length that tells us where we how far we
are from the target so if we're in
deceleration range we do one thing you
know what I mean otherwise we do
something else so if we're in the
deceleration range then what we need to
do is figure out where in the
deceleration range we are and that would
set our deceleration and in theory we
could just do that directly so I think
and maybe this is just stupid but I
think what we could do there is say
whatever our deceleration range is let's
just always I'm sorry less than whatever
our deceleration range is let's just
pretend that we map the curve into that
space and finish that way there's a
couple of different ways we could do
this my thinking is that you solve the
curve for where you are in the
deceleration and put the P back that far
does that make sense because we have one
more piece of information which is what
the speed was that we were traveling at
at that time right and we know you know
we know what that is if you look at you
know in terms of the speed of the T
parameter right the Delta that's passing
that's being passed in there I mean we
can even do it with finite differencing
by looking at at the two values but in
terms of getting the derivative of this
key value you know you can compute it
directly by just saying well it's a
times T times T you know this was T to
the third so it'd be three times eight
times three times two right plus two
times B times T plus you know C so we
can compute the derivative of the input
value trivially and since we know that
these are we're constant values there we
know what the derivative is is just D
blend times those values like we can we
can do that derivative directly as well
so we'd be able to compute what we were
actually using as a speed wherever we
are in these curves pretty trivially by
just setting D blend however we want I
mean just computing D blend whenever we
want
so that should be possible as well let's
transfer how we would want to set this
up and it's kind of a little bit of a
mind bender so if you imagine us going
from one location to another then if you
were to set up what the curve should
look like there
[Music]
you would want to set the maximum speed
you're going to hit based on that
distance and then do a little ease and
ease out of just that much probably
right
I would think
hmm meaning like based on where you are
and whatever your speed was you can then
say well if I was going to assume that
my speed was based on some other
position what would that position be
right so you know meaning in this
construction if I take a look in my
speed is whatever it is X or something
right or s then I know there are two
places on the curve I could be right I
could be here or I could be here you
know what I mean and so if I look and I
say I'm this distance away from the
thing I know that this stuff always
looks a particular way
then there are some ambiguities I guess
which is like if you don't know whether
or not you ever hit your max speed so I
don't know it might behoove us to try
and remember whether we're in the
acceleration or the deceleration region
meaning if you stored your DP and your
DDP so you had both the acceleration and
velocity then you could differentiate
between the acceleration region and the
deceleration region by looking at what
your what your DDP was yeah you know and
again if we looked at at the if we look
at the equations you can figure out
pretty easily what that's going to be
because if this was your equation then
then again I can just do the same thing
it's going to be six right times 82
times B and this is just going to be
zero sorry what right
is that right because yes see to the
first is one time see to the zeroth
which is one which is just one
I believe that's my story and I'm
sticking to it
oh wait no that's a constant that's not
a variable so it's just that right it's
C times T so this is T to the zeroeth so
T to the zeroth does not appear anymore
so it doesn't get a derivative so I
think we could just we would know all
these values and could store them and so
then we would kind of know where on that
curve we were I guess I mean the other
question though is why wouldn't you just
store T what why would you just store
what your T value actually was and maybe
that's a better idea it's like look this
is where we were on the curve and I
guess the reason not to do that is
because as it moves around you want to
preserve you know these are the values
you wanted to preserve meaning you
wanted to save you wanted your velocity
and acceleration to stay the same and
you wanted them to match you know what I
mean but you're creating a new curve so
you might be at a different place on a
new curve and the Delta that you'll
apply will be different so you really
want to match the actual physical values
that the player could perceive not the
internal T value which doesn't mean
anything to them you know so like I said
this stuff is very much more of a black
art once you get outside of just doing
friends and twos because you can see why
there's a lot more complication here and
you have to kind of define something
very nebulous as to what's supposed to
be going on and it makes it pretty hard
but if I want to push forward on that
right so let's see what we get here so
I'm gonna look I'm gonna what I'm going
to do here is I'm going to look at the
DDP and the DP valve stuff like that I'm
gonna try and figure out what's going on
in terms of
how to apply those and go from there
okay
so let's suppose that I am in the you
know I am looking at where I was and I
know so I know I've got a DDP and a DP
let's say I want to solve for the curve
that would get me there and that has
those two values right so I want to
solve essentially for the you know the V
and use that would produce those values
now I can look at this more as a 2d
curve and but I don't think I want to I
think I just want to look at it as a 1d
curve with a fixed shape right so I
think what I want to do is try to solve
like I want to try to solve this as a
sort of puzzle of the form okay I know
that I have a curve I know that the
curve looks like something and I don't
know what this is I'm going to call that
D for now so the length between here and
here is D right and what I now have is I
have a camera position somewhere along
this which we'll call P right
now what I don't know is I don't know
where I started from
and I don't know where I'm going on any
previous frame so at some point the
camera was like here and was asked to go
to here and it started moving and it
eventually got to like here at this
speed right this is the speed it
eventually got up to the speed and what
I know is that it will continue to
travel at that maximum speed until it
gets close enough to the point to
decelerate right this is sort of what
I'm talking about here um and then when
it gets to that point it will decelerate
down and and then will be you know will
be done does that make sense so I want
to kind of solve for that behavior and
there's really one other annoying point
about that and that is if the curve was
to collapsed so let's suppose that
actually you know if this is the those
two regions if they were to overlap like
this so you had you know this and oops
should draw that differently
so in this case right if I've got a
thing that's like kind of going up like
that and then I got another curve that's
kind of going like that then there's
actually a point here where we have a
different max speed now because we can
never get up to the other max speed and
I don't know what we want to do there it
makes a difference because if this is a
constant versus a variable it makes a
difference so if if our max speed is
something we always know exactly what it
is and when these two things overlap
then we just they there's a discount
discontinuous acceleration at that point
I don't know how bad that is like one
way or the other I don't know whether we
need to treat this as something that
kind of goes more like that you know
what I mean so I guess we'll cross that
bridge you know when we come to it
all right um so let's assume for
something to start off with a little bit
easier let's assume that we were always
gonna solve for like a single one of
these maybe I guess rather than the slit
in half one so let's suppose we were
always solving for a parabola curve so
we know that we're just going to do that
and so we have a particular location
along the curve that we are and we have
a particular destination that we know we
want to get to and so the question is
just where on the curve are we so we
want to solve for T in an equation that
looks like this right and that's because
we actually had an F an integral F here
that was our original
right and so we knew that we took the
derivative of that and we got this so
it's actually like that you know what I
mean
but it's of that form it's a quadratic
of that form so if we know this value if
we know F prime of T right which we
would know because we're storing it it's
the speed if we know F prime of T then
we would know what T was because we can
solve for T right it's a quadratic
equation with a solution and so we can
do the what is it I don't even remember
the quadratic equation at this point
it's a mmm it's like you know - it's
like you know - the plus or minus square
root of 5 over 4 AC you know some
nonsense like this what is it
know
it's something more like this and I'm
saying um what is it show me the
equation please I was close it's not C
square it's B squared so it's negative B
plus or minus b squared minus 4ac all
over 2a so weird how you like sort of
vaguely remember these things when you
haven't done math in a while so I can
solve for this and I'm going to get two
answers to where that derivative was
equal to that value right so I'm gonna
get two answers to like where the motion
where the speed was equal to that the
reason for that is because well and I
guess now I think about it that's the
solution if we are actually solving the
cubic itself but if you think about it
if we just want to know on here on the
speed curve where we were that's easier
because the speed curve is actually the
speed curve is actually going to be
broken into two parts there and we know
the other derivative right we know we
could store that as well right so the
680 plus 2b we know that 2
and so in a sense we can just solve for
that one probably right couldn't we if
we just stored our acceleration whatever
our acceleration was I mean correct me
if I'm wrong but why can't why couldn't
we just say here's what our acceleration
was and then get back the value and
that's simplest because that doesn't
involve a quadratic equation so I'm not
sure why we wouldn't do that
that seems better so let's see we just
did that because then we could solve
that directly meaning if we store this
value and we want to know where in the
curve we were on the new curve so we're
mapping from the old curve to the new
curve because it might be the same but
it might be different right then
determine where we were on the curve we
could just map it backwards and say well
we know a we know B in this case and so
to map it backwards onto this curve we
would solve the equation for t minus 2p
u divided by 6 a so you know be that um
but the problem is that's not in world
space right so that assumes that we were
interpolating these two this way and we
need to actually look at what that speed
would be so there's actually a
multiplier here of another value right
and that value is this is that whatever
that stretch is does that make sense
so really the speed is this multiplied
by the distance right so whatever that
distance is has to get multiplied in
here so you might say the speed is 680
plus 2b times whatever this length is so
the length of like P target minus P
current or ya you know whatever that is
you know what I mean
so if we think about it more from that
perspective so what we actually stored
was this value and we need to get this
back then that's when this becomes a
harder problem because we don't actually
know what this value is either so we
really have two unknowns we have we
don't know what T is and we also don't
know what the distance is right now the
reason we don't know what the distance
is is because the whole thing we're
talking about here is to solve for what
the curve would have been so if we were
to parameterize this on two things the
total length of the curve right and then
the T along curve then we know we can
always perform our update as we wish and
we can store the information that we
wanted to store it right but what we
have to do is we have to solve properly
for these things so if we have a total
curve length then what we would be
saying is the difference you know the
way that we're updating it is we have a
T plus delta-t right
and so our f is this meaning the the
amount of change is going to be T
whatever the time is plus whatever the
delta time is right so if we want to
know how far along the curve we're going
to go you know and we've got so in here
right we want to figure out what's going
on here then you know in theory this
works meaning we just need to know
whatever the the function of T was at
the time plus whatever the function
the delta T was you know what I mean now
this we don't care about because this is
where we are right this is just P we
don't need to compute that so all we
need to do is compute the derivative to
move us along the trajectory we're
trying to go
we know the delta T right because the
delta T is what's passed in its this
value right here so that's a trivial
thing to get as well so really what
we're talking about is what's the F
prime well we already said that the F
prime when you pass this thing in right
is and you know what I may have jumped
the gun there a little bit it's not that
it's delta T times f prime of T my bad
right that would be the the update if
you're moving along it um and really I
guess I don't need to go that route
because again if I know F prime of T I
can just set my location there and then
I just remember the derivative so really
what we're doing here is just using the
derivative as a map so all this is we
don't even need this for an update and
don't think of it that way right all
we're doing is saving what this was so
that when we do our next time we will
keep the same apparent change in
velocity so it's smooth does that make
sense so I need to know my F prime of T
so if I in obviously my F of T as well
so if I'm going to update with an F of T
and I know that my F of T looks like
this
right I know that's what that looks like
but the way that's actually going to be
interpreted is this way how do I turn
that around so if I was doing this and
let's assign this to some value you for
convenience if I know that I have a P
you know from and I was going to do 1
minus u times that and then I was you
know because we're doing a loop here and
then over here I was going to do u times
whatever the target is how do I
rearrange that to only really talk about
the change in those two right well if I
multiply that out I would get P of F
minus u P of F Plus u P of T right which
is another way of just saying P of F I
don't know if you can see this I might
swap these around Plus u PT minus UPF
right so it's really just P of F plus u
times PT minus PF so my update function
because this is where I'm coming from
right wherever it was I'm Jimmy hmm and
this is where I'm going to so my Delta
update here in this case could be
phrased in terms terms of the difference
between these two values which I could
just consider a single value for all
intents and purposes right meaning
trying to think of how to put this into
a phrase that makes sense
this value is the entirety of what
determines my velocity I guess it's time
trying to say it the derivative of this
is nothing it doesn't have T in it
because U is the only thing that
contains any T's here probably shouldn't
use T for that um so if I consider this
to be some P from value plus au times
some Delta value right this is some
Delta P value okay then I know that this
is the entirety of my derivative
function right so my f prime of my T
here or you know and I could start from
here my F of T if that is pf+
and remember U is this nonsense up here
so it's a t cubed plus BT squared plus C
right so if this is the way I phrase my
function start at the starting location
which we don't know what it is right
it's just somewhere that you started
from we don't know then we're going to
the update here the nice part is once I
take the derivative if that's what I'm
mapping from this goes away and that was
what I was trying to get at so we're
left with effectively two unknowns here
for our purposes because Delta P's
Direction is known it's always in the
direction of the target from where we
are so the only thing we didn't know is
how long is it right and you might say
well you know how long it is it's just
how long from our current location to
where it is is that's the length no
because we're talking about a curve that
may have been executing for some time
and we're in the middle of it so
actually this extends behind us and
that's the whole thing that we're trying
to get to right so once we take the F
prime of T then what we're going to get
here is this is effectively a scalar
value so we have Delta P let's pretend
it's in the front times all of our junk
and Jimmy
in order to do that derivative it's
pretty simple we can still do exactly
what you did it before because this
Delta P can just multiplying to
everything right so we would just have
Delta P 80 cubed plus Delta P be T
squared plus Delta P C and let me just
get rid of that for a second right this
is not varying but it is a variable and
so when we take the derivative we're
still left with the exact same answer
it's three Delta P 80 squared plus 2
Delta P PT plus Delta P ok so if we
store both of these things which again
we can take it again so if we start both
of these values we would have two
equations in two unknowns and we could
get back our T value right we could get
back whatever the T value was supposed
to be and whatever our delta p value was
so if we want to match the velocity and
the acceleration
what would our Delta P have to be now
and what would our T have to be now to
produce that answer
right so it's somewhat nasty like I'm
not sure we really want to do this
because it seems kind of crazy but not
sure what else you would do it seems
like you would have to solve a cubic
here which doesn't seem good you know
maybe that's not true so I'm not sure
how you would go about actually solving
this you know if you look at this
equation if you solve if you solve this
in terms of the quadratic you would get
T equals you know negative B which is
this term so negative 2 Delta P be plus
or minus square root of B squared so
it's that again
so you would end up with a delta you
would end up with a delta P B squared
right minus 4ac so you'd have Delta P a
or a delta p c is just Delta P so it'd
be again a Delta P squared in there over
to a so to a Delta P so you'd end up
with something like this for your
solution for T in terms of Delta P which
is not pretty as you might expect now
there are some nice aspects of it so
since there's a delta p squared in here
that actually would pull out of the root
term I believe because inside there what
you're actually left with is Delta P
squared times B squared minus 4a and so
the square root of that should
distribute just fine right so you should
be able to pull that out and effectively
get rid of it and you know what that's
actually obvious so the reason that's
obvious is because if you look at what
happens here there's a delta P in every
term so you could have just divided the
entire thing by Delta P and you'd be
done so actually it doesn't depend at
all on that I guess unless I'm wrong
which means you actually can solve for
the T without knowing what that Delta
was
sort of ah no you know why because we're
not solving for zero that's why what
we're actually solving for here is a
value that we had before that's the
problem so you know in here we're going
to have some some value that actually we
want to to to maintain you know whatever
the previous value was you know call it
whatever you want call it X or something
right
so we since there's an X here that x
value which is the value that we're
solving for comes to the other side so
you've really got an additional term
here which is that this C is minus X
right so in the 4ac you'd actually have
two terms there yeah so again it's just
pretty nasty I'm not sure I mean we can
solve it and we can we could use
computer algebra system to solve it to
so we wouldn't make so we wouldn't
necessarily make any mistakes but it
does seem a little over complicated for
what I would like you know what I mean I
would like to just be able to say look
let's just map this to a curve that
would make sense for where we are
and if that makes sense
I can't think of any other way to do
this I don't think you could do this
meaning I don't think if you look and
you actually stored this instead which
would get rid of the actual T value so
you'd end up just going hey whatever
your triple derivative is takes T out
and so you know you've got you know
you've got a correspondence between your
old 6pa and your new 6pa and so you just
solve for that first I mean I guess one
thing is could you just store what the
length was last time
and then when you go to use the length
this time you just look at the
difference between those two things to
determine what you're going to do
yeah I really don't know
[Music]
so I guess what I'm leaning towards is
suppose I were to store where I was on
this and its derivatives and I just said
I want to or maybe I just said I want to
construct something such that the
derivatives match maybe so
so you know the idea here is I want to
make sure that you know F prime of T and
what if I were to say that he is
actually gonna be something that we know
what it is so we're always looking to
take this same step if I only wanted to
do Delta P right that would be easier
basically if I can specify one or the
other it makes it extremely easy the
problem is having both trying to back
figure out what would happen seems bad I
I could try if I formulate this I could
try just seeing what the solution ends
up being if I just let if I just let it
plug and chug so I don't do it I'll it
because I would definitely make a
mistake if I tried to go through that
entire thing especially on this kind of
large blackboard thing it's bad enough
on a piece of graph paper it'd be awful
on here
so if we were actually to call this you
know the function this you know what
what would happen there so if this was
if we were trying to solve this to
maintain our velocity and our
acceleration and so we actually had all
names for each of these things so let me
try to make it a little bit more
concrete so if I say my f of T equals
the you know initial position plus the
Delta P right I don't want to call it
Delta P cuz that's gonna be hard to put
into a career algebra system so I'm
going to call that I guess D for Delta
right
time's my tea terms so I would say a chi
cubed plus B T squared plus C T uh and
in our case we don't really have a CT
per se do we we I think we set that
actually out to zero so oh no it equals
no it does it's zero so there actually
is no C term but we'll solve for it
anyway in case we want to play with
those I guess if we're gonna be computer
algebra yet so our derivative here as we
know is going to just be the derivative
of this thing with D tacked onto it
right because D doesn't change I mean
it's not a constant but it's not a
variable I know that's a weird thing to
say but it's not it's like a partial
derivative in this case it's not
relevant to the thing we're actually
solving so you know in this case we
would say okay it's D I'm sorry 3 dat
[Music]
squared plus 2 DB T plus DC and we know
we want to solve that for some previous
acceleration here so I guess I don't
know what we'll call that but I guess
we'll call the derivative of T we'll
call that you so since we want that to
actually be u in this case we want to
say it's 3 D 8 T squared plus T DB T
plus DC minus u then if we take the
derivative one more time of that right
then that is 3 D that's all right
6 da plus 2 DB and that all goes away
this here is zero and zero and so these
are the equations we're trying to solve
this has a T in it
right so looking at this I guess I don't
know maybe did I make a mistake here but
it looks like actually for the double
derivative this would this is gonna be
something too so maybe we'll say that's
V right so if we are recording U and V
and we want to match them we end up with
this equation which actually is quite
easy to solve for T right so you know
that part's not that hard it's only
really this one that becomes a bear
so let's say let's let's double check
our math there let's get let's get a I
guess just Wolfram now for the best
place to do this I'm not sure who's the
best to solve here I don't know how we
tell it to solve multiple equations
yeah here it is
so I guess you do like commas here and
I'm not sure how you specify what you're
trying to solve for it looks like you
say for after it so I guess you would
say for X Y that seems right so we have
two equations here they are we have and
I guess we can just write it directly
which is U equals 3 dat squared plus 2
bTW that's all right DB T squared that's
squared plus DC right and then our other
equation is V equals 60 80 plus 2 V DB
oh those don't appear it's not what I
wanted so we want it to solve for D and
T
oh hey did I do something wrong there
do I need to do this any better this
always happens when I try to use
computer algebra systems I never know
how to get them to do what I want so you
can see how ridiculously ugly that is
right it don't look good I mean there's
the solution and maybe we should just
try it but it doesn't seem like a good
idea and debugging it would be a
nightmare right because it's not an
intuitive like there's nothing you can
really pick out about this I mean look
at what it might mean you've got like
sort of maybe a little bit like the
combined length of the a B vectors here
and then some I mean yeah it's not
really you know I don't I don't see a
lot of way we would build a physical
integration out of that and Mathematica
is horrible for that like it's really
hard to get it to give you something
that you can then reason about it just
kind of dumps out a giant scale or
nonsense about you and off you go
[Music]
ah so I don't know I don't have really
any good ideas right now I feel like I
want to percolate this it on this a bit
I guess one other thing we could look at
is maybe what if we looked at it more
like we just want to have a consistent
way of accelerating and decelerating
that follows our curve but we just
always map it into the same size curve
and we just say well wherever we would
want to be on the curve we figure out
that location based on where we are now
and we step based on that curve so we
just look at our current velocity you
know and we just solved based on that
because again you know solving this just
for one of these variables is actually
much easier right if we just wanted to
get rid of the D you know what I mean
if all we were doing was solving for T
then it's really straightforward it's
just a basic quadratic and you could
even solve the other you could even
solve the second the acceleration
instead and then it's not even that so
you know 60 80 plus 2 DB right if we
just said well yeah okay so it's V
equals 6 80 plus 2 like that you know
that's even easier right so if we wanted
to just say look we're gonna use we're
not gonna try to be that fancy about it
so we're gonna just store our DDT and
we're gonna map that back into wherever
we would be at the current time on the
curve that is where we are you know
I don't know but you know we want to be
able to step towards the position as if
we were going as if we knew where we
were you know on the curve as if we
could
yes if we could just take that step
let me just try that a little bit and
see so let's suppose that we stored the
DTE and the DDT
so what we're storing there is basically
saying look we're just storing on the
curve where we were I mean I guess what
you could do instead is just say look
you just we just store what the T value
was that we were trying to be at maybe
so we do keep that T interpolation
around like maybe we look at that and
then we say all right you know when
we're going to interpolate here we say
how far away are we you know we know
what what our parameters would have been
last time how far away from this are we
do we need to switch to another part of
the curve or can we keep going with this
part of the curve right and once we get
up to a certain speed then we know we
can just keep going at that speed I mean
that's really the only idea I've got and
then when we get close to the end as
we're looking at those T updates right
we're just looking and saying well we
know we're on the downward slope so we
look to see you know how far away is the
thing that we're stepping to and we just
fit the curve to to that and as it moves
we just move it as well I don't know
it seems under defined so I I'm really
having trouble coming up with a good I
know that this I know that I have
literally never seen a good solution to
this problem so I'm not surprised it's
tricky like I've never seen a good
universal interpolator they're all
pretty bad and there's a lot of kind of
crazy stuff you can do with them which
is like there's you know there's actual
like more statistical fitting model
kinds of stuff you can also like we've
done proportional derivative controller
before and then there's also things that
use sort of like noisy things that try
to predict under noise like where things
are going and then tries to fit that you
know we could go that route too but I
was hoping to try and see if we could
maybe push through to something usable
on stream because like I normally do on
handmade hero I try to work through
stuff myself so you can see the process
of it but we don't always get to
something good
and in this case I'm really not seeing
too something good from first principles
on this one
so I guess one thing I would do is say I
know the length I could always store
what I thought my interpolation was from
last time and I could always store my T
value right and I could just say well
I'm going to adjust those two things
heuristic alee so that as best as I can
you know I produce
as best as I can I produce a smooth
value you know so you've effectively got
you know two values that you store
you've got what you thought your length
was last time and you've got what you
thought your T was last time and you're
just gonna update those two values
heuristic ly to try and you know make it
so that you're always stepping along a
reasonable curve you know it's not good
but like you know if you imagine
something where instead of this
construction like I saying before if
what you did instead was you said well
we're gonna take a step right and the
way that we're going to take that step
is we're gonna say look I want to go
whatever the the blend value is here I
want to do the step that is a long that
I want to step that far along the line
however much my blend value tells me to
step right that's restructuring the
thing in the old way where it's you know
if I have 1 minus u times target P plus
u times from P which
which was the lerp we were doing that's
just the the part I was saying before
about how that's from P minus u times
from P plus u times target P which if
you then pull out the you it's just from
P plus you can see in here you've got
the we go if I rearrange these two terms
here if I just pull out the U I get a u
times target pig - from P so if I said
that I was gonna parameterize it along
those lines then what I can do here is
say well let's imagine that I had the
sort of normalized direction vector so
you know I've got some derp and that's
always correct it's whatever the total
Delta P is it's always that direction
and if I don't have one then it's just
zero right
so I know what that is and I know that
my update is always going to be along
that line assuming that I have to update
at all and so in this case I know that
this would always be some blend value
times whatever that length value is so
for example Toto Delta P length right in
this case times the direction that's the
actual update step based on the blend
and so then what I could say is well
this can be a parameter that I'm playing
with and that I can store from frame to
frame and my T value can also be
something that I store from frame to
frame and then it becomes a bit of
finesse about which one about how I
update them right
so in this case you know it would be
something like this so you know if I was
to store these two things and then
adjust them so you know maybe we get a
delta P in here like that
and then I'm actually storing it out
this way and then the question is like
how am I actually gonna produce those
things so you know then there's there's
some update that happens with these
things but then I still always take the
same step this way and the D blend and
the DD blend maybe you know don't need
to be there I mean I can leave them in
because they're valid if we ever want to
use them for some other reason but then
let me save them you know and off we go
right so if I want to update that beast
you know in in some kind of sane way
here where I knew that I'm getting these
two things and then I want to do
something with them right um then the
first thing I could do is I could say
well look if if I was gonna use this
would it be a sensible thing for me to
do to just use whatever it was last time
right so meaning when I go to take this
T value and I want to move by whatever
the Delta step is that I'm asked to move
by whatever that is you know if I do
that to update this value and then I'm
going to look at what the actual change
would have been and I probably want to
do this right another way to do that I
guess would be this
so you know if I get the t-value and I
update it this way and then I say well
you know what if I actually just plugged
in that T value here so I you know I'm
gonna get this out of it what would that
you know what would that what would that
give me you know what I mean
so this is not entirely correct though
here so yeah like one of the problems
that we would have here is this
construction is sent quite right because
we don't know exactly where the you know
where that Delta P would have actually
placed us so you know really we need to
say something more like this
yeah so the target P minus the direction
like yeah I mean even if we did that I
just trying to talk this through sorry
I'm I'm taking this out my header we
can't actually do it that way because we
don't have the from P anymore so we
would have to turn this into something
that was a step that was based on four
back projecting where we were and then
taking a step forward towards the goal
from there we don't have from P here and
it's not actually this because right if
it was that then this Delta P value
would have had to have changed I guess
is the way to look at it
yeah I don't know
I'm not feeling in here folks not
feeling it
so trying to think through some other
options I mean one of the things we
could say I suppose is if the target if
we start our target and velocity and we
always assume that we arrive at the
target in one second right or at some
time right no matter what it is then
given our current velocity what is the
curve with this particular velocity that
would give us that and because we don't
have T we've just the T is not really I
think that still gets us back to having
to solve the quadratic because I don't
really see any way of making that
simpler because you're always gonna need
to know those two things
I mean I guess so here's a super crappy
way to do it if we actually just assumed
generally speaking that we were gonna
set the T value and the T value or
rather the we were going to ya know I
don't know I have no good solution to
this problem other than the nasty solve
the nasty solve is the only thing I
could think of that would let us
actually produce the thing that we want
which is to figure out which other curve
we could be following that would place
us there you know pleasantly right track
I'm just trying to think of any other
things that we could really do there and
I can't really think of what they are
another way to I guess parameterize this
would be to say like what if we just had
a velocity here and we were going to say
that the velocity is updated based on a
curve rule so that we have to solve for
something that will produce that but
that's the only thing that we saw for so
like if we know that we have
some kind of an update rule that just
does whatever it does so you know we've
got something here that produces our DP
and so it's something along the lines of
what this would be doing here right so
it's it's something along these lines
where we produce the D blend and then
you know we've got we've got to figure
out what the dip you know we're we're
always going to actually still be
applying this thing as as one of these
so we're going to actually take
derivative based steps so we're never
going to try and look at the first order
curve the zeroth order curve we're only
ever going to actually use an actual DP
and then we're gonna store the DP back
right so we're doing a more traditional
update step we don't know what T was
right but we're basically gonna we're
just trying to compute a DT DP pair
always so the DT we know and the DP is
just something that we're going to try
and compute to give us an update step
and we're going to do it in the standard
way where we would say in the case where
we would arrive at the target exactly
we're just gonna get there directly but
in the case where we wouldn't then we
won't
right so you know if we say well the
total Delta P length if that's less than
the step we would have taken so like if
that's less or greater than TP I should
say then we actually do our update but
otherwise we don't
and again this always happens in
the direction so you know we're gonna
step we're gonna step in derivative
space we're gonna have a target P here
and blah blah blah and we're gonna back
assign these right and so in this case
we would assign whatever we did use as
the DP is what we'll use again this time
and in here what we'll say is well
whatever we used as the DP is now zero
because we ever reached our target so
we're killing our velocity entirely
right makes sense um and so when we come
down through here we kind of don't
really know what we're doing and we
don't really know how we're gonna
produce this stuff right but if we look
at how this would get produced then
really what we need to figure out is
yeah um so really what we need to figure
out is how we would be producing this DP
right and so if we set the DP to like
the total Delta P length or something
like this right and if the DP was
greater than our maximum speed or
something like that oh and this is
actually times DP DT right so this is
you know I guess you could call that
belt that's the Delta P so it's the
actual time step that you're taking you
know the actual amount so in that case
where we're actually gonna take the step
we take the step otherwise we set it to
zero right and so here what we would say
is well the DP is going to be equal to
you know whatever the maximum speed is
in this case I don't know if it's over
1.0 then it just equals 1.0 or something
like that right um and that would give
us a linear blend right like we had
before without the curve in theory
anyway well if I haven't typed in
something wrong it gives us a very slow
okay that might that might be excessive
so let's say it was ten let's make it
faster than that right so there's a
speed ten version oh and actually I
guess what I really want to do is that
and so there's a non good version right
but we can see that the update is the
least happening properly so now the
question is just alright we know we had
a lot of trouble figuring out how we
might compute this value but what should
DP be in this case right like what do we
actually want our derivative to be can
we compute that from some curve that we
compute more heuristic aliy if solving
it is going to be pretty nasty right and
unclear if we really want something of
that complexity operating in here where
we can't really form a geometric
understanding of it right so if we want
to update that a little bit more
directly there and just play with it
more directly then what I'd want to do
here is say well I have the DP from last
time right so what I'd like to do is I'd
like to make something where we're going
to be stepping along a curve here so I'd
like to make some way of figuring out
where on the DP curve we were you know
based on what I'm going to construct to
create it right so maybe I just do a
series of constructions on curves to try
and solve it and see what would happen
in that case you know and so you know if
I was going to construct a curve onto
the target P you know maybe I can try
constructing a curve that's a
deceleration region so
you know maybe I look at it like this so
if the total Delta P that I have to go
is greater than some maximum then I want
to accelerate up to my maximum speed
right so I'm trying to increase my speed
so you know I've got my accel range here
right so if I know that I'm greater than
my acceleration range so maybe I'm you
know I'm over you know one or two away
then what I'm trying to do is I'm trying
to fit myself to where I am on an
acceleration curve right um so maybe I
say this sort of thing if I'm if I'm
greater than the than the combined of
these then I'm just trying to fit myself
to a curve to figure out where am I in
an acceleration curve and the
acceleration curve is of length this
okay um so what I would do is I would
solve with a known length this equation
for T right which I already know is easy
it's just that you know what I mean um
so actually I guess I'm solving for T
here
so my previous DP I guess I can pull out
here my previous velocity that I was if
I solved it this way I would get what
the T value is by saying V minus 2 BD
right over 6a and so if we look at what
that gives us we know what a is we know
what B is and so D in this case is the
only thing we don't know but we do
actually know what it is it's the
acceleration range because that's the
curve that we're mapping it into right
so we're gonna see let's map ourselves
into and oh and this by the way is the
DP we're solving for right so let's
solve for the T that we should get there
and then what we want to know is let's
get what our velocity should be now at
that point so what should DP be if we
were gonna map it up right like what
would it be and so in order to get what
that DP should be now what we want to do
is feed it back into this equation and
get what the actual derivative was at
that at that point right so we want you
know whatever our Excel range value is
here times whatever the derivative of
this curve is which is this right for
that given T value
that's what I would argue right again we
know a we know B bla bla so the only
thing that we didn't know here in this
case was T and now we've done that and
updated our DP so then we're saying look
that's what the derivative should be it
should be this because that's the
derivative of what the actual function
was in that case right I mean I think
that's roughly correct and then we would
say well okay well in the case where the
total DP length is actually less than
the deceleration range so you know we I
mean I guess we could even say look if
it's less than the deceleration range
you know here we're gonna do this sort
of thing and then we're gonna say look
as we accelerate this T forward we know
we never want the T to go past 0.5 so we
would essentially say like if T is
greater than 0.5 T equals 0.5 right
other way to say that would be T equals
clamp between 0 and 0.5 meaning look
we're gonna accelerate to max pede if we
can and only if we're inside the
deceleration range would we back back
down right seems what we want to do so
everywhere outside of there the
acceleration range we're gonna map in to
where we were and then we're gonna move
forwards by some amount you know to move
our T forward there so this goes away
and this is like that
right I think
you know don't quote me on that so in
this case we're just gonna say look
let's let's recompute this thing with a
known range and this is kind of just
maybe saying look we're just gonna use
the T acceleration value in this case
and if we see that we're less than it
then we're gonna solve that we're gonna
use the same DP to solve back into a
deceleration curve which might not be
what we had been doing but now we've
fallen into the deceleration range right
and so now what we need to do is when
we're in the deceleration range we need
to say what was the T that we were at
for that level of deceleration given
what our distance is now I guess I'm not
sure what we would do I guess
if we're inside the deceleration range
we just do the step without doing the
deep consideration maybe
meaning if this is actually true maybe
we map the T and we take the T step
based on distance instead you know what
I mean instead of by T so in other words
here instead of solving for T if we
solve for D meaning we solved for
distance now
and I guess that's not even really a
solved that's just saying look let's map
how far we are so Artie you know we I
guess we're really just saying look take
whatever the T value is which is going
to be our total P length in this case
right and then we would take so that's
how far we are and we want to map that
into our deceleration range that's our T
value right and we're just going to step
it forward now we want it to actually be
a strictly decelerating curve in that
range so what we would want to do there
I think is say well we're actually gonna
step down from you know we're actually
shifting this so that we start at 0.5
and go so we really want that if that
makes sense
and oops and once we've mapped that then
we're just going to take the actual T
step directly
and we don't really need to do this we
could just take the T step directly but
I guess I'm not going to do that right
now
um that's absurd probably stupid and it
probably won't work just for the record
this stuff will want to work in a
slightly different way so for right now
what I'll do is I'm not gonna blend
those because we will want those I I
also think we probably like as we were
seeing we really don't want those
blending separately we want those to
blend oh wow you know what I can
actually just do this we actually want
those to probably be set directly off
the camera because it looked like they
really shouldn't interpolate on their
own because there was like some bad
effects that look like they were
happening there all right so let's try
and get this working now I'd rather I'd
like to have it sort of at least working
crapoly and then we'll pick it up again
on next dream
so this actually takes the the DT into
account here so I guess really now I
think that's all correct
but the D cell there needs to update T
right
I so yeah looking at these as we kind of
move along the curve there and get
whatever that derivative should have
been
I don't know if this should really just
be computing the T equation directly
because now that we're moving along the
curve the DP is really just a residual
value we store for solving so it seems
like it will waste to do it this way but
I'll keep doing it this way for now but
that looks fine
yeah
so I feel like that should be okay
so I'm not really sure why we're not
able to get any motion there I guess
with a max speed of one that's not great
so I mean you could also say well this
this is probably not great I am
interested to know if we're just getting
a slowness factor there but we want to
push that back into the thing
you
so it sort of works it's not good but it
sort of works so okay so looking at the
XO and D cell range there and just
thinking it through a little bit better
I'll probably leave thinking about this
because I want to percolate on it and
think about what we might be able to do
here that's a little bit better but yeah
in terms of acceleration
we should have seen that kind of come up
to speed like I'm not sure why we were
seeing what we were seeing there exactly
like we should have seen that come up to
speed a little more gradually because
the DT here is in real-time right so
this is going to go over the course of a
second right and this should solve back
into the same thing
Oh although are we solving the did I
solve the wrong thing there that's the
derivative that's the that's not the
velocity if that's the acceleration um
so I need to actually do that slightly
wrong there it's really that that we
have done the equation for which yeah I
guess I don't know any particular reason
we can't do it that way but that is
different
we can do this a lot cleaner in fact we
can pull these two out you can see
they're computing the same thing so all
you really need is the tea you know I
mean and the end of range but I'm not
gonna do that quite yet cuz we don't
really know what we're doing here um so
if I do that and then store the DDP
instead and the DP is only used for the
computation you know maybe that's a
little better because we're using the
wrong thing there but I don't know like
I hack that in pretty quickly so there's
probably other problems it seems like
we're not really getting what I expect
though and like I don't know what's
going on with that I think that's just
these um so what I could do is change
those you know while we're playing with
this I could go ahead and change the fog
and alpha spans to just be like out in
the middle of nowhere you know what I
mean
it doesn't help that we get jerky frame
rates that I'm not really sure exactly
where they come from at the moment
possibly the fact that we're a little
too stressing on the graphics card but
I'm not sure
but you can kind of see it it has a
hitch in there too so yeah so just
thinking through what we would want to
do here you know during the acceleration
phase right we're basically saying look
we want to try and get up to the speed
here so we see like where we were at and
then we would figure out what we would
want to compute based on oops don't ask
me why that's that way and then in the
deceleration range we would just say all
right map us into however far away we
are from the target we're going to and
we'll just slowly you know kind of
decelerate there and if we wanted to
again like I saying we could sort of
make this thing just actually take the
step by reverse computing what the T
actually is doing and doing the lerp
right so you know in here we could just
say well that's what the DDP is for
placement but you know we want to
actually do the lerp here and we do know
where we're going right we're going to
the target P always and we're going from
the target P minus whatever the deep the
whatever the the size of this curve was
along that the direction right so we
want to loop from whatever the the d
cell range we want to loop from here to
here using our standard T value right
and so in order to produce that
smoothing we need to do this
but it would just look like that then to
produce the value that we retained for
future solving we would just say well
the deceleration range is the multiplier
and then the you know the six times
eight times T plus two times B that's
the sort of the version of this that
gets us our derivative right so you know
we could do that and then you know in
here where we're actually doing the
where we're still doing sort of that
that update I think that just works okay
probably
but the DDP part of it again is just
gonna be you know this here um so yeah
so looking at the acceleration range if
this is the acceleration range this is
how many units we want to accelerate
over you know what I mean then that's
how that would work and then down here
we would have two of these in the
acceleration case like you wouldn't have
to do that but in the deceleration case
you would right so you would essentially
have this
alright so either we get there and this
is zero because it would just be T
equals one which should in theory give
us zero for this because that's what
that's set to so in theory this should
be actually the deceleration range
version should just work and the
acceleration range it's the only one
that actually need to destroy this value
right
um I'm just trying to look at this here
so yes so looking in here at the range
we want to accelerate over there's also
I suppose in addition it's it's really
not clear to how fast you want to do
those two things so you have a speed as
well of of how you want those to go so
in the deceleration version now where
it's actually just stepping directly
there I'm not sure so this is a little
bit off so if we take the total P length
and we look at the deceleration range
then we're gonna say we're gonna map it
into that space right so this is the
part of the curve that would be
decelerating
then this part is actually needs to be
to that range because we're only taking
the halfway so we're actually lurking
such that it starts twice as far back as
that I believe that's correct
yeah so I'm not sure again though why
I'm getting that I think I might have
made a mistake in this one so let's make
these a little larger just temporarily
so if we're within the deceleration
range we map the T so that we're getting
the deceleration range to basically be
half of T goes from 0.5 to 1 right then
I want to blend there and I want to say
I want to lurk to the target P between
these two things that's that 0.5 is
actually where we would start on this so
the deceleration range times the
direction times 2 is actually back where
we would have been we use the blend this
way to go into the target a like so and
then we have the DDP equals the
deceleration range times this but again
that actually is wrong too so that
actually needed to be 2 as well in there
so I guess that's about right maybe but
it still it doesn't seem it doesn't seem
like it's really working at all so I
think I've got something very buggy
happening there but I'm just not sure
exactly what it is
Oh weird I'm not actually updating the
cameras position here though that was
weird so what was it doing in that case
what is going on there I'm gonna this
case at the moment by the way
so what am i doing weird there so I'm
lurking between this location on the
target P and I'm using the blend value
for that and I know that this has to be
something between 0.5 and 1 so I know my
T value is something reasonable right so
that seems fine and really so I don't
know I don't see a lot of issues with
that when I do my lerp here the GDP
value isn't really used right so that's
not getting used because I'm not hitting
this case so I don't really understand
how I'm getting that behavior what am I
doing wrong they're doing something
really wrong
because I should be able to map that in
right I mean there's nothing weird about
what's happening here I don't think you
know that should be really
straightforward
so I guess the mapping here is a little
bit possibly wrong but I don't think it
actually is I mean I guess the way you
could write this instead is to say that
if it's less than that then you're going
to map it into the actual double
deceleration range right and so when you
map it like that and and but you you
know when you do this you're gonna
naturally have to it's going to work out
to the same exact equation because you
have to offset it because you want the
back half of the curve right so I mean
it's gonna be that one way or the other
I mean that's that is the T value that
you are along the curve and then the
clamp T value is just saying well when I
update that you know I'd better not go
over one that all seems fine to the
blending value is literally just
computing the straightforward blend so
it's just doing the exact blend we were
doing before and then the lerp is just
using that value to get to the target so
as far as I know like this is the only
thing that could be wrong and I guess
there's plenty of opportunities for that
to be wrong I mean if I'm going from the
target position - whatever the direction
is times two times the range
oh I do still have to do the solve right
because that's not actually correct that
would only be correct if the speed was
linear right so that tells you your
linear displacement along the curve so
you do still need to do the solve right
you need to be able to solve for T along
that position so if you map where you
are in the deceleration range that only
tells you what your output T that's this
equation right but it doesn't tell you
what your input T would be so you
probably still do want to solve it this
way because if you don't solve it that
way you're in kind of a world of hurt
right I'm trying to think if there's any
other way to solve it
because you'd have to solve a cubic
wouldn't you I mean you have to solve a
T's cubed plus BT plus CT
so yeah for that deceleration I have no
idea how you do that without doing a
cubic solve
hmm I tell you man this stuff is really
nasty this is why most people just strap
proportional derivative controller to
everything call it a day it's because
actually trying to get something that
has a predictable curve behavior turns
out to be really nasty
[Music]
so I guess what I could do is I could
solve for the curve that's at this
starting from this point with this
velocity and hits the other point with
the velocity of zero
what would the curve be but I still
don't really know how far along that
curve to step but what I mean to say
there is I could say well during the
deceleration phase if I wanted to I
could do something like say well I know
I've got you know this this construction
that I did up here so I know I've got
this and I guess what I would say is if
I wanted to have the acceleration that I
have currently and I want to end at zero
and I know how far I have to go you know
what is that curve look like and so that
would be saying yeah that would be
saying like okay
I guess that would be saying okay I know
that I want to have an acceleration port
proportional to this T value anyway
because I know I can't really solve for
the actual T value without a lot of
stress so I do still want to produce the
value as a DP value and the DP value is
going to be whatever you would expect to
be along that target but then you'll
overshoot I just do not see any good
solution here to do it this way
everything really wants you to solve a
cubic or specify time I I see literally
no good answers I'm gonna have to work
on it
I'm gonna have to see if I could come up
with something that I think would be
reasonable here we can't always fall
back to something that is basically just
a proportional derivative controller you
know which we can clamp out and probably
be fine I just it would have been really
nice if we could have find something
better than that right you know I would
have I would have preferred that
certainly if we did want to do something
like that then it's easier right if we
do want to sort of not try to have a
resolved rate curve proportional
derivative controller update steps are
very straightforward which I guess is
one nice thing and I guess I'll put one
of those in for now because I would like
to end the stream with having something
reasonable in place for that and so if I
get rid of all of that stuff that we
were doing there what I want to do here
is look at the DP and I want to match my
target DP if ideally as well and so we
kind of need to get that value from the
game at some point and we're good so
we're gonna need that but so we're gonna
need a DP of the target and right now
I'll set that to zero but it's gonna
give us bad behavior and so we're gonna
have to you know get that out but the
proportional derivative controller
construction you've seen me do many
times before it's not very complicated
all you're effectively doing is doing an
update step that you would normally do
in anything else I'm not gonna do it I'm
gonna compute it in two steps so I'm
going to compute the DP first here and
this is this is gonna be the speed so I
might say like it's just a velocity
value so I might call it that because
it's not the actual vector um if that
makes sense but we're gonna compute a DP
vector here
then we're gonna update it based on the
time step here right and so I'm gonna
use the same construction that I used
before which was this and the reason
that I'm going to do that is because I
want to know in this case if the length
of the thing if you know if the amount
that I was gonna step by is going to
exceed the the is gonna exceed the
distance that I needed to go that I'm
gonna actually do something more like
this right so in order to produce the DP
you know the actual speed value it's
really just a measure of the distance so
it's the target it's you know it's it's
the the Delta that I need to go here
right and I guess you know now I think
about it I could probably produce it
this way so maybe I take it back I can't
just call it this um so the difference
between where I'm going and where I'm
trying to go to right whatever that
value is I apply some kind of
coefficient to it and that is my you
know sort of a coefficient right and
then I've got another term which is a
term that specifies how I want to adjust
the target velocity so whatever my
current speed is that I was using versus
the speed that you know that the target
itself is moving and this is going to be
what my acceleration value is so
actually I guess I should have written
that as a deep DP there right and so I
want to remember what my actual DP is
and I guess I want to be able to you
know feed that back in here so that I
can so that I can can update it right
like it written back yeah alright so
using a simple update step like this
allows me to set two parameters two
tuning parameters and those tuning
parameters are how much I want the
velocity difference to be accounted for
and how much I want the positional
difference to be accounted for
right and so each of those terms comes
you know as I get further away from the
target this term becomes more dominant
as I get closer to the target this term
becomes more dominant because you know
this one starts to fade away and it's
more about the difference in velocity
between the two things which this often
times will be zero and this often times
will be larger because I'm trying to
like get those you know to to line up to
come to rest
um so typically what I want to do here
is I want to say well what whatever the
difference is in these two things you
know I want my I want to match the speed
of the target what's gonna be zero so
this this value is actually gonna like
penalize me for going too fast right and
we're gonna have to play with these two
values and see what we want them to
actually be right and we got to actually
get this in there at some point so now
in order to produce this this actual you
know make all this work right I've got
to be able to integrate this D D you
know this d DP up right and so in order
to integrate it up I need to produce a
DP value which is actually like the more
correct speed there right I need to
produce the actual I need to produce the
actual velocity and since that wants to
be smooth I need to take the
acceleration and I need to produce the
the delta from that right so I need to
say look I'm going to take the
however much I said I was supposed to
change here and I guess that's one of
those two yeah cuz this is all this is
all in three dimensions now right so I
need to take however much I was supposed
to do here I need to integrate that up
so I need to produce this by multiplying
by my DT you know and I need to add
whatever the old one was so whatever the
cameras DP used to be I'm doing gonna do
that now so once I produce those values
then finally I need to take the step so
whatever the p-value should have been
here I need to take that actual step and
doing that actually requires me to if I
wanted to do the integration a little
more carefully here you know technically
P is equal to whatever the acceleration
was here and I should probably write the
DT on the other side of this right it's
actually 1/2 a teaspoon to grate it up
twice and that's the acceleration that's
actually the correct way that it would
that it would apply over the time step
and then I've got my velocity which I've
just computed which is this right so
that's that gets applied times the times
DT in this case I just want to apply the
old one and then I want to add whatever
the old position was right so that's the
full integration with the proportional
derivative controller in it and then
I've got my my case where I would just
set it directly to look at the target P
with that I could do anything else and
so in that case again this would just
become 0 or actually it would become
whatever the DP of the target was
because that's I'm just moving
with it am I my GDP in this case would
be completely zero case I care I don't
but in case I do right and so yeah
moving looking at what's gonna happen
here I mean you still need an if to see
whether I'm close enough to the target
that I shouldn't actually take the step
and so this update here is one giant
vector right this is effectively a new P
in a sense right and so if I wanted to
take this as a delta P it's just this
right that's the amount that I'm moving
it by if I wanted to take that Delta P
what I can do is say look if the length
of the Delta P is less than some amount
I don't care about and I could avoid the
square root here by just saying look if
the length squared is less than you know
some epsilon right or sorry if the
length squared is less than the distance
to the target right so in this case
whatever the total Delta P was and these
are not is there anymore
so if the length squared is less than
how far I have to go then just you know
or maybe I'll get to the right if it's
greater than then do the actual update
step otherwise just assume I arrive at
the target you know I mean um and then
we just track that Delta P each time so
you know when we write everything back
we write back our Delta P as well so our
camera keeps its acceleration and stuff
and that's again just a very simple
controller they're not good they can
overshoot they could do a lot of stupid
things but the bonus is at least if I do
bug why it's doing something weird like
that if the length squared is of the
Delta P sorry it is less than if the
amount I would move it is less than the
total that's what I meant to do
and now you can kind of see like the
cameras just kind of doing its thing
I got a again we don't have a lerp for
the for these guys right now so we got
to kind of pretend they're you know out
in la-la land they're like so um but
that will give an always smooth approach
there you can kind of see and the easing
in is not quite where we would like it
and you can see it kind of circling
there a little bit and so you know you
gotta adjust these terms a bit to make
them stiffer I don't know what the best
time to be probably something higher
here no we could put we could put those
in as dialable parameters as well right
in our camera code
yes so I think we want some pretty high
values for a there
so you know again most of the reason why
you use one of these is just because
proportional derivative controller us
have the benefit of they kind of just
work and they don't give you any
resolved like any absolutes so you can
get some drifting and some weirdness in
there but they don't really have any
other issues related to them in that
sense so I would like something better
than that but just that exploration did
not seem fruitful and it seemed like we
were gonna get something pretty hard to
control if that makes sense we can clamp
these values as well so we can make sure
that we're actually not gonna get into
some really bad state
cuz that's usually what you worry about
when your values start to overflow so we
can put a clamp in there and we should
probably do that but the other thing I
want to do is for these with the target
expected focus Minzy and that stuff um I
think what I'd like to do there is just
make it so that
I'd like to have some notion of the
interpolation being based on how far we
are from the target that makes sense
like I want the expected min focus and
stuff I would like that to be kind of
more based on just where the camera is
but the problem is it's hard to know how
to do that exactly I'm not sure how to
put in a good blend here you know
something that would make thing these
things track the distance better
I mean we could kind of make them follow
this approach
and another way maybe to do that would
be to say look we can figure out how far
we are from the target camera and use
that as the blend amount or make that
imply the speed I don't know
blending these together is going to be
sort of tricky because if you think
about what we actually want Jimmy um
when we're setting these like the entity
focus in the room focus values here for
for these blending those together
blending those is going to be tough
because you can see what happens there
how we get a blackout right that's
because they're getting set
instantaneously to the new one so we
want to blend smoothly between the new
one and the old one but we what we
really want is something that maintains
sort of a notion of of where the
intermediate target would have been
versus us like I almost want to say that
when you're doing this blend you know if
you're looking here the room focus see
is based on the camera arm and the
camera arm is something that we sort of
vaguely know what it is because we know
what it was and then we know what it's
going to be and so you could almost
imagine interpolating that as like
another target parameter that could be
interpolated along with this right
so yeah I don't really know how else we
would do that other than setting it up
to interpolate sort of the same way that
this is interpolating or just probing it
I don't got a lot of ideas there if I'm
honest about it you know that's the
target entity focus see the current
entity focus see he's just looking at
where the right like wherever the entity
is that we're trying to look at
we know that wherever we are so this is
the actual entity focus Z and so the
thing that I'm wondering about is like
do we want to just base things off of
that more I don't know what that would
do probably nothing good so yeah a lot
of puzzlers here I'm not sure what the
best way would be to make that code
happen because you want it synchronized
with something that I'm not sure exactly
what it is
and you want to interpolate at some rate
that's roughly commensurate with how
fast the cameras interpolating but since
the camera is using a proportional
derivative control you really don't have
that option you know hmm so that's a
little bit tricky but I don't know so
I'll just throw them into the
proportional derivative controller with
the rest of the system and see what
happens I wish I had a better answer for
you than that but I don't and so if we
were to do that you know we just compute
that directly right we would say all
right you know what's the speed of these
things right and then we'd update them
so we just say yeah like this code
literally and this is all F 32s now but
you're literally doing this and when you
go to compute this thing you're gonna
use the same thing but now like the
targets and stuff are specified from
here so you'd basically have like okay
whatever the target expected focus mimsy
is right is where we're going to and
whatever the expected focus mimsy is
this where we're coming from you don't
have this term because you know it's
always zero because you don't haven't a
changing value of that really although I
guess you could argue that you actually
do when you're going downstairs so maybe
I shouldn't say that so maybe you really
do
have this which is the DP target value
for this thing right and then you've got
the velocity in there you then compute
what your DP is and you do it exactly
the same way and you use the you know
expect to focus them in there you
compute the Delta the exact same code
and then you see you know if if the
absolute value of those two things or
just the square of those two things you
could do right you could also just do if
square then you you set otherwise you're
done right
since I don't really think this should
be changing much because most of the
time the target relative to the camera
since you're moving the camera I think
you could probably eliminate this term
so I'm going to say like for now this is
always zero and so you would do this for
both of them
for both min and Max right oops
and then you call it a day
so yeah that's I think most of what you
would be doing and you know if we did
this real quick we could just say those
are the three update steps and we can
pull that out into code that actually
makes more sense
and is little were used on the next
stream so the total Delta P in this case
I need to actually compute right so this
would be the best value
and in this case - we've got the the
p-value is not actually that right it's
this so in this case we would just set
them directly and off we go and you can
see how we would be pretty easy to just
make the utilities that did these for us
so even though it looks like a lot of
code it's just the same code so we
should be able to just run that twice by
calling a function right and we'd be
done so you know that in theory attaches
the same proportional derivative
controller to both things but they're in
different spaces in one sweetie and
one's 1d so you know we don't have a lot
of reason to believe that they're
actually gonna work particularly well
and you can kind of see that there it's
taking a lot longer to do that now we
can adjust all the parameters to try and
make it so they you know are stiffer or
because that you know they're like I
said they're in different spaces so I
don't know I mean we can certainly say
that you know the a B here are not the
same a be that we have here you know
maybe this is like way stronger or
something but like I said that's that's
maybe something for next change time
like massively over time now it's like
almost four o'clock
and you can see where the DP target
might have been useful there right
because that would probably have
improved the the speed at which would
interpolate up to the entity there
are we not using the entity no we are so
what was that it does it does seem yeah
well anyway maybe I'll make this even
stronger than it was
because it just doesn't seem like it
catches up quite quickly enough as it as
it seems like it should
oh and you know why it's because it's
not actually measuring what the entity Z
it's it's measuring what it will be
after it interpolates so I can sort of
see why that would be wrong too
so we we have some more work to do there
right yeah so we'll have to take a look
at that I'll go to a really brief QA but
I I gotta go like it's way we're way
over time here this is a disaster
Paul MMH moving my racket to Linux is
always like sort of an eventual goal
someday you know we already have a
problem we're like like I don't want to
use Windows 10 because I really don't
like Windows 10 it's very unpredictable
and bad I mean they can't even chip
updates anymore right you saw what
happened the October update they tried
three times to ship the update and
couldn't do it it's like a fourth times
a charm kind of situation and and it's
just the unpredictability of it updating
it's on its own and doing all these
ridiculous things it's just not it's
Windows 10 is not a real opera it's not
a production quality operating system
right anymore
I mean you're not it's not something you
would ever trust to run mission-critical
stuff you know it's it's so far past
that ensue you know like I would like to
switch to Linux because I can lock that
down you know I can pick which kernel
gets built and I can put it on the
machines and I and I don't have to worry
about Microsoft like ruining our week
all the time by changing some update or
doing whatever right and so you know I
really want to do that but the problem
is that since most people don't use
Linux for things like this game
development on Linux is not that common
most of the stuff isn't it I mean I
don't even know what the status of n
site is on Linux hopefully it's you know
okay or there's something like that
there that you can use reliably right
but the Dib buggers aren't very good
you know gdb is very bad it crashes most
the time on this machine like just like
I just tried to debug a very simple like
program was it nearly as complicated and
made hero and gdb would crash every
second run just gdb let alone if I try
to attach a front end to gdb and that
crashes on its own often right and so
like it's just not I don't know like the
actual debugging
of it seems pretty bad the actual dev
environment for it just seems really bad
and I don't know why you know I don't
know why it's so bad since it's
something that lots of people do dev on
now
is the planet change to character face
direction when they move in a direction
over that we mapped a different key it's
a map to different keys so right now the
way that it works is you you can point
any direction you want and you can hop
in any direction you want which will
probably remain the same I don't know
for sure but probably right you can see
the proportion of college of stuff just
doesn't work that good for that for
first sliding I I'm we may want to
change it to something more linear like
just update those linearly you know like
we may want to not have an a/b value
like you may want to just do this
and you just say hey yeah we don't we
don't use a proportional derivative
controller for these we just say look if
we were gonna step you know the Delta
well you know I'm not gonna do that
right now there's just too much code
right if there were truly good better
than visual studio debugger for Linux
would that make Linux viable for game
dev probably although I don't know how
good the GPU support is still it used to
be very bad so hopefully that's better
but I'm not really sure I guess what I
would say is it would be a big big
improvement and you need both a debugger
for code and for GPU so both of those
need to be available
it looks like the average size dream is
currently too big to be seen without
scrolling is that what we want in the
end or is it just the average size room
is so I'm sorry yeah we we will play
with that later but we want to support
both
Oh as for code releases code releases
won't be released till after the game
it's it says right on the webpage two
years after the game gets released we
will release the code the updates for
you get applied for the camera for the
fog all right I'm gonna wrap it up I
gotta go
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for those set of handmade here it's a
pleasure coding with you as always even
if we couldn't quite figure out how to
get a good solver based approach in
there
I don't love for shield River
controllers for a lot of reasons but you
know that seems to be the most
straightforward way to get one that's
tunable then I guess that's what we got
to work with people reason for a reason
I do some other things sometimes in my
own code but yeah I I can't think of
anything in this particular situation
that really is going to be simple enough
so I don't know so we may just be stuck
with that and if we are that's okay
anyway that's it for now I'll be back
probably next weekend with the final one
before winter break you can always
stretch the watch page for the schedule
I try to keep it updated until then have
fun programming and I will see you next
time