hello everyone welcome to handmade Hiro
sure we code complete-game live on
stream last weekend we put in some stuff
to check to see if any art asset files
have changed and if they had changed to
go through them and load them into our
game using the PNG reader and pull out
the basically parts of the asset based
on the grid system that we had set up we
stopped there and we don't really know
exactly what we're gonna do for tags
because now that we have like
specifically laid out art assets the way
the artist wants them we may want to
sort of update how we're doing our tag
system to better align with that right
too we may want to tweak that in fact
I'm almost certain we do but doing that
it's gonna require us to think it
through a little bit better and so you
know we're kind of on a little bit of a
journey in that sense where we're gonna
have to kind of figure out what we want
to do there because I'm not really sure
and we'll kind of see as we go it's our
first time really looking at these
assets so that's kind of what we're
gonna be starting down today essentially
what we have to do is actually put these
art assets now to use and putting these
art assets to use means being able to
start tagging them and other things like
this and so that's why it's kind of
gonna force the issue like we can't
really even do a simple version of what
we want to do here because in order to
put the art assets into the game at all
just after we load the bitmaps the thing
that will allow them to be used is to
tag them with something so probably what
we're gonna have to do first is just
make something that since synthetically
uses our existing tag system to tag
these assets with something that can be
looked up and then from there hopefully
we will have gained the insight
necessary to make a simplified system
that just accommodates exactly the kind
of assets we have and can probably speed
up the way we're doing tags right now
we're doing tags pretty sloppy right now
because we just have an anything-goes
arbitrary sort of vector matching system
and it looks like the assets we get
don't really need something like that so
we can take this opportunity to actually
take a step back from the tax system we
had and just probably remove some of the
stuff from it what
you'll make it faster it's simpler
easier to use all good things so
hopefully that's clear if it's not clear
we'll just stick with what we got till
it doesn't become clear because we don't
want to make any changes to our system
if we don't really know what we're doing
right that's no good so we want to
actually get a clear signal first a
clear idea that we actually have
something specific that would make an
improvement until I actually get that
sense I'm not going to touch it but
that's certainly what I'm looking
towards and I'm hoping that's where we
would get after we play around with it
for a little while and and sort of
understand our art assets a little bit
better so what we could see here is
where we left off is this check for art
changes concept this is basically
something we can wire up in one of two
ways
right now what I'm going to do is I'm
just going to wire it up to a key so we
push it in an update to the art in the
future we could use directory change
notification or just a timer to check
periodically things like that so we have
a lot of options for how we can actually
trigger the check for art changes but
that's sort of a separate issue we don't
care about that it's not very relevant
they're all totally fine solutions some
have like maybe a little bit better than
others but any of them will work fine
the important thing that we have to get
to is just what happens once it triggers
because just let's say hitting a key
right now will do it and then we have to
worry about okay so when you actually
know that there that the user or the
file system has indicated that it's time
to look and see what changed what do we
actually do so just to recap what we did
there was we said all right when we do
check for our changes we're gonna ask
the platform layer to give us all the
PNG s that reside in the art asset input
directory we're just going to loop
through those and we're going to ask you
to to basically take the take the file
name hash it so we can look up and see
if we've got an existing version of it
and also split it into some pieces and
this is relevant we did this sort of
proactively because again we know we're
gonna have to do something with that
those pieces are separated by
underscores and that's what we're gonna
have to use now because remember the PNG
the artists don't have any idea how to
mark those up right you know in
Photoshop you can go in and
texts and stuff that will come out in
the PNG and things like that we could
have our artist do stuff like that it's
just it's not something that artists
generally do and it's putting an extra
onus on them
to deal with that and so I'd rather just
not so instead what we'd like to do is
reduce the file name artists understand
file names they work with them every day
so if you can tell them okay the file
names should look like this that's much
easier for them to verify and work with
then use some obscure text an annotation
tool in Photoshop that you've never used
before right so you want to try and keep
things simple in that sense and so we've
tried to do that but what that means is
we have two parts the final name
specifically not the cause of the file
to tell us what this actually is so we
get an a bitmap that's great it's got
the information it's got the stuff that
the artist drew but what it doesn't tell
us is what that stuff pertains to right
we just get a bunch of images okay
here's a character or something right
how do we know if it's the hero or one
of the other orphans from the orphanage
or is it a monster like a snake or
something that's supposed to attack you
you know all of those things all we get
is a sprite sheet that's that's all we
have so the file name is the thing
that's gonna allow us to do that and so
what we have to do is we have to work
from a file name four words to get the
tags that should be there for each
individual asset so that's what's gonna
start to come into play today and
tomorrow so that's very important right
now it's just thrown away so right now
we just we parse it but we don't use it
so we're going to be putting that in to
use that parsed file name separated by
the underscores there but right now
we're not doing that so that's the
that's something we're going to be doing
so then what we did is we look to see if
we have the file in question already
processed if we do then we know that
we've sort of mashed an existing asset
and have to update it if we haven't then
what we do is we create a new sort of
storage thing that says okay here is a
new artist that we've not seen before
right so that's how that goes so while
we're doing this there's one thing we
didn't handle here and I'm not sure
exactly how we would want to handle it
it's kind of a
question to answer what will happen if
we don't make any changes to how this is
working right now is if you delete it in
our asset file the assets would still
remain in the PAC file until you rebuilt
it fresh right so let's say that you
created ten sprite sheets for ten
monsters monsters one through ten if you
then deleted monster seven sprite sheet
it wouldn't matter you could still use
Monster seven all day long in the game
because it would still be in the PAC
file because it had been imported and it
would just be there would be no
indication that was gone there are
reasons to and not to do that but even
if we say that we want to continue doing
that well we will probably want to do
and I'll put it to do in here cuz I
don't think we put one in here for it
yet what we will probably want to do is
at least warn the artist and or
programmer that that has occurred so if
they delete Monster seven we should
probably warn them hey Monster seven is
still available in the PAC files you
deleted Monster seven you should just be
aware of that fact like we should
probably hoping it says like if and if
maybe if someone in the game uses that
sprite maybe it should be marked as such
like maybe we should put a purple
outline around it or something like that
because probably you never want the game
to get into a state that you've deleted
the source pings but you're still using
them effectively because that's like
almost an error state like it's even
though the game can still go if you you
probably always want to be in a position
to rebuild your assets from scratch you
don't want to be in a situation where
the PAC file on a particular machine is
holding the only copy of the art assets
right like that
not really where we want to be so I do
think we probably want to do that you
know something in here where we can say
like do a sweep mark to set all assets
to unseen then mark each one we see so
we can detect when files have been
[Music]
deleted because if you think about
what's going on one of the props so this
is sort of a meta comment that I'll make
it's true about file systems in general
so one of the core mistakes that was
made in the design of most modern file
systems is that deleted files are no
longer present so this is a really
crucial in my opinion mistake and it's
not how file system should work so in my
opinion the way a file system should
work is deleted files should still show
up as deleted that's just I mean that's
just how they should work so for example
if you have a directory and you have a
dot txt B Tech C dot txt and D dot txt
right if you delete C dot txt what you
should see if you do directory of that
is you should see C dot txt parentheses
delete it now that may sound like a
weird thing why is he saying that why is
he saying it's an obvious mistake that
file systems do this rather than just a
preference thing the reason is because
deletion is an act it is a thing that
the user actually did and by removing
any trace of the fact that they've done
it it becomes impossible for you to
properly synchronize directories you can
no longer tell the difference between a
directory that had ABCD and then had C
removed then one that just had a B and D
and never had a C in the first place
what this means is that backup utilities
file synchronization utilities
networking utilities all of these things
now have to keep backing stores to
determine whether or not you deleted
files and when it comes to
a situation where you have deleted files
it only really knows since its last
snapshot it doesn't really even know if
maybe there was a file there and then
you deleted that file which is the
information it can't get if it didn't
take a snapshot in between the creation
and the deletion right so a lot of
modifier says to make this mistake
there's attempts to add it back in so I
think like windows volume Shadow Copy
Service
I think understands this now so I don't
quote me on this but I believe that
modern file systems now have a little
more of this getting added back in but
it was kind of like a huge dark period
where we didn't have it and so now it
still doesn't really exist in the file
API is and even accessing that becomes
difficult bla bla bla what we are seeing
here is just a tip of an iceberg of a
mistake in a design of the general way
we consider file systems to work and
here it is rather than getting the
obvious thing we want which is a listing
of all of the file names that have
existed in this directory and which one
still exists
instead we're getting something quite a
bit worse than that which is just a list
of the files that exist currently you
can take this one step further and
understand the fact that really you
should have a change grid with every
file name so every file name rather than
saying what the last right time is not
particularly relevant what you need is
the last change index and every time
that the file is updated you can create
the changes right again that would allow
us to see whether these files were the
same or different and if we miss changes
in between right so at least this would
say oh the last time you looked it was
changed number 32 now it's changed 4000
someone made 8 different changes that we
didn't get to see right again
information so a lot of this information
gets lost and modern file systems just
do a bad job with it they are starting
to add these things back in you know
like the old VMs file system actually
understood versions when you change the
file you could see the old versions of
the file automatically stuff like this
so there were people understood better
in the old days what file systems might
be
we got rid of a lot of that in personal
computing and maybe you'll get better
back in but this is just one very small
very simple example of how that
manifests itself in making it harder to
make tools that work with files again
very very basic there's a lot more we
could say about it but hopefully that
gives you some perspective on why the
basic file operations that were exposed
with say fat32 and things like that are
just are just not very good right there
they're not the course that you would
want and a lot of people don't know any
better so they think that that's just
what a file system is but it shouldn't
be it should be more than that and you
know hopefully someday we'll kind of
klar way back to there because this is
not news I'm not saying things that are
revolutionary I'm saying things that are
if anything retroactive they're saying
hey can we get back some of the
technology we had in the 1970s and which
went away in the personal computing era
and which now you know is kind of hope
going to hopefully come back hopefully I
say that with a big hopefully because
who knows alright so anyway so we want
to do something like that eventually
probably right now that's the least of
our concerns the tags are gonna be the
bigger problem so we don't really have
to care about that too much that's sort
of a minutiae point a nice to have if
you will so what we're really looking at
here is the the core stuff here once we
get one of these things in and we see
that we it's out of date and remember
this will work correctly when we've
never seen the thing before because the
file date will just get initialized to
zero so that's that will never be a
valid file date that comes through so we
will automatically trigger this case
either if the file has actually had a
write update done to it so the file date
has changed from the old file date or we
will trigger if the file date was zero
here right because then this will never
be able to be matched so it'll it'll
definitely enter this once we get in
there we're gonna make a temporary arena
and do a bunch of processing and then
throw that away so what you can see here
is us going ahead and reading all of the
information out of the file just sucking
the whole thing into memory because we
know all our pngs are not so big that I
can't fit in the memory of the machine
certainly so then we run the update
asset manager from P&amp;G and you can see
that right here and that is the part
that we really have to work on we call
out to process child import the reason
for that is we're probably going to want
to expand this very shortly to work on
non tiled imports for title screen stuff
like that we already actually do have
something we can test with that oops
that's wrong directory in our art import
directory we've got this little title
screen here that we can pop up so this
example of just we could put like you
know on the press start page or whatever
that is not tiled so we would like to
have a way of indicating that we're
gonna import a non tiled image that will
not go through this right but here's the
main course of action process tile
import as you can see we go through
process tile import what we do is we
break the file up into those tiles
remember again the tiles is how we've
organized things into sprite sheets what
we want to do is check each tile to see
if there's anything in it because a lot
of them will be blank and what you can
see here is when we when we do the
min/max here for any given tile that's
actually gonna tell us sort of the
bounds of that tile and when we know the
bounds of the tile we can then know
whether there's anything in it because
if we never expand the bounds at all
then we know that there's just nothing
in that tile so coming through here you
can see us doing those those operations
right figuring out whether there's
anything in here once we know that there
is we take a look at it and we say have
we already processed this tile before
like a previous version of the PNG if so
that's our asset index if not we need to
get a new asset index once we come
through and have an asset index we will
then say all right let's reserve some
space to store the new data for this
thing we won't do that if the existing
space for the thing would fit it right
which it which it will in some cases so
let's say we imported PNG and
immediately after we import the same PNG
again that space we use to store it the
first time we can just use the same
space again right then we come through
here and say okay we we now can store it
we just need to update the data and the
asset record to reflect the new size the
new information that
put there and so really again getting
back to what I said the very beginning a
stream the real part that's missing here
because we got some stub functions but
they're gonna be pretty easy to
implement these are not difficult stub
functions to write so the real work
today or probably tomorrow if we flush
this out and test it we probably will
leave this to start on this tomorrow
will be that this will be the hard work
the hard work is gonna be figure out
what to do about the tags because again
the tags are kind of a separate issue
and we really don't know a lot about how
we're gonna do it but what we do know is
that we're probably going to do
something different from what we were
doing before before what we were doing
is sort of storing into the file these
tag sets but really what we've what we
see when we look is that there's sort of
almost two sets two types of tags now
and this sort of starts to get at what I
was saying about how I think we'll gain
some insight here yeah I think we'll be
able to gain some insight into what's
going on what I think we're gonna find
is that really when we look at these
sprite sheets what we'll see is that a
given sprite sheet type like a character
sprite sheet just has the same tags I
mean they all mean the same thing so
rather than having tags for searching
bitmaps probably the bitmaps can just be
in a direct lookup scheme that
corresponds to whether it's a character
an item or a block or something right so
that can just be a hard look up that
doesn't have any tag matching then what
will happen I think a butt like sort of
in the upper in the part right before
that the tag matching will probably be
on what you're matching right so you
know we've got all these different
orphans you know what I mean they could
each be tagged with different tags like
oh this is an orphan that has these
skills or as though it's something that
picking a particular orphan or a
particular monster or particular glove
or a particular hat right those those
choices
are probably the ones that are going to
be more based on tags right and we may
or may not depending on how we go want
them to be fuzzy like they currently are
or maybe they'll just be hard tags I
don't know so we'll see but what it
looks like at least to me is inside a
particular set where you're saying this
is a sprite sheet of type blah they're
all the same each character sprite sheet
has the same meaning here's the left
word use the right word is the
attacker's or whatever right and so that
doesn't it doesn't need arbitrary
tagging and arbitrary tag search anymore
so waste of time and storage and effort
to do that so I feel like that's the
first place we're really gonna be able
to simplify there here's a cat by the
way I would like to get the cat in the
game soon all right so that's where
we're at
let's go ahead and start by implementing
the stub functions we've left for
ourselves so what you can see here is
we're gonna need extra room to store new
assets when we find assets that we don't
actually have storage for yet and so
what I'd like to do there is I'd like to
be able to take and go ahead and show
you what I mean here on this one so what
I want to do is take this array that has
our assets in it and I would like to
make that array expandable and so the
way that I'm gonna make expandable is
just say look there's a maximum ass
asset count right and when we load the
game in a release setting perhaps the
maximum asset count is the same as the
asset count but when you load it in a
debug setting what we'll do is we'll
make the maximum asset count much larger
than the actual asset count which allows
you to grow the asset tree for free
because you won't have to do like a
recopy or anything like that now one
thing I don't know is do me snap a
pointer to this anywhere taking a look
here it appears that we don't really do
that in any real way so what that means
is we should be able to grow this array
as well as long as we always refer to
assets by an integer and never by a
pointer outside of particular situations
we should be ok and so what I'm a
suspecting we could do here is if we
make some kind of a system that would
grow this array in at times when we know
that we've locked everything down and
all the asset processing has stopped or
something like that that would allow us
to do this now that's harder than it
seems because when you have
multi-threaded asset loading you have to
have now some way of locking that down
and preventing like making sure that all
the asset loading has completed expand
the array and then allow the asset
loading to continue right so we need to
have some kind of a semaphore there in
order for that to occur
however I believe could be wrong about
this but I believe we sort of already
have that
I believe we sort of went a little bit
down that road already and if you take a
look at this
what you can see here is that there's
actually a lock around accessing the
assets here and so we already have sort
of a notion that assets can't be
referred to inside or outside of certain
times and so we kind of went a little
bit down this road already so we
probably won't have to completely
rethink the way we're doing things
probably slight modifications would work
but again for the immediate future we
actually don't have to do anything quite
so complicated what we can do instead is
we can just and this would even work
period like we would just do this we
could accept a solution period right
it's not necessary for us to go further
than this so we might not but I'm saying
you could if you wanted to by using some
locking there but what we can do here
when we allocate the game assets is when
we actually produce that asset array
what you can see here is we do a push s
that's here and we do it for asset count
what I'd rather do is say all right
assets max asset count right is going to
be equal to however many assets we think
we want and then what I can do is say
well if we're in developer C here
we go if we're in sort of a developer
build so we've got sort of this hammy
internal handmade slow him with right if
this is an internal build so it's
supposed to allow people to refresh
their assets right
if handmade internal is set then what we
can do is say well okay this is going to
be something that's running on a
developer machine or an enthusiast or
whatever right they're running the
internal build so when we do max asset
count we're going to give ourselves a
Headroom where we're basically saying
okay just allocate a ton of space
additional space or something right I
mean you could go nuts like just a crap
ton of space that'll never hit right you
can update art assets all day long
that'll never hit so what we can do
there just give us ourselves enough
Headroom that our arraign never actually
has to get relocated and then we never
have to really worry about that and
again if it did all that you'd have to
do is close the game and restart it
right because then it would again load
in hover assets you have plus another
65k worth of asset Headroom so again
it's worth noting that sometimes the
simple solution might be better here
because rather than introducing all
kinds of locking schemes and relocating
this array just give yourself enough
space to work with and you're done
right this isn't an end user operation
so it's probably fine all right so if we
do that allocation now we've added a lot
of extra space at the head room for
internal builds what that means is now
if I go oops that's not at all what I
wanted at all I wanted that if we go
here to reserve asset all that's going
to do is it's going to say look we
better have room for this
and we could eventually actually provide
a real error here in fact you know what
I'm gonna go that extra mile why not
let's change reserve asset to something
that says will return true or false
right and I guess maybe I'll just call
this asset index and keep this as result
and what I'll say is okay if the asset
count is is such that I can provide this
then I will provide it otherwise I will
not so what you can see here you know
what I suppose now that I think about it
we actually have a zero here so we
actually don't need to do that I could
do it this way
so that would reserve a new asset and
then what I can do is go down here to
reserve asset where we call it you can
see this is the only place we call it
what I can do here is actually process
the air like handle the error here and
so what I can do is say if we got an
asset index do this otherwise don't so
then we've actually said oh okay like we
we will handle that error and I can put
in here an actual out to the error
processing because you can see here
we've already got error reporting so I
might as well make use of it right I'll
say okay
right so this way if we did set this to
a relatively low number for some reason
which I don't think we should but let's
say we did we would actually still at
least get an error message here and the
person could know that something had
gone wrong and then try again
furthermore we can do here when we do
update asset package from ping another
thing that we can do is since we know
when we have errors we could say that if
there are errors will try the file again
right so for example in here where we
set the file date what we could do is
say well instead of doing that before
maybe we do it after and we only do it
if there were no errors so basically if
the file in question if the file in
question doesn't have any errors on it
when we when we iterate over it then
then we consider it updated if it does
have errors we consider it non updated
so the next time it'll try again right
there's reasons to and not do to do that
let me update that slightly since there
are in since these errors are internal
errors we may just want to detect those
specifically so what we would want to do
here is say that the match that we got
right
you'd probably want to do something like
that
I'm guessing it's hard to say if we had
a lot of these I'm trying to think do we
have any others of these that's really
the only one all right I'm not gonna do
it I'm not gonna do it if we had a lot
of ways we could internal error I might
but we really don't so it's fine
another thing we should do is probably
clear this yeah I'm saying we don't
really have any way to clear a stream
right now and so if we want to reset it
I guess I'll maybe call this reset so
before we process anything we would say
all right
reset reset the error stream here that
seemed reasonable
trying to think of that like that
take it back I don't so I think what I
would rather do is just have a way to
put stuff in there right so what I think
I'd rather do is actually just have the
status be in there so when it goes to
read this thing I think I'd rather just
put in a like a marker and maybe we
would have some way in the future of
being a little bit more specific about
the fact that this was a break you know
something like that so I don't know
exactly how that should go I'm like kind
of vast letting on it but like basically
like we want something that breaks it up
so we could see older errors I'm just
gonna keep them cuz why not so really
when we import I'll just I just want a
thing that shows me where the last you
know the most recent import began so I
know what I know when we you know sort
of had previous ones and I won't think
that those errors are part of the
current import so I don't know something
like that I haven't really decided how I
want to do that I feel also haven't
decided whether I wanted to / this this
memory this Airstream I don't still
don't know whether I maybe want it just
one error stream that's for the whole
system so all of that's a little bit up
in the air right now but that's the
current situation all right so what's
the problem
ah so okay anyway moving on this like I
said is a pretty simple function to
implement so it has been these are
slightly more complicated the reserved
data part I'm gonna skip that one
because that's the one that's a that's a
little bit Squinkie we'll look at that
in a second
but for right asset data and right asset
these are not probably very complicated
by comparison the the main problem that
we're going to find is that we have to
worry about the headers and where those
headers are so again we may have to
reorganize our files a little bit or
allow sort of a slightly different file
format or something like this okay so as
far as writing asset data is concerned
this is pretty straightforward because
we already know where we're gonna write
the data so the complexity is gonna come
in here where we have to actually figure
out where the data for this asset should
go so write an asset data itself is
really just going to be as simple as
using the file handle that we already
have in you know stored in our there we
go that we already have stored in our
asset file structure so this platform
file handle here all we really need to
do is take that asset file platform
handle there and when we do are our
right it's not called write files it's
called
there it goes
oh we don't have one we do now
so really all we're gonna do here is
just call whatever the right function is
and that function is gonna be an exact
mirror of the read function so it's just
gonna take where you wanted to put it
how big it was and what it was and
literally that's like all we're gonna do
right we we don't have anything else we
need to do there that's it's that simple
and the same is more or less true for
right asset but like I said because the
assets have to get expanded this is
going to be a little bit trickier for
what we're doing the reason so a little
bit trickier is because the like if you
take a look at how we've got these
things stored in file formats so you can
see here the way that we've got our
stuff stored is that we have an offset
to an assets array and we've got an
asset type and tags these two things
here you can see what those actually are
so the asset type count
let's go scroll through these things
here here it is so you can see sort of
the way these things work and to a
certain extent
again I think reorganizing these files
is going to make a lot of sense for us
right because we can do a lot better
than what we did here now that we know
what we're sort of storing but the HHA
asset type itself this part here is what
will cause us the problems so assets we
can already just locate at the end of
the file and grow so we can put more
assets on there and that's no big deal
but the asset types we will have a
problem organizing the assets inside
that asks irate if they have to be
contiguous all of the assets of a
particular type have to be written out
contiguously for the asset type thing to
work right so there's a lot of different
ways we could attack this problem and
I'm not sure exactly which way we want
to do it and so we'll kind of go through
it slowly but regardless of what we
choose what we're going to have to be
able to determine is when we want to
update the information about an asset in
a file we're going to have to figure out
which file that asset is in right and so
what we did conveniently is inside the
asset system itself when we're actually
talking about a particular asset where
is it here right when we're actually
talking about asset we remembered what
filed that asset was in right we know
that piece of information and
furthermore we're going to store the
asset index in the file as a separate
piece of information which again is sort
of it's because we have this need to
relocate where in the file it actually
was right now we're actually not
tracking that we should probably put
that in before we forget I guess so you
can see it happening here
so if we wanted to keep this piece of
information we definitely could what's
going to happen here is the file index
that we're dealing with here
right is coming in because we're looping
over the files individually when we are
looking at which asset index this is
globally speaking it's going to be it's
going to be this asset count here - the
base asset count a basic - the base
access index for this file so you can
see here where you know we're loading a
particular file when we start here we
sort of need to understand what asset
we're on separate from the global asset
index right and yeah I mean I don't know
how we want to store that exactly the
easiest way is probably just to go like
this right so then in here we can just
say
like that so we can pretty easily keep
track of which asset index this was in a
particular file but again that's not
really probably how we want to store
these now that they're being updated so
I'm guessing that this table will
actually will change the way that we're
storing it right
we won't store it the way that it's
being stored at the moment okay sue yep
we've got a lot of different ways we can
do this so here's another proposal right
asset data again I think and reserve
data are pretty straightforward because
I think they can just tack on to the end
of any particular file it doesn't really
matter so I'm not too worried about this
function we'll talk about that a second
so it's really just this function that's
the problem and the reason that's that
this function is the problem is because
we have this situation where again the
the weight the ways in which we might
want to store that permanent storage for
looking at Bassets and stuff it just
isn't conducive to insertion it would
require us to rewrite a bunch of stuff
there are two ways we can go about
solving this problem and I'm probably
going to choose the following one
because I think it's just easier
we know that asset importing doesn't
happen very frequently right meaning it
happens every time an artist changes a
bitmap file but that's it
so what we could elect to do is change
the way that we're currently thinking
about our asset files so take a look at
what we do right now if we look we've
got three HHA files right and those get
loaded
oh and test fonts I think gets loaded
too right okay so we've actually got
like three we got five different HHA
files get loaded right each of those
files
contains bitmap and sound data and also
then contains the structure information
necessary to reference those bitmaps
sound data right what we could do is
change the meaning or change the way
that those hhas work such that we have
the ability to reference data in other
files from a given file what that would
allow us to do is just rewrite the
complete asset header every time right
I again I'm not sure that that's the
best option
let us definitely an option another way
we could do it is just to make it so
that we rewrite the header every time
for the current four like we take one
file and we say okay here's the file
that you're editing and whatever file
you're editing that's the one that gets
rewritten but it gets its header
rewritten every time in which case this
would not actually be the function the
function would be like that that seems
pretty reasonable I would say
sooo my guess here's what I'll say I
think that I think I like that the best
so here's what I'm gonna propose I would
approach we don't actually modify
anything we just leave exactly it is
what we do is well like I said I still
might want to modify the way the tags
work so that but that's separate
discussion doesn't involve this what I'm
gonna do is I'm just gonna rewrite the
entire header so every time we rewrite a
file we just rewrite the header of the
file and and off we go
the thing that I don't super love is I
feel like maybe there's one thing that
we should change because doesn't make a
lot of sense and we don't really need it
to be this way since we load the whole
asset array every time it seems like it
would make more sense rather than having
the asset types range stuff in here to
just have it so that every asset itself
stores which type it is just seems
smarter because we we loop through them
when we do the merge it made sense when
we didn't do a merge now we do emerge it
just seems like that smarter right
because if you're gonna do a merge
anyway you might as well just store that
information directly right
yeah so I think that's the one change
that I would propose now there's a
couple of different ways we could do
that we can actually do that without
changing this file format really if we
wanted to by just making the asset types
array have as many entries in it as the
assets itself let me take a look at how
our merge works at the moment
yeah I mean that just seems a lot saner
to me I think that makes a lot more
sense
so I'm gonna propose that we make that
change let me do a little let me just do
a little bit of fancy footwork here and
then we'll go do that so I think we can
do that without much effort actually all
right so let me go ahead and and change
the the platform right datafile part
here because we didn't have one of those
so here's read data from file here's
right did if to file and again it's like
exactly the same write read and write is
basically identical sometimes you
implement these by just having a flag
which says which one you're doing in
this case we'll just have another call
back into the platform layer but that's
the idea in the win32 side again it's
gonna be frightening simple so read data
from file if you take a look at that
function it looks like we support 64-bit
reads so yeah so here's a 64 oops a bit
right data I guess as well we could do
the same thing and again what you can
see here is it's really just we would if
we just call write file instead of read
file it should be basically the same
right it should be basically the same so
this is just by its written now instead
of bytes read and instead of us dest we
have a source but other than that it'll
be exactly the same that's really all
there is to it there we go
why that's called source should be
called handle okay
platform right data to file correct oops
no wait there we go
and in the win32 layer this should be
handle here
[Music]
that looks better okay
not sure why
oh because this is right data that
should do it so now we have a platform
right it's exactly the same as the read
so no real big difference there we let's
see cannot convert that from file handle
so I guess we just need the address of
it better than that we're fine yeah so
writing asset data is pretty
straightforward now reserving asset data
will also be pretty straightforward and
rewriting the header should be pretty
straightforward too so a lot of this
stuff is now going to be a lot simpler
but right asset is now no longer what
would happen in fact we now no longer
have to do that at the end of each thing
instead of what we're going to do is
after the entire thing happened it's
it's right here right so after
everything happens then what we're gonna
want to do is only right here actually
do the the right of the file so right in
here we need a you know right HHA header
or rewrite right so we're gonna have to
work on that in a second but that's
basically all I think we would need to
do assuming that we make a little bit of
a change to how we're conceptualizing
and this goes away now how we're
conceptualizing that asset import so
what I want to do from the moment
[Music]
well I'll comment this out I want to run
the game and make sure it's fine and
then what I want to do is make a slight
change to how we're storing those pieces
of information and I'll do it in a way
that still reads the old files because
it's I don't think it's very hard for
that's good I was working on some old
witness walk map stuff I don't think we
want to run that or maybe we do that's
probably something we could run I guess
spoiler warning I'm going to be giving a
talk on
the witnesses walk manifold stuff that I
did and so I wanted to also make some
changes that I never got a chance to
make during the actual development so I
I was playing around with it again
so anyway what I want to do is make sure
I can reload the I want to make sure I
can reload the game and have all the HHA
still work and so what I want to do here
is look at that file format oops what I
want to do here is look at the file
format and see how I can send it to do
the thing that I wanted it to do so
right now the problem that I have with
the file format right is that this stuff
is it's it's very confusing right to see
how the asset types and the assets are
lined up right you have to read the
asset array then read the asset types
array and use the contiguous regions of
assets to to get their types what I
would rather be able to do is just have
every asset have its type included in it
right now that is not necessarily
directly possible without changing the
file format a little bit because the
assets currently don't store a type in
that way so if you take a look at what
an HHH s HH a asset has in it it doesn't
have a type so it may seem like there
isn't room to put that in there and we'd
have to expand the data set for the file
format right but I would argue what we
don't really have to do that because
what we can do instead is have this
asset types array here we can just
change the meaning of the asset types
array to actually have the same number
as assets and tell us what the type of
each asset is right
that just works so what we can do
although it's a little bit piggy is we
can actually just output this array in a
different way
in fact I guess we can just I mean
correct me if I'm wrong but we can
literally just output one of these for
every asset that just has first asset
index the asset index one past last that
index the first s is plus one with the
type so we can then optimize an HHA
header for loading by sorting all the
assets by their type ID but we don't
have to so now that I think about it we
actually don't have to do anything I
think that just works so let's take a
look in memory here I think this is
actually just gonna just work in memory
we don't do that anymore do we we do so
we do here right so really the only
thing is gonna have to happen it changes
this part here because this part won't
quite work anymore because the assets
won't be compact in that way so let's
just take a look at that part I think
that's really all we're gonna have to
modify so when you when we do get get
best match asset from you can see what
it does is it's gonna look through the
asset types here I mean we could just
make that a chain right we could just
make that in a linked list or something
and we'd be done you know
and and that's exactly the part that
we're gonna want to upgrade with the
tags with the matching anyway
so it's like I feel like this part is
something that I don't really care about
right now it's gonna modify it anyway
but let's just say for sake of argument
that I changed it to something like this
just to maintain the current way that
things are working now in here what I
would do is say oh yeah you don't do
that right instead what you do is you
just kind of like loop over these things
and I was acid index work here yeah so
so all I really need to do is is chain
these assets together and of course I
would need to know as well for each
individual asset I need to know yeah
kind of like how what its asset index
was globally so you know this gets a
little piggy er here if I actually want
to keep that piece of information
so I think
I think what I may do is just do that
when we do asset types here I will say
okay the asset index is just assets
first asset of whatever oops
whatever the type is that you asked for
I could actually do this as well you
know what that's what I'll do
makes it even easier so for right now
what I'll say is all right so we've got
an asset index that asset index is going
to be the first asset for that type ID
right and it comes back and then when I
as I move through there and and this is
gonna have to be written sort of
slightly differently right it's going to
have to be written I guess like this
so what I'll do is I'll just say all
right we're gonna we'll chain through
these and look for assets of this
particular type as we walk through them
we'll do the standard tag match we're
doing before work and this whole routine
will probably just change but I just
want to maintain the current behavior
for now so we'll go through those and we
can look through them as a list so they
don't have to be contiguous anymore
inside the asset array which allows us
to update assets in a non contiguous
fashion and I think that's probably
sufficient so then instead of having to
build these arrays which you know what
are we talking about here what did I I
didn't yeah there we go change that to
that now what I'm going to do is say
okay let's yeah so this one's a little
bit harder because this this one for
doing random assets it still has to do a
walk through again not really the end of
the world do we use this
I'm just curious we do not
I'm a nerf that for now this one's
pretty straightforward because this one
is already it's already set up to do
that so this will just give us the
answer we want directly and so all we
really need to do now is this right so
we need to chain these things together
in some way so what we want to do is
when we get one of these asset types out
here what I want to do is just use this
as a chain so let me go ahead and look
at how this is currently happening
so basically we're loading all these
right and we yeah so every time we as we
load these in really all we're doing
here is as we load in all the assets we
just were putting them contiguous we no
longer have to do that so actually this
is not necessary to do this way anymore
really if we don't want to we can just
do that up here actually and so they're
really the only thing that we yeah like
this this actually storing them that way
would simplify this as well so like here
where we do where we loop through the
files
[Music]
we we could just do it right inside
inside that right we we don't need to do
this part again so we could really
simplify this loader as well I think
quite a bit if we wanted to a lot of
things we could improve here anyway so
going over the files this way which is
again dumb the only reason this is
structured this way is because we want
those we were trying to keep ranges
contiguous that's the only point to this
at all
otherwise you can flip these two right
and go by file in fact I'm just I'm just
gonna start let's go start so start
doing it so if we go through each file
here and then ignore this bit entirely
like so if we loop over the files and
then for each file we loop over the
source asset types and just get rid of
this interior match right this was an N
squared loop essentially that was doing
into an interior match just forget that
and instead now we can actually make
this routine more efficient because you
know because we're not creating packed
arrays which were more efficient to look
up in so you know it's it's a trade-off
but once you make that other trade-off
it's now free in here to just go through
the source asset types and now just
thread them directly so when we come
through here we don't need to track a
lot of the old stuff that we were
tracking before it's simply not
necessary anymore for that yeah I mean
off you go
so when we come through here we read out
the source index stuff here we go ahead
and produce the asset cap type we load
the array of assets we then loop through
each individual assets and we put the
tags in and so all we would have to do
here is when we produce the global asset
index we just need to thread it now so
if you look at the first asset of type
bit all we have to do is say ok the
asset it's next of type is going to be
whatever the first asset of type was for
that asset type which is whatever we
whatever it said it was up here right so
whatever it said that's what we grab and
then we set that one equal to us so
standard singly linked list right so now
we just have list an asset list that
allows us to sort of say ok that's you
know
that's the asset GI probably because
it's boiling hot and allergy season here
it's very although I shouldn't say
boiling hot because it's it's actually
not compared to other parts of the
country CL is actually apparently fairly
cool by comparison at least that's what
I'm told so now when we load those
things we have a different method of
storing them but what that means is now
they can be interleaved in any way we
want and they don't have to be
contiguous in the file and you're gonna
have different ones in the file if you
want to you and bla bla bla bla bla
right
the only thing that we do have to do is
make sure that our first are this thing
has to be zeroed right so the question
is is it zeroed and really that just
boils down to when we push bootstrap
this guy is it getting cleared or not
and I think it is right you can see in
the source file hash here we never clear
the source file hash so we're just
counting on that to be zeroed anyway so
the question is did I mess anything up
there probably the answer is yes and we
can see all right shockingly the answer
was no you know what are the odds still
everything works just fine um so anyway
that's all good everyone's fine with
that and everything's happy and bouncing
around and Joyland so once that's the
case now we have the ability to rewrite
our HHA file anytime we want and we can
interleave the asset types any way we
want as well it's not efficient anymore
it would be better if we just included
them in each individual asset so that's
a little unfortunate and it's something
we probably should fix in the file
format eventually I'll make a note of it
but we don't really have to fix it right
now so we can maybe look towards an
optimization pass some time in the
future to play with that and there's not
a lot of reason to fix it at this time
sooo getting rid of the asset type sorry
eventually and just storing that data
directly in the assets would definitely
be an improvement so we also have
another kind of a little bit confusing
situation here but it's not really that
bad the thing that we have that's a
little bit annoying is we don't really
have a way of saying what's primal for a
particular asset we just have matching
tags eventually we probably have to have
a thing which goes and zeros out some of
the asset stuff in other hhj files as we
replace them I don't know how much we
care about that exactly but you know
it's worth noting so anyway that's the
only change I think we have to make so
now what we need to do is we need to
make a way to actually store this stuff
out and so what I want to do here is
again I'm gonna I'm gonna sort of change
a little bit how this is working for the
asset index and file file and next stuff
here right so for a file index I'm just
gonna now say that that we're gonna
require for a given asset file we're
gonna require that it's it's marked as
editable I think that's just I think
that's probably the right thing to do
like
I'm torn I don't really know like which
one we should do but I feel like we want
to kind of say that there's one asset
file that's editable and the rest aren't
so like you're editing a particular file
and like it won't go like changing the
contents of other hhas it'll only append
to that one that you said you were
editing that to me kind of sounds like
the right thing to do I don't have a lot
of explanation that I just it feels a
little weird if the the reason that I'm
just not sure what else to do about that
is because when someone goes to create
or do an import right there's no way for
the game to know which HHA file you want
to put that in right there it's just a
PNG that it's importing the game doesn't
know where you might want that so it's
gonna have to pick something if we don't
make there just be a rule that when you
start up you basically say here's an
editable HHA file that you then specify
like hey anything I import during this
process put it in this HHA file or
whatever if we don't have that concept
then we're sort of in a situation where
we can't where it's just always
ambiguous like it's it's never gonna
know what HHA file you were actually
trying to edit and it doesn't have any
way to know what to put in it cuz like
if you have five HS any files in on the
drive it could put it in any of them
write it there's no right or wrong
answer to what HHA file to put a new
import in that it's never seen before
right so I think we probably want to say
that there is some kind of a pointer
here that's like hey you know or an
index
like that and so when you reserved space
you're reserving space in that specific
file and if that's not set to something
valid then it just doesn't allow you to
edit it's just an error right I think
that's what I want to do I don't know I
think that's the right I think that's
the right solution so that's what I'm
gonna say I'm gonna say there's an
editing HHA concept here if if we go
into the actual game layer here you can
see we set the file count like so right
I one of the things that we typically
have done is you know we set the file
indexes such that file index zero is is
a null file right that's what we didn't
do that here but that's like we did that
for assets for example you notice the
asset count precedes to one so I kind of
feel like maybe we do that with the
files as well just leave a null file in
there that way you can say stuff about
the file index being set to nothing for
example I feel like that's a good idea
so you know if I did that something like
this I feel like that's probably a good
idea and later when we loop through
these things I could just say look you
start with file index one it's also true
that now we can merge this stuff so you
know there's really no reason that we
can't just do the tag read here
right and that doesn't have to happen
anymore
seems reasonable okay so moving on so
this editing HHA index right that's
going to be set to 0 by default and that
means that there is no HHA available for
editing so if I were to run here oops
this shouldn't be that it should be this
yeah and so I think that's right now
just off there's the yeah the file
counter is only for us not for the
platform where anymore
all right so what I want to do now is
just say all right we have the concept
that there's a HHA that we're using for
editing and that's you know a special
case and what I want to do is make it so
that now this routine is always where it
like that's always where that goes so
for example when we do check for our
changes if if we're going to go through
this process here then what I want to do
is make sure that we don't actually ever
entertain that notion if we're not in a
mode where we can actually edit
something right so what I want to do
here is say yeah don't even start this
process if you can't possibly finish it
right so I call that again editing HHA
so like if there isn't an HHA that were
actually actively editing at this time
then that's like just that's just a
straight-up error right that's like not
something that we want to allow we could
print out a message here eventually I
don't know how we're gonna do that
exactly but something like that so there
has to be one of these once we know
there's one of those we go through it
then at the end we'll rewrite it so here
now what we would say is if we made
changes rewrite HHA directory or
whatever right and rewriting the HSV
directory we know the one in question is
the HHA index and off we go I could I
guess also do it this way
oops like so where that HHA will now get
rewritten seems reasonable yeah so
that's the function that we're gonna
have to write and it's relatively
complex so that that one will be a
little bit of work right but we already
did one of them inside the simple asset
processor so we can probably just import
the code from that and it shouldn't be
too big of a stretch right hopefully
this so we have to be able to rewrite
that directory so the two functions that
we're now missing are these two
unfortunately for us they're not
particularly complicated when we do a
reserve asset now and we we get sort of
a new asset out of the file we want to
clear that asset if it's not already
cleared and set it to stuff right which
we're gonna do up here we need to set
the file equal to whatever the editing
file is right so when we come through
here and we say you know here's the
asset in question we need to set which
file that is when we reserve the file so
you know in here we say like okay
whatever the file index is we probably
just want to remap it like we want to
move it to a different file at that
point the file that's being edited if
we're changing this asset and I'm not
sure yeah again like I said I'm not sure
if we want to allow editing of assets in
in a different file than the one that we
have open for editing
[Music]
I mean probably we don't write like
probably we want to do a thing here
where we would say look if this asset
isn't in the file that you said you
wanted to edit then we're not gonna let
you edit it right
so as I push down a little further I
don't like that I'll be honest so maybe
maybe what I said before just isn't the
right thing maybe we want you to have as
many files for editing as you want so
maybe this is really not editing HHA
index it's really just like you have to
say which file new stuff goes into but
if you want to you can still edit old
files like that so it's like alright if
we know where this asset goes we'll put
it in that file if we don't know where
it goes it goes in this default ahoj
right or something it sounds a little
janky to me but like I said I don't know
what to do about it because maybe you
have I mean like just thinking it
through to its logical conclusion
supposin and artist is working on
updating some files there's like two
hhas one for like something and one for
an expansion and they just want to edit
the art for both at the same time I mean
there's no reason they can't
so like why force them this close and
restart the game just to switch which
one they're editing like why not let
them edit both at the same time right so
I don't know seems plausible
so in here where we do the reserve asset
when we assign a new asset then what
we'd say is like okay that asset goes in
the default appending file right so it
just says also this is no law no longer
a thing I guess
so we can just say if asset
acet I'm sorry file index equals zero
asset file and x equals assets default
append hh-hey index and then off we go
so then we have the asset files here
which will now grab one of those files
out here we could assert that this is
nonzero we may have to reserve data in
this particular asset file for the asset
to save if we need to that's all fine so
I think that's all pretty reasonable so
then what we need to do in the side of
the asset file here is we also need some
way of remembering what the high-water
mark was of this particular file that
we're editing so we would need here like
a u 64 that's like file size right but
once we have that then we're pretty much
done with that part of the process and
the way that we're gonna do this is
gonna be pretty interesting so so bear
with me here this is sort of a compact
file I don't to call a trick just
something that we can use to make our
lives easier
let's say
oops
so what do we have right now what's the
problem that we have right now well
we've got an array of asset information
and you know it kind of looks like this
right it's got like yours asset 0 &amp; 1 &amp;
2 &amp; 3 well we don't actually talk about
them that way we talk about with other
numbers but you get the idea there's
assets in here
right then we also have another thing
which is just like arbitrarily sized
data that's like bitmaps for these
assets or whatever right or sound data
or whatever it is and these assets
storing them an offset that says like
where that stuff is oops but we have a
problem these two things appear
sequentially in a file right so let's
say we stack them together then what
happens is only one of them can grow
right let's say we put the assets first
and the bitmaps second well that's all
fine and dandy because now when we get a
new bitmap in we can just stick it on
the end and that works great and if it
happens to refer to an existing asset
that's just fine because we can just use
the offset in here to point to it right
but the problem is what happens if we
need to add a new asset record it's
gonna overwrite some of our bitmap data
and that's no good right same token if
we put the bitmaps first and then we've
got the assets array afterwards well now
we have the opposite problem it's free
to add assets on and as long as they
refer to existing bitmap data we're fine
but as soon as we need to add new bitmap
data we would overwrite some of our
asset data so what do we do right are we
just are we screwed the answer is to
understand the relative size between
these two things right this is huge this
is tiny how many assets might we have in
this game 5,000
10,000 how many is Ana realistically
going to be able to draw it's not going
to be a hundred thousand she would her
arm would fall off right so if you think
about the size of these things let's
just do a simple back of the envelope
computation let's say she draws ten
thousand assets and let's say that each
asset is actually like you know 256
bytes or something like this right
that's two and a half megabytes of data
a modern harddrive writes two and a half
megabytes of data before you can even
say the words two and a half megabytes
of data bitmaps on the other hand are
1024 by 1024 by four for one of them one
of them that's four megabytes large if
we don't compress them we might but the
starting that's the worst case right if
you got no compression on them that's
what you'd get so even just getting you
then they'll never be 286 bytes no
matter how well we can press them right
best-case scenario we get like eight to
one sixteen to one or something on them
let's say they're all super cartoony and
hardly any shading we get sixty to one
right even sixty to one compression it's
nowhere near the size of one of these
even if each one of these was a full K
long it's still nowhere near it right
it's a full 64 K just for one compressed
bitmap if we were very lucky right so
what that means is we can't assume that
this is massive this is tiny if it's
tiny what does that mean it's free to
rewrite it right it's free ready to
point five megabytes used to be a big
deal it's nothing now an artist machine
can rewrite 2.5 megabytes before
Photoshop can even select the lasso tool
not counting if you accidentally heaven
offend accidentally hit the open in
bridge button at which point you could
rewrite all of the world's knowledge
many times over to optical media and you
would be done before Photoshop could
even open
if dialog box right so writing that two
point five megabytes ten megabytes
however much it is is basically free so
what do we do we treat that as a sort of
a rewritable section that we just move
to the bottom of the file every time so
every time we import right what we
actually do is we've got a file that
looks like this assets at the end
bitmaps at the beginning right we
overwrite the asset array with new
bitmap data it's gone now then we
rewrite the asset array on to the end
easy peasy right so what that means is
that actually what we do here and I know
it's a little weird is we don't really
store the file side so I need to talk
about now cuz I need to start explaining
what this actually is right we need to
call this the high watermark basically
right and what that is is it's saying
look there is other stuff in this file
like the asset array but we already read
it into memory like we've got it so now
what we're gonna do is if we need to add
to this file we're gonna obliterate that
part of the file we're gonna overwrite
it with bitmap data and then we're gonna
slap onto the end a new version of the
stuff we just obliterated because hey by
the way it's different now anyway make
sense so this is a pretty simple way to
split up your files and not really have
to worry about that fact another way you
could do it is split them into two
different files but we don't really have
the need to do that right this keeps
them more concise
and it's pretty much free to do like I
said the size of those additional pieces
of array information are just so small
that it really doesn't matter so so all
we have to do here is go ahead there's a
header in the file it's got an offset to
the assets and the asset types we will
just relocate those to the end of the
file every time and rewrite the header
and we're done right so once we
understand that fact what we have to do
is do a little bit of work to determine
where that high-water mark actually is
and so for the moment we will sort of
have a little bit of jenkin assign the
file system to do this because we didn't
think we were ever going to actually
allow rewritable files so the as a
result we don't have a high watermark
stored in the file which is what we
would have wanted so we would have
wanted to write that in here so
determining the high watermark is
actually a little bit of a dance that we
would have to do to determine whether or
not the asset array actually appears at
the end or not if it does we can use it
if it doesn't we can't it's no big deal
either way but that's the that's the
current setup right so that's what we'll
do and we'll go from there I so yeah
it's like I said pretty straightforward
but that's just the understanding that
you have to have going into it all right
so to start with we can make this easy
and we can just like lose space in our
asset files that we don't really we
shouldn't really lose but we can by just
always setting the high-water mark to
the actual file size but then what we
can do is we can do better than that
later on by setting the Hutt's by
setting the high-water mark to actually
be our our file size - any arrays that
we did that we're going to rewrite that
we detect a beat
at the end so coming through here what
we want to do is when we load in these
files so right about here where we start
to load in these files what we want to
do is let's remember like you can see we
open the file here right and we read
some data out of it that's the header
right what we want to do here is store
the header so that we always know what
the header header is thankfully we did
exactly that right can we get that
information then what we want to do is
store what the what the platform tells
us the size of that file is so we want
to be able to set the high-water mark
here like so and the file info structure
can tell us that so remember in the file
and stress info structure here we've got
this file size that tells us how big
that thing is so we can just set the
high-water mark to that and know we can
always write past it but we can do a
little bit better we can say if at end
of file something like this if a
particular array is at the end of the
file then we can just back up here right
here so we've got three arrays tags
asset types and assets right and we can
rewrite them all if we want to so what
we want to do is say all right if the
file header tags array
which by the way is this long right if
that's at the end of the file then we
want to back up by that amount and so
I'm in make sort of a thing here that's
like back up watermark or you know
retract watermark something like that
and say look take this this is the file
the high watermark is at the end of the
file by default
for each array in the file just look to
see if it's actually at the end right if
it is at the end back it up this may
look weird
but I'm gonna loop on that and what I'm
gonna do is say look why did that not
line up do I have like one too many of
those or something there we go I must
have had one too many of those
I'm gonna say alright if we have done
any of those I actually want the inverse
of it so I really want to say if none of
these retracted then we're done right
another wait I guess I could just say
it's like wile any of these is true
that's probably a better way to put it
do nothing right so basically what this
will say is look see if any of the three
of those at the end of the file if any
of three of those at the end the file
back the high-water mark up then do it
again right that way we don't have to
care which order the author of this HHA
put those in we can back up the
watermark by checking them basically
nine times right check each three three
times to see if we back up right yeah
that's that's it
so all I have to do is just write
something that does that check so the
internal retracted watermark function
there's a count there's an offset and
they're the size like so and all we're
going to do is say all right if the
offset equals the watermark - the count
times the size right and by the way I
guess we can allow this to be full
64-bit math if we want to right so if
the offset that you're telling me that
this array had was actually where it
would be if we started at the end of the
file backed up by the size of the array
then that means this is at the end of
the file so
then we can do is say all right the
high-water mark is now back that amount
right or rather I guess we get to say
equals the offset so now where that
array starts it's actually our new
high-water mark because we don't
carefully obliterate it right and then
all we have to do is just remember
whether or not we did that and tell the
outside code right
so that'll now find the high-water mark
even if the file was written without an
understanding of that this better be
yeah so now we have to do now that we
actually know the high-water mark is
actually implement these two functions
in terms of that information right
we know the high-water mark in any file
so now in order to reserve data in the
file oh there's one of the thing we have
to do actually uh yeah pretend I didn't
say that I'll do it now so what we
actually need to do here is we need to
go through all the files that are in the
asset system actually so we you know we
really want to actually do this kind of
a loop here right we want to go through
each one of these and say look if if the
file is modified rewrite the directory
right so this made changes thing
actually does not need to be here
it really actually wants to be up here
so when we reserved data on an asset or
change the data that we wrote out to an
asset when we do any of those operations
we now want the file so this stuff here
right we want this stuff to be noting
that fact so asset file made changes or
modified is going to be true if either
of these two things happen right and
then here we can set it to false in fact
this is where we should set it to false
shouldn't be set to false here right
like that
yeah uh so that's more like it
[Music]
almost I've time
that's a little more like it I don't
know why I call that asset file there's
really no reason for that okay so now
when we do reserve data we can actually
do this much more we can actually
implement all this stuff pretty
straightforward now right down to the
right modification agents say this this
will take a little more work because we
have to actually rewrite those arrays
but for the most part it's like I said
pretty straightforward so this function
now becomes trivial all we're gonna do
is say look whatever the high-water mark
is we just need to that much more data
right so the result is just whatever the
high-water mark is that's where we're
gonna write to you know and then we just
advanced the high-water mark by that
amount right really really
straightforward then we want to do right
modifications to HHA all we have to do
is rewrite the header right and then
rewrite those arrays whichever ones we
want like the tiger a tiger a acid type
array and the and the assets array
itself so that's really it
yeah I mean I think that that's all
there really is to it you know the the
write this function is going to be a
little annoying to write it's but it's
it's still just busy work there's not
much to it you know you can imagine it's
just gonna take it's really just gonna
be a thing that sums these up and then
writes them out that's that's it
I mean there's not going to be anything
magical to it that's if we rewrite the
tag array which I don't really that's
the part that's gonna be changed and not
really sure how that's gonna look but
you know it's pretty straightforward
either way so we'll sum up those and
then we just need to take the h @j
header right
and I guess weakened really just
modified in place the magic value the
version the tag count I said the magic
value in the version should be the same
the tag count will become the tag count
the asset type count will become the
asset count because that's the way we're
going to write those out now the asset
count will also be the asset count these
offsets will be fairly straightforward
they're just like the high-water mark
with offsets applied right so this is
and this is
so really really simple right and we
know what those sizes are we know that
like the tag array size is just the tag
count times the size of an HHI tag
struct and we know that the asset types
array size is just the asset count times
the size of HHA asset type and we know
also what the assets array size is
because that's just the asset count
times the size of the assets we don't
use that yet but you know we will so
once we have that information we can
just allocate space for those and then
flat write them which are probably more
efficient than issuing lots of little
platform reads so what I might say is
like pass us the temporary nough and
let's go ahead and push arrays on there
for each of these so then we would have
you know a tags assets write each of
these and again it's fairly
straightforward so we've got the tag
count worth of those we've got the asset
count worth of these two right eye and
those just go into the temporary now we
then loop so this two loops are the
assets one to count everything and then
another one here to actually fill them
out and then we just write everything
back to the file right that's
very very simple we know what we need to
write so we just say look here's the
handle we need the offset the size and E
and the information we have all of that
so we just say the offset is whichever
array this is so well we want the header
as well right so we'd say write the
header out then write those arrays and
that'd be it
Tiger a size asset type size type arrays
size and asset race size and each of
these is just the temporary buffer we
use to create it right so that's really
all we need to do there so really all we
need to do is implement these two
functions that gather which ones are
relevant to this file because the assets
are kind of scattered we don't have them
stored per file in any particular layer
there like a global list
well global array so we need to actually
have some method here of Lupi through
them right and what we're gonna do is
we're just gonna look at each individual
asset and see which file index it is if
it's the file index that we're writing
then off we go and I guess that behooves
us to can write it like this
because that way we can check that
without having to do a subtraction to
figure out which file index it is so
again pretty straightforward here it's
just like how many assets are there
so those that would give us a loop over
all of the assets and then what we can
do tomorrow is just do that gather right
that's supposed to be an S these are
supposed to be dots so are these so
syntax errors everywhere what is the
problem oh yeah there is that
well that's not actually that's gonna go
anyway um yeah
[Music]
asset type array size asset types and
this is a sets three don't ask me why I
named it that probably should change
that all right
and this can probably just go like that
and off we go so I think that's
everything
and that sets us up tomorrow to actually
finish and start working on the tags
problem so that won't be fun because we
don't really know what we want to do
there exactly but I'll go ahead and Q&amp;A
now here we are we've been making an
editor for the engine know that it is
generated
it's a procedurally generated game so
there isn't an editor in that sense
today I mean to put word mark know I
didn't is that what I typed
Thanks
I did I did not although some people do
pronounce it warder like I want to get a
drink of water would err
my name is I may have missed this but
where are you handling the growth of an
existing asset presumably you'd still
need to mem copy a huge portion of the
bitmaps to insert new data or move from
the middle no you don't really need to
because again one of the things to
remember is that you don't actually care
during development whether you have
extra bitmaps sitting around in the file
right so let's suppose that a previous
time the bitmap was 64 by 64 or
something right and the new ones like
1024 by 1024 or something right just
rewrite the new one to the end of the
array if it's bigger just write a new
one and leave the old one lying around
right when you then at the end at the
very end when you go to ship the game
you can build a pristine one that only
has the exact ones you need in there but
you don't have to keep other development
there's no reason why during development
you can't just have old old bitmaps
lying around the file that just aren't
referenced right
cynic khalipa I probably missed this but
why do you want to continuously pack the
bitmaps and the header so basically what
we want to do is we want to have control
over our distribution file format and so
this gets into a bit of a philosophical
situation that probably isn't that bad
on something like handmade hero but it
gets bad as you get bigger
I don't like load times load times are
really bad and they're actually just
still really bad even today and so I
don't want to iterate over all of like
the PNG source files every time you
start up the game
like that's just inefficient and I want
the game to start up immediately and the
only way to really do that is to have at
least the metadata sitting around
telling you where all the information is
that you might need to grab you know
having an ability to directly grab it so
in order to do that you need to unpack
sprite sheets into individual tiles and
build a metadata set that can access
those tiles quickly so that is the part
that I want to always be true about the
game whenever it's running not just a
shipping version but at all times I
don't really care if they're packed like
if you wanted to do a separate kind of
system that just views files everywhere
but it actually still built that
information correctly so that it was
fast and has no load time that's
actually fine I don't mind right I just
figured why not pack them into a single
file it's just easier and then I don't
have a billion file sing around on my
drive you know
his asset file actually a file yes it is
it is not something we just store in
memory so basically an asset file is
well okay it rep it is remembering the
fact that there is a file it itself is
not stored in the file if that's what
you mean I'm not sure which mean but
like for example when you load the game
what happens is handmade hero loads all
of the HHA files that it finds so
currently it loads these five for each
one of these it will create an asset
file so it remembers the oh and it has
an open handle to it so whenever you
need a resource it can just fire off the
load immediately and grab it from there
thanks separate question again from much
earlier stuff I may have missed what is
the likelihood of a hash collision with
the asset source names and how do you
handle that well we don't use hash
disambiguation the hash is just a way to
speed up the lookup so it's not an issue
would be the way to say it we do a full
string compare right I mean is this what
you're talking about so hash collisions
are not really relevant to us so we
wouldn't keeping different files for
different assets and keeping another
file just for the index be better for
source control so it depends what you
check in to source control I guess is be
the way to say it for our purposes we
can't check in any access to source
control so it doesn't matter
github can't handle the size of the
files that we would put in there they
don't let you have you know ten
gigabytes of assets on the bait on the
kind of repositories we have I don't
know if they let you do that period
actually they might I don't know
if you were designing this for source
code control because you actually do
have source code control of your own
that would actually work then it depends
whether you check in these dependent
files or not right the way that I would
probably do it is I had check in the
source files and I'd let machines build
their own on the first run probably and
the reason for that is because
individual people need ability to modify
the files and I don't really want them
to check those in necessarily because
they tend to be you you have to do a
bunch of work to make sure that works
correctly you need to have those be
tagged properly so that people don't
check in things have been processed with
debug versions of a processor and you
got to make sure the name
reflect what version of the code
generated it and all these other things
so there's a lot more complexity that
goes into an asset pipeline if you want
to do the full deal but we're not really
going to be doing that
what makes I OC piece it's a great API
how does it work better than on the rape
you guys it works for the inner piece
because it allows you to put all of your
so it allows you to unify all of your
read and writing requests through a
single message queue that multiple
threads can wait on right and it allows
it uses your pointers like basically it
allows you to use C or C++ style
extension like if you know like let's
say you got a C++ class or something
well okay maybe not a C++ class to C++
is dumb but let's say you have C and
you're doing extension with C it allows
you to use your own structures as the
i/o structures as well and if C++ wasn't
you know made by monkeys it would have
worked there too it it only doesn't work
on C++ because C++ is dumb but it's just
structured very well for allowing you to
use it where it falls down is actually
not anything wrong with iOS CPI OCP I
think is pretty great Oh almost across
the board it's an API where it falls
down is that Windows itself doesn't
actually allow you to use iocp for
everything so at that point it sort of
becomes not that useful for anything
other than just like servers because you
can't use iocp for things like your
Windows message queue or you know
wave-wave out completion or trying to
think of some other things grep the
graphics fences right and so what you
would want to do is have all of those
things go through iocp so that basically
you just have a worker thread one per
core if they all block on the i/o CP and
as soon as there's something to do it
comes in on the iocp
right it'd be perfect and you can do
that as long as all you're doing is i/o
but as soon as you add things other than
IO which games do it all falls apart and
so the problem with iocp
is that it doesn't it's not embraced as
the operating system api and so it's
really only useful for servers as a
result which still makes it relevant to
games because like your game server can
still do this but it makes it much less
useful for game proper like a game
client because most of the things that
you actually care about can't go through
il CP
ureteral I was thinking on the direction
of always having a running build on
source control yeah if you're gonna
always have a running build on source
control that doesn't have to process
assets first because that we still would
right you'd hit run and it would have to
process the PM G's right the first time
you ran it so it still would be a
running built in source control it just
wouldn't run immediately like it would
if you'd run it before but if you
actually wanted to check out and run
immediately you have a lot of work to do
to really make a good system that works
that way I would almost argue you can't
really make a system that works that way
unless you write your own source code
control current source code control just
really isn't up to the task
in my opinion when where am i doing the
witness development presentation that is
not announced yet
I've read the sequel quick follow-up is
that just a matter of using the one
massachu for more than i/o or when you
need to use multiple message queues so
the way to think about it is this the
ideal system allows you to have one
thread per core waiting on a cue and the
cue tells that core what the next thing
is to do right because then you never
have unpredictability in thread
switching because there are no threads
to switch iocp does that properly when
you are only doing i/o because you can
create an i/o CP and then you can point
all of your i/o towards that iocp and
you're done as soon as you have anything
else you would want to do at all
anything else it doesn't work anymore
because even if you create other
separate message queues right you can't
wait on an i/o CP and another message to
you at the same time so you can't even
wait on to i/o cps at the same time you
can only wait on one right so again it
as soon as you come out of that system
and need to look at a wider system it
just all falls apart largely I think
because Windows does not embrace iocp
as its method
and so it makes iocp very fragile and
not very useful for other things because
you can't there is no way to work around
it either right like you can't there's
nothing you can do you you can't use io
CPS with a worker thread model if those
worker threads have to do anything else
because they'll never know that there's
something else to do they can only wait
on the iocp or some other semaphore so
for example and this is nuts
wait for multiple objects doesn't work
with IOC fees right so again the design
of the INA cps was good but they're
useless is severely limited because none
of the other windows api is work with
them and so once you end up in a
situation where you've got this thing
that can't work with anything else it
becomes impossible to actually use io
CPS
for multimedia applications because the
only thing you can use iocp for in a
worker thread model system is IO
it's literally IO CPS or not right so
that's the problem I desperately wished
that the architecture of Windows had
been everything goes through an IO CP
you want a Windows fence it triggers an
IO CP right you want to know when the
sounds done playing or a buffers under
flowing and sound
it's an IO CP when a buffer completes
right that would have been an amazing
world where you know all the birds were
singing and and the Sun was shining
Windows is nowhere close to that because
because of course we all know why
because they were too busy popping up an
ad for their stupid Authenticator app
like they had resources for that they
didn't have resources to make a clean
interface for their actual message model
in their APIs ISM that's not on the
table like that's never happening right
but what is happening
is Cortana integrated into my desktop
listening to what I say and doing stupid
stuff I didn't want it to advertisements
on my home screen and whatever that
stupid toast was that popped up and told
me to try Microsoft Authenticator they
found time for that but time to actually
make their architecture work sorry guess
we couldn't find a meeting room for that
we were too busy having like an argument
about whether Clippy should come back
and dance around on top of the Start
menu before you could click on anything
that said
all right
we closed down thank you everyone for
joining me for the episode of handmade
heroes I'm a pleasure coding with you as
always I think we're almost done with
our journey for adding like kind of a
new artist friendlier asset updating
system to handmade hero we did the PNG
reader we've done incremental update of
the asset files so now really all we
have to do is tackle the tags problem
and I think we're good to go
so we'll start taking a look at that
tomorrow hope to see you back here for
that
and then we just have debugging right we
just got a debugger thing and make sure
it actually works well because I'm sure
we've got some mistakes in there
somewhere there always are but that was
pretty painless actually didn't take
that long to do from start to finish
honestly even including the PNG reader
which I thought was gonna be worse than
it was so not too bad I'm actually
pretty happy with that not a huge deal
alright that's about it if you want to
follow along with handmade hero on your
own you can always pre-order it on
handmade here org it comes with a source
code so you can play around with it
yourself you could try your hand doing
the tag system if you are interested in
and see if you can do that before I get
to it we also have a updated website
thing that you can use now if you want
to we have a watch page you can use to
watch the stream and it also has the
episode archive on it and a bunch of
buttons you can use to to jump to things
like the mailing list we have the
handmade fund also has been updated now
and it's got a little explanation video
about what it is for funding community
projects that other folks besides me are
doing definitely check that out to get a
chance and of course there's always you
can click on the handmade hero head to
get to any other referrer Molly Rocket
websites if you're interested and
reading my tech blog or anything like
that I've seen what we're up to that's
an easy way to to sort of get there from
the handmade hero site as well that's it
for today I'll see everyone back here
tomorrow for the tag stuff until then
have fun programming I'll see you on the
Internet