okay hello everyone and welcome to hand
made here oh sure we could a complete
game live on stream I we yesterday did a
chat actually so I didn't get to think
that I wanted to get to we do have one
bit of cleanup to do from a previous
stream I might hold that off for a
little bit just so I can start on
something today that I kind of want to
start on and that is I wanted to talk a
little bit about sort of finalizing or
at least putting into its final API form
the arena's memory arena stuff that we
have been using on the stream for all of
handmade hero and what I wanted to do
there was I wanted to sort of show a
little bit more about how the arena's
could be made to be more flexible during
development if we want them to be and I
kind of just wanted to give you a little
bit of an outline on how that would go
so I'm just gonna do that and I'm gonna
talk about that a little bit now oops
so if you remember back when we first
started doing dynamically allocated
memory which is you know what we have
used for most of the things in handmade
hero are going are you know allocated at
runtime what we were doing is we're
essentially saying alright let's go
ahead and take a giant block of memory
right
and so this giant block of memory would
be as much memory as the game was going
to take let's say so you know maybe it's
gonna be 4 gigabytes of memory if this
was like a big triple-a game or
something like that right and we had I
don't know if we have it set that way
right now but at one time we tried we
did set it to 4 gigs or whatever it
might not be set to that anymore but you
get the idea so what we would do is we
would then say like okay we're gonna
partition this up and we'll partition
this up into like one gigabyte OB for
like you know the world or something and
you know 2 gigabytes of that will be
from 4 assets or something and one will
believe to scratch space I don't know I
mean right we'll just partition it up
and then we would sub allocate out of
these when we need things and obviously
there's a nice benefit to doing it this
way it's obviously keeps everything nice
and simple but it does have one obvious
drawback of doing this which is that
while it works fine if we know that we
just want to constrain the game a priori
to 4 gigabytes of memory which we may
want to do in the final shipping version
it does make an obvious sort of
limitation to the game if we wanted to
say just let the game use as much memory
as the game wants to use right and this
may not be super important to something
like handmade hero because I'm handmade
hero it's probably true that we will
have a good idea of what the memory
bounds for the game are when we ship it
so that we could just say here's how
much memory it tends to allocate and
we're done but you could imagine a
situation where you didn't want that to
be true so an example would be let's
suppose that we were to ship a world
editor with handmade hero sometime and
now the user wants to be able to make
levels in these things and because there
or whatever and you know how people are
with a mod games they we don't want to
constrain them to only making worlds
that are a certain size that fit into
our pre-allocated footprint we would
rather let the user make worlds as big
as they want so long as they have enough
RAM for it or something
right and obviously right we can even
come up with approaches to that problem
that are different we could start
allowing you to do things out of core
which we have a pretty easy way of doing
in our system now actually because we do
have that sort of world storage that
packs enemies and then unpacks enemies
and all that sort of stuff so we could
actually switch to out of core and maybe
sometime in hand-made here will actually
do that just to show how you would do
that because it's pretty easy given our
current architecture but that's neither
here though there even in that situation
you may want to give you may want to
empower the users to use as much memory
as they have because hey they paid for
it and if they paid for 64 gigabytes of
memory in their suite gaming rig and
they want to use it you should let them
right I mean you know if we can just say
like hey like dedicate more of that to
the game then great right and so there
is a certain amount of value here to
being able to say maybe we can let
arenas grow to whatever size the user
wants them to grow to and just let them
kind of roll the dice right if they want
to max out their system and crash the
game because they allocate too much
memory that the system can't handle or
something oh well and we could even be
sensible about our allocations if we
want to and you know try to do things
that will make sure that we can issue an
error message in that case cleanly so
the game doesn't crash it just says hey
you're trying to make a world that's
bigger than what can you could fit in
your machine or something so you know we
have a lot of options there but point
being it would be nice to be able to do
that similarly another thing that would
be nice is during development we don't
really know a whole lot about our memory
profile during development because we're
making decisions here and there we're
changing the way things work we have
things like the debug arena that's not
even part of the shipping
so why we would ever care about Priya
allocating that it doesn't make any
sense we used us to even really think
about how big that should be because
it's purely a debug thing we just want
to expand to hold as much debug
collation data as we need it to we don't
want to have to pre partition it right
and so again even if even if we assumed
that we were going to ship the game with
a fixed allocation block and not allow
any of its arenas to grow at dynamically
that doesn't even that doesn't mean that
we don't still want that expanding reach
bar because it can simplify our
development process by a allowing our
arenas which do not have to be shipped
at runtime to grow dynamically like in
the debug case and even the arena's that
we do want to make sure our fixed
allocation sizes because that's maybe
something we want to guarantee about our
runtime even those also don't have to be
set to be fixed sizes during development
so that way during development we don't
have to think about it but then as we
get towards data development then we can
start to look at how much memory are we
using and then convert to fixed at that
point right so expanding arenas useful
thing and they kind of extend the arena
concept very naturally in a way that
allows you to make them grow to take up
as much space as they need so let's talk
about what's happening right now with
our arenas and how we might implement
this it's actually very very simple so
if you look at how our arena's work
right now there's a certain amount of
memory there's a base pointer right and
a size and then you can imagine at the
end there's essentially sort of an
ending pointer right it's like that's
the end of this arena and so what
happens when we allocate right you
remember we've got this pointer at the
base we initialize a pointer that's
pointing there which is where we're at
and every time you ask for an allocation
we just move that pointer down right so
we essentially say okay if we're going
to write something in that's you know 64
bytes we write in that 64 bytes or we
don't really write it in we just
returned the pointer that we're
currently at and then we move 64 bytes
down
the next thing just gets stacked on top
of it right and then we do a little bit
of work there where we try to do
alignment as well so we allow you when
you allocate we may push the allocation
around a little bit but otherwise it's
exactly it's all analogous right so if
we wanted to what we could do is say
well we already have an assertion in
there if you go look at the code where
if the app pointer is all the way down
here and you tell us to allocate
something that's too large so the new
app pointer would overflow the bounds of
the arena we already have an assert in
there to tell us we blew our memory
budget right so what we could do instead
of that assertion if we wanted to is we
could just say oh well when we throw it
when we would have thrown that assertion
up and said hey halt the program tell
the programmer you messed up what we
could do instead is go ahead and
allocate a new block and just put the
app pointer there and then keep going
right and just do that as many times as
we want to right we could keep
allocating new space for Arena as we go
and so we can just fill it all the way
up you know up until we run out of
memory in the machine to allocate it can
just keep growing and growing and
growing right and mind you since this is
allocating pieces at a time those pieces
are still guaranteed to be contiguous
because if I couldn't have fit the piece
I put the whole piece on the next one
what that means is we don't have to
worry about copying things from this
arena when it expands you know a similar
technique like the dynamic array right
dynamic arrays are the kind of things
where you know okay I've got you know a
few elements here you know 0 1 2 3 4 or
5 whatever and then I want to insert a
sixth element but I can't because I
don't have enough room to insert the
sixth element there were only well I
should say the 7th element there's six
elements here I have six elements in
here I want to insert the seventh I
can't do it because there's always six
elements in the array there's no space
so then what they do is they say well
okay it's fine just you know reallocate
a buffer and if you can reallocate in
place great if you can't reallocate in
place just
get down the old values and then you'll
have room and so that copy has to happen
anytime you couldn't have like gone back
and asked the memory allocator if there
was if there was space here that the
memory allocator hadn't used that
happened to be adjacent it can just you
know pump it out but otherwise you know
you got to do that copy this doesn't
have to the copy because no one is
addressing into this thing right if
they're addressing into something
they're adding into a sub portion of it
that was allocated with a single call
and we know that that will still be
contiguous because we're never breaking
up those allocations across boundaries
right so if we would like again it's
very easy for us to go ahead and make
our arena's support this natural
expansion process and so I thought even
though I don't really know that we need
it too terribly badly I felt like since
people kind of didn't have a when I talk
about the arenas people are like oh
that's reliefs because a lot of people
are just only taught dynamic allocation
they're not necessarily taught some of
these other nice techniques arena
allocation is a very common technique in
production programming it's just it's
kind of one of those things that isn't
taught as often anymore again because of
this kind of like weird move to like not
knowing what memory is doing and stuff
like that right but old-school
programing arena is very very common
very very straightforward thing and so
since a lot of people hadn't really seen
those and I think should absolutely see
them I just wanted to take a day or two
and show you how to make the expandable
kind because it's very very simple and
then you can use it in all sorts of
other areas where you might want to use
arenas but maybe we're afraid to because
you didn't want to have to pre guess how
much memory you were going to take for
example in an application or something
like this right so what I would say here
is the first thing we're going to need
and I think we already kind of started
this a little bit we just never really
Danny thing with it is we're gonna need
a way to get more memory when we need it
and so we have our platform API is in
here right
where is that guy
here it is we have our platform api's
and we need to be able to allocate and
deallocate memory so you can see those
calls are here I don't know if we
actually ever used them I can't remember
yeah we don't even use those calls but
we did throw them in there so I think we
already have set ourselves up to do what
we need to do which is be able to get
more memory when the time comes right so
this should be very easy for us to do
now it'll probably only take me a little
bit to add the expandable to the
expandable concept to our arenas but we
do we will still have another problem I
suspect that is going to be a little bit
trickier to solve on the platform side
and that is just the loop live code
editing once we allow our arena so
dynamically allocate we have a little
more work that we're going to have to do
in on the loop live co-editing side of
things but we will also get a really big
dividend when we do that I don't want to
spoil what it is yet
those of you with sharp handmade brainy
brains probably already know what it is
that we're going to get but for those of
you still in suspense let's go ahead and
get started here so we can get to the
payoff that'll probably tomorrow though
because I spent some time talking about
so I don't know if we'll get it all in
today so here is our memory arena and
you can see here we've got a size a base
and a used and so it's just kind of
going up there I don't know I don't
necessarily know that that's the most
efficient way to store it as opposed to
doing a point or whatever but you know
this is basically the same thing right
we're just saying here's how big it is
total here's our amount used so anytime
we know where that at pointer is like
right this app pointer here we know is
this far up from base and this is the
maximum we can go right so if we come in
here and we say well we want to push
some memory on here and this is
interested yeah we want to push the
memory in here and as far as I could
to call all of our allocation then goes
through this push size call so if we
just modify this one we should be good
to go what it does is it says alright
you know figure out how much we actually
need to push on there based on the
alignment you can see it happening here
and then you can see the the assertion
which is going to say oh wait that's not
the assertion I'm looking for though
this is the assertion the assertion
which is going to say hey if where we're
at plus how much we need to allocate is
going to blow out the size then we're
just gonna stop we're gonna halt right
there oops as I pull the as I pull the
the thing out of the slot I should
probably check to make sure that I
haven't disconnected the audio okay
yeah I'm still going that's good so yes
so really this is the if that we're
talking about here this is the if that
we actually need this is the the
condition that we actually need to
satisfy so what we could do here is we
could say well alright what we want to
do is say if instead of making an
assertion if we were going to exceed the
size right what if we could just do
something here that would allow us to
expand the arena and not have this
problem where we're going to where you
know where we're going to run out of
size right so hopefully you can kind of
see where we're going with this it looks
like handmade memory has nothing in it
apparently all right everything's in the
H file so the memory arena here right it
has this face pointer what we need to do
is if we're going to blow the size what
we need to do is basically allocate
another chunk of memory to replace the
base pointer with a new base pointer
that we can use now the problem here is
we don't actually know how much memory
we should allocate because we could just
allocate however much we just need right
now but that's not very efficient
because then the very next time someone
calls us to allocate something we're
gonna have to do it again right meaning
if this person is asking us to allocate
you know 64 bytes of memory and we find
that we're at the end so 64 bytes won't
fit we certainly don't want to allocate
just a 64 byte chunk from the operating
system to stuff this thing into that be
horribly inefficient and and we would
have to do the same thing again next
call so we want to do instead is think
okay if it's a really large allocation
right if the person asks for 16
megabytes of data here then it may be
make sense to allocate the 16 megabytes
and give it back to them no questions
asked right but if they're only
allocating a small size 4k or something
like this then we probably want to have
some minimum allocation size that we
always allocate because we know we're
gonna get more allocation calls the
future we want to minimize the amount of
times we have to go through the opera
system right because if we start going
to the operating system too often we
lose most of the benefits of the arena
in terms of efficiency we don't lose the
benefits in terms of cleanup because
cleanup is still nice and easier much
easier than it is with sort of spaghetti
string smart pointer nonsense right but
we don't get the efficiency anymore
we're back to being inefficient like a
regular alligator is once we give that
up right so we'd rather do here is have
some minimum size so we want to do is
say okay we've got a memory since this
is going to be our block size right like
how much we're going to allocate we know
that we want it to be at least as big as
the size that we're trying to allocate
but we also want to know more
specifically
that we're going to allocate at least as
much as our minimum block size like so
right another way to write this I don't
know if we have a min/max macro I think
I think we did and I think we make them
in it as a macro I don't really remember
find out yes good good
so another way to write this would just
be to say I want it to be whatever the
larger of the two of these is right I
want if you know if the the size
requested is bigger than will use that
if the minimum block size is bigger then
we will use that right so at that point
we know what we want to do we want to
now allocate you know depth that memory
from from the system so we want to go
back to our platform code here and we
want to use the allocate memory call
right so you want to say allocate memory
and now we need to get this from
somewhere and of course in hand-made I
believe we have that it's this platform
API I think here right so we can say hey
platform allocate memory the memory
we're going to allocate is whatever the
block size is and I don't know that we
pass anything else oops
I don't know that we pass anything else
in there I think platform allocate
memory project size yeah it does and
that's gonna give us back a void star
right so that new void star would just
be our base pointer now right so if you
take a look back at the memory Arena
here we now have you know if we were
going to overwrite this memory Arenas
data we would have something like this
we'd say okay there's an arena science
pointer and we know that that's going to
be our block size I'm not pointer value
we have a base pointer the base pointer
is going to be the allocation we have
used which is how much we used and
that's going to be 0 and then we have
temp count and temp count would remain
the same because if we're inside a
temporary memory block
we're not going to you know no longer be
in one just because we moved to a new
block we're still inside a temporary
memory situation right so now once we're
done with that we should get to the
point where we can assert right that we
have the space that we need we should be
able to say that this at this point
should always be smaller than the arena
size right so there you go
and hopefully what you can see here is
we're not quite done yet we have some
more stuff to do
but you can kind of see all right so
what we do is we say every time we're
going to overflow we just allocate a new
block and we just pretend that we were
back at the beginning
and so the allocations can just proceed
as normal now get effective size four is
a problem for us in this regard it's not
a problem for us practically speaking
but it is sort of a problem if we wanted
to really be sort of judicious about our
code here because if you look at what's
going on when we say get effective size
for to figure out how big of a thing
we're actually have to allocate what
you'll see when you come up to the this
call is that this is gonna be based on
the alignment offset and when we ask for
the alignment offset you can see that it
matters what the used value was so it
matters essentially it matters where you
were in the arena as to what the
alignment requite criteria how much
we're gonna have to move to fulfill the
alignment criteria right because if
we're on the third byte of the arena
then obviously if you want four byte
alignment we're gonna have to move one
byte forward before we do the allocation
meaning the effective size is the size
plus one if we're right on the zero byte
then it's just going to be the size
because we don't need to move anywhere
to ensure our alignment and so get
effective size four is actually going to
return a size that is not actually the
size we will need in the new allocation
right the new allocation we could assume
is always aligned the reason we could
assume that it's always aligned is
because if we're going
to be allocating from the operating
system we can assume that the operating
systems block allocations that come back
should always be aligned to the maximum
alignment right but even if we didn't
want to do that we could pass the
alignment here to the operating system
to let it know we want align memory but
again operating system memory is always
going to be aligned in Windows to 64 K
boundaries so at that point you know
there's no reason we're ever gonna do
that so if we wanted to we could
actually change this to being instead of
size it could be size in it right
because at that point we kind of know
that we don't have that problem anymore
so really what we would want to say is
sighs you know equals size in it here
and say you know note kc the base will
automatically be aligned now and and so
on now what's interesting is it looks
like we didn't assert our alignment
after we do the alignment which is a
little weird but either way whatever I
should probably add one of those in here
meaning and there should be a thing
which says hey Garen you know try to
actually ascertain that when I did the
alignment it was actually aligned right
yeah but anyway so that's pretty much
what we're looking at now you can see
that we have a problem here which is
that this minimum block size we don't
have we don't know what the minimum
block size is but fortunately that's not
a particularly onerous problem for us
because chances are we can put that on
the arena itself meaning when the person
created this arena probably they had an
opinion about what that minimum block
size would be and even if they didn't we
can by default I'll make that minimum
block size be something reasonable now
when we actually initialize arenas I
think we don't use clear to zero at the
moment let's see yeah because the size
value here is getting set the size and
the base are getting set the like so
right so we call this initialize arena
we could very easily just say okay the
minimum block size in here
when we do minimum block size is just
gonna be whatever it's gonna be you know
64 K or something
so the minimum size were gonna allocate
when we allocate is gonna be that and
you know off we go or whatever so with
that maybe that's too small you know
maybe it should be a megabyte per I
don't know you know you're free to do it
maybe a gigabytes better I don't know
probably not gigabyte so you know I
don't know we could do to do KC tune
default block size eventually but really
what we would want to do here is say
okay chances are when people initialize
these things they would also want to be
able to specify you know that minimum
block size themselves so for example
they could do something like this in
line void initialize arena where we give
it the memory arena and then we say the
minimum block size and that would be
kind of an interesting thing as well and
what you would see there happen is we
would take all of this stuff oops we
would take all of this stuff and
actually just initialize it to zero and
then inside here we would pet we would
set that minimum block size now you may
be asking well what's going on here
you're not giving any memory to start
with and the answer is well once we have
expandable arenas we can choose not to
Bob not to bother iliza them with any
memory right we can just set a minimum
block size and then just know the first
time someone actually does an allocation
this arena it will go allocate something
of the minimum block size right so we
don't need to pass in a base pointer
anymore if we don't need to we can just
initialize an arena to zero essentially
and then just set the minimum block size
right now I would go one further and say
let's support zero is initialization
here I'm a big fan of zeros
initialization it's one of my favorite
things I think it reduces bugs a lot and
it also increases the efficiency in a
lot of ways potentially depending on the
circumstances so the other thing I would
say is let's have a clear to zero
ability on this arena by saying okay the
minimum block size could be set to zero
and we have a default block size
thing here so essentially what we could
say is hey if you don't set a minimum
block size because we know a minimum
block size of zero can't be valid
because that would not allow you to
actually allocate memory at all so what
we could do there is say alright if the
minimum block size is at zero then we
will use it if it is zero we'll set it
to the default right so when we push
through here we'll just say if arena
minimum block size is not set to
anything then we will just set a minimum
block size equal to whatever our default
block size is right and so now you can
see a really interesting thing that
we've done here this is something I'm
always pretty excited about what I can
do when I can do it we've got a
relatively complex thing that even has a
pointer it in whatever we were still
able to make initialize initialization
zero is initialization work right I feel
like that's a that should be a term like
you know how people have our eye like
resource acquisition is initialization
are our AII I hate that pattern I think
it's a really bad pattern how about zero
is initialization zi i zi i like you
know ra - equals bad zi i equals good
right that's all you need to know there
you go
programming done so yeah zero is
initialization is really nice if you can
do it it means you can just take memory
block clear it to zero and know that
it's ready to go you don't need to have
constructors you don't need to worry
about pointers pointing to things it's
really nice so if you can make it happen
it's always kind of nice in this case we
now have a really good way to make it
happen and that is to use this sort of
trick of checking the middle block size
now what you'll notice is I kind of kid
that in there in kind of a nice way we
already have to do this if check to see
whether or not we've hit the boundary of
the memory well that's not going to
happen very
often right the whole point is if we're
trying to be efficient we're not going
to hit that very often so what I did is
I buried this if inside there so it's
nice we don't have to worry it's not
like we're this cost us very much to do
because adding that extra check is it's
already pretty much free because it's
only inside this fairly rarely taken
branch so the work we do in here is just
not relevant right this is this is
called so infrequently hopefully if
we've tuned our parameters properly that
we don't have to worry very much about
what we do in here so it's pretty much
free to to add that check I believe
because I don't think we'll pay any cost
for that so it wasn't like the checking
every time is somehow less efficient all
right so that is a growing arena we need
to actually add this in now
let's see here
I and there's just max
well that's it handmade out H is it
alright fine now it isn't so yeah I move
over here so my head's not in the way
all right so now we've got pretty much
everything we need the platform bit it
inside memory here we do have the
problem of these arenas I think get used
in places where platform I don't really
know if platform always exists is one
problem so you know something that kind
of would it be nice and I'm not sure
exactly how we would want to tackle it
but one thing that would be nice is if
we had a way of always getting that
platform variable somehow from somebody
regardless of you know having a way of
getting that call regardless of where
you were and so you know if you're in
the dll we want this to be visible to
you right and we sort of can do that
global variable here I don't know if
that's actually being used to make this
thing static or not because I don't
remember what again we set at this point
our our definitions to there but global
variable yeah static so what we could do
there if we wanted to write is we could
make that an externally linkable
variable if we wanted to and we could
make it so that that way the you know we
could forward declare it in various
places or other things like that and
make sure that it actually works now the
way that that happens is I believe it's
inside game update and render you can
see here where we basically copy the
platform API from the memory that were
Pat from the memory block structure that
you know the thing that comes in from
the platform layer and so when we do
that copy right that's initializing
our version of the global variable and
in the platform code which is is still
using the arena's as well right in the
platform code we have that same data
here right we filled it out in game
memory so we could we could easily make
it so that this thing was accessible in
some way by the shared you know by the
by the code that's in the platform layer
as well we just need a good way of
actually doing that right and so one way
that we could do that is in the platform
thing here where we say in handmade H
where we say platform like I say we
could try to try making this an extern
right and then if we make it an extern
we can actually put it up into we can
put that up into the platform code and
say hey yeah no matter where you are
there will be one of these that you can
access but you're gonna have to get it
from different places depending on the
circumstances right so we could say
right here that they're gonna be able to
get one right that you're going to be
able to get one right and so then what
we need to do is we need to figure out
where we can define that thing so that
it's accessible oh hey look we're
already actually doing that apparently
right so yes so we just need one of
those in both places right so in
handmade dot cpp we needed one and we
can put that right here and then in the
win32 layer we needed one and so now we
have two different platform layers and
each of them can be used separately now
the problem here with platform is I
don't know that we ever actually said it
I know it's there but do we use it
anywhere
we do so there's our update so then
we're all good I think right yeah
virtual a lot blah blah blah so I think
that's it I think that's really all
there is to it to getting that platform
into the right place now mind you at
this point we have still not really done
the actual hard parts of this we did the
easy parts but we have a few hard parts
left to go we've got about 15 minutes
left if we run it now nothing's gonna
happen any differently obviously and the
reason that nothing's gonna happen to me
differently is because if you since
we're allocating our memory upfront
anyway none of our arenas will ever hit
that condition they would have asserted
before right if they had if they had hit
the end of them they wouldn't we would
have been seeing assertions since we
weren't seeing assertions we know we're
never going to hit the allocation case
so right now our arenas are actually
running exactly the same way that they
used to be running but what we can do to
prevent that from happening and force
them to go through a different path
right is we could go in and say all
right let's take the debug storage size
thing and let's make the debug storage
size not actually let's let's not have
there be a debug storage size let's
remove that entirely and we'll just use
a growing arena for our debug size right
so let's say we just get rid of this we
go into our game memory code and we just
say no right it's not it's not happening
right and so now what we could say is
well whenever this stuff is actually
accessing this debug storage right
although now I think about it we I don't
know if we need to have the successful
both places so this may be a poor choice
because we'll have to put the arena out
there although now I think
I suppose there's no real reason why the
arena can't just be out there I mean
seems like that would just work push
that on the stack for a second so yeah
you can kind of see us doing this this
thing here where we're lucky
initializing these arenas and blah blah
blah blah right and when we do this
arena initialization stuff right this is
all forcing us to kind of think about
things that we maybe didn't want to
think about and you know subdividing up
this memory but we don't care about that
right we don't care about how much
memory these things are using it's just
for debugging so this stuff is all just
stupid it doesn't actually help us at
all
and it just makes it harder for us to
program because it's wasting our time
thinking about how big we need to make
these things now it didn't waste very
much time that's true but why waste any
time if you don't have to since we can
get the we can get all the same benefits
from the arena that we were getting
before we don't have to give anything up
and now we wouldn't have to say how big
the things we're going to be right so
what we could do instead is just say all
right the per frame arena in fact maybe
this is the best way to do it
to start with well okay what this way so
the per frame arena inside our debug
state we're just going to make the per
frame arena be you know a dynamically
growing arena right and I guess we
should have another arena in here now I
think about it though the debug arena
itself when does that actually get
created that's the one I probably
actually want to do there
as well
hello it's this one so yes so that just
takes the total memory size of the
entire debug system right and the per
frame arena just takes half of that it
looks like you know whatever the half
whatever half of that actually is so if
I wanted to start out what I could say
is like all right debug state debug
arena and debug state performs they are
both getting initialized at the outset
here if during debug start and and so
what I want to do is I want to
initialize these arenas with a certain
minimum frame size I guess I don't
really care what that minimum frame size
is so you know if I wanted to I could
just do it like this
right I could just say initialize them
to 0 and that's all we needed to do
right if I want to and again I'm gonna
need some weight here to tell whether
you know things are initialized or not
but that would be the only thing that I
would actually have to do right so yeah
I can go ahead and do that do this
initialization bit and then I don't need
the total memory size or any of this
stuff this stuff can all go away
entirely and now I just end up having
like okay there's you know
there's some things that get
automatically allocated for us right
this also means that we wouldn't have to
ever throw anything away that we didn't
want to throw away so it also means we
don't have to do the sort of borrowing
thing we could just record as much debug
information as we want and and so we
could also you know create extremely
large runs of store debug information if
you wanted to and just let the arenas
allocate so we could do that if you want
to I'm actually going to call in it
arena here
it's just initialize and say that I'm
gonna pass a well you know what no I'm
just gonna stick to my guns there we go
so those arenas are going to get
initialized to zero which means they'll
just use the default block size and so
all we have to do now is clean up sort
of the the basic emit pass requires
l-value
do I not pass a pointer to the struct is
it this apparently it is so yeah I think
that's all we really have to do when we
call debug frame and you know we're
grabbing the debug state out of this
debug storage thing here and that's just
you know in the game memory that's just
where we have to store that particular
piece of information and whether or not
we get it depends you know if we get it
or not depends makes the decision as to
whether or not we actually do the debug
work so the question here is how do we
how do we get this thing started right
because before we would just pass a
block of memory in and say here's the
block of memory now we actually have to
do something we're okay you know if
there was no arenas or whatever those
things have to be initialized before we
go and so what we need is we need some
way right of recording the fact that
these things you know in the game memory
recording the fact that these things
were not set up yet right and so in
order to do that what I would need to
do is have something in here that we can
use for our initial you know for our
initial for Ford like our base pointer
right so I would need to have something
like this right that allows us to go if
that pointer is valid then we know that
we've that we know we've initialized if
it's not valid then or rather if it's
you know we could we could have it and
clear it to zero let's say right then we
know that things have gone kind of
pear-shaped on us right so let's take a
look at what would happen if we did it
this way so if I did it this way you
know and we assumed it was cleared to
zero presumably all the rest of this
stuff just works the only difference is
when we go to get this thing out we
would just look at that pointer whatever
that pointer was instead of actually
taking a memory block and casting it so
now we would say like all right when we
do debug get state again it just looks
at it that way and that's really all
that we would be doing similarly we
don't have to account for the debug
storage size in here anymore the debug
storehouse could be removed and then the
debug storage itself also could be
removed so now we've sort of started to
do this correctly of course we also have
the problem now where we want to set
when we when we do the game memory we
want to in here set game memory well I
guess it's probably cleared to zero for
us huh let me just double check that it
is yeah so debug state by default would
be set to zero so what we want to do
here is we would want to well honestly
we probably want to do something a
little bit weird we could if we wanted
to create the debug struct like here
right we could just create a debug
struck one of those starts next but it
it would end point to it and then it
would just be all zero so you knew it
was initialized but a more interesting
might be to just set that debug state
pointer to not be
anything at all and if we set that debug
struct pointer to not be anything at all
then I feel like we're in a more
interesting situation because if we set
it to be nothing at all instead of
looking at initialized right what we
could do is just return memory debug
state and initialize would just be
whether or not that was was set to zero
or not right
so namely when we call debug start here
right and do the if not initialized and
let me take a quick look just to make
sure I loop saw wrong thing so that's
the only place that's called right is
right down here so what I might do is
say let's make debug in it we'll pull
this out and then what we'll say is okay
we're going to return a pointer here so
if you need to initialize a debug system
you can just go right ahead and do it
right and we're gonna need some things
that would have been passed through here
right we're gonna need some stuff so
when the debug start situation happens I
guess I also don't know does assets need
to be here yeah it does we'll have to
pass probably something here well maybe
not I don't even know do we have to pass
anything here do we use anything here
let's find out compiler tell me
oops so we do need to know the width and
the height that we start out at because
it looks like it's placing an initial
thing at that location so that we can
kind of go through here and say like
okay we got a path we got to pass that
in but otherwise that's it so what we
can do here is say like okay when we
come down here we can say take a look if
memory debug state is not valid we can
set memory debug state to be debug in it
and if I switch myself over here I
should be able to see where are we
getting that width and height from stop
blocking my view please all right so
yeah oops
passed the wrong things isn't that
always the way
oh yeah so yeah so once we have this
done where we're gonna say like okay if
we need to initialize it we'll
initialize it in here and we don't need
the if anymore obviously because we're
going to actually create one of these
ourselves when we go to initialize the
debug code what we need to do now is
have some way of getting that initial
memory for the debug code now it was a
bit of a catch-22 situation right what
we want to do is initialize these arenas
here we would probably want to allocate
it out of the debug arena but we don't
have a debug arena yet so what do we do
well it's kind of funny if you think
about it one of those debug arenas is
really not there's nothing magical about
it it's just a struct right all is is
this struct so if we wanted to we could
do this we could say here's a memory
arena right and what I want to do is I
want to take my memory arena and like do
a bootstrap on it right so it's just
it's set to zero there's nothing in it
right now
it's an
then what I want to do is I want to get
my debug state from the boostrap arena
right so now I have allocated some
memory because the memory reader will
allocate a block of memory it'll give me
back my debug state right then what I'm
gonna do we just say hey guess what guys
that debug state you know that's
actually gonna hold the arena so we just
block copy the values in here into our
debug a state right and that's it does
that make sense I know it's a little
tricky but it's very very simple at it's
at its most basic right
oops I gotta tell it what we're actually
allocating there you go right and so now
hopefully we can you know I probably got
some bugs in here so we're gonna have to
do some stuff but hopefully we can go in
and actually see sort of that one piece
of it work let's go ahead and switch to
debug yeah and okay so we look at memory
debug say it's not set right so we go in
here we create one of these bootstrap
arenas right and the bootstrap arena as
you can see has nothing in it at all so
then we say hey I need a debug state
structure please so we come in here and
we say all right well give us one of
those how big does it need to be you
know that's how big it is it's pretty
big it's pretty beefy we take a look at
what the minimum block size is and we
find that the minimum block size hasn't
been set so then we set it to one
megabyte right then we say okay we
wanted that much memory here's the
minimum size mm size is bigger so we end
up with a block size that's that's the
minimum block size we try to allocate it
we come under the platform
layer it calls virtual Alec with that
size now we've got a pointer to that
much and that's how much the size is
used right it's all good we then do the
alignment we zero out the block of
memory that we allocated and now we're
good to go
and now we have our debug state right
but our debug state has a debug arena
that shows that it has nothing in it
which is not correct we want to use that
part that we just started with so we
copy the memory in and now that debug
arena is actually the bootstrap arena
and from now on everything else goes
just fine now at this point what I'm
realizing is all of this stuff that's
initialize to zero is a complete waste
of everyone's time because I was
initializing the whole debug state to
zero because I kind of wanted that to be
a zero inertia last thing so I have no
idea why any of this stuff is set to
anything other than things that are non
zero right so really that's all that we
would set this does not have to be set
none of this stuff has to really be set
I also don't know why any of this stuff
is even here because I don't even know
what it is I guess that was just some
test code that's still in there for no
reason whatsoever similarly we don't
need to set things to false because
false is the default and so there we go
so that's actually our new startup code
right ok so sorry back to the
walkthrough so here we are right so now
we've got our debug state and it has its
own arena like we wanted and the arena
is getting used we return it back and
now we have inside our memory pointer
right we have the debug state should
actually be set there it is and it's got
of course the arena that we saved right
in here and we also are set to
initialize although initialize isn't
actually needed anymore so what I would
like to do is just get rid of it before
we forget because it's I don't want
people to think that that's doing
something when it's not doing anything
right okay so let's do p-- s-- that's
not what I wanted I wanted to step
through that let's try that one more
time ok so then after debug state is set
we now have everything doing
it's its thing like we expect and it
looks like we get hung up in here
somewhere I'm not really sure where so
let's take a look it's probably just a
bug that I have inadvertently introduced
doing who knows what
what is our hash index okay
while not results
aha so this is actually this was our
code to make sure we only used a certain
amount of space for the debug arena
stuff and we don't really need that
anymore right so this is just gonna loop
forever because it's like well I don't
have any room I have zero room so
there's no way I can ever store any
debug events so we really don't really
need that anymore
it's super not necessary but I don't
know that doesn't necessarily mean we
want to do it that way right we could
still say that we want the per frame
arena to be capped at some level right I
mean I don't know we could just say that
we don't want to take our betrayal route
Matt's room but if we did want to take
arbitrary amounts of room I just want to
make sure like let's say that we just
always did this push struct here right
and didn't do the freeing I'm wondering
if free oldest frame just filled this
frame get called in the course of
business so it does so these will get
cleaned up naturally so what I'm
thinking here is what we could do is
just say no let's not do that anymore
instead of like reclamation here and
doing the first free stored event thing
right what we could do instead is say
like alright take this code and just
assume that you've never free if you if
you want memory you can just have it
right oops
and then off you go
so yeah now that arena is just a
dynamically growing arena right so you
notice we've taken something that
previously forced us to specify how much
memory to take and replace it with
something that we don't have to specify
how much memory to take and it just kind
of will grow as necessary and all the
rest of the code runs exactly the same
and you can see here that we're still
stable we're not doing any allocations
or D allocations for frame right we're
totally stable because it's only going
to grow to the size it needs and then
it's gonna stop right so again pretty
much all the benefits of the of the
arena allocation scheme but now if you
choose instead of forcing yourself to
specify the boundaries at that
allocation time you can instead not
specify them and have it grow as
necessary and then again you just have
to be aware of the fact that you are
rolling the dice now because the
operating system may eventually run out
of memory right now that's probably not
gonna happen these days cuz there's so
much memory running around but maybe
think of a different platform think of
an iPhone or something something where
the memory might be tighter there you
know you can't just expect to just keep
allocating gigabytes of memory and not
have any consequences of it right so
again don't want to just go hog-wild
with it but it's nice to have this other
tool the toolbox
are we done yet no we've got more stuff
to do tomorrow obviously that we have to
do to work on it so we're gonna have
some more things to talk about tomorrow
right now though we're over time by five
minutes so let's go ahead and go to the
Q&amp;A anyone who has questions and answers
please go ahead and give them to me now
I think in Sabah is starting to be a
little bit like Microsoft a
trs-80 if you allocate new block after
clunk in temporary memory and temporary
memory is going to restore incorrect
values isn't it yes so this is why I
said we're not done yet the begin temp
end temp has to be implemented using a
technique that I'll show you tomorrow
it's it's not particularly difficult to
implement it's just we have one more
thing to do there the other thing that
we haven't done is for loop live code
editing we need to make those
allocations work in a predictable
fashion for saving out so we'll do that
as well so we got we've got at least two
more things to do I don't know that
we'll get to both of them tomorrow
beginning in temporary will definitely
do tomorrow but depending on how long it
is to debug that because although it's
easy to implement it's easy to
accidentally get a little thing wrong in
it sometimes so you know assuming the
that goes smoothly we'll get we'll start
on the loop type coding part but it may
not be we may have to go into Monday to
finish that part how easy or possible is
it to transfer code from Java to an
engine that does graphics well and if it
is possible or easy to transfer which
one would you recommend I'll be honest I
don't I don't really program in Java at
all and I I mean not to be too flippant
about it I don't really care about Java
at all so I haven't ever read up on
anything like that so I have no idea
absolutely no idea I I would say that
you know if you're looking for a Java
ish language meaning something that has
a lot of like garbage collection and
bytecode e things to it you know unity
is an engine that's programmed in
c-sharp
for example and c-sharp you know if you
program in Java
I feel like c-sharp is not a huge you
know incredible leap to try to make
right so I would say you know if if that
was your goal I would I would probably
not do Java Java just Java doesn't seem
like a particularly good language to use
for games nowadays because I don't feel
like a lot of the platforms that you
have to choose from
have embraced Java at all whereas like I
said c-sharp is like very prominent now
in games because of the fact that unity
chose to use it and so now you have the
option of tying into an engine set there
and a whole suite of middleware designed
to help you if you go to c-sharp route
if you go the Java route I don't like I
can't think of a single professional
like the only game I know of even really
that ships in Java that anyone ever
cared about was minecraft and that
didn't use a pre licensed engine the
engine is itself is written in Java and
even you know and minecraft isn't a
high-end graphics game right it's it's
pretty low-end
so you know I don't I really just don't
know of any kind of well you say does
grab as well I don't know of any
high-end graphic stuff that you can
easily tie to Java they probably exist
somewhere but I don't know so again I
would say not my area of expertise I
don't do that kind of programming I only
do the kind of low level gaming sorts of
code so I don't have a really strong
opinion all I can say is that if you
were you you know if you're just kind of
taking a bird's-eye view of it it looks
to me like if I was gonna pick one of
those higher-level languages it really
wouldn't be Java because you don't have
you're not gonna get much support there
right I'd go see sharp may Muni also or
try blueprint you know right is unreal
one there aren't that many game engines
out there right you know there's
lumberyard there's unity there's Unreal
there's game maker game maker isn't a
does graphics well kind of a thing
though right game makers made more made
for older style graphics so I don't know
that you would include that one but
there aren't that many high-end
rendering engine out there to pick from
and none of them use Java as far as I
know
would it be a good idea to store a point
to the allocator function inside the
arena struct instead of using a global
it is if you have a slightly different
architecture than we do on handmade Hiro
on handmade Hiro we do not have
different memory pools so there isn't
there's only ever going to be probably
one alligator right but if you are in a
heterogeneous environment where you may
be getting memory from different sources
then it makes a lot of sense to store
the alligator function inside the arena
but on handmade Hiro it probably
wouldn't be necessary because we
probably would never recall anything
other than the global now if that again
I don't I try not to do things
prematurely so even if I sort of
suspected we might do that I don't think
we will but even if I suspected we might
do that I probably wouldn't do it now I
would wait until we actually were
allocating from multiple pools just so I
could see what the most proper way to
integrate that was at that point but
like I said when you say would it be a
good idea I would say it's it's
definitely good idea sometimes I don't
think it's good idea for him a hero but
it's definitely a good idea in a general
sense of it is a technique you should
consider using if you have the need to
have different arenas at runtime
allocate from different sources how do
we free old memory blocks if the base
pointer always points to the newest
allocated block again you can have to
wait for tomorrow on that it's exactly
the same code as we need for the begin
and end temporary blocks if that makes
sense and so we just have to we need to
do that implementation and so as soon as
we go do that implementation then you
will see perhaps I'm missing something
but how to do you go back to previously
allocated memory blocks like for freeing
memory and saving it out and relocating
it again we'll cover all that tomorrow
so so don't worry that will be very
clear it's it's not difficult it just
requires us to do a little bit more work
in that if statement that I was talking
about where we don't care how long it
takes we just need to put a little bit
more
work in there and then once you put a
little bit we're working there we will
have the information that we need in
order to rewind our arenas
yeah yeah ma'am no ma'am ma'am ma'am
ma'am ma'am yeah meow meow meow yeah
yeah I'm out yeah I'm at my up now all
right we are just about out of time and
I don't see any more queue Cullen's so I
am going to wipe it down let's close it
up close it up and close it up all right
thank you everyone for joining me for
lips on a handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as it always is
if you would like to follow along with
series at home you can always pre-order
the game on hammaker org and I upload
the source code every night for your
experimenting pleasure we also have a
forum site you can go to if you want to
ask questions a patreon page you go to
transport our video series a schedule
bot you can use to find out when we are
live in an episode guide maintained by
the fabulous midlow who keeps it up to
date with time coded markers and
everything so if you want to catch up on
old episodes stuff that we covered in
previous episodes of handmade hero that
is the place to do it that is it for
today I will be back tomorrow for the
last stream of the week
tomorrow is a 5 p.m. stream again so
again keeping with the the alternating
time slots for people who are in
different time zones hope to see you all
here for that it's just gonna be us
finishing up our memory arena's like I
said might take us two more days my
tickets one depends on how quickly we go
tomorrow but basically we've already did
you've already seen the idea very very
simple and so now we just have to
implement the ability to rewind our
allocations and we will be good to go
that's it for today thank you for
joining me I will see you guys on the
Internet and then hopefully tomorrow 5
p.m. take it easy everyone