hello everybody and welcome handmade
hero show recoat a complete game live on
stream we've got so much to do there's
all kinds of things we can do now we're
just yeah we're in we're in party mode
for Krampus laugh and calm for sloths
and we need to yeah we need to just go
to town so you know of the things that
we can be doing there's a lot of them
there's some quality of life things that
I was doing yesterday like now we can
sort of have some hotkeys for our stuff
here where we can switch between like
debug output stuff we want to do I'll
probably do a little bit more of that in
the future but we don't really need it
right now so I'll let that be a bit more
on demand we want to go do some asset
system stuff we want texture handle
recycling and I'd like to add audio
asset better audio asset loading in
there and so when we go to add sounds
maybe I'll do that I don't know I need
to do it right now but the texture
handles recycling would be a problem
that we need to address some point and
then finally we need the ability to do
the sort of the saving and loading of
permanent alignment point stuff so in
terms of what we do first I'm just gonna
start there I'm gonna start at the
saving and loading of the line points
because I've it's kind of been we keep
pushing it back like we're kinda me like
we gotta do that we gotta do that we
gotta do that and we just haven't done
it and I'd like to go ahead and do that
because it's it's really important for
us getting all the rest of our graphic
stuff done and you know I want the cat
like I want you know we showed how we
can edit the cat forward do like great
where the head just snapped the body and
all this sort of stuff so I'd like to be
able to have that work and so when we
come in here and you know we do this
editing like we did before where I say
I'm like oh yeah let's make a place how
it snaps on to the head or whatever
there and you know we can adjust all
this stuff now see there you know now
that we can put this stuff together we
want to be able to save that kind of
information and right now we just don't
have that right
you know we have no we have a wheel we
have like no way to preserve this so
even though we did all the work to make
all of this stuff all this stuff kind of
like clean and efficient right we don't
really have any way of actually saving
what we did and you know and there's
also like little editor things like like
that's too thick I can't see what's
going on there there's also like I'd
like to add synthetic hits here for
other parts of this thing because right
now you have to have clicked on where
the head is to edit the head which is
not as good like if I click anywhere on
an entity I should probably get all the
things on the entity automatically or at
least have a little cycle so I can go
through forwards and backwards and so on
but anyway so now that we have the
ability to edit that stuff and I just
want to be able to now go back here and
hit the Save button where I can you know
do all that work and then when we come
back into the game it's the same as it
was before and there's two pieces to
that one's easy one's hard
the easy one is we actually already have
saving implemented into our data file
format so that's just calling a function
in fact if you hit save and import it
would just save I believe it so like if
for example in here if I if I hit
important save I think that because that
will save the file well you know I take
that back
it may not because nothing changed right
there was there was no actual there were
no new bitmaps loaded presumably so it
probably didn't actually save the file
cuz none of them would have been marked
dirty but point being if we had imported
a new texture it would have marked the
file dirty resaved it and then this
stuff would have saved so then when we
restarted it would be there I don't
actually think it's gonna be here now
cuz I don't think it picked up any
changes on the import because we didn't
change anything yeah but it would have
so implementing that part of the save
feature would be simple and in fact I
guess we can just go do that now because
that part is just a question of saying
which files we wanted to save in the
first place and that's it
so we can do that and then the other
thing we need to do is we need to have a
permanent storage file format for those
alignment points and that's the text
part of things that I wanted to do and
that's harder it it's not actually a
difficult code it just it's a bunch of
parsing stuff like we just don't have
any of that and so putting that in there
will take a little bit longer because
it's just a it's just new code there's
no it's not like we already have a bunch
of stuff that does this or reads textile
formats and so on we do have some
parsing stuff so it's probably not as
hard is it might be in that sense but
you know it's it's definitely something
that that will take a little longer than
this which would probably be fairly
straightforward so if we go to the
in-game editor we look at the save
function here where we've got like
should save you know and then it says
like okay let's let's save the file
check for art changes here you you know
this part where we where we say say
we're going to save the problem that
we're gonna get is we need to be able to
mark things as dirty and have the I I
don't actually know that we really want
this to happen per se right look we
probably need something more like this
you know something like this or do you
know do save preparation or something
like that where you know we're gonna do
something like this and we're also going
to mark the files as dirty right so in
here we'll mark all the files as dirty
that that need to get marked dirty and
then what we would have is instead of
saying should save what I want to do
instead is say like you know I want to
say do save preparation or like prepare
for save or whatever
I want to do prepare for saving and
prepare for saving we'll do whatever
needs to happen and then this will will
execute the save on unit in and of
itself right I think I think that's
probably what we want to do in fact I
think what we could do actually save all
changes no I think about it we could do
it this way like so I think we could
actually do this and then what we would
do is inside the asset system where we
do check for art changes this would not
happen here anymore right so what we
would actually do is have this rewrite
or write all hij modifications so in
here right this is what we would call on
the game assets and the the temporary
nough in this case where we you know
we're using the one from from up here
yeah I think we just want to do yeah oh
it already was doing that so yeah like
this is more what we want because then
we can just say okay you know when you
want to do your you're saving right
check for art changes would not really
be checked for art changes it's just
like import changed assets right and and
we would call that and then save all
changes whereas if you hit save we'd
just do save all changes you know what I
mean so I think that's more what we
would want to do and save all changes
would do this and in here when we go to
do the save all changes we now just have
to do the stuff that we were going to do
where we need to take a look at any
changed assets and make sure that they
get saved out you know in a more
meticulous fashion right so there's two
ways we can do this one is we can well
you know I guess I would say we really
kind of wanted we probably want to do
this in a way that that is actually
fairly specific so we probably just want
to loop over all of the changes that
we've done so the undo stack back to the
last clean undo sentinels so you know
when we do a revert for example like
this code here so this is effectively
what we want to do but we don't want to
actually undo the changes so really what
we'd want to do here is say look you
know we've got this change list here for
the in-game edits so we want to look at
like each of those we want to start at
whatever the clean undo Sentinel was and
we would just want to go to there I mean
we could do it this way
so if we look the undo stack like the
first thing you would undo is the next
pointer on the undo sentinel stack right
we would want to loop until we got to
wherever it was that you know was
considered no more edits right because
we keep that watermark of like when the
last time you saved was and then we've
got sort of the edit here right where
we're really / - next there's a I want
to say there's a condition here that we
need to take into account which is that
we may have done a redo operation that
redoes passed the clean undo Sentinel
and
I'm not really sure what we would do in
that case because we would have to redo
you know at one point someone asked me
like why have two stacks and I was like
I don't know why not have two stacks it
seems a little clearer but when I'm
thinking about that I'm like maybe it's
true that we should have had just one
stack because you can see where the
there's a bug here I think it's already
exists in the revert because let's say
that the clean undo sentinel next is now
pointing to something that's in the redo
stack this just wouldn't terminate it
just crash right when it gets I mean
what wouldn't crash it would assert
right which is the same as crashing so
it makes me think that maybe we do want
that to happen as as an undo redo
and I guess what you would need at that
point but you know now I think about it
doesn't really solve the bug because you
still need to know where whether that's
in front of our behind you
so yeah so I guess the way I would look
at it to say all right so the clean undo
sentinel next this is not really
sufficient right we need to know where
that was so we'd like we'd have to do
this where we have this notion of a
clean edit right and then what we'd have
to do is say well whatever the changes
that we've made since the clean edit is
what we have to mark now if you want to
revert then you have to look to see
whether the clean edits in the undo
Sentinel or the redo Sentinel and you
have to undo or redo whichever one it is
until then if you want to save all your
changes then you would need to do the
same thing right you need to figure out
which stack you're in and you need to
walk that stack until you get there so I
think what we'd want to do here is say
look find this thing and maybe we say
something like in-game edit fine or find
clean edit list
right
and in here we would say you know if the
if the ingame edit existed or not and
this would just take one of these so if
you asked us to match that pointer we
would say okay you know here's our test
as long as the test is not equal to the
sentinel we'll look if we find one of
these we'll say okay here's our result
so in here we just say look if the test
equals the match then go so we look here
we say look through this list if you
find the thing you found it if not you
didn't right and so here we can say if
the Edit
that we're talking about which is the
clean edit if the Edit exists in the
undo sentinel then it is the undo
sentinel list that we're talking about
so result equals editor undo sentinel
else if the edit exists you know I guess
in this case we could say result equals
editor redo sentinel and assert that the
edit exists in there because it's an
error to ever be in a case where somehow
it didn't exist in either of them right
so I'm gonna do one other thing here
because I need to I need this to make
sure that if the list is empty or that's
or the match was equal to the sentinel
that we return right away and so what
I'm gonna do here I might do this I
might say that
so now what I can do is say if the
sentinel equals the match
you know same because we do at startup
have clean edit just point to the
sentinel right it's just nothing so if
it happens equal to sentinel that needs
to still return true so we need to
basically do this
and then and then I think we're good
right so what we can do now is implement
these more properly we can say when we
go to save all the changes that we're
going to save what we could do is see
which one of these we need so we can say
the in-game edit list in question equals
fine clean edit list and there's the
editor and then we can just loop through
that list and know that well we don't
know which list it was in but we also
don't care right we know that we have to
go through everything up until that
point so we know that we just need to
take whatever list were given and go
from there oops why change that to list
for no reason so when we're doing this
then here's the part where we would mark
this asset for writing etc and then at
the end of this we would mark the clean
edit as being at the end of the undo
sentinel or the redo sentinel or whoever
right because we are saving all the
changes so now it's fine so that seems
like it doesn't matter whether we use
the undo or the redo one in this case I
don't think I have to think about that
I wonder we may need to include an
actual link
so I'm not really sure we'll have to
test that I'm not sure whether we need
to put something in there or not
my gut instinct says we don't because as
long as we specify what this was
supposed to be there's only two cases
either it actually was something in
which case that something is now being
tracked as the state that had to be
valid if it was nothing then there isn't
anything on the undo list anyway and so
once you are in that position you should
be good to go right because you can't
hit redo anyway so I think that's okay
so really the only thing we need to
modify then after that is just the
revert function like I said it's not
really correct anymore so this needs to
do one of two things like what we really
need to do on revert is we need to say
hey tell us which one of these two it is
right and you know I could actually do
this myself because you know since I
need to do two different loops it
doesn't really matter I guess but you
know in this case I got that backwards
there
if it happens to be in the undo stack
then I just keep undoing until I'm done
and if it happens to be in the other
sack right so you know that's the same
path as before if the clean edit was
actually in the other sack though then
what we would need to do and let me also
do that assertion
I didn't mean to delete that because you
might as well can continue with that if
it happens to be in the other stack then
what I would need to do is do reduce
right now that this is the same you know
meaning I'm still waiting for this to be
the case if that makes sense but I would
redo I would keep doing reduce to get to
that point because I'm actually instead
of undoing I need to do reduce to get to
get there if that makes sense and so
that case happens when I save the game
or save the state so I mark something
and then rather than the user making
edits they actually hit undo a couple
times and now if they want to revert it
means reverting is actually redoes
changes it doesn't undo changes it
redoes them to get back to the state of
the file you know what I mean so I think
that's correct again we may be going a
little bit further than we need to here
because this is just an in-game editor
for our own use and getting all this
stuff right is probably not super
necessary but you know
it is an educational stream after all so
there we go don't know if there's any
other things yeah so when we actually do
this loop now and we look through the
list to find whichever list has the
clean edit in it we look through to see
where that is we need to go for each
edit and figure out how to mark that
edit is something that needs to get
rewritten right that needs to get
written back and so in the actual file
the the asset manager right inside here
we kind of have these we have like a
notion of where the thing came from that
we store like the file index in the
asset index and file so for each one of
the assets that we know we touched in
the edit we can go to the asset file and
mark it as modified so we know that it
needs to get written back at that point
allow editing is an interesting thing I
don't know if maybe we should be looking
at that allow editing flag to see
earlier on in the process to prevent you
for example from selecting things you
couldn't edit or prevent you from
selecting things yeah I mean I don't
know what we probably would have to do
in the future if we wanted to be super
good about it is if you tried to edit
something that was in a file that
doesn't allow editing we would create a
new file for you and then the edits
would go in there right so it also means
we could change the way that we are
doing like we could make that local HHA
we could make that be a thing too
so we'll see we'll see how we want to do
in the future for now however all we
really need to do worry about is
modifying setting that modified flag to
be true anytime we've done edit in an
asset that's in one of those files and
that part's pretty easy because it
doesn't actually matter like how many
times we set that flag so basically what
we'd be doing here is saying well you
know file modified equals true
so what we really need to do is get
whatever the asset was for this change
right you know something like this and
in here we would just say well assuming
this change related to an asset of some
kind then we need to get the file for
the asset which we kind of know is just
look it's something we can just look up
directly in here right because we know
that there's the list of asset files is
maintained by the system I don't
actually know assets source file
I'll be honest I don't really know to
what extent we need this anymore but
all right doesn't matter um so anyway
we're all we're gonna do here is set
that modified equal to true and so all
we have to do is get the file you know
for that asset right and in here when we
you know for this particular asset when
we get that that file back we decided to
modify the trip so the thing that we
don't really have at the moment like I
saying is the other side of this which
is that if an assets gets modified in
here we kind of want to specify that it
needs to get rewritten that it's
specific data needs to get rewritten and
so that part is a little bit harder like
I don't know exactly how we would I
don't know exactly how we would do that
cleanly there's two ways we could one's
probably a little more work than it's
worth because you know C++ and its
terribleness but really all we want to
do here is just create a little local
hash table and use it but of course that
would bring us into template nightmare
land if we were gonna have stuff that
that was able to do that where we just
want to mark like okay which assets do
we actually need to save the file which
ones we don't and so you know I don't I
I don't love the idea in here of having
it so that we have to rewrite that but
you know the other thing we could do is
just rewrite all the text files every
time let me save or just diff the
contents you know of those text files so
I think I may just leave it at that and
we'll go from there
so I mean here we do get a set for edit
and we go look up in one of these files
here let's see
so set active asset turn eyes see no no
no no that matters so right here it's
basically this stuff so what I want to
do is have something that for one of
these types which again you know we
don't really know what it does because
they can be any kind of edit in here
then what we want to do is something
like this where we say okay you know for
each asset or rather for this edit look
at what type it is
and if we know what kind of you know
edited actually is then we can get the
asset back pretty easily you know we can
say get asset and do it this way
something like this and then later if we
have other types that can also report
one of those we can have a way of
getting them in here as necessary so
once we have that then we really just
need something that allows to get the
file and I don't actually know that
we've ever done that you can get a file
from a file index but not necessary from
an asset so but that's probably fine I
mean we could just say get file and and
leave it at that
right so get file we passed the editor
assets and file index for that asset and
that may be sufficient right that is not
what I meant to type
and neither is that what else we get
alright so in terms of the matching
there I'm gonna go ahead and switch this
build to debug mode and just step
through there cuz I want to see what
that actually does because we added some
stuff there and I do you know I know
what I wanted it to do but who knows if
I made a typo in there somewhere and
just want to make sure that it's
actually gonna do what I wanted it to do
and not some other thing that is
unrelated to those so let's suppose I
come out here and I want to edit the
little cat head again and you know in
sear I just can select the the cat right
so as you can see it's it's a default
state doesn't have anything special here
so I'm gonna like edit it a little bit
I'm gonna place it on the ground in a
more specific fashion I'm gonna set the
base of neck I'm gonna move the base of
the neck up to roughly where the base of
neck should be and then I'm gonna select
the head again
or whatever that's called this piece
right and then I'm going to adjust that
so that the bat piece does roughly what
I expect as well I don't know exactly
how I want that so now I've got two
assets that should have been edited
there and I want to set a breakpoint so
I can watch what the assets what the
in-game editor does when I say that I
wanted to save it so let's see I think
that was called save all changes right
and now if I go to the HHA and I hit
save I want to see what it does so first
it's going to look to see where this
thing is
and it correctly located it here
hopefully correctly I located it here
which is exactly where it should have
located it so hopefully that is what
happened then we can say all right for
any given
edit like I should have if I look in
here now for any given edit I should
have a thing where I see like you know
what what had actually changed and you
can see here it said like ok asset 307
edited it's 0 the line point right and
so you know what's actually what's it
actually gonna do I want to get the file
back that should be local doubt HHA I
think should be the file in question of
course I don't actually know if it is or
isn't
I should probably bake some naming stuff
into the header of the file so that you
can actually see after you've loaded it
what it actually is because I don't
think the platform stores the file name
maybe it does I don't know I don't think
it does though does it well let's see no
it definitely doesn't I mean you can
even see that it's not a pointer right
it's like a kernel handle or something
so in here I'm gonna say that this file
is now modified so it's gonna set that
to true and of course I'm assuming it
did set it to true even though Visual
Studio so help to lead prevents us from
being able to see anything after we step
out of a scope do not know whose idea
that was but that person if they didn't
already quit and go work somewhere else
is fired so you know here's this setting
all those modified Flags presumably all
in the same file because these all come
from the local HHA we then said so that
like we assume that the edit is we
assume that the edits clean now now
we're gonna go through here and there
should be that local HHA should actually
be marked as modified so when we get
there which is here we should write all
of them out again and that should be it
so now in theory that data was saved to
the HHA and so if we load the game again
we should get back to a situation where
those edits are preserved again only in
the HHA and we can't see that that
actually is true
right so that's really all we need to do
to save the stuff and if you didn't mind
Rhys aligning everything in the game
every time you wanted to build the hhas
you could just do that right that could
be the end of it but like I said I'm not
sure we want to use that as our as our
permanent file format that seems
ill-advised you know what else we should
do we should we should well we're on the
subject in entity Jen the cat head in
here I'm I'm not sure why we're getting
you know if you look at what's happening
here I don't really know why we're
getting these happening in the same
place like I don't understand why these
the why they're z-fighting
exactly because if you look at like the
entity visible piece body and entity
visible piece head stuff it looks like
we should it looks like maybe it's
ignoring the offset or something
and so I wonderfully maybe have that
code wrong a little bit because sort of
these are offsets relative to where they
should be just placement wise right so
in the sense they should just both be
set to this you know what I mean like
that's the initial settings and if we go
look at what actually happens when you
create one of these you know what I mean
and we go over here and look at what
where that actually places things then
presumably like you know it's kind of
stuck in the ground right you can see it
you can see it's stuck down in there
right but what I'm not sure about is why
because in theory if the alignment point
is on the bottom of the cat the point
that it's standing on should be like up
here somewhere and so it should be
starting up like I worry that we've got
a bug in the entity placement code and
we haven't really streamlined that code
yet we only just kind of put in the
basics of it yet
and so I am a little bit concerned and
like if you look at a lot of this stuff
there's just a lot of nonsense going on
in here
and we haven't looked at it in a while
and we probably needed to get a little
more serious about it because especially
if we're gonna start saving data out
where we're like doing actual work to
position art assets we don't want all of
that positioning to be based on a
mistake you know what I mean
so when we do stuff like the alignment
here and we set the initial P you can
see like this stuff is you can already
see that's wrong in a lot of ways the
initial P this piece offset actually has
to be added afterwards because it's
supposed to be the offset from the
location that you would snap to right
because the piece offset is a separate
offset so you know that is really what
should be happening there because that's
what would allow this to say wherever
this thing snaps to here's how much I
want to offset it which we want to be
able to do for things like Z and stuff
to like offset the position that you
know we want to be able
do so you know so that's that and
looking at the entity ground P part of
things I guess I don't know how that's
actually being set and I would like to
know where that is
so we may want to look at that a little
more carefully to make sure it's
actually on the ground but the offset
parameter is the only thing I was
worried about here like where are we
getting that from so when we say offset
what do we mean and it looks like we're
talking about you know mostly animation
there so that's fine
so that really shouldn't be anything at
the moment so it's really just the enemy
ground P so assuming that that's the
case what is happening here we've got
the P sprite specific or so we're using
that whatever that parent is and the get
P percent for the parents alignment with
that all seems fine
and then we're changing that height
ratio there so that Vettel looks fine
and when we go to get the the parameters
when we use the initial P that should be
the the point that that it aligns around
right so let me just make sure
here's sprite values for upright so
inside here where we specify the
alignment of this thing we do subtract
backwards based on the alignment X and
alignment Y so if the alignment is at
the base of that thing
then I mean that should do it right like
so I feel like I feel like the only
thing I'm not sure about is what happens
with the min P that that all makes good
sense and the sprite scaled x axis stuff
let me just double check then we can go
see if there's anything else weird going
on there but in here it's want to make
sure this is kosher yeah so that all
looks fine so we start at that base P
and then we push around from there so
yeah I'm not sure why that's stuck in
the ground and and I want to get the
bottom of that first so I'm gonna draw
some of these things because I that's
not good right that's that's not a good
thing
what's happening there so the the fact
that that seems like like this point
here and in fact you know if I look in
the editor here let me pick this cat if
I look in the editor here at where the
points have to be that's way too thick
that stuff needs to be based on like the
screen space size or something
can I get that thinner alright that may
be a little too thin
I know it wasn't even just didn't have
selected there we go
so looking at that I mean you can even
see just like if we look at the
alignment points you can see that it's
to parent alignment point is that red
block right so if that red block is
where the thing was standing why isn't
it you know why isn't it up on this
thing you know I mean that just doesn't
make a lot of sense it seems like it's
not actually placing that entity on any
thing which may be true like for all I
know like it may be that we didn't
actually place this entity on anything
like when we do one of these place
entity calls like that part is a little
bit Squinkie in that you know the
standing on thing I don't like I don't
know is it set to anything I assume it
is but again I don't really know what
happens in that case like it's been a
while since we did anything with that
and so when we do a world position P for
placement I don't know if like the
standing on thing properly overrides
that or what happens there right so I
feel like that is a little bit busted
probably and you know we should double
check to make sure that's all flowing
properly and you know cuz that's a part
of the code that we haven't really
gotten to yet like that's a part of the
code we haven't really pushed on much so
where am I Jenning my cat here you can
see here we create the pending entity
here and the reference to the
traversable is is here
you know and looking at this I guess I
would say I can't quite tell but that
does look wrong if that's the like here
we've created an entity for the for the
floor right and we've said that the
traversable on it is at zero zero zero
but when we push a piece on there and
you know we can look it like this stuff
when we push a piece on there all this
stuff comes into play and like who knows
you know is the zero zero actually there
or not like we've got all this nonsense
going on here and these offsets and all
this other stuff so you know we got to
make sure that this stuff actually is
accurately placed where it should be
placed if the assets location so in this
case like we have a dimension here
that's 0.5 times the wall height and we
offset it by negative 0.5 times the wall
height so if we assume that's a radius
then this is trying to place it
downwards so that 0 0 0 is the correct
location to stand on
so yeah I'm gonna go ahead and draw
whatever those traversable points are
first I think that's the easiest thing
to do because like I said I'm just I'm a
little weirded out right now and I don't
really want to move forwards until I
have a good understanding of what's
happening there so we've got a little
thing for drink - rustles here let's
rien a bat a little bit I don't really
know what this is for
looks like we were drawing some kind of
a rectangle for no real reason so I'm
just gonna go ahead and actually say
let's draw a cube on it
so we know that we've got the entity
ground point here I guess and at least I
think this would give us the position
that we should be looking at there in
terms of the traversable so if I wanted
to draw a cube that would show me where
that was you know I can I can use
essentially this code for drawing a cube
and so if I wanted to put one of these
on there at this location and then
define some kind of a point there you
know maybe it looks like this I'm gonna
use a known color here
maybe magenta and then I'm going to
render that those traversable x'
so you know they're definitely in the
right place so something is busted about
the way we're we're placing the cat on
there and that's what I'd like to
address because before I I'm not gonna
go any further till I have that exact
right so those all look like they're in
in exactly where we think they should be
and so I want to know why the cat isn't
getting placed on to that traversable
properly now one reason could be if
that's not what actually happens
meaning we didn't actually do any code
like maybe we didn't actually do
anything that tries to snap people to
traversable x' meaning if someone's
standing on something maybe that's not
how that works I don't know so I'm gonna
look real quick just to see what happens
when you add a cure oh and I'm gonna see
what happens there so let's see where
that is so in here it looked yeah it
looks like you actually have to do it
looks like you actually have to do this
call for the cat
so I don't know I think we're gonna look
you know look this is code that we want
to go do eventually look later on anyway
so I guess I won't worry about too much
for now but you can see like this is
just a little bit much at this point so
I guess if we just say that
um yeah I guess if we just say that
that's good enough for now
but really we want to get that stuff a
little more automated this is just too
much busy work to be doing here and we
don't need to do it because it's gonna
do this again later anyway so why this
would be happening upfront I have no
idea because entities should just be
placed in in regular sim space to begin
with because that's what we're actually
operating in at the moment so I don't
know what's going on there this this is
just garbage so that seems stupid I
don't remember what the region is called
here just just regular region I guess if
that's dumb and you know before we get
to hot and heavy in that code which will
be more gameplay side of things we
should just clean that up because
there's no need for that that's just
silly so let's see what's going on here
of course that that does not appear to
have helped it definitely moved our cat
to a different place right but it does
not seem to have actually fixed the part
I was interested in so again still not
really helpful here I also where is the
get entity ground points
so we also don't really have you can see
there's just a lot of vestigial remains
stuff here and we don't like look so we
don't even have the notion of identity
ground point anymore and for obvious
reasons because pieces can have offsets
to them already so this stuff is just
irrelevant right so you know this is not
something we would ever need to actually
have because entities would always be
related to wherever they were and the
ground point part of things is not
really a thing like I feel like this is
just not really a thing so I'm
interested to know who's actually using
that and why and the answer is
absolutely no one so what we want to
find out is why is this position not
being in like placing the cat squarely
on the ground like what is the what's
the issue there because we should see
the red point of the cat snap directly
to the purple point of the ground
because that's the initial placement in
theory of what it should be so this is
the thing I want to do here is just
figure out is something else stupid
happening so in here where we highlight
somebody I'm gonna also in addition to
highlighting you know the various other
aspects of this entity I want to just
you know show where's the entity
position you know look where's that at
show me like a white marker or something
at that location
so I can figure out what the heck
happened in terms of its placement
because at the moment anyway I don't
really know and I'm gonna make this a
little bit bigger at the moment I don't
really know whether or not the entity's
position value is wrong or whether the
these transform stuff is wrong and so I
want to eliminate I want to get down to
figuring out which one is the the
culprit before I start trying to bug
anything so looking at the cat from the
underside here if I select it you can
see the white point there so it's the
entity's actual position that's wrong
because the white point is properly
pegged so for whatever reason even
though we were trying to set it so that
it would be there it's actually not
there and we don't know why so we now
have a concrete reason why who's to
blame right and so we want to go figure
out what's displacing the entity's
position in that fashion and so that in
theory anyway is like the the get sim
space traversable thing we were
recalling here oh haha so I think I know
why that would be the case so if you
look at what happens here in the room
gem so if we're gonna call this function
you'll notice we don't place this entity
until here right and so really we
probably need to wait to do this
somewhere else so we kind of want to do
something more like this I guess
because if we plate we have to place
this entity before we can place an
entity onto it right so we kind of want
to do this and we want to do this only
if the traversable count is one I guess
so now will will have actually placed
the floor tile prior to calling the
placement of the entity onto the floor
tile and lo and behold now we're
actually doing the thing correctly right
and so now if I actually look at this
this this cat here you can see that it's
it's welded properly to the to the floor
the way that I would expect
unfortunately as with like one of the
reasons we need a proper debug camera
here is I can't really focus on that as
well as I would like you know I'd like
to be able to to zoom in on just that
thing and so that's why we really we
really really need a debug camera at
some point here a real one
because otherwise we'll never be able to
edit this stuff properly but that looks
about right and so if I look at the
alignment points here now and we whoops
that's the head in theory like you know
if you were to place it so that it's
square on there it would look exactly as
it should yeah like it lines up exactly
as it should uh and so yeah just like
this is exactly what I would have
expected to have happen and it looks
correct and now you can also see this is
the thing I was talking about before
about how we need some idea of how we
want to bias the Z values because if
you're sitting on the center you
actually have a part of your sprite that
will naturally dip below and so we need
to you know we're the problem is a
sprite encode stuff that technically
comes out this way
in negative Y and the renderer doesn't
know that so it just thinks it's a plate
that's extending down into the ground
and so that's the part not be able to
see the bottom of that cat is the part
there that I was talking about and you
know that's about biasing those Z values
so that we don't have that issue but
otherwise now that's all correct and now
we can also do what I want to do before
with like offsetting these sprites so
now oops so now when we create these
entities we should be able to use this
the piece offsets themselves to make the
sprites be offset in Z offset in Z in
various ways that would allow them to
sort of shift location a little bit more
to in terms of how that wants to happen
the only thing that's a little confusing
is I almost feel like you want these
peace offsets in this case to be
relative to some coordinate system on
the actual sprite so Z would actually
come off this way and x and y would be
the other way
as opposed to it being being interpreted
in the world space which seems less
useful you know so for example if I say
that the head is displaced that way I
feel like you really want that to mean
in the plane of the sprite not in the
world so I'm not sure I'm explaining
this well but like you can kind of see
how that displaced this right I'm not
sure to what extent that actually makes
sense you know maybe it's fine what to
see so I feel like that's something we
got to think about a little bit more to
hard to say but the good news is like
all that stuff just kind of works so
that's fine
where's the other cat where's the other
kind
that would be about how that would look
because I'm not sure where that piece
should be probably like there may be
kissing ish
so yeah I think that's about right in
terms of placing the cat I don't know
how big cats should be that's sort of
another question
it's like that's sort of right maybe
goose cats are obviously harder cuz we
don't really have a real ghost effect at
the moment anyway but you know you can
see that it's translucent Hanno's
translucent at the moment because she is
a ghost cat so I guess that's all fine
and yeah
I guess that's all fine and dandy um so
yeah so for now like that would just
work like I was saying before we don't
really have any we don't really have any
issues with saving stuff and reloading
it like if I saved and reloaded here we
would get back to presumably all those
cats would be a line the same way that
they were you can see there we got that
going where the other cats are here
right like so and so I think that is all
we need for if we just wanted the HHA so
the only other thing we would need is
for permanent archival storage and for
now I'm just gonna say like maybe we
ignore that maybe we put that off I
don't know we could we could definitely
put it off until such time as we wanted
to actually rebuild hhas or something
and then we could try doing that where
we you know have a thing which dumps all
of the things out to texture man HHA and
something like this so I don't really
know right it's hard to say I'm not sure
how I feel about it one way or the other
so I think what I'd rather do honestly
yeah I'd rather just kind of go forward
with other more pressing concerns
because like again like having the HHA
there is now fine with me I don't know
like
yeah I don't know what I will say is we
should probably start keeping track of
all the stuff that we should have to do
and maybe we can use I don't know we can
use the github for that or something
unfortunately the github has gotten a
little bit owners lately because you
know I I don't really have a way of
signing on to it very easily I don't
think I don't know if I did it here oh I
guess we did so if we know how do I get
to oh okay I see yeah right look if I
sign in here I can't actually do it
because I need to do two two-factor
authentication to actually log in right
so that's gonna say we could start
trying to keep it to do list on there
because that way we can actually
everyone can see it
who's on the private github but I'll try
logging in later after the stream I'll
grab my phone maybe try to keep myself
logged in so we can use it so yeah
looking at the situation here I guess
what I would say is
there's just a lot of things we could be
working on and I'm not sure which one of
them's which ones I actually want to do
I kind of want to just start playing
around with it we've got so much stuff
though that that's like on the to-do
list now like everything could be on a
to-do list right um so I don't know what
I want to do exactly who knows what I do
think maybe I'll do at the moment so I'm
just looking at like this stuff and I'm
thinking about the fact that ideally we
want you know there always to be stuff
we don't really want a scene where
there's just nothing there you know on
the you know having like nothing on the
outside seems bad and so you know ever
there should always be like tiles out
here probably to like you know that fill
out further I'd like to do something
that I want to make the camera work
properly the camera doesn't seem to be
right at the moment like you see that
weird discontinuity when it goes between
centering on rooms that's what's very
strange I'm not sure what's happening
there the lighting the projection code
is also wrong did you notice that
so like first we have some kind of bug
in our scene production that's like not
actually correctly projecting where the
lighting band should be you know what I
mean so that was pretty weird too so we
just have so many things that I'm
looking at now I'm kind of overwhelmed
by all the stuff that I could do and I'm
not sure which of it I should do first
just really hard to say so let's let's
see what else we have for stuff
so inside handmade art what do we
actually put in like we got grass stone
floor we got the walls we got the cats
we put the cats in there without Krampus
and Krampus isn't in there yet we also
have some monsters that we haven't put
in yet we've got ground cover we got the
hand
got hats here's some trees and stuff
Chris don't ask me why windows can't
show this alpha why's got title screen
yeah so mostly yeah I mean like one
thing I'm not we haven't really talked
about is how to scatter stuff around so
like okay so this it loaded it with
alpha this time apparently I had no idea
why so if we look at the like something
like these forest obstacles right I do
think you know these are some things we
want it like one of the reasons we have
these is we were sort of thinking about
how are they gonna look I think these
are probably at a set up fairly
reasonable like a stray Leary's large
but I do wonder like you know if these
were three different Tufts of the tree
it'll probably work better because then
as they slid relative to each other they
would probably look a little bit better
I'm just guessing because they wouldn't
be yeah I don't really know if that's
true but like I do think like maybe like
the Tufts at the top and these should be
like separated out that's hard to say
but you know looking at furniture like
the lamps and stuff here and these
things get to try and get these in there
and I don't again really know like one
of the ideas here was for us to start
thinking about how these things should
be labeled and brought in and so you
know looking at these I'm like well how
would we label these things
it's like a throw rug there's like
tables
you know and they just don't really have
any association with each other they're
just things that happen to be in the
orphanage so I feel like they probably
want to be broken into like separate
files to a certain extent there we're
like you know you would probably have
each file then you would just text name
it what it was actually gonna be
yeah I really don't know I really don't
know
I wonder what it is that makes it so it
shows alpha or not like why does it show
alpha sometimes on the forest obstacles
and sometimes it doesn't like did you
notice it's it's got it now right the
Alpha composited this time right so why
what what what is it what's the magic
like this time it didn't it's kind of
magic like you what I it's like how it's
almost a game to figure out how
Microsoft wrote that code like I would
how do they make it so sometimes the off
deposit works sometimes it doesn't like
what why don't they do and if you zoom
in far enough it does it comes back you
know so yeah I don't know I really don't
know what we should be doing right now
so let's let's think about this so we
want to get our characters in there so
we can get like the hopping and stuff
working too and like this cuz right now
we were sort of worth worrying about how
we're gonna tag that and the camera
stuff or we can we get outside yet so we
should make it so that the outside
generates an outside right I mean that
seems like something reasonable to be
doing so in here like we have like stone
floor and stuff like that and so you
know maybe we should also make a thing
that's like is there you know look the
on boundary thing it's like you know if
outdoors
boundary equals false kind of thing so
basically like there's some kind of rim
spec thing and like the rim spec just
says if it's outdoors and again we're
this is not real code
this is totally fake i I'm just hacking
these things in there this stuff will
get developed quite a bit more when we
actually want to push on it hard but I'm
kind of just putting in the things that
we might you know showing some things
you might want to do so that we can get
educated about how we want that code to
look so we can look a bit if the spec
outdoors then we don't have walls and if
it is outdoors then you know we would
need to not set this stuff right so we
would say tag floor and stone floor or
whatever we would need to set the grass
stuff up so like that
so we mean to do like okay if outdoors
we have a different kind than
you know this is gonna be like tag grass
or something and that way we can say
that some things outdoors and it will
get generated as outdoors of course you
know it's not really doing much but at
least we can sort of see what that would
look like and so then in here where when
we look at like the forest paths and
stuff like that when we create those we
can just say that those were supposed to
be outdoors and then you know it will
get generated that way so in here we've
got like you know the garden and the
forests back I think are the two and so
I don't remember when we were sort of
mucking with that but I guess just here
so if we look at those two maybe I
dropped them here like the garden spec
outdoors equals true and the basic
forests back outdoors equals true and
then those will be like set to be
outdoors areas which just you know it's
really basic at the moment but so I
think wasn't there like a backyard path
over here or something yeah so like this
is outside this is like the garden area
right I should also probably turn off
those attachment points for the moment
because we don't really need to be
seeing those probably put this on a on a
debug thing as well so we can turn it on
and off oops
sorry about that um so yeah like
you know those don't have walls around
them which is fine you should probably
put like trees in there or something or
who knows what and then yeah like out
there there's also you know this parts
forest path as well so that's all fine
that all seems reasonable uh so I want
to see what I maybe want to focus on now
is just like let's let's improve that
camera code a little bit and because I
don't really want to go work on it
there's just there's enough things to
work on here that I'm not sure which one
would be the best but the camera is
constantly annoying me and so being able
to work with that a little bit better
would probably be a big improvement
because right now like I totally can't
do anything with that and also we've got
that lighting projection problem so you
can see that like even though I can see
around these other areas it's not
actually properly picking where the
lighting should be occurring right so
and I and there's a lot of reasons for
that but you know a lot of them have to
do with the fact that I think that code
was not taking into account the
perspective and the angle very well and
so and and I don't know exactly how we
really want to do that going forwards so
yeah and you know if you look at the
area that we're simulating right is much
larger it would be nice if our lighting
was more about what was visible and you
know we may be able to kind of move more
towards stuff like that as we improve
how the lighting actually works but at
the moment anyway we're kind of we're
kind of we only have like rudimentary
quality on the lighting which is
unfortunate but anyway and you know like
you said you can see why I'm reticent to
give it up though because you get nice
results from it right like even just
looking down there this is just a much
more interesting looking space with
crappy lighting then over here which is
what it would look like with no lighting
like you don't want to really explore
that you do kind of want to explore that
and so I really that redoubles my
assumptions that we really want the
lighting to be good and we probably want
to spend some time on it continuing to
spend time on it getting it good because
that is what we want almost it's a speed
issue it's really just speed I mean what
we have right now is actually quite good
lighting in a sense but this lead is
horrible and so we need to yeah make
that not be horrible so moving on from
here I think yeah maybe just looking at
the camera how much time I have but
let's maybe we can start opening up the
camera I could also do recycling texture
handles those the two things come to
mind what time do how much time do we
have left
which time do we have left how do I know
how long has the stream been live one
hour and 56 minutes so probably two so
we probably have about 20 minutes to go
25 minutes to go do we start at like 115
maybe so I think we've got like I think
we've maybe got yeah maybe got 25
minutes to go missing uh so what I want
to do with the camera there's a lot of
kind of crappy stuff that's happening
with the camera at the moment and I
would like the camera to not be crappy
and so I think we want to do is like
force the camera to be good and to
actually the right thing in in you know
in terms of how its represented
coordinate system wise and so on do we
need any of this stuff we don't need it
this this has been long long forgotten
code so you know the way that this stuff
works right we've got we've got all this
stuff you know here's update camera for
entity movement right and we say like
hey here's the the camera that we're
looking at and here's the sim region and
and we've got like what any of the
camera supposed to be following you know
and that's not bad like that that seems
totally reasonable as a call so that
seems fine I don't care about the debug
white P by the way
yeah I don't I don't know that we care
about that very much but can we still do
this by the way does this mean we can
carry a light around with us maybe I do
care about it because I would like it to
keep happening so in here we've got the
group the diva light be the radius the
color the emission and the lighting
point state so what it was it
complaining about that actually looks
right doesn't it Oh this appears to be
the problem
so can we carry a light around with us
if we do this yes we can that might be
good for the time being since we don't
really have our lighting solid that's
probably better right yeah
now we're just a hopping light cube
what's the problem it's fine all right
so let's talk about the camera now that
we you know now we've got a like a
marker for our entity and I can carry
the light around with me so a couple
things you want to do first of all we
never want to see a lighting edge so
like that crap up there should never
happen we want to set the the fog value
like we want to have some notion of
where the fogging should happen and
where alpha fading should happen for for
upper floors and crap like that and did
that just hop through duh it hopped up
on top
no it upped it hop through
so I'm allowed to actually hop to a
traversable that is that far away
why is that so I can't hop through
double walls but I can't hop through
single walls I guess that's the search
region for the traversable is just that
far away seems ill-advised to say the
least
just out of curiosity why did we do that
I'm just curious I have no idea why we
did it that way left a look so yeah I
just feel like we shouldn't be able to
hop through those and I'm not sure why
we can I assume it's because the hop
distance here is just too much and
should be much less than it is so
there's one that actually works more
properly right I don't know how far
apart the tiles actually are like I
don't know what we actually set our
scale to in that case but now that's at
least correct and it can't get through
walls all right sorry about that just
notice that I didn't know really what
was going on there so I figured we might
as well take care of that issue all
right so yeah again back to the camera
thing so there's a couple things that I
would like to do here one is that I
would like the camera to behave in a
number of ways it's not behaving now so
first of all like the way the debug
camera works right now you can kind of
see that the debug camera is actually
just a displacement off of whatever the
simulation region center is which means
that as I hop from room to room it
actually shifts the camera I don't
actually want that to be true if I
switch into debug camera mode I would
like the camera to just stay exactly
where it is
right and if I want to move to a new
location I will tell you but I don't
really want that to be happening
asynchronously of my commands just based
on you know the movement of it in some
separate sense so I want to be able to
represent a debug location and a regular
location both and so that should
probably happen I'd also like to make it
so that the movement of the camera is
always guaranteed to be seamless so the
fact that this right now
this part here can happen at all is
annoying and I think it's because we
don't map the camera into world
positions and back but we should right
so like that's just bad
and we don't really want that to happen
finally we want there to be a way that
says look find out where you have to be
to view this room like right now we've
got some kind of crappy like thing in
there that that I don't know is like
using some kind of heuristic to figure
out how far back the camera should be
and I don't want that to happen I want
to basically say look this is the region
that you should be able to view you get
some exposure control in there this is
the region that you should be able to
view so I want to be able to to always
guarantee that the entire room that I
asked for will be in there in there and
I guess the thing that we didn't I think
we actually we basically said look some
rooms are gonna be big and they're gonna
scroll so I think that's why we did it
this way but what that means is the
camera should also if we're in a room
that we have to scroll to view that
should be handled right so this the
camera should should gradually scroll up
if you're in this region to show you the
part that you were in and it should
gradually scroll down in this case to
show you the part that you're in now and
left-to-right or whatever so larger
rooms should scroll and we don't have
any of that in there now so there's a
ton of things that we can improve about
the camera and that's what we should
probably start on the main thing I'll
start on now is just none no more
Kitching so like none no more of that
hitching nonsense by the way what
happens if I just make the world dark
just curious
that's pretty cool
[Music]
all right so let's fix this camera let's
find out what the heck is going on with
our camera and and let's try to do
something that's not so horrible so
first things first how restore on the
camera and why and what kind of crap did
we pull in here that's making it lousy
so we've got this notion of the game
camera and it's set up in here it's
saying here's the entity that I'm
looking for here's where I am it's got
the simulation center the offsets the
target P all this stuff right in special
so the first thing I want to know is why
like what's all this garbage why why are
these things why do we even have an
offset Z right like why is that even
there why aren't we just interpolating
our world positions and look why are we
storing the simulation center why is any
of that stuff happening right and I
assume that the that the problem that
we're having the basic problem that
we're having is we don't really know
where the simulation center should be
[Music]
without knowing like without knowing
what the entity is in a sense right and
without knowing what room were supposed
to be highlighting right so I guess the
reason we have to store that simulation
center is because that has to move
around right like we have to be able to
go like okay here's where the simulation
center is going to be and here's where
the P is and whatever and so we kind of
want to go into this with a little bit
of trepidation but you know generally
speaking you can see it's not set up to
stupidly it seems okay right it doesn't
seem totally busted and because this P
and the simulation center because these
things are themselves
absolute world positions I'm not sure
why we're getting that jerkiness so I'd
like to know if I can I would like to
know more about why were we're being
pulled around that way one of the
reasons we may be in some nastiness is
just because we at the moment don't have
any we don't have a real interpolator
like our interpolators kind of crap you
can see this to do right here is is
telling you exactly that but I'm not
sure why we're getting such like we're
still getting pretty unusual results
there's like a discontinuity that
probably shouldn't be there even with
the fact that our camera movements not
good so if we go in here and say all
right let's find out what the camera and
any movement is let's find out how how
and why we're screwing things up so it
is mandatory that the camera Center be
the Scimitar center for this good or
preferably because it cannot add the
offset from the sim center to the camera
as this placement or will fail when
moving with room rooms at the changeover
point
okay
why would that be given the fact that
we're the ones doing the changeover like
we're the people who set the simulation
center differently right like we do that
so you know maybe this is a case of us
just kind of being dumb because the
simulation region itself should always
be the simulation center and if we're
going to reset the simulation center
that should only happen after we've done
all of the camera computations anyway
when we go to call this
we don't do anything else after that
so I don't know that yeah I mean you
know that happens that's the last thing
you do and mandatorily so
so I'm not really sure I also don't know
why this wouldn't just have the camera
being entity in the world who had it
updates itself that's something that
happens is the last thing it wants to do
but all right so there's a lot of stuff
that I'm not sure is on the up-and-up
here we're gonna start by assuming that
it's okay to do this at the end and what
I'm gonna say there is look we know
where the simulation center is and the
simulation center always came from the
camera to begin with right like when we
go here to set the simulation center
inside like begin sim or whatever right
so inside that we specifically say that
you know this is where we want the to
start things off right and so we know
that right up until here you're always
using that Center anyway so I'm not sure
I'm not even sure why it thinks this is
true
because who cares what that simulation
center was as long as you just always
call map into chunk space for whatever
the current region is who cares what you
set this to and when like as long as you
set it at the end of the routine you
don't use it for anything why would we
care
and like even this this looks just wrong
like why would we yeah so I'm just gonna
say I don't believe this and you know I
don't know that that that's what should
have been happening in the first place
so looking at this stuff this pre pass
we can do more work on later this this
isn't really the problem here this is
just for identifying special camera
locations or things like that that that
you know whatever we can talk about that
some other time because that's not the
problem here we're assuming that we're
just not doing any special camera so if
we're in a room you can see us saying
look the simulation center should be the
center of the room because that's how we
kind of wanted to find this game meaning
we're simulating stuff around room
boundaries so that's fine
and if we look at stuff like the target
P and the target offset and all that
crap I mean that seems fine for now we
know this code doesn't matter for the
moment and so when we let me go here and
we say all right the candy series is
mapping chunk space this thing the
target P is map into chunks base this
thing and the target of a offsets gonna
be this then you know the thing that
strikes me is as busted is this is now
dependent on this change and so it's
gonna be wrong for one frame but why
didn't we just do it over here you know
what I mean so so this just seems dumb
right it just doesn't it doesn't add up
like it seems like I don't know if if we
were just like if we just got confused
when we wrote it originally or if we
like maybe we weren't really thinking
about it right or maybe it was because
we were like coming at it from the wrong
we like have it working one way and you
know as we changed it we came the other
way but you know this is this should
just be a based around the simulation
center I mean that's what it should be
because the camera is just another thing
that should get mapped into that space
and we shouldn't have to do this at all
in other words this should be the region
origin if anything else right it should
it should be this right it should not
matter what the camera simulation center
thinks it is these things are things
that are happening relative to the sim
space anyway so just do them in that
space right and then when you map them
in you know off you go and that way we
could also map this more at the outset
and things would probably be better
there too but that's sort of a separate
issue right so I'm not sure why we
wanted to use the simulation center at
something I can't say exactly whether
would have caused any bugs per se but
just doesn't seem a good idea because
everything in this game should be based
around the simulation region always and
the fact that the camera stores what the
next frame simulation center would be
should not change the fact that
everything should always be happening in
subspace because otherwise you've got
two different spaces potentially and
that just further adds to the confusion
right and and there's no point to it
so I would say like we would rather do
this for sure now again I'm just gonna
double check that that runs okay because
I think it should I still don't know
where our bug was coming from though
like we were having sort of a strange
like hiccup bug there and I I don't know
where that's coming from so like you
could do you see it you see that weird
like the height maybe is what changes
discontinuity discontinuously and so
it's like the offset Z's are are
happening weirdly and I
I guess that but that makes sense too in
a way because the cameras offset Z has
to be based we have to be interpolating
the position so the offset Z is not what
you want this camera offset Z should
never really be there and the camera
target P P and target P those should
actually just have the Z in them
directly right I mean that's probably
how we should have been doing it but you
know I guess we weren't so oops but
looking at how that's going you know
what you like I said why is this even a
thing you know why aren't we just saying
well the target P should include
whatever the offset Z is and you should
just interpolate to it right I mean why
isn't it just this
because this is a position it's saying
look I want to go from here to here and
that's what I'm doing
when we compute where we would like it
to go sure talking in terms of an offset
Z maybe something we want to do because
it just helps us construct the final
target but why would we have that be
something that's maintained separately
for no apparent reason and I don't know
why right like the Delta should just
work you know in this case and we
shouldn't have to worry about all these
weird like offset Z nonsenses because
who cares right so this should not be a
thing and yeah I mean I don't know what
to say other than it shouldn't be a
thing
yes so in terms of get camera rectangle
at target in this case what we'd like to
do is say in terms of the Z here we want
to just know we want to know for the
point that we're actually stimulating
around right
so forget camera rectangle at Target
even this this world camera rect just
isn't very smart because again that's
it's not a rectangle it's a frustum now
you know what I mean
and so this is kind of just not right
yeah so a lot of that stuff is kind of
stupid and I'm not sure really how else
to describe it other than that let's
look at how these things are actually
written in here and you know I'm gonna
I'm gonna hack this in in a second I'm
gonna well are right now I'm just gonna
say like alright suppose it's eight
units away who cares I don't care right
now but let's let's look through that
code a little bit more cleanly and see
what happened what's the problem here
just our particle systems were unhappy
about that so now what I want to see is
like look when we're when we're
interpolating now I expect this to be
always correct so I want to know why
we're getting an offset there because if
we're just interpolating only two you
know just those two positions so we're
just interpreting a p2 another you know
p2p I want to find out where our
discontinuity is coming from why the
frame boundary is causing it because I
should be able now if I'm always using
the simulation origin I should now
always be able to unpack the cameras
location relative to that simulation
boundary and that should give me what I
want right in other words this is always
in in
absolute space now so it shouldn't be
able to be wrong even across a frame
boundary and so we need to go find out
why it is like what's going on there
that would be incorrect does that make
sense so let's go see how we're
unpacking that so in update in render
worlds when do I actually create
so there's my Z rotations so yeah so
this actually is fine right because it's
gonna be this is where things are going
to be unpacked relative to as well so
this should still work
and so I think like yeah like the reason
that we had been doing it the other way
is I think we were maybe thinking
something else was causing frame hiccups
but it wasn't that but that is actually
what the problem is you know and so I
feel like we need to find out what the
real cause was and I think we were just
papering over it by assuming that for
some reason you couldn't do it in
absolute space but you totally can like
that should just work right because the
relative subtractions should still
produce the same results that's my story
and I'm sticking to it
right because this simulation center is
now is that's going to be zero zero zero
and so when we packed the camera into
this origin it's just about where we
unpacked it before and when we unpacked
it we need to make sure we always unpack
like the camera what is it called the
simulation center
yeah as long as we always map everything
relative to the origin of the simulation
region that should always be correct and
then as long as we set the simulation
center correctly what is Delta from sim
yeah that's that's fine
so when we begin the simulation mmm
when do we set this yes so we set the
simulation centre here so everything
will be unpacked relative to that which
is what we want right that's good
so I'm not sure where else we could have
introduced a bad thing there we look at
the focal length look at the cameras Z
it's just whatever we got out of that
column right get the OT what the heck is
camera offset okay so that'll be zero
so that could just be removed that's
better world mode camera dolly should be
set to zero
always unless we're doing debugging so
this should also just be zero and in
fact always is so not really sure why we
had that either
so this is complete nonsense and
probably explains why we were getting
the bugs before so if you look at this
we were saying here's the rotation of
the camera right but that means that
we're actually taking where we said the
camera was and rotating it to line up
with the with the pitch right but we
still don't want to do that right what
we want to do is make sure that we use
that pitch to figure out where we wanted
the camera to be and then that just
should get rolled into the Delta right
because otherwise we've got otherwise
we've got interpolation yeah like this
this was this is just um so let me say a
little bit about this first because like
when we were hacking this together we
probably didn't go over it very well
when you're doing animation
interpolation generally speaking you
want to make sure that you actually
interpolate things in the way that they
really exist
so parametric constructions that are the
kind we add here where we're like oh
let's let's take a location and then
back up from it and Bend that around and
then here's where the thing is
interpolating in that parameter space is
almost never a good idea and the reason
it isn't is because the viewer usually
expects things to be smooth in the
absolute parameter space like outside of
it because they're thinking of this as
like a camera moving through space they
don't want it to be smooth in the
parameter system of the cameras that
doesn't make any sense so then you end
up constantly fighting that so this is
bad and should not have happened and so
we want this stuff to actually be
something that's set up more in the
intro in the camera side of things you
know not here so the debug camera will
address in a second because that's again
a sort of a separate issue but let me
just take a look at what's going on here
now so now I don't think we'll get any
hiccups at all right and you can see
that we're not because now we're
interpolating for
to frame and look at how nice and clean
that is so that's how we should have
been doing it before but I don't know I
just had like you know a lard head that
day or whatever and so it was screwed up
so what we want to do now is in that
camera code we want to go add that lean
in there am i say lean i mean david lean
the director who made Lawrence of Arabia
we want to go in there and have that
lean be part of the camera offset so
that it it correctly figures out where
the actual camera would be in world
space based on how we want the camera
tilted right um and so that's you know
that's what we actually want to do here
so you know off we go so in here we get
the camera Z out what we want to do is
send that camera Z when we're actually
doing the look where's the camera right
we want to pass that in so that when we
do update the the camera in here it
knows like you know what that vector
would have been so then when we do the
displacement we just say oh if that's
what you like to look down if that's how
you're looking down then what we'll do
is we'll set the location to be you know
when we're creating one of these things
here where we asked for where the target
is going to be you know we'll say well
the target P is whatever it should have
been offset you know for lies we'll just
multiply by that vector so that now
we're actually going to move you back
along the Tilted vector so that you
still look down on it but I mean all of
that gets rolled into the desired target
location not so we're not feeding
forward a bunch of hard to interpolate
values so now we can still look at the
center but we notice how clean the
interpolation is no bugs and there's
none of this garbage to do up at the top
or garbage note from me saying that
there is some nonsense about having to
have them line up frame by frame right
so now the interpolation is exactly
perfect and we never have any of that
our interpolator still sucks don't get
me wrong it's a weird exponential frame
based in term
litter which is terrible so we want to
fix that but at least now there's no
jarring things that's just it's buttery
smooth and we got it buttery sirs by
removing code right because I had extra
code in there that was stupid and adding
stupid code doesn't make it better it
makes it worse just ask the C++ standard
committee they've been doing it for 30
years so what we want to do now is we
want to go fix the projection part of
this because like I said we now need to
have a good way of figuring out where
that lighting region is I won't do that
now cuz that's a good thing to start on
next week I mean next time next dream
but that's what we wanted to fix there
so that's that's so much better and I
apologize for not just typing that in
the first place but off we go so I'll go
to a brief Q&amp;A now and take any
questions and then we'll wrap it up for
today
JMC 5:16 have you ever found yourself
angry with something in the game maybe
the progress of a certain part if so how
do you get past it
I usually don't look at it that way I'm
always angry with the state of my code
and that is just what makes me keep
trying to make things better I guess if
you always think all the code is
terrible then that does help in a sense
because it means that you don't
necessarily have any more motivation to
do one part than any other book part so
you're free to make other decisions
because you're always like well
everything in this game could use work
so if this seems like the most high
priority thing I'll just go do it
because it's as valid to work on as
anything else are you playing to switch
up the interpolation with a smooth damp
function i I would say that I don't
super care for the jargon smooth steps
smooth damp things like this I I don't
know why we have those names I worked in
animation for you know code for five
years six years something like that and
I just prefer to be more specific about
it right so what I will be switching the
camera to is either second order or
third order interpolator
that uses the velocity of the camera at
the current time as a constraint that is
what I will be switching it to do you
ever feel like everything needs to work
to the point it's demotivating you're
not even sure or everything needs work
to the point where it's too motivating
you're not even sure to start yes and no
so here's what I would say in a perfect
world where I just had funding to do
whatever I wanted all the time and the
things Fermat thought magical it never
would demotivate me because I always
want to work on all of it so I just work
on it and I wouldn't mind so really the
part that's the motivating
realizing that you will never have
enough time to do stuff before it has to
go out the door or you just become
bankrupt and poor and whatever and so if
I worked in a research lab I would never
be demotivated like ever because I
always want to work on it but in the
real world yes it can be de motivating
cuz you're just like I can never I'm
never gonna get all this done you know
and so that's unfortunate
right but it's that's just true for
everything I mean no matter what you do
it's always true that you could have
done more even if you use a licensed
engine and plugins and used as much
off-the-shelf stuff as you could
whatever the part is that you're making
you coulda done more right it's almost
never it's only if you have a very
limited idea of the possibilities that
you'd ever be like well that's perfect
right like so it's just something you
have to live with you know it's
unfortunate but it's also in some sense
you could look at it in a positive light
in that hey it means that as long as we
still have some market for shipping this
stuff there will always be work to do
because there's always things you could
have improved on in your previous time
you did it so you never have to think
about it it's like well I mean we're
just done now right
Carrie Johansson so we've been debating
the merits of using a garbage collected
language like go in a network situation
where you have absolutely no prediction
of what data load will be coming in do
you think a language let go would be a
good choice I feel like you've answered
a question like this but I honestly
don't remember response um I guess what
I would say is garbage collection
doesn't really ever seem to solve
problems for me that I care about
because the way I would state it is that
garbage collection isn't garbage
collection is not you is not solving
memory allocation in any way that
anything else doesn't solve it right
it's just one way of managing your
memory and so if the answer is that
garbage collection is the optimal way to
manage the memory then I could have
written something that effectively did
that right and so at that point it's
like well is using go better than doing
that sure probably I mean I trust that
they probably wrote a good garbage
collector for whatever they were doing
and so that seems reasonable but
identifying an actual real-world
situation where garbage collection was
the most efficient way to manage the
memory I can't really even think of one
I've certainly never seen one and
usually what garbage collection is is an
excuse for you to not figure out what
the optimal way to manage the memory was
and so a lot of times when you talk
about garbage collection what you're
really talking about is do I want to
save programming time not worrying about
memory management that's very different
than saying I wanted to write the proper
program here and so it's just worth
understanding what you're actually doing
so I would say if you're choosing go
in a sense what you're saying is I am
okay with this code performing worse
than it should in exchange for me not
doing some certain work and that's very
different from saying it was a good
technical decision it may be a good
managerial decision but garbage
collection is almost never a good
technical decision because you could
have probably done a much better job if
you thought about how the memory should
work right so I would really emphasize
splitting those two things apart because
that's usually where the arguments start
if someone's arguing that garbage
collection was actually the best way to
manage the memory they're probably wrong
it almost never is
maybe there's a circumstance where it is
literally indistinguishable from what
you would have done optimally but that's
almost never true so really the only
arguments made for for garbage
collection is managerial here are some
reasons the programmers on this project
aren't good enough to deal with memory
totally valid managerial decision if
they aren't use a garbage collector
it might work right they might still
screw it up because garbage collectors
can't fix things where you leave
references around that it doesn't know
you're done with right so you can still
screw up but you know that's a totally
totally reason I'm Angelo decision the
partners loss pressures aren't good
enough to the amount of analysis and
work we'll have to do to get the memory
memory management correct isn't going to
be worth it on this project because we
don't have the time or we don't have the
resources or we'd rather do something
else or our competition is all terrible
anyway so we will still be faster than
them even if we don't do a very good job
right all of those are also valid
managerial decisions so you know just
understand what you're arguing about and
if you're arguing about some of those
things I want to save my team time I
don't think that seems good enough we've
had a lot of bugs like this in the past
so we just assume we can't really handle
it properly
bla bla bla bla all valid
managerial decisions valid arguments
garbage collection is good at managing
memory here probably not a valid
argument like probably just not
is it better to work on a fun task or a
test is more important if you have
limited time that's a tough decision
because one of the things about fun
tasks is you may get them done quicker
or you may do a higher quality of work
on them so I feel like that's a really
tough thing to answer obviously a more
important task is more important to do
so you should probably do it instead of
the fun task but if you're going to be
doing lousy work or you're
procrastinating all the time and the
more important task isn't getting done
maybe switching to the fun task for a
little while is a good idea
and no we don't this is a procedural
game so there's no scripting language in
it all right I'm gonna wrap it up yeah
again on that garbage section front I
would really encourage people to think
to make sure they know what they're
arguing about when the argument things
like that and you know garbage garbage
collection just it's really usually not
worth arguing about also because it's
just like I think the answers are very
clear right garbage collection is never
the best code pretty much ever I don't
think I've ever seen a situation where
garbage collection is going to be the
most efficient way to run that code
right and so as long as we agree on that
then we're really just talking about
managerial decisions and those are very
fuzzy so I don't know that there's that
much arguing you could really do like
you know sometimes it's clear-cut these
programmers are beginners they don't
even know what a pointer is like use
garbage collection and come on like
they're gonna screw it up it's fine but
if you have a bunch of experts and they
really know what they're doing should be
using guard section I don't know how
complicated is the code is it editing
based how much realistic flexibility is
there and how much the asset space is
and so and so forth you know do we have
to get this done extremely quickly maybe
we just don't want to think about it and
performance isn't the issue you know and
hopefully we can all make a reasonable
decision there I mean we know what it is
it's it's not like it's weird what
garbage suction does it's very obvious
what it does and how it does it so you
know and so really the only thing I
would encourage you let's say it's like
let's make sure you get the technicals
down for every section isn't good it's
it's a lousy way to manage memory in
terms of if you're trying to get optimal
performance accept that fact and if we
can if we can accept the fact that
that's true and move on to talking about
whether using a lousy memory manager is
in fact better than then doing it
ourselves
he's a separate discussion and you can
say yes to that you can say yes right
all the code you will ever write in your
whole life
we'll probably not be optimal except
very small tiny maybe little little bits
you know and so it's okay to say we're
gonna do something none optimal here and
we understand that but it's the right
decision
and so that's what but you want to get
that right
don't confuse making a trade-off with
saying that you're doing the right thing
in some abstract sense because that's
not what's going on you're making a
trade-off you're saying let's have worse
performance in exchange for something
and as long as you know what that
something is and you've justified it
well that's a totally reasonable
decision but you don't want to argue as
if you didn't make a trade-off because
you did right
all right what did we change what did I
change it says Save Changes what were
the changes can't tell me what the
changes are no don't change them I guess
I don't even know what the changes were
heaven forfend I didn't mean to make any
changes thank you everyone for joining
me for another so the handmade hereit's
or the pleasure coating with you as
always I felt good to fix that camera
bug was driving me nuts and hey we
simplified that code you notice the
theme of leyte is just simplifying code
now and everything gets better why is
that the case it's the case because
again with exploratory architecture
we're prepaying we don't know exactly
how things should work there's a lot of
slop there and as as things build up and
change and mutate there's garbage code
that's in there and bad ways of doing
things that naturally kind of happened
as we as we brought systems up together
but once we're now at a place now where
we're like yeah this engine is pretty
reasonable and it's got most of things
we need now we can see those areas where
things come together and it becomes
obvious how they can be made much
simpler and work much cleaner and so
we're just go we're just going in there
and cleaning those out right and
cleaning those out
it's like polishing the the artwork
right you know you get this sort of
rough plaster cast of this thing and you
look it off it's all rough and gross and
now he's going in there and like you
know getting it all smooth is like oh
well that's actually quite beautiful
like now that we get to it right and so
you'll see that theme that will continue
to play out over the next few months as
we bring the actual game into a game
state like a actual like this is a game
you'll see me doing that over and over
where like things that were complicated
and weird before now that's clear how
they work they just get nicely polished
over and become a very simple thing you
saw it with the asset system now you're
seeing it with a camera code and that
will continue to be true the renderer
kind of went through that it'll go
through one more time hopefully the
lighting happens that way too but
platings the worst part so that'll be
the harder one but you know it's good to
see right that's a good sign that's not
a sign you screwed up at the sign you
did your job you did the right thing
and you're finally getting to the to the
correct
texture that now you could say hey we
figured it out you got it now all right
so there'll be more surprise streams
coming I can't say when because then
they wouldn't be surprises so you know
keep a keep a check on the live stream
page here and I'll be updating the
schedule as it goes also there's also
that the Twitter you can always check on
the handmade hero Twitter it's got a
it's got a feed that goes on you know
what I'm saying
this thing it'll you know we says when
we're live and and all that stuff so you
can always get on there if you want to -
all right that's it for today remember
if you want to follow along at home you
can always peer to the game on handmade
here Oregon it comes with a source code
so if you want to play around with it
you can just hit that big green button
and you can either it's got a github
thing on there and it's got a source
code download the github is kind of
unsupported but we haven't had any
problems with it yet so seems like it's
pretty good for people like to use that
as an alternate way of getting the
source so go ahead and check that out
and that's about it till next dream have
fun programming everyone and I'll see
you on the Internet take it easy
everybody