thing start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade here on the show we
could complete game live on stream we
are in the middle of doing our profiler
which is pretty baller at this point
we're just kind of like cleaning up some
interface stuff but it's pretty neat all
the stuff I can do and I don't know I'm
pretty excited about it I feel like I'll
probably start using this profiler at
work at some point because it's like
pretty cool and I don't really have a
good one hmmm in our current code base
that's that's it all interesting so
since this one works with
multi-threading and it works with hot
code reloading and it works with you
know stored data over many frames it
just seems like it's kind of like does
everything and I feel like it's probably
something that I should use everywhere
because it's pretty awesome anyway
today is day 262 so if you want to
follow along at home and you're one of
the folks who has pre-order the game on
him a hero org you want to unpack day
261 source code that's what I'm starting
with today I think today basically what
we're doing is just interface II kinds
of stuff basically getting our profiler
to show more of the data that it
actually has because it's got a ton and
we just need to now like add interface
to allow us to easily access that data
in ways that are convenient when we're
developing so right now when we open it
up you can see that I left it in a frame
stack display kind of a thing that's not
that really that useful at the moment so
we're gonna go in and start working with
this today to kind of make I'm gonna
make the the frame graph stuff and I
what I might do I was trying to think if
there was maybe a way to do this I was
also thinking that it might be
interesting to make it so that the the
the elements themselves are proper
properly linked at the top level so that
you don't really need to iterate over
frames as much you can always hit well
I'll show you when we get in there but
point being what I wanted to do we have
like a frame bar kind of thing going oh
I want to do is make it so that we can
see frame bars occurring over time
essentially and so we did some work
yesterday to change the way that we were
sort of storing things to make that
really convenient to do and also to
allow scrubbing and stuff like that a
little bit easier so what I want to do
now is just go ahead and kind of like
explore that so that's really all we're
doing today is getting that stuff going
someone launch for coder here and and
get down to business by the way I am now
using for coder for all my editing
always I now no longer use Emacs
anywhere so I'm a hundred percent for
coder at the moment excellent work Allen
this editor is fantastic and I have had
it crash on me a total of two times for
the entirety of the time that I have
used it and neither of those times were
in work losing scenarios so I have
literally never lost any work with four
code or even though it's like alpha
something something something and barely
even a released version of the thing it
still been like incredibly solid
basically the only crash problems I've
had is shelling out to build like
shelling out to when I go to like do
compiles for some reason once in a blue
moon that will crash probably due to
something fantastic happening with
Windows launching the executable for the
build or something but anyway point
being so I've been loving for a coder
and if you're not on the for coder
bandwagon yet not really sure what to
say
I guess you're just using a lousy editor
sorry anyway let me go ahead and load up
the debug system here and let's take a
look at those frame bars because I had
this sort of draw frame bar situation
and what I want to do is make this draw
frames of our thing work more like what
I wanted because it wasn't really doing
anything that I wanted I just sort of
started it and it was it was not really
done because we decided to reorganize a
day a little bit so what happens in here
when I grab one of these elements and I
come through here and I say draw frame
bars I'm gonna pass down one of these
stored things and that's not really what
I actually want to pass down for drawing
frame bars now the thing that saying
about wanting to harmonize this a little
bit is what you can actually see here
from from what from what we've gotten
the code you can kind of see that
there's like
different paths that have to happen when
reviewing an element that we've
specifically picked because remember you
can click on an element the profile and
we can say like okay the probe is not
going to view this element right and
that's this thing right here where it
gets the grid it like uses the grid to
get a particular element that's going to
view and the problem with that is that
if that's zero then we won't get back a
viewing element right and then we're
going to get a different kind of thing
back we're gonna get a root node back
that came from the frame and if a root
node comes from the frame then it only
has just that frame as the data I think
right meaning it doesn't have what we
want to do I think is past an actual
element down to the rendering code so
that it can go through the frames that
are in there and I just I'm not sure I
don't like the way there's this
dichotomy because now these functions
have to be like aware of whether they're
getting a frame based thing or not and
it's just like I don't like that right
it's creepy it's gonna create multiple
paths through the code and what I'd
rather do is like collapse those things
so that they can be more unified okay
and so what I kind of wanted to point
out here and this is the thing that I
was getting at when I said I'll show you
when we get there is that now if you
look at the way our things are
architected inside a debug element
itself we now have this sort of sub
concept of frames right so inside the
debug element there's a thing called a
debug element frame and that stores all
of these events inside it right and then
those events themselves can have trees
inside them which say like what stuff
got what stuff happened you know - yes
like like children blocks of them or
whatever and so what that means is now
our debug frame this thing right here is
actually kind of redundant right and if
you take a look at the information
that's actually stored in here that we
actually need right it's really just
begin clock and clock and wall
seconds elapsed that's it right that's
all we really would need it to store and
so if we were to somehow make this sort
of this concept of frames here that
we're actually using if instead of using
the root profile note and attaching it
to the frame like this if instead we
just had a debug element that was the
root profile node that could actually
serve as the container for all of those
profiles right and that to me seems like
a much more interesting way to go now
how would we do that right well we're
already sort of doing it because when we
come in here and create the root profile
node we had to get from somewhere
somewhere anyway right so um see here
root node do-do-do-do-do there it is so
here's where we were actually storing
that and you can see when we do this
sort of parent event thing we grab the
root profile node and if that's not
there right we go ahead and we store one
and we store one by using this null
event right which basically creates it
underneath whatever the element is okay
which creates it under whatever the
element is that we were going to use for
everything else right but why why do
that right why not just make an actual
debug element at the start that is the
actual frame element and then that
element can be the one that they are all
stored under and then instead of ever
having this we just make everything go
underneath that we can in fact we can
even still store the real profile node
here but in we just make sure we still
do have a backing element that's always
there so in here when we actually call
the store event thing instead of this
what I want to do is say like there's a
debug state profile element for like
route profile element right
so now like every last thing that's
stored that is one of these route
profile events is in there and that
means we can walk that array which is
going to look like any other frame array
so now all of our frame arrays are going
to look exactly the same and we can
always pass down an element and that
unifies that part of the code which is
what we want right you always want to
look to see if you can collapse things
into using the same format right the
same kind of data because the more
things that you can have it used the
same format of data right the less
proliferation of code paths you have and
that was what we were trying to do and
have continued to do with the debug
system is just sort of proliferate out
to find out what we need but then
condense back down into the smallest
possible set of things that does what we
need that creates efficient more compact
code that'll be easier for us to manage
right even right now we probably got too
much and so over time we just want to
compact that down all right yeah more so
than anything else the best code is less
code right like because the smaller no
matter what you think about clean code
or object-oriented or not I'm trying all
those things the less code you have to
focus on the better it's going to be
usually because it's just less to keep
in your head less to test less to go
wrong right so just like it's just good
so what I'm going to do here is I'm
going to just introduce a debug element
probably actually you know I'll put it
down where we're storing the frame stuff
right so down here we will say debug
element root profile element and then
we'll just create that root profile
element now this will just automatically
work the root profile element we will
have to create when we do our debug
startup right so when we first create
the stuff that we need which is going to
be in debug start when we're not
initialized so like in here right when
we do all of this stuff and create our I
don't even know what this stuff is this
is all really old code when we first
create all this stuff I'm just gonna say
all right oops at that time I'm gonna go
ahead and say
that the root profile element equals
however we create an element in here get
element from event is there a way to
create one without getting it from an
event I think there's one for getting
element from grid right yeah
so here's get element from grid and get
element from grid unfortunately yeah but
see that doesn't actually create it yet
get element from event does actually
create it and since we don't actually
want to do any sort of look up here and
we don't really ever want to create a
debug event for it I'm not sure that
that's actually all that useful for us
but we could you know if we wanted to we
could still make this work that way I
suppose and maybe for regularity
purposes that would make sense but the
other thing we can do is just pull this
code out if we wanted to because there's
really not that much that we would have
to do push struct I'll clear it is there
any initialization that needs to happen
for this thing there isn't right I mean
there's nothing yeah there's nothing
here and it's not in the hash so we
would just need to put it in the hash
somewhere
yeah well I guess I'll just do it this
way I don't think this is necessarily
great but it's alright so if I create a
route profile event and then I just say
get element from event debug state route
profile over parent false I don't want
it to do any hierarchy creation nonsense
I don't want it to do add element to
group either
what does add element to group do if
there is no parent so that seems a
little busted right because it's going
to do an insert on something that isn't
necessarily there so I feel like in this
case the parent group thing it should
really do like if there is a parent
group right because we don't want it to
like insert if there is no parent group
so that seems like a smart thing to do
so yeah so the route profile event
that's gonna be in interface that H what
I'm gonna do here is just be kind of sly
here's the debug event we don't need to
initialize anything at all right
the only thing we need to do is make
sure that this debug event has a grid
associated with it and that grid should
be parsable and so in order to ensure
that it's possible in the same way as
everything else what I'm probably going
to do is just use the debug named
parameter right so I'm just gonna say
root profile event grid equals debug
name and that debug name is just going
to be a root profile node or element
rather or maybe just root profile and so
once that's created then we now have a
root profile element that will store
everything that we needed now I'm just
gonna let this run to make sure that it
works at all and hopefully it will I
don't know if it will or it won't
so yeah that's doing something I don't
like that though we told it not to add
this get element event I told it not to
add so why did it add parent group
equals parent parent is zero in this
case so it should not do an add element
to group here right and it should not do
it should not ever do this because
create hierarchy is also false so I want
to just quickly step in and see why it
decided to do that because I'm just
assuming that that is is what's causing
it although I guess technically it could
also be because of our code up above
right where we do root profile note up
here in theory it could be because of
this part right and so when this is
calling store event I suppose that might
do something like that with the nil
event stuff and I'm not sure about that
you see what that will be
so that store event should not be doing
any of that right that should not be
happening so it feels to me like yeah
like I still bust ice I'm just gonna
step in there real quick I just want to
make sure it's not really bothering
anybody at the moment like we can
continue doing what we were doing even
with that but I just wanted to make sure
I don't want that to be happening
unnecessarily so here we are about to
create that read profile we'll go step
into gentleman from event will call
debug parse name and then we'll call get
element from grid this is just gonna
look through the hash to see if there's
anything there there isn't anything
obviously it's the first thing being
created so that's to be expected or one
of the first ones so then we're going to
add it in we'll copy this the grid out
which is what we want we will use well
we won't create the hierarchy what what
parent parent what is the parent getting
passed I passed a zero there did I not
what did I do
I just did something stupid obviously
obviously so ah it auto fills it in
ah
well obviously that's a problem I'm
gonna hit shift f5 on that and I'll be
honest with you I want to see I'm using
my inside voice right now okay there's
no need to get upset there's no need for
histrionics fear people we're just gonna
make this a very quiet dignified edit so
really really I think what we want to do
here is actually just this I think
that's what we actually want to do yeah
that's it right there all right so now
we're in better shape so basically what
I did was I just said hey guess what the
only time this is getting used is for
for events it should be in the hierarchy
in France it shouldn't we might we never
actually want to add them to a group
when they shouldn't be
that was a vestigial remain for when we
were actually using the add to group
stuff for profile events and we don't
really want that to happen anymore I
don't think so I'm pretty sure that
that's actually how we would prefer
anyway so now we can leave it like that
now that we have done that little
fancy-pants maneuver right with now with
extra pants what we can do is when we
come through the thread into the graph
stuff we can drastically simplify what
this has to consider in order to do the
stuff that I wanted to do and I didn't
want to go write it the other way
because it just would have been a mess
and now we should be able to write it
fairly straightforward so now what
happens is we do this viewing element
thing instead of ever getting events out
of it which we don't need to do anymore
right we can just skip
that part instead of ever getting events
all of it will just say hey get whatever
the element is that you were supposed to
view and then if that's not true
right if there isn't one of those then
we'll just say okay view the root
element view that one this stuff goes
away goodbye and now we just say okay
when we're get whatever we're gonna draw
we're actually gonna draw as an element
now which has all the frames included so
now when we call draw frame bars what we
can do is instead of passing a root node
we pass the viewing element okay so
that's good you know I hate having so
few characters on a line the things I do
for you stream people to keep it so you
can read it I can fit like four times
this text in one of these panels when we
have a higher res display anyway
consider yourself so very lucky all
right well maybe I'll leave that in
there for now so anyway when we do drop
frame bars now when we pass a debug
stored event actually this is gonna be
passing to you about elements and this
is the element this is the root element
that we're doing and so now when we come
through here things should go a little
smoother for us now what we should be
able to do is say okay let's loop
through all of the frames and fernette
you know what I'm just gonna get rid of
this at the moment I'm just gonna say
you know what I don't want this right
now we'll deal with it later so we'll go
through all the frames here's our frame
index zero we're gonna go ahead and say
there's no such thing as that anymore
that's just garbage forget it doesn't
matter and we're just gonna loop through
all of the ones that are in our root
elements frame set right easy peasy
lemon squeezy like so we also know how
many frames there are here because we
just know in fact additives make the
frame count be this
like so frame camped there we go and
then we want to get the profile nude
it's as easy as just saying alright
whatever the element is that we're on we
want to access the frames of that and we
just want to get the profile no doubt of
that
right cuz this remember how this works
right I'm just gonna just gonna pop back
here for a second so we're in one of
these things right and we can grab out
the profile node now of this guy by
taking whichever well I guess there's
multiple events in there right so we're
going to grab this thing out and then we
want to loop over the sub events of this
thing so we can go from oldest to most
recent right although really we could
also say if we're just profiling one of
these we could profile just like the
most recent event because if this is
kind of a little bit of a yeah I think
we want to do them all so I think what
we want to do right is we want to loop
over any any entries that are in this
one that we're viewing so we just
because if there's multiple than we want
to see them all right I think that's
true
so what I want to do is say okay for
each one of these this stuff I'll have
to construct ahead of time right we'll
do that in a second for for each one of
the events in here stored event equals
see what's this going to be called this
is just the route event I guess just
trying to side whether we loop over it
and then do children as well or whether
we just loop over this one I think we
actually just loop over this one we'll
find out in a second so I think this is
probably all we want to draw all right
so instead of like first child and that
sort of stuff right what we want to do
instead is just just loop over the
events that have been entered into this
element right and then if we go down to
a sub element then obviously we can we
loop over those right and what it would
always allow us to do that operation so
in here we'd say okay the story event
that's going to be our route event
oldest event I know what this is doing
here okay so we go through this we say
go from the oldest until there really
aren't any more now why did I delete
that that's actually we wanted and then
we just draw them as before now the the
tricky part here is just going well we
need to know what the actual total
duration was and that I believe is this
part what we want to do right here and
we're not actually updating that yet so
we need to now have that we need to
actually record that span properly right
because we yeah we need that particular
piece of information as we go now I
suppose
hmm I suppose that is a little redundant
as well like the profile node
information stores its individual
duration but we also know you know we
also have the information about the
total clocks that we're sort of saying
read store here and let me just draw
this out because it's a little bit again
I'm just wondering if there's still one
way we can make it a little bit flatter
so here's what's happening at the moment
right so at the moment we have a debug
element and that debug element is the
root profile node or I should say root
profile element right that root profile
element has in it a series of frames
right
and inside one of these it has a series
of events and this is however many
events restored on this particular frame
now we happen to know that for the for
the root this should only ever be one
because we only ever keep everything
under one stored event right but it sort
of strikes me as like since we have the
ability to store multiple things under
here I'm wondering does that actually
mean
we shouldn't have that extra layer right
like we shouldn't bother actually having
we shouldn't make it so there's only one
under here we should just make it so
that all of the events that happen on a
frame at the root actually just add
themselves directly here do you know
what I'm saying and that seems kind of
logical to me so in other words we would
go all right up let's see where it is
inchoate debug records
so in collate debug records when we come
through here to do begin block instead
of saying like if not parent event and
like getting the parent from the root
like collation flame root profile node
instead of that we'd say like no you're
always gonna add this thing as an event
underneath the the standard debug
element right if there isn't a parent so
in other words this if not parent event
thing just wouldn't exist it just goes
away so if there's an open close if
there's an open code block then your
parent is that code block if not
then your parent event is going to be
your parent event is actually just
inside that element meaning there like
there is no parent element right I feel
like that works in other words this
store event right here you just store it
directly in the element and you don't
add it to any parent
so all right here's my argument for why
I don't think you can quite do that and
the reason is because this chaining is
per element right so if I have several
different types of things that happen
during a frame right so I've got you
know I've got like collate records and
I've got you know I don't know whatever
they a game update you know whatever
they are these chains are actually per
one of those and so I think this
actually does have to stay exactly the
way that it is where it's using the
profile nodes and it can't be sort of
sucked out in that way and so when you
actually say hey we're going to draw a
particular set of frame bars here what I
want to do is have it so that I can
access you know all of the frames of
something the problem is the profile
node itself it kind of makes it hard
still even with that even with making it
so that they're all under the same one
so that you can uniformly treat them as
elements it just seems like it's kind of
hard to still work with because that top
one is actually not really it's not a
profile node it's just this sort of
container and so it only will have one
thing on every frame as we go across
frames there's only one thing in it
which is the whole container
maybe that's okay you know maybe that's
fine but I guess that's just something
to be aware of right so as we come
through here and we do frame index right
and we get one of these things we pull
out the root event that we're going for
we can actually we actually can make
this the root profile node because it's
actually would be a profile node so we
can access the profile node like so do
the same things we were doing I think
that still works and then we come
through here we can do the root node
first child like so and that might be
okay right that might be okay not a
member of debug element frame right so
in here the only question is yeah how
many of these do we draw because there
might be multiples but I think in
general we would only want to draw one
particular one of them but maybe like I
said what we would have to do here is
draw we would have to draw all of the
instances of it for ones that weren't
frames so what I'm going to do here is
just do most recent Frank event at the
moment but maybe that needs to sort of
be expanded yeah
and I probably should look to see
whether there is a most recent event as
well if there isn't a most recent event
we probably shouldn't
oops let's make this a debugs for an
event so we'll take a look but like I
said I may have to adjust that a little
bit
so okay so these are the frame bars
exactly as I have actually hoped that
they would be right so as you can see
this kind of gives us now a better idea
of what our performance is over time in
terms of variability so it makes it very
easy to spot frames where things happen
that are unusual right you can see the
pink bars which are like frame which are
asset loading that have like spikes in
here we don't really have any way right
now showing multi-thread stuff on the
frame bars like this so you know they're
just gonna kind of over write the other
ones I'm not sure what the best way is
to draw those exactly but you get the
idea now the thing that I was saying is
I don't think maybe works quite right at
the moment you say I want to drill down
into one of these so let's like move to
here so here's the actual game update
running right and if I come through here
to game update and I want to see this in
more detail if I click on that you can
kind of see now that we've got a game
update and render on here and well I
guess I don't know if game update and
render actually has any sub I think it
should right it's supposed to have some
sub stuff and we don't really see
anything on here right so we're still
like I've still you know it's still just
not quite what I want in terms of
getting that code structured so that you
can drill down properly now if I drill
down again on it then I actually see the
actual bars of course we're drawing so
much now that we tanked the framerate
which is not fabulous obviously
oh poor poor game poor game is drawing
too many things it's ok game that's just
what happens sometimes you look inside
one of these look at ah look at all that
stuff yeah so I'm not sure how we avoid
just having crazy amounts of stuff
getting drawn all the time like we don't
have much of a level of detail kind of a
thing right that we can lean on for this
let's take a look at one other thing
here though if I go to debug collation
so if i zoom in on debug collation now
we can actually see here is the the
debug start code and here's the debug
end code just kind of fun to write yeah
so almost there but not quite there yet
I don't know what else we've got here in
terms of stuff we could click on
so this is begin sim
and that's get World chunk
yeah so I'm interested to know since
basically that's just a lot of busy work
on our part that's I don't know that the
graphics driver is probably getting
bogged a spy's because we don't
efficiently handle high volumes of
primitives that's not what our render
stuff is stuff to do at the moment I
also wonder what the difference is
between release and regular builds there
is it was curious because that is
something we could speed up if we wanted
to we have tons of room to do that with
so hard to say
let's see here so let's see what was I
looking at I was looking at game update
so so it's still pretty bad but it's
actually quite a bit more usable so you
know again if we wanted to we this
probably isn't really too much to draw
we probably could if we wanted to
actually draw all this but I suspect
what would be better for us is if we
just maybe put in some logic to handle
things where there's lots of small calls
and just show that in some other way
maybe that seems like a better idea I'm
not sure exactly how we do that but
again that's kind of what we're supposed
to be doing now all right so let's keep
going here let's also make it make sure
that we can still draw our old-style
draw frame bars I want to be able to
draw a profile in and draw a profile in
will now take will also take viewing
element and then I will go back to draw
a profile in and say that that takes
well
I'm not actually sure what that will do
that will take debug elements elements
and it will say I don't know like I
guess this is just gonna draw the
current frame always so it's debug state
most recent frame ordinal so it'll grab
that out there and since there's
multiple events that it could draw I'm
not sure again what the right thing is
there to do this is kinda always the
thing what to think about this a little
bit more carefully but I guess we'll
just assume that we're gonna draw
whatever the first one is but that's
kinda that's the like sort of slightly
odd part is really this should now loop
over all of the events because if there
are multiple ones you want to draw them
all presumably right so yeah but anyway
I so will take the route event and we'll
say that most recent events because the
one will draw and then we'll just say
like assuming that there is a route
event there to draw at all we will draw
it and to do that we would just use
Route event profile node
so here's our oldest play back again I
just want to make sure we could still do
this display okay
and you know here's our here's our per
frame you know and here I can drill down
into this one and see like kind of all
the nonsense we were seeing before right
and I can see all this crazy stuff it's
doing get world chunk yeah all right
okay so that's all pretty good that's
all pretty good so I think really mostly
what I need to do now is I need to make
it so that since inside a particular if
you're just jumping in in the middle
right if you're going into a draw
profile and you've got multiple events
in a single frame for this thing and
you're trying to draw like that
occurrence I guess like what you want to
do is know the beginning and end bounds
for that thing so like you know if we
said here is trying to think of what the
most logical way is to do this right
it's it's kind of a really difficult
problem let me just kind of explain why
so what happens is let's say we have
something like get world chunk right
so if we have something like get world
chunk it's gonna happen many times a
frame so inside a single frame here's
just here's like frame zero inside a
single frame we're gonna have like many
calls to this thing so here's call zero
here's called one year's call to vehicle
three whatever so now in the user
interface if I say I want to zoom in to
this call right that's kind of tricky
because that call is not really a grid
it's just the first instance of the get
world chunk call and so if we went to
frame 1 right there may not even have
been a get world chunk on frame 1 or
more to the point let's say we zoomed it
on three maybe there were only two calls
to get world chunk on frame 1 and so now
there isn't even one to view right so
saying we want to zoom in on get world
chunk is like a grid-based thing that
allows us to always no matter what frame
iran we can say here's what we're
viewing but if we want to see a specific
instance of that there really isn't much
of a way for us to do that in a stable
way other than something kind of janky
like just show me the zero with call to
it or something so what I'm thinking we
maybe should do instead is just do like
a pre pass over it and maybe that total
clocks idea for example was a good one
and so what we do is we'd say all right
let's take the total clocks and we'll
just string these things end-to-end
right so so we'll condense all the calls
for get rid chunk down and so when you
get world chunk you can't view just a
single get world chunk all you're gonna
view all of the get world chunk calls
and we'll collapse them into one like
viewable one thing it's not the world's
best idea right I'm not claiming that it
is but it's just I think that's maybe
what we should do and so in order to do
that what I would say is as we go
through these and we get profile notes
for them we can sort of sum up
total duration and when I could do two
is I probably could just get rid of that
from here because doing a pre Passover
it probably isn't the end of the world
I'm guessing because the amount of time
it takes to go through them and draw
them is going to be the substantial part
anyway but we could also do it during
collation right that's also totally a
plausible thing to do so yeah so let me
take a quick look at what that would
look like we've got total clocks here
and inside the profile nodes themselves
I just want to refresh my memory as to
what we're actually storing there so
inside the profile nodes themselves we
just store the duration and that's in
clocks right and so what I could do is
just say there's a total clocks value
for any one of these things that that
occurs in here I suppose that could also
be you thirty-two as well although there
I suppose there's no real reason for it
so we'll leave it as a su 64 at the
moment yeah and I wonder it we're never
using the aggregate count at the moment
right so we could get rid of that as
well
and then what we could do is keep all of
them all of those in you 64's because
now it's the same amount of space right
the this part right here we could
actually keep these both that's you 60
for us as well just in case it's long
now the parent real to I think we
really would prefer to keep his uses for
as well so I think I'm just going to go
ahead and make that happen and then
we've basically got a you 32 here that's
reserved so we could actually keep the
since I expand that we could actually
keep the the Agron in if we want to
we're just not using it yet so I'm not
going to bother so here I'll just say
might as well keep this at full
precision just in case
so let's not actually cast that down
anymore and yeah so this will actually
just not get casted and I think that's
good
all right so let's take a look your next
step I'm almost out of time so yeah so
next step is to keep those total clocks
I think seems reasonable so let's take a
look at total clocks and where we would
do that right is when something gets
added when we do a store event we're
adding it into the you know wherever the
frame index actually is and so when we
do that that pull this part right here
give a government frame that's actually
what we would need to be incrementing
and so I don't know I don't know if we
have that information at the time of
storage so I think we're probably going
to have to reverse look it up if that
makes sense
so this is why I say maybe we want to do
it after the fact
I'm not sure because I'm not sure if
it's going to be easy for us to do it
the time when we know the duration is
here so adding the total clocks would
mean we'd have to add it here and I'm
not sure I mean I guess we kind of know
the information that we need but it's a
little inconvenient right we don't have
the element we'd have to look up the
element again you know or store the
element so I think I'm just gonna skip
it I think I'm just gonna say let's not
do that for now maybe that's a dumb idea
but like I said it just looks a little
cumbersome to keep that information so I
think I'm just going to delete that for
now and so what we could do is actually
just have a way of computing
meaning we can spend some processor time
to get the same information and it just
be a really trivial routine so like you
know all we would have to do is have
something that's like get total Fox and
we'd pass debug element rain and this
would just do oops force of habit
debug stored event event equals frame
oldest event events events equals events
next and I guess this is just literally
regular next right and then we would say
frame total or rather you should get
four result equals zero result equals
plus equals event profile new duration
and then we would return that result so
now if someone wants the total clocks
they can get the total clocks relatively
simply
so in here if we want to do the debug
profile lining things up like that what
we can do is say let get me the total
clocks for this frame
like so and once we have that then we
can actually loop over these and draw
them like as a set that would be the
same that would happen outside but then
what we do is we'd say stored event
event equals root frame oldest event
this is the exact same loop event goes
event next and then in here the root
node of the thing or I'm not gonna even
call it root node probably at this point
also this can happen at here as well is
just gonna be whatever this events
profile there it is and this I guess
this actually all of this stuff actually
can happen out here too
when we do deep a profile node we grab
out the profile node that's for this
event and then we would draw it and so
the only thing that we have to do now is
make sub rectangles out of this that
stack up based on how many of these
events there are right how much the
duration is right and so what I want to
do is take whatever my profile rect is
and just subdivide it so what I would do
is say okay there's going to be a new
rectangle to which is the event rect and
that's gonna be equal to the profile
rect and to pass that down at the moment
let me just run this and make sure it
works
just want to make sure this stuff still
works okay and so then what we want to
do is as we're looping over these
profile nodes to draw them what I want
to do is I want to change the event Rex
that we're using to basically like only
be stacked up for did not have any space
in between it right so the first event
rect and I guess I'll do like min
o'clock or whatever or relative o'clock
so the first event rect is going to be
at the you know at the leftmost edge and
then I want to like advance it every
time we go by however much clocks that
particular event took so I'm gonna do
that I'm going to compute it every time
so we don't end up getting off by
accumulation rounding because these
could be very like tiny things happening
so I want the event rect min X and I
want the event rect max X to be set and
what I want to do is set those based on
the profile rect itself based on its
size and relative view their relative
clocks right so what I want to do is say
like profile rect min X plus profile
rect max X in both cases and oops
yeah in both cases what I want to do is
is just create sort of a that that
standard linear interpolation so I want
to do basically like a 1 minus T kind of
thing T in both cases so the first T is
just going to be whatever this relative
clock is in the parents total space
right and we know what the total space
is this right here
so whatever the relative clock is over
the total clock is what we want and we
want those things to be divided to
divide out we're losing a fair bit of
precision here and we could do this in
double potentially if we wanted to try
and be a little bit better right we
could do this if we wanted to and you
know maybe that's a good idea so since
we're just doing one divide it really
wouldn't be particularly expensive on
any machine weird ebbing on to do the
divide and double so you know off we go
excuse me so once we do that right you
can kind of see where I'm going with
this we know that every time our min X
the next time through is going to be
equal to whatever our max X was the
previous time so what I can do is make
like an X X kind of a thing and we would
just start that out that profile rect
min X because we know that that's what's
going to be and then each time through
here we just do next
x equals event rect dot max X or
something like that right and then that
way we only compute it once each one of
those once and so this is always next X
so now we only have to do one of those
we do the divide to figure out where
this is going to be on the relative
clock and we go
now the relative clock of course has to
be advanced by however much this event
actually is like however many clocks it
actually took we want to move forward by
that amount and that tells us where like
our sort of new location is now we might
not have to keep that because we have
our parent relative clock in here as
well so we could just use the parent
relative clock to tell us that piece of
information I suppose no we can't
because that's actually telling us the
full spaced out version which we don't
want so this looks roughly correct okay
so I don't actually know that I have a
particularly good test case for this
unfortunately either which isn't great
but at least we didn't break anything so
that's nice what I could do well you
know what I could do I could go down
into the game part of the game and look
in here and see if I can like look at a
particular one of these and they should
be stacked up on each other of course
there's probably nothing actually
happening inside them so that doesn't
really help should probably construct
some kind of a test case to actually
view that but that's I believe what we
actually want to do and the same thing
is going to be true over here meaning
this we would want to do exactly the
same code basically all right I think
I'm out of time
so I'm gonna go to Q&amp;A
in savate asked a very provocative
question
it said relationship status it's
complicated for the movement to be its
own main function inside and who can
treat agree with that I mean that's
doesn't look like queue so I can go eat
dinner guess what that means I can go
eat dinner
see you got your reasons for what's so
bad with a new debug view isn't this
still way for your tries on typical 3d
game yes so just to be clear I don't
think any of that slowness is rendering
related meaning like I'm pretty sure
that there's nothing stressing the
graphics card there I mean I could be
wrong but I'm I would be shocked the
problem is the way that we have set up
the render at the moment we don't have
any way of pushing like a huge set of
rectangles down in a nice coherent chunk
so what's actually happening for every
single rectangle draw is it's like
creating a record under the debug I mean
on to the render group right and that is
getting shoved down to OpenGL as OpenGL
immediate calls which is then getting
assembled into a buffer by the graphics
card which is then like buffering it up
and something that it's like it's gonna
be a big it's really really inefficient
how it's currently sending those down
and so we don't ever see that happening
with any of our game code and the reason
for that is because the game is about
drawing like sprites so there's very few
vertices and lots of texture right
that's how that works
and so it's deceptive because then it's
like oh it looks like the rendering is
slow here when we draw lots of
rectangles but it's actually not
rendering slow it's just the conduit is
slow because it's not set up for this
purpose and if we wanted to improve that
we actually could right we could make a
special path just for drawing lots and
lots of rectangles and then it would
probably find right we just have some
big vertex buffer and we'd write
directly we'd say like begin chunk of
rectangles we'd write all the rectangles
into there and issue them all as one big
batch and then there'd be no copies we
wouldn't need
a lot of memory on our debug on our
render grip for it either and that would
be fine right bougie Oh 8:15 will you
make the UI immediate mode the UI
already is immediate mode dude in
basement 1 will the demographics
graphing update even if the game is
paused yes and unfortunately we don't
even turn off debug recording right now
which we're going to have to do we need
a way to pause that it's one of the
things we need to do long boolean right
now the outlines and the profiler
overlap each other it makes it a little
harder to make out the colors or the
change to run to the other the obvious
solution would be to draw them with a
slight offset from last each time but
there any problems with that once the
rectangles get really small I think in
general nothing you do is going to work
when the rectangles get really small so
I think most of that is really just
about when you have lots of small
rectangles you need to like have a level
of detail solution there which I don't
know if we're gonna do but you know if
you were gonna try to keep pursuing this
to make oh like a really really fancy
system you would want to do that you
would want to have some level of detail
there is our current types up code
framerate independent will the game
simulation run the same at any framerate
so the current code is like well first
of all there's another thing as
framerate independent code literally
I've never heard of a single thing
that's ever been framerate independent
you are always frame rate in dependent
and the question is just to what degree
right now I would say we are not not
particularly framerate dependent meaning
you could get basically the same results
with a fairly wide range of frame rates
however eventually that would break
right because we don't for example if
your framerate got extremely low like
let's say one frame every five
seconds we don't subsample the input at
all so you move like in these huge steps
right and you would never really be able
to probably do most stuff like firing
would be hard to do and moving would be
hard to do and so on similarly you could
if you cranked a frame right up so high
that the frame time rounded down to too
small to actually accumulate any
movement we would break there as well
and that's true basically every game
loop that I've ever seen in any game
ever so usually what you do is outside
the game code itself you cap the frame
rate on either end and you basically say
we're never gonna let it run it less
than one frame a second and we're never
gonna let it run it more than you know a
thousand frames a second or something
Zen mystic are we going to do the batch
way then now probably not I mean I don't
care about this how fast this code runs
at all right I just want the profiler
there so I can see what's going on with
the game all the time and spot problems
you know so that I'm not like clueless
about it
dude in basement one off-topic have you
ever defined structures inside of
functions no because when I like like
sort of when I was still changing my C's
plus plus and C Styles around you
weren't allowed to that's not like legal
like so if you had tried back when I was
still like one of my coding subs was
still in flux you couldn't do this like
that's not allowed so nowadays you can
and I've never really gone back and
thought do I want to do that somewhere
so there might have been times when I
would want to do that and I just never
even think of it because I'm so used to
it being illegal if that makes sense I
don't know why it was ever illegal
because it seems like the compiler
doesn't really have to do any work to
make that happen it's a really basic
thing but I guess maybe for debug
information it's a little complicated
because now it means you have scoped
types which before you didn't and for so
I could from code for producing code I
can't imagine why it would ever be
really a big any big deal with the
compiler at all but for debug info I
guess it does make the debugging feel a
little more complicated because now your
types have to have to be linked to the
scope instead of them just being global
six degrees of game rate gaming is there
any advantage to making physics
dependent on frame rate other than
convenience well generally speaking if
you have a very physics II game with a
lot of fancy physics code going on in it
typically you want to lock that down to
a predictable time step because physics
can be very time step sensitive and you
don't generally want to run at greater
than or less than the standard testing
framerate so typically what I've seen
games do if they're very physics II is
they always run the physics at its given
time step like whatever that is a
hundred and twenty frames a second let's
say they'll always do that many updates
of the physics and then when they render
if they'll just render whatever the most
recent one is or an interpolation
between the two most recent ones or
something like that so a lot of times
what I've seen is games don't want to
have variable physics frame rates and
the reason for that as physics is very
sensitive to the frame rate and you
really don't want the game to change
that much with a game like handmade hero
where it's not about like a lots of
complex physical interactions between
like 3d rigid bodies and other stuff
like that you can typically make the
game feel roughly the same with within a
pretty wide tolerance from like 15
frames second to 120 frames a second the
game will will still the behavior of the
game in general will still be roughly
consistent by just using basic
techniques but that's not true of
complex physics usually they tend to
diverge quite a bit so
all right I think we're done here I
think we are done here
i'ma wrap it up
thank you everybody for joining me for
another set of handmade here oh it's
been a pipe of cutting with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with the code at home you can always
pre-order the game on hand mahira org
and it comes with source code which I
update every night for your experimental
pleasures sounds a little weird if I say
it that way anyway we also a form you
can go to ask question a patreon page
you want support video series and a
tweet bot which tweets schedule at you
if you want to know where we're gonna be
live and we are going to be live 5:00
p.m. Pacific Daylight Time tomorrow for
the last stream of the week you don't
want to miss that it's to think it's
less from the week it's Friday right
yeah last movie tomorrow hope see here
for that and if I don't see you here for
that well I will just cry so will
everyone else that's about it for today
I would also remind you that if you want
to use the editor we used on the stream
you can type for a quitter into your
browser and go to this patreon page
right here my friend and if you
subscribe this patreon you can get your
very own copy we use on the stream the
five dollar reward one and I also pack
my config file into the handmade hero
source so if your someone is following
on with him right here and you wanna
switch to for code or just look in the
misc directory of the handmade hero
source it's got it in there
that's about it for today
have fun programming and I'll see you on
the Internet take it easy