there we go hello everyone and welcome
back to handmade Hiro sure we could a
complete game live on stream we are back
from two weeks of being off for the
holidays I was not even in the great
state of Washington so I could not do
any streaming but I can now because I'm
back and I am at the handmade here
computer we left off with a very very
simple task or at least step one of what
we need to do is a very very simple task
I don't know if you remember what it was
but we were going to go ahead and put
sorting into our renderer so that our
sprites would appear in the correct
order
and in order to do that we needed to set
a few things up we did that setup so now
all we really have to do is write a sort
and the first sort we're going to write
is a very very simple sort so it should
be pretty easy but we do have to do one
other thing if I remember correctly we
have to decide and possibly manipulate
our data a little bit decide how we want
to handle the fact that we need to
rearrange the order of things so let's
get right to it if you happen to have
pre-ordered the the game and have access
the source code then today is day 2 29
so grab day 228 source is that correct
let me just make sure that's correct now
that we're back here that day 228 was
the last one so day 229 is what you want
to be working with if you want to follow
along with what I'm doing today now if
if we wanted to just underscore what
we're doing here for people who maybe
don't necessarily know what's going on
or who forgot that's unusual I don't
remember this being in there did we for
some reason overflow are our size stuff
this is in our render group to output
where we're actually creating our
temporary nough memory did we have too
much stuff that we were doing with that
I don't even I don't remember this is in
the Phil Gramm chunk work stuff I don't
remember us needing more than that but I
guess maybe we were that's interesting
well point being yeah I guess I won't
show
the thing I was going to show you
because the change we made when we
started means that we hit this which is
basically that when we're doing our
ground chunks like it you know what I
could do I could turn the ground chunks
off for a second and then show you
because we do have to talk about that
stuff anyway which is where we're
getting the memory for that that stuff
but hold on a second so let's go ahead
and turn those ground chunks off so they
aren't causing a problem by overflowing
how much memory memory they need to do
their job alright so if that's an handed
game now right didn't we remove it out
to handmade worlds I think so
so there's Phil Gramm chunk so I believe
with our Phil ground chunk stuff if we
just take this out then we don't have to
worry about what they're doing because
they just won't ever actually compute
anything and off we go all right so
here's the actual game running and it's
not actually waiting for any vertical
retrace right now so a renderer just
happens to be really really fast even
though it's in software because it's you
know it's only doing a few sprites here
so it's running way faster even than it
should right
but anyway ignoring all that what you
can see is if I move around the world
my sprites aren't sorted at all so
they're just kind of randomly like you
know he'll go behind that tree there's
no reason for that and as he moves he
might even change the sort order and the
reason for that is they're just drawn in
whatever order the entities come up in
the region in the same region and that
order can change because it's not even
in forest it because you know the
simulator doesn't care or anything like
that and so you can kind of see that
that's obviously not gonna work for the
game when the game is done we need the
ability to create any kinds of scenes
here and even just the simple basic room
that we created a bunch of trees around
even that it doesn't work right without
sorting so we need some way of sorting
these sprites so that it knows that like
oh okay this tree has to be in front of
the sky if the guy is further back like
that we got to draw this on top of him
similarly here it has to know that he is
always on top
of the trees so that's that's really all
we need to do but that's that's the goal
now we have a problem here I'll go ahead
and turn this back on so we can see this
is what we did just at the end of last
stream which is we need some room to do
our sorting that was essentially what we
were trying to do there and what happens
with that sorting room is apparently if
we do our ground chunk fill let our
ground chunk fill stuff run when it
tries to do its rendering it ends up in
a situation where it's asking for more
memory than it can handle and you can
kind of see what's happening here is
we're asking the task arena for memory
but it looks like when we do that it's
kind of used all of its memory so I'm
gonna I'm just gonna take a look in here
and see what's going on I think when we
do allocate render group I don't
actually know I'm interested to know
what happens here let's take a look at
what happens here so when we do an
allocate render group how much memory
does it take so yeah it looks like
what's happening is in here and you can
we're kind of jumping around because we
have multiple threads I should probably
go in here you can see if we go to our
thread display you can see that our
threads are actually doing stuff right
like we have two people who are
allocating render groups right now as we
speak those are our ground chunk filling
threads doing well doing exactly what
we're watching them do and what I could
do here is I could go ahead and freeze
this thread which says don't run it
anymore so that way when we step we're
only seeing this guy yeah so anyway if I
look in here you can see the max bush
buffer size is a one megabyte so it's
going to use up that one megabyte of
space and the arena that we have for
these this this sort of work these task
arenas I think they're only one megabyte
big so we basically don't have any room
for doing what we need to do there and
so you know again that's just something
that we would have to tune how much
memory we want our
helper tasks and it's based on how much
they would need how much you know we
want them to use so if we actually take
a look at how that gets initialized in
our transient State here you can see
when we do this we could just say like
okay if we give them each two megabytes
to work with then we would have enough
for both the sorting space and the other
space and then we wouldn't have the
situation of running out of memory
presumably so let's take a look at that
and see if we can make that work because
if I if I'm not mistaken that means that
whenever we come through here we would
have allocated all the space so now in
theory we should have one megabyte free
I believe let's take a look when we come
through here I want to see the work
tasks arena yeah there we go
so now we can see what's going on
does it use it should only that that
doesn't make any sense did I just miss
read that it should not take more than
just the one megabyte oh we just use all
that's remaining that's the problem
right there that's the problem right
there
so really I guess it doesn't matter what
we set that to we could have just set
this thing to be less so I could even
leave these if I wanted one megabyte and
then just pick how much we want those
push buffers to be for field round chunk
right because it's this value right here
if we pass zero it says just use
whatever is left in the arena but we
wouldn't want to do that right we'd want
to say like okay yeah maybe just use
half of it or something like that right
and then we'd be fine so that was the
problem is it just eats up all of the
space that's remaining so even if we
allocate more it's a project you know it
doesn't matter okay so anyway point
being we're back to some semblance of
okayness here and everything's fine
except we haven't actually implemented
our sort
because like I said we didn't get to it
at the end of the previous dream so we
need to actually do the work of sorting
and we sort of set ourselves up for this
again by like just reserving some space
so that we can have room to sort we've
got this little thing called sort space
here and we have a tile sort entry which
is a thing that we created I don't
remember where we actually put it
hopefully we put it somewhere reasonable
but probably not it's just sitting right
here let's go ahead and move that in
fact let's move both of these I'm gonna
move these both out here where I can see
them all right there we go so we have
this thing called a towel sort entry it
has a thing called a sort key and it has
a thing called a push buffer offset what
we need to do now is we need to do
something reasonable here where we can
actually sort these so I'm gonna start
by doing the simplest possible thing you
hear me say that all the time but again
it's usually the best course of action
gets something working first and then
think through what works what doesn't
work in it in terms of what you actually
need and how optimal it is and those
sorts of things so I'm gonna do the
simplest possible thing and I'm just
gonna explain to you how we're gonna go
about doing a basic sort of the things
that we have to do that I'm gonna go to
the white board which is actually
probably gonna take a little bit I
should have started it loading a little
bit before sorry black board I bad not
white board all right so I need to draw
something out here so as soon as
mischeif goes ahead and finishes loading
which again it takes a while because
we've got so much data in the black
board but once it finishes loading I
will sketch out for you here on day 229
what it is that we're trying to do just
so you can get a feel for it if it's
something that you're not familiar with
so render sorting okay so we have a very
basic problem to solve the problem is
we've got two things or more right we've
got a and B and we know that a is
supposed to show up in front of B and we
want to make sure that we then draw it
in a specific order so if our render is
front to back we want to draw a first
then the second if our enters back to
front which is how it happens to be
right now we want to do B than a and
I mean by that is if our renderer
basically occludes things going back
towards the screen so meaning it will
draw a and then it will like clip what's
behind it and draw be that would be
front to back meaning it draw the front
stuff first and the back stuff after
right that's front to back whereas the
other way which is the way we're doing
it now is back to front which means it
will draw whatever is in B and then it
will slap a on top of it and a clued B
by making a so that kind of solid where
B it to overwrite what B is right this
is what we have to happen to be doing
which means we want to do B than a so
what we want to do is we want to take
something some list of things which has
stuff in it like you know whatever the
things are and then it has something
like okay it's got a B and then some
more things we want to take lists that
look like this where a comes before B
and we want to produce instead lists
where those things are in the opposite
order right where we know that the
things that are behind always come
before things that are in front of them
in these lists right and there may be
lots of things like that so if there's
another thing that C right we know that
we always want to see the thing our
lists should be like whatever the list
is and that it should just have C could
have other things but then B other
things and then a whatever but it always
has to appear in the order C be a never
in any other order in that list okay so
that's our goal that's what we need to
have happen now what are we starting
with in this situation right what we're
starting with is some push buffer that
just has stuff in it right and that
stuff can come in handy order so we may
have a coming first we may have C coming
second we may have be coming third and
who knows what else right and so what we
need to do is we need to take this push
buffer this this is the thing that
actually has the information in it to
and this is fairly large right it's got
you know it's got position and the
bitmap pointer and all this stuff these
could be many bytes these could be 64
bytes this could be 128 bytes these
could be pretty large okay so we want to
do is we want to produce something that
lets us draw this in the order that
it actually needs to get drawn now what
we could do is try to reorder the whole
thing meaning we could go and say okay I
know that this has to look like this
instead so when we do the sorting I'm
gonna like copy the whole be well in
this case the whole see over here and
the whole a down here and the whole be
up here but that's a lot of copying
especially if the sort has to do
multiple operations to like get things
into position so maybe we don't want to
do that or if we do want to do that
maybe we will only want to do that at
the end and we don't want to do that as
we're trying to produce the list and
moving things around so we probably have
to do in the way a lot of sorting tends
to work who knows we'll see what we end
up with but the way it tends to work
oftentimes is we have some kind of a
sort buffer which is just the minimal
information that we need to execute the
sort properly and typically what that is
is it's two things right it's an index
and a key the key is the minimal amount
of information we need to produce the
sort and the index is something that
allows us to get back to the original
data so that we know what it actually
was
so in this case this could just be an
offset into our push buffer and you'll
notice I've set us up for that here by
having put buffer offset and here is the
key which is just something that allows
us to sort and that I've used at r32 and
so what we're gonna do here is just say
all right let's ah let's produce this
thing which is basically just 64 bits
per entry right each one of these
entries is 64 bits it's 32 bits of key
and 32 bits of index will sort on the 32
bits of key and then we'll after we're
done sorting and we know this
everything's in the right order will use
the 32 bits of index to go grab the data
that we actually need it simple enough
right
okay so if we do this then what we need
to do is we have two separate tasks the
first task and one that is kind of ad
hoc is we need a way of producing the 32
bit sort key so what we need is we need
some way of producing a value which
represents the draw order of these
things now this is easy if we just have
a single Z value but we don't why don't
we well it's because of the two and
half D nonsense that plagues all two and
a half D games it's just the way the of
the world whenever you're doing an
approximation you have to deal with the
consequences of that approximation okay
what are the cost codes of that
approximation well we have two things we
have a Z value right we do actually have
a Z value because we have things like
here's the floor and here's maybe a
floor above it right you know here's
maybe this is a dungeon and here's the
like stairwell down to a driver so we do
have the concept of this thing stacked
on top of each other right that does
exist but we also have the concept that
this is sort of a little bit isometric
which means that trees in the front of
the same floor and trees on a floor okay
so let's collect ground sorry trees
towards us on the ground are in front of
trees that are away from us right
because remember when we were looking at
this example here where we have this
going on there is no Z difference
between these things the handmade Hero
guy is standing on the same plane as the
trees but intuitively we know that these
trees should be in front of the handmade
hero guy down here and the reason for
that is because we're sort of faking
this we have a fake three deenis of the
tree it may just be a sprite but in our
imagination it's extending upward
because it's it's again it's - and at
the it's simulating the fact that maybe
there was a verticality to that
particular thing okay
so we've got this other concept here
which is that the y-value right the
closer the y-value is to the bottom of
the screen the more it should sort right
that the closer it should draw and the
further back the less it should draw
right and so what we want to do is
introduce some concept probably of
mixing the Z and the Y value together to
produce a single sort key that will let
us sort them both and you can imagine
how we might do this right
imagine that we took the Z value and we
multiplied it by some really big number
right like we said you know if our Z
values typically range from like you
know negative 32 to positive 32 or
something like this then you can imagine
us multi
flying it by some really big value like
1024 to pack it something you know into
something and then we take our y-value
and and we pack that into the bottom of
it so we have like 16 bits of Z and 16
bits of Y right something like this if
you imagine doing something like this
where we put the high part of the Z in
here and the low part is the Y then we'd
have a single value which we know will
sort us properly where it's basically
the plane that you're on goes in the top
part and where you are on that plane
goes in the bottom part and we you know
would hope that that would that would
work for us something like this right
now again this sort of approximation who
knows right in two and a half D lands
there is no perfect answer because we
don't have full 3d models for everything
which means that we can't actually
perfectly sort everything the top of the
tree is not going to sort right of
something that was like flying in it
around it that should have been above it
in this other weird way and it wrapped
around you know blah blah blah
you could always create something that
will break the two and a half D case
that would require you to do a full 3d
thing but for our purposes we should be
able to come up with something okay
so that's that's task one oops for the
love of God mischeif they cannot
properly parse the alt key it's so bad
like you alt tab to it and they think
that they got an old accelerator they
didn't I don't know I wish they would
fix that maybe they have I should ask
them if they've ever fixed that anyway
we can update our version of mischeif so
task one is make the keys and two is
sort right so those are the two things
we need to do we need to actually put
keys in there and then we need to sort
and so how much time do we have we've
got about a half hour we should at least
be able to make our keys and it will
release an approximate thing where we
just like you know stuff some keys in
there for testing or whatever and then
we can do our sort and we should be able
to implement a basic sort and just show
kind of how that worked and then we'll
go from there
all right so let's see how far we can
get
the half-hour that we have so in here
actually gets to get more we started
eight minutes late so technically I've
got 40 minutes mm-hmm all right so
here's our render group to output you
can see that it creates some sort space
calls do tile vendor work so any do
tiled render work oops we just basically
do nothing we just in fact we could even
collapse these now if we wanted to write
but here it is
and so render group to output wait what
but what are we doing here oh it's just
we have two functions called render
group to output that's kind of annoying
don't you think well oh well what are
gonna do so anyway in render group to
output here we are and we run through
all of the things that we have and you
know while we're running through all of
these things we're actually drawing them
well what I want to do is stop doing
that and it's gonna be a little
inefficient at first because right now
we don't try to build up this array
separately like we don't try to build up
our sort array separately as things are
actually pushed on although maybe we
just could you know it now I think about
it we just can't do that so really all
we need to do here right is for our
render group to output we just need to
change things a little bit so let me let
me sort of show you what I mean by that
so what we want to do this this runs
through the push buffer which has all of
our grabs commands and it renders them
in the order in which they occur what we
want to do instead is run through the
sort array and render them in that order
right now this is worse for streaming
the memory because it's random scatter
gather but that's just the price of a
sort there's nothing we can do about
that because we have to sort the things
we can't make them contiguous in memory
because we don't know what order they
need to go in until after we see them
all right now maybe we could do
something crazy in the game code that
outputs them in sorted order but again
that starts to get into optimizations we
probably just don't have to do because
it's not going to be that big of a deal
for us but point being you can
understand sort of what I'm saying about
the scatter gather part so instead of
just running through the base addresses
and doing the space as rows address plus
equal signs of entry
instead of doing that we're not going to
do that instead what we're going to do
is we're going to do something where we
go sort entry index equals zero
sort entry indexed is lit less than the
sort entry count however much that is
we're going to go through each one of
those and for each one of those we're
going to do is we're going to jump into
the push buffer at wherever the tile
sort entry tells us we need to be right
so we essentially have a Taos or entry
here which starts at the beginning of
the entries and each time through right
we're just going to increment it by one
and we're gonna see in that entry what
the push buffer offset is for the
element that we actually need to draw
okay so here's the push buffer offset
and so right here where we grab out our
data everything else can be the same
this whole thing can actually be exactly
the same right so we really don't need
to change anything about we're doing
we're just changing the the loop from
streaming serially to doing saying
that's gonna jump around so here when we
grab our header instead of doing render
group push buffer base plus base address
now we're just gonna say well the base
address is this right and we no longer
need to track the base address through
the loop because the things going to
tell us every time okay so in order to
do this all we need is that entry count
and the entry pointer and so for the
render group itself I believe we already
sort of had that right you can kind of
see in here that we well actually that's
not true because it's multi-threaded we
really want this to be different for
each one so technically for render group
to output when we do this thing with the
clip rect and all that sort of thing
what we want to do is we want to
actually have a separate one I think for
each one so we want to pass this in here
we'd want to say like how many sword
entries are there oops and what are they
right so this is the tile sword entry
entries
right and that's literally it for
changing the render routine everything
else will just work fine and now we
don't have to do any of this nonsense
either where we track the base address
so that's all gone which is kind of nice
because it means that now we don't even
have to do that work it's all just kind
of handled as part of that that push
that we're pushing all right so let's
say we do that well we have a couple
problems first of all when we actually
call that we don't have any of this
information when we need to actually
call render group to output so we do
need to do is we need to figure out some
way of getting that particular
information now you can see in here when
we call this render group to output
thing we we have the sort space which is
this this thing here right like where's
our sort space we do have the entry list
so we've got that we know where that is
but we don't actually know yet for each
individual one of those things we don't
actually know which of those applies to
which tile if that makes sense so I
think I want to break this into two so I
don't overwhelm you with stuff normally
I would probably just do this in one
pass but I just want to point this out
so I'm gonna plan out and then we'll do
it in a separate pass the way that we're
rendering the screen right now right it
works like this where we take a chunk
and we render that chunk and the reason
that we do that instead of running the
whole screen is because we we assign
different threads to different chunks
so while thread one is working on this
chunk thread two is working on this one
thread three is working on that one's
for is working on this one etc what we
want to do eventually is probably make
the sorting happen there too so that the
the sorting can be multi-threaded what
that means is we would want to only have
in each of those lists are our entry
lists we only want the ones that pertain
to this particular chunk which means
they should get clipped per chunk as
they go right I'm not going to do that
yet I'm just gonna do it as if they all
kind of go into the same one for now but
that's the basic idea okay so
I'm not sure how exactly we want to do
that or maybe we only want to sort it
once I really don't know because I don't
know let's do the sort once at the head
end and then what we'll do is we'll see
how long the sorting takes and the
sorting takes too much time we'll put it
on the multiple threads how does that
sound
that seems fair and the reason that that
would kind of be nice too is because it
means that the we wouldn't actually have
to have done the sort space thing
meaning we don't actually have to we
could make it so that actually there's
all there's just one this the sorting
thing doesn't actually have that
restriction to it we could do it that
way I'm so torn so if we do it that way
then the other problem is that we
there's always so many things in
programming here's all the things that
are going through my head right now so
the push buffer is not fixed size
obviously and so we also don't really
know for that that's sort of that sort
list we also have this situation where
we don't actually know how we don't
actually know where anything isn't it so
the best time to build up the sort
entries this tile sort entry array the
best time to do that would be at the
time when things are actually pushed on
so again that sort of argues for having
just one of those arrays that kind of
gets built at the same time and in fact
we could do it from the top down so that
basically the end of the push buffer
just builds up that array and then we've
already got it ready to go right that
again would argue for not having this
extra sort space here which means the
sort space thing that I did was just you
know not that we spent any time doing it
but I'm just saying you know it was
unnecessary so I don't know maybe we
don't want to do that so let's let's
think about this so if we were to do
that right it would look like this
inside the render group we've got this
thing that's like push buffer element
count in there we would have like
sorting right and the way that would
work is as we go or I guess we could
even say it would work like this like
you know what did I call those things
it's also an entry so sort entry at
right what I could do there is when we
initially start the render group so when
we do an allocate render group then when
we do the push buffer base thing we
would just say okay the sort entry at is
just the push buffer base plus the max
but buffer size so it's at the end and
then every time we do a push render
element which is this thing here every
time we do a push render element what we
would want to do is inside that push we
also put an entry onto the array so
instead of doing the assertion we would
otherwise do which is this one right
here if group put further size is lesson
master size instead we do sort entry at
so we'd say it's got to be before where
that's going to be right and what we
could do is say you know actually
furthermore it could be sort entry at -
however big the the the tile this guy
the trial sort entry is right so
basically I've got to I could even draw
this since we've got our blackboard back
online we've got two things we we're
sort of using the standard stack heap
kind of style we have two places we're
pushing we push stuff on here as we go
which are the actual entries and we push
stuff on here right which are the the
sorts so when we're done we have two
things we have the data that's all in
here and then we have the sort at the
end which is just a packed thing of
those 64 bits it's this thing
it's this guy he's at the end right and
so what we need to do is we say well
we're out of space if these two things
get each other right so if I was to push
on as big as you want me to push on and
I added an entry at the end would I
collide or not assuming I wouldn't then
we just do it right so we say okay group
push buffer or group sort entry at
rather - equals size of tiles or entry
group sort entry at group push buffer
base so now I know that I've got a tile
sort entry at that location and I can
use it right so the pushover base plus
where the sort entry is I back up by 1
and now I've got that one to use I can
then say okay whatever the sort key is I
need to put that in here now the problem
is we don't have one like I said that's
something we have to do so we're going
to need a sort key and then the other
part I actually do know which is the
push buffer offset right because the
push buffer offset is actually just this
push buffer size thing here right so
before we advanced it it actually would
just be correct so I can just do that
and then we'll put these two guys down
here so that would just build up that
array for me and the only thing I would
need is now whenever you push in a
render element we would actually have to
know whatever the sort key is so that
breaks all our existing stuff because we
don't have a sort key but so you know
what that's okay because that's like I
said something we got to do right okay
so if we were to do that then when we do
render group to output we don't actually
need to pass those things it can
actually get them because now we know
what they are right now we know that the
sword entry count is just the render
group pushed buffer element count and we
know that the sword entries is just the
push buffer base plus the sword entry
app
and so we actually have everything that
we need for those renders they can just
do their thing okay all right so yeah
what what am I looking at here
max push buffer size cannot convert from
you eight star oh that's not supposed to
be a pointer offset that's just supposed
to be the value so that's that's all
we're talking about here right that's
all we're talking about missing in
parentheses of course it's not good so
let's fix that so now all we need to do
is actually put in that sort key and
then we could start actually using this
so push render elements when we do this
we need to pass a sort key for now I'll
just say like okay we've got the offset
here and we know the like we know that
that when we do those push bitmaps we do
the transform thing where does that so
here it is good so the dim basis this
this whole thing here gives us RP right
so the Dimpy that peasy we could use as
a sort key for now and then we can make
it a little bit I guess we can add the
the sort of Y component in as well on
top of that so let's see if we can do
that if we do push render element here
we should be able to say something like
push render elements let's see
short key equals dim P well you know
what who else calls this push rekt it's
got a basis clear well clear it's gonna
probably just always sort to the very
bottom there's only a few people so I
think what I'm gonna do instead I'm
gonna actually say that whatever that
dim basis thing is I think the basis
maybe should just compute that it's
these things here right entity basis P
result it's these things here and so
what I might say is like hey guess what
guys let's just make it so that we
actually have in here on the sort key
I'm just gonna try that see if that
works so then what we would do is say
alright the sort key is just the dim
basis sort key and that way anyone who
calls that will automatically have the
sort key that they actually needed right
and so in here we'd say oh you know push
rekt it that's gonna get the basis so we
just do basis sort key and then in terms
of the the clear I guess we would do
something like real 30 to minimum here I
don't know if we have one of those
that's a good question
and made math dot H and made platform
not H do we have any minimums or
maximums there it is real 30 to maximum
so this would really just be that I
guess I could do this
so that would just be hey it's the
minimum possible value so it's gonna
sort the furthest back if we assume that
the values go in that direction again I
don't know which directions we want to I
guess if z 4r z it comes up at you so it
would be the furthest back would be
consistent with the way the rest are
render is going so let's just say that
that's how that is all right so there's
push render element at with the real
thirty-two minimum so now what we would
need to do is when we call that get
basis P right we would need to produce
the sort key so in here when we're doing
orthographic or anything I guess really
in either case maybe we can compute them
the same way the sort key is just going
to be the result PZ and the result py I
think we could just for now just do it
that way so we'd say okay take some
large value you know like I said I don't
know what we want to take 4096 who knows
do that and then we want the result wide
to offset it now Y gets negative as it
goes down and positive as it goes up
actually so we want this this is
actually going to be the opposite
direction because we want it to get
higher as it comes closer to us which
we're saying is kind of down towards the
bottom screen so there'd be a way to
produce the sort key for now again we'll
probably have to visit you know actually
think that through a little bit more
carefully oh but we don't know what the
Z is so we probably need to use this Z
here at that original Z there we go okay
and I don't know we might want to use
the original Y - yeah I think about it
I'm not sure
I'm not sure I really don't know like I
said we're gonna have to we're gonna
have to think about it
because we it does the offset properly
and we don't have rotation I don't know
I'm not sure which like I said we'll
revisit that a little bit later but
point being we've now got what we the
basics of what we need in there for the
sorting and now we've produced that
array properly which means that when we
do render group to output we actually
have everything in place to actually go
through the entries right and we've
actually put the entries together so we
actually have a valid array so in theory
this should actually draw as well and in
fact we could test that right now to see
if that did anything not fantastic but I
guess that's actually okay because that
could still be correct since we don't
actually know what order when the things
got pushed in they'd be in the opposite
order so actually that kind of makes
sense yeah I think that that might
actually make some sense that on the
other hand does not look good at all
all right so where are we at why are we
getting why are we getting nonsense on
the screen I don't know we got to debug
this so here's our sword entry stuff as
it gets produced and we just have to
figure out is this stuff oh well it's
because the clear would come last so
yeah I mean really since we're not doing
the sort yet that may actually be pretty
much the entirety of the problem let's
just test that let's see if I start at
the at the end and go to the beginning
what happens
I'm not sure so if we do them in reverse
order because remember we push them from
the top back so they're gonna be in the
reverse order when they came in and so I
just want to see okay so that was really
the entirety of the problem it's just
that that array was flipped around I'll
explain that in a second in case anyone
missed it all right so that's all good
so all that was happening there right
since I was pushing from the back of the
buffer I was pushing this way it meant
that the order was exactly reversed
which meant that the clear was like the
last thing that would happen because the
first thing that got pushes the clear so
it's here then all of our stuff would be
on it and so when it went to render it
it would render everything and then
clear right and so again we don't have
to care about that because we're about
to sort this array so really all we have
to worry about is getting our sort keys
correct and this can stay the way that
it was but I just wanted to test that
and make sure that was true okay so now
we're back to doing it in the wrong
order so the clear comes last and we see
nothing but a blank screen let's go
ahead and sort these okay so in order to
sort of things what we need to do is
when we do our render group to output so
before we do anything else guess we've
got our tiled right yeah right here so
here we go we've got tiled render group
to output and this sort of breaks things
up into tiles right and then it calls
this complete all work thing so what we
want to do here is before we do
something like that that render group to
output we need a way of saying okay
we're done and now you can sort and I
don't know if we have that yet on our
render group like I don't remember if we
have I think we might because we had
sort of a begin end thing that was going
on which I think is this I don't
remember it when that actually happens
though I don't remember if that happens
like before or after I I really just
don't remember I think that happens too
late right
inside renders false in fact it
definitely it's too late that that
happens after the output already
occurred so basically what we have to do
is when we call these like this render
group to output or this tiled render
group to output that has to do a sort
right it has to make sure that things
are sorted before it doesn't name or
work right so what we would have to do
here is go all right let's say right
here we do something like sort entries
and both of these guys would do this and
I'm gonna put it too little to do here
to say don't do this twice which means
if we wanted something that got rendered
multiple times for some reason we would
end up sorting multiple times which we
wouldn't really need to do because the
list would already be sorted just
something to think about so here's our
sword entries and what this needs to do
is it needs to go through that list and
it needs to sort everything now what
we're gonna do what we're going to do is
we're going to do the simplest possible
sort like the dumbest possible sort we
could and that's called a bubble sort
right so here's our bubble sort now
essentially what we need to do is we
have something that's got values in it
right you know five three one zero two
four six right now we want these things
to go in a particular order so obviously
we're not going to try in 16 minutes to
implement any kind of fancy sort but we
might be able to do a very simple sort
and like I said so let's try to just put
it in the dumbest possible sort and then
we'll talk about sorting in more detail
tomorrow so how would we go about
sorting this in the dumbest possible way
well if you just wanted to be absolutely
stupid about it right all you have to do
is go well if I just went through this
array and I looked at adjacent values
every time I saw a value that was out of
order
right because it's it's it's really easy
to conceptualize just testing to values
right if the array was only two things
big it'd be trivial to sort it all we
would have to do is go well which one's
bigger
whichever one's bigger make sure you
swap it so that one comes second so in
this case they're out of order put the
three here and put the five there that's
it right if we just do that for every
pair right then we know that when one
pass through
we have moved every element at least one
place closer to its eventual destination
right so the three would move up here
right and the five would go here the one
would move up here right
etc etc like they would kind of move and
as we go down so even if something that
was wrong was all the way at the end it
would only take and passes through the
array to get it to its correct location
right because it's gonna move one every
time even if the one or the zero I
should say let's say the zero was in the
worst possible place every time through
it would move up by one because every
time we compared two pairs together we
would move it up by one and so we know
that if this thing contains n elements
we would need to do n passes at maximum
to go through it to move something if it
was all the way at the end all the way
in the beginning so that would be you
know what they would call N squared
right that would be an N squared
algorithm it has to do N squared units
of work because asked to look at n
elements and asked to do that whole
thing and times in order to potentially
move something if it was in the worst
possible place right so that is actually
called a bubble sort that thing of just
like just compare every two and swap if
they're in the wrong place and just keep
doing it as many times you need to till
you never have to swap anything which
again in the worst case would mean that
you'd have to do it an entire pass of
the array for every entry that there was
because you might have something that
was that far away from its eventual
location that's called the bubble sort
now it's not really a good name I don't
love the name bubble sort I would
probably call it a gravity support if I
if I could rename it and the reason is
because a bubble sort suggests that
there's two different things like you
know if you think about bubbles usually
bubbles is like I've got air and I've
got a bubble you know and like air and
water right and here's my thing and I've
got a few little bubbles and everything
else is water and I'm just trying to get
the bubbles to the top right and that
kind of talks about this part well but
this is not a heterogeneous array it's
all the same stuff so it's really just a
gravity sort it's really saying apply
gravity to this thing so that heavy
things sink and light things rise right
and everything in it is moving there
aren't just like a few things moving and
then some other substrate right it's
basically just constantly applying
gravity and letting things like sort
themselves out almost like shaking up a
jar with heavy things and light things
in it so that they you know naturally go
to their correct positions but whatever
that's not what they called it it's
called a bubble sort so that's what we
have to call it because that's what they
named it it's a bubble sort so it's
literally as stupid as I just said it's
a loop around the outside and if we
wanted to truly make it N squared we
could literally write it n squared we
could say like outer equals zero
you know outer is less than then count
plus plus out or something like that and
then inner right there's less than count
plus plus inner something like this we
could literally do it this way and I
will write it that way at first so you
can see how it's N squared you can see
that the total number of iterations here
is count squared right
it's count loops of count loops we can
early-out on this and I'll show you that
in a second but
right but inside here all we have to do
is say okay we know we've got a sword
entry array so my entries whatever one
that I'm looking at here I don't
actually want to go all the way to count
I want to go to count minus one because
I'm going to look at pairs so I don't
need to go all the way to the end of the
array I know when you go to one before
the end of the array because I'm going
to look at two different entries I'm
going to look at this it's called tile
sword entry I'm looking at entry a which
is which is here and I'm looking at
entry B which is one pass fit right and
all I want to do is say that if entry a
sort key right and I we can do whatever
we want here but if NP a sort key is
less than entry be sort key then I need
to swap them right and I can do that
swap really easily I can just say like
okay grab entry B entry B equals entry a
entry a equals the swap value right and
we can pick whichever way we want to
sort these so in our case our sort key
is least what it should be first so what
we want to do is say well if I guess we
really want to talk about this way if
well if entry a sort key is higher than
entry B's meaning it should be after it
then we want to do the swap right
because then Phoebe a is lower we want
to keep it where it is but we want them
from least to greatest right but we
could again like this is your choice you
can choose how you want it this can be
any function as that you want as long as
it's going to produce a reliable
ordering of these things all right so
that's our sort and that's literally the
whole sort that's it there really isn't
anything else to it so anyway if we were
to do this this is like I said this is
the push buffer element count and this
is the oops
yeah in fact I could actually just do
that right so anyway here's our entries
that's at the push buffer base plus the
sport entry app probably want to make an
accessor for that this is kind of a
little janky doing that every time but
there we go so there's our there's our
code for sorting and in theory I mean I
probably didn't type it exactly right
but in theory that would work right now
what's interesting is it actually is
already working because remember these
things were these layers have Z so now
it's not even relying on the order that
we put them in we could put put them in
any order and they'll still sort
properly now which is kind of nice right
but let's go ahead and take a look at
this guy all right that is not great
obviously uh although I'm not even sure
that that's wrong because those ground
tiles are in no way told that they're
behind anything else so there is that so
I'm gonna go ahead and do something here
like those we don't really have anyway I
think that might actually be right is I
guess I'm saying we don't have any way
of saying that they're standing on top
so we really want for that sort key we
kind of want to say that those ground
tiles are are behind or like lower down
right so when I do when I do that fill
ground chunk I want to be able to like
put in that those are underneath so like
I guess it here where we do
this stuff ah where is that render
ground chunks yeah this stuff when I do
this push v map here to place the thing
what I probably want to do is say you
know the Z on this guy is actually a
little bit further back you know
something like this so that it's always
gonna be you know a little bit further
back
oops didn't mean to do that
all right hmm all right so that may just
be that we haven't quite implemented it
right so I'm gonna turn these off for
now let's get this working with some
stuff we can see and then I will we'll
go back to getting the ground chunks in
there properly because we don't even
know if our sorts working properly
although it works properly for this so
maybe it works so let's see all right so
that actually does appear to be working
properly you can see that we're now
consistently sorting and we also have a
couple problems here like you can see
that like my torso sorting in front of
my dude and you know like I said we
haven't done anything to ensure that
that's not gonna happen
you can also see in here that all of our
trees now line up properly too like
they're sorted properly down the side
there which is kind of nice yeah so this
stuff is all kind of sorted nicely which
is which is great so I think our sword
is working properly you stop to think
about the way that we're doing Z&amp;Y like
I said we have a second job to do that
we haven't really done we've just kind
of let lie which is that how we produce
the sort key thing so we need to think
hard about how to produce our sort key
we're gonna have to do some real work
there but that looks like the problem
with that now we could that probably
means that if we just put them if we had
more of a bias in there maybe it would
work but again that really just means we
have to go like work on that sort key
stuff which we can do tomorrow let me
just tell I just wanna check to see if
that's true so that's kind of odd I
don't know why that's
I don't know why that's doing that that
is a little confusing to me because that
should have worked maybe that means our
sort key computation is wrong as well I
don't know either way oh wait a minute
that Delta thing that that's not
actually the way that that works okay
yeah these are not this is not actually
using the transform that's why this is
ignored by the sorting so that's
actually why okay so yeah so we're gonna
have to do something a little fancier
there we're gonna have to do something a
little fancier there so basically the
reason yeah if you look that's just
getting passed as the offset but the
actual Delta is the actual transform is
actually no it's not actually applying
any transform at all the transform is
like the thing that that happens in here
right it's where is that guy where do we
apply the transform it's this guy right
so really what we would need to do when
we're when we're sort of applying this
is when we do our ground chunk rendering
we'd have to do something like this we
really need to clean up this the offset
pista you get so many problems with it
we need to think about how we could make
it better that makes sense but for
offset P what we could do here is say
like okay the bias could come in here if
we wanted and that would probably do it
I would think let me find out I just
want to know from my own yeah that's
what I thought so that's that's really
the main problem there is is how that
bias works out so we'll have to we'll
have to do something a little bit a
little bit more logical with that
okay so let's go to a brief Q&amp;A I guess
we have technically three minutes left
but I voiced a shot I didn't have time
to grab a drink today I was so rushed
all right so let's see if I can actually
trigger the Q&amp;A from here there you go
sorry we were unable to connect to chat
that doesn't help
how do I connect to chat again hello
hello let me see QA there we go
better dang wag do you know the Vulcan
release date no I do not
oh man in sohbat just totally nailed it
dude
in sohbat grim Joey can you talk about
pros and cons of heap sort and quicksort
and/or explain quaternions well we're
not gonna explain quaternions but heap
sort and quicksort basically sorting in
general we'll talk about tomorrow well
either tomorrow or the next day
basically tomorrow we might go fix our
sort keys first and get that right so
that the code is all done just with a
really bad sort and then we can write
some other sorts like show how another
some other sorts we could write try
writing one of those and explain why it
may or may not be better than the bubble
sort if that makes sense so so we'll
definitely do that but but not it here
in the Q&amp;A we need that's like a that's
like a full episode every or what sort
of you planning to ultimately replace
bubble sort with I don't know I you know
my tendency is usually to go with a n
log n which you know is I guess is the
lowest you can possibly do rather than
what's the C Center library does which
is it usually uses an N squared one if
that makes sense because the N squared
one's usually faster in practice but I
don't know if I really care what's
usually faster in practice I think I
probably care which one I know will
never do a really bad case but who knows
maybe we just never have enough n so it
probably doesn't matter I don't know
it's really hard to say since we're not
sorting millions of things it's it's
kind of a little weird if that makes
sense
midlow bubble sort is the simplest sort
I worked my way to doing a section sort
in my practices to assume that must be
down there for simplicity well I mean I
feel like how do you get any simpler
than that I mean it's so simple it's I
mean I feel like it's kind of the
simplest she'll sorts are almost the
same kind of thing so those may be two
but let's see quickly games N squared is
actually faster in this cases yeah so
the the reason that that happens is
because like N squared is the worst case
like when you talk about those things on
the n when you talk about analyzing the
running time of things from a complexity
standpoint what you're talking about is
the worst case and if the worst case
almost never occurs in practice then
what you actually care about is the
expected case like the common case and
the total cost for any individual
iteration of the loop right and so what
ends up happening is sometimes
algorithms which have the lowest worst
case complexity aren't necessarily the
fastest in practice because the worst
cases never get hit right or the size
isn't big enough so that the constant
factors that the actual cost of running
a single iteration of the loop even
though the loop gets run less often it's
it's so expensive that it ends up
costing more and you have to again it's
based on how many things are doing if
you never sort enough items to have that
scale come into play if you're only ever
sorting a thousand items and that's not
enough to really get you far enough up
to X but exponential curve then the the
one that's technically worse is actually
better we'll talk about that tomorrow or
either tomorrow or Wednesday
Angus holder can't you just use binary
insertion to put items into their
correct position so the array is sorted
the whole time that way render group to
output doesn't have to do anything um
you can but that's not always such a
good idea and the reason that that's not
such a good idea is because if you do
that you're constantly pulling in
everything in the render group output
array back into the cache because you're
like stepping through so we try to
explain that so I've got this array and
here's you know sorting afterward and
here's sorting during okay so the
important thing to remember is whether
you sort after or whether you sort
during it's the same cost because
sorting a sorting so you're still gonna
do all of the work of sorting even if
you sort during because like you said
binary insertion well binary insertion
is just a sort that's a kind of sort
right so you're just running a binary
insertion sort as you put things in
right so if anything the cost will be
higher when you actually do it here
because you have less information you
can't see all the elements at once right
so it's never gonna be cheaper to sort
during you can only be the same cost but
a point is it can never be better so why
might you not want to apply it at that
time well the reason you might not want
to apply it is because if I have to
insert things all right I'm putting
things into this array right in one case
I just put them in in order right so by
the time I get out of this cache line
and into this cache line I never touched
this again right I just keep adding and
adding and adding whereas if I do the
sort enduring right then I put things in
here I put things in here but then I
need to come back here and maybe put
thing in here and move that
thing over here and then I need to put
this thing here and move that over here
or I need to put in like pointers and
change the pointers just out of those
things right so I'm constantly touching
all sorts of stuff in here and what that
means is everywhere and there is always
getting pulled back into the cache and
it never gets flushed out right so we're
sorting after one of the nice things is
I just stream these things out and these
things could just fall out of the cache
and never get touched again until at the
very end when I go to draw from them
again right when I go to to actually do
the sort and then they all come in and
I'll stay in during the whole sort right
so you need to be careful it's deceptive
you may think that you're saving work
but you may actually be doing more work
right depending on how that cache stuff
ends up working out so I would say yeah
there's there's no reason not to
consider insertion sorting as you go
maybe it does repair for you but it's
it's tricky don't think that it's a win
without actually testing it and seeing
if it's a win because oftentimes it can
actually be a lose the lag script have
you ever made something of this sort of
project before when you streamed you
just do everything as you go sort of
improv coding or do you do stuff off
stream to repair what you're actually in
a codon stream I do know preparation on
the stream and the reason for that is
I'm sorry I do never know preparation
off stream the reason for that is
because the point of this product is to
show how you work through programming
problems and so the idea is that I have
to face the programming problems cold
and you see how I would work through
them as if I was actually working
through them when I actually go to work
every day at my normal job have I done
this sort of thing before not this exact
kind of project but obviously I've done
a lot of gang code before so it's not
fair to say that I've never done
anything like this before obviously I've
had a lot of practice doing similar
sorts of things but I've never done a
game exactly like this game I've never
even done a two and a half D Zelda
exploration kind of game so I've never
even worked on that kind game before so
maybe it's fair to say that a lot of the
things that we're doing on here I am
seeing for the first time and tackling
for the first time it's just yeah is it
really you know I've had tons of
experience doing game code and game
style programming before so I definitely
have a lot
advantage there and there's a fair
number of things I just go I know how to
do this already so there's that but I
try to keep it fairly fresh and I try to
tackle like I said this this this game
itself is not one like I've done before
or anything like that
and so so you are going to see me work
through things the first time for some
certain segments of the code it's my
first time doing it that way
see Flixter are we going to rage
homograph straight stream tomorrow night
after this one I is that the worries
going to quaternions I don't know if so
we probably should
/ h / HC or / AC how do you disable
syntax highlighting and Emacs while
keeping comment and macro highlighted oh
well that's not actually what's
happening I just I just it's it's still
doing syntax highlighting right you can
see that these are like different colors
from that or whatever I just don't like
a lot of busyness with the colors I
don't like a lot of syntax highlighting
and so that's actually just in my Emacs
file oops that's not it yes max there it
is in the Emacs file and this if you
pre-ordered the game you've got a copy
of this it's in the project directory
under misc kind of see here that I do a
bunch of set face attributes these sort
of things I think it's this stuff right
here I don't know you list hardly at all
so but you can kind of see here where I
like set colors of stuff so sometimes
what I'll do is I'll just set like you
notice strings and constants I just set
them to the same color and stuff or
types and variables are set to the same
color so it looks like there's that I'm
turning some of it off but I'm not
really it's still all on I just assign
the same colors to a bunch of different
things because I don't like too much
busyness the lag strip is your visual
studio custom theme anywhere I really
like it it's just the dark it's the
default dark theme is really all it is
and then I think I just set oh you know
what though I think it is if you again
if you pre-order the game I think it's
in there yeah it is it's handmade hero
settings MSV c 2013 BS settings it's
actually in the misc directory of
handmade hero so it's actually in the
project
alright looks like we're done with
questions so I think I will wrap it up
alright thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of hand made here
at some pleasure coding with you as
always it's nice to have sorting in our
renderer now our stuff shows up in the
right order so tomorrow I think what
we'll do is we'll go look at that sort
key stuff in more detail before we talk
about sorting more more efficient
sorting potentially what we want to do
is go take a look at how we compute our
sort keys so that we can get all of our
stuff set up and like for the ground
chunks is like that so that everything
is like biased properly and more things
like that so we've got a bunch of work
to do there so we'll tackle out tomorrow
and then Wednesday we'll talk more about
sorting and look at a little bit more in
depth about you know again I showed you
how to do the simplest possible sort
we'll talk about how to do more complex
sorts and probably implement one of them
so you can see the difference and with a
number of items were sorting right now
you probably won't be able to tell the
difference in runtime because it's just
not that much time spent in the sort but
it's worth understanding for what you
need to sort bigger things and we will
have to sort more items as we get more
entities in the game obviously when we
have more stuff on the screen that's
that's gonna incur bigger cost all right
again thanks very much for joining me if
you would like to follow along at home
you can always do so by pre-ordering the
game at handmade hero Network it comes
with a source code so you can actually
follow along with what we're doing at
home if you'd like to and so that's
pretty fun way to do that we also have a
forum site which actually is soon to get
a pretty big upgrade thanks to the guys
at handmade devs we've been working
pretty darn hard on getting a real home
for for projects like handmade hero that
can have a good forums that can have a
good like source distribution and stuff
like that and pretty excited to see what
they're doing they said that they'll be
releasing that sometime early this year
I think so we shouldn't have to wait too
much longer so that's a big deal for
right now you could still go to the
janky version of the forums it's using
Joomla that's awful but if you want to
ask questions that's still the place to
do it
but coming soon pretty excited about
that and and yeah really looking forward
to that we also have patreon page you
want to support this video series if you
like what you saw you can subscribe to
that it's
is very much appreciated we also have a
tweet bot that tells you what the
schedule is if you want to catch it live
check the tweet bot it always says when
it's gonna be live and speaking of when
is going to be live we will be back here
tomorrow 5:00 p.m. Pacific Standard Time
to talk more about the sort key stuff
like I said so hope to see you back here
for that until then have fun programming
and I'll see you guys on the Internet
take and use everyone