hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here the show we could a complete game
live on stream we are going to do some
editing features today essentially the
problem that we have at the moment is
that we added some stuff to our sort of
art asset format that is not something
that we really have any way to input so
basically like we have information we
need four different
sprite pieces things that are supposed
to snap together and we now have ways of
describing how they snap together but we
don't have any way of actually ever
specifying any of that and we could just
make a text file format that we then
like have to edit by hand but rather
than doing that what I would rather do
is make it so that there is a way to
edit it inside the game that then I
could just hit save and it just writes
the text file for me because I don't
really ever want to edit the text file I
mean I'd like to have a text file there
so I can just look at it and verify
that's correct
and sometimes it again if you don't have
a lot of time to write tools text files
are kind of your friend because you can
use like a diff utilities and stuff on
them and source code controlling us how
to merge them for example so you can
leverage a lot of stuff there if you use
a text file format so I kind of do like
the idea value textile format - right -
I just don't want to actually thumb make
them by hand because I think that would
just be sort of annoying and take a long
time and so that's really all I wanted
to do this weekend is make something
that I can use to edit that information
and it's not particularly hard code is
just a lot of code cuz you gotta write
something that writes text files and
reads them and I got to write something
that edits this stuff and last save it's
just a lot of code right so it's good
take us a little while to do but it's an
optically hard code it's not code that
it's gonna like bend your mind or
anything but it isn't it isn't small
typically it actually takes a bit of
typing so if you remember correctly the
point of this was just like for example
we had some cats we loaded in and we
have different pieces there's cat heads
and cat bodies and we wanted the cat
heads and the cat bodies to both you
know to be able to sort of
five snap points that would just like
stick on and so right now what we get if
we try to put a cat in there other and
again scale was also part of this right
we just get a cat of an arbitrary size
and we have no way to like adjust the
size in-game right it's just whatever
numbers we randomly picked so we we have
that problem the other problem we have
is that the they're not snapped together
the head doesn't go on the body at all
so it's just ridiculous and totally not
what we want and so what we want to be
able to do we wrote something here where
we can pick stuff pretty easily what
we'd like to do is be able to click here
and like you know bring up some
information where I can edit that stuff
what is the scale of this cat you know
so I can set it something reasonable and
how do the pieces of the cat snap
together to create an actual correctly
formed cat this is not hard like I said
before we're just talking about
basically implementing some floating
point values you know editable window it
just takes a long time because we don't
have anything like that but we can
borrow our debug code which sort of had
some stuff for doing this we can borrow
debug code and kind of use that so we
don't have to re-implement everything
but we will have to do some typing okay
so how do we edit this stuff well what I
would like to do is have some way you
know cuz what's actually happening in
that code that we wrote for picking last
week is we know when we exit this
routine we actually have information
about who was selected by the mouse
cursor right so when we went through
here we already did the work to figure
out who's being picked and we have that
piece of information so really what we
want here is a way of providing that to
some system that can do something with
it right so if we have a pic where it
says like hey this is this is the entity
and this is the piece of the entity that
was being picked or whatever how do we
get that out of here
right and so that's something that I
would like
to address so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to introduce some pretty
simple stuff here inside world mode is
one place we could put it but I don't
love that the reason I don't love that
is because if you think about what's
happening here is basically what we
reading is we're not editing entities
because we're never actually editing
entities if you look at something like
for example since John was on the stream
earlier if you look at games like what
John makes braid and the witness the way
those work is the designer makes
entities and they place entities in the
world right so the core unit of editing
is an entity that is what you would be
editing and so what we would normally
think about our editing system being
built around is editing an entity right
and so it would make a lot of sense if
we were in one of those engines to do it
that way and that is how those engines
work you edit enemies however in our
engine that designer that replaces any
entities we don't have that concept the
the generator places them and it does
whatever it wants right so which
creating entities all over the place
it's parametrically determining there
there's values and so us editing an
entity in our game makes no sense it's
not a designer eGain in that way the
designer if we had one would be working
on the generator not on the entities
right and so what we're really editing
here and the parameters were actually
concerned with are actually parameters
of the art assets we don't really have a
lot of need to edit parameters of
entities because those have to be edited
in the generator and I don't really know
how you would make an interface for
editing that through entities you'd have
to do something really crazy like tag
the route that everything went through
the generator and have a really cool
edit system like flowed back to that I
could imagine doing that if this was a
product I was spending full time on
every day I'm not going to try to do
that at two hours a day on weekends only
right because that's like a huge it
sounds cool it's a little bit far field
right
so we're gonna be editing that generator
mostly by hand and if we do have an
interface
for it it's gonna be an interface that
goes directly to the generator it's not
gonna try to reverse through it so we're
editing mostly art assets and the
parameters we're editing our artistic
parameters that go on to the art assets
themselves what that means is that we
don't really want our editing system to
be restricted to entities because why
should it be maybe we've got some
interface stuff in the metagame maybe
the cutscenes for example anything like
that if we want to be able to specify
information to those art assets they're
not entities there's no entities there
right and we don't really want to have
to introduce entities into that system
for no reason when really the only thing
we're trying anything is art assets so
really what we want to think about here
is how do we expose editing of art
assets not of entities because we those
are two different things and we really
just don't have a game where edit
entities can be edited they just can't
be edited right the thing that has to be
edited is the generators parameters and
that would be a different interface
which we might make at some point for
fine-tuning or whatever but it's just
it's a different kind of thing so what
we want to do here is we want to focus
on the fact that assets are the things
that are being edited and we want to
kind of put this code in something
that's gonna be asset editing based so I
think what that's gonna mean is it's
gonna be something that lives at a
pretty high level it's gonna be
something that lives and talks to asset
system more directly and doesn't really
go through the game code it's more the
game code telling it what was selected
is about it right so I think what's
gonna happen here is we're gonna have
something where for example we've got
this switch statement here and what this
switch statement does is says what kind
of game what are we running what do we
need to do here let's go ahead and
update the title screen up to the render
cutscene update the world whatever it is
that we're running that's what we're
going to do and what I'd like to see
happen here is to expand our notion of
what's going on in this particular
context to include an overriding editor
that sits above everything in the game
doesn't matter what mode you're in
you can still propagate information out
to the editor and have it edit
asynchronous of well not asynchronous of
I should say edit
irrespective of who is the actual
arbiter of what goes on the screen and
not so what I'd like to see here is
inside the game state right which I
which is kind of the over anything that
controls that not specific to which
game-mode you're actually running I
would like to have that game state be
the thing that the checks this this
information right so in here I want to
have something that's sort of like you
know asset editor or something like this
or just like in-game editor something
like that you know I'm talking about so
I want to have something here that's
just an in-game editor thing and that
in-game editor thing is going to be
something that allows me to communicate
this information in a mout right so just
gonna make a file
let me jump this stuff into that file
and we're gonna go from there so here's
in-game editor and again one of the
things that I might do this would go in
the debug system if I were making this
game for me I'm not making this game for
me I'm making this game for you
and as a result what that means why can
I not save this handmade there we go
since I'm making it for other people
substantively to learn and work in it
means that things like being able to
edit the art assets are gonna probably
ship in the actual release version of
the game that's a little atypical it's
not a hundred percent atypical because
some games come with editors in fact I
mentioned braid braid came with an
editor on the PC if I remember correctly
you could pop up like John's interface
for editing you know things in the world
and you could edit that right that's my
recollection anyway I could be wrong
about that so it had like the PC version
had an editor I think it didn't ship may
be necessary I don't know if it
necessary shipped immediately with the
game but I think it did because I think
the PC version was also delayed because
it was Xbox exclusive or something the
original one I don't even remember
remember anything about that but I just
remember I think the PC version could do
that so it's not out of the ordinary for
a game to include any editor it's just
not necessarily how I would normally
think silent only shipped games with
editors
I'm an enormous if games I normally just
have tucked so I don't know but point
being
Nora it's not something I would consider
I could certainly going the debug system
so anyway inside here if I imagine
what's going to go in here I would say
okay there's gonna be an in-game editor
and what I wanted to do is go write some
code that does can give meaning I'm
going to shove the things it needs to
edit into here but I know that one of
them very clearly is going to be like
what kind of bitmap editor or what kind
of what sort of look apart what what
kind of art asset am i editing you know
which which art asset am I actually
looking at and which art asset on my
editing here so if I go into HHA edit
for example MS IHSA edit the asset
system right we know the inside here
we've got like a set of loaded assets
and there's information about those
assets in here right and when we go to
match against assets we can do stuff in
this system where we go through and we
we do various things we usually are able
to pull out things like a bitmap ID and
say look this is the bitmap ID amusing
and then it will go and try to edit that
bitmap ID right so what we want to be
able to do here is respect the fact that
all of our assets are loaded at any
given time there's just an asset array
and I should be able to talk about an
asset in the nest array and I want to
edit that particular asset if I did that
I would be able to get back to one of
these that asset has a bunch of
information in it including the original
file format information from whence it
came that means that the header itself
will be in there right
and the HHA asset structure will
actually be there that's one of these
and what you can see is that has all the
information I need actually in order to
edit it it'll say what type it is and
it's got the information for the bitmap
sounder font baked right in there
the only thing it doesn't tell me is how
to immediately write it back out but if
I was starting with one of these
structures to begin with I have the file
index and which asset it was inside that
file which means I can also write it
back to disk anytime I want this between
a great position to make this be the
foundational element of our editing so
what I'm gonna do here is say alright
look let's just say let's just say well
hypothetically say in a hypothetical way
with
let's just say that we had some way of
recording a set of art assets that we
may want to edit okay I'm just going to
say that hypothetically so if I say I
have an edited editable asset or
something here right and I want to say
look this particular asset index is
something that I'm recording that should
be edited and maybe I put in there as
well sort of uh I don't really want to
call it a priority it's not a priority
it's more like a z-depth it's more like
a sorting value so I want to be able to
say look a lot of times where there's
gonna be a preference to what is
probably edited so for example if I hit
test things in the world and I look at
all the things that I've hit tested I
may want to say one way or another that
things that are far from the camera are
less likely to be the thing that you
were trying to edit them things that are
in the camera now it's not 100% true
right because like let's take this
scenario for example I make mouse over
this thing and and who knows maybe I
wanted to edit the body not the head
right
or maybe I wanted to edit the square
this thing was standing on but it's big
as fat and I can't I can't get get at it
right so it's not a given it's not a
given that I want to edit the closely
the cursor it's just more likely so I
want to provide some kind of an
information there that's like a sort key
right it's just saying look I'm gonna
give you some information I'm gonna
prefer things let's just say here that
closer to zero is better let's just say
that because that's what I want to say
and I'm gonna say it so I just said it
closer to zero is better so we're
basically going to say that like
anything that's greater than zero
decreases your chance as you go out and
makes it more likely to be ignored and
maybe I'll say that less than zero is
discarded right so when you provide
these things I want you to be giving me
things that that are above zero and the
further above zero then the further if
they're behind if they're lower than
zero those are just discarded I don't
know why I just want to do that that's
what ice it's you know I'm programmer
I'm allowed to make arbitrary decisions
and the CPU has to obey me that's just
how it goes so what I want to do here is
create um the notion of an editable like
asset group and in here I want to track
some number of these so I might say
there's an asset count and I might say
that there's some number of these assets
right then I'm looking at in each one of
those editable assets let's say maybe
there's 16 of them or something like
this you know when I do are these
editable asset groups maybe I have
something maybe I have some idea of like
when I group grab these things up what
I'm looking for and maybe I wanted to
scarred them I could add a filtering
here for example as well but we'll see
we'll see how we want to do that
so anyway in the in-game editor what I
want to do here is I want to have an
editable asset group and I want this to
be the current group right and I'm gonna
do something like I'm gonna use my sort
of standard trick that I like to use
which is active and hot and these two
things are a little bit different the
active group is the thing that I'm
actually editing the hot group is the
one that's like under the cursor right
now which may not really be something
I'm looking at if I'm in the middle of a
net operation or it might be if I am in
the middle of it if I not know that I
have Irish and I'm just like picking
entities right so this is the structure
that I want to provide and then what I
want to do is I wanna be able to gather
these and then I want to be a limit
these depending on the circumstances you
know what's going on there I want to be
able to do different things
so this editable asset group probably
wants to bundle up into an editable
query or something like this like a like
editable hit test or something like this
and what I want to do here is say that
the editable hit test is going to have
you know idea of what the the test group
is that it's going to write to you know
and it's also going to have probably the
information that comes from that game
input structure so in here you know
we've got some information about the
mouse this sort of stuff
is it that's really not true you know
what I take that back that's a lie you
know what I probably want to do I think
I want to do that a little bit
differently what I probably wanna do
there is just provide just the basic
Mouse information so probably what I
would say is it might not provide any
real information there other than the
clip space Mouse pee the clip space
Mouse pee is probably gonna just be the
V to not to be 3v3 includes Z from mouse
wheel we don't really want the mouse
wheel getting passed down here because
hit testing is not about the mass wheel
hit testing is not about your feelings
it's about the to deeper space on the
screen where the Ray should shoot out
from so what I lost something like an
edible hit test that's the thing you can
pass through here this answer is one of
our big questions and solves a problem I
think we were having for which is that
when we look into that world mode and we
look at what was happening between the
world non-entity there's a piece of that
that wasn't particularly good right it
wasn't great and that is here on the
update and render entities you can see
that we're passing down that game input
structure really the game infrastructure
has no business being here if you look
at what's going on there it's really
just used to get that clip space P and
then do some work on it that's not a
really appropriate way to be doing this
because remember pass that game input
that's passing a lot of information now
look at all the stuff it could be using
there can be using a controller state
the time step we don't really want to
know those things why do we want not
wanting those things because look we
don't want to pass information to things
that don't need it because they might
accidentally use it right we don't want
to give ourselves the opportunity make
mistake I'm not a fan of the weird C++
object-oriented encapsulation nonsense
where everyone has to be isolated from
everything else and like everything in
your code is some ridiculous walled off
redic you know incapable little lump
right that's no good but I also am NOT a
fan of just having everybody access
everything for no reason because I'd
rather keep things that should be
accessed on the on the parameter line so
I can see what everyone's using and know
it's kind of a little bit of functional
programming right it's a little bit
functional programming idea sleeping
through that things that you should be
editing should come in as your
parameters right and the more we pass
giants trucks that have everything in
them the less we really know what each
person is using it becomes really
onerous to pass everything to everybody
so it's not really
all the time not to mention its
inefficient in a code sense to always be
passing everything as a function
parameter but it is generally true that
you want to keep in mind what is going
to whom and why because you don't want
things to get too out of control anyway
so what I want to do here is I want to
go again to that in-game editor and I
want to go ahead and pass in oops not
that the hit test that we're doing here
because I want this person to always
respond to that hit test if it's
appropriate right so in this case here
what you can see is we're gonna use that
that hit test I don't really want to do
it I don't want to do this work unless
we actually need it right so what I want
to do here is say all right yeah the hit
test in this case is only gonna happen
if we actually have one if we don't have
one that we won't in here again we'll do
the same thing so if we had a hit test
we'll do it when we record this we'll
see if we have the best hit we'll push
the volume out line blah blah blah right
this part is a little bit more
squirrelly right it's a little bit less
clear what we want to do here but what
you can see is we do probably want this
same basic idea
so in this editable hit test here what
we might want to do is have a way of
passing down a selection volume like
that so maybe there is a thing here
which says like highlight rect right and
highlight color something like that so a
way of in our hip test also passing back
look we'd like you to highlight this
thing that's just what we're gonna tell
you to do and you're just gonna have to
trust us on it simile in here I want to
record that probably so I'd like to say
in here look this is the highlight
rectangle that we're talking about so
this is the this is the the rectangle of
this thing that we put on here that also
allows me to maybe if I want to get rid
of the sort key ID I don't know I still
might want it because I don't know that
I really wanna do this
we'll see what happens we'll play that
one by ear so in here this will change
it's not actually about best hit not
equal to f3 to max that's not sure
simile up here best hit is not really
what we're looking at best hit is not
going to be used anymore
in fact it's it's something that we will
probably expand to more of a group
search but basically what it's going to
happen here is this thing that we're
saving like hit MV piece and that sort
of stuff that's actually just gonna get
resolved inside here so what I'd rather
do is say look this stuff is gonna go in
here temporarily I'm gonna work on this
a little bit differently the hit P and
the hit dimension yeah all that stuff
not really what we're talking about here
I want to just kind of ignore that for
now and move it out so it's really the
picking array that sort of stuff this
stuff that's what we actually wanted
there and that's going to be doing the
picking for this particular routine when
we do the picking now what we're gonna
do is this stuff here is gonna when
we're doing our push volume outline
that's that's gonna work directly off of
the rectangle in question we're gonna
pull that out and we're gonna deal with
that in one second here but if we have a
writer group in a hit test we will want
to do our volume outline here and the
volume outline is going to be determined
again by this in-game editor and if it
wants to do a highlight rect right
that's what we'd like to do there here's
what I'll say now that I think about it
that's dumb waste space we can do it
better let's roll it in line we'll have
a highlight asset index it'll go on a
one frame lag it'll be fine
we'll say what we want the highlight
color to be and we'll stay with the
asset is we won't specify the rectangle
right then what we'll do is we'll pull
this out we'll actually put this
directly in line here and we'll say
[Music]
there was that Center half dim there it
is
oops right there this will be better
will be simpler and more fun and
exciting for everybody really so in here
what we want to do is when we're going
through these right when we're going
through these the render groups of doing
the hit testing right so in here you can
see us do the hip test if we wanted to
highlight this thing in particular then
what we'll do is we'll highlight it here
right so if we have a hit test I guess I
can do it inside this check like so
we've already pushed the MT transform so
that's fine and I recall how so the hit
P I don't really want I want the one
that's not already offset there so it's
not this one it's just this one right
and the dimensions are the same here so
so I'm gonna do all of this in line so
the first thing we're gonna do is we're
gonna take a look at this T hit Rea your
sex box what I'm gonna do here is say
look if the T hit that I get back when
we look at those when we wrote our
little simple ray caster here right here
it is doesn't do anything fancy all I
want to do is see whether or not that
value that comes back is not equal to
the f32 max right that's really all I
wanted to do so if it's less than f3 to
max then we're going to process the hit
I'm not gonna do it this way at all
because those are gone right those are
gonna go in here I've got my H in my C
file swapped there we go so what I want
to do is every time I get a hit I want
to provide that hit option so ad kit I
want to pass the hit test that I'm using
here which is this one and I want to
pass the hit in question so here's the
world position of that hit here's the
world radius what I could do is past a
rectangle here but I don't really want
to in fact I guess now think about it it
doesn't really need that information so
can I think about we don't even really
need that I just need the asset index in
the sort key so what I could do here is
pass T hit as the sort key so that's the
key we're using for sorting they're the
asset index and you know what I could
say I could just say less is better so
you can pass negative things if you want
to so anyway when we do our ad hit here
I'll go ahead and say look any kit is a
good hit to add to the hit system it can
determine whether or not it wants to use
those hits or not that's entirely up to
it and then what we'll do is we'll pass
whatever the piece of information err
that are relevant here
here's a piece index we also have an
ending index I'd like to make both of
those things perhaps well you know
honestly do I really even care about
those I don't know that I really care
the asset may actually be sufficient
because since I can only edit an asset I
may not really care if I mouse over
something I'll just highlight all the
assets on the screen that have that
thing maybe that may be a little bit
absurd because it like for example when
you highlight a floor it'll highlight
every floor piece that has that on the
other hand maybe that's a good thing
I don't really know hard to say yeah
hard to say we'll see how it goes I'll
play around with it we can always add it
back in if I don't like it I'm gonna
play that one by ear
so here's what I'm gonna say let's start
out with a highlight color here here's
our highlight color the highlight color
is gonna come from that hit test because
we have this highlight color what I'm
gonna do is say if I hit then great if I
don't hit this thing the highlight color
is going to be multiplied by 0.5 F so
it's less so it'll highlight the
entities the other things that are not
under the mouse it will highlight those
as well but
not as much that basically just gives us
a better way of seeing what we're
actually edit and what we're not gonna
edit I think that's a good compromise
between the two I'm gonna go ahead and
put the highlighter in here what I want
to do here is say look I need to know
what the asset index actually is that's
a little bit of a difficulty here
because I get the bitmap ID back I don't
remember to what extent the bitmap ID
actually lines up with an asset index I
think it might I don't know it's been a
long time programming is slow on this
project because I do it so infrequently
that's just not the first thing in my
mind so let me take a look at what that
bitmap ID is actually supposed to be
because I don't really remember
is it a enum is it a struct I think it's
a struct it's got a clear value okay so
basically all of these things the bitmap
ID sign ID font ID they are just asset
IDs at heart right that's all they
actually are so what I should be able to
do here is I should be able just push
the value on there and say look that's
the actual thing that I want to be
editing so when we go into a kit here
I'm gonna say here's the asset that got
hit it's whatever this this bitmap ID
was this bitmap ID here right so that
bitmap ID I'm gonna pass that in now I
could just let it take a bitmap ID I'm
not gonna bother I'm gonna crack it here
but I could pass it in and have three of
them one for sounds one for bitmaps or
whatever I don't know it's not really a
big deal anyway so that's what I'm doing
that's gonna add a hit to the system
then what I'm gonna do is I'm also going
to see is that bit might be bitmap ID
value equal to the one that's supposed
to be highlighting right so if I come
back into the in-game editor and I just
want to know what's the asset index that
I'm highlighting here like what do I
actually want to show what does the
system think it wants to highlight if
this is that one then I'm gonna push the
volume init line on it right and if it's
not that I'm not going to so that gives
me a way of integrating the hit testing
into the rendering routine very cleanly
it allows us to do one pass and produce
the hit test buffer if it was requested
at the same time that we do our
rendering and it just simplifies things
a lot
there's no baggage being gone there just
a little extra CPU time that's spent in
the case where you actually wanted to
build it and you need to spend the CPU
time if you're going to build
right yeah there's no such thing as a
free lunch except at vendor sponsored
sponsored conferences so what we want to
do here is say that is how we built it
now we need to use it and we need to
support this specific function that
we're talking about here where we can
add a hit to the system right so what I
want to do is I want to have a way of
adding a hit here it's gonna be crappy
and stupid and I won't really care too
much about how it works because again
it's only something that goes on when
the editor which means gonna be on
machines that people are trying to do
actual dev work on which means they
should be okay with things being a
little slower if they need to be so I'm
not gonna worry about the speed very
much here here's the asset index that
we're going to be editing and then here
on the tee hit I'm gonna put in the sort
key here like so and again like I said
we could make this be a bitmap ad if we
want to him not sure if you want to or
not but we definitely could that's
something we could do we can think about
later if we want to to add a layer of
type checking there in case we think
that's important at the moment I don't
think it is particularly important when
we go ahead and add in hit tests what
I'd like to do is make sure that there
actually is a hit test because this
shouldn't really be getting called
because it means you did a bunch of work
I don't want you to be adding hits in
that case because it means you did a
bunch of work you probably shouldn't
have done so let's take a look at what
happens here if we're looking at one of
these editable hit tests it means we
have a destination group in here that
destination group is important that's
the thing we're going to be working on
so here's the editable hit group I'm
sorry asset group I'll call that desk
group equals desk rip right just pulling
it out of here for easier Naaman clay
Chur the desk group I'm going to go
through the assets here and look to see
if I have one that's how should I put
this I'm going to look to see whether or
not I should prefer this one to other
assets in the set right all the things
that are that are being in here so I'm
gonna use the sort key to just say look
we're going to do a few 16 may have been
a bit much so I think maybe what I'll
say is let's say that's not six
maybe it's it's more like eight let's
say furthermore I could just say that
asset camp isn't really a thing maybe
it's just assets and there's just eight
of them and we look through them I don't
know or maybe there aren't I don't know
I'm not sure how I want to do that so
what I'm gonna do here is say let's look
through these and compare and find a
place to add it I'll say asset hour
sorry test index equals zero test index
is less than the desk group assets so
I'm just keeping eight of them for now
there's test index and so what I'd like
to do here is just look at each of these
editable assets and I'd like to see
whether this one should be replaced or
not in fact I might call this desk right
so we'll look at this particular one and
we'll say all right if this particular
destination asset if it's sort key is
greater than the sort key that we've
received we would like to replace the
one that's here with the one that we're
getting now right so we want to move the
rest up if that makes sense
and so that's the case that would go
here if any other case we just proceed
so in the case that we go here then what
I'd like to do is do a copy so I'd like
to move everything up and then I would
like to insert the one so in this case
what I'm going to do is say I know I'm
gonna overwrite this so I'm going to
overwrite it with the one that I've got
right this is just an insertion and what
I'd like to do is just make room for it
so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna say
okay whatever however much the asset
count was that's how many I would have
to copy - the one that I'm on right so
if we look at what we've got here I've
got an array and I've got from my test
index as the one I'm overwriting so I've
got from there right excuse me up to the
asset count another way to write it
would look actually more like this
start at this one right I want to go
from the test index plus one and I want
to go upwards all the way till I get to
the end of I don't know why I didn't
type that I want to go to that get to
the end of the array right another way
to say it would be I want to see if I
can get to the end of asset count right
if we do it that way I don't know I
still don't know which way I want to
really write that right I want to go up
to there and I want to push everything
there one forward so I want to basically
say all right the copy index I want to
move everything up one unit so it always
wants to copy forward what you can see
from here is the problem going to have
is as I copy me over writing the things
that I would like to copy right because
it's gonna look like this but as I go
I'm always going to be copying
oops sorry that's not a man as I go I'm
always gonna be overwriting the thing
that I'm going to copy next with the
thing that was before it and that's not
gonna work
but again pretty easy to fix right could
do something like this now what we want
to do is we want to expand this array in
the case where we can so if we had an
asset count that's less than the maximum
asset count we can have right if it's
less I want to add right I want to add
some space and so once I do that this
becomes safe because I know that this is
always at least one or more so I can
always subtract one from it and say I
want to start there
I want to go backwards and I want to end
on the one I was going to fill out right
I want to end on the one I was going to
fill out so now I can just say look the
copy index always copies from the copy
index minus one so I go back until I
would have copied the one that I'm
actually gonna overwrite I copy that one
and I stop right at that point we're
pretty much done this maintains that
sort of list by just doing a simple
insertion sort on just a few things
right and pushing them up each time as I
go that's about all there is to it not a
lot more will do bug that routine typos
or slips of the minor common and these
sorts of things will debug that and
check the logic later but that's
basically all we need to do for add hit
so then that leaves us with just the
notion of the in-game editor to begin
with and we need some way of like you
know render or update and render editor
right and that's something that we're
going to have to that's gonna have to
process this like hit and you know
what's interesting about it is it really
doesn't need this because it's got a
pointer in it so at some level the hot
group that's that's in here it just
already knows everything that happened
cuz that's what it did so I don't really
know honestly if it needs to get past
that I don't necessarily think it really
does so probably more what we what we
actually have is something like this
something like this and so what really
what's going on here is we're just
saying alright there's one of these
we're gonna send back most of the time
not all time and what we're gonna do is
this by the way we'll obviously want
this well what we want to do here is
we're gonna create this thing we're just
gonna say alright obviously this thing
points to the hot group right this
editable hit test oh no you know what it
does get sent in and out so I can do
what I was gonna do first right yeah so
never mind so we can do begin hit test
we can say add a little hit test result
so right we can do that we're gonna do
is I could return it as well I just am
not sure which one I want to do you know
maybe you do this I don't know so hard
to say so maybe we do something like
that and then here we say and hit test
right and we pass it in like that so I
think that's more or less what we'd want
to do there we'd pass in the editable
hit test we'd go I don't know maybe the
only thing I don't like about that is we
were sort of using the fit test
so they don't like about that and you
know what I don't I don't love that let
me tell you what I like better I do I do
think I like this better I think I like
this better I think I like passing the
hit test in and I think I like saying
something like this and maybe we do that
we basically say like look whether or
not you should hit test is actually a
separate setting and you always get one
of these
that you use and then you all sometimes
they ask you a test and sometimes they
don't you know I'm saying I like that a
little bit better excuse me
so they don't go with that I'm gonna say
that the result desk group is the hot
group which is exactly what I want there
I'm gonna say that the hot group in this
case - I want to clear it to zero
I want inside my highlight color and I
want to set that - exactly gonna set
this to be the clip space Mouse pee and
we'll play with these a little bit more
highlight asset index it's gonna be zero
so we're just gonna really do some
arbitrary stuff here for the beginning
hit test in the end hit test call not
gonna do anything just yet we'll you'll
see what we do there a little bit later
on and then when we've got our should it
test thing we're just gonna use whether
the desk group was in or out what that
means is that when I'm gonna come back
here real quick and just when I was
doing that if hip test I'm assuming we
always hip test so I'm just gonna say
look it's now it should hit test because
I'm assuming always have one of those
going on whenever we're in one of these
routines and it's just a question of
whether or not it would like us to do
the extra
sing or not right and so that way we can
sort of take this out here and make this
be something where we can always
highlight regardless of whether or not
oops regardless of whether or not there
is a hit test in progress we can
actually always provide highlighting
supports because that might be something
that happens even when we're not trying
to hit test and not trying to overwrite
any of that information so I think
that's what I want here
and that seems fine to me when we do our
end hit test here what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna say look inside the in-game
editor I'm gonna keep an idea of like
what the like editing or what the active
asset index is and I'm gonna go ahead
and and preserve that value so for now
what I'll do is I'll just round trip it
always which is not what I will do
eventually but I'll say active asset
index here and then in here I'll rewrite
it in so active asset index equals hit
test highlight oops
whatever the first one is in the hid so
basically I'll say it's equal to zero if
we had a hit so if the hit test asset
count was written zero because remember
we may not have any hits then the active
asset index equals the hit test assets
zero asset index right so that's really
what I want to add that's really what I
wanted to do there and that'll all work
just fine I think let me go back to
handmade H and we've got this in-game
editor here remember we're gonna have to
include it so in here I'm gonna have to
say like handmade in-game editor right
and in here I should provide these
functions that will be called by
everyone
the rest of these not really so it's
really just these two that people might
be calling the other ones are more
specific and then inside handmade H I'll
just include that as well make sure that
gets compiled that should give me the
ability to actually put the editor in
line now so what I can do is in this
code now what we can do is say all right
let's make sure that we begin the hit
test as necessary so inside here the
gamestate editor hears that hit test
will allow it to begin a hit test as
such and then what I'll do at the end
here is a nd hit test and allow the
editor to do whatever it is the editor
does right but we don't care
and so in here we'll actually let the
editor do whatever it wants to do should
it actually feel like it's editing and
provide that hit testing information as
well right so then that looks relatively
clean to me that all looks like it would
flow pretty nicely and so then what I
need to do is for the people in here
we're actually know how to use it I have
to pass down the hip test and that's
fine so then when I go into world mode
now what you can see is update and
render world is actually going to get
that information passed into it now so
in here we will essentially have a thing
that says here's the hit test and that
is the thing that will actually get
passed down not the input when we go to
the simulation and the rendering the
entities and that sort of stuff those
things will actually the input will not
be the thing that gets passed in
presumably anymore
I can't remember what that was getting
used for exactly we look this up the
other day and it was a little bit weird
so it's brain input so I don't know how
I feel about that either way the hit
test is what comes in here
and that should be better here that is
actually so that's a little bit of a
problem because that wants a hit test
always like I say and in this case
simulate wants to not do any hit testing
at all that seems fine actually
so actually though what I can do is just
pass a no one which is also totally
valued valid
um that seems good I what's the problem
here ed oblate it's not overload
operator you're right about that
I do not disagree and this will pick out
just the X Y and then in here we've got
our desk group so basically in here this
is the thing that would have that in it
and so what I can do here is also say
like this is a should hit test call so
really what I want to do is say hey look
if this thing was a hit testing then
will up if this thing was a hit testing
mode will update if it wasn't then we
won't do that
right so that's good and then I think
we're done
so now hit testing should be happening
in line pretty much all the time and so
now we should go in and and make sure
this stuff works one thing that's a
little messed up actually you can see
it's sort of happening right now is that
I think asset index zero is used for
entities that is also used for entities
that just don't have any bitmap IDs on
them so I kind of need to have a way of
of not allowing that to be a valid hit
you know what I'm saying so like in here
we would sort of have to do like this
all right so now what I want to do is
make sure that we can actually get that
picking and doesn't look like it's quite
going through correctly at the moment so
I want to look at what's going on there
so if the desk group is not equal to
zero we're gonna update Jimmy to be
whatever the first asset is Oh duh so in
here we never allow ourselves to append
which we kind of want to do so what we'd
like to do is yeah this this loop is not
really done yet so what we do want to do
here is say something more like well in
this case we break right and if we
didn't add so you know something like
added equals false right if we didn't
add it and we could have added it then
we want to just append it and there's
probably a better way to write this loop
it looks a little messy right now so I
feel like we probably could do a better
job with that but basically this is all
I'm saying
so like yeah if we didn't add one then
and there was room we need to add one
rights that way we can continue to stack
them up here I mean
so now as you can see we can pick
anything that we want to and anything
that shares that asset ID will get
highlighted because we reading all of
that now you can see we highlight the
actual one that you're on and we also
highlight all the other ones maybe a
little too much right so maybe we want
to change that to something much more I
don't know much dimmer right so you can
kind of see like it highlights them very
very faintly or maybe we don't want to
highlight them at all
I don't know right it's hard to say yeah
I don't really know how to I don't
really know what we want to do with this
we'll see because yeah it's sort of an
open question I'm not sure which we want
to do there yeah sorry I just don't know
um so anyway what I'd like to do is play
with this a little more now so let's
suppose I want to do something where I'm
going to show the bitmap assets that we
actually have listed in here and you
know we did some nice work here with the
HHA edit stuff where we can dump an
asset and we wrote some code that like
kind of like does a good job of dumping
out what's going on it shows asset names
and where they came from and which
spritesheet and all that stuff so what
I'd like to do is end the errors
remember I wanted to keep the errors
there too so I'd like to be able to get
all that stuff out into the actual game
as well where it can sort of print out
everything that we
[Music]
and then allow us to edit those things
in some way right allow us to make some
sense of it right and I don't have a
really good plan for that so I'm just
gonna sketch out some stuff and then
start implementing it right because we
have the ability to do that now so I'm
just going to do it uh so in the in-game
editor what I'd like to do so let's do a
couple things here let's just say first
of all you know we want the ability to
have a mode probably in the editor so
there's like an edit mode where we're
not editing there's an edit mode where
we're like you know Asset picking or
something I don't know I mean you know
what I'm not gonna fill these in I'm
just gonna say well we know there's
gonna be some modes right and I'll just
call it editing for now because all I
really want is brilliant but we'll
probably expand that notion out a little
bit more so in here I'm gonna say like
mode and that's the mode that we're in
and then we got like what we reading is
listed here and I'm gonna say I'm gonna
say that like probably there's just a
keyboard shortcut or something that does
this because there is I don't know and I
would like that to be something that's
like toggleable and and whatnot so we
run pretty quickly into some issues here
that we're gonna have these are very
centralized issues that that you have
really in any situation once we
introduce an editor layer we're gonna
have to be careful to make sure that
when we do things in the editor they can
prevent further action from being taken
downstream in the game
and the reason for this is let's suppose
that we want to be able to type in a
value like we want to be able to type in
1.0 or something well if the one or the
period or the zero key or something or
let's just say we want to type in a name
like what wh 80 the W key is the a
movement key and the hero would start
hopping around right so we want to make
sure that we have ways of differential
regions so that's another reason for
this will probably tie in this editor
mode will tie that in to our input
processing loop so that input processing
is suppressed when we are editing
alright so I'm gonna go into edit mode
here and I'm gonna say that when we do
begin hit test I'm gonna say that if the
editor mode equals edit mode you know
editing then it will fill out the hit
test and if not then it won't and so
that way what'll happen is right off the
bat in that situation because it's
initialized to zero that the editor will
by default not be picking things right
so what I'd like to do is then add a
toggle so we can get in and out of that
mode as necessary what we can do there
is when we're in our begin hit test call
we could take a look at the input and
the game input there we go inside the
game is but we have information that we
can use here F key pressed basically
lets us know which one of these things
is going down or up so what we could do
here is say look if the input F key
pressed for you know let's say I'm going
to use f9
[Music]
so let's say I say we've got fq press 9
that's gonna put me into my edit mode or
maybe that's going to take me out of it
maybe let's do it this way so I'll just
look at these FK presses here so if I'm
in my edit mode or not I can just toggle
between them with an F key press so when
I'm actually and you know I look at it
I'm not thrilled with it I think maybe
f1 and f2 might be better
I think those were locked to other
things but I kind of liked the idea of
loops it should probably on the left
hand because I'm using the mouse I don't
want to go all the way over to f9 and
f10 really but we'll see we'll see how
we go with that
so there's edit mode on and off and I
may have some more edit modes that I
want to put in there right so there's my
edit mode it's all good and now we'll go
ahead and actually put in some time
display so like I said don't really know
what kind of editing we're really gonna
be doing here exactly but you know so
let's you know say that this you know I
guess we kind of do know here we're like
editing bitmap right so we're editing
bitmaps in this case what that means is
when they head and hit test comes on I
can't do something like we do in the
debug UI so in here where we've kind of
got this you know we've got these
notions of text ops and all this sort of
thing right what I want to do is
something very similar that so when when
we go ahead and do our like debug sort
of setup there and we kind of give
ourselves a drawing surface we really
just wanted you that
so in here where we set everything up
right and we do our debug in it that's
really what we want to be doing so we
wanna we want our our debugging it where
we do like the width and height and that
sort of stuff right
we want our debug stuff to follow this
this rule and so in order to do that we
need to create a render group and to
create a render group we just need to
call begin and clear out the depth
buffer so that we don't have any depth
fighting with with stuff that's
underneath what we're trying to draw so
I'm just gonna have a function here
called like render editor or update and
render editor or something like that so
inside and hit test we're gonna call out
to that and that's going to take our
editor and it's gonna do a render group
it's gonna need the game render commands
probably the assets that's well in order
to draw from the font because it needs
that information right it needs to know
which kind of font is going there I
don't remember push font to be honest
with you I don't really remember what
that does that's like one of those
things that you're just like alright I'm
sure that does something cool but I have
no idea what it was even though I wrote
it still don't know and so you know what
maybe from here too I could actually I
could make this be something that's
called from outside right so updating
render editor could get these things
that's pretty straightforward yeah
so if I'm going to do that I need to
make a camera transform that gives me
what I want which i think is basically
this so I can basically say look give me
a camera transform say render group here
give me a camera transform that's just
going to be an orthographic projection
with no clipping to speak up really and
that's what we're gonna draw to and then
I should be able to just dump text you
know text down into there and I think
inside the text op stuff I'm not really
sure to what extent the debug state is
really necessary I think it just gets
the font from those things you know and
so I think we could expand this text up
to be something we can use pretty much
anywhere that we want to and that might
be good so we can get the size to so
this seems good to me you know so I
think we'll maybe make this into a more
general routine right we'll make this
into a routine that that can be used
anywhere and that maybe you use as a
render group more if that makes sense
somebody tell me what push font is
because I've known
so okay so what pushpot does is it just
makes sure that the font is loaded
I mean that that's all does it doesn't
do nothing else
that is is not what I was looking for
so what does it actually load it just it
just loads the the like glyph and
Unicode map that that's it right it
doesn't load the bitmap IDs so you know
I would say to be honest uh that was not
probably a very good idea so you know
I'm not gonna change it right now but
you really don't need to do that like
for a game we can just keep the the font
tables in memory so I think those could
have just been in the hhas as
permanently loaded data that doesn't
need to get loaded delayed because they
just don't take up that much room the
number we're not gonna have very many
fonts you know there's gonna be like 10
fonts in the whole game tops or
something so you're talking about like
you know 200k or 300k of data or
something like this it just doesn't make
a lot of sense to have gone through that
extra effort so that was probably dumb
and didn't really need to happen
you know I'm saying to you so oh well
you know don't know why we made that
decision but we know we could find out
why because we can go back to the
handmade hero archives and look but I
don't know why because I forgot so
anyway let's go ahead and keep going and
we can get the font stuff straightened
out so inside our debug UI stuff like I
saying you know we've got the font and
font info stuff here and we we can go
ahead and do exactly the same thing
inside the in-game editor right so then
we get our font stuff straightened out
that font stuff is I assume just yeah
like pretty basic like loaded font in
HHA font so we can get those two pretty
easily
I think that's all good
render groups when you call begin render
group I don't actually remember does
that return it though wholesale to you
[Music]
yeah so I thought so it should really
look like that more like that
and as far as font idea is concerned I
don't really know exactly how we get the
font ID for the debug system in the
first place let's take a look so we just
we just do it this way so we we look for
a debug font and the same would probably
be true here right and so we could do
this on initialization as well and we
probably will in the future for right
now I'm going to leave it like that and
we'll get the font ID here so this would
give us the ability to start rendering
text is fine and so you know let me just
compile to get rid of the bugs here the
typos and such so we need to specify the
width size that can come straight out of
the commands there probably right
so we have our window with and window
height right here and that's presumably
all we actually need so I'm just gonna
say that the width and height of this
system come from the commands window
width and window height that may be
about it what I do need to do is call
this because no one will be calling it
so at the end of hand-made where I
finished the hip test at some point here
we need to update and render the editor
which I guess I can do here and that
provides us an easy way to do it because
we are slipstreaming the render commands
here and that's pretty straightforward
we also know that we do have the game
assets in tow because those would have
had to be initialized right up here so
we can pass those as well so everything
is in a good position at this point in
the code to ask the renderer to to
render so now we need to do is actually
try to have a way to leverage our
existing display code so we don't have
to write it all multiple times that
shouldn't be too hard either so ok again
we get back to where we were so you can
see we're just kind of doing our thing
here and that's all fine so now what I
want to do is make a way of displaying
that information if I go over to the
debug UI stuff and I look at that text
up again I think these are the sorts of
calls that I want to be able to make
here what you can see from them is that
they take the debug state and that's
really the thing that would prevent me
from be able to use them the rest of
stuff like drawing size text I could
just use exactly it is and so really
it's it's this debug state that would
cause the problem what I can look at
here in doing is making this into a more
generic piece of code that can be used
so that I don't have to worry as much
about that
right and some of the other things here
even probably could be used as well like
just looking at these sorts of things
here right you can see like a lot of
these things or things that I might want
to use tooltips for example so I kind of
feel like this debug UI thing and the
layouts as well it feels to me like this
probably just wants to actually be moved
into something that can be used without
the debug system right so I think really
we can lean on a lot of this code I
think a lot of this code we can just
kind of like clean up and package into
sort of a generic like UI displaying
thing and we don't really have to
rewrite it you know it looks like we've
got all the stuff here that we would
want and so what we want to do is take
it out of the debug system so that you
don't have to be using it for the
express purpose of debugging so that it
can be used for an in-game editing
operation that's supposed to ship with
the game and not necessarily compile out
but who knows these things may kind of
merge slowly over time too it's hard to
say because we may want to ship with
something but you know we don't we
fundamentally don't want the debug
system to have to run at runtime because
it's too slow
so we do kind of want to make a little
bit of a distinction between those two
things right so I think I'm going to
keep that going for now I would like to
know why I think like is hex could be
something that's kind of in the generic
library that we've got here you know
we've got a bunch of stuff here for that
sort of thing and I do kind of feel like
you know we there's there's really no
reason not to have
be in here you know we've got is white
space so why not a new tax right so I
think it is hex would be totally
reasonable I think a get hex would be
totally reasonable to put in here as
well that's right those seem really
straightforward
I feel like get hex would maybe already
have existed to like
uh so I guess we didn't have a hexlen
that maybe that's the only one so that's
fine I guess
you know totally fine let's keep moving
forward so I'm gonna look at the debug
UI stuff and maybe like I said pull that
out into just generic UI so we might not
call this debug UI anymore let's take a
look at debug interaction I want to
understand that a little bit better
because that may want to move into the
debug system only not sure that's pretty
hard to determine but this stuff you can
see so other than the fact that it has
the debug state in it
this layout stuff is otherwise pretty
you know pretty pretty not that for lack
of a better term it allows us mostly to
it looks like it allows us mostly just
program it the way we would want
let me try putting this in to sort of a
handmade UI or handmade well you know
handmade debug UI is not a bad name for
it because it kind of is for that but I
feel like maybe handmade developer UI is
better because it's not necessarily for
debugging but it's only for editing I
don't know it's really hard call but
let's take a look and see what would
happen if we were to sort of make these
things a little bit more generic so I'm
gonna look at interactions are equal and
I want to see where that's getting
called traction is hot so here's an end
element call right and you can see it's
using this interaction thing to see
whether or not it's something that
should be interacted with in the debug
state but you know again that
interaction could be very made very
generic
so yeah it's laughs I'm just not sure
where I want to break this code off
because one way to do it is to just use
the the drawing bits and so I'm just not
sure whether you know which is those I
want to do - I just want to do the
drawing bits or would I rather
and I'm not sure what I want to do on
this side of the code might be
instructive to look at so maybe I want
to do something come to me and say look
if the editor mode is not equal to none
right so if we're gonna be doing some
editing I'll do this stuff and then I'm
gonna look and see well what mode am I
actually in and if I'm in the bitmap
editing mode then I'll do like some kind
of call here like or like I don't know
you know what I mean
and so in here what I want to do is say
well there's a bitmap editor right and
so the bitmap editor wants to do some
stuff with the information that it has
accessible to it right so it wants to be
able to say something like I know I've
got an active asset index so I would
like to display the information about
that particular asset right which we
kind of know what that looks like
because we know it looks like this so I
probably want to do something like this
well I guess you know we could just have
that the inline with it right you know
it could be something more like this um
where's that sitting so if we're in the
asset edit mode you know then we want to
basically do something like this right
and so in here when we're in the asset
editor we want to be able to print this
out right and in here there should be
something which which lets us sort of do
each of these individual things so in
handmade asset h you know i need to be
able to get one of these assets
excuse me out so i want to be able to
get you know an asset so i want to go
say asset equals you know get asset in
the asset system and I know that the one
that I'm looking at is like the active
asset index right so we want to be able
to get that out I probably need to say
something like you know if the active
asset index is not equal to zero you
know what I mean I could also do it more
like this right and I'm not sure you
know exactly what that look like but
we'll look at that in a second so then
in here you know we've we know we've got
a couple different things so we know
we've got the HHA asset and that's going
to be equal to the asset HHA thing and i
might just call that hij for now we know
we've got the annotation
so I've got those two pieces of
information here we've got a header I
don't know that I care about the header
much we've got kind of the file indexed
stuff what I can do is pull the file out
so you know I can also grab the file
that you know that it came from because
I know that as well like so and that
gives me I think most of the things that
we would be looking at here as I go so
in in this case I then want to more or
less do this you know what I mean I want
to be able to like I want to be able to
put all this information in there right
so I want to do something like all right
all of the like a piece of lint floating
by me I want to be able to put the
errors in there you know I want to be
able to put put the tags in there I
don't care about this because that's
just a global tag list so yeah so I want
to just be able to put all this stuff in
there now the hh8 annotation stuff I
don't actually load any of that
information in the annotation part is
not saved if I remember correctly so
like we would have to issue file reads
to get that information and so at the
moment I feel like the way we would get
that is probably also by having the
loaded asset thing so meaning we would
kind of need
we would kind of need that load as well
like we would need this same concept in
here this thing would need to exist in
both places
and I could literally just copy it out
which I might want to do yeah I think I
do want to do that and then we can do is
we can lazily load those potentially so
we don't actually load them in normally
but if someone starts editing we would
would be I guess the way that I would
put that so the loaded HHA annotation is
just like well you know that's what
happens if you load one of these in like
so and so you know we we would do
something like this
so I can call the asset system and say
hey I need the annotation for this thing
because I'm an editor and I need that
sort of thing so you need to give me
that right and off we go
so once I do that and this could be like
marked as such so you know that these
are not calls that like are supposed to
be happening in the normal course of
gameplay they're just things that are
supposed to be happening when an editor
kicks in right which is legal in the
release mode it's just not performance
oriented tested well whatever like it's
like kind of a spec fringe thing that
only a developer is gonna be using
potentially right so I think that's what
we would like to do here that is what
makes sense to me anyway yeah so then I
just want to dump everything right I
want a way to like dump everything and
so I want to do like you know something
like this so I want to do something like
I can do a begin section sort of thing
and I want to be able to put some
information probably on that line
something of this section would be like
so what I kinda wanna do here to say
like look it's it's sort of an if sort
of thing so I want to kind of do a thing
where I'm like look this is a section
and maybe I have two ways of printing
this out so you know there's a section
that shows you all of the data about the
asset or something like asset layout or
something like that and if you do or
don't get it you might print out things
differently that's all I was thinking so
what I want to show here is I want to
show like in the actual asset thing I
want to show like a bunch of this stuff
so I want to like
we want to show like the state I want to
show the file index and I want to show
like the asset index in that file right
like I kind of want that layout stuff to
be available so that we can know like
especially we got the debug stuff that
we're editing we can know like what that
is I'm gonna put in here just the global
asset index so something like that so
that we can see these things
[Music]
and maybe I want these to sort of be a
little bit more Squinkie I need to think
about these a little bit more
[Music]
I need to like think about these a
little bit more don't quote me on this
because that's probably not not what I
actually want so we're gonna play with
this a little bit more but then once we
get to the asset itself the fight the
actual like information you want the
other thing I probably want to do is
like if you can section like asset file
like that and maybe this kind of makes a
little bit more sense over here too
I'm just I'm sorry I'm not describing
what's in my head very well basically
what I'm thinking is how I want these
things to be output cuz I kind of want
them to maybe be sort of more similar to
a printf in that way and it's hard to
decide which way I actually want that to
go right and so it's hard to think
through exactly what I want to have
happened here and I'm in my head kind of
weighing some different options and I
really should be talking about them out
loud so that you can hear them what I
want to do is make the easiest possible
way to describe this data so that I can
see it and also for the ones that are
editable edit it there aren't that many
that are editable so I'm thinking like
this is probably a waste of everyone's
time because you can't really edit any
of these you 32s and you're never going
to be able to write so I don't really
think I really need that actually so I
think it should probably be more like
something like this where we say okay
you know there's gonna be like a like an
expandable or collapsible section
probably and maybe that thing sort of
tells us some information about the
asset itself
like something like that you know
and in there we're just saying look
alright you know we've got this this
sort of set of things that we're gonna
pass down to you and what we're gonna do
is we're gonna have certain ones of
those be editable potentially but most
of the time they're just going to be
output as individual strings that just
get displayed you know what I mean it's
it's just again I'm really having a hard
time seeing that far in the future so
it's hard for me to even type in what I
actually want cuz we're gonna have to
kind of get down there a little bit more
to see it but let's focus on what we
actually need first so I've got these
bitmaps here right
and so in there these are the things
that I actually want to do this reserved
is probably gonna be a scaling value I
would say
[Music]
although I think we actually decided
that goes into the align point itself so
the scaling values are actually in the
align points not in here so that's fine
this this might in the future though
have a source size that actually like
the original slides I think that might
be because we may need that alright so
basically this is the main thing that
we're trying to edit right is the HHA
align point and so let's focus on that
right so we know we've got some number
of align points so we want to have a
little thing that lets us edit those
somehow right so we want to do a thing
here that's like you know begins section
alignment points you know we're going to
do something like this and you know
we're gonna have a layout here or
whatever and what we want to do is go
through all the alignment points that we
have right
and for each one of those aligned points
provide the data and also a way to edit
that data right so if this is the point
then I've got a couple different pieces
of data here I've got P percent size and
type I want to be able to edit all of
those right so inside the file formats
there I believe we've got ways each of
you know each of these and I want to be
able to edit all of them right so I
actually want to be able to do the
parent thing I want to be able to do the
type I want to be able to do the P
percent will just continue calling that
that and then we also want the size
so I want to get all of those and I want
all of them to be editable furthermore
at the end if the I really probably want
this to be out here and I want this to
be a while loop that does this and each
time through the while loop I want to
check to see for every one of these
points whether it actually is valid or
not right so each one of these points
I'm gonna have a thing where you know
we've got a line points in here and
whatever I want to have a thing that for
each of the align points I assume honest
I guess I don't even know I assume we
want these to be like if we delete one
from the middle of the array we want to
collapse the array I assume but honestly
we don't really have to do that because
we could just choose to like display the
twelve points and you delete the one you
want and there's just twelve slots
because that's actually what's going on
so I guess I might say we're just maybe
I take it back maybe we're just gonna do
it like that so in here what I want to
do now is I want to like have these
things be like I want to be able to have
these things be editable so there's like
it attaches to parent boolean here you
know what I mean and you know if that
gets toggled I'm going to do something
with it right I've got like a size here
that size has bounds that have to be
respected so we know that like we don't
want it to we don't want you to be
changing it to really nearly so well I
guess I'll leave that for a little bit
later
um we've got a pipe
and types are a little bit harder
because they allow you to select you
know in order to select from it for the
type County the list of what are the
things that the type represents and I'm
not sure the best way to do that exactly
in this case however we may be able to
get away with something fairly
straightforward by just saying well
here's the set of align points that the
code understands right and we can easily
translate to and fro so in some sense we
could say it's easy to pass what the
thing was because we can always say a
line point name from type right like
that the hard part is inside this
routine it's gonna be pretty hard for it
to know what the things are that you
were actually editing we can do some
tomfoolery here we can do a thing that
does tell it I don't know that we really
want to so I may just leave it at that
for now and we may have a crappy editor
for this I can show you how to make a
better one sometime if people really
want too hard to say so let's go ahead
and create the edible percentage stuff
here
soon here what we want to do is we want
to be able to edit all of these things
so we all we want to be able to edit
both the X&amp;Y as well and we kind of want
that to be an editable XY position sort
of thing we all have to specify the
bounds here probably as well and I don't
know exactly how we want to do that but
it's probably something like this and
the same is probably true here like I
don't really want things to be too small
and I don't really want things to be too
large or whatever right so I'm just
specifying a range so that it kind of
knows what the scale is sizes may just
not need that because sizes are
generally best edited you know I'm gonna
get rid of that sizes are generally
edited best to fit a relative motion so
I think that you know unlike positions
which are absolute kind of motions so I
think that's probably how we would want
that to work out um so this would allow
us to express what needs to get edited
as far as the things we actually cared
about with the alignment points and such
and if any of them actually get set then
what we can do is call the corresponding
function inside the asset system file
format stuff to actually set that stuff
back right and so we want to do here is
like set the alignment point based on on
whether these things happen
now I don't know that we need to put
that inside each of these but I want to
make sure each of them gets called so I
think what I'm going to do is just do
like an edited thing and you know just
have that be false and then in each of
these things you know I'll I'll set it
to true
and you know there's ways we could do
that that are better and you know what
I'm just going to do them I'm gonna do
something like this so in here we
basically like let's begin an edit block
I'm gonna specify what the editable
things are here they are so do this and
then do if and edit block then do that
so that way we have a clean way of
saying these things that added together
if they were edited in some way then
it's a good time for us to say let's set
everything on our point and by the way
we'll have to have an ability to flush
back to the HHA now as well
I think that's really mostly what I want
to do I wanted to have a way of
specifying the Airstream here so I again
want to be able to load that and print
out some more of these things but I'm
not sure I really care about the rest of
them so yeah what I do want to do is
move this into the bitmap side of things
so I want to put that in here right and
then other stuff that gets edited we
don't really have any need for font
editing and so on right so you know if I
look at what I actually need for editing
the things I actually wanted to edit
they're actually pretty minimal so I
could I could really just focus on doing
this and not care too much to get
carried away with other stuff that might
be nice to have but isn't super relevant
at the moment we really would just need
this and then when you actually edit one
of these we will need a way to save it
back and so we'll need a way to sort of
say look this stuff kind of has to be
marked as dirty and later we'll save it
and we may want to do like the ability
to revert or undo as well because we may
not want to save the changes
so although we want to always set the
align point whenever you make a change
we don't actually want to allow you to
make changes to the file directly we
want to just do them in memory like
we're doing here and then we'll have a
way to flush them to disk after the fact
so yeah I think really this doesn't have
to happen at the moment and I think we
can just do it like this and focus on
that and we'll see and we can expand it
to be better later but the moment that
maybe the more reasonable thing right so
if we were to come through here then
what we would need we need to have a way
to make this layout thing actually do
something and you know to be clear it
would look more like this right because
it's gonna have to have actual stuff in
it but that's mostly what we're talking
about
and I think really what's gonna happen
here is that each of these points to
would would really be specified
like this can just be one line of data
right it can just be one line on the
screen and I would like it to sort of
collapse that up right into like just a
thing that it shows a single line of and
so you know I kind of want to say
something like you know begin line and
wine and this would be something like
you know I want to be able to say this
is the enth one of these you know what I
mean
that's more or less what I want to do
you know and there are some other ways I
could do that and I'm not sure which one
of those would be the best but it's more
or less that where I basically just have
let's make a line it should have this
stuff on it
and if I think I also here want to say
you know if this point is like an on
point so the type is null
it's where are you lying there it is so
if we're talking about this if it's just
none right then I kind of just want a
like
a button that just says add point right
or maybe that so just list the ones
around user you can click on one and it
would add it so if in this case you did
it would just create a default alignment
point there so it would do like a set
alignment point and it would say like
alright by default then we just say like
you know it doesn't go to the parent
the size is 1.0 and the p percent is
like point five twenty five so if you
create a new point it just creates that
and then you can do whatever you want
with it after that right so I think
that's fine right so off we go
we build a line of of crap here we put
these editable things in there and that
gives us all of that like if we
implemented that it would give us
everything that we wanted we do need
some way of deleting it so I think we
also want to be able to put here a way
to like delete right so we want to have
a button that deletes it and if we were
going to delete it then what we would do
is say okay like set the type to be
none right and that seems fair right
that seems like a pretty easy way to
construct the interface that we would
need for this set of things to work and
I don't know like there's two ways we
could have done this I'm not sure which
one we really want cuz they're pretty
different so one way is that you
actually just stuff everything into the
format function and the other way is
this so to show you what I mean it'd be
like more like this I so like
something more like this
so you'd basically do like okay you know
this thing is gonna have two branches
here one of which is HHA aligned none
and in that case you're just going to
have one button which is like the unused
thing and the other way is you're going
to have this and either way they're
gonna have a backslash and at the end
and maybe both cases they've got the
number right and it's just that's the
line right if that makes sense
and I can still do it the other way so
you know you could still do it this way
it's really up to you which one you want
and so
it would basically look like everything
stuffed behind a printf the printf looks
like this in these two cases we do these
two things and then what you do is you
wrap your values in things that create
little trucks on the stack that tell the
system what each thing should be so this
all gets stuffed into one thing right it
looks like this where you just have like
you know I'm saying to you
does anyone know I'm talking about here
right and there's advantages and
disadvantage to each of them in this
case the problem is you end up in things
where you have to create synthetic
variables to record results such as if
you want the button here you can't just
do if button delete you have to do like
delete like here's the thing to edit
right and I don't know which one of them
you know you would prefer I implement
it's six and one-half dozen the other
it's both of them are problems with the
way that C and C++ work neither is
particularly good language for these
sorts of operations there's a lot of
limitations to it and that's just kind
of the way it goes but you know you can
sort of see how they would shake out and
you know where you might like or not
like stuff
in either case right so this is what
they would both look like and yeah
that's that's all I got for you I mean
that's that's the difference between the
two and one thing you can't see about
them is they're not that different right
I mean they look pretty similar and it
really just comes down to whether you
prefer to be able to specify your
formatting this way or whether you want
to build it up out of calls like this
and I don't have a strong opinion about
which one of those two things should
happen there are advantages to each
right and I don't know so I think maybe
I'll go with the more function heavy
approach for now rather than this one
just because it seems maybe a little
more in keeping with how we have tended
to do things on handmade hero and so you
know maybe I'll say this is what we're
gonna go with so that'll leave us with a
bunch of things oops that'll leave us
with a bunch of things that we haven't
implemented and so what we'll have to do
here is no with this asset memory header
so we'll have to do here is implement
these things tomorrow like that
basically tells us exactly what we're
going to be doing and so we'll do that
and probably using again that code that
we already sort of had as a way to not
have to re-implement those things
because they're all pretty much already
what we want and we just need to extend
them a little bit does that make sense
so I'll go to a brief Q&amp;A and we'll
we'll write that stuff tomorrow
off-topic how do you index large
messages would you divide into multiple
chunks yes I would divide into multiple
chunks generally speaking my experience
with GPUs is that you just want to
minimize the amount of space things take
you know so there's like very little
chance that you can't break things into
chunks of 65,000 vertices right I mean
come on
like how can you not right so I would
always break them up into those chunks
so that my indices could be smaller have
I changed my fur coat accustomed since I
handed over to Alan Alan generally keeps
it updated so that if you are mmm what
do I want to say if you're for coder if
you if you're if you bought for coders
super super or whatever it's called
you just get it so it should be in the
distro I think he keeps it up to date so
as he changed as discussed earlier he
like backports it and I usually just
pull the changes from him
not really on topic but how would you go
about implanting a generic resizable
array as you said you don't like to use
templates in my experience there is no
way to implement a generic resizable
array in c and c++ period it doesn't
work so you assuming you want to be
typed like just forget about it doesn't
work templates are horrible for this
macros are horrible for this void
starters are horrible for this you need
a meta programming language anytime you
want a generic anything you need a meta
programming language because you want to
look at stuff like when the array I mean
let me just let me show you a very
simple example of how bad c and c++ are
at this and why you need to let meta
programming language it's it's very very
obvious right
and like I'm gonna say this this is
always enrages me so I apologize to the
comments I'm about to make about how
stupid everyone is but I'm going to make
those comics invariably because I get so
angry at C++ because it seems to be
specified by people who never even write
any code it's just it drives me insane
and so I end up being very angry about
it which isn't necessarily productive
because they never change so it doesn't
matter I might as well not but what can
I say
so here's what C++ looks like right I
mean generally you would do something
like this right or that I think is their
typical way they write it and they say
you know here's my thing I'm gonna make
you know and you know I want to put some
stuff in it of course they would always
they would always write class even
though it you know I love it they do
this all the time even though that's
just of this I don't know why but anyway
so you know I want to make one of these
things and you know it's gonna have a an
array pointer sorry it's gonna have an
array pointer in here that's like here's
the storage you know and then inside
here I'm gonna have you know like a
count or something you know and then
what I want to do is I want to influence
things that let me just like put stuff
in whatever the science theory is so you
know I want to have something like an
operator you know that it's gonna let me
access things in here and something like
this you know and inside here I'm gonna
pass an index right so I can create some
size things and I want this thing to
just work you know I just want it to
work so I want to say when I look at
element 16 its there and I can write to
it you know what I mean so in somewhere
like here they would do something like
okay here's the index right I'll return
that but by the way
you know if the index is out of bounds
then you know like allocate and copy or
something right there's some there's
some function in here it'll do that this
is basically what you do right so then
in here I say oh I want one of these
things this is gonna be awesome
it's great and then somebody writes this
okay so what are you going to do now
right what are you gonna do well the
language literally gives you no way to
do anything about this it's just over
before it starts
this will literally call allocate and
copy however many times the grow rule
goes for so people end up doing things
like oh I'll do like twice the size
right like each time or something like
this so I grow by an exponential amount
or something like that right
that means I'll waste all this storage
whatever it's so clear from this code
how many things you needed right this is
how many I hate it in the container it's
obvious right so one of the things that
you want to do the obvious piece of code
that you would write if you're
metaprogramming right is you go like all
rights for each place and I don't know
the syntax of this meta protein language
because they've never given it to me but
for each place you know container calls
operator blah you know get parent you
know parent or containing scope you know
equals get parent scope we're it ever
right while you know this look up
through each one you know easy
a loop if is loop okay
you know get bounds of the loop look at
the balance of the loop if I can see
what they are then allocate that many
ahead of time right that's that's what I
want you know in my language I want to
be able to just write that in there you
know look and see what happens in this
loop how many there are
better yet you know give me some way of
of asking the programmer right maybe I
can't see what this is like it's just
like foo say like look if it's a loop
then like remind programmer you know did
you reserve space for those and then put
this print this out for each one of
these and then allow the programmer to
say yes I did on them right and remember
which ones they were or something all of
these things would be really good
instead what happens is they're just
like no you know what you forget it
there's no way do any of that so you
just end up with this every time and if
they forgot to do this then the code
just sucks you know what I mean
it's just the idea behind having generic
things is they're only useful if I can
actually make them do the right thing
that I would have done if I just had
written the code the right way in the
first place right and if you can't do
that
then what's the point I don't this is
bad code right if this ever runs your
code is bad there is never a time when
this code is good ever ever ever ever
right
exponential growth is not a good
predictor it's terrible it either wastes
space or wastes time but it's it's or
both usually right so if you want a
generic container that I'm
to not have to think about using then
you need to actually have our sorry
imaginary Kenner a container that grows
automatically it should be smart it has
to look at the code and figure out
what's going on right and if it can't
figure out what's going on it should
throw up a warning like hey I can't tell
you got to tell me I don't know what you
know tell me how many things this loops
gonna do right give me that give me that
bonus that's generic programming that's
encoding the logic necessary to create
the correct code into the code what c++
does is it gives you the ability to
encode the worst possible crap code to
be automatically generated by your
compiler because it's like if i wanted
to have the dumbest possible intern
implement everything that I told them to
implement in the worst possible way that
c++ right it's the dumbest possible
intern running the worst possible code
and that's the only thing you can
generate you can't ever write generic
stuff that generates good code that a
good programmer would have written
because it doesn't give you the ability
to look at the enclosing scopes where
things are used so you can't actually
encode the logic that a programmer would
have used to do something smart there
and you can't failing that you can't
even output code that tells you that you
to please do it for me
right I can't even output something here
that says oh don't do this inside this
loop this way right so like I don't know
what to say
right and so basically every time
someone does us uses the C++ feature to
implement something what they're
effectively doing is saving themselves
typing time by putting code into a
generic system by accepting worse code
then they would have had if they had
written it in the place from scratch
right
and it's that's not what you want in the
language you don't want to have to make
that trade-off I don't want to
constantly be thinking oh do I want to
save myself some programming time by
making this into a crappy generic thing
that doesn't work very well or do I want
to spend the extra time to write it
correctly and like should I defer that
decision too late like I just want to be
on the write it right like why can't I
just read it what games give me a
language that lets me write it correctly
you know how hard would that have been
I I would argue not very hard you just
need to give people access to the ast
and you need to allow them to ask
questions about the structure of the
code that they were being called with
right and I don't think it's
fundamentally that hard it certainly
isn't as hard as making compiler that
does all the rest of the crap that's in
C++ 17 X 11 27 35 Blade Runner 43 or
whatever right like it's definitely not
as hard as making that compiler it's way
easier because they've added so much
crap on top of crap on top of crap
trying to solve problems like these that
would have just been solvable if you'd
allowed the programmer to have a meta
programming a actual meta program you
know
I watched the episodes that you
presented premultiplied alpha and I
remember you mentioned that you prefer
to defer multiplying by alpha at the end
hmm can you explain what that means
also what's the benefit of pre mult than
the fact that it is a linear operation
if that's the case I can only see the
value if you're compositing multiple
transparency layers opaque geometry on
one layer and fancy doesn't really
benefit from it am I missing something
you are missing something but I'm not I
can in the second half of the question
the first half the question I'm not sure
exactly what you're referring to
Toofer multiplying by alpha at the end
I'm not sure what you mean by that
because I don't remember the context in
which I set it so I apologize I can't
give answer to that on the reason why I
use premultiplied alpha actually you
need alpha to be linear everywhere it's
not just for multiple blending
operations and the reason for that is
that inside almost every rendering
operation there are linear operations
happening whether you like it or not so
for example bilinear blending it's got
linear write in the name every single
pixel we draw goes through a bilinear
blend that's how we get scaling to look
smooth is the bilinear blend right that
bilinear blend will produce an incorrect
result if the underlying information is
itself not linear because a bilinear
blend blends linearly if the underlying
stuff is not linear then the bilinear
blend will produce a nonlinear result
and so even just shrinking a sprite down
reduces produces incorrect results if
you were using non premultiplied alpha
so premultiplied alpha is is necessary
right from the first time you start
doing anything even scaling now because
modern hardware is very powerful
you can decide and do other things now
you could use non premultiplied alpha
and write your own blending routines
that do things inside them to fix it but
assuming that you're using the hardware
bilinear blend you don't can't do that
and so to be on the fast path you
typically still want premultiplied alpha
even today so hopefully that helps
answer the question a little bit
and as for whether or not see those
first forces used as templates or not it
doesn't force you use templates but if
you want to write a generic container
you have to they don't provide any other
features for doing so so it's like
either you don't get a generic container
or you have to use templates they have
no other meta programming features I
think they're adding introspection
somewhere at some point right finally
that was my understanding anyway and
whether or not that goes through a
different path or something I don't know
I don't know how these aren't gonna end
up shoehorning that in but just in terms
of generic containers I would love to
write generic containers C++ does simply
doesn't support them to my satisfaction
so I don't bother but in an in a proper
meta programming language all of my
containers would be generic it's the
asset to a fixed from day for something
I wasn't able to build some of the tools
coming up a little bit oh that's a good
point the test asset builder probably
needs to get merged in now which I
should probably do you know this is
something we should probably do soon so
I don't really want to it tomorrow but
probably next weekend we should merge
the font stuff and the sound stuff we
should just move those in for the
automatic importing so that you can
basically just never have to use this
stuff again right that would also allow
us to stop you could do a build straight
from our source inputs again which is
better right that's just a better thing
so we should do that soon but no you
can't really do that at the moment all
right that's it for today
all right thank you for joining me for
this so to hand me here it's Owen
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with the
series you can always hear the game on
handmade hero or it comes to the source
code which allows you to follow along at
home and play around with stuff that
we're doing I'll be back here tomorrow
and we'll implement that editor stuff by
basically taking our debug UI code and
just maybe unifying it a bit so that we
can use it for edit versus debug and so
on hope see you back here for that until
then have fun partnering I'll see you on
the Internet
take it easy everybody