hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream i think we basically finished
everything last time and we actually
correctly had our program translating an
input text file into an output text file
while doing the import such that we can
now add things as we wish which I do
wish I would like to add edits from the
in-game editor which allows us to edit
alignment points I'd like to have that
come out in the text file when it gets
translated and so that's really all I
want to do today I want to get that
working and then we can move on to
something else I was thinking of maybe
we could augment the text file to have
thoughts and fonts and and sounds
because those are the two things that we
don't have a text-based import format
for at the moment seems like a good idea
I don't know anyway let's take a look so
if I remember correctly we are the
champions because if you look in here
now base came about HHA an inch our
cutscene that HHA are fully rebuildable
files that you can now rebuild from
nothing but this magical sources
directory and which is filled with PM
g's and tags files which say how
everything should get packed and that's
it that's pretty cool because it means
we could do a full game rebuild at any
time we want and it will still have
everything in it correctly including all
of our markup like tags and stuff like
that and alignment points so that's
pretty cool and it turns out that this
just kind of worked if you go back into
the game and run it it runs exactly like
it used to
now of course it's running in debug mode
so it's a little bit slow
which is less good and also you can kind
of see that well the head isn't there
right now why isn't the head there well
the head isn't there because we don't
have any alignment points to find so
heads can't snap to bodies
cuz there ain't nowhere to snap to and
we have an in-game editor so if I want
to open up the in-game editor I can
click on something like this body here
and I can actually switch to something
where I can edit it right and we're in
debug mode right now so the frame rates
terrible but you know it doesn't really
matter I'm just kind of showing you what
I'm talking about so I can do stuff like
define the point where the head should
snap on like there and then hey the head
suddenly does snap on right and I can
even position that point exactly how I
want to and I can switch over the head
and all that stuff and I can set the
alignment so it's not sunk into the
floor I could do all those things the
in-game editor but again what we were
trying to figure out is well okay we
need those things to persist in a way
that when we rebuild the files they
don't get lost so what we did is exactly
what I just said we now have a way of
making all that happen and we can run a
full import and preserve the text file
and so what we really need to do now is
in that import where we're actually
doing that whole situation I believe
actually and I think I think it was
called sync we changed it synchronize
asset file changes right what we had is
in here we would go through each of
those hht files
we'd reprocess all of them see if we
needed to load any changes or anything
like that like from pngs or whatever and
then we can insert stuff as necessary
into there right so you can kind of see
that happening let me part put it over
here so my head's not in the way so you
could kind of see that happening here
where we go through and where we're
doing like parse top of a block for
example you can see this copy all input
up to and including was what we were
using to sort of move things from the
source file to the destination file
while we were parsing that text file and
that allows us to insert things back
into the text file while preserving the
author of the text files original
formatting and comments which is pretty
cool so
not destroying anything like we would if
we just rewrote the file entirely
ourselves right it's kind of cool we
don't change the order of things we
don't change the formatting we don't get
rid of the comments we just copy it
directly so if we look at what we
actually need to do here you can see
here is an alignment token parse and you
can see what that does is that allows us
to read in all of this information about
alignment points now alignment points
are the things that we're trying to edit
we have the reader for them what we
don't have right now is something that
actually writes them back out again so
what we would like to do is if we've
added one we'd like to go in and rewrite
it so that's what we need to do now
after I finished my oatmeal cookie um so
here in is align points right you can
see us gather it here and what you'll
notice is that at the moment it's not
even used right so literally we read all
these aligned points and we wouldn't
have even used them if they were there
and we don't write out ones that were in
our current alignment set and just that
we don't you know that we didn't see
okay
so the question is what do we do about
this well I think the first thing we
probably want to do is say if we've got
this whole alignment point thing right
what we should probably do is let's
extract all of the alignment points we
currently have and put them into this
HHA align point set right because if we
have the whole set of alignment points
that we currently think are there then
we could go through and as we read in
new ones look to see whether they're the
same or different as the ones that
appear in the file if they're different
we will strike the one in the file and
put the new one in or strike the old one
and read the new one out depending on
whether we're doing an import or an
export right so we can have a flag that
tells us what are we trying to do here
we're trying to like overwrite the
existing file or are we trying to
overwrite what we've got in memory using
what's in the existing file right so we
have two things you can do there and we
want to implement those and then the
other thing we want to do is as we see
each individual one when we make that
decision about like okay we've seen the
line point in the file either we
replaced it with our own version or we
read it in and used it in place of the
one we used to have when we do that
operation we also want to just record
briefly have we process this alignment
point yet that way when we go through at
the end and look and say all right we're
gonna go look to see for each alignment
point did we ever see this alignment
point in the file if we're writing out
our alignment points then what we want
to do is take any of those that didn't
exist in the file and add them into the
file if we're reading in alignment
points what we want to do is take any of
them aren't existing in the file and
clear them so that they're not in our
h aj s anymore right so we have this
like two-way thing right we just want to
synchronize these and we're gonna be
told by the calling code which way to
synchronize are we writing out to the
file or is the file coming in to us and
one of those two things will be true so
we'll know how to merge the data merge
is probably the wrong term update the
data is probably the correct way to say
it because obviously we have a situation
where one or the other is going to be
primal and we just need to know which
one it is
now this is the only thing that operates
this way because at the moment we don't
actually have any edits for anything
else and we don't really need edits for
anything else in the future I could see
us maybe wanting to allow tags to be
edited in the game so that you can tag
things more directly that way maybe
right it's just unclear that that's
really all that useful to a certain
extent because since we can just open up
the text file and edit it in there I'm
not sure what benefit it really has to
putting it into an editor seems like
kind of just a waste of time
alignment points I don't think are a
waste of time because they're a visual
thing and so you want that instant
feedback so you can just dial in the
exact point you were trying to set so I
feel like alignment points make obvious
sense whereas I feel like anything else
that you're adding editing for is really
just gratuitous so why bother right
that's my thinking on it at the moment
it may change we'll see but that's
really so all we're gonna be focusing on
is that so if you take a look in here
how this alignment point gets read I
want to change this align point written
part because that's maybe well I mean I
don't know if it's really talked about
the name
I want this boolean I just don't know
what I want to call it because written
is a little bit of a different
is probably not right I think what I'm
trying to say is a line point processed
right like is this have we gone through
and done something with this alignment
point yet whether that's reading or
writing so that I think is just a better
name for it but let's go back in here
now so when we process one of these
aligned points what we're gonna do is
say all right here's all of the data
that comes in for that align point you
could see me grabbing it all there's the
grid X&amp;Y there's the index there's a
percentage size and type these sorts of
things so when that read occurs what you
can see here is we're going to issue an
error if you tried to say an alignment
point that we don't currently have
otherwise we're going to process it and
also if you don't if you you know have
the two parents specified incorrectly or
something will issue an error there as
well assuming that we got to the end
okay then we're gonna be actually
writing out this alignment point into
the array you can see me doing that here
I get it at the grid you know grid X
grid Y and then which point it was like
this and you can see me setting the
things there for it so we've got the P
percent getting set the size the type
right and so what I want to do here is
also in addition to that I want to say
that I processed this one so in here I
want to say a line point processed and I
want to say that this one was processed
right it's a true so that it was
processed now there's a couple of
different ways that we could do this and
I'm not sure how exactly we want to do
this because there's a inverse way we
could state it that might be a little
bit more sensible and I'm kind of
leaning towards it I think I might want
something more like this so anytime we
see a line point we say a line point
unprocessed equals false rather than a
line point process equals true and so we
here we set unprocessed equal to false
for everybody and then in here we would
have right we're gonna have a four
Loup that reads these alignment points
in from their current setting so for
example you know we'd have something
like this so we've got an iteration
through the grid and we're going to set
a line point unprocessed equal to true
for anybody who's actually got one of
these alignment points currently so so
we need something that looks like this
right and there's going to be an if here
that checks to see whether the thing
exists currently in the bitmap itself
right so this needs to do a lookup grab
the information that we actually have
about this particular this particular
sausage gentleman right here right and
what we'd like to do is then from that
we would like to say whether or not it's
got one this way we start out knowing
what they all were this allows me in
here to say okay when we go through I
can set a line point unprocessed such
that we can mark all the ones that we
saw inside the text file and then at the
end we can go back through these and see
which ones we didn't process right so
we've got one loop over them there and
then we've got another loop over them
here where after we're all done with
everything we can put it all in there so
you can see us having it we've got it
right here where we do the where we see
the closed brace before we copy
everything out we can insert
any ones that we didn't already see
right so it's gonna look something you
know like this if one of these things
was unprocessed you know and should have
been right then we can decide what
exactly it is we're going to do with it
if we were writing out this file then
what we would do is we would replace the
weed weed insert all of these ones that
we're missing whereas if we were doing
the opposite we would clear them and so
that's really all I'm talking about
right so we we set it up we say look
let's remember all of the things that we
actually saw weed that we already have
let's track them as we see them in the
text file and then the ends we will go
ahead and rewrite the ones that we
should change and or clear in the hht
out in the HHA the ones that we didn't
see depending on whether we're importing
or exporting right hopefully that makes
some sense so it's a little bit
complicated to do that obviously we've
it's just a bunch of bookkeeping if you
look at what's going on here you can see
that inside match we do a get or create
asset source file and so this match
right here that is really the thing that
that asset source file there is really
the thing that we're looking for so if
we go to asset source file you can see
and here we assert that we've actually
got one and so in the case where it's is
default we wouldn't but otherwise we
always try to get one
so basically we're only going to need to
do this processing if we actually have
somewhere to store it if we don't have
anywhere to store it them this is all
academic and we're going to be
outputting errors anyway so you know
to worry about it so inside here we're
gonna say look did we get one of these
files and if we did get one of these
files then what we want to do is take a
look at the asset indices involved and
that will give us the asset in question
so if we go ahead and look here we can
say all right we know what the asset
index is for any particular grid
location right oh no wait a minute this
says it's YX is that how we have been
doing it oh yeah it is okay whew
sorry my bad I got nervous there I
thought that like I had commented it one
way and did it the other way everywhere
but no it's only just now that I was not
obeying the convention um so we can go
ahead and grab out any given one of
these asset indices so here's that asset
index we can check to make sure that the
asset index exists if the asset in that
doesn't exist then we don't have to do
anything because there's nothing to load
so just a cleared a completely empty
version is actually what it should be
and we're not going to mark it as
something that's been used so in here
after I look at the asset index if we
actually have one then I want to do a
actual access of that asset so I need to
do like a get asset call and I need to
say give me this particular asset please
when I get back that asset I could
double check again that it's there
although really this is a I probably
shouldn't check this is an assertion
really if for some reason that value was
wrong that's not like the kind of error
that we're talking about where it's like
user error that's an actual just hard
error in the system because that means
that our import like our actual like
asset loading code is broken and needs
to be fixed that's not an actual soft
failure that like somebody typed a
character wrong in the agh team we just
want to report it it's not that kind of
an error I don't think so that should be
a hard fail someone needs to do some
debugging if that ever occurred because
if this asset index is is an actual
number like you know not zero then it
should absolutely
exist in the asset array it's not legal
inside our system to have an asset index
that points to nothing off in the in the
distance right so anyway once we get
that asset back now we should be able to
verify that it is in fact a bitmap right
so we should be able to do a further
assertion that basically says in
addition if you know if there was
something here it should also be a
bitmap because the grid only stores
bitmaps so the asset type here should be
an asset bitmap that type bitmap and if
it's not again
that's just buggy and we need to fix it
because the grid is you don't import
anything else into the grid right that
makes sense now we may rule that relax
that restriction when we go to do sounds
we're gonna have to see how we want to
address that kind of an asset change so
we may need to like you know we may need
to sort of adjust the way we're doing
things here as we move towards different
types of assets that are being imported
or exported right so we do have some
things that need changing there and
we'll will kind of as we grow the asset
system a little bit we'll have to work
that out but anyway assuming that right
now we just say look we're only doing
bitmaps and so the ass has to exist it
has to be a bitmap and we just want to
air out otherwise once we have that done
then inside here we do know where the
data for all this stuff goes it's in
here right and so in here we can just
look to see does a particular alignment
point exist or not and in there we can
basically use the file formats calls I
believe there's one in there somewhere
here it's it's just the type
so I guess we should just look at the
type so in here if we look at the type
the bitmap align points have these so I
can basically say alright if the align
point in question whichever one we're
looking at here if it's type is none
then it's not going to be used so if
it's not equal to none than it is used
right so when loading these in it's just
that this is the so this is the entire
code here this will go through every
grid square it'll say if there was an
asset that we know about that exists
inside this grid square in terms of an
import we will remember that that's
happening and these are the align points
that it had right so we'll set unprocess
equal to true and then we just need to
actually copy out the align points as
well now we could do this a little bit
more straightforward I suppose we want
to by just using a copy since we're
already looping through it I don't
really see the need we might as well
just actually do it manually because why
not so in here we can say look copy out
in addition that whole that whole bit
map align point so that it's stored in
here and we can now fuss with it right
so that extracts all of the bitmap
alignment points into a temporary
holding place and the question that I
guess I would ask now is is that really
what we want to do is there any reason
to do that because we don't really need
to avoid touching this if we're writing
these out then we want to update the HHA
anyway so I guess the question is do we
need to do this copy or not what I'm
gonna say is let's do the copy because
the other the other option right would
be align points could just be a pointer
like into the HHA right so we could just
point into the hhas version of the
alignment points and say that's the
thing that we're going to be operating
on and we don't really need to store it
as a separate copy there you know the
main reason not to do that is just
because this is a user editable file
right so I mean user is the wrong term
because you know we really mean
developer edited file but you know and
wide number of people might edit these
files especially you know kind of a
point of handmade heroes learning to
program someone buys the game and they
start messing with the hht file we want
to be able to produce relatively
straightforward error messages and we
don't necessarily want to you know break
the in-game data if you did like a
partial import so one thing we might
want to do here is just if the parse of
this block did not succeed in its
entirety meaning if there are any if
there were any parsing errors we may
just not want to write anything back
right and so if that's the case we
probably don't want to directly modify
the alignment points in memory we want
to avoid doing that for any block that
didn't successfully parse so I'm
guessing that the best thing to do is to
do the copy here even though we could
have just made this a pointer and gotten
rid of this extra part of the array
again I'm kind of just like six and one
half dozen the other on it but I do
think that that maybe makes a little bit
more sense doing it this way so inside
here again we do have the ability to do
exactly what we did here which is you
know get the asset and and write it out
we're gonna have to think for a minute
though because if you look at what goes
on here before the asset has actually
been imported there's really no way that
we can do this clear alignment points in
the h/h a bit so this is really the this
is really that we're just trying to like
output the alignment points or or clear
them in our temporary array we're not
actually going to access the asset and
the reason is because yes it hasn't been
created yet right so we're just
modifying our temporary array and later
on
we'll figure out what we want to do
about that so if we were trying to write
an h HT out then what we would want to
do is write this out like the string
right we want to like put out the
strings here so in order to do that
that's not really that hard one thing I
do want to do though however before we
go any further is again want to just
double check that we didn't have any
errors in fact I guess I don't have to
do that because we would have broken out
of the loop if we had in there so this
is fine and we can do it so when we come
through here what I want to do is say
all right if we were writing this out
here's where we have to sort of print
this out so this is like our print out
part here is the part we have to clear
it clearing it's pretty easy it's just
gonna be like you know this we've got a
null alignment point we want to romp
over one that already exists so aligned
points grid y grid X point index should
now equal null aligned and we should be
done so at this point all aligned point
unprocessed any one that was set there
we have nullified and so now they won't
actually come through in the HHA when we
update the edge at a later on for each
individual asset so we'll look at that
in a second the more important part here
for our purposes at the immediate moment
is we need to have the alignment point
output to the hht properly that's gonna
require us mimicking the pattern that we
talked about where is that for parsing
so this thing right here right so this
pattern has to be essentially duplicated
and in the reverse so instead of parsing
it what we want to do is now we want to
write it you know what I'm saying so we
want that whole thing to come out
properly I believe this has to be like
that yeah and so in here we need to
start sort of changing this to actually
write these out so when we you know we
need like a thing that like outputs to
stream now fortunately we've already got
out F which I believe is exactly what we
want so we should be able to say look
let's do all of our out FS here so we
can write this stuff out right okay so
what we'd like to do first is say well
these align points or things that we're
just updating in the file so we'd like
to do a copy all input up to an
including of this closed brace only
problem is we don't really want the
including so we want up to but not
including as a separate thing this token
so basically the same call that reason
to copy things in we want that that to
have to be able to work
oops without including the token that
we're talking about and that way we can
actually do this insertion here and then
copy all the rest of the stuff right so
we don't want to include that close
brace we want to include everything up
to the close brace then we want to do
our grid copy then we can copy
whatever's after it right so we're
basically just squeaking in the middle
there and it should be pretty easy for
us to do that because if we just look at
this function it's you know it's really
straightforward it's the same exact
thing except instead of doing this we
just do that right so we don't really
have to do anything all we have to do is
just take the exact same function and
slightly modify how we were actually
doing it right everything else is
exactly the same and we could if we
wanted to make these be you know sort of
I don't know how you want to put it we
could unify them let's say by just
adding an extra here because you can see
the only difference between these two
routines is that what
imagine the token texts count and so
what I could do is I could do it like
this where we just say you know what
these two routines are exactly the same
the only difference between them is that
this one passes this which is the number
of extra characters to write in that
case makes sense so that way these are
both identical they there's no
duplicated you know cut and pasted code
that you know might get out of sync or
something there all right so all we need
to do is just say look it's gonna do the
exact same thing each time the only
difference is one of them takes the
actual token size and uses that the
other one doesn't so it just stops the
beginning of the token and then we're
done
so that makes those two nice and
versatile so we can do whatever we want
with the two of them but they still
share the exact same code so we don't
have to worry about you know changes in
the future accidentally breaking one of
them and not the other or whatever so
inside here we now have to finish how
we're gonna actually output this point
and if you look at how it's working here
we need also you can see it reading here
the Open bracket closed bracket so on so
we need to write out a line this right
here we need to write that out oops
and then we need to write out open
brackets a closed bracket and a integer
write another one and another one right
the XY and index we need to write out
there and you know I do blender if we
should write and write these in the same
way that we're reading and writing them
internally I kind of feel like it should
look like that probably so I kind of
think maybe this should because just to
be consistent it'd be weird if our file
format is different than the way the
code works internally there's no reason
we can't do it that way but it just
seems like you want to keep everything
working the same way just to make it
less common overhead once you learn one
way you have to learn another that would
be my suggestion but so then what we've
got is open bracket number closed
bracket open bracket number closed
bracket open bracket member oh nope
that's wrong it's a comma well that
makes it uh yeah I don't know about that
I feel like it should again I feel like
it should look the same you know what
I'm saying
I don't know oh no it's tough because if
we do that it's XY you wouldn't do all
right all right
I capitulate I could pitch you late it
should be different if it's a comma
won't be the same either way all right
it's fine I'm fine don't worry about it
I'm not gonna get grumpy
I'm already grumpy all right so we've
got the x and y and then we've got the
point index fine I'm a little unhappy
about it both fine and then we've got an
open brace close brace after an equal
sign here right so it's that and we've
got some commas so we've got the P
percent the size that sort of stuff
right so we're doing p % 1 p % 2 and the
size and then the type right and that
type is probably gonna be a length
string but I think we added our own
specifier for those so we've got
largess so you us there everyone's happy
then we have a question about whether or
not we would use to parents or not right
and then that's the end of it
so it will look like this but then
there's also a question here you know
maybe we include to parent maybe we
don't and so we'll have to have that
part specified cleanly as well okay so
what do we need here well we needed the
grid X which we have we have the grid Y
also have got the point index that's
good and now we need all of the actual
alignment point data that would be like
the point p % 0 so these are the things
that come out of there so we'd have the
P percent one size and then we would
have the type which we want to turn into
a string right and then we would also
have an is it a parent thing so we do
this which is a jet align to parent and
if it was to parent that we want to
append something and if it wasn't then
we don't and so I'm just gonna use this
little trick I often do this where I'll
just I'll use the format specifier to
stick a string on the end and then I
just won't stick any string on the end
in the case where the thing isn't true
right so we can do this and append that
to parent flag as necessary but we won't
append anything in the case where it's
not so really the only thing we have to
do here is turn this thing into a string
when we do that you can see getting a
line point name from type you can see
that happening here so we want to go
ahead and get that like so I'm not
really thrilled about the way this
particular function works here because
the align point is a little bit hairy
explain you what I don't like about it's
a little bit nuanced but one of the
problems that we're gonna have is when
you're looking at alignment point yeah
oh well you know what maybe I already
did it though
yes I did okay nevermind so I'm fine
with it I'm a little bit ahead of myself
so this get type here is exactly what I
wanted because I was trying to say is I
don't like the idea of not knowing how
much stuff I have to and off in order to
figure out what the type is but it's
okay I did actually add an access or for
that and in fact I even add an INXS or
for this so those kind of finicky rules
there that are maybe something's we want
to change feature
I did add actual ways of accessing them
more properly and so that's great and
that makes it easy to write this code
with some confidence that it won't break
if we change how these things are
encoded in the future which is what I
was concerned about so anyway inside
here we've got a line point name from
type with a get type that's exactly what
I wanted and that we got the is to
parent there so all I really need now is
the actual line at point itself so
here's the HHA a line point that's just
going to come out of a line points grid
whoops grid y grid X point index and now
we can do that export process right all
of this is just what I was using for
reference we don't actually need it for
anything so out it comes and then again
if we were actually trying to import
from the file we don't want to do this
this writing out instead what we want to
do is in here we want to clear right so
that's what we did
now if I come down to the align code now
we've got a little bit more work to do
what you can see here is Azra to me as
we're reading these things in I probably
want to do this as well so what I want
to do here is say look if this thing if
we're trying to read these out of the
file
then I want to actually do the copy and
if we're not trying to read these out of
the file that I don't want to do the
copy right and so that's pretty specific
so in here when we see this token and
we've got a line again I'm going to want
to do the same thing that's doing before
I want to do a copy up to but not
including for the token that we're on in
this case right and what that's gonna do
is that's going to say look everything
up to here I want to make sure it's in
the output file if we're trying to
output a file and then what I want to do
is I want to take all this data that's
in there right
and I want to see if if we're actually
trying to produce a new hht from the
from you know for saving out in hhd
files opposed to loading one in then
what I want to do is I want to copy the
data in its entirety like whatever was
here I want to copy but if we're not
trying to do that so if what we're
trying to do is just load in and romp
over it actually I guess that's not
quite true what I just said so what we
really want to do here I guess is say
look we want to copy everything up to
the alignment point I want to read in
the alignment point and then I want to
see whether or not the alignment point
matches the alignment point I already
have so I want to do like a memory is
equal call and I want to say alright
I've got the point in question right
which is you know gonna be something
like this and I should probably
I guess I'm only gonna do it parsing
succeeded so it's probably only gonna be
in here right so what I want to do is
say look I want to do some sort of
comparison here where I say whatever I
parsed in I want to see whether these
two things are the same or different and
if they're different I need to overwrite
them if we're actually doing our save
right meaning if we're actually
transferring with data so what I want to
do is say well you know what let's do a
test here and see what's up
let me first check we'll create one of
these things we'll do this a little bit
differently than what's being here so
we'll do this will create an alignment
point temporary structure we'll set it
all up right and we'll say okay set the
P percent the size and the type get all
those things in there then what we'll do
is we'll say hey does it differ from the
one we already have so here's the one we
already had and this will tell us that
right so it's like we've got the one we
parsed and we've got the one that
existed are they the same or are they
different and the other thing that we
might want to say is well well now that
I think about it I don't really know
that we do need to do what I'm about to
say
let me keep writing this and then we'll
see what happens so we're gonna check
this the memory is equal and if the
memory is equal then we can just copy
the entire thing so we can essentially
copy everything up to wherever we are in
the tokenizer like so so all that stuff
will get copied although it's actually
that uh so we can copy everything that
we've seen because we know that this is
just a duplicate and we don't have to do
anything else on the other hand if it's
actually different than we need to do
something more specific here and that's
gonna require copying back and it's
gonna require ignoring everything in
this whole range because we don't want
to copy this alignment point at all
right
and so looking at it here when we do
this require token of a semicolon this
is actually gonna cause us some problems
because if the alignment point was
different here
[Music]
you know we may not even want to write
it out right it may have been deleted or
something and so this causes a little
bit of an issue for us because this
require took in semicolon we need to
have consumed it and potentially gotten
rid of it
and so I'm not sure how we want to
address that
hmm
I say let's think this through very
briefly there are only I'm trying to
think if there's other cases but I think
there's only two cases there's the case
where we load things in from the hht in
a case where we write things out which
is not as complicated as I originally
thought it was
but anyway so if we are loading things
in from the hht then we never write
anything anyway so it doesn't matter
what we put in there that's all
irrelevant all we need to know is that
anything that we read in to me anything
that we read in is the answer right and
so one way to think about it would be
look this whole thing where we do any of
this right we only really need to do
this in the case where we have where
we're writing right so if we're writing
then we're gonna do that if we're not
then we're not and so when we come
through here we really don't need to do
any of this if we're not writing so
if we've got an agency out file then we
have to do this work otherwise we don't
we don't have to clear it because
nothing would be in there we wouldn't
have said it to anything because we're
not using what's in the HHA we're
reading it right so those two things can
be simplified a little bit because now
we know that look there's we don't
actually have to do any work in either
of these two cases these are just for
when we're rewriting the hht right
so the only case we care about here is
when we're rewriting the hht that's the
only time that we actually need to do
anything because otherwise we just read
everything in all ways right so you
could think about this is just saying
well actually this looks a little more
like this we can always set the
alignment points like when we read them
in and we're just not going to use those
in the case where we're writing things
back out right like whatever we parsed
in we're not going to use in fact you
could actually think of it this way
right we write things out or read them
in exclusively so if we were writing it
out we don't the only reason we care
about what we parse from the file at all
is to know whether we can preserve this
line of text or not that's the only
reason we're doing it right
and then the in the opposite case we
would just say yeah the align point
sorry excuse me
so I don't really know in this case if
we're gonna write it out yeah this is
the part we have to do if we're not go
write it out then we can copy it in and
off we go
so the tough part is just the fact that
we really want to consume the semicolon
and so I think I'm just gonna cheese it
because since we only want it in one
place I don't really know that I want to
spend a lot of time working around that
everywhere for no reason so I don't know
if this is a good idea or not but
consume semicolon is just gonna equal
false and so all the time it's gonna do
this right and then in here I'll just
say hey you know we're gonna consume the
semicolon in this case right that's just
this this thing does that right so when
we come through here and we get to the
end then we're gonna consume the
semicolon so here we go so we're gonna
require that semicolon assuming that we
get it and everything's fine then we'll
go through and actually do the copying
right so I you know at each stage will
think that through and so here once we
get here if the memory is equal then we
can do this and if it's not we don't do
anything actually that's not true
we need to mark the fact that we don't
do it right now this doesn't actually I
wonder if we can actually get away with
not having that and that would also make
it so we don't even really need that
call although I'm gonna leave it in case
we want it later but since we've always
copied up with a semicolon anyway in any
previous context I think we can actually
get rid of that and so this is all we
actually need to do although since
that's not true there might be comments
in between them so let's say we keep it
there then if we come up here we can
make another call that ignores things
and what this would do is say yeah if
there's an HST out then what we're gonna
do is just hard set this like so and get
rid of that and whoops and that that all
seems pretty good to me oops
so I think we're okay and I think that
would actually do it the only thing left
to do is right now we don't actually use
any of the stuff that we parse in so I
think that's the only thing left when we
do this call update asset metadata that
is probably the place where this would
occur
so inside update asset metadata we would
want to as necessary take whatever the
stuff is that we are that we read in and
romp it over the the information that's
in the HHA right so for reading things
in or writing things out we would do it
if we're writing things out so
interestingly enough like if we're in an
in a writing out mode then we just romp
over it if we're in a reading in mode
then we I'm sorry if we're in a writing
out mode we don't touch it if we're in a
reading in mode we do right
so I think we should probably do this as
a pointer meaning in here when we grit
get the asset index for each asset we're
gonna want to go ahead and set the the
information on that asset so we want to
do something like hey we want to take
this asset if there's a new alignment
point array then we would copy it in you
know like if something like this guy
right so if there is one of these we
would want to copy it in although you
know I feel like we'd rather just do
that outside
hard to say um if you look at what's
going on here right so we come through
and we say alright we're parsing we look
and see if we've got a match assuming
that we do we go through and update the
metadata and so it would be like right
here that we would do it
since update asset metadata is already
looping through the grid it seemed
reasonable to do that's here but like I
said I'm not really sure passing this
would be somewhat of a pain but maybe
not that bad and so we could make one of
these where we just say alright look
pass in one of these and we're gonna
overwrite it
if do you pass this one right so it's
like yeah I don't know and then how
would you know whether yeah I just I
just don't like it I just don't like it
so I think what I'm gonna do there is
I'm just gonna say look let's let's put
put another one of these on the outside
and we'll just do it that way alright so
if we go to update the asset metadata
then I will copy this data back in so
I'll say alright you know here's assets
in question and each one of these will
get copied back so in here we'll say
that the align points for the bitmap get
romped over this only happens in the
case where we're not writing out the
file and I think that's all we want
right so in the case where we're not
writing out the file then we would do
this in the case where we are writing
out the file then we
wouldn't now it's a little bit hairy
the reason that it's a little bit hairy
is just because if we're writing out the
file and you know you hadn't seen this
block didn't exist anywhere like in
other words this wasn't something that
was ever an asset that had existed prior
you know I don't know that you want to
erase aligned points that were in there
when you do the save so we do have a
little bit of a of a what is save and
what does load mean problem because on
the one hand we could say that if you
hit save it just over writes everything
right
meaning if if there's a block that
doesn't have a mash it like eliminates
it right and I don't know you know like
that that's kind of going down a whole
nother route that would be like saying
in this parse top of a block in here
where we do get or create asset source
file we wouldn't actually do a create we
just if we were writing it out
exclusively we would just check and say
does this exist if it doesn't exist blow
it away right like meaning we'd skip it
I don't know I'm just gonna leave this
for now because that sort of gets into a
whole nother level of what do we want
the editors stuff to do I don't really
care about I just only edit alignment
points so for names gonna say let's
ignore this and we and we really won't
talk about that but you can see why
there's like a bunch of things you could
start to think about and want to
potentially do as you kind of move
through that that space of what's
possible if that makes sense all right
so let's take a look at our errors now
this is what context assets that's why
that's wrong
it's nuts in there I'm not sure what the
types are of these I'm not talking about
basic category HHA asset that's what's
going and then asset is this HH a bitmap
yeah all right for out F we need to
actually pass the stream but after we do
that we should be fine memory is equal
needs the size obviously this needs the
context
this is same thing same thing and there
alright so a lot of stuff going on there
but I think that's basically what we
want and so we can look now and see to
what extent we're in the ballpark right
again just looking through it now that
we've done all this I do think it's
somewhat costly to do it the way we
decided to do it it's kind of cool
I'm glad I've done it once meaning
preserving the actual way that the human
wrote the hht rather than romping over
it with whatever the computer would have
generated for that particular in memory
asset I'm glad I've done it once it's
kind of interesting there are some costs
to it I feel like it's more fragile
because you know III don't think because
text files allow you to put things in
any order it's hard to make something
that does a clean diff style thing where
you just look at two things to memory
are they different if so write the whole
thing out right that doesn't really work
anymore cuz you got to do it like line
by line like did this line differ and if
so like save it or whatever right now I
could imagine a way of doing this better
and that would be that for every line
what you would do is you'd essentially
create a structure that was like here is
the version of this thing that just
stores a string for every field instead
of the actual field right and then when
you do your data diff anything that's
differ
you update the string and then you
rewrite the strings the actual strings
so that you've you like loaded all in a
strings you diff the data and every date
of the changes you change the string
corresponds the data then you write it
all out would probably be like the wor
systemic way to eventually do it um but
I think you kind of get into a systemic
situation there where you're like unless
you're doing like a whole system this
way with tons of different types of
fields and everything it's probably not
worth the time to really build that out
but you could see a generic version of
this that you could do and it would be
interesting like I think that would be
an interesting thing to make so you know
I like I said I hadn't ever really
looked at that before but it's
interesting so I'm gonna go ahead and
say look let's start playing around with
this inside our tags files where we've
got like base game hht what I want to do
now is I'm going to create a backup of
it and the other thing that I need to do
now is actually have a way that we can
see what our output is because if I
remember correctly we never actually
implemented that function so in the wind
through to file layer we've got this
sort of replace file contents and it
just doesn't do anything right and so we
need some way of doing this atomic
replace a way of actually writing
something out and then replacing the one
we have
so I need to open a file write the data
to the file close the file verify that
that was fine and then swap the two
files so that the new one and the old
one have like traded places you know I'm
saying so that's kind of what I want to
do here and the problem with this is
that a lot of times you can't really
like I don't know that Windows ever
created what you actually want for this
so what you want to do like the way you
would normally do this in an operating
system is you have the idea of an
unnamed file right which UNIX has like I
nodes do not I I nodes don't have to
have a mount point they can just exist
right so if you're working on a file
system that has the concept of an
unnamed file then what you do is on the
drive that you are trying to place this
thing you say give me an unnamed file
here's all the data write it all out
finish did that work if all of it worked
then swap it with this other files name
or if it didn't work just forget that I
know it ever existed don't link it in
and reclaim this free space right that's
how atomic replace is supposed to work
unfortunately Windows as far as I know
doesn't have a way to do it and there
are some issues related to how it does
work on Windows I'll try to sketch it
out for you now
we'll kind of jump in here and I'll show
you what I mean
so what we want to do now is we want to
take advantage of the crappy version of
this the crappy version of this is since
you have to have all the files have a
name
[Music]
give me a temporary file name that I can
use so that at least I know I'm not over
writing a file it already exists and
then when I'm done I'll rename it you
know in again no real reason for this
file probably almost ever to like exist
at all there are some times when you
actually want this which is give me a
name that doesn't exist somewhere but
most of the time you don't actually want
that you want to do something different
than that right but oh well so this is
what we would like to do now is be able
to do the atomic replace here and the
atomic replace there's a couple
different ways we can do this right but
the very the very first thing we want to
do is just call this so that we can have
a temporary file name that suits the
purpose that we care about right so what
I'm going to do is I'm going to call
this
and what you can see here is there's
some really dumb stuff involved right
but anyway this you unique thing here
makes like no sense for what you think
about what the API is doing if you
unique is zero get tip file name creates
an empty file and closes it if you
unique is not zero you must create the
file yourself right
which doesn't make a whole lot of sense
but anyway we want it to do that we want
to have it create found close it so it's
zero and again just to underscore how
bad this API is what you really want is
you just want give me the file so you
want it to actually return you a handle
right but again I don't know if they
ever added that they may have added it
finally at some point but I don't think
they did I'll scan briefly to see if
they did you didn't there didn't used to
be one yeah I don't see it so anyway
we're gonna pass a zero for that but you
know again that's sort of a separate
thing the path name is the directory
that we want so we need a way of getting
the directory out of this so we're going
to have to do that part right so we need
the dur name and then the prefix string
is the part that we are going to use for
sort of making it clear that it was ours
so we'll just use like handmade here oh
and this is going to be like some kind
of a file for like a temporary file temp
would be good but we already have the
age of T as a tag file so we need some
way of marking this as a temporary file
so I'm just gonna say like it's HH
underscore for now like it's just a
handmade 0 file and there's nothing else
on there so anyway we need that prefixed
string this has got to be a wide string
because it's gonna be calling this the
the W version it's what I'd actually
want fact I probably should have clicked
on the Wi-Fi
like so so these are both gonna be wide
strings the unique file number thing is
just going to be zero because we want it
to figure that out itself and then the
temp file name is actually their return
they asked for it to be max path
characters which again is just dumb
because that's not the largest it can be
and you know what can you do you know
that Windows does what it does so you
know it should really be based on more
information than that because you know
what the path name and prefix string are
so we actually know how long that would
be
so what Windows should probably do is
tell you how much it needs to generate
the max path or something there I don't
know better still would be it just
allocates it gives it back to you and
you free it but take some one half dozen
together anyway so VAW clarity here
which is going to be our filename and
they asked for math class plus a
millimeter which is that so we'll give
them that and then we just need to know
when we actually call this here we just
need to know what the directory name is
and the directory name is what's going
to come out of the information that we
were given so we'll do that and we'll
use the UN that's returned which is just
to tell us what's going on here where's
the return route there it is there's
unique numerical file if the unique
thread is nonzero the return faster so
have the same number of function fails
it's zero so we'll just say okay let's
if on that assuming this returned
something then we're in good shape we
should have the file name now and so
then what I can do is call create file W
then I can call write file and then I
can click call closed handle right and
we can write out this file and if all of
that succeeds and nothing goes horribly
wrong then after that's done I should be
able to swap the files
right so in order to swap the files
we're gonna need to be able to rename
things in order to rename things we need
to call move file it's not called rename
in Windows I don't you know just don't
ask me why it just it's called move so
the move file function I don't know if
we need the extended version of the move
file function we might let's look at the
flags so we do need replace existing but
that's about it so that's all we would
do there so we're just gonna say like a
move file at that point this is an if
meaning if everything succeeds then we
want to do a move file with replace
existing and again this is pretty easy
it's just the existing file name and the
new file name right I probably shouldn't
name it this way right so we've got a
file name that we're gonna overwrite
with temporary file name so let's
actually make those explicit we generate
the temporary file name we try to create
that file if we do it's going to look
like this so we try to do the create we
then try to do the right and the right
is going to determine whether we can do
this so we've essentially got like that
so that's roughly what we're trying to
do here and since atomic replace file
contents is something that can easily
fail like anything that touches the
drive like that is something that could
just fail the write could fail the
creation could fail the getting the temp
file could fail you know we have no idea
so when we do atomic
place file contents like that it really
should return here some kind of a
boolean value that lets it know whether
the right succeeded or not because
there's no other it's not like the other
one where we have existing handles so it
can just set the flag on the handle like
if you remember the way we did that
before it was just saying look there's
an error flag on the handle we don't
have the ability do that because there
is no handle you're just doing one
atomic replace and then you're done and
so you know if we do it that way then
what we've got is that b32 there that
should come back that's the status of
this thing right so it's like okay
there's a result here the result is
gonna get set depending on whether move
file succeeds or fails which I believe
is a return value of just a bool right
either it works or it doesn't and so
it's true with it's usually yeah so in
the case where we actually get move file
to work then we want to return true that
we were able to replace a confidence
it's the if anything else fails we'll
never get there and they were fine so
what we need to do here is say actually
I'm going to do this right so we're
gonna try to create the file assuming it
worked we're gonna try to write the file
and then we're gonna close it no matter
what so you don't want to leave the file
handle sitting around and then we want
to check did it actually successfully
write if it did successfully write all
the data according to Windows then we
will do the move and be done with it
right all right so let's take a look if
we want to see how to create this
particular file so let's do the right
file first since that's easier so the
right file function is pretty basic
it just needs the file it needs the
buffer which is this
it needs the size and unfortunately well
this is a little bit nasty it doesn't
actually have the ability to do 64-bit
writes so we'll practice hurt that we
already assert that in other places and
we will never be doing a 64-bit right
but it's just kind of a dumb aspect of
it right so yeah so let's take a look at
that one a point of the variable it
receives number bytes written when you
sing synchronous H file parameter right
fell sets this value zero before doing
any work or error checking
you know overlap doesn't do 64-bit
writes does it
well um so anyway we can't do an actual
64-bit right here and in this case we're
gonna have to ask for the bytes written
because it looks like they demand that
which is not great but oh well oops and
out nope don't ask me why this is
happening so we need to actually pass
that and what we could do is we could
make this a little bit Squinkie err we
could say all right well you know here's
the bytes written and maybe we double
check this just in case windows can
return true in this case and actually
return true that it wrote some bytes but
not all the bytes for example so what we
could do is say all right let's do this
and then we'll say well right ok we'll
assume is false and then we'll set right
ok equal two bytes written equal size
right what's kind of fun about that is
if we do it this way that actually means
that now we if you pass in an actual
64-bit number this function would fail
seems good because then at least the
person knows it didn't succeed right and
we could also put this in here right and
so that way this you know if this was
actually something larger than 32 bits
and the bytes written comes back as
however much it comes back it would go
like hey you didn't write the whole file
so don't you know don't do the time
replace good prevents data loss seems
reasonable so that's all good and we're
just down to create file W which again
is also easy I will go ahead and coops
grab that out and here it is so now
we've got the file name we know that
windows gave us the file name so that's
easy the divide the desired access is
just going to be generic right there is
no reading of this file so we don't need
that access not that it would be a
problem if we did but we don't we don't
want any sharing at all
there's nobody else should be accessed
this file for any reason in any way so
none of that stuff needs to be set the
security attributes in this case is
going to still be 0 we don't have any
circular t descriptor or anything like
that that we want to inherit we want to
create this file always and we want it
to be new right so what we'd want to do
is clear it and this what this does if
the photo phase is writable the function
over writes the file right and so we do
want that to occur so we want create
always technically I think open existing
would probably work because this
function is supposed to create the file
for us so I think open existing would
work here but you know oh well so anyway
we've got all of that set we then have
created Flags and attributes in template
file there isn't a template file so
we're just down to flags and attributes
and the flags and attributes I don't
know that there's anything in particular
that we need to set probably just normal
file I treat temporary might be
something we would set but I don't know
that we really care I don't think we
care so I'm just gonna set file
attribute normal for now and leave it at
that so we create the file write the
file and then we're done so really our
only sort of difficulty here is we need
to create some temporary buffer to store
the will not temporary buffer we need
that like parse the file name to extract
where the path part of the file would
actually occur so we're gonna have to
actually do that part and I believe
we've got a file name thing in
where we look for like fine last slash
or something thought we did maybe not so
I thought we've done this before and in
fact you can see it here but I guess
it's just called removed path well
that's fine so if we go back and look in
platform adage here
here's the platform file info for
replacing the contents I guess that I
think about it that means we have the
actual Unicode version of the filename
which is good so we should probably
preserve that which means that yeah like
you know in here where we do win32 Open
File this part here here is the existing
file that we're replacing so this is the
existing file name and so what we want
to do is process that to find the end of
the path and
so we need to scan that for the last
place where a slash would be and then
mean that becomes our directory name so
that seems fine but just looking at it
here
[Music]
let's think about this bring me back to
my temp file where's my temp that's move
there it is
so what do they actually want so
interestingly they don't even say
whether it should include the trailing
slash or not so that's interesting but
since this should have the entire path
in it already I should just be able to
scan for the last occurrence of a slash
and if there isn't one then then it's
just nothing right so should be able to
do this I shouldn't be able to walk this
entire structure
and since this is utf-16 it means we're
looking directly at the characters
themselves to see whether or not we have
a slash so what I would do here is say
okay if star scan equals this kind of
slash or that kind of slash will support
both no matter which kind of slash we
see we will assume that then that is the
last slash so we'll find the wherever
the last one is and then we will just
temporarily update this thing to use
that for the get temp file name which is
kind of Squinkie but we can do it right
so what we would do here is say hey
existing file name or rather the place
where the slash is we're gonna overwrite
with null and then and again this is why
I hate null terminators you're
constantly modifying strings for no
reason we could have just passed as the
length right if if windows took length
strings length strings are always better
there's like almost nowhere that you
don't want a length string but anyway
all right so we just can quickly do that
and that way we don't have to do any
copying or anything like that it's just
existing file name that gets us the temp
file name and that would just work right
so we can scan it find it swap it and go
but again it's just like really stupid
because if you use length strings you
never have to touch the strings to like
extract a pieces of them you just pass
the pieces it's much more efficient if
you use null Terminator 's either you
can't do it at all because poking in a
null would would be bad in that
particular case for some reason right
because multiple people need to use it
time or you're constantly doing like
poking and all UNPO kunal coconut right
and the only alternative is copying the
string everywhere so you're constantly
copying string is copying string is
copying string it's copying strings and
you never need to write you're just
you're really just proliferating a
tremendous amount of copying and or null
poking but usually more copying cuz a
lot of times you can't poke a null in
that's only like this is one of the few
times when that actually works and so
length strings just help it avoids all
of that right so you know it's it's it's
tricky to to see sometimes why mills are
bad way to do strings but they usually
are almost always okay so let's see
cannot convert argument 1 to LPC stir
that's because I put an A in there and I
meant a W so that's unsurprising that
that didn't work looks like that was all
we need now three arguments okay oh
right it's a move file XW that takes the
existing argument all right so now we
can try it and we can see what's up and
again now we just got to do a bunch of
testing find out what we screwed up I'm
gonna go ahead and put a breakpoint
there so that I can watch what's going
on oh it looks like we're still updating
it start up interesting so it looks like
we're getting a issue here what's this
what's
how are we getting the how are we
getting an error here so this is saying
we got an asset index back which we did
but that asset is not valid it's a type
1 asset which in our case is a bitmap oh
whoops
yeah maybe we shouldn't have two fields
name type so the asset has a type which
we're kind of using temporarily right
now as a patch for our tag system forgot
about that eventually that will probably
go away but it was in there as sort of a
stopgap measure and I completely forgot
that we had done that so that's not
that's not constructive that type field
has nothing to do with the one that we
were actually talking about so yeah that
was dumb so the assert here that we're
actually looking for oops report in this
case it's the HH a type that we're
talking about and that's really the only
type that the asset should have had at
all in the first place but again because
we're patching around the fact that we
haven't really finished up how we want
to do our tag searches I mean it's fine
it works but it's kind of crappy we are
just kind of using that tag that primary
category tag is something that we use in
a different way so yeah it's just kind
of it's just um but that's the way it is
for now we have to obey it so it looks
like this
alright let's try it again so the import
ran there and that looks like we've
still got some problems there because
we're not seeing this that wouldn't have
written the hht so it this is just a
straight-up import but it does look like
we're getting some align point weirdness
there potentially I'm not quite sure but
the fact that I don't see that fact I
don't see that there
makes me think that's the case now to be
honest that's actually correct
I guess because yeah the default is to
not have any points so actually that's
correct
where do we add that default alignment
point and why did we add it or when cuz
yeah now that I think about it that was
just something that I guess we were
adding during imports as an I don't I
don't even remember where we were adding
that do you folks remember we were
adding that
here it is
so you can see here we used to set this
default alignment point and we set this
default alignment point any time we went
to write an image out to the HHA and
that's totally wrong now look we don't
want that at all
I'm gonna look for any other yeah so
interesting enough I think what we
probably want to do I guess is when we
are loading in if we are doing an h HT
out meaning we're writing the thing then
if there isn't an asset we just want to
set a default alignment point probably
right
so because everyone needs a default
probably I mean we don't have to we
could force you to create one but that
seems kind of stupid so what I would
assume we would want to do here is say
all right when we are processing these
if we're loading them in like this then
if we have an asset without any
alignment points we insert the default
one there's a snafu here which is that
that means there is no way to delete the
alignment points entirely like if you
want someone who just doesn't have any
but I don't think that should really be
legal to be completely honest
so yeah I guess what I'd say here is if
we go through this entire thing and said
there's there were none right like there
just aren't any then we would maybe call
this right it's kind of crude hard to
say but I think maybe that's what we
want so we'll just do here like no
alignment points equals true and if
anywhere in here
there was one then we would say that's
fine so we'd say if there's anything in
any type field ever so that this thing
could be considered an alignment point
then it's fine right and when we do that
spin through it's just this
all right so let's see if that's a sane
way to do it and I don't know if it is
but you can see that that restores the
behavior properly so that now like
things have that default alignment point
so I'm gonna go ahead and just do a
basic right out now you know that I've
saved like I said I saved a backup here
of that file and what I want to do now
is I want to say let's just try
rewriting it without actually doing
anything at all so I'm going to do
import and save here and we're gonna
take a look at what happens so we're
gonna call atomic replace file contents
and if I step in I want to watch this
win32 code to see if it works at all
let's see what the existing file name is
it's tags intro cutscene that's correct
because the tags intro cutscene file
Jimmy the tags intro cutscene file
actually does have no alignment points
in it so those will get inserted now if
that makes sense which maybe we do or
don't want since we're gonna replace
this file I'll copy that one too just so
we've got it and I'm not sure how I feel
about that because if things only need
the default one do they really need to
get saved you know I'm not crazy about
that so here's a question can we do this
in some way where this default would
just happen automatically so that it's
what's assumed
like here's a question for you suppose I
was to get rid of this can we just call
this on the initial setup so we here we
would say look if we're writing the file
out then you know we're writing the file
out if we're reading the file in then
we're reading the file in we know we
have those two separate paths maybe in
either case if there's an asset we set
the default
I'm just trying to think about how you
would do this so that so that you don't
actually need to specify a default as
existing here's here's one thing I would
say I wonder if maybe that's something
that's just better done in the query you
know what I mean like when we actually
go to get one of those points should we
just fill it in there so when you do the
when you do when you look for a JJ
chokes the line default should that be
something that you just do separately so
like
like where do these actually get used
so I'm guessing it's find a line and so
for find a line maybe it's like look if
the result type is zero so we just
didn't find anything maybe we say if the
result type is zero then we'll set the
results equal to this so if we're
looking for a complete type of H AJ
align default right and the result type
is zero
can we do it does that help because that
would get us out of the business of ever
inserting defaults at all right that did
not work at all wouldn't this have to be
two-parent though as well like how was
this working before I'm not sure about
that because it feels like this yeah
what I've had it been a little bit
different but so if we call the other
thing I guess is for first align let's
see where that's called maybe it's that
function that we actually need to modify
yeah okay so so we probably shouldn't
really be calling that anymore but that
actually looks like what we need
so for this what we probably want to do
is say when you call get first align we
would say look the v2 result is gonna be
this
if the bitmap info align points zero dot
type is valid then we get it but I don't
love this and so I don't know how I feel
about that going forward but for now I
think that's more what we need so then
they'll be a default alignment or should
be a default alignment well it didn't
look like that worked that would create
you know a P percent here where we we
only get the Boop's we only get the P
percent in the case where there actually
is a valid when otherwise we'll assume
the the point five point five forget
first align and that would be the same
as having inserted the default I think
so I'm not sure why that wouldn't work
although again I thought find a line
would have been what we were calling
there inside the entity system so I'm
not sure what's up with that because
that should have been
so here's what we could do could also
say that we just get oh so I was right
it is the two parent that's why it
didn't work
this was getting set to two parent
because that's what two parent is right
there okay so yeah when we do find a
line we could assume that like you know
we set this and you know what I'm gonna
I'm gonna return it to the way I was
doing it before I think that's correct
so if what you were trying to do was
look for this then we will give you a
default but only then
better yeah alright let's see if that
helps me there we go
and so now those files should be the
same and so if I do important save good
I don't hit my I don't get my rewrite
case so everything is preserved exactly
so then if I come in here and say let's
go ahead and change one of those Lyman
points can I get it to rewrite it which
is a little hard in the slow version of
this thing let's see oh I got to pick
somebody first so let's pick this
and I'm going to add an alignment point
so we got the two-parent one here I
guess it should technically be like that
ish we've got the base of neck should be
about there and then I'll do import safe
so we'll have to debug this more
tomorrow but now we can at least take a
look I think to see whether this
function works properly I'm hoping that
now we're not rewriting the other file
yet we're writing base game that's the
part that I just fixed so that should be
good and then we can see okay did we
find the last slash okay looks like we
did let's see what our existing file
name is just tags that's correct let's
see if we got a temp file name looks
like we did so what is that temp file
name it's tag slash last hh7
eight-to-four dot temp okay so assuming
that was okay we'll go through here
we'll do our write to that file
it looks like the write worked close the
handle and if the write work then we
will go ahead and do the move right so
now we should have replaced the file
with the new file and off we go
right so that all looked look great the
only thing we might want to do here is
since it is something that contemplates
a failure case and you can see here
where we've rewritten this file it's
different now since we're contemplating
a failure case here the other thing we
might want to do in that function is
that you know if if we didn't you know
if we couldn't get the replacement that
we wanted there is a point where this
can fail like somewhere right here right
where the temp file has been
created but we don't want it to be there
right so this will remove it but if we
couldn't remove it right so if we if the
reason if the move didn't end up going
as planned we want to do a deletion
right we'd like to delete that temp file
so that it's not hanging around on the
drive for no reason
and so that's that removal call it
should be there for cleaning up so
delete file W right so we we probably
want to keep that in there let's go
ahead and open up meld which I think
we've got right and let's just see
what's going on with the files that we
rewrote so here's handmade and oops
here's the tags files so let's take a
look at the original and then the
updated version and see what actually
got rewritten so looks like in here
right you can see that we wrote out
those two files and oh hey look
everything else the same so it actually
worked perfect right it's exactly what
we wanted
there's the alignment info in there just
just so and my only question is is the
zero zero correct because I don't really
know I don't remember what the actual
grids look like in that particular file
but everything else is fine we didn't
put our tabbing in here and we don't
have a backslash n so I think we want to
add that back in there but other than
that looks fine so let's see if now when
we run if everything works okay or if
it's busted
and and we'll go from there because
remember now it's still we on load at
the moment we have it hard-coded to
call the import function which is not
probably something you would do normally
but that's still happening so if I grab
one of these right here let's just see
what we've got
yeah looks like it it reloaded it just
fine right so I think we're in good
shape so I'm gonna go ahead and update
that part to be able to insert those
back sessions but other than that I
think we're in good shape so now that
we've got that sort of through line
going there yeah I think we're happy
happy campers so in here I'm just gonna
put four spaces not the cleanest way to
do this we could have a much more
complicated system if we want to but for
now that's fine for me in the back
session so it preserves some manner of
formatting there alright and the reason
I say it's not perfect is because if you
were really trying to obey the file you
have something that looks to see what
the indent level is according to the
user at any particular point and does
that right so you know we're not getting
into that level of craziness here but
you could imagine that being the case
um all right let's go to the Q&amp;A now and
we'll finish this up tomorrow
just like looking for bugs and stuff and
anything else that we feel like doing
and then next weekend we can start on
there's other elements right
no the worlds are generated procedurally
do you think it is better to design for
the top 10% of programmers or the
majority in language or API design um so
I guess what I would say about that is
it depends what you're trying to do so I
don't think it's a better or worse kind
of question it's a what is the purpose
of this thing you're making kind of a
question right and so if your goal is to
make you know like let's say you're
making something like a scripting
language for you know an operating
system or something then it probably
doesn't make sense to design for the top
10% of programmers because it's kind of
just a utility layer that's used by
everybody and a lot of the people using
it aren't really even programmers in
quotes anyway there sis admin's or
something and so you know your your
design is should be tailored to who is
going to be using this thing if on the
other hand you're trying to make a
language for writing like large end-user
software then I think it should
absolutely be tailored to the top 10
percent of programmers because we've
seen what happens when you don't and
it's horrible I mean that's like the web
or something and it's like it's like
unusable
it's not like I'm usually bad and it's
just horrid it's it's like using a
computer from 1960 I mean it's absurd
the only reason you know that it's not a
computer from 1960 is because instead of
printing things as text you get like a
pretty graphical display but everything
else is exactly 1960 it takes several
seconds to process every request it
fails a lot of the time it asks the user
to intervene on things that are
incredibly technical clear your cookies
refresh the page what like what are you
talking about right I mean this is
absurd that a user would not even know
what a fricking cookie was you know
and so we've definitely seen what
happens when you expect real software to
be written by non programmers and that's
what you use every day online and it's
terrible right in an old stream you
mentioned that you like having all
allocators like push let's go through
macros instead of direct function calls
what's your reasoning behind this two
reasons one is so that they can cast
based on the size properly so for things
that are not doing just a blind sized
push that helps but for things like push
slides which don't need to do that
the reason I like them to go through
macros is so that they can provide file
online information during debugging so
if I want to know who's taking memory if
all I do is have a regular push size
call that Doug isn't a macro I have no
idea who's calling that but if it's a
macro I can insert the file and line
number in there and that way if I track
who allocated what I'll know so it's
really to enable that kind of debugging
and then of course in non debug builds
you just turn that off right so doesn't
cost you anything since there are a lot
of questions do you think I could
interest you in a pair of zircon
encrusted tweezers I mean what I will
say is that obviously zircon encrusted
tweezers are the best kind of tweezers
you know they're high-quality
I don't know if I'm quite ready to
retire to Montana yet
but when I do I will absolutely get a
pair of my own zircon encrusted tweezers
would you move to clang and implement
custom build tooling probably not with
clang cuz clang is really unwieldy and
gross if you ever try to open up the
like internals you're like oh my god
you know what exploded in here so I
probably wouldn't do any custom tooling
with clang if I was gonna do custom
tooling I would you know I would write
my own program of some kind claims a
nightmare
may I ask a larger off-topic question or
should I say tomorrow's pretty soon well
you might as well ask it and then we
could see
is there anything like operating system
garbage collection my professor talked
about not needing to free calls to
malloc due to something like that I
would imagine yes no idea what he's
talking about but I'm not sure either
well I guess what I would say is it
depends what your professor was talking
about but yeah there there are that does
exist it's a little misleading to call
it garbage collection per se but it is
sort of a thing kind of like garbage
collection traditional garbage
collection means that periodically a
supervisor of some kind interrupts your
program looks to see what memory is
reachable and unreachable from things
that are currently known to the program
and then returns those things that are
unreachable to the free pool of memory
right that's traditional garbage
collection that in a literal sense does
not exist typically in operating systems
however a light form of that does any
modern operating system now has to
understand what resources are used by
each process in the operating system so
that if that process tries to do
something illegal crashes runs out of
control it can be contained and stopped
right so a limited form of garbage
collection which is to say it's probably
better you better think of it less as
garbage or more as an arena you can
think of your processes resources as all
being in an arena marked for your
process and when your process terminates
it will all be freed
right file handles memory allocation IO
ports whatever right all of that stuff
is pinned into your process when you
open it or allocate it and when your
process closes it all gets closed and
freed so when you call malloc if you
want to reuse that memory again yourself
during the course of your own run of the
program in the same process you need to
call free if you don't ever need to do
that if you just use the memory and then
exit you don't need to call free because
the operating system will clean up that
memory by default if that's what your
president was talking about they are
correct and that's true in any modern
operating system in antiquated operating
systems where computers were less
powerful and things like that couldn't
really happen then this was not true so
so let's go ahead and take the last one
from Gary Johansen I talked to one of
the hammy debug teams
what's a handmade debug teams I don't
know and they made it sound like it
would be doable to expose all debug
symbols on an API level this seems like
a very powerful thing since people could
build custom logins on top of the
debugger itself this seems very powerful
I'm very leverageable is there anything
wrong with that is there some reason you
know a visual studio does not expose the
information to an API mm-hmm no actually
the opposite is true Visual Studio does
expose debug information as an API or
more appropriately
windows tool help does Visual Studio is
actually built on top of tool help and
there are PDB accessing things in there
so where's the actual so I guess to help
doesn't have it to help only has the
process inspection so maybe I'm wrong
about this I thought there was a way to
do that
I thought there was one of these but
maybe there isn't yeah here it is
so they do ship these they exist tool
help is the one for inspecting processes
and threads I for some reason thought
that the pdb stuff is in there but it's
not so it's all here right you can
access it so what's a debug help
yeah here you go
yeah debuck help sorry I got the yeah to
help was one yeah okay so you know it
does it does exist that's that's the
thing
yeah
alright that looks like about it so I'm
gonna go ahead and close it down okay
thank you very for joining us an episode
of hand made here it's a pleasure coding
with you as always that was a big push
we did several weekends of making like a
clean text in out thing that could allow
us to edit it both directions and it was
pretty cool it seems like we got it
working now which means we can mark up
our files all we want inside the in-game
editor which I probably will do tomorrow
and then we can test it out make sure
that we can edit everything cleanly and
then it doesn't like corrupt everything
and to generate and get horrible or
anything so we'll do that tomorrow
and that's also good because that means
all of our assets will now be usable and
we can play around with them a lot more
flexibly than we used to and it also
puts us in a good position to start
thinking about how we want to do the tag
querying and updating and stuff like
that to which we'd like to do and since
we have some things that we haven't
figured out how we're gonna really label
and use yet like the ground cover and
stuff like that that may be a way that
we can figure out those parts for our
system now that we have an easy way to
edit and mark things up we can try
marking it up a couple different ways
and query it in the file in the game and
see does this work or is it cumbersome
you know and so on so that's what we'll
do tomorrow
and we still would like to add sounds
and stuff so that'll be a little bit
further down the line but for the moment
let's just play with the bitmap stuff
make sure it's really working make sure
we're happy with everything and then we
can move on hope you see you back here
for that tomorrow till then if you want
to follow along with with the series at
home you can always fear to the game on
handmade hero dot org if you're free out
of the game comes with a source code so
you can play around with it and do your
own experiments we also have some other
stuff at my rocket if you might want to
check it out you can always click on a
handmade hero head and we've got stuff
here we just released meow the infinite
which is our new comic if you like web
comics might watch I can
out just click on me on the infinite and
and off you go
there's also my blog and you know the
bottle rocket homepage everything's up
there so yeah don't be afraid to click
on little handmade here I had there's
good stuff in there that you can explore
until tomorrow that's it for today have
fun programming and I'll see everyone on
the Internet
take it easy everybody