all right all right we should be live
now in theory and there yes the twitch
buffer has like you know finally catch
up with with however many seconds they
need yeah we're good all right so yeah I
guess we can start just kind of
introducing ourselves so we'll go around
the table I'm Jake I'm one of the
programmers on the team I haven't told
you I'm also a programmer
I'm PD I'm Jared I'm the producer I'm
sitting off screen taking notes okay the
fourth the off-screen programmer yes
okay and yeah just kind of give you a
little bit of a background about our
project so we're at school at Carnegie
Mellon at the entertainment Technology
Center and so part of that is after your
first semester you do semester long
projects where you just kind of focus on
doing one thing and so this semester
we're focusing on building a game engine
seeing how that goes so we kind of been
like doing our research in it of like
okay what before the semester starting
up like what goes into a game engine
there's a lot of things out there like
handmade hero and Jason Gregory's game
engine architecture book it kind of go
over all of it but we really didn't feel
like we know how to do it until we kind
of sat down and tried to do it ourselves
that's very true that's very true and so
we're going through that and then we're
the goal of the semester is to kind of
go through and when we were looking at
how other people did it we found a lot
of people who would wait till the end a
lot of like this other student projects
they wait till the end and then tell you
all about all the cool features they did
but no one really there wasn't many
others like your hand made here a series
that kind of went through like their
decisions and their thoughts throughout
the whole thing and so we kind of want
to go through the whole semester of like
documenting okay we made this decision
and this is why it's probably not the
right decision but we'll see where it
goes and then two months down the line
kind of say oh this is why it was the
wrong decision
and then talking to professionals like
yourself about okay we're doing this
project what what kind of advice do you
guys have and where you started and kind
of what other engine developers have to
say about the topic that sounds really
cool actually keeping track of why you
make decisions is definitely something
that I wish I did more often there are
certain projects where I've been like I
really want to make sure I get some of
these things correct and on those I
always take meticulous notes on them and
other ones I just don't for whatever
reason and you usually end up wishing
that you did because you're like why did
I think this was a good idea again and
like it helps to be able to go back and
know because sometimes it wasn't a good
decision and but it's interesting to
know why you thought so other times you
forget why it was a good decision and
then you go to change it and only after
like a couple days of doing other stuff
do you run into something like oh that's
why I have a trite few you know future
self was dumber than past self in that
sense so yeah I do think that's a very
good good practice to try yeah we're
very curious kind of see how it works of
like being further down the line like
how much we learn over just doing
because we only have about three months
to build this game engine so it's very
simple in yeah we've just seeing how
much progressively I bet by the end of
the semester we'll kind of turn around
and like all that stuff we made at the
beginning was just almost garbage
compared to what we're doing yes yes
that's that's probably true but I mean I
guess the other thing I would say is
there's definitely a tendency to
undervalue code that you have written
that is working a lot of times those
programmers it's very tempting and and
you're not wrong
right when you look back at code and go
wow I could do so much better but one of
the things interesting about that that I
find anyway is that a lot of times there
are a bunch of things you did in there
that you're forgetting are important and
that work and like it's almost like I
tend to look at code in a little bit of
more of a Darwinian sense these days
than I used to where it's like code that
can do something has a certain value to
it that code that's in your head that is
better doesn't have yet right and
depending on how complex the code that
your the problem that you're tackling is
sometimes you can drastically undervalue
those things that went right simply by
virtue the fact that the thing works you
know that they did and so I would also I
often try to encourage people especially
you sort of programmers with less
experience to sort of go don't be too
hard on your existing code if it works
because there's probably more to learn
there than you think there is or another
way to say it was you did better than
you think you did I think there's a lot
of talk about people you always say
clean code or is it elegant or is this
sort of thing and there's a tendency to
discount it worked as a really important
part so always be a little bit proud of
something that worked and and take more
time than you might otherwise to
appreciate why it worked because there's
often more there than people think there
is and then they go to like do some
high-minded redesign of it and it turns
out worse than the original version
because they didn't spend time
appreciating just like what went right
you know
so yeah separate thing but yeah this
whole whole stock we're just kind of
trying to get pull as much information
like that out of you so as much like
sure so how we're thinking of doing this
interview as you saw in like the
questions is a kind of like a
pre-interview where we kind of try to
get to know you a little bit better with
some kind of more basic questions and
then kind of go into an interview more
focused on the technical details of game
engines feel free don't feel free like
you need to hold back or anything we
might not necessarily understand but
that's kind of the point of this okay
yeah and so I guess first kind of
question simple question is a key tell
us a little bit about your background
your your schooling your hobbies and
stuff like that but you think find it
interesting that could be interesting
for game and development type of work so
I guess you know this this answer is
probably not going to be very
interesting so I'll try to keep it short
essentially I started programming very
very young compared to people probably
from my generation simply because a lot
of people wouldn't have had
access to very much that they could do
to program but my father happened to be
a programmer and that was somewhat more
rare in the 1970s I was born in 1976 so
the number of people whose fathers or
mothers didn't that in that day and age
actually it was more common for females
to be programmers as well actually I
think percentage-wise there were just
very few programmers at all right yeah
and so the chances that you had a parent
or you know in relative or something who
is programmer or even a neighbor was low
and the chances that you had programming
materials like compiler or books that
were about it or someone you could ask
was also low so it was pretty rare to
learn as early as I did I learned when I
was about seven years old my my dad
taught me basic on deck rainbow computer
and I just loved programming from then
like forward and even before then I used
to love typing on a computer just the
act of typing so I really never did
anything else I think I maybe gravitated
towards programming game engines because
it's a really interesting technical
thing to do and kids love games so at an
early age you're attending that's like
what you see most I you know I I
wouldn't have been naturally drawn to
like the the simulation of you know
thermodynamics that someone was doing it
Lawrence Livermore Laboratory at that
time as interesting is a technical
problem that may have been a child is
not aware or thinking of these things
today with the internet that may be very
different people may be getting exposure
to lots of other things that a computer
can do and they might think more about
that but you know I wasn't so what ended
up happening is I just really I worked
on that sort of stuff just on my own at
home on various different computers that
we had and I literally just never
stopped I didn't go to a college or
anything
I just ended up going into the game
industry sort of right out of high
school and I never have really done
anything other than game engine
programming hobby wise I do think I've
I've always been interested in sort of
the artistic things that go along with
game development so hobby wise I do tend
to look into and practice other things
like I've learned to do 3d modeling and
texture
and I've learned to do sketching like
concept sketching in that sort of stuff
and I and I learned to play piano I took
lessons as piano as a child and that was
very helpful to understand music stuff
so there's been a bunch of other things
that I've done that helped to understand
and allow me to communicate with other
people who work on other parts of the
project in ways that are much better
than I would have otherwise yeah but I
never really took seriously any other
profession or occupation oriented thing
I've never really had that experience
for all I know I would like some other
occupation better I have no idea what I
would say is that the only interesting
takeaway I think from any of that it's
just that I would say that learning to
do other things even if you don't intend
to do them is very useful from not only
the fact that you can communicate more
effectively with the other people who
are going to be doing those things so an
engine programmer who knows how to do 3d
modeling is kind of very valuable in a
lot of ways on a team because the
modelers have no way of communicating
with you other than in the language that
they understand and about the tools that
they understand and if you literally
just don't know all of like what goes
into making a 3d model if you if you
don't know how to paint something in
ZBrush or you don't know how to like
resurface something in 3d studio or
whatever um you don't have to be great
at it but just knowing what goes into
that can be very nice because it means
that you can then understand exactly
what they're going through on a daily
basis and be more effective at helping
them or understanding their complaints
when they have them or assisting them in
getting their tools into a state that is
better for them and I saw I feel like
those things are very useful for engine
programmers to have if you don't like
doing those things it's not a bad thing
there's plenty of room for engine
programmers who just want to focus on
optimization there's a whole suite of
people who just do that but if you do
find yourself being more I don't know if
polymath is the word for it but if you
do find yourself wanting to have a
broader experience those things are
helpful and you will find those valuable
as you as you sort of work on technology
even though you're not technically doing
any of those other things yeah question
follow-up question to that is do you
find artists
or like designers coming to engine
developers and asking those questions or
is it more you as an engine development
kind of need to go out and see what
other people are doing and communicate
with them that way it's both so one of
the things that you'll find is that
artists in particular I think are very
boxed in in their understanding of what
a computer could be doing oftentimes and
this is because they have been sort of
brutally treated by tools like Photoshop
or any Autodesk product you might care
to purchase and so you know they may
have gone into art or computer art with
sort of a more boundless imagination of
what was possible but they have been
beaten down I mean you can pretty much
expect that any artist has been beaten
down to the point where their ability to
imagine what a tool could be doing for
them is very limited because they've
constantly faced just I don't want say
rejection but they've been constantly
faced with barriers to them ever
realizing any thing in their head they
may have had right so anything inside
that boundary you can usually count on
them to communicate to you so if it's
just a case of like I think this thing
should be working in Photoshop but it's
not or we would like a way to be able to
use this Photoshop feature but your
engine isn't supporting it those are the
kinds of things that an artist might
bring up to you things that they have
sort of been taught that the computer
does not do they don't know programming
a lot of times and can't be expected to
realize that that's just because Adobe
doesn't do that right like it just yeah
that thing isn't exist so anytime that
you can observe an artist working or
spend time just looking at how they have
to go about creating things or working
with with the tools that they use to
make things is very valuable because you
will see things that a programmer
obviously knows could be fixed but then
an artist just may not realize can be
fixed and again I think that's just
because
that you know they're an artist they
think in art terms and they have never
have the ability to change the tool in
any meaningful way a lot of times yeah
so they just they just think that what
they have is what they have to live with
and and they especially the older the
artist is or the longer that they've
worked in with computer stuff the more
they will just accept the reality of the
tools and you can no longer expect them
to bring you any kind of pie in the sky
idea even though that may have been
something they would have thought of
before they were sort of taught rigidly
what is available to them another way
let's say it would be artists are used
to adapting to their medium when someone
gets a charcoal Penn State have to use
charcoal and they learn to use that
medium so it's exactly the same
computers after they adapt to the medium
they can no longer tell you what they
wish they would have because they've
been trained out of it essentially most
the time all right yeah that's a really
interesting point of view on that guy
actually going back a little further to
when you were saying you started
programming at seven and you're
interested in games too
when when you were around seven were you
making your first games or were you just
kind of experimenting making like hello
world type programs yes so when I was
seven both of those things are accurate
statement so when I was seven in basic
basic the the the basic language was
very much what you might think of as on
like an Apple 2 or something if you've
ever seen one of those old form you know
in a history museum or something so I
wanted to make a game but not only was I
not really capable of understanding a
lot of the stuff that would have gone
into anything that you would think of as
a game today but basic wasn't super
capable of doing anything at any speed
in those days anyway I mean even if you
just wrote a semi language you couldn't
do things at very high speeds in those
days for obvious reasons so all I made
for games were things that would
basically print out like some text like
imagine a text adventure where instead
of actually because I didn't know how to
implement the back of a text adventure
it's more just like a multiple choice
right so it would print out like a line
of text and like be like what do you
want to do and it would be like one or
two and I would just hard code the
results right so you can think of it
kind of
of games that are sort of on the level
of interactivity of you know a today's
game by say David cage do you want to
push the button to do the thing or not
right like and that's all you get right
so it was that without all of the fancy
graphics was all I could do for obvious
reasons a to my brain was just not
capable of understanding at all no
experience and then the fact that
computers are so slow to write so so
yeah they were games but yeah yeah I
think everyone's kind of first game
mm-hmm
so then going off off of that when about
would you say you started creating your
first engine like about how old / like
and water around what were you thinking
of building so the first engine that I
liked I would say that I attempted to
build I guess I would say that I did
build it is in eighth grade for a
science fair project I built this thing
that was essentially a I guess you could
call it King's Quest without animation
so - maybe a better example would be
like a magnetic scrolls kind of a thing
but from the old days where it had like
a picture and the picture could change
based on the state of the world so it
wasn't like it was completely static it
could show you different pictures
depending on like what room you would go
to or like if you open the door it would
change the door from a closed version to
an open version but there is no real
like animation in any real real time
sense like you didn't see characters
walking around and there was really no
spa animation so you know pretty pretty
back back pretty far in sort of the tech
center and what you do is you type in a
line of text and it would execute it so
opened or closed or North those sorts of
things
that's yeah you could do any you know
whether or not you want to call it a
game engine as opposed to just a game in
an engine that we're sort of together I
don't know but it was design started to
be an engine so there were like separate
pieces in a sense and that was the first
one that I really did
and you know obviously it wasn't good
but it was it existed something
definitely so kind of moving a lot
forward in time now to handmade hero
so we're as we're kind of building up
for this project we were checking on a
lot of your videos and you're at like
470 now I'm sorry something like so I'm
going on as long as this how do you do
you ever refer to any of your past
streams or how do you keep track of
things going on so like with such a long
project by yourself so I think there's a
couple things to appreciate about
handmade hero which is that the
development streams are very short
they're an hour to two hours there's
really there's only once or twice we've
done like a marathon where I did four
hours you know so 477 or whatever right
now let's say let's just say 500 500
hours or even a thousand hours of
development I is really not very long
for a 42 year-old programmer that's you
know a couple months of development time
if I was working full time and so I
think that the it's easy to think well
this is so many episodes because if you
were just coming at them to watch them
you know when you were gonna like I'm
gonna sit down and watch handmade hero
the whole thing it's like oh my god
right
but it's really not very much
programming like if you think about how
much programming each of you has already
done in your life it's probably pretty
similar I mean you spend a lot of time
programming if you're a programmer and
the amount of time it would take you to
get to five hundred or a thousand hours
of programming isn't really that much
you know and if you haven't already hit
that now you'll probably hit it before
you graduate from whatever program
you're in now but you know even if you
don't do that your first year of
full-time work you'll definitely hit it
right so I don't know how much program
guys have done but you've either already
done it or will soon do it and so it's
easy for people to overestimate the
difficulty of
of keeping track as I get that question
a lot and I think it's just because
people don't realize it's bigger
it sounds bigger than it is it's
actually a very small engine splendor a
hundred thousand lines of code every
time I'm programming I'm explaining at
the same time their entire episodes that
are nothing but whiteboard essentially
or a blackboard in this case discussions
and Sue the amount that I actually have
to keep in my head in handy here is very
small but if you watch some serious I'm
like I will say on a day I don't really
remember how we did X like you can find
episodes where I've said that and what
hopefully you can see is what I then do
is I just go into a very straightforward
process that I always I always just
assume that if I wrote code competently
in the first place a cursory inspection
of it later should reveal to me how I
decided to do things it won't
necessarily reveal why because I may not
have encode anything I tend to not
comment code until it's done done cuz I
find that the comments end up being out
of date and end up being
counterproductive I write it's actually
describing the thing that was before the
latest one you know and it's actually
worse than having a no comment and so I
I think that part of developing a good
programming style it has a lot less to
do with things that people normally
focus on which are like these rules you
know did i overload operator equals to
prevent a copy big they focus on all of
these rules that they really have never
even really tested or proven in
production really save you any time and
they ignored like the most important
things which in my opinion are how easy
is it for me to read my own code later
and know exactly what it does right I
mean and that's like one of the most
important things you can do and so
that's really I think what keeps hand
made heroes so flexible and easy for me
to not have to worry when I come back to
it on a weekend to start doing a stream
is I just know that's part of being a
competent programmer is writing
in a way that doesn't require me to keep
it all in my head I can easily go look
at the function names and I just know
what they do and this is doubly easy if
I'm the programmer because I know what
assumptions I make and if I just always
make those same assumptions then I know
I don't have to investigate those things
further you know I know I'm not gonna
call new in the middle of a thing
because I never do that right so a lot
of things like that if you develop a
programming style that you find is
effective simply leaning on that style
in your own code will allow you to keep
it flexible keep it easy to remember and
recall when you do forget so I think
those are the two aspects one of them is
about becoming a good programmer in a
sense which is is is making sure that
your style actually pays real benefits
and not hypothetical sort of textbook
unproven things but the other one is
just I think people overstate the
difficulty of the handmade hero thing
it's it's not that hard when the code is
that small you know try doing that on
the Unreal Engine codebase right I mean
I would not be coming back to it and
going like oh and I'll just do this I'd
be like what is going on here like let
me step through it in the debugger for
six hours before I really know you know
so yeah and you said like interesting
there where you're talking about your
own personal kind of standards and
conventions so when you're on the team
of people who have maybe have different
kind of things that they lean on do
suggest that everyone kind of you kind
of start recognizing people's styles or
do you try to force people and
conforming into one style which might
get them uncomfortable with something
yeah like I I know exactly what you're
asking and it's an excellent question
and I think that honestly I think there
is no good answer to it I'll I'll say a
few things about it but I guess what I
would say is that is probably one of the
biggest problems in programming today if
you imagine that programming in a sense
is a two-part process because I think it
is
one is and they're not separate
processes but there's two you know sort
of things that are going on anytime yeah
one is coming up with a language and the
other is speaking in that language so we
talk about having a programming language
but we really don't have the programming
language that we use what we have when
we talk about a programming language is
a building block for the language that
we will use it's more it should probably
be called a programming alphabet if
we're honest or a programming phonemes
because usually what happens and in any
game engine this definitely happens is
that first you take the language that
you have like C++ and you build your own
language on top of it which is sort of a
functional language of core things that
everyone will talk about you know how is
the memory managed and how do we
implement sort of the render pipeline
and what how do we pass things back and
forth what is the job control story you
know all these arts things yeah those
things form a secondary language and
this is a it's in some sense a very
recursive process you could think of it
as making lots of languages on top of
each other and some perming languages
and some program projects are so poorly
thought through that there's like
languages on top of languages on top of
languages in some sense right and so if
you think of each programmer is sort of
having their own ideal language that is
what they would like to see that
substrate that's right on top of the
regular language that they all had to
conform to yeah they're all fluent in
that presumably their own one so when
you bring two programmers together you
essentially have a problem where it's
like hey you and I should write this
book but you speak French and I speak
Spanish right and it's like okay well
how do we come together to write this
book that's you know still in a Latin
style typography but it's neither of our
languages and we get right and so I
think that the jury is still out I might
even say that the appellees and the
plaintiffs and defendants are still out
on what on what the right way to do that
is there's certainly procrustean
approaches that are like here at
you know company X we demand everyone
have this many tabs and their thing and
every class looks like this and there's
a file for every block there's people
who specify everything right and it's
like everyone must have conformed
there's other places that are just like
do whatever you want and if that will
figure it out the boundary right will do
something and and everything in between
and I think that we don't know the
answers to what's right about that and I
would be absolutely lying if I said I
thought I had a good solution to it what
I can say is that there is no question
in my mind that there is a difference in
speed efficacy and quality of code that
comes from shifting from your native
language into another one so shifting
from your native programming style into
somebody else's costs you and you have
to balance that cost against the fact
that when we work together we can get
more done if we have more competent
programmers on a project assuming each
of them is capable of writing something
useful for this project we can get more
done you know up to a certain point
obviously there's communication costs
that might kill you at some point but
four or five people on a project should
be able to get more done than one person
on a project my experience with working
on the witness was definitely that I
took a pretty massive productivity hit
working in that codebase compared to my
own and and there's nothing you can do
about that i I do build some of my own
language in there like I put some of my
own tools in there as overtime so that I
can be effective but it's on an
on-demand basis and there's an entire
article I wrote about a time when I had
a bug that I had only because I made a
wrong assumption about the math library
right and that's a perfect is like the
reason that me and John blow are both
able to write certain part types of code
quickly is because we both make
assumptions about what our math library
does and if you couldn't make those
songs we I had to literally read the
code for cross-product or something
every time to figure out whether it was
right-handed or left-handed I would be
much lower at having way more bugs right
blah blah blah and so
it's really hard to overstate just how
important that is and I think a lot of
people don't necessarily realize it
because if you've never programmed by
yourself on your own engine at a time
when you were a fairly mature programmer
if the only time you ever did that was
like in your basement or whatever right
and you've never done that after you've
had a lot of experience and are more
self-confident and have more of an
opinion about what should be going on
you may not realize how fast you
actually are when everything is done the
way you expect because you've only ever
done it at valve or something where
everything works maybe a little bit
differently than how you would want to
write or something yeah and so it's it
is a very important thing to be aware of
I don't have an answer but it's
important to understand all right yeah
thank you so then I've kind of going off
of that you mentioned a little bit about
are you working on the witness and kind
of adding your own layer into there has
there been like a hat per se that you've
done recently or seen recently that you
thought was a either really unique or
kind of interesting to to do or like way
around the code base or something like
that how can you be more specific what
does that mean a hack so kind of going
off of like not necessarily following
the rules that are kind of laid out by
like the other person programming it or
so typically probably not like handmade
hero but maybe like when you're working
with someone else's code so I may not be
understanding the question correctly but
if I'll restate it to see if I am so
what you're saying is that if you are
programming in a code base that was not
that you did not yourself design yeah is
there anything that I can think of
that's a particularly interesting thing
that's done in that code base that goes
against the grain of the code base but
that was interesting is that yeah yes
that's what I mean so I guess what I
would say is that I would really I would
probably never consider that to be a
particularly grad of
flying experience so know that to me is
just always a sign that there is a
problem with whatever the code base is
because generally speaking if I have to
do something that I feel is antithetical
to how the code base is architected or
works in order to get something to work
properly then fundamentally speaking
that's really just more of a statement
about the poor quality of the underlying
thing and not a statement about
something good about what I did so if I
you know to put it in other terms I
might say so you know have I ever felt
particularly psyched about something I
accomplished when programming on
Microsoft Windows and the answer is no
I've just been aggravated the entire
time that it was so annoying that I had
to go to these Herculean lengths and
maybe you know I could look back on it
and and warp it into a sense of pride
that I was good enough to make this
thing that worked around a really bad
system but I guess at this point anyway
in my life I don't have a pride about
that I just feel bad I just feel like
this is it was a waste of my time and
it's gonna be a waste of everyone else's
time and it's just a shame that stuff
like that's still around and never seems
to get fixed I'm sorry to answer that
question with a downer but yeah going
off of the kind of your answer of that
when you notice something that you're
like you feel like you're doing
something like that is there you do tip
and like you're working with other
people is it typically kind of go to
address address the person or do you
kind of try to dig down into what
they've done to figure out why it's like
this just kind of curious about your
thought on that yeah okay so that I that
I definitely I think I understand that
that question um so I guess what I would
say is I would not take my advice or
perspective on anything that has to do
with that so I don't like working with
people on code I like working with
people on other things I love working
with artists and so on I don't like
working with other people on code
because I don't care to do exactly what
you're saying I just want things to be
done well and if they are done well I
don't mind using whatever paradigm the
person who did them well has if they are
not done well that I'm just aggravated
and I don't really want to go have a
conversation with that person about it
that's not to say that I I'm not trying
to belittle that I think working on
teams and learning team communication
and how to work effectively on a team is
something that's a great thing for
people who want to work on teams but the
reality of programming is that you know
everyone has their own preference and
one of the reasons I like programming is
that there's a lot of things I can do
and I can earn a living
not having to communicate with people
about what I'm doing I can just do it
the way I want and get it right so I
would say most of the time my preference
for working on things is I work on my
thing you work on your thing we
communicate about those things but not
about the code and I don't care how you
did it and I don't want to butt in on
how you were doing it and to the extent
that I can
I just want those things walled off so
that your code doesn't affect mine and
mine doesn't affect yours so we really
just don't have to worry about it that
said I appreciate how it is not always
possible to put yourself in that
position especially if you're working a
larger company or on a very large
project and that is just why I don't
work on those things okay and so kind of
continuing off that so having like a
fans and like backers to hand-made arrow
have you felt like that's and the people
watching you as well do you feel like
that ever influences the way you do
things or kind of changes your thought
process about any of the things that
you're doing on the engine or is it more
they're just kind of there along with
the journey with you um it's the latter
in terms emotionally I guess I would say
meaning that I don't think of people who
buy handmade here as backers it's just a
pre-order for a game you get the source
code if you want it it's not a
Kickstarter I don't require a certain
amount of money to
do it I'm doing it whether no one ever
bought it or not so I don't really think
of them as backers if they were backers
in the traditional sense of the term
meaning I had promised some specific set
of deliberate deliverables or something
that they were funding to make happen
I might consider things in that way but
since it's not that I really don't think
it's that way I made here it's think I
wanted to do I wanted to have video of a
programmer making an entire game from
scratch so we could go back and look and
see like what where do things get done
how do they happen right and all that
sort of thing and you could jump around
it and all that source I just wanted to
have that yeah that said it is
unquestionably true that having people
watch on the stream affects the series
and the reason for that is twofold one
is that there are a surprising number of
experts who show up to the stream from
time time and from time to time yeah and
those experts know things I don't know
so for example you know someone might be
more of a platformer expert on a
particular aspect of OpenGL or something
than I am and they'll tell me on the
stream so I'm there's something that I
might have programmed worse and they'll
pop up and say oh you know you can do
this or that's not support on this card
but if you do this it is right those are
things that are just better now like the
it's like having a second it's like
having a free code review that I don't
have to really spend any time on right
it's just happening I don't even have to
wait it's just happening over the
internet with thousands of eyes waiting
to point out something that I could have
done better
and that's kind of a cool free resource
it definitely means that there's
sections of the Hammad hero code that
did things right that would have done
them wrong or you know if right and
wrongs may the wrong term but did things
better than the way I would have written
them or did write them and then
corrected yeah similarly like there's
been times when people have pointed out
resources I was unaware of I the last
time I had really done any x64
assembly language work well mattress
emulation
intrinsics work I didn't know about
Ayaka the the the Intel code analyzer
mm-hmm cuz didn't exist and so when I
saw stream I was like I really wish that
I didn't have to count all the
instructions and that there is a way to
just you know compiler should just tell
me what they are and you know I think it
was Fabien who was just like there is
like go you can go download Ayaka and
use it and I was like oh my god and like
that tool is awesome like it's exactly
the tool I wanted and who knows how long
it would have taken me to find out that
that tool existed if he hadn't randomly
been watching the stream and told me you
know I mean yeah so it's definitely paid
dividends having a stream that I have
nothing to do with the original stated
purpose of the stream just having
experts in various domains especially
ones that I am NOT an expert in has been
helpful
even in my knowing Bayaka helps me in my
own programming dirt day job right like
so that's been great yeah been really
good I'm kind of going on the other side
of you of like the the people following
along kind of in the same boat
exhaustive like learning how to do
things with regard to handmade hero
do you think people can use handmade
hero is like a sole source of learning
kind of watching from the first to well
following you kind of through it or do
you think it's a really good use of like
watching this and doing some other
things and kind of doing your own thing
all at the same time because like you
said you have the zip files available at
the end of the days and stuff like that
that's a really tough question so I will
start by saying that the goal of
handmade hero was to do it the way that
I'm doing it because I wanted to have
that complete record and it was designed
to be there because I thought there were
things people would learn by watching an
engine programmer just do what they do
rather than them telling them the result
they ended up with mm-hmm
and I think it's been really good at
that because I've had many people
actually tell me that that was a big
breakthrough for them they were like
just seeing what you actually do totally
makes me feel more comfortable about
doing how to go about this right yeah
and so that I think was the only thing I
was trying to really do with handmade
hero so that's the thing that I think is
important to take away from the series
and what I hope people get out of it
everything else I have no idea because
the goal wasn't to teach people 3d math
I just do that as of course too serious
as I wanted it to be I wanted people to
see explanation of those things yeah I
don't know if it's a good way to learn
it um I don't know what other things
would be valuable so I think I'm not
really sure probably the answer is I
mean one answer is if I was gonna make a
course for people to learn 3d math for
engines let's say it would look like
handmade here oh yeah right so that's
definitely true whether that means
there's other resources available right
now that are better than Hanneman here
oh I don't know but I know that handmade
hero isn't the best we can do I could
say that for sure because if I made one
I wouldn't make it like this and I'm the
one making handmade here I'm already
saying it's not the best for that right
yeah um so I I guess that's really all I
can say about that part of it the other
part that I would say is just to focus
on the part you said about using as a
sole resource I don't think you ever
want to use any one programmers ideas or
code as your sole resource and the
reason for that is because it's assuming
everyone's brain works a little
differently and that the most efficient
way to think through a problem is not
the same for everybody
yeah then unless your brain literally
works exactly the same way that mine
does and there may be some people out
there who it does right but it's only
gonna be some people then the chances
that all the things you might want to
know about programming are encompassed
in what I have to say is zero there's
going to be very valuable approaches and
things that I not only might not be
aware of but even if I am aware of them
might just not like and not think are
good that you will think are good and
that are effective for you so I think
it's important to be exposed to multiple
different programming styles so that you
and and even more so than that I think
it's important for our programmers brain
to be able to distinguish between those
styles in a concrete way because that's
the way you can find the primary styles
that work for you and I think like when
I found myself I probably say when I was
like 23 24 maybe I don't know how old I
was at I'm about the same time as I
found myself actually thinking how do I
figure out what elements of programming
style are good and bad for mice like I
am NOT taking anyone's opinion you know
I don't care what people write in these
books I've realized that they don't
really know what they're talking about
all the time I want to come up with mech
I want to come up with ways I can
evaluate this stuff for real and I want
to see how it works when I do it about
that time was when I felt like I became
a much better programmer like it was a
you know you always feel like you're
getting better but that was a really big
divide and I think that it's important
for programmers to try to cross that
divide for themselves and it they're not
gonna cross it by watching a series like
mine and assuming that everything I do
is right because even if everything I
did was right for them they still
haven't developed the critical faculties
necessary to know why and that's a
problem so not only is that a problem
but I also suspect that for most
programmers not everything I do in the
way I do it will be the way that they
should do it because they will find
different techniques are better for them
okay all right so we're gonna kind of
now move on so we have a few questions
that we so part of our project is also
as we said to talk to professionals
we're gonna edit and then transcribe
these so that way other people can kind
of learn from them because we found we
think that blogs are a really good way
to kind of learn process that's how
we're doing
of our learning and so as I was saying
we're trying to help
novice novice engine programmers and so
when you first started programming like
larger scale game engines what was like
the most confusing part or maybe even
not even large-scale but when you first
start programming game engines well
we've kind of the largest confusion that
you might have had approaching those ah
so this is a very intricate question and
I'm not sure how I'm gonna answer it in
a way that can be concisely transcribed
and useful okay
let me say a few things about the
question and then maybe you could ask a
follow-up question that will get at the
heart of what you want to know and again
I transcribe that all right perfect
okay so there are two fundamental there
are two fundamental problems that I
think are involved in game engine
development that set it apart from a lot
of other types of development the first
one is that it is it is not a stable
problem in any way 99% of everything
that programming does in the past or
today looks a lot like standard in
standard out right you can phrase it as
here are set of inputs and here are the
set of outputs that come out of it so
most of the things that programmers are
used to thinking about in the way that
they're used to thinking about them is
I'm working on deep learning here's a
set of input images and a set of output
tuned neural net parameters how do I
make the best translation between these
two things right I'm a natural language
processing person here's all the corpus
I want in and here are the like noun
tags I want out or the sentence tags I
want right and so I think one of the
core one of the
biggest challenges for an early game
engine programmer is making the leap
from input-output thinking to this
amorphous systemic tons of things in
crazy states come together in this weird
way to produce an alternate reality that
you can experience right and it's very
confusing how that happens at first
because even though you're not
necessarily aware of it everything
you've ever done prior to that looks a
lot more like this input-output phrasing
right yeah um so one of the really good
things that you can do at first right is
to try to figure out the the sort of
what I want to call the the core loop
the the golden loop the the the golden
differentiator of a simulation which is
like a flight simulator a game the
things that have this right is they look
like this real time loop of I have a set
of entities States right I go through a
simulation to change the states of these
things that's a certain process I then
go through a way of presenting those
things and then I return to the
beginning right yeah just getting
yourself comfortable with that and that
everything that you build has to build
out of that is just the first big step
it's not input-output anymore it doesn't
look like a web program it doesn't look
at the neural network
it doesn't look like a parser doesn't
look like a server does look at any of
these things it looks like that
hopefully a lot of people are able to
make that leap without too much trouble
but it's just worth noting that's the
first big thing you've got a kit so you
figure out how to do that make a very
simple thing that has those properties
and get it working understand that
everything from now on will have that
structure not the other one right yeah
okay the other thing is the complexity
explosion right
so again because it's not input to
output where you have this very clean
sort of thing you have all of these
systems that are all happening the same
time they all interact they all overlay
on top of each other the physics and the
rendering and the blob is that the other
thing game design entities scripting all
this stuff comes together you really
need to be able to do discoverable
architecture in order to do these things
correctly and most people are just not
familiar with that process and what I
mean by that is I called it compression
oriented programming in the past what I
mean is the technique of writing
something in the simplest way possible I
think this is Jonathan blows term that
he uses often he says like write
something the simplest way possible just
whatever is obvious to you don't even
think about the rest of the game engine
I just need to do this one thing think
about it more like the standard and
standard out that we're all used to how
do I just freeze it to just get the
input and the output to do the thing I
need to do just in isolation anything
else no code design no cleanliness no
nothing just no abstract thoughts just
concrete you need to be able to do that
clear everything from your head and just
do that and then pull that out into the
architecture and one of the biggest
mistakes that I think even experienced
game programmers will often make is they
go the other direction they try to start
with the architecture and drill down to
the thing they want to do and I have
never ever in my entire life seen a good
result from that it almost always has to
be refactored
at the end because when you start from a
conception of how something will plug
together you don't see all the details
you don't know all the things that
you're really gonna have to do when you
go to solve the problem so you always
forget some whereas if you just
implement the real thing first and then
pull it up into the architecture fit it
in you almost always end up with better
results so I like to think about those
problems and this gets away from
question a little bit so I apologize but
I like to think about dough so much
there's thing called boundary value
problems in mathematics right yeah and
there's different ways of solving them
there's like shooting methods I start
here I see where I end up they're
solving backwards where I try to see
what I could different um building up a
skillset of how you work on code that
allows you to work from either side of
the problem ends up being really
valuable in this case because like I
said you usually want to start with the
solution loft it up into the
architecture but in addition to part of
that prop process when you get to a
certain level of that lofting you want
to think from the other side down as
well you want to go what should a good
API for this look like what are some
things I maybe didn't think about when I
was implementing it that I should maybe
change that wouldn't break the algorithm
but that would let it work better with
this integration so it's kind of like
this you you almost want a ping-pong
game process where you start at the
solution work backwards a little go to
the architecture side work forwards a
little come back and it's that the best
programmers at doing this sort of thing
are able to come at it and make it fit
really nicely at the end so both sides
can be happy yeah I'd like to give a
shout out to Allen Webster for that by
the way he's he works at rad game tools
now but I've talked about those two
things separately and I never really
talked about them together for some
reason and he actually asked me a
question he's like I've heard you say
two totally separate things I've heard
you say start from the solution and work
backwards to integrate and I've heard
you say always write the usage code
first well which one is it and I'm like
you're totally right like it's like it's
that you do the first thing I said until
you have the thing correct and working
and integrated then you work forwards
and go how should I talk to this thing
what are the changes I need to make and
why never connected those
my brain no but I give him full credit
for that realization that you should
always talk about them together just
talking about them separately doesn't
help anybody yeah I can see talking
about him separately cause like a little
confusion after hearing the second even
in my own brain it's it's it's clear
that I was doing something intuitively
that I'd never internalized and probably
was therefore forgetting to do sometimes
when I should have done it so I'm I'm
very thankful to him for having like
identified that rather important gap all
right
so we've been reading through some of
the handmade hero forums and we came
across one where you were kind of like
restating the the goal are talking about
who this handmade hero was actually for
and I think one of the lines you're
saying is that it's not about making a
game but it's about like I think you
said inspiring engine programmers or
something along those lines yes and you
said there there's a shortage of people
who are trying to be engine programs yes
why do you think that there's a shortage
of engine like people trying to get into
the engine programming space versus
versus like the other in spaces so you
know I I don't really want to do too
much data free analysis on this I guess
is what I would say because it's
attempting to provide answers well if
you ever read the newspaper you will
know that's very common for people to
like to provide answers to things that
they obviously just don't know what
they're talking about right and have no
data to support them so this is a
question that sort of demands if it
wants to be answered correctly demands a
data answer which is are there really a
shortage of engine programmers and if
there are why right what's the reason
for it I don't pretend to know the
answer to either of those questions what
I can tell you is that if today you told
me I needed to staff up a 10-person
Engine team which is a modest engine
team I would have almost no idea where
to get eight of those people right and
the two that I maybe do know where to
get I'd have to hire from some other
team right and now that team has to hire
two engine /
that's right yeah uh and so I'm strictly
talking about this from a personal
experience in the game industry it is an
anecdote not a statistic where I say
that I just don't find that people know
where to hire engine programmers and I
mean I know so many people who I know
plenty of people who have hired people
who they really don't think are even
that good at engine programming but who
were definitely the best they could get
I mean they could not have gotten better
intrapreneurs but they wished they could
have right
and similarly I know plenty of people
who would hire another engine programmer
right now if they could find one but
there's no one who meets their cutoff
right and so some of that is just like
well you know if especially on smaller
teams you can't afford to hire lots of
junior people maybe so maybe there's
some raw talent out there it just needs
to be developed you know and I can data
wise I don't I don't want to make claims
about this that I can't substantiate
because I don't have the data but in
terms of real experts on this it's just
very hard to find and I can't offer you
a reason for that
but I just assume that the reason is
that I even in today's day and age were
a lot of people license engines the
bottom line is even something as simple
as using unity kind of requires you to
understand 3d math at a pretty decent
level if you're not gonna ship one of
these games with all these like obvious
bugs in it right and so it's just it's a
hard profession it demands that you know
a lot of things it's not for the faint
of heart it requires a lot of expertise
a lot of time spent learning even to
just be a competent engine side
programmer like I'm gonna modify Unreal
Engine in a small way I'm going to
modify a real in small way I'm gonna
make a plugin that does something I need
to do or even I'm just gonna competently
program a motion controller in unreal or
something yeah these are just skills
that people just don't seem to have in
abundance and so you know even today
when it's like well you can just go get
an engine so you don't need to build it
from scratch
we still haven't it's just
we have not gotten to the put to the
point where we've we have enough talent
verses and at a strong word expertise
really we don't have enough expertise
versus how much we could be using to
make games better yeah no sorry I wasn't
trying to make you pull any any yes it's
it's that's just a personal experience
and you know it's I I suspect if you
talked to other people in the game
industry they would have similar
opinions about how hard it is to find
good engine programmers and I and you
know I don't want to put words in their
mouth so you should ask them but I just
it's not the kind of thing that you can
just go find someone to do and I think
we're getting better at pipelines for
finding artists it is much easier to
find a highly qualified artist today
than it was 10 years ago
thanks to social media thanks to online
tutorials education about what goes into
making a game asset probably thanks to
even school curricula that was not
around in those days what I have not
seen change is the number of of engine
programmers the last three engine
programmer hires I know about or was in
any way involved with all came from
handmade hero if it wasn't for handmade
hero never would have found him and who
knows if they even would have done it
maybe they would have something else I
don't even know so you know that was
really again the reason for handmade
here was exactly what I just said it's
in that that intro sort of fluffy video
I did there it's right it's like it says
I believe this way of life is worth
preserving it's talking specifically
about a practice and a discipline and a
mental model it's not I want to show you
how I make a game never said that right
I said I this way of life specifically
this and I meant that like I don't mean
what's the easiest way to make a game
what's the most cost-effective way I
don't care at all about that and I feel
like that's something that's covered
well enough elsewhere right yeah yeah
all right
so then talking a little bit so you're
you're making handmade here and you've
obviously made engines before handmade
here it is there certain aspects when
you I was listening to on your videos
and you're saying you've made at the
platform layer like 15 times and you
kind of know how you like it but is
there certain things like that that you
kind of always just pull in from each
project or do you ever try to like say
oh I've done this ten times before I'm
going to try it this new way to keep
exploring or they're just tried and true
systems that you kind of follow along
with uh so I guess I can't really answer
the question because I am only 42 years
old and not wise enough to know yet
look maybe when I'm 80 I'll be able to
tell you if I had a piece of code that
was worth reusing here's a couple of
things I can say along those lines for
the very first time on 1935 which is the
main project I'm working on now for the
very first time I decided that I never
want to write a platform layer or
standard library again I'm like I'm just
gonna do this one final and I'm gonna
move on I'm just gonna make that
statement
so I actually on this project and this
is a very long project for me it's it's
you know I'm I'm expecting honestly this
project is probably a five year project
which is a long time for one programmer
it's not that much I mean five
programmer you programmer years whatever
want to call those yeah whatever the
mythical man-month would want to call
that in you know I know if you guys know
the the Brooks book the mythical
man-month
it was a classic of old yeah it's about
IBM 360 don't worry know if you were
alive so for the first time on this
project I decided to do that I felt like
I was ready to do that and I tried very
hard to do that whether it succeeds or
not I'm not sure but what I will say is
I took an approach that was slightly
different from approaches I had taken
before
and I did to bring it back to the
beginning of our session today I did
exactly what you were saying so I have a
file and in it every time there is a
question about what I'm gonna do in the
codebase I document exactly why I
thought there was a question so why did
I think that the answer to how this
should work is not obvious I discussed
the solutions that I've tried and I
select one of them and say why I ended
up selecting that one out of the ones
that I tried so there is literally for
the first time on any product that I've
ever done a 100% complete documentation
of why every last thing works exactly
the way it does right yeah and so I am
trying to do that on this project and
we'll see how it works out prior to this
project I've never really felt like that
was something that I wanted to do
because I've always felt like there was
probably room to grow each time yeah and
that was usually because I never sat
down and said let me think all these
things through because a lot of time to
do a platform layer you just do it right
and this time I approached it with the
other the other angle so we'll see how
that goes but that's definitely I think
even for myself who who advocates a very
limber style of programming where I
don't think you should really calcify or
do a lot of upfront design sorts of
things even I if I want something to be
the be-all end-all this is the one we're
gonna use forever I do want to spend up
more time recording and justifying
decisions I don't do them from the top
down like a UML diagram disaster
situation or anything like that
but I do I do feel that a higher level
of rigor is necessary and what I try to
do in this situation is sort of play the
devil's advocate as if I had more than
one program the project come at it from
different angles can I justify it from a
speed perspective can I
to fight from ease-of-use perspective
can I justify it from a future like
compatibility with possible hardware
directions that sort of thing okay and
so we'll see ask me in ten years if it
worked I so so kind of going off of the
last question a little bit more of when
let's when handmade hero is done or like
your engines and the pastor done
specifically actually specifically
talking about handmade hero when it's
done do you expect other people to kind
of use handmade hero to make games or do
anything with or is it purely for the
the kind of like that the process of
watching it I know we kind of going over
this a little bit but um the the latter
it is designed to be a standalone
project that shows all of the parts that
you would have to do to put together a
game that you could release on Steam
where you didn't use anyone elses code
to make it that's the entire goal of it
doesn't have any any ancillary goal it's
not designed for people to use for some
other purpose or anything like this that
said two things one I would like when
the product is finished to essentially
do an audit if you will of the codebase
go through it all and I would like to
point out because I know there will be
many because this is a very limited time
project the total number of hours that
we spent on handmade here is less than a
year of programming time so lots of
stuff in it is very rough right yeah I
like to do an audit find all of the
places where I think that roughness
really shows and write up exercises that
programmers can go and take thing I'm a
hero code base and fix something I
didn't have time to do right and I just
say like this piece of code should be
able to be better in these n ways pick
one of those n ways and fix it that's
your homework assignment right yes I
think that would be really good for
engine programmers to start with in an
engine that's made a bunch of decisions
whether they're right or wrong you've
got to live with them because that's
gonna be your job when you're first
starting out probably here's the Unreal
Engine it does 50 different things wrong
you can't change those they're baked in
the architecture it would be
massive change to fix them or whatever
so you got to live with them how do you
make these improvements or how do you
fix how do you make this one part better
leaving with those constraints so the
hammer here will be no different
here's a bunch of things that does wrong
here's one thing we would like to
improve you have to take it as a whole
and just make that one improvement so I
would like the codebase to serve as that
in the future yeah and I think it can
serve is that pretty easily the second
thing I'd say is in terms of expecting
people to use it now I kind of do expect
people used to make other games because
I've had many people use it for other
games already I've had multiple people
write to me and ask is it okay if we use
this for our game and I've always said
the same thing just make sure it doesn't
conflict with handmade hero and you're
fine
I've had people already release games
who did them for like game jams and
stuff who use them at your codebase so
there's games already shipping that are
on the hammer hirako base so I guess if
that portends anything the answer is yes
people will use it however that was
never my intention
gotcha so moving on to so we while we
were doing a little more research about
you we all read your piece on the walk
monster thought it was a really
interesting tool but towards the bottom
we like where you talk about you're like
still open questions while you're
writing it of like oh you could add this
feature this feature in this feature at
what point does investing into it like a
test system like this become a net loss
versus or like spending too much time
investing in a tool versus just using
the tool for what it was originally made
to do I suppose what I would say about
that is that although as programmers
gain more experience if they are a
talented and hardworking programmer they
will gain a certain amount of what I
would call taste I think I might want to
attribute that term to Jeff Roberts the
person who founded rad game tools and
wrote the video codec that is used in
every game that's ever shipped in the
history of time
he I think used that term taste and I
still use it which is to say the things
about decision-making that we probably
cannot now possibly ever but at least
not now boil down into a rigorous
science or you know anything of that
nature
I suspect yeah as a parent gains more
experience and if they are good and if
their conscientious they can gain more
taste about how to make a decision like
the one you've stated okay I think it
was probably completely implausible for
anyone to be able to give advice on how
to make that decision
you either have enough experience to
read the tea leaves to know and you're
conscious of programmer to make a good
decision or do or do the tests necessary
to make that decision or you're not and
I don't think someone can really help
you gain that early not yet anyway maybe
we'll learn so in the future what I
would say is that people almost
categorically undervalue visualization
so if you were going to err on the side
if you can't decide whether it's good or
bad to make a visualization you're on
the fence make the visualization that's
about the only advice I can give the
chance is that it will be not useful
compared to its cost are almost zero if
you get to a point where you're pretty
sure that you don't need any more
visualization then you can stop but if
you're on that fence if you're like oh
this could help us it might not I'm not
sure go go visualization that's about
the only piece of concrete advice I
think I could give
yeah I kind of going off that too so
just a little I'm just curious of on how
the tool so after you kind of did all
the visualization did you have to kind
of fly through the map and try to figure
out oh like there's this red circle here
or because there's like a leftover
collision box isn't even better did you
kind of have something that would pop up
and like populated text file or
something like that I'll answer that
question briefly because on
I think it's Thursday I'm giving a talk
at the Busan indie connect conference
where I will show demos of all of the
tools we developed for walk
checking and processing in the witness
okay
they are drastically more advanced than
the ones that I wrote about in the walk
monsterpiece and walk monster in fact
was never used on the witness we
replaced it with things that are many
times better than it so it was more
really more of an exercise walk monster
was of determining that we had a problem
and that we had a serious problem
uh-huh but the solution to that problem
was actually much more involved in went
in a different direction so I guess what
I would say is all of the problems that
walk monster was designed to prevent
we ended up either preventing
systemically in ways that they literally
could not happen or developed better
visualization tools for that are much
better than walk monster and you'll see
those on Thursday they've told me that
it will be recorded but it doesn't
matter I'll post a recording of it
either way so presumably they'll either
be the official recording or I'll post
one and you can that'll probably two
weeks or something okay and you can link
to that in the write-up if you want to
get perfect so one of our kind of last
questions about handmade hero is say you
lost everything and you had to start
from square one again
what would you is there anything that
immediately comes to mind of like I do
this section differently or approach
things differently well I mean yeah
obviously there are but that's because
of the point of handmade hero which is
to say that the whole reason for
recording the process was I wanted to
see I wanted people to see me go down a
few avenues before picking the one I
wanted or to see how a amorphous
unstructured piece of code resolves into
a structured one so for example fairly
recently one thing we did over the past
three weeks in fact was we made the
renderer standalone in a DLL that now
anyone can use to make a renderer that
does all the things that handmade heroes
does so the depth peeling and like stuff
for sprites and the
your coat all that stuff is kind of in a
separate library now so if you wanted to
just make a game that has an instant 3d
hybrid sprite block renderer you just
have one right yeah those are exactly
what I wanted people to see in handmade
hero so if I lost the whole thing I
almost would say I would start a
different project because if I was going
into handmade here with the knowledge of
how everything worked out which I now
know it would totally ruin the entire
point of the series watching me type in
code I already know how to do it get
isn't worthless that's what a blogs for
right or a github repo here's how to do
it we're done right so the whole point
the series was to show that so I on
handmade hero it was critical that I not
have a solution in mind when I started
for at least some of the major parts of
the project preferably all all right
and then question about making builds so
making a build of the game can be kind
of a like a witness a build either like
making the engine of dll or kind of
compiling the game with the engine kind
of together kind of doing that process
can be a little bit of a hurdle or kind
of something unknown at least from our
point of view and so when you're doing
something like that is there any good
advice that you have to start it like
early and keep it going on or is it like
kind of what advice you have on creating
builds early and like keeping them going
rather than breaking ideal sue I might
understand the question but I might not
so okay if I may ask some clarifying
questions yeah so if you were to
substitute into that question rather
than game engine some other thing like
what have you worked on in the past even
a small project just give me anything
that you've done for school work or
so we work we worked on like a like
unity games and do us everything well so
I can pin missile program um I worked on
something with the had somewhat of a
bill that we make you simple with C
maker is just like a really really
crappy version of Photoshop so
essentially taking the different pieces
we made it also something of like a
switch to make a utility for hospitals
to use it with things so okay okay I I
think I had a question now so is it
correct to restate the question as
follows we have not traditionally worked
on code where we actually built an
executable from scratch so we have not
we have no experience really with that
process how should it work is that yeah
okay okay so it's not yeah because I was
not sure if you meant for a game engine
specifically and I was like well what
would be different about a game engine
but you're just talking about the
process of working outside of someone
else's build they've handed you yes it's
okay gotcha so I think what I would say
about that is that it's a lot simpler
than you think
one of the problems so so i'll veer into
an anecdote here at the risk of eating
up more of your time at know if you guys
getting bored sitting in your chairs
here so if you've ever used an email
program which by this point we all have
you may have occasionally been kind of
amazed in a sense at how how they
managed to have so many bugs are so many
problems in something that all it really
has to do is just send a piece of text
from one place to another right it's
like it's like one of the simplest
things you could do over a network and
it's been done for decades and it still
kind of somehow mysteriously impossible
for them to get it right
so back in the old days at Bell Labs
which was obviously one of the like
crucibles of software engineering of
place that created
see and UNIX for example yeah they had a
term for this and it was called mailer
science and it was a joke that they
threw around because nobody could ever
understand how the people who always
ended up working on the simplest
problems made the biggest mess so it's
like why is this meal program so broken
it's like mailer science man it's just
mailer science so I would offer the term
build science as today's equivalent of
that we currently have some kind of
weird programming culture where people
you you would there's a term called
build engineer all I can say about that
is what is going on right so the way to
approach a build is to realize that
computers today are so fast that almost
any game engine you care to make
especially on a team as small as yours
can be built with a batch file in like
ten seconds anything you do more
complicated than that is a waste of your
time people throw in integrated
continuous build servers and see make
and ninja and distributed builds and
Python all these it's like no just
forget all that get rid of it it's not
necessary all you need to do is just
make a thing that says CL here are the
files this is the exe I want build
that's it I'm hand made hero we show how
to do this the first day yeah it's
trivial you don't need anything more
complicated than that and I would
encourage you to start there okay
eventually somewhere down the line there
are some arguments to be made and
programmers who I respect would make
arguments for doing some of the slightly
more complicated things like a
continuous integration server when you
have multiple platforms so once you get
to like oh we're shipping the switch the
PlayStation 4 the Mac the Linux the PC
build the Xbox one bill the ps4 build of
this
right uh-huh it can be hard for an
individual programmer to have everything
installed on their machines to keep
those builds up to date and to know if
they've broken some totally other build
that they don't even have the SDK for at
that point sometimes sometimes it
becomes valuable to take that step if
you do it sensibly and make sure that it
doesn't interfere with the quick fast
simple build that you use day to day so
I would put that up but otherwise
especially if you're only on a single
platform a single line build is the
build you want it shouldn't be more
complicated than that single lines with
a single batch file couple lines is
plenty and I would also say that there's
really no excuse for build times to get
above 10 seconds there's a utility that
I put out called C time that times
builds and keeps a record over time you
look at that graph if it's crawling
upwards figure out how your builds are
slow and fix them okay so that's the
advice I would have and if you have any
practical problems with that like I said
handmade heroes first day just shows how
to do that or just look at the code I
can send you our batch file after this
and you can look at it it's super simple
I advocate using what's called a unity
build not related to the tool but what
that is is essentially just saying look
make a C file that just includes all the
CPP files you want build that one CPP
file that's your build ok that's that's
super useful information now it also
speeds up the build quite a bit because
the fewer CPP files that the the fewer
translation units the compiler
translates the faster it typically goes
because every time you split into
multiple translation units those
translation units usually include some
of the same H files which increases the
processing load so by merging them all
together you process every H file only
once which can drastically speed up some
builds like by orders of magnitude
sometimes if those H files are complex
ok
birthday so we are actually done with
all of our questions that we have for
you the last thing we have would be so
as we said we'd like to do like a
company with like the kind of edit about
a five minute story that you have on
game engine development but you think
it's interesting so it can be anything
of your choosing so if you have any
story that you'd be willing to tell and
I'm not totally okay as well yeah I mean
that's sort of the problem with that is
there's lots of I suppose stories but
I'm not sure which one are really all
that interesting or or useful so oh go
ahead yeah or just gonna say it doesn't
necessarily need to be useful at this
point this is one thing that we want to
show people for the sake of programmers
and maybe even other people who get into
the space and see maybe the work we've
done but they don't really care about
that but they might be interested in
seeing just something short that could
introduce them and then hearing
something interesting about space like
oh wow I didn't realize dealing with
that or like that just sounded really
like a really funny problem that it's
more or less of that so you don't need
to necessarily have it be super useful
with anybody as one unit five minute
video you'd have to give me a second no
take your time
yeah absolutely
yeah I really just don't know I mean one
of the things that's true about game
development is that the things that are
interesting to you are not interesting
to other people and so you know I mean I
guess what I would say is that all of
the things that I that come to mind when
I think of them I can't imagine them
being particularly interesting anecdotes
to anybody most of the time you know I
think when I think back about what were
sort of the most interesting game
development times they were almost
always in sort of circumstances where I
had been looking at something the wrong
way and then you know after doing quite
a bit of work on it or something
realized there was sort of this other
way to do it and that insight is kind of
really really fun for for the person
who's been working at it but I just
don't know how to turn most of those
into into an anecdote sometimes in
lectures you know I've sort of told like
I've had a lecture there's a at the
papers we love conference where I talked
about figuring out that you could blend
quaternions using linear interpolation
instead of spherical interpolation and
how that discovery came about and like
some of those things we're really
exciting at the time and they just
there's not much you can really anecdote
anecdote eyes about them although you
know I could I could sort of stretch one
out I think if I had to pick something
to say that would go into a compendium
of the kind that you're talking about I
think probably what I would say is that
when I was little
because I've always been a programmer
like like I said since I was very very
young I always wanted to program and in
those days there was really no internet
and no communication with anybody so I
didn't know any game developers and I
didn't know anything about game
developers right I just had computers
that I could program at home and I tried
to learn to program them and make games
on them as best I could and that was
really all I had to go on and my father
who was a programmer was not a game
programmer he worked on traditional like
tools for Digital Equipment Corporation
which is a now-defunct hardware company
right and so most of the things that I
might have wanted to know he didn't
necessarily know like he didn't know
hardly any 3d math or anything like that
that you would use for game development
because it's just not that's not common
knowledge among programmers right so one
of the things that was really exciting
for me as a young programmer was when I
was still in high school I had met over
this previous summer some programmers
from Microsoft and they were going to
lookingglass which is a company that
again doesn't exist today but they made
a bunch of games that a lot of people
consider seminal like Ultima Underworld
and System Shock and theif the dark
project and flight unlimited just a lot
of very important games in the pantheon
of games when people are talking about
history they were going there to port
flight unlimited to Windows because this
was at the very early time when Windows
didn't really run real-time games for
the most part because it didn't have a
way of actually writing graphics to a
back buffer like you would in das and so
they were going to go do that and they
asked me if I wanted to come and my mom
let me take a few days off from school
so instead of going to school I went
into Cambridge and I like got to go work
on the
windows port of flight unlimited and
it's the first time I'd ever really set
foot in a game company and I think about
that time often these days especially
because as you get older you definitely
become more sort of cynical about
everything about development about
companies about everything you know
everything you do and it's easy to lose
sight of what you love about things or
what was important to you but I think
back about those those days now and like
it was like the most magical experience
I imagine it was probably similar to if
as a you know a lot of children grow up
maybe dreaming of playing in the NBA or
something and it's like you know some of
those children probably get to randomly
get to go out and shoot a free-throw you
know with their favorite team you know
or something like this and it was
exactly that experience for me I you
know just even seeing what it looked
like to walk into a game development
studio and see what the people there
were doing and like meet the people
behind it and I remember literally like
everything about that experience like I
remember we went to a grocery store next
door called bread and circus and we
bought like some bread and cheese and
apples and stuff and brought them back
and like ate them around a lunch table
things that are inconsequential I'm sure
to everyone else who work there still
like stick in my memory as like I don't
know if you can call it a formative
experience because that's a sort of
different thing I suppose but it's
definitely like it just shows me how
much of an innate draw towards this I
had and I expect that other people who
you know if if you want to know whether
this is the kind of thing you might want
to be doing with your life if that's
kind of the way you feel about it if you
have those kinds of feelings then you're
probably right um but if you don't
maybe not right I mean it's a hard job
it's not like playing games it has
nothing to do with that and so I feel
like you have to almost approach it from
that same thing and maybe the NBA
examples pretty good if you like
watching people play basketball that's
not the same as liking playing
basketball and it's good to know which
of the two you want to do because if you
just like watching basketball then
there's no harm in having an ancillary
job you could work on the communications
team for your favorite sports team just
like you might work in the production
department of your favorite game company
but engine programmer is the on the
court job that's really demanding and
demands the kind of dedication I think
in a lot of ways that an athlete has to
have you're expected to know a lot more
you're expected to work a lot harder
you're expected to know such a to have
trained your brain in such a demanding
way at some level that I think you kind
of have to have a certain love for it to
really want to do it and and to get back
to maybe one of the questions you asked
me earlier that might be why I think
it's so important to try and expose more
people to it because I think there's a
very limited number of people who really
have the desire to do it and finding
those people is important to me and I
think that it's worth doing and there's
so many other jobs out there for a
programmer to have that are not as hard
as this and that aren't as demanding is
this that I think that there's plenty of
other jobs for people to go to and I
think they will go to them if their
heart's not really in it so finding out
if your heart is in it is good and and I
would encourage people do that as early
as possible I don't know if that's the
kind of anecdote you wanted but but
there you have it yeah that was pretty
spot-on it okay so we're actually done
with any of our all of our questions I
don't know if you have any questions for
us regarding things but if if not we
really thank you for all the time we've
taken and we really appreciate all the
questions you were able to answer for us
and oh we got my pleasure those were
excellent questions and I
wish you guys the best of luck on your
programming project making gay mention
is very difficult the only piece of
advice I would have is don't be too
ambitious with what I've accomplished
you know I always tell people make
asteroids first and it's something to be
proud of if you can even do that from
scratch because most people can't most
programmers can't so best of luck
everybody
thank you so much have a great day you
know we'll definitely be trying to watch
the view same comfort okay yeah if you
want more information on waka monster
it's got everything because it's not
walk monster the talks actually called
killing the walk monster because we got
rid of it and and I will explain how and
why so good
[Music]
uh so I'm still live here I didn't look
to see what was going on
chat I don't know how many people whoa
we've got a lot of people watching
actually I suppose
I don't know if anyone has any questions
SF gardener says that was fun
cool what was that
that was just there there is a team I
believe that Carnegie Mellon they said
so there they're in University who is
working on a game engine development
project and they were sort of saying
that they wanted to an email to me they
were saying they wanted to get some
people's perspectives on just engine
things as part of their project and that
seemed like a really smart thing to do
and so I just you know said sure
anything I can do to help so these this
interview was just the questions that
they had I don't know how helpful my
answers are gonna be but you know I I
just tried to provide as much
information as I could that me you know
maybe is useful to the project they're
trying to put together because they're
kind of putting together some learning
materials to it's well I guess for their
own use and for other people's I suppose
what is the killing the walk monster
thing is talking about so it's it's
there's this thing called the Busan Indy
connect
[Music]
[Applause]
there we go it's a festival in in South
Korea I believe this is the shop from
last year it's a combination event one
of the parts of the event is that there
are indie games that are going to be
shown kind of like in the mega booth or
you know like a look in a festival
setting I think there's some judging to
see what gets into what doesn't but I
could be wrong about that I'm not sure
how that part of process goes I wasn't
involved in that but then there's also a
small conference where a couple
different speakers are speaking and
Chris Hecker is I believe going to speak
on spy party stuff I believe this is a
spy party design lecture they for some
reason haven't put the talk descriptions
up i believe chris has sent them when I
just don't it's just not up do I think
it's a spy party design lecture that
chris is gonna do I don't know what
Tyrone is talking about but I'm assuming
he's talking about publishing work they
do it Nicholas I don't know I don't know
what this blockchain one is about mine
is about the wok system that I
implemented for the witness and so it
it's talking about the taking from the
point that I wrote the article original
article on wok monster let me see oh man
this is okay let's try more specific
guess there's another thing called one
monster it's it starts with this article
where I talk about what a thing I did on
the witness and shows some of the
techniques that we were using early on
in the project or not necessarily early
in the project but early on in the
testing of the wok system and it starts
there and goes through to discuss the
final system that we developed for for
doing all of the walk movement and
everything and then
I believe so I think these are sponsored
sessions from various different
companies like Amazon I think Nick
Sutton er is another invited talk though
and again I don't know I don't know what
it's on because the things aren't up
here but I believe this was also an
invited talk it's not a sponsored talk I
think like this one this one and these
are sponsored maybe but I don't really
know like I said once they put up the
descriptions will be a little clearer I
don't know why they're not up yet but
you know they're not up yet anyway so
that's happening and it's it's going to
be recorded apparently so it will be
available afterwards if you have a
chance to come to Busan definitely come
come say hi I will be there giving that
lecture how do you find the source of
excessive memory consumption when all
you have to work with is a core dump as
a further restriction it's not feasible
to reproduce on your local workstation
because the program is an online game
server and the conditions only arise
under certain circumstances with a lot
of active players well I mean don't you
have a memory tracking system in this
thing I mean I wouldn't ship a game
server without a memory tracking system
I'm not sure what to say other than that
all of my systems are we even handmade
hero has the ability to track the memory
if you want to and you know we could go
further down that road we probably will
at ship time to add individual
allocation tagging which we don't do
right now easily could so I mean that's
the way you that's the way you track it
down is you just look at for example
let's suppose that the two ways that
your thing interactions memory is malloc
and free you know I mean I don't know
what ways your programming interacts
with it but you isolate those two points
you overload them with macros to pass
the file and line number then on every
memory allocation you do a hash lookup
of the
line number and you increment or
decrement that line numbers total memory
allocation and then that way when
something crashes you can just have it
dump that and you can see exactly which
line of your program is accounting for
all of the memory right so salute all
ski do you think a networked
multi-threaded 3d engine is too
ambitious for a three months dead period
yes absolutely I would never try to do a
multi-threaded 3d engine as my first
engine and I certainly wouldn't do one
if I was only going to spend three
months multi-threading is is
extraordinarily hard and and I don't
think it was something you should do on
your first time out now that said some
people's idea of multi-threading is not
really multi-threading so if you're
going to do something more like a very
weak multi-threaded thing then maybe
that's fine but assuming you're actually
trying to get multi thread performance
meaning you're trying to use
multi-threading to actually be faster
than single threaded that is something
that is not easy to do a lot of people
multi thread things and getting slower
so I certainly wouldn't recommend doing
that like I would recommend if you do
want to do multi-threading on your first
product it'd be more like handmade hero
where it's single threaded for the most
part and it just lot launches worker
threads that wait for workloads that are
small and localized because that's
something that it's not harder to think
through that that'd be my recommendation
on that I really enjoy the hard jobs and
games but don't think I have the innate
drive that you do do you have any advice
or experience with other domains that
may be just as challenging I don't know
any other domains that are challenging
in breadth so game development has a
breadth challenge to it that I don't
know any other domains that that really
come close because games kind of
intersects everything it's like
photorealistic rendering and high
performance optimization and servers and
clients and real-time input processing
and
game design and all that like everything
comes together for games everything that
humans know how to do is in a game right
so I don't know anything in breath but
in terms of just finding hard problems
oh I mean there's tons of things go work
on molecular modeling for a protein
synthesis I mean go work on figuring out
how to how to better synthesize x-ray
imaging or how to do 3d visualization of
cat-scans
you know like there's tons of things in
the medical field you could be doing or
biology you could go into security
research right like how do how do we
secure the power grid how do we prevent
cyber warfare things how do we harden
routers like all of these sorts of
things you go into operating system
development right hard real-time
operating systems tons of stuff to work
on there there's so many fields that
have hard problems in them so you can
easily find other hard problems
in programming and and game development
is is unique I think more not because it
has our problems there Harper's Eric
it's the breath it's the breath of the
problems that's interesting game
development that's what really sets it
apart you know you know not the depth I
think I think every programming
discipline has the depth it's the breath
that's different about game development
there's anything else on here
fubar count been programming for about
six years hobbyist and currently
university always struggled to push a
game project to completion do you have
any advice on how to see any product to
its end no I'm bad at that I just like
working on technology so I'm not really
good at pushing game projects to
completion pushing tech projects of
completion I might have better advice
for game products I don't
I would ask John blow I would really
seriously try to like get on his dream
and ask John blow because he is someone
who has both had trouble pushing game
projects to completion and not had
trouble pushing game projects to
completion and I think he would be the
perfect person to talk about that
difference and the things you can do to
try to get over that difference as fast
as possible
and and I don't have the necessary
experience to offer advice you know
kind of go haphazard through these
questions here I don't guarantee that
I'm going to answer all of these are you
into isometrics how would you approach
creating game in isometrics that using
3d well isometrics are a lot easier
because there's everything has a
universal sort order so you can usually
just draw up front to back and be done
with isometrics because there's no
perspective happening there so I think
that you probably okay but maybe not I
guess now that I say that I it's not
really true like I don't know if you
read Andrew Russell's post about this
I always spell his name wrong I'm sorry
Andrew yeah we spell it more like
Russell I think the first name but um
this is kind of a good post about how
it's not actually that easy isometrics
this is kind of an interesting way to
talk about how excuse another one right
I might refer you to that because I
guess I guess now think about snot it's
not really that straightforward
this year at a big database conference
there were two papers about avoiding the
penalties of cache misses by prefetching
and then using KO routine to do work
while the cache is being fetched do you
see any applications for this in games
it sounds a little weird
I mean it's not the weirdest idea so
first of all a cache miss is not that
expensive right so a cache miss is going
to be like what like 300 cycles 400
cycles usually in game development we're
pretty good when we start getting down
to that part of the project of figuring
out how to interleave things we want to
do so that we always have something we
can do math on while we're fetching you
know so like do I think I would want an
entire system for doing a KO routine in
a 300 cycle window especially given that
hyper threading does that automatically
so if I just have two threads that are
doing stuff for my game on the same core
when I hit the 300 millisecond bubble
the other thread will take over I mean
that's not literally what happens but
the other thread is issue it can issue
instructions into the AL use into the
execution ports right it doesn't sound
that useful but you know I haven't read
the papers it sounds like something
we've already kind of know how to work
around or are usually good enough at
doing that I can't say it excites me
like I'm not itching to go read that
paper it doesn't sound like one that's
gonna be high in my list I guess I'd say
but you know until I actually read it
I'm not gonna
I won't dismiss it because you know
maybe it's more maybe there's more to it
there you know so
and he's good at six weeks I know I will
be posting a schedule when I get back
from do song is uh I'll be in South
Korea for a week so until I get back I'm
not gonna post schedule and I won't be
streaming from there do you think John's
language will make game program easier
in a significant way as opposed to just
the million list of annoyances yeah I
mean hardly say I haven't looked at it
in depth but the meta programming
features that are in it are far so much
better than the ones in C++ that you
could really dramatically improve your
programming by using them it is not as
simple as eliminating an annoyance now
how good those meta program features
actually are in practice at the end of
the day I don't know until I actually a
chance to play with them
boy I I mean the difference between C++
and jii in terms of the ability to like
really leverage code is going to be I
mean it's not even gonna be close
you know C++ offers no meaningful meta
programming at all it's it's almost
completely useless for meta programming
so you know that's gonna be a pretty
pretty huge
chris fehn a bit about AZ do um I mean I
can explain a little bit about it but
I'm not sure what I'm gonna say that's
not gonna be the same as what you know
if you just read just go read it like an
nvidia tutorial or something but the
idea a CD o stands for approaching zero
driver overhead for those of you who
don't know and I'm sorry if I've got one
of those terms wrong I apologize the
acronyms fly all over the place in this
industry but AZ do is is basically
acknowledging the fact that a modern 3d
graphics card like an Nvidia 1080 like
the one in this machine is a processor
in its own right I mean it could run a
whole game over there right like it's
it's not made for that so there's a
bunch of things it does inefficiently if
you were to try and run an entire game
over there but it's a full processor
right and so the extent to which it
needs the main processor to hand hold
its execution is pretty minimal so what
a video attempts to do is say look if we
just prepare buffers in memory so when
we're in the game we just prepare
buffers that are formatted appropriate
for the cards consumption we should be
able to have the driver do almost
nothing it should be able to just kind
of you know knock on the cards door and
say hey I've got a new set of data and
code for you to execute do it and that's
it so rather than the driver sitting
there like manhandling when the GPU is
gonna do this and do that and checking
for states and changing the states and
recompile shaders ad do is just about
saying look let's just prepare actually
correct execution buffers for the GPU
that have all the stuff in them it needs
that it can just read and then what
we're going to do is just tell the GPU
read it go and so the driver becomes
much less involved and frees up a bunch
of CPU time for you to use for your game
that's all it is really you know Devils
in the details but that's the concept
I think that's all the questions
all right I'm gonna close it down here
you