hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show Rico to complete game live
on stream we are right in the middle of
doing some light probe coding on the CPU
side we're being a little conservative
with this game we're not trying to do
GPU side lighting primarily because we
would like to maybe run on lower end
systems eventually then that would
necessarily imply so I'm not necessarily
sure we want to go quite that route
mm-hmm so we're trying to something a
little bit simpler than we might do if
we were assuming that you're gonna
everybody who plays handmade here I had
that and have an RT X card plugged in or
something like this but we are right in
the middle of that code trying to update
our system to use light probing instead
of surface like actual surface level
probing because that was just too
inefficient and also didn't really
provide us what we needed for sampling
like things that don't contribute to
lighting so sprites and stuff like that
like on the ground or like like ground
cover grasses and things like that but
we want to be able to sample lighting
from I was a little bit confusing how we
actually wanted to do that we could have
done it but it just it was gonna be a
little bit weird right it couldn't have
been very dynamic and we would have had
to have sort of extra procedures in
place for handling sort of special
education a lot of sort of stuff so
we're just trying light probes as a way
of sort of cleaning that stuff up having
a uniform sampling regime for everything
and giving us a way to understand our
lighting is necessary because again we
don't want to end up with a lighting
system that's so expensive that we can't
run a really crappy version on of it on
low-end machines and still have
something resembling the look of the
game and then crank it up to higher
levels on higher machines or something
like that we want some flexibility there
and we didn't really have it before so
that's mostly what we're looking for
here solving those two problems I'm
going to go ahead and get started
oops and if you remember where we were
at we just finished adapting the ray
caster to return the information
necessary for us to do light probe
sampling during light propagation reason
we're doing that is because the light
probes are what store the information
now they are what will store the
information services them cell
will not store that information and
since surfaces won't store the
information for lighting it means that
we need to be able to get from a
particular surface hit back to a
lighting answer and that requires
querying the light probes with a point
and a normal so that's what we actually
needed to get that means that our hit
result so if we go down there and look
at our ray cast function our hit wants
to have slightly different things and so
that's what we did
we changed to returning a hit normal
which we got pretty efficiently I was
pleased
there's probably slightly more efficient
ways than what we're doing but we did a
pretty good job of that yesterday I was
happy with what we came up with it was
it's not the stupidest thing in the
world and this hit position which is
trivial to get obviously whenever you do
a ray intersection
you know the t-value so all we had to do
was just march forward by the t-value
and you get the hit position so that's
pretty straightforward as well now there
may be easier ways to record that I'm
not exactly sure if we're doing it quite
as efficiently as we could in here it's
possible that we already have the
information necessary to directly we can
start the hit P and we can do other
things like that yeah so you know we'll
see but generally speaking we're in good
shape
we return all the information necessary
so the reference color up side the
reflectance color of a surface the point
that you hit and the normal at that
point that gives us the ability to
propagate that information along the Ray
to whoever was trying to sample it which
brings us to the part of the code we
want to work on today which is where we
actually do that propagation now you can
see how this particular function works
and we're gonna rework it a little bit
this was designed to do light probing in
a very specific way from surface to
surface so it would cast rays from
surfaces to hit other services and
convict the light along those rays
that's effectively all we were doing
because that's all we wanted to do and
this solution is a temporal solution it
goes over time so we didn't consider
multiple bounces in a single propagation
step and the reason for that is because
every frame is the back basically a new
bounce set right so we're counting on
multiple frames to do our multiple
bounces and again that's for efficiency
obviously we could have done multiple
bounces in a single frame but that just
doesn't make sense from a performance
standpoint because you're never gonna be
able to take enough secondary rays to
really make enough of a difference there
with the kind of performance profile
that we're looking at so we want to do
is let that temporal sort of crank do
the secondary bounce propagation for us
and that of course gets us an arbitrary
number of bounces as well because every
frame is a new bounce propagation and
since you can propagate off all after
each frame you're propagating light off
of a new set of bounces it means that
you're effectively getting four five six
seven eight bounces down to the
diminishing point for sure because of
depending on how fast you blend them in
obviously you'll get different levels of
contribution for those secondary
tertiary quaternary bounces but
generally speaking even if you're
assuming a very reflective paint of some
kind 80 percent 90 percent light
transmission you still only need you
know five six bounces or something
before you're kind of getting to a point
of diminishing returns so you definitely
need secondary tertiary bounces for sure
in any realistic scenario those are
gonna contribute actually pretty
important information to your lighting
no question but at some point nine 1011
bounces you're probably done at that
point with anything that that's really
going to be that perceptible as anything
other than a general light boost maybe a
little bit of a of a general light floor
boost and so that's something we can
easily account for by just turning our
lights up a little bit right so it's the
character of the lighting that you're
trying to capture after a couple bounces
you've kind of got the directional stuff
under control and when you get out - you
know bounces above eight let's say
you're kind of in a position where
you're really just talking about adding
an amount of light to the scene and not
really having to care where it's coming
from
and so at that point you can compensate
typically
it's just again the number the more
bounces you're talking about in a
diffuse remember the difference between
a specular and a diffused bounce is that
a diffuse bounce of lighting spreads the
light out right it's it's going fairly
evenly throughout the scene off of the
point that you hit and that's the only
kind of light transmission we're really
simulating here specular bounces which
are those sort of bright highlight
bounces they're almost reflections right
the more specular something is the
closer it is to a mirror effectively
those kinds of transmission they require
if you have a lot of those services
that's where you start to require more
bounces of course those are also more
easy to simulate with ray tracing
because you have less rays because every
time you hit a surface you only have to
cast out a narrow band of rays to find
your answer this is also why like modern
ray tracing in hybrid approaches like in
games where you use hybrid ray tracing
in sort of the modern r-tx optimized
kind of way with with stuff like that
that's what they are using that for
right they use the r-tx to handle the
glossy reflections because those are
easier to Ray trace right the wide
diffuse distribution you typically need
something more like this so that's the
part we're trying to tackle here and
it's also the part that's most important
for our game because we want a soft kind
of warm look to the game we don't want a
lot of specular it's not a it's that's
not much how the art looks supposed to
be kind of a warm diffusely lit kind of
a game anyway and so again we're trying
to design a lighting solution that
simulates the kind of lighting that we
want and specular isn't really part of
that equation for us so you know spot
specular is something that we might want
to put in that's fine that's a render
time thing for light propagation we care
about the diffuse part and so that's
what we're working on here okay so what
we want to do is fundamentally change
this loop a little bit we were talking
about going from sample points which
were all on services before and we were
going
to collect lighting from other sample
points on services so it was from a
point on a surface we'd cast we'd see
what service we'd hit we look at the
sample points on that service and get
the light back from it that's not what
we're doing anymore what we want to do
now is similar instead of looping our
sample points we loop over light probes
but you can consider those to be the
same basic thing right if we just call a
sample point a light probe we just
changed the name then this part is the
same so so conceptually this this part
is changing only the very smallest
amount it's really a naming difference
to that effect and what we actually the
reason we did that again is because we
don't want these sample points that to
be on services so the reason we're
calling them lighting probes and the
only real conceptual difference there is
that now these sample points are
floating out in the world they're not
embedded in objects so that's the only
conceptual change there at all otherwise
exactly the same we're gonna loop over
them we're gonna cast Rays out of them
so exactly the same otherwise however
the next part is the part that really
changes more dramatically when we do our
ray casting we're gonna get out a point
in a normal in the world that point in
the normal in the world and reflection
color as well is the surface we ended up
hitting and here's the big change what
we used to do is for each one of those
hits we would look and say which of
these surface points are around there
gather those service points up average
they're lighting together based on how
close they were
that's our lighting sample we're not
going to do that anymore because now
we're gonna do is go from that point
that we hit and instead of gathering
surface points on that same surface
we're instead gonna go look up what
light probes are nearby and average the
light probe lighting together right so
that's the primary change we're really
gonna be making in this loop here he's
saying let's switch from a system that's
gathering surface points on a surface
for our lighting to gathering lighting
probes that are floating in the world
and averaging them together in sort of a
trial in ear light trial interplant
so that's a fairly big difference but
again conceptually it's not a huge leap
because we're doing almost the same
basic operation we're doing a spatial
gather followed by an averaging weighted
planned really right and so it's the
same basic idea it's just
very different type of gather and blend
that's really what's going on here right
and so now we just need to go do that
it's just plugging away to actually do
exactly what I just said but there's no
mystery to what's going on it's exactly
that so let's step through this loop
step-by-step take the if zeros out get
it compiling and that's pretty much all
we really want to accomplish today again
lighting is slow it's a lot of work a
lot of math has to be optimized so it's
just it's the kind of thing that's
that's not a fast thing to do typically
if you're writing it by hand like this
okay so we know we're going to take a
look at the lighting solution that we
get and we know that this compute light
propagation call as you see here this
compute light propagation call really
really wants to be multi-threaded this
is a situation where we really want to
use all of the resources of our CPU
because if we have eight core 16 cores
or one of these crazy new AMD chips with
64 cores of logical CPU on there or is
it 128 I can't remember where they have
64 actual cores or thirty two actual
cores with hyper-threading I don't know
who knows how many logic goes there but
there's a lot and so if you had some
crazy machine but tons of cores which
are becoming more and more common these
days and AMD is pushing them more and
more we want to use them all because
that'll just we can just crank up our
lighting quality or lighting quality all
just get better and better and better
the more cores you give us that sounds
great to me right so what we want to do
here is just go alright compute light
propagation let's grab that solution out
that comes from the lighting work packet
we've been given and again we expect
this compute like propagation we want to
make sure that it can be called from
many threads at the same time with just
different chunks to work on and so
that's something we want to keep in mind
we don't want to do anything in here
that we think would lock up our system
on doing some kind of a query or
something that would be a problem and so
off we go so here we are we're gonna do
our random series here that we've got
that's going to allow us to pick random
rays that we sample out of or other
things like that so we kind of want to
do a thing here where we we do a
sampling you can see us getting a sample
point entropy
out that's just a single value we're
gonna use I think for when we actually
see you see what that's used for are we
actually still using that yes we are
okay so you can see what that's doing
there the sample point entropy is
basically randomizing in our so if you
remember how we do the our sort of
casting throughout the world our sample
point entropy is given to us as a trans
I can't explain this we don't want to
have to generate Rea directions every
frame for every point because if we did
that generation of the actual random
points would actually dominate our
runtime we can probably raycast about as
fast as we could generate those points
so it would be a really expensive thing
to do so what we already did in previous
episodes if you saw them is we created a
sort of set of points we can use for
sampling that's like a little hemisphere
we can use to cast out from and what our
sample point entropy does is it just
says look let's pick random sets of
those that we're gonna throw out from
our individual sample points right so if
we're doing a block of sample points we
want to make sure that each frame we
pick a different random sample direction
from our set of sample directions we
don't want to just always sample the
same direction because that'll lead to
pretty bad artifacts we want to get some
noise in there so that we can sample a
broader sort of a better coverage of the
things out from it so that's what we're
doing here and we want to keep doing
something roughly like that so that part
of the code probably wants to say the
same the only real difference we
probably want to make here is since our
light probes are points floating in
space now we probably don't want them to
do a hemispherical sampling we probably
want them to do spiracle sampling
there's a couple other things we'd
probably want to do such as remember
which direction roughly speaking which
directional color each ray is designed
to contribute to so that way we don't
have to figure that out either and we'll
see that as we kind of go a little bit
further on in the in the init process
now moon color is something that we want
to sort of make a little bit more
procedural I'll put it to you in here
for that just we remember we generally
speaking don't want to add a sort of
ambient moonlight to things that don't
actually get lit by the moon and so for
example when you go in doors or if you
are in a dungeon area you know we
wouldn't expect moonlight to really be
getting in there or if it was getting in
there it should go through an aperture
so we want some way of controlling that
potentially however we may also just
want to put in like ground patches or
something that would prevent you from
getting to the moonlight I don't know
but the reason that this is important to
understand is we you know you might say
well can't wouldn't you always hit
something if you're underground would
you always hit like the ground when you
cast up the answer is yes you would if
you actually could reach it but remember
when we simulate we only simulate a
local region we don't want to bring in
the entire world for ray casting to be
way too expensive so we may need to have
some idea of a like a basic ground plane
that you can't get out of so that even
when everything's been paged out you
will not get moon light going into your
dungeons simply because the actual
ground was so far above you when you're
like seven eight dungeons deep right you
don't want to have to load up all of the
ground tiles - just so you hit them and
don't get moonlight that's really
inefficient so we probably need some way
of controlling that moon light in a way
that's not going to require us to
actually compute the fact that there was
a ground up there stopping us so you
know something to just be aware that
that's got a workout right okay so and
we could do a really simple cheat for
this even right like you can imagine
cheating this really easily when we
actually go
to put our light probe in there so you
look at this this is our light probe
structure we can pretty easily extend
this structure with a simple flag field
the flags field could say things like
whether there should be an ambient light
in which ambient light it is stuff like
that so we could hack this too when we
place those light probes we know whether
they're replacing them in an interior
and exterior scene so we could cheat
that right that's the thing that's easy
for us to cheat out and so we've got a
lot of options for dealing this it's
just we need to deal with it some way at
some point so let's go in here when we
start looping over sample points what we
really want to do here is change the
nominal HR just to understand what we're
doing but otherwise it's gonna say the
same we're not going looping over sample
points per se we're gonna be looping
over light probes there's a difference
between those two things obviously and
we want an understanding of what's going
on there so we want to actually change
this to a light probe index because
that's what we're actually doing but
otherwise we want to be the same we're
probably gonna want to have us loop over
the specific light probes that we're
doing so this should be like first light
probe index and that should be coming
from our work function here so first
light probe index is gonna come from our
work order and one press last light
probe index same thing right so we just
want to change our nominal Eicher so
that we understand we're looping over
light probes not sample points anymore
they are our sample points but we just
want to change that meaning so that
people understand when they're looking
at this code or I'm reading this code
later when I forgotten how it works it's
clear you're looping over the light
probes those are our sample points off
we go
so now lighting point which is this
thing here is not going to be used
anymore and in fact this stuff is all
gonna go away we're going to want to
delete this and this thing here is gonna
get right and so when we send down our
light data we're gonna be sending down a
very different kind of light data more
like what we experiment with of the
beginning we're gonna be sending down
more of a vox alized piece of lighting
information
and so you know just keep that in mind
all right so here's our lightning point
we want to change this now to be like
probe it's gonna be straightforward
translation so we're just gonna grab
that out in order yeah in the range that
we're given and again that range is in
case you for getting this that range is
effectively the slice that this
particular core in this particular round
is going to operate on so we've sliced
up our set of light probes and we're
handing them out to different cores
effectively right so each core will
operate on a different set of lights
alright so the first thing I would like
to do here is we probably actually want
a little bit of a nasty if statement
here I'm guessing now maybe we don't
maybe we do but we probably want to take
our light probes here and have some way
well no actually you know what we would
do this the head end so no this is fine
we're gonna keep doing this way so we
probably want here to say all right what
are our light probes let's go ahead and
grab those out of this range and then
when we come in here we're going to want
to take the way we were generating our
ray casting before zooming hmm and we're
gonna want to modify it a little bit to
do what we're doing and now you can see
here actually this this wasn't really
something that we talked about before
but if you look at what's about to
happen here we're gonna be able to
simplify this code as well which is
really kind of great so if you look at
what had to happen before our lights
were we're on services that meant that
we only wanted a sample Hemisphere's
around those points because we're only
stamping hemispheres it meant we needed
a basis system like a three-dimensional
structure around those lighting points
so that we knew how to construct our
Hemisphere and that meant that every
time we took a sample point we then had
to do work where we would do a bunch of
F mads here well actually more like a
bunch of well there are ask mats a bunch
of F Mads we would have to do those to
recreate what the hemisphere looked like
when placed into that sort of
hemispherical context for this
servus were on so if you just again to
bring everyone up to speed because I
know some people you know you don't have
chance to watch everything we do here in
handmade hero remember we're creating a
hemisphere of directions that we're
gonna use to sample that hemisphere is
stored as a static set that we use for
our sampling we can't do a hemisphere
just arbitrarily because if we have a
sample point with a direction that's on
a surface we don't want to cast back
into the surface because they're all
it's going to hit that surface and that
goes any information so we needed to
orient our hemisphere so that's pointing
away from the surface right we don't you
do that anymore
we can sample full spheres of lighting
now because we're using points floating
in space another reason why light probes
are a good idea right and they are
explained why I didn't use them at first
is because I had a thing I didn't think
I could do in my head but it actually
turns out you can do it and I was just a
gap in knowledge there so the light
probes can handle that for us which
means that this stuff actually will go
away right we don't actually need that
anymore we can say look let's get rid of
that let's load up the sample point for
our light probe and let's loot it four
times so we're just basically doing a
load in distribute here it's called a
broadcast sometimes I think but we're
basically load that up and we're gonna
load effectively a sim deregister is
filled with the x y&amp;z one Cindi register
each of the x y&amp;z of the light probes
position because that's where all the
Rays are gonna come out of right now
remember we've got some debugging stuff
in here I don't know why this doesn't
say if handmade kernel around it it
should because it's the bug stuff but
you know whatever we want leave that in
there because we're gonna have to debug
this and we might want to lean on some
of this stuff so I'm gonna make sure
that this still works again here's that
light probe point so let's just put that
in there and this was showing us the
coordinate system of this thing we don't
have that coordinate system anymore so
I'm just gonna go ahead and throw in a
generic coordinate system just show cuz
that's what we read back to be using now
cuz we don't change per point but again
just just leaving this so that it's
still
same there we go and so now when we come
in here and we want to take our sample
direction you can see us doing that here
this part here where we recreate the
sample direction by reinterpreting it in
the coordinate system of that sample
point that's the part we don't need to
do anymore right so we can just delete
that whole thing this is the sample
direction right here we're good to go
it's the raider action adventure fantasy
delirium eyes spheres that we can use
we'll deal with that stuff later not
important right now but point being we
just going to assume that this sample
points here will get us a full full
sphere worth of samples when we go and
modify it so then we'll just trust that
this needs to be a whole sphere I'll put
it to you in here
okay so we know we need to do that and
that's fine it won't be hard I don't
think to modify our hemisphere point
sampler generation system to just do a
Hema studio sphere instead of a
hemisphere the reason for that is I'm
pretty sure that the way we did the
hemisphere was just doing a sphere and
chopping it off right um so I think all
we have to do is to remove some code
probably from our hemisphere sampler
where we were just previously saying hey
let's limit this to just the hemisphere
but I don't know we'll go check it out
it shouldn't be hard anyway all right so
here's our ray casting call we have that
here where we call our ray cast and
that's just a little walk this will
probably I would assume when we do an op
x bill if this look it welded in so it
would probably just get inserted here
because the only place is called and
that's the way we want it we want to
just be merged in here because we want
it all to be nice one simple loop no
function call overhead and so on so you
can see here we're creating the reap the
ray p4x structure but we don't need that
because actually this has that in it
that's just gonna be the Ray - P right
so this this right here is this so it's
already been computed by the interior
code that goes away and so then we're
just left with the the part where we
need to actually compute our sort of the
the actual light gather that happens so
we're gonna loop over the number of
Ray's we were asked to rate asked and
we're going to Ray cast them in here
we're going to want this to be a
handmade internal I think we want to
again leave that in there
this has to be light probe index and
this right here should probably be debug
probe index that we should change but
again probably want to leave that in
there because we will have to debug this
code and we want all the help we can get
when that comes to it so there we go and
in here where we've got this part where
we're we're
pushing the debug lines on here looking
at what's happening here again sampled
d4x we still have that's just our way
direction
that all looks fine to me
this part here I think is a little bit
different let me just see what we have
left so we have the hip point so I think
all we really want to do instead of
doing end point instead of doing this
all we really want to do here is
probably do a check to see if the thing
was a hit or not so we probably want to
just do if hit do one thing if not do
another thing we don't have a tear a
anymore so in this what we'd like to do
is say all right if we hit draw the hit
and the way we would draw that hit is
just by saying okay we know that we're
starting from the Ray origin like so
right which is like probe P because we
don't want the full for X version of it
so we're starting at light probe P and
then we want to end at this at this
position right so this that we want to
end at what the lighting system tells us
so we need to be able to extract that in
fact you know what here we only need to
call this once and we only need to do
that we'll just build end point
differently in the two cases right so
what we'll do is we'll say okay we've
got the end point here we can just say
that we'll move a certain amount along
it like that if it didn't hit goop's
like so so that's all we need to do
there I think this is also all we need
for end point then write that get
component calls exactly what we want
it unpacks a Sindhi version into one
slice so it takes one slice of it out
slowly so what we want to do there is
the sack same thing we want to take the
hit position so
oops the hit position which is this eye
and just unpack that into the end point
right and so there is all we really need
for that I could also make this be a
little bit squeakier right it could be
this if we wanted it to be not really a
big deal right something like this so we
can't do something like that I don't
know if that's good or bad doesn't
really matter I'm it's just some debug
code no one cares about it and so that
gives us everything we really need there
and yeah right seems good
off we go so that gives us the ability
to draw one of these things and again I
like I said I think we're gonna need it
because we're just gonna run it it's not
gonna work we're not gonna know why
right we got a we have to debug it step
by step make sure our regeneration is
correctly sure but casting works
properly make sure make sure make sure
make sure right all right Jimmy so now
we get down to the actual transfer this
is the actual expensive part the two
like the two expensive things are the
cast which you saw which is actually
quite fast per primitive but it has to
do things like traverse a little
bounding hierarchy and stuff and that
sort of thing is slow there's just a lot
of tests you know that go on and things
like this so it's all good so you want
to go ahead and do that and the other
thing we want to do
is everyone gonna do that we need to be
aware of that right that's that's one
slow part the other slow part is here
and so that's the part we have to work
on now and that's once we know a
particular hit point we need to actually
get the lighting sampling so I think we
probably want to try to do this wide for
as much as we can but again because the
SSE instruction set is
really not very good it doesn't handle
fetch and so the thing that you always
have to end up doing is as soon as you
want to sample a texture or a spatial
gather or whatever you have to downshift
into scaler it really sucks but that's
just the way it goes and that's exactly
what we're gonna have to do here now we
can still try to write this as fast as
possible and we're gonna want to do that
later because I think it will be an
expensive part of the routine but for
right now what I'm gonna do is I'm just
gonna completely downshift
so the first pass through there's not
gonna be any at all there's not gonna be
any Cindy in this entire path we're just
gonna down sample immediately I start
down shift immediately to scaler and do
everything in scaler again not we
actually want because I think we can
still get some Cindy out of this but for
starters when we're debugging it let's
keep things simple so the way we're
going to do this here is we're gonna do
the down shift we did here secondly if
the Ray P that we get back that Ray
position that rate hit position that's
going to give us the point where we want
to sample our probe we also have the
probe sample normal I'll get that back
for now like so and so we get those two
things I don't know why this is normal
instead of n just because I guess there
we go
so when we get back to P in the end that
gives us what we need a sample and again
we have to downshift here because we've
got a down stuff to do the gather so
what I'm going to do is do the full
downshift get inside the the light
system here I think we have like waves
sampling nowhere so here's that code so
this is effectively what we're looking
for right get probe lighting for
and get light from probe you know I'm
saying so I think if we combine those
two although we mirror you have those
actually have the entire thing we
already wrote the entire thing here
where's wait why doesn't that have a
normal in it what get probe lighting for
it's supposed to take a normal so this
is wrong this was supposed to take it
normal and isn't right I think we've got
a buggy bit of code here just in terms
of what's being passed down here maybe
for one second because I think we should
fix it so in here you can see us calling
get probe lighting for that assembles a
lighting probe based on the cell
position in the UVW you can see that
happening here and returns you a single
probe you can use for your lighting so
in here when you do this that's correct
right get light from probe so maybe we
just never call that so maybe it's not
buggy it just we never know whatever
calls it I guess no one ever calls it
all right never mind um so we just need
two of these to do our sampling and so
let's go ahead and do that I guess so we
can hear where we're going to do our
sampling what we want to do is first say
please give us the sort of composite
light probe that we're going to need to
do this operation so that's this call
here right where we'd say give us back
for this lighting solution and this
spatial index this the light probe
spatial index is something that we're
just expected to have here so I assume
that's something that we need to get
well actually that's actually something
we could just get out of the solution I
think
it's this thing right so we get that
spatial index that's the thing we need
to use to do our querying so we passed
that along and then we know what this is
here it's the probe sample P so that's
what we want to build our let composite
probe out of so that's taking 8 probes
and smoking them down to one probe that
we can use to sample the lighting based
on like a tri linear filter of the 8
surrounding probes from our current
location so then what we need to do here
is we need to actually do the lighting
so we need to find out what the lighting
is that's just a question of saying hey
for this composite probe and this normal
what's the light right and that's it so
once we have that lighting sample we're
ready to do something with it and the
something that we want to be able to do
with it obviously in this case is figure
out how much light in our receptor probe
there's two light probes involved here I
mean technically there's nine
there's a light probe we're sampling and
that's not contributing anything
necessarily I mean it might if it
happens to end up being one of the
gathered ones and then when we actually
cast out and we get a hit we gather the
eight surrounding ones in the voxel
smoosh them together to form one
composite probe based on our position in
that voxel and then we want to figure
out how much light is gonna get sent
back basically to our receptor probe
based on this right so that's it that's
all we're doing so when we do that
sample here Jimmy I that lighting
function is probably garbage right now
and we probably want to go in there and
make it better than it is but we're
gonna trust that it's written properly
so we can improve it later but whatever
it is
something happens here and we get back
the lighting amount that means that this
is the amount of light that we expect to
get along that's for that sample normal
that's how much we expect so you know we
kind of want this to be to take more I
think so this get light from probe I
think what we actually want here is not
it's just not phrased properly I think
we want to do is get light from probe
this should not be in this should be
like indirection or something right
meaning when we get the light from the
probe we want to know what light would
be coming from a particular direction
probably I would think although really
not we kind of just want to ask how much
light is going out in a particular
direction
so I think really what this wants to say
is just like how much light goes out in
that direction generally and the bounce
is just gonna be colored by the surface
normal so I think it may actually be
like this I think that's maybe the best
way to say it so we're gonna query it
for like an emission direction for now
and we may need to change up how this
works because once we decide exactly I
want to store these things we're storing
them kind of in a basic way now we might
try to store them in other ways in the
future so if we're just but just a basic
idea here so we're gonna say in an
emission direction so in terms of the
probe sample normal and now that I think
about it it's unclear to me that we
actually need that all that much I'm
wondering if maybe that was just a waste
of time to actually compute those
normals to begin with like maybe we
don't even really need them we could
just say that look we're just gonna
sample how much light would come back in
the direction we're trying to find right
so I don't know and you know in terms of
the probe yeah like I just can't I don't
I don't know that we ever actually need
that probe normal maybe for filtering
purposes but I mean really all we would
need to do with it is say how much light
was transmitted in this direction but
yeah so I think what we actually want
here is simpler so I think all we're
really gonna say is look the direction
we want a sample in so you know the
emission direction right and when we
look at this here you can see us when we
take the submission direction I think
this doesn't have to be normalized it
doesn't look like it has to be
normalized because we kind of do a
normalization of it here so I think the
emission direction is fine it can just
be arbitrary I don't
no but I think that's okay it plays a
little bit because this is this is not a
to norm it's a one norm talked about
that before there may be reasons why you
need to normalize to the two norm first
I'm not sure we have to think about that
so I don't know but anyway the emission
direction here we pretty much know that
it's just whatever the probe sample
point is so basically like where we
actually are hitting we just want the
probe sample point and we need to know
where we started from
right so the light probe P the light
probe P is what we're trying to send
light back to and the probe sample P is
where we are so the emission direction
we are Chris we're cuz you know curious
about is that right so that's the
emission direction you want to get back
and we're gonna get back a color now we
also need to know at this point we we
kind of want some idea of like how much
transmission there should be so we kind
of want a cosine fall-off on that thing
because a surface that's very oblique to
us would not be something that would
send much light back whereas if it's
right straight bouncing it would so we
maybe want a cosine term in here if that
was the case this goes away and maybe
I'll just get rid of it preemptively and
we'll just say this is what we'll do so
this right here we actually want to do a
normalizer zero on to make sure that
this thing is normal right and so when
we do this emission direction this
really wants to guard for div by zero
probably
which will probably be easier to do in
the symphony version anyway when we do
the emission direction here and we're
ready to go we now need to take into
account that probe normal and here's the
only place where I think that can really
be necessary so what we want to do here
is do the like fall off like the
reflectivity fall off basically where
we're going to say take the inner
product of that probe sample N and the
emission direction right so we're
basically saying what we hit the normal
of that surface versus the direction
mattress and light back if those are
right in line with each other we send
the maximum amount of light back if
they're 90 degrees apart or more we send
no light back right that's basically
what we're doing right so we we
basically say clamp that sir to one
can't have negative transmission so if
you're behind the surface how you ever
would have gotten behind the service I
don't know because this is a raycast so
really that should never happen but in
Cindy when we send me this it's pretty
free to clamp to zero so we probably
just should to avoid any weird edge
cases anyway once we get the reflective
fall-off back then what we can do is
take the actual light sample values so
here's where we do our light sampling
that light sample is just going to be
multiplied by the reflective fall-off
right and also by the Hadamard product
of the reflective color so the
particular thing we hit remember in that
rate I have to get the ref color here
whatever we hit that can have its own
color so that allows us to have like
walls that themselves change the
reflected light so that if the wall is
entirely red it will reflect red light
instead of reflecting white light when
white light is showing off it and so on
so we want to support that because we're
gonna probably want to use that later
even though we don't really use it right
now
so in here where we do reflective
fall-off we do the haddem our product of
that light sample there what we want to
do is add that ref color in right and so
that gives us the actual like light
transmitted value that is how much light
we should be sending back along that Ray
to the light probe and it also contains
what the RGB color oh it was this stuff
where we get light boxes and this
garbage here none of this is relevant at
all anymore this all goes away it's not
getting as simple as it looks because
remember all this crap has to happen now
so it's actually still very complicated
it's just hidden inside these two
routines which is where we'll have to
start bringing more optimization to bear
in the future because you know it's not
really going to be sufficient so anyway
that's all we really need to do there
and that is what will give us the final
value we're actually going to use for
our transfer value and you can see here
what it looks like we've already got
that it's called transfer PPS so I think
actually we just do that and then the
rest of the routine would work correctly
looks like here actually the angular
fall-off was already coming in here sort
of so alright so I guess I guess this
stuff just wants to be done regardless
so it looks like this code just wants to
be done for everything I guess you can't
do these though well wait but you can't
really do that for everything because
you don't know the normal and yeah I
don't know all right never mind
I was confused there that's this can
only happen in here because you don't
have a hit point otherwise right so I'm
not sure what any of this was doing
there this yeah this this is just
garbage this doesn't look right at all
so I'm just going to delete it well all
of this looks looks wrong to me
so yeah um the accumulated weight I
don't know what that would be for now
because we have pretty much a consistent
we don't need that anymore because the
accumulation could just be done
matter of fact like the light probes can
just be you can just summit in here you
don't need a secondary pass at all
because you know what the wait you know
that the weight is just however many
rays we cast for probe period right
that's what happens so I don't think we
need this anymore either I think we
could just do a pre multiply by whatever
that weight is and be done the
accumulated weight isn't a thing anymore
so I think all we really need is the
accumulated PPS that can just add the
transfer PPS back in there photons per
second I think it's what we were sort of
calling that and the direction is just
not a thing anymore
right so I think that's all we really
need to do now we need an additional
piece of information here because when
we do the accumulated PPS for a
particular sample point because we're
now doing this as light probes we need
to actually remember several different
values right so we need to like when we
sort of pack that stuff up we have six
color values here right so like if you
look where we do our light probes each
one of them stores six light directions
at well six light colors one for each
face of a cube centered around the point
so we want to have a way of summing that
right and we're only summing into one of
those each time we would probably like
to ensure that we always some one sample
into all six
I would assume I can't think of a reason
really not to and so this system here
right where it's doing ray counts 16 I
think what we kind of want to do is make
that be a multiple of like four right so
we'd probably want to do like the rate
count is 12
each time and it does two samples into
each of the six you know and I'm saying
to you and so I think what we'd want to
do is roughly like this right now we
don't actually want to do a mod six here
right we want to actually just do an
easier way of doing a mod round on this
guy cuz yeah like you don't want to
actually have to do a mod six although I
guess you could kind of work out a way
to that more simply so what you really
want to do I guess is when we're doing
these samples here I think we want the
sample points array to be able to pull
out the directions right so we want
probably this you know i'm santi so
effectively and here when we pull this
thing out we could say that the sample
point Direction index comes from this
hopefully that makes some sense I guess
technically since this is the sample
region I guess now I think about that's
not actually correct it's actually the
Ray index that's the thing that you use
twice so like that and the Ray index
just tells us for a given sample which
one it comes from right something like
this and there'd be 12 of these or 24
right it depends on how many you want to
do but or 18 I guess 18 would probably
be the number closer to what we were
doing right so I think we want something
like that so we would effectively say
like okay we do 18 of these and then the
thing rolls around as we go if necessary
but I think that's all we really want
and this can be beefed up by the number
right so the sample point dur index
there yeah cuz that ray index doesn't
get modded so basically this thing just
has to be the array count of the work
sample pointer index right so I think
that's all we really wanted there and
that way
we know that this always gets summed in
and they get something in predictable
way that way we don't have to track
weights anymore cuz I don't really think
we want to do that we'll just make sure
we always take one sample in each
direction every time seems okay if it
turns out in the future we really want
to be able to take more samples like
laterally cuz that because the game
spreads laterally more or something then
we would need to change that up but
otherwise I think it'd be fine there we
go so what we would then say here is
like when we look at the ray count we
would have a waiting here like a ray
weight and so since we would know
in eight in the case of 18 right so if
the rate counts 18 we know that six is
the number of directions right so we
know that if we're taking six directions
we need to divide the Ray count by six
to figure out what the weight should be
of each one of those right so once we
know what that Ray weight should be
actually I guess it's the other way
around
so for example if we take six samples
each one should get a rate of 1 if we
take 12 samples each once you get a rate
of 0.5 right so I think that's what we
want to do there and then when we sum up
the transfer PPS we can just multiply by
the Ray weight and we're good to go
right so I think that gives us the
correct accumulated PPS which then we
can copy back in in terms of this stuff
here where we're doing like letting
points with initial PPS and emission
people yes like that I think that's not
really necessary anymore so I think all
that goes away this goes away that goes
away a lot of this stuff kind of just
falls away because we've replaced it
with something else now so we'll be able
to kind of butcher this up pretty darn
good in a second here but I think that's
mostly the sketch like that's basically
what we're looking at let's go ahead and
try to make sure that we can compile
this down so let's let's fix our like
basic our basic issues here so I'm going
to take this first sample point index I
might change this to first light probe
index because again remember we're not
going over the samples any sample points
anymore our sample points will not exist
shortly the points that we sample that
are now the actual light probes
themselves so we're just changing that
name to reflect the fact that that's
where we're sampling from one passed
last light probe index one pass
[Music]
like probe index there we go this is how
many times gonna take we stole that
right there we go this sample point
during this that's off of the solution I
don't know why I type to work there
that's wrong else we got
this is like probes not like probe
sample point index is light probe index
now same thing here
so let's see where we're at
so get probe lighting for needs the
spatial index which we have the solution
which we have the probe sample P which I
think we have let me just make sure I've
got all that right but probably what we
have to do just predefined this right so
yeah I think what we want to do is just
block this up into here for now actually
so you know what we may want to do - I
don't know but we may want to just make
this in its own file this voxel thing
maybe I don't know maybe that's just a
waste of time
we'll see when we go a little further
whether we want whether they actually is
enough code here - making it worth
splitting out it might not be but we
need to come be able to call those two
functions so I just gonna pre de Ferrol
in there so here we just got a this part
is just a in the transfer of PPS we want
to be able to handle that ambient moon
light potentially as that comes in here
and so oh wait
I'm a dingus aren't I so you know that
thing I said about not needing the
weights Julie actually no I guess we
don't cuz we we're always gonna have an
ambient light or black coming back for
our samples if we don't hit something so
no the Ray weight is always correct
I'm not a big Asst but yeah we do need
to remember that there's a now there's a
sample direction that goes with this so
we're gonna have to figure out how we
want to handle that in a second but back
here with our transfer PPS we do this
operation this part where we look at how
much you're facing the moon which is I
guess what this would be about this
again is gonna be the direction that we
were going and so that is actually this
right here
you notice realized the solving the
emission direction this way is stupid
because that's always the raid erection
so actually all you would have to do is
just do this right so that was stupid
don't ask me why I did that because it
was dumb so you don't actually need to
do this subtraction there there's no
reason it's you already know the answer
so all of this stuff is fine and and I
think that's all good so all we need to
do here is say that that emission
Direction is common in both cases in
here where we do use that emission
direction it looks like what we want to
do is take the Z range of this guy like
that looks like that clamp was on the
wrong thing but that's okay but still
work it just was doing more work that I
needed to it looks like we just want to
take that Z direction
clamp it and multiply the moon color
that tells us how much moon was coming
in it means the moon light can't come in
on an angle which we may want to do
because it would just take an extra dot
product to do that and that's a pretty
cheap operation to do so it seems like
probably getting a direction for our
ambient light would probably be smart so
I don't know that seems like kind of
just wasteful there but let's take a
look here yeah so I think we're almost
done if we look at what's happening here
where we're distributing up our work
here we got the points for work and all
that kind of nonsense happening right
that's just gonna be the light probe cap
now so it's really just probes for work
now and we're slicing those up however
we want and this is just first light
probe index and this is probes for work
right one past last light probe index is
going to be the same thing and then in
here we're just looking to clamp this so
we want to say that if we were going to
go over the end I don't know that we
actually have a light probe counting
here but we're gonna need one right if
we're going to go over the end then we
just clamp it off there
we also don't do any computation for
light probe zero apparently and that's
probably just so we can remember the
fact that there is if we are in a voxel
that doesn't want to say there's a light
probe there then it can just be zero but
I think actually
I guess what I might say about that is I
mean I guess it's true that we don't
need to compute anything for it but it
would actually be fine if that's a real
light probe anyway it doesn't matter we
can leave this in there isn't it's not a
big deal so I think now we're down to
just the fact that when we're storing
the accumulation we don't really have a
good idea of how we're storing the
accumulation so if we go back and look
at the accumulated PBS here uh which is
somewhere yeah here it is if we go back
and look at the accumulated PBS right
we're basically saying these two things
don't want to be here anymore this thing
does want to be here anymore
but we don't want it to store just one
light sample we actually want it to
store six light samples and so we can
you know we kind of need something that
looks more like this right yeah I'm
saying to you and we could do it that
way but I don't really want to because I
don't like these kinds of constructions
it's a pointer to three VIII's is just a
little yeah so what I'd rather do is
just say look we're gonna allocate this
as if it had that stride in it I'm sorry
6vc I think we're about six not three I
don't know why type six in there uh so I
think we want something more like that
right we want to accumulate the six
samples and I think they probably want
to be contiguous
[Music]
it's pretty hard to say this gets into
the part we're having I have never
implemented a light probe system before
and have had I implemented one before I
would probably have some opinions about
how you want to store and manipulate
these things and the reason I say that
is just because if you look at how the
if you look at how this stuff is going
to get gathered it's unclear that you
really want to gather it in ways that
aren't sort of nicely done on a power of
two boundary I mean maybe you do but it
would be nice if this thing was more
power of two ish and if you're talking
about six light directions then pretty
much nothing you do because there's a
three in there right three times two is
six so you're always gonna have a times
three in there you're never gonna get a
power of two so you would much rather
you know talk about tracking you know
eight light directions or something
I mean I guess all I'm saying is you'd
rather track eight or four values and so
I don't know what the right answer is
there I think that's something we're
just gonna have to play with but so I
think what I'll say at the moment at the
immediate moment is I'm just gonna
cheese this out and then we're gonna
look at this in more detail because I
feel like this is something important
and I just don't know what the answer is
offhand but I don't love this like I
don't want to be multiplying this by six
that's just dumb
so that's just kind of garbage I feel
like you want this times eight just my
two cents so I think that's something
that's gonna require a little bit of you
know squeak eNOS there and we'll see so
on here I'm just gonna say look this is
just gonna be six times this for now
we're gonna nip these guys they're not
gonna happen and then we'll you know
take it from there
and this is not gonna happen either
right and we're gonna get rid of that D
eventually so that's pretty much all I
really wanted to do that's that's the
entire thing I wanted to do today was
just sketch out that routine and how
that was going to work and we probably
should go in now and just start cleaning
it up a little bit we're not running it
right now so you know we don't have to
look at like what it actually looks like
in practice or anything like that but I
think I've got about thirty minutes left
maybe let's say and so I think what I
might want to do here is just yeah like
go ahead and finish up any cleanup that
I might want to do so in I mean just
just deleting stuff so that when we
start debugging it there's not just crap
lying around the
that don't matter right so let's start
by saying this stuff has to go we don't
care about these points anymore those
are gone the scratch arrays we got to
take a look at but those points are
definitely gone so so this is gone and
what we would replace it with when we're
dumping the data there is it's the light
probe count that's actually what we want
to know how many light probes are you
pushing down into the system and off you
go
so in here where we actually set this
stuff up the extended point count isn't
a thing we're not doing hierarchical
sampling at this point think so we're
gonna get get rid of that as well that
should go away the entropy frame count
and T update all this stuff should
accumulate these things I think all that
stuff is fine for now although we may
need to tweak it a little bit based on
what we're doing and we can sort of
reenable this stuff now - maybe that's
about to you but let's continue with
just the sort of the trimming if you
will so where we get this solution point
count and we get it from the group here
that sort of stuff as far as pushing
light probes on
you
I don't really know how I want that to
work but I think it should probably just
be a free slot scheme and people just
pack and unpack out of here
so just to unpack what's going on in my
head right now we have the entity system
and it now operates on a caching basis
and we know exactly when enemies come
into and out of the working set
effectively that means that it's pretty
free it's not 100% free but it's pretty
free for us to say that light probes
just live in the lighting system and
they are allocated out to entities on an
as-needed basis right and so when an
entity comes into the working set if
it's an if it's a light probe it just
gets a slot in the light probe system
and when it gets removed it just loses
that slot and that's kind of the end of
it the reason that I think that system
makes a lot more sense than what we were
doing before is there's a tremendous
amount of unnecessary work going on
right now where we're copying these
lighting informations
into and out of the system for no reason
we could do exactly the same thing with
the light boxes as well right meaning we
don't really need to do what we're doing
right now where we are every frame
pushing down all of the boxes that are
involved because what we can do instead
is just anytime something that is a
reflector comes into the system we put
it into the lighting system and anytime
it goes out of the system we take it out
and nobody needs to copy anything any
other time right so treating the
lighting system as another free list
effectively which is just a thing that
allocates out lighting resources to
entities as they come in and out of the
working set seems to me to be a smarter
way to do it than what we were doing
before
I mean correct me if I'm wrong but that
just seems like it saves a heck of a lot
of work that just that just seems like
such a much better idea to me than what
we were doing which seems dumb
I'm not sure I want to start doing that
right now but I'm definitely I'm gonna
say go ahead and say that's almost
definitely what do I do now for for
light probe probes themselves I could
see an argument being made for just
saying look the position of the light
probes might change every frame I mean
they can move around who knows what
they're doing
we might not want to worry too much
about that so it's possible that the
light probe positions and like the Box
positions it's possible that those
should themselves be recorded every
frame right so if you look at you know
the lighting box here where you've got
the radius and the reference color of
the emission and the texture index and
all this stuff right if all of this
information that we're looking at here
is updated every frame then you'd want
to write rewrite it every frame is it
wouldn't matter but if a lot of that
stays the same and it's just the p-value
the changes you know that's I guess
where the argument comes in it's really
hard to say though I don't know that's a
tough call that's a tough call
that's DEFCON what I will say is that
light probes this color value here
should almost certainly be stored
stabili and it should be stored probably
outside in a table in the lighting
system and then when you allocate light
probes you allocate their indices off
and you write their p-values in as part
of the process so I do think that light
probes want to be stable assigned boxes
I'm just not sure i I just don't know
yeah I just don't know so the other
thing that I think we need to take into
account here is we're not using the
emission value right now and we're
probably gonna need to so the emission
value the way that we get lights into
the system is having a non zero emission
value on a lighting box and so maybe
that's another thing I'll do right now
before before we forget so if you look
at the way our lighting kit works right
where's that value here there it is so
if you look at way this works you've got
a rough color and that's how stuff is
reflected off the surface but we also
probably need here an emission value and
the reason we need an emission value is
for actual lights so reflections one
thing but we need to actually I'll put
things that emit light into the system
and so in this equation that we computed
before for the lighting here mmm where
are you there you are nope there you are
so in this equation where we computed
the lighting here you can see that like
this code doesn't allow you to ever get
light into the system the only light
ever comes from the probes since probes
themselves don't you MIT light what do
we do right so in order to emit light
into the system we do need an emission
value to come back from our raycast
results and so when we take this this
transcript ups here in addition to the
light that gets reflected we also need
to add the light that is emitted right
so we would need here to take that
emission value and multiply that by the
sample ref color as an addition to the
system right hopefully that makes some
sense
and if we wanted to I guess you could do
prior to the Hadamard do the addition on
the inside now cuz the fall off yeah so
yeah so I think you probably want to
look roughly like that right and that's
how your missive lighting gets added in
there so that just means that the
raycast here needs to remember this
which is annoying because it does add
one more thing that needs to get
remembered but it's not the end of the
world it's a pretty cheap select and
that's it
right so the hit omission here just
looks like this okay so that allows us
to record that piece of information
which we definitely do want yeah it's
not it's not a v3
so did we not have a way of getting
components of f3 twos that we must
so you can see us doing it here I guess
we were just meant to do this I suppose
actually sure what we were supposed to
do here oh it's just the element not a
great name is scheme there past me so we
inside the point count thing here we're
back to where we were just looking at
these basic changes we needed for output
lighting points right we just look at if
this stuff this isn't how we're gonna do
this stuff anymore we don't want to do
any of it we don't want to do any of
this stuff so I'm pretty sure we can
just kind of nuke this code it's it's
not what we want at all so I'm gonna go
ahead and do that because we're gonna
want to output our voxel and our light
samples and that sort of stuff let me
see what else we got here for errors
so I think I'm just gonna leave it like
that for now and I'm gonna go ahead and
go to Q&amp;A cuz I think I don't want to
start on anything else now I want to
kind of leave it till next time because
now we're effectively doing everything
and we just want to start doing the
plumbing of moving those points in to
the system right and going from there
all right
I may also pop over now people wanted me
to fix these problems I added a very
helpful comment here so the problem is
type names being reused as field names
here so I guess in handmade types that H
I'll just take a look at whether that's
from 286 I really don't like having to
do this I think this is an absolutely
ridiculous thing I would like to
personally say that I think each and
every person who approved this changed
the C++ back should never program our
program ever again or if they do they
should not do it in a way that can ever
affect anyone else's code because they
just so very clearly have no idea what
they're doing I mean there should be a
path to redemption I suppose so if they
can explain clearly and lucidly why this
is an incredibly stupid idea that should
never have been done then they can
program again but until then you're out
to that line
alright so in the tokenizer that was 148
there now I get to change all of these
I really can't stress enough how anyone
who makes a decision like this should
never be allowed to design a language
it's nuts it's like such a case of the
inmates running the asylum right it's
like it is absolutely absurd it is the
kind of decision that is so incredibly
bad that you just have to wonder why
anyone would ever think it was a good
idea maybe if you were like only
programmed for a year or two or
something right
because I'm sure I thought all kinds of
stupid stuff when I was nine right but
man if you're at the point where you're
actually deciding how a language works
this is not acceptable not acceptable at
all what's the other one in game editor
somewhere in here a line point at it
I guess I would classify this decision
into the category of extreme arrogance
right so if you're working on a language
spec and you go you know what here's a
piece of code that would work just fine
there's no reason the compiler can't
generate 100% correct
unambiguous code for this but you then
go ahead and disallow it all you're
doing is saying hi I'm so arrogant that
only the way that I think programs
should be written is the Ray that they
can be written at all in my language
right and I have no idea how you get to
that point where you're like this would
have worked and we went out of our way
to tell the compiler to not generate the
working code because heaven forfend
someone should do something in our
language that we thought was just a
little bit weird probably because we
don't know how to program and so we
don't actually know what constitutes a
good one all right
and though it's not about undefined
behavior it's about diagnostic error
messages undefined behavior is also
completely unacceptable there should
never be anything in a spec that says
the behavior is undefined you should
define the behavior using the
appropriate bounds right just say the
compiler should generate the most
logical reasonable least surprising
thing that it can on this platform
that's all you need to say
just don't say surgery place for
undefined behavior and say the compiler
is supposed to do its best to generate
something like this for the platform
that in question that's all you need to
say and then everything works just fine
never say it's undefined behavior
because that is ridiculous why would you
ever want to say that there's no
constraints on the behavior of the thing
it's ridiculous
so now questions it looks like so I
think we're good to go right
where's the little where's that little
twitch window I have always now try to
check to see if there's anyone we can
raid after we're done on handmade hero
and usually the answer is that nobody is
available to raid of the people that I
would raid but but it's always worth a
quick little check right where is the
thing that you do with the raids
so is John live
No
nobody's nobody's life there's nobody to
raid so I guess we can trade anyone
today again again no one to raid
Chino's 3 says how do you know if you
wrote undefined behavior code well in
C++ the answer is you did it's basically
impossible to write C++ code that does
anything useful but doesn't have
undefined behavior somewhere so the
answer is you did the question is how do
you know where in your code you're using
undefined behavior that question is
harder right because there's so many
places in the C++ spec where they just
said it was undefined behavior that I
mean I don't know how to tell you how to
find it
right that's why it's so bad
compilers don't even warn you when
there's none behind defined behavior
which is interesting right and that's
part of the ridiculousness I mean like
for example write a typical way that you
might see something like undefined
behavior is suppose you have something
like I don't know the spec says if you
overflow a signed integer the result is
undefined right and so the compiler
can't really issue a warning because
everywhere you ever operate on a signed
integer you might overflow it right so
the undefined behavior only happens in
the case where you actually do overflow
the thing so it would warn you about
like every addition you ever add
something to you know so it's pretty
hard but it just depends on yeah like
which ones you're trying to find it says
there's a clang UB sanitizer yeah I mean
I don't know I've never tried it I don't
know how well that works
it probably catches some but the other
problem too is that undefined behavior
usually there's a lot of things in C++
they actually you want to use the quote
unquote undefined behavior because it
results in better actual CPU code for
most compilers on most platforms and so
again that's one of the really big
problems with undefined behavior it's
just it's dumb it's there's never have
been any I mean
another way to say it would be if you
can't put bounds on the behavior of your
program spec you're not done yet
your your spec isn't complete if there's
undefined behavior in it it's not a spec
it's a goal right undefined behavior
should never appear in a specification
you should always have a clear statement
about what the compiler is supposed to
be trying to do in all cases and if you
have to leave room meaning hey these
different platforms like for example you
know maybe two different platforms have
two different ways they handle certain
floating-point conditions you don't want
to specify things exactly because then
you can't generate good code on both
platforms so you need to leave space
sometimes and that's great but never
ever ever ever ever say undefined
that's absurd every single part of your
spec can be defined it can just be
defined to accept a range of possible
results but define the frigging range
like say what the space of acceptable
results could be don't just say we don't
know because that's absurd and you're
not done yet
what's the weirdest macro I don't know
I've I've never made macros that are
that weird I mean the ones in handmade
hero for the debug stuff are the
weirdest kinds of macros I think I ever
do they're ones where you have to pass
like the same argument like through
three different macros to prevent the C
string izing and pacing operators from
like stopping each other from working
you know what I'm talking about right
where we have to like generate debug
names by passing like things through
three times so that they don't use just
the actual like if you want like the
underscore underscore line underscore
underscore to become a string or
something you got to pass it through you
like fold what's the full screen purple
flash that happens in your editor
sometimes
ask Alan I don't know it's just a bug in
for coder I don't know what the bug is
have you seen a grand ceaseless air
explosion audition I have someone sent
it to me yesterday
in fact on the stream and it's pretty
great two of them work and see like
basically because they use includes but
I don't know that I really count those
as much because includes are ambiguous
anyway
so although the it would be nicer the
compiler printed out reasonable answers
for those things those aren't as bad the
C++ template ones are hilarious have you
seen the Grand C++ I'm sorry did you
enjoy it yes I did
why is there no one to read John blow
where are you
did you enjoy John smackin Smith I was
actually out at a movie and I have not
had a chance to watch it yet as I didn't
see it live
pragma strip imagine a light probe that
has no direct visibility to a red wall
but it could reach it by one indirect
bounce I don't think the light probe
will ever get any red contribution from
that wall no matter how long you iterate
unless you cast secondary rays from
surfaces no so that is definitely not
true let me show you the diagram for
that just to make it clearer what's
going on there that is if I actually had
a drawing program open okay so let's
just construct the case that is exactly
the case that you were talking about
there for clarity so let's talk about
secondary bounces here all right so
let's draw the 2d case so it's easier
for me to draw but obviously it doesn't
matter it works the same in any number
of dimensions because rays just go along
their direction and bounce so let's just
construct a case where there isn't
direct visibility in 2d and then we'll
go from there so you say imagine a light
probe so let's draw the probe this is
our probe no direct visibility to a red
wall so in order to create no direct
visibility
I'm gonna have to do something like put
an obstacle in here right so let's do
maybe our room is shaped like this right
and so if I want to I can put a wall
over here that I can't hit right this
here could be my red wall
makes sense okay so the argument is what
you're saying is that this red wall can
never contribute to the lighting of this
probe even though we might argue that it
should and the reason that we would
think that it should right is because
any light that hits this red wall could
legitimately bounce off this wall right
let's say we've got a white wall here or
at least a gray wall so it's it's a wall
that doesn't change the lighting so if
we have a white wall or a gray wall up
here what we're saying is we know that
if we were to simulate n bounces we
could bounce off of this wall here right
and hit the light probe on an indirect
bounce so light comes from some light we
don't care where that is I mean we can
put the light anywhere it doesn't matter
but you know if there's a light here or
something like this right light hits the
red wall it bounces off the red wall
hits the white wall or gray wall bounces
off that and then hits the probe and
your argument is our system won't ever
pick this up and I believe the reason
you're saying that is because we just we
only transmit light back like this along
this ray right it's not a fair statement
of what you were arguing there this is
the the transfer
makes sense okay so the question is is
that actually true meaning is it the
case that since we only transfer along
this ray we can never actually get this
value back and again my argument is no I
would say that that's not the case now
there is one possible way this maybe
could be the case and that's if you
don't put enough light probes in your
system right and then that would be true
but that's gonna be true of everything
meaning if you don't put enough light
probes in the system then your lighting
is not gonna be accurate period
right you need a dense enough sprinkling
of light probes in the system in order
to capture accurate lighting period so I
don't really think that's a particularly
good case get out so let's assume a
reasonable set of light probes in this
area right so I don't know how many
light probes we would have necessarily
but you know they're probably scattered
throughout the environment something at
least like this right so each one of
these points would be a light probe and
we probably out even more in 3d right
because they'd be volume but you've got
light probes sprinkled around right okay
so what actually happens in this system
remember is every frame each of these
light probes will send out some number
of rays at the moment the number is 18
but we can sort of tweak it for
performance so we're gonna this number
will typically be as many as we can
afford right so this number is 18 right
now it may be it'll only be six maybe
it'll be twelve it's gonna be set to the
highest number that we can run and not
slow down the game right so we don't
know what this will be but it will be
something and so each one of these light
probes will send out that many per frame
what that means is on the same frame
that this probe was sending out this
particular ray here to hit this hit it
was also sending out several other ones
right and hitting other places
but we all agree because the
construction of your argument
presupposes it we all agree that it will
never hit this wall right because I
specifically placed an obstacle that
shadows that wall completely so we know
that it will only be grabbing from
around here so now the question is can
it ever actually receive light from the
red wall well remember on the frame
where this particular probe sent out all
of those feelers all of these probes
also sent out their own set of 18
feelers right or six or twelve however
many what that means is this probe this
probe this probe probably this probe and
maybe sometimes this probe all hit the
red wall correct because this one
probably sent something out in that
direction
every so often maybe not every frame
this one very likely did this one almost
certainly did because anything in that
direction will hit it same with this one
in this one so we know that on any given
frame probably three probes at least hit
the red wall right so those three probes
all picked up light from the red wall on
that frame make sense and which probes
were they well they were these two
probes which probably don't matter in
our case and these three probes which
definitely do right this one
occasionally this one fairly frequently
this one almost always when this light
probe hits anywhere on this wall it will
definitely then sample lighting from
probes which have hit the red wall on
the previous frame right it will then
gather that light from those probes
which includes the contribution from the
red wall leading this probe to now have
some red wall contribution
makes sense so the answer is in one
frame can you get light from the red
wall no in two frames can you yes now in
our system we average over at least 60
frames I think so as long as that number
doesn't drop to two which would be
ridiculous I mean we may drop it down to
something more like ten in the future if
our legs really good but we average over
at least ten frames and we always use
the lighting from the previous frame so
for secondary bounces like this this is
sufficient but the answer is the number
of frames you average over is how many
secondary bounces you get so actually
over 60 frames we're actually doing what
amounts to 60 bounce lighting now that
60th bounce is a fraction of the
contribution right it's not happening
very often so it's kind of meaningless
to say that but certainly within those
first few frames three frames four
frames five frames we're definitely
taking into account all those bounces at
a relatively high shading rate right uh
was that convincing or not okay awesome
sounds like that
that was that was convincing and yeah
and again this is by design when you're
doing real-time lighting you don't
usually have the kind of computation or
power necessary to do multi bounce
diffuse lighting inside one frame right
it would be nice if you did but you
typically don't and so what you try to
do is specular like highly reflective
surfaces those don't Rose won't require
spreading of bounces right so what I
would say is specular lighting you try
to do within one frame because delayed
reflections wouldn't look very good so
you try to do specular inside one frame
diffuse lighting where things are
scattered a lot you never try to do
those all in one frame so typically what
you want to do is design a solution that
allows you to propagate that light over
several frames and because diffuse
lighting is exactly that it's diffuse
it's hard to see specific changes
they're gradual anyway so it tends to
not be very objectionable in terms of
artifacts because diffuse lighting can't
change that rapidly anyway right so the
worst case for you really is when you're
doing that kind of frame by frame
propagation is if you turn off a light
then the propagation of that light it
will it will kind of fade out rather
than instantly going out that's about
the worst case for diffuse lighting that
you're gonna see and and that does not
bother me in the least right
so but also I mean I should say separate
than that that's also one good reason
why the faster you make your lighting
the better because averaging over you
know 60 frames or something it does mean
that you can't do like flashing light
propagation very well or things like
that as you get that number down if you
can get it down to eight frames 16
frames then a flashing light sort of
does work a little bit it can't flash
too fast but it could flash like once a
second and still look okay but so so you
do want to kind of it's still worth your
while to try and get it down as low as
you can and so denoising and getting
yourself down to a situation where you
can do eight frames to blend 16 frames
to blend something like that not 60
frames to blend 120 frames or blend it
does help you it does make the game
better and more interesting to look at
to get that speed down but again that's
really all you're up against for these
sort of longer bounce sort of things is
just trying to get it down for like so
that lighting changes as lights move or
turn on and off you just trying to get
some of the lag out of it
we all done the questions and yeah for
the folks on the chat that are talking
about signed overflows so again like
undefined behavior there's never an
excuse for it in my opinion ever but
this is why I was saying nonspecific
behavior is still okay and the reason
for that is because you do need the
compiler to have flexibility sometimes
to generate good code and so what you
want to do is you want to define the
range of possible answers to be the
range that is necessary for good
optimization but you don't want it
broader than that right so if you don't
want to specifically say what happens
when a signed number overflows because
it may cause problems for optimizing
compilers that's okay what's not okay is
just saying it's undefined that's
totally not okay because at that point
all programs are basically broken all of
them that ever add two signed numbers
together right because who knows right I
mean you may have needed to check for
those things I do if statements or you
wanted to know what was gonna happen you
can't just say it's undefined everywhere
say what you need to say and nothing
more
right if you need to leave ability for
that go right ahead and furthermore just
add a keyword if the person wants to
know that assigned overflow will wrap
let them specify that right let them put
it thing in there that says this signed
type of signed integer has to wrap mr
compiler right just do it that way
there's no excuse for undefined behavior
never I've never seen one and I don't
think I ever will you can always do a
better job than that
and still get all the same benefits it's
just lazy and it's wrong it shouldn't
occur in a spec ever there should never
be something called undefined behavior
ever for any reason you can define
boundaries do that or you can add
control to the programmer do that but
never ever ever just say something's
undefined it's just unacceptable
alright looks like we're done looks like
we're done with questions we all we had
there was some other yes this we got to
go fix this one to at some point that
was the other Linux compilation bug
thing all right thank you everyone for
joining me Phillips with a hand made
here I throw a puncher cutting with you
as always we'll be back next weekend to
start like actually pushing light
through the light system now that we've
sketched out all the code that's just
it's just bookkeeping now but we want to
get that bookkeeping correct so we'll
start on the bookkeeping and that's what
we'll be able to start debugging and
testing it and getting to the point
where we think it's actually propagating
light correctly and that'll be fine once
we get that done I think maybe next
weekend we got a shot at getting that
stuff all working we may we may not
depends how many bugs we run into if we
get all that stuff working next weekend
that would be great because then we're
just down to like pushing to the GPU for
our lighting stuff and that's going to
be pretty pretty cool right in two weeks
if the scheduled post onto it
did I not schedule anything for wait is
the schedule busted
Oh weird
it looks like I forgot two days the 24th
and 25th hold please is that intentional
am I gone that weekend or something I
know is that my vacation and just don't
know nope
so that was 100% unintentional the 24th
at least should have been scheduled the
25th maybe not
[Music]
all right hold please everyone
well we real-time edit the schedule for
handmade Hiro I should update that
because I think that's wrong so I don't
know why I skipped that I think I was
just putting it a bunch of dates and
just for god I guess 20 1908 so it
should be what the 24th so maybe what
we'll do cuz I guess I made a mistake
there maybe next weekend what we can do
is on the 24th because I do have
something kind of scheduled on the 25th
a little bit inconveniently there if I'm
looking at it so I'm not sure how I want
to do that exactly but what I might say
is let's just say the 25th is off but
the 24th is not
I'll also note this in the schedule does
that look better now
let's take a look
schedule bot what do you say there we go
alright so in that cases we will
probably only have one stream that
weekend we'll have to decide maybe that
would be a good time to do the two just
to explain how skinned mesh skinning
works maybe since we'll only do one that
weekend so maybe we'll do have a chat
maybe we won't I don't know we'll see
but then we'll resume at any rate August
31st September 1st at least then we will
resume doing the lighting plumbing if we
don't do it next weekend alright anyway
regardless I hope to see you back here
next Saturday for whatever we end up
doing on handmade here until then please
have fun programming I'll see on the
internet and as always if you want to
follow along with the source code at
home you can always preorder the game on
handmade here it up or gonna come to the
source code if you want to play around
with it until we next meet that's it for
today I will see everyone back here next
week take it easy everybody