and welcome to hand made here oh sure we
code a complete game live on stream we
are kind of at a fun point in the
project at least I've been having a lot
of fun with it we're sort of at that
point where all of our design decisions
are kind of coming together and you can
kind of see how everything is supposed
to interrelate like a lot of the
exploratory stuff we did is now
resolving in a good way and so you know
we're able to to just get a lot of stuff
right I don't know a look at it is we're
able to kind of get to the point where
we're like okay we see exactly how
assets should be managed now or we see
exactly how this can be done in a simple
nice clean way we don't have to worry
about it anymore blah blah blah um oops
did I launch that twice I did don't ask
me why we go and so it's pretty exciting
because really what you know the place
we find ourselves in it's just this
really kind of nice open field where we
can say look anything that we go spend
time on will probably yield some really
good fruit right away right we're you
know we're in good shape there and so I
think what I want to do today just kind
of finish up some of the stuff you're
doing I'm gonna finally go
I want to peg these guys to the corner
of the screen I've been talked about
many times you notice that our debug
stuff doesn't peg properly to the corner
of the screen like it should you know
what I mean and so I think I might go
play around just real quickly with that
today just make make these things work a
little bit more the way that I might
want them to so that's one thing that I
think I would like to do the other thing
I would like to do is in the so we
played a little bit with the camera
making it a little bit less perspective
II just to let the 2d art stuff work a
little bit better I think now is the
time to go really harp on that camera
code so that is another thing big on the
table and then finally and the thing
that maybe will take up a fair bit of
today because I don't know I wanted
started the camera code stuff but we
actually have all the stuff in here for
editing alignment points we need to do a
little bit of grunt work to save those
out it's trivial for us to implement
saving back to the HHA in fact we don't
even have to implement it it's literally
just a call that says hey we save this
file so that's a no-brainer but the more
the more difficult part well it's not
only difficult but the more work
intensive part is we have to go make a
backing store for those that we can
consider an authoritative file so in
other words something that's like a text
file that we can put aside the PNG s and
consider it like canonical data for
handmade hero so that we can say this
text file
you know describes the alignment points
that we marked up on this thing so if we
ever want to completely delete the hhas
for this in their entirety so they're
just gone there's no more hhas if we
ever want to do that we can and we can
still rebuild the entire handmade hero
assets packaged together with the
metadata can all be built again from
source so we're just trying to close
that loop because if we just save them
back to the hhas you know we could
consider those hhas authoritative but
then it makes it a lot harder to you
know store in a permanent archival
format everyone understands text files
source code control understands text
files they're easy to verify visually or
you know restore if they get broken so
you know it just seems like a better
idea to have that backing store there
that's that's really all you know all
there is to it little stretch first very
important and then we'll get to work on
some of these things so maybe what I'll
do the outset is again just just maybe
clean up some of that debugging stuff a
little bit make that a little clearer
one of the things
that I'm not sure how I want to do
here's we had some lighting test stuff
in here before you can see I'm like
pressing some keys right now for example
and changing lighting you know all
around there I I think we want to stop
you know now that I've got more
interface stuff I think maybe we want to
go get our interface story together our
developer interface story together bind
our F keys to something that makes sense
and put the debug system and the editor
together in some way in that like make
make it be so you hit f12 do editing f2
to do debug or whatever so it's like it
just makes them some more solid sense
that's mostly all I want to do there and
then get the get these things pegged
properly when you turn them on
get those pegged properly to the top of
the screen so I would like something
like that to happen and so like let's
just get that going because it's been
annoying me and I really don't want it
to keep annoying me all right so let's
suppose that in yeah in in the world's
today that we want a more centralized
that that handling of the you know
pressing the f1 f2 whatever that is so
in here in handmade game editor our
in-game editor like the way that this
stuff works is you can you you know when
you hit a key it's gonna set this editor
mode and like that mode that we set is
just kind of ad hoc right now so you
know edit mode underscore you can kind
of see where that's where that's
happening inside begin hit test it looks
to see whether you push from those keys
and then sets that up and you know
again that I kind of feel like we want
this to be handled in a more centralized
fashion I don't really know how that
should happen it's kind of a little
confusing certainly because I haven't
really thought through where that sort
of stuff should happen but I think we
want something a little bit more you
know like in in this code this is our
main game just you know central Nexus
where we actually like put stuff out to
the debug system and all that sort of
thing so it kind of feels to me more
like you know that should probably
happen inside excuse me
inside this general process here
right like that seems like more what we
would want to do and so I think here
would it be where we would want to have
the ability to have the fast F key
access where we could say you know or a
whatever the F keys are that you press
they can yield various results right and
some of those results might be things
that the debug system looks at some of
those might not be but I may want to
kind of centralize that
devmode you know what I mean and so what
I'm thinking just in my head about how
you know how that might come together is
rather than having that editor have that
in there mm-hmm maybe this is actually
just like a more broad concept so maybe
this is like a dev mode and the dev
modes are actually things that are that
span across multiple systems so I can be
in one of n dev modes and depending on
which dev mode I'm in I may get an
editor running or I may get a debug
system running
but generally speaking since they what
those systems kind of want to monopolize
the user interface at that point
potential
I'm thinking maybe that's how we
arbitrate that aspect so rather than
forcing all of those systems to tie
together through the same UI which I
don't really think I want to do because
I kind of want the flexibility to have
different things completely take over
the UI potentially depending on the
circumstances rather than harmonizing
all of those I think what I'd rather do
is is have that dev mode be responsible
for who gets to do which of those things
you know what I mean and it could still
be very ad hoc this is developer
specific code doesn't have to be super
polished or anything but I think that's
roughly what I want to go with and so
you know we'll have the asset editing
stuff in there as as one way things
could happen we could have like
profiling be another example we could
have you know settings be another one
you know that sort of stuff so these can
actually be quick ways of accessing
basic elements of the debug UI as well
as the editing UI
yeah I mean that seems pretty good to me
and and we could make it so that yeah
like you know you push f1 and you get
none you know maybe we have like
something like this I don't know you
know I'm saying
so something like that seems pretty good
to me I might say that this should
practice would go a little bit more like
this so this may be this is an f1 this
actually starts maybe on f5 through f6
f7
I don't really know necessarily how I
would I would want that to go something
like this
[Music]
right like something where I can kind of
have different types of stuff that we're
doing there I don't know if we actually
have I mean if we if we look at what's
in there now most of it's largely
useless you know we've got simple ways
of setting some of these things but I
feel like those these can be expressed
better than they're being expressed now
as well you know all this stuff could be
expressed better we don't have stuff a
renderer is still in there
yeah so like a lot of this stuff is just
a little vestigial remains and stuff so
as we clean that up and make it actually
more useful in the modern context and
we've got our lighting tests on here
which is sort of a separate line of
things it just seems to me like we can
this stuff can get improved and we can
we can make this better right all right
so I'm gonna proceed with this and we'll
see where we get with it again this is
just trying to improve that system make
it a little bit more useful to me so
what I want to do here is if the if the
person presses f1 then they just clear
you know they're not in a dev mode so f1
is the way of getting rid of the dev
mode entirely at any time you can just
hit that and it goes away I don't want
to make that the escape key because the
escape keys
actually a game-related key so I'd like
that to remain free for processing by
the game in an actual game setting so
that that just doesn't have to ever be
special
especially handled it's actually just
you know always uniformly correct
so editing assets would be on f2 or
maybe a four I don't know which one I
want we'll see then three is is nothing
at the moment and four is nothing so
then it's five would be the first time
that we get another mode here so then
we've got like five six seven and eight
so we've got profiling we've got you
know rendering we've got lighting and
we've got dumped and I don't really know
if we're gonna actually use all these
you know who knows this is dead mode and
then and then instead of these things
set on the editor these are just gonna
be like a dev mode parameter that sits
on the game so what I want to do is is
make again like that's central it's so
it's just part of the global game state
that anyone can always access because
it's like a developer global overriding
mode that anyone who wants to just stick
some debug code into that piece of their
code can switch on this variable if they
wish to and do whatever they want and so
that's intentionally not hidden it's
intentionally going to be exposed
globally and the reason for that is
because I don't want it to be
heavyweight operation or a routing
operation to access it I want everyone
who ever wants to do anything related to
it just be able to insert that code
directly and that's that's actually the
goal right so if I were to take that
code now and in the in-game editor stop
using the editor mode so rather than in
here saying in game editor
mode getting rid of that and having it
use the the game asset mode I'm sorry
using the game state it means I would
have to pass the game state around here
which maybe I don't necessarily want to
do um so what I can do is I can mirror
it into the editor if I want to so I can
put that in here and then whenever we
begin hit test write whenever we come in
here I can just say well the editor game
mode is going to be equal to the game
States game mode always right so I'm
just gonna force that Tunis to be what
happens right and we could even make
that be like a thing that gets passed in
here and that's just so I don't have to
pass the game state around because I
don't really want to have to make sure
that that it was good passed around the
editor should be sufficient I could link
it back but I'm not going to so there we
go
and then in here we supposed to be dev
mode and so everyone who's checking that
needs to then respect that value in here
we've we've probably got this in an
order that's not that's not flattering
so you know the editor gets included
first before the game state and we would
need some more centralized location for
defining this stuff that's actually not
that hard to do right we can just put it
right here and then we should be fine so
here I just need to take any place that
was referring to the you know to that as
an editor specific concept and I just
need to now refer to it in sort of the
more unified context but that's it and
then here let's see where we're at so
the game state this actually has to
happen a little bit later because we
have to have actually initialized our
game states so but once we have then we
can actually do that checking so we
probably want to do it somewhere here
right like that once the game state has
is known and initialized uh this needs
to take the game state dev mode again
because it gets replicated just every
frame back in there but otherwise that's
fine
alright so now when we run we should use
the new format which is to say f1 turns
things off oh you know what else I have
to do is stop using that for lighting so
I now want to deep this like I'm just
gonna disallow anyone else from using
this stuff so you can't actually access
any of these features anymore now we may
still want these these features to be
available so rather than like literally
delete the code what I think I might do
instead is just bucket them out here so
that when they you know like this right
here when they are needed again I could
call something to have these be maybe
tied into the interface right meaning
all of this stuff could actually be
debug UI that actually happens right we
could make this be available as part of
the lighting like a lighting UI feature
you know what I mean and so you know if
we look at debug interface here or
whatever I could make like a kind of of
clickable button or something I don't
remember if we already have one of those
or whatever but you know now that we
kind of have a better idea of how that
stuff is flowing through we could we
could use one of these things to make
like a debug button right so we could do
like debug button you know they're
lighting and or you know in fact that
right there is just that we know what
kind that is that's like a debug b32
right so
that's just that
what's she lighting
what was she letting go again sorry
forgot it's world mode show buddy right
yeah so these could just be something
like this and this needs to do a little
bit of clearing here so this one
actually kind of wants to know when the
thing was changed so that's a little bit
more complicated this one's actually
just a s32 value or I guess I should say
kind of what more wants to be a u-32
value almost but again that's that's
something that you could edit
so we could say debug what is debug box
to rod I don't know what kind is maybe
it's a u-32 I'm not sure
and this again is just to be 32 so all
of these we could do this way and maybe
we will make something better for those
lighting pattern I don't remember what
that is oh yes I do that was a thing
that allowed us to test our Rea
distributions so like you know yeah we
could still do it this way
this one also wants to be that way right
so this is a debug button but you can
push and it's called like a cumulation I
guess I don't know how we want to do
that exactly I guess it's more like hey
which one is this yeah I'm not sure so
we'll know test lighting cumulating what
is that doing it's like saying we won't
turn it on or off and then I guess we so
I guess what we want to do here is say
look if you if you swapped which one it
is it should return something so that we
know we want to do that operation
so we more want to do this like if
accumulation sets to true
so the way this worked originally is if
the cumulating was set to true it turned
it off so it's not accumulating and then
the accumulation got set to zero if said
accumulating true it just set to that so
I'm guessing what we want to do here is
just say all right so if we're not if
you toggled it to be not accumulating
then what we would want to do is set
this to zero otherwise we don't have to
do anything right I think that's my
argument so anyway in here this is
basically like our debug lighting and
that needs to take the world mode so we
can look at reenable exact in in a
little bit but I want to make sure that
we get the basis down first so I just
wanted to button that up so we didn't
delete any of that functionality just in
case we want to do some stuff with that
again as we when we move back to working
on lighting a little bit more so now in
terms of the features like being able to
hit like f1 f2 and so on I want I now
want to get it so that like this stuff
goes away or comes back depending on
which one of these buttons I'm pushing
right and so trying to move forward on
that a little bit
so so I guess what we really want to do
here is inside the debug system where
we're actually setting up what we're
drawing you know we've got and and we or
did this once for the lighting so you
know if you look at how this stuff is
set up we had like a thing called like
function group yeah this so we allowed
people to dump whatever they want into
these various groups and then we display
them in different ways and so you know
if you look at what happens with that
oops with that function group thing you
can kind of see how these trees are
added and then they're they're added it
like locations and this was actually the
problem is this stuff doesn't snap right
the way that I would want and so I think
really all I want to do here is create
some of these you know here's the
profile group for example as well I want
to create some of these variables that
are that are gonna be stratified by by
where that came from
so in order to select which one of these
we'd be doing like you know we'd go down
here and we look at the function group
thing this add tree here so rather than
like how many trees do we have I kind of
just want that to be more on the F keys
you know what I mean so
so I think all I really want to do is
when we're doing our when we're doing
the debug and and we go through here
this stuff should be more predicated in
terms of one ends up getting drawn and
in fact yeah so I'm kind of seeing like
how this should probably come together
so maybe that's memory right and who
knows what other stuff we want to put in
here but so
so I guess what I would say is this
stuff here like where we do this format
string whatever like all of this stuff I
think now kind of wants to be you know
wants to be more systemic so rather than
making this stuff be like function info
size and function info and like that
sort of stuff I think we kind of want
this stuff to be handled more like the
other UI where they're not the floaty
trees we just pick which one we're doing
and we go from there so you know we
could preserve the draw trees path but
as something you can still call to if
you're in whatever mode that is but that
wouldn't be the default way of doing
things right so instead Jimmy so instead
of having this global debug table HUD
function as well like we would just in
fact I guess now I think about it we
could just make that
we could even make that HUD function be
something that's actually determined
outside yeah so I'm not sure exactly how
I want that part to shake out but what I
what I am fairly certain about here
right because I want to have a couple
different things that are going on here
so I would like to have debug profiling
be one of them I'd like to have debug
rendering be one of them
I'd like to have debug lighting be one
of them and I'd like to have you know do
you bet memory be one of them and that
would sort of determine which part of
this tree you were actually looking at
and why um I guess like maybe we don't
actually need a function for it per se
but when I'm looking at what happens
here we we tend to want to build like
customized statics status strings so I
feel like that sort of stuff kind of
needs to be somewhere in here right and
so I don't know like I feel like we're
gonna want functions for it because
we're gonna want to do other kinds of
customized iteration that's you know
maybe at least somewhat specific and
maybe the answer is that should have
been done as a debug element type and so
the trees are just you know descriptions
of what should happen I don't know it's
pretty hard to say how hard would that
be to implement so if we wanted to make
those be nonspecific like meaning if I
wanted that to just be a generic line
how hard would that be for me to
implement in the debug system like if I
wanted so you know we've got these
various types of things when we're
actually outputting this stuff right
we've got all this logic you know here's
all these things you can draw you know
what I mean
so if we have all this can't we just
make a thing that's like yeah you know
you look here and you see you know last
frame info or whatever and that's
actually this so it looks trivial to
actually have that happen so maybe
that's just what should happen that just
seems a lot more sensible to me so I'm
gonna go ahead and say let's go ahead
and and make this collapse down so you
know here's the last frame info and you
know this stuff can just be rolled into
here this is the old version of that but
here's the new version of that so we
should be able to just grab that and you
know do it this way instead so when we
look at this piece of information here
this the rest of this stuff stays the
same and then the only difference is it
goes into this like temporary text
buffer thing rather than you know into
it's the the that sort of pre created
yeah pre created area so that should be
fine and similarly like the way that
we're doing this thing down here it
looks like this just tallies up for a
particular function what you wanted I
don't see why that couldn't also be one
of these things so like if I said this
thing was a function summary or
something
then this I feel like would also you
know should be able to be represented in
the same way meaning like I don't
substantively know why that wouldn't
work so like this
right printing it out the same way that
we were printing out this and then
calling basic text element seems like it
should work you know and you know maybe
I could even say well by default this
says like function not found or
something I feel like that would be
reasonable so in here where we do like
this you know global table HUD function
well you know these in theory have data
associated with them right like you know
if I say that I've got some kind of
bitmap ID or whatever right then I'd get
it out of the the value of of whatever
the you know event thing was and
furthermore I assume any way that you
know if you look at what like a default
value is then you can see here like we
say like debug event to text so like
just looking at when you have those
debug events when you look at these
write debug events to text things you
can see them using all of this
additional information right so like the
value are 32 and all that stuff so if we
were to look at at that this stuff then
we could easily say that one of those
functions summaries just has like text
in it right so like you know it could
just set the value string pointer to be
whatever the thing was that you were
actually looking for or the name you
know whatever the actual piece of data
is that shows up in here we could use
that as the query so in theory you
should be able to in the debug system it
should be just like there shouldn't be
any weirdness about that you should be
able to just go ahead and and grab
whichever debug thing makes more sense
there right I mean that just now that
seems pretty basic so anyway I think
that's what I would rather do so rather
in here than saying like let's have this
global you know global debug table
where'd that go
so rather than looking at the global
debug table and saying well there's only
one you know you get one summary
function you should just be able to have
as many summary functions as you want
and then where there's those are placed
you know they're they're placed wherever
they are so that HUD function thing was
probably just me screwing around
so let's just let's get rid of that like
let's just get get rid of that and then
in here Jimmy when we get one of these
events we'll just say look let's look
for that event it's gonna have a value
string pointer attached to it and that's
the that's what you should look for so
just get that get that thing right and I
suppose what we could do here is we
could also say instead of calling that
function not found what we could do to
is actually print something out there so
in this case like when we can't find it
then we could actually do a printf here
and say
you know if you asked me to print
something out and I can't find it then
I'm gonna you know I'm gonna tell you
like this so I think that works don't
need any of that nonsense there so that
seems good so as far as HUD time
function that's not going to be a thing
anymore we need to define one of these
function summary things and so what was
it gonna be in handmade interface so
that needs to kind of go in here as the
thing that you can have and then will
have to have a way of adding one of
those obviously but we can do that
pretty easily so let's see event
undeclared identifier that's a good
point
we haven't actually gotten the event at
that point I feel like the null event is
something we probably just want up here
um unless that lease to get cleared
every time does it all right I took it
back I lied
so I'm gonna make that happen each time
and that way everyone can use that if
they want to so in this case we've got
kind of multiple versions of event
happening here and I can see why that is
not fabulous because yeah we don't
really want to have to those looking at
events I guess I can just call this sub
event here like so
all right so in theory that should all
be fine and we just need a way of
actually adding those now and so now
hopefully you can also see like we don't
have any lines for the start of those
trees and the reason why we don't have
any lines for the start of those trees
is because now we aren't printing them
out there anymore right so when we
actually look at it you know in the
debug interface that's just I think
that's cuz when we did the debug stuff
originally you know it wasn't our finest
hour certainly we kind of struggled
exactly with how we wanted to do it and
we never really ended up at a place that
was all that great and so it tends to be
more complicated than it needs to be and
it doesn't really do a lot of stuff that
you might want and so we had sort of
these like route info function info
things I think we just want those to go
away right and that's how we were doing
it we were basically creating a
temporary buffer to write this into and
then we you know pointed these things at
it and that's just not a very good way
to do that right that's that is not how
we would actually like that to go and so
we kind of want you know when we create
these variable this variable link here
that we were creating we would rather
have this just be when we click
thing we know that we can expand or
collapse that thing kind of separately
from it so I want to go in and see how
exactly we specified this stuff I don't
know if we've actually got yeah that
that actually looks fine so when we
create a variable link in here you know
it it has the element and then it has
children so I think that basically means
that this type here can be anything that
you actually wanted it to be I believe
so if you look at what the debug element
is on it I believe this could be set to
whatever you wanted so when we do this
stuff I feel like that would work let's
make sure it does but basically what we
want to do here is set this stuff up for
a success right so looking into this
debug elements the debug type here must
have been set to something so when we
have create variable linked which
creates one of these sort of things that
can can create trees or whatever when we
do one of these things I was curious
what kind of thing it actually creates
by default and it looks like it actually
creates it doesn't put an element in
there at all right so if it doesn't put
an element in there at all that means we
could attach an element to it I would
think and then the only question is did
we do something weird where we don't
process elements on things that have
children yet I mean and it looks like
unfortunately that is sort of the case
you can see here like when we come
through can't have children of a link it
then says well okay then then you don't
you know you don't do this
if that's the case and again that seems
less good right because we don't really
care one way or the other about you know
we would rather just be able to draw
this and also have it so that if you
interact with it it can expand the
children so I'm not sure why you know
that is actually that way and and I also
don't really know why we have the link
name replicated there like how often
does that really have to happen so I'm
gonna go on a bit of a rampage here and
just try to clean this stuff up a little
bit as well I'm deleting that for now so
yeah if we come through here you know we
should if I run this you know we'll get
nominally those names placed in there
right and that's fine and so what I want
to look for I want to understand what's
happening here when we have this name
field like what is that name field
actually doing and is it actually
necessary so looking through where that
actually gets called
[Music]
you know it looks like it's really only
used inside the profiler tool tip and I
guess we replicate that name out here
but otherwise it really isn't
necessarily you so I'm out try this I
want to see everyone who calls that yeah
so this this just doesn't seem necessary
to me
so it looks like the reason if that's
there primarily is that getting you know
it it does a simplified extraction of
the name out of whatever the parse name
field was there and I'm assuming that
the reason we were doing that is because
we wanted to save that name off and not
have to extract it every time you know
what I mean which is certainly
reasonable but again I don't really know
you know I don't really know if we made
that decision particularly well so
looking through here you know on the top
clock's list again it just uses that get
name for the element function there and
it does that for the label for the arena
C right so it's just getting the name of
their source but most the time it does
look like people just use the name from
the actual events that are in there and
that just seems better
so what I would say is everyone who's
accessing the name directly so you know
I would I would say I don't know why
this can't be that right right that
would just work wouldn't it
and so now everybody who accesses the
name field is just asking for it through
that excess or and so I think and I
could be very wrong about this but I
think what we could do there is say all
right so get name on a debug element is
actually going to be a little bit more
complicated than it was before and what
we'll do is we'll actually you know when
we go to get the the name of the thing
we can actually produce the name on the
fly potentially if that name should be
produced on the fly that seems like a
better idea and we can look to see if
you know to what extent that wouldn't
work but if everyone is going through
get name we can at least play around
with it yes I guess what I would say
okay so if I wanted to make that
automatically handle sort of more
complex cases where I want some of the
names to be able to generate summaries
instead of being named something
specific then I think what I can do is
when you are calling that get name
function now I can make that be actually
you know the I can actually have that
call through to here
so yeah I don't know whether these
things I don't know to what extent this
part actually matters all that much but
I certainly can mirror that behavior and
so what I would do here is say let's
let's say that in order to access this
thing when you call get name on a debug
element you actually have to pass the
same thing as we were passing before and
maybe it thunks through to this thing
right so in the case where the element
actually does have an event structure
associated with it then we can do
something more like this
for a lack of something better to do
now in terms of what the flag should be
here I guess I'm not sure probably none
of these things maybe just add value
I mean I couldn't yeah I'm not really
sure what I would put there but let's
say add value and so we would just dunk
through to this and here is the part of
the code that would actually do this
stuff so it would actually you know it
would actually do sort of the null event
nonsense handling here so this stuff
where it looks to see if it can get you
know a it looks to see whether it can
get one of these pieces of information
so for example like you know this stuff
here where it goes and does the debug
state frames that kind of stuff
and so I think it really just means that
the get name function all it would
really need to have passed to it would
be the debug state itself like so and
then I don't know if inside here you
need to get for a debug event to text I
guess I don't know whether we would want
to add it in here or not but yeah we
certainly could like again this stuff
really I feel like could be made a lot
better you know this is not good and we
could improve this dramatically I'm just
not sure how much of that improvement I
really want to make at the immediate
moment so we could through to here
we could also do something slightly
different which is to say that we you
know by default take whatever the name
is but then like you know if this thing
when we look at what the type is here
we can opt to do something different
here and I mean so you know when we call
get name on this thing then maybe we
don't actually ever thunk through to
that but we just handled those two kind
of weird cases where we've got sort of
the the function summary and the last
frame info here domain so again not
really sure I don't really like the way
that that looks particularly much but
you know it's good enough for now so if
we take a look at what happens inside
the debug type last frame info and we
want that to be accessible elsewhere we
can't just say well all right you know
that's something that goes in here and
maybe we continue to thunk through this
this way but eventually we could unify
these two things in a better way so you
know we'll call the get main function
there and it will output it the same
would be true on function summary so you
know this right here
he's gonna do that format string so we'd
call get name and and you know maybe we
pass you a buffer that you can use but
then we return it just in case we want
to short-circuit that process and then
we you know inside the function summary
type we've got you know we've got this
whole thing as well and you can kind of
see how we would want to make this a lot
better than it is kind of going forwards
for size buffer and and I'm really
tempted to do so but you know trying to
keep it to a minimum so in here we can
just patch that and then you know this
will overwrite sort of the default
result and it's just a hack - it's just
a total like way to patch around what's
happening rather than just rewriting the
thing around it to do what it really
should have done in the first place so
either of these two is then the same
meaning if you get either of those since
we now want those to be able to be
selectable expansion lines then we end
up in a position where we kind of have
to make this stuff happen and so both of
those are going to want to do you know
the the debug state call and they're
going to want to have that buffer
available in case they need to fill it
so those can call it that way now and so
when you get the name of the thing it
can expand the name into something more
complete
and so then the question becomes oops
oldest torrid event I don't actually
know what oldest stored event is in this
case tell me what that was
zooming here I guess we don't really
need to do the nil event case so really
what we can do here is say well you know
if the oldest stored event actually
exists at all
then you're gonna do this otherwise
you're not and we can just do it that
way right so you know if eventually you
got this thing or if you didn't then
that's you know off you go and I think
that's all we really need we could do
that a little bit cleaner than we do in
fact I suppose I should do it this way
so we just switch on whether or not we
got a HUD function and we just set this
to zero first right and that's pretty
basic so I think that's good news that's
gonna work
so I think that's pretty good function
name can also default to the value and
then in here anytime that we were
previously doing that get name where we
need to do a format string there we
could have a buffer that does the get
name the element gets passed last the
debug state gets passed here right yeah
so any way that we anywhere we do that
we want to actually call the get name
that way and you know we could try do we
could again like not call it in certain
places if we know that we don't need to
but it's still yeah I mean like I said
this is not really the way I would want
to do this you know if we were shipping
this system as a real thing I would go
and rewrite a lot of that stuff to work
in a cleaner way but at the moment you
know throwing in a bunch of disgusting
stuff here is totally fine with me
because I don't this system is not
really supposed to be ever seen by an
end user and so if we want to eventually
make it something that's a little bit
more real we certainly can do that but
at the you know will rewrite it at that
point not right now let's see oops
but that's it so you know it's ugly but
at least it's you know simple if you're
gonna do something ugly you might as
well do something simple ugly and
complicated is worse kind of why this
code isn't good to begin with so I think
that should allow us to get now a more
like anyone who wants to make one of
these things be an actual type I think
now could do that so they would be able
to stick actual type of debug event into
that hierarchy and have that debug event
produce the actual name so you know
nothing should change in the immediate
sense because the the trees in question
were not created with any particular
events underneath them and so now if we
wanted to create an event underneath
them so for this element if we wanted to
put into there some kind of a you know
some kind of a frame information that
actually had a stored event of a type we
could do so now if we're just looking
for last frame data then in theory this
one you can literally just change the
type and I think it works so meaning in
here if I just change the type of this
thing to be one of these I think you're
good to go at that point right meaning I
think that one oops
I think that one just kind of is all you
really actually needed it to do so I
think that works although I don't
actually know if a debug element is ever
created for those things to be
completely honest with you so let me
just see if I may need to create an
element that does that so you know the
diba the variable link
so yeah like the debug variable link
itself
I'd like that that also has a name like
what's the point of that so we want that
to use the name of the element for sure
right
yeah I mean so I guess the problem there
is it doesn't necessarily always create
one of those elements which is kind of
nuts like I don't know why we have to
have links and elements because since
the elements themselves I mean I guess
the idea I guess the idea here is just
that like okay elements are a little
heavier weight because they have to have
debug frames worth of stuff stored in
them maybe
but I mean if I'm just you know looking
at that I'm like well why wouldn't you
still want to create an element for each
of those so that the variable link that
links to it links to it properly you
know what I mean
like I feel like you really want to
force there to be an element at any
given time and the element is the thing
that you know stores this information
because well I think you kind of want
that to be true for debug variable links
doing next in previous and first child
last child right so unique you kind of
just want to then then just have the
element come off of it I would think so
I kind of feel like you really want to
do that and just trim the fat out of
that hear what I mean I think that's
what you want to do and it does mean you
will create dummy elements but I think
that's way better than what we were
doing before which seems like a really
bad idea
and so when you create one of these
variable links I think you want to pass
to it you know what the element was that
you were using most of the time right
and just looking through here like yeah
I mean that just seems like obviously
right so when you clone a variable link
right in this case it it will copy the
element so really the only person is
create who needs to fix what they're
doing so really create variable link is
the if you will pardon the pond weak
link so in the click in the places where
create variable link is called you know
there there is the element and here
there isn't and you would want to create
a synthetic element for it
same youth here same with here same with
here so really these all of these should
really just be this this should not ever
happen right and that should go like
that so this one here where it does
create variable link that's going to
pass this this is not going to happen
and so all of that's fine when you go
through this process and you're doing
get a create group with name and you
pass the name then when you do this
checking again that's gonna want to look
to see if the group has the same element
pointer really or an element pointer
with an equivalent name it's what you're
actually looking for and so I think what
you want to do here is say create
variable link with like a dummy element
you know what I mean so you're gonna
you're gonna push that on and you really
want this
so there's an element that's just a name
that's all it does and then that gets
you know gets this code yeah so I think
that's all you really want here so when
you create the very like you do you
create you know you create a name
element care
the name element is gonna be debug state
your name length name you know what I
mean
and so in here where you do the strings
are equal tests the strings are equal
test is going to use whatever that debug
element itself was using so inside the
create you know inside here you would
just have that temp variable which is
used to figure out what the name
actually was now since you don't want to
actually be doing expansions in here I
would say what you want to do is like
actually in here say okay get named
direct you would want to have a way of
saying in here tell me what the name of
this link would be if we weren't going
to expand it at all so if it just had to
look at the most direct version of the
name and really that's just a way of
saying I want to make sure it has an
element so you know we could also do
this and I mean honestly maybe it's
pointless to have a variable there
right so I think that's more or less
what we want given you know in terms of
making a situation that maybe isn't
great into something that's at least
okay and I like I would love to spend
some time improving this but you know
maybe just not today
cuz I don't really want to spend more
than a stream on it and that would kind
of be more getting into like let's let's
do a second pass or improving the debug
stuff so assuming that I want to do the
get name here we know that the link you
know has a has an element there and I
can get the name of it when we actually
use that it's this yeah
hmm
what is the complaint here
Oh parent
so where is create variable Lincoln why
was that not accepting that create
variable link why is that not accepting
what I want it to be called seems fine
is it just create name element oh yeah
so actually it's the fact that this
needs to have the debug state so I think
that's fine now so this would be like in
here now we can create the exact things
that I wanted because now we can create
arbitrary pieces of you know arbitrary
elements that can represent anything we
want and we can put them in there which
is what I actually wanted to have happen
in the first place right
um so I think that's pretty much done
now so when we want to create one of
these see bug elements I'm gonna look to
see how we were creating those before
because to be honest with you I have no
idea right
like that's not creating one yeah I
don't even know who was ever creating
these
so it looks like it literally this is
the only place that we ever did that and
here's how we were filling it out so if
we want to like inside create named
elements you know I guess we can I guess
we can create one this way so we push
one of these on we it doesn't have a way
of globally identifying itself so that's
just going to be zero
same with this like all of that stuff it
just doesn't have and then as far as
these are concerned the name of this is
going to be what it was was pushed in
here right so it's it's really gonna be
this function and I think that's all
there is the type is going to be
whatever type you ask it to be yeah and
that's it
it doesn't get inserted into the hash
table you because you can't look these
up they're not they're not hashed
they're not they're not hashed by grid
because there is no grid and I think
that's basically it if you want to put a
debug type in there so debug element
type or what was that thing we called it
just just debug type so if you want to
put one of those in there you can and
then you can just specify what type you
wanted the thing to be and so for things
which were
you know for things that are just sort
of arbitrary you know these would want
to be I guess they would want to be sort
of written here as something special so
they're kind of like a debug type
they're just a name you know
and so by default that is what you would
say in fact we could you know maybe even
have that be sort of what would normally
happen and then if you want to make it
be something else because it's got a
fancy way that it wants to to get at its
information then it can you know and I
guess I mean I'm not I'm not sure how we
want the function summary part of things
to go like where we want to get that
piece of information from the function
summary bit I mean cuz how it looks that
up is kind of I I don't really know how
it should be looking that up
so that's part is going to be we're
going to look at that a little bit more
carefully so I'm not going to touch that
just yet
all right however this stuff can now be
backported just fine
so I think you know if we if we now sort
of say all right that was that was that
that was what we're doing then this
stuff okay I'll be honest with you I
don't understand what just happened
there that shouldn't have done anything
oh because we did actually reach in and
change it never mind so I think that's
roughly what we wanted to do but you
know again pretty hacky so let's see
what's going on here in terms of making
this I don't know what
why that's unhandled because the type of
name as the type should be fine it
doesn't like the fact that when we're
interacting with this so it looks like I
guess the reason for that is because it
expects there to be events coming in for
this thing and obviously there aren't
going to be events coming in for this
thing so you know it's not an auto
modify variable it should be a an
expansion event that happens there you
know like a toggle right and
in order to push that on properly you
know I'd have to I have to make sure I
can have to make sure I get that part
correct but at the moment I just want to
see what was the problem with the
unhandled bit so that's actually pushing
it through this path which again I'm not
sure why it's doing that
yes so so this on the can have children
front so I want to figure out what's
going on there so in here on the can
have children front
yeah that that doesn't really make a lot
of sense to me so I feel like this is is
just dumb that should go like this and
that should really be does it have
children not can it have children right
so this should just be that so I do
think this stuff could be simplified
rather dramatically now you know just
looking at that code in there if we went
through it and took a bit of a hammer
and chisel to it I think we could rather
rather dramatically fix it but anyway if
you look here that's a bit weird so it
looks like can have children is
evaluating to true for people who don't
themselves actually have any children
which is a little confusing to me am I
wrong about that right I mean it looks
like so that is actually getting treated
as if it if can't have children is
always as if gap so there's always
equalling
so I wonder are we actually storing
these as circular linked lists we are
alright yeah this code needs to get
sledge-hammered anyway the code is not
great but it is functional and that's
something so let's just finish off what
we did want to do and and yeah I think
we came at this so reversed when we did
it you know figuring out what was going
on it really needs a pass at the end to
go okay now that we figured out how all
this stuff is getting threaded through
and stored like let's actually go
through and make this make more sense in
terms of how we're actually you know
using it which we never really did you
know so it's kind of just got too much
stretching and pulling and then it never
had a part where we went through and
actually tried to streamline it so it
kind of suffers from really roundabout
things happening that now could just be
simplified much like what we did with
the asset system yesterday where we just
said oh we could clean out this whole
set of things you know and then did so
it's just it's just it's unfortunate but
anyway um so now that that's working
let's go ahead and make it so that we
can again like have a more like direct
access UI for those things so if we're
looking at like the you know this stuff
here what I kind of want to do is just
maybe get the dev modes and and
correspond them to the dev modes so like
maybe the way this works here is is less
like this and and more sort of a you
know maybe we will store the route group
but maybe we also say like okay we've
got variable links for like Devon modes
and inside the you know the stuff in
hand made that a chore restore what all
those dead moves are just so we don't
have to bother with that we just say
that there
account in there and so when we look at
the dev modes these various pieces that
we want to kind of put together there
can just be setup
/ / dev mode right and so then all we
would do is say when we go to render
this stuff right rather than let's go
pick a particular look let's go draw all
the trees instead what we would do is
just say when we add these trees and
actually I guess I know how to think
about it yeah oops so sorry about that
that's not what I okay
what I meant to say was here so instead
of having the tree Sentinel maybe we
just say look we're not gonna have trees
working that way anymore instead what
we're gonna do is say there's a set of
trees they don't they don't have like
next in previous and they don't link
together maybe they don't even have a
position so you know this stuff now
becomes just a we're gonna draw a
particular variable link based on the
dev mode and so if I let's where where
do we draw the trees here
yeah so if I look at this right you can
see it kind of doing its thing here I'm
gonna say like let's just you know and
you got draw tree link you can see it
creating the layout there and then doing
it so you can you can see this happening
I'm gonna go ahead and say let's just
forget about that so I will you know
we'll leave the tree Sentinel in there
for the moment and then I will actually
do what I said I was going to do here
which is like set up the dev mode links
and set up those based on the count that
there are and then we'll just we're
gonna draw those directly so inside the
debug setup code you know rather than
calling this will just call this when we
create the initial layout right when we
do where is it so when we do this
guess I don't know what the group raised
so really I just want this right so
inside here we would say this thunks out
to a thing that draws an individual tree
and I want to kind of make it so that
the move box thing is probably outside
so like it's probably something like
this you know I'm saying and then here
it only does this part and in fact I
don't see any use of the layout in there
so it's really more like yeah it's it's
really just this
what I don't know is why we care about
the tree group I assume it's for
differentiation purposes and I suppose
that's okay it's just a pointer that we
use for differentiation so you know in
here you can see like the only thing we
do is we use it for that differentiation
that's it right and that's just so that
you can store information that's
dependent upon both things so you can
like expand something in one tree and
not in another so that's actually okay I
don't mind that
so we'll keep passing that down but
we'll just what we won't really use it
in in a large extent we will we will
probably just kind of ignore it right
okay so if I was to put in the stuff
here that needs to actually happen that
looks like that this uip is just like
where did you want it to be like that
we've got the you know we've got the
draw tree link nonsense happening here I
think that's all there is
yeah
so this can still work as it was working
if we wished it to it just passes that
UI key down this way and you know the
group as well and then what we can do
instead of actually ever calling that
because I don't actually want to call
that and you know again in here we say
like what the debug tree was in question
we can actually call this directly now
so instead of calling draw trees which
we're sort of saying I don't really care
about anymore
instead what we're gonna do is called
draw tree the debug tree tree is just
gonna be a ridiculous like a nonsense
tree that we just used for that
differentiation right so it's not really
it's not really there and that way we
can preserve the functionality of if for
some reason we wanted two trees to
actually happen we could do that and
then we'll worry about what this v2 is
in a second here but then we will say
whatever the dev mode links are for this
particular thing so in this case right
we've got some set of them here whatever
those dev mode links are those are the
things that we're actually going to use
so we're gonna reach into the game state
find out what that what those are
actually set to and remember we can I
think get that I don't remember how we
were accessing that particular piece of
information but we were
it's like get game assets right so you
can see here from the game memory you
can get the game state out of it so we
we are able to read that information
without needing to know anything else so
in theory here we should be able to
actually grab the tree in question
because we can say whatever that game
memory was you know that we were using
so I think where we call debug and write
we know what that is
so in debug and here you know we should
be allowed to do that if we wanted to
and that's where we would read that
value out
so that seems fine we can just do a
check here just to be like you know if
game state dev mode is less than a rate
count key bug state dead links we can
make sure that we've got one that isn't
gonna be like illegal and then we can go
from there but so I think that's fine we
need to actually pass the tree here like
so think that's it yeah and so now if we
run this we should not have any drawing
from the debug system no matter what I
put pic here right if I then go and ask
it to give me one of those debug
overlays I should be able to now get it
by just when we actually do our setup so
when we do like the debug and it's stuff
so here by setting these things up in
two particular locations so for example
I don't actually know which ones of
these things we want to actually supply
but for example if I just say that the
debug state dev mode links and I pick
one of the F keys that I wanted there so
like you know inside handmade H I just
say well whatever was supposed to be
linked to profiling you know all stuff
the profiling one here so like I said
don't really know how this is supposed
to work um um but maybe it works like
this who knows
but anyway so then I've got like the dev
mode links for rendering equals
something you know and I don't know what
it would be but then the debug state you
know dev mode links
two modes lighting memory and then maybe
like just like dump like I said I don't
know what that is maybe but right now
that's going to be like the route group
and then we can start reorganizing this
stuff so you know if we imagine we're
doing something like that you know then
like in theory you know I can set these
two that's weird why is f5 cause the
editor to come on
someone know what's going on there
where's those F keys
I don't know why that would be doing
what it's doing that's bizarre
don't you agree we're setting the dev
mode and you know we pass it down just
so it knows what mode were doing but
it's like it should always be so uh
that's interesting so it turns the
editor of the editor believes itself to
be in that mode when we when we actually
hit that button so like you know when we
set the dev mode to dev mode profiling
but I've no idea why so I'm interested
that I'd like to do a little stepping
into there just to see what's going on
because that's a peculiar one inside the
editor Oh
because writes yeah that's actually how
we wrote it so for now I guess we want
to do it this way and we'll cross that
bridge when we come to it all right so I
think that's fine and then we just need
to create like the correct correct
position from it so we'll see what
happens so it doesn't like looking at
that which I guess I can understand so I
don't know where those groups actually
are so we need to kind of get this stuff
going right so in terms of building what
interface we want here I think what I
want to do I guess so you can see how
we're doing like a debug data block and
then we say like okay here's the things
that go inside the profiler right in
terms of how we're we're making that go
we kind of want it here say like look we
want you to put that inside one of our
things like what we want we want the
ability to like specify that stuff and
so I'm trying to think of like what the
best way to do that would be because we
don't really want what I did here which
was just to do it inside this so in
terms of placing those things somewhere
I mean I think I mean guess I don't
really know but
and even this I don't I guess we don't
really even need that anymore so I think
what we want to do here is just say look
these devmode links things are just when
you actually when we see you ask for one
of these things to go into the HUD then
it just does I think that's all we
really need to say probably and I
suppose I suppose we could even just
make that be some way that you just set
what the debug thing is set to I don't
know there but anyway so like if we look
at what's going on here yeah like I want
to be able to say like set this thing
this data block to be the one that's
actually being used when we go into of
the debug collation pass so in here you
know when we see the different types of
data that are coming through it seems
like you could just say well whoever the
parent is if I say that that's somebody
who gets stored to the debug state than
it is
you know so you know what the default
parent group is right here right and so
what you could do is just say yeah you
know if if I see one of these things
like I could just say that and so then
the only question is like what is the
VAT like what goes in there here what I
mean and then you would say something
like
makes sense and so in this case I guess
since we know you know you're allowed to
do whatever you want as far as data is
concerned so you know you have the event
here so you should just be able to say
look that just all that does is set this
up so inside here you also have a thing
that's like oh there's there's that when
you encounter one of those inside here
it's just gonna take whatever that the
dev mode value is you know and it's
gonna use it
so it'll say like whatever the event
value would have been like this you 32
it'll just say like if that's less than
how many of these we are allowed to set
then go ahead and do it right so I think
that's all we would really need to do
for that set HUD and so inside here
where we actually you know record these
things they and they you know pop
through whenever we're doing one of
these debug event records I think that's
probably it you know what I mean
so let's see I don't know if that's
actually true but if I wanted to make
one of these for the debug system
and so it's just all it is is just that
value the debug name probably can stay
what it is and this is probably just
that and this is gonna be dev I guess
well I guess it's still just that no it
bid be set HUD right yeah I guess I
don't really know so yeah that works so
I think that means kind of the nice
thing about that is the debug system
doesn't really have to be aware of any
of these things now so you could just
say you know that's rendering that's
lighting and you know it would just work
right and that's pretty cool actually
so I think now we're mostly done with
what I wanted
I think that's pretty much everything so
that's a lot more than actually what I
hope to accomplish I was gonna just do
some quick sup move on but I kind of got
a little bit more into it so that
actually is more than I needed but I
think that's what we want so then all I
need to do is just snap this to the
upper corner and I think we're done so
you know when we look at what the actual
layout of this frame is when we look at
whatever the render state is I want this
to not be 0 0 I want it to be like the
upper left corner let's say for example
so this information this is actually
what I need it to be and I need to be
able to get what that wit and width and
height actually are so I want this and
in order to get those two pieces of
information I would need to look at the
render group which we have I believe
it's it's off of the UI though if I'm
not mistaken just actually down here
and so you know I I just want those to
always be up there now like I don't want
them like floating around I want to have
them be what what they actually are
let me hope let me just see here where
is render group it's actually in the
commands of render group isn't it yes
this so it's actually just render
command settings with so I'm going to
just use that more directly
so now I think that's all wired up
properly and in theory we would get the
correct location for our debug data
maybe maybe not
we'll see there is something really
weird that's going on with how we're
getting the letterboxing they're like
you'll notice the same thing happens we
should look into what it is the same
thing happens here like this should be
correct and it's not so our like
transform is not quite right that makes
sense so this is a little bit more easy
to use now too right so we can quickly
jump to whichever one of these were
actually trying to use and we still
should be able to do the global one too
like if we want to put a thing in there
that's like go back to the weird like
complete ontology one we can also make
this default to be bigger now too so it
would just by default extend down to
show more of our of our profile at any
given time so we're you know we're
getting there
we're getting there this could also be
extended to the full range of things
I'll go ahead and stop for now but
that's good I'm glad we got that out of
the way let me go ahead and set this to
and that way yeah we only get one and I
can also make this now which which would
be better - I can make the editor UI so
instead of it being sort of blocked up
against the on the middle of the screen
it can also use the UI space oh that's
kind of cool so the UI space actually
says what the min is so I guess I could
use that instead as well so like for
example here
I'm not sure that that's correct so this
should really just be we have any like
min dim there we go let's go say this
should really be this because it was
being specified in a rather weird way
there um but the UI space min and Max
there I don't really remember how that
was getting set up but I wonder if we
should just be using that I don't really
remember when UI space gets set but I
wonder if we can just use that in in the
thing you buy space min
and when that gets set up
so when you begin the UI frame it sets
that up to be zero zero two width and
height but that's not right is it
because that's not where it actually
starts like what's going on there
oh it's cuz it's centered in yeah
alright nevermind so that would work so
if that's center dim then why doesn't
this start at the top
did I do something weird yeah so it
needs to be min max right like yeah I
thought so so this actually has to be
set slightly differently but it should
be the entire it should be the entire
thing so I guess I fell right I guess I
see why I did this before so we want the
thing to go from the minimum to the
minimum X plus 700 and the max Y so I
did have it written right before I was
just being a little weird so now when we
do the editor right it should be the
whole sidebar and the weird part about
that is just for some reason we have our
transforms a little bit confused with
how this is working it seems like we're
somehow not getting maybe because of the
title bar we're not actually getting a
properly aspect ratio of things so when
you do the transforms you actually did
non-conforming aspect ratio so we kind
of got to go look at why that's
happening but otherwise if that does
mean is inside here this actually is not
necessary so I kind of jumped the gun on
that so what we can do here is actually
use
where we say you know this is where we
want to start displaying all of our
stuff and so when we draw the tree you
know we'll do it that way and that would
let me no longer have to be sort of
weird about how that's getting passed in
oops and that's already even a variable
that we had so we could have just used
that directly all right
and so those we probably want to also
make switch by default there you and I
mean and there's that yeah so this is
gonna be good this is this is much
better than it was
well we'll we've got a little bit more
work to do there but we can we can do
some other stuff all right let's see
what's going on here how would you go
about exposing a very object-oriented
API to see without ending up in the
disaster that dx12 did with their C API
especially if the API is something like
a device for its central access point um
I guess I don't really know I haven't
programmed dx12 myself so I don't really
know what the issues are with that is it
is it really a disaster I mean you know
I guess I haven't looked at it um so you
know maybe it is
oh my lord
yeah all right so fantastic um I guess
what I would say is normally if you were
just saying meaning you didn't work at
Microsoft on api's and you're like a
normal human being it's really not that
bad like you know if you have an
object-oriented API and we even do this
in handmade hero in a sense that we have
plenty of things that use a particular
state structure you know if you just
have something like you know then you
know just just write that or
whatever and it's just it's fine right I
mean there's nothing not object-oriented
about this right I can just say look I
want to get this device I want to ask
the device for a texture I want to free
the texture I want to close it right
it's just it looks fine right if you
just if you just actually only put in
the things you need for the code to work
then it just works it's only if you your
head is filled with all of this crazy
you know modern programming nonsense
that you think you would need anything
more than that I mean that's all you
need and there's nothing non
object-oriented about it I mean I don't
need to see anything in here this could
just be in a pig handle right I mean it
can be fully that or it can be you know
this right and this API works just fine
you know that there's nothing just
sensible basic stuff can already be the
same as object-oriented you know can
follow any object-oriented principle you
want where everything is hidden from the
person who's calling it and you never
reach inside the struct in any way it
just works right so it's only because
people somehow think that there's
something other than like generating CPU
instructions that they're supposed to be
doing at their day job but you know if
you just focus on what do you actually
need to write in order to get the thing
to happen then it really just works and
it doesn't have to be so crazy but
unfortunately people think that all that
complexity is somehow good it's not just
it generates slower code it's harder to
read it's hard to understand hard
learn harder to maintain works with less
languages you know that everything about
it is bad right 0zi says off-topic best
way of moving data from disk GPU what I
think I really wants to get a GPU map
memory chunk and map my asset file right
over there
assuming I'm prepared the data to be GPU
friendly what I have right now is
letting from disk and memory and then
either doing jail buffer sub data or map
view and copy the data how can I avoid
this copy um I don't think you really
can most of time on Windows
unfortunately and the reason that I say
that is because since it's a
heterogeneous environment in terms of
the GPU the problem that you're going to
run into is that while you could
probably do something sort of like what
you're talking about
with buffer with like vertex and pixel
I'm sorry vertex and buffer data like
like things that will be fetched by like
the vertex shader geometry shader things
like that in your defined format that
will work so you probably could do
something pretty close to that maybe on
PC it's harder but the problem is a lot
of the data you're downloading is
texture data and if you're downloading
texture data the problem is that that
format that the graphics card needs the
texture data in is not the format that
you have it in and you might ask why can
I just put it in the format that the GPU
needs it in and the reason is because
each GPU actually needs it in a
different format so I'm a little bit out
of my comfort zone really describing why
this is true so I would invite you to
take this with a large grain of salt you
really need to ask someone who's a
serious PC graphics programmer like in
other words their job is not to write
all the rest of the game code all they
do all day is PC GPU work because that
is a that is a job it's a full-time job
for multiple people at at you know
triple a game companies or whatever
texture fetches are extremely expensive
graphics pipeline elements because the
the way in which data is processed in
almost every other case is predictable
and can be streamed and to understand
this I guess the way I would point it
out is if I have a set of vertices and
I'm gonna draw those they represent
triangles then the GPU pretty much knows
it's going to go through these vertices
and transform them and it could
transform them into a cache or a
temporary buffer or all sorts of other
things like this right so it knows that
that's gonna happen or at the very least
it can say well if I need to transfer
them these vertices I can transfer them
in blocks and save the blocks and throw
out blocks after I'm done with them so I
never really need to have that much
scattering gathering of those buffers
most of the time right now for really
how to describe it in the correct way
but point being it's not so random
access it's fairly consistent how its
accessed but texture data is completely
different texture data is typically
fetched completely haphazardly right
like any given little piece of a
triangle that happens to be visible is
grabbing some random thing from some
random bitmap in a random texture and a
random place and getting just these four
pixels and using them right and so
paging that stuff in and out to like
have the the caching of it be coherent
it's like really tricky and you're
trying up to the entire pipeline to
minimize the amount of time you're
waiting around for textures to come in
and they're doing all kinds of crazy
stuff in there
all kinds of caching all kinds of like
trying to have most like lots and lots
of texture fetchers outstanding so
there's lots and lots of like virtual
threads in the thing waiting for texture
fetches to come back to like complete
operations so like we're running tons of
pixel pipelines in parallel and like
ping pong in between them based on who
got their texture fetches back so it's
this huge deal right it's not simple
it's very very complicated on the
hardware side because that's where like
all this time is being spent waiting for
these textures and you really have to
minimize that down right so where this
gets into the texture format issue is
that while the action will like bits of
a pixel or the same as you think they
are so like if you say this is an RGBA
texture then it probably is like an RGBA
texture and each pixel probably is 8
bits are 8 bits G 8 bits B 8 bits a
right that's like probably true what's
not true is that the way that you send
it down where it's just like a line like
one row of pixels and then another row
of pixels and other pixels that is not
how it will be started on the sword in
the GPU what will happen on the GPU is
that it will have to be what's called
swizzles which is when you store pixels
in some kind of a zigzag pattern and the
attempt what you're trying to do there
is remember caching still happens on the
GPU for things like texture fetches and
all that other stuff so when you go to
fetch a cache lines worth of data so 64
bytes or something you want the chances
that that has all the pixels that you
might need for that set of operations
you want the chances of that happening
on one cache line to be as high as
possible which is probably not like if
it's a 64 byte cache line let's say it's
probably not 16 pixels in a row this way
it's probably like a 4 by 4 block of
pixels or something right so what the
graphics card does is when you submit a
texture buffer it has to copy it anyway
it copies it out of the zigzag order and
in
to a new order right now sometimes that
happens on the GPU side and sometimes it
happens on the CPU side and it depends
on whether the GPU has an accelerated
Dees Whistler or something in it right
but that has to happen and on a lot of
drivers that happen to the driver so the
driver copies it from one place to
another using this whistle pattern and
then this the GPU just uploads it into
the memory using the mapping aperture
right so now you might ask well why
can't we just or always store the thing
prease whistled and then it could just
get transferred like any other buffer
data and the answer is because the
correct pattern force whistling depends
on how the memory crossbars were set up
on the GPU so when you go to fetch
something there's actually different
patterns of memory depending on how the
memory banks are laid out that are more
or less efficient because remember when
you fetch from memory it's not always a
uniform kind of a fetch if I fetch like
one byte from each of several memory
banks I may be able to do that faster
than fetching in from one databank or
maybe the opposite strew may be fetching
in from this one need a bank is faster
than fetching and from each one right
and so there's all these like
interleaving patterns that happen and
how the memory addressing plays out and
since you care about how fast that is
the Swizzle pattern needs to match the
design of the cache to memory crossbar
right not a hardware designer I spend no
time studying that stuff so I have no
idea what the constraints are there or
why they are the way they are or any of
that other stuff but what I can tell you
is every graphics card has it set up
differently and so depending on the
graphics card you need differents
whistle pattern so you can't even store
your assets in a format that you've
guaranteed is the right Swizzle pattern
for maximum performance a particular
Kravis card because each graphics card
will have a different swizzle pattern
that is the fastest for that this is why
if you're on PlayStation 4 Xbox one
you can priests whistle your textures
because the textures are in only one
fastest format it is a known GPU with a
known memory cross bar pattern so you
know that you just put them in the
format that it wants Swizzle pattern
wise for this one piece of hardware is
always right but that's just not true on
the PC now there have been attempts like
DirectX specifies a pre Swizzle pattern
the problem is they specified like one
Prius visible pattern or something and
it's not the right one for all cards so
it's still not it doesn't solve the
problem if every one standard on one
Swizzle pattern eventually in the future
it would solve the problem I don't think
they've done that yet though so you're
kind of faced with that problem and I
don't have a solution for you right you
just kind of have to deal with that and
so it may not really be it may not
really be a a thing where you want to
try to go as far as you're saying where
you just do the mem map and mem map into
a GPU buffer the other thing that I
would warn you about is when you map
memory into a GPU address space you you
may end up in right combining memory and
you don't necessarily know if the
operating system is doing the right
thing with respect to how memory mapping
is going to work in that case this is a
little bit more in the weeds but when
you are talking about memory that's
backed by hardware oftentimes it doesn't
use the same cache write combining rules
as like just regular CPU memory as a
result reading from that memory can be
incredibly expensive way more expensive
than it would be if it was regular GPU
memory
hmm so if you use some kind of an
operating system operation on memory
that's mapped to the GPU you really want
to make sure there's no chance this that
the operating system might think that it
can read from that memory because if it
ever does try to read from that memory
you may be in a lot of pain right so I
guess I would just point that out it's
not so much whether it reads or writes
its if it does those two things together
meaning if it writes and then reads back
something from that memory that would be
really bad because it it has to do
special things because of the cache
coherency with whatsoever happening on
the GPU it it has to do other things
where it uses write combining in these
ways that makes it so that reading back
becomes much more expensive that's all
so I'd be careful with that stuff I
don't have any specific recommendations
because I've never tried to do what
you're talking about so it may be just
fine but I just would be careful about
that I would check to make sure it's not
happening
updated dumped you speck a little is
this clear about things yeah let me take
a look the text wrapping station uses a
semicolon this says it's issues
therefore element names are not allowed
to semicolon only elements that knows
how much data they are reading can
contain semicolon yeah format
terminology general format tree view
yeah that's definitely clearer I'd have
to be I have to play with it a little
make sure I think that that split out
the right decisions there but yet that's
exactly what I'm talking about
meaning there just needs to be ways of
saying look I'm dumping stuff here and I
don't want to care if stuff has
semicolons in it so I can just make
multiple compounds and that will just
work so that looks more like what I was
yeah what I was saying
so oops fallacy is basically overusing
inheritance
no like I really want to emphasize the
fact that the problem with
object-oriented programming is is like
I've said it many times is the
object-oriented part meaning the problem
is the way that that you are told to
think about your program is just I think
fundamentally incorrect and the reason
for that is because this you know a CPU
doesn't have objects it's not a thing so
it's built upon a fictitious holy human
created artificial model rather than
something that comes from what the
computer actually does which you know I
mean obviously a computer is human
created but it's there it's the thing
you're actually using so it's actually
tangible and real and has actual real
answers when you look at what it's doing
object-oriented is like a fictitious way
of thinking about those things that none
of the things that you talked about you
an opportunity programming map to
something that happens on a computer
they're all things that are that are
just mental imaginary things the
programmer is imagining or that the
programming language imagines are true
but they are not true it is not true
that you can't access the internals of a
struct of a class that you have a
pointer to you just can write and so
operatory your programming the way the
reason I I don't care for it is not
because of any individual part of it is
bad because you
usually like opportunity programming
doesn't really have many techniques that
are part of it that didn't already exist
independently of it right it's more
about the fact that I've very
programming is a is a mental paradigm
that's talking about how the program
resourcing of their program and that
mental paradigm is not useful that's the
problem so it's not that inheritance is
wrong or encapsulation is wrong or
polymorphism is wrong it's not that
individual things that actually mean
something in an implementation sense are
somehow wrong because nothing
implementation wise is wrong as long as
it generates code right it's that if you
follow the object oriented programming
mindset it usually leads you to
construct programs that are not well
working they don't they don't usually
accurately arrive at the simple correct
solution to a programming problem they
usually have a lot of additional things
that were not necessary for the problem
and as a result they are slower harder
to read harder to maintain harder to
adapt to other circumstances harder to
modify harder to optimize right and
that's the problem so that's really the
case not that there's something
inherently wrong with a particular
technique right
that's that's all I would say and so if
you want to use an object-oriented
programming language and you want to use
object-oriented programming features I
don't even think that's necessarily bad
right as long as you are being
clear-headed about what the code is that
you're generating and you're thinking in
terms of what the actual result how it
works and what it does and you're
prioritizing that then I think you're
gonna be okay you know it's more a
problem if you if you allow these
fictitious constructs which were made
for various like imaginary reasons some
of which may be beneficial some of which
may be not but without the tie back to
what you were actually trying to do
which is create CPU instructions for a
computer to run you don't have a good
way of determining between them that's
how you end up with this proliferation
of people talking about things that are
obviously not true right where they'll
end up talking about oh this code is
better than this code and you're like
why and then they list a bunch of things
that actually don't have any practical
truth they don't actually produce better
code on a CPU and so you're like no like
what you mean to say is for your
imaginary world you created which you
may well believe in but you don't have
any proof that there's anything better
about it right you're saying that you
like this better it's it's sort of like
saying I think this picture is prettier
than this other picture right and that
may be true for you and beauty is in the
eye of the beholder but if you can't
point to something concrete that's
actually happening then you shouldn't be
advising other people to do it without
first that disclaimer that's like the
thing I'm telling you to do is really
just about my own personal aesthetic
preference you know and your own
personal ecstatic preferences are not
that's not engineering right that's art
zero is the greeting answer so is it
possible to memory map a file to GPU
pinned memory for non texture data then
I think about a complex 3d Mouse sounds
like you can't avoid this mem copy
I agree the textures are trickier
especially if they're compressed already
I mean so here's what I'd say I can't
think of any fundamental reason why the
operating system couldn't be written
such that you can overlay a GPU mapped
aperture with a memory map file I can't
think of any reason why you couldn't do
that but as far as I'm aware I can't
think of what API gyrations you could go
through to make Windows actually do that
and so I'm assuming that they haven't
actually implemented that so I would be
surprised if you can get it to work but
I mean I I don't know like I haven't
tried it so I'm not prepared to say
maybe it works but you have to
understand like so the way a memory map
file works right is the operating system
reserves inside the memory paging table
it reserves a range that's as big as you
told it to be so you say I want to map a
gigabyte of data in this file to this to
a location in memory and it goes okay
I'm gonna reserve that location and set
all those pages to be false when you go
to access one of them it will fault and
cause it to go a war you faulted here is
that mean the program crashed oh no what
actually was happening is they're
touching a reserved part that's supposed
to be mapped to a file that's fine with
me all loaded in from the file and then
allow that thread to resume right that's
what it's going to do so in order to
have something that was both mapped to
the GPU and mapped to a file you would
have to have the operating system be
able to set up the page table such that
it's set in the page table not only is
this set to be backed by the file so
when there's a fault I read from the
file but it's also set to be mapped on
the PCI bus aperture out to something
that's in GPU memory maybe you can do
that maybe it can't I don't like I said
I've never thought about that so I've
never tried it
go nuts you know I mean I don't know but
yeah I would point out compression is
relevant here it's unlikely that you're
gonna store all of your data in a police
in a professional high-end setting
you're not gonna store mesh data
probably raw you probably will have
compressed it and then so it doesn't
make a lot of sense to map the file
because typically what you're gonna do I
mean to map the file directly to GPU
memory maybe it makes sense to map the
file to just your own memory but
typically what you're gonna do is expand
the data out into GPU memory you're
gonna read a smaller more compressed
chunk from your data file format and
then decompress it into the GPU space so
again the the idea of flat mapping there
doesn't necessarily make a whole lot of
sense right now I think there have been
yeah I mean AMD anyway had some virtual
texturing stuff where they thunk through
two pages on disk and I can't remember
how that stuff's implemented you know so
there like I said there may be ways to
map GPU pages to file pages like that
maybe in the OS and I just don't know so
I'm sorry I can't I really can't speak
to it you know I can like I said I told
you I can tell you basically what
happened what would be required on the
OS side but I just don't know if
anyone's implemented that they may have
that you know they may not have quick
success the main thing of concerned with
is since I've never really programmed an
opportunity to programming I can't be
sure if I'm sometimes transitioning into
OOP accidentally and it really bugs me
since you could say that device or
texture structs or objects or stuff like
that um again I being religious about
object-oriented programming is
is bad and being religious about not
using object-oriented programming is
also bad in a sense meaning it's not
it's it's not like there's a programming
God who's gonna like come down and smite
you if you accidentally do one or the
other right so the correct philosophical
approach is just to say look if I'm
going to make a decision I should make
it on something measurable okay and that
is really all you need to remember if
you can't think of a reason why writing
code way a or way B is better or worse
if you can't come up with a measurable
thing right then it can't be that bad
either way or it's just it's past your
current ability level to know and you
know if something's past a current
ability level then it is you know
everyone is constantly getting better at
what they do including me including
everyone else and so you can only make
the best decision that you can make at
the time I mean that's just all there
all we can ever expect of ourselves to
do the best we could with the
information we had and would we like to
all be smarter sure but you know we can
only be as smart as we are on that day
right we can only have you know as much
as we can have and so when you look at
something and you go is there a way to
decide whether this thing is better or
worse right
you can usually suss out that just from
looking at what the results are of doing
it you know and if you want to look at
something object-oriented wise and
you're like you know I have an A or I
have a B and someone writes something
like this
I don't know why these aren't shifted up
here that's where I think they normally
go but I don't know I don't ever type
those in anymore so like I couldn't tell
you um so you know if you're talking
about this and then you're like well I
have a choice between these two things
and you know as a result I've got a
choice between these two things and so
in here I'm just like you know I would
access this thing this way and in here I
would do it you know this way right you
can make assessments in an objective
sense about these two things the first
thing I can say about it is there's no
difference between the CPU code
generated in either case right meaning I
know that this is going to increment
this value by one so the only thing that
I could really say is that well if the
compiler was going to screw up the code
gen for one of these it would almost
certainly be this one because there's a
lot more involved right
so you know it's a slight negative mark
on B because maybe the compiler
occasionally gets a sort of thing wrong
if we have too much of this happening
but otherwise I know that they they
don't there's no difference in the code
speed really there in any other way
right so then I just have to ask myself
well if I wrote it this way and this way
versus this way in this way what are the
practical difference as to how much I
have to type in and read and you know
you can see the difference between these
two things is massive right I mean
there's no question about which one
you'd rather type in this is way simpler
it's way
it's like way easier to read way smaller
than this it's a giant monstrosity right
even though it's doing no there's no
difference between these two things
right even if I want to have a new one
right and well I will get to that in one
second so they're basically like the
same kind of thing right and so in this
case I can say well what am I getting
for all of this extra typing and you
know you'd have to ask and I was trying
to programmer what they're getting
because I see you're getting nothing if
I want to go change how this stuff is
happening I can always just add you know
a an underscore here and change and
force everyone who's using it to call
into some accessor later if I want to so
if I don't have any reason to do that I
shouldn't bother because I'm just making
everyone's code worse all the time by
not doing that and so usually the idea
behind these you know the argument made
is that well you're you know you're kind
of like planning for some future change
that you might make but basically what
you're doing is forcing everyone to do
all you know a lot of object-oriented
programming patterns are about forcing
everyone else to do 100% of the typing
they would ever have to do if you ended
up changing everything about your
program every time rather than only
forcing them to do the typing necessary
for the things you actually end up doing
so this forces you to do all the typing
for any change you might make in Ex
ahead of time and then if you never
change X well you just wasted all your
time and everyone else's time doing it
right
whereas this does create typing in the
case where you then need to make X be
something that's a that's an accessor
based but you only pay it when you
actually do it right um and so when you
look at those two things that's pretty
easy to understand that difference you
know it's not very complicated so it's
pretty easy to say well why would I do
this like it doesn't it's just lots of
extra typing for no benefit right and so
the thing the reason why you pick one of
these things is not because someone such
as my
l told you object-oriented programming
was bad it's because you should be able
to do that analysis right and
furthermore you should be able to do the
analysis of if you knew ahead of time
that X was going to change then you
should have made accessories for it
right
so you should be able to do that
analysis and if you're not doing that
analysis then me or anyone else telling
you to or not do I'll be throwing your
programming really isn't helping
it's just cheating and so you should
spend your time figuring out how to get
better at this kind of analysis rather
than following my advice or someone
else's right now I'll take this a little
one step further and show you a place
where a difference of opinion could
arise and why you should be making
decisions for yourself there is one
difference between these two this one
lets you initialize it in two ways and
this one only lets you initialize it in
one way so for example if I want to say
you know a a here it's different than a
a initialize this one B that is the same
as that there is no I always will get a
zero initializer because it's got a
constructor here right so there is only
one way to initialize it and the
initialization is required right and so
in some people's world they're like I
want everything to always run a default
constructor because I want this set to
zero to always happen and I don't really
want the person to ever be able to do
anything else right and technically you
can do something else because if you
want to you could do something like this
where you basically make something the
size of a B and then you know put the B
in there right so you can still go
through a lot of gyrations to do it but
in my mind I would rather just have the
two simple ways of doing it one that is
the clear and one that is not the clear
and so I choose because I prefer this
ease of use and this paradigm I choose
this way of programming because I find
it to be more efficient
other people might not and they would
rather have a default constructor in
there so they should put that in there
right and that to me is a less clear-cut
win I think I can make a strong argument
for why this is better but it's not the
same as the like a priori forced
everyone to use accessors thing which i
think is like a pretty bad decision
like I said everything in
object-oriented programming is like that
meaning every last thing you might
choose to do is something that you don't
want to just assume it's bad or good you
should look at it if it's the first time
you've seen it and try to make an
assessment about whether you think it is
helpful or hurtful and in what
circumstances so some things you may say
are always bad other things you may say
are only sometimes bad and sometimes
useful right in it and that way you can
choose to use or not use them whenever
you find that you're in a circumstance
where they would be good right so
0zi in the example that you gave you
assume that you have access to the
source code that might be the case in
handmade hero but if you're using a
library you don't have sometimes extra
the CPC source is another reason to use
unity build without libraries sorry I'm
not sure exactly which example you're
referring to so I can't really clarify
much of that you're right that Oh OOP is
bad when every single field of a class
is to get excetera however in general it
is better to only have getters for most
fields making sure they can only be
change for the class itself it's the
same reason Global's are generally to be
avoided state changing really makes code
our default so I don't really agree with
that so I guess what I would say is I
really tend to factor things more
broadly than that so the way I look at
it is either someone should have access
to a struct or they shouldn't if they
shouldn't have access to the struct then
the whole thing should be opaque meaning
they should not even be able to see the
definition of the struct it should look
like this right or if they can access
the struck then it shouldn't have
getters and setters
generally speaking right and the reason
for that is either I trust the person
who's using this thing to know what
they're doing with it and it's generally
the kind of thing where people are
allowed to change the values in it or it
isn't
I don't usually find that mixing and
matching those makes a lot of sense
so having getters for fields is usually
again just a waste of typing for
anything where I don't think there's a
high risk of error and then where I
think there is a high risk of error or
I'm trying to ship like a strong library
where I really want to be able to modify
things behind the scenes I go this route
so you don't get to see anything about
it you just get back a blind pointer and
any operation you do goes through me
right so
I tend to categorize those things more
broadly which is why you don't see me
putting getters and setters on anything
that's generally used inside that region
and so again I think that's really
important because what the up getter
setter or just getter thing tends to
encourage is walling things off too
early so rather than allowing this much
code the ability to do that modification
and drawing the wall out here you tend
to draw it in here and then you just
have tons of extra typing that wasn't
necessary because in reality all of this
code really kind of did need to know how
those trucks work and then I agree that
the people out here don't need to know
but those people maybe should never see
the internals of that struct anyway
right so that's how I would put that
yeah I'm gonna go ahead and wrap it up
there we go all right thank you everyone
for joining me for the upset handmade
here it's my pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow my
series at home you can always order the
game
well pre-order the game on handmade hero
org it comes to the source code so you
can follow along with it at home we will
be back for another surprise stream
sometime I don't really know exactly
when but keep your eyes peeled because
we are still celebrating
Krampus laughs which I believe is
officially today but we've been sort of
having two or three weeks of celebration
there let's find out
so it's maybe yeah I don't know I don't
know when it actually happens the 6th of
December yeah okay so on the preceding
evening December 5th
so it's tonight the hairy devil appears
on the streets sometimes the company st.
Nicholas and sometimes on his own he
will visit homes and businesses or it I
don't know if it is it a he or an it on
his own so I guess it's a he the st.
usually appears in the Eastern Rite
vestments of a bishop and he carries a
golden ceremonial staff that is not a
vestment of a bishop but I guess that's
just sometimes unlike North American
versions of Santa Claus in these Oh the
st. does not Krampus nevermind stuff
that's never and that's Santa Claus or
Saint Nicholas if you will
concerns only with good children while
Krampus runs were the bad Nicholas waits
as gifts well Krampus supplies coal and
Rutten bundles I don't know what those
are Krampus rootin so there we go so
there's competent and you know there you
go see he's got it there's a little kids
in the back just quality fun for the
whole family
chrome for self highly recommended so
have a good conference laugh this
evening we'll be back tomorrow for some
more post Krampus laugh revelry until
then have fun program I'll see everyone
on the Internet