hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here are the show Rico to complete game
live on stream welcome we I think want
to keep pushing on what we were working
on yesterday I had some ideas over the
sort of last night just in terms of like
stuff I want to do and I think I want to
keep keep on doing it so what we did
yesterday
for those of you just joining us who
maybe missed yesterday's stream no I
don't care what we do yesterday is make
it so that the exterior right the like
out outside part is filled with stuff so
you know we just wanted to make sure we
stuck tiles sort of around the game
region you know I'm saying and the
reason for that is just when we walk
around here we want to make sure that
wherever we go the users not seeing like
empty space out there right we want to
be able to fill that with trees and
stuff so we needed a system that just is
aware of what that empty space is and
once they know what that what's the
system knows that empty space is we can
then write arbitrary programs later on
as we go to polish the look of the game
that fill it in with whatever we want
right but we need a system there that
will be smart enough to do something to
fill it we need it to know like what
needs to be filled and why right okay so
here are some things that we need to
finish doing to that system and you know
I want to kind of talk about what I was
thinking about doing there and why I was
gonna do it the way I was gonna do it um
so what we ended on a problem yesterday
and that is that we didn't really have a
coherent way of checking where these
things should be placed there was a good
sort of happenstance that I hadn't
thought of when we started but it just
turns out to be very helpful and what
that is if you look at these room
volumes we had been creating these room
volumes and the reason that we were
creating them was because we have code
we want to execute whenever we're in a
particular room right so for example one
thing
you want to do and the prime motivation
for creating it at the moment since
we're not really concentrating on
gameplay we're just concentrate on
presentation at the moment what we
wanted to do was be able to program
where the camera was and how the camera
behaved right and so that's why we kind
of have like for example you'll notice
that one of the things that we're doing
is when we move from room to room here
if we're in like a tiny room the camera
is programmed to just focus on that room
and it stays locked right because that
was just a thing we wanted to do camera
wise there and then if you're out in a
larger room we programmed it so that it
would lock on dimensions of the room
that were small enough to be focused so
you can see as I move side to side as I
move side to side nothing happens to the
camera but as I move vertically you can
see that the camera will follow me right
and so this was just something that we
added the room volumes for and we
probably will use those room volumes for
other things in the future as well but
that was the main reasoning behind us
adding them this time so that is all
well and good but what happens here also
I'm kind of kind of interested in to
know something here why do we not have a
room volume for the hallway did you see
that it didn't get paged in we have a
bug in that page in our overlap
detection perhaps do you see that that
was a bug we didn't have before so
that's something we should probably look
at sorry to randomly switch topics on
you there but just wanted to point that
out so that's the bug we should look at
because right see that and it does get
paged in eventually but it looks like
it's not the overlap test is not
actually working properly on that or
something right something weird is
happening there anyway back to our story
so what the point is here is we've got
these room volumes that we're going to
be using for other stuff and that we're
already using for camera control so we
needed to have them and the really nice
part about them that I hadn't thought on
before but that actually turns out to be
pretty useful is that when
we go to fill in the exterior part of
the world with the apron like I was
saying where we just kind of fill in the
area outside of any actual playable area
just so that it doesn't look blank and
we know we can put trees in here and
whatever else we want to do to make it
look you know like it's actually
something real these regions allow us to
know where we shouldn't fill so rather
than having to actually manually test
for example whether or not there's like
an actual entity in each slot just the
room itself is enough to tell this
system not to put anything there right
so that's pretty great
that helps us immensely in in
simplifying how we're actually placing
things out into the world there so I
think what we want to do is embrace that
and have that work but it's not 100%
trivial and the reason why is because
when you get to places like here where
rooms are stacked on top of each other
if you're not careful about how you're
doing the testing such as in this case
right you can see that these were just a
little bit low and so when they come
through here they say oh don't put
anything there because this room would
actually be occupying that area that
they would be in so they're they're
disallowed right we you know don't put
them in there
it's what's what's happening and so that
is the problem that we actually ended on
and I think that the answer you know the
solution to our problem here is actually
something that we want to kind of
embrace to simplify our code anyway
because I started at the end of the
stream simplifying our code that we were
using for figuring out where to place
things in the first place
and what I was thinking we really
probably want is a helper function or a
helper struct and let me show you what I
mean by that so if I open up handmade
here oh and I go to the sort of the room
generation code which is the code that
we're actually where we're actually
talking about
how were sort of stamping things down
into our world right this the room sort
of the the world generation code
operates sort of semantically to like
place rectangles down and say here's
where the rooms are gonna be right but
then we have this other problem where
it's like okay once we know where the
rooms are going to be we have to
actually stamp down entities into them
right and so that's the first time that
we actually do work that's in you know
the kind of work that involves placing
things into the world and so at that
point we end up with code that kind of
looks like this you know we're we're
iterating over like tiles and that sort
of stuff right and you get all kinds of
code in here we don't we haven't really
thought you too hard about how we want
to do it but then you can sort of see
we've got the generate the apron
generation code over here is doing
something similar right and we end up in
all sorts of weirdnesses where we're
like oh okay so what's the math where we
want to say like okay place this thing
as a wall it should be this far off the
ground I guess and how big would that be
or what would the collision volume be
for that or you know all sorts of things
like this and that just gets baked into
the code you can see all this sort of
random stuff getting baked into the code
here and the problem is each piece of
code each each portion of that that we
do is giving us what amounts to a baked
in assumption about how we're placing
things in the world in a way that we
probably don't really want because it
leads to brittle like inflexibility and
brittleness and in fact you could argue
if one wish to make such an argument
that what we're seeing out here in the
world where we go to you know
investigate this part of the world and
find the exact problem that I was just
alluding to where you've got rooms that
are on the bottom floor right I like
this you could argue that this very
problem right if you look at what's
going on here it's because the two code
paths don't share a uniform idea about
where one room is and where the other
room is
these tiles should not even be legally
placeable here because these were
supposed to be tiles consisting of
solely in the upper floor they were only
supposed to be filling the upper floor
area they weren't supposed to extend
down into the lower floor at all but
because of just random baked in math
that I was you know cutting and pasting
and doing there they do right so you
could argue that this bug right here
just in even before we get into it any
further than that could just be seen as
a problem relating to the fact that we
don't have a coherent way of talking
about actual you know world tiles in a
systemic clear way so that the semantic
statement this needs to be inside this
tile doesn't mean anything because it's
just masked you're not all of the code
so what I'd like to do is make that be
more codified so what I'm going to do to
try and make that work is I'm gonna go
ahead and introduce something here and
I'm gonna call this you know we've got
this this Jen room grid for example and
it's got like a series of tiles and this
sort of stuff on it for example right
and so what I'd like to do is I'd like
to sort of introduce an iterator that is
able to move over these things maybe
that works with this room grid as it is
I'm not sure but basically I want a way
to say give me the volume at this tile
location and allow me to ask you to give
me things that are based on that tile so
if I say I want something that occupies
the whole X Y of the tile and starts
about 10 percent of the way up and goes
for 1 foot or something right I can see
that semantically to you and this system
will give me back an accurate rectangle
that represents that right so I that's
what I want to get like I want to get
something that
that rather than me happiness through
the math well through the thing it just
bakes all of that into one little helper
struct and then I can just call
functions that will use the information
in the helper struck to construct new
rectangles that are the placements that
I want right so that's what we're
looking for
all right so let's assume that here I
don't know we've got something like the
gen rim tile right is this thing up here
so maybe we call this like Gentile
volume it's genteel it's the genteel
volume so if we have a volume maybe what
I want to do is say look there's a
rectangle three in it that's the actual
volume right I probably want something
that says what its absolute position was
so you know we've got sort of a Gen B 3
which is the like tile pose something
like that something like that so it's
the coordinates of the tile and then
I've got sort of the volume of that tile
whatever that would naturally be and I
don't know maybe that can actually just
be a question that we've asked up here
I'm not sure so I have to think about
yeah in terms of the basis of this thing
like where the actual let's let's take a
look at how that's actually working in
terms of the basis of what this would
actually be to give back three threes
so it's a world position here that the
base pays off of so maybe maybe that
goes in here as well so we basically
have like here's where the base position
is right here is the tile coordinates
that we're talking about and then I
think do we ever yeah so we've got a
chunk position from tile position here
right that would give us this so we
could from that always convert back out
so I think maybe that's all we've really
needed to say so we say all right here's
the base position here's the tile
coordinate and then from here you can
ask just questions about it all day long
we could also if we wanted to have this
utility just have the sim region baked
into it
because the sim region would also be
able to tell you that piece of
information I think because you know the
the origin of the sim region is the
change base key so that would be
sufficient I think for that I'm just not
sure exactly how we want to do that it's
tough to say so anyway yeah if you look
at what's happening here right you can
see for example we've got this X index Y
index bit here
I'm just trying to think through exactly
how this wants to work
I'm gonna start by converting this and
see what I get in other words I must see
what I what actually happens here and I
guess when we look at this you know I
wonder too if we wanted I wonder too if
what we actually want to do here is say
that there's just ways of getting these
off of the gender room grids so
basically if you just create a grid to
begin with you know what I mean and then
you you could ask for these tile volumes
off of the grid then we could put for
example the base position here into this
and then when you get these tile volumes
back that might be an easier way to do
it too I'm just not sure so I'm gonna
write the usage code first and assume
that that's what we want before I go
trying to define this because I just I'd
since I did I want to work from this
side of it because I'm not really sure
exactly how I want that to look so I
think the easiest way maybe would be to
take the generate apron call which is
less complicated and do that one first
and see what it is that we actually want
there so let's take a look so I'm gonna
also while we're at it I'm gonna kind of
make the stub functions here so I have
someplace to cut and paste the code to
write and so what you can see here is
like this for example where we've got
this Jen apron spec apron spec thing
here and then we do this this is
basically exactly the same as what we're
doing in the code above we get the
dimension of a volume whatever that
volume thing is and then we go ahead and
pull out like values about that we're
going to use for you know various
reasons right so I think what we wanted
to start with here is some way of making
this thing happen automatically so you
know maybe what I want to do is say
something more like all right we've got
temporary memory that we're gonna start
at the top of this thing and then I want
to do like let's begin gridding an area
so I want to say something like you know
create grid
and I want to tell it that the grid that
we're using is like this so basically
give me a grid that's going to work in
this you know with respect to this
particular volume and then I want it to
make all this stuff for me
no I'm saying
so basically when I ask you to create a
grid
I want that to create all of this stuff
automatically and maybe the best way to
write this would be you know more like
this right so create a grid you can use
any we got scratch memory so you can do
whatever you want go nuts and then once
we're you know ready to kind of move
from there or and you know what we could
even do like an edit grid here so maybe
this could even get baked into it right
there's not a lot of reason not to
because these things are completely
dependent on it so what we could do here
is say yeah like do all of this right
all of this stuff goes in here this
entire thing right so we've got like a
begin gray to edit and that thing is
gonna give us you know all the stuff we
need and then we can do a and grid edit
and that'll do the cleanup portion of
our program right so here we say begin
grid edit and off we're gonna go there
maybe we even stick this thing in there
because why not uh and then here I think
this is something that we probably don't
really need to do so because what we're
doing here is just iterating over all
the tiles right and so what we might
want to do there is just take the
simpler route and say maybe we just have
a way of iterating over those things
and so maybe we do something more like
this you know this thing who knows how
that's gonna work right now but
basically what we're gonna say is look
this thing gives us back something and
we just tell it you know what something
like that you know I'm saying so we
essentially just ask it like we want to
iterate over all the tiles in the system
please so just do that like I don't want
to know how you're gonna do it and I
don't I don't care how you're gonna do
that at all you're just gonna provide us
with like this stuff here and then we're
gonna ask you questions perhaps about
this system right so you know we we're
gonna have like queries and stuff that
get the information that we need out of
here
and that's you know it's your
responsibility to give us back the stuff
that we expect in terms of like
questions about the tiles we don't care
how you're iterating in them we're
basically saying we don't we don't
really care what order you iterate over
these tiles at all you know you could
randomly iterate over them in any way
you want just donate it right over the
same tile twice right and we're happy so
you know and then if we take a look at
what's going on here we can sort of say
well this whole nonsense is just to
figure out where the tile was in the
first place right so there's gonna be
something that's like probably you know
a rectangle 3 that's like get volume and
so this kind of stuff would give us the
vault the rectangle in simulation space
where this tile occupies right so that
we can base everything off of that in
the future so this would just be
something that takes you know one of
these edit tiles and returns the volume
that we have so once we get the volume
of this thing and but and maybe we don't
even need to call get volume technically
on it because it may be that they've
already has it but I don't know we'll
leave it as get volume for now but we
could just do tile call Youm in fact
maybe I like that better
so you know this thing here we can sort
of say like hey if overlapping entities
exist in this tiles volume then we don't
want to do anything if they don't then
we can do whatever we want to do here
right and that means although this
nonsense can just go away because what
we could do is we can issue this query
first and then once we know what we're
actually doing then we can compute all
this nonsense right you can see what I'm
trying to do here right you see how much
simpler this code can be once we get to
this point where we just say kind of
begin grid edit you know and grid edit
like so and you know if we don't have
someone faster in there um if we just do
a system like this I think we want to
pass the generator to the grid as well
right yeah but I probably want
everything passed I don't know if the
gen the gen just trying to have worlds
in it I don't know if it does I'm
assuming it doesn't because if it did we
wouldn't have to pass it around but you
know don't take my word for that um it
does have the world in it oh no yeah it
does it's right here so I don't really
know what that's there for
does anyone know why I say I don't know
why that's there hmm
well okay so I'm just going to go ahead
and put it to do to remove that because
I don't think we actually need it for
anything so I'm gonna do to do here
because I think that we can nuke that
and if we did it would be good right
because why pass something around but
you don't actually need so let's see
here so if we're gonna go ahead and do
this nonsense here iterate over the
tiles we should then be able to ask hey
if you know any of these overlapping
entities exist in here we can get the
region out of the not sorry the ghent
the grid so we can get the out of our
edit grid we can get the the region out
of there we can say whatever we want
this collision region to be we should be
able to create that region first of all
we would need to know the location of
the center of the thing we need to know
like where we're actually placing this
thing and so yeah I don't know what we
want to do about that positioning but
let's say what we wanted to do was place
the entity so that its position was just
like at the bottom of you know look at
the at the center of the bottom of the
grid right so maybe we would call this
something we would say like get a bottom
center P or something like that right
and so we would ask that about the tile
and it would tell us that like that
bottom center point and then when we
want to set the collision volume it has
to be relative to that point and so what
we would do I guess is say something
like make relative
where we can then ask for some volume
right and get something like this
and then we could just say look how high
do you want this thing to be and you
know the wall height here could be
something that's somewhat random so we
could just do like the whatever the
series is off of the grid we could say
like give us a random value here random
between and you know we want something
that's at least point five high but
could be as much as one high you know
and I'm just making those numbers up so
you know we'd pick them something else
all of this stuff would go away entirely
right and we would just be left with
this bit here and so yeah I think that's
all we really needed so we would create
the collision volume we create the the
point there this part here where we're
adding pieces for the piece type cube we
really just want that collision volume
and the P the point there right so I
think we can just say if we want to take
the collision volume and use it as the
actual values here that's utility
functions we definitely want so we want
to be able to say you know 0.5 times get
dim and in the collision volume right
and that's the half dimension to the
radius of the thing right and I don't
know if we've got a get radius call yeah
and we can also ask for the center and
that's just saying hey the thing we want
to draw is just the thing that we're
actually using for the collision volume
because remember we can make those two
things different but in this case I
think we just need them to be the same
right so I think this is what we want
and you can see it took that huge big
ugly piece of code and it turned it into
something rather pleasant this is pretty
easy to work with you know it makes
makes things look pretty easy I could
also say like rectangle three ball
equals just to make it clear what's
going on here
you know there's the height of the thing
there's the volume we're just gonna sign
the volume here and then the volume can
get used here as well and that just
makes it a little bit easier on the eyes
for people who've coming to it who don't
know we don't know what they're
necessarily looking at there you go so
we're gonna pick a random height for the
thing we're going to get a volume that
space is starting for the minimum Z and
going up that amount of height we
obviously need to pass at the tile here
we're gonna add an entity and give it
that location and that collision volume
that we just computed we need this to be
made relative still though didn't mean
to get rid of that and then we're going
to use that for the piece as well so
that's going to be yeah that's going to
be that
although I feel like this still needs to
happen first right so basically here's
where we're gonna place the thing here's
how high we want it to be the volume has
to be something that's made relative to
whatever this location is here that
we're gonna place the entity and then
the collision volume is just exactly
what we create here and then this here
is you know specified by the relative
volume of the local bought space volume
and I think then we're good right uh sue
I guess I'll start a file I guess in
here that's like handmade edit grid
something like that
and what I want to do here is pull this
code out I don't know how much of this
we went out they were probably all of it
right and I kind of want this stuff all
to live in here so that yes
[Music]
so that these are basically just
utilities and then all of our gencode
just is written in terms of them so
these are gonna come out here and these
are gonna come out here and now we have
to go through and actually implement
this stuff that we said we were going to
implement and then I think we're good to
go
so you can see we've got a couple of
functions that we want to put over in
our rectangle stuff and so that we kind
of have to put in here I don't see yeah
I don't see any of these existing at the
moment so we're just going to plop those
right on down in here and so this is
going to be take a rectangle three and a
position and return a rectangle three
that's relative to that position very
simple function all it is is it's just
going to take the offset function we
already have and it's just subtract you
know so we're just subtracting P from
all the elements of our right so we're
just making it so that p is now the
origin around which our is expressed we
then want to come in here and oh well
that's actually part of the that's
actually not part of the rectangle
although I do kind of want a rectangular
version of it so I think I will stop
probably stop opening here so if I do a
rectangle 3 here for a rectangle what I
want to do is say the result of that is
going to be get Center R and then I want
the result Z to be the get Minzy of our
right so it could be that I think it's
right yeah get min corner so those are
the functions that produce that you know
very very simple utility functions but I
just want to be semantics so it was
clear what was happening right I and so
now we just need the parts that are
actually Grid specific and then I think
we're good to go
so in order to get to parts that a grid
specific we know we've got these and
again I'm just using snuffleupagus
oriented programming here right I'm just
saying what do I wish that I had write
it in terms of what I wish I had and
then implement that because it's hey
it's what I wanted right I know it's
what I wanted because you know I just
pretended I had snuffleupagus and and
then and then made us novel of I guess I
so assuming that we implement this and
these we would only be left without this
and this right so here we would have
the function prototypes for what we're
trying to do and so now it's just up to
me to fill them in which is a lot easier
than actually having to design anything
right I don't have to think about
anything now I literally just have to do
what I'm told
which is the easiest possible place to
be for a programmer because there's no
more decisions left to make right okay
so if we take a look now at how we've
written this and we want to know for
example what's gonna happen in each of
these functions if we're going to talk
about begin create edit then what we're
looking at here is we have to take the
world generator certainly and then we
have to take the rectangle 3 I'm sorry
not the original page the jhen rectangle
what's it called what's what's a cogent
volume and the volume that we expect to
use to create that you know that grid
the grid in question so we know that our
grid here is going to have to store this
right because it's going to have to
release the memory when it's done all
the memory that's using the temporary
memory that's using for all the world
changes is going to have to get released
back to the system so you know that's
one really simple thing we know that we
need right I always I need a big water
bottle I got to get one of those all
right so when we do there begin create
at it here's our begin temporary memory
we know that we have to release it later
so here it is we then know that we want
to get the dimensions of this thing
obviously we're gonna want to store
those right and we're also going to want
to take a page from our room gen
playbook where we ported this guy up
here to using like tile count Minzy and
tile doing that stuff I think we want
that stuff here so we're basically gonna
say look here's the tile count here's
the min tile
here's the tile dim and let's do
everything off of those right so here's
us doing that the new way we're gonna
want to record those two things in the
grid we know that we wanted to record
the tempura Murray in the grid like that
and then here we also want that mean
tile the tile dim is off of the
generator so now we've got that and uh
yeah I don't know that we need anything
else here right so all the rest of this
stuff we can defer to later because we
got all of the information that we
actually wanted now we want to record
which random series to pull from and so
that's going to come in here so we've
got that general game entropy that's the
thing that we're using for our
generation and when we do n grid edit
obviously we're gonna need to save this
region so when we actually do record our
begin world change here we're gonna want
to do that so I think all the rest of
this stuff just goes away so we're
looking at mostly this at first right
okay
that's sort of what our attic rid looks
like now once we have our Edit grid in
place to do this part I want to look
again back at generate room to figure
out how I want that to happen I believe
because we kind of made a cleaner
version of that I believe that we would
rather use so if I look here at what we
were computing we've got these like room
dimensions and the main room P and the
maximum P and stuff that's another
rectangle 3 so why we didn't actually
compute it as a rectangle 3 I don't know
we should have
we just didn't so I think we actually
want another one here which is basically
like like this where we're saying okay
here's the entire dimension of this is
the entire dimension of the room and so
if I was going to create that I can
still do it this way temporarily so if I
pull this stuff out and say well the
room dam is like this stuff right and
the min room P and the max room peered
Jerian that way then I can just do a
rectangle min max or there we go
mini room P max room key and now I just
have the room dimensions as I want them
and I can ask for the room do more I can
ask for whatever I want right so that
seems good taking a look at this what I
want to do now is use this piece here to
talk about how we get all the rest of
our stuff excuse me uh so now if we look
at the general grid I think that that we
can probably again just supplant this
now and use the edit grid for everything
which will have all of this stuff kind
of bundled up but we'll see you know
we'll take it slow we'll see if there's
anything else we need to do there
specifically we'll see all right so the
change rect can be actually computed
directly now from the room dimension and
the tile and we know really know what we
want to do there but we're just gonna
say it's one wider right that's what
we're saying arbitrarily so that's fine
and then here we're gonna leave this
sort of not specifically talked about
quite yet
we're gonna talk about that a little bit
further down and then we don't need this
anymore because this stuff is already
now getting taken care of separately so
the region which is actually this eye
that needs the temp memory but we've
already got it right we can push this
all in the same place we know the worlds
it's that the changebase p wu is this
and i feel like we probably want that to
be stored I'm guessing we do I don't
actually know but it seems like that was
something we would want to store so out
that comes and the change rect I don't
actually know if we want to store that
anywhere we may not want to and so I
feel like we're probably gonna want
something that looks more like this
don't quote me on that but that's
probably what we're gonna do so if we do
this and then we just look at the only
thing remaining it's really the general
grid here and what we can do is we can
either continue to have a genuine grid
but I don't think that's really any
reason for that sorry I suspect is we
can just make this tiles be part of our
edit grid and get rid of Jen room grid
right and so then we can have our edit
tiles be things that are looped over and
accessed you know however we want to and
the storage for them we'll just be
stored inside the Edit grid directly
right I think again don't quote me on
that that's just what I think we're
probably gonna want to do so let's
suppose we do that and we say ok this
gen v3 here which is dim is actually
just a tile count right and so what we
want is to open
this is the only part we actually need
right that's the tile storage there so
we want to be able to do this exact same
thing we were doing before in here we
just want to use the grid temp mem there
well I guess this is always gen temp
memory now that I think about it but you
know honestly I feel like that should be
in here so I feel like it should be like
that or something you know what I'm
saying to you so we would we would do
something where we would actually record
that kind of out well I don't know I
don't really know I'm gonna say here's
what I'm gonna do I'm gonna say this I'm
gonna say look just call it memory for
now so yeah so on here we're gonna start
off by saying let's let's just set
ourselves up here I guess I don't need
to record the memory for any particular
reason yet so I won't bother but we
might later so we're gonna create one of
these grids and then we're gonna do all
this work and then we're going to return
the grid when it's ready for action and
I think that's everything that we
actually needed to do we don't need to
do lips to do that so we don't actually
need this because we've already got the
tile count so that should be sufficient
there as well
like so and that's it right that's
everything
yeah so that'll looks good to me that's
a complete setup of the grid when we're
done with the grid we don't have to do
anything because everything just goes
into memory Rina so we just say hey get
rid of it all we don't need it anymore
and we're done with our simulation
system that like expanded all the
entities out and like looked at what
they were in the region in question so
we can throw that out as well so we just
throw out everything basically and it
just writes the changes back to the to
the stationery world so I think that's
everything we need there and so that
tells us what our edit grid struct looks
like and then we're pretty much down to
just an oh and by the way this can go
away completely so then we're just down
to the Edit tile and if you look at what
has to happen here we need to be able to
produce information about these tiles
specifically the most important piece of
information is what the actual volume of
the tile is but we also need to be able
to iterate the tile so we need some way
of recording like this sort of thing
right and since we don't actually know
what we want to do with Heights
here I want to change this a little bit
I want to call this iterate tile plane
and I want to call this like you know
relative Z or something right so
basically if you know that you're just
doing a planar tile or in fact I might
even go one further and say iterate as
planar tiles and that just says look I
don't actually care how many floors hi
this thing is I'm just going to treat it
as if it was one floor because that's
actually what we want to do for a fair
number of rooms probably like so I'm
guessing that we just want that as a
default you can use and then when you
when once we actually have a
circumstance where we want to like
generate an actual tower or something
and you know I'll be honest I don't know
that we ever do because even at our we
might just want each one of those to be
a room so I'm just gonna call it iterate
as planar tiles at the moment and assume
that we don't really want to really ever
talk about multi floor rooms as actual
single iterations because we probably
want to place them separately I'm just
guessing as separate rooms right that
just happened to connect or have empty
spaces right so I don't know but we're
gonna call that this for now just to
make it clear that anyone who is calling
it at the moment is not intending for
you to iterate the z-axis of the volume
should it contain more than one floor we
want to treat it all as one floor anyway
and that's all I mean by that right okay
and so for now we don't really have to
worry about that stuff but later on I
just wanted the naming to be clear so
that later on when we do potentially
have to upgrade that in some way it
won't be like what's going on right okay
so the Edit tile needs like a gen B free
v3 which is like the relative index of
this thing off of the edit grid right
and so these are like exactly what's
happening here and so what we want to do
is in order to determine whether or not
this thing is valid there's a couple of
different ways we could do that but I
think probably the most straightforward
is to just check if it's inside right I
think we've already got that that's not
what I wanted to look at so I believe in
here we can just say like is in volume
right and is in volume should tell us
that that piece of information so I'm
just going to take a copy of this saucy
gentleman right here and say look we
should also be able to call this like
this right and go okay tell me is in
volume for the components of P so I
don't have to manually pass them myself
right so I think all we would have to do
for is valid on an edit aisle is to just
say alright if it's in the volume as
given by the edit grid then I think
we're we're good right although actually
you know we never create a volume
because it's based off of 0 so not sure
how I want to phrase that like you want
to do it this way something like that
and I think I'd also like to pass this
here since it's pretty free to do so and
it prevents me from having to store it
in the tile iterator itself so yeah what
I want to do is say like alright if it's
in the array bounds although you know
what now I think about it what's one
more pointer who cares this is the great
time code I don't care at all so maybe
the right answer is now it goes in there
so we could just say look if it's inside
here then it's then it's good otherwise
it's not and then that would just be
this
so for this volume here where we do
these results we would just say that
this is 0 and this is bounds ok so this
way we just check to see ok it should be
greater than 0 it should be less than
whatever the bounds are no
and that's all we need to do to check so
assuming that we're inside those bounds
off we go now one thing I don't know is
that tile count I'm a little confused
now because when we do the tile count
are we actually adding the 1 yes we are
so that's what's happening there that's
like where's the one coming from we are
so I think we should just be able to use
that and be fine with it so in here we
say like okay let's do and let's do a
check that's the only check that we
would actually need and so now we can
get rid of this stuff as stuff that
needs to happen and mostly just look at
that code right there and also we can
look at the code and the other one stuff
that we want to do all right so in here
yeah when we're iterating we just say is
it in the array bounds for this thing if
it is then it's valid otherwise that
it's not um when we want to advance
things get a little bit hairier but it's
not too bad still what we would say and
in fact I may actually get in the habit
of doing this as well so I don't have to
keep saying that right so what I want to
do now is take that relative index and I
want to advance it as if I was doing
four loops on it right so what I want to
do is say look the tile relative index X
I want to increment that every time we
advance but in the event that the tile
relative X X now at that point is out of
bounds so like if that if that
advancement would cause it to be greater
than or equal to whatever the tile count
X is like meaning I overflowed it then I
want to change the tile relative index X
back to zero and in what I actually
wanted to do was increment the Y you
know I'm saying
now maybe the Y pushes us out of bounds
but that's what is valid is four it
would trigger that and we would exit the
loop so we're basically just turning to
four loops into one call that does what
the to four loops would have done right
and it's a little less efficient because
obviously it has to check every time it
increments X it has to check X in a way
that
in a way that maybe isn't as clean as
having the loops themselves isolated but
it's really the same number of
conditionals in a way right at the end
of every X you're gonna do this check to
see and you would have had to do that in
the for loop so it's a little harder
maybe for the compiler to see what's
going on but otherwise it should be
roughly equivalent most of the time I
think I have to think that through
but anyway again in the creation code we
really don't care it's totally fine this
is this is this is all child's play
right so at that point we just need a
way of it like starting this up right we
have to start you know the iteration
somehow and really since the relative
index always wants to start at 0 0
anyway because why not you know since
that just gives us some nice linear walk
with tiles anyway the only thing we
really have to do is just set the grid
equal to the one that we come in we're
just remembering that function but other
than that just initializing the 0
actually works which is great
so that means I think we're down to just
ways of getting like the center and the
volume and stuff like that right and so
what I'd like to do here is just have
some way of computing this this
information and like stuff like get
volume and all that kind of nonsense
right so in order to do that
[Music]
I guess what I might say is maybe we
should just make this volume just be
directly computable so like what if we
just said yeah look that's all always
there just for convenience and so then
we could just say look when you're
actually doing the general stuff what we
were doing sorry room Jen all we were
actually doing here to figure out where
this crap was you know was we were doing
like this kind of nonsense right and you
can see here like here's how we figured
out what the position of the thing was
right and so I feel like what we could
do is just create the volume here you
know directly and
how did we end up I can't remember what
our decision was on the half tile Dib so
we offset the room position and we don't
offset the entity positions looks like
how we decided to do that because I was
vacillating on that and I'm not sure
still I really know what I want to do
about that right
and if I had I think what I want to do
is not this so I think I don't want to
do this right I think we can do this in
a more straightforward fashion so let's
suppose that up here instead of doing
this we just don't do that at all so the
main room key is always nothing right
and the max room P is always the room
dim so zero zero zero is always the
origin and that's the minimum and that's
just how we roll right if that was the
case then every time we get a volume out
of this thing and I think that means I
don't want this because this is just
going to be very easy so every time we
get a volume out of this it's gonna look
something like this the min and the max
are literally just taking the exact tile
dim they grab this out again right and
multiplying out the coordinates by the
tile dim right so the min P is just the
tile
Rayland X X tile Rayland X Y tile
Rayland X Z right we're just gonna take
that and we're just multiplying it by
the tile dim
and similarly look max P is just min P
plus one in each direction right so in
order to actually get what these in
depth being in the end it's just min P
equals Hadamard right times a tile dam
and I think that just creates the volume
right which is just much more
straightforward of a way to do it than
what we were doing before do you see how
that works
asked me after if you don't understand
but I'm just saying look we're on a grid
just take this grid point and take what
it would be to go positive 1 in each
axis on the grid and that's the volume
why am i screwing around right
just do that then it doesn't matter
whatever you make the grid you can do
whatever you want the it'll always
produce the correct volume as long as
that is the grid right and so I think
that's all we actually need there and
then we can just say that the rectum in
max of this is the total volume and so
therefore if we ever want to do a get
volume form in Z or something like this
all we have to do is say that the result
of that is to get the total volume
whatever the total volume is of the tile
and then just change the height so the
results max Z equals the result min Z
plus the height that's I mean that's
kinda self-explanatory right
yeah so I think that's pretty much all
there is to it similarly this code now
is just literally calling the code like
you know I mean what could be easier
right I mean it's really really basic
now which is nice okay so now what we
got to do is actually include these
files remember we haven't actually
included them in the build so they're
not doing anything right now they're
just sitting off to the sidelines
collecting dust as slightly differently
magnetized pieces of our hard drives
platter
well this is an SSD so actually it's not
that at all
anyway so I need to include this h-file
I need to include the CPP file and I'm
going to need to go in and port the old
code now over to the new way of doing
things and then I think we're in a
better spot you know we've got
everything kind of cleaned up at that
point all right so where is this room
stuff happening room gen whatever blah
blah blah so this is after the gen map
maybe handmade
a edit grid that's the key and we've
also got handmade edit grid H in here
should be I guess here maybe let's see I
don't know if that's true okay
so I yeah this stuff that used to work
on a genuine grid now just works to work
on an edit grid but other than that I
think it's basically the same we just
changed the name of a couple of things
so this dim here is actually tile counts
but other than that I think it's
basically the exact same code so we
don't really have to do anything
differently there I don't think this
would also be the same
[Music]
let's see what else you got
top count tile count and tile count okay
um this is just memory this is off of
the grid now this that and this that
right right and my hammer about that I
think I'm right about that all right
um this Jen room grid is an edit grid
don't ask me why I didn't change that
but I didn't shut person from tile
position what is the problem here a grid
based P grid min tile that's that should
be correction it is there something what
am I missing about that
Oh identifier not found okay so we need
that to be part of the grid stuff that
that actually makes totally reasonable
sense actually so we need chunk position
from tile position which is this thing
here that actually needs to kind of be
moved out into the edit grid itself
because that's sort of a more primal
function right so that's something that
has to be available here which is
earlier than it was being available
before so I think now we are down to oh
and this guy needs in the region in the
region I think now we're down to porting
the old code to work with the new code
let's see the grid needs to be pulled
out here but otherwise I think we're
good and let's see yeah so this is our
kind of old code what I should probably
do first and it will be slightly wrong
but what I should probably do first is
make sure that this stuff runs sort of
exactly the same as it was running
before well I guess I don't really want
to do that to be honest so I think I'm
just going to port it I'm just gonna go
straight straight into the port you know
go big or go home that's what we say
here on handmade here we don't
necessarily say that but we have said it
I think someone said it was probably
that someone was me but who knows so
anyway when we do a begin grid edit we
don't need to pass the world I think we
decided that we do need to pass the
apron volume though so that's going to
remain what we're lapping entities exist
this tile volume this needs to be get
total volume right enough that goes this
stuff all seems to be right as far as I
know that should all be fine I'm not
sure what this is complaining about here
let's take a look at the error actually
just so we can get some idea of what it
actually is saying it's wrong there why
am I not able to step through these I
have no idea
let's see function does not take one
argument overlapping is this so it's get
total volume ease and address uh that's
that's true and make relative doesn't
take one argument either what are you
talking about
get volume from Minzy is that not get
flying from NZ that takes in an edit
tile which I'm passing and a height
which I'm passing as well what is the
issue there that's what it's supposed to
do right I mean that that seems correct
what's what's wrong with that you want
to know what's wrong with that
oh well yeah you're correct
there is no entity yet so I think that's
all correct so now we just got this port
to deal with now all of this stuff we
basically replaced so in theory we can
just basically delete like most of the
code from this routine and replace it
with this so right at the start here
where we're doing room Vall that in
theory like all of this goes away none
of this is necessary that's all gone
this is gone that's gone and we're down
to just this right so inside here is the
stuff that we have to port the rest of
it goes away when we get down to here
right that's the four legs you can see
the marker on the side there it's the
for tile yeah so that's what we wanted
that's all fine and then this is gonna
be replaced with the end grid edit right
so the end grade edit happens there the
begin grid Edit happens up here and yeah
then we're kind of moving on from into
the actual reporting so now in order to
get this position which we wanted before
that's actually we already wrote that
it's actually this right so this value
is just that this is what's at what we
wanted it's the center point of the tile
with the lowest possible C value
so that's pretty much just a non-issue
this function now probably wants to be a
utility function that operates off of
this because we're what we're trying to
get here is the storage value from this
you know I'm saying so we don't really
want to have to do it this way anymore
because we've already got this so I'm
gonna actually make this work a little
differently I also want to transform all
of these into testing functions that you
can use that don't require you to do
funky arithmetic and we can just bake
all that in to the function proper so
let's assume we were gonna do that
I'm just looking here what else I want
to do yeah so you know stuff and so on
happens and blob all of this looks fine
this obviously is the grid region that
we're talking about here on the lamp is
we're gonna have to figure out what we
want to do with that I don't know we're
gonna do with some of that stuff yeah so
a lot of this stuff is just gonna get
cleaned up here all right all right all
right so this is gonna take a little bit
of us just slowly working this through
but it's not going to be that bad at the
end of the day all right so this is the
grid region the collision volume for the
room I think we just want this to be a
way that we get the entire room volume
so here I'm just gonna say like get grid
volume
you like this right from the grid I'm
gonna want to call that the tile count
here I think it's safe to just use it
directly I don't think I need an access
or for any particular reason they're not
gonna obfuscate that for any particular
reason
what this part here is a little nastier
because we need to get the various
volume parts of the room here to do the
like mapping for the world room chunk
space stuff so that we're gonna have to
look at separately as how look that
should probably be an access or as well
but but I'm not sure so let's go ahead
and take these one at a time
so let's figure out how we want to do
tiles if I jump in here and take a look
at how get tile was working I can
probably just make this be a helper
where we just say look if you wanted to
pass an edit tile then you just can and
it would just do that and so for now
we'll just do this furthermore you don't
really need that so you can pretty much
just do this right and I think that
takes care of our of our issue there the
problem is this doesn't really want to
be called tile and this is why say I
don't know if we want to like sort of
line that up with this a little bit
better
meaning the stuff that's actually in
here like the open structure old bit
there but like maybe it just gets copied
into the tile so in other words if we
wanted to you know we could do this and
then you could just get those pieces of
information I don't know it's hard to
say but anyway
something like this I think that's what
we want something along those lines I
definitely don't want any of that in
there but I think that's more or less
what we want and so I mean here this
would be like edit tile contents right
and that would just be the same code
it's just I'm just changing the name
nothing particularly weird happening
there
same here I could probably just search
and replace this I don't because there's
nothing we didn't actually change
anything about the code
[Music]
yes so I think that's mostly it right
all right so we've got this query here
we've got this in volume query here
which um not super sure what that's even
doing so it's basically saying okay it's
just saying our is this tile inside this
connection right so that's kind of like
the absolute tile location so we kind of
want this right
and so this when we say like is this
thing in this volume right we want to be
able to do that and then when we're
actually looking at those right you can
see what those were right
so these want to be in terms of absolute
right if this you know absolute value
lines up with that absolute value then
off we go this on edge function is just
a function of the tile and we should
just be able to ask that question right
and so I want to be able to do a couple
of these so here's the is on edge and
that's just going to do like exactly the
same thing it was doing so that's
totally fine and then the other thing
that we want to do here is allow you to
get that absolute value so that is again
really simple it's just an addition so
in order to produce that we take the
relative index and we just want to take
the grid base right and offset it by the
relative index and that gives us the
absolute index right nothing nothing
fancy okay so here this X index and why
index those are actually just the
relative index right so if we just do
something like this then this is P dot X
and this is P dot Y
just makes it a little easier mm then if
I had to expand that whole thing out
what else we got okay on lamp is I
whatever like I don't even know I guess
we just let it do that if that's what
you want I'm not going to stop you what
is you can edit I'll just no yeah right
sorry
so here we're just that all this looks
fine this P dot X nonsense here
so this is the part we're gonna have to
start actually thinking about what we
want to do because we now have ways of
making this less hacky and we should
okay so yeah mostly we're start with
that this is just grid region so I think
that's just fine this is tile contents
right and that's all good no issues
there I don't think I don't see anything
weird anyway and so now I think we're
down to just the last few things all
right so that's happy so let's talk
about these first because I think these
are probably the easiest ones to do
because they don't really involve any
thinking so this collision volume forget
room volume off of the grid is pretty
straightforward so the grid hmm excuse
me the grid itself that collision volume
is just a v3 if we know the grid we know
that it goes from well it's this right
we actually created the min P to Mac
space so it's like done and the other
one is kind of a little bit saucy ER so
it's basically saying I need to get like
the min part of that and the max part of
that and I need to base them off of this
so I I'm gonna make accessors for those
because it's still like it's a little
wonky and I don't want someone to screw
it up so basically you know
this sort of thing all I'm doing is
calling this but with the right thing so
that someone can't screw it up because
it's just a little bit too much to
remember exactly about what's going on
here right um so yeah I don't know if
you should have to pass the world
probably not if the grid is supposed to
just have all this garbage in it anyway
let's just go ahead and say that does so
for example it's got the world generator
in there and so you know it can get the
world anytime it wants to so the change
base fee in this case right is just the
we could we we stored this this value
off right which is this and
and I think that's really all we need
right so I think we're just doing that
and then we want to do grid room dem men
and then when we want to do the max
version it's the same thing but with Max
and that's it right and so to create the
two world positions that that's what we
would be doing and assuming we got
everything else right that should just
work in theory right that's a forward
declaration there so we're just going to
tell it that hey there is a world
generator we're pointing to it you don't
know what it is yet but trust me it'll
come and then here we just do get min
world P get room max world P and that
just takes oops
the grid so our construction grid is now
pretty powerful right you could do all
this stuff for us and so hopefully that
just keeps us from having to worry about
all of our kind of finicky little issues
there this part here where it needs to
know what the tyldum is we could just
say for the moment like we just did that
and it's fine I don't know if we want to
do that or not but I'm gonna leave it in
there and so now we've got the remainder
of our time coudn't about 15 minutes or
whatever let's see if we can debug all
this stuff so we're probably gonna have
to go through this a little bit more a
fine-tooth comb because we just did a
massive set of reengineering this stuff
right and so you know we probably
introduced our fair share of errors in
there but we'll see if we can get it
done before the bell right so starting
off I will say there aren't a whole lot
of errors obviously popping up so that
was smoother of a start than I thought
[Music]
enough actually all looks quite good
that's exactly what I wanted to see and
those are like flatlined right at the
baseline there which is also what I
wanted to see so that's all good and we
can go maybe look and see and try to fix
this error over here
because if there even is one looks like
it fixed that air as well so so that was
a pretty hardcore win there I want to
say that that basically just was totally
solved so you can just see what's going
on with the rooms now when you're moving
backwards it's not finding the next room
boundary and it's actually literally not
paged in so something about the way I'm
doing the room boundary now is weird and
I want to say like the reason I think
that that's probably happening is
because we're making our room boundary
our entity for the room is based around
the zero zero zero location probably I
bet that's what's actually happening and
so if the min corner it's probably
counting on it being in the middle and
pulling it in as opposed to doing an
overlap in terms of how if you remember
how we pull stuff out of the world you
can only have things that are half a
room's radius away so I think what we
need to do if we want to fix that right
is that this crap isn't going to work
what we actually want is we want this
and so what I'm doing they're saying
look we need this because people get
packed into areas and there's a maximum
entity radius in terms of how it will be
unpacked
we can't just arbitrarily expect rooms
to get unpacked if they're at their
minimum here and this thing is like
unpacking the cells around it it may
never get to entities that were packed
with their entity center there right and
so I suspect that's probably the issue
let's see if it is
yeah um so that's all good I'm gonna go
ahead and turn off the collision section
drawing now and we still one of these
days we got to make put that on a switch
I'm just I'm being lazy I just don't
feel like making a little debug console
for it what can I say
that's just that's just the way things
are so yeah if we turn that off and then
we take a look at our world it's looking
pretty respectable now right like like
now you don't see like dead area right
and so yeah I mean our lighting still
needs to be finished obviously but like
you you don't see dead area well okay no
you do there's some dead area right
there
hmm so that's a bit of a puzzler because
that really doesn't look like it has
anything to do with anyone underneath so
that's something different that does
that happen in all rooms of this nature
or just that one so it's not happening
there what about the garden area yeah
there it is again
right
hmmm that's gonna be not very much fun
to debug at all it could just be like
slight imprecision right in terms of how
we're doing her and the overlap or
something so I could try to hand wave it
away by saying that but I would feel
more comfortable if we actually tried to
figure that out and demonstrate first
that that's actually what was happening
there right because it seems like really
weird that it only is happening along
certain edges and I don't know how to
I don't really know how to assess that
so if I was going to play with this part
of it
I'm just want to see from my own
edification so suppose we didn't add
radius to here where we dropped the size
of this by like an epsilon right and so
essentially what we're doing here is
like take the volume we would have been
querying and just shrink it so that we
don't have floating-point precision
issues at the edge and I don't know that
that really I've done no work to
determine that that's the case it was
just like well you know I could make an
argument that was happening so what you
can see is that does fix the problem
which we could call good enough for
government purposes right I mean
certainly anytime in recent American
history that would have been good enough
for government purposes I'll tell you
that right now so looking at this yeah I
mean I think that would probably just
give me enough information to say that's
probably what that was but so anyway I
think we're pretty good now I'm
relatively happy with with that
so yeah I think mission accomplished
all right try to think if there's any
other last little thing I wanted to do I
think we did everything though ah well I
could do this since we don't actually
think it's necessary let's remove it
so yeah I'm not sure why we must have
decided at some point we were like
forget it it's got to keep the world
anyway I guess and so we had like done
we probably had done some stuff where we
were like oh you know we thought we were
gonna pass this around but you know as
it turns out we weren't okay so I think
now we're all good all right so I guess
we can go to the QA let's just make sure
this we're running okay looking good
looking good yeah so I think we go fix
ground cover then we fix lighting
well not fix bunker we implement ground
cover you finish lighting and then we
clean up the tag system and then I think
I am very sad to say I'm out of things
to do which which puts us into game play
programming land and which as you know
I've tried to avoid as much as possible
but you can only avoid it for so long
eventually the engine does everything
and you don't have anything else you can
do yeah
we've got to fix the the camera Z height
should not move with the character
bounce with character hopping we should
fix that as well okay does anyone have
any questions
where's the little cute cute a return
[Music]
do you plan to implement any fancy 3d
audio stuff not really because the game
is 2d really I mean it's 3d it does a
bunch of 3d effects and stuff but since
you don't like you're looking down on
like a 2d dungeon
I don't think 3d audio really makes much
sense because everything's supposed to
sound like it's coming from directly in
front of you right and so you know I
mean you could come up with like weird
reasons to do stuff like oh let me try
to make it sound like you're in the
stack of dungeons so things on floors
above you like sound like they're behind
you or something like that but I don't
care much for that sort of thing
when you code in pure sweetie do you
have your own string library do you
always use subset of C++ and their
standard string library oh dude I don't
touch the C++ standard library at all I
would never ever ever use the C++
standard library it's horrific write
your own string for sure will you at any
point remove the double walls between
rooms
I don't know I haven't thought about it
I mean there's no real reason to remove
double walls between rooms except for
aesthetics but if we decided that it
aesthetically looked nicer to have a one
wide thing then we certainly could it's
not hard to do so maybe I don't know
it's not something that I had thought
about see Geoffrey's comment I don't
know who Jeffrey is oh my a dream call
gate is two minutes not I've been into
max okay I found it up in the chat there
let me fix that
those room add calls we don't use right
now so yeah that's why that's why we
didn't see any actual consequences from
that it's because this is like kind of a
slightly vestigial remain we we probably
need it because we want to be able to
display like a map in the future but we
you know we just don't do anything with
it right now but you know to me while
displaying that map eventually that was
what that was supposed to do well let me
see what else we got for comments what
we're doing hamyuts sine cosine yeah we
are doing we will do those eventually
because they're the only two functions
in our entire code base we didn't write
ourselves so we want to we do want to do
our own sine and cosine eventually so
that we can be completely completely
from scratch right
I have a feeling you'll find more engine
work to do once you starts the gameplay
stuff well yeah but it won't really be
engine work do you know what I mean it's
gameplay work at that point like it's in
other words it's not stuff for
presenting the world and managing stuff
and you know streaming and it's like you
know it's just it's stuff that only
exists because you had a gameplay
requirement like I want to know if these
two things collide or I want to pass
find from here to there then you're
adding like nominally engine code but
it's really it's just they're in service
of a specific game play feature so yeah
I don't typically count that quite as
engine work even though obviously it can
be reused sometimes without ever letting
a tiny animation tool in the editor I
don't really want to focus much on
animation which is why we haven't done
that
cuz typically at that point you need to
pick like an animation tool to you know
to standardize on or something you
really don't want to write your own
editor for animation unless you plan to
make a big investment in it because
artists aren't gonna want to use some
hacky little thing you made would you
recommend any books for learning C++ I
just am NOT up on the current books I'm
sorry I would stay away from anything
that really talks about C++ because C++
is kind of garbage so I'd mostly focus
on learning C so whatever is good books
for wearing C would be good does the
apron cover everything we need now I'm
just wondering if there may be any point
in using our elevation and Cameron or
the figure out the necessary extents for
the apron for floor as far below us it
would only be the case if we actually
had rooms that are high up above the
ground level once we're going down then
no because for going down I believe the
way we want to do that is just have the
outside be filled to black because
you're not really supposed to see down
there anyway right it's supposed to be
solid we may speaking of that we may
want to add
blocks to the exteriors of areas
underground to just basically prevent
you from being able to see down we
probably will want to do something like
that darkened Dario the world apron is
meant to make the outside of the world
not look empty could there be entities
in side of the world apron as ambien
entities so there could be but I think I
would probably rather not and the reason
for that is if a player can see an
animate thing I would like them be able
to get to the animate thing that's kind
of just a more of a game design
principle than anything else which is to
say that anytime the user sees like a
monster or you know creature of some
kind I want them to be able to get there
so I would rather have areas you can't
access be clearly labeled as such so
that you don't think that there's some
way to get there and spend your time
trying to get there does that make sense
so I would probably shy away from doing
that even though there's no reason we
couldn't do it obviously the engine
would handle just fine
it's the particle system complete yeah
kind of we probably will want to write a
few more sort of pathing functions
because right now we kind of only have
like poof and we'll want some like
explosions or something I'm out know
what we'll want but we'll probably want
a few other things so there might be
some changes to that as we actually put
in process but mostly the it's pretty
much is what it is right we just change
a few of the sim trajectories so you
know we'll want to add a couple more
trajectory types you can pick from if
that makes sense
so yes so we will be placing more things
in the apron but they should all just be
like trees and rocks and crap right
have yous get SVN or other vcs's for
actual collaboration what did you think
about them I have actually used I've
used get SVN CVS perforce
and I think that may be it so I've used
those for in actual in an actual what
work environment like a real projects
that you know sell for money or whatever
and have multiple people on them and in
terms of what I think about them I think
that source code control systems are
very much like email they're a simple
problem that the people who make source
code control systems managed to
dramatically overcomplicate and it makes
it very unpleasant if I had to state the
overall reason why I believe that to be
true it's because they all seem to be
written with the same methodology in
mind which is let me implement what I
think a bunch of source code control
system functions are and then let me
dump those in the lap of the user and
force them to create a process that is
actually what they want out of those
pieces
whereas what you actually want is to
first say what are the set of things
that a programmer actually does with a
version control system and let me design
the system that has those as the
functions so for example a pretty simple
type of operation that you should be one
command in any version control system is
I need to get the state of some other
programmers machine onto my machine
right now I don't want to lose the work
I was doing I don't want them to have to
do anything I just want to just your a
source code control system make my
machine have a copy of his machine on it
please because I'm need to debug
something that you just hit write or
whatever this usually takes like 17
steps in these version control systems
and it usually screws up because you oh
you forgot to reverse and code double
back stash the previous change into a
head revision and so now you're abstruse
refactoring system put the line endings
all into one file and deleted them and
you're like good thank you that's great
right sue invariably whenever I've tried
to use any source code control system I
always get that that is the outcome the
outcome is always that hey I can list
probably five things and those five
things are the only things you pretty
much ever need to do with a source code
control system and you've implemented
one of them and forgot the other four
right and so then when programmers have
to do the other four they're issuing
like ten commands in your source code
control system all of which are
error-prone just to get like what's just
what is what it should do right so they
all suck is the answer and they don't
just suck a little bit like they suck
super hard
what about simple ambience like birds
flying from tree to tree I'm just I'm
just not okay with it like if you want
birds flying around they can fly around
inside the rooms that you can actually
access but they shouldn't land on like
the trees in the other places I think I
would I would prefer if they didn't do
that low mesas and in theory you can
have the composition of elements a theme
of the apron be visibly different yet
still complimentary so that it's clear
that is in fact an apron exactly that's
kind of my game design philosophy there
it's like I don't really want the player
to be confused about what is and isn't a
potential goal so I don't really want
like birds flying over an area they
can't get to because maybe they thought
the bird was flying somewhere that they
want to go to right and so any time you
know maybe a bird can fly and never land
over an area that the player can't get
to so long as they were heading towards
an area the player could get to so that
it would indicate to the player that
there was something over there explore
I'd be fine with that right but I don't
like I don't like possible miscues to
the player about that right
do you consider any AI related code as
gameplay programming is there anything
you can implement engine-wise in order
to ease the coding process of these
topics for example I could see
pathfinding and role generation as a
possible candidate I'm not sure what you
mean those two things seem unrelated so
how are you what do you mean by AI
related code and then world generation
you're saying AI as like you know like
putting a neural network into the world
generator or something I guess I'm not
sure I really super understand the
question
what about rolling fog cloud entities
out there just a bunch of trees and a
large grid sounds kind of weird yeah
well it is kind of weird I guess but
that's just how it goes how do you write
thread safe code in C or do you use C++
standard atomic in that case well thread
safe code really just has to do with
having access to lock increment and
locked exchange right so I just call
lock exchange it's a it's an X 64
instruction right you don't need
anything fancy you just need to compile
that X 64 instruction so you just use
whatever the compilers way of omitting
that X 64 instruction is and off you go
but what if the birds don't fly in a
straight line as the crow flies well you
know I don't know how would you
implement a game like diggle's so I've
never heard of that
what is diggle's it sounds almost like a
joke name is this a real game
the myth of Fenris is that okay so it's
it's from 2001 let's see here
giggles so let me see I can't actually
find any actual digging here let me find
a video where someone's doing something
okay now I see what's going on there
so it looks to me just like their de
storing a volume right yeah so I mean I
don't know that you really would have to
do anything all that different from what
we're actually doing the only thing you
might want to do is you know maybe you
want to invert the way we're thinking
about the world so that essentially
everything below a certain Z is
considered solid and what you store as
entities are actually what we're the
empty area is rather than where the
solid area is just to keep your storage
costs down but other than that I think
you wouldn't really have to do much you
could probably just use exactly what
we're doing now and just invert the
meaning so rather than storing solid
areas you store empty areas right all
right I'm gonna go ahead and close it
down
there we go all right thank you everyone
for joining me for those sort of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow series at home you can
always pair to the game on hand made
here org and it comes with a source code
so you can play around with it maybe you
would like to try implementing diggle's
yourself and switching our sort of world
representation to be able to store the
idea of empty areas instead of solid
areas you know it's an interesting it's
an interesting difference I will be back
next week to do more programming on our
probably ground cover at that point
until then have fun programming and I'll
see everyone on the Internet
taking use everybody