hello everybody and welcome handmade
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are going to do I
guess you know honestly what it is
really is skeletal animation is what
we're doing today we don't have a need
for the deformations stuff that you
might do in a normal skeletal animation
system because we don't have 3d objects
we don't even really have any bone
binding information for our 2d objects
per se but even so we do kind of want to
animate them as if they did meaning we
want like a bunch of secondary stuff so
when our characters hop around we want
the heads to be kind of springy and we
implemented some of that stuff before
but the way that we did it was in a
fairly rudimentary sense where you
couldn't really build up any kind of
skeleton a priori and give it
information that would then look to the
art to see how it should be connected
and so what we want to do today and we
set ourselves up to do this yesterday
but we didn't actually have time to go
and start working on the code for the
actual sort of skeletal part of it is we
want to go in and add that ability
because now we have a little editor in
the game that allows us to like markup
our stuff with points that say out
things snap together that's basically
what a skeletal animation system does
offline usually so for example if
someone inside Maya creates a little
bone structure that bone structure is
typically exported and then you load it
into your game and those bones tell you
the information that we would want
inside handmade hero which is how does
each piece connect and where do they
connect right but we don't have that
information because our stuff just comes
in two sprites and that's intentional
because we don't really want to insert
tools into the art chain that are
complicated because this is supposed to
be an educational project and we want
people be able to add to it easily so if
they just can draw a bitmap in a bitmap
tool you want them be able to put that
into this game eventually right if
people are playing with it themselves we
don't want them to have to learn
something like Maya we don't want them
to have to learn something like spriter
if they can just use like Photoshop we
want to be able to get stuff into the
game but what that means is there's no
markup in there right there's nothing
that says how heads connect to bodies
and inside our
code we could special case every last
little thing and just describe all of
that in code but if we did that then
people who add new head's new bodies new
whatever couldn't really ever change the
basics of how they worked they couldn't
have heads that attached like lower on
the body or something for someone who
was hunched over or whatever right
they couldn't have bodies that had a
long skinny neck and put the head up at
the top instead if we hard-code all of
those ideas about how things are
attached directly into the code it
becomes much more limiting in terms of
what you can do when you put art into
the game and want to implement new
entities that maybe don't look exactly
like the old entities that were already
programmed by me so that's the goal and
we did a lot of work to make that happen
we have the ability to specify
attachment points in a fairly arbitrary
way and we now have an editor that lets
you in game adjust those attachment
points what we don't have is anything
that actually uses them right so we're
trying to do now is go back to that
stuff where we had the rudimentary
skeletal animation going on and we need
to rethink how that's working a little
bit to sort of start to use these points
and see where they should more
appropriately go right we want to figure
out kind of where that stuff is supposed
to happen and so what we want to do is
we want to have a way of saying look
when I animate this thing I animate my
my you know my the base of this this guy
like the torso whatever and maybe that's
attached directly to the world so I just
moved that point around but then the
head is like attached to the torso so
any animation that the head has I really
just kind of want to be able to describe
it relative to the place where it was
attached I I don't want to have to try
and animate the head to always appear to
be on the body
I want it just to naturally stick on the
body wherever it should and then I can
add any secondary motion I want right
that's the basic idea behind a skeletal
animation system is look we know these
things have to maintain their
connectivity that's you know how they
would work in the real world so I just
am going to keep them that way all the
time by default and they're offset from
that is all I'm really going to be
animating right so that's what we want
to start working with right we want to
start getting that sort of we want that
idea to be baked into how we're
animating things which is going to
require us to unwind a little bit of
what we did and sort of port it to
something that's a little bit more about
relative movement but fortunately we
haven't really written much animation
code we just did some basic stuff so
it's not like we have a ton invested in
the old way of doing things anyway it
was kind of all sketched out just in a
basic way so that's what we're moving
towards today I think we should be able
to make a good dent in that so let's get
started oh okay so running the game so
we could take stock of where we're at
here oops I guess I accidentally nuked
our thing when I did MS dev CL on the
priests name there okay there we go uh
so you know getting started with this
you can see you know we've got right now
we're loading the cat as our as our hero
so what you can see is we're at a point
where we've done all the work to import
new art assets such as the CAC we have
an editor that would allow us to select
the cat and we can even change like
alignment points and stuff like that
right but what we don't really do is use
those alignment points in any way to
actually connect things so a couple of
things here are the things I want to do
in in no particular order today so we
want to snap the cat's head to the cat's
body right we want it to go up here so
that's gonna require to set two
alignment points one is this alignment
point right which says where on the cat
head we want to snap to right and so
it's probably something like this point
right here so you want two things one we
want to do that snap in two we want to
see that snapping point so I want to add
something that's when I'm doing this
right when I'm editing an alignment
point I want to have a notion of the
fact that I'm editing it and I want to
draw it so I can see it because right
now I don't really know where it is like
I've got a vague idea that it's probably
in the center of this thing
this this rectangle here that we're
drawing is
election box but I don't really know
right so I want to draw that point too I
need to be able to say when I do this
stuff here so I say look that's the
default alignment point but then maybe
later when I'm doing this I add one
right and I'm gonna add in here the base
of neck I want to be able to snap those
together so I want to be able to say
look the default of this goes to the
base of neck
you saw me write the code for that
yesterday so the entities the entities
know they're supposed to be doing that
they're just not doing it so I need the
implementation of that snap so this will
snap to here when I actually set it and
then finally of course I need there to
be some way to draw that so when I'm
moving this around I need to see that
point so I can position it right where
it it should be in terms of the head
attachment right so I need all those
things then we got to do a couple other
things
remember selecting an entity it might
have multiple parts of my have multiple
components I want those components
listed in the editor so I can pick which
one I'm editing head or body right for
example I want that in the air so we got
to get that in there and then finally we
need to start talking about sizes right
now like this cats way too big right the
cat should occupy like one square it
should be fairly tiny on the square
that's something that we want to start
working on in terms of how we specify
the sizes of things and that's gonna
require two things one it's gonna
require us to start obeying these
relative size information pieces that we
put on there but number two it's gonna
require us to start thinking about how
we want to actually specify size to
begin with because we have we want that
to work in a very broad parametric sense
what I mean by that I mean that let's
suppose you are a human right and then
you are turned into a cat there's two
ways we might want to think about that
one is that you become a cat cat size
and one is that you become a cat at
human size right another way to state
that would be if a human got a cat head
for some reason
cathead shouldn't be cat head sized
probably chances are what you wanted is
for the cat head to be human head sized
what that means is that we have two
notions of scale we have a notion of
scale that says how big the thing is
relative to whatever the general scale
is so for example this bitmap is
supposed to be roughly this size for a
head so head shape how do I fill out the
how big should this bitmap be scaled to
occupy the size of a head then there's
another scale which is how big is this
entity which determines how big its head
is regardless of which one of those
bitmaps it chooses if it chooses a human
head or a cat head it should still be
the same size similarly if a cat ends up
with a human head that head should be
small like the small cat head would be
so you see there's there's different
things there right there's the size of
this head relative to other heads so we
know how they all line up to keep all
heads to be roughly the same size no
matter how the artist drew them and then
there's how do we actually want to talk
about the size of this entity and we
have those two things already in the
game but we have to make sure that now
we're rigorous about it because a
mistake in that line will cause us to
lose that ability to mix and match parts
and we'll have this gigantic explosion
of special case hacks that are doing
things like checking oh if I'm a cat
head on a human body then add this
excellent right we don't want any of
that we want that to just work so it's
excellent we know everything we have to
do we've got a clear test case here like
I want my cat to look right when it's
hopping around and obviously it looks
completely wrong right now
so we know when we've done the right
thing and so let's just start working on
that part of the problem right and we'll
take each one of those things as we go
okay so let's start with something basic
let's start with being able to see the
point that we reading and pick which one
of the things in the list we're going to
edit we know those things have to happen
we just got finished doing the editor
let's actually go ahead and add some
stuff to it while it's still fresh in
our mind
how it works so that if we find there
are some things that we can't do that we
would like to do that can be improved
right so what we want to do here is say
look inside you know inside this system
there's we want to maybe be able to draw
our attachment points like we maybe want
to be able to draw which attachment
points are being used or something like
this and there's a couple of different
ways we can do that
I think the way that I would like to do
it first is just by drawing all
attachment points and then maybe we add
the ability to turn them on and off at
will let's see again and remember one of
things I was ragging on QT the other day
and here's another good example of why I
rag on Qt all the time it's because I
hate those retain mode kind of things I
just want to show how easy it is when
you're not doing that to just add things
in in a trivial way right it just it you
don't have to retain any information you
don't have to make creation calls or any
of this sort of stuff you can just add
stuff freely and it just becomes very
very easy I know our UI system is crappy
because we spent no time on it so I know
it's not very good but still even in
it's such crappy state watch how easy it
is to do stuff to it without ever having
to really change the UI system and
keeping all of the data on our side
under our control in the place that we
want right so let's go ahead and do that
so if I want to inside my editor right
let's say I want I know that we've got
these instant in the file formats I know
that we've got like this notion of these
inside each of the bitmaps I've got this
set of alignment points right so I know
that I've got these HHA alignment points
and here you can see like how many of
them there are right I've got 12 of
these and so that's how many we were
drawing right so what I'd like to do is
I'd like to draw all of them I'd like to
draw them all in different colors so I
can see them quickly let's say so I'd
like a color table I don't know if we
have a color table it looks like we do
maybe we have a color table but it's not
the world's best color table because as
you can see here doesn't go up very high
one two three four five six seven eight
nine ten I'd like to get maybe at least
sixteen colors in here yeah I'm saying
to you about thirty forty fifty so I'd
like to go ahead and make it so that I
can draw these in some you know
different color right I'd like to I'd
like to have more of these and
furthermore I kind of want this color
table everywhere so I'm gonna call this
well actually you know what it is it's a
it's already even though it's debug
color table its it's already global and
it's not tied to the debug system so
that's fine right so you can see here is
we kind of have our Fulbright's here
we've got red green blue then we've got
magenta cyan and I'm sorry yellow cyan
and magenta we then have sort of the
half colors right we've got you know the
half colors here for each of our our
Fulbright's and we have all the
permutations of that and then when we
get down here we kind of start to run
out of colors at this point so I'm gonna
have to make up some new ones
maybe what we're gonna do is some more
subtle gradations there you know maybe
we can do some clothes that look maybe
more like this so if we do that that
gives us a lot more options for for how
we distribute because since there's more
of these you know I can I can kind of
run the I can run the clock out there
for a while and just say all right we've
got you know that and then we've also
got boobs maybe I'll do it keep the
order the same there got that and that
and then I've got this guy and that gets
me up to 16 don't know if those are the
best color choices maybe we can try and
pick some better ones later but you know
there we go that's talking about color
table so I want to be able to draw these
points and I want to be able to draw you
know so when I'm renting one of these
elements I want to be able to show where
all the attachment points actually works
and that will help us in the future to
like kind of debug what's going on with
it so if I drop into the entity system
here and we go down to where these are
actually being processed so inside the
piece indexes here for each piece we can
see in here whether or not this is the
the one that we're trying to highlight
right and so when we push the volume
outline on there what I can do in that
case as well is I can for each of the
none for each of its alignment points
that was set I could draw that here as a
point right I could draw a little box in
place so that's what I want to do
so let's do that let's get the align
point index and we'll just go through we
know what the bitmap is it's in here and
what I should probably do here is maybe
make that be something that happens in
here because it we don't have these
otherwise right oops
and furthermore if I'm doing two of
these
maybe this are equal here maybe that
should just kind of come up here oops so
there I've got like a little highlighted
option that I check and that way you
know as far as the hit test is concerned
I can always just ask that it you know
is it highlighted and that way we know
that if we want to change the rules for
how we do highlighting we just do it in
one place we don't have to do it
everywhere in the code so if we're
highlighting we go through all of these
so here's that bitmap I have to fit my
info I guess oh and furthermore I guess
that's have to go inside here because
it's only if we actually succeeded in
getting the bitmap we know that that
bitmap info is the thing that has the
actual line points on it right remember
that's this thing here so you want to
look at all those aligned points in
order like so and as we go through each
of those aligned points we want to get
out what the align point actually was
and draw it now we don't want to do that
because we can we can do the get type on
that we don't want to actually get the
align point in the case where the align
point is set to none because remember
everything can have 12 of them cuz we
just packed a bunch of data in there and
just you know that's how much room we
have so we just used it right everything
can have 12 of them and if you can have
12 of them it means that a lot of them
aren't gonna be set we're never gonna
have 12 like the number of attachment
points probably 2 or 3 for most things
so in that case you can see we really
want to check first you don't want to be
drawing a ton of points that don't mean
anything it just clutters the view so
here in HHA a line point ap I'm just
gonna grab the one we're talking about
in this iteration of the loop I'm gonna
ask what type it is
and I'm gonna say if that's not none at
the moment I don't need to know the type
any more than that and it may be in the
future we want to be able to stick some
information on there or something but
the moment we don't want that so I'm
just gonna say I'm gonna get the type
and if the alignment point is not none
I'm gonna draw it right I'm just gonna
draw it in there so in order to do that
I don't know like our renderer doesn't
really have the idea of points per se I
don't think so you know I'm probably
gonna have to put a cube on there
because we don't really have anything
else right it's not so much that I want
to push a cube it's just that I don't
really have anything else so I'm gonna
push a cube on there and I'm just gonna
push a really small cube on there right
I'm not gonna use any actual texture on
it so I'm just gonna take the render
group and I'm gonna use the white
texture on it so I'm not gonna actually
put that and then I'm gonna set the
color so we know what the point is gonna
be whatever the alignment point should
be so we don't know what that is till we
compute it we do know the radius is
going to be something tiny and then we
know the color Jimmy we know that color
is going to be that that sort of debug
color table stuff that I was talking
about before so let me see do we have a
get D we don't have a get debug color
call yet
it would appear take a look here
I tell you these little crackers are
good but they kind of got stuck in my
throat I need to work on my sponsorships
I need like a sponsorship for those
little oatmeal cookies there's super
delicious you know I'm saying you got to
sign those those big deals those big
advertiser deals hi I'm Casey Mira Tori
when I'm programming I like to eat you
know I don't forget their nature valley
almond buttered biscuits and sometimes
they get stuck in my throat but don't
let that stop you from buying them
because they're delicious and when you
eventually die from choking you'll be
happy that you choked on whatever they
were called all right so let's go back
in here you can see us doing the debug
color table mod thing here not a fan of
that let's just make that a call it get
should be in the first place
so in here we can just say look you know
give me a get debug color for or get
debug color three and then you can just
pass in whatever you want and so it will
index that for you
and so in this case what we want to do
is say that the result is equal to the
debug color table reference by the value
mod the however many there are right so
that way it will wrap if you pass in a
value it's too high you'll just keep
getting cycles of those sets of colors
and if you wanted a version that was
bigger so that it had the one implicitly
added so you don't have to do it
yourself you can just kind call the
debug color for one and we'll thunk for
you and append the one right since most
people are going to want to do that
anyway we can also go a little bit
further
and have you pass him what you wanted
the Alpha value to be just for maximum
convenience and then we'll set the
default value that way you can even
specify the Alpha yourself look at that
service ladies and gentlemen I mean I
tell you it doesn't get any better than
that
so get debug color for we're gonna do
the the render now I'm gonna pass that
index in so that it will draw it there
and then I want to make sure that I'm
doing that push cube properly looks like
I've got everything now I don't need any
of those other things there should be
fine so now that I get that push cube
that should draw all of those points and
the only thing I've it and it'll tell me
right or it should tell me
somewhere in here is hoops
I forgot that has to go here now there
we go
the only thing that actually is a
problem now is that if you look at the
the call here I need to compute this
thing right I got a compute where this
alignment point is relative to the
bitmap and so that's gonna be sort of a
separate pass that we'll have to do a
little bit later for now I'll do the
basics to try and make it work but we'll
talk about that in a second I
we need the alignment point to the get
type bits
there we go sorry just needed that that
doesn't want a pointer at once the
actual values so now we're just down to
this align P so I'm gonna go ahead and
take that align P and try to compute it
here so we need to figure out where it's
gonna be relative to anything and you
can see us you know here we don't really
know what we're doing right we're
passing this in to get bitmap to him and
also there's sort of stuff fortunately
for us once we have the bitmap dim we
can sort of maybe do a little bit kinda
sorta if your squint at it and don't
look too hard the get bitmap dim call
oops that's an asset rendering that get
bitmap dim call you know all it's doing
it produces those sizes when it actually
goes to fill that out you can
see it creating the Dimpy here that sort
of lets us know what's supposed to be
happening so if we want to we can kind
of abuse this call we don't even have to
re-implement ourselves we're gonna abuse
that call to generate other point
locations not necessarily how we want to
do it in the end because like I said
this code is gonna get rewritten now
that we're doing it as more of a
skeletal system we're gonna update we're
gonna upgrade that code but for the time
being right this will at least keep the
computation consistent so there's that
Dimpy coming through there that's all we
should really need to do so all we need
now is instead of passing this here what
we want to do is that ap we want to get
the P percent of the particular one in
question right so now we're passing
instead of this one here was just doing
it grabbed the first alignment we'll use
that this one's saying for each one we
want to go ahead and actually get it so
now looking that through here what's the
problem can't really read this because
it's going off the end here push cube
trying to match argument list render
group render texture v3o so what's the
problem there show me show me the call
should push cube call oh right
just need that replicate that value out
since we want forgot our cubes and not
really cubes they're actually arbitrary
boxes should probably be called push box
if we're being honest about it so anyway
what I'm doing now is I'm drawing those
points in now we can test to see if
that's working at all and it might not
be right so we'll see so there's it's
drawing a point right and I can add more
of these points here and see if they
work at all
you know we're drawing I mean I don't
know if those are being drawn the right
place they're probably not but there we
go we're actually drawing them they're
probably not because this doesn't
include the offset of the entity so we
need probably to go in here when we
actually draw it we're gonna have to do
this sort of thing right so we're
actually yeah like in fact looking at
this I think so if I'm passing in the
enemy ground plus the offset plus a
piece offset which again this is you can
see why we want to simplify this right
there's way too much stuff going on in
there the Dimpy gives us what exactly it
gives us that offset minus the alignment
stuff so that that actually looks though
that looks like it should be correct to
be honest with you right because I mean
look at how this is gonna happen we're
gonna call this we're gonna take the
ground key plus the offset plus the
piece offset right so we're actually
ah
that's gonna tell you where you would
base the bitmap right so what you
actually need here is these need to be
pluses you know I'm saying so it's not
quite so it's it's really we want the
dim align X and the dim align Y and so
so this really doesn't give us the
correct values we could cheat it though
if you look at what happens here we just
want to go out from there on the
alignment so what we could do is is
cheese out by just telling it to go than
negative right so it's like produce the
opposite sign when you do your
calculation and that's probably a
reasonable trick in this case I think
famous last words
so if I go to the point editor now let
me just see where we've got here if
that's actually the right thing I'm
trying to think about which one we're
editing to I don't really know well if
that's we should see that peg to this so
that still doesn't seem to be the
correct thing I feel like that should
have been the correct thing though
although it's being drawn
no I think that should have done it
correctly so what I'm missing something
I'm actually missing something because
that should have been okay because if we
want you know if you look at what this
is doing here it's subtracting how much
you want to align by it subtracting that
away so when you draw it I guess the
thing is you need to take where you were
drawing the head and actually put it on
there so I suppose technically the issue
there is this piece of information that
came back here right this piece Dimpy
that is actually cutting the base so
meaning the base is wherever we drew the
thing and then the align point needs to
be pegged still to that do you know what
I mean so I think it's still correct to
use the negative there it just we need
to account for the alignment that was
happening in the previous case what's
that called
Dimpy is that what's called no oh sorry
it's a bitmap damn bitmapped in there we
go so we need to pre say okay I'll set
the bitmap however you're gonna bitmap
draw up there we then need to base our
alignment points thing off of that
because otherwise it won't be pegged to
the actual movement of the bitmap and
then we want to go the opposite in right
I know it's a little mind-bending that's
graphics for you so hopefully now it's
actually correct in theory right
and it does appear to be because there
it is underneath it I would like it to
be above I want it to be raised up a
little bit because I don't want it to be
occluded so that we can actually see it
in this case so I would like to say you
know let's also in this case move it a
little bit towards the camera so I would
like to say like maybe move it
one unit towards whatever where the
camera is pointing we actually do know
where the cameras pointing because we
have a notion of the cameras axis right
you can see even here where we do that
you can see you've got inside the group
game transform we know what direction
the cameras
pointing that cameras the axe is just
pointing back towards it so we can move
it closer to the camera so it's a little
bit easier to see where that alignment
point actually is so I'm gonna go ahead
and do that as well so that should give
us a way to draw all of our alignment
points which will let us see what's
going on on any particular entity here
so if we like click on one of these guys
oops I gotta go in editor mode first if
we click on one of these guys and try to
edit it if I look I should be able to
now see alignment points for everybody
again why is that not that should have
been closer to me I'm not sure why we're
getting that sort of gross that offsets
not enough do we just make sure let me
see what's going on there because I'm
not really entirely certain
let me try moving it much closer to the
camera in this case and we'll see if
that works so there that that works
better maybe it's a little bit too much
you might say but in this case there we
go so if I'm editing the alignment
points let's say I create two of them
right so here's me changing the
alignment point on the head here's me
changing another point on that surface
right and so you know if I wanted the
nose I could place that there and then
now when I changing the base alignment
point you can see the nose stays
properly pegged to it so I think that's
now a letting us edit those pretty
cleanly right that seems pretty good to
me now there's some things I could do
here again since it's free for me to
move these close to the camera I might
move them quite a bit closer to the
camera in this case and then just make
them smaller so you know what I could do
is say like move them three units closer
to the camera and just make them very
very tiny that would allow them to
always kind of be floating up near where
we were we could instead try to do
something where we render them on a
separate path so they don't get depth
occluded I don't really want to go down
that route because it just adds a lot of
complexity of the renderer that I'm not
really sure I want right so here we go
with that there's the point that's maybe
a little too small it's go ahead and
just make that slightly larger maybe two
five let's say and
make that a little bit bigger there I
don't know if that's actually gonna get
any bigger out there it goes
there we are maybe a little bigger still
and we'll call that a day so now we have
the ability in the game to to create
arbitrary attached points and see them
which is what we needed so you know I
should be able to literally go in here
and add all of these the other thing
that I'd like to do because you can kind
of see now you know if I had all these
things let's say I just had a ton of
these points everywhere right now here's
the part so I said I was going to show
some stuff that was easy with the UI and
then I proceeded to not actually go do
anything related to the UI really
because this is all just in the renderer
now's the part I was gonna say so maybe
I don't want to render all of these and
maybe I want to see pretty clearly in
here what each of those actually what
their colors were and so what I can do
really trivially just just super simple
right because again with oops I don't
know I did that we've have another open
again when you have you UI that has a
nice immediate mode interface to it it
makes it a lot easier for me to just say
Oh anytime I wanted a button on
something I'll just make that a button I
don't have to create it I don't have to
track it I can just I don't have to use
any types in the UI system at all I can
just say look this used to be a label
it's gonna be a button now right and
that's all I would have to do so in here
I can say okay you know I want this to
be a button right and you know I don't
have a button F because I didn't write
one of those so I'm just gonna create
that myself here although I could make a
button F pretty trivial I just don't
really think it's worth it well because
you know you think about it it's just
that code right there I mean why not
save people the trouble it seems
reasonable right I mean here's that call
for the button you know what I mean
so you know why not do it I mean maybe
I'm the only person who ever calls it
but yeah maybe someone else will find it
useful seems reasonable to me all right
so what do I need here I just need dev
ID and I would need to have the enabled
flag here because I can't pass it as
default parameter since there's just who
knows what parameters come in there but
otherwise it's mine right I could also
make this enabled come back here if I
wanted to make it more consistent with
it I suppose but I'm probably I could do
that so all right let's go ahead and
just pass those through all right so
anyway let's let's go ahead and call
that button F now and I will pass the
various things in here I want to create
an editor now for this stuff where that
button can be clicked on and off and you
know I'll be honest now I think about it
even though I'm glad I made that but
enough really this is gonna be more of
an editable boolean probably so it's
probably more like more like this
editable boolean F and in this case
right I want to be able to say here's my
editable boolean and I want to edit some
boolean that turns the rendering of
these points on and off right so like I
want to be able to say like render this
on render this off do you know whatever
you want right and so again it's super
simple for me to do this because I can
always just make any of these things do
that I just I don't know whether it's
better to do it this way or not it's I
really couldn't tell you at this point I
start thinking like well maybe you know
maybe I should just do this format
string here because it just seems like
it might be getting a little long in the
tooth it's so easy to create these I'm
tempted to just do it but in this case
maybe it's better just do it this way so
that it's usable by everybody you know
it's just that right so if I wanted to
create a button here you could push I
don't know whether I want to do inedibly
or not I maybe we'll just use the button
because I want to be able trust my own
backdrop color too so I think what I'll
do is I'll just pass it here I'll just
say all right if this button gets pushed
then I'm going to toggle whether
rendering of that things on or off I'm
gonna use dev ID from pointer to create
a point here a to create an attractor
here the classifier in this case I don't
need the label text I just made the
enabled is always true pretty much well
you know what that's not true I could
make it so that ones that aren't used
are always off you know that that is one
thing I could do so what I could do is
this here could be the enabled and then
the backdrop color I'm just gonna use
get debug color for for that point index
which is the same thing I used in the
renderer to select what the point color
was right and then all I need now is I
need to actually say well so I want to
be able to click on all the buttons
there and I want something in my editor
to track I just want to know which for
each of those alignment points I want to
know I want to know whether they're like
on or off right so I want like something
like draw a line point you know I I want
something like this and I want that to
be set based on how many there are so
you know for let's see here where is it
it's not it
so in file formats I just in here want
to be able to say however many of there
are of these right so I want like an
array count of these and unfortunately
it's kind of nasty because you can't
it's sometimes difficult to reach in
there and get one of those so you kind
of have to do ridiculous stuff like this
to it to be able to actually access
those things so I'd have to think about
how to actually get the array count out
of that thing I might just do this
and then it can just mirror it like that
right so in here I'm going to say look
that's how many of those we're gonna
have and then inside the in-game editor
I can just you know keep my own list of
those so I can just feel like alright
you know for each of these and we'll
just set them all to true so then when
we actually go to run this I'm sorry
when we actually go to compile this
right the only thing we're really
missing here
whoops format string now I guess I could
call this point name or something temp
is not a very good name for that um we
need a pointer here and we need to know
what we're actually going to be toggling
in this case right we need to know what
the what the difference what the render
difference was here and so what I want
to do is I want to snap a copy of that I
mean I want to snap a pointer to that
boolean because this is the thing that
I'm editing right I'm editing whichever
the point whichever one of these points
here whichever one of those billions I'm
talking about for this particular point
that's the like point toggle that's the
like draw toggle for this point so I
know that I want to I well I know that
that's the thing that I want to edit I
probably want to draw the color
differently so if it's enabled it will
drawn its color if it's not it will just
draw it as like a generic like dark
color or something I don't know what the
color should be but something like that
and then if you click on it the draw
chocolate just gets get swapped right
and so that's really all I need to do
don't ask me why I left that boolean
line in there it doesn't belong there at
all and so now I just created an array
of edit of those things to be editable
and when I go in here to actually edit
them
now when we look at that you can see
that it's actually each of those each of
each of those things is available for me
to click on right and so I just wanted
to emphasize did you see how like really
I went in and added the button F because
I thought maybe that would be convenient
but we ended up not needing it so
literally I didn't have to interact with
the UI system at all I didn't have to
create anything I didn't have to store
any pointers I didn't have to set any
user data I didn't have to respond to
any events I had to do anything I wrote
one little if statement and I was able
to make these match the colors of the
things their control the data I actually
wanted to control which was array of
boolean that I made and put where I
wanted to I never have to worry about
them being out of sync they're always in
sync they cannot they literally cannot
be out of sync right every last thing
was perfect and it was three or four
lines of code in QT you'd be inheriting
from stuff you would add to like go have
some custom color thing you'd be setting
things back and forth and connecting
it's like show me the thing where that's
three lines of code in QT and then I'll
start thinking that those are okay
interfaces like they're not right this
is the entirety of the code that got
written this this right there
technically it's one line of code right
to do all of that anyway so one line of
code and mind you would be one line of
kony if there were an infinite number of
buttons and not figuratively indifferent
of buttons if there were literally an
infinite number of buttons it would
still be one line of code right because
you know it would only be calling it for
the ones you actually wanted at that
given time anyway enough bagging on QT
and other badly designed it yet so in
here right when we asked for the button
and we toggle it you can see in here I'm
I'm not III I don't want to ever draw it
if it's not set in the first place so
I think I probably want here too you
know in this we're we're doing the
enabled thing I think I want that to be
the other way round meaning I
accidentally said it so that it I told
it that it was enabled only when it was
set to none what I actually want is I
want and enabled when it's not set to
none right so that was just a miss type
on my part so this is what I actually
want so only ones that are set get the
color and the other ones can't be turned
on or off anyway
that way you only see those ones right
in this case and that allows me to turn
them on and off I don't know that I'll
be doing that much but it's a very least
I wanted the colors there so I figured
while I was setting the color I might as
well of made it clickable because it's
no more work for me because then I can
say oh I don't want to see these I'm
just looking at just those or I don't
know
you know don't ask me why I just did
just have how I did it we probably will
never click that button but it can't
hurt to have it right so all right so
now that's done and what I do need to do
now is I need to figure out some way
I've got the rendering and here is that
rendering kind of wasp oops not that
that rendering wants to be set in here
to kind of correlate back right like
each I don't want to draw this if it's
the drawing is is not enabled you know
what I mean
so I need something here that will allow
me to access that piece of information
now I have the hit test so that's
probably a good place for that so what I
want to do is add into my game editor I
want like a function here that I can
call
that's like should draw a line point and
it will pass the hit test and through
some crazy set of gyrations we don't
care what it is if I pass you in
alignment point index you have to tell
me if I should be drawing that alignment
point index right and so in here I will
call that now and say you know should
draw a line point and so if it's none I
won't draw it and if it's a turn
off I also yeah that's another case in
which I won't draw it right and so now I
have to figure out a way to actually
implement that function right because
it's not defined now and so I need to
define Eid to make a route I need to
make a way to get back to from the hip
test I need to be able to do like
something like this right I need to be
able to loops so I need to be able to
say like the result is false if the AP
index is in the array bounds of this
thing right so I just want to say look
if I can just give him back whatever
that you know whatever the alignment
point toggle was in this case so I need
to do something like this the hit test
at the moment doesn't get back to the
editor but you know what it's pretty
easy for it to do so and I don't mind if
it does so the in-game editor cure can
be there and then people can ask that
question in the editable hit test I will
have to initialize it right if I just
ran it now we'd crash because that hit
test would not actually be able to do so
let me also predefined that okay so if I
was to run now we just crashed because
that thing's at zero so as soon as I go
to actually ask that question you can
see we get we get biffed right there
right so I need to set that when we
actually create the editable hit test
hit test so inside the begin hit test
call when we create one of these we need
to set it up so that it can always get
back to the editor that created it and
ask that question other than that I
think we're pretty much done so that
gives us the entirety of that particular
visualization like I said which was the
first one that I wanted the ability to
see all the hit test points that were
involved okay and so now let's just make
sure it works you know here's all our
limit points as we edit them and I can
turn them on and off in this case and
they work just fine right so I think
that's all good we've accomplished what
we want to accomplish there and we don't
really have to do anything else right
that's all yeah that all works pretty
well uh you know I just realized moving
it along the camera Z isn't what I
actually meant to do
I meant to move it along the vector
between it and the camera let me just
take this moment I know that now we're
supposed to be doing that let me just
take this one to explain what I'm saying
so what I wanted to do is I wanted to
see where on the bitmap these points are
but I didn't want to add a special
purpose thing to the renderer to draw
them without the depth testing on right
I didn't want that to I didn't want to
complicate our renderer to do that since
this is only for the debug tools and the
debug editing right so what I wanted to
do was just move them closer to the
camera so they would just sort that way
to begin with right now there's two ways
I could have done that I didn't think
about the other way because you know I
just wasn't thinking I guess and I also
don't know whether that way exists
inside push cube we have a way of
actually biasing our death coordinate
that's the W we we made our W actually
be able to do that that's probably what
I should have done that's a much easier
way of solving this problem and so maybe
I'll go do that but what I was gonna say
I just wanted to illustrate you can see
when I move around those other points
change their location relative to the
head the reason is because of the
perspective effect they're right they're
actually hovering up there and what I
kind of brain farted on there was that
if you want things to stay in the same
place
relative to projection you need to move
things along the line from the point in
question to the camera position not
along the camera Z which is actually a
line that's just perpendicular to the
screen
right one is actually the line along the
projection and that will keep them in
the same place and the other is a is a
perpendicular line to the screen which
won't
and so I screwed that up that was wrong
if I want to fix that problem is when we
go in here so if I look at push cube
right and we look at what's happening in
there the Z bias it goes into the the
peeper ammeter here but we're only able
to pass a an abstract P there we're not
really able to set a Z bias that right
there is where the Z bias would go and
so if we wanted to we could add the
ability to specify that out maybe I'll
just do that because why not and then
that solves our problem without me
having to actually compute that line
which is trivial to do but why bother so
here's that Z bias and I'm gonna set
that equal to zero so that most people
who push a cube never see it I'm then
I'm gonna go ahead and go back into the
entity renderer
and then when we're pushing this cube
down I'm gonna set that Z bias so rather
than doing this which moves it I'm gonna
use the fact that we have a Z bias and
I'm gonna go ahead and set it and I'm
gonna set it to something very high so I
essentially want to move it quite a bit
closer to the camera like way way closer
to the camera right I don't know offhand
unfortunately just trying to think
through here I don't remember what we
were passing here so we need default
cube layout 0 for the admission 0 for
the light source so it looks like that
so now hopefully we can still draw these
things and you know I'll be honest I
don't see them so I guess it did not
work which is unfortunate
so I'm assuming if I set that to zero it
would meaning they will get drawn right
yeah there they are
I want to see so if I set this to Tendo
they presumably don't draw no they do so
I guess that ten is just not enough is
that all the problem is it just that we
need more Z bias than ten is that all
well now they're not yeah now so I don't
know that doesn't look like it works for
some reason I'm have to go look and see
why because I'm not sure how we compute
that Z bias that's the only thing so I'm
kind of just like blindly setting values
and seeing if they work which is usually
not a good plan but since I wasn't
really planning on looking at this
particular thing maybe it does it and I
don't know does it go the other way like
is it supposed to be more like that
I'm gonna have to go look at the shader
applying the guessing is not work does
not work so I'm guessing that that must
bias the Z and a whit let's look at this
look at the shader because now I just I
just don't know and now I'm curious so
if we go to the OpenGL shader what do we
what are we actually doing there with
that parameter so if I go to busy by a
shader I think is what would be being
called herbs OpenGL out there here's the
Z bias program so you can see the Z bias
here it grabs the the W value from that
and then what does it actually do
it creates a modified Z and sets that it
takes the it takes the vertex scene it
just adds the Z bias to the actual Z
value what why do we do that what is the
okay so we're reduced asleep at the
switch here because look we load the Z
bias out and then we do the transform
but why wouldn't we be applying that
after the transform right I mean is
there really I mean okay so I guess if
you really want to think of it that way
it makes some sense to apply it before
hand because you if you're trying to
make sure that it only makes things
appear to be standing up more tall than
it should only ever work in the Z
direction I mean that's true but is that
really necessary I mean is that the best
way to do that because you know does
that actually produce better results
than if you just added the Z into the Z
you know once you actually transfer them
if you just offset the Z by a certain
amount
hmm either-or looking at that I don't
see why this wasn't working right
because if the Z vertex is Z value
actually just gets added directly like
that it should just work
after the transform right look I don't
see where the problem comes in here
because after you do the GL position and
you you know you take the modified Z
where you've transformed both things and
then you take the modified Z for use
with the depth buffer that should have
just worked and I don't know why it
wouldn't have
I guess one reason is maybe we got too
far so it it clipped itself off I mean
that could be meaning if that was the
case then you know you just needed this
to be something else it just needed to
be a different value that is actually
within those bounds I don't know we can
try it I don't think that's it so that's
interesting
there you see it working just fine right
but not in this mode so not once the
camera is locked but I have no idea why
it must be because of the way we're
computing the Z depth or something I
mean look at that that actually works
great but go like that and suddenly it's
broken
and even if you know even if I get to
almost exactly the same position I mean
that's very close right
I mean that's almost imperceptibly close
that's super close so something about
the Z bias do we like turn off Z bias or
something when we're in that camera mode
like what's going on there right it
could be because of the Z range so one
difference is you know in the if we look
at what happens in the renderer I
believe the Z ranges are different in
those two cases I guess you know in here
we've got a bunch of settings for like
ranges of things and the near clip plane
far clip plane I guess are things that
are actually getting set there you can
see the near claim far clipping it
passed in here so if I actually go to
world man look at what those are you can
see that if the FARC if we're in debug
camera mode the far clip plane is like
set to a drastically different groups
different value in that case and the
near clip plane is too so in debug
camera mode so I guess what's happening
is in debug camera mode the near clip
plane is set in so so you can see it's
set at 3 so if the camera was like 8
above wow so basically this is getting
clipped by that clip plane so it's like
it has to be less than 5 because 5 is
exactly where it would have been clipped
oh my lord that is a mind bender but
okay so it was getting clipped off the
near clip playing because the near clip
planes actually pretty far out in the
game camera Wow folks graphics always
too complicated for its own good so
in this case you can see now that it
stays pegged pretty well right and it it
will drift a little because remember the
head itself is tilted a little so you
can never get it quite exactly right
I could myself account for the tilt and
if I wanted to do that you know it would
be pretty straight forward it's just we
have to first take the next step that we
were going to take out here in order to
do it and that is you can see here we
create x and y axes that are actually
bent from what the at ones in the world
are and so as we pull those out here
which is exactly what I wanted to do for
the actual usage of these points that's
the piece transform part here was gonna
be about as we move those out we'll be
able to really peg it exactly so that's
that's just a better thing all around
because that will allow us to have
perfect pegging in a second here after
we do that part of it but before I do
that and we may have to wait to the next
stream for that because I got other
stuff I got to do right now what I do
want to do is just get back to the
editor side of things there's one more
thing we need and that is that when we
pick something in the asset editor
remember I picked this I've got this
problem I go to a senator I pick it
what's going on here which one am i
editing I'm editing the head I'm hitting
the body I can switch the alignment
point editor but I can't control which
one of those two things I'm editing
that's not what I want I want instead to
be able to pick out of the asset which
one of those I've got how do we do that
we need to add a secondary thing that
allows us to look at some of the things
that were clicked on and pick them
separately so one of the things we
didn't do in our UI is have a bitmap
picker it should be pretty easy actually
for us to add exactly such a thing to
our UI system because it's pretty
flexible so if I just go ahead and add
that in it will allow us to do a pic
probably pretty easily so let's say I go
into our editor I can probably add the
picking pretty trivially honestly I can
probably do something where it actually
is what's room in I'm looking for it's
probably pretty easy to actually add
this editor without seeing the bitmap so
I could just add a little nubs to pick
them I'll do that first and then after
we have that working properly I'll go in
and add a widget that actually just
shows the bitmap itself because that's
easier for us to use and shouldn't be
actually very hard to edit because like
I said if you make a good UI API to
begin with it's pretty easy to just tack
stuff on to it so let's go ahead and do
that inside the asset editor what we
have here is editing an active asset
what we want to be able to do is switch
which active asset we're actually
editing and so the way we can do that is
back out here inside update and render
we've got this notion of like you know
undo and redo right so you know in here
where we're actually editing this thing
so I'm in the editor and I picked this
we kind of just have this understanding
right here of what's going on we don't
have any narrowing any selection stuff
let's add some selection stuff okay
so what I'm going to do here is say
let's let's add some stuff here let's
make a row for this let's have something
that shows the selection all the things
in the selection and so the way I can do
that is just do a for I loop over what I
already sort of set up to do this which
is inside the in-game editor we have
this notion of an active group
what's an active group well an active
group is the thing that has almost
exactly what I wanted it's got a number
of assets in it and I can loop through
which ones they are right that's exactly
what I wanted so in here what I can do
is say okay let's go through each of
those so for the editable asset group I
can just say what's the asset index it's
actually an asset index index if you
think about it right because we're
actually indexing into a list of access
indices so it's an asset index index for
each of the ones in there actually it's
not in a rake count it's for that active
group editor active grip
group there it is ask count for each of
those that we have in our pick I can
draw something that lets me sub select
out of those whichever one I wanted
right so what I can do there is say well
for each of those you know if if they
push a button that's whatever you know I
don't know it's gonna be a bitmap button
at some point probably right if I pick
this bitmap button then I I switch to
that asset that's that's all we're
talking about here so I've got an
editable asset in each of these cases so
all I want to do here is say this is the
editable asset if I go to this active
group and pick out one of the assets so
there's the asset index index when I get
that editable asset out what I can do is
say look here's the button it's gonna be
this asset index and this asset ID those
are actually the things that are going
to get picked here and what I can do is
you know we already know we already know
what that looks like so insight editor
interact we already had a thing that was
gonna do that so in here you did those
pics and whatever and I don't remember
exactly how we did it it's here right
yeah so you can see it here let's just
pull that out let's make these be
something a little bit more specific
there so like this whole thing probably
should come out and we'll look at how
that's going to go in a second so what
I'm gonna do here is I'm gonna instead
of doing what we're doing before I'm
gonna say editor active group equals
editor hot group so when you pick an
asset we're actually gonna do this and
then we're going to do inside there is
set the asset index to whatever the
first one was right
so I'm going to do like I guess I can
still do this now that I think about it
all I want to do here is make this a
little bit more systemic so I'm gonna
say look this is the one it's this one
right that's the one you should use and
so then I'm just gonna pull this out
here and maybe I'll even do this
so essentially you can to clear it you
just pass zero right so then I've got to
think here this is going to be setactive
asset it's gonna take the in-game editor
and it's gonna take the asset you
actually wanted me to select like that
makes sense and then so in here we would
just say look if there if you pass me a
valid one I'm gonna use it but if you
didn't I'm just gonna clear it makes
sense so then we just have this is now
something that's a utility function so I
can make that happen wherever it wants
to so in here if someone was gonna
select something I can just say set
active asset and I can say this is the
asset to select so now all I need is a
way of actually drawing the various
assets I don't really have a way of
doing that right now I'm just gonna draw
a blank thing instead and that way I can
switch between them just as a test and
then we'll make the bitmap thing that
actually lets us you know do that
specific selection so now when we go
into the button code I just have to
actually sit here there we go I just
have to actually pass the rest of the
stuff I need a dev ID here I can do that
probably by just using the actual dev ID
of the asset itself I'm guessing
don't think there's any reason why I
couldn't do that maybe there is maybe
there is enough to think about that a
little bit later the classifier in this
case good I don't know just be you know
the Edit asset there we go
because that's unique in this case and
so then we've got label text and enabled
there's the label text the enabling is
always gonna be true the background
color can stay as it is and then we just
we need to change this to be a bitmap in
the future and so we're gonna work on
that in a second here so I think that's
everything we would need to be able to
sub pick assets inside there and so now
you know when we select one of these we
should have a thing that shows how many
assets were under the cursor there and
be able to actually pick between them so
you know we can we should be able to
select different assets in this case you
can even see like if we look there was a
another asset that it was picked it
probably isn't is that really an asset
that's probably just a room which
doesn't probably have anything in it
right but you can see now when I pick so
let's say you know let's say I picked
down that line right so like the pic was
like right there I need to make it so it
doesn't actually reap it on camera
that's probably something I should do
but you can see when we pick down that
line you can see now I can select
everything that was down that line just
by just by doing this right which is
pretty awesome you know what I mean
so now anything that's under the cursor
all the way down like 16 deep we will at
sixteen eight so eight deep down we can
you know get hey probably that's the
answer right there one two three four
five is in me so everything down there
we can now pick outside of the UI in a
little like convenient little picker
that's exactly what we want in that case
because that allows us to really cleanly
pick between these the thing that's not
so clean about it is we can't tell who
we're talking about that's why I say
let's go ahead and add something that
actually shows a little tiny little bit
map don't
big just a little bit map in there that
we can then use as the differentiator
okay so in order to do that what we need
is some way of actually looking up with
the bitmap is fortunately we have an
asset index in this case so we should be
able to actually look it up in the same
way we were looking it up here so we
should be able to do something that
looks essentially like this outside in
the selector and then we just do it for
all of the things that run to there
instead of only the active one just in
this one case so we go ahead and get the
assets we see if those assets are
bitmaps and if they are we can display
them here and we can use the actual
bitmap itself as the way of displaying
what's going on right so we know we've
got to get bitmap call that we can use
to actually get the bitmap after the
fact and then we'll actually do that
here so I'll bitmap loaded bitmap equals
get bitmap right assets bitmap index
which is whatever the asset index is so
I think that's all there is to it
and so when we now come in here like
that I just need to pass this bitmap in
and along with that a notion of the
signs so like how tall the bitmap should
be I don't know how tall it should be
let's just say we're gonna draw it in a
64 by 64 square so I'm gonna say that's
the width and the height of what I want
the actual blocks to be and so I'm gonna
be able to say bitmap button this is
some bla bla bla bla bla that's gonna
happen here and then I've got some
things like highlight or active it
should always be active the highlight
should only be true if this is the
active asset and I know that that's true
because I can look to see whether this
is the one that's being edited at any
given time by saying well if the Edit
assets asset index equals the editors
a Civ asset index then I know that this
should be highlighted right I does that
make sense so you know something like
this that should be everything that I
need that's it for the for the u.s. to
have it so nicely actually implement
that in the actual bitmap system itself
as we go now I don't actually
necessarily in this case need to
actually load the bitmap so I could make
it so that that passes instead of a
bitmap pointer it could just pass the
bitmap ID right I don't really know
which one of those it should be if I
look at what happens the code here
I could probably simplify this quite a
bit if I just didn't have to do that
right so another way of looking at it
would be to say well maybe it would just
be nice if we could do this
you know um because that simplifies the
code gorilla and then that goes into the
bitmap button code which is better
because that code can then you know be
shared across anyone who wants to pop up
a bitmap for a button for some reason so
that seems a little bit better on the
whole so I'm gonna go ahead and make the
extraordinary claim that that's what
should happen I realize that maybe I'm a
little far afield there but okay so if
we do bitmap button and then I do WI
layout here and we want all the same
stuff basically so it's you know it's
the same code in terms of what's going
on but instead of the care label text
there I'm just gonna do a bitmap ID okay
we then need to know the width and the
height we whoops that actually came
first and then we need like enabled and
and highlighted so there's our code for
bitmap button subtly speaking we want to
do this right so we want to do basically
the same stuff here but this part has to
trick change rather dramatically so it's
only like that like the very preamble
part that's really gonna be what we're
using here and so we need to kind of
rewrite this part to be to work with a
bitmap right so if I go up and look at
what goes on in here just looking at
what we've got
yeah like you know this we're gonna have
to do basically this stuff and it's
gonna have to change pretty dramatically
so we want that as our basic idea of
what's going on in the code but it's got
to be modified quite a bit so we'll
start by saying ok let's get started
here in terms of looking at the UI
itself we really just need the assets
pointer here so it's really the render
group that we care about not so much the
UI you can see what's going on here
we're not really using that UI as much
well we kind of are so we'll keep that
out but we really want this we want the
render group to be out here so that's
coming out here we don't have a text
bounds we know what the rectangle is
because we've been told what the
rectangle is so we know that we've got a
rectangle min/max essentially that looks
something like this
you know I'm saying saying there so we
know we've got something like this and
then we've got this dimension stuff here
which is which could be sort of written
off the same thing as well right so we
can do that but if you look at what it
actually needs in this case the height
part so it's it's really the dim could
really be expressed I guess more
succinctly this way right so that gets
our dim that's how much space we're
going to take out we ask for that and we
get back how big it should be this all
probably works just fine we've got the
backdrop color here that we wouldn't
have because there really wouldn't be a
backup color per se so this is probably
a
an on a non thing because we probably
want to do a rect outline of this thing
when it's selected and then just nothing
but it's not I guess I don't know that's
hard to say maybe what we really should
do is just pass one in here and then
have that lighted up or not that I
really just don't know but either/or
once we actually get here what we want
to do is we want to do a push bitmap
call to actually draw this thing so
let's just start with that and then
we'll play around with the rendering a
little bit later on so maybe like we
just don't do this yet and we say like
yeah not gonna happen
so in here we'll do the the push bitmap
let me look inside the renderer for how
we want to do that where is our where is
our drawing is it push up right and push
bright so it looks like we more or less
want this right that will give us this
will give us what we're looking for in
terms of a quad that's constructed it's
not necessarily exactly how we might
have wanted the construction to be but
it's good enough so here we need to get
that renderer texture so we need that to
have been queued up so we'll have to do
that here so that's I'm gonna have to do
the center P is pretty easy it's gonna
be whatever the element bounds of the
center of the elements bounds are so
it's really just gonna be this and we
know that we don't care so much about
our Z location here I guess it's the UI
text transform is where it should be
roughly because it's on the text layer
so I believe it's that is what we would
want our Z value to be you know what I
mean
the size is just the elements bounds the
color is going to be well all
the rest of this stuff is the same so we
don't really need to worry about into
the rest of that I think that's just
that's just all there is I think the
menu v-max UV we could pull out we could
if we wanted to we could actually use
the width and height to pull that out
into the menu v-max UV I'm gonna leave
it this way for now because I actually
think it would be nice throughout the
see how much of the texture our stuff is
occupying you know unfortunately
sometimes it's not very much and so I'm
gonna leave that for now but we could
change that later all right so the next
thing we have to do is actually
implement that that sort of ability to
get the bitmap out so that's really just
gonna be this we're just gonna try and
get that bitmap ID if we get it we're
gonna call push sprite and we're going
to go ahead and and pass the the bitmap
texture handle texture handle I think I
think it's dr. handle and then if we
can't we're gonna ask the asset ID to
load it we're not gonna set them missing
bounds because this is an editor it
shouldn't ever it shouldn't ever cause a
delay in rendering the border in this
case I'm not sure that we know what that
is because normally that gets passed in
as layout thickness so I guess in this
case I'm just gonna say it's always the
layout thickness you can't really change
it
maybe we should allow you to change it
but in this case I'm not going to if we
pull this code out into a separate pass
then we would the item interaction here
is just the interaction specified
the group in this case is the render
group v2 v3 Z is that all was there
another one push right rectangle 2 2 v2
so in this case it wants that alright so
we'll see in theory that should have
given us something I may have messed
something up there but that should give
us the ability to have bitmap buttons
maybe hopefully possibly who knows Hey
look it worked really well so there's
all of our there's all of our sprites
the problem is like I said we're just
doing 0 to 1 so we're just seeing
whatever the texture had in it in its
entirety which may not really be the
best thing to show there but you know
for the moment it's fine with me and so
those are all the things you know that
we that are poked behind the cursor so
if I actually go here and and I can
drill down on that line you can see like
each of these each of those is all the
same right like there you go
because each of those is is one of the
the same kind of tiles you know what I
mean and so if I pick something that's
more kind of goes through a couple
different things then you can kind of
see ok so there was a floor there was
the cat there was the old torso on the
guy there was the another floor tile
there was the right you know cat tile
there's the wall let's pick through
there so now what I really need to do is
I need to find some way in here of
I want to find some way in there of
picking like like drawing a like making
it clear whether it's selectable and if
it's selectable it wasn't selected you
know what I mean so I want in there to
have something like when you select this
thing you know if it's highlighted then
we push a rect outline on there I guess
that does something and I don't know
what that something is but like you know
it's just I don't know maybe you can set
that color probably I'm guessing but you
know something like that so you know
when you're in here I want to be able to
see that I can't really see it probably
because it's not thick enough I would
also like that to be afterwards so it
has preference so that's gonna be what
are our transforms inside WI I don't
actually even remember to be honest with
you there's a couple different sorting
layers that we were using to keep things
out so we've got the text transform
shadow transform UI transfer and backing
transform tool tip transform I'm not
sure which of those really we want I
guess I'll say you Y transform what are
those what are those set to
so I guess I might want this to be text
transform and this to be UI transform
I don't know so we'll just make that do
what it does and we'll see what has to
happen afterwards all right so how do I
set a thickness anyone now there we go
so I want this to be reasonably thick
selector maybe that
seems pretty good right so now I can set
like okay you know I want why does that
why does that go away what is this
wonder what is this something oh that's
the room so I wonder if I should
double-check
maybe I should still ask if the asset is
a bitmap when I pointed out here mmm
because maybe we do want to just look if
there's not a well maybe not all right
don't know so I'm going to go ahead and
say look let's see if this works
suppose I want to edit the alignment
points on these two things so the cat
right so I can pick the cat here and I
can just say you know here's the
alignment of the cat in general right
and you know maybe I just want that to
be whatever that is I don't know what it
wants to be but then I can add another
alignment point there and say look
that's the base of the neck it's going
to be like right there right and now
that set up properly I flip back to here
I say that's the default alignment on
this thing and so that makes it pretty
easy for me to edit like I mean that was
trivial and that's great so and then I
can go back and save it when we
implement the save feature or whatever
right so that seems pretty good and so
now those things just have to actually
get used we're at the five-minute
warning now so I guess I'll leave it
there for today that's pretty good I'm
pretty happy with where we got on that
and we'll go from there
can I give QA no I can't so I've got to
do what we've learned is I have to do QA
in pound hero only right there it goes
all right any questions on that does
anyone have any questions on that
on what we just did questions concerns
does anyone have them
does anybody have oh I like that feature
that's kind of fun you can see what the
top of the scope was by mousing over
that's nice don't know that I'd ever use
it how come a-near clip-point is set at
five and not closer it's not set at five
set three but the reason it's set closer
is because we wanted to eliminate things
that were in front of the like like
upper floors and stuff so that's just
what we had picked because of how we
decided to construct things you know
what I mean
so that our alpha fading clips that out
there if that makes sense
we'll be showing linkages between
alignment points there are no linkages
between alignment points at the moment
if that makes sense
oh are you saying I'm sorry not know
what you're saying are you saying you
want to draw the just the entity I'm not
sure let me say a couple things about
that and maybe answer the question maybe
doesn't our art assets do not have the
concept of linkages between alignment
points they just have alignment points
entities specify when they are created
which alignment points they want to use
to line themselves up but it's per
entity so every entity can be
constructed differently if it wants to
be so there is no way to edit that it's
intentionally in the procedural
generation side of things so we don't
need to draw the linkages between
alignment points because you can't edit
that that's strictly in the game the
only thing that the art asset is allowed
to specify is if someone wanted to use a
particular type of alignment point which
one would it be right so that's why
we're not drawing that does that make
sense
what would you say is crappy in your
current implementation about the I am
GUI a lot of stuff is crappy about it
right because we wanted to minimize the
amount of time that we spent
implementing the actual back end right
we just wanted something simple there
and so it's got a lot of hacky stuff in
it right it was just whatever is the
fastest is what's in there
you know so if you were actually trying
you know let's say you're trying to
compete with QT right and you want to
make an eye on GUI that's supposed to do
that you need a lot you need to spend a
lot more time on like your widget
rendering and how the layout works like
you need to put a lot more code in there
right because a lot of that stuff has
nothing to do with the user interface
that's just it's just polished right and
so all of that work would have to be
done and it's not done and ours is
crappy right it doesn't look very nice
you know and so yeah you know you need a
lot of that to be done if that makes
sense
your visual design and typography
exactly the things I was complaining
about on the pre stream about how CSS is
terrible all of the stuff that CSS sucks
that we need to do
a good version of that to make a nice
beautifully laid out properly aligned
fonts nice edging nice anti-aliasing
like all that stuff that's all real work
that has to be done now granted QT
doesn't do most of that either booty
looks like crap most the time too but if
you were actually wanting a really good
GUI system whether it's I am or not
that's a lot of work that has to go into
there's a lot of graphical polish that
has to go in there would it be useful to
add mouse wrapping like in blender so
you can drag past the end of the scream
and ending values sure if this was like
again that's exactly what I mean by
polished that if you were trying to make
a very polished editor sure you would do
that we probably wouldn't spend time on
that because it's not really super
necessary
okay not seeing anymore questions
so maybe we can wrap things up early
it's an overhead when checking for if
button when doing that every frame well
so two things about that first of all no
not really and the reason for that is
because if you're drawing something then
it's usually comparatively free to check
the boundaries of its rectangle which is
all the if button does so in terms of
overhead it is an overhead that
literally can't really show up on your
profile now the larger question which is
isn't it an overhead to have to redraw
the entire frame every time yes but
that's not a restriction of I am GUI you
can easily just call I am GUI once and
just you know save the results into a
bitmap and only call it again when the
user actually tries to click on it right
if that's what you want now granted if
you do that then you can't make you eyes
that respond to Mouse moves in complex
ways which is one of the powers of I am
GUI so I usually advocate just draw the
whole thing every frame when someone's
actually interacting with it because
then you can be much more responsive and
everything can change as the user moves
it around which is nicer so I prefer
that but if you just art maybe you're
just concerned in minimizing the amount
of battery usage or something like that
then you can trivially just not call the
UI to be redrawn or edited or anything
until they actually click the button
right
will you ever make an emote or just
steal one of John's so you'll have to
forgive me I don't know what that means
am I allowed to make new emotes I is
that something I can do and if so how do
I do it like I don't I you'll just
forgive me I don't know what that is I
stream on Twitch but I'm not much of a
twitch streamer if that makes any sense
don't forget to Like and subscribe
thanks for the 12-month sub and so on
but I literally don't know where that is
like I'm looking now and I have I have
no idea where is there a thing for that
on the dashboard or something
what's the reason you I use this loses
state when you HOT load so the reason
for that is it it doesn't always right
but sometimes it does and the answer
that is one of the ways that you make
creating the UI easier on the user is by
letting them use things like transient
pointers to identify things so for
example if you look at where we set
things up when we're using the UI you
can see inside dev ID from pointer you
can see where we're passing transient
pointers sometimes right you see that
how that's happening
those transient pointers are only valid
in the code as it was loaded originally
when we do hot code reloading some of
those things may get reallocated or
moved around like string pointers for
example and now they don't refer to the
same thing anymore so the UI system when
it goes oh he's not he hasn't selected
that thing anymore it's like you
selected some different thing or
whatever right that's where the state
gets lost does that make sense and so
you could make it so that it preserve
the state but I don't really want that
because I don't care that much about
preserving the state during hot load of
the editor so I don't want to force the
people using and by that I mean me but
the user of the editor I want them to
still be able to just use pointers
because it's just more convenient for
them to do it means they don't have to
introduce IDs and stuff that they don't
want can you play around with it a
little more well I mean I'm happy to do
so but I think I did all the things that
we could do by the way we really need
that these two guys not snapping to the
corners is really driving me nuts I got
to fix that one of these one of these
days I'm happy to play we ran with it a
little bit more I just don't know what
it actually is that you would want me to
do I mean here let's add some points we
can move them around
I guess in here somewhere
and then in here I could I mean what I
could do right
it's oops I moved that to the wrong
place we have undo so I can undo it
right
I can even undo the creation of those
things right so that all works real well
so we have undoing redo which is good
you know I can pick some of these other
things and the you know the selection
isn't undo isn't an undo or redo so
that's properly separated out between
the two you know I can and I don't know
that's some more in here I don't know so
I mean yeah I can play with it but I
don't have much you know I I don't
really have any it doesn't do anything
other than what you already saw me
program it to do so with software
rendering you can do hot regions that
are redrawn when the user fiddles with
UI elements can you anything similar be
done with hardware rendering yes
certainly so what you need to do if you
want to have hot regions that are
redrawn only when the user fiddles with
the UI elements and you've already seen
me implement the code necessary to do
this actually inside the renderer so
we've already done stuff like this is
you just create so remember even in here
is currently stands right now we don't
render directly to the back buffer when
you've rendered to intermediate buffers
which then get composed to make the back
buffer so if what you wanted to do was
eliminate redraw on the UI and so you
would only redraw when the user fills
with UI elements what you would do is
create one more back buffer that back
buffer would hold lease the UI and every
time you draw UI you draw it into the
back buffer for the UI then that gets
composed onto the game right and you've
already seen me do all those things all
those things we already did inside the
renderer so you can go back and watch me
do those we did them so we just add one
more back buffer that's the UI state and
then what we do is we never clear that
buffer right so we just draw the UI into
it and we leave it
it is and then whenever we want to
redraw a piece of the UI we clear just
the rectangle that occupies that part of
the UI and then we redraw with the with
a scissor region just set to that we
just redraw that part so it's very very
simple actually so the finish became
sick with almond milk no so you just key
you get an ax to draw something cute
like a cat and then you upload the kitty
image to twitch
well yeah but where is there somewhere I
guess I can just search online for how
do I upload emotes you know what here
I'll just I'll just send an email and
you know I'll I'll try to figure that
out
so here's an email I will add Anna and
myself and we will try to figure that
out but yeah I mean so the reason I have
not done that is because I literally
just don't know anything about it so
I'll go search for like how do I upload
whatever and we'll go from there let me
see if I have any more questions
[Music]
a page on the twitch dashboard huh all
right I don't know where it is
maybe it's under like clips or
collections or something I don't know
I'll just I'll find it I'm sure there's
a tutorial okay I'll just search the
tutorial I'm sure there's a tutorial
somewhere is it costly to re update the
image to the GPU so I think this is a
question on so it says what is the best
way to add an add to an atlas map is it
costly to reuptake the image on the GPU
the answer is no it's usually not costly
and the way that you do it is you in
OpenGL you use text sub image to update
just that sub image we're doing almost
exactly the same thing just with a
texture array so instead of calling text
sub image 3d you would call text sub
image 2d makes sense so that's really
all there is to it
what do you think about a tree based on
do system where you do not lose the redo
state when changing after undo but
create branches I think they're cool but
the interface to an artist can be pretty
confusing so you have to the the thing I
would encourage there is to think about
how are you going to expose it in a way
that the artist won't get really
confused about what you're showing them
right because remember an artist isn't a
programmer they don't know about things
like tree based change representation
right they just look at what the app
shows them and they learn to use that
and so you have to present it in a way
that they're going to let go oh I get it
right and you certainly could do that by
showing like a timeline that has
branches on it or something but then you
have to ask to have also is it worth it
like art is the value that they're
getting out of having that extra UI
that's kind of onerous and overbearing
is it worth it right and maybe the
answer is yes me the answer is no just
something to think about
so thoughts on ML will your game use it
M L the programming language maybe you
mean machine learning I guess what I
would say is regardless of whether you
mean ml the programming language for a
machine learning the concept the answer
is still no the game won't use it so I
guess I can answer the question even
without knowing what the question is you
said you wouldn't use the internet at
work I'd like to do that but I'm missing
MSDN on the GL document and the GL
documentation what do you do when you
don't have this information locally
available asking because I prefer not to
have the internet brown coding to things
you can do number one for GL
documentation you can download the spec
which is what I do from OpenGL org or
the Chronos you can just download the
spec and then it's used that PDF offline
and that works pretty well so that's one
way to go the other thing for MSDN is
you can try to get offline MSDN it's
hard but you can try it I would say look
just bite the bullet do your research on
MSDN online and just bite the bullet the
fact that you have to use MSDN a few
days keep that programming isolated and
then go back to having no internet after
you're done I really wish you could get
MSDN offline unfortunately you can't
anymore but what can I say
one bit brain you talked about threading
being hard to say would use open and P
if that's it no so when I meet when I
say threading is hard what I mean is
that architectural e speaking threading
is very difficult and it's very
difficult because C++ doesn't really
support what you need openmp probably
doesn't either I haven't spent a lot of
time looking at it but what I'm talking
about is things like if you have a large
number of threads working on something
let's take a very simple case so let's
suppose that all of my game is running
and then the user decides in the
settings menu that they're going to
switch from OpenGL back end to direct3d
back end right every thread that was
currently working on something graphics
related is now some kind of wrong you
know I'm saying anything that was
working at an asynchronous transfer is
wrong anything that was waiting on the
results of a compute operation is wrong
there's a lot of wrong going on and
those all have to be shut down and their
memory has to be properly reclaimed and
their resources have to be properly
freed and all of those things right and
new things have to be started up that
all properly use the new direct3d
version of everything right these kinds
of waves through the codebase are very
hard to model and hard to make efficient
in my experience and I just don't see a
lot of people solving those problems
they can they usually do one of two
things either they solve a problem that
I really just don't have which is how do
I get a bunch of threads to all
cooperatively work on a math problem
it's like that's like day two of
multi-threaded programming like it's not
an issue so things like OpenMP I'm
guessing don't really have much to offer
me because the problem they're solving
is a problem I don't actually have right
or they solve the problem
the C++ way of now every last little
thing does 10 times more work than it
has to do so it's like everybody is like
creating tons of allocation free release
open lock like tons of just interrelated
disastrous lockup on every little thing
whether it's opening a file advocating a
little bit of memory doing this doing
that right and so I just the the right
answer is something that correctly looks
at these waves and can break them apart
for you and can automatically do the
aggregate freeze and releases that you
need and we just we're nowhere close to
having that kind of correct analysis you
know so like job management just isn't a
problem like that's not a problem I have
job management is trivial so if the
primary thing you're offering me by
getting your system is job management I
I don't care right like that's just not
the that's not the hard part you know
talk to me when you do really good
aggregate memory management
that's super efficient and doesn't do
stuff like have to walk trees or check
things like that's actually just really
kind of knows like okay I can set these
one or two points where I know after all
these things correctly finished I can do
one block free and when these things
need to start up I can do one block
allocate and I properly have them laid
out and look like when it actually does
all that stuff okay but until I see some
evidence that that's going on I'm
skeptical and maybe only oh maybe only
baby has it I haven't looked at open
mimpi
maybe it's awesome I doubt it but you
know maybe it is all right I think we're
all done
thank you everyone for joining me for
the upside of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you can always pre-order
the game at handmade hero or it comes
the source code so that you can play
with it yourself until next time have
fun program you'll see on the internet
it probably will not be next weekend it
will be much sooner because we are still
celebrating Crump of Slav I hopefully I
said that right Columbus laughs for the
next couple weeks which means there will
be lots of surprise dreams probably all
throughout the week so I will see you
back here probably sooner rather than
later but until that surprise occurs
have fun program run I'll see you on the
Internet
I don't know if John's dream in a day
but I set up the handmade hero twitch to
automatically host John if he is so if
he is it should switch right over to him
if he's not well I guess we don't get to
see that today but hopefully we do all
right I'm gonna sign off thanks for
coming everybody see everyone next time