hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream we have some implementation to do
today
we want to make a little UI for fussing
with stuff we actually kind of know what
we want to do because we sketch it out
yesterday just determining what actually
we wanted you know what cut what we
actually wanted the code to do and how
we wanted it to do it we sort of have an
idea of that now and so really what we
want to do today is if I clean that up a
little bit in terms of just making sure
it actually is what we wanted
and then figure out a way to get it on
the screen we sort of have the code for
this already in the debug library and so
really what we're talking about here is
we added some keys that allow us to let
go into a debug mode here and like you
know we can select some things and stuff
like that and what we want to do is if
we pick different things and again we're
not really sure about a lot of this
stuff we're just sort of hacking it in
there and then we're gonna see like what
do we actually do when we've got it and
we can tune it a little bit to be more
like what we want but when we pick
something in here we want to be able to
do is get access to like a property
sheet over here that allows us to edit
some properties and so in order to do
something like that we just need some UI
now we have some UI right we've got like
this stuff here that we did and it does
allow us to do some of this stuff like
we can toggle things and and stuff like
that right so we actually have some
things that allow us to do what we want
already written we just you know we
don't really have them integrated in to
the game side of things they're just in
the debug library and we kind of want
this to be even if you compile the debug
stuff out of the game we may want this
in there we we really don't know what we
want to do with that stuff long term we
kind of have to decide on that as we go
and and I don't have a strong opinion on
it but what we do know is that an artist
for example is gonna need access to
these tools and that says to me that
like the full thing that has like all
this stuff we don't want that exposed
like an artist doesn't want to see this
they don't know what this means
and we don't want them to have to know
what this means that's a bunch of
cognitive overhead for them that is
meaningless to their job but nothing in
here is gonna help an artist get their
job done so all we're doing is throwing
a bunch of new stuff at them they have
to understand that literally is
worthless to them right and so typically
for if we're talking about something
that an artist needs to be able to use
we want to keep it to things that they
actually care about because otherwise
we're literally just wasting their time
their their job and the thing that they
presumably enjoy is drawing they don't
care at all about how many milliseconds
a particular thing in the game takes
that's the programmers job and the
artist should never have to care right
and so what we want to do is we want to
make something that an artist can use
here and think about how that's going to
work and so it should be able to be
something that with minimal amount of
instruction and artists can just
remember how to do and do and they don't
have to learn a bunch of programming
nonsense or things about the internal
structure of our code we don't want them
to have to think about those things
because again it's just it's just gonna
waste their time and it's gonna get less
art done for no reason so what we want
is something that's going to be art
friendly and that will be in the game
whether or not there is this debug
system on at all so let's think about
that as we're kind of going forward with
it but because we do have that debug
code available it does mean that we
probably want to leverage the fact that
we have that debug code because since we
have the debug code it doesn't really
make a lot of sense for us to rewrite
everything when it's already basically
doing what we want so the question in me
is more like can we just take what we
did here turn it into sort of a more
generic version that doesn't really care
whether they're client from the debug
system or not and then use it in both
cases because it is basically the same
sort of code it's just whether or not it
gets compiled in or not is more
dependent on who's doing the calling and
so that's really what we want to focus
on so we create a thing yesterday that
was a little editor system here that's
the sort of bare-bones version of what
we want and what we sort of did is we
sketched in what we imagined it might
look like to call this thing and so
here's an example of what that would be
and what we sort of did is we said we
imagined we could sort of make these
sets of calls here specifically so you
know I pick an asset here's an asset
that I've selected it looks at what type
the asset is and right now we don't have
any sound or font editing because we
don't really know what that means
you know maybe it never means anything
because maybe there's nothing really to
edit on those we don't know but if there
was something that it we could add it
here so really we're talking about just
a one thing we wanted to edit which was
the bitmap type and the only thing we
really wanted to edit in there at least
at the moment are these alignment points
and what we wanted to do is this set of
operations we want to be able to say
let's list an alignment point let's say
which number it is in the file right
because there's eight of them or 16 of
them or something
I remember how many line of points there
were how many Lyman points were there
twelve something like that anyone
remember twelve so there are twelve
alignment points in the file right so
you could just specify any of those so
we're gonna list all twelve alignment
points if an alignment point is empty
you can click on it and it will
initialize it to a new one that's not
actually set to anything specific and
then you can set it to whatever you want
and then in here if we have one already
it will say this the specification of it
and allow you to remove that alignment
point if you so it we're so inclined and
that's really all we needed to do with
alignment points for now that was that's
literally everything there is for us to
do there's a little bit more business
involved in here that we're gonna want
to add a little bit later it doesn't
really have anything do with the UI but
what we would want to do here is because
we know whether or not our alignment
points like we know when we add one we
know when we change the settings and we
know when we delete one we may want that
to be something that is saved on an undo
redo stack and we definitely want it to
be able to flush to a file so we're
going to have a few more operations that
we need to implement those operations
aren't really operations that relate to
the UI because those are things that you
know
would either rebound to a hot key or are
just gonna use this button feature again
because they're just things that trigger
like save to disk or whatever so they
don't really affect our design of this
too terribly much so I think we don't
need to worry about them at the
immediate moment although we could if we
wanted to sketch them in for example you
could imagine something like this this
is not a particularly good way to do
this necessarily but we could just
imagine well and you know we could even
make it a fairly good way to do this I
suppose we want to it depends on how
we're feeling whether we're feeling
saucy or not but we could have something
like an in-game edit here right and you
could imagine something that allowed us
to build a little linked list of edits
somehow you know what I mean
and right now maybe we don't know
exactly what those are but we keep a
list of them in fact we could just do it
this way so you can imagine us keeping
like two lists here where we've
basically got lists of in-game edits
that we want to be able to track so as
we edit things you know we would save
them as in-game edits that could be done
or you know undone or redone or you know
whatever we want and at the moment we
really only have one kind the only thing
you can edit are these points and then
you can imagine us adding an undo and a
redoing here what that means is at that
point once you've you know committed to
having something fairly real there which
we can do pretty easily then we can
imagine what this other section might
look like
so when you are in the editor proper
then when you come in to update and
render editor if you're actually in any
mode that involves editing at all then
what you could hypothesize is we would
do something like say you know if you
know files are dirty or something like
this you know something here that we
look and we see whether the files are
dirty then we add a button that allows
us to say
you know what I mean and this would do
the save here and then we could also
furthermore imagine you know some things
about the Sentinels here the undoing the
redo so in that case we would want
something like if button
you know undo and if button redo right
and these things here would probably
have something to do well you know these
are the sorts of things that you want
maybe muscle memory for perhaps possibly
I don't know and so you might even say
that these should be things that allow
us to say whether something is enabled
or disabled so maybe it's more like that
right and then we just say like undo
only is there if the the list is is not
empty right so if there is something to
undo or redo then these buttons would be
available and if there is something to
save then this would be available and I
think that would be mostly it what I
would imagine is that if you look at
what's going on with these we could
probably do something where we would say
look you know the whatever the undo
Sentinel is pointing to as its next
pointer I think tells you whether you've
saved so like yeah I think it would be
this you would say
basically what we could do is say look
whenever you save whatever the undo
Sentinel is pointing to as its next
operation that would tell you
specifically whether you need to save or
not right because if you undo back to
the same place that it was at the time
when you saved then you don't need to
save again I think that's true I'm
making that up but I think that's true
so you could do like like that we could
also make these things be you know sort
of more we could we could make these
things be a little bit more systemic
here too just so that it's clearer
what's going on because other people
might want to call those and really this
is you know totally totally basic it's
just this
and so you know each thing here would
would be just a really really simple way
of checking which ones of these had
anything in it so here's one do
available here's redo available and is
empty is also similarly super basic
right it's just saying look I've got
some edit that I'm pointing to here and
I can say if it's if it's an empty ring
by basically just saying if if the next
pointer points to me right so I can just
say look the result is if the Edit next
pointer equals the edit then it's a it's
just a single link sitting there by
itself so it's not a real list right and
that's just a quick way of checking to
see whether a doubly linked list is
empty or not right that's that's all I'm
talking about there nothing nothing
fancy we could also assert in that case
that either the result is not true or
the Edit previous pointer also equals
edit because it would be illegal for the
next pointer to point back to me in the
previous pointer not to that's just a
bug and so we probably want to also
check that when we look and see if the
Edit pointer if the edits if whatever
the list is that we're looking at in
fact you know let me bet it's not a very
good name for that I'm going to call
that list for now just so it's a little
clearer what we're looking at there so
if the lists next pointer equals the
list then the you know so basically this
thing here equals true then if that was
false meaning this thing didn't point to
it then that's okay but if it's true
then we need this to be true right I'm
not I think I'm not phrasing that
exactly right here for this check what I
want to do is say like either the better
way to say it because and also because I
actually want to check two conditions
here I want to say either the result is
true and like this result is true
this is true you know or not results and
not lists right I want one of the other
of these two things so either I have to
have list next you know equal to the
list itself in which case the previous
also has to equal this itself or in the
other case if I didn't have that then
then then the other pointer sorry then
the previous pointer also had better not
be because it's either empty or it's not
in both directions it can't be empty in
one direction and not in the other
because that's just a linked list bug in
our code and we don't want that right so
if we have something like this then we
can have we could have some kind of you
would probably want something like this
this is probably what we're looking for
here and I'm not sure exactly how we
want to I'm not sure exactly how we want
these to be specified the thing that I'm
worried about is like I can do the
basics that would look something like
this but the problem with that is that
all of these buttons would be really
near each other and some of them are
really dangerous like save overwrite the
file and revert would be like undo all
of your changes that you've done since
the last save and those are pretty
dangerous things and you don't really
want them close to the undo redo buttons
necessarily you know what I'm saying to
you
so we need to think a little harder
about that
I don't know what the right answer is
there but we'll have to think about that
a little bit more anyway this is what
we're basically looking at here right so
if we then look at what's going on in
the endgame edit you know tracking the
undo and redo is really pretty basic
it's it's really just saying look at
what do we have for edits at the moment
you know we've got I guess really only
one kind of edit which is and what are
they called a line point edit yeah and
in a line point edit is really basic
it's just saying look here's the asset
index here's the align point index and
then and then just what's the data right
and it was like changed from value
change to value right and so you know
each thing we put in the stack can
basically encapsulate everything into
one of these edits that we have right
yeah I'll call it that yeah yeah I'll
call it that yeah so you know in here we
sort of got the various things that we
want to edit here and one of the things
you can do in these situations to make
things easier ourselves in case you ever
want a macro is you can just name the
member the same as the type right and
that means that people would only have
to pass one thing as a parameter and
they don't need to pass the second thing
because the the type is the name in that
case and it can be handy so we don't
really need a type field here at the
moment but presumably someday we would
we don't know that we actually would but
someday right and so there would be
presumably
an in-game edit type and that type would
just say
what was supposed to happen right so you
know it would be like an edit a line
point would be the only thing in there I
guess there's an edit none something
like this we can also just do it this
way so that again everything matches
right and I'll kind of show you what I
mean by that in a second
so this lets us store this information
what's also nice about this is if we do
it by index instead of by pointer it
means if you really wanted to and you
were you were trying to be like crazy
complete about this editor
you could save the stacks out as well so
like when you saved in HHA you could
have a section that was like here's the
edit stack too so if people wanted to
keep their undo stacks around it could
cause this stuff is fairly stable
meaning it doesn't change based on where
you loaded the thing in memory you know
which is kind of nice so that's fairly
complete right and what that means is in
here what we could do is we can have a
way to edit these things we could have a
thing for align points in this case I
would say because it's so simple
I think the thing you want to do is just
make this be virtualized knocked the
Seaway but I mean just like and that's
virtualized so what would the word be
wrapped so in here we would just do like
edit the line point instead of set and
all we would have to do there is instead
of passing the align point like this we
would instead pass the base the basic
indices used to get at it so we'd pass
the asset index and the point index
instead and then the rest of the stuff
would be the same as the align point
setting function and so in there we
would say okay let's go ahead and grab
out what those things were that were
passed to set a line point like so right
and all this function is going to do is
just thunk through to that same call we
don't
with all of this stuff right but it's
also going to it's also going to do the
work of capturing the for and after
state right so it's gonna say something
like hey here's a new edit that we're
going to use so give me one of those
maybe I don't know I'm not sure so in
here we would basically say hey I want
to capture one of these edits maybe this
thing actually is a little bit Squinkie
and we actually do something like this
and then what we do is we say all right
we're gonna allocate one of these things
so this should come back with one of
these we want to capture the state of
the align point first so the change from
value is going to be whatever the the
align point actually is at the time then
we're gonna set it right then we're
gonna say the change to value is
whatever it is afterwards right so this
allows us to create and edit that we'll
remember what's going on we capture the
state of the thing before the Edit we
set it we then capture it back right
whatever it's gonna be so we know what
both of them are and getting the HHA
line point is pretty straightforward
right it's just a thing that gets the
asset first like this via this asset
index and then it gets the point index
now when we do this we want to capture
those two pieces of information as well
right we want to get those things
captured so we can have them you know
remembered and then these will capture
the actual data that's important right
here and there so we want to be able to
access this what's interesting about
this is when we do this edit align point
you can see kind of what's going to go
on here we really would like is this to
be a little bit more captured as well we
want to do a like apply edit thing in
here well I'm gonna hold off on master
for a second
all I really want to do I think at this
point is I want a way of this being a
little more systemic so what I'd like to
do here is I'd like to have a way of
getting that HHA line point so what I'd
like to do is I'd like to pass in to
this like the stuff that you need and
I'd like to be able to get that thing
out so if I pass in an asset index and a
point index I'd like to make this stuff
be known so I don't have to do it every
time right I just know I can get an
asset and then I know I can get an hij a
line point from the asset using this
and then what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
say these all use that that make sense
so that's pretty much how that would go
and then all of these folks now if we
wanted to do undo and redo on them it'd
be pretty basic that's the entirety of
the change right and that's pretty nice
because that means that if we actually
want to do undo redo then all we have to
do to implement that is we just have to
have a in fact we can make this even a
little bit more ridiculous by doing this
so if we want to we can do this which is
in game change type right an in game
change type just have two things like
change from and change to and so from is
the zero entry to is match will be
complete here is the one entry and so we
know how many we need there right make
sense and so what we can do there is we
can be even more ridiculous and make a
single function that implements both
undo and redo pretty easily right so
what we would do there is first we need
something that's like apply edit you
know what I mean or apply it at change
and what that would do is it would take
the ingame edit in question and
whichever one of these you wanted to do
right so if you wanted to apply the from
you would pass from if you wanted to
apply the two you'd pass to make sense
so at that point all you have to do is
pass the edit and that thing and it will
pull it out of the change and apply that
so it'll switch on the type of edit
whatever edit it is it'll grab a line
point is really the only thing I think
we do we have a legal default case yeah
so in here when we're doing our edit for
a line points then that means really all
we need to do is just take this thing
and get that out once we've got that
then we can just apply the change using
this stuff so we're gonna need to pass
the game assets here presumably we want
that well I don't know if we even want
the editor maybe not but we least need
the assets because we need to be able to
get access the assets out of there I
don't know if we need to pass the editor
maybe we will maybe we won't but you can
see here we just say look look give me
the thing that I'm gonna edit and I do
it and then once I have that out all I
need to do is just assign whichever one
they wanted me to assign right so in a
line at it I can just say whatever this
edit changes here we could actually
propagate these out words as well I
don't know that I really want to do that
because I'm not sure how that's gonna
shake out in the future but all I'm
gonna do here say alright whatever the
type is that's what we're gonna apply
right so that's it and once I have that
I can actually implement my undo and
redo kind of fairly trivially your and
I'm saying so if I end up in here what
I'm gonna say is alright when I do this
apply edit change I need to pass the
assets I need to pass which in-game edit
I'm talking about and they need to pass
which one of these I'm doing now if I'm
doing an undo then I want to go
backwards so I'm trying to apply an edit
change from right I'm trying to like
apply what the Edit was before the thing
that I'm talking about and if I want to
do a redo that I'm gonna do the two
because I'm trying to plot put it to
what it was after the Edit because the
redo is saying that was undone and now
needs to be redone
you know what I mean so what I want to
do here is say alright for the undo redo
sentinels all I need to do now is say
okay
let me go ahead and take an in-game edit
right and I want to pop the first thing
off of the undo stack so whatever the
editor Senate Sentinel is I'm gonna pop
the first thing off of that stack and
I'm gonna apply it and then I want to
push it as the first thing to redo right
so I'm just moving it from one list to
another and applying its change in that
direction similarly I should check here
because just in case the list was empty
I know it's weird to say that the list
would be empty because in this case
we're saying that you can only press
this button if this was available so
maybe another way to do that might just
be let's make sure our system actually
works cleanly an assert that it came
back okay although this would crash
right away so I'm not sure that the
assert is really going to do anything
that it wouldn't have done otherwise
because it will just stop probably but
you know either way
so anyway same thing here
so if we want to redo we'd pop this one
and then we apply the to change and then
we push it on right so that's the
entirety of like undo redo and where's
my is dirty did I we didn't implement
his dirty so let me just kind of
implement that real quick because it's
really also very simple so if I want to
check to see if it is dirty case all I'm
gonna check here to say look if the
Editors undo sentinel has a next field
that equals the clean undo sentinel then
it's clean so i am asking if it's dirty
so it's just a not of that right i so i
mean more concisely if the next winner
is not equal to the clean undo central
next then it's not right so that's how
we would determine whether or not it's
dirty anytime you hit save we're gonna
save the thing here we don't really know
what that's gonna look like yet so we're
gonna kind of leave that for the moment
but what we would like to do is say when
we do save we do know that the clean
undo sentinel next at the end of
everything we do want that to be saved
so whatever the undo sentinel was
pointing to at the time right when we
saved we want to save that as our clean
marker because we know that that is the
thing that means we don't have safe
right so in either of these two cases
that's gonna be the case and that's we
just don't know what those features
actually look like yet you know so and
who knows maybe we won't even have a
revert maybe you just have to restart
the game if you want to revert I don't
know we'll see we could probably put it
in there anyway
well actually I suppose technically
revert is just this so if I was to say
if I just made these to be calls that
you could make I guess what I could say
is if that's undo and that's redo so uh
oops don't know why I just did that I
was my head was thinking about the
revert feature so if that's undo and
that's redo then in theory if you wanted
to revert I guess really all you're
going to do is this
right I mean is revert just keep undoing
changes until you get back to the place
where the file was before you saved it I
mean immediately after you last saved it
or loaded it if it's brand-new
I mean I think that's actually all there
is
I don't know so there's a couple things
here that we would want to do
potentially I'll just point them out
that we could implement a little bit
later and all to stick it to do in there
so that you can see it it's basically a
thing that says to do we may want to
group and it's together so that undo can
undo more than one change at a time this
facilitates undoing edit operations as
the user perceives them rather than how
they're implemented internally in the
case of edits that edit multiple things
at once and so you know like imagine we
have a feature that's like clear that
clears all the alignment points if we or
like if we wanted revert to undo to undo
a revert undoes the whole revert at once
you know what I mean then you can
imagine wanting to create a bulk undo
that's just like here's all these
in-game edits that are just you can just
chain them together you know if you want
to right so it'd be really easy for us
to implement that and maybe we will but
I just want to sketch that out for you
really everything else is pretty
straightforward but there you go so
that's actually completely
implementation of everything except for
save which kind of needs to go through
the asset system we have the ability to
write changes back but we haven't really
figured out how we want to do that yeah
and so that's something that we're gonna
have to look at right so save we'll have
to implement but everything else here is
pretty much sketched out now so this
does all the editing it keeps undo
changes everything looks good so really
I think the only thing we're talking
about now is we need some way
sketching in this this UI so what I want
to do here is again I don't really want
to talk about UI as UI and the reason is
because I don't really want the I don't
want to confuse the user interface of
the game with the user interface of the
editor or the debug system so what I
want to do is have like handmade dev UI
h might be the right word for it you
know I'm saying and handmade WI dot H
will probably look something like this
right and so what I want to do is start
gathering up the dev UI stuff that I
think you know like something like this
you know what I mean where things that
are clearly that I want in both systems
unless I start pulling them out of here
and putting them into here right and
then I'll force the debug system to go
through this stuff and that's how we
will that's how we will begin to use the
same code in both places right so I'm
just gonna start only with the text
output function so this function here is
obviously very useful and I want to be
able to do it I keep forgetting I don't
have my I need to update my for coder I
haven't copied like this is still an
older version of our code or I haven't
updated my for coder to the new one so I
forget that I can't see to open the new
file automatically I can do that on the
new one so anyway I want this text off
here to be shared and so what happens
is the things that can't be shared are
like the debug state stuff and the debug
state stuff is necessary in a couple
places for a couple things right so if I
was to pull out all the things that I
needed it would look like this right and
so in here we would just say look is
there font instead of all the rest of
that stuff we would need a font scale
and we don't know where we're gonna get
that exactly I guess we're gonna get it
here for the time being so we got the
font scale pulled out what else we got
for debug state and then we've got like
a shadow transform and a text transform
and those were just two things that were
designed to put because our stuff was
being sorted that was designed to put
things in front of or behind right so
like you know things got sorted into
buckets where the shadows went behind
the things that were in front of them I
don't know that we really want them
anymore we forced ourselves to do that
because our render previously sorted
everything our renderer no longer has to
do that it can just not sort like you
can just call it without the depth sort
stuff on and it will just render things
in the order in which they come so I
don't really know that we want those two
things but I'm gonna say that we still
have them anyway I think that's what
called a render object transform or an
object transform or something like that
yeah so we have a shadow transform and a
text transform I think right and those
things were coming from here
and if we had some way of getting all of
those then I think see if we had some
way of getting all of these things then
I think we are good to go right because
the rest of this stuff is self-contained
it looks up all of the rest of the
things it needs using the asset system
and so it really needs this is the set
of information that it needs in addition
to just the basics for for you know
printing out stuff so I think I also
don't know if font scale actually does
anything ever we could potentially
remove that but you know so the natural
thing to do here I would argue is just
say like make a struck that has exactly
things in it that we want I mean that's
what we wanted right and you can imagine
the version of this that gets made for
the debug system it would just look like
a thing that copies those over right but
this is what you would need and we could
make that look like this in which case
it would just be that sorry but assuming
that we filled all of this out I also
don't know why the spots ago wouldn't be
baked into these but maybe that's not I
don't know doesn't matter point being if
we have all of these passed through this
is basically like what we need to know
for our like dev UI
Debu I context I don't know what you
want to call it but it's the thing that
allows us to to draw and do stuff right
so if we just change this to saying we
have a context pointer right and the
context pointer is the thing that would
get us all of these things then we can
certainly pass we can certainly pass
that out here I don't know that render
group I don't know if that wants to
actually be a pointer there and not it
may want to just be one of these but I'm
not sure so for the moment we'll leave
it as a pointer it's fine so we're gonna
do this and then once we grab all those
things out we're good to go
that means that it went in our startup
we would need something that basically
does this for the debug system you know
what I'm saying so something that would
prep one of these you know how we want
to I kind of like that as a word but I
do do e
but I'm going to actually capitalize it
because camelcase
if you're you're in for the camelcase
you might as well keep it going so we
would want to do Oh what did I do that
was totally not what I wanted I got
carried away there with the word de veau
e
there we go that's what I actually
wanted to do
um so we could do that I don't know if
we want instead to do this I mean that's
another option right maybe that makes
more sense but the reason that I'm not
as interested in that the reason I don't
love that is because I could see dev UI
being its own thing that stores like
State and stuff so the WI context is
more the thing that's like a drawing
pass you know it could be alternatively
called WI pass you know what I mean so I
don't know so if I were to go that route
with it then inside the debug system and
anywhere that previously someone was so
like you know inside just go grab like
inside the debug you know startup stuff
then what we're gonna do is in both of
these places like in the debug system
where they're no longer necessary are
they really yeah
is that actually true
I mean they're getting used are we sure
they're not necessary all right um look
at that later anyway so in here we know
that we need one of these things and we
you know so we know we we need one of
these WI contexts and we know that we
want to initialize that so when we do
our luck debug startup stuff right so
everything gets initialized once we have
everything ready to go here I want to
create one of these things so I want to
say like dev UI context you know does
that prep probably wants to be that so
if I've got one of those once I grab it
then I want to be able to fill it out
here I've already done that that's what
it is
right and so that allows me now to call
this call anytime I want to let me go
ahead and pull this out here and then
the text op is just the same thing but
it's you know the WI stuff and that's
about it
so there's WI techstop thing
and any here we would have to do this
and so now we need to do is actually
provide those things to the system
because obviously you know the debug
system here we go so in the debug system
these things need to be included
somewhere want to see where those
actually get included
all right so I guess inside handmade H
we can just put those in here I'm not
sure where they should go at the moment
I'll put them in here for the moment and
we'll sort of push them there oops
what's going on so I can just free to
find that because that'll get to find a
little bit later I don't know what else
isn't there
did we end up with this in the wrong
place
so we've got WI not H and WI dot CPP so
I must have just had a typo
okay um looking at these this should
probably be called font info so let's
keep going from there this is actually
the get asset stuff and okay so we have
this is actually all in the other code
which I don't really want to deal with
right now so I think probably what I'll
do here to me is I'm just gonna nuke all
of this stuff while I just verify that
we didn't break anything
sorry that's behind my head there I
don't I can't see it either
but I don't need to because I'm just
making it a dummy function and so all
I'm gonna do is just nuke that because I
don't want to look at those areas yet I
want to look at these areas first so
what I want to do is make sure that the
debug system still works and can use
that can use that same system like can
can use that thing we pulled out and and
draw properly because that's what I want
to focus on first make sure all that's
working that part of it
that's actually fun info what is this we
must have accidentally deleted that
and this is just because we need to do
this right so I think that's good and so
now we can call the text out thing from
anywhere and you can see that it's still
working just fine so that's good and
what we would like to do probably is
move some of the other font stuff out
into there like you know the tooltips
and stuff too so I think we want to like
we want like the tooltip buffer to be to
be there too would be my guess um so we
can see what we want to do about that in
a second we'll think about that a little
bit more later all right so now let's
take a look back to the in-game editor
cuz now that I pulled that function out
now I want to debug this thing by
stubbing out these other pieces and and
kind of going from there so let's start
by getting all of this stuff compiling
and stubbing out the functions that we
don't have yet so here this get asset
call that looks like it returns a memory
header I'm not sure why it does that I'm
not sure why it it returns a memory
header so I'm gonna look just so I can
find out why right so it returns a
memory header
because it affects which one was the
most recently used so this really isn't
yet asset per se it's really good asset
memory header
which I may update it to reflect this is
the action will get asset call why these
are in line I have no idea they just are
so that's actually what we wanted for
good asset and this is good asset memory
header they're definitely different and
so these calls here really should be get
a Sat memory header in here we need the
actual bitmap so here we should do an
assertion that this asset is in fact a
bitmap
that's actually correct so we want the
HHA inside we want the actual file
information so we want that let's see
what else a line point edit so we need
this to exist so what we want to do here
is we want to have a way of having the
in-game editor allocate change lists and
they never go away
so those things basically these are
allocations that are never freed ever
you just want to pile them up for
eternity we could try to recycle them if
we get too many of them but hopefully we
would never get too many of them cuz you
really don't ever want your undo list to
go away so you want to just keep piling
them up until virtual memory hits right
which is a lot of edits so the in-game
editor here when we do an allocation we
want to allocate by type so what we
really want to do here is say we need
two things we need the type of change
we're doing right to edit you were doing
so this is the type and then we also
need the well I guess that is the only
thing we need because the size doesn't
change to see Union so we've got a
result here the assault result is just
going to be a push struct the second say
it's an in-game edit
you know what no I don't wanna do that
I'm gonna do it as a you wait we'll see
why I'm second so if I take the ingame
edit here and I just say well even that
I don't have to do yeah it really is
just a void star anyway so if I take the
in-game edit here and I just say look I
want to take the I want to make one of
these I need some like undo memory here
right like this is the undo memory we're
gonna use so I want some undo memory I
know that it's gonna be this type so I'm
gonna push one of these in game and it's
trucks on you know I changed my mind I'm
gonna do this so we're gonna do one of
these in game instructs when we get the
result back we're gonna set the type
equal to the type that we're told and
we're we don't want it to actually have
any membership yeah it's just kind of
hanging out as its own list so it's next
in previous pointers just point to
itself and that's all that happens so
then we can return it and it's good to
go I think that's everything and so then
I just need a pound to find cure that'll
do the thing that I wanted to do with
the type so what I want to do is say
whatever the type is that you're trying
to push on here
I want to allocate one of those by
passing the type here with this prefixed
to it and then I'm going to also cast
that type so you can see why I wanted
this to be that thing oh not cast sorry
I want to reference that type so like
this right so I'm going to basically get
you the address of that sub field and
I'm also gonna use that to pass type so
that's why I named it the same because
then you could just pass one thing to
the allocate editor at it and you get
the right member and the right type
field to find for free right that's just
a little convenience there that helps
keep things simpler for everyone who's
calling you so we need some undo memory
what else do we need point index you're
telling me that's not a thing it's a
line point index all right this is and
this is edit changed
what else we got should just put this
undo memory in there so if I want some
memory for this sort of thing I should
be able to create one of these memory
arenas just from whole cloth
if the in-game editor is gonna be here I
should be able to say that there's
in-game memory or I should say undo
memory here and that undo memory should
probably be clear to zero bull I want to
say I I don't know
we'll find out so we also want to be non
restored memory so I would like to
initialize that because I would like it
to be non restoring memory if possible
here what I mean
so I want the allocation parameters for
it to be platform memory non restored I
don't think there's anything else that
you really need there so you know we
could just have it so that the memory
arenas allocation flags are just set to
that so I think I think when we call in
and the editor actually does anything I
mean we should be able to do this
so we can create an it call that'll do
it
at some point in here this all looks
fine just like I was pulling off the
wrong struct in a bunch of these cases
other than that so now we sort of have a
couple just like it wants an actual
point on these so that I like bit amp
bit amp sounds like some kind of a like
chiptunes editor so it looks like now
we're down to just unimplemented
functions right
which is where we want to be
so I think that's everything that we
wanted there I'm gonna pop over to dev
you eye and I'm gonna stub those
functions out real quick and then we're
going to have to start working on the
merge which will take a while that's
label there's an enabled flag
there's the stuff that allows us to kind
of pick those pieces apart there here's
our editable x' so these are things that
we would pass addresses to because the
person who's calling them needs to be
able to change them so
and we also had it at pxy and this one
took pounds so you kind of knew what the
range was that you could move it in
alright so did I miss begin section I
did all right so I think that's all the
functions were calling at the moment let
me see if that's true there might be a
couple of it there's actually there's a
couple in the other thing that where
that's not true
this is all the UI functions we're
calling but we have to implement one or
two functions in the actual
section needs a I see but anyway sorry I
got distracted there there's a couple
things in the actual non the the adding
things and removing things from the list
stuff like that that we didn't implement
over there actually so technically
that's not there are a couple of other
functions that we need to define but I
was talking about I think we got all the
UI functions me to define I'm not sure
what the problem is with begins section
where is layout
I guess layout doesn't exist is the
problem so I'm gonna make it exist we
need button to have a default parameter
so if you don't specify false or true
it's just always assumed to be true
that's true so edit a line point
actually needs to take the asset index
and the point index and that will have
to take the assets as well
so how many arguments does it take then
so it takes the editor but we don't know
why oh yes because it needs to allocate
something that's why we probably should
just have the assets attached to the
editor because we're having to pass them
around everywhere here and it's not
something that changes so we should
probably just nuke that and have that be
accessible from the editor itself seems
like a sort of more sensible thing to do
so yeah
so now we get down to some of these
things here pop first push first those
are things that should be pretty
straightforward to do so let's go ahead
and put them in there so what we want to
do is we want to have a pop first call
that takes whatever the link is that
you're looking at previously it takes
its next pointer and pops that off and
so what that's gonna do is first of all
assume that there isn't something it'll
check to see that it's not circular so
it's not like a little art I should say
dub like just one thing and assuming
it's not then it will actually like
unlink whatever that one is that's after
it so it'll unlink previous/next right
and return that so it'll just unlink
this one and it'll it'll return that one
as the result from the pop first the
push first doesn't really need to check
anything because it knows it's gonna
actually do like that sort of thing so
we want to just do the link like so and
so on here we'll just have our two basic
link list functions link and unlink
not something like this so if we want to
unlink something we only need that thing
and if we want to link something we need
to know where to link it in so if we
want to do the unlink operation all we
need to do is say whatever the thing was
that was before us is now going to jump
and point to the thing that was after us
and similarly what we're gonna do in the
reverse case right is is similar right
so you want to take the previous thing
and make its next pointer point after us
we're gonna take the next thing and make
its previous thing to that point behind
us and then we're done
then we just want to sort of get us
linked up to ourselves right if you want
to link something in then we need the
previous next pointer to point to us we
can do this a little bit more cleanly
though in a second so we'll do that a
little later what we want to do first is
to our previous pointer to our previous
we want to set our next pointer to its
next pointer and then we just need to
say our previous next points to us and
our next previous points to us and then
we're done right so we just say look
we've got one thing we want the thing
that points to the thing behind us well
we know what the thing this is doing is
supposed to be behind us the thing
that's in front of us is whatever was in
front of the person who was behind us
right because we're going in between him
and the thing that was after him so
that's what we do and then what we want
to do is say all right take the
previous/next point it to us take the
next previous point to us and now we're
fully linked so once we've got all of
those operations in there we're good to
go we a couple little things clean up
there push first here needs to take the
actual thing to push we for some reason
did it so in both cases it's got to take
the Edit that we were trying to push on
we for some reason don't have their
begin line
begin line takes a wi-lai out why does
that not work oh because we don't have
one to find yet so in here we need to do
a WI layout layout we don't actually
have one yet so nothing's going to
happen but we need to have one to start
with we need to get editable type
working we'll do that in a second but
and then the layout itself has to get
passed down in here and we'll do that
and the problem there is that the
address here is some enum and we need
that enum to be compatible so it can be
edited so it kind of needs to be like a
u-32 there right that it can change and
that's not super safe but I don't really
care
all right so the only thing I really
wanted to change before we start
integrating that in is I do want to have
a WI edit block here and I do want that
to come back like this and I want you to
have to do that we'll see why in a
second but basically I want to reserve
stack space so that I can keep the
change stack and have nested edit blocks
if I want to so I want you to have to do
a block for that and so when you do
begin an init block I want you to in
here right
begin edit block I want a dev you I edit
block I want to basically have you have
to do that I could also actually have
you do that because then you don't have
to use the ampersand that's probably
better so you know something like that
so I did want a legal change there but
otherwise we're okay and we'll see like
I said kind of why I want to do that
when we actually go to implement that
all right so I think now we should be
running the Zack same as we were before
we have all of our editor functions
implemented for effectively and in
theory we could actually start even
editing our points if only we now had
the stub functions wired up to these
functions that we already have and we
sort of got part of the way there by
pulling out into the WI we pulled out
the text function so we can draw text
now but what we don't have is any of
those other features so if we look back
for example at the debug UI we don't
have any of the interaction features and
we had layout features here you can see
them right like that we're trying to do
layout functions and we just we don't
have any
merger of those two things yet and the
question is how much of these do we want
to merge I'm not sure my suspicion is we
more or less want to merge them
completely in other words if debug UI
dot CPP kind of goes away eventually
that would I think probably be a good
thing because if you just look at what's
in there it's mostly all stuff that is
valid in both places right like there's
a couple things here that are sort of
not really maybe exactly what you would
want but to a large extent it's pretty
darn close to being the same so we
should be able to merge these in a way
that isn't too owners
and and a lot of you know like almost
everything here is the same right like
almost everything here is what you would
want as you're sort of making these
things happen
so you know I I would assume that for
the most part we want this stuff to kind
of merge up right and you know I'm
looking at this stuff so we're when we
actually do layout elements they exist
really only on the stack
it looks like too
so again you know I think a lot of this
stuff really can be you know I don't
think much of this stuff really has to
be modified what what are the things in
here do we actually have Vitter like
look we can't even I feel like the tear
off features and stuff that we have I
don't really know that we're even doing
those anymore
yeah not sure but looking at these right
we've got we've got all these things
that that look a lot like stuff we would
just keep you know I mean it really just
looks pretty much the same
I mean it looks the same to me anyway so
I feel like most of that stuff is pretty
pretty much okay so looking at this
stuff here you know debug interaction
[Music]
looks pretty good
the I'm kind of interested to know so
let's suppose we started plucking away
at this thing I just want to know like
what extent you know what are these
things used for cuz I don't really know
anymore right we haven't met him a long
time ago
I'm not for sure's right so who sets
that thing does anyone set that thing
okay so obviously that was not necessary
and can be removed
so it looks like that must have been for
something that we were using before and
that we're not using now I'm not
entirely certain but apparently that's
the case so let's take a look at some of
these other ones here presumably at
least one of these guys is actually
getting use by somebody somewhere or not
debug variable link then maybe
so it looks like tare value is the thing
that was using that and so if we just
say that we're not going to use the
value tear off stuff at the moment we
would not need that either and I don't
we've like never used it I think we
experimented with it a bit and we've
just never really cared because we don't
save that stuff so so if we just get rid
of that what happens so it should have
worked with alt UI but I tried that and
it didn't actually work what's the deal
with that I'm gonna see what happened
why why couldn't I do that tear
operation it was supposed to work with
alt but I don't it did not work with alt
and I don't know why and I would like to
know why so if I run this here I'm gonna
run this and I say alt you know that it
doesn't do anything
you know I'm saying so what's up with
that
[Music]
so alt UI is not actually the Alt key
it's some other thing is there a reason
it's not the Alt key let's just make it
be alt down right maybe we didn't have
alt that time all right so now if I have
alt down okay
all right so I'll leave that in I mean
it works
so we'll leave that in there that was
just a case of us not wiring up the
input I guess because maybe we didn't
have alt at that time and so it's just
confusing said we had to keep the ended
down but ended down so we had to hold
down the right button and then click the
left button or something I don't know
it doesn't matter point being it's fixed
now so I'll leave that in there because
that seems reasonable to me to keep if
it's working a debug element I think is
the main thing we use so I'm pretty sure
this is used everywhere right because
that's the thing you use for most often
yeah so that's good let's see so that
all seems okay and you know those things
are pointers so they don't have to be
too even compiled in the if these types
were undefined it wouldn't matter so we
can basically look at everything except
for the debug ID and the debug ID is
just a blind value so really this thing
could be also lofted up as like a dev ID
or something right and so if I look for
everywhere the debug ID is used if we
change debug ID everywhere to just be
dev ID and it's a thing that you're
always allowed to use that seems totally
plausible so I think that's maybe what
we'll do as our change now I don't have
a lot of time left so I'm gonna make
that change and then we'll probably stop
for the day and next weekend we'll unify
these two because I don't really want to
get started on that because it's not
gonna finish in time so I'm gonna go
ahead and put that into the platform
we're in handmade types probably
yeah so we'll throw that in here that's
going to be a dev ID and then everywhere
that we were going to use the dev ID I'm
a debug ID we're going to use a dev ID
ah
looks like we're good to go so now we're
almost there I feel like we could take
this time to pretty up some of our debug
output to because that's we're unifying
these two things we could kind of clean
up a bunch of this stuff if we wanted to
as well I think so that might be nice
and why is our library slides wrong have
you noticed that like why what's going
on there I feel like our baselines are
wrong I don't know where that's why
that's happening but our baselines are
messed up for fonts and I think you just
can't tell cuz a lot of these things you
wouldn't necessarily know but it looks
like we've got some bugs there as well
that's probably something you're gonna
have to take a look at at some point
right can see the dashes there floored
down there so I don't I don't know why
right
so think that's good for today I'm gonna
leave it there and we know exactly what
we're doing now so WI I mean I can start
pulling some of these things out where I
got five more minutes left so I could
you know I could do this type just for
now put this into WI dot H and just make
this be an interaction type that is now
unified into the system
and that should only take five minutes I
don't think it'll take us to it longer
I'm really just searching and replacing
guess I might as well do those both the
same time actually
and sorry for the boredom here but this
is just basically searching replace
looking forward to adding I've been
waiting a while to do more for coder
stuff because there's been some changes
that I'm kind of waiting for to do my
next big update but one of the big
things I want is remembering the search
and replaces that I do so that I can
just repeat them you know what I mean
so I think that's all good now so I
think we're we're pretty much set to pop
here and I'll call it a caught there
I also would like to know at some point
why our positioning is messed up we
probably should fix that I'm not sure we
must have done some positioning stuff
that was we used to probably have it be
positioned relative and now it's
positioned absolute which doesn't
correctly account for expansion
oh and ginger bill you had the question
for after the stream do you want the
viewer to be able to edit things are
just few things um my answer is that I
don't think you necessarily want to get
too far down the rabbit hole so I would
say don't editing is not a thing it's
just viewing uh and I guess the reason I
would say that is because if you go down
the route of I need to be able to edit
things then the data file format that
you're gonna specify has to be a lot
more complicated potentially because
you're basically saying it has to be
something usable and but as like an
input a permanent storage format
basically and that just opens up a huge
can of worms so while I do think it
might be eventually useful to say okay
once you make a really great viewer and
it's awesome and it does everything we
want you know then version 2 is we
figure out how to update that to
something that's usable in an edit sense
as well great but I wouldn't do that
first because I feel like it would get
in the way and over complicate things
and it might result in a in a poorer
viewer at first because it just it
broadens the scope out in a really
uncomfortable way and so I wouldn't
focus on that right because it just it
brings in so many other issues with if
so many other competing concerns as
opposed to just a like app here's how I
dump a log of data which is like very
well-defined like what's the easiest way
to just specify a stream of data right
whereas once you get into all these
other things like editable it's like oh
well how does it link up with other
things how do I put IDs in there that
tell me that this thing is maps this
other thing in my program and like how
do i specify how many there should be or
how many could add or what the possible
values of this thing are like all of
those things now become important and
before they really weren't so I feel
like it's just it just while it's a good
thing to do someday maybe
it's not a good v1 because I think you
should scope it down for v1 get it done
and good and then you can always broaden
it out later right there's nothing to
stop you from adding on and making that
a later thing
- any advice or resources to read on
shadow mapping implementations I don't
I've never implemented shadow maps I
don't like them I feel like they always
look bad you have to do a tremendous
amount of work to make shadow Maps not
look bad outdoors in the Sun sometimes
it's ok even then I see a lot of really
bad implementations there's a lot of
speckling along curved surfaces and
stuff and you have to be really careful
so I would say yeah in terms of reading
up about it there I don't even know what
the latest games are I think I can't
remember which one got using the witness
it might have been Cascades base shadow
maps but I can't remember they're all
bad I don't like shadow mapping it's
especially bad because for direct
shadowing like Ray casting is exactly
what you want because it only takes one
ray per pixel to determine the shadow of
a light source you know it's it's not
the same sort of thing as diffuse
lighting where it's very hard to compute
ray tracing lines so I feel like I feel
like the push towards ray tracing if it
does nothing else will make it so that
we never have to use shadow Maps again
and that day cannot come too soon I can
tell you that right now so hopefully
that would work and then we won't have
to care about shadow maps anymore but uh
who knows maybe not there's also
problems with like you know I don't know
maybe you're trying to use tricks to get
softer shadows by using like the shadow
map in a convolution and stuff like that
right so and that doesn't necessarily
work for if you're doing ray tracing I
mean I don't know it probably does still
work for ray tracing and
since because I mean you could just I
mean you could just still record every
ray that you trace back to the every ray
you trace back to the light source
recorded into a bitmap and then blur the
bitmap or something and then use that as
a secondary lookup so I mean maybe you
still could do it I don't know are you
still playing I'm removing the CRT and
the game layer yes actually
I don't know why we haven't done that
yeah I think because I haven't gotten
around to putting in a cosine function I
would like to do that though I knew to
the CRT and my project and it reduced
its size from a hundred fifty K to 35 K
I did not think it insert as much cred
it inserts a tremendous amount of crap
into your code tremendous tremendous
even if you don't use anything it seems
like just the startup code for the CRT
in Windows just dumps a truckload of
code into your thing and I you know to
be honest I've never gone through and
actually looked at what it all is all I
know is you don't need any of it so it's
pretty much good to just get rid of it
because it's at all of it's useless like
100% of it so yeah I mean I I don't know
do you think premiering books are worth
the effort to read or is there a better
way to learn I mean like anything else
it depends on the book you know you know
there's probably some books that are
worth reading and then there's books
that aren't so I don't think it's about
whether it's a book or not I think it's
whether the books good are we still
thinking to port to Linux and bare-metal
raspberry pie yeah I would like to it
someday but I mean we're talking about
after we're done honey so would it be to
get additional performance information
for the cpu I know until provide some
stuff for things like branch prediction
and cache misses um it can be very
useful in a game like handmade here it's
not particularly useful because we just
don't have that kind of performance
concern really at least not at the
moment but it's definitely the kind of
thing that it's definitely the kind of
thing that if you're doing serious
performance work and you're running up
against barriers that you don't
understand and when I say don't
understand I don't mean because you're
like not
experienced in everything that I mean to
understand as in no matter who you are
if you try to program a CPU to the
limits you will hit things that you
don't understand if you can't have
analysis right and so those cpu counters
are really good for figuring out things
you don't understand why they're
happening cuz you'll get into situations
where you're like why isn't this thing
getting the throughput that I think it
should based on my calculations and the
answer just becomes oh because of this
other thing you didn't think of and so
sometimes those performance counters can
help you with that
in hand-made hero most of things that we
have that might be performance targets
like lighting they're not really at that
point we are usually an algorithmic
optimization territory right now and so
having performance counters like the
ones on the CPU are not really gonna
help us so we wouldn't care about that
for our stuff but they're depending on
what you're doing you can definitely get
valuable information from that stuff for
sure
we'll be avoiding the CRT on Linux in
the future probably not because we won't
spend very much time at Aleks port linux
is not really a platform for gaming
currently like it's not a place where
games get purchased almost ever and so
it's not really a focus of game
programmers perhaps sadly it might be
nice if tons of people bought games on
linux they just don't and so we probably
won't spend much time with linux version
you know we'll probably just do like an
SD l port or something and be done with
it
because it's not a primary platform you
don't really want to spend a ton of time
on non primary platforms set maybe the
Raspberry Pi
because we do it might be fun to do one
bare metal platform and do that really
cleanly so you know but Linux isn't that
Linux isn't a bare metal platform how
can you turn the validity of a book and
its usefulness I don't know you have to
people who you trust who have read it
other than that I'm not sure you really
can you know
0lp p.m. it's close enough supporter
don't think of supporter as being
spelled wrong think of it as you were
spelling it like a internet startup
company would because everyone knows
that supporter su PP o r te r is not
worth several million dollars of venture
capital Series A funding but supporter
su PP o RT R on the other hand better
yet su PP r te ly might be even better
think about it
what's the empty space in the thread
debug view which empty space are you
talking about
did you just mean like out here I guess
I'll explain about this space is in the
hopes that that's the thing that you're
talking about so let me pause and I'll
show you so at the moment we in on
handmade hero we have so if you take a
look at each of these things here we
have on this CPU eight like cores right
and so in here we've got like one two
three four five six seven eight nine I
guess I'm not sure how many there
actually are because these two lanes are
empty
we've got nine slots if you will for
doing work and they show up as two bars
each because like one bar is the
subfield like this is do lighting work
and it's inside compute light
propagation right
so I don't know why we chose to draw
them that way exactly it probably could
be drawn better than this but each of
these is actually one channel should
probably like stripe them so you can see
the channel so at startup what we do is
we look at at the number of cores I
believe if I remember correctly maybe we
don't maybe it's just fixed I can't
remember but we create basically queues
for doing work
and they're separated out into a certain
segmentation so there's one main thread
that runs all the time and that just has
most of the game on it right like stuff
that's not performance critical
generally speaking just all runs in here
so this is the one main thread then for
parts of the game that are super
performance critical here are a set of
threads and this one's included because
it will do work as well but here are a
set of threads these lanes are just idle
they're not doing anything until there's
work available so when there's
performance critical work like solving
the lighting is the main thing we have
right now we don't really have any other
performance critical stuff that's just a
huge batch of work to do it goes onto a
cue that each of these threads will take
work from so they're all working on the
lighting and that's why you see them
show up here once the lighting is done
there's no more work to do right so they
don't have to do anything for the rest
of the time these slots here are
actually slots for things that are
basically waiting in the operating
system so when we need to load an asset
so we're gonna request some asset from
the operating system file load wait and
process it they go in here so they
almost never do anything and that's also
why this is oversubscribed that's why
there's you know threads for work one
two three four five six seven there's
actually as many of those as you would
really have cores except for maybe one
that's available for like keeping this
from from getting stalled or something
and there's two of these that just sit
around doing nothing most of the time
except when there's load work to do
right so we kind of tried to like scale
it that way so that we would not have
too much oversubscription
if you're wondering why we don't have
anything out here well the reason for
that is that this right here is actually
the end of our work right so the end of
the game's actual work happens right
about here this is the debug system here
right and this is us waiting for the GPU
to finish so really nothing goes in here
ever no matter what because there's
nothing once we've done all the work we
can do
we're stalled on the GPU waiting for it
to finish the previous frame so we can
start feeding in a new frame so that
empty space is never going away this
empty space might get filled up this
part down here might get filled up more
as we push if we end up with more heavy
work to do it'll get filled up more but
otherwise it will also stay roughly the
way it is right now am I already testing
J I know I don't have a build of J at
the moment
when updating the anchor points does
this mean the HSA files to be recompiled
each time that happens uh no because the
AJ file itself just has slots for that
so it'll just get written into the hij
file it'll just be a write exactly as we
do it now when we import an asset
how would you change the work scheme for
a mobile platform where we're concerned
about battery usage
well I wouldn't because basically like
there is no such thing as being
concerned about battery usage when
you're making a game in the sense of
work distribution the reason I say that
is because you either have to do the
work or you don't so the only thing you
can really do in a game if you're
concerned about battery usage is do less
right there's nothing else you can do so
what you would have to do is say look we
just turn the lighting off if the
battery if we're worried about battery
usage or something I mean there's
nothing else you can do because if you
have to do the lighting you have to do
the lighting you can't do it in it if
you could do it in a way that took less
power you would have done that
originally cuz that's just gonna be
faster and better anyway right so it
that's none nonsensical question in a
lot of ways you can't change the work
scheme for a mobile platform for battery
usage you have to change the game design
right you have to change it so that you
don't have to do that work because if
you have to do the work you have to do
it this way which is max score is all
doing as much as work as you can because
that's the only way to get the legend
done on time if you could have done it
with less you would have and should have
right and so if you're in a situation
where you're like this is too much work
to do for a mobile game because it uses
too much battery or something like this
then you just have to change the design
of the game to make it so that those
things are not required right those
things have to not be critical that's
really the only thing you can do at that
point
Arif can new lighting propagation be
computed while dirty while doing GPU
during evenings oh so no and the reason
for that is because this was all the
lighting that we had to do so it's just
it's fast enough on the CPU if we if we
needed more time to do light propagation
this bar just moves down the reason
we're waiting for the GPU is cuz we were
done quick
we finished fast we don't have we don't
have any more lightning to compute so we
could crank up the lighting samples and
take more time but you know that that's
just adding work for no reason that
makes sense
which doesn't seem like a good plan
something happens where I can't move
what did I do
I don't know what I did
it's gonna be nice to have our
characters in here without all the weird
like giant cat dismembered cat things so
I'm gonna be happy when we finish that
little debug UI or editing you I should
say
uplink could or we can only start to
render if the letting is done
no actually so that's not true so the
GPU is an asynchronous processor and so
what actually happens is the GPU is busy
computing the frame from the previous
submission well we're doing the lighting
for the next submission right so
remember this profile doesn't show us
any profiling for the GPU so when we
look at one of these things what we're
seeing here is the CPUs perspective so
it knows it did this work and then it
knows it's at around waiting for the GPU
to finish right what that means is the
GPU was actually working the entire time
because during some part of this it was
working on the last frame and during
some part of this it's working on this
frame right but what we know is it's
taking a full like sixtieth of a second
to do stuff now that's not really true
either because since we're in vsync we
know that everyone could have finished
early and might just be waiting around
right so the GPU is probably waiting on
the vsync here too and it's not bad to
be waiting for have everyone waiting
around it means everyone was fast enough
everyone went fast enough to finish and
now they're just waiting but if we
weren't if we're actually if this is
actually the amount of time the GPU is
actually taking then there's still
nothing else we could do because we
finished all of our work we can't
overlap with the GPU anymore because we
are completely overlapped with the GPU
right the GPU is cruising along
rendering the last frame while we're
doing this stuff we submitted the frame
here this is where we submitted the
frame right or maybe back in here
somewheres
a little bit more accurate about where
we submitted the frame technically we
told it what the frame was here but it's
probably been working on it somewhere
here and then it took it and who knows
right I mean but we gave it all the
information it needed at this point
and who knows when it started we don't
know probably right in the middle but
hard to say depends on how long it takes
to process the frame on the GPU we we
could go look at like an insight would
probably be able to show us how long it
was taking
I read your article on the manipulation
to work you did on the witness and it
helped me to bug my problems do you have
a good way to manipulate rotation is it
to R a test on a sphere and then take
the DMS hit and see how long the Delta
Ark is in the sukkah axis usually for
rotation the way I like to do it is I
like to take whatever the plane is
that's tangent to the rotation axis do
the hit on there and then project to see
where I would be on the ring that's how
I like to do it and you need two cases
you need one where the plane is facing
you and one where the plane collapses to
a line and then I use a band basically a
box and I use where you are along that
line because once the plane collapses
then you don't want to use a ring base
manipulator anymore does that make sense
all right
could you get insight to work into
double thing yes we have insight working
now and it works quite well they gave us
an updated version and it works no I'm
sorry
that wasn't why it worked it worked
because we had to completely uninstall
and reinstall that's what they told us
to do and that worked so there was some
kind of weird like you can't install an
insight on top of the existing driver
you have to uninstall all the drivers
and all event sites and then reinstall
or something it was some weird like
installation problem so we did that and
then it worked and now we've used it
multiple times the stream and it seems
to work really well like we've been able
to like go in and look at textures and
figure out that we weren't downloading
something or whatever so like it's been
good it's it's been good all right
thank your for joining me for hand mate
here oh it's been a pleasure coming with
you as always if you would like to
following series at home you can always
go to handmade hero org and pier to the
game it comes with the source code so
you can follow along at home I'd like to
finish up that edit UI next weekend
hopefully so that we can
Snapple our stuff together and start
putting a bunch of stuff into the game
it's really the main thing I think
that's keeping us from giving a thumbs
up to the like asset import pipeline
because it seems like everything else is
working we'll see when we get there and
maybe there's some things we're
forgetting but that's the the big one is
just that annotation part we just didn't
have it and so now we're working on
getting how do we put those those things
in there so we have a little more to do
we got to get that UI working and then
we may need one more weekend because we
want to have a permanent storage format
for it some kind of text file we can
read and write that gets stored off of
the PNG so we can rebuild everything
from scratch anytime we want to in case
we want to change hij format we don't
really want the HSA for necessarily to
be our permit storage format that that
maybe not be a good idea so having a way
to put a backing store on there is
probably something we wanted to but it's
pretty good looks like we're coming up
on Christmas here
which of course is also in the game
handmade hero because Krampus of course
visits around the Christmas times and so
that's a good time to be finishing up
that and then maybe we can basically say
that we're starting off the new year
with weird game stuff implementation
stuff that we want to do and that's you
know oh it's kind of a good breaking
point is around the holidays around the
new year so anyway that's it for today
hope see you back here next week until
then have fun programming everyone and
I'll see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody