okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero sure we could a complete
game live on stream in this particular
case i will say that yeah we're on a
little bit of a diversion and it's the
diversion that i decided to take just
because like i said before on the stream
we won't really get a chance to talk
very much about you I code in handmade
hero because it's not a game you know
it's not a forex game it's not you know
civilization or something where there's
a lot of you I it's not the sims where
there's lots of like pop-up menus and
radial menus and crazy stuff like that
and so I just thought I would do a quick
detour to sort of talk about those sorts
of things and give us maybe a little bit
more debug you I than we would otherwise
have like if we were just sitting here
going what's the absolute minimal thing
we could get away with for a debug
display it might be something very genki
with like you know only like minimal
keyboard controls or maybe we would just
implement just a console and there's no
overlays and no mouse interaction at all
it's just the types of text and get some
printouts or something but I thought it
would be a little more interesting if we
actually kind of went into detail and
had sort of more of a like more of a
like discussion about how user interface
code is implemented and again this is
not meant to be a full explanation of
that because implementing user interface
like you know a full user interface
library is a big topic and weren't you
know plenty of time on stream to it you
know that would be something that we'd
spend you know 100 days on if we wanted
to do like here is the complete UI
library meant to ship like applications
on and all this other good stuff so I'm
by no means trying to say that we're
going to cover completely but I just
want to do some things where we kind of
show what's going on and so I'm going to
do some program it's a suit day 200 so
you want to unpack day 1 99 s source
code and I'm just going to continue down
a little bit this sort of path of
pulling things out cleaning things up so
you can kind of see how to make a little
bit of reasonable UI code again if this
is something that you are interested in
doing for your code yourself when you
are making your engines or your games or
whatever you're making if you want to
add some UI to it or you want to add
debug you I to it as well again that's
just kind of what we're
here so you can remember kind of what we
did is we started to talk about these
interactions and we sort of pulled out
the code that does these interactions
into something that was a little cleaner
and can now be used a little more
generically so we have stuff like oh you
know if you open the profile it's got
like a resize interaction here and we
didn't have to rewrite that interaction
for here we could just use the same one
and furthermore we could even constrain
the aspect ratio by just adding one or
two lines of code in the thing that
actually draws these guys and so again
what we're kind of doing here right is
we're focusing on how we we can
architect this code for its desired
purpose which is really flexible quick
ability to add new UI things so that as
we want them we can just add them and we
don't have to worry too much it's not
like a big overhead the programmer to
put in new widgets or new tool just like
that so that's really what the focus is
kind of the way that we're architecting
this as we go and that's a pretty good
way to go with a debug you I right
because specially with the debug you I
you really don't want to be spending all
of your time later on in the game when
you're trying to do something else IE
not working on the debug code you know
you want to do the debug UI code and you
want to have it done and then later on
you know if you want to add something
you don't want to be in this situation
where it's going to be this huge
investment of time to go like riorca
tech the code and pull it apart to add
this new widget or whatever you need to
do you want to be able to just really
simply go in and change a few quick
things leverage existing code really
easily and have the new widget that you
want it or whatever right and so that's
kind of more like well like I said what
we're talking about here okay and so
what I wanted to look at today since we
kind of obstructed that widget code I
mean the interaction code reasonably
will yesterday there's more we could do
but i think you know like i said it's
not this is not meant to be an entire
you know massive section on you I or
anything I what I would like to do now
is take a look at the actual way that
we're doing the drawing of the debug you
i right and there's really two things we
can do with this I don't know we can
start with that today or I can push it
off till tomorrow I'm trying to think of
exactly I want to do it because the
other thing that we could do is do the
deep copying of values because the other
thing that I was saying is you know we
had this thing where when you
copy something like if I copy the
renderer over here and I make another
copy of it it does this kind of weird
thing that you can see where it like it
has kind of because it's just a
referential copy it puts everything
exactly as you see it and everything is
mirrored completely and we don't really
want that right and we also want the
iteration to kind of be locked to just
inside its children and they're just a
bunch of things that that we are
currently living with for but that way I
don't think we would want and so I don't
know how relevant that is to the drawing
part of things so i don't know i think
i'm a stick with just let's go ahead and
make the drawing stuff work properly and
go from there okay so so let's let's
just take a look at that and we'll see
what we can do from there alright so
what I want to do here is I want to take
a look at how we are currently drawing
things and I just want to start pulling
it apart in a way that it's not quite so
ad hoc right because if you look at how
we are drawing them now I did and again
this is what I think you should do this
is not like oh we were bad people for
doing this way it's just you don't want
to leave it this way what I did was I
said like okay inside debug drum menu
here is a for loop and what I will do in
this floral loop is I will go through
and for everything that I have it's a
type that I want to draw i will just go
ahead and put the code in pure that
draws it and that's exactly what we did
the interactions the first time too but
then you know we went through and said
okay let's make a little type called
debug interaction that can sort of
capture what those things are that we
want to do so that then we could start
leveraging actual calls to these things
to make it so that they are no longer
totally ad hoc that we can do things
like interaction is clot test to see if
particular interaction is hot so we can
highlight things properly and then we
can just assign the whole interaction to
something to make that the hot
interaction like we do here and it just
kind of makes it again it start spinning
up that code and making that code a
little bit more reasonable so what I'd
like to do is that same exact thing with
the drawing code and you can see here
that I've got the drawing code it's just
very very ad hoc right I just kind of
create things like I'm computing minimum
corners maximum corners I'm doing like
these sort of putting widgets in the
corners of these things and computing
where that is myself and so what I'd
like to do is maybe pull that code out
as well so that we can start to think a
little bit more directly about that
right so we can start to have shared
code where we're having sort of like
duplicated duplicated code and that way
we can sort of make those things a
little richer and make those things
potentially a little more interesting or
a little more robust by focusing on just
having it in one place and so we can
make sure that place does things well so
all I'm going to do here is start by
just again doing the standard kind of
compression oriented programming sort of
thing I'm going to basically try to just
put out here some things like I'm just
kind of a loft up some of these things
that we're doing into a function and I'm
just going to see what comes out of it
right so if i look at these two things
here like in particular like the bitmap
display and the counter thread list
right we can kind of see and you know
what even let's let's let's take a look
at this guy here as well right we can
see that a lot of these guys they sort
of have this notion of starting at a
particular place and that place is
almost always the same right and in fact
we kind of have a situation if you if
you want to look at it where we've
really just kind of duplicated totally
willy-nilly some very specific things
that are happening here if we wanted to
change like how the indentation works in
these things we'd have to change it in
all three places right so you can really
see how that code is kind of getting
duplicated out there right so I think
the first thing I'd like to do is pull
that out into something that can be
common right so I'm just going to go
ahead and start here by saying that okay
maybe we've got some of these things
like the depth you know and the line
advance maybe I'll just go ahead and
pull those out here so that's when we're
actually working on these separately and
you know maybe this at Y and at least
look kind of like good candidates to
write maybe like this and I could even
if I want to just make that be a nap
right so you can kind of see that these
things are being used so I'm just
grabbing them out and putting them here
and so then if I wanted to I could say
that this was you know something like a
layout or something like that right and
I'll take the layout and I'll say that
when i initialize that i'm going to you
know take all of these things that I was
doing originally in two variables I'm
just going to bundle them into this
structure so nothing has changed
everything is exactly the way that it
originally was but now these are in the
structure and the reason that I'm
putting them in the structure is not
because I just want them in a structure
it's because now it's trivial for me to
pass that whole state over to another
function and so essentially what we're
doing here basically is we're sort of
making our own little version you know
like almost our own little closure we're
basically saying we want get to have
some layout routines these layout
routines are going to have to know about
this stuff and since it's pretty hard
from you sail I can see that they're
like local functions or something what I
can do instead is just bundle up the
actual local variables into a struct and
have that struck to be something that I
can then pass as like the first
parameter to these layer routines so
that they will be able to do the things
that is that they need to do you know
all right so if that is what you know if
that's taken care of then you can start
to see how like in here maybe some of
these things can start to be automated
right and so right now we have a sort of
an annoying thing where we do this at
why get min corner thing that happens
right it's kind of the reason that we
did it that way and with the bounds
being the way they are kind of like
being processed in here like almost all
of that stuff is just because we were
trying to share the advancement code
we're trying to make sure that the
advancement code is the same so you the
bounds would like to flow out but
there's no reason for these bounds to
even ever flow out of these case
statements there's nothing that even
says that there's not multiple bounds
for object potentially but we just were
kind of trying to leverage that sort of
single code path in terms of advancement
so now when we think about it we've got
like opportunities now to make that not
be a thing so what I'd like to do
instead is start to look at that in a
more holistic way
right I'm going to pull the bounds
inside for now right I'm going to have
it be something like this so I've got
these bounds everywhere there in here
are going to be local functions here we
go and you even remember it was kind of
a finicky to do the text thing because
of the way we were doing it because we
had to like make it come out with the
bounds and all these are the things so
you know we actually were kind of
bending over backwards to support that
as well so here we are with our oops
that was not my intention let's get back
there so you and you can see then we get
down to here and we're going to use the
bounds to advance my why and what I
would rather do like I said before is I
would rather have something where these
guys themselves do a little bit more of
that work right they do a little bit
more of that advancement so maybe you
know just start with something like
let's say we call advance on the layout
something like this now that's not
exactly what I want yet but that's
roughly what I want it to be and I want
it to be you know something like this
right so I'm just going to go ahead and
put that in here temporarily again this
is just kind of like a very simple sort
of a thing and I think also we can go
ahead now and and just do exactly what
it was doing which is to get that min so
that that made a matter so if i go ahead
and say ok there's an advanced function
this advanced function takes the layout
there's the layout and cure is the
bounds oops then what i want to do is
take that bounds oops let me get the
minimum of that get the minimum corner
and then I'm going to take that why
we're just gonna make the layouts at y
equal to that get min corner that's all
we were doing before and that's all
we're going to do now right so now if i
come through here and kind of port this
stuff you can see that now I no longer
have to do this this assignment
component why is because we're actually
just going to take it directly so that's
nice as well and so let's go through
cure and now port like all the rest of
the compile errors that we're going to
have for having switch this up a bit so
here we've got layout add X right we've
got layout
oops at top why that's good let's keep
going through here we've got another one
cure like so we've got the bounds min
the spacing why is now in there as well
see what else we've got um see here oops
that's not a pointer not a pointer
really not a point there we go okay the
depth is also part of the layout as well
the line advance also part of the layout
what else we've got keep on going we
have again the line advance we've got
the depth and we have let's see let's
see here we go and not much more here so
there we go layout spacing xbase y at X
go and depth my advanced mind advance
nothing particularly interesting nothing
to see here just the basic boarding and
I think that's about it so now in theory
we should be back to the point where
everything is oh yeah you know what this
is a little bit weird because I guess we
never really specified which one of
these guys it was going to be so that's
a bit strange we'll probably have to
talk about that in a second but that's
fine we can fix that as well let's see
here because that looks like said
actually well I guess I don't have to
move it in there
there go alright so this should all be
the same as it was and it does look that
way right so that all seems pretty
reasonable okay so now what I'm going to
do now that I have this layout structure
and everyone's using it I'm just going
to go in here and start to pull out
things that are obviously like very do
you know sort of duplicated right things
that that look like there's just no
really real reason for them to have to
be done custom they could be shared
right so in this case like when we look
at the counter thread list you can kind
of see that like the dimension is
something that's wrote specified like we
just have the concept of a dimension for
this thing and so there really doesn't
need to be any particular reason for us
to do this computation here this could
be something that anybody with a
dimension could use right so we could do
something like all right instead of
having like advanced or whatever this
sort of thing we could just have
something where if you want you can get
a rectangle to back where you could just
say like you know I don't know if it's
what with the right thing here like
insert or place just maybe like place
rectangle or something like that and all
you would do is you'd say like okay
what's the dimension of this thing so I
would say something like here's the
dimension of the thing that I want to
place and then you'll just returned to
me the rectangle in which i should draw
that thing you don't I'm saying
something like that and so we'll start
and again we want to do something we
want to do a little bit more than that
but again we'll just start there again
because it's a simple thing that you can
see I can see it in the code and it
should be pretty trivial so if we gret
if we place that out you can see we have
min corner and Max corner here and we're
creating them this way right and then we
end up making this sort of rectangle
balance thing out of it right so in
order to do that you can see that all of
this stuff is stuff that I know about on
the layout right I know the layout
various at things and all and all this
sort of thing
right I know all of that and so now all
I really need to do is just make sure
that i'm only using the dimension stuff
that gets passed in here like so but
everything else is the same and so what
you can see here is is this is all
calculated for me automatically that's
all good we then can make the rectangle
min max and we can return that and
that's all we would have to do to do the
place rectangle now we can basically
replace this code right here by saying
all right I want to make my rectangle
tube of the bounds I don't know what
size P but that's the location where
we're going to do that so sighs p is
really just the max quarter min corner
of this thing so i guess we would just
do like get max corner of the bounds get
min corner of the bounds it's really
just that that's the size B so now we
can kind of say like all right all of
this stuff does not matter we'll just
grab the dimension pass the layout and
then all of this stuff just kind of
nicely goes away right and all of this
stuff just kind of works so in theory
now our profile stuff is going through
there and should just work and it does
so that's nice so that's step one and
now step two would be it would be nice
if we could do the same thing you know
just just leverage that same code and
you can see here how we have sort of
this bitmap scale notion and what we did
is we sort of corrected the bitmap scale
notion by using this right we connect we
sort of corrected that bitmap display
dim x that stuff but then once we did
that work you know and you can see here
actually that min corner like we were
passing it here but we don't care where
it actually was because we were just
getting the dimensions so really this
could have just been complete nonsense
and min corner could have just been
moved down here right there's nothing
because all we need to know was the size
of the bitmap we didn't really care
where it was right
so what we can do now is say like all
right after doing just this little
preamble and correcting the size which
we want to do we can now leverage this
code that we pulled out into the layout
routine to have it do the layout for us
which is what we want because now again
we're reducing that code duplication and
making it so that things are kind of
nicely coherent right and now you can
see is it's going to get that size peak
which we can copy from here hopefully
you are getting the same sense that I am
about that size P if you're not that's
okay we'll talk about in a second but
anyway yet you can then see like okay
this guy needs to get the min corner of
the bounds in order to draw the bitmap
there but then again we've successfully
compressed that code which is great so
now this and this are using the same
layout routine and that's exactly what
we wanted because now again anyone who
wants that sort of thing can just make
that happen right can just make that
sort of Bounce thing happen really
easily for them and they don't really
have to do any any work anymore work on
it right okay so what I'd like to do now
is I'd like to expand potentially this
notion because when we were doing that
like I saw like I can't just pointed out
the size box is also the same on both of
them so it would be kind of nice if the
layout routines could just do the size
box for us because again then every time
if we want it to go add something that
work the same way the other fees profile
or the bitmap views work if we want to
add those we could just leverage that
code right we could make it so that
anyone wants a size box it's free they
just say like oh I wants by the way I
want a size box right and that's what
you want in a good UI system you want to
be really easy for people to just say oh
I wanted to use that thing and it's as
easy as possible for them to do so so
how do we do that part right so to do
that part what we'd like to do is pull
out these things you can see there's the
size fee right and let's see where that
that drawing happens right so you can
see it all happening here we've kind of
got this apart occurring there like that
and so if you look at it we've got some
things that are that are pretty
tricky here right so first of all we
know that the size P is related off the
bound so that's pretty easy for the
layouts us to understand it's pretty
easy for it to know how to draw like
whatever it wants to draw like a you
know whatever it's trying to draw like
that little square that's not a big deal
sighs interaction is pretty obvious what
it's going to be but you could always
override it as well so that's not a big
deal but this part is a little trickier
it needs to be able to override whatever
happening in this because we want to
make sure that these is in rectangle
calls don't sort of conflict with each
other right if I was to do this then we
have sort of a bit of a problem on our
hands right because if you look at what
occurs when you do that you can kind of
see that now the upper part well you
know maybe you can't see that actually
maybe only I can see that because it's
like not going to be clear enough on the
twitch but well you actually know what I
can do for you here's what I'll do if I
just make this much bigger and obviously
this is ludicrous and you wouldn't want
to do it but it just makes it clearer so
if I come in here and open this guy up
again now I've got a giant sized box
well you can see that only part of the
rectangle works this part works just
firing I can grab it but in here it
doesn't work in here it thinks I was
interacting with the circle I'm with the
bitmap itself and it does the tear-off
interaction which is what we wanted to
do but not when we're right there when
we're right there I should be reacting
with this that is because like the way
that we are doing our hip testing right
now is just in order which means that
whoever hit test first is the weakest
and whoever hit test last is the
strongest in terms of who gets
preference because it just over rights
whatever the earlier head tests were
right now we could introduce a z-value
or something here if we wanted to sort
of sort those but it you know it it
might be you know I don't know if we
really want to do something like that is
that really necessary you know and so on
when we could perhaps just make sure we
architect this thing to you know to tell
us essentially whether or not we're
interacting with with what's in that or
whether we're inside that particular
thing so what I was thinking is you know
we could do something more along the
lines let's just I'm just spit
ballin here what if we did something
that was more like this where we said
Jimmy what if we did something like okay
we want to do a rectangle so we do
something like begin rectangle you know
like this so this is like a this is a
layout or well element will just say
right and this is going to be our only
element really that we have so we'd say
something like you know begin elements
rectangle and we pass the dimensions of
that rectangle then we would say you
know something like ad size or make
sizable or element set sizable make
element sizable I don't know the name I
don't I'm not just saying that I
literally just don't know the name so
like I want to make this element sizable
you know whatever it is so let's go
ahead and do that and then at the end
you just do something like if and
element like that and we'll just say
that this will return to you you know
whether or not you should process your
interaction whether or not you're like
the mouse is going to be something that
you're going to deal with or whether
it's something that was dealt with by
the layout system right so it just kind
of lets you know and that way we
wouldn't have to introduce things like
ze or stuff like that which may just
over complicate things for no real you
know obvious value if that makes sense
seems pretty reasonable and so if we do
something like that then we would end up
being able to abstract presumably all of
this stuff away right like all of this
stuff could kind of get sucked up into
this system here
that was a little tight go there and so
this would start to look pretty nice at
that point right we would sort of have
this ability to do the layout like this
and you know yeah this is just a regular
drawing code that we're using to draw
everything we wouldn't need to draw the
size box that could be handled up here
as well so yeah I think that's pretty
good I might say that like maybe we draw
this first so that we have the UI system
control like on top of us but otherwise
you can see this is starting to get like
much nicer now and doesn't have all of
this stuff in it and and this guy would
get even simpler right because this guy
doesn't need the size interaction or any
of these things with the size box he
just has his draw profile in call right
and so he would be even simpler he would
just look like this where we do like
elements excisable end elements
something like that and then here it
would just look like this right so I
think that's really good I think that's
pretty good so all we would really need
there is a way of saying what the
dimensions actually were that we wanted
sized now there's a couple of ways we
could do that I'm going to go for the
most direct route here I don't know if
it's the best idea but I'm going to do
it so when we pass the dimensions I'm
going to pass the address and then it
will just know when it's sizable it will
use the address that was already passed
in this function right so now you can
see we're getting like really pretty
simple here for the most part and um
yeah well you know what now that I think
about it there is one thing that's a
little bit trickier here right which is
that we don't know what the bounds are
perhaps until the element is finished so
that might make it a little harder in
that sense I'm not sure how I feel about
that
hmm well let's find out I'm going to go
a little further with this because I
can't quite predict what I want so I'm
just going to see how it goes by playing
around with it so what I'm going to
assume is we have something like this
where we just do draw profiling at the
end element of bounds like this right
and that's I guess just what I'll do for
now and we have make elements sizable
there so this all kind of works out and
we have something that looks like this
now at that point advanced is no longer
really necessary either because advanced
can happen inside here inside where we
do our our element stuff so we can also
kind of just say that you know the
advancement happens like in here right
and so I think we're now down to like
some really straightforward stuff so you
can kind of see we've got all this stuff
compressed pretty tightly there's not
very much code that you would have to
write and in fact this part right here
we could almost also do we could almost
let that happen automatically as well we
could say something like the default
interaction gets passed in here like
something like default interaction you
know I'm saying and then it would just
look like that right and that's pretty
good too so maybe we'll do it that way
as well
that that's pretty good I feel like so
we just say okay we have a tear
interaction here that we're going to do
and then we would say you know this sort
of thing default interaction is the tear
interaction and there's that element
again right the bounds min x been why
thing minus equals layout spacing wide
that should also probably be in here and
we should probably just have a way of
turning it off I'm guessing so it's
probably something like okay you know
we're going to add the spacing right
here right and then we just do something
where that would be turned off so we do
something like you know if there was
some kind of override for the text so I
think that looks pretty good to me that
seems like the right thing again this
guy's code is a little more complicated
just because he's doing more unique
stuff right but it seems pretty good
again it's simplifying quite a bit and
so then here I think we have roughly the
same thing happening we're getting the
text size that can happen at any time
and then we're sort of doing a bunch of
fussing here with these things here is
obviously our height like we know what
the height is and our width is just
going to be excuse me our width is just
going to be the text bounds with so I
feel like you know we could probably
duplicate this pretty easily by just
doing like you know let's see here do
this exact same code if we were going to
phrase it in this exact way right we
would just do something like okay begin
an element the v2 for this guy this is
the dimensions right the v2 for this guy
is going to be
the text bounds get width text bounds
and then whatever the layout line
advance is right something like this and
so this stuff can kind of go away I
think the debug text out that's going to
be whatever the the bounds come back as
right and all I can also this item
interaction is the default interaction
as well so all that stuff goes away
right and so looking at this stuff well
I've got left PX that's just going to be
the get min corner right that's just
going to be whatever my element bounds
are after it's finished and then the top
where we do the get starting baseline
thing I believe that's just going to be
so get the max corner why and then we're
doing this sort of like offset to align
the font properly to align where that's
going to be baseline wise but then this
goes away as well you know so i think
that's relatively clean again like seems
all pretty straightforward i like the
look of it it's pretty reasonable and
now all of these guys are going through
the same path so let's go ahead and see
what it looks like if we just implement
those exactly as they are all right so
what would I do there I would go ahead
and say we have these functions and I
think those are actually the only
functions that we have right so we've
have like a function here that rude
turns a layout elements called begin
element rectangle right and it takes a
layout and it takes a pointer to the
dimensions of that rectangle we then
have a layout elements here where we say
that we want it to be sizable and that
would add the size box to it we then
have a way of setting its default
interaction
and that is just going to be a debug
interaction and finally we have a way of
ending it saying that we were done with
all of the specification that we wanted
to to have so I think that's all good
the way that this is working now we can
kind of just do with this all in line at
the moment so I feel like that's
probably good enough so I'm just going
to go ahead and do it all in line you
could defer this stuff to the end so
that when you call end element you do it
trying to think if that makes sense it
probably does let's go ahead and say
that does so here is like a b2 to be v2
dim there this will be the size quainter
as well there will have the layout
itself in here just putting these
together here eh this probably wants to
be in there as well and all this is
really doing is naming a bunch of stuff
and and storing it around so that it can
be done in sort of that piece male
fashion so that people can kind of
construct the UI elements they want and
get it right so yeah I think that's all
good I feel like that all makes
relatively good sense so let's just go
ahead and implement that when I do begin
element rectangle what I'm going to do
here oh and then of course we have some
out params
which was like the rectangle to which
are the bounds so what I want to do now
is I want to make it so that basically
when you call end element that puts
everything together so essentially like
all of the stuff that we were doing here
so place rectangle essentially all of
this stuff is going to happen here like
everything right so the default
interaction thing is just going to go
ahead and set the element interaction to
interaction the make element sizable is
just going to set the size pointer to be
the same as the dim pointer and the
element dim I'm sorry the the begin
element layout is just going to
initialize these things to reasonable
values right so the layout equals the
layout the gym equals the dim size is
null the interactions know the bounds
are no that's it so once all those are
set then when we get down to the end
here we now need to figure out how big
this thing is supposed to be right so
the first thing that I would say we want
to do is like we want to create like the
total dim of this thing and the total
dim is obviously going to be whatever
dimension that they actually asked for
but now like maybe like we say if you
want a size the thing right you want to
change the things sighs maybe we want to
put like a sizing frame around it right
a be a little bit more like a
traditional thing where there's you know
you can grab any corner of it or
something like that and pull it out or I
don't know right it doesn't even make
any sense to say that really so I
suppose I don't even know why I'm saying
it but let's just go ahead and pretend
that you can do that and so we're going
to do that all right so we have one of
these elements we said that we're going
to make it sizable and so what I'd like
to do is take the total dimension and I
just want to expand that dimension for
by however big I want sort of
that size boxes hit area so if I take a
look at the map I think we might I don't
know if we have a grow or a big house
key some in here let's see if we do
doesn't look like we do I thought we did
there we go ad radius to write so I'd
like to do is take the total dim and the
total dim welcomes are going to do it in
line here it's just add radius to
whatever that actual dim was and this v2
is going to be like the frame you know
it's like the chrome of this thing and
we'll start out at 0-0 but if the saw if
we have like a thing that we're trying
to make you late for the size will take
the frame and we'll make that be like a
you know sighs handle width or something
with that frame size angle pixels she'll
do with that right and so we can just
say ok there's you know sighs handle it
sits for pixels wide or something like
that so we're going to add that like
around sort of the outside of the thing
right and then we now have the actual
dimensions of the entire frame which is
again bigger than the dimensions of the
thing that we're actually going to
return to the user we're going to tell
the user that the thing is like the the
inset of that the original dim ok so
then we're going to produce the min and
Max corner of the like of the total and
the minute max corner like we're based
going to produce these rectangles right
so I'm going to start by saying like
okay maybe maybe we've got a like total
min corner and total max corner and then
we have a yeah and then we and then we
have the sort of the inset one as well
so we know that this is actually this is
all actually correct right this is
actually the corners of these things but
the depart where we subtract the dim
instead of of you
using just the interior dim we want to
use the total dim here and then
similarly for the max corner we want to
use the total damn for the width I think
we had about 20 minutes on the clock so
I'm going to go to about 6 15 or so 620
all right so we did that then we know
that if we want to create the regular
min corner and the regular max corner
like you you know I guess client is
usually what's called like in windows
for example i don't know i call it the
interior maybe the interior min corner
is going to be the total is going to be
the total min coroner offset by whatever
that radius difference is right so if we
add the frame to the total min corner
well i guess we have to technically do
since it's kind of annoying because of
the way that we've built things no I
guess that's right you just add the
frame you're done right so that's total
min corner the interior max corner is
just going to be the min corner plus the
actual dim right whatever that dim
whatever that dim is and the actual dim
is just the element dim like this I feel
like that's what we would need to do
there that seems right I feel like this
part the total max corner again can just
just be the total min corner plus the
total damn that's just the definition of
it so we can just save ourselves some
time there and that all looks about
right to me so now we have both of these
things so we can produce anything that
we want now we can have the total bounds
and that's just the total min corner and
the total max corner we can also have
the elements bounds that we're going to
return to the user we now know what that
is as well right we have the interior
min corner and the interior max corner
like that and in here we can we can now
use those to produce exactly what we
want our size stuff and our our thing
that we return and we can do all of our
size checking and everything else that
we want to do
so in here this is the code that does
the advancement of the app why and so I
think what I'll probably do is push that
all the way to the end and the way that
will do that I guess the way that will
do that is will say whatever the min
corner is of the total bounds we want to
do that and then we want to advance by
the spacing right so I think that's just
about correct and then we need to sort
of do that special case for the text
there where we have somebody who's
telling us what the spacing between two
lines of text should be which is
different you know then when we're
putting rectangles together so in here
when we do the rest of the stuff okay me
when we've got the size box that has to
come in there this is the code for
putting that size box in place for now I
guess what we'll do is we'll just draw
sort of that total balance as like a
maybe like a black border thing and then
we'll put a little thing in the corner
of it well no because we went allowed to
be see-through so what I'll actually
just go ahead and draw the whole border
of the thing right so to draw the border
of the thing what we'd like to do is is
first I'll just draw the upper trying to
think can we even just well I'll just
I'll just draw each individual part
because I think we're probably going to
want to make this a little bit fancier
in a second here so drawing each
individual part you know we know we have
to put a rectangle here right something
like this and then we know that we need
to pass whatever we want the color to be
for now I'm just going to pass anything
that's not the size box portion of it
I'm just going to pass black just for
now then the size box will have a
separate thing will treat the size box
exactly the same way as we were doing
before so fierce that size box code the
size P never actually gets used except
in the size box there so I'm just going
to say will create the size box we have
the size interaction we know everything
that that's going to be and we know
exactly
as well who it's going to modify because
they pass that into us so everything
else here I think can just totally work
right and I feel like end elements is
doing the work should probably also take
the debug state so it can do
modifications to it although i don't
know maybe everyone wants that so maybe
really that should just be something
that gets put in here again these are
going to be on like sort of in the
compilers purview to like eliminate and
simplify I think for the most case so i
don't i'm not too worried about like
sort of storing extra pointers and doing
stuff here because they're just kind of
temporary variables and that's all they
really do all right so there we go with
the with the debug state that all looks
good to me so in here i can also pull
that out right i could say that the
debug state equals the element debug
state and i could say that's layout
close to home now that's just like
convenience okay so i think that's all
good so I just have to finish this stuff
up here so the size box is the only
thing that we don't have here I'm going
to make the size box be a rectangle min
max actually and the way that that's
going to go is I'm going to have the
rectangle min max go from the get I kind
of want it to be you know that that
lower corner of the thing so I want it
to be the get min corner of the well
this is that annoying thing that's it's
not quite the min it's like the min-max
corner so I have to actually create the
v2s to pick out the thing that I want
which is kind of annoying but oh well so
we want the max corner of the Interior
right bounds and I guess you know what I
already have that I know its interior a
max corner I want that X and the y I
want the interior max corner y as well
right or I know sorry VIN corner because
i want that lower one and then I want
the interior
sorry the total max corner X for the
width and I mean for the place to go out
to and I want the interior min corner
equivalent as well for the for the total
so I'm just kind of drawing from the
from the from the interior to the
exterior so that's just that little
corner piece so that's the part that
will do for the size box for now and
then for this guy I just want to do
again essentially that exact same thing
I'm going to sort of hand code here the
rectangles that would give us a border
around the thing and then we'll kind of
look at doing something maybe a little
bit fancier in a second so all right I
got to draw four edges so i'll start by
drawing the left edge and i'll draw the
left edge i'm going to draw it without
the corners in place for the moment and
there's a rhyme or reason for that but
we'll talk about in a second so i want
to draw it without the corner so i want
to do is the width at sort of the the
interior min corner right and the end
the total min corner let those in the
wrong order their total min corner
pyramid corner sort of form the min and
Max that I'm drawing 2x wise and then
the Y is just going to be the the
minimum Y obviously right would be you
know as realized these two are backwards
to aren't that right this this is going
to be greater than this always right so
this these are these are the minimums
here and these are the maximums so
anyway I'm going to start at that Tobin
corner going to go to the max winter for
X and then in why I'm going to do
essentially the same thing right I'm
going to I'm going to just pick out I
want to go from the the the interior min
corners why up to the interior max
corners why so just spanning that entire
interior length right and I can just do
that exact same thing on the other side
so
so if I want to do the interior max
corner to the total max corner right I
can do sort of the yeah that was a big
mistake as well I can do the outside one
so that's the left edge on the right
edge and then I can do the top and the
bottom here in exactly the same way
right in fact you could almost it
probably just copy exactly what I did
like here so it's going to be interior
oh well but because we're going upside
down left to right I don't know it's a
little bit flipped around but either way
so for here I want to be able to start
probably at the total min corner why and
go up to the interior min corner why and
for the X i want to start from that
interior min corner X I want to go all
the way to the interior Mac Mac's corner
X right so that's again exact the same
thing here and that can be duplicated
because this part is the same and now
it's just going to be these two guys are
going to be slightly different right
you're going to start at that interior
max corner and go to the total maximum
so that will draw all those rectangles
let's take a look here there's steak
there epub state
let's see what else we got ad radius two
electrodes can convert all advertised
idries to rectangle to v2 is that not
what we had with a V 2 and 0 oh right
that's actually just a dim so we don't
need to do is add radius to at all just
add a to the dimension 2 times the thing
that's that's pretty easy so that's good
so there you go easier than thought it's
going to be so then this guy the size
interaction needs to be part of this
used to be defined first that's all fine
the mouse p we don't know and so the
mouse p also would have to be something
that kind of comes in here that's a
little annoying and we probably want to
actually fix that in a slightly separate
way so we'll take a look like that well
you know what actually we can fix it
right now that would just go in here
right that would be that would be where
that goes because that way when you
recreate the layout you put the mouse be
in there and it flows through everything
properly at that point okay so let's see
this guy has to take the debug state now
as well oh and you know what that's
actually a good point too why aren't why
isn't that in here right because again
these are just I think these will all be
relatively easy for the product pile out
although to be honest with without no
aliasing turned on maybe it will get a
little confused unfortunately but yeah
this is not super performance oriented
code so presumably we wanted to worry
too much about it we'll find out so yeah
that is how we would have to get at the
DIA web state but I think that's better
because then it doesn't get passed every
time can just something like that right
alright so moving on
when we do the layouts here we would
just say debug state equals debug state
and mass the equals mouse p and then
those are done okay so what's going on
here we got our bounds we're doing our
push Rex that stuff is going to happen
here and it is going to happen with the
element bounds and let's see element
bounds apparently what bounds we talked
about here okay we're talking about
element bounds again we go we've got
getwidth identify are not found I think
it's actually get dim why oops text and
layout is a dot there let's see beacon
element rectangle that's just going to
take the address all right so we made a
lot of changes so I'm sure this will be
a complete catastrophe but let's find
out wait that's got a size box oh we
didn't put it we didn't put a predicate
around that um okay my bad sorry about
that guys you know I forgot about that
so yeah after we can struct all these
things this stuff all of this is
actually only going to happen right all
of that stuff is actually only going to
happen if we had a size box so let's
just make sure that's out of there
that's not good why is that happening
what just happened there if element size
you push all the wrecks if not you don't
we didn't make the element up well that
do it we told that it was sizable
operator error okay good so that's
working now we just need to go in and
actually add the default interaction
right so if the default interaction with
something so like you know if
this elements interaction what did I
call that interaction type if they set
it to something then I want to do
looking if and I guess I could put and
is in rectangle for the actual interior
bounds so the elements bounds right if
that's the case then i'm going to set
the debug states next hot interaction to
this guy and I'd like this to I'd like
the size box to take precedence even
though now they don't overlap if we
chose to have them overlap I would like
that take precedence so let's see how we
do so somewhat surprisingly everything
seems to be actually working pretty well
ah so yeah well that went a lot better
than I was expecting to be fair so yeah
we did it um expecting after debug some
of that well that's fine I'm not going
to complain about not having to debug
okay so now if we wanted to write we
could also make it so all of these size
pieces like this was actually a thick
frame that actually could have sizing
associated with it or something like
that right where you could go in and and
actually size from any of these pieces
that you wanted to I don't know that we
want to really do that right now because
we're kind of getting to the end of the
stream but point being that's all now
possible and of course we should also
check make sure that like these guys are
also working properly they are right so
that's all good looking nice looking
nice so yeah okay I'm pretty happy with
that pretty happy with that
so now we can also start to expand see a
little bit more so i think i'm going to
save it for tomorrow because i think
that's that's like we're a good stopping
point we pulled out all the layout code
so then now it's pretty trivial to just
like that's the entirety of the code
that it takes to code a new element now
which is pretty great and we can just
start adding more things in there like
if they're movable or terrible or other
things we can make that sort of
encapsulated in there so that you can
just add more properties that you might
want to your to your stuff all right I
don't know if I can go to a QA because I
don't have the ability to connect to the
internet apparently it's pretty awesome
its just oh poor Linux it never actually
ever works unfortunately I wish it did
cuz I would switch to it on everything I
could but I can't so I won't so I guess
I'll just go ahead and reboot this
machine so i can actually use the
wireless in it and we'll just hope that
maybe that works not particularly
optimistic of course since reboot
doesn't work either i have to actually
fill up a nerve pinch this machine and
then start it back up again but yeah so
i'll probably have fun reinstalling the
sky tonight i guess if i regress back
down to 14 which is what it was running
on previously maybe that would work i
don't know i would certainly be
interested in suggestions from people
who actually run linux on optimus
laptops people who run linux on desktops
they don't quite understand just how
hard it is to get linux to run on an
optimist laptop it's like almost
impossible nothing ever works sound
doesn't work the graphics don't work
sleep doesn't work and of course
Wireless doesn't work and so if you are
someone who has a lot of experience with
getting the next to work on Optimus
laptops modern Optimus laptops do let me
know if there's a particular
distributions that you found actually is
reliable on them because I would you
know I'll try installing some different
things
right and see if any of them work since
I have to reinstall it anyway it's free
for me to try out some different things
alright so if you have questions please
post them with Q colon because I
probably and do it quickly I guess
because I probably will only be able to
see questions for like 15 seconds or
something but we'll do the best we can
it is kind of crazy how not working this
laptop is yeah this is this is a
disaster I can't see anything can I why
don't you connect to chat with your
desktop it's a good question I because
it was nice hat kind of having the chat
up on the side that I could just look at
and it used to work so I'm going to get
it working again and that way I can have
it so I'll do that tonight I'll actually
get it working to a certain extent
hopefully reasonable I could also maybe
just plug in a net cable or something
like that I don't know it's so weird I
don't understand how like it can't
connect to the wireless any more like
how does that even happen how does it
even happen I don't even know so it just
disconnected again how is it like how
are you connected to the wireless and
then it just stops working it doesn't
make any sense like what is happening
inside i wish i could see the code right
now i want I mean the Linux code is
public right so like I want something
where I can just kind of they need some
like a linux code explorer when I can
just go see like okay show me who is
actually responsible for the wireless
networking right now what is the code
doing such that it could connect and
then just spontaneously disconnect even
though nothing has happened you know
nothing at all and and I wish I I wish I
could understand this but I don't it's a
mystery to me and there's like tons of
different wireless networks listed here
and mines listed but it just doesn't
think connect
so fascinating is this like what I don't
know either like is this what it's like
like when Linux developers are like
using Linux tit is this what it's like
for them did they have some kind of
magical machines that work or they just
like cool with it or they're just like
gal you know it doesn't work it doesn't
work like I just won't use Wi-Fi today
or until this Colonel gets revised or
whatever yes I think that's not going to
happen all right so I guess there's no
QA today my job for this evening will be
to restore the laptop to working order
so that I can actually answer some
questions on the stream you will have to
wish me some luck with that because it's
linux and luck is usually very much
required so hopefully if I'm if i am
lucky i will be able to find a
distribution that will work on this
laptop without me having to go like
patch the drivers or something but you
never know okay so i will why it down
hopefully the stuff that we did in
today's dream was pretty straightforward
so there wouldn't be too many questions
about it essentially what it was you
know was sort of the same thing i did in
the witness right and so you know if you
want to take a look at this some more
you can go if you type k senior tory
calm and it'll just redirect you to my
page easy to remember if you look at the
working on the witness series here
they're not very i want to move this
over to the new web gem stuff because
it's better but like you can jump
through these the first like I think up
through 11 maybe our grass but then
number 11 starts talking about almost
exactly the same thing so the witness
code looked exactly like our code from
before this stream kind of looked and
this is like the sort of stuff that was
happening in that code and again it was
just because nobody bothered like really
cared
about that part and you know John's
pretty good about like not over
engineering stuff so it's like if people
haven't done a lot of you I then there's
just not it's just like whatever it's
whatever it is but it's still really
written pretty sensibly because John's a
good programmer and so you know that's
what we had the beginning stream today
like when i came across in the witness
it looked exactly like what we had this
dream today sort of everything was done
manually all the time for the most part
and very few things had been compressed
out and so what I did is I just went
through and did exactly look and see I
even made the same thing like a panel
layout guy who does starts doing the
layout and I just kind of started
reducing the code down and like I said I
think that's sort of the same thing
that's like John's approach to so it's
like again I don't think it was like
John wanted the code the other way I
think John just never cared about this
particular use of code and so he was
just kind of waiting for time to
actually do any of that stuff I assume
and I was the person who would happen to
be writing a lot of you I could so I was
like now is the time and so literally
it's you know what I showed in today's
dream is literally something i did on a
production project like not less than
two years ago right because on any
project especially one that's as big as
the witness nobody has the time to go do
the right thing everywhere right let's
forget it there's too much stuff to do
and too much to worry about and so you
have to pick and choose we're going to
do stuff and so the right time for
something like what i did is when
somebody's going to come along and do a
bunch of heavy work on this thing then
that is the time to go hey let me get
more serious about this right and so
like I said this is exactly the sort of
thing that happens and in like so I
literally this is the kind of thing that
I actually do in real life it's exactly
the same and you can almost see it
playing out exactly the same way so if
you look at these articles stuff I did
on the witness for like just cleaning up
the UI system a little bit for the
editor is exactly the same stuff that we
did today it's just really standard very
straightforward coding and it's like I
said it's a really good way to go lazy
compression is a really good programming
methodology because it means you're not
spending a lot of time over
engineering things that don't need that
but it does mean that like you're not
going to end up with total spaghetti
code because you're actually doing the
compressions when necessary and you know
it's generally the case to like on the
witness right now the places that are
spaghetti ish are just the places where
people haven't had the time to go you
know actually figure out how to like
pull the stuff out of it and make it
like cleaner right and so every so often
somebody when they're like oh my god I'm
going to go have to do a bunch of work
in this code I know it's kind of messy
that's the time ago okay hold on stop
before I do that let me go pull some of
the stuff out a little bit more before I
start making them it worse by adding you
know more UI code on top of a kind of a
super verbose stringy implementation let
me stop now is the time to like figure
out some compressions on this get it
down to a nice simple core and then then
I add on right don't be the guy who just
comes and is going to add a hundred UI
features and and just cut and paste all
the code and adds at all and it's just
that you're you know don't be that guy
when you come to something you like you
can see that the programmer before you
haven't yet put it into like a toolkit
kind of thing they're like go do that
work first don't leave a giant mess for
them you know it's kind of a good thing
so anyway you can take a look at these
are supplied shove posts on it there's a
quite a few actually right 14 15 16 yeah
17 so that's that's that all right thank
you everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade here it's my
pleasure coating with you as always if
you would like to follow along at home
you can pre-order the source code on
handmade hero or well period of the game
it comes with the source code I'm Hannah
media org you can download it every
night I upload it right after I'm done
so you can always work on sort of the
the most recent one just like I am we
also have a patreon page you want
support the video series you can
subscribe to that it's always much
appreciated we also have a for website
we can go to ask questions or view anted
episode guide with previous episodes if
you missed any and want to catch up we
have a tweet pot you can go to if you
want to know what the schedule is and
yeah if you want to let schedules for
tomorrow I will be back here 5 p.m.
pacific daylight time tomorrow and we
will do some more you I coding starting
to look pretty good
like I said we're getting there we're
sort of starting to get things into a
pretty nice clean way and so we can
start to sort of Titan a few more screws
down on that and then add a few more
things to kind of let us the thing that
I really want to do is be able to view
like our profile and view our memory we
need some UI for that that'll work a
little better than we've got now so
there we go hope see you back here
tomorrow until then please have fun
programming and I'll see you guys on the
internet take use everyone