hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream yesterday despite the fact that I
had an out of shame situation where I
had actually put the displacement for
our for our world entity tracking into
the wrong line of code thus causing us
like literally fifteen minutes and about
you we didn't have to to uh-huh
everything went smoothly otherwise and
so the thing that we were attempting to
do which is to move our entity unpacked
storage into sort of a secondary cache
that operates on in front of our world
access it seems to be going just fine
and so what I want to do today is just
actually finish the next part of that
which is instead of always creating and
destroying all the entities every frame
in the unpacked state I want to actually
just leave them around so we any time we
kind of go to do unpacking entities we
only unpack ones that aren't already
unpacked and we leave ones that are
unpacked unpacked now I don't anticipate
that taking really any time at all
that's probably quite simple because all
it really involves is not doing some
work we're currently doing so why do I
think we need two hours to do it well
the reason I think we need two hours to
do it is because the other end of it
actually is relatively difficult because
it's unclear exactly how you would do it
and that is packing them back up again
so if we unpack our entities into sort
of a cache they get operated on I and
they just stay in that cache and keep
getting operated on as long as they're
needed
the thing that is unclear is what how do
we know when to pack them back up right
and so what we're looking for is we need
some kind of a way of remembering what
are all the world chunks that have been
unpacked and could be repacked or
something like this and we need to
only repack entities when it seems like
they're not actually being used and so
on and so what we really need to start
taking a look at is some way when we do
our updating of our entities we need to
look at some way we can logically deduce
when is the right time to take those
entities and pack them back up and it's
kind of tricky because I mean honestly
like the only thing can really think of
to do is not particularly efficient and
that is to just say as we do a pass over
our entities the entities that are
actually inside entities that are
outside of the active region can look to
see if their world chunk is also outside
the active region and if it is you pack
it back up as I'm saying that it
actually doesn't sound as stupid as as I
thought it was so maybe that is what
we'll do but either way that looking at
that sort of aspect of the system is
really the part that then is the part
that will require the finesse so
unpacking entities is easy because we
get called explicitly to do it knowing
if entities are unpacked is also easy
because world chunks get removed from
the system entirely when their impact so
it just wouldn't ever happen they just
stay in the set so the thing that's
really going to take our time I think is
figuring out exactly what to do about
that sort of other that the other
repacking step so let's go ahead and
just dive in here there's a couple
things we can do to get started that
really don't require any finesse at all
they're just cleaning up code that now
we don't probably need or want because
of the changes that we're making let me
just go ahead and rerun to make sure
that we're all on the same page here but
I think we're good we left it in a good
state yesterday here's the game running
everything's fine just as it normally is
so no no big deal there so if we go into
the world set here and we guess I'm open
on this side I'm gonna open up the pass
that goes through the sim region here
and how we do sort of those entity
references and that stuff I want to take
a look at something I put it to do in
for which was the traversable reference
and the entity reference stuff I think
they all use enemy reference yeah so
this stuff here where we sort of have a
pointer index dichotomy I think what we
want to do here is change entity
references to just be entity IDs I don't
think we really want this anymore
I think we want to just reference by ID
always and anytime you want to get an ID
from now on I think what you want to do
is just ask the hash to give you back
whoever that particular idea is that
you're talking about right and so I want
to get rid of that because we sort of
have this this nonsense going on right
now where when we were sort of filtering
this stuff through we we have this
let's see repack we have this nonsense
going on here where we have to do this
like pack and unpack these references
and stuff and it's just looking at it
you're like why are you doing that every
time on these entities when all you're
saving is like a hash table lookup which
probably isn't particularly expensive
especially since this hash table is
probably mostly hot it just it doesn't
make a lot of sense to me so it just
seems like a much ado about nothing it's
packing something that probably just
shouldn't ever actually be unpacked at
all it should just stay the way it is
and so I'd like to go ahead and make
that change and get that going so the
first thing I'm going to do there is I'm
just gonna get rid of entity reference
and I'm gonna see what happens when I do
that so I'm gonna I'm gonna delete that
and I'm gonna have an entity ID replaced
there so we just say look when you want
a reference identity you just use an
entity ID there isn't anything else that
goes on there and so when you do like is
equal on these things you can just
actually call this is equal over here
you don't do references or equal you
just say that
and so that's the change we're gonna
propagate through the code and that's
all I'm gonna do first so that's gonna
require anyone who is previously using
the reference as a pointer is going to
have to now use it as a hash table
lookup so we do have to fix that one
part in repack entities as necessary
that was the only region this reason the
sim region was being packed
I'm sorry past so we're going to get rid
of that parameter as well and I'm gonna
delete the packed reversible Skol
correspondingly when we registered
entities back in the old system oops I
don't know what that just did when we
were registering entities here what we
would do is we add them to the hash
string register entity and then we had a
second pass where the entire thing we
were doing here was sort of doing this
occupier traversable reference nonsense
that was happening here and so what we
want to do is clean that out like we
want all of this stuff to now just work
directly off of entity IDs so this loop
also needs to go away
so we need to again to simplify this
code down because it seems clear to me
now that we've put it out there that
it's just a wait it's just nonsense it
doesn't need to be there and we're just
adding complexity and failure
possibilities for no reason so we want
these things to the extent that they end
up persisting in the game if they do to
all be entity IDs that you just referred
to and so both the traversable reference
itself in the two places where that's
used and then the entity IDs I'm sorry
for the occupying that came from there
those are now in of the IDs as well and
so all of that stuff I think I think
that probably cover all of it and so now
we just have to change the usage code to
be aware of that it can't use pointers
anymore when it calls things it has to
actually use sort of a lookup into the
hash table all right so when we do it
get traversable here get entity by ID I
think is the function that we need and
it's it's already it pretty much just
does exactly what
want so there's not a lot here that we
have to do other than string to thread
you know we got to thread our function
calls with access to the hash table so
the real only annoying part is like this
is gonna have to happen in a couple
places because in order to get the hash
you have to know where the hash table is
in the first place and so this part is
gonna be a little annoying but other
than that other than providing that
access I think that's really all we
would need so again that's just kind of
pushing this down a little bit it looks
like looks like most of this stuff
doesn't really need it though so here we
would need it again get some space
reversible for this we would need this
part this needs to be a good hash by the
again right so right here dub use the
same region there we go
okay and what's the problem there none
of the two overloads get reversible do
we have
I meant get finiti by ID don't ask me
why I put get hash by ID that's not what
I wanted at all okay and that looks like
that's not actually advertised anywhere
so I'm gonna go ahead and pull that up
now that everyone's gonna have to call
it I'm gonna put in the H file so
everyone can see it
so see where else we've got
so when we do lieutenant ereference or
load traversable reference i think those
are just for unpacking so i think i'm
just gonna delete them entirely those
should really never happen at all now no
one should be calling them because you
can just load directly and it's fine
right all right so same is true of this
stuff we don't need to pack these
anymore so again this just cleans up the
code it's just it's just code that that
was doing unnecessary work that i don't
want to do okay so again couple more
calls here you can see these calls are
not provided with the sim region so
again this is really just gonna be me
threading that access to the hash table
through here and it's fine you know you
don't have to it's it's totally fine to
provide access to some more things as
things are necessary you'll notice I
tend to not provide access to things if
I don't need them and that's just to
keep the code more functional more
narrowly scoped and so I try to only
provide access to stuff once I see that
somebody's actually doing something and
so in this case I can see why it needs
to happen and so it's happening but
until then I tend not to do that and
that's why these have never taken the
same region simply because they didn't
need it even though they sort of are in
the same region domain of functions all
right excuse me
so here when we're packing this
reference in here we have the entity and
before we were creating a reference out
of it by putting the two things in there
but of course now there's only
thing in there so this is really just
going to store the ID excuse me and
that's it same is true here if we didn't
find it then the result index is just
zero of course in this case it's unclear
to me why we didn't just set it to that
in the first place why result is not
just set to zero at the top and then we
don't have to track anything in fact
yeah I mean looking at this I kind of
want to say that it doesn't make a lot
of sense
so the yeah I mean rather than checking
on that it seems like that would make
more sense wouldn't it because there's
no really no found never gets unset so
it just seems like that's just a little
bit easier so it's like hey there you go
off you go now
I also don't know why we need to return
that because it seems like we could have
just returned this but yeah I don't know
also one thing I would say is why we
aren't setting the results entity to be
the no entity ID I don't know that's a
little bit weird - in fact let me just
look we're we doing that oh I see so
really let's do that I think that's what
we actually want to do there if that
makes sense just to make sure I don't
know what this see actually hasn't it I
just value so if we just want to clear
that right what I would probably just
looks like maybe I wouldn't write it
quite the same way at this point I
probably would return this traversable
reference as the return value now so I'm
not gonna make that change through the
middle out changes but I might just say
to do Casey why doesn't this just return
a traversable reference so
we'll have to look at that later all
right so let's keep going in here where
we've got naught is equal we've got a
traversable reference here and the body
occupying there I'm not sure why that's
not working because it looks like that
should be traversable references in both
cases it was an entity reference that I
replaced right
those weren't traversable references
before were they in here oh they were
all right I don't know why I replaced
those then just being stupid forget that
yeah that's so that's fine if those were
traversal of references I don't know why
I did that that was just dumb all right
so let's see here transactional
occupying wants the sim region now which
we have so does this want that all of
these want them and looks like we're
still going and this is going to be the
same thing here all of these just need
the sim region so this is really just
again threading access to the hash table
through the call chain but not actually
changing the code
really really simple stuff um so let's
see again and I don't think anything
here that's really just adding that
parameter same here and here
and so for this again that pointer
doesn't exist anymore so we're really
just talking about that as the only
thing that happens also we need to pass
the the region for the gets in today's
reversible now to look in the hash table
same thing here with the entity ID and I
think that's mostly what we're dealing
with and so that is I think all we
really need to do and now I just got a
cleanup errors that we've got here
so okay first of all gotta switch to a
debug build so I can actually see what's
going on let me just change the debug
build there and I suspect we also will
have a some issues here with not maybe
clearing some things we needed to clear
because we sort of changed the rules as
to what was going on here I also don't
know I may have accidentally by changing
these the wrong way I may have made some
mistakes so I might also before I start
debugging take a quick look at all the
places that those were being used just
to make sure I didn't screw anything up
there so if that all looks fine to me
that looks fine that all looks good
totally fine
yeah these these look good you know I
don't see any issues there
this all looks totally fine so I don't
think I created any problems using the
occupying and came from part of things
so I think that's all fine there so now
we just got to kind of go through and
figure out did I ruin anything you know
did I did I ruin anything in that change
that causes that causes problems let's
take a look and since we're getting a
hard error there I guess I we are but
I'm not really entirely certain what the
actual problem is okay so it looks like
actually this probably isn't an error
this is just something that we kind of
want to handle and currently aren't so
in here where we do get entity by ID
this is assuming that the entity handle
is always valid and we don't want that
we just want zero back when it's not and
so what I'm going to do there is I'm
gonna just go in to get entity by ID and
I'm going to say look assume that you
get back zero here unless the ID value
is actually valid right and so that's
really what we want I also don't know
why get hash ID from ID whatever produce
a zero oh because it's not in the set so
that'd be fine too
um so I messed that up in fact let me
just show you what I did there I deleted
the wrong part didn't mean to make that
change what I meant to do was this right
so I want to get the hash entry only in
the case where the value is actually
valid if it's not then it's just a zero
so like this person isn't chasing
somebody or isn't occupying a square so
zero is an eval advanced oh that's all I
was trying to do there so taking a look
at this it looks like we're back to good
and so I think that's really all we need
to do for that clean up I don't think
there's much to it I'm gonna hop around
for a little while to make sure that we
didn't introduce any other breakage but
I think that should be fine and again
that just gets us out of the business of
needing to
do any work really on that pack unpacked
side of things because that that work
really just shouldn't have had to be
done as you can see it was a pretty
minimal change so it was really like
much ado about nothing
and it was wasting a bunch of our like
sort of wasting a bunch of code
complexity on something that absolutely
didn't need to be there um so I think
we're good everything seems fine let me
check to make sure the little hopper
dudes down here or hoppin still there we
go yeah so now we've got that out of the
way if we take a look at what's
happening for example in the unpack its
I'm sorry in the begin world change it's
much nicer now right as you can kind of
see because the ensure region is
unpacked call is the only thing we
actually do there isn't this separate
pass happening afterward to link up
these pointers for no reason and so
that's good
similarly on in world change all we do
is just do the basic repack and that
basic repacked isn't doing anything
weird either right so that's really good
so this is just a better position to be
in as we start this next sweep so now
what I want to do is I want to figure
out some way of not repacking all of
these entities every time what I'd like
to do is pack only those entities that
belong to world chunks which are no
longer necessary that's what I'd like
and so I need to do a couple things to
make that work the only complicated one
like I said is figuring out which world
chunks those are and so yeah I'm not
entirely certain but I think I can make
some educated guesses so if you take a
look at what's happening when you ensure
has unpacked what it does is it loops
through and it actually pulls these
world chunks out of the world entirely
that's actually great so if I were to to
sort of put this in terms of traditional
CPU architecture uh if you think about
the way a memory hierarchy is typically
set up in CPU lands you have sort of
rings of storage that get increasingly
further away from the processing core
right so I've got the CPU core and then
I have like an well I have a register
file right which is the closest possible
thing stores the actual values of
registers but then I've got outside of
that an l1 cache an l2 cache oftentimes
an l3 cache and then main memory right
and you can even include like hard drive
and so on after that right so there's
like these sort of like expanding waves
of memory and what we're doing here is
essentially making what amounts to the
l1 cache of our system in a sense so
we've got the sim region which is like
the processing core and we've got the l1
cache sitting on it which is the
unpacked entities and then we've got
what is effectively the l2 cache or main
memory depending how I look at it it's
the one after the next one out is the
actual chunked world storage now in CPU
architecture when you talk about caches
there's a notion of whether they're
inclusive or exclusive of each other and
what that means is if I have an l1 cache
and an l2 cache these are places where
information can be stored but the
information can be the same information
right so if I ask for a particular part
of main memory and I ask for it from the
l1 cache the l1 cache may say I don't
have that I eat ask the l2 cache the l2
cache says I may not have that it asked
main memory that main memory may now
come back to the l2 cache reside in the
l2 cache come back to the l1 cache
reside in the l1 cache as well and then
get handed to the processor right
and now that same piece of information
the copy of whatever was in the main
memory at that location I asked for that
cache line is now filled in l2 and l1
right if that sort of thing happens in
your cache our key it's called an
inclusive cache right meaning that
things that are in the l1 can be
included in the l2 and vice versa
but there's also the concept of an
exclusive cache which is to say that a
particular cache line is either in l1 or
in l2 and if I fill l1 with a cache line
it moves out of l2 and does not exist
there any longer right and so in our
case the kind of a structure we're
building is an exclusive structure we
are storing our world information in
world chunks we're going to be storing
them only when they are not in this
local cache where they're expanded so
just keeping that in mind that's the way
it's currently set up right now I think
we want to keep it that way
so what happens is when we ask the
unpackage chunk we remove that entire
chunks contents from the system it's
gone and it's all unpacked into the
local cache like fast unpacked entity
store and then later if we're going to
repack a chunk it's basically it's it's
almost like not repacking the chunk it's
like creating the chunk wholly new right
where it's like making a totally new
chunk to pack right okay so what we want
to do here is we want to figure out how
to know what chunks to repack and if you
look at the way we're doing it currently
we just pack our chunks all of them
right so when we loop through here we
say if this thing wasn't deleted right
because you can delete an entity if this
thing wasn't deleted then we met then we
pack it back into the chunks and then at
the end we say we've got no entities
what we want is a way of conditionally
calling this code in here instead of
just always calling in for anything
wasn't deleted we want to call it for
anything that wasn't deleted and isn't
likely to be used next frame right
that's what we're actually trying to do
here and that is why I say this is the
part that's really confusing right this
is the part that's hard to figure out
how we want to do it and so one way we
could do it is to just see whether or
not the end EES lie outside the active
region and then if they do we pack them
back up
[Music]
so when I'm saying that it sounds like
ridiculously stupidly easy and I was
like this is gonna be the complicated
part but I'm like is that just it do we
just pass a region and say here's the
here's what I expect to be unpacking
next frame anything that's not close to
this just just repack it I think it is
that simple because we're spatial so I
think that just works I honestly think
that that may be all there is to it so
if you imagine just saying expected been
jumpy expected max chunk P I think I
made a huge deal out of something that
literally is just completely brain-dead
stupid if we just pass essentially what
we either just passed the same region
already or what that we use to unpack or
we just pass what we think the next
frames one would be then I think we can
just just repack those entities and
that's it
not only that but we can do it only if
our entity load is currently over a
threshold invaluable so we can basically
just only repack when we feel like we
need to repack and not otherwise I don't
know man I think that's all there is to
it
so when we produce this entity P here so
what we could do is say look we've got a
couple of different cases we have to
handle now so the first thing is we have
to handle we do have to handle deleting
entities right so so that's actually has
to happen and we don't want to repack
things when we delete entities and so
what I want to do here is probably
something like this I probably want to
keep a thing that's like removed from
unpacked which is not the same as
deleted and so I probably want to do
something like look at the end of this
we're gonna process this slot because we
you know we probably want to reuse this
slot as sort of a free list for
unpacking entities so we're probably
going to maintain a chain that we use
for allocating new entities through the
slots right I and so I think all we
really need to do here is say if we're
gonna delete it then we remove it from
unpacked and we don't do any actual
packing that will just get rid of it in
here we will say if some criteria that
we're about to invoke let me move it
over here so my head's not in the way
then we have packed it and we will say
remove
from unpacked right and here we probably
want to do total entity packs - unpacks
would go here because it's it's every
time we remove one that would happen you
know that deleted part that might
actually if we ever delete entities I
don't remember if we do but that might
have been why we had a differing pack
and unpack to remember those numbers
were slightly different I don't know if
we ever delete entities so do we I think
we do I don't think we ever delete any
entities but anyway so if we take a look
at what's going on in here
the first thing that we want to do
before we actually you know this is this
has to get implemented right so this is
the thing but what we want to do here at
Polk and also this is the thing so I
think what we want to do here is say
look if this entity placement world
position let's just see does it fall
within these if it doesn't then I think
we want to pack it if it does then we
don't right so let's take a look do we
have a way of actually doing that right
so you know we've got these s 32s here
and what I really want to do is just say
are we inside some you know in fact it's
one of these right
it's a min/max pose thing of like a
compound's like an interval right I just
don't know if we have anything that like
checks for a range like is this inside
of these two things and I just want to
see right if it does or if it doesn't
and
I don't see any so I think I'm gonna
have to just write it it's a very simple
function but I I don't see it right yeah
I'd also like to change all these in
lines I don't know why we still have
these in lines here so in line should
just be internal we don't really use in
line anymore it's it's not it's kind of
an old-school thing in line used to do
stuff it doesn't do stuff anymore so
it's just kind of a stupid keyword to
have around it's just distracting you
know I used to use it kind of to remind
myself what was me in line map but it's
really just kind of distracting at this
point because it's like the compiler
does whatever it wants to do and unless
you actually try to force it in line
things yeah it can just decide not to it
doesn't matter whether you put in line
in front of it or not so here in world
position entity P this is the part where
I want to do a check so I'm gonna just
see like if there's an is but you know
isn't contained something like that and
so I want to do an expected min chunk P
n VP expected max chunk P like that and
I want to do like an is contained
function that'll just do the check like
greater than or equal to or whatever on
that set of bounds and you know maybe
like in volume something like that I
don't know I'm not really sure how to
say it well but something like this and
so if we actually say you know this can
change can is contain in chunk volume
and we did like a min or min chunk
max chunk and test chunk like that then
what I want to do is create sort of
giant relation here as my result and
return it and this is just going to be
checking greater than or equal to for
each of these things right so the min
chunk these are actually what chunk X
chunk why's it like that yeah
so basically what I want to say is look
the test chunk chunk X has to be greater
than equal to the Mensch unk of each of
these y&amp;z y and z right and then it
needs to be less than or equal to the
max junk oops and I think that's the way
we've been doing it like I think when we
pass these it's it's less wrinkled look
I'm just going to take a really quick
second to check to see if that was the
convention that I've generally been
using not that we've been using it much
here but yet you can see right we tend
to use an inclusive outer bound on there
so there's our R check we just look to
see if the test is in between the min
and the max including being on on one of
those exactly and once we've done that
what we want to do is use that check to
determine whether or not this thing is
packed now in the case where it is
contained we actually don't want to
check it out to pack it right so we want
to not there because the case that we're
when we're actually packing entities
into chunks is we're packing them into
chunks when they're outside of the
region we expect to simulate not when
they're inside it all right
um so taking a look at this this is just
again the the this is just the standard
packing that we were doing before this
packs it up in there and we really don't
have to do much else than that I think
that's gonna be basically it so I think
all the stuff I was like this is gonna
be really difficult and blah blah blah
it actually I think turns out to really
not be difficult at all so off we go so
the other thing that I think we want to
do here is inside the world we want this
cash to be fairly like intelligent I
think so in here where we've got max
unpacked nd count and unpack sanity
count I think what I want to do is track
these things a little bit more
specifically so that I know when I'm in
a more pressured scenario right and we
don't have to I essentially don't want
to be packing things if I don't have to
might be the way to say it so in other
words until I actually hit a certain
thresholds I don't want to bother
packing up entities
I'm not sure exactly how I want to track
that but in imagine this right so I
essentially want something like current
unpacked entity count and like unpack
identity like well to be honest we can
kind of get rid of this and probably
just thread it to begin with so
something like this where we have
current unpacked entity count and what I
want to do is something where in here we
would say look while the current
unpacked entity count is greater than
like our threshold alike
I'm almost making another parameter
something like this then we would pack
so in other words if this criteria if
we've exceeded the number of currently
unpacked entities then we want to pack
otherwise we just don't so even if these
things are really far away we don't care
we'll just leave them unpack because we
want to use all of our cash space and
not waste work so when we come through
here then we say alright this current
unpacked entity counts this thing goes
down every time that happens and it goes
up every time this happens and that's
our actual that's our actual number
and so here we will assert that the this
number is greater than zero because you
shouldn't ever be able to pack out more
than the total number that exists and
here when we unpack we're gonna add that
in there now
when we add an entity this actually
occurs as well and so I think what we
kind of want to do here is we want to
track the creation of the entity that
here this may also been a source of our
off of our numbers being off in fact
this probably was when we do a create
entity here and we use one of these
slots then we want to do this now I
think we can actually make these things
more commensurate utz because what we
could do is when we actually create
enemies I think what we want to do here
is call this every time so this is gonna
be more like a allocate an entity slot
you know and it'll get called by this so
this code right here I think what we
want is like not that actually we want
something like a you know acquire entity
unpacked and then a slot call right and
so you know this sort of this thing will
be doing something along these lines who
knows what that's going to be doing
something like that but will be
acquiring an entity slot here for this
and then we would also acquire a entity
slot the same way during a call to
create entity right
in fact I guess creativity would just do
it directly so yes so this call here is
actually gonna be a choir unpacked
entity slot it's not going to be called
create entity because that's not what it
actually does if that makes sense
I think I think that's what we want and
then when you call create entity on the
actual sim region which is where people
normally call it this is presumably the
place where this would I
really happen right so in here you would
create you would you know acquire an
unpacked entity slot and then this would
zero it because it wants to create a new
one but most of the time you wouldn't be
doing that right so I think that's more
what we want here and we just need a
free list and I think we're good so in
here we're gonna say look let's acquire
an unpacked enemy slot then we fill it
up with whatever the heck we want to
fill it up with don't ask me why we're
asserting the source here because the
source literally came from something
that you could literally like the way to
make this not be zero would be extremely
difficult
you'd have to back this up by the entity
index from the end of zero like negative
that's I don't that doesn't need to be
there I don't know why that was there so
yeah looking at this I'm just gonna
clean this up looking at that you also
see well this is going to happen during
this so if that's probably fine
so we're literally just looking at this
right we just move the source in and
then we we update that chunk Delta so
again
simplifying the code more and more and
you can see that eventually this is
going to be an actual unpack and not
just a copy so we're really kind of
getting down to two what we need and I
think this is gonna go away
and also this part right here is also
going to go away
all right so yeah this stuff I don't
know if we really want to handle this in
fact I don't think we do I think we're
just gonna do this we're gonna start
that up in here and we're gonna make
sure this is big enough that we can
never really create enough to flood it I
guess what we're gonna do I think that
looks fine uh so I think that's all good
um I don't think there's anything else
we really need to worry about there I
think that's all good fine I like it
it's happy it's it's good yeah so now
what I need to do is kind of clean up
how we're doing the entity unpacked
enemy slot stuff and we just need to
kind of make this sensible so I don't
really want to bother with two different
ways of doing this so I think I might
just string these ahead of time and
here's how we're gonna do that so when
we've got entities if we look at the
entity struct right you can kind of see
in here is just a big bag of garbage
what I want to do is just say look I'm
gonna treat when these things are empty
I'm gonna treat this as actually sort of
a different kind of struct one that just
has like a chain through it of entities
so that I actually can store the free
list using the space that we would
normally use to store MV information
because obviously I can write and that's
pretty easy and there's a lot of ways I
could do that but probably the easiest
one would be to just use this ID value
to just store whatever the next slot is
or something like that that's probably
the most straightforward way to do it
the other way I could do it is this way
so basically I could just chain these
like that now the reason I don't love
that it's cuz this is bigger than this
so really ideally you would want to do
it on something that was also eight
bytes wide and something like that so
you know not the the cleanest thing in
the world we can't of course just put it
somewhere else where it would be but
again I really don't know how I want
that to play out
I really couldn't tell you so I feel
like probably the way I'm gonna do it is
this instead and we're just gonna
pretend that it's a different type when
we are keeping our free list right and
so in here what I'm going to do is say
in you know in this sort of world of
unpacked entities and all this sort of
stuff we've got first free entity like
that and I'm gonna get rid of unpacked
entity count we're not gonna have that
anymore we're just gonna have this when
we actually create the worlds in here
when we're not gonna lies this when we
create our array of unpacked entities we
are gonna do a loop through all of them
and the maximum region entity counts is
not going to be what we use here so if
we look at that value whatever that is
right maybe that's the most it could be
in a sim region I don't really know but
the max unpacked entity count and in
fact this value I don't even know who's
using that it's just this right yeah so
for any given sim region that's sort of
the what the hash table lookups can be I
don't even know if we're gonna need that
anymore we might be able to just get rid
of that but point being in here when we
initialize this regardless of what this
thing actually ever is and maybe we make
that something like this
then in here we want this to probably be
significantly larger right because
there's no reason for us not to store a
ton of unpacked entities because it's
just a cache and we can choose to make
that cache as large as or as small as we
want it to be so I don't know what we
want that value to be right now but
let's say it's gonna be something like
that and then in here we have our
threshold and our unpacked entity
threshold is just how when we are
nervous right and so maybe we say like
look and you know that could even do
this this way when we get so many
entities that we get up close to how
many there would be in a sim region is
the Headroom
let's left then we start repacking
things to try and make sure we always
have plenty of headroom right for what's
happening seems reasonable to me uh and
the other thing about it is if we ever
run out we can always try to pack at
that time so you know we could sort of
say you know when you run out try to do
an emergency pack and pack as much as
you can back in to the space we could
try something that I'm gonna not deal
with that kind of stuff just yet but we
could certainly try it so let's take a
look here so if we loop through these
for our empty index zero and the index
is less than world max impact entity
counts we can grab each of these by
basically just casting so we can say
look we've got the unpack end of the
array and we're gonna go forward by this
mini and then we're gonna treat it as if
it was a free entity right and so what
I'm going to do is say that free entity
has an X pointer right
that's right here and so I'm just gonna
chain all of these together right I'm
going to say that you know each one of
these one this each one of these points
to whatever the next one would have been
so you know something like this
now obviously the very last one we don't
want to do that oh you know what I could
do this in backwards order to so
something like this right where we
basically say live through each of these
for each one of them I want its next
pointer to point to whoever was before
it which will be zero on the first one
but then the rest of them will kind of
just point to each other and then at the
very end I'm just gonna say the first
free entity it's gonna be whatever that
prove was so now I just have a chain of
all the entities right in the entire
thing and so if I want to actually
initialize one of them all I have to do
is pop one of those off and use it just
the way that we always do
and so in here where we do
whereas our there it is when we do a
choir unpacked entity slot we now no
longer ever reference this array instead
what we do is we just say here's the
first free entity right we say the three
enemy pop equals that we pop off a free
entity here and we say look did we get
one right if we didn't we're in big
trouble but we can still process the we
can still avoid crashing probably maybe
by saying look we've gotten no entity
we'll return it right but this is
basically game over at this point so we
pop one off and we better have one
assuming that we do we then say that the
first three entities whatever the next
one was on here and then we say the
resulting entity that we're trying to
you know that we're trying to provide
that entity is going to be this one that
we pop just cast into an entity right so
now we've got it make sense we just
return that and the only other thing we
need to do is make sure that we would
you know record the fact that we have
another entity in the system that
someone's actually using a slot for
right so then that'll just automatically
happened when we flow through here and
also when people call community when we
go to delete entities again delete
entities only sort of happens here so in
the remove from unpacked side of things
when we start getting rid of entities
what we want to do here is say alright
when we're gonna remove an entity from
unpacked then what we do is we say the
entity in question which is this has to
go onto the free list so we say free
entity free end equals free entity right
so we just say look let's start looking
at this entity as if it was one of these
free Hannity which is just a pointer
chain we say that's next pointer equals
the first free and the first free equals
it now it's on the list and we record
the fact that it's on the list by
reducing that packed and a big count so
the count goes up here and down there
and so now we have the ability to sort
of just move things in and out of the
set and we don't really ever pack them
up again unless we think we really have
to and they're outside of the region we
expect to be using in here where we say
syntax missing we are just basically not
pre declaring that so that's not in here
what else we got unpacked entity counts
ah so when we run through our Envy's
here and we're looping over all of them
having to sort of adjust our entities
each time it would be yeah I don't think
there's really anything we can do about
that I think we just have to loop over
all of them and and actually operate on
them like this has to kind of be this
right and if the entity exists then
that's fine we could just check the
flags to see if it's deleted or not
right and just not update ones that are
deleted
I mean I yeah I guess I don't know what
we want to do here there's two options
we have because since we do have to
adjust origins for people since we do
have to do adjust origins for people the
problem that we're going to run into
here is just that either we loop over
everybody and check the flags or just do
the operation I mean we don't care if
it's deleted we can still do it in fact
you might want you to avoid the if so
you just always do the add add add um oh
but I guess register enmity you would
want yeah so I mean basically what you
have to do here is this right
and it's not really great right because
the problem with this is no matter how
many entities we have in here we have to
loop over the entire array every time
which I guess is okay but just it's a
lot right and we really wish we didn't
have to do that and again this kind of
gets back to like these entity and also
this entity if it's not inside the
bounds doesn't want to be registered
either right so we kind of have a
problem here where when we look at the
entity let me see what happens here yeah
so when we look at this entity and we
look at active versus inactive here
again essentially that that check kind
of wants to go up in here because we
don't really want to be processing
entities that aren't in the in the right
area
so I'm really not sure how to handle
that part
hmm
hmm I say so here's what I'm gonna do
but again I don't know we may have to
think a little harder about this and see
but all I'm really gonna do right now is
say when you actually create the world's
I am gonna actually go ahead and
initialize these to have the deleted
flag set right so basically the flags
will be guaranteed to be there
effectively and we'll just say this so
everybody starts out marked as deleted
so they won't get touched and they're on
the free list we loop over every one
every time and then when we do a
register entity on people like this I
can also set the P values to be nonsense
when we first do our initialization as
well
so yeah effectively what would happen is
this does a check to see whether this
entity is actually going to get used it
all and so it would be a check oops it
would be a check here where we say if
this entity overlaps the entire set for
the sim region which is this then we
would use it and so when we register the
entity here right like we call register
on everybody but a lot of people just
won't get registered and that's fine
it's not great
I can't we're not gonna win any awards
for this of course they don't really
give out awards for programming but if
they did handmade heroes not gonna win
them but I we can at least do something
and see how how it how it goes right so
yeah as we go through here okay so
another issue here we would have in fact
entity flag deleted almost we almost
need something more stringent there
because when we actually do the the pack
back on that thing we are we don't have
any marker that says this thing is
actually like literally gone that
deleted is like so we almost need like
vacant or free right
and down here we would say when we
actually pack this thing in we would say
entity flags or equals free or equals
three
and so then up here instead of setting
these to deleted we would just set them
to the fact that they were free not
deleted and similarly I guess like
really everywhere that we were using
deleted that's that's the it's actually
free that we care about
right so in here when we yeah when we
check it's free there that's for here
yeah so yeah again not really great not
sure not sure what we want to say about
that other than it's not really great
but off you go so we could do this the
other thing we could do potentially is
use 0 as that thing and we'll see how
that goes
so for now what I'm going to do is I'm
going to take this and I'm just gonna
use this exact same information we were
using before as the min chunk P and the
max chunk P but I'm gonna put to do in
here that says maybe use the new
expected camera position here instead
just so we can maybe get a little bit
better coverage there
all right so we're gonna need some way
and first so we're gonna have to debug
this stuff but we're also gonna need
some way to make sure this is actually
working by tracking that value of what's
unpacked and what's not
and a whole bunch of other stuff so we
have a ton of work we've got to do here
the fact that nothing shows up on the
screen is always a just a ring
nice encouraging sign there so that's
not great but anyway let's go ahead and
sort of walk through this a little bit
more carefully here first
I don't really want to start debugging
this until I actually check all the
stuff I have done because it was a
little bit crazy so the first thing that
happens here is we take all the unpacked
entities and we make those into a chain
like this so we basically just have a
big string of entities and all of those
entities are marked as as being free so
they don't really actually exist in the
world and then we have that first vanity
that points to the head of the chain and
each one points to sort of the one
previous one now when you create an
entity what you're doing is you're
calling acquire unpacked entity slots so
that is gonna be in here you're gonna
get one of these things right and you're
gonna clear it out and they're gonna do
stuff with it right and that's just how
that rolls so when you do that that
should be fine you pop one of these
things off you write and we may be in
here when we do that thing we might want
to do like Flags equals zero just in
case somebody didn't clear it on the way
out we know that that one's not free
anymore it actually exists and then we
track that number so then when we do
ensure region is unpacked we loop over
all of the entities that there are and
we say if the thing is not free we
assume that it's something we actually
have to use right so we asked it to be
registered
into the system um in order to register
an entity we just look to see whether or
not that entity is inside the volume for
this particular simulation region and if
it is then we are gonna process it now I
don't actually know if that's gonna work
because I don't know if we were counting
on some things getting unpacked into the
region that don't have bounds but I
don't think they could because they
wouldn't exist in chunks really so I
don't know about that we'll have to see
anyway that's only for things that
previously existed in the world for
things that haven't been unpacked yet
we're gonna do that here so we take the
art you know we take a chunk out we loop
over that chunks entities and for each
one of them we acquire the unpacked and
any slot that we're going to put it into
we copy the value of it and we offset it
to update it to where that would be
relative to the chunk right
we then requested to get registered with
the system in the exact same way as it
was before and then we yeah and then we
we're done
yeah I don't see anything particularly
weird there when we go to repack
entities we say alright we're gonna
track whether or not these things are or
aren't going to get deleted if somebody
tried to delete this entity then we're
definitely gonna remove it from the
impact set otherwise we may not and so
then we come in through here and we say
look let's find out where this entity
actually is in you know in space and
then we say if the current unpacked
entity count is greater than the
threshold we set up for repacking and
this entity's location isn't inside the
area that we expect to use next frame
then we're going to just repack it let
me do it this way right and we say by
the way go ahead and remove that from
the set because we're no longer going to
use this entity anymore so then we say
if that actually happens we're going to
set this entity to be free we're gonna
use it now we assert that we can
actually decrement here so we assert
that somebody actually acquired this
many slots before we put it on the free
list and then we decrement that unpack
count right that looks about right
[Music]
so I don't see anything like obviously
super stupid there I don't think
yeah it seems alright to me curious
how do we get to our or do we not have
start Global's display
yeah it looks like we only have like
renderer lighting memory and we don't
have just our regular Global's which is
annoying because I want to see what that
number is and I can't write and that's
not so good
the fact that we're not getting any
entities visible is a little strange I'm
going to start by doing this I'm just
curious what happens if we sort of
always have the entities entered into
the working set that's unexpected so
what's the actual error there
it occurs to me too that I wonder if we
should just be using entity chains in
general because I suppose there's no
reason we can't just I use MD change
just in the general case I don't know I
haven't really thought of it much but
this is particularly strange I'm not
sure why end block this looks like an
assertion right because we're moving
explicit zero to explicit zero but we're
not actually on an assertion here so I'm
not sure what the assertion actually is
according to this it's in a remove world
chunk and I guess I don't know what the
call to end ticket mutex actually looks
like but I'm going to take a look so it
would be pretty hard for that to I mean
that's not going to cause an assertion
so who is asserting their I don't know
what's going on because we're presumably
somewhere like around here can we get
any more information about this so the
chunk pointer
it's actually zero so the result we're
gonna return here would be zero but that
should be fine right
I mean that's not illegal so I'm not
sure why we're getting I'm not sure why
we would be getting an error there so
it's not like one of the early times
that this happens it takes quite some
time for this to actually get grumpy
like it pretty much has to start siming
it looks like before that's the case I'm
assuming this is actually in begin Sam
yeah so is this the first time that we
do a simulation or is it do we actually
simulate more than once before the crash
that's I'm curious to know
interesting so it actually takes a while
of simulation for this to go haywire
which is which is even more interesting
so you can see here the current unpacked
nd count as we run is actually holding
steady until we hit this which is
particularly strange so I'm not really
sure what I'm looking at there what I
think I want to do now rather than
actually debug that error is I think I
just want to make a slightly more
defensive more self-contained set of
code for this so that I have a higher
chance of hitting some useful assertions
I think that would make it easier for me
to track it down sometimes when I just
wing something like that and it's kind
of a little stringy I sometimes I'm like
well I could spend a bunch of time to
bugging it and find out what the problem
is but what I'd rather do is maybe add
code that the code finds the problem
because I want that code in there anyway
in order to catch errors and so I think
what I'm gonna do is maybe take that
route if that makes sense also this we
now know we don't want so I think I'd
like something more like that something
that maybe is a little bit more specific
about what's going on here
I'm not sure whether I want these to be
stored into linked lists as well that I
just basically moved between free and
not free and actually you know there's
another way we could do this which is we
could just perform what is effectively
heap compaction in the sense that
whenever you free an entity we just move
one from the end of the list into the
current location and that would keep
things compact as well I kind of wonder
if we want to do that
I think I might want to do that because
if we did this via a heap compaction
then it would keep the code simpler as
well meaning if I do if I do restore
this behavior right and I say instead of
keeping a free list we're just gonna
make it so that we compact entities down
right I don't think we pay much for that
it's just copying only when we actually
want to free entities and I feel like
that would allow me to keep it simpler
by still getting basically the same
rough behavior so meaning if we just
don't do this and we do that instead so
we say that this is our unpacked entity
account we allocate you know the empty
array and and we just call it a today
also we don't have this and we don't
have that then as we go through and
actually work with these things when we
acquire an unpacked entity slot it's
literally going to do just the thing
that it was doing before which is that
you take the world entities well we're
still gonna have to do it here
so in here when we say let's grab an
entity we just do unpacked entities +
unpacked and accounts like so and that's
it
I think yeah that's it
and people who who allocate those can
clear them if they if they desire then
in here we would always just use
unpacked entity counts and as we loop
over these we're always going to update
and register that's complete nonsense
that wasn't really supposed to be there
that was a bug in here we don't really
need that free list stuff at all but we
still do need to process one of these
entities and so the way that that has to
happen if you think about it is we sort
of have you know we still have this loop
here and it still looks mostly the same
but the big difference is that when we
get down to the end here if we're trying
to remove this thing then we're not
going to actually advance right so oh
and also obviously we Oh may weep over
this number so when we come down in here
we say all right you know we want to
advance our entity pointer or whatever
else we're doing here and track our
handy index but if we're going to remove
one we instead of actually advancing
past this slot we're just gonna grab the
last person in the array and copy them
into this slot right so in other words
we're just gonna bulk move whatever the
entity was at the end of the array in
here to fill the hole
does that make sense but then we don't
want to move past it because that person
may also have been deleted and so we
want to check again and not you know not
advanced now there's more efficient ways
we could do this we could walk backwards
from the end to see everyone who's
deleted and copy the first free non
deleted person which would be a little
bit more efficient but I'm not gonna do
that right now I'm gonna do this more
straightforward way which is simpler and
all that is is saying look into the slot
that we're currently at I want to write
whatever the unpacked entities are
whoever is in the very very last slot
right so I'm basically gonna say who's
ever in that very last slot and that's
I'm packin II cannot remember if I index
with acts actual unpacked entity count
I'd be one past the end of the array but
what am i doing said is decrement the
unpacked entity count first which moves
me into the actual last slot while also
recording the fact that I deleted
somebody and then I'm going to take that
information and romp it into the empty
slot we're currently on and then we're
gonna move forward right and I think
that's mostly all I wanted to do and
that's it all right so now we're not
keeping a free list around Tina so
that's simplified that code quite a bit
and we should only be messing with
unpacked entity count
I only just a little bit right we should
only be looking at that value when we
either here this is annoying because
it's my head is in the way
so looking at that right we're only
really doing something here we started
at zero
we only increment it when we actually
are putting one onto the array and then
when we process we always look through
just the unpacked entities so we don't
have to deal with that part anyway and
here if we're going to actually
decrement them we decrement the amount
only here so it's like more
self-contained and just simpler so I
like that a little bit better and then
we also aren't chasing chains or
skipping people all the time which is I
think it's just better now when we're
actually in the sim region we still have
the problem in here that we want to test
this part so I'm gonna first run it
without that test but then I'm also
gonna run it with that test and see now
if we if the error pops up in a
different place at all I'm just again
trying to see what's going wrong because
I don't really know yeah I don't really
know what the problem is so I'm gonna
sort of progressively try to refine down
to to see who's who's causing it
assuming that if we implemented the code
correctly before we get the same error
so it looks right so this we're getting
a same error with two totally different
implementations of that allocation set
right and so that's a pretty interesting
piece of information it suggests that
there's a logic error not an actual like
code here if that makes sense
and what you can see here is our
unpacked entity count is somewhat high
but not even high enough to trigger the
packing which would be here so it's
pretty hard to say why we're seeing this
this error at all right and again we're
getting it in a really weird place that
I don't super understand I can't really
quite tell what that piece of code is
and just looking at it
yeah it really looks like an assertion
but I'm not sure how an assertion would
be occurring in this timed block region
looking at that time function part of
things
I'm also not sure like what are we
looking at here for the chunk regions so
I guess what I would say about that is
that looks suspiciously huge I don't
know why we would hit an assertion
necessarily in the location that we're
seeing but it doesn't make a whole lot
of sense why the sim region would be
that large so that is a little bit
confusing
to say the least and I don't really know
what's going on there so can we get some
more information about that
so if we look at what our minimum is
here versus our maximum so in our world
like one unit is one meter and so this
is asking for a six kilometer region of
the world 11 kilometer by six kilometer
am I reading that right which makes like
no sense
so things have gone massively off the
rails here and I have no idea how so my
first question is where are we getting
those numbers from like can someone tell
me constructively who came up with that
value if we look at the symbols here I
guess the world camera rect and because
this is creating a union we must be in a
situation where the sim bounds and the
world camera rect are like totally
different I guess that's the only thing
I could think of so we must have gotten
way off track here so if we look at
world camera rect can kind of see the
world camera rect is off in its own sort
of orbit there and then we look at what
the sim bans themselves well they've
been kind of destroyed at this point
I mean it just looks like the camera is
totally divorced from where the sim
region is I guess
I mean that's just what it looks like
so I suppose that one thing that could
be happening here is we're just exposing
some bugs that we had that we're sort of
not occurring when we didn't have
enemies cached in this way I am a little
bit curious here so if we run the game
and we do prevent anybody from being
added when they're not inside the
simulation region we don't get the crash
and I'm curious to know how many
entities we actually register if any or
where our simulation region actually
even is because I guess it occurs to me
that we don't have a particularly solid
understanding of how this startup
process actually works in terms of
placing the camera somewhere in the
world to begin with and so I wonder if
we've got some startup be kinds of bugs
there that just happened to work because
the way the same region was working
before or something weird like that so I
want to investigate this a little bit
further here and what I want to see is
is anybody actually abled yeah does
anyone ever get at it okay so somebody
actually gets added to the sim region
which is good right who by the way
[Music]
just some random set of people they do
appear to be kind of coherent so they're
probably off in the same room this makes
some sense what's their p-value so their
p-values actually seemed somewhat
reasonable but maybe quite a bit off to
the side so can't quite tell the closer
to 0 0 0 the more closer you're out of
the target right although that may not
be in hundreds century I don't know if
the targets actually offset if I don't
remember the camera the targets at 0 0 0
and remember how we chose to do that it
feels like these things should sort of
be seen at this point so I'm wondering
why we're not seeing anybody
you know
like if all these people with those
p-values which are pretty close by
what's the actual problem so let's take
a look once everyone's been unpacked
so the problem is the camera entity
cannot be found so we have not unpacked
the I mean the actual player
that seems kind of like what you would
expect because the players entity would
be added close to the end since it only
gets added when you actually start the
game so you create the whole world first
and then you add it so that's what you
would probably expect I'm curious let's
just see what actually happens during
this process so when we go to add one of
these players in here what's going on
what's my p-value so so here's what I'm
like trying to set this player to right
we're gonna make this nonsense happen we
set it up so that the entity that's
being followed by the camera is in fact
this entity which seems good and that
all seems fine right so totally
reasonable
so once we've added that player into the
worlds wait a second I want to run that
one more time show me that one more time
please
okay so I'm gonna look at body um I'm
gonna look at this identity call
so when we call create entity here we're
gonna allocate an ID that seems fine
we're gonna call acquire unpack and any
slot that should give us a new slot
right which it does and that seems fine
we're gonna clear it we're going to mark
it we're going to add it to the system
and we're not actually marking it as
active but I suppose that's okay
so that's all fine seems good so now
when we go to get the end of the least
this time it should definitely be there
unless we screwed something up so I want
to see what's happening here when we
call get entity by ID we should now find
it in the hash for sure right yeah so
now that we've got the camera entity we
should be able to actually do this call
correctly and figure out where the you
know world is it's going to be looking
right so we're we've got the camera to
eat we call in here and we say update
camera d4 I'm sorry update camera
friendiy movement and we're looping
through here to find like rooms I guess
right
I wonder if the problem is we can't find
any rooms let's find out no we found a
room that the players in so we're gonna
remember that ask the trunk space right
so that seems fine
here's where we're now looking target
wise that doesn't seem weird
what's our Delta P totally fine so now
if we take a look at what the actual
camera came out to be there
so I guess I would not have expected oh
yeah because the camera is like hovering
up above things so yeah chunk chunk P
that does seem to be where you would
expect the camera to be you know four
chunks above where it's viewing maybe so
assuming that's what that means that
seems okay
so I'm really just not seeing a lot of
weirdness here
so I guess I'm gonna have to maybe look
at the end of think the end
yeah I'm a semantic advanced music I
don't know I that actually looked pretty
sane so I think I'm looking for
something relatively subtle I thought I
might see you know I didn't know if I
would have some really weird like
totally out of bounds values or things
like that where it's been like oh man
that just got totally borked I hadn't
seen anything like that so now I'm
wondering if it's just like a subtle
positional packing unpacking problem
something like this when we come through
here and do our insurer region is
unpacked right we've got that that
concept of the unpack origin right where
we say we need to apply this Delta
because whatever the sim region says the
origin should be we need to move it move
everything right that's that's to make
it correctly be placed around that
origin you know what I mean and so the
first time we call and show regional
impact there wouldn't be anything
unpacked anyway and then we call create
entity which would put things into place
around the origin in some way or another
and then we would repack our entities
which is fine or leave them up right so
they're either just not gonna get
touched at all or they're going to be
you know packed in this in this way here
when they get packed in this way I'm
assuming and maybe we've got a bug or
something but when we get packed in this
way I'm assuming because we've set
removed from unpacked to true then in
here we'll just get compacted so it
shouldn't be there any more to be used
it would have to come out of this pack
state next time so I would assume my
furthermore my assumption is this
probably isn't ever getting called
because our actual total entities state
number of entities we can keep unpacked
is less than the total number of
entities we create in the world right
and so I'm assuming that we
don't even really need to consider this
part of the code because I don't think
this ever gets called I suppose I can
check that as well meaning at this point
because we have a small enough world
everything fits in the cache and it
shouldn't matter right and let me just
verify that that's true on a second so
if I run I'm guessing that that just
never happens like ever
right so we know that our bug exists
entirely I would say unless this is
happening because of this or something
but that you know you have to set the
flag to be deleted to ever have that
happen I don't and let you know I get we
could even see is that ever getting
called right does this path hit ever so
this is whether or not we ever get
packed at all or delete yeah we don't so
we're never actually exercising this
code path so the bug can't really be in
this code I'm the only way we could have
a bug as if that was supposed to be
called and wasn't right but that's it
so we should literally never call any of
this in fact that means we should never
have to call this either right because
there are no world chunks we've never
packed any up yeah so our bug exists
entirely in here you know I'm saying
this is where we're having our issue in
here and of course you know the this
code that's you know doing sort of the
the sort of pre checking on this stuff
this is the entirety of it so what's
wrong
right like what's going on weird there
and I yeah I honestly couldn't say week
whenever you do one of these unpacks
which you know we're doing here and like
begin world change anytime you're
actually doing one of those unpacks
you're passing in whatever the sim
origin was and it's using that origin as
a new unpack origin which means it looks
to see what the difference was between
the last time it did anything and now in
updates all of those positional all
those entity positions relative to
whatever that origin change was so the
all entities are now relative to the
origin at all times right I do think
there is something we do need to sort of
do here which is that if it entity was
too far away it really does need to get
unpacked because otherwise it would
shift too much so I feel like in here so
we do want to pack things back up
sometimes and we want to do that because
again the whole reason we sort of keep
things and floats relative to local
origins is to avoid floating point
issues you know you get to you can do
things one of two ways
either you can do that which is more
work but can potentially be more
performant or you have to use doubles
but that's really all you can do if you
want large worlds because floats aren't
big enough to store really large worlds
anyway so yeah we know we're not calling
that code path we know we're only
calling this code path but I don't see
any actual issues with this code path
because that looks like it's doing
exactly what we would expect now I don't
know if maybe I guess one thing we would
like to see is how many entities got
registered in a particular sin marina we
should probably track that value and
print out both of those but we do know
at least some are getting registered
right and it seems like what the problem
is that mainly we're having is somehow
the camera the entity we're following
with the camera itself doesn't get
registered which doesn't make a lot of
sense but apparently is the case right
this so yeah sort of puzzled
I'd like to track it down but I'm afraid
it's gonna take too long so I may leave
this for next weekend this what we will
do is we'll go find the bug so yeah you
can even see there's our world kind of
off in the distance right but the
cameras in nonsense town and it's
actually buggy as well so you can see
that it was having trouble like finding
where entities were like look at all the
stuff that's stacked on top of itself so
we do know we've got a positional bug we
just don't know where it is
right but we do know that that is
effectively our problem so when we're
setting up these p-values when we loop
over our entities to update them we're
screwing up somehow
and the question is just how since it's
so simple you think we'd be able to see
it but it must be just maybe a little
bit subtle because like I said there's
not really a whole lot going on here
this doesn't touch the bounds this will
always update it whether or not you're
in the bounds are not so it should keep
those positions coherent whether or not
you fall inside here right we're not
looking at that criteria to see whether
we update or not so I don't really see
maybe this math is wrong
like for example this could be backwards
right so maybe we need to think this
through is this adjustment backwards we
wouldn't have known because this code
never got executed before because we
always packed everything back up right
so we couldn't have said oh well that
can't be true because it was working
last time but it never would have
touched this code because everybody got
packed back up so it was only ever doing
this code here so we know that this code
is correct but who cares because that
code never gets called anymore
so if we look at this and we say is that
origin adjustment correct so let's do
the math on that and see if it actually
is because maybe we just reversed the
polarity there but I don't want to just
go flipping signs around and hoping we
get it right I'd rather take a look so
here we are on day 5 44
and so what we essentially have going on
here is we have on frame n minus 1 which
is the previous frame we have a
simulation region and we have an origin
right and then there's a p for an entity
so this is our origin here sorry I've
got to get this on a flatter surface not
that my handwriting is good even then
but if we have an origin here and we've
got an offset value which is P here
right and then we move to frame n which
is the frame were on now
and what we're seeing is that the origin
has actually moved so we had an origin
on frame n minus 1 so we'll call that Oh
n minus 1 right and it was here but now
the origin is over here at O n right so
this this has moved and we previously
had a location P that was relative to
this origin that now we want this right
so we effectively want this was P n
minus 1 this is now P n right and so if
we were to write the equations for these
what we would say is they look the
absolute world space location for P
right so P in world space which is never
supposed to change it's just in a fixed
location in the world in an absolute
sense is going to be equal to the origin
of n minus 1 plus P at n minus 1 right
it's this it is also supposed to be
equal to the origin n plus P at end
which means that if we take these two
and equate them we say that n o n minus
1 plus P n minus 1 right has to be equal
to o n plus P N and what we want to know
is this we know all of these right
but we want to know what the new P is so
if we were to solve for the new P we
would have to transfer this to the other
side and we would end up with this
equation Oh n minus 1 plus P and minus 1
minus o n right refactoring the terms we
get P and minus 1 and we have these two
terms here so we would add oh and minus
1 minus Oh N and that right is our
update equation to find our new P n we
take our old P N and we add n minus 1 to
n this means the old one is positive and
the new one is negative and I want to
say although I don't remember that if we
look at who gets the positive and who
gets the negative it's the wrong way
around
the new one is supposed to have the
negative right that's the new one and
the old one is supposed to have the
positive so yeah we had a negative we
had our sign flipped there and I don't
know if that's the problem but that was
definitely a problem because I don't
think I messed up that math I don't know
and hey lo and behold that was the
problem
so yeah math is hard let's go shopping I
don't actually remember what that
particular Barbie said you know let's be
honest
Barbie wasn't wrong math is hard
shopping is easy but hey math can be
more rewarding than shopping sometimes
and so that's why we do it right so now
I think we're often a good space here
and hey we can now leave our code in a
good state for the week that was the
update I wanted to make and I think now
we're mostly done the only thing that we
really do need to do here is we just
want a check on distance so you know
probably what we should say
is something like you know distance from
origin equals length squared entity P
and we just want to say look if this
distance from origin is too high so like
max allowed distance you know I don't
know but don't get more than a hundred
meters from the center I don't know what
you want there so you know fundamentally
speaking we have 24 bits of precision in
a floating point value right so I feel
like I don't really want things that are
gonna be you know if I talk about the
number 16 million and I talk about
shifting that around I probably would
say you know fractional maybe we would
be talking about thirty two thousand
sixteen thousand something family so I
would probably say maybe maybe a
thousand is actually so one kilometer
away from the origin is probably okay I
don't know how safe we want to be there
so I'll say because we can actually tune
that value to whatever we want but after
we compute this distance from origin
what we would be doing here is saying
look if this thing is too far from the
center we're just gonna unpack it
because at that point things have gotten
into a bad state and so and we don't
really want to yeah we don't really want
at that point
you know what I just realized we don't
have to do this here either
do we
this is really pretty awesome okay so
actually now that we've done all this
you never have to call end because we
could just do this at the beginning
right so rather than you estimating what
this is we can just make this be some of
yeah oh oh that's much better
right so actually forget everything I
said all we really need to do is this
forget this what we really wanted is to
just do this loop right where we are
doing the removal we just want to do
that the next time you ask us to unpack
because then we actually know exactly
what the min and Max chunks are because
you're handing them to us right and if
somebody would have been placed outside
we can literally enforce our precision
exactly by saying if the update Delta
right would have placed this person
outside of the correct area then we will
pack them right so we can do this we can
say look we're gonna update this this
this unpack origin here right and when
we do this update we can just say if you
would have crossed that side we'll pack
you we can even do it a little bit
better I'm gonna doing two steps just to
make sure I don't screw up because we're
kind of out of time here but what we
should be able to do is say all right in
the case where this thing is potentially
going to be repacked
and we just say oh you know pack it if
you're gonna otherwise register I think
that's it that's way better because now
you just do one pass over the entities
to do your unpack and that also repacks
them if you needed to right yeah and so
what I want to do there is also say here
in this case where we do this this guy
and we haven't really tested this code
fast so we kind of have to do that but
when we're gonna repack this stuff what
we want to do here is say look don't
actually do this math because we know
that everyone is cool is is correctly
near the sim region right because nobody
could have been unpacked they weren't
near the sim region what we're now going
to do is apply an offset from the old
sim region to the new sim region right
but we don't want to actually apply that
update if it would create too much of a
distance so instead what we actually
want is this update the person in this
case don't update the person in this
case so if the unpack origin would have
made you too far from right would have
put you outside of our safe of our safe
like floating-point precision zone right
then we need to pack you for sure like
you must be packed at that point it's a
requirement
so if wait where do we even put that
check in their head wait so if distance
from origin is greater than max allowed
distance or should have been in for or
the unpack identity count is greater
than the unpack threshold or or it sorry
and and this person isn't contained
so this is a requirement you have to
pack otherwise if this is over then you
should pack anyone who's not inside
right makes sense so then when we come
through here we would say all right
maybe we assert this as well and then so
when we come in here we say all right
because we know that this should never
happen now we need to pack this guy but
the problem is we actually don't want to
pack the world position of this entity
am I missing where do we add the the
world space in here though
so this code looks like it did I mess it
up before when I was changing it around
because where do we actually pack
oh no it's because of this map into
chunks face bit here right yeah yeah so
when we do map into chunks face with
this right here we don't actually want
to use the world unpack origin well I
guess we do we just don't want to update
this until afterward right so we want to
essentially do this right oops this so
in here we want to say hey anyone that
we were gonna repack we repack them
using the old origin because we're not
gonna update their Delta that should
pack them properly right and then but
once we've processed everybody from the
old origin then we update to the new
origin right I think that's correct
furthermore I don't need this to be
doing it's nonsense anymore I'm just
going to do it this way all right so I
think that's all we need and now that
code is is much better and we can tune
that as we actually get world's large
enough to matter we can fix that looks
like what's the problem here
so that could should only happen in this
case I'm going to break this out a
little bit like too far for precision
I'm going to call that this and then I'm
going to call this outside volume and
that way I can write this and say okay
compute you know all of this and say if
it's too far for the precision or it's
outside the volume and we're over the
acquired entity limit and in fact maybe
I'll make that one too
and this is just so I can expect these
in the debugger conveniently so what I
want to say is if we're too far for the
precision or we exceeded our count and
we're outside the volume that we expect
to use then we assert in here that we're
outside the volume because you shouldn't
be able to be too far away from the
origin right that shouldn't be possible
when we do this operation here and so
let's just make sure that's true all
right so let me see so now we come
through here I should be able to did I
and I probably didn't put this into
debug build what we really need to do is
just have the lighting turn off I never
really need to be in release mode I just
need to turn the lighting off so if we
then look too far for precision it's
true count exceeded is zero is outside
volume is zero all right so how did we
end up in that situation what's the
distance from origin oh I didn't square
up we're using the length squared we
need to square our max allowed distance
as well so that's actually that
all right so it looks like that was just
a slip of the lip of the square as they
tell it say and so I think we're fine
and again I don't really know what that
value should be we can revisit that when
we're sort of doing any kind of
numerical tuning pass on this code but
now I think we're in good shape let's go
to a brief QA I'm pretty happy with how
that turned out that's exactly what I
wanted we are now in fact it's better
than what I wanted so that like that's
great
now we don't copy entities anymore when
they're still in the cache and yet we
can still have worlds that have like
billions of entities in them if we
wanted to and it would be fine I mean
we'd have to write something that pages
to disk if we truly wanted billions
would you do Linux programming if you
had a remedy GPG on Linux um so I guess
what I would say is I would certainly
consider trying it at some point again
because the main thing I don't like
about Linux is the debugger so I would
consider it on desktop anyway Linux just
totally dives on every laptop I've ever
had because it doesn't handle Optimus
graphics particularly well which I've
always kind of had the Nvidia ones you
know so I don't know that I would ever
try on a laptop but on the desktop I
would consider trying it if I had remedy
sure will there be a memory difference
with too far from precision versus no
too far from precision well I it doesn't
really affect the memory usages at all
really pretty much at all I mean it sort
of has a very like a really really sort
of tangential effect would be that you
will pack a few more entities sometimes
if they were way out so you'll pack them
earlier than you would have packed them
but it's not going to affect the memory
I'm working on a product where the
client has written some prototype
mathematics code in MATLAB I've
translated most of it however I have
some discrepancies at the output and I
can't figure out if there's a better way
to debug the problem then a whole bunch
of printf debugging thoughts I mean not
really I feel like most of the time when
you end up in that situation you kind of
just have to make checkpoints where you
dump the state and you see where it has
gone wrong right the only thing I would
mention is make sure comparing apples to
apples right if MATLAB is doing all of
its computations and like extended
arithmetic or something and you're doing
all your computations in float well
that's a pretty obvious place you could
diverge right so make sure you're both
using I Triple E same bit level floating
point matchup right blah blah blah but
then yeah you usually what you have to
do is define some checkpoints I would
recommend a sort of a general branch and
bound kind of approach so you know start
by dumping the state in the middle of
the routine in both of them and see if
it diverges if it's not divergent then
dump jump halfway in between the
remaining code and do it otherwise jump
back up halfway
so basically binary search your code to
avoid having to dump state more than you
need to but that's about all I can
recommend without any more details
when you're hopping around in a large
room it appears when you're hopping up
it seems that the outer area is lighter
than the area around the player is this
on purpose lighter that the area
oh are you maybe you might be just
talking about the lighting region are
you talking about I'm not sure what
you're talking about but I'm gonna say
so are you talking about like this
square area that's because we right now
just have a bound in there that only
computes lighting in a region but that's
yeah that will go away when we go finish
the lighting code which is coming up
soon actually ground cover and lighting
because I now that we've got the cash
stuff working properly I feel like it'd
be pretty easy to add that stuff in here
right
how large a world does the float
precision allow in this case do you mean
how large of a world does the float
precision allow in handmade hero in
general we don't have any float
precision problems in handmade hero so
they wouldn't be the limiting factor the
limiting factor would be the fact that
we use a 32-bit XYZ index for our
spatial partition so the limiting size
of the world is actually that not floats
so if you go look at this part here the
chunk size which you can set I'm sad to
say I don't actually remember what that
is chunked in in meters so let's take a
break point there and I'll tell you so
if we took a look at the worlds and we
look at the chunk dim in meters
here it is why is there an an how is our
code even working if there's a man Oh
duh because we can't
as always you can't inspect anything
when you're in a release build let's try
that one more time
so yeah so if we look at what the chunk
diamond is the meters here it is right
and so if we multiply those out by the
s32 maximum figure you're talking about
either 2 or 4 billion depending how you
want to look at it let's say that on the
low-end 2 billion so we would be talking
about something like 46 billion meters
would be the span there so 46 million
kilometers by 24 million kilometers by
10 million kilometers would be the world
size so it's it's impossibly huge I mean
you could if you started hopping in one
direction for the rest of your life even
if you were the oldest living human and
you started when you were zero you'd
know you'd never get there right I mean
it's bigger than way bigger than the
earth
the assertion that we didn't find was a
dude debug table assertion assert macro
and side record work oh okay
can't put a message box insert marriage
- kind of story easily no not really
heard about posits better precision and
faster than normal floats Oh I sort of
heard of those but I haven't actually
looked at them I don't know how legit
they are right like I would have to wait
till people who I who know more
numerical analysis than I do said they
were good so I haven't looked at them
but I had heard of them yeah at least I
think so maybe it's something else there
was sort of I remember this coming up
before but let me take a look maybe this
is a different thing
oh no so it's from 2017 yes so yes I did
sort of see this I had not really looked
at it and I don't know it's not my area
of expertise so whether or not it's like
a snake oily kind of thing or whether it
actually is good
you have time to explain on the zooming
towards the mouse position and how it
can be implemented I thought I went over
this I thought I literally went over
this last week didn't you ask me about
this last week
you have any advice and I'm sure the
uniqueness of UI element IDs in an
immediate mode UI in a setting in which
the number of elements changes from
frame to frame yeah so there's a lot of
ways you can do it but the way to think
about it is just first of all immediate
mode you eyes don't require this concept
a lot of people again like I don't know
I've never taken the time to really
explain everything you should probably
know if you want to know how to do
immediate mode gooeys and it people
managed to get so tangled up in knots
it's nuts but assuming because they're
two separate concepts there's the
concept that you don't want to store
information on the client-side about
particular elements in which case you
need a way to generate IDs without
storage right that's just a separate
algorithm that has nothing to do with
the immediate mode you can still do
immediate mode where you actually
remember labels for things right
that's totally a thing you can do so I
could store the labels on my side and
just send them down to the system and
say this is the label I want you to use
and I'm allocating labels on my side
that's still immediate mode right the
point is just the library isn't the one
telling you what they are right but it
is a valuable thing to understand how to
generate ideas for things in ways that
allow you to not have to store them
because that's just sometimes more
efficient and makes for easier code to
not to do that and so the way to think
about it is to think about traces
through your code path right and you
need to think about when I go through a
particular code path how can I identify
items that I'm visiting in a way that's
unique and oftentimes with that boils
down to is bundling two IDs together
which I often will do so for example you
may have a situation where you say well
okay I've got like
you know this list of things and I could
use the like pointer to where I'm
storing them in memory as a unique ID
but I've got two separate times I'm
displaying them in two different places
and they're different UI elements so
what I typically do in that case is I
just bundle two ideas together the ID
the pointer is part of the ID and the
other part is like some ID for the code
change it could even be a pointer to the
function that is the route through this
thing right or whatever else you want
and so typically what I do is I use some
kind of a trace like that and it doesn't
really have a name because no one's
created a name I probably should have
created a name for it because I created
the name for immediate mode GUI but I
just never created a name for what that
is called but it's basically a unique
trace through the code path that says
you know something about a particular
location that you don't want to have to
store and there's lots of ways you can
do it but basically bundling is the
biggest one combine multiple ideas
together to create something that's
unique
it's the most effective way of testing
code I come from web development
background and there's a very heavy
focus on unit testing and test-driven
development I'm not sold on the dogma of
that and I don't think it's really used
in game development which makes me
curious as to how you do test and game
development effectively um you might
want to take a look I've sort of talked
about this like many many many times
before so you might want to just go
watch like an existing one rather than
me repeating myself if you just go down
here and type in test-driven development
you can see some answers that I already
have that you can see if those sort of
answer it for you
the broad-stroke version of it once
again is just that testing is just like
any other kind of development
it's basically a trade off like
everything else of time versus results
literally everything you do in
programming can be stated this way
testing is just another thing and so
like everything else at anytime whether
you're on games or web or anything what
you should be asking yourself and what
almost no one does but what you should
be asking yourself is can I save
development time in toto by writing
tests or by not writing tests and that's
always the thing you should be doing
some systems it is very clear that you
could save a lot of headaches by writing
some tests to bulletproof them because a
the test could be easy and
straightforward to write B they would
have good coverage on what you actually
need and C the system is subtle so tests
are likely to find bugs you couldn't
find easily any other way right that's a
system that should have a test written
for it another system like the user
input handling in a game forget it how
are you ever gonna write testing for it
it's never gonna happen right so unit
testing is completely out of the
question but sometimes you may be able
to find other ways of testing the code
creatively so for example one things we
do in game element is we do randomized
user interpret it user input testing so
at least we can find out if the code
crashes or gets to unusual States we get
a speed random input to it right and may
you'd find something in the future we'll
probably have AI driven
input testing right where we may be
trained a eyes on things that players do
somehow and then run it and see what
happens right so you know there's other
ways of testing but the most crucial
thing to ask yourself anytime any any
time it's just is this saving time
because if actually what's ending it
happening is you're writing tests and
writing the test is taking a lot longer
and not finding enough bugs then if you
just haven't done the testing then
you're actually making a worse product
period that's not even arguable that's
just true right if you could have spent
that time making more features or doing
other kinds of debugging that would have
found more bugs than the testing found
you are literally making a worse product
so dog was always bad because what it
does what Dogma does is it gets rid of
the reason why you did something right
and so you always have to remember the
reason why you write a test is because
you think it will help you find bugs you
either a couldn't have found or B would
have taken you longer to find write you
know that so apply that logic every time
don't just write the test think is that
going to happen here yes or no right so
the reason that we don't do a lot of
unit testing gaming usually is because
the systems are too dynamic and the
output is not well-defined is this
particle system working properly I don't
know did it look good right so one of
the reasons that we oftentimes have to
do a lot less unit testing than maybe
even we would like to do because maybe I
would like more unit testing to be sure
that something's working we just don't
have a lot we can test right that's kind
of the the real data right and so I
think that's the that's the real
difference is it in the web world
sometimes you can forget that that's a
very simplified problem space where you
know you have really clearly defined
inputs and outputs a lot of time and so
that testing you can do
in the game world it's really hard to do
testing because typically the actual
output is ill-defined right and so the
things we typically end up doing unit
testing for to the extent we do them are
really low-level things maybe the memory
allocator sine and cosine outputs you
know do they handle the range basic
graphics operations does blit work
properly and produce the right things
when we give it known inputs right stuff
like that
you said last week that you explained
the zooming towards the mouse point on
the whiteboard I did say that I didn't
mean to say that I guess I'm just not
sure how to explain it in any way other
than what I already explained just in
terms of so I mean I I even just
literally just said it even earlier on
the stream I guess so I don't know I can
try to give you a rehash of this but I
would really say what you wanna do is go
back and watch earlier episodes of
Hannah here when we talk about this sort
of stuff so let's just talk about a
basic operation okay I have a function
called stretch right and I'm not call it
and let's say that this function allows
me to supply to it as parameters a
p-value which is the minimum corner and
an S value that is the scale okay that's
what I'm gonna do and these are
interpreted as drawing a shape that
starts at P right and goes to s times
width this way and s times height this
way okay that's a image scaling
operation like you were talking about so
fundamentally I have some origin and a
coordinate system over here right and
we're talking about drawing stretching
an image and I've got a function that's
going to do that I'm gonna pass it these
two values I have a width and a height
of an image that I'm drawn
and that's known but I'm gonna supply
the s and the P to like place this thing
somewhere and scale it right makes sense
so what you're asking and how I'm what
I'm assuming you're asking is like okay
so the user like flicks the mouse wheel
okay and I've got something in my code
that's like alright s plus equals some
map you know mouse wheel or something
right like something here you know DD
mouse wheel DT right x times time or
times the times the wheel Delta I don't
know right this is what you're asking I
you know I've I've increased my scale
value and so then what I see on the
screen is this thing gets larger right
but the mouse cursor was like here and
it always gets larger around this base
point let's say instead of around this
point here and what I want is I want if
this was where the mouse cursor is I
want it to get larger around this point
so it should actually expand outward
that way as well instead of just
expanding outward this way this is what
we're talking about
is that what we're talking about okay so
again just write the math of what you
want first and see what you can see from
that so let's start with our state
change we are going from one state to
another right we effectively like I said
before we have an N minus 1 so I'm gonna
label these we have frame and minus 1
I'm gonna call that a ok
we are going to apply the mouse wheel
and that puts us on frame N and I'm
gonna call that B so fundamentally what
we're talking about here is a transition
from A to B we're saying our s is fixed
so somebody you sin thues iasts is
changing the S value and so our entire
responsibility here right is moving P
that's all we have to do we just have to
figure out how do we move P because
that's the only thing we can do right we
don't we have no control over anything
else the scale is now what the scale is
based on the mouse wheel equation that
you've written whatever it is and so now
we need to know how do we change P to
put this in the correct location sucked
at this point up here is fixed to the
viewer right that's what we're doing so
we fundamentally have a situation where
here's all the variables we have we have
P a right this is the location of the
blit you know on a we have P B the
location on B right we have s a this is
the old scale and we have s B this is
the new scale right I should just call
this old and new but you get it
right this these are our parameters and
furthermore we know width and height so
we know the width and height of the
image right and we know Mouse we know
the mouse position right so we know like
m right okay so Mouse position doesn't
change image dim doesn't change these
are given and they're constant right so
we just these are just like numbers they
don't have any relationship to anything
we need to solve for or care about
they're just gonna be constants that
feed in they don't change over the
course of the two frames that we're
talking about here and they are just
values we know we're given them right
okay the same effectively in a sense is
true for these right they're not
constant in a sense they change but
we're these are all given so this is our
only unknown this is the only thing
we're trying to figure out is PB we have
all the rest of the information is being
given to us right that's a good
situation being we have one little tiny
thing that we want to know all right so
let's write out the math for what we
want we're looking at the screen this is
our screen space right and what we want
is we want to produce a situation where
our PA which is here and our PB which is
some fictional point after the scaling
right whatever it is
we want to produce a situation where the
mouse point maps to the same location in
the image in both cases right makes
sense
so another way to say that would be the
offset from the mouse 2p should be
exactly the same both times except for
obviously the scale will change right
because we're scaling it up and down so
we could write out the entire equation
from mapping this into the image face
and back but we can probably
short-circuit that process by just
saying well whatever this mouse point
here is since I know what it is I can
produce this arm here for the mouse
cursor point and say that the point P is
just going to be whatever the opposite
direction of that was this value here if
I want to produce the new offset from
the mouse location to where P should be
it should be directly related to this
scale right so the first thing I'm
tempted to do to simplify the problem
down rather than half the map because I
could write the equations to map it
which would be the 100% math way to do
it and maybe we'll do that second but
what I would like to do here is just say
let's change the problem to just be
written around M right so let's do that
so the first thing we would say is P of
a right which we know is which is this
this point here we want to write that in
terms of M so we have this new sort of
value which I guess I'll call P maybe
I'll call it P Pam pa in mouse space
right that's going to be equal to
whatever PA is - my mouse location right
and so that's this vector here
and now I'm saying that I want to center
around the map so I'm also gonna say
well we've got PBM and that's gonna be
PB - the mouse right and remember our
goal is to find this so since we know
this we could alternatively just find
this and we've got what we want right
because we can find the PB by just if we
solve for this we can just do this plus
M is PB right so we're talking about
these two offsets and what we want to do
now this is known this we can just
compute right what we want to do is find
this because this is known and if we
know that then this becomes trivial okay
so how would we do that well since we
know what this is right we know PA minus
M we know that for our given scale right
that we started with si right we know
that this is some distance into the
image whatever that would have been at a
unit scale times that scale right I'm
not sure if I'm saying that particularly
clearly but it draw it here again so we
know that if this is the mouse the mouse
cursor location right inside my image
and this is the the base value where
we're doing our blit then we know that
this vector here is this if this were
width and height the normal amount not
scaled by anything right then if I apply
a scale to this I would also apply the
scale to this right so whatever the
scale amount is I know that my P am
value right my PA m value is effectively
equal to my scale value right tying some
original vector that would have been the
size of this vector had we not scaled it
so at unit scale right so effectively
the P unit Mouse right
does that make sense and we know that
PBM which is the new one that we're
talking about right that one and I'm
sorry I should have called this a
because this is the scale for a is
whatever this value is right times the B
scale so I know that effectively P a.m.
is sa P um and I know that BM is SB p um
right
are you with me so far I'm asking
okay so I know that my mouse offset can
be represented as some offset from
something I don't even know and this was
the part I was saying is I'm gonna take
a shortcut I could have written the
equation for that we could have tried
and solved it and gotten to this point
but I'm just pre getting to this point
and saying look I know that there was
some vector in the unscaled case if I
scale it by a I get a M if I scale it by
B I get B it what does this allow me to
do who cares well I can solve this now
right I can solve this in terms of BM
because I know si I know s B I know am
all I don't know is this a term that
appears in both of them so the heck with
it right let's just simplify this if I
take P am equals s AP um right I know
that equation I want to basically write
this BM equation in terms of SB I just
need something to substitute in here so
what I'm gonna do is solve this equation
for P um and then plug it in right so if
I do the divide right you said I did
that I just divided this out try the
scale out now I can plug in P um into
this equation so I get PBM equals SB
times this right here
pa m over si lo and behold right what I
get is an equation with no unknowns
anymore other than the one I wanted
right sb over si times P am right now
what is this look at that it's just the
scale factor that I applied right it's
just the change in scale
sb over si right is this the change in
scale
from A to B see I'm saying so all I have
to do to find this new vector is to just
multiply by the change in scale of the
one that I had already right that leads
us to a trivial update step all we have
to do is say all right I've got my mouse
right I know that that's a given
so all I have to do to update is say
take the P that I have produce P am by
saying P a which I know - my mouse right
assign this now I have this variable
right I need to know what my new P is so
let me compute that by taking SB over si
and multiplying it by my P am which I
now have right this is really simple
right the location I did the blip before
and the mouse cursor all I'm doing is
subtracting those two producing that
then I'm multiplying by the change of
scale that's my new one and so now where
will I draw my new blip where will the
new blit be well I have the equation for
PBM right all the way back up here it's
this so PB well PB M equals PB minus m
solve this equation for what I want
which is the location of the new blip
right location of the new blit just move
the M to the other side is that so
writing in the entire thing out we know
that the PBM is this right so writing
this out I have P B equals P B M plus M
right in this case so up here if I just
substitute B this entire thing in I can
make this equate just one equation
that's simple right
so my PBM is the change of scale times p
am
doing this here right make sense so the
new location is the change of scale
times the Delta that Delta vector plus
the mouse cursor I can keep going
what's P a.m. right let's P AM PM is PA
minus M right so put it in
make sense right I'm just substituting
PA em back into this equation that I had
before I may have gone too far but we'll
see so multiplying this out you get SB
over s a PA minus SB / SI m plus M
and so changing this variable so I can
do the subtract it would be si over si
right so that is going to be plus si
minus SB over a times M so looking at
what you've got I think I probably
wouldn't expand it out you can see some
intuition here potentially if the change
in scale you're gonna change in scale
the doublet location from last time
right and then you're gonna offset it by
the mouse location using the change in
the like inverse change in scale me and
I'm saying I probably wouldn't bother
right I would probably stick to this or
this right but that's that's what we're
doing does that help
and fundamentally speaking I mean I
don't know we'd have to go check my math
makes ready to make a mistake right I
mean because math is easy to make a
mistake but understand that process
right just you have to be willing to
write out the math because you know
fundamentally speaking the only thing
you can change is the location of the
blit so the question is how do I get
some map that tells me how the blit
location changes with respect to the
scale and since you're already telling
me you want centered around the map
mouse that's just what I assume I'm
going to want to do right alright so
let's talk about this slightly more
cerebrally just for the last thing cuz
that's just like grind the math off it
goes conceptually speaking another way
to think about it is what is scale right
what does scale mean so scale in our
world is a multiplied and multiplies
work around in origin
right so if I have the number 5 and I
multiply it by the number 6 I get 6
times further away from the origin
as 5 or 5 times further away from the
origin s 6 right but it's always around
the origin so on the number line right
if 5 is here and I multiply it by 6 I'm
going 6 times further away right and if
it was negative 5 I'd be going 6 times
further away just to dist in the other
direction but I'm always going around
the origin so if you said I want to
scale around the mouse cursor another
way to think of it would be make the
mouse the origin temporarily right
because what's actually happening well
here's my actual origin and here's my
p-value if I just freaking say s times P
right if my P prime equals s times P or
the way I've been writing it is PA equal
I'm sorry PB right equals s times PA
right so I'm changing this scale around
or whatever right that's happening
another way to look at it is like look
forget all of that stuff what's the
actual change in scale that I'm going to
do right however much I want I could
call that s if I want to but we've been
calling it s B over si which is like the
change in scale right because my
previous scale was something I've got a
new scale now right does that make sense
and so in that particular case I'm just
talking about the difference in scale so
what do I need to do to my P location to
update it right and in this case we just
say look if you want it to scale around
the origin
just make it relative to the origin
first right so I can just say all right
let's do a change in in variables here
right let's make P relative to M how do
I do that well I say P you know minus M
whatever that is right and this is I
guess a right and I need that variable
right so I'm going to call that
something P a.m. right and I'm just
changing my thing now I'm gonna apply my
scale right so I want a new thing which
is like my p BM right some new things so
this is step one step two I want to
scale by the change so this is the
change I'm gonna scale it and I know
that it scales I know that it scales
around my origin right and then finally
I want to produce my new point which has
to be relative to this origin so I need
to add the origin I was using back in
you know I'm saying
right and lo and behold just doing that
conceptual process right make it
relative to the mouse scale it then
unmake it relative to the mouse right
relative to mouse scaled on relative to
Mouse you know I'm saying hey if I just
expand this out look what I get
look familiar it's literally that right
there right
SP over si pay M plus M so you can do it
a couple different ways this is just the
purely conceptual way and that's just
saying look make it relatively thing you
want to scale scale it and unreal ative
this way up here is the plugin the math
and just say what you want and grind
they both end up with the same answer
and they both can suit you in different
cases I tend to prefer doing this way
when I can think of it because it's just
conceptually geometric is easier for me
but this way is good to practice it's
good to do this because sometimes you
will be in cases that you cannot
conceptualize right and somebody just
asked could you make a matrix out of all
of this and plug the coordinates of the
mouse and scale and yes absolutely this
is a matrix which translates to negative
M so if you imagined
if you imagine each of these three steps
as matrices it's trivial in two
dimensions right you have a three
dimensional matrix because you need to
be a modular so you can't represent
translation so you would literally have
the unit matrix here right oops the
identity matrix
you need your negative M so it's
negative M X negative my that this is
the matrix that translates to the origin
right we'll call that I don't know what
we'll call that we'll call that nothing
I'm not calling anything right now we'll
call that X we'll call that you
transform that's it I'll call it t1 for
a transform for step one scale we know
what that is right
si over SB si over s be zero zero one
zero zero zero zero right it's a scale
matrix just with this loop sorry
it's SB over si right again just the
amount of scale you wanted to apply and
then we want to put it back we want to
we want to translate it back
there's our transform - here's our final
one again identity doesn't touch
anything except the position MX my right
there's our three matrices one two three
we want to apply them in order to
produce this effect so basically we're
going to say what is our total matrix so
this is the total matrix for the entire
transform from A to B what's that going
to be well remember if they get replied
from right to left because the point
ends up on the right so for example you
know you're gonna do something like this
right where I've got a bunch of matrices
times the point to produce a new point
right mm-hmm
we want to know what this total matrix
is total matrix is going to be t1 times
the thing plus t2 t3 right that so that
applies them in this order first do this
then do this then do this what does that
end up equaling if we actually multiply
them out well we need to multiply these
matrices together first of all so let's
take them in sequence I have my T one on
this side 1 0 MX 0 1 and y 0 0 1 I want
to multiply by this SASB matrix I'm
gonna save myself a little bit of time
and just call this s because we only
have it there so SB over si is just s
right sorry SB over si right so we want
to multiply that by this matrix it's
just SS scale multiplying this out what
do I get right these two here I'm going
santa-san term H multiplication column
by row
there's my s right 1 0 0 s 0 0 0 s 0
nothing happens here 0 0 nothing happens
here move to the next one nothing again
move to the next one the S comes through
again nothing happens here multiply here
what do I see well I got a negative s MX
right see that come in there then I got
to multiply this here what do I get in
this column again negative s my right
and then
and then here we just get a one okay so
here's our first matrix now we need to
multiply this guy who's now taking up
this spot we need to multiply on the
left again so I'm gonna drop this down
here like this and we need this rt3
right this term
oops so here's our T 3 1 1 1 0 0 0 0 MX
and why want to do the same
multiplication again let's do it here we
just get our s again right because it's
just gonna get multiplied through
directly here we get nothing here we do
get something right stuff starts to
happen negative s MX in the first term
then 0 knocks that out and then MX here
right coming through again same thing
here nothing there this gets multiplied
by the 1 and then again we get some
values coming here negative s my and
then our plus my 0 0 1 finishes off the
matrix and here we are right so that's
our final matrix right it is expanding
out SB over sa SB over si in those two
slots and then here we have our in this
part of the the point equation this is
at M and an M right we can think of this
as as an actual vector right so what
we've got there is we've got M minus SB
/ s a times M right so that's that's
what we're actually multiplying in
so then if we want to see what this
actually does well this term can be
simplified because that's just inverting
right that's like saying you know M
minus SB / SI m it's just the same as
saying well si over si and I can just do
this actual subtract because these two
terms are the same so it's sa minus SB /
SI times M right and that's all that is
all right so that's the matrix that we
would end up with I believe unless I
messed up my matrix multiplication and
so then you have to ask yourself well
does that do the same thing right so if
I actually have SB / SI 0 0 SB / SI 0 0
right this is a just a scale and then
I've got my sa minus SB / SI m 1 what
happens if I actually multiply it by
something so in this case I want to
transform my original point right I want
to transform PA as a vector so su PA x
PA Y right I want to transform this
vector by this matrix well it's pretty
straightforward and of course there's
the one here because I'm doing my I'm
was doing it in homogeneous coordinates
but if we imagine multiplying this well
the SBS a is in the scale location so
we're just going to end up but the first
thing is just going to be SB / SI x PA
right that's pretty obvious and then the
next thing that we're going to get is
this times this right oh sorry naught
times this is times 1 so we're going to
add that to it so we're going to add sa
minus SB / SI times M right and that's
the update step that we would actually
do
now is that actually correct I don't
remember easily could have made a
mistake there yep it's exactly direct
spr SI x PA + sa minus SB SI / m right
so the matrix version does exactly what
you would expect
Entei I didn't make any mistakes
apparently all right hopefully that's
everything if there's anything you don't
understand in that we could try the
chance if that makes sense
hopefully that's like a ton of different
ways you're gonna get this problem go
work them out yourself
now go do all of that yourself study
until you can get it right because
that's the only way to train your brain
nobody starts out being able to do that
you just have to do it a lot and then
you can write and so you should be able
to work out all of those that's you know
that's all just that's all just like
what a graphics or generally physics C
programmer should just you should just
always be doing stuff like that just to
keep yourself brain going and
understanding all those relationships
because if you don't you'll never dull
never really sink in you got to do it
don't just take the answer like do it
you know work it out yourself on a piece
of paper you'll get it wrong a bunch of
times that's totally fine you even on
stream you watch me do it on the
blackboard I'll get them wrong so
totally fine do not panic it's just
practice it's like anything else it's
just practice you got to do it and with
math it's careless areas are easy so you
just got to check your work or use a
computer algebra package to check your
work
and help you but with that I'm going to
end
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for lips at a handmade hero it's been
a pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with the
stream at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero org the game
comes with the source code even right
now so you can play around with it and
have fun with your own math solving
don't forget to try solving math
yourself I was horrible at math in high
school and grade school and stuff keep
that in mind
math is about practice and diligence and
using a computer to help you with things
that you have trouble with to visualize
and so on not that kinds of crap that
you learned in school which is taught
poorly and focuses on the wrong things
and makes you do things on tests in a
time pressure environment which is the
absolute worst place to ever do math
ever so keep that in mind I will see
everyone back here next week I believe
unless I'm wrong about that
pretty sure next week I'll update the
schedule at which point we will start
adding ground cover and lighting fixes
into the game because we now have the
caching and so hopefully that should
open up the door for us to do all kinds
of fun stuff now to finish up the sort
of look of the game which is really I
what I'm kind of trying out finally I
want to kind of get us looking kind of
final so that we can then just I guess
we just do game play which I hate and
then off we go
all right tick news everybody
you