here there we go hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show where
we code a complete game live on twitch
we don't use any libraries or engines
here we cover the entire game
development process from from scratch so
that you can see absolutely every piece
of code that's involved in actually
making a game run because somebody
somewhere had to write every last little
thing like you see me riding on this
stream today in order to get a game to
run no matter what game it was and even
if they use something like a license
engine well someone had to make that
engine and so we are showing how to do
absolutely all of that not just the
little light fluff that sits on top but
actually the entire the entire suite of
things that are required so what we're
doing today is we're doing a little more
work on our sound mixer which is coming
along nicely we just want to kind of add
some features to it it's a it's a fairly
bare-bones sound mixer at the moment and
so it does some kind of advanced stuff
like get dynamically stream sounds off
disk and stuff like that so that's
pretty cool but we haven't really added
much in the way of ability to control
the sounds that are being played so for
example you can set the volume of the
sound but you can't animate that volume
over time so sound couldn't like fade
out or something like that so we would
like to do is go in there and add some
of those features so that our sound
mixer can do a bunch of things that we
might want it to do when when the time
comes to actually tune the sound
environment for the game so that's what
we're going to be working on today now
if you would like to follow along at
home with the source code today is day
142 go ahead and unpack day 141 source
code because that is what we are going
to be working with today all right let's
go ahead and get started here here we go
and so yeah if you remember we have just
at the end of yesterday string we had
just pulled out the audio code into a
into its own file right and you know one
of the things that I should probably
mention that we haven't mentioned we
haven't really looked at in too much
detail but a lot of times people are so
incredulous of being able to write
everything from scratch right there like
that's that's just ridiculous it's not
possible you know a better thing to do
with your time would be to download huge
numbers of libraries and try to get them
all to build together and spend all your
time trying to figure out how they
worked well you know audio mixing wise I
mean take a look it's just a brief look
at actually how much code we wrote here
so here's the asset system right it's
about eight hundred lines of code and a
lot of that was just us defining some
test assets right so really it's you
know it's something like 600 lines of
code that was to do full dynamic
streaming of all the assets in the game
separately threaded right that's all
that took and that also handles dynamic
streaming of sounds that are long right
so you can have a long piece of musical
dynamic extreme than 600 lines of code
right the audio mixer here's this is a
test sine wave right so including the
test sine wave all the audio mixing code
here and things that tracks the sounds
was a hundred ninety four lines of code
okay that's probably less than the
number of build script modifications
you'll have to make to like go compile
someone saw Leo library right um so yet
you know I can appreciate wanting to
reuse code and if the code out there was
really good all the time and library
distribution worked really well and and
people programs really reliably and
great you know maybe that would be good
but the reality of it is that oftentimes
if you know what you're doing writing
the thing yourself takes far less time
than getting the premade thing to work
and then heaven help you when you get to
the end of the product and you find out
that there's bugs in it or weird things
that you can't fix and you have no idea
how the code works and now you've got to
go learn it all yourself well you'll
definitely end up spending more time
then right and so a lot of times it's
worth just taking a step back and
realizing just how few lines of code
these things actually are if you just
write them sanely and don't go into
object-oriented nightmare land and do
all these weird
kind of modern programming practices
that are very counterproductive if you
keep those things out of your code base
and just write the actual code you need
it turns out that these just aren't
taking very much space right so yeah so
I just want to emphasize that just
taking a quick look at just how small
this code actually is and again we wrote
it in this you know this past two weeks
I think one hour a night was all it took
for us to write all the assets streaming
all the sound stuff right so just keep
that in your mind and think about just
how easy that actually is it's worth
reminding yourself that that it's just
not that hard once you know what you're
doing to actually write these things and
maybe you don't ever want to be someone
who knows what they're doing and that's
fine too but you know assuming that you
actually don't mind doing the
programming practice and getting up to a
certain level of proficiency once you
get there you know to a reasonable level
of program proficiency I think you will
probably find that building your own
stuff tends to pay off quite a bit and
really doesn't take very much time
compared to how much it would take you
to use something frustrating and that's
possibly not exactly what you want right
so just a little public service
announcement there I try to sprinkle
those in occasionally just to remind you
of why we do things from scratch because
seeing how easy it is sometimes is a big
deal and so let's go ahead and continue
on let's take a look at what we have
here and what we might want to do so in
our playing sound system we have this
concept of a volume and what I'd like to
do is I'd like to extend that concept of
volume to allow me to animate the volume
over time and now normally the way that
I would do this there's there's some
ways that i would do animation in a
graphic sense that are not the same as
in a sound sense there's a lot of
differences between the way sound
programming works and the way graph
experiment works and the reason for that
is because graphics is actually a very
low frequency phenomena we talked about
this a little bit but basically graphics
you are talking about something where
you are outputting a frame of
information to the user you know at most
90 times a second
in like a VR scenario but often times as
few as 30 times a second in sort of a a
high complexity lower frame rate game
right and nowadays maybe in a common
scenario 60 frames a second right but
audio is something that happens
primarily at something like forty eight
thousand times a second and when you
think about what happens at that sort of
that high frequency it just leads you to
do some things that are a little bit
different than what you would normally
do and so for example in it we've seen
this in the renderer you will notice
that in the renderer we tend to batch up
static sets of things into like lists
and when we just draw them right and the
renderer itself doesn't really need to
understand that all that much about how
things are animating but that really
doesn't work for something like sound
mixing because for sound mixing you can
imagine this loop that we've got here
right you'll notice get outputs many
many frames it outputs like something
like 800 frames if you will right which
we call samples in the sound room but
that's what they are they're frames of
information we output 800 of those every
time we output just one frame of video
data and that means that there really is
no way to architect the audio system to
work the same way that the video system
does which is to say that all or most of
the animation capability is taken out of
the final compositor and placed in the
hands of a higher level component of the
engine that's not typically true and
sound typically in sound there are at
least a few core animation components
that will be sitting directly in the
mixer and that is because those things
need to animate for every frame just
like they do in video but those frames
are happening so fast that they have to
be done inside those composite loops
right and so what happens is in sound
mixing you tend to have stuff like the
animation of the volume or a few other
things that might be animated like that
tend to be happening directly in the
mixer and that's how we're going to have
to do it now and so like I said the way
that I might handle animating a value
over time in other parts of the engine
and you've seen me do some of those
we haven't really gotten to animation
complex animation stuff yet but you see
me do a little bit of that anyway those
techniques are not applicable to sound
at the low level here what has to happen
here is that animation stuff has to
occur directly inside the actual system
that outputs the sound samples directly
and we will see a little bit of about
that in rendering potentially there are
times when we do need to push animation
concepts a little lower so that they're
actually in the renderer proper but it's
rare whereas in the sound system it's up
front and center and very core concepts
like volume which is you know one of the
most basic fundamental concepts of sound
volume and and frequency of the sounds
that we playback those are actually
going to be handled directly in the
mixer out of necessity not because it's
architectural e convenient for us to do
so not because I like it better that way
but because it is just a fact that it
has to be handled inside in order to be
efficient ok so what we want to be able
to do here is we want to be able to set
our volume so that we can change it over
time and so what I'd like to do is
introduce the notion that the volume we
have is kind of twofold right there's a
current volume and then then then maybe
there will be a target volume right so
when we set the volume of a sound what
we will be doing in the future instead
of just setting its volume directly is
will sort of be setting a target volume
that's like a request to the mixer to
get to that volume at some point right
but it won't be discontinuously setting
that volume directly and so that's the
first step that I want to do is just to
introduce that separation because
basically we can't just go around
setting those volumes anymore and having
discontinuous volume changes what we
need to be able to do is we need to be
able to have our volumes here
oops this is in the wrong place I think
where is that we gotta put here yeah
sorry God will distracted there to do is
in the wrong place anyway so what we
need to do here is me to be able to set
a volume so that people in the code you
are trying to talk about the volume of a
playing sound and want to change the
volume of that playing sound can do so
but so that it won't lose the
information that we need later to
smoothly ramp to that value because in
order to smoothly ramp that value we
need to know what it currently is so
we're going to track the current volume
as a separate thing from the other the
other information so then we'll set this
target volume and what we want to do is
here in this loop where we are going a
you know sort of overtime what we want
to be able to do in this loop is figure
out what the volume should be at every
sample we want to kind of change it
right so you want the volume to smoothly
animate as we output the sample so that
in each sample it's going to use a
slightly different volume now there's a
couple different ways we can do that and
they have some they've got some
trade-offs right there's there's
different ways that this that this could
work and there's obviously reasons why
we may or may not want to do certain
things but what I want to do is is do
this sort of most straightforward
version first but that has a little bit
of a potential caveat in it and then
sort of when we when we are finished
with that maybe we can talk about
whether we want to change it or not and
we'll take a look at the cindy version
of it to sort of make that distinction
but it's basically a performance issue
is the reason why it's worth thinking
about so anyway so what I want to do now
is start to extend this concept a little
bit so let's go ahead and think about
this here what I want to do is when we
do this play sound call I want to have
another call but people external can
make where they can say you know
something like chain
volume right and so when you call change
volume what I want to do is you'll pass
the playing sound in like so just maybe
we'll pass the audience day as well
you'll pass in the sound whose volume
you're trying to change you'll pass in
what you wanted the volumes to be so
you'll pass in like what you want volume
in the tuna two channels to be like this
but what we also want to do here in
addition is give it some indication and
we don't really have anywhere to store
this yet but we'll add something we want
to give it some indication of how fast
we want it to get to that volume right
because the sounds at a particular
volume now and we're gonna say this is
how we want to get up to its next volume
right but you know we haven't actually
said anything about how that volume how
fast that volume will change does it
take a second to go from the current
volume to the new volume does it take
you know is it instantaneous does it
take a minute is it super long you know
what's what's the what's the actual time
frame and so to figure that out we've
got two ways we could specify it one way
is we could specify how long we expect
it to take in seconds basically right we
could say this is how many seconds i
want to take to reach the new volume and
that's a good method for if we know that
generally we want things to take a fixed
amount of time the other way we could do
it is we could specify that we want it
to happen at a particular rate and then
that would mean that it would happen
however fast it happens would be sort of
based on the Delta between the volume so
if it was a certain volume now and it's
going to be a certain volume later if
that is a large gap it will take longer
than if it was a small gap so when we
pass in those values that's that's sort
of how that would work now i think what
i'm going to do is I'm going to lean
towards going with the the other way
where we say how much time to take and
the reason that I want to do it that way
I think is because I feel like most of
the time that's what people will
actually want to specify they'll want to
say
need this sound to be at this volume in
a second or whatever I feel like that's
likely and they aren't going to want to
go look for us to see how loud it is now
and then figure out the rate I feel like
that's probably the case but we could
certainly change that later that's
something that we can't really write the
test case for just yet so I can't really
prototype it because we just don't have
enough in the game that's really using
sound or anything at this point so it's
hard to say and the one thing you know
that I can think of right off the bat
that we would use this for is fading
music in and out and it seems pretty
clear to me that the way we would fade
music in and out is probably going to be
something like saying that the music
fades in and out over two seconds of
time or something right so I feel like
that's probably the way that we're going
to want to do it so we'll leave it that
way so we've got the volumes here i'm
going to say that we've got seconds time
in seconds right or duration maybe a
fade duration in seconds and so if the
fade duration in seconds is 0 right that
would tell us that we want to
instantaneously change the volume and if
the fade duration is anything other than
0 then we will figure out what that rate
should actually be right ok so let's
start out if the fade duration in
seconds is is something wonky right then
what we want to do is just full on cold
set the sound right we just want to say
all right the current volume is going to
equal the target volume now and it's
going to be whatever the dude passed in
right so it's like that otherwise what
we want to do is say all right well if
you're going to take a certain duration
seconds then what I want to do is I want
to set that speed that you know I
probably want to report a speed here
right so it's going to be something like
d current volume write the velocity of
the volume that D current volume is
going to be based on the difference
between the target volume
and the current volume right so like
this right so I'm saying I want to get
to the target volume I'm at the current
volume so that's how much you know
that's that's how much distance I have
to cover and then I've been told what
the fade duration in seconds is so I can
also figure out like how long it would
actually take me to get there and then I
can set the speed to that so that we've
got you know a speed that would actually
be reasonable right and what I hopefully
you can see here actually as well is
these are you know these are basically
executing the exact same equations right
I'm looking at exactly the same
equations on these and so what I could
choose to do pretty easily is just set
these to be vectors right if I set these
to be vectors then what i can do is i
can make this into just a vector
equation in both cases right and you
know i'd end up with you know something
that's that looks much cleaner and not
really have to worry about duplicating
it out for multiple channels and also
its kind of handy if we want to make
this into something that that eventually
handles you know five channels of audio
or something like this we could make a
v5 and all of this stuff would
presumably still work so i'm going to go
ahead and do that that seems like a
reasonable thing to do and yeah so there
we go now i don't remember if we made a
vector division operator so we may have
to do one over there but yeah either way
let's go ahead and and set these guys up
correctly there we go yeah I thought not
let's see here and so that's okay i
think i may leave a 11 / fade i may
leave that undefined and just do it
manually here cuz i'm not sure i really
want the addition operator to be in
there for vectors so that would give us
a delt on the current volume now what I
would like to do when we initially make
these guys I would like to now go back
and think about these other ones that
are in there and make
sure that you know we always set our
target volume to the same thing as the
current volume and that the D current
volume is going to be a zeroed thing so
that we don't by default we're not
moving the current volume around like
you know or anything like this okay so
now we've got this it's pretty easy for
us to do sort of the stupid thing which
is not particularly good but we can sort
of do the stupid thing to get ourselves
started here right and so let's just
make sure this is also playing right you
can kind of hear that the music still
playing and we can say that the little
bloop weird bloop drop thing is playing
so what we want to do now is we want to
come in here and start to to mess with
the volume here right so we've got the
volume we can use that as a vector here
as well and when we're in here doing our
volume stuff we can just grab it out at
the at the last moment okay so when we
have the volume what we want to do now
is whenever we're going through this
loop we want to change the volume based
on you know sort of as we step through
those samples we want to change it so
that we're using that that volume
velocity basically right we want we want
to do something in here where every time
we take a step we want to basically you
know we want to do this right and we
want to change the volume for every for
every sample problem is right now we
have the volume in terms of a change per
second right and so if you think about
this this goes back to our old friend
dimensional analysis we haven't talked
about him in a while because we've been
working on sort of structural
programming sorts of things but when
you're in the world of velocities and
stuff like that it tends to be a good
thing so we have something where we've
got a value that's in that that's in
sort of volume per second right that's
what we said right you can see that up
here where we have
literally volume times one over seconds
right so we essentially had one over
seconds times volume right and that is
literally volume over seconds but that's
not what we want right we have volume
over seconds but what we want at the end
of the day is actually volume over
samples right so dimensional analysis we
know what we want to do here is we want
to cancel out seconds and we want to
introduce samples as the divisor right
so what we need to do is multiply our
source value our input value here by
seconds over samples to get us into
volume change per sample right I you
know you know I'm saying you feel me
dawg so in this case we actually know
what this is because we have forty-eight
thousand samples per second right we
know that samples per second is the
inverse of what we want here we want
seconds per sample so all we have to do
is invert our samples per second we just
have to do one over our samples per
second to get seconds per sample so it
should be pretty easy for us to do and
if we take a look at that sound output
buffer that we defined right sound game
sound of that Mary now you can see that
samples per second is actually a value
that we put like right in there right so
we can actually take samples per second
and we can you know invert that to give
us the value that we need and that way
we're not even dependent on that
constant the operating systems just
telling us what it's playing the sound
back at and then we can you know you
know we can adapt right we'll never
going to do that because we will author
all our sound samples at a particular
frequency and will want to play them at
that frequency but point being the mixer
itself wouldn't care so all right so we
have
no seconds per sample and that's just
going to be 1 point 0 / samples per
second and samples per second comes from
that sound buffer so there we go so if
we want to create d volume here what we
need to do is just take the current
volume and multiply it by that seconds
per sample as we saw that's what will
give us the value that we actually need
to step with and so we're going to do
that stepping in here now the problem
that we have is that this will never
actually complete right it'll just keep
changing the volume in that direction
forever and so a not particularly
correct way to do this and we're going
to have to do a put to do this is not
correct yet need to truncate the loop
what we want to do here is say oh okay
you know when we when we have the volume
and the target volume we want to be able
to look to see what's actually happening
if we've actually hit the volume targets
that we've tried to hit right what we
want to do is say something like okay
you know if if d volume and this is
probably something we need to do it per
channel of the volume right you can
imagine so we have like a channel index
here and we would do that for whatever
the channel can't actually is in this
case it's we can only do it for two but
I guess let's see here how about we say
hey where's the channel count we don't
even define a channel count really we
just have stereo out so I guess we're
just going to have to hard code that
there could do it this way could say
channel can't teach an old count is two
output channel count like that so if we
say output channel count here what we
want to do is say if the you know if the
d volume is greater than zero or if the
you know d volume oops channel index
argh we go is less than zero in either
of these cases we were animating right
and what I want to do this is great
emacs thinks this is a template now so
it's thinks I'm indented here which I'm
not watch what happens when I delete
this and and get it back to its normal
state oops cut that back in there or
maybe not is this guy what has happened
why do you think I'm indentity max I do
not know ye max thinks I'm indented here
oh right yeah I get this weird thing
sometimes where Emacs thinks I've made a
template when I do this I have no idea
why it is it's super strange and then I
have to go like deleting them so
sometimes when i get an indentation I
don't thinks like I I have to go do this
weird thing I've never really been able
to reproduce it reliably but yeah that
time it was fine it was just missing if
so we're good didn't have to do the the
weird dance of hunting for for greater
than to less stands that it thinks our
templates initializers or something like
this all right so off we go in either
case we know that we're animating here
and so what I want to do is just say
alright if the volume that we're
actually trying to hit right if the if
the you know volume that we're actually
trying to hit is it something that we've
achieved then
stop doing the animation right so
basically if like the current volume in
this case is and you know the d volume
was was what was positive so we're going
up to towards the target volume if the
current volume has met or exceeded the
target volume then I'm just going to go
ahead and and assume that we hit it
right and we're going to stop so we say
you know we're done there and then the
the the d volume the d current volume
can stop animating entirely right and
the same thing would be true in the
opposite case we would just do the other
direction of comparison and again we
would be done and I think I actually
should say i want this the other way i
want to set it to the target volume
right i want to say it should match the
target biome exactly now this is not
actually correct what's going on here
because like I said it will overshoot a
little bit because it will do more of
this loop than it should have done you
know it'll go further potentially so we
need to actually make sure the loop only
executes for as many as it it should but
for the time being let's go ahead and
run that okay so now we don't actually
have right any fading going on but what
I can do now is if we want to fade that
sound out right I can just take make a
set a breakpoint in here somewhere right
in whereas our handmade audio I guess we
don't have handmade audio yeah let's see
how about output playing sounds alright
so let's try that again
I would like it if this were would keep
playing while we were in the bugger
should probably try to set that up as a
sort of trick thing anyway it's playing
so now if we if we go in here and I you
know I set a breakpoint what i can do is
i can i can step in and I can just
full-on cold set you know one of these
playing sounds to start fading out right
because I can take a look at playing
sound and and I can change what the
that's odd are we oh yeah you know what
I forgot about the little caveat that
we're still compiling in in release mode
so we don't be able to change anything I
wonder if you know what's one thing we
should probably do I wonder if this
would be a good idea now that we can
because our code is fast enough I wonder
if we should just turn off 1920 x 1080
so that we can just always compile in
debug mode I wonder if we'd be fast
enough to hit 30 frames a second there
yes we are so that would allow us to
keep going in debug mode which is kind
of nice right so I think maybe we'll
we'll keep that good all right so if we
go back in here now now that I can
actually look at playing sound so if I
want to I can set the target volume to
like to fade out right I could say that
I wanted to set the target volume to
fade out and I could set the D current
volume to be something like I wanted to
fade out you know at a rate that was
going to be pretty slow right so it's
going to fade out like so that would
basically be you know again this is
volume for sample so this is saying that
it would take you know five seconds to
fade out the sound right because it
negative 2 per second negative point 2
per second would take five seconds to to
add up right so let's see if that does
anything
oh you know what though it's not really
going to do anything quite yet although
I guess I should probably have not
closed that we could have just used live
code editing to change this I never
actually wrote back yet the volume so we
also at the end here do need to actually
write back whatever the volume actually
is right so as we do these volume steps
we do want to actually save with the
volume is at the end of the loop so that
we could do it which actually now I
think about it it makes this a little
bit tricky I was trying to store the
volume in in a thing that would not be
dependent on the samples per second but
having to do that this gets a little bit
ugly right because if i was to store
back the volume i need to store it back
so that every frame you know I record
how much volume change happen in the
previous frame if I was to do that here
I'd have to reconvert this value the
volume value right back up wouldn't I oh
no you know what I could just use it
directly that's that's not true that's
not true I was I was all right look a
little out to lunch today that's not
true I think we can literally just do
that and we're fine so let's try that
one more time and I'll go in there and
set a breakpoint and I will set the D
current volume to you know negative oops
2.2 8.2 and the target volume to 0 so I
just want to fade out the sound right
seems reasonable so let's see how that
goes trying to unset this breakpoint
there we go
there we go and off it goes so yeah
that's fading not particularly difficult
but we have not really done sort of the
nasty part of it yet which is dealing
with what happens when the fade doesn't
quite line up perfectly right because
this is going to be a loop that has
about 800 steps in it right it's going
to do this loop about 800 times when it
comes through here to do 800 of those
samples and so what you have to think
about when you're in there is like what
happens if the volume would have hit the
target level just like right in the
middle there we don't want to keep
adding that volume in right so really we
need some way of actually making sure
that that loop won't do that that won't
it won't overshoot now this is already a
loop that kind of re-enters itself I
mean reenters is wrong word reruns
itself if it runs out of sound to mix
and there's a next sound there's a sound
that comes afterwards right it'll do
that reloading so I feel like what we
could do here as an easy way to fix that
problem of not stopping the volume
directly where it should be stopped is
we could you know in here we could check
to see when we expect to hit the volume
and clamp samples to mix to that if it's
going to be greater right if samples to
mix would have gone past that we could
just clamp it there and then this loop
would re-enter itself again would rerun
itself again and mix the remainder of
the samples I think so let me just make
sure there's nothing weird that would
stop us from doing that I don't think
there would be I think it just means
that we would have to get rid of this
assertion right
because now this assertion would just
totally fire I'm going to leave that
assertion in there for a second just to
make sure it does fire but I think
that's all we need so what we want to do
here is sailrite again this is going to
be a channel thing like so and what we
want to do here is just say that as we
go through the the channel stuff and we
could also set a bull here right as well
which is going to be something like in
fact I guess this output channel count
should probably something more like this
audio state output channel count what we
could do here is say volume ended keep
sort of a a a set here where we will say
whether the volume going to end so that
later when we get down here we don't
actually have to do these checks at all
anymore if that makes sense so what we
would do is say all right you know for
each one of these if the volume ended on
the channel index then do that for it
and don't bother doing any of those
checks because we're going to do them up
here when we actually calculate when to
end so what we want to do to calculate
when we're going to end is we want to
see if the d volume for this channel is
not 0 right because if it is 0 then the
volume isn't animating so there's really
nothing that we need to do right to make
that work if the volume is animating
then what we have to do is just say ok
how many samples is it going to take us
to get from the current place to where
we're trying to go right so we want to
say we have a volume that we're at right
we have a volume that we're going to
which is that playing sound target
volume right and what we want to do is
say
eh all right we know that this is how
far we have to go right this is our
volume Delta right so we know that this
is how far we have to go in volume space
right and we know that this is how much
time it will take us right we've got our
d volume or sort of volume sample count
maybe it's the best thing to say this is
how much time we this is how much we
move every sample so if we take the
Delta and figure out how many of these
volumes is going to take us to get there
that would give us the sample count for
the volume right now it's going to give
us a floating-point version of the
sample count so what we need to do is we
really want that to be truncated and
round it up right so we want to do is
something like saying all right the
volume sample count is actually just
going to be you know some kind of a
thing where we where we round that up to
to the nearest sample and then we just
go ahead and use it so when we do that
rounding we then want to make sure that
we will truncate this this samples to
mix if we need to so if samples to mix
is greater than the volume sample count
we could do before hitting the volume
cup for this guy we are going to only
allow it to do that many right and
furthermore we are going to record that
fact so that at the end we will stop the
volume ramp from actually occurring okay
so there we go right uh that's about it
and did go and actually this should also
be volume ended see each channel index e
channel index so
and oops and this should be our account
going ended as well so I think that's
pretty much all we have to do let's go
ahead and check that out
you
so let's let's try taking a fade in here
should probably set up a good test case
for this summer to keep going and
editing these but let's say I want the
target volume this time to be 0 point 5
or let you know it will do 0.0 on the
left channel and 0.5 on the right
channel and then that way we can hear it
should still be in one year basically
right and then the D current volume I'll
set something again really low Oh point
one for that guy Oh point one so it
should take about 10 seconds to fade out
and let's see how that does
and so hopefully this is exactly what I
thought it was this was the I saying it
should stop the loop early this was the
assert that I left in there
intentionally right and so hopefully
what that did here was that actually
sort of truncated it to one of the those
those values so that samples to mix was
less than what it should have been which
I guess was 1600 to 30 frames a second
is that correct so I was saying 800 it's
actually 2800 I was thinking the number
for 60 Hertz so let's take a look volume
ended 01 and so the volume that ended
first right is the one that got 20 point
five and that's exactly what should have
happened because right it should take
longer to get down to zero then to 0.5
so that's good that's sec what we want
let's go to the disassembly on that just
to skip over that that mauve there we go
set next statement
and there's it hitting again and now it
should be the other one and that's
exactly what it was so that's good again
let's skip over that perfect
awesome uh all right so you know
certainly haven't exhaustively tested
this sometimes you can have audio bugs
that are very subtle so you know I'm not
going to put some kind of official seal
on this and say that it's fantastic or
anything like that but now we've got
animated volumes and so we can now do
panning animated and we can change the
volume over we want to change the volume
as well so that's all good yeah so
really the only thing we might want to
add in addition here would be pitch
changing right and so pitch changing is
is sort of a different beast altogether
but I don't know whether we want to
start that mm this time or not yeah yeah
so let me talk briefly about actually
the stuff that I want to talk about that
was really do this so one of the
problems with doing things this way
though that I'm doing them here where we
just do a delta value that gets stepped
over time is that sometimes this can
lead you to not hit your volume as
exactly as you should hit it right and I
don't know to what degree that could
cause little minut errors in the sound
the reason for this is that if you take
something that's going to happen over
1,600 samples and you're adding a little
bit every time well if so you know if I
have a volume change that I want you
know X and I do 16 instead of just
adding X to the thing I do 1600 editions
of x over 1600 well that's all fine if
you're doing precise map but this is
floating point math at a computer and
floating-point math is in precise or the
question is is there error that will
accumulate when you do this right so
another way that we could do things is
by just setting a particular volume and
going to that volume by multiplying out
the new volume every time
right and the way that would work is we
would take sample index and we would
divide it by samples to mix to get like
how far we were in in this mix and we
would have a beginning and an end sound
value and we would just do the linear
interpolation between those right and
the reason that you don't want to do
that is because it requires you to do a
reciprocal like a you know an inversion
every step potentially or something like
this and so you may not want to do that
but these days you know the math I'm
chips is so fast that it's hard
sometimes to really argue against doing
stuff like that that are better a little
bit more robust because it turns out
that the chips today it's not like a
divide is a huge deal anymore right it's
really not that big a deal so sometimes
it doesn't really make sense to sort of
cut those corners if that makes if that
makes a little more sense so yeah so
that's one thing the other thing that we
could do here is instead of adjusting
how far in the loop we go we could
instead just adjust the Delta vol.2 to
hit it at the end so if the volume was
going to get there before the end we
just reduce the Delta to make it so that
it does line up at the end exactly right
so we just back solve for that instead
of solving for the samples we just back
solve for the Delta volume that would be
necessary to hit it right at the end
right so that's another way we could do
it and again I don't really know that
there's a strong reason to or not to do
it in any of these particular ways
unless we actually hear problems that
we're trying to fix or have reasons in
the code why we want to do them so i
probably will just leave that be for now
and will redress that when we move this
assembly because maybe in the sindhi
optimized loop which maybe is going to
want to operate for example on four
things at a time say four samples at a
time or something
like this we may find that it becomes
important there to be able to do those
adjustments a little bit differently or
something like this right I don't know
so I'm just pointing those out there I'm
just I'm just saying what the idea is
but that's basically where it's at so
let's take a look now at the change
volume stuff we aren't actually calling
that so maybe we need to kind of test
that routine here and what I'm what I'm
going to do i guess is i'll just go into
where we're currently calling the sword
sound stuff so when we do our play sound
calling here and we play the music I'll
just go ahead and store a handle to the
music when I actually play it in there
so in here I'll do playing sound you
know music or something like this and so
I'll say you know we've got the music
like that again this is just kind of
placeholder code so I'm just using this
for testing purposes so we'll grab the
music there and then when we do some
stuff like I go in here and I push one
of these buttons maybe I'll make up fade
in the volume and down fade out the
volume just so we can play with it a
little bit more so what we'll do here is
in the the audio system I'll make a
change volume call and I will have that
do something useful here right so game
state audio States it will take that
music and i will say that i want to have
you know a ten-second fade on the music
and i want it to fade in or out
depending on which i do so if i put up
it'll fade in and if i push out it'll
fade out right that should be about yet
oops and i forgot that the volume is
supposed to be for two channels
like so so we'll just do it this way and
you know I'll also you know why not in
here we could also do a thing where
maybe we do a quick pan like so so we
can move things between the two left and
right speaker or something like that
let's see no user define operator can
perform the conferred what what is the
problem here you want the ampersands
i'll give you the ampersand if you want
it you got it alright so here goes all
right forgot to have to actually have
stanch it a guy
that is doing absolutely nothing what
did I do wrong what did I do wrong is
our change volume code busted let's make
sure it's being called first change
volume because we tested the code and it
worked fine in our test let's see so
fade duration in seconds is 5 so it
should skip that one over fade Oh
fantastic I never actually set the
target volume didn't change volume so
glad we went ahead tested that target
volume should equal volume that kind of
goes to that saying and the Delta kind
of has to have it have happened already
as well so yeah so that was just a total
nonsense routine that should not have
worked and did not work all right
there we go so now it's in the left
channel right oh and I suppose we should
take out our test assertion as well
assert total samples to mix because this
is actually going to happen now
right so there's the paint one left
here's the pan back to the right
voice back to centered
you
and fade 201
all right I think that about wraps it up
for today and tomorrow I guess we'll go
do frequency changes that seems like
probably the best idea to me but for now
yeah let's let's go ahead and take it to
the queue and the a let's see here do we
have Q&amp;A hopefully we do there we go
expect pre stream questions today uh-oh
does that mean we were on the twitch
frontpage what does that mean can you
show again how you skipped a failed
assertion by going to disassembly
certainly I can certainly do that yeah I
guess we may be never really covered
this on me on the stream so let's yeah
so I'm just going to go ahead and blow
an assert right here this is the end of
your program hahaha so if I'm going to
you know have an assertion the fires
then there's a couple different things
that you can you that you might want to
do here right if you're using one of the
system assertions there's you can
usually just use ignore right to go
ahead and have that not be a problem but
if you're not using the systems
assertions then you don't actually get
that luxury right if you hit ignore
it'll just tell you again which is I
don't even know why the ignore is there
it's four different types of exceptions
I guess really where you could ignore
them so that's because we haven't really
written a you know a fancy assert but
just because we haven't written a fancy
assert doesn't mean you can't skip one
if you wanted to because all that we did
for the assert if you remember right in
in handmade we sort of put in our our
poor man's assert here all we did was
just right to know right so we write we
wrote to the null pointer which we know
will immediately cause a memory fault
and the operating system will halt our
program as if it had you know done an
illegal memory operation because that is
what it is doing right so what that
means is that if we go to the
disassembly we should be able to see
that illegal memory operation right and
you can see that illegal memory
operation right here
I and you know you can see in the
assembly what's actually going on so
here is the test that sets up the jump
it's seeing whether or not this are a x
value is is well this is this is sort of
a test reserve kind of a thing right
this test instruction well I won't go
too far into this let's simply say that
the test sets up a condition flag which
jump if equal jumps on right and so what
is trying to do is say oh okay you know
if this assertion was not supposed to
fire than what i'm going to do is jump
to this address if the assertion was
going to fire then i won't jump and
it'll execute the next line well where
is this address right this oh seven fef
91 DC 617 well it's right here right the
only thing it was trying to do was jump
over this line of machine code right so
let's trying to do is go from here to
here if the assertion wasn't supposed to
fire so if we don't want the assertion
to have fired we can just right click on
that line and say set next statement
because that's what the code would have
done if the assertion didn't fire so we
know that we don't really have to do
anything fancy to patch anything up
because it would have just been there
and so for there we can just go ahead
and run right it's going to come right
back here in a cert because this assert
is happening every time but that's just
a you know how you would skip a single
one now if you wanted to skip all of
them I suppose you could try to edit the
code bites here to be honest with you
I'm not sure I am really the person who
would know how to do that
I'm not even sure if you can edit them
can you edit them I don't yeah so I
guess what you'd have to do is you'd
have to go into the memory window if you
wanted to patch out the assert I mean
you know let's say that you were not
that crazy and you don't know assembly
language particularly well like i don't
so i don't know the code bytes for
specific assembly language instructions
so i'm not going to perform that level
of surgery by any stretch of the
imagination you could still imagine you
know making life a little easier in
yourselves you really wanted to you
could do something like this where you
basically said okay there's a persistent
variable here that's like ignore right
and then what you're going to do inside
the ignore is you're going to say if not
ignore then do the thing right something
like this and so you could do that if
you wanted to oops forgot to put an int
on there so this is a bool 42 so we go
in there now and you hit that assertion
right if you wanted to again this is
still a pretty poor man's version of
this but I'm just kind of giving you
what the idea is right you can see that
does a comparison on that ignore value
as well here now instead of just doing
the jump right and so what you can then
do is say oh ok now what I could do is I
could set that ignore a value I could
set that ignore value true that's easy
to do you can do it in the watch window
no problem now when you come out here
and you you take a look at that you know
at at the set next statement and come
out here you can just let it keep
running and then it will ignore that
assertion forever until you restart the
program right
so so that's something so yeah you can
do stuff you can do stuff like that if
you're if you're feeling fancy about it
what we will do when we do our debug
code pass is will actually write a real
assertion that does some more stuff
that's you know a little bit cleaner
than actually just faulting but just to
give you the idea that hopefully that
gives you an idea of how that stuff
works let me take out the assertion that
I just put at the beginning of our
program would there be any case where
you would like to increase volume
nonlinearly up possibly but you know
honestly it's kind of hard to tell with
sound most the time usually your ear is
not that good at sensing stuff like that
so typically linear is fine you care
mostly about the speed at which things
are going so you do want to be able to
control that but you don't necessarily
need to control the shape of the curve
all that much typically typically but
you know again it all depends on the use
case right handmade here is not a game
about sound it's a game about other
things that happens to have sound which
is the way many games or most games are
but there are games that are about sound
in games that are about sound may want
to do more advanced sounding so you know
like with anything on handmade hero
we're basically doing sort of the basic
version of everything to a professional
level of quality but any given thing
that we do you could choose to go way
further on right and and if your game is
about that thing then you would want to
really go into depth on that and sound
is an example of that handmade hero is
not a game that needs some kind of crazy
elaborate sound system you know like
maybe rock band let's say or fracked OST
or whatever it was called might want
because their games about sound right
and so it's important to remember that
when I say we don't really need to do X
what I mean is in order to do a
professional a professional quality
version on this
we don't need to do it that doesn't mean
that the circumstance would never call
for you to do something of that kind so
far you can just change the volume of
individual sounds should we be able to
change the volume of the master output
as well um I mean we could probably do
we probably would want something very
simple they're like for example we might
want a thing which was just like you
know master volume like this and then
that that audio state would just by
default you know do master volume equals
the you know default volume and then at
the head end whenever we're doing these
these volumes right you would just pre
multiply it in right so whenever you
grabbed out the volume you would just
you know you could you'd pre multiply
the volume in there and then you don't
pre multiply presumably on the way out
well I guess you know what probably the
easier thing to do would actually just
to leave it in here so that way you
don't have to mess with the iterator in
and out so yeah you'd probably just do
something where you actually just
multiply it in the loop we could we
could if that turns out to actually cost
us appreciably we could we could not but
that would be how you'd throw a master
volume in there really not a whole lot
to it
but that would that would let you do
that well handmade here at support
spatialization EG sound mostly in left
channel life on the left side of the
screen sound boasting the right channel
if on the right side so we support that
in the mixer now and i guess it's up to
us whether we choose to use that feature
when we're actually when we're actually
playing sounds in the game and i don't
know which one will want to do i think
that will when we get further along in
the game we'll have to see what the
sound mix sounds like to us and whether
we like it sounding that way or whether
that's too distracting and we'd rather
have it sound more centralized in
general how hard would it be to do a
fade out fade in for the music when the
window loses focus or gets focused back
well obviously as you've seen it's
trivial for us to do that in the mixer
now because we implemented that so that
would be free but it's harder for us
potentially to do that with windows
because windows kind of cuts you off
there so what we'd have to do because
right now our the way that our sound is
set up it's set up in a mode where we we
kind of have audio device access when
we're active and then we we don't play
when we're not active what we would have
to do is change when we request our
sound buffers from windows when we set
up the primary audio device which if you
remember a long time ago we did we would
have to change the way we set that up to
tell windows that we want to play sound
all the time not just when were the
active app but you can certainly do that
so you know if that was something that
you really cared about you could
certainly do that
so what did you end up doing to de vol
if it wasn't linear interpolation it was
d volume is linear interpolation if you
implement assert using ? colon instead
of if you could use it as part of
expressions or other such places where
you can't have an if statement but why
would you want to use an assert in that
way because the certs compile out so
they can't be part of statements if you
want those statements to work the same
in debug or release right so do you have
an example of where you would want to
use that because i don't think i've ever
wanted what you're saying and I'm
wondering if maybe you're thinking of
something different than what I'm
thinking of when you say that kasto 5s
sorry I haven't followed everything
you've done lately did you already
implant audio clipping could you be more
specific about what you mean by audio
clipping we have not done anything with
the dynamic range of the audio if that's
what you're talking about so for example
in here right now we have not done a
clamp right so I can even put that in
here for you
oops that's not where the clamp goes I
meant here so you know when we're in
simdi and it's free for us to do so we
will throw a clamp in there but we will
probably never do anything wonky like a
compressor all right is that it for
questions
okay gasps Elias is managing the other
than exchange yes no we have not done
anything for that and I don't think we
will I don't suspect that we will I
don't really feel like this game will
need an audio compressor I could be
wrong about that but I just don't expect
that it will
with respect to is research with respect
to assert I don't know why you would
want to put one expression but
apparently that's how it's usually
implemented it can't hurt right sure it
can because if someone accidentally put
in a certain expression that's like bad
right that's code that's probably broken
so I don't really want to enable a use
case that I can't think of ever it
actually occurring so so yeah it can
hurt right you don't want code if you if
you can't think of any legitimate reason
why anyone would want to write a piece
of code then you don't really want to
enable that if the compiler could be
catching it and cause an error right so
so I wouldn't tend to do that unless I
had a valid use case in mind and if I
had a valid use case in mind than I
would because i'm not one of those
people who likes to like lock down all
the code and make it really hard to work
with because you were trying to prevent
all these mythical errors from occurring
so I'm totally not you know I'm not one
of those people but on the flip side if
I literally can't think of a single
reason why I would ever want to do
something and I can and the thing that
you're talking about the only things I
can think of our times when you would
want it to not happen then that is
something I'm going to leave illegal
because that all the compiler can is
just going to help me right
you
you can't just hard tip audio though if
you don't use a compressor limiter you
would have to at least use soft clipping
with an age thing that's actually not
true it's like games totally ship with
with hard clipping it's it's really it's
really not as big of a deal as you think
and it happens very rarely in actual
practice it's really not that big of a
deal will you implement audio file
compression I don't anticipate doing so
by that I mean I don't anticipate
putting in a special-purpose audio
compressor if we can get away with it
because I feel like it would just take a
very long time to put one in and it
wouldn't really be all that educational
because I'm not an audio compression guy
so I would it would literally be like
watching me implement odd vorbis from
the spec or something would you just be
a long time of watching me do it where
I'm not really adding any insightful
comments because I have no idea I don't
have insight to share right I'm just
like well spec said this is what they
did so that's when I'm playing back
right uh so i would like to not bother
i'd like to just shove it all through a
basic compressor and just live with the
fact that our file for prints bigger
than it should be and you know if we did
do something with compression it would
be after we're done with the whole game
and in something like that but because i
really just don't want to it's just not
that interesting and I don't want to
insert this huge block of of stream time
to dedicate something that I just don't
feel is particularly relevant
what would an audio compressor do so an
audio compressor is something which
attempts to squish the range of the
audio in a nonlinear way right so
typically what happens is if you think
about how we squish volumes we're
squishing volumes in a linear way so you
know we have something where we do like
volume time sound right and so what that
does is the volume range is between 0
and 1 typically and so if you have some
sound sample and you multiply it by
point 5 it gets like half as tall right
so you know this is this is the the
point five sound here and this is the
the one point 0 version of the sound and
so the problem with that is that if you
have very loud sounds and very quiet
sounds it's sort of like HDR imaging you
end up in a situation where you just run
out of room to do everything this way
and you want to try and make it so that
all your sounds fit in there so what you
try to do is instead of mapping the
sound in that linear way where you just
have like a linear ramp of some kind for
your sounds what you do instead is you
map it to some kind of a curve so that
as it gets louder you know here's the
input volume and here's the output
volume as sounds get louder and louder
they stop actually becoming all that
much louder in practice right so from
here to here it actually is quite a bit
much louder by moving this far whereas
if I if I increase the volume by that
same amount at a much louder and I'm
really not getting very much right and
so what it what it does in practice is
if you look at like the waveforms right
and here is you know my my crazy sound
that I'm playing back right what it does
in practice is it makes it so that you
know you've got a normal linear sort of
looking sound profile here but then as
things get up into like a band at the
high end it compresses a huge amount of
actual linear volume range into this
little band right that's that's what it
does
how much optimization would the mixer
require you know honestly probably very
little we might even be able to leave it
the way it is but I was going to show
you how to do it and Cindy just just cuz
but it's it's not like the GPU the the
graphic stuff where we did sort of our
own version of a GPU where we had to do
some pretty good optimization to make
everything go well that's not really the
case with the mixer the mixer in its in
its unseen deed state is probably still
pretty fast and we certainly won't have
to multi-threaded I wouldn't expect what
is the difference between a limiter and
a compressor so you're asking the wrong
guy i am not an audio guy so i'm not
even qualified to say you know what all
the different things are limiter or
compressors or the many other things
that there are out there so you you
should probably ask an audio an audio
person for a good explanation because I
have no idea what most audio filter
stuff actually is technically you know
looks like that is it all right good
deal
good deal all right well I guess we will
go ahead and wrap things up I didn't
feel like we got too many pre stream
questions that seemed like a pretty
reasonable set of questions to me let's
see here close this up all right thank
you everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with
handmade here at home and play around
with the source code yourself you can
always go to handmade hero dot org and
pre-order the game it comes with all the
source code so that you can play around
with it and learn from the stream as we
go we also have a forum site you can go
to to ask questions while you're doing
that and it also has an ant 8 episode
guide so you can follow up on like old
episodes and watch them a little you
know catch up if you've missed some we
also have a patreon page where if you
would like to support the video series
by itself you can subscribe and finally
we have a tweak bot the tweet bots will
tweak the schedule at you and let you
know when the stream is going to be live
so if you like what you're watching and
you want to catch it again the easiest
way is to just subscribe to that tweet
bottom it will tell you or just check
the tweetbot manually it's always got
the schedule for the day and usually the
whole week up there for you that's about
it thank you very much for joining me we
will not be here tomorrow I have a prior
engagement I believe wait is that no
that's not true tomorrow's Wednesday try
wednesday you know i'ma have to check
the own schedule we I think we will be
back here tomorrow yeah we will be back
here tomorrow am i right 24th yeah I got
to use my own tweet bot just to know
when the show is going to be on so yeah
we will be back here tomorrow 5pm it's
Thursday that's off today just so
everyone knows but I will be back here
same time same place twitch 5 p.m.
pacific daylight time tomorrow for
another episode of handmade hero so if
you would like to join me for some more
audio coding we will go ahead and do the
frequency change stuff so we can we can
pitch shift our sounds up and down a
little bit
which you know again not super necessary
for our game but it helps that a little
bit of variety to your soundscape makes
things a little easier on the audio
engineering so it's something that we
want to enable just small pitch bends
right we're not talking about auto tune
or something here but small pitch bends
can be pretty handy so we will we will
go ahead and implement that far and then
we're coming up on the end of the stuff
we need to do for audio so it's been
good it's been really efficient coding
again we're knocking all this stuff off
our to-do list is great so yeah I'm
looking forward to having a fairly
complete engine here we're getting we're
getting good work done so hopefully all
of you out there excited about the
progress we're making i know IM and it
feels good to be coming up on on sort of
you know having a pretty capable engine
that we can play with for for the
remainder of our game coding time so
thanks for joining me i will see you
guys back here tomorrow until then have
fun coding and i will see you guys on
the Internet at large take it easy
everyone