hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are going to be doing
some bleeding today before I get started
obviously if you've seen the banner
we're doing a Kickstarter right now for
our comic if you like comics please
check it out
that's what that little fellas doing up
there that's what me I was doing right
there all I gotta do is click on it and
Scout a trailer and all the information
and all that stuff so please check it
out we're just gonna hop right into it
today we're gonna go to probably the
blackboard first I'm gonna guess because
we got to talk about what it is that
we're actually gonna do we did some
analysis yesterday and I'm pretty sure I
understand now like sort of what I need
to do to my routine to do it to make it
do what I want it to do if you remember
what we ended up with is and I'll run it
here we and I guess I'll show it here as
well let me go grab the lighting code so
here's the ray caster so if you remember
we took a look and I was just playing
around with this routine to see what was
going on with it and looking at some
stuff and by analyzing the routine just
to figure out what was going on in here
I was like oh right we kind of need to
be more systemic about how we do this if
we're going to switch to doing a KD tree
because we build a KD tree right now we
don't really use it we use it as if it's
just an a/b hierarchy if we actually
want to use it as an a/b tree we're
gonna have to start getting smarter
about how we do things and we're gonna
want to do a little bit more careful
work with how we handle our hit
detection so again just to remind
everyone where we're at if I go ahead
and run the HH light prof routine you
can see here that we have a way of sort
of pseudo validating our stuff by
looking at what our Texel error ends up
being so we know we don't regress on our
hits much and then what we can do is we
can look at the total seconds elapsed
this is just us running our ray casting
a lot to see how long it takes and we
want that number to go down now ideally
we'd like to get that number to go down
a lot right like we'd like that number
to be going down to you know three
or to like we'd love we'd like some
really massive improvements in speed if
we can get them and we don't actually
know that we can but we do have some
suspicion at least that we could because
you know we we at least know that we're
not doing anything particularly smart in
here other than the fact that we do
trace for rays at a time so we have sim
D and we have a reasonable box Collider
but we don't really have anything else
particularly smart going on in there
now one thing that I might want to do is
start printing out the leaves and
partitions information because we
actually gather this information but we
don't use it so one of the things that
you can see in fact if we go to handmade
lighting dot cpp what you will see is
that in the internal lighting core which
is here what you can see is we actually
compute this information so we we do
these work casts initiated we tally all
this stuff up and then in n lighting
computation we print it out right so we
have a thing that does the tally here we
can do that ourselves right so we can
actually do this inside the test routine
as well and what I'd like to do is just
start printing out what those numbers
are so that we have an idea of how much
time we're spending in each loop roughly
it won't tell us exactly how much but if
we assume at least tell us like how many
things were processing in each case and
so if we take a look at the at the
actual HH light prof code and we take a
look at after we do that dispatch right
here where we get outside of the root so
we're done doing the lighting and we're
ready to print stuff out what I can do
here is I can actually sum summarize so
basically like here I can take a
summation I can do a summation of the
work count so you can see we we actually
initialize these or create a certain
number of these
right you could see like a lock work
count this sort of stuff right and I
don't remember I feel like this is
supposed to return the work count
probably uh internal lining core yeah so
the actual work count that's done comes
back here so we can just sum that work
count we can sum the work count right
here we guess we can sum all of these
various values and if we do that we can
then print out some of the information
that we get so we can say look here's
the information in fact we can do that
we can actually do that perhaps even as
a matter of course now I think about it
so like if we want to write we could do
this we could say well always some ate
it we'll put it in here right and then
we'll print it out as part of the like
performance estimate right so in here
we'll print it now I hate printing
I hate actually using the the the code
to print 64-bit numbers it's always
terrible because it was like designed by
people who had no idea what they were
doing and so I'm just gonna print these
as float even though they are not float
right so what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
take like total cast initial initiated
actually I don't care about that I just
want total partitions tested and total
leaves tested right I just want those
two numbers for now like partitions and
leaves right and what I'm gonna do is
I'm just gonna cast those two doubles on
the way in so that we just have a
printout for them that doesn't rely on
weird format specifiers so I'm going to
go ahead and compile that and see if I
can get this printing out just
information for me about how many things
we were doing and so when we do this
what we should see is a on the
performance estimate we should see how
many of these things we do and so over
the repeated runs you can see it you
know it and the other thing too I think
I might print this out in both cases so
whether or not we're doing the
performance or not let's print it out in
both cases
because that way I can also see how much
a single run is versus multiple runs
just easier to look at um so if we take
a look at that you can see like here's
how many we're doing on a single run oh
wait we zero them every time so never
mind it's yeah we don't need that
because it's gonna that is for a single
run duh it's not it's not multiplied out
all right so that's just telling us like
how many partitions were testing versus
how many leaves were testing right and
we also had a partitions per leaf value
that we were printing out in the
lighting and I think we want that
because that lets us know like how many
partitions it takes us to get to the
actual thing we want which is leaf
testing so what we want is well you know
what I guess maybe I don't care I know I
think about it but if you take a look at
the ratio of these numbers I guess which
is sort of what I was talking about you
can see that like actually this one is
almost four times more than four times
yeah I think it's more than four times
is that right you know you know I'm
gonna print it out I just said I wasn't
I'm gonna print it out so this is this
is the partitions per leaf I don't know
why I put K in there there we go so what
I'm gonna do here is just like here's
our total partitions tested here's our
total leaves tested so I'm literally
just gonna take this and I'm gonna
divide right and I think we have a safe
ratio well actually don't know if we
have one for doubles and since we know
this is never zero I'm just gonna do it
right so now this will tell us the total
partitions per leaf and you know this
one is probably wants a little more
precision so this one probably wants
more like point two or something I'm
guessing just so we can get a little bit
of significant figures in there so if we
take a look at what this does when you
know after we run the test this tells us
that we're you know how many partitions
how many leaves this says there are four
point four times as many partitions
tested as there are leaves tested right
so a couple numbers we care about right
we probably also care about the total
right so we might want to just do like
this where we do that so add them
together and now we know like the total
amount of work we're doing is so the
number of like actual loop bodies which
is this number here we know how many of
them are being tested just for like
calling purposes which is this number
here we know how many of them were
actually testing and using results from
so like these are actual boxes we do the
collision and we potentially update our
closest point and then we know like what
the ratio of those two things are is and
so that's pretty much all the
information that I really need there
what you can see is it's like okay the
total number of loop bodies is 2.8
million right which is a lot of loop
bodies and you can see that's why this
is so slow right because our routine
isn't that slow it's just that's a lot
of stuff to check right and so the
question is where's that stuff mostly
coming from we could see it's four times
more likely that what we're doing is
testing a partition so we're spending a
lot of our loop bodies in partition
testing we don't actually know that
that's the book of the time because
we're not timing the two loop bodies
separately or anything like that but we
do know that we're just executing that
loop a lot more and since the two loops
look similar and if anything this loop
is more complicated because that's to
push stuff on a stack it's a pretty fair
bet that like that's a really bad part
of the routine right it's called way
more often it's called almost five times
four point four times over four times
more often and it's probably more
expensive so we kind of know that making
the partition tester smarter or better
using less partition testing or I mean
doing something smarter there right
could make a big difference in our
routine so I think that's what we
probably want to focus on and the first
thing that I think we should probably
try to focus on is just simplifying this
down so that we don't actually I think
we should try to make a special-purpose
design for the part for the KT tree I
don't think we should stuff it in to the
AAA be like it is being stuffed now now
we can still store it uniformly if we
need to but we're gonna want something
better I guess it's what I'm saying all
right so what are we gonna do hmm
is the real question right so what are
we gonna do here we need we need to try
and figure out a solution here to our to
our situation that'll that'll improve
the partition testing in some way so if
we actually take a look at the partition
tester so if I go to my raycast here I'm
gonna need to yeah I'm gonna need to
figure out
qingxue me sorry I'm going to need to
figure out some way to change this
routine here to be able to do what it's
doing faster and one of the things that
I want to be able to do here as well is
like I was saying we need some way of
let me just go to the blackboard we need
some way of processing the hits in order
so that we don't waste time processing
things that we know we can't hit or
another way to say it would be we need
to make sure we don't waste time
processing things which we know won't be
better hits than hits we already have so
if I actually load up Milton here and I
just drop in a day five ninety five
so is that actually the right day it
seems low was it 594 yesterday
yeah I guess it was it doesn't look like
that's quite up yet the new one
begging Lanie validation 594 mmm mm-hmm
let's see here
actually you know what I still want to
right the wrong day down so the video
that we last posted was 594 yeah okay no
problem no worries mm-hmm all right so
if we want to do a KD tree here which is
what we've constructed and how we are
actually processing it right now we're
just not aware of it meaning our routine
is processing it as if it's an a a B
tree so we in other ways we built a KD
tree but we test an a a B tree right so
normally a KD tree is the thing that
just splits in one dimension every node
so if this is like my node and I'm gonna
have like a a and B branch here or
something that I go down the way that it
splits space is you know you've got a
bunch of objects in the space and it
picks a split plane and it sorts them
into an a side and a B side right and so
the KD tree is just doing that
recursively so then you take the a space
and you you put that right with that and
so on so you only split by one dimension
at a time X Y or Z and that's the
entirety of the idea behind a KD tree
what we're doing is we're building the
tree that way but then we actually store
these as boxes so we don't ever take
advantage of the fact that the entire
information for a node can really just
be one plane and when you test against
it you don't need to test against a box
you could just test against that plane
and know what you were going to be doing
so
ideally what we'd like to do here is be
cognizant of the fact that this is a
Katie tree because we could probably
speed things up if we did and one of the
things we'd like to do because obviously
we can start by just doing a plane test
and working with the plane because what
we could do is say well look if we're
pointing if we have a plane and we
classify which side of the plane we're
on right that's very easy to do because
it's just the plane equation right
so whatever the plane is we know that
the plane equation tells us which side
were on and because this is access
aligned we don't even need to do an
inner product because we know that
whichever axis it is right X Y or Z
whichever axis it is we just use that
value right that value minus the D value
of the plane is gonna tell us which side
were on so it's literally just a
subtract of one of the axes from a
constant value that's it right super
super simple so we know we can test
which side we're on really easily and
then all we have to do is see the same
thing for the Ray direction
so whatever the raid erection is we can
classify which direction we're going and
if we're not billing in the in the
direction that would point us towards
the plane so if our if our Ray is
pointing away from the plane we know we
only have to test the side were in right
we never have to test the other side if
we're pointing towards the other side
then we need to test our side first and
then the other side after right and so
the problem that you know that we have
here is that we have to sort of we have
to create a stack that would be more
amenable to that process because right
now we don't really have a stack that
can do this we don't have a stack that
allows us to like do all of our work and
then when we pop back up actually yes we
do nevermind we can do that easily we
just okay so we just push this on the
stack first and then we push this on the
stack and then it will pop back to this
eventually right so totally fine okay
so that's one thing we can do and that
would be easy right
so that's simple and then the other
thing we can do is if at any time we can
pretest and say look if there's no way I
can make it to this plane so whatever
the distance from this plane is along
the Ray and that's an actual
intersection so that's harder to compute
because we have to know the actual T
value wait no it's not no it's not at
all
never mind so even that's easy to
compute all we have to do is just walk
add our current team n values like our
hit at our current hit value if we just
take our Ray add our hit value to it we
will get a point if that point is
actually on the if that point is on the
other side of the plane we know that we
could hit some but thing on that side of
the plane and be closer if that point is
on the same side of the plane as us we
don't have to do that branch at all
right because we know at that point that
the value that that nothing we could hit
on the other side of the plane would
ever be a closer hit than the hits we've
already had right so we could do a lot
better potentially here and I don't want
to say definitively that this will be
faster because I don't know like
anything on a modern CPU unless it's a
very clear-cut thing you can never say
that you're going to be faster when you
do something if you already have a
routine that's relatively optimized
meaning you know you've done the work of
putting it in Cindy and it's not doing
anything
incredibly stupid then even though you
can have a suspicion that well this
should be faster because I think it can
do less processing and it can do less
math so that should equal a faster
routine right it's just intuition it's
not true until you actually test it and
verify
that fact right so I suspect that this
will give me a faster routine but that
is purely a suspicion
it is not actually any guarantee so we
again want to take this cautiously and
say alright let's try to let's try to do
this by replacing this routine but we're
gonna leave the existing routine in
place probably because we don't actually
know yet whether it's gonna be faster
right
so this routine here that we're this
this part here we're gonna have to
replace okay so what we need now is we
need a way of encoding exactly what I
just said into our into our stack so
we're gonna have to pull something off
the stack that we can actually use in
some way that gives us a bunch of values
and the values that we need are going to
be like you know are gonna be I should I
say this so I want to write this routine
first and play around with it before I
go modify my stack because I don't know
exactly what I want to store that's what
I'm trying to say so let me sketch out
all the things I just said like how
would they actually have to work I want
to try and do that first so that I have
like a solid thing where I can be like
okay here's what I'm gonna have to do
now let's design the stack that gives me
easy access to those things right okay
so if we take a look here at the the
things I'm gonna need I need to know
which one of the values in the plane I
actually want right because what I'm
gonna need to use that value as the
classifier right I I need to I need to
load out of my source data my Rae or
whatever I need to use specifically the
that corresponds to the correct
dimension now the problem that I'm gonna
have here in terms of making this fast
is you know I would like to avoid doing
something like a horizontal ad and I
don't really need one because like I
said doing a dot product with with an
doing a dot product was something where
you actually know already it's just one
of your values either positive or
negative
I just am Not sure I'm not sure what the
fastest way to do that is with an
intrinsic because while it's easy to
pick a dimension I don't really want to
have to branch every time I would like
to be able to load using a value and I'm
not sure you can do that so if you take
a look for example at the extractor
teens like here right you can see that
they're set up around immediate and
that's the problem I'm talking about so
for example uh yeah let me what do you
call it let me let's let's go here so
what I want to do here is like I guess
that could be swizzles they could be
wait wait wait wait wait wait no it's
not as bad as I thought actually I can
just do this with some constants because
now that I think about it right we
already have our Ray as X's wise and Z's
because we're four wide so actually I
don't have to be as nervous as I thought
it is a little annoying because in order
to avoid branching every time I would
need to I would need to basically do
like three instructions to select the
actual one that we need right but other
but it's okay otherwise so so I think
we're actually all right here so what I
can do is I can say all right we've got
a couple values we want here like I was
saying we've got like a classifier so
this will basically be the thing that
says for this particular plane what are
we gonna do and what I need to do here
is I need to do like a select
effectively right I need to be able to
pick based on a based on some kind of a
thing that's stored in the actual stack
I need to be able to pick from X Y or Z
and yeah I don't know if we actually
have that we do so you can see here I've
got like select and then I've got a mask
value right so what I need to do here is
I need to do is select and then I need
to do another select right it's how this
would work
and so the Ray position for example like
where the Ray actually is I can generate
here so what I need to do is say like
trying to get what the fast wait is to
be so what I need to do here is say like
okay you know the Ray direction or the
Ray position right so we've got Ray
origin I believe is what it's called
this value so I've got rate origin and I
want to select from like the x value
or the Y value depending on like the
mask that picks one of the other right
so I want to do this with like an S mask
and then I want to do here another one
that's like okay I've got ray I've got
classifier or I guess most people call
this Y mask and then we have a Z mask
right right origin Z and so this is just
doing a dot product by doing two selects
right and again I don't know if that's a
smart thing it may be that we really
would rather just do the multiply ad
which is two instructions but issues on
two ports not sure mm-hmm
hard to say actually cuz the Select yeah
I guess we can worry about that later
but yeah hard to say but anyway if we
have the the Y mass loaded here and the
Z mass loaded here from our stack or
something or Frye actually be from the
box somehow right we would load those up
probably by just loading a single
floating point value and replicating
right I would assume so that's probably
how this would work it would be like you
know our our KD node here and we would
say like whatever the Y mask is and
whatever the Z mask is those would just
be stored as two floating point values
that we would load for expedience so I
think that's all that would happen
we then have a classifier now that we
built that can pick out the thing we
want and so we can do that twice and get
you know the basically like the origin
class or like the origin side you know
I'm saying and the direction side
and this will just pick based on the
raider action instead of the race side
and I don't remember it's just raid D
right yeah so and this tells us where
we're starting so relative to this KT
tree like which side you're on
and then it tells us like which whether
we're gonna stay on that side or not so
basically if these two sides are the
same you know and I'm saying and
actually I suppose we can also this
actually we can classify a little bit
differently rather than using the Ray
direction we can actually use our
current team in like I say I'm can step
out to our current team in and use that
so another way to look at it would be
instead of doing rey de r yeah we can
just use yeah we can just use a slightly
turn value and since we can do subtract
as well on this there's some of the
things we can do a little later but
anyway so if you go in here and we take
der side right this is actually gonna be
like end side I guess and so I might
call this like the start side you know
and the inside because it's like where
the race starts and where the Ray ends
and so what we'd want to do here is not
rady we'd want to do like Ray end and
Ray end is just going to be like an ad
right so it's gonna be like a V 3 for X
ray and equals ray origin plus whatever
the current like minimum value is right
so it's it's this right it's this now
since I think we do probably want to
know that value fairly frequently we may
want to start storing that right so the
hit P we may want to stop caring about
tier a at some point and actually start
caring about hippy but I don't know
we'll see you about that
so this is actually what we need
here and so we produced that and on here
we're gonna do like okay so hit P right
hit P hit P so that's all fine and I
think that gives us the actual
information that we need so this gives
us our origin point this gives us our
hit point so we have a start in our end
and the only thing we need to do now is
actually subtract so we need start side
to be like you know start side - and we
need n side to be inside - some like
plain D value right and this is just the
thing that were that we're using to
adjust so that we know that we're if we
just did this we're just picking the
coordinate but the plane is somewhere in
that along that axis and we have to
remove that value so that we're relative
to the plane right now the fact that
we're subtracting this from both things
means that I'm not sure we actually need
to do that we'll see us the math goes if
it might be that we can just ignore that
but so from the box from the like
permanent storage of the KD tree we
would need to know the masks for y and z
and then the plane and then from those
three floating point values we can
produce exactly the thing that I said in
the on the black board we now know what
side we start on what side we end on and
we can tell what the sign of those two
things is if we want to as well right
which is which is probably what we care
about for for testing okay so that's the
actual information that we needed and
now we just need to figure out what
exactly we're going to do and like I
said there's only three things we might
want to do here we might want to push
both things on the stack or we might
want to only push one why they want to
push both things or no things that's all
right we all want to push both things or
one thing technically there's a case
where we would push no things but in
order to
that we wanted to not push anything at
all we would need additional piece of
information which is the the minimum
plane bound or if there's other bounds
we wanted to check so basically the
question is do we want to do that or not
and what I mean by this is if you take a
look at how the KT tree is structured
what's gonna happen here is that let's
suppose we have a bunch of crap right
scattered around we do a KD tree
division right and we're gonna do a ray
cast like that well if we were to do
this testing in AABB land we would have
two AAA bb's to test against this one
and this one right and what we would
find pretty much immediately is that we
don't actually need to test either of
these two things so we would just never
descend once we go to a KD tree the only
thing we're gonna have is that we're on
this side of it we're not gonna know
that actually we don't need to test it
because there's the bounds of it or not
close to us now what we normally would
do in a KT tree is we just will we just
keep going right there's another bound
there's another bound like there's
another bound there's another bound
right and so on so we would always go
down and test at least one thing for
every raycast even forecasting outside
that may just be better it's hard to say
right the idea behind the KD tree is
minimize the number of actual tests like
that you do to walk down to leaves and
then test the leaves right so what we
want to do is keep this as simple as
possible and again like I don't know if
it actually is you can see how much work
we're doing here it is a fair amount
actually so it's unclear if we can beat
it or not might you know modulo our
loads here's the actual work we're doing
mostly the selects are the cost here and
then we've got to subtract so then what
we want to do here is say look either
we're gonna push we're either gonna push
two things or one thing right so that's
all we really need to know is we're
either pushing one thing
two things and you know this might be a
case for that conditional move because
in this case we know that we'd always be
pushing one thing so we know that like
box tap depth plus plus is always going
to be equal to like the closed side
right and then the only question is like
do we push the far side right so it's
like this you know maybe it will happen
maybe it won't right
and that might want to be conditional
move now like I said because unlike the
previous routine we need to do all the
work to determine this there isn't extra
work that gets done because there's no
binary and here or anything
I'm II know binary or I think it's just
like literally we and these two things
together and whatever the result is we
push or don't write so we would do this
classification we would then you know
push this on and we would just see can
we make it to the far side or not if we
can't make it to the far side we just
stop and that's the end of the story
right so
I think that's it
I don't know so in here we basically say
okay we've got two box that pushes we
want to push a closed side in the far
side I think we need to know in order to
determine which so the start side the
reason we need to know the start side is
just because we need to know whether or
not we we need to be able to select
which of the two sides we're going to
push right so the the reason we need
that is because we need to figure out
what close side even is so close side is
going to be equal to like something that
has to do with what start side sign is
right so if that makes sense so another
thing that's interesting about this now
that I think about it too is that
there's only one of them
so interesting mm-hmm
so the Rae origin is the same for all of
the Rays that we pass in here so we
don't actually need to do multiples on
this one right this is not actually for
wide so that's a bit of a brain teaser
isn't it so the question is if that's
not for wide what do I do with the rest
of that
yikes
so the problem that I'm seeing here and
it's not a problem as much as an
opportunity I guess is the way to think
about it is that if I want to know for
my KD tree which side I'm on the Rae
origin for all four Ray's is the same so
it doesn't need to be computed wide
you're just computing the same thing
multiple times that's just kind of
wasteful so you're wasting three lanes
worth of arithmetic that you could have
been doing something on right and I
guess I don't know though what can i
what could I possibly use those other
three lanes for because there's no real
point to it now I could classify 3k DS
at a time sorry for
and I guess I just should
I mean yeah I really don't know what to
do there I'm sure there's a right answer
people use KD trees for ray tracing
specifically like this is a very common
technique so I think I must be doing
something stupid or not thinking of
something obvious because I'm not sure
are you paralyzed that particularly well
because it's like well the origins in
the same place and when I want to
classify that how do I avoid throwing
away the work there I could classify
this against it and it's children at the
same time but if I do that what do I do
for push purposes I really don't know
that's a stumper
what why is the what was my computer
just doing it just did a little luck
waiting for I don't want to know what
that was um that's a real stumper so I
don't know what that implies so so I
guess so I guess the answer for for me
here is I guess I do want I guess I do
want to put a more some more information
into this thing like
like if I'm gonna have to classify the
origin of this Rea relative to something
I might as well classify it relative to
four things right and if I'm gonna
classify it related to four things I
might as well classify it relative to
like two bounds like a minute a max
bound at the very least right
so I guess what I would say is it'd be
pretty easy to switch this to using two
of the lanes using four of the lanes
I don't know what I don't know what to
do with that I'm really stumped so using
four of the lanes would suggest that we
would also need to test the second axis
at the same time so like we could always
include Z bounds and just like like we
could use some kind of weird hybrid tree
it's like a alternating XY tree with Z
encoded on every rung because you can
yeah I'm sorry I'm stumped on this so I
want to go read some KD tree literature
at this point which is what I would
normally do I mean I would have normally
done that first but I do try to always
figure things out myself on handmade
hero just to walk through that process
for you and it's a bummer here because
I'm pretty sure people have already
worked this out to within an inch of its
life
so I know someone's doing something
smarter than the things that I'm saying
because I can't imagine they haven't
they've definitely figured out better
stuff I'm just not thinking of what that
better stuff is offhand and so like
yeah filling up so they the good
news is the far side point like the end
side that obviously always needs four
wide because the hit on each ray is
gonna be different so that's not a waste
of time but the Ray origin classifier
definitely is and I just I'm just not
seeing what to do with that additional
information I mean I guess the answer is
just don't use it yet I guess I mean I
don't know man I just don't know hmm all
right well let me see what happens if I
go a little further with this and I'll
just like I'll just say that this is the
best we're gonna do it sucks sorry so
we'll do the crappy version and then we
will go just look at some literature on
it like what the current research papers
are on fast like GPU ray tracing for
example would have talked a lot about
this sort of stuff and we'll we'll do a
better one from having read about it
then because unless I come up with a
brainstorm soon like this is not smart
what I'm doing here so
you
so once we select what we're actually
doing so once we select one of these
things we then can determine which side
is the closed side in which side is the
far side so we're going to load out of
the KD tree right we're gonna load
something based on an address like a 0
or a 1 so it would basically be like
sides here and we would use a sign bit
right to determine that so we need like
a value that will either be a 0 you know
or a 1 here that will load which one the
closed side is and then we have the far
side is just the KD sides of of not fat
right so this is like the closed side
index and this is not the closed side
index right so you just load the other
one now there's other things we could do
here and possibly that are possibly
smarter another one we could do is just
say like you know I don't I don't
actually know which way we want to do
that but like something like this but
we'll see I don't actually know how we
want to do that but basically like you
know the the knot of that would be what
we'd load out anyway so if we load the
far side in the close side we would then
push the close side on and then assuming
that like inside is different right we
would push the far side on but otherwise
we wouldn't and again that's something
we can try to make be you know a
conditional move or at least give the
option of a conditional move in here so
we could say like alright if the N side
is different then we push the far side
otherwise we don't right and again I
think that has to happen first so yeah
this is this is gonna have to happen
first so I suppose this would probably
have to be an IFFT at that point right
so we'll see because the the see move
would be dependent like this would be
dependent I don't know if we would
really want that it's hard to say so if
the insight is different then we're
gonna push the other side to look at you
know first and then we'll push our side
and look at that now the problem that
there's another problem that I see here
which is that when we're looking at
these we would also want to the prop so
like another problem that I'm seeing
with this is this actually wants to be
done before you look at this particular
side of the plane so if we assume what
we're pushing on here is regions that
themselves are divided we don't need to
test those so this is a little bit
Squinkie as well right
like maybe the right way to think about
this is a little bit different so maybe
the right way to think about this is
like look we're gonna do a hit P here
and we're gonna like take a look and see
if we can reach this thing because we
know which side when we push something
on we have to kind of push on a
particular side right we have to say
like we're pushing on this side of this
of this thing right and then when we
actually go to test it at that point in
time is when we want to see whether or
not like we don't want to push on a side
then do another side get a closer hit
come back and actually test the other
side because we don't need to test the
other side anymore we've gotten a hit
that's closer so we would want this to
happen earlier right so this is kind of
more of a like this sort of thing and
this is probably more of this sort of
thing I'm guessing so in other words
like the only thing we're doing when we
test a partition is deciding which side
to push on first and when we actually go
to process one of the sides that's when
we would check to see whether we
actually could get there or not right so
you know
so we'd have we have to do this right we
need to do it like is this side is this
thing that I'm in right now is this
region reachable and if the region isn't
reachable it can't push anything else on
if the region is reachable it just
pushes both things on because the test
for whether or not the far side should
go on there is done later right so I
think this is getting slightly more
sensible so let's look at this one more
time
so I guess we just need to know are
either of these two things is the start
or the end are either of them on the
correct side of the plane right so
that's all we do and if they are on the
correct side of the plane we push both
if they're not on the correct side of
plane we bail I think that's it
Yeah right and this can just be like
that and I mean those could definitely
be conditional moves if we want them to
be but I'm not sure we do right yeah
so I think there's more we can do here
but I'm I'm guess I'm that's what I'm
zeroing in on I don't know if that's
really the smart way to do it and the
reason that I think it's not smart it's
like I said it just seems like it wastes
too much work to me I are just I'm not
sure furthermore there's another piece
of information there's a thing another
thing we can do here which is we can
just remember this value right so we can
compute this and store it right so we
can do like a thing that looks like this
where we are in the like start side bit
right and then when we get here we can
just do like right because this is the
Ray origin is classified relative to
this plane universally anytime we look
at this node of the KT tree whether
we're looking at the left side or the
right side of the node we know that the
origins answer is always the same no
matter how many hits we've processed
because unlike the ending point of the
Ray it doesn't change the Ray origin is
where it is the rate end point gets
closer and closer to the origin with
each successive hit so that one has to
be tested fresh right so once we produce
a start side classification we can just
remember it and then we just use it here
and we don't actually have to reproduce
it every time so I think the only thing
we have to actually classify is the end
side
so we have to load a why mask as a mask
and a plain value right we have to
produce where we think this thing
currently is and then we would just take
the two bits and look at them together
right so I think that's
so the only other thing I'm not sure
about here is how we actually want to do
the bit classification so out of these
things is going to come a sign right and
that sign you know we could just do a
multiply or you know we could have a
multiplication value that we push on the
stack that we use for that are something
but I'm not sure which one we want to do
in that sense but so we just need a way
of knowing for each plane that we push
on here we need to know which side we
were trying to do whether the far side
or not right
so I suppose what we could do is just
use an XOR to toggle this and maybe
that's the end of it
again just not sure so when we load one
of these up it's going to have which
side the start side was on and because
we know which one of these is the closed
side at this point in time we do know
how to classify that so we could pre
classify this correctly what we don't
know when we get here is which side this
represents in terms of end side you know
i'm santi so which side which way this
sign bit should be tested is not clear
we would need an additional piece of
information to know that right
so that's the tricky part
hmm and I'm also still not sure about
about the like testing the farside part
of things and the reason that I'm not
sure about that is just because I don't
actually know I don't actually know
whether that's a smart thing to do if
these were actually region science maybe
I need to make it so that actually
you're you actually have the data stored
in a side
you know maybe that's just easier in
other words what I could do is I could
just push sides on here and then the
sides themselves would actually just
have redundant information like oh you
know here's the plane that's it's going
the other way and so you just load that
up and it works you don't have to
remember that right but I don't know
and I suppose the other thing that I
didn't do here is we don't always need
to push both because if the if the Ray
is I mean I guess I'm pushing both
because you're gonna test the inside
either way so it's like look it'll get
cleaned up in the next pass but I don't
know if that's the smart way to do it or
not right and maybe that that's too
wasteful and I don't I don't really know
all right so let's look this one more
time we if we assume we can load up
these masks for what we're pushing on
here right if we assume that the sides
encode that they're gonna encode I guess
we could just have them in code yeah I
guess we could do that so I guess we
could just have the two sides and code
which one they're doing so I guess we
would just do something like this so
there's like a test mask in here right
we would figure out the inside we would
get the n sign out of here right or by
extracting this thing and the same is
true here
and then what we'd want to do is say all
right so whether or not you're on the
correct side is going to determine is
going to be determined by the test mask
which will tell us which one of these we
want to do so the n-side bit and the
start side bit these are going to be
acts or basically so it would just be
this sort of thing and the start side
bit comes from like the stack right
because that's something we actually you
know that's gets pushed on in here right
so yeah I think that's what we want and
I guess it may be the case that you
don't actually need to do a test mask on
the start side bit because that could
already have been handled in here so I
guess really it would look more like
this
so you'd have which inside you were on
and you need to test that and you mM
already produce the start side which you
know you're gonna want to go down this
one so you're saying like look always
process this and honestly that's not
even a start side bit that's just
basically saying like look whatever the
one whatever the like start side bit is
whatever the like always process right
you're gonna always process this value
and in fact since you're always gonna
process this value next it seems like
really this is where you should pull
something off of the stack anyway right
like the actual way that this should
work in theory would be that the entry
value would get pulled off the stack
here so this you would just assign like
this is the next person to process so
you just say like here it is right
whereas this one would actually pull it
off I want to take a look at that so
let's suppose that in here where we've
got this entry being pulled off the sack
I'm actually gonna make that be the if
zero
so I'm gonna take a look at how this
would work so in here what we would say
is look man we're actually gonna just
process this value so we have something
like our like you know her stack value
or whatever right
that's our weird thing that we're
recording it's like a packed magic thing
right and we are gonna do a while depth
is greater than zero right so we do want
to do that hmm and furthermore it's
really a do-while loop like the depth is
not zero at the start so we can just do
this right when we come through here we
would do this testing and we would say
like okay like you know in here we want
to do whenever we do our always process
Katie sides whatever the heck we're
doing in here this goes on the stack
this doesn't right so this thing that
we've got here is actually just the
Nucor stack value like we're gonna
process it right so we loop back through
and we process it and as we go we're
just always processing the close side
like we're just looping on the close
side and we may leave bread crumbs for
us to go back and process the other
sides but what we know is anytime we
pull something off the stack it is the
far side right so we don't need to do
this that like this testing actually is
only going to happen when we pull
something off the stack right so
basically if we actually need to grab
something off the stack so if we didn't
hit and we need to grab something off
the stack
we grabbed it off the stack here and
that's when we do this
right yeah
something like this I think
so yeah so normally we have something
we're going to be using the closed side
so we would be looping on the closed
side each time we get the curse stock
value out that's the one we're gonna do
if we come through here and we pull
something off the stack we'd actually
the while loop would actually happen
here right this is probably not a great
way to structure this like maybe this is
stupid
we'll see so in here we now just need to
search backwards on the stack for so you
know maybe you could just even do this
so either we got something here
otherwise we search backwards on the
stack until we find somebody until we
find something to process actually I
guess that would be here
and I don't love that right it just
starts to look too complicated yeah I
want to take a quick pause there because
I just realized something
so I do wonder should we change this
around so let's just take a quick look
at this here oops
did that end up being right I don't know
if it is that right there we go um so
one thing I want to take a look at here
is I want to see what the behavior of
this thing is how sensitive the current
routine is to where we put those loops
so we're getting like 6.5 through here
right 6.3 6.5
looks like 6.3 pretty regularly right
yeah so if I was to move this loop so
that this loop actually happened inside
what would that do so in other words in
here where we are going to do the push
so if we say look here's how we're doing
this we do a push on this where we where
we're going to push this on the stack if
instead of that we actually grab this
thing right and this case moves on to
the inside I'm just curious what that
does so basically like making that outer
loop just always happen and then there's
a branch inside here and this is the
only branch right and I assume it should
be the same but I'm I just want to know
like will that change the performance in
any reliably different way or won't it
right so what that would look like is
yeah in this current path here we would
do this
so this is the hit test right and we
would do the push in in here like this
right so in here we would basically say
like okay in fact we don't even need
that to be in the else container do we
oh I guess we do yeah so we would just
do like okay if should push and like
whatever the thing is that we're about
to push if that thing is a so this if
whoever we were about to push which is
like the box pack structure here if that
is a leaf container then we just process
it right up front you know I'm saying to
you like that and if it's not then
that's when we actually push it on if
that makes sense
so this would not be source index
anymore this would be like leaf index or
something
and this would be leaf index as well
and then this would not be box it would
just be leaf
this is a real pain in the butt like
yeah I know what's your point
like I'm trying to use those again but
apparently you're that's like not good
enough for you or something like okay
you know what
this is ridiculous I don't care that
that hides it
what error is that this is really
annoying
are you happy now
compiler there so I'm just curious what
that does with the runtime like I don't
know if that should have a nickname or
if it has a positive effect seems
consistently pretty positive right so
basically like processing something as
soon as you can seems pretty good right
like don't push it on the stack I just
wanted to know what that would look like
so not pushing something on the stack if
you don't have to is like a plus there
it would appear so yeah like I'm gonna
get rid of some of this stuff here so
I'm gonna assume this path is right I
don't need this anymore really so yeah
like iterating over the Leafs in a loop
inside when you actually go okay this
thing is a leaf container now so I'm not
going to actually push it on the stack
I'm going to do it right away it seems
like that works a little bit better it
could just because of code
reorganisation like it's hard to tell
without better profiling tools whether
that actually improved things or whether
it was just like oh the loop alignments
different now or you know things like
this but you know it's worth worth
noting so yeah
so yes so what I would say is I think
that means I do want to do what I was
saying before which is that inside the
alternate version what we would want to
do is we'd want to look here and say
like you know is this a leaf container
right and if it is we would do our box
testing here right so our box testing
would go inside here when we determined
that we've that we're going to process
somebody it would go in here and then if
it's not a leaf container then we would
do this nonsense right
[Music]
all right so yeah looking at this again
so still a little bit confusing and we
want to be able to work this routine a
little bit better what the heck
where'd that come from there we go it's
starting to sort of take shape but again
I'm not really sure it's in the right
zone at the moment it's looking still
looking pretty wonky I'm not sure I love
it
I'm glad we sort of randomly got a
little bit of a speed up there just from
like yeah just from like figuring out
the just from figuring out the fact that
we could loop on the internals there I
also want to do one let me do one of the
thing before I go any further than that
I also want to know what its estimated
timing is so when we do the profile run
here and we print this out since we know
what the repeat County is I also want to
produce the milliseconds here so so like
something like this take the total
seconds divided by the repeat count
multiplied by a thousand
something like this so we can sort of
see like what do we think the frame rate
of this thing would be you know how far
away are we from good is another thing
that just feels like we would might want
to know that so yeah like if we look at
what the expected millisecond says here
assuming that I did that correctly right
it's total seconds over the repeat count
so that's like how much time we took
over how many times we did this thing
that should give us the expected
milliseconds right now what's weird
about that is that looks way too fast so
like if we divide that by the thread
count which right now is like six let me
do this in double that seems totally
nuts
and possibly wrong although it could
just because of cache effects or
something
so I mean looking at that it would it
would suggest that like somehow we're
running at a speed that would be 60
frames a second already even before I go
try to fix this thing but that's not the
frame rate we're actually getting
although maybe it is so one thing I
don't know is because I I need a frame
counter and we should probably put one
in where if I don't do any of this so I
get rid of internal and slow if I don't
have anything else compiled in I'm not
sure how long it whether we actually hit
60 frames a second or not right so if I
actually load up remedy now and run
ourselves here's handmade hero I don't
actually know if we hit 60 frames a
second I don't think we will but I don't
really have a way to profile the frame
time outside of this so what I think we
need is a way to put the frame time up
here in a way that won't that is just
always available right like so also that
should not be possible in an internal
build case anyone was wondering we got
some work to do to remove that stuff
right I mean like you shouldn't be able
to pop any of that up in an internal
build so that's a little weird but so we
need some way of printing out what the
actual frame time is and I suppose
there's other ways that we can do that
too like if we want to we can probably
do use like insight or something and
just ask it to tell us what our frame
rate is right and that would be like a
unbiased external measurement right just
to see what happens so let me try it and
just see what happens if we run this
using the frame profiler
and just see what it thinks right so you
could see it thanks for getting like 21
milliseconds of frame which is not quite
good enough and the weird thing about
that that's a little hard to understand
is why we're getting such different
numbers from our capture as from here
you know what I mean and part of that
could be I don't know like to what
extent the GPU is messing with us right
that's that's a kind of a question I
don't actually know
but see here
hello
does not seem that I can actually toggle
to insight unfortunately there we go
good enough alright so in here looking
at insight just to see what the actual
status is like
I'm not sure what I'm looking at here
why is this not shown I want I want to
see the actual frame profile which this
should be but that doesn't look right
here I'm saying
because if it's it should be more than
nine milliseconds right I mean at the
very least it should show me like us
spending time as well but doesn't appear
to at the moment show me more please
that is the range profiler so all I
really wanted to know is to what extent
are the graphics causing us issues let
me just do one of the thing because this
is easier than trying to figure out if
Nvidia is giving us bogus information or
not this is always the way with modern
computers is you're just kind of
swimming in a sea of probably wrong
information trying to figure out which
one of it is right so if we just open a
like low-res window right like you know
like that so it's just super low res to
take some of the heat off the graphics
card you know I'm saying how fast are we
then you know what I mean and I don't
know and so that would be a good thing
to ask in video as well if we're the
same speed then we know that it's really
doesn't matter like hopefully which is
presumably the case but we haven't
optimized our rendering at all for the
graphics cards so it's possible that
we've also got cruft in there right and
I don't know okay so at least in theory
and who knows but at least in theory we
are it's us who's taking the time right
and you know at least as far as I can
tell that seems to be the case because
that's dropping the resolution
dramatically and I'm not seeing a
difference in frame right there so we it
you know at least as far as I can tell
it's not that now I don't actually know
because the transfer time like how long
it takes to get things down to the
graphics card could be an issue for us
right now so don't actually know that
that's
I can't say for sure but at least I know
that like the pixel shader isn't a
problem for us right
not on this card anyway alright so and I
guess there's one other thing I can do
too which is in the lighting system I
could just not compute it right
so here I could do this and that would
just turn the lighting off the actual
expensive part and so here is us you
know walking around in the dark right
and let's take a look at what that is
that should be a lot of frames per
second right
so that's locked 60 right so good
because nothing else is happening there
meaning we are still running the full
render pass we're just renting it with
garbage lighting so at least in theory
that should mean that if we get the
lighting running fast enough we would be
60 frames a second right and we're not
blocked on anything else I mean we still
would want to fix a bunch of other
things but you know so alright so that
seems fine and yeah I mean that seems
totally fine yeah so I think we're good
there and and let's do one last test if
I go to the Ray caster and you can see
us doing a red cast here where we do the
two the two of these if we so rate
bundle and I so we just do one pass over
the sphere each time so if I turn back
on the tiles for example which we had
turned off so there's like a there's
like a checkerboard pattern right that
you can imply that you can apply here so
in in full cam here so in here if we
want to we can turn back on the
checkerboard which would reduce the
number and that should do 60 frames a
second as well
oops
can just try to validate the fact that
nothing weird is going on here so if we
do the checkerboard rendering the
checkerboard lighting we can hit 60
frames a second sometimes but not always
and it looks like it's whether or not
we're moving which may have something to
do with how we're updating the lighting
grid or worse where we are like that one
you can see is much worse right not 100%
sure why probably because there's more
geometry in here
I would guess but it's clear we can hit
60 right so it's clear we can hit 60 the
question is just getting there without
having to do those shenanigans all right
okay all right so that's all good
which brings us back to trying to
structure a loop for a better KD
processing which is a little bit of a
brain bender but let's let's keep at it
so oops so let's take a look at raycast
here again there we go
so in raycast trying to work backwards
we know we're gonna have something that
looks like this right in here
so we know don't need a second for loop
so we know we're going to use this leaf
index loop here and we're going to use
this to go over our actual a a B B's to
produce our Rea collision tests here
[Music]
so I think working backwards from there
assuming it's not a leaf container we
know we have to keep walking down the
close side of the tree and just all
we're doing is making a stack of our far
side of the tree right so basically like
whatever the current stack value is
going to be like the closed side index
right so whatever whatever we're gonna
do on the next loop is just we're just
gonna keep walking down that side of the
tree and we're just gonna leave a stack
around that's the that's the far side
right so then all we need to do is say
well when we don't when we say like oh
whoops
like that's not actually a thing right
that we're doing when we say look this
thing doesn't need to be processed the
thing we're on does not need to be
processed then what we need to do is pop
the stack at that point right so we just
want to do a walking back up the stack
so while the depth is greater than zero
we just want to keep doing like a depth
you know - - right we want to do like a
cur stack value thing and we want to
like figure out whether this thing is
actually working you know I'm saying
like figure out whether we actually can
use it or not
so if the n-side bit like if if it can
be used we break right
[Music]
so I think that's how that would work
it's still not quite right so when we
are we need to decide like what the
primary like you can you can rearrange
this loop in so many different ways
because the things that have to happen
can be placed in any number of locations
right when we're actually gonna process
one of these things what we're really
doing here is just determining which
side we're gonna process right and so
maybe what you would say is can we make
this primal and I don't know if we can
so let's suppose we made start side
primal and then we said okay we're gonna
process the close side right so we then
say look if the close side is a leaf so
we say yeah classify which side were on
if the close side is a leaf you just
process it right and that's fine
if it's not right then you then that's
your new then that's your nuker stack
value right
yeah yeah all right I think we're
getting a little closer here so if the
closed sign is a leaf container then you
do it if
of course the problem is then you're
never gonna process far aside leave
containers so no that would not work
right so if you're actually doing closed
site and farce idea that wouldn't work
at all
[Music]
I'm not really sure how to build this
loop so this is complicated enough that
it seems like what I need to actually do
if I want to do it right is I'm going to
have to basically do each individual
thing write it out completely so here's
what I do in every single case and then
literally just compact those cases I
think that's the only way I can really
do it I just can't think of another way
to do it you know i'm santi cuz i've
tried like you know being slick about it
and it I can't seem to get it together
right it doesn't seem to work and so I
feel like yeah like nothing I'm gonna do
there is actually gonna help me right I
don't know how we got into this state
exactly
now that goes there I think that goes
there so I yeah I think I'm gonna have
to I think I'm gonna have to do
something something simple I mean
something simpler at first but much more
verbose and then try to compress it down
into place because so I have several
problems right that I have to solve so
for every split plane where we have
something that looks like this we've got
the following cases so case the first
case is this right so here's like a and
B so and you know what let me do this a
little bit differently let's do it like
this a be case one right then I've got
case two a and B right
then I've got case three which is a and
B oops
then I've got case four right and the
nasty thing about this is there's
actually two cases like there's case
like the two and four actually give rise
to five and six which is to say that
whether or not you've traversed this or
not right so this moves backwards over
time and you may end up like another way
to say it is there's a five case which
is that you were to but then you become
one and here you were four but you
become three right and the reason for
that again is that if I have this case
and so I think it's a case to where I
process a and B when I go to process a I
may find that my clothes hit was like
here and then I know now no longer need
to process B even though when I looked
at a I did right and so that's why I say
that that kind of needs to be a deferred
thing so the stack needs to push beyond
there so when we go down what we're
effectively doing is figuring out which
side were on is it a or b and pushing
the other side onto our stack when we
then go to load the thing off the stack
then that's when we need to
when we load something out the sack
that's when we then need to test it
right and that's why I was trying to
zero in on something where we walk up
the stack here right and so when we're
walking up the stack here we're looking
for one that we can then start to
descend again right does that make sense
so it would seem like this needs to be
you know I don't know
it's this sort of thing where we say
like look if this thing is a leaf
container and you know there's another
way we could do this we could just make
this be like look everything has some
boxes so there's just a box count right
and this you know it's like that right
so everything has a box leaf count in it
and we loop over the leaves doing those
as a thing and a lot of them just have
zero because they're internal right
there they're actual just nodes that
classify things so then we have to do
like okay after we process anything that
actually was Leafs leaf like in here
then we have to go through and this
determined who's getting processed and
who's not getting processed right so
although you know what maybe this may be
now I think about it I guess we don't
really need to do that because we need
to know the result of that if anyway so
we're gonna be stuck doing two ifs here
whether we like it or not right which is
unfortunate now what we can do is we
can't help it out a little bit here by
putting this branch by making a little
bit less of a branch here because we
know that we're always gonna have some
children otherwise we wouldn't have
continued down here so what we can do is
we can make this be a do-while loop so
that we only have the branch at the end
right rather than the branch the
beginning as well so we can do this if
we want to right so that there's no
branch at the beginning because you know
once once you hit this branch we don't
need to do a second branch because we
know that this thing should always have
children otherwise it wouldn't have been
a leaf node right if it doesn't have any
Leafs children then it wouldn't have had
its bit set right so so when we do this
branch and we know like look is the
close is the is this a leaf container
then after we figure out whether it's a
leaf container we need to do this
nonsense right
try to line this up here so we check to
see if it's a leaf container if it's not
a leaf container then we go into the
else clause where we try to do the
classification once we figure out what
the classification is we push the wrong
side like the side we're not gonna do
right now right we pushed that out of
the stack yeah man this is brutal we
push the wrong side on the stack then we
process the correct side right because
we know this is now a splitting region
so if it's a splitting region then you
know as opposed to another region so
then we do this we then say all right we
push the sides on correctly and off we
go
right
but wait so what's the case where we
actually don't descend so the case where
we actually don't descend is oh is
actually the leaf case interesting so I
think that's correct right so if we're
on a leaf we do we do that work and then
we walk the stack to find the next
person we can start treating as a region
again right so the first time we find
someone who actually passes that test
and then if if other you know if it's
not a leaf container then we actually
just do the classification on it and we
split it right
so I think that would be roughly the way
to do this I mean I don't see a lot else
in terms of yeah I mean it seems like it
I don't know right in other words you
check to see if this is a leaf container
assuming it's a leaf container you do
everything in the leaf container and
then you hunt up the stack to see who
the last you know what's the last thing
on there that you need to check to do
right
[Music]
seems plausible you then just see like
yeah is this thing because we know all
the things on the stack were things that
were far sides we just see whether or
not the far side thing that you're
grabbing out is is actually reachable if
it is you stop right and you do the work
so right if this is reachable you stop
assuming that you weren't a leaf node
all you do is you classify and descend
leaving behind you like breadcrumbs all
of the things you didn't process so they
can be checked later by this side of the
routine if I'm understanding that
correctly and not totally screwing it up
in my head that actually does work out
to be pretty simple at the end of the
day right and there's no dependent
pushes so you push always so if you
didn't do a leaf process
you always push and all you're doing is
determining which one you're pushing
versus which one you're using
so I don't know that seems really
straightforward after I've kind of gone
through it more carefully but is it
right it's a good question
so you always need to load those and I
want to say you don't need this test
mask so what I think is you would
basically say all right I'm going to
select which one of these I do using the
mask which is basically just telling me
which which dimension I'm picking I
adjust using the plain D I then know
looking at the sine which side I'm on am
I on the positive side or the negative
side so I know that we have an a mask
extract in here somewhere and it's just
any true I think are all true or
something like this any true so here
we've got like a moove mask right and
the move mask is you know it's a little
bit deceptive so what I want to do is
basically say like to extract like the
sign and the move mask will do that
because I believe it always extracts the
high bit which happens to be the sign
bit so I can use this here so because
this is classifying the origin I know
that I only need to know just that one
move mask this could actually be done
just entirely in float so it's really
all SS instructions not PS instructions
but yeah
so if I just do like sign masks or
something here or like sign of the I
mean I really only need the sign of the
base value so you know it's like so if I
take start sign and I do a move mask on
it and I just say like look I want to do
an end
I want the sign bit so it's gonna be
like you know that on on the
floating-point value but I believe this
goes by bytes so it just be the fourth
bit presumably so that be the one bit so
really I mean this right right that's
zero bit the 1 bit 2 bit the 3 bit I
want to say it be that and since I
really guess I want to do it where I
just shifted this down by three instead
we'll double check all this in the docs
but I just want to extract just the sign
bit from the first one right so I is I
is tracked that and I just say hey yeah
so push one keep one right is all I need
you to do I need you to push one and
keep one and then when I need to do my
other loop which is the opposite way
around this one is looking whether the
n-side gets in there or not we know the
start side is not on the same side as
this so we just need to know whether the
N side makes it there or not right is
the way this would work so the exact
same code
would work the only difference is we
need in we need to do an extract on
everybody and then we're just gonna test
for truth right so in here we would just
say okay the start side or the inside
bit here is a mob mask and we just want
to end it with whether or not any of
these would be the case so after the
move mask happens we just look at the
sign bits of anybody so those sign bits
are gonna be like the in hex each one of
these is four so the high bit on each of
these is what we would want assuming
that that actually is what that is I
don't actually know if that's true so
we'll have to go look at that but this
basically means that somebody needs to
one of the Rays can reach it of the four
rays we have right so at that point the
only thing we need to do is actually be
able to load this crap out of the value
we have which is this right so what are
the things we actually need to know well
the things we actually need to know
there are are literally just these
values so we need to know a Y mask a Z
mask a plain D and you know if you look
at what this actually entails it's
really basic right so I don't know what
the fastest way is gonna be to do this
but it's going to be pretty
straightforward because we can pack
literally everything into a you 64 I
would think
hmm-hmm-hmm so if we did something like
this we actually don't even need that
and this could be six these could be
16-bit values that we push on here yeah
anyway so I don't know I mean in theory
this actually works how good do I think
it is I don't know but in theory this
would actually work and this is trivial
like this is like really very little
code this does one check but has to do
two loops because it has to do the stack
walk and that seems bad potentially
but I'm not sure what else you would do
so I mean I think this is what it looks
like so I'm going to leave that off for
now
and that's what we'll work on next week
I guess we'll go to brief QA so yet now
when I'm looking at it it's getting
better right like it's not as bad as I
thought it was first if this is actually
the right thing I do feel like this part
of things this part seems like it's
probably sort of wrong maybe and the
reason I say that is again it's just
it's not using all the lanes it should
be and it's not so I don't know we'll
see
anyway we'll go ahead and do QA little
Q&amp;A here but I'm okay with it I'm okay
with that
and you know
oh man in cybot it's about wins the QA
already
is this PHP no it's it's C PHP like many
languages borrowed C's structure so it
looks PHP does look like C to a certain
extent is there a good way to get
intuitions about bit mass etc or is it
just practice
I mean bit maths are actually pretty
simple it's usually more the fact that
you write them in hexadecimal often
times that makes it more complicated I
mean there's just there's just 32 or 64
lanes and they're either said are not
set so you're just thinking of these
little like lanes that come in and you
know what what do you want to happen
with the individual bits and moving them
around it's not that bad right the only
thing that I've seen here is for move
masks I just always have to refresh my
memory to what it moves because there's
a lot of ways they could have chosen to
do that and I think they chose the smart
way but if you take a look here
so like the move mask PS so that's that
if you do the move mask PS value here
you can see what it says it says the
most significant bit of the
corresponding pax Ingrid is a floating
point element in a so I just didn't know
which one it's doing so let's see what
does it actually say okay so actually
it's not even as bad as I thought it was
it's it's actually even easier than I
thought it was so actually all we have
to do is this it's actually just moving
just the high bit of of the four values
so it's literally just this
right so I just couldn't remember what
what move masks I had available because
if you think about what this is doing
you have a hundred and twenty eight bits
that's the register you're actually
talking about so the actual value inside
the CPU is 128 bits we're using that to
compute four separate floating-point
numbers so 32 bits 32 bits 32 bits 32
bits right 4 times 32 is 128 and I want
to know the sign of each of those Story
2 bit values well the sign bit of a
floating point value is the highest bit
it's bit 31 right or bit 32 if they're
starting with 1 so so mean bit 0 2 bit
31 it's the last bit it's bit 31 so I
didn't know what move mask did because
there's different ones so I remembered
this one I was like well move mask epi8
that moves the high bit of each byte
right so you can see this one so if if
that was the move mask and I couldn't
remember what it did but if that was the
move mask then I need to go four bits in
to get the sign bit but because I
actually have a move masked PS in this
instruction set I am just only getting
the sign bits so I just have a four bit
value where each bit is the sign bit so
it's actually much more useful right
do you write sheet or could often for
work not often no I try to keep GPU
programming to a minimum minimum because
it's always really janky like GPU
programming just sucks
I mean GPUs suck they're not I don't
like them like I wish we didn't have to
have them I wish we just had CPUs that
were fast and or just people didn't have
GPUs so you didn't have to use them you
could just write software Enders and be
done with it
you know do some eyes feel the urge to
make handmade here a truly 3d um I mean
it's it's a lot easier to be all 3d in
the coat so the code for doing all 3d
and the runtime is way easier than two
and a half day like way easier so that
part is nice but the problem is your
asset pipeline becomes a massive
nightmare so as soon as you go 3d you
10x the work of your asset pipeline just
massively massively you have to have
like a bone system and animation system
and like packing that down and fitting
it from the art tools and you got to
have texture mapping and UV coordinate
assignment and all this stuff so your
runtime gets a lot easier than having to
deal with a 2.5 D stuff but your asset
pipeline becomes a massive massive
nightmare
not to mention now you have to have 3d
artists instead of 2d artists and they
have to do stuff and you have to decide
how you're building those assets or
they're gonna be high res they can
protect on below res there's gonna build
low res directly or you're gonna use
bump Maps or normal Maps displacement
Maps blah blah blah blah blah right and
if you use a commercial engine so I'm
saying your asset pipeline becomes
Unreal Engine 4
exactly if you go look at how much cruft
there is in something like Unreal Engine
or unity or that stuff the actual
renderer part of the 3d is not where all
the
cruft is it's the huge giant thing that
has to sit there to get stuff into it
right and so it's always it's always a
trade-off where you're like look if you
can get away with 2d yeah it's a little
more annoying because you got to do
these tricks at runtime to figure out
how you're gonna actually render
something attractive when you don't have
the data you need
but that expense is small compared to
the expense you will pay in the pipeline
if you decide to go full 3d it's the pie
it's the pipeline that kills you on 3d
not the renderer the renderer is easy I
mean it's not easy especially you've
never done one before but it's not
anywhere close to as hard as the
pipeline in terms of sheer like you know
man out like the time is gonna take you
to build the thing you're gonna spend
way more time dealing with your asset
pipeline than you ever are gonna deal
with your renderer I'm a bit behind the
FA's do you ever trace secondary rays
that bounce off and ran directions it
might lead to array packets nope
so the way we get around that because we
do have fully infinite bounce lighting
like we don't have any I mean it's not
infinite bounce it's 100 bounce lighting
or something like that and I know you
want to classify it but the way we get
around that is we actually just convict
so we shoot out Ray's from our sample
point and we gather the light and store
it for next frame so we're like a bucket
brigade right so we we do the secondary
bounces for the previous frame that were
caused for the previous frame on the
frame after right so it's basically like
just over time and so the result is we
get a little bit of lag in the secondary
bounce tertiary about like the more
bounces the more lag but we never get
deep ray decoherence because of that
that makes sense
can't sleep uh supposed to leaven you
something like OB 1 1 1 1
yeah it can so yeah I never do but they
introduced a bunch of stuff here it is
so originally see only had these decimal
octal and hex this one it looks like it
says C pus US 14 so it's actually not
suicidal Evan but looks like cos was 14
so if you want to rely on the fact that
you have a modern compiler you can use
this and then it's just like you know a
1 101 100 1 1 1 right I don't do that
because I try to avoid using things in
the C++ spec especially new things
because deceive us like is a disaster
and I want to be able to write my own
compiler for my code and not have to
worry about 8 billion stupid C++ spec
things that are useless anyway so I just
try to stick with basically C and I find
that operator overloading is really
important so I use it just to make the
code legible in math but I generally
just don't start using things that are
adding entire like Lex or things or
whatever and not that this is heart like
this is not hard to add to your lecturer
it's super simple but it's just like I
don't want to like necessarily Wed
myself to their notation or any of that
stuff so I'm just like look C is fine I
don't see bus plus is just a waste of
everyone's time doesn't save you time
it's just a bunch of crap you can learn
and then your makes your code worse
right so I just say like no forget about
it
C is fine and it keeps the code simple
so that when you want to go move off to
some other language which you will want
to do because C++ is garbage you know
it's easier to port that code because
you're not using all this weird C++
nonsense
you know I am GUI situation how do you
create a unique ID for a UI control what
I don't get is if you draw everything
immediately if some condition changes
both ID also change um so if you want to
use IDs in any API it doesn't matter
whether it's a.m. or not the rule is
just you need some way of assigning IDs
and the point is that the app itself is
the thing that should assign the IDS it
doesn't matter how you assign them if
you want to assign them using allocation
which makes your thing basically
retained mode GUI you certainly can just
don't put that in the library let it
pass the ID forward usually you can
though because usually whatever the
logic is that you use to draw the
control it's got to go do something like
modify a particular value or something
that has a unique ID already and you can
just use that so usually it's a win
right I say I mean he wrote gone as
planned or did you not have any
expectations or scope when you set off
on the journey I didn't really have an
annotation or scope but I was gonna be
only 2d originally so the main thing we
did differently was that it's got a full
3d render with lighting which is a
pretty big ad but that's the main thing
we did differently I guess how many
percent is handmade here are done I
don't know
the engines almost finished we basically
just have some cleanup to do after the
lighting is done but the engines
basically finished so it's really just
the gameplay which will be sort of
open-ended like how much gameplay we
want to pack in this thing I don't know
I'm not really a gameplay person it's
I'm not a designer so it's not my thing
so I don't have any concrete like it has
to be this way stuff so we'll see it's
unclear
would you consider removing handmade
here too ji when it releases probably
wouldn't necessarily move it to ji if I
was gonna do J I'd probably want to just
try something in it first like I
probably do something new in it first
right like just a small thing just to
see
alright let's go ahead and wrap it up
all right think you're ready for joining
me for this sort of handmade hero sort
of pleasure coating with you as always
if you would like to follow along with a
series at home you can always peer to
the game it comes with a source code so
you can do your own experiments I
sketched out what that Katie tree think
needs to look like so over this next
week until I'm back next week and to
work on it I that might be a good thing
to play with for those of you looking
for a challenge try to do your own Katie
tree do some timings on it see if it's
better does it actually improve our
performance or doesn't it I think that'd
be a great thing to practice on right so
give that a shot for those of you are
interested we're also doing a
Kickstarter right now at Molly rocket
for our comic we're doing a print run of
it it's gonna be pretty cool so if you
want to check that out the banners at
the top the handmade hero art page as
well so you just click on that it's got
all the information there that's it for
today I'll be back here next week when
I'll take a look at implementing that KD
tree stuff as the way that we sort of
worked it out today and we'll go from
there I will probably now switch over to
my streaming machine to see if John is
streaming he's been streaming a lot
lately and we will go dump everyone into
his into his stream if if he is on again
which I don't know if he is so I'm gonna
go check and see if he is a rage channel
naysayer 88 unfortunately not so I guess
we won't be so that's it for today then
you'll have to find your own stream to
go to now so until next time a fun
program run and I'll see you on the
Internet pinkies everybody