alright hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the show Rico to complete
game live on twitch no engines no
libraries we try to take a look at the
entire pipeline here so we can learn
about every last little detail that goes
into game development no nook and cranny
unexplored really sometimes we explore
them to great detail in fact and you're
like no don't go any further into that
nook and or cranny but there we go
anyway and that's just the nature of the
show
now yesterday we started something where
we wanted to sort of do this dynamic
lead generated ground texturing that we
were working on and I would like to get
back to that but before I do I'll just
point out that anyone who pre-ordered
the game on handmade org who wants to
follow along should have gotten a link
in their email and that link will have
the source code in it and you want to
unpack day 84 is source code to match
where I am today because we're here on
day 85 I know it's a little confusing
cuz we missed a couple days last week
due to the fact that I was away so now
that the fives don't line up with weeks
anymore I don't know how we will have to
like skip a few days some other time to
like get it back up to alignment but for
now it's all crazy
anyway anyway so what we did is we made
a we made a little repeating ground
texture thing here which we could sort
of generate well it's not really
repeating sorry it's non repeating
ground texture that can kind of just
generate ground that goes for as long as
you want and so what we did is we just
generated one buffers worth and you can
see it getting displayed behind the sort
of the the trees here that I'm moving
around in and what we need to do now
where we stopped yesterday is we need to
figure out a good way to make it so that
as we scroll off to where there isn't
any more of this buffer we can start to
you know we can generate what would have
been in the next part of the buffer so
that as we walk further through the
world we just are constantly getting a
nice non-repeating ground texture built
out of those splats that we
you know that we were kind of using to
make them so you know I've thought about
this a little bit just just right before
the stream I was thinking about it what
we had been working on there's something
that I thought of that's actually I feel
like a slightly smarter way to do things
that you know we haven't actually done
this part yet but instead of doing it
the way that I'd suggested we were gonna
do it I was thinking we could do it in a
slightly smarter way just one of those
things you don't necessarily think of
right off the bat because you know hey
it's it's on stream and and well
sometimes it gets crazy in here but the
thing that I was thinking was what I
said before was Oh we'll have like you
know we'll have this back buffer and
we'll draw the ground texture into it
and so like the screen is here you know
and here's the buffer right and as you
move around it when you get to the edge
will like blit what's on the screen like
backwards to make room for new stuff and
we'll move the screen backwards as well
but then I realize that's actually kind
of dumb and the reason that that's kind
of dumb is because we're already
spending the bandwidth to copy this
buffer onto the screen anyway right it's
already got a scroll around and since
that's happening what I was thinking is
why don't we just make the buffer be a
set of tiles anyway right so we just
break it up into tiles you know like I
don't know how big they are maybe
they're you know 256 by 256 or something
right
just tiles and then what we'll do is
we've lit the tiles you know on to the
screen into the location they're
supposed to go and that way we never
have to do any blitz here all we do is
reallocate tiles to be locations on the
screen right that's it like we don't do
anything else it just works so there's
no bleeding there's no management of it
it's literally just some array of tiles
and we can say how many we want so let's
say you know we've got a 256 by 256
tiles right and we want to have
you know I don't know how many of them
let's say we want to have 64 of them or
something like this or I'm not sure how
many we would actually need at our
target resolution
you know if we're 1920 by 1080 right
then you can imagine like if we if we
let Emacs quick calc calc for us if we
want to say 1920 divided by 256 right
that's 7.5 in this direction and same
thing for 1080 divided by 256 that would
be 4.2 right so we're talking like
something like 8 times 5 or 32 to cover
the screen and so if we wanted you know
to cover the screen and then some we'd
be talking about you know something
substantially more than 32 so yeah so
maybe we do 64 or something like that
right so what I was thinking is why
don't we just make an array of these and
then we just have for each one of them
where it is in world space then when we
move the screen around we just look to
see if any of them are you know we
basically like march through all of the
tiles that we think we want on the
screen in you know and and the end sort
of the apron around the screen and we
say make sure that these are in our set
of 64 and whenever it needs to fill a
new one that it doesn't have in that set
it'll just evict whatever the least
recently used one that we had was and
replace it with a new one right and that
seems a lot more sane to me because then
there's no bleeding ever right you're
only doing the copy to the screen which
we had to do anyway and that just seems
like a much better idea so I think this
is what I'm going to implement instead
of the thing I said I was going to
implement and since we haven't done any
of it yet we don't really we didn't
waste any time so it just seems like a
smarter thing to do and so that's the
thing that I am gonna do so really the
only thing that needs to change here is
let's let's go ahead and take a look at
this here the only thing that needs to
change here is you know this we've got
this sort of ground buffer that's
sitting here and this ground buffer P
really all I'm talking about is let's
just make an array of these right and I
think you know now it's probably a good
time to introduce that transient arena
because if anything what if there was
ever anything that was properly
transient meaning something that can be
recomputed from scratch and does not
need to be saved in any way
it's these ground buffers right because
these ground buffers are completely
generative from information that we have
were saying that we're saying that's the
rule for how they're even created and so
I think I want to introduce that that
sort of transient arena at this point so
I'm gonna I'm just gonna call that the
transient arena right and we're gonna go
ahead and initialize that like we were
initializing the World Arena and these
guys are gonna come out of that right so
we're gonna have some some notion of
these here we're going to have struct
ground buffer or you know we could make
this fairly general to I guess we don't
really have to call it ground buffer but
I'll call it ground buffer for now and
we'll see if we ever use it for anything
else
ground buffer brown buffers and then
we'll also have a ground buffer count so
and in here the ground buffers will just
be again positions in bitmaps that's it
and I don't think we necessarily need
anything else for them can't really
think of anything else for them at least
not offhand so yeah so let's go ahead
and expand that that notion of the world
arena here and again if you'll remember
what we set up our game to have is we
set up our game to have two sort of
memory areas right one memory area was
for permanent storage I said and what
that is is something that needs to be
preserved from frame to frame then the
other area that I had allocated is one
that we haven't used yet
and what I wanted to do with that one is
for stuff that we don't really care what
happens to it
so if it does get preserved from frame
to frame maybe that's good maybe that
saves us work but if it doesn't then no
big deal and so for example if we were
going to reload a game or you know sleep
like you know a game like that shut down
temporarily we wanted to like come back
to life or something the stuff in the
transient arena could literally just not
be stored at all it's something that we
if we we could trade time basically CPU
time to regenerate it right it's not
something that's good that's got to be
saved and so you know we haven't really
seen much that we need to do with that
yet but this is kind of a good first
thing so you know let's go ahead and and
actually start talking about about that
so we've got our transient storage size
and there's nothing in there so I'm
gonna make the transient arena basically
use that whole transient storage size
and I'm gonna go ahead and and do
transient storage there so so I'm gonna
initialize this other arena and now we
have a second place that stuff can come
out of essentially right we don't really
have any other stuff that we want a
partition yet in our in our world stuff
so you know we'll probably get to that a
little later on but for our transient
arena now we'll just have it be the
whole thing and we'll start by by
allocating some space out of that for
these ground buffers so when we come out
here to the ground buffer I want to
again you'll notice we set ourselves up
for success by having to make empty
bitmap take which arena it was going to
use so now I can ask for it to use that
transient arena and similarly I can go
ahead and make the whole array exist in
there as well so I don't know how many
ground buffers we want to have I suppose
that might be something that's based on
how much memory we actually have so it
might be the different profiles of the
game have different numbers of these
ground buffers because obviously storing
more ground buffers means we have to
recompute them potentially less often
but let's just say for now we're gonna
store 128 of
quick caplets see if we want to do 128
256 by 256 textures at four bytes per
pixel how big is that going to be let's
see that is a 32 megabyte backing store
right which seems totally reasonable on
modern machines 32 megabytes of the
backing store is not very many and that
seems like a reasonable cache for our
stuff so I don't feel like that's asking
too much we can even go hog-wild here
and do 256
I don't know if that I mean that could
just be crazy so maybe you know cut it
down a little we'll see those are
numbers that are easy to - no no real
nothing's really based on them so it's
fine anyway so if we go in here and say
all right we've got we're gonna make
this this empty bitmap we need to first
we need to make 128 of them but first
what we need to do is actually make
space for the array right so we need to
make space for the ground buffer array
like so ground buffers and that's going
to be one of these let's see where do we
have our push thing I don't remember how
we wrote it to push array there it is so
we're going to do push array out of the
transient arena and we want to push a
like this many of this struct here that
we've defined the ground buffer struck
like so and then we're going to loop
through them and allocate empty buffers
for them right and I guess for now we
won't even draw that ground chunk yet
that that we're going to deal with that
a little bit later on so here we go
ground buffer index equals zero ground
buffer index is less than that count and
then for each of those for each of those
we are going to grab out which ground
before it is so this is the ground
buffer game state ground buffers like so
we are going to get the enth one of them
and then we're going to
allocate its bitmap and we're going to
set its P presumably to know do we have
a no world position I don't know if we
do or not what exactly I thought we did
because I thought we had some stuff that
wanted no world positions but I could be
wrong about that no position that's what
we wanted so we we basically I want to
say that you know these these ground
chunks aren't initialized yet they have
nothing in their bitmaps their bitmaps
are empty so you know they're ready to
be composited anyway now make empty
bitmap is probably a little bit
overzealous in this case too because if
we look here it's it's calling zero size
and so what I might do is I might say
you know clear to zero is the thing that
you can do and it's going to do it by
default but in this case we don't
actually care so there's really no need
to do that so what I'll probably do is
say alright you know what don't clear it
because we are gonna clear it later
there's you know we gotta clear these
every time we update them so just don't
bother doing that and also what I might
what I might also say is let's go ahead
and oh hello why are you not marked
internal mister mister function call
there we go
so what I might do also is say that okay
you know if you pass a loaded bitmap to
this thing it'll clear it for you so
that we can have that be a little bit
more straightforward right so this is
just gonna be a clear bitmap bitmap like
so and and that's going to take that
bitmaps memory and and clear it I guess
we should double check to make sure that
it actually has some memory first but
yeah so the total bitmap size is that
and that'll clear it so okay so when we
do this make empty bitmap we want to be
able to set a ground buffer width and
height that has nothing to do with this
stuff that we computed before this turns
out to really not be necessary for doing
the tiled based architecture
which is kind of nice it gets us out of
this estimation process so that's
actually kind of great we can just say
you know we don't care about that at all
and so what we can do here is just say
all right we want a composite at a
certain level and so whatever that level
compositing is that's what we're going
to use so we're gonna do ground buffer
width and ground buffer height are gonna
be out here they're gonna be things that
we spec out and we're saying 256 by two
six for now but again that's something
we could tune later right so there we go
and then we're going to to use those
anytime that we are talking about these
things right so that should be
relatively correct for most of it oh hi
there spelling error that's no good it's
get that mouse out of the way
and that is not bitmap that is results
ground buffer okay so here's where we're
actually drawing them so now we have to
actually start thinking about this a
little bit again this is we've we've the
drawing is gonna be really pretty basic
it's really the compositing that's gonna
be the interesting part
well actually it's probably not even the
compositing to interpret it's going to
be that determining what to recreate and
when but yeah so let's go through here
and say all right for each one of the
ground buffers that we have right we're
gonna be the exact same loop here that
we were doing before this is where we're
all counting on John below to save us
and actually finally make C have good
stuff that allows you to loop through
things without typing this every darn
time and without having to go down the
deep dark rabbit hole of C++ guaranteed
to let you almost loop through the
things you want to loop through but then
frustrate you at the very last minute
anyway yeah so all we're doing is we're
basically going through exactly these
these same things here that we were
going through and then what we're going
to do is is draw the it in exactly the
same way right we're going to use that
that ground buffer that position exactly
how we were using it before
we have a little bit of a question here
and I don't think there's necessarily
right answer to this question one way or
the other but that is what exactly is
the you know how is this aligned so I've
got a bitmap it's got a width and height
how is that aligned around the ground
buffers position in world you know in
the world is it is P the center of that
bitmap is P the upper left corner of
that bitmap you know that's that's
mostly what we're talking about here I'm
going to say that this is the center of
the bitmap and the reason I say that is
because it's not entirely out of the
question that we will just let these
things
Splatt out so that they won't actually
be 256 by 256 clipped rectangles they'll
actually have some like overhang if that
makes sense this is kind of one of those
things that it's hard to say what the
right answer is to one way or the other
so I'm not sure what we want to do with
that but for now I'm just gonna say it's
the center and we'll cross that bridge
we come to it if we need to change that
so assuming that it is the center then
what we need to do here is first again
we need to do let's start with that
subtraction what we're doing here is
saying okay tell us where the ground
buffer is this particular ground buffer
tell us where that is relative to where
the camera is right because that tells
us the offset from the center of the
screen right so from there again we we
now know that okay this is the center of
the screen right this is the screen
Center X and we then want to move well
this is kind of like a little bit stuck
in there I could put this in here a
little bit better like so
there we go so what we want to do right
is we want to take the center of the
screen in X&amp;Y right we want to move by
whatever that Delta tells us to do and
again unfortunately we have to write and
there's so many I guess we could do that
right here there we go we want to first
change it from meters to pixels because
we're drawing in pixels here right again
this is something that the render will
do for us eventually once we actually
have one we then want to say from the
screen Center we got to move by whatever
that Delta is in pixels and we have to
move the negative and why because
remember why in our world goes up
towards the top of the screen but why in
our screen space goes down kind of an
annoying thing again this is stuff that
the render coordinate system will take
care of us once we move this stuff into
a real render it's not really that big
of a deal
it seems annoying at the moment but it's
really not that big of a deal so I would
don't don't worry too much about it and
then we've got our width and height
which we're sort of offsetting to figure
out where the ground buffer should be
right now once we have that we have to
draw it and that's that's really it but
what we want to do is make sure that
we're not drawing any ground buffers
here that aren't actually valid right so
once oops ones that have not actually
had any you know been filled with a
particular world position value we need
those we need basically those to be
known to us right we need to make sure
that we we know which ones those are and
so I believe we've got in these valid we
do so I'm just going to do that check to
see if the position of it is valid and
that'll be our test to see and I'll put
a little note in here just so we know
note a P is invalid I should say an
invalid P tells us that this ground
buffer has not been filled
okay so that will draw all of our ground
buffers at the locations that they're
supposed to be if they have actually
been filled with valid data right now I
want to take a you know another step
here I want to I want to go one step
further and say that well what we want
to know is we also want to know which of
our ground buffers actually has been
getting used right because we want to be
able to fill these ground buffers with
new information and we want to know if
we needed to make a new ground buffer
for someplace that we're scrolling
towards or something like this we want
to be able to fill it we want to be able
to know which old one we can throw away
if that makes sense and so if you think
back here what I said I was sort of
saying okay well I don't know where I
was saying it don't see it for some
reason that's odd I thought I drew this
I'm losing my mind I'm losing my mind
people I thought I drew a little like I
thought I drew a little thing that
looked like this I guess I didn't well
anyway if we have this right if we have
56 by two views by 64 which actually now
I think we said was 128 but that's
whatever so if we have this array right
and we've got this array of chunks and
they're each you know they correspond to
some location like this ones here
and this one's this one over here and
this one's that one over there right so
now if we have some way we haven't
figured out exactly I would do that yet
but if we have some way and again this
is said the P tells you right where it
is if we have some way of saying which
ones we want filled and we find out oh
we want this one to be filled right we
need that too we need that to have data
now how do we know which one of these
old ones to get rid of because some of
them were still using probably and we
don't really want to get rid of
something we're still using and so what
I'd like to do you
has introduced the concept very simple
what concept to start with which is the
no soon of an LRU
right we're at least recently used the
stands for least recently used L R u L
are you I want to introduce the concept
of at least recently used scheme and at
least recently used scheme is just
something which allows you to say
whatever one of these things I least
recently did something with right like
at least recently drew it on the screen
and so we can just assume the something
that hasn't been drawn for a long time
we must not need very much anymore and
it's not the best indicator necessarily
of what won't be necessary we don't
really know if that's a good idea we
could for example use a different scheme
which is whatever one is farthest away
from the player at that time right but
you can imagine situations where it
actually is more robust to use something
like least recently used or something
else like that where we have say a
situation where the player can teleport
between two places right and like
they're going back and forth between
this teleporter for some reason then
looking at how far away something is
might not be the best way to say whether
that thing needs to get filled right it
might be better to just go whatever
we've been using recently we should just
keep because it seems like it's a good
idea right
so I don't really have a particularly
strong opinion about how we want to do
this so I'm just gonna do a very simple
way of authoring this first and if we
find out we need something better later
we can do something better later so all
I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna introduce
a linked list right I'm going to
introduce a singly linked list here or I
guess I don't know what might we need a
doubly linked list to remove things I
don't know that we will
hmm hmm
actually I think now that I'm thinking
about this I'm taking it back I think we
may not really need that now that I
think about it
you know what we don't need that we've
already got an array right and we're
going to be looping through this array
so we're gonna be starting at the
beginning and we're gonna be looking
through it to see which ones we need to
render right if we encounter one that
doesn't need to be rendered right at
that time we could just go ahead and do
array compaction moving this stuff
moving the the subsequent things up into
its position and shuffling it down past
the end of where there were things that
actually did need to get rendered we
could do that because if you look at
what's actually in this structure at the
moment it's mostly just a world position
and a loaded bitmap and the loaded
bitmap actually doesn't really need to
be there if you think about it right
because a loaded bitmap oops I got a
where's my stroke where's my loaded
bitmap struck where do where is it there
it is a loaded bitmap really all we need
is this right effectively we don't need
any of this other stuff right we just
need just the memory pointer because we
already know that the width and height
this constant across all these things
you know I'm saying so we've really just
got that so how big is a world position
let's take a look so a world position is
is what 1 2 3 1 2 3 so it's 6 4 byte
things it's 24 bytes plus 8 bytes it's
32 bytes so probably it would be just
fine to just actually keep our array in
sorted order to be completely honest
with you
that may actually be the smartest thing
to do hard to say that may actually be
the smartest thing to do
yeah I'm not sure I'm not sure the
linked list scheme the way that would
look right is it would introduce more
stuff in here we'd introduce like a at
least the next pointer possibly a
previous nice partner let's let's try it
let's try it this way
let's try it I'm just I'm just let's
let's go for it that's I mean you know
why not so instead of doing it this way
I'm just gonna say loaded bitmap bitmap
and you know what I could also do here I
can introduce an exemplar so I could say
basically like you know what there's a
loaded bitmap that's like ground bitmap
like template right and basically what
we'd say is okay the game state you know
ground bitmap template we equals make
empty bitmap and then actually all we
store out of that right here is we just
store that we just store the memory
that's it we just store what this thing
said the memory was and then when we
want to draw it all we do is just use
that guy that ground bitmap template we
just use that and overwrite the memory
pointer which whatever the member point
is that we want because we don't need to
store the pitch and all that of the
stuff multiple times there's no point to
that at all right that's just kind of a
waste so if you think about what we're
doing here we base to say all right okay
okay okay you know I take it back we've
got a loaded bitmap and you know what
it's true we weren't even using that
stuff in here for the most part so it's
really just the drum pick might call it
music but anyway this is the actual
bitmap that we're gonna draw we grab out
of the ground buffer we grab out its
memory so weight sorry the gamestate
round fit map template so and we just
grab out its memory and stick it in the
bitmap that we're going to use and then
we use that bitmap right that's that's
really it
yeah so that seems relatively relatively
clean and this can really be the bitmap
width like so and in fact that basically
means we don't have to store these
either right because they're implicit in
that bitmap yeah I think that's
basically all we really need so that
also means I suppose that this can just
be you and 32s
there and those can be used directly and
then they will be saved automatically so
that seems relatively clean I like that
that seems like the right thing to do
this is a dot and off we go
bitmap memory ground buffer that's about
as well it's doc whoa I'm sorry I didn't
even realize the game was still running
that's my bad yeah we're totally mucking
with the memory layout here so it would
not be a good time to have the automatic
DLL loading being loading in and
thinking it was interpreting the old
data in the new way all right
so that seems to me pretty sane so now
all we have to do is actually think
through well you know what we could do
first before we try to do the LRU scheme
we could just do something that actually
makes these bitmaps get composited
because we got plenty of work to do
there as it is so yeah first let's
verify that nothing draws when we run it
yeah so I've got something bugging in
there because it shouldn't be drawing
any of these because it shouldn't get is
valid on any of them right so I just
want to make sure that that wasn't
happening and of course it is happening
so let's just do bug that quickly and
there's one other thing that we can do
to do debugging first that's what is the
problem here
what is the problem here ground buffer
count ground buffer P and X so what is
my let's take a look here what is my
situation with ground buffers there's
the ground buffers come on there we go
ground buffers let's just take a look at
them here there they all are just using
that comma 1:28 notation to see where
everything is
so why are these what did I mess up here
why are these set to like real things
something is busted I hope I didn't do
something weird with my transient arena
because we weren't supposed to be using
anything in the transient arena yet you
know I'm saying so but then again we
haven't ever tested it so there's that
so these are all set properly right you
can see them set being set properly so
let's go through here and see what's
going on when I come through here so
ah-ha
I guess not there we go so it turns out
I was using that transient arena in my
sim arena right here alright so way to
not put it to do on that KC that was
just sloppy programming right there now
it didn't actually cause us any problems
because I'm founded right away but I
still think that's an owl of shame
because there should have been but to do
there that said something like once we
talk about the transient arena make this
actually do something real right and we
didn't do that at all so yeah okay so
now we get into more of the memory
partitions stuff actually which is to
say that what we we actually have the
need to have an actual memory partition
on our transient arena right and the way
that this works is there's two ways that
you can do the
right and I don't know which way we want
to do in the end it depends on how you
want to think about your memory right
so one way to do it is to say that we
always have a fixed amount of memory
right the memory amounts fixed it's
however much it is it's two gigabytes or
something that's what our game runs in
or who knows right and then you just
pick how you're going to divide it up
and you know off you go
I guess I should really I guess I should
really say three ways this is this is
like completely fixed
this is 100% fixed layout right and the
advantage of this scheme where I'm
basically saying okay you know some
stuff lives in here then we've got
another thing in here for the renderer
let's say and then we've got another
thing in here right and and this is some
other stuff whatever right the benefit
of this is it always works 100%
predictably right you know exactly
what's going on and there's no mystery
to it
the downside of it is these things
aren't flexible right so it means that
you know if you wanted to have if there
was a game that could take advantage of
having the renderer like take more
memory sometimes then like you know the
physics or something in certain
scenarios where that was more
appropriate it could do it right you
know that's like the downside is that
doesn't happen then there's like you
know pseudo fixed which is to say that
you you have some amount that you're
going to live in right so that's still
the same but you don't necessarily say
where stuff is so during your frame
processing right
you like pile some stuff on and you see
where that ends and then you pile some
more stuff on you see where that ends
and you pile some more stuff on right
and the problem with this scheme is if
you don't know what these bounds are you
might just run over your 2gig limit
right so it can be a little
unpredictable in that sense and what do
you do when you hit that right so you
kind of have to know that you've set
things reasonably in order for that to
work at all and finally you can have one
that's just kind of like free-for-all
right and that's where you still use you
can still use the arena stuff like I'm
using you don't have to change that but
what actually happens is you start off
with allocating some memory and you
start partitioning it and then when you
run out you just go back to the system
and ask for more
right and you just chained these blocks
together as you go
so that the very end you can free them
all certainly and you know how many you
have and you can clear them and do all
this stuff with it but there's no finite
bound on it so it's like I don't know if
you want to try to allocate 18 gigabytes
it'll just keep on going and allocating
and allocating and allocating right and
so I don't know which of these we'll end
up with in the end it really largely
depends on sort of I guess how hard of a
set of constraints we can impose on the
code so like you know this is usually
the best way in terms of robustness
because you can 100% guarantee that
everyone operates out of you know every
system but it might not be that it's not
necessarily the best for things like
modding and flexibility right where you
want people to push those limits now you
can always make this be parametric right
so you can make it so that you can
always say oh yeah give it 16 gigs
instead and now each of these things is
8 X bigger than it was so you can still
get some flexibility on it that way but
you know you can understand why a
certain design of the game would have a
different partition potentially than
some other design and so that's why
sometimes people like to go with these
other schemes well to be fair a lot of
people just go with the like you know
the WTF scheme which is just like we
call malloc everywhere woohoo you know
and they have no idea what's going on
that's not fabulous so we're not even
gonna consider that one we're just gonna
kind of scroll it off the screen here
we're gonna pretend that that doesn't
exist right but yeah again there's
trade-offs different ways of thinking
about things it's all fine but anyway
point being so we have this transient
arena and what the transit arena is
forest for stuff that is non-essential
right so we have multiple things that
want to access it so what we want to do
is introduce some
sort of a system something that we can
use that makes it easy for us to use
that memory effectively right so I've
introduced this transient arena here and
that's the thing that subdivides that
arena what we really probably wanted to
do here was also have the permanent
arena and we would allocate the World
Arena out of that I'll kind of explain
why that's necessary when we get to some
part where we actually have multiple
things going on with the World Arena but
for now we can ignore that and just say
okay so we've got stuff that wants to
happen in you know in the transient
arena and then we also want after that
stuff is allocated to have another set
of things could be allocated right so
what we want to do here is we want to
make bit you know essentially a notion
of where the boundary is between the
stuff that actually has to the boundary
between where the transient arena itself
I'm not sure how to say this right we
want to make a boundary between the
things that persist from frame to frame
in the transient arena because they
still carry over like our ground buffers
don't get a race frame to frame they
just could get a race frame to frame
does that make sense I'm not sure if
that makes makes sense to you but I'll
try to show you what I mean so let's
suppose for example we had a thing that
was like transient arena right I'm sorry
transient state like this right and we
move the ground buffer in here like that
does that make some sense and then what
I want to do is I want to say oK we've
got an arena you know we've got that
transient arena and I would like that to
actually live in here right and this is
totally separate from our game state it
can be completely regenerated as
necessary right and what this is going
to do is this is going to tell us this
is going to keep track of what stuff we
actually have already put in sort of the
bottom part of this of this transient
dream
so like we've got you know a stack of
stuff that we're growing and we're
saying that our loaded bitmaps to the
ground buffers like this is going to be
ground buffers right and they just lived
there we know how big they are they are
always that size so what we want to do
now is say anything else
so sim regions for example the sim
region memory wants to be in here right
that's where the sim region stuff wants
to live we want to make it easy for this
image and stuff to start after the total
amount used for the ground buffers now
similarly we may want to be able to
partition it into other stuff up here or
what we may want to do is essentially
bungee cord the sim region stuff so that
the way that the sim region's work is
they grow down right but then when
they're done they pop back up to here
and whatever memory they used is gone
right and that's probably what we want
to do with them for right now so let's
start out with that and we'll get a
little more complicated as we go but
we'll start out with that all right so
first things first
zoomy what we want to do here is we want
to have initialization for the transient
State
so this is the transient initialization
right and it works exactly the same way
as soups
initialisation there we go it works
exactly the same way as this does right
it's it's literally exactly the same
this stuff is identical right so what we
want to do is take this we want to move
this down here and what we'd like to do
is say okay let's assume at least we
want to make sure that there's no
possible way that we couldn't fit at
least the size of our transient state
inside the transient storage size right
and then we're going to assume that that
first thing at the base of that
transient storage we're going to assume
that that is our transient state right
so that's what's gonna happen there
like so okay so assuming that you know
we don't really have a.m. we don't
really have a way of knowing which ones
of these got cleared and I think our our
definition was that stuff always had to
initialize to zero so I think the
easiest thing probably to do would just
be to have it initialized actually be in
here that seems like the best policy so
I'm gonna go ahead and say that that's
what our policy is for right now all
right so if we if we see that our
transient state is not initialized then
we're going to initialize it right
that's what we're going to do exactly
the same way that we did it before and
we're going to initialize this arena
exactly the same way as we initialize
the other one like so right so this guy
is going to come down here like this
again I wasn't really planning on doing
this today but it seems like a fine time
to do it so we'll go ahead and do it so
transient storage size again we will
take away however much we use just to
store that one state structure and we
will go ahead and and there's a you know
there's a clever way we could have done
this as well which is to initialize the
arena first and then allocate the thing
out of it but yeah six of one half dozen
the other anyway so this will start us
out with that arena and now we can
allocate all of these things out of the
arena directly right just like we were
doing before and and we could we could
call this trans state so we'd have to
keep typing transient I suppose so maybe
we call it like this like that ran state
oops trans state yeah something like
that
and maybe we call this Tran arena as
well there we go so if we take a look at
what happens here it's all exactly the
same as what was happening on the other
one but now it's just happening in sort
of the separate the separate area right
and that's the only difference between
what we were doing before and what we're
doing now it goes ahead and gets all
this stuff out so
gamestate is gonna be trans state as far
as this thing's concerned like so that's
all good and let's see if I can compile
that there what is my transient see what
else trans state is initialized we go
and transient arena is now Tran arena so
and one more time two more times there
we go so that's gonna all be in there
and the interesting about this is you'll
notice that now the transient arena is
left at exactly the location that we
would want it to be for the sim arena to
use it right so what we want to do here
is just say oh okay
when this thing is using the sim arena
what we would like to do is we would
like it to just be able to use whatever
was in the transient whatever that
transient arena was right and so what we
can do there is we could just probably
pass the transient arena for now maybe
we want to actually make a sim arena in
the future but for now we could just
pass the transient tournament directly
right and now it's gonna use that sim
arena and that'll be fine and the only
thing that we have to fix now is when
the simulation is done we want to
basically Bungie back to that location
so it's you know the sim regions gonna
use that arena it's gonna fill it up
with stuff and when it gets to the end
we just want to kind of go back to the
baseline that it was you know was that
was just after the ground buffer stuff
that we had allocated right and so to do
that I'm just gonna introduce one more
thing which is like sort of begin you
know temporary memory or something I'm
gonna know exactly what we're going to
call it but we're gonna call it that for
now we're gonna call that begin
temporary memory and then at the end I'm
gonna do the same thing and temporary
memory right and the temporary memory
we're gonna have I don't know if we want
the arena's to actually do pushes and
pops
I'm considering I think we do I think we
do so we're gonna do it that way like so
and then at the end we're going to do a
little insurance policy as well we're
going to do something like this
check arena and we're gonna do that for
our game state rolled arena and our
Kings our trans State train or email
like so so now we just got to implement
these guys we've got those pushes we got
these pushes and stuff on here right so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
initialize these they're really really
simple all they're designed to do is to
spring forward and back in memory space
right so if we take a look at what these
do there is there's one extra level
security we could do here I don't know
if we actually want to I'll think about
it in a second after we're done with
this but basically all we're doing here
is saying okay you can begin an end
temporary memory like so when you
actually do that the arena itself you
know what I'm gonna I'm gonna do it I'm
gonna put in the extra layer security
why not so we'll have a little temporary
memory thing here temporary memory and
that's all it's gonna do right is is
store that used thing it's just gonna
store where the used field was because
that's all we need in order to restore
the state right and so I'm gonna go
ahead and say excuse me I'm gonna say
that we have temporary memory and this
is the sim memory and then when we end
that temporary memory I don't know why I
put it here supposed to be down after
you're done but what do you gonna do
then I'm gonna say all right we're done
with it here right and I'll also put the
memory arena in there so that you don't
have to save both of them
and so then the temporary memory thing
will return that it'll say okay got a
temporary memory results the results
arena is whatever arena got passed in
the result dot used is going to be
whatever that arenas used state was at
the time when it was called yeah and
then the additional security I was gonna
put into was just the fact that there's
going to be something like a temp count
on the arena which will get initialized
to zero and every time we begin
temporary memory I'm just going to in
current it and every time we end I am
going to subtract it does that make
sense this doesn't take that any more
temporary memory tent men right and so
hmm if you look at what this does that
just sort of lets me know how many times
this thing has been locked right and we
might even make this an int so we can
see if it went negative it'll be easier
for us to read basically so anyway so if
we take that arena we set the arena used
equal to whatever the temp them used was
right and we might also do an assertion
here and just say let's assert that we
are always going you know we're always
retracting memory we're never jumping
forwards because that would indicate
probably a bug and whoever was calling
us and let's also assert here for
example that the temp count is greater
than zero because otherwise we should
not be decrementing it that would be bad
right and and yeah and then we can
finally add just one thing in here which
is which is check arena
and that's just again another assertion
and that assertion allows us to verify
that we ended every frame with a
balanced number of temporary memory
begins and ends just so we make sure
nothing funky happened right so this is
just an assertion that arena temp count
is exactly zero always at the end
all right so oops that's no good
although I guess why did I do that I was
dumb we just do that all right uh that's
not right that's that is more correct
here we go
don't know why I was really wanting to
access results there so let's see so
these are now all off of Tran state
right so we want to go ahead and fix
that so here's a here's our trans state
trans state and same here trans state
that looks about right to me and these
need to take addresses but other than
that they look good and so we probably
won't step into that we just slammed a
bunch of code in there so we probably
want to see what's going on let's go
ahead and do that so if we step through
here let's see what happens so when we
do our our sim memory here and and our
trans again sim memory and our trans
state Fran Arena so you can see there is
exactly what we computed in Emacs in
quick calc there's our 32 megabyte
backing store foreground tiles here is
the total size it's that giant I don't
know if it's one gigabyte I don't
remember how big it was it's big right
looks like a gigabyte right yeah
and then we're gonna go ahead and create
a temporary memory region right now so I
don't know where the there we go so if
we go ahead and create that temporary
memories you see we're just snapping
what the use thing is we increment that
counter and now we can kind of go
through the sim region we can do our
stuff the sim region is now busy doing
it's it's allocating it's it's things so
if I jump down here we should see it
this should have moved up presumably
although it didn't which is odd oh no it
did you can see it did so it used a
bunch of memory
now we'd like to do is when we when we
hit that and memory we should see that
bounce back to what the previous use
Kant was which it did and the temp count
goes down to zero our check arena should
both succeed because there's no open
memories there and yet and off we go so
now we've got that straightened away so
our arena's are working properly now and
that's good what I would like to do now
is again get these guys actually drawing
and what we could do is when we make
them write we could actually do
something here where we initialize some
of them to be drawn and so an example of
that would be if I just drew one that
was at the cameras location right so if
I told it for example our draw ground
our draw ground chunk is now going to be
like some kind of a you know it'll
probably called like fill ground chunk
or something like this right and we pass
in the same stuff we're gonna fill the
ground or ground chunk it needs to know
which ground chunk we want to fill we'll
just use the first one I'll do it to do
here this is just a test fill so what I
want to do here is say okay this is this
is game state presumably I want to say
alright let's fill that first one let's
just fill that first ground buffer right
you know gamma buffer plus zero
basically we'll fill that first ground
buffer and what we'll do is we'll say
that we want it to be at where the
camera state actually is right now like
that and that should work
roughly correctly uh ground buffers yeah
and then fill ground chunk needs that to
be an address connect four dollars to
two loaded bitmap star ah yes well
actually that's something we could
totally work around with Phil ground
chunk I suppose yeah yeah yeah since I'm
only saving the memory out of them you
have to do this
nonsense every time which isn't ideal
admittedly right but I could do this
like so transient states you know that
and then it's just ground buffer that
buffer that would actually be all that
was necessary to recompute it and so
then we have something we're gonna say
okay loaded bitmap buffer equals trance
state round proper template isn't their
ground buffer template we're did my
grandpa for a ground bitmap template
sorry bitmap template but the memory
equals the memory from that ground
buffer and then the other thing we want
to do is you want to take the ground
buffer and we want to set its P equal to
the chunk P right and that should be
good so buffer arrow equals buffer dot
like we've got them that used to be an
address so does that but off we go it so
now maybe if we're lucky we'll see one
and we did now obviously a buffer of
that size doesn't need to be covered
with such prodigious foliage so you know
go ahead and cut that down a little bit
that may have been excessive I admit
that so you know alright so that feels
fills one of the chunks and now we are
in a position to fill multiple chunks so
I would say if we hadn't have had to
take the arena dye version we probably
actually would have had this working
completely today which would have been
pretty cool but I'm gonna wait till
tomorrow we're almost at the QA I'm
gonna wait till tomorrow to actually do
the filling scheme because we have to
talk about that LRU stuff a little bit
more but we're almost there and then
once that's done that'll be it
that'll just we'll be able to walk
around and have an infinitely
non-repeating ground texture that we can
fill with anything we want which is kind
of cool I'm pretty happy about that
actually so that should be kind of nice
so yeah let's let's stop for now I don't
want to get into something what I'm
gonna have to stop because it's gonna be
exciting to have that
repeating texture and I want to be able
to go straight to I did not want to have
to kind of go through a bunch of of like
oh you know just let me eat a few more
minutes at the Q&amp;A kind of thing so
let's just go to the Q&amp;A now and do it
that way so we'll see we shall see
girl and Oh bloom what is the most
expired food you have ever eaten that is
not a question that is related to the
programming girl and oh if that is for
the pre stream game Davey could you
explain what pop and push are and how
they work I don't get it we didn't
really use that nomming creature
anywhere did I just I probably just said
that or are you talking about these game
dev II could you be more specific do you
just mean what I'm talking about when I
say when we use the temporary stuff or
whatever somebody tell me what you mean
by pop and push just just just so I
don't answer like the wrong question
basically
I will I will wait patiently for the
elaboration
or not okay pop and push her memory
swords yes I can talk about that
alrighty so at the start of the game
so remember and again this I realize I
don't say this enough because I come
from a time when this was just a given
that everyone thought this way but I
realized that nowadays it's it's
possible to be a programmer who's
actually worked for many years and not
even think about things at all this way
so I'm just going to be very explicit
here because I realize not everyone
comes at it from a similar perspective
so first let's just say something memory
is a big line right so memory is
something in which I'm going to store
data and there's addresses to it right
and so I can talk about my computer's
memory how many however big it is I
don't know how much does I think this
this might have this this machine you
might have 12 gives 12 gigs of memory
right physical memory you know is
starting it is byte zero and going to
byte 12 gigabyte right but I'm actually
in virtual memory right because all
operating some views virtual memory so
technically you know this 12 gigabytes
of memory I don't actually look at
directly I don't actually see that
directly in terms of addressing right
what I see is virtual memory right so I
see a virtual address space imposed by
the CPU where it basically says okay
I'll tell you what Casey you've got this
virtual address space and when you want
to allocate memory right when you want
to use some memory I'm gonna tell you
that some part of your virtual address
space starting at byte something let's
say you know byte X and going for
however big you asked for so if you ask
for one gigabyte of memory it's gonna go
to X and an X plus 1 gigabyte right
these are the byte values literally like
a number some number that tells me where
we are in this thing and that's mapped
to some set of pages in physical memory
and I don't even know how it is right so
I never even see
the physical memory we're always dealing
with virtual addresses right so it's
interesting to talk about this sometimes
when we get down to it but as far as
we're concerned right now we're working
totally in a virtual address space right
that's managed by Windows and the CPU
and we don't even know exactly what it's
doing a lot of times so when I get
memory at the beginning of this of the
game if you remember we way back in one
of the early episodes we just allocated
I think it was one gigabyte of memory
for what we called transient storage
right and so what that does is it takes
a virtual big one gigabyte line and
reserves it for our use and it tells us
a number which is the base of that line
it tells us where it starts right so if
you imagine that I'll continue drawing
it this way so this is the start of our
transient memory so for all intents and
purposes you know we have a base pointer
you can see it in here hand a platform
down H memory
right here so you can see that we
basically we get past this at startup
this is what the platform layer
allocates for us it's got a void start
transient storage that's a pointer it's
the number that's in our virtual address
space where the start of that transit
storage is and it's this big however it
transmits storage size sets right so
this right here is transit storage
pointer right the points to right there
and this size is transient storage size
right so now when typically other stuff
would call like you know new write in
C++ or malloc and C or whatever in your
language whatever it is that allocates
something whatever you're used to
thinking in what that does is it
essentially actually does a similar
thing here it's got a big flat line
right and it goes and it finds a region
where it can stick the thing that you
wanted and it sticks it in there but
we're not using any of these because
honestly I think they're all kind of a
waste of time what we're doing instead
is we're just saying let's just manage
this directly because it's not that hard
to do and if we just managed it
ourselves we get a lot of benefits and
we we don't we get a lot faster and a
lot simpler in a lot of in a lot of
places in my opinion doesn't mean
there's anything wrong with these I just
don't like them my preference is is no
so what we do instead is we say all
right what happens when we need to do
anew what happens when we need to make
some storage well what we do is we just
say ok whenever we need to make storage
we just stick it at wherever the next
free space is on this in this line we
start at the very first byte byte you
know whatever the start of the transit
memory is and we just put it in there
and then we make whatever is immediately
after it the byte immediately after it
be the new space where we would put
things of new things comes in so if a
new thing comes in we do the same thing
right and I call this pushing because it
always just adds on to the end right
it's like pushing it on to the thing it
pushes it on pushes it on pushes it on
right it makes more sense
you think of it growing from the bottom
up I just didn't draw it that way but
you're like pushing something on top
right putting things on the bottoms a
little weird but I tend to draw them
from the top down because I like to
think of like this as being increasingly
positive going down that's just how like
humans are hard-wired because we read
top to bottom so when I say pop what I
mean is well if we pushed a bunch of
things on but now we don't need them
anymore we could just pop them off by
taking whatever the number is that we
started at so let's say we started here
this is some number X and we go down to
get to some number Y if we want to erase
all these things effectively that we
allocated if we basically want to do a
free operation we can just take whatever
our thing that was saying where the next
thing to allocate was and reset it to X
you can just jump back down and now
those things are effectively gone
because whatever the next thing that
gets allocated will overwrite some of
them right we'll just overwrite them so
push is a lock and pop is free right now
the restriction here is you have to do
these in order right you can't free
something out of the middle of this
stack and so the thing that gets the
thing that that is I think the reason
people lean on these so heavily is these
are out of order allocations and free
things and we have to implement that
ourselves we already did it with a free
list in one place and that's what I
prefer to use I tend to prefer to use
free lists so that once things get
allocated they never really go away
unless they're purely temporary and I
find that's way more efficient and I
never run into all those problems that
people have where they're like oh my god
we got memory fragmentation and we're
allocating so much per frame and all
these a locks and oh my god and whatever
is going on and plus it allows us to do
a lot of easier stuff in terms of
visualizing our memory space but that's
a thing for a later date so that's what
I mean in terms of push a pop but if you
didn't want to do any of this if you're
like I don't know Casey I don't like
this it feels freaky you could just
imagine doing new and free everywhere
right but you can already kind of see
why there's some nice thing
about doing it this way like just think
of all the complexity we didn't have to
have because we were doing it this way
right all I had to do to just make that
whole sim region go away right was just
this one call begin temporary and then
at the end we said and temporary right
that would have if we were doing that
with the crazy you know
garbage-collected point or nonsense all
of this work would have have to go on
behind the scenes to go okay what's in a
sim region okay these things are in a
sim region mixer okay destroy all of
those what are they pointing to destroy
the things that they're pointing to okay
wait are these pointers is that thing
still reachable all that stuff is just
gone we never pay it at all right the
most optimal code is the code that never
gets run I think my K Bret said
something like that right and we are
right in that sweet spot here we don't
have to do any work to clean up what we
do all we do is we set one number it's
like the old number the new number
equals the old number whatever like our
stack top equals the old stack top
that's it right and that's just so
powerful and so efficient compared to if
we had been doing these things we would
have had to either implement a bunch of
stuff ourselves to do it or lean on a
garbage collection system some
pre-written garbage source and to do it
for us if we didn't want to just be a
nightmare territory all the time here
right and so that's why I highly
recommend exploring doing your own
memory management cuz you may find that
for a lot of the stuff you do it's
incredibly efficient and really pretty
simple but it's just not that much to it
how will the ground texture chunking
handle adjacent rooms with different
types of ground well that's more of a
world generation question so basically
like the world the the tile chunks I'm
sorry the ground chunks or ground
buffers I guess we're calling them or
just saying get me whatever had to be in
this region but whatever we do to fill
that can be as complicated as we want so
it can do like some ground and then
overwrite it with some floor and even
like feather the edges between them or
whatever that fill operation can be
incredibly complicated right and it'll
get complicated even without what you're
saying even without just overlapping
because yeah you're saying you're saying
base for like I have a chunk and like
here's a room boundary you know and this
is like some kind of a tile floor here
but this is like you know grass or
whatever right and the answer is like
that's the compositors problem so we'll
work on that we deal compositing we
don't care about that for the rendering
stuff that we're doing here we're just
trying to figure out how we fill it in
how we place it in places but yeah
that's just stuff will do well like you
know it'll do the ground splats and then
it'll like draw some tiles in there and
off we go similarly you'll have to
handle stuff like oh there's a river
running through this this thing and like
here's the edge of the river or whatever
right and the ground is here but like
water is here or whatever running
running along it or something right so
there's plenty of stuff that we have to
deal with there but that's really that's
really more about the procedural texture
generation aspects and not about the
chunking scheme because the chunking
scheme is whatever chunking scheme is
is that it for clues is that it for cues
I think that's it for Q's we're done
earlier today aren't we
well alright no more queues I guess
we're good to go I will wrap things up
all right let me close this down
save our mischief like I like saying
save our mistress close this alright
well that was an easy one
thank you everyone for joining me for
another episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always I've kind of excited for tomorrow
because then we'll have our ground tile
working I think because we've basically
done everything we need to so really we
just have to do some kind of an LRU
scheme there and we'll be good to go so
that's gonna be kind of fun to have a
nice ground texture and then we can
start looking again at kinda you know
how to kind of do some some multi-level
stuff there just to try to finish up our
ground like handling our whole sort of
ground state because we really haven't
done the collision detection stuff that
we need to do to finish that up so I
still got there but we're we're in the
homestretch on this sort of on this sort
of stuff and then we're in you know like
I said we're in front kind of we're kind
of a fun time I think we got a bunch of
code to do that will that will probably
go by fairly quickly I like the debug
code and that sort of stuff and so it'll
be kind of interesting I don't know it's
all good
yep it's all good and and yeah I guess I
have nothing else to add other than I've
studied for tomorrow because I want to
see that work and we've done pretty much
everything we need to do to make it work
we just didn't quite have time today to
actually go in and and have some you
know have something intelligent scheme
about what gets filled win so we'll do
that tomorrow and we'll be good and that
will happen again at 5:00 p.m. Pacific
Pacific Daylight Time so same time the
same place as today I hope to see you
all there
if you would like to follow along at
home with the source code you can do
that by pre-ordering the game on
handmade hero org if you preorder the
game comes with a source code you'll get
a link in your email which you can
download anytime you want
in fact if you lose it there's now a
little habit reset button down here in
case you lose your download link so
that's a good thing too so please check
that out if you're interested also we
have a patreon if you want to support
the video series you can always
subscribe to that it is greatly
appreciated
we have a news and forums site where you
can ask questions and you can get ports
of the game to Linux and Mac the
community have done there's also an
episode guide that's annotated which is
really great for catching up on old
episodes and do not forget to check out
the most awesome artificial intelligence
ever created by humankind ladies and
gentlemen the hand made hero tweets
scheduled tweet bot which tweets the
schedule at you we believe it may slowly
becoming sentient we don't know this for
sure but we think that it may have been
because it is so powerful and now even
understands time zones so that's
something to be pretty excited about so
if you want to subscribe to that it'll
tell you when the show is and that's
pretty handy so thank you very much for
joining me hope see you here tomorrow
again at 5 p.m. Pt PDT or PSD I guess
and until then have a wonderful day