burning hello everyone and welcome to
handmade here the show Rico complete
game live on stream we actually we may
we don't even know but yesterday we may
have finished our sprite sorting first
pass we don't know because we haven't
actually gone and passed the requisite
information down to it yet from the
render layer we basically wrote the code
that is necessary for doing all of the
sorting for our sprites in the game but
in order to do that we decided we needed
the rectangular screen space area
occupied by the sprite and that was not
something we were traditionally passing
to the renders the renderer although it
knows that information I shouldn't say
not passing the renderer that's not we
work tricity passing down to the like
render output layer the rasterizer I
should say and so that needs to happen
and it's not particularly difficult to
do but we actually need to do it so
before we can even test our sorting code
and I mean presumably will have to debug
it as well and all that good stuff we're
going to need to start passing that
information down and making sure we
actually know what all the screen space
rectangles are for our actual sprites so
let's go ahead and do that now can't
think of a reason not to today is day 3
06 so if you're going to try and follow
along at home unpacked a 305 source code
that's where I'm starting right now and
that is where you should be starting if
you want to follow along alright so here
we go if you remember where we left off
we don't have any crash bugs or anything
like this but as you can see all our
lovely lovely sprites are gone and the
reason for that is of course we're not
even sorting our since we're not sorting
anything correctly the clear is probably
getting sorted to the front or something
like this and so you know who knows
anything can happen at that point so we
have no idea what's going on in there at
the moment so we got to start with
passing correct data down see where we
are there and then
drop in and start debugging it and make
sure that everything is actually working
properly once we've got it having data
that it can actually use so let's go
into the code here there's inside render
group we know that we've got the sort
key we know that we we call the push
render element only three times we call
it for bitmaps in the well you know what
I'll just show it to you we call it for
bitmaps four rectangles and for the
clear so here's the push render element
for the bitmap here's the Bushmen of the
rectangle here is to clear it since that
seems to be going behind my head a lot
I'm going to go ahead and jump over here
real quick so that it's easier to see so
for something like the clear well for
the clear we kind of know what we would
need right for the clear we know that
we're going to take up the entire screen
and so that means that the you know if
our algum was working properly that
means the clear should always be sorted
behind everyone hopefully right because
it will overlap with everything and need
to get pushed back behind everything so
when we're talking about the sort key
that we're passing here trying to
remember exactly how this worked out I
believe the push render element for the
sort key in here you can see that it's
not actually passing screen area right
so are not really setting the screen
area that screen areas here by the way
you'll have to excuse my typing to be
about this little slow today I've got my
fingers taped up which I can only use
three fingers on my left hand so it
makes it a little bit licks a little bit
less let's use the word evolution which
is not actually a word but it's a word
that we just made up to mean that it's
not as fast as it would be if your
fingers weren't taped so there you go so
let's pretend we were going to start
passing the screen area down here
because basically we know that if any
render element wants to be sorted which
all of them have to be four correct
rendering we know that we're going to
want to have our rectangle what did I
call it rectangle too is it a rectangle
to I or rectangle to I'm not really
entirely certain which one we ended up
using so let's take a look here
we did a rectangle do so with a
rectangle too I want to pass that down
as the screen area and then I want to
save it and now this should give me an
error in the code anywhere that I don't
currently pass that which is the three
places we said before of course I should
also jump back up there should also put
an actual semicolon at the end of the
line because hey that's important all
right and why do I keep I don't want to
be on that side of the screen bro there
we go so yeah so here we go and now we
have to go for each of these guys and
figure out what it is now the easiest
one should be the rectangle because the
rectangle you mean here it is it's
actually doing that information it's got
you know the it's got the rectangle
itself because that's exactly what it's
going to fill so presumably when we do
press render element here it should be
fairly straightforward to go okay we
know what the rectangle is that we're
trying to fill let's just go ahead and
and make it happen now I don't really
have to guess about what that is because
presumably if I went into the open
gelcoat here and just took a look at
what I actually do when we get the
rectangle you can see okay it's a
rectangle from P to P plus entry dim
right so it's like the two corners so if
I want to create screen area from that
if I want to create you know one of
these then what I should be able to do
is pre multiply this dim here right so
this is scaled dim hard to type with no
fingers on so scale dim is going to be
computed here screen area is going to be
a rectangle min max and that rectangle
min max is going to be the scale dim
plus the p
but of course that p should have been
transformed first right so if you take a
look at what happens here we're going to
use the basis p instead so i want to use
that transformed p instead of instead of
using the other stuff okay so that's I
think probably the correct screen area
we'll have to verify it obviously but
that seems correct to me now for push
bitmap things are a little more
complicated because for push-fit map we
could be passing an x and y axis so at
first like i did before where I kind of
cheese doubt the sprite bound stuff we
could do exactly the same cheesing here
just to get things working but you know
we're probably going to need tighter
bounds eventually actually it's gonna be
the opposite these bounds will be too
tight they won't they won't extend as
far as they probably need to so I'm
going to take a rectangle to hear the
screen area I'm going to pass that oops
yeah I'm going to pass that through and
then here inside the rectangle screen
area part i'm going to do a rectangle
min max and i'm going to just do exactly
the same thing that we were doing before
where we say like okay let's pretend
that it's going to be Jim basis p and
Jim basis B plus size so we'll assume
that we've got the screen area here and
the reason that this is not going to be
quite right just to sort of give you a
little background on that if you're not
sure so oops
so what's going to happen is in the case
where we're drawing a regular sprite
this will be correct so if we know that
we've got an x axis of 10 and a y axis
of 0 1 and we don't have to worry about
any rotational effects then we know that
this is going to be fine that's actually
going to be the screen area of the
sprite is going to be given by the P
that's transformed plus that size is
going to give us the two corners of our
bounding box in screen space and we're
good to go however if you imagine what
happens were this to be rotated right so
suppose our x-axis were not that suppose
we had something that had been rotated
on its side like this or furthermore it
could be like sheared a little bit so it
could even be something this kind of
parallelogram e well now whatever that
size used to be you know is maybe
pointing to here well that is not
actually the rectangle anymore because
it's been sort of warped and so we don't
really have any protection here we're
going to have entirely wrong results if
this thing's spinning around at all so
for example let's take the worst
possible case where this thing was
rotated completely around we're going to
pick this is the rectangle for the
screen area but the actual rectangle is
going to be here if we rotated it all
the way round right furthermore the
rotating rectangle could be much bigger
or much smaller if we just pass bigger
values here so for example if the x-axis
and y-axis for three long instead of one
long you know this is how big would
actually appear but that's how big we
would say it was so it's definitely not
going to be acceptable to do this in the
long term and we're going to run into
bugs with that no question if we leave
it like that but for the moment we
aren't really using that very much only
the hopping hero really uses that all
that much and so we can get a quick
sense of whether the album's working
before we tackle that part any you know
anymore so let's start with that
want to come back to that soon ok so we
I don't remember what we called that
function so we're going to kind of have
to look it up let's rekt min oh so we
can actually do a recommend dim we've
got a utility function that actually
just does this automatically for us so
recommend dim is better anyway so that's
great to make sure parents for push
render element does not take four
arguments that's right brown screen area
where's my push but what did i do here
ah got to add to the macro add it to the
macro added it to the macro people you
know playdota may have impeccable micro
but here on handmade hero we have
impeccable macro uh i'm gonna go ahead
and pass that down and i think we're all
good now all we have to do is come up
with a fake rectangle for our clear
which should be the rectangle that
represents the entire screen right and
i'm hoping that that's actually not too
hard to come by because presumably if we
have a render group that's going to have
to know stuff like what the what the the
bounds of the entire screen are so i
would think that we would have a way of
figuring that out and it looks like so
we will we do have an active camera
transform which tells us what the screen
center is unfortunately hmm there we go
and we have the monitor half dim in
meters so i suppose if we do meters two
pixels on that then we would be able to
figure out what our screen rectangle
actually is however that does seem a
little bit draconian and in screen space
you'd think that we would just be sort
of storing what that actually is so I'm
gonna say rather than you know dealing
with all that I feel like it'd be fairly
easy to just do like screen area
here right or something like that I feel
like that would be relatively
straightforward but you know what no I
think that's fine so I'm just going to
say let's go ahead and pass the screen
area down here and then what we'll do is
we'll just initialize that when we when
we initially create the render group and
then we'll just know that we always have
a valid screen area that we can use
because I'm pretty sure we just know
that information at startup we don't
just we just don't tend to preserve it
now where was my almost there that we
had does the render group just get
cleared to zero no it can't this has to
be set properly so where were we setting
that what am I missing we must set that
information somewhere I must have moved
it somewhere accidentally where did it
go
hmm well since I still have not written
a fine for for Cody yet let's do it here
monitor half dim ah flogged those
hamsters Microsoft you can do it
it looks to me like we just don't ever
initialize it at all maybe that's true I
guess let's find out so if I want to
find out I'm just going to go to
handmade render group here where we
actually create one of them so this gets
passed update and render world gets past
that from so does the render group
actually come all the way down it's been
a long time since we working on this
code there was quite a break so I kind
of forget some of the decisions we made
hmm now there we go so it's right there
what am I yeah was my search not working
a reside tight I must have been typing
something wrong because for some reason
when i tried to search for this we
didn't end up jumping to it I must have
gotten a little bit backwards for some
reason so begin render group is what I
actually wanted to look at right this
was the function that I was actually
talking about and I feel like that
should be here and render group that CBP
right but it's not and so that's a
little bit weird alright so let's find
out where did that go did I accidentally
misplace it
what is going on I just did that search
should I not so there's me searching for
begin render group and it like can't
find it oh because I mean not in
rendered group there we go so what's
interesting about this to me is does
that it implies i guess it is true so
even though perspective perspective
actually sets the monitor half-demon
meters kind of down here which is a
little bit strange i'm kind of weirded
out by that but that's okay anyway that
was a little bit of it aside i apologize
for that anyway point being inside begin
render group we should have some way to
figure out what the actual and i guess
now i look at it it seems like we only
actually pass this to prospective or
orthographically past the pixel height
in the pixel width I don't actually know
why that was our decision we may want to
revisit that because it seems like that
should be there on startup but either
way when we do this we can then
therefore set a rectum in dim here where
we just say like oh okay it's 002 you
know pixel width pixel height and I
don't know if we can v2i that can we we
can so this will set that in both cases
so that we have that information around
for the clear and now I think we are
passing our sort always down correctly
right so that should be good okay so now
we have to actually start debugging our
actual code because now we've got actual
screen areas that somebody set to
something that means something so let's
start by taking a look at these so our
screen areas should have something in
the we find plausible these are in you
know basically in pixels and so we
should be able to see something here
that
we think might be plausibly a pixel
value and you know I don't know we'll
find out so yeah like that that looks
kind of wrong to me right like i like i
feel like that can't possibly be a
correct screen area value I mean what
would we be passing that would have such
a ridiculous coordinate right- 2076 28
right so it's like basically the whole
it's like a giant thing the size of an
entire screen off to the left of us I
like I don't know that doesn't seem
particularly logical on the other hand
it's possible that that's just because
there's something that's very large in Z
that's close to us that could have
gotten blown out I suppose that is you
know a theoretical possibility so you
could look at the sort key and see what
it is so it's zmax is actually 0 which
would be right at the camera I feel like
we're going to have to throw things away
that are that close because we can't
really be handing all of those to our
sort to so to a certain extent that
seems like a bit of a problem and in
fact I'm going to take a look at that
I'm going to take a look at that right
here so we have our entity basis p
result situation here where we have
result valid equals true and then here
we have result value equals true
distance to pz greater than near clip
plane so i guess the thing that I'm
wondering is the near clip plane is
almost certainly set you know so that 0
would be clipped out of it right but in
this case it looks like it's not doing
that so that does seem a little bit
weird now that could be just because the
values that we're using for Z are not
accurate let's say maybe but that just
strikes me as a little bit odd you know
we can close this
okay that definitely strikes me as odd
so I want to see well I want to see a
couple things about that actually but I
definitely want to kind of get some idea
here of yet of who were actually dealing
with let's take a look at be yeah yeah
that makes me uncomfortable that's not
great uh where are we at here by the way
also is this just the first pair ok now
we're so all the way up to the sort of
the latest set I'm not sure what I
wanted to bug first I can obviously go
after the part we're at right now but
I'm kind of just disquieted by those
values and I want to make sure that I
that I understand where they're coming
from I don't feel like I really do right
now so I'm going to try to take a look
at what's going on with those and I'm
gonna say I I'm going to say probably
the best way to do that is to maybe take
a look at the place where we're pushing
render elements and say that inside here
it's relatively cheap for me tubes
that's not where I want to be inside
here it's relatively cheap for me to do
something where I look at what the area
is that's passed into the screen area
rectangle right I could do something
where I say like assert get area of that
screen area rectangle is you know less
than you know 2,000 by 2,000 or
something like this
and I guess I don't know if we actually
implemented an area get clamped rekt
area has area it looks like we never
really implemented a area function for
these guys but I'm going to throw one in
here so for this guy would be in line v
to get area and here's a rectangle to
and obviously the area of rectangle is
just the width times the height so the
result here is really straightforward
it's just like what's the width and
what's the height you have those yes oh
no we don't we just have get dim so
that's just the computation for the area
right nothing particularly unusual there
and if I actually don't make a typo and
in theory that should give us what we
need man I am just a mess today I think
having the flipper hand is not helping
so I'm hoping that this assertion will
just fire when we get one of these
particularly large screen areas the
reason that I wanted to do that is
because I just I don't really want to
have to debug it so far down the line
right so I wanted to be able to break
when I have one of these giant
rectangles because now you know
now I can just go ahead and set the next
statement here I can step out right and
I can see who it was that was actually
causing this to occur right like who is
actually calling this function and
obviously we're going to have this same
problem unfortunately a couple more
times I could probably skip the last
push okay uh so I actually didn't want
to go further at the moment that's okay
uh so it's this part right here that
that's causing it so I guess you know I
guess I was worried for for not in this
case those actually are valid like those
should be that big that's actually true
so I'm okay with that because those are
our giant those are our giant sort of
world pens the things that we draw to
show where the simulation region is so I
suppose that isn't actually concerning
that's a valid that's a valid rectangle
I'm not going to freak out about it i'm
gonna i'm going to say that's okay so
let me go ahead and turn that guy off
and I'm now just going to look at the
actual bug but I was a little nervous
about that I just wanted to make sure I
I was not not nuts alright so for some
reason we have disabled the push struct
there I guess because we hadn't finished
yet so that looks like just a case of us
having to re comment in the code right
so that's that's not particularly
exciting that might be the only problem
there I doubt it but it might be right
okay
uh all right so a couple things about
this first of all I really don't know
what we're looking at but you can see
we're running incredibly slowly right
and one of the things about running this
running incredibly slowly is I'm
assuming and I don't know but that it's
I'm assuming it's running incredibly
slowly for the reason that I talked
about before which is that we can't
leave an N squared loop with this many
elements going through it so I'm
assuming that if we look to see what
takes all the time it's going to be
billed sprite graph but I don't know
that for sure so let's first actually do
that because I want to make sure that we
actually do know what's going on for
this entire process as we do the work of
actually getting this you know correct
let's time each of these for the walks
right graph portion and the and the
builds fry craft portion and also i'll
go ahead and turn on while I'm at it
I'll turn on for are you there you go I
will turn on our debug view which
handmade internal is actually on so I'm
assuming that means it's still on but
it's just not sorting to the front can i
right about that oh oh the horror we
can't actually see of course the
hilarious thing is how much faster
release mode runs but yet we can't
actually see our debug hut overlay
because it's kind of stuck to them
sorting in the render engine obviously
kind of really annoying because you can
see the screens just a mess and until we
get the start working our debug overlay
display won't won't be correct either so
that's kind of a little bit of a slap in
the face there but we're not completely
without ways that we can
we're not complete without ways that we
can fix that one thing we can do is I
can sort of make it so that our debug
overlay puts itself in a better position
where we you know might be able to take
a look at it since I only wanted to look
at the speed I guess I'll postpone that
for a little bit just to see if we can't
get the sort working a little more
correctly first and then maybe our debug
thing will pop to the front I wanted to
take a look at the speed originally but
looks like maybe that's not in the cards
all right I was surprised with how fast
that ran with really with optimizations
on but we'll take a little look at that
in the future so as we can see we're
still not really getting correct sorting
results at all here and in fact we're
getting some pretty non sequitur things
like for example we have you know this
big obviously in front things sorting
behind this obviously not in front thing
what is interesting about this is the
sort does seem a lot more stable in a
lot of cases like we're not getting a
lot of flickering and stuff that we are
still getting some and so I don't know
but either way we obviously need to
figure out why we're not getting a sort
of a reasonable sword out of it and the
only way I think we could reasonably do
this because there's too much stuff on
the screen right now I think what we
need to do is maybe like turn off a lot
of what we're doing and just focus on
rendering a couple things and seeing
what happens with those few things right
so what I might say is well okay you
know we've got update and render world
here maybe I'll switch back inside I
think it's in handmade CPP maybe i'll
switch back to doing the title sequence
the title sequence is kind of nice
because it's just a bunch of big fat
plates right there's not thousands of
things going on and so maybe we can take
a look at how the sorting routine
performs on these and that will help us
now of course one thing that's not great
is these
these actually appear to be sorting
somewhat properly so that's less good it
would have been nice of the first one
was completely completely trashed but it
looks like these are doing what they
should do so yeah but I'm still going to
step through them and see what we can
see I would also point out that these
are sorting very reliably incorrect you
can see the drop shadow is sorting in
front of the regular text and so it's
kind of interesting to me just one of
the things that's a little bit odd is
it's interesting to me that the sort is
working reliably for the background
layers here and it's working unreliably
exactly the opposite of what it should
do for the for the text right for the UI
overlay now one thing I'd mentioned is
if you look at build sprite graph it's
taking all the time that's exactly what
I had suggested would happen that's
where the N squared comes in and so
that's good that's exactly what we want
to see because we know how to optimize
that and we can trivially make that much
much faster so as long as that continues
to be the case with the sort that the
only problem is building the sprite
graph we're going to be happy campers
because that means we're really not
going to have to worry too much when it
comes time to optimize it we know
exactly what we need to do if that
changes what's not so good all right so
I'm trying to see here like do any of
these ever render wrong or all of the
backgrounds rendering correctly at the
moment I mean that all looks real good
not seeing a lot of errors here
and i'm not sure why
come on Krampus now Krampus is rendered
correctly it looks like well hmm all
right uh well unfortunately you know
those are working and I guess it's weird
to say that unfortunately it's working
but you know that's what can I say I
guess one thing i could do is see if
it's dependent on the ordering in here
you know i could go ahead and say well
you know if we've got intro layers one
or whatever it is here what if I you
know / muted the order a little bit here
so what if i took and i moved eight you
know up to the front is it just
rendering is it because they happen to
already be in the correct sort order is
that why it's rendering them properly
you know or or what's happening okay so
so that's good so it looks like our sort
is just a little busted right now and
it's not doing what's supposed to do
because you can see here it just it was
just because these have to be in the
right order I had a hunt that might be
the case that's why I tried that and
turns out I was right so that's great
now we have a case where we can actually
take a look at what's happening in the
code that's very simple I can also go in
and turn off handmade internal so I can
go into the build up at I can turn off
sort of our debug code right and what
that means is now we're in a really nice
situation because now when I'm running
the number of things on the screen right
now is really tiny right it's just a few
bitmaps that I know are being blit in
the right wrong order so I can set a
breakpoint here and i can probably
actually step through all eight of these
things and see what the values are and
just figure out whether we're making
correct determinations about them or not
right so let's take a look at what we
actually see here
so here we have an A and a B now we know
that these two are going to to overlap
each other I believe what's a little bit
weird is they both look like they have
the exact same screen area which I'll be
honest doesn't make sense to me Oh
fantastic well this is probably has
nothing to do with anything bug wise oh
well actually it might but that's just a
we have a comparison by their you're
never really supposed to compare
something to itself and yet we totally
were do you see how this we wrote this
year we got new index a goes from zero
to the input node count well we started
off by comparing a with itself right we
take whatever the indexes that we're on
and we're going to make no BB that so
we're going to ask whether a thing
intersects itself and we're going to get
back yes and we're going to add an in
front of edge in one direction or the
other from a node to itself that
actually creates an immediate cycle and
is a problem so you know that actually
is saying we need to fix immediately
that's definitely a bug and not a good
and a bad one right not great not good
so now let me just see what happens just
why I now know also what our target is
okay so same problem no change so that's
good but now at least I should be able
to look at an A and a B and C that
they're different and they are which is
what I wanted to see so we should know
just like I'll verify this with a sort
key but what we should see here is and
we do we should see that B is well okay
so let me take you back to this code
here where where is it at there it is
okay
so I guess one thing that's a little bit
confusing here is if these are rendered
in order meaning if we go through and
put them in order we push from the back
of the stack down the render stack down
to create our sort keys so it means that
we're probably going to see this guy and
this guy in order right the first person
we're going to see is this second person
to see is this so actually this guy is
not involved in the sort right now in
this comparison I think it's going to be
these two guys right that's my
assumption anyway but so if we see them
we know that the way that we wanted
these things sorted was we want the the
higher Z values right the things because
the whys aren't really that relevant in
this case so we're taking a look
strictly at Z values here presumably
although I guess the other thing that we
have to figure out here is are these set
to to upright or not I assume they're
going to be set to upright equals false
but we can verify that in a second
meaning are these Z sprites yes these
are Z sprites so that's what we would
have wanted so that's fine so we've got
the Z Max's for these two guys one is
negative 39 1 is negative 29 and so what
we want to see in this case is we want
to see the higher z-value be in front so
a is the higher z value we want to see a
be the thing that want a to come out in
front we want to see them intersect they
do so that's good we take the two
indices we say a's and front bees and
back at the moment that happens to be
the correct sort order the initial guess
so we don't want to swap them here and
we don't so that's good we create a new
edge we we push it on there we take a
look at what the front whatever the
fronts sprite actually is that's going
to be node a and then we say well a is
the one in front B is the one in back
here
her and then we say okay whoever was
previously in the slot as the first edge
in for the for the front most bright
it's going to get replaced with our new
edge and we're going to daisy-chain
these on right so that looks roughly
correct to me right and what we should
see when we do this here is we should
see only one time when is in front of
fails and that's on the last one right
that's when that's actually going to
happen and there it is yep and so on
this one it flips and that's because I
changed the order of those guys and so
now exactly the same thing is going to
happen here right we're just going to
come through and do exactly the same bit
where we create these edges and so
that's all fine I you know it's not the
best it's an N squared blowout of stuff
like I said but you know that's the part
that will have to add that will have to
make better later so once we create
those it looks like we're putting the
correct edges in there for the most part
so I think the next thing to do is to
take a look at what happens when we walk
the graph to figure out why we're not
getting what we expect to get right so
here we go I'm going to go into walk
sprite graph we're going to prep our
things like you know preparing the out
index array we haven't put anything in
it yet we're going to step through here
we're going to start with the first node
we're going to call recursive walk we're
going to verify that we haven't visited
it and then we're going to say that we
have visited it right now this first
this first person here shouldn't have
any edges coming into it it should only
have edges going out of it because it's
the frontmost thing so presumably we we
see an a you know a next edge with same
front which we did we're going to want
to walk to what
the one is that's behind it and let's
just take a look at what that index
actually is all right here we are on
zero if I step in we stepped into 6 this
is exactly what we would have expected
the reason for that is these get pushed
on to that edge list so what we would
expect there is that index six which is
0 1 2 3 4 5 6 is this guy right here
right now that guy shouldn't really have
any there's nobody who's more behind
than him so in theory he shouldn't have
any edges and he doesn't so the first
thing that we tell the renderer to draw
right is whatever this guy's offset is
if that makes sense so the first thing
that we tell the render to draw is
number 6
although wait do I have that right yeah
I mean that seems correct alright so the
first thing that we tell it to draw is
number six we then do another recursive
walk and this time we've got five now
five should have an edge that goes to
six potentially which is what it does
however six has already been visited so
we skip it right so now we're going to
write five in there this is looking
eerily like it's working correctly so
I'm a little confused as to why we're
seeing the results that we are seeing
again it'll skip six here so you know
that that looks naively like it did
roughly the correct thing all of these
guys should now actually be drawn so
it'll skip all of these because
everything is overlapping so the first
graph walk does the correct thing and
similarly if I look now it out index
array oops I guess there's not really a
lot of way that I can tell exactly what
that is but yeah I I think that does go
in the order that i would expect because
they're going to go in increasing order
right except for the last one which we
moved right which is this guy so that
looks exactly like what I would have
expected like exactly so I have to admit
I'm a little confused about why I'm
getting weird results there that looks
like a correct ordered sort to me and
and I'm not sure I'm not sure where I
went wrong so I gotta have to push
forward a little bit maybe I'll see
something in here I hope so i don't want
to have to leave this as a cliffhanger
for the weekend let's take a look at the
sordid indices array yeah so again that
looks that looks pretty good right i
mean that looks to me like what i would
expect I come through here and I say all
right what's the what's the entry we're
on I'm going to take
that's not what I expected to see and 30
because we overload entry here that's a
little bit of a bizarre catch but okay
there's that entry is 512 168 224 283 36
so those all look you know that that all
looks quite good to me so that is that
is quite puzzling because that looked
like everything was working correctly so
I think we're gonna have to step it up a
notch because I'm clearly wrong about
that and I'm going to need some way of
labeling these things in a way that I
can more clearly tell what's going on so
we did have a way of doing this if I
remember correctly when we do our render
entries and where were those let's see
so inside here we did have a thing for
debug tagging right when we do handmade
slow and I don't really know that we
have anything in particular right now
that we are putting in the debug tag
though but we can we set a group debug
tagged as we go so what I'm going to do
inside the intro layers bit here is I'm
going to go ahead and just verify what
these all are by when we actually let's
see where they are update play intro
cutscene rendered layered scene so here
is our rendering where we loop through
each of the scene layers and do our
little dance right what I want to do
here is before we actually issue the
bitmap call I'm going to go ahead and
set the render group debug tag not to
equal the layer index just so I can
verify that I actually know what it was
right and so you know it starts at one
and and so if I go back to my cut scene
I can sort of say which one of these is
which I can look at the debug tag for
any entry and I can see you know I can
see what it is if that makes sense now
similarly that's going to be a little
bit of a pain in the butt for us to read
and the reason for that is because the
sort key is not in a good place for that
that makes sense because sorry should
stay or key we're looking at the sort
keys and we don't have access to the
render group entry header in a
convenient way at that
point but what I can do pretty trivially
there is I can just say like okay put
the debug tag in both of these things
right and so in the case where we're in
the handmade slow path then when we're
putting stuff in yer I can say well
alright I you know keep the header and
the entry so I can do it like this both
having the debug tag there we go so now
if i come through here i should be able
to see this going again the same way but
now the debug tags I think well let me
make sure I'm in the right part of the
scene here there we go now if i come
through and I take a look at these I
should be able to see the debug tags on
them just to make sure so there's the
debug tag of eight that's exactly what I
thought I was going to see right
remember I said I think they'll be in
reverse order and so off we go I don't
really care about this because i thought
this function was working correctly so
not to learn anything new by looking at
that unfortunately at the moment so what
I want to do is look at this when we
actually go to build the output order I
just want to see when i do the output
what do I actually what order do I
actually output in so here we're about
to output somebody and so what I want to
know is who is that somebody so the
first thing that we're going to output
debug tag wise is debug tag too so
looking back here at the cutscene debug
tag too would be this that's a perfectly
reasonable choice give up tech 3 is this
that's exactly what i thought four five
six and when we get to the end we should
output number eight right yeah I'm sorry
numbers one yes
so uh the only thing that I can think of
well we'll we'll take a look at one more
thing but so if I go ahead and run there
we go we're still obviously not getting
the correct drawer too though because
I've just seeing this giant thing in my
face so the question is what if we take
a look at it the other way round so this
is how it was before and it was
rendering properly what does it out put
in that case right because now we should
see it out putting something something
wrong I mean I mean we should be able to
see it out putting something other than
the draw out or we saw last time and so
let's take a look at that so the first
thing out well you know what I think we
might be in a in the gap initially let
me just make sure we get into the there
we go so the first thing in Ephesus new
book tag one that's what we expect two
three four five six seven eight so in
both cases it seems to be doing exactly
what I think it should be doing so again
this is almost like I talked about
yesterday this is one of those bugs
we're clearly one of my assumptions is
wrong because I have verified that the
code does exactly what I wanted the code
to do right I've looked at what the code
is doing and it does what I want so that
means there's something happening that's
probably relatively simple but that I am
not remembering or thinking about
correctly in terms of how the
surrounding code works such that what I
think the correct output of this code is
actually doesn't yield the correct
results right so i have to go kind of
figure out what that is and we're pretty
much out of time here but you know i'm
going to take out just a quick look now
that i've actually verified the best
case the interesting thing to me here is
sort of looking at how that sort is
operating what's interesting about it is
moving the things around
I'm wondering if my indexes are not what
I'm thinking they are quite correctly
right because if you think about how
this code is working I have this notion
of a sort sprite bound and that's the
thing that I'm actually sorting and at
this point it's gotten a little bit out
of hand like the offset blah blah blah
all that stuff to a certain extent I
think we can probably simplify this down
a little bit after we're done getting
this working but anyway I've got these
sorts bright bounds in those sorts of
right bounds where they're coming from
is inside the render group when we do a
push render element where's that at when
we do a push render element we push
these in pairs so I push the header I
put a push on like the the information
about the render the thing that needs to
get rendered and then i create the sort
sprite entry for it and its offset is
wherever the push buffer is at the
moment so it's wherever it's this right
it's where the it's where the the push
buffer actually goes so that's kind of a
index into it the thing you know
whatever I'm sorting that's that's
what's supposed to happen there right so
I've got all of those guys stacked up
and then when I come into the render
portion of things that I'm trying to
sort them all when I do my walk I'm I'm
sort of writing out the index of who at
whomever I'm ons whatever the offset is
that was recorded with that sprite bound
which is just a pointer you know it's
basically like an offset from the
beginning of the push buffer into the
the thing that actually needs to get
rendered right so what I'm trying to
figure out is since it looked to me like
changing the order in which those things
were changing the order of the of the of
pushing these things clearly change the
result the out the rendered result but
did not appear to actually change the
order in which I was drawing them
that was really pretty weird you know
what I mean I just I'm not sure I
understand how that was super possible
uh very very confusing I know what it
was right these don't actually contain
the bitmap IDs so that's actually pretty
basic yeah so moving this here just
means that this lip yet okay that makes
perfect sense since I don't put the
bitmap IDs in here they just correspond
directly to the thing that's in the file
moving this here just basically had the
effect of making all the layers be the
wrong settings right so that's actually
not a test I can do fortunately doing
that test did make me verify that we
actually are doing the correct sorting
so I guess in some sense now I know the
sword is working at least nominally
properly for a bunch of things stacked
on top of each other it worked correctly
that doesn't really tell me why it's
failing in the more complex scene
unfortunately so I guess we're going to
have to move up a level of complexity
here and start to look at what happens
in a more complicated scenario no one
ever said it was going to be easy okay
so that's fine that's actually good I'm
I'm okay with that it took me a little
too long it's been one of those days it
stick it's taken me a little bit too
long perhaps to figure out that that's
not a cause for concern but I'm happy we
step through it and watched it work
correctly so I want to re-enable this
stuff but I need to set us up for next
week in order to because we want you
know we're going to want to leave
ourselves ready to go for next week
getting the getting the sort stuff to
bugged and sped up I want to trim out a
bunch of stuff so instead of you know
all those extra screens I'm just going
to do one screen first
because and this is what i assumed to
would be the case uh just on just as one
screen the sorting is wrong right so
hopefully we can now kind of do it you
know winnow away the number of things
that are going on here to make it so
that we can quickly test the sorting in
in some easier way right so if i look at
what's happening first of all i could do
some fairly straightforward stuff trying
to see here when we do add standard room
and add wall and all that stuff i'm
thinking maybe one thing i could do is
say well okay obviously i can i could if
zero out all this stuff so now we just
have the hero right and it also looks
like well i'm interested to know if i go
into a standard room and i remove all
the Z tiles I'm interested to know what
happens so let's see here
so in here while we are adding stuff if
I just say you know what don't ever
actually create any ground identities
please
that is not what I would have expected
so somehow there are no clip wrecks all
of a sudden
I'm not exactly sure why not
tell me more because the presumably
there should always be at least one clip
wrecked right or is it not the case that
we always push a clip wrecked on at the
outset well let's take a look so inside
handmade render group when we do begin
render group what do we do about clip
Rex and I guess the other question is is
clip Brecht serio something that we were
special casing before in some other way
so it does look like we always expect
there to be at least one clip wrecked
right and it looks like when we do
perspective or orthographic we always at
least push one clip wrecked on so I'm
not sure exactly why it that suggests
that nobody is ever actually calling
perspective orthographic so I'm kind of
interested to see since I know
perspective should be getting called how
did we end up with no clip Rex so there
is current clip rectangle X right we
push the clip wrecked on there come
through here and we do whatever it is
we're doing and we can even see what
would it be render group so where's the
commands there's the commands so you can
see the commands here here's the current
clip rekt count is 1 so when we come
through here let's let's go ahead and
skip to the end we've got eight clip Rex
we're going to come through here after
having done that and temporary memory
checking our arenas all is good their
output some sound not like we played
anything and then that works fine ok so
now what is it the second time through
that we crash I guess so I know that I'm
passing in the render commands here
they'll start out with no clip Rex right
so I guess what happens there is if I
remove everything that the hero could
possibly stand on I guess the hero can't
be added so we pop back out and I'm
assuming that means we sort of exit the
cutscene here and we end up in a state
where we do play title screen
and i'm not sure i don't i guess i don't
know why we would ever get a case where
nobody calls a clip rekt push like at
some point presumably someone is going
to call perspective but i guess maybe
not always and apparently that's that's
my bad that's on me update and render
title screen it does a clear here but
you know what's interesting it never
actually sets the screen does it it's
getting into render group from somebody
else so the question is that the render
group ever actually have like any kind
of orthographic anything called I guess
it doesn't so this is just a straight-up
bug actually I don't really love the way
that works I feel like that's really
error-prone I feel like to a certain
degree when we call begin render group
I'm not really sure I understand why
begin render droop can't be the thing
that takes the screen size right like I
don't really know why that is and if we
take a look at the pixel width stuff I
guess it's just because we didn't want
to save it but there's no real reason
why we can't save that information you
know what I mean so it kind of feels
like that wants to be something that
gets that just gets initialized properly
inside begin render group like it seems
like it seems like that wants to move
here so i think i'm just going to move
it here and see if there's any reason
why we can't do that if that makes sense
especially since the screen area never
actually changes right it's not like
that's something that changes depending
on which projection we're using the
screen area stays the screen area and so
here you know if these functions want to
know that piece of information well they
can get it pretty easily right it can
easily get the pixel width yeah or the
pixel height without really having to do
much work you can just say oh that's the
under group
like so yeah and I guess these don't
have any real reason not to be our tues
so that seems reasonable to me let's see
if the rest of the code agrees because I
don't know if it does and then
furthermore that means this can just
automatically do the push for clip the
push clip wrecked at the outset and now
we're not in an invalid state ever which
is much better
none of the three overloads oh is that
so better apparently not oh you were
talking about this weren't you here we
go um that doesn't need to happen
anymore so perspective now doesn't need
to do that orthographic doesn't need to
do that yeah and so we need oh well
that's right below us there we just need
render commands with so that just seems
better all around now we saw the fact
that I deleted everything that our hero
could possibly stand on which isn't
going to be good it's going to kick us
out of the main game code so that's a
problem but at least we found a bug in
the process you got to make things a
little cleaner now and then if I pop
back now to where we were doing this and
I go to add standard room I'm going to
go ahead and give our hero one thing to
stand on that's because I'm a very
generous person obviously I'm going to
let him stand on one thing so I'm going
to say well okay get rid of the else
Clause but given the one tile at 22 and
there we go
so the interesting thing to note and
this is why I wanted to run this test is
it appears that our sort is handling our
Y sprites just fine like you'll notice
the whole left and right side of the
screen the trees are all correct on the
other hand RZ sprites are all messed up
so that tells me a piece of information
that I wanted to know so i think we'll
be able to make a little bit more
progress on this pretty soon but i'm way
over time so I'm going to end it now ok
I don't sorry I don't really have much
time for Q&amp;A I am yeah I'm Way over time
but I'm glad we got that straightened
out there
alright so let's defer questions until
monday when i'll have a chance to kind
of go over things a little bit more but
it looks like everything is now in in
reasonable shape and i think the sword
is sort of working but i think we have
our z comparison a little bit wrong so i
think we should be able to kind of like
get that corrected it not too much time
anyway thank you very much for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
with the series at home you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero or
it comes with a source code and so if
you want to follow along that's a great
way to do it we also have forum site you
can go to if you want to ask questions a
patreon page if you want to support the
video series we also have a schedule
about the tweets schedule you and a past
episodes guide if you're trying to catch
up on old editions of the series will be
back here next week probably starting
Monday check the tweet bot if you do
want to know when that is until then
have fun programming and I will see you
guys on the internet take it easy
everyone