hello everyone and welcome to what would
have been a episode of handmade hero but
Linux ruined it so instead we're
probably just gonna have really short
stream today and maybe I'll boot up
handmade ray and play around with that a
little bit because I'm not sure what
else we could do since we've wasted
basically all of our time trying to get
Linux to capture audio and mostly
failing although I guess maybe we
slightly succeeded a little very little
bit I don't remember where we left off
on our ray tracer so you know it's it's
a pretty straightforward little simple
program that we wrote as a stream test
one time and you can kind of see there's
very little in it right we just sort of
have a ray tracer and then we have a
couple support functions that are just
like some math functions and stuff that
we needed and then we have like some
Lane based stuff here so you can see
we've got a you know a thing for sim D
where we can be like 8x wide or 4x wide
and what we do inside here is we can
actually sort of pick which one that we
want in the actual build I believe we
had a way of specifying what width we
were using I don't actually remember if
it was in the build maybe it's not in
the build I don't remember but basically
we just pick between them so that we can
sort of say do we want to use avx2 or do
we want to just use sim D and again I
really just don't remember how we were
picking that let me take a look and see
so it looks like it's just this pound of
fine here this Lane width so I guess we
could pick it in the de bill in the
build if we wanted to we could do this
right and if I just make that predicated
now we could define Lane within the
build and if we don't define Lane within
the bill that'll just default to doing 8
for now right but if if I go take a look
at where we were at with the ray tracer
because I don't really remember in terms
of running it I believe what we did is
inside this directory here what we would
do we yeah we actually had sort of a
procedure we would do where we would
list like how we were doing on every day
right back and we did it I mean there's
only four days but so if you take a look
here you can see we would like record
how long it took to do the ray tracing
and
like what the quality level was for each
of these and how many total bounces
there were and what the performance was
and all this stuff right so we kind of
had a pretty good setup here just in
terms of like you know starting to
structure the raytracer and here was I
don't know why that's I know what that's
doing there hello there we go so you can
see like these are some of the tests we
did on our ray tracer they're just you
know some basic spheres that we put in
here and it produces pretty reasonable
output but there's no lighting function
in it so it's really like we didn't
really have anything that actually tried
to do any kind of real lighting you can
see here we've got like sort of glassy
reflections by just controlling how at
versus regular reflections right by
controlling how spread out it was but we
really don't have much in the way of of
any real lighting in there so I think
the thing that we kind of stopped on was
we never actually produced any real you
know when we actually cast out Ray's we
just did the part where we see whether
we hit things and then if we hit things
we you know bounce but we never actually
did anything that tried to be more you
know did any important sampling or
computed any material properties or any
of this sort of stuff other than I think
just a parameter for like how glassy it
was or something like that right and so
probably what we would need to play
around with next is we we'd probably
have to play around with the part where
we actually you know figure out how to
do some kind of a of you know some some
kind of a reasonable argument for
lighting and you can see that the way
that we broke things up here is we just
have here's a tile thing right we would
say look let's get let's aim at a
particular pixel let's cast something
out in a direction using this cast
sample rays and then we'll just write
the the thing back right so if we want
to try and go a little further with this
we would probably start editing this
function which is you know great
oops I can't cast sample rays oh it
keeps having simple this is the function
that we'd really be looking at here and
we could you know we could start to work
that out
so let me go ahead and try getting the
basis of basics of this running again
and I don't know if we actually made a
batch file that would run it or not it
looks like maybe we didn't and so we
probably want to make a batch file that
runs it
probably in the derated directory I
don't know let me go ahead and see what
happens when I actually run this thing
because I don't remember what we
programmed it to do either so it looks
like that just kind of does some ray
casting which is good and there it goes
and then it's done and you know there's
the there's the output that all looks
pretty straightforward let me see if it
generated a reasonable bitmap I guess
it's just that test up it map yeah so I
think it's pretty reasonable we can run
it we get some output and off we go
and I'm presumably we can crank down
that sampling level as well if we want
to so meaning we could change it so that
it out put it in image more quickly but
maybe had like less anti-aliasing cuz if
you look in you know if you look and
zoom in here you can see we're casting
like a lot of rays even just you can see
the level of anti-aliasing we're getting
there that's coming entirely from you
know just jittering the the ray cast
when we cast the Ray out at the initial
setup we aren't using blue noise right
now I think we're just using white noise
so that that sampling is not great but
you can still see that we're just
casting it a heck of a lot of rays and
everything comes out pretty smooth here
right so so I think we're certainly well
above where we would need to be sampling
level wise all right so moving on let's
take a look here at what we can do so
you can see in the cast the sampler a
caster here you can see we have array
index and we're just going over how many
Ray's we want to cast and you can see
that we're calling a random bilateral
function here soap mm-hmm
if you take a look at how the random
bilateral is looking at working you can
see us doing our are sort of how were
you know how we're generating our random
numbers you can see that it's sort of
like three dependent X ORS right and I'm
guessing that that's probably pretty
good I mean it we're probably going to
be able to stick with that for a while
I don't know that we're gonna need
better source of entropy we could do a
little work on that but like I said I
think that's probably fine and probably
all we really need to do is work on our
bouncing so if you see here we do a
bunch of plain equations and we test all
of the planes in the system to see to
what extent they are hit by the by the
rates that we're casting and then we go
through our spheres and we ready cast
the spheres to see if they're hit and
then when we're done with that all we do
is say well now that we're done you know
now that we've figured out where we're
gonna hit we just load up whatever the
material property is at that hit which
we've saved you can see hit matte index
here and once we know that then we are I
think good to go for doing our light
calculation so you can see the light
calculation actually just happens and
here you can see there's a cosine
attenuation term which is just there
because of the you know the light shaft
the the incidence of the light shaft
against the geometry is gonna have a
cosine fall-off and then you can see us
just multiplying whatever that
reflective color is there and then what
we do as I think is we just change the
raid direction right so you can see it
here we do essentially a interpolation
between what a pure bounce would be and
what a random bounce would be and we use
a basically whatever that glossy
coefficient is there to determine how
pure of a bounce versus how random
abouts we want right and you know again
the reason we say these are not accurate
permutations I assume is just because
this this part here this is just a
generic 3d offset right that's being
applied it's not really guaranteed to
have any particular distribution over
the Hemisphere we haven't really looked
at that in fact we're not really even
looking at what the hemisphere even is
right at this point and so this part
right here is also pretty inaccurate
just in terms of that but it's probably
also again not really the weakest part
of the system anyway so then we go and
we
we're gonna loop basically so that you
can see this thing here it just goes
until the max bounce count and I believe
it will just stop if it doesn't hit
something so like it'll bounce as many
times as it can and then you know it'll
it'll end after that so it's trying to
hit a light source at some point or at
least it's hoping it hits a light source
at some point right and if it does it
gets a color if it doesn't then it's
just a useless ray that will contribute
nothing right in the sense it
contributes something which is to say
that no lights coming from that
particular set of bounces so that's
something but again not you know not
particularly interesting to a certain
extent so the other thing that we don't
do here is we don't do any light source
targeting so you can see we don't ever
try on purpose to like hit anything
either and so that's a that's a little
bit of a problem too because if we
wanted to start having some hard shadows
right so if we wanted something that was
sort of like a sunlight or a specific
light source and you can see we have a
light source here this red light source
for example we're not really doing
anything in particular to try and make
sure that we look at those light sources
particularly well either so there's that
too so I don't know what the first thing
we probably want to do is I think one
thing we may need is some exposure
control so one of the things that again
also that we're not doing here is we're
not actually taking into account the
fact that we probably want to compute
light values like how much light we
actually have and then we need to expose
the image right we need to basically
take those light files and map them into
the visual space somehow probably using
some kind of a nonlinear mapping right
and right now we're not really doing
that either we do do an sRGB in code but
that's not the same thing that's just
taking a set of light fires and encoding
them in so I'm not sure for example what
we set the light value of that red light
to be I'm gonna look at where we create
the world
I guess that's here you can see the
materials that we've set up and if I
look at the material structure you can
see in here we've got an emit color and
so you can see here we're emitting some
stuff
this zero is probably the sky right
that's that background emission and
here's like that that red sphere and so
you know it's set to four which is like
you know somewhat bright light but we
don't really know what these units are
we haven't specified them you know if I
set that light up to 20 I have no idea
what would happen right but I can go
ahead and run it here and see right but
again like because we don't really have
any idea what those units are or how we
don't really even have any idea of how
we think they should behave it's pretty
difficult to really say right so let me
take a look I assume I don't have this
opener I don't let me take a look at
what difference that creates so you can
see here like if I was to turn that up
you get more you can see that there's
more light coming in to the sort of
parts that bounce and hit that but again
like you know if we looked at what was
happening here I would say - and you can
see it's brighter in there as well but
one of the interesting things about it
is you do see not that much light coming
into these services here which honestly
you know probably it should have and and
one of the things that I think is you
know possibly a problem there right is
if we don't really know much about that
sampling so if we don't really have much
of a way to have that sampling take
effect I don't know you know I don't
know if really we it feels like we
should probably see more red in there
but to a certain extent we may not
because we just since we're just
completely randomized bounces it doesn't
really know that it needs to look at
that light source particularly much now
on the other hand that part does seem to
be catching a fair amount of the light
coming in so you know I don't know again
just playing around with it a little bit
to see where we're at in terms of what
what we're doing here let me run this
one more time I'm going to take a look
at what's happening here with the width
if I just keep cranking that that up
more and more and again you can sort of
see like all right so in here still you
get very very little of that red in here
you get a lot of it but it feels like I
don't really know to what extent that
that does
feels super accurate to mean and maybe
it is you know I don't know but it
doesn't feel super accurate to me it
feels like maybe it's it's again under
weighting sort of the light that's
coming from there and I don't know it
could be possibly to because I don't
really know very much about this surface
I didn't I don't know if that what
that's actually set to we could take a
look and see what the plane is set to so
it looks like that has a material index
of one which is this and again that so
that just makes me suspicious right
because if it's a perfectly diffuse
surface and it has a perfectly gray
reflectance you would again you would
think you would see more of that light
being shone kind of in here and again
maybe that's not true one of the things
you would do if you were actually you
know developing a ray tracer like this I
think is you would want to try and get
some references right so you'd maybe try
and use an established ray tracer to
render a trace the same scene or you do
maybe the Cornell box or something like
that right and so you know there's that
I'm kind of interested to see what
happens if I introduce some more planes
as well so for example here's you know
one plane equation that we were using if
I introduced another identical plane and
you can see here what the plane
structure looks like it's just the
normal the D value and the material
index so if I created another one that
lets say pointed down positive X and
then I move that backwards so you know
it was kind of maybe a little I don't
really know what our units are here so
I'm not again not sure it's been a while
since we've worked on this but if I just
place a plane somewhere which is what
I'm gonna do here and take a look at
what happens in you know in the case
where I get you can see it slowed down
by the way and the reason for that is
because now a lot more things will be
hitting that plane all right so there's
the plane and it you know it cuts
through here and you know everything
bounces kind of off of it I will say it
doesn't make a lot of sense to me
exactly how that plane looks it looks
like I do we have a really weirdly
eccentric sort of projection value
because you would think that if it was
maybe it's really far away I guess but
it doesn't really feel like it should
have been quite so angled right because
this is directly onto the x-axis I don't
know where our camera is though so
that's so it looks like our camera is
it's supposed to be at 0 in X right I
mean that's that's what that suggests to
me so I wonder if we're just very
eccentric here because that doesn't feel
quite right to me now maybe it's because
our units are you know maybe that plane
is actually very far away so let me try
and let me just see what happens if I
just move that less away I also wonder
do we have a thing for input inputting
the Rays per pixel so we can take
quicker snapshots that might be a good
thing to add while we're at it so like
in here do we actually you know do this
art count at all it doesn't look like we
do in fact raise 4 pixel is just hard
coded so we might want to do is take it
have some way of inputting the max or
sorry the Rays per pixel just so this
would go faster in those cases okay so
that looks a lot better to me so I guess
I just it's probably because that we're
in meters or something roughly so you
can see that that makes a little more
sense to me not sure what's going on in
here
I guess that's just where we intersect
so this is that plane right and you can
see it doing a reflection of what it
sees right let me say this is that
sphere I mean and this is where the
sphere like intersects with it right so
that's just you know I guess sort of
what you would expect at least I believe
that's what's going on there right that
would be where that that's the sphere
line right there so it intersects like
right about there right um all right so
let's try to improve how we're doing the
lighting here and the first thing I'd
like to do is maybe start to have the
light very based a little bit on
direction and again I think we're gonna
have to start putting in in order to
decrease the noise we're gonna have to
start putting in some important sampling
just to figure out like where light
sources tend to be coming from and to
try to sample those a little bit more
specifically
then then we were sampling the other
ones right I also think if we don't have
pure red light which is you know you're
never really gonna have a pure red light
I'm curious what this would do to the
scene as well let's go ahead and add
that so I can I can make this raise per
pixel be something that we can configure
on the command line as well so I'm gonna
go ahead and do this I'm gonna say like
if our count equals two rays for pixel
equals atoi on that args one so that'll
just allow us to very quickly you know
at the command line if I do this will
get 1024 if I want to I can say Oh
actually just use 256 right or some
other small number and that just allows
us to take a sample much quicker and
it'll just be noisier right so again it
makes reasonable sense and like as you
can see it's even with how crappy it is
it still looks okay right
like in other words it does seem to be
doing a good job of producing lighting
that you know it's at least somewhat
plausible
I just don't know to what extent I
really believe that that it feels like
it's under counting the lighting in some
places here I don't know that's just
that's just a my intuition I feel like
there's a little bit of weirdness going
on there so let's go ahead and see what
we want to do yeah going forward here so
assuming that we want to improve the
lighting quality a little bit when we
take a look at how we're doing our
bounces here I guess what we'd like to
do is have some way to of in here
specifying some kind of reflectance
function that actually makes some sense
right and I don't know if there's these
days I feel like there's some pretty
standardized brdf functions floating
around out there and so maybe what we'll
do I guess this is actually official so
I'll I'll keep it in the search history
maybe what we'd like to do is look for a
standardized brdf I think Disney
standardized on one
and I don't really remember exactly what
they were but I was thinking you know we
could we could just see if what what
that what that would be
because I thought there was a
simplification when they did and I
figured if we could tie into a standard
one then that would make it easier to
put in like I figured like they probably
have yeah so I think this is the thing I
was thinking of right so we could
probably do something where we could
sort of tie into something that someone
had already standardized and then just
use that right so you can see here like
they've got kind of a set of parameters
that they decided you know to use for
their films which I don't know if maybe
that makes everything look like a
plastic Pixar movie but you know prop
presumably not presume ibly they tuned
it that way because they like it that
way right but I don't know so I'm just
kind of looking to see do they have a
simplified like yeah like it looks like
that right um but I wonder if they have
one of these that is simplified down and
they say like look here's a material
library for it or whatever right and
looks like they don't summarize this
very well but our base diffuse model is
this so they basically say one plus
fd9 t minus 1 1 minus cosine theta to
the 5th power ok 1 plus FD 90 minus 1 1
minus cosine to the fifth power as well
over the bait the base color over PI so
I'm assuming it looks like none of this
it looks like they really only just have
that one roughness parameter and then
the base color parameter so this would
be pretty easy right for us to put in
there just looking at it and so the base
color is I was just the color the
roughness value is this one and you can
see right it goes from here to there I'm
not 100% sure where's the rest of the
stuff for a specular and do they
actually talk about that specular D so
here's their specular stuff and I'm
assuming then we combine all these terms
they're combining all these terms in the
standard way which I believe they listed
up here right I'm guessing now that's
just the general that's just the general
micro facet do
so do they break that down again or do
they just use it that way it's always
hard to read papers on stream
so I don't know I'm gonna say let's
let's see if we can go for this maybe
this is a bad idea
you know here's the Disney principle
here's the Disney principled brdf in a
shader toy right so yeah like if we look
here it is right if we look this looks
like exactly what it says in the paper
right and see here this is basically the
exactly what we want to do just gonna
make sure that it actually looks like
what I think it would look like
so I mean it looks like they are
literally just doing that alright so
let's try this and and we'll just try to
you know redo these parameters ourselves
right so let's do the Disney let me see
what the best summary one is I can find
of it it may just be this paper but
maybe there's another place that we can
look we'll just grab some of these
things here what's this so here's some
reference code to looks like this code
is the actual Disney one like this is
copyright Disney right so the this
presumably is what they actually think
the code should look like right now this
is a little bit obfuscated right because
we don't know exactly how they worked
these out so you know we may have to go
back and kind of work it through
ourselves to make sure that we know what
we're actually doing in each of these
cases cuz if we were to just like use
this code directly we wouldn't really
know what we were doing right because
it's just like all rolled into one
but we can at least use that as a
reference I suppose separately right
let's take a look here I assume this is
the same PDF we were looking at
because this is just the same thing
right yeah alright um so I think we have
enough information here to just kind of
yeah I don't know that doesn't look
pretty good I'm hoping this is a good
good idea maybe this is a stupid idea
I don't know I'm hoping this is a good
idea but but I don't know you can also
see here like here's like here's another
reference to implementation that
somebody else did and this is an Arnold
right so that's the standard I think
this is an Arnold is that right so this
is that's the standard ray tracer that
like most people use in like film right
you see that a render man so I think
we're all right we can kind of proceed
from here so let's take a look at what's
going on so this right here they're
listing the standard micro facet model a
micro facet model for those of you don't
know what that is
it's basically saying look what really
happens with light is you know you've
got photons and they hit a surface and
the surface we think of as flat is
actually made up of a lot of little fine
surface detail where all the atoms are
arranged in particular ways and so what
we want to do is talk about the actual
like small surface geometry and how that
reflects photons that will tell us how
to actually compute you know a lighting
function and as you can see here it's
like well there's some diffuse term you
know what I mean that we don't know what
it is you can see here it's like of
unknown form right and then you've got
this term here which actually tells you
something about the way the lighting
comes in and you've got a bunch of
Thetas in there and the reason that you
have a bunch of Thetas in there is
because of course you have the direction
that the lights coming in and the
direction that the lights going out
right and you can see here that they've
kind of defined how they're going to
talk about it they say if a surface
friction can occur between a given light
vector L so L is the incoming ray you
know that's gonna bounce out view
vectors V so that's the direction we're
sampling you don't have to think of
these as light and view you don't ever
think of them as like the light source
and the camera you can think of them as
sent instead of just like what direction
are we trying to figure out how much
light is going out and what direction
are we looking in to see how much light
is coming in right so you can think of
them more that way right so anyway there
must exist some portion of surface our
micro facet with a normal aligned
halfway between l and V because that's
what's going to reflect right and so
here's how they create that vector using
H and then they say all right here's the
general form for it we have a D function
that's going to be based on the half
vector and F function that's going to be
based on something that they did not
define why did they not define D I'm
missing something
yeah great they totally left it out it
put up here anyway L&amp;V which we just
talked about so I I don't know what why
do they not define D they I mean we can
go back to here and look at what it is
but that's really weird don't you think
oh there it is here it is here it is
theta D is the difference between L and
the half vector so basically that we can
just compute right all right so most
physically plausible models are not
subscribed to microphones forum and can
still be interpreted as microphone
models and they have a distribution
function if Rennell factor and some
additional factor they could consider
geometric shadowing factor geometric
shadowing factor just means like how
much the micro geometry actually like
prevents photons from hitting other
parts of the micro geometry right the
only real difference Cree micro facet
models and other models is whether they
include the explicit one over term right
which is this right here for models that
don't include that factor an implied
shadowing factor can be determined by
multiplying the model by this after
factoring out so okay
that all makes reasonable sense right I
mean it doesn't tell us anything because
it hasn't told us anything about what
these functions actually are but at
least we know the structure of it now
right like that's not so mysterious now
because we broke it down into what these
things actually mean for those of you
always ask like how do you read papers
like slowly is the answer right so
anyway here's them showing a bunch of I
think the I'm guessing Morrell 100 is
because I probably knew at some point
but it's probably just a giant capture
set where they took actual materials and
put them under like gonio reflectometer
so it's this thing right
I and what you can do with a goniometer
is basically you can put something into
it and what its gonna do is it's gonna
have like a very accurate like photo
detector right and a very accurate
photon emitter and it's going to try and
like shoot photons at the surface from a
very specific angle and collect how many
photons come out at a very specific
angle and so it can build basically a
complete model of how a particular
surface reflects light right and you can
do this in different ways right you can
collect at multiple places at the same
time you can build like basically like a
poor man's gonna reflectometer by
basically just putting cameras and light
sources in various places and seeing
what happens but basically like that's
what happens right and for our purposes
because we're just trying to do like
computer graphics not actual simulation
like we're not trying to do physics here
we're trying to do like pretty pictures
we don't really need like a real go neo
flecked reflectometer or a real brdf and
that's exactly what disney's talking
about here they're basically saying look
let's start with the real world and now
the real world looks and then what we're
gonna do is we're gonna try and figure
out what setup parameters we can give
artists to make them give them the
ability to create services that appear
like they work and exist in a real world
like the one we're used to but so that
they can be more artistic about it and
not actually have to worry about whether
it's really simulating light or what
material is really on you know Woody's
shoe in Toy Story or something right
so Merle is a set of samples that are
captured right so you can see here they
were taking paints woods metals fabrics
stones rubber plastic right all kinds of
things and apparently you can just get
this right and you can you know use it
if we actually looked at that here right
you can see the Merle database you can
you can see the actual results here I
guess you could probably just download
these right so if you look here here's a
binary of each of these things and you
know honestly if we wanted to we could
just go that route it's kind of
interesting maybe we should
I don't know what the format is here we
could take a look at like the readme and
see if it says see here here's the
reader right so you know maybe we go
that route here's here's an example
right you can see it doing the read here
so it calls read brdf read brdf
basically says like alright you know f
read this thing in and you can see like
there's a theta a so there's two angles
right and then it says yeah why does it
how many is it reading here dims so it's
just reading the dimensions of it oh I
see nevermind sorry it's just reading in
first counter that says how many of them
there are and then it reads the whole
thing right so you know what this seems
a little more fun to me right because we
don't have any artists right now and so
we can't do anything so maybe we just do
this this seems a lot better so what if
we just downloaded this let's see what
the license is on it let's see here into
a commercial product so we're not making
a commercial product so I think we're
okay there right and presumably we can
just download these and use them now
maybe there's one that's more permissive
that would let people use it in a
commercial product I don't actually know
let me take a look
um doesn't look like it I don't know if
anyone can think of one maybe we can use
that but you know I'm assuming that they
would be okay with this as an
educational use since this is literally
what we would be using it for is
educational purposes so I'm assuming
that they're ok with that and we can
include the copyright notice in there as
well and actually I don't have to
distribute it in fact that's even better
I just won't include it will just
download it and put it in a separate
directory and then anyone who wants to
can use it and that way it won't get
distributed with anything we do so even
if they don't like the fact that fact
it's okay so well we won't be distribute
well just show how to load it if you
wanted to so let's go in here and
download some of these things I don't
know if you have to literally download
them all manually that seems like a real
pain in the ass
pain in the butt not supposed to swear
but I don't know it doesn't look like
there's any way to download it as more
of a group so I'm gonna go ahead and
just download some of these here so in
fact let me take a look and see if is
there one that's particularly good I
don't actually know it doesn't look like
there's any way to see which ones are
which on here so let me go ahead and
download some of these so let's download
some of these here
let's take brass for example since it's
something we might have an idea about
let's take something it's like light red
paint um red fabric silver metallic
paint I don't know to layer gold to
layer silver if there's anything else we
want here grape
stick sounds good chrome alluminium
probably want some less exciting things
to green fabric light brown fabric
neoprene rubber seems okay now we've got
some right and then I don't see anything
here that says what the structure of it
is but since there's a brdf reader
involved here I'm assuming that we can
just go ahead and load this in it looks
like they have you know three parameters
here theta H theta D and 5 D I'm not
sure why you would have a three
parameter model but I guess that's
because you don't really need the
additional one I'm not sure but so we
probably want to look and see how these
are encoded because I'm not sure exactly
I guess we could try and reverse
engineer it from the code but it would
be nice if I could find some Doc's I
would rather be able to read about it
right like please reference the
following paper
a date of different reflectance model
let's take a look at that
all right so here is ah good good good
good
this is what we need we just needed
something right that would tell us what
we were supposed to interpret these
values as and so you can see here n is
clearly the surface normal of the thing
that we're reflecting off of so that
helps teal it looks like a tangent
vector to the surface so those are
pretty easy for us to understand and
yeah I don't know which ones they're
using okay so looks like this so they're
using F D and Phi D plus PI like I think
yeah so in here we're basically saying
all right 90 bins for H and D so H and D
looking here so there's H right Phi H
sorry there's H and there's Phi D theta
D so theta H theta D right it's a little
hard to read that diagram honestly not
sure where that ankles being measured
off of is I think it's being measured
off the half angle so I think theta D is
the is the drop down of Omega I here or
wait that's not a mega what is that
waita I don't know what that is
what letter is that it is Omega oh never
mind
it's like I don't know if there's a way
to I know there's way to digital but I'm
like I don't remember there being @w and
I was right it was Omega nevermind
shouldn't doubt myself I usually doubt
myself when it comes to math things I
just don't do it very often so it falls
out of the brain quickly they should use
this as the way to digital logo and just
say it's a new Greek letter called way
to alright anyway so Amiga I hear in
this case I think that's what theta D is
measuring and say to a just measuring
here and so let's see so they're
basically saying they they restrict this
by saying we're only going to sample for
four theta D right we're only going to
sample instead of allowing this to very
arbitrarily or I guess I should say this
Phi D here where they had
I don't know where that was
they don't actually show an original Phi
D it looks like but instead of allowing
it to very arbitrarily they're basically
saying alright we're going to pretend
that we always do 90 I'm sorry a PI
which would be a 180 right off of it so
I'd like them to show another diagram
there cuz I'm not sure exactly what they
mean by that they didn't actually show
it in the thing let's take a look let's
see found that specular Peaks were
difficult trip sent using the natural
coordinate system theta in theta out and
v diff and Phi diff again not really
talked about here I guess we have to go
read the reference paper for that which
would be unfortunate rather they just
said exactly what it was because again
I'm just having trouble with this last
term these two are obvious because they
actually drew them right
well even that's a little bit not great
but that's the angle from the normal to
the half vector right and that's the
angle from the half vector to the
outgoing but what is that maybe that's
just a really bad Phi well maybe that's
all it is maybe that's just a really bad
Phi oh yeah it is so never mind it's
just because they used a really weird
Phi here so never mind okay so we've got
it so basically what they're saying here
is like okay so Phi D in this case I
guess they're trying to measure the
angle of gosh it's kind of hard to read
that right you can see why I'm having
trouble with this diagram this angles
coming off we're saying Phi D is like
the angle around the like the rotation
angle around and then theta D is the
rotation this way so the
so basically like if you imagined this
was drawn as a plane we basically have
the rotation in the plane is Phi and
then the rotation like kind of in the
perpendicular like to bend it downward
is Theta D right I mean it looks like
that to me so if we were to look at what
this is showing here they're basically
saying like okay we are doing a plus Phi
I'm sorry or plus PI rotation here we're
saying that if we were to rotate this
thing 180 degrees meaning if we were
gonna you know basically like flip it
around here they're saying that we
believe the function will be the same so
we're not going to sample it with with
the flip I guess right so normally they
would have done 360 bins and now they're
doing 180 bins I guess I mean that's
that's how I read that I don't know how
you folks read that that's how I read
that so then we get our samples and off
we go and so then at that point what we
really just need to do is create
whatever these values would be right we
need to actually figure out what these
values are to feed into our function
here and then we can look them up right
so that's the that's the goal and we can
look them up in the actual table and
then have our reflectance which is going
to be very costly and probably slow
which is why I say we probably need to
you know use a simplified thing
eventually but I'd like to try using
this as our first thing so that we can
actually use real measured materials and
see what they look like so if we go
ahead and take this model and try to
implement it right what we're
effectively going to need is a 3d lookup
of this of this thing and we're gonna
need to do that we're gonna need to
construct what those parameters are
based on the reflectance that we end up
seeing so let's go back to the source
code here and and see
oops no no no no wait where's the wait
how come you can't undo closed tab
anymore
what happened that yes that did it
alright so taking a look at the the
source code here and brdf read so what
it looks like they have is just three
dimension values which tell us how many
of each thing there are and then there's
just exactly them and they've pre said
basically that they have to be this
exact resolution so I guess that makes
our job a little easier
because these values will actually just
be exactly correct right now I don't
know if we care about that part so much
but maybe for lookups it's good to have
it be that way
I doubt it matters that much but so for
the moment I think we will forego that
and and we'll we'll try to make it be a
little bit more arbitrary alright so
what I'm going to do here is take
material and I'm gonna have like a brdf
table and brdf table is just going to
have like account for these three things
and then it's going to have a values
pointer and we're just going to look
them up in here this table is just gonna
be very simple and each one of these
materials is going to be able to have a
brdf table pointer in it I guess like
this and so if we want to we can now
have each one of our materials have some
kind of a brdf with it in fact I guess
we don't really have to do it quite that
way what we could do is just put the
weld the actual table directly in there
right so we could have the brdf table
just exist like this and so we could do
is have it like so that we know where
there are not things or a light source
or not based on the admittance I guess
or I guess we could make the brdf table
itself have those emission values in
there I'm not sure how we
actually exactly do that I guess we
would have maybe some kind of a
information in here about how much light
is coming off versus how much light is
being reflected or something like that
but anyway I think that's all we would
really have to do so here we would we
know we're 90 90 360 in this case but
again I'm not going to hard-code that in
so I'm just gonna make a quick function
here that will load the brdf table into
memory and so if we want to load these
brdf tables we just can so here there's
going to be a like a load brdf like that
I believe we have internal right yes we
do so what I want to do is load this in
the RF 32s right or at least can be
represented as f 32s are they doubles in
this this world what are they so it
looks like they're doubles we don't
actually need doubles so I will probably
elect to convert them rather than yeah
rather than than not but what do I do
here is just say okay there's a load
brdf and and maybe we'll say load
Murrell because different people could
have different brdf formats so we'll say
this is a Murrell file since we know
that it's a Merl binary that comes from
them right so I'm gonna say that here's
the file name here's the file I'm gonna
do an F open on it and we want to read
it as a binary file so when to pass on
our B they're gonna go ahead and make
sure we put out errors and here I'm
print out if we can't open the file just
so the user knows you know you're in the
wrong directory or we didn't provide the
right files or who knows what so if I
open the actual file I'm gonna do an F
read to get the so the the actual
dimensions in there and again I'm gonna
want to give this a target like where do
you actually read this thing so I'll
call that the destination so in order to
do the F read you can see here there
it's just three integers apparently so
they literally just wrote like three
integers in a row out at the beginning
so all I should have to do is basically
read those into our intz here directly
presumably so we can just say like
there's the counts we're gonna do an F
read and the F read needs to take the
file pointer and the the in size but
otherwise it doesn't I don't think well
I'll do this the way they did it they
were saying look here here's the
destination that'll be the same we're
doing three intz I'm just gonna multiply
it out myself so I'm just gonna say look
it's gonna be the size of this thing
here and I'm gonna read one of them and
that's it it's the same exact thing oh
that was correct it's the same exact
thing they were doing but I just instead
of doing the multiply there I'm gonna
let C do the multiplication for me so
going to read those in then I'm going to
allocate the the amount of space I'm
going to need here so I know I need to
load the number of F 32 s that would be
implied by that basically three wide
three dimensional table so it's gonna be
desk count 0 times desk out 1 x desc
count 2 that's the entire thing what I'd
like to do here is say well we kind of
know we're gonna have to read this right
after we allocate it and we also know we
need to load in it as doubles actually
so we're gonna need two things here so
what I'm gonna do is say there's a total
count right so we have like a total
count value that would be
also I don't know that I want these in
so I think I'm gonna use these as you
32s instead so let's say there's a total
count here and then there'll be a couple
different total sizes so there's going
to be a total read size and that total
read size is just gonna be the total
count times size of a double right since
the next 64 like so and then there's a
total table size and that's going to be
a total count times a float so then what
we can do is allocate the total read
size and the total table size like so
and then I need to read and convert so
I'm going to do an F read into my temp
table of the total read size like this
and then I'm going to do a conversion
and so you can see here I'm just trying
to make this as simple as possible for
myself and that's just converting down
converting from a double which is way
more precision than we need into
something much simpler right so that
would presumably do it I'm gonna close
the file off here and I'm gonna free the
temp memory because we won't need it
anymore but that's about it
right um oops all right I think that's
all we really needed and so now we have
the ability to load these Merl binaries
I need to actually put them somewhere so
I don't actually know where that
downloaded to probably the desktop yep
I'm gonna grab all of these like so
and then I'm gonna go over to our W here
and I'm gonna go ahead and make in here
wanted a new folder I want a new folder
thank you I'm gonna make a moral
directory and I'm gonna go ahead and
paste this in there so now we've got our
Merle stuff here and I'm gonna go ahead
and try and load some of these up right
and just we'll go into the debugger and
and see if it works so when I go to OD
which will put us into debug mode I'm
gonna try and load some little Merle
binaries in for these things here so for
each of our materials I'm gonna try and
load in a Merle binary and and put it in
here we don't really know what these are
supposed to be and you know what no I
think about it wait I missed some I must
have missed something
oh yeah
so they I was gonna say they should be
red green and blue and there are so
there's three each
so it's RGB right so it is a little bit
different let me go ahead and fix that
first before we do any of this but we're
gonna go ahead and do Merle binary here
load Merle binary and I'm going to go
ahead and take these materials what I
might do is at first I might say let's
take some of the planes out here
I'm sorry take some of the spheres out
so we have a much simpler scene this way
we only have like one plane and one
sphere and that way we can just use
materials zero one and two and then
we'll load binary Zinn to each of those
don't ask me why I did that I meant this
and so this way I can target each of
these and just see if this works at all
so we can load materials into each of
these they're going to be like whichever
ones we want so maybe like grey plastic
can be sort of our base one here this
material zero I guess doesn't need one
right because it's not reflective it's
just the sky or whatever right load
Merle binary for this last guy here gray
plastic we'll use something more
reflective or interesting like Chrome
right and we'll just see if we can get
this working at all
so if we do that like I said we got to
expand this to be by threes and that
also means that the material should be
by threes as well so it should be like
this right and so then in here when I do
this malloc what I actually want is this
should be size of v3 and this should be
size of s 64 times three then when we do
the total count and we go through here I
guess we don't really have a V 64 but
that's okay and so when we go through
total count what we would want to do
here is actually step this like that and
we'd want to do something like this
so we'd want to do is do like alright 3
x value index + 0 3 + 1 3 2 right and
convert those all to float and then
bundle them into a V 3 and then we have
like successfully like compacted that
information right so I think that's what
we need
why are you complaining Lane V 3 wait
Lane V 3 o is V 3 o YZ Elaine V 3
currently do we not have any way to talk
about Elaine V 3 V 3 normally oh so we
just made that B Lane V 3 always alright
well I don't really care about that
that's fine and we may need to change
the format of these anyway because we
don't really know how what the best way
to load these is gonna be although I
would imagine we won't have much of a
choice because it's gonna be different
for each lane so there is that so we'll
try to load up these Merl binaries here
the problem that we're gonna have is you
know when we are actually looking at
sort of the input of the output here
we're gonna have a pathing problem right
so we need this that we need to know
where these materials would actually be
because we don't know right so we need
some way of supplying like a material
path for the moment all hard-coded but
we're gonna need something better than
that eventually right so let's suppose
we did that let's see if I go into
remedy what happens I'm gonna change my
working directory to be the data
directory here yeah oops
[Music]
so that all seems good and then I'll run
it that doesn't look good
let me take a loop in there so looping
over this see what the total count is
and I just want to see what the rest of
stuff is ninety eighty that I'll just do
all the conversions free it alright
so that seems to work why are we not
getting any print out here though did I
break something
sure
what I must have a read error what did I
do wrong there read that in total read
sighs that seems right that looks
correct to me we are reading
number things out of temp that all seems
reasonable why am I getting a am I
getting a bug there what am I missing
probably just being stupid
it was a bad stream day-to-day as you
know Linux totally ruined my life
the total table size looks good that all
looks that it looks good what's what's
wrong why don't you like that please
please crash again
let's set it down to a very low number
of rays as well so maybe it's just very
slow and let me take a look at what what
it output is well there's our test
bitmap all right so that's okay for
starters for our test fit map so what
I'm going to do now is since I don't I
don't know why that hit a crash there
that's really kind of weird and
disconcerting but anyway what I want to
do now is actually sample this this
value so when we hit something here and
we want to figure out what the
reflection is so you can kind of see
here we have like a bunch of terms and
what we want to do is actually just use
the values that we get in now there's
some weird stuff that we probably need
to start taking account of now which is
you can kind of see there's some weird
like I don't know why there are these
scaling values in here right and so I
kind of want to see if they explain what
those are
so I don't see a lot of explanation here
about what the scaling values are
actually therefore because since they're
storing floating-point values I'm not
sure why you would scale anything
because you wouldn't you have just baked
the scale into the actual file so I'm
not sure what those are meant to
represent right you see them saying I
and those values show up in here too
right
so yeah so here's look-up brdf value
right and here's like they're saying if
this is the this is the input theta you
know this is this is the input angles
you can see here that they say give me
the results and the results they give
you are scaled by these values but I
don't know why like why wouldn't you
just scale the values in the file right
I mean I'll I'll go one further and just
say I also don't really understand why
aren't they using the actual offset
lookups
like here's the double table for brdf
and they do basically like ind which is
where you are in the file right and then
they do the stride over to for the green
and over nothing for the blue that's a
really weird way to look that up is it
not just like like do you understand
what I'm saying why is this so
complicated like why isn't it just three
times index plus one or something
do they did they write these out in a
really like idiosyncratic way theta diff
index times B READY appear as Phi over 2
times theta D it looks like they wrote
them out like blocked like maybe the RG
and bees go strided but I can't really
tell right I mean that's what it looks
like they did here which is nuts I have
no idea why you would do that why don't
just do RGB RGB RGB RGB I mean right so
really what that means is this is not
correct right so actually what goes on
here apparently is this is the red
Channel
I guess meaning if we look at what the
dimensions are of this thing you can see
here okay so we've got you're in a
sampling res data
Sam permits a 2d feed the fees over two
is you know what they're saying they're
doing because they have they they did
that plus PI mirror that's the plus PI
mirror getting folded in their sewing I
have half the resolution so in here we
would basically say like okay if we if
we assume that this is how that looks
then this look up here the read all
comes first so the first full tote full
count of values are the Reds the greens
are after one of the third dimensions
worth of things and they're looking that
up oh sorry no they're mine the greens
are after H times D times two so that's
the greens are one read next and then
this is two Reds next okay so it's green
it's then like however many there are in
one total count
so wanna say that's what it's doing so
it's reds greens blues in this way right
so it's RGB that was really hard to
untangle but that's all they're really
doing here they just don't have a stride
this just happens to be the stride and
this just happens to be twice the stride
because Phi D is normally divided by 2
right that's fine
so then what we want to do is be able to
construct we want to be able to look up
into this table so what we need to be
able to do is when we actually go to
compute this bounce so in here right
well what we want to be able to do is
create the raid erection here and get
the attenuation factor right see here
apply the correct attenuation factor and
so all of this stuff is still the same
right but in order to get this
attenuation factor what we need to do
now is base it on more than just the
cosine right so what we want to do is
move the attenuation computation down
right so we want to do this and then
based on this Ray direction and we don't
really need cosine of 10 anymore like
that is going to be rolled into the brdf
now because we've got sampled data so
what we need to be able to do is say
alright we have the normal of the
surface that we hit I guess right and we
need to do the attenuation here for
whatever the thing is that we're
bouncing off of and so we have the raid
erection that we're outgoing and we have
the raid erection that we were coming
from which is this and we need to store
that so this is going to be like the
next raid direction right and then after
we do our computation we would we would
compute it like we would assign it in so
based on the Raider X and the next raid
direction so those two things combined
we need to be able to do our sample so
somehow out of those two we end
than normal that we're actually using
the next normal there I also don't know
when does that get assigned is that get
assigned up here somewhere where does
next normal so it's not really next
normal it's really just normal right we
don't actually keep that value so it's
the normal that we hit it's just called
next normal for no really good reason
here alright so what we need is here we
need our reflectance right so here we
need our like our FC value and what
we're gonna do here is we're going to
take our ref C value and we're gonna
apply it and so our ref C has to come
from a brdf look up and the brdf look up
is going to be whatever the material is
in this particular case and presumably
we did do the material look up at some
point here so you can see we did a
gather right here for for that matte
look up because remember this is wide
now so basically what we need to do here
is this I guess this is a lane v3 right
yeah so what we need to do here is say
alright when we do this ref C we need to
do a wide lookup and we're going to be
providing to our brdf lookup function
which is going to have to do a gather
we're going to have to provide that
information now what I don't know is the
emit color here right when that does the
load I don't know where Matt emit color
was getting used you find that out so
the mission just always gets added in
immediately so that's fine so we need to
edit that part at all right so all we
need to do now is is implement a brdf
lookup function and we know what the
material hits were and we know what are
all of our information is here so in
terms of the two vectors it's negative
ray direction it's the next normal and
then it's the Ray direction next ray
direction right and with that in mind we
can build our brdf lookup function which
is going to be slow but that's fine
and so in here we've got world materials
this is our material array and we've got
the mat index which is going to be
two-lane u-32 we've got our raid
erection here that's pointing off
towards that's like the direction we're
sampling so that's basically like our
sample direction we have the normal now
X let's call it normal and then we have
here this is our I guess that's that's
incorrect
so this is our what are they because
this is the view der and this is the
light direction right so that's that's
sort of what their nominal Eicher was
like where the lights coming from where
the view is and so if we go back now and
look at how this is coming in we need to
know these values so we need to know
theta in and Phi in and theta out and
Phi out and then this does sort of the
conversion to their sampling so we're
going to have to reproduce
that to look it up in their table but
first we have to produce those angles at
all right and so this is why I say this
is gonna be very expensive and bad like
really terrible and we're probably gonna
have to like do our own implementation
of a costs or something here right but
if we go look at how where was the
diagram here it is so if we look at what
this is giving us for parameters what we
have here is there's like there's the
normal vs. so so if we look at look at
this diagram basically right and this is
the standard coordinate frame so if we
look at you know and I guess I don't
know which way we want to do this but if
we look at these two pieces of code
side-by-side so if we look at this this
is taking in the theta in Phi in oops so
this is Theta in and Phi in so those
those two are very simple for us to
understand because that they don't
encode anything right and then we've got
here theta out in a Phi out and again
very simple to understand because
they're just the polar coordinates of
these two values if you look over here
in terms of what those are these are
versus the half angle right and the half
angle I guess is is I assume it's it's
defined as being well you know what I
can't really tell what is what is the
half angle actually half of let me take
a look prove it especially we vary age
the angle between the normal and the
half vector right
just double-check what they think the
half vector is of course doesn't look
like anyone says what the half vector is
here
sorry half - vector the angles respect
to the half angle half factor between
incoming and outgoing directions okay
that's pretty easy for us to produce
right so looking at this it's unclear
like we may just want to produce this
directly cuz it doesn't look like I mean
this isn't any easier to produce than
this if all you have is the vectors
really it feels like we should kind of
just go directly to this right like we
should just we should just compute these
direct these directly in my opinion so
in order to do that we would just first
do the half vector right this thing they
call the half vector and the incoming
and outcoming we would just do viewed er
+ leichter
multiplied by 0.5 right I mean that's
all we would really need to do and that
produces the half vector so that's the H
here right and then if we wanted to
start figuring out what the angles are
between these two things well one of our
problems is these two are normalized but
this is not normalized right so we're
gonna have to think about that a little
bit but if we take a look at what's
going on here and we just say like
alright so the angles we need are theta
H theta D Phi D and Phi H do those
correspond to something in here and
looking it looks like feted if theta
half so standard chords - half diffe
chords theta 1/2 phi half theta half phi
half and then diff yeah so it looks like
once we know those we can look this up
directly and you can see that here we
have to look at kind of see if what
they're doing with with these five
different decks and theta diff index so
theta diff index looks like it's it's
looks to me like mostly just clamping
right and and mapping the angle out to
the resolution resolution of the table
so those seem fairly straightforward and
easy to reproduce like that there's not
anything mysterious going on there
so really it seems like all we have to
do is focus on producing these right and
so let's just try to predict reproduce
those so in order to reproduce those
what we need is we need feita 1/2 and
phi 1/2 and then we need sated if and 5
if that's how they want us to produce
the encoding right and then from those
we need to do this mapping on each of
them and and off we would go right then
we can actually look up in the table
all right so in order to produce these
what we're looking for here is just the
a cost basically of this thing in this
reference frame and one of the problems
that we're gonna have here is we don't
really know what the tangent actually is
and the problem is that we do kind of
need to know that because in order to
properly like orient these things there
has to be a direction of the surface
right the reason for that is because
surfaces that are well services that are
isotropic meaning they reflect light the
same regardless of rotation don't care
like they wouldn't care what this is
because the function that we're looking
up would be symmetric - no you wouldn't
matter how you spun the surface but for
a nice tropic services they reflect
light differently depending on the
orientation of the surface right and so
we would need a tangent frame here as
well in order to measure things like Phi
H because that's in this plane so things
like theta H like theta H here we don't
care what you know it doesn't matter
right what the orientation of the
surface is for theta H I and for theta D
robably the same thing but for the two
Phi's
right it feels like those are going to
be ones that in order to measure them
properly we would need to
to have the tangent frame right as far
as I can tell that that'd be the only
way you could actually do it right and
and looking at this right what is this
stuff for so you can see them actually
doing it here right which is kind of
weird
so it's interesting the way they were
actually doing the lookup here is they
were saying well you didn't give us
vectors you gave us the original angles
which you probably had to do a bunch of
work to measure and then what we're
gonna do is we're gonna immediately turn
them back into vectors right cuz we need
to take the half angle which they did
and for some reason they normalized both
of these even though they didn't need to
because they were gonna normalize this I
don't know why but that's just what they
did
right and then once they took these you
can see like exactly like I said they
basically take an a COS of the half
angle vector and 1/8 tan four of the
other two parts of it to produce right
to produce the the values they want and
this assumes that you've already mapped
it into the tangent space right because
these are already relative to the
tangent space so yeah so it seems like
mostly what we need to be able to do
here and what we don't we don't really
have is we need to be able to provide a
tangent space which I'm honestly not
sure how we would do for pretty much
what we'd have to do is when we do our
collision and we produce the normal so
like if you if we look down here when we
produce the normal we're gonna also have
to produce a tangent right and what we
could do is change the name here normal
and tangent like so so when we go in
over to the normals here
just do a search in replace so we'll
just call that normal like so and then
we also have tangent and so tangent will
give us the ability to do that mapping
right if we have the normal and the
tangent we can do the mapping now since
we generally are going to also we're
gonna know more than that as well like
we can probably also know the normal the
tangent and the the by tangent like the
thing that completes that coordinate
frame and makes this an actual like
basis right I'm trying to think if we
need that I think we do because we're
you know we're probably gonna want to do
this right and that way when we come
through here and we say okay like let's
conditionally assign these two normal
tangent by tangent like this and same
thing on the sphere so the norm
here's fear relative ray origin yeah you
can see so that produces the the hit for
the sphere the thing that's gonna be
tough for us right is producing the
normal yeah so right loading up the
plane normal it becomes pretty easy
because the plane itself can just store
the other parts that it needs so in the
plane right when we define our planes we
can just also store like three things
the tangent and the buy vector right the
by tangent I could name these a little
bit more explicitly here so if we said
normal then in this case we could also
just if we actually hit these then we
could just load the other ones in maybe
I'll load them all
right so we load those in and I do my
conditional assignment then I would have
everything I would need to do the full
mapping and in the case where I have a
sphere it's a much harder problem
because we don't really know how to
produce the other values and if we go
over to let me just grab my sketch pad
here
so if we're looking at a sphere the
problem we're gonna have is okay so we
know we hit this point on the sphere we
know the normal is just the vector from
the center of the sphere to the outside
of the sphere because that's you know
the surface normal at that point so that
gives us a situation where we sort of
have you know you imagine this is the
surface of the sphere up close at that
point that gives a situation where we
know the normal but what we need is
another basis right something that's
going to give us like you know something
like this then we can actually use as
like this is the coordinate system of
the sphere and so you can see why I'm
like I don't really know exactly how to
do that especially because spheres by
definition can't have one right like a
sphere cannot have a coordinate system a
two dimensional coordinate system
assigned to them it's mathematically
impossible to do you by definition will
have a pole somewhere right
the phrase you might hear sometimes is
you cannot comb the hair on a cue ball
you cannot pet a spherical cat might be
another one
Circle cow
[Laughter]
[Music]
that is not what I meant but that is
great
that's alright so this is the one I
actually wanted the hairy ball theorem
the hairy ball theorem the point of the
hairy ball theorem is just yeah it's
it's the example so a torus right on a
torus you can assign a field you know a
two-dimensional grid and it works
properly
there's no anomalies anywhere no
singularities you can see if you try to
do it on a sphere you always end up with
some problems right where you're gonna
have at least one Pole right I like that
there's actually a human head in the
Wikipedia page yeah this is this is like
what I was trying to say so the problem
that we have
due to the hairy ball theorem is that we
don't have a way of assigning some thing
uniform now that's ok we don't mind if
we have some singularities right this is
just an example raytracer so you know
what we need to do is come up with
something that will give us a coordinate
system we can actually use sorry to bump
the microphone there and so what we
might do is say well ok you know maybe
we just use whatever would be the
lateral like whatever would be the cross
product of that and like the up Vector
right and in the case where we actually
are looking directly at the up Vector
we'll just get that will be our pole and
that'll be degenerate right I mean
that's one thing we can do another thing
we could do is try to just generate an
ortho north Agata basis using
some other scheme I'm not sure what it
should be but you know we can certainly
work it out so I'm going to just say all
right let's suppose that we're just
going to do some kind of a of a you know
generation of a basis here that's just
kind of garbage but we'll just produce
it either way so I'm going to go ahead
and say that we're going to do a cross
product of our normal to produce our
tangent and then we're going to do a
conditional assign like this and so I'm
going to cross the normal with I don't
know just the up Vector to generate one
and then I'm going to take the cross
product again so basically like whatever
the normal is in the up Vector I'm gonna
cross those two I really should cross
them the other order probably right hand
rule wise I probably want to cross the
up Vector with the normal like so right
because the normal Z and this would be
why I guess the normal would be X this
would be Y what do we want the normal to
be I guess technically the normal is Z
actually so I want my X my Y and my Z so
if my Y was sort of the up vector at
this point I would want what yeah to get
the X so the tangent vector would be X
the by tangent vector would be Y in this
case okay so if I get my tangent vector
out then what I want to do is cross from
the normal back to the sphere tangent to
get my other basis and then these just
need to be normalized right
right do we need to do anything else to
that
I think that should be sufficient so
that will give me a tangent in a by
tangent what that means is that now I
can map these things into the space of
the actual reflection completely so you
know when these things get passed in
here I can do that mapping so what I'm
going to do is is say I'm gonna pass the
full coordinate system here so I'm going
to do normal tangent Phi tangent and
then the brdf lookup I'm gonna go ahead
and pass those in so normal tangent oops
by tangent so and then what I need to do
is actually do this mapping so in order
to produce these two vectors map in I
need to do basically a transform on them
using three vectors that I have you know
the normal tangent by tangent I want to
map into that space which is you know
just taking the inner product with each
of them to put them into that space so
if I want to now I can I can basically
do that that transform so that would
just look like alright my you know my
view durand my elder vectors right which
I'll just call V and L here oh you know
what I guess I can take the half vector
first and just map the half vector in if
I want to as well
not sure which order you would do those
in necessarily right we need to produce
the half vector and then we could map
the half vector and if we want to I
guess and hot wait so what do we what do
we actually need here just want to make
sure so
yeah so to compute the diff factor
they're doing a rotation what are they
doing for that they look back at what
they're actually trying to grab there so
looking at this they want to do the
difference the diff I don't know what
they want to do so they want to do the
theta D between H and and Omega here and
they want to do the Phi D which I assume
is just the thing I'm not sure about is
this diagram sucks like this part right
here I have no idea what they're trying
to measure I guess they're trying to
measure if I had a vector that was that
was perpendicular here to H I would be
measuring the rotation of that to point
towards this vector I guess like I
really just do not know what this is
supposed to measure it's pretty
confusing right this one is not
confusing to me
so these are just the polar coordinates
of age and that's really easy to
understand but what this is I don't I
don't quite get right and I guess maybe
I should be looking this up
right because maybe that that's
explained in more detail there but
that's the only part I don't really get
is like what what that one measurement
supposed to be but either way we can
start so theta 1/2 and Phi 1/2 those are
pretty easy right ones in a cose and
ones in a tan too right and in order to
figure these out we just need the x and
y so 8 and 2 is like YX usually right
and so we would we will know what those
two are once we actually map the half
vector in right so if I map the half
vector into that space and it's the out
grinder size we need L&amp;H right so once
we map the half factor into that space
this would must be H dot Y and this
would be H dot X right and this would be
the a coast of Hz right so those are the
ways that we would measure we would sort
of map those out right now we don't
really want to have to take 4 rather
obvious reasons
a kosis and a tans in this way
like we would rather not have to do that
obviously but at the moment we're kind
of stuck with that so we'll have to
figure out what we want to do with that
a little bit later and probably what
we'll need to do there is downshift
right we'll probably have to do this for
now I don't know where the
gather functions are they our area so
yeah so for like the gather functions
here in order to extract this stuff we
need some way of pulling out the
individual values so like we need to do
something like this right and then we
need to like extract the values out so
we need to do like this right
extract zero is we really want extract n
right so we want something that's going
to do like this
and then we're probably fine but anyway
so over here we've got our LW and rhw
right and those are our wide versions of
these vectors so the first things that
we need to do there are we need to take
the LW and the HW are just going to be
mappings into this space space of the
vectors so to map the half vector in
it's really pretty easy right it's just
an inner product in this case I assume
so if I do a v3 oops how do I load a v3
with actual results I don't actually
know oh well you know what I can do it
this way think assuming this actually is
the way I think it is yeah so it's just
three are three twos so I just do it
this way so I can just produce the inner
product right of the light direction
with each of the the pieces so we know
that the tangent is our X the by tangent
is our Y and the normal is our Z so this
makes a little coordinate frame and by
taking the inner product of the light
direction with each of the pieces of our
coordinate frame I end up with the
transformed vector and the same would be
true of this right and so this is just
really doing a matrix transform on it
right mm-hmm
without bothering to ever build an
actual matrix because why bother
so this maps them into the space giving
the tangent space of the reflection and
then this produces the values we
actually need the theta 1/2 is the a
cost of whatever the Z value would be
and the atan2 in this case right and so
then the only question is how the heck
do we compute these things because I
have no idea what they are right now one
of them I'm pretty sure I know what it
is and I can compute that one pretty
easily again I'm sort of just guessing
but where's that there it is
um so if you take a look at the what
this looks like here I'm pretty sure
that theta D is just gonna is just the
separation between these two right so
it's the angle of separation between the
two vectors that looks like what they
drew right I don't know but it looks
like what they drew and so if that's the
actual case then that's a really easy
one to do because again it's just an a
Coast but it's the a Coast of the inner
product of the two vectors right so for
example here's the inner product of the
half vector with the light direction
right or is that's what's with the
outgoing direction that's the incoming
direction right so if we take it with
the incoming direction there why would
this well I don't care um so yeah if we
just take it with the income the the LW
here that we've produced I guess it's
technically these two right although it
doesn't matter I could have done it
beforehand so actually I don't even know
why we would need I guess I don't even
know why we would really need to do this
transfer but we'll take a look at that
later I guess so the diff the inner
product difference here right those two
that is specifically what we would take
the a coasts of right and so if I want
to do an extract on that
that would be the theta that we need for
that lookup and then the Phi that we
would need right in this case that's the
one I just don't know what it is I don't
know what that's supposed to be telling
me right and their implementation is
pretty confusing they're doing a
complete like huge set of of things here
to solve it and again I don't really
know what they're trying to produce
there so they are taking a rotation of a
vector the in direction and the normal
and why would they be using the oh right
because the in Direction is we're
talking about that's the light vector
and the normal minus Phi half so that's
the input here right they're rotating
the opposite direction into a temp
vector then they're rotating that vector
by the by normal by theta half into the
diff vector and then producing that okay
I sort of get it maybe so I think what
they're sort of trying to do
yikes
just trying to figure out if this is
just really this is tear this is like a
horrible diagram I should also look to
see what is the 1998 sinkovitz
so here's the same incredibly terrible
diagram right but at least the Flies are
easy to read now
changing variables because some features
of common beer distill lie alone new
coordinate is proposed for attribution
in terms of the halfway vector and a
difference vector which is just the
incident ray in a frame of reference
which to have a vector is at the North
Pole okay so that is exactly what I
thought but I'm not sure the the problem
is that's under specified right because
there's any amount of rotation you know
you could have any amount of rotation
you wanted there right that makes sense
surface normal surface tangent surface
by normal should probably call the by
normals of the by tangent if that's the
phrase were using
all right mr. problem here oh these are
not RGB anywhere yeah um so yes so
figuring this out it's gonna be a little
bit weird so how would I
normally do this trying to think
[Music]
trying to think of how I would produce
that efficiently I don't think the way
they're doing it is particularly good I
mean I think a lot of this is not
particularly good and not how I would
necessarily do it but that's sort of
beside the point
so let's look at the diagram
so essentially here's what we're trying
to do we have a coordinate frame right
and the coordinate frame looks like this
right so we essentially have a
coordinate frame that's the normal
vector to the surface the tangent vector
to the surface and the bind normal and
these form are x y and z respectively
you know if we think of this as a
standard coordinate frame and this is on
the surface of something like on the
surface of the sphere right what we have
is a 1/2 vector that we've produced and
we've mapped it into this frame so it's
just sitting in here right and that's
our 1/2 vector and then we have another
vector which is like our light vector
right and what we want to do is we want
to say what would the coordinates of
this thing be in polar coordinates if
this were actually the new Z vector
right so if we rotated this up to here
you know I'm saying what would this be
at that point what would what would we
consider this to be at that once we got
there right so this whole thing we're
kind of shifted up and this became the
new bottom right and so if we looked at
this in 2d instead like to make it a
little bit easier to understand for
those of you watching
if we did something like this we're here
as a normal here's the half vector
here's the light vector right so here's
the tangent down here what we're looking
to do is say let's pretend this were
actually the coordinate system right so
now everything is relative to this
we're like rotating it into place and in
2d this would just work because we
wouldn't really have to care because we
could just measure it directly but in 3d
we actually do care because we need to
be able to do this on the actual
hemisphere so the whole thing has to
come up and we need to know like what
the displacement what the polar
coordinates think of this thing are
that's why I say we can just take the
inner product to quickly get one of them
right which is the opre which is the
theta diff right that we can just get
directly by taking the arc cosine of the
inner product that's trivial the thing
we can't really do is quickly take the
other part of it and the reason for that
is because that part of it requires
actual other basis vectors the question
is is there some way we could easily
generate those basis vectors right and
that part I don't know since we don't
know how the half angle vector actually
well so we know the actual half angle
vector angles and that's why they're
doing that rotation
I'm just not sure yeah so you can see
the way that they're trying to do it if
we go back to their source code right so
the way that they're doing is saying
well alright I know I do have the half
angle vector that I actually computed
right so this is the winding this this
is the rotation of it in the plane of
the tangent like so that's this right
here this Phi half that's the winding in
this space of the half angle vectors so
if you map the half angle vector down to
like here I guess let's pretend it's in
the positive side so here's the plane
that it's in right we met we map that
down to like here and we just say look
we've already measured this part that's
the theta half what's this part right
this part here that gives us the the Phi
half right so what they're saying is
let's spin this vector back around let's
spin it right so that it lines up
exactly here right so we're going to
move it back to like there right and
then what they're gonna do is take that
vector at that point right and rotate it
around the by normal so around this and
you can see why because they rotated it
into this plane so now they're gonna try
to rotate it this way they're gonna
rotate it up there right if that makes
sense and so what they're effectively
doing is they're taking this vector
they're performing the rotation on this
vector that would rotate it such that
the H would now have been pointing
directly up so this makes perfect sense
now it's just man is that expensive
right like producing that is kind of
nuts
[Music]
can crap here for a second there's gotta
be a better way to do that
so the first thing we know is that if we
were going to rotate that thing just
once to put it into position we could
have done that and they didn't do that
and I'm wondering if that's because it
won't produce the correct the correct
actual transform because there's you
know just bear with me for a second here
so let's suppose that we have the
surface normal here we've got the half
angle I'm sorry the half vector here and
then we've got you know tangent and by
tangent and I say look I just want to
rotate this up into place well I already
know this angle right I know what that
angle actually is because that's my my
theta half right I mean isn't that what
that was we double-check that I'm not
making that up
I mean we could find it trivially even
if it's not but I just want to make sure
I remember what we're actually measuring
here yeah so we know that angle right
and so the question is what is the
rotation if I just want to do one single
rotation to put this back into place
what would it be well theta half would
just be you know the cross product of N
and H right n cross H gives me this
vector right and then if I rotate by
this much it would put it into place in
one rotation not two right so if I did
want to rotate L into place I could just
do that one rotation and that would have
put L into the place that it should
should actually be right I mean that's
just kind of by definition the question
is are they trying to take something
that's not are they intentionally not
taking the shortest path are they
intentionally doing those two rotations
for some other reason because they want
the winding they want the spin in this
place to have some specific measurement
right
and that's a part that I'm
meet rub a little bit of a hard time
figuring out because the way that
they're applying the rotation is rather
than this rotate directly they are first
rotating into the plane of the tangent
so their first rotating here and then
rotating there and I don't know that
that that probably would produce a
slightly different spin so that as you
were going up here you were actually
spinning a little as well right because
remember the route that you take to move
H into n so the route along the sphere
will produce different spin this way
right around the normal and it looks
like they are doing a different one I
don't know why they're doing that one it
seems dumb to do that because it
wouldn't matter which way you've encoded
this would it I mean since the
anisotropic of the surface is the thing
that you're actually measuring it seems
crazy to do this coordinate system
because this coordinate system is just
more operations instead of just doing a
single rotation now you have to do two
and that seems really stupid
I mean am I wrong I don't suppose rose
Inca which is watching the stream right
now and can tell me whether whether I'm
wrong about his coordinate system being
less efficient than it should be
right but that seems that seems busted
if we assumed temporarily that we could
use that we could do this direct
rotation then what we would say is well
okay so if we now need to measure the
spin relative to this vector of the L
vector which is sitting somewhere in
this space right what we want to know is
the inner product of that on this
coordinate system because we don't
actually need to rotate the vector if we
can just get these vectors directly
right and of course we can get these
vectors directly because these vectors
are just the half angle cross-product ad
with the normal which gives us this one
right and then we would just do the
cross-product again with the H and that
vector to give us this one the inner
product on each of those gives us the
result that means no transcendentals
right yeah it's too hard to say let's
say no sine cosine right so I feel like
that's actually better anyway I'm just
gonna say that's what we should do and
if we want to Oh actually oh yeah you
know what we could even do this the way
they're doing it because if you were
going to first rotate into this plane
then rotate into this flame you can
probably still do that can't you because
you would just go versus the tangent
first so you'd do H cross T which would
get you which would get you this vector
and then you would cross the two
to get the other one so I think you can
actually do that if you want t to be the
prevailing thing that you'd rotate it to
first I think you could just cross those
two so I think we could do that I think
we just do H cross T and I think we can
just do this in a way that's way better
than what they were doing like way
better not like a little bit I really
want to be able to draw this out
unfortunately I don't have any like
diagramming stuff in here but like I
mean I want to be able to like draw this
like you know in the editor of the
future you'll be able to just like see
the things on the side so as you change
the formula in here it would just draw
it you know but you know that's not ask
for miracles folks so anyway if you
wanted to in here right I could just go
alright let's create that coordinate
system as well and just produce it and
we can produce it wide we don't have to
downshift for that which is great
so what I'm going to do is I'm going to
produce those those other basis vectors
here so I'm going to call that like
defects and diff why I guess then these
are the things that we would measure
those against and then when I want to
produce the actual results it's much
easier right I can just do the a costs
on this X this x and y inner right so
it'd just be this right so we do the
the half vector with the LW and then we
would just do the the you know the diff
X and the diff Y with the half act with
the light vector and I think that
produces everything we need and these
again are just cross products it's not
complicated
right so the diff X is just going to be
let's take that's gonna be take the half
vector and I just need to get the
winding right here so where's my diagram
yeah so take the half vector and the
tangent I want to produce a standard
coordinate frame where this is gonna be
the N and so in order to produce the X
what would I want to do well I'm
actually gonna round up reasoning the
why cuz it's historia so I would just do
the cross rect of H down T like this
right and then after I've produced the H
down to T version then I just need to do
you mean the recross of that and so the
H down at e-version then I would do the
that up to H to get the T back right and
these are backwards now right
so think that gives me everything I need
if I then do my extraction here this is
all now I think all sort of done
properly those are all measured the
inner products are all taken trying to
think of why this one this isn't exactly
like I don't really need these to be I
guess it doesn't really
which which one I'm doing this but the
half vector here is HW they don't really
need to be mapped into that coordinate
space though right it that wouldn't
really matter I don't think because it's
you know it is the space that it is so
that why I mm-hmm
it doesn't matter that it's in this
coordinate space I think that's kind of
dumb that I do that but we can work out
simplifications like that a little bit
later anyway let's see so if Y here HW
here and then in here where we do this
now we just this is an a cost and this
is an eight and two and in this case
it's just the extract of that defects in
ER so it's just like extract defects in
ER sub-index extract defects in air
seven X so this would just be Y over X
this is extract just the inner like so
I'm trying to think if there's anything
weird happening here so this part here
the HC h YH x again I don't think since
those are just this this doesn't
actually have to happen this way either
so the theta half we can just do extract
sub-index extract sub-index extract
sub-index and these are just going to be
the half vector right so I think that's
everything we need from there and then
we just need that one extract function
so if I actually look at what the
extract zero what we actually need here
is just something that'll do this
right and I think this probably needs to
be a pound too fine because that's going
to be an actual immediate I would
suspect so it probably needs to be like
this right and then we're gonna have to
have like an M convert like one of those
things where you extract the actual
value there
I don't remember what they are because I
never remember the Intel intrinsics are
so crazy the naming scheme is just nuts
but this so basically we just passed
which one of these we want so I believe
we can just do that the problem is again
it's not a variable right it has to be a
constant and so it's kind of a pain in
the butt because we want this we want
this to be able to give us something
that we don't have to produce a loop for
you know ideally so that part's kind of
annoying because I'd have to wrap this
into macro or something and it's just
because we don't have implementations of
a coast and atan2 yet we need those to
be wide and so the downshifting here is
you know it's obviously like really bad
and not at all what we want but I'm not
really sure how to get around that
without implementing these two which
would take many days of work right so we
don't have much of a choice of that oh
and I seen many days of work I mean many
streams of work uh so anyway that's a
bit of a problem and I'm not sure how to
really get around that we could try
using in
one that we actually extract based on a
variable but those are much harder to
come by so maybe we'll just do something
really crappy right now for the time
being and actually just access off of
the you know
off of it this way
right which is again not not good and
not really what we want to do but it's I
think it's the best we're gonna be able
to get since we're already probably
should right wind up pretty soon here we
go um so let's see this right here is
just gonna return a double because
that's how oh well you know what no they
have--they afloat versions in the sea
runtime library right don't they yeah
all right so let's just finish it up so
we can close up for the day for each of
these we're gonna have to do the lookup
again slowly and then we're gonna have
the return value which is going to be
what we actually get out of the brdf
when we combine it so there's like a
result here right and that's what we're
going to return and so what we want to
do there is we need to be able to like
pack stuff into this thing so basically
like when we when we do the gather here
we're gonna have to do like our results
you know the X is going to be this the Y
is going to be this the Z is going to be
this kind of thing right so we're gonna
have like a color value that we actually
look up here and then we're gonna have
we're gonna have to put that back in
somehow right and presumably we'll have
to do it like I don't know there's an
insert here gather f/32
yeah they're at 32 again nope it's not
what I wanted yeah
so wait a minute how is that working
index time stride Laney 32 index plus
base pointer what
how can you multiply a wide index by a
stride and load an f32 off of it
what how is this even compiling anyone
care to tell me that makes like no sense
to me
so like the lean operator to star I do I
do not know how that's even remotely
legal right this is supposed to be wide
isn't it oh oh
I see what we're saying never mind
that's the part we did we did a version
for non-wide so never mind not that's
not as scary there we go that's what I
wanted to see all right totally fine no
worries everything's fine right okay so
anyway if I wanted to do this here again
this is really crappy and we don't
really want to do it this way what we
want to do is just do this wide so that
the whole thing is just you know these
these we want to have wide versions of
these and then we only want to have to
do the lookup just just that part
obviously we can't quite do correctly
but I guess you know what I can do - is
this Lane v3 here what I could do is use
this gather and and and you know do it
this way right so I could do something
like this where we do a gather f/32 on
each of these and then the result is
just that right I mean another way to
look at it would be I could just do this
and this way if we do a base pointer
plus astride with the indices like this
what we could do is then we'll just
build you know whatever these indices
are we can build those and then let this
gather for us that's one way to do it
the problem is we're still gonna have to
pack the indices so I guess I don't
really know that that saves us much and
you know kind of six of one half dozen
of the other
so I don't know this is the old this is
the problem with pre a vx5 1270 intel
never bothered to give you a way to load
anything so it was you know kind of a
kind of a lost cause but anyway so if we
want to load like table lookup right
they didn't implement table lookup for
some reason so anyway inside here if we
actually assume like okay load we'll
just make this work the other way around
then what we can do is say well alright
result dot X what we'll have to do is
like address off of that right like this
and place these values in there using
each individual sub line right so this
would look like this
and then we would just assign them like
that so that way we can assign the
colors in here and that way this thing
can look up just regular so in the brdf
table for whatever material we're
talking about select materials and I
don't know how these are being extracted
here I guess they just get extracted
that way yeah a lot of this is just so
so ugly you know
so anyway if we go ahead and grab this
particular material index out and get
the brdf table hmm maybe I'll do it this
way then what we need to do is take a
look at those values here and then this
is gonna give me the value that I
actually want so if I look it up in the
table here the question is what's the
actual index right so I know that the
index is going to be proportional to
these things when we get these values
out but I know I need to map them in so
I've got an index here and what we need
to do we probably want to do an
assertion right that says I don't know
if we've been asserting anywhere in here
yeah so we probably want to do an
assertion that makes sure that we're not
out of bounds right so that just so we
have some idea of whether or not this
thing is is you know totally nuts or
something but so like right here I can
assert that whatever index value we want
let's just assert that it's within the
the bounds of this thing so that'll just
make sure we know oops
we're not gonna fetch outside the table
and then what we need to do is actually
figure out what our indexing table
actually is and this is the last step to
the process so we've got all of our
angles here this is everything they
wanted from us right in order to
actually use one of these brdf files and
then you know they've got the way that
they're mapping it in here and you can
see that right in here so you can see
the way they've mapped it in they want
to clamp it so that if the theta is less
than zero that means it's more than 90
degrees so they're just saying look if
it's more than 90 degrees we don't do it
right and that seems fine so we can do
like theta 1/2 less than 0 theta 1/2
equals zero right totally fine then
they're doing like alright what's the
half degree so they basically try to
take they divide by PI over 2 right
which is 90 degrees so they're dividing
by 90 degrees and then multiplying by
whatever the sampling resolution
actually is right that seems fine
they're literally just mapping the range
of 0 to PI over 2 to the arrange of the
array right so what I might propose is
like saying something like this
like let's call that eyes ear oh let's
take theta 1/2 and divide by PI 32 half
PI 32 right so we've we've converted it
this way and then let's just clamp 0 1
that because now that's given us our
exact range right of lookups and then
what we can do is just map that into the
sampling resolution to get our index
right so maybe the right way to do it
would be this way right so do the
rounding take that dimension multiply it
in although I guess you don't really
want to round right we want truncate
actually so we really just want this so
we want to take our table and that first
count we want to multiply like so and
that might over fetch if we literally
got right up to 90 so what we may want
to do is say all right maybe we do it
this way where we I don't know what the
mapping should actually be if you look
at how they're doing the mapping here
it's a little bit Squinkie like it seems
like theta 1/2 degree there it looks
like it looks like they clamp after the
fact right and I'm not sure if that
really makes sense
I suspect suspect it might not you know
I'm saying to you
mmhmm yeah I'm not sure so I think what
we might want to do is say all right if
we did it this way and then do it around
so we did that I think that's probably
the right way to do that mapping I'm
guessing don't quote me on that but
probably something like that right we
then need to do another one because
again we've got so many of these
parameters coming in here so that's that
vector
oh and you can see here they're doing
some other things here right then
they're saying well okay whatever that
half degree is we're gonna multiply it
by the rest what so they then square it
and then square root what
why anybody know what is that about
I have no idea what that's about
divided by 90 degrees multiplied by the
resolution
so now you've mapped it all the way out
multiplied by the resolution again then
square root it are they just trying to
get more resolution in a particular part
of the sampling range yeah they are
that's exactly what they're doing
but that's not correct if you wanted to
do that you would have to have squared
it beforehand right that doesn't
distribute this this can't be right can
it
am i nuts there I mean if you look at
this this seems totally wrong because
you've taken theta half which is the
thing you wanted to map nonlinearly and
you've multiplied it by the actual table
size then you're multiplying by the
table size again and then square rooting
this thing that only square roots half
of the part I don't think this is right
is there a bug in this code because you
know I mean just just think of it this
way right this is the value that we want
to map nonlinearly right it's this and
we want to square root that right but
the problem is they've done that after
already multiplying it by the table
count and you can't distribute that that
doesn't work right I mean just do the
multiplication I mean here if you don't
believe me maybe I'm just not here so
let's suppose that we take this at face
value so we've got theta half over M PI
over 2 right so what that's going to do
is that's going to produce a value from
0 to 1 right because we've got something
that can only go up to 9 degrees
we're going to divide it by 90 degrees
and then we're going to get a value from
0 to 1 that we're gonna use to range map
into this thing right so we're going to
call that our T value basically right if
we then say T times the sampling res
data age right so now we've got T times
the resolution we assign that to theta
1/2 theta half dead right and then we do
temp equals theta have to egg times that
right so that's this value again so that
makes this T times R squared right I
mean that's what that would do we then
square root that so we're square rooting
and this is the actual index value we
then use so we're square rooting T times
R squared right
that gives us I equals R times root T
right is that right
all right well nevermind I take it back
that's actually fine it's just very
convoluted because you didn't need to do
it so the math does check out it's just
again very inefficient I guess because
you didn't need to do any of that you
could have just Square rooted this and
then multiplied it right so I guess the
math does check out now that I've worked
it through but why would you do it might
be the better way to say it yeah because
it's just this right I don't know where
our square root is that's right there so
that's all you really need to do like so
so this is our f 0 and then we just need
to basically multiply up like that and
then you know off we go so it's just
they did an extra multiply and I just
don't know why again it doesn't really
make sense but it wasn't really they
weren't really trying to be efficient in
that code probably so they really just
didn't care but just seems like a really
convoluted way to do it so anyway they
want this to be a nonlinear mapping
mm-hmm that's fine
we can make it a nonlinear wrapping
however at that point why did we take
the Eiko's if we wanted a nonlinear
mapping just don't take the eCos just
use the inner product right and then we
would have had the nonlinear mapping I
think so that's also pretty weird right
like I feel like this is
just undoing what the a cosine did
so again pretty weird not really sure
what's going on there if you look at
what's going on now just trying to
figure out where we're getting here so
we have our theta half index as you can
see it's right here right that we're
using for our index we've got our five
DIF index and our theta diff index right
so looking at this we don't really need
the Phi half we just need five DIF and
then these two right so this is actually
unnecessary we only need the hwz that
makes sense
yeah so anyway then we come in here and
we do theta half index is the one we've
got theta diff index is theta diff and
Phi different Nexus 5 diff so we got to
look at those so theta diff index is not
nonlinear so that's literally just
mapping it directly into the resolution
so dividing by 90 and going and then
it's clamped to the table size right and
if we look at how they've defined that
theta def is the same so it's also a
half angle so basically it's the exact
same code just without the nonlinear
mapping right so if we want to we can do
this exactly the same way we did it we
just don't square root it
so again pretty easy and so then the
final one is the only one that's
probably more complicated gonna ask me
why I didn't change that to a one
and I also have to look at how those are
stride it out but so if we look here at
fide if index dated if index at a half
index it looks like this Phi defend x1
here's the reciprocity so this is just
basically saying look we're gonna make
it be symmetric about pi right so
basically they're just doing you know a
bump up so when we look in here and we
look at the five DIF and we're you know
we did the eight and two here we're
gonna say if five diff is less than zero
if I diff plus Z equals PI thirty-two
right and that's all that's doing so
then here it looks like we multiply out
by the sampling again and off we go
and I guess this resolution value is
actually sort of garbage that's a 1 by
the way right date a half day to D and
so Phi D is here so we want half of this
value but that's what we're actually
going to get in the count right because
according to this they stored that in
the file but halved right so the dims to
value is presumably halved right so that
means it's already been halved for us so
if we do this we should just multiply
out to the correct thing if we want this
to map zero to one we just multiplied by
I've been divided by PI right so that's
0 to 180 which is what we would expect
so those are in
and presumably we just roll them out so
we just be like all right in terms of
how these things are started we don't
even know we're going to look here so
the FIDE if index is the part that is
not strided at all so that's the
increment by one so the i2 gets nothing
the i1 is multiplied presumably by the
count of one let's see
sampling res Phi over 2 okay so that's
count 2 right
and then the I write is that right
that's thetad if they to DIF and then
theta half is the full stride so theta
1/2 which is this one is count one
perhaps count two right there's like
zero chance that this will work there's
way too much stuff in it but that's what
it says right so we've done something
and we can maybe call it a day um I
don't know that's gonna say I don't know
what's going on here but we can we can
check we why can't I see my source code
do we not have debug info for this guy
so no what happened
not sure why but it's not letting me
actually view the source
oh it's cuz we're deep down in the
visual see guts alright so you can see
we did actually get outside the table
here not exactly sure why that would be
maybe because we're indexing these
slightly wrong I mean let me double
check that f2 part of things but let's
take a quick look at where we're at
and just get that part fixed cuz that
part we should be able to fix although
this doesn't have any values here so
wait a minute what table is this what
table is this I guess so one of the
problems that we would have here is just
that everybody would need to be
initialized to a table that just had
like one normal reflectance in it
because we need to be able to load these
wide so you're going to have people with
zeros yeah and think of that so we need
to do kind of like a null version of the
brdf load you know what I mean
or we can do like an if 0 on it I
suppose but it seems better to just fill
them in with actual values I would think
so we probably want is something like
null brdf or something like that and
what null brdf would do is it would just
initialize the the destination so when
you actually do a sample there you you
won't get a bogus value
so this is just initialize it to a table
of 1 we can just do like okay there's an
f32 that's like the like or a v3 -
that's like the you know the null brdf
value or whatever right and it's just
like or maybe it's like no reflectance
or something right it's just zero and so
values will just point to that right
let's try that again so we can get an
actual run here okay so the thing runs
which is surprising to me because we
sort of threw so much stuff in there I
wasn't really expecting it to but I'm
guessing we will get garbage for output
more or less and we sort of do sort of
don't that's not as bad as I was
actually expecting so kind of surprising
but you know so I'm happy to call it
there and we'll just we'll pick that up
on the next time we do our handmade
right I'm gonna go to a brief QA I'm not
going to take many questions probably
assuming the stream worked at all
all right
when computing the sphere by tangent
could you just nas the tangent before
competing to buy a tangent so you don't
have to NAS the by tangent afterwards
probably numerically I guess I don't
really know in our case we don't have to
be 100% precise probably so probably yes
I mean let me go grab that part
yeah I mean I assumed you could do it so
since you know that these two are normal
you know that they're gonna produce
something that's just the angle the
difference is going to be the sine of
the angle between them you will have to
normalize that one and then you assume
that these are at right angles to each
other now so DIF y + HW have to be
orthogonal so you could eliminate that
one and you should also be able to
eliminate the one we did down here
somewhere where was that yeah so here
you could do it this way right and then
that should those should be fine right I
usually don't do that till I'm actually
like getting the code more specifically
a bit
talking about rayon linux and more
beautiful code there is still a github
issue about memory loading and sim D
yeah I mean I'm again probably not gonna
look at that the moment is the B RDS
essentially a function that tells us
which raise within the hemisphere to use
do you mean brdf do you get uncanny
valley impression sometimes when looking
at Ray traced images if so what
strategies might you have to mitigate
that I'm not sure what you mean by
uncanny valley not in this kind of a
situation because I mean at least for us
we're just talking broadly here about
you know things that are spheres and
planes so you're never gonna get an
uncanny valley looking at spheres and
planes they don't exist in the real
world right oops brdf sorry typo yes so
the BR d a-- function no it's not
telling us which rays within the
hemisphere to use what it's doing is
it's telling us for any given rays in
the hemisphere so one incoming and one
outgoing it tells us how much the
surface reflects that's it right so
basically we choose before we ask it we
choose where are we trying to figure out
where the lights going and where are we
trying to ask about the light incoming
and we give it those two things plus the
surface geometry so the normal the
tangent the by tangent and then we say
hey brdf how much light should get
transmitted from this direction to this
direction that's it
well I finish this tomorrow probably not
handmade rageous what we use when
something goes wrong in the streamer
when we're trying to test stuff my
camera framerate seems low um yeah
probably
I mean it's being captured by Linux
right which can never do anything so
it's probably just not capturing the
webcam because it's too terrible to do
it I'm glad the sound was fine though
have you thought about implementing ggx
for handmade ray I don't even know what
that is so the answer is no I haven't
let's just assume that this is what you
actually meant no I haven't thought of
it um shockingly
how much of modern skinned mesh
animation did you contribute to I don't
know I guess that depends on what you
mean
haha this is what I'm talking about a
Cornell that edu okay sorry I'll go
ahead look at that up so SRM pube
locations SRO 7b t DF PDA nope nope
so I mean I guess the problem here is
like yeah this is just another like we
wouldn't if there's a database of these
that we could load then we could do it
right
provide one I mean the only reason we
did this particular thing is because we
could load a database right and and
maybe there is a day if there's a
database of these then we could
certainly load them right but
well obviously all right but what
function choose the outgoing rays to use
because it will affect the outcome of
the picture it gets fuzzier if they're
raised red and more directions no so so
that's kind of the point let me
illustrate this for you because this is
important to understand I mean to the
extent that anything in handmade array
is important to understand because it's
kind of just a side thing that we do
sometimes but all right
so if you actually look at the way we
started doing handmade array when we
were just building the Ray casting part
and we weren't actually trying to do
anything with light transfer then what
you said is sort of correct meaning when
we have a surface and we want to know
how much light is coming out in this
direction then if we only cast array or
rays in this direction or in a tight
cone in that direction then what we will
get is something that looks like a
mirror roughly right and if we cast rays
in all the directions uniformly then
we'll get something that looks kind of
like chalky right or very diffuse right
and we call this mirror version specular
right but all the only reason for that
the only reason that's what's happening
is because we have no light transfer
function so we were all equally weighted
right we were taking all these rays and
we were adding them together and just
averaging right we're just an average of
all the samples so obviously the more
you take samples in one direction the
more the color will look like what's
coming from that direction and the more
you just take samples in all directions
the more it will just look like the
uniform light so it appeared because we
were not waiting our samples at all it
appeared as if just what directions we
chose to send our arrays was what
determined what the surface looks like
but that's only true if they're equally
weighted what the brdf gives you is the
weighting right and so what it does is
it says oh well for a mirrored surface
when you happen to ask me for things in
this direction I give very high weights
and when you ask for things in any other
direction I give you very low weights
and so it produces a mirror by waiting
all of the mirror Direction samples
highly in all of the off mirror
directions very low right however it
also lets you do all other types of
surfaces because it can do things like
having like certain fall offs or weird
bumps or weird shifts and stuff right
and so with the weighting that what this
does is allow you to have any kind of
surface not just ones that do only
mirror or only diffuse or some blend
between the two this lets you actually
do any kind of incoming light
distribution that you want
and by the way we can reverse this
process as well eventually for
optimization purposes and say if we
notice certain places where the brdf has
a lot of information and other places
where it's weighted very low we can like
only take samples in directions that are
pretty high right so we can reconstruct
this exact behavior from a perfect
mirror BDF by sampling along the PDF but
again if we take the brdf and figure out
how to sample it properly rather than
just assuming that it's either a mirror
or either diffused or somewhere in
between what we can do is then produce
any reflectance and sample it properly
rather than just only having one
sampling strategy right did shader
weighted skin mesh animation exist
before you started meddling with it sure
how did it evolve and do you see any
future improvements possible in it yeah
I mean again not really sure what you
mean my work on shader weighted skin
mastery animation stuff first of all
started before shaders could produce
skin mesh animation it started when the
CPU had to do the skin deformation and
yeah it was very poorly understood at
the time it's true most the people who
were doing anything like that weren't
doing it real-time and it was a few
people were doing it there were a couple
a couple different places doing it we
were one of them valve was one of them
and what was the other name of
there was another one and then there
were some weird techniques like there
was a really strange one that was this
sort of weird hybrid like render
software rendered version by the people
who made if I sacked Sachs Pearson was
the guy who did it it was this weird
game where you played like this little
baby who ran around and like possessed
people or something I can't remember the
name of the game
I can't remember the name of the game
but yeah I mean essentially what we were
doing is just working out how we would
do these things in real time the the
cinema world like Pixar and a couple
other places that did this sort of thing
did it slightly differently usually than
we did because they had a lot more
controls they were layering on top of
each other so they didn't really think
of skin meshes quite the same way that
we do whereas now games in film pretty
much used the same more or less way of
looking at things usually then it was a
little bit different but no I you know I
don't really think there's much to say I
mean one of the main things that I
contributed if to the scent that I
contributed original research in this
area as opposed to just like
implementations people were using would
have just been the fact that you can
linearly blend quaternions that was a
big change that's not really necessarily
specific to skin to mesh animation it's
just animation more broadly but nobody
had analyzed that before I did and then
once I did then now everyone does that
far as I know
yet toxin 16 so what I would say is like
I would be totally fine implementing
other stuff too like I just wanted to
implement a couple lighting functions in
here we could totally implement a GD X
function the question is what we need
something to load right and we now have
to load it like we could just have
measured parents we build into the a
person we just need some date a date of
some materials so we can like load up
velvet and see that it looks sort of
like velvet least as just a poor man's
test like I just need something so I can
load up something and see if it looks at
all right
you know Messiah yes yes Messiah correct
that's the game Thank You Ryan
they were doing something totally
different
yeah yeah
so it's a little hard to see I think
also because I'm pretty sure this stuff
was software rendered so the character
had to be fairly small on the screen
right but you can kind of see like it's
a really weird like rendering idea but
it was it was allowed them to get much
higher polygon count characters because
it's sort it's almost like a voxel II
kind of render if I remember correctly I
think it was software rendered I don't
really know but anyway all right I'm go
ahead and wrap it up
close this down close this down thank
you everyone for joining me for what
would have been another episode of
handmade hero if Linux hadn't ruined
everything as it always does I will be
back here tomorrow when since hopefully
the sound is sort of more or less maybe
kind of working slightly I'll go listen
to the recordings to see if I think it's
okay but basically yeah I'll be back
here tomorrow to try and do some actual
programming if Linux is okay with that
and if it's not we will just throw the
machine out the window and maybe
hopefully have a camera down at the
bottom we can get a good slow-motion
video of a computer breaking apart into
pieces as usual if you do want to follow
along the series at home you always
upload the code every night so if you
preorder the Hammad hero game on our
website you can download the code and
follow along at home with what I'm doing
and I do include the handmade Rey code
in there in case you want to try playing
around with that yourself at some point
I will be back here tomorrow to try and
do some programming hopefully see you
back here tomorrow and hopefully it'll
go smoother than it did today until then
have fun program everyone and I'll see
you all on the Internet take it easy
everybody