hello everybody and welcome handmade
here I'll show recode a complete game
live on stream we have to improve our
lighting quality today we actually I
think we debugged most of the weirdness
that was going on yesterday with the
lighting flicker and today we have to
start dealing with the fact that we
would like to produce good lighting
results without introducing flicker from
our sampling and there's a lot of ways
we can do this there's a lot of things
that we kind of need to start looking at
the primary thing I want to start with
because what we were having trouble with
at the end of yesterday is I want to
start trying to get to a place where we
can have good balanced lighting so
basically like I want to start to be at
least slightly more rigorous in
understanding how light is put into the
system and how it drains out of the
system and right now we don't really
have a very coherent way of looking at
that and it's a fairly confusing problem
because you're trying to come up with an
approximation for something and your
approximation is gonna be nothing like
what the real thing is doing because
again I've said this before when we
started with lighting you're talking
about a process that the real world uses
you know billions or trillions of
particles to evaluate and we are talking
about thousands or tens of tens of
thousands of particle equivalents that
we have to use to evaluate and so
basically the fundamental way in which
we look at the problem has to differ
from how nature does it very
dramatically because we need to carry so
much more information for every one of
those particles than nature test right
so we need to kind of be very aware of
all of the ways that we can try to
sacrifice some of the accuracy without
sacrificing apparent visual quality as
we change over the nature of the
computation from what we know to be
correct to something that is incorrect
but still pleasing and that's very
difficult thing to do because you just
don't have nature as your guide right
when you're simulating something and you
can afford to do a good simulation of it
you're actually although you know the
cost to you may be high in terms of
learning and math and understanding of
the problem you kind of do have a nice
benefit which is that you are looking to
nature the thing that you actually
wanted to replicate you are looking to
it as a guide and it can guide you in
our case we really can't do that we are
looking to create a sort of parallel
process that is very different from the
way that it actually would be computed
and that's why it's a very challenging
sort of approximation to develop because
it is so far afield from what's actually
happening so anyway so I see there as
being a couple important things that we
need to focus on now as we've tried to
improve the quality of how we're doing
our letting transport given the low
number of samples we get to take so what
we effectively want to compute is you
know a very simple you know going back
to the original problem it's actually
fairly simple right it's just sort of a
series of these bounces you know if I've
got a surface here and I'm trying to
complete compute the lighting at this
point so this is my you know this is my
sample point for the lighting and no
matter how we structure it even if we
drastically change the way that we're
doing our sample points how they're
distributed what they mean whatever
we're still always going to come back to
this exact fundamental problem which is
that at the sample point we
fundamentally want to have a ton of
different information about how things
bounce off the
surface and then bounce off other
surfaces in the world and so on and so
forth right and the problem that we have
is that normally what we care about is
we care about a continuous process of
light being emitted from an emitter so
something that generates light which is
photons right coming out continuously
these photons are going to bounce around
and then eventually get collected by a
sink which is our eye right so there's a
photon generator and a photon
you know Eliminator essentially and the
total flow of photons through the sink
is what we are measuring now the reason
that this doesn't help us that much in
terms of a fundamental structure is
because although it lets us know one
crucial thing about the problem which is
that for the surfaces in the world the
path along which you go to get from the
emitter to the sink is what's important
and that is true that's true for ours
that's true for here immediately
subsequent to that everything about the
problems looks different and here's why
first of all like I already said the
number of photons emitted by an emitter
and received by the sink are drastically
higher in the real world than we will
ever get to with the hardware we're
talking about right they're talking
about trillions we're talking about you
know ten thousand so that scale alone is
a problem but beyond that we have a
second problem that really changes the
nature of the solution and that is
because we know we cannot do a good
enough sampling of this process we know
we're going to do much lower level
sampling of it much lower quality we
need to be able to deal with it across
frames and in order to deal with it
across frames it means we have to store
the information about what
surfaces lighting characteristics were
on the surface or at least ample points
right and that's crucial because now we
have to have a way of recording what
sort of lighting is occurring at a point
and that is not something we ever had to
deal with in the previous formulation
the previous formulation just says I
have a path through the world therefore
I know that a photon would have gone
this route and I can evaluate what each
bounce would have done to this photon
probabilistically done right did this
photon reach the eye or not and what
wavelength was it that's all right but
now we're introducing this additional
concept which is like light stored let
you know some information about the
lighting stored at the sample points and
one of the problems that we're running
into right now in our lighting algorithm
is we have no formal way of talking
about that at all we have not developed
any sort of rigor to that measurement
it's just a completely made-up
floating-point number called emit C zero
right and we have no idea what it means
no idea at all right so I think that's
the first thing we have to tackle is we
need a formulation for stored light
that means something and even if that
thing is basically identical to what
we're already doing just understanding
it a little more deeply about what that
number is supposed to represent I think
will help us as we try to improve our
algorithm because then at least we know
what we're talking about and we're not
just fiddling with floating-point
numbers hoping that something goes our
way right which is a valid way to find
an algorithm if you really don't know
you know random search is totally fine
but obviously if we can get better than
random search we would like to you know
there's no sense being random in your
search for your algorithm if you can
find some way of doing some math or
doing some thinking to get you to carve
off the space of possibilities into some
narrower space so that that search can
be more constrained and more successful
more quickly right so pretty basic I do
there so we need a formulation for
stored light that means something and
then the second thing we need is a
understanding of emission and I don't
know what we want to call the sink side
of things emission and I guess
nullification extinguishing
so basically in our system currently we
don't distinguish between the light that
the game told us was getting emitted on
a frame right that's the emission values
that are actually specified like we've
got those little hopper snake dudes who
are hopping around and they've got a
little lights attached to them right
we've got our white cube that we well
it's not oh the cube it's more like a
prism our white box that we move around
and that emits light and we've got the
skylight which we can turn on which
emits light as a dome so those are three
things that are emitting light right now
but all they do is just right into the
emit c0 array which is the same place
that all of the surface stored light
from previous frames that's bounced
around that's the same place that that
goes so right now we don't even do any
thinking about what it means to mix
something that's emitting light
continuously as a generator of light and
something that's just storing the result
of light that has bounced around and
again that may be fine meaning it may be
fine to have those in the same array
working the same way but we need to
understand that what does that mean
because one is measuring one quantity
one type of thing in nature and one is
measuring something different in one
case with the actual emitters we're
measuring something that radiates
photons itself right a lamp the Sun
whatever it's something that has a
actual physical reaction occurring
inside it that is generating new photons
so photons do not to come from anywhere
they are coming out of this thing with
no need for anybody to do anything right
the other elements all the rest of the
elements in emits e zero besides those
ones that got set by actual emitters in
the render push call all the rest of
those values are all talking about light
that is transient right it's light that
came from an emitter at some point in
the past and is now sitting on this
surface and can be bounced away all
right now there's a final thing that I'd
like to include in this analysis one
more thing so this is let's call this
number one we'll call this number two
there's one more thing and that is the
difference between the render color and
the emission so one more thing that we
don't really address is when we have
light that's inbound on a surface we are
using a single value that will then be
pushed to the renderer that colors that
surface right so the surface itself has
a reflection color there's an inbound
light color and that inbound light color
times the surface color is what we use
to render the surface now that result is
the same result that we use to bounce
the light around so on any given frame
the thing that we draw on the screen is
the same thing as what we're saying will
be emitting light on the next frame that
seems reasonable right because that's
how light works what we when we look at
a surface what we see is the light
that's coming towards us from the
surface it's light that has been bounced
off the surface so the render color that
the eye sees and the thing that other
elements see when they go to take light
from a surface it makes sense that those
would be the same right so that's not
weird
you know that's reasonable but we have
no rigor about that either right we
don't even say what that value is stored
as is that suppose
to be flux is supposed to be the number
of photons passing that are inbound on
this site as far as we know is it
supposed to be the number of photons
that we expect to leave the site and so
on and so forth right now it's I believe
the number technically what we're doing
is is you know the amount of photons
inbound on the site because we haven't
multiplied it by the reflection color of
the surface yet we're just storing the
inbound light so I think that's the the
in radiance at that point is what we're
actually storing in no particular units
right but just some a value that's
quantifying that right and so when we
push that down you know it seems
reasonable right but we need to again
understand make sure all of that
understanding is clear and that there
isn't a difference that we need to
respect there that has you know
ramifications for the for the way the
lighting is transmitted or anything else
like that right so we just want all of
those in there and I think out of these
you know these are the two that need to
kind of get really worked on this like I
said I think we want to kind of just
nail down but it seems like we sort of
addressed that early on and haven't we
have not been to fast and loose with
that like we did actually correctly
remember like okay here's the light
inbound the surface and then when we go
to transmit that light or render that
light we multiply the real active color
that seems you know plausible to a
certain extent right okay
all right but okay so one let me just
point one thing out
there's thought of on point three the
reason I think it's worth considering is
because for example one of the things
that we're having right now is we have a
little bit too much we have trouble
keeping our light balance correct and
one of the things about number three is
that for example when we are
transmitting light between surfaces and
we're taking the inbound light on one
surface and we're translating it into
inbound light on another surface I don't
know for example if we are correctly
representing the power drain necessary
on the outbound surface as compared to
the inbound surface we may be for
example subtracting away the light
multiplied by the reflection color which
would be wrong you know there's there's
a couple things like that right so it's
it's just worth noting that like again
although we are sort of this is more
rigorous in the system than the other
two it's more it was more thought
through a little bit it's still not
thought through all the way and it's
probably not at the point where it needs
to be in terms of our understanding even
if the code is right we need to again
make sure that we're actually thinking
about that everywhere that we need to be
thinking about that okay so that's
that's how I want to think about that
okay so let's talk a little bit about
what we need what we're trying to
accomplish here in light of these three
things so we have situations now where
we've got this sort of thing occurring
we've got you know p0 and p1 and the
first thing is that really we can use
right now what we're using is
uni-directional transport right so what
happens is we find from a sample point
in the world
we find another sample point in the
world and right now we actually use more
than one so right now we're actually
blending so you know if we've got
another p2 here and we happen to land
you know more in between the two will
average right so we're using a blend but
the important part is when we do this
hit we only move light from here to here
so it's unidirectional because it only
goes this way
now we could stick with you in a
directional transport and we may want to
the reason that we might want to stick
with unidirectional transport is because
it may end up being that if we need to
do a decoupled version of this algorithm
it may be that unidirectional transport
is easier to decouple into something
that can be multi-threaded or you know
GPU or whatever it's possible I don't
know we haven't looked at it yet but if
we assume temporarily that there isn't
some ancillary performance benefit to
unidirectional transport that we don't
know about yet because it only exists in
a structure of the routine that we
haven't addressed if we're just talking
about the structure of our current
routine bi-directional transport would
be much more efficient here why because
what is the expensive part of our
equation well the expensive part of our
equation is finding the path right we
don't the problem is not the few
calculations that we have to do to do
the light transport the hard part is the
fact that when we go to figure out what
we hit we have to look through like
hundreds even with the spatial hierarchy
hundreds of things to find out what that
path actually was and so finding the
path is expensive and rather than only
using the path to transport light one
way what we really would rather do is
use it to transfer transport light both
ways right because if we do a
bi-directional transport where we
basically say oh when we
transfer information let's take light
from these and give it to this one let's
also take light from this one and give
it to these and that way we can look at
light equalization between two things
which again very common in radiosity
it's not an unusual thing so since we
are basically a radiosity scheme at this
point seems like a reasonable thing to
try because that gets us twice the
efficacy from our pathfinding because
now instead of having to wait for p1 to
find the path back to p0 we can just use
the fact that p0 found a path to p1 and
know that p one could have seen p 0 if p
0 can see p1 p1 can see p 0 there's no
difference in the sidedness of these
paths
it's just whether a line connects them
so as soon as we find a path from one to
the other we also have paths from the
other to the one that's just a given in
how ray-tracing is structured right
either there was an obstacle Block in
the liner there wasn't so if we change
using bi-directional transport I also
think we would be able to get more
leverage out of the same number of path
lines twice as much information there
which is great so what I'd like to do is
certainly explore that as a separate
option which is just to say we can start
looking this as a bi-directional problem
I think we'll get more efficacy there ok
so let's start talking about this a
formulation for stored light to mean
something
so let's say I've got something that's
emitting photons here I've got a
reflector and I've got a collector here
and by the way this is not me trying to
teach you something this is me literally
trying to figure this out so I'm not
suggesting that I already know the
answer
I'm just pontificating about it just
completely open-ended so if this is
something that's emitting I guess I
should say collecting I said a meeting
so I have something that sending photons
this way and I have something thats
collecting photons over here and I'm
bouncing them out then the thing that I
need to know for a particular surface
here right is if I was going to take a
frozen moment in time right so if I want
to look at like an instant in time what
I could say is I could say something
like I want to know the photons per
second right that are passing through
this reflector because even though this
reflector like even though there is no
color right technically at this
reflector because color is something
that only happens when we perceive it we
can still store the quantity that we
care about for reconstructing this seam
so let's say we wanted to remember a
single value that would list get rid of
this emitter and just remember the
reflector and then properly calculate
what happened at the collector right
well photons per second is the thing
that we could keep right if we know the
photons per second that we're inbound
here and coming out this way right that
were that were transiting this bounce
just this one bounce
the photons per second for that bounce
would tell us exactly what we needed to
know to figure out how many photons per
second are getting collected at this
collector right now this ignores the
color like I said but you could imagine
extending this pretty trivially to three
colors right red green blue by just
throwing the photons per second for each
so that's not that complicated we can
kind of just think of this as monochrome
so if we think of each of our reflectors
as having a photons per second that's
inbound and outbound right that is a
sort of different understanding of it
than what we're using now what we're
using right now is more like actual
number of photons in a sense in that we
keep them on the surface and then send
them away so we don't really have the
notion of the photons per second that
are transiting through we sort of just
have a notion of the number of photons
that are sitting on this surface right
and that's kind of confusing the
difference between those two things is
subtle but it could make a difference so
it's worth noting that the thing we
actually care about the value we
actually care about is an idea of how
many photons per second are transiting
through this particular surface and we
don't really have that in the current
system but we could imagine that it's
probably related to the number of
photons that ended up stuck on this
surface but maybe it doesn't really you
know who knows all right so
uhh
for example suppose we were going to
suppose we were going to change the way
we looked at this problem a little bit
here is a way that photons per second
versus photons would be important like I
said we are sampling you know we're a
shooting based radiosity because we
can't afford to do anything else which
means we're just taking Monte Carlo
samples right actually very much like
the paper that was referenced yesterday
we're just taking Monte Carlo samples
and then trying to reconstruct what the
radiosity is out there we're not doing a
large linear system solve which is one
way you can do radiosity we're not doing
anything that would be considered
considered a simultaneous solve it's an
iterative shooting scheme right the most
sort of basic kind you can do because
that's what we can afford to do at 60
frames a second overtime and we're
trying to make that converge to
something that would be a stable
solution right and of course converge to
a stable solution is not even really
what we want because lights are moving
every frame and stuff like that so we're
just want it to be something that
becomes consistent over time if
everything was stationary right okay so
for example let's suppose we have
photons per second as an estimate on a
particular reflector and now we want to
update the world well you could imagine
a shooting photons right not photons per
second but actual photons from an
emitter looking at how many hit the
surface and bounce out and update our
photons per second based on that number
right so we have a quantity that sort of
saying how much generally bounces
through the surface well how much
bounced through the surface this frame
right how many went in here so every
time something hits a surface we send it
out we send out all of it right we do
full we just bounce photons around like
a photon tracer would but then like a
radiosity solver would we then say okay
let's try and figure out what that means
for our stable photons
right so again you can imagine sort of
thinking about this in two different
ways
they're sort of the concept that we have
a certain number of paths that are that
we're evaluating and then we're trying
to update a value which is photons per
second which can be only loosely related
to what the path says right the path is
just one sample that gives us a hint
about how the photons per second is
probably changing so
so given that let's talk about what
happens when we want to evaluate two
surfaces let's okay yeah so let's expand
on this concept so let's suppose we were
talking about photons per second
everywhere so an emitter also has a
photons per second and that photons per
second value is constant right so we
know that this emitter you can't modify
the number of photons per second it's
putting out because it will always put
out the same number of photons per
second that's what makes it an emitter
right so unlike the other elements in
the system and this is kind of an
important piece of understanding like I
said we're trying to get to this
understanding by thinking through the
problem about what we know about light
so if an emitter is putting out a
certain number of photons per second
then it should never be modified meaning
that value that's in its emission
quantity doesn't go down it can't write
because an emitter outputs light all the
time it's not something that can be
diminished it's always gonna have the
same photons per second right so rather
than thinking and I think this is good I
like where this is going rather than
thinking about the system as an array of
values and we put some quantity in one
place and we let it flow to another and
it goes out of there almost like water I
don't like that as much as thinking
about it in terms of photons per second
so the emitters are basically a separate
array that's saying here's where light
is always coming from these are
constants and then we have a secondary
array right which is thresholded on that
so we're basically saying it the
secondary array which actually computes
the photons per second for everybody
those get cold copied in and hard set
always to the same photons per second
right and everybody else's photons per
second are equalizing out and can be can
be mushed around right that's a more
coherent way to think about it for me
because it goes back to values we can
actually put our finger on
right flooding photons into a value in
letting them drain out creates this
weird thing about what should that
quanta be and how should we normalize it
whereas photons per second is something
I can put my finger on and say it's
constant for emitters everybody else it
equalizes out based on our samples right
what we guessed that it should be okay
so now we come to sort of the the crux
of this understanding that we need to
determine and that is suppose we're not
talking about emitters we just have
photons per second so all of these are
photons per second and now we've got a
situation where we've traced a path
between two of them so we know that for
example if this is you know sample zero
actually let's just use a and B so if we
knew we have a point a and point B right
and B has a certain you know we'll call
this F B we'll call this f of a we know
that there are certain amounts of
photons per second passing through these
points based on our previous estimate
now we don't know how to make that
estimate but we know this is an
iterative algorithm so we're just going
to assume for the purposes of
determining how we do our updates we're
gonna assume that we have determined
some number of photons per second that
are passing through these points but
that's all we know now in one case
because it's in a in a sense this is
inductive right it's saying we know you
know we know what the first thing is we
know what F 0 was we don't know what F 1
is so we're trying to get the thing that
takes us from F 0 to F 1 and we do know
a start-up case which is an emitter we
know the sample the protons per second
at the emitter because we're specifying
its what makes it at emitter so we do
know how we're gonna get our
first set of photons per second so now
the question is if we assume that some
people have photons per second-- we just
don't know who they are
how do we update other people based on
that information so if we know right
that this has a certain amount of
photons per second passing through it
and we know that this has a certain
number of photons for a second passing
through it and we know that they are
connected so they can send photons to
each other how can we update the photons
per second in a way that starts to
properly equalize our light so I think
the first thing we want to recognize is
that the photons per second is not a
value that comes and goes and I think
this is where I was where we're sort of
my basic idea before of how to compute
the radiosity was just kind of wrong was
that I was doing it more based on quanta
which is just not a useful way of doing
it again photons per second I think I
think this makes a much clearer picture
photons per second is not something that
comes and goes photons per second is
something that we need to use an
estimate of what we think the photons
per second should be based on what we've
seen and what we were so I think what
we'd rather do is for every person that
we're summing we want to take every you
know photon per second path that we
found right and averaged so if we found
a number of these paths for B for the
you know on the next frame the
subsequent one is for every photon
splitting passed we found we average
those photons per second together
right so we basically say well if I saw
this guy right let's say this is f of C
if I saw this guy and this was a certain
photons per second and I saw this guy
and this was a certain photons per
second then obviously and my say average
I mean using the cosine influx right so
we're gonna wait based on angle
certainly using the averaging those
together should give us the photons per
second inbound at this point right it's
not addition it's an average why because
we want to know the average photons per
second passing through this point it
doesn't add them up as if they were
quantities that shot at us individually
it's just an average of what's the light
I can see well the light I can see is an
average of all of the photons per second
of all the surfaces that I can look out
and and proceed right and if we want to
take that a step further in the future
we can have different surface Quantic
qualities that actually react
differently to different angles as well
but I don't know that we you know in
other words not just cosine fall off but
actually have lobes of reflectance I
don't think we want to do that because I
don't think we're shooting enough raised
to really do much surface approximation
in that way but you know you could see
how you would extend this technique in
that way so I think we want to do for
every path we find we averaged the
photos per second module of the cosine
term and then we assume that our photons
per second can only change at a
particular rate and this is to avoid the
flicker right so again we assume now in
addition that you know we blend with the
previous frame
based on a maximum change rate so again
I think we're really close
algorithmically to what we want but we
just need to change our thinking about
it a little bit and change what our
quantities mean and I think once we
change what our quantities mean to
something a little more amenable to what
we're doing I think we're gonna be okay
so mainly just changing to an average
and then retaining that concept of a
blend at the end okay so that all makes
really good sense sense to me why does
that make a sense to me because that
solves number two as well now we don't
have to think about photons coming from
and going to somewhere because all we're
doing is thinking about the flux we're
just thinking about the amount of light
passing through a surface we are no
longer thinking about an individual
piece of light that goes now we are
thinking about that in terms of the path
tracing but we're just using those
particles as tracers to figure out how
to update the photons per second we're
not using them as if they were actual
quanta of light that we're pushing
around right it's very subtle smallest
little difference but sometimes the
smallest difference can make all the
difference right and then finally this
for number three I think we get the
answer out of that as well which is that
once we know the photons per second and
again we can keep through our path
tracing an average light direction
that's all we need to hand to the
renderer the average light Direction
plus the photons per second of red green
and blue channels that should be enough
for it to do the lighting computation
that it needs to do at that point right
so I think that's a fairly sane way of
looking at the problem and again photons
per second is an abstract idea we don't
have to actually measure photons per
second because photons per second would
be an astronomically high number so
we're talking about some scaled quantity
that just relates to the photons per
second so say 1.0 is a million or a
billion photons per second or something
right we don't have to actually tie this
quantity back to something physical in
terms of its actual value we're just
trying to tie to something physical in
terms of its meaning and that's crucial
because that's the part that will allow
us to do a good solution right the
unit's are irrelevant in terms of their
scale they're not irrelevant in terms of
their semantic quality so understanding
that this is a linear quality relating
to photons per second that's the
important part and some part that we
weren't really talking about or thinking
about before where as the what whether
it's actually photons per second or some
other like billion photons for a second
or something that part is not relevant
because the scale is tunable by us based
on the exposure value we want for the
brightness of the scene what we want our
light values to mean so that's just a
separate part of the equation we can
look at later it doesn't matter for
purposes of the lighting because the
lighting is going to produce the same
solutions regardless of what the scale
of those values actually is it's just
the renderers brightness that will
change so we need to you know be aware
of that in the second half of things
essentially so I'm pretty happy with
that I'm pretty happy with that let's
take a look at how this routine is gonna
change cuz not gonna change that much
and then I also want to go ahead today
if we have time in addition to this
change well I haven't even opened my
command console yet there we go
in addition to this change I would like
to go ahead and make the bi-directional
version if we have time today because I
I'm pretty sure that is just
a smarter way to do it because finding
those halves is expensive and so I think
we want to as much as possible unless
there ends up being a really strong
reason why we are unable to do so I
would like to make it so that we can
reuse each path that we find ok so let's
take a look at how we're doing this here
so inside went in when we open up our
lighting test here what we've got is
we've got our emit C 0 and our emit C 1
values and what I'd like to do is now
make these values mean something a
little bit different perhaps than they
were before so what I'm going to do here
is go just gonna play around with it a
little bit just to see if I can set up a
situation that makes a little bit more
sense to me in terms of how to structure
the routine and we'll go through it step
by step so we know we've got two things
here we know we've got emit C 0 and we
know we've got to MIT C 1 so what I'd
like to do here is I'd like to move to
considering the emit C 0 as the actual
stated emission values of the light at a
particular time and emit C want well
okay you know I may be getting ahead of
myself here let me not say that quite
yet so we know that the emitters are
never gonna change their emission values
right so they're always going to be
exactly what you know whatever they were
we know that it's only the the average
value that's going the the the new value
for the next time that's going to be
changed so I think what we want to do
here is we want to rather than do this
as a plus what we want to do is see
whether this is an emitter or not and
update it that way right because if it's
an emitter it's gonna cold set the
photon value and if it's not that it's
not now there's
ways we can look at this one is that we
can support things that are both
emitters and reflectors I don't know
whether we want to do that or not we may
want to and if we want to then we need a
good way of understanding that that's
what's going on which means we're going
to need the you know we almost need like
a third array for that I think
because I don't really see a lot of ways
around it let me explain what I mean by
this
okay so let's suppose I have a surface
that's an emitter but it's also
reflector so we want to be able to
commute compute both at what's an
example well let's suppose this thing is
emitting red light but it's actually a
gray surface otherwise right so if green
light came in we would expect green
light to come out proportional to how
much went through that would be an
emitter reflector now why do we care
about this it may seem like a thing to
not really care about well let's suppose
we want things in the world that are not
lit that become lit and we want that
light to fade in well if they're not lit
originally they need to be reflectors in
order for you to see them at all they
might they just be black right but now
what's gonna happen is as the light
starts to fade in the instant you get
any emission there at all if you could
only be an emitter or a reflector it
will suddenly snap to black then
gradually become bright in red and lose
all of its previous color that will be a
nasty visual artifact so if we want to
be able to transition between an emitter
and a reflector nice and smooth even if
we don't care about anything else just
that effect I think we want to do both
so the thing that I'm concerned about
here is that if you look at what happens
with emission reflection on the
subsequent frames I need to be able to
know that I'm not adding in like this
additional emission that's coming from
the user I'm just saying that this is
how much has to be emitted at a minimum
right so I need to know the difference
between the emitted light and the
reflected light because if I don't keep
those quantities separate I don't know
on the subsequent frame how do
the emission value coming from the user
because I don't know how much light I
was trying to say I was taking above and
beyond that previous emission value so I
realized that's a little confusing
I just don't know another way to deal
with it at the moment
right so what I'd like to do is is maybe
just expand this a little bit and we can
collapse it down later you know we can
in the future try to do something where
we you know try to do something where we
handle this in a way that doesn't
require extra storage or something as we
optimize but just right now I'm just not
sure how to do it any other way so I
want to I want to be explicit while we
get this routine working the way we want
and then later I can optimize it if I
think I understand a good way to do that
right so I'm not going to call these
emit c0 and it's c1 or anything like
that I'm gonna actually start to be sort
of more explicit about this this is the
emission array so that's how much light
something is giving out let's say well
okay let me start with things I know so
this is my photons per second right like
we just talked about and so this will be
the starting or this is like accumulated
PPS
so we know we need an initial photons
per second and an accumulated photons
per second and we also then need some
emission photons per second which we
will add into the accumulated photons
per second to produce the final value
right I think that's essentially what we
want to talk about here I think not
entirely sure but you know what we may
not not need to track that though I
think we may only need to track these
two and then we can just add in the end
by doing this a second time I'm gonna
keep it as a separate array for now but
I think we can maybe get away without it
okay yeah okay all right so
let's go ahead and move forward with
this so let's suppose that we have the
let's suppose that we have these values
initialized the way we were doing it
before so we have the initial photons
per second and we want the initial
photons per second to be the old value
plus any emission that was going to come
through right and again these are we
don't have a specific unit for this so
we're just going to use whatever the old
units were and that's fine right we're
gonna stuff the initial photons for a
second this way
and the average direction to light is a
value that we're summing up and
averaging so this was actually this may
have been a big source of our flicker
actually I didn't for some reason
address this I didn't think about it
when we fixed the fact that we were
erroneously computing it before and that
was a source of flicker you know another
source of flicker is just the fact that
we are not waiting the average of these
two things to force the direction to
bend slowly over time so the other thing
that we want to do is we want to have a
stable update coefficient here right so
we want to have something that
effectively says all right
what is our sort of update per frame or
what is what is our update rate right so
our update sort of blend coefficient
here let's suppose that it's going to be
something like point 2f so it takes you
know five frames before we update our
lighting or something like that right
well if that's in you know maybe that's
too high I don't know you know this is a
tunable coefficient we have no idea also
we are doing this now
so let's get rid of that comment so if
that's the case then what that means is
that the the direction here actually
wants to be multiplied by that inverse
right so what we want to do is say 1.0
over the T update is what we want to
multiply this direction by so that it's
weighted much more strongly than the
average direction to light that we're
taking from everybody else right
that way when we add in all of the other
light samples that we get we can
minimize them that way now it's probably
the case that we would rather since we
don't know how many past samples were
going to take it's probably the case
that we would like to normalize those
separately and then blend in so another
way to look at this might be that we
really should clear this value and then
blend it afterwards right so it could be
that this should just be set this way
and then in the end when we go through
we do actually want to do that update
and now this stuff were this stuff where
we do that the blending
[Music]
I think we should be fine to just always
blend it will mean that at first things
get a little slow yeah maybe we want to
just use it right out of the gate
so I guess this is fine I guess the way
we're doing this here is fine
so this T Update value here is what
we're going to use so when we come
through here and we do our update we do
want to do exactly this meaning we want
to average our light direction with the
previous direction that's an important
step and I think we were getting flicker
from that before unfortunately
so we probably should have taken care of
that previously but unfortunately we
just didn't so now we've got that that
part and what we need to do now is we
need to take a look at our take a look
at our other values here and write those
back properly now I would like it if we
could do this a little bit more sanely
here it would be nice if we if these
were always if these values always kind
of could just be done in one loop I mean
I wish we can always do this and we just
stuff the values the problem is since
we're doing them over a set of points
like this I'm not sure how valid that
actually is but you know since we don't
care about the speed of this loop yet
it's not it's not part of our slowness
really what I could do here is actually
do the if inside so I could actually do
an if valid here and deal with that and
make it so that we actually can simplify
this down
all right so what I mean by this is
inside here where we're we're we're
doing our update per point instead of
going directly with the box storage
value we're gonna grab those out that
way they can be set to default values in
another in any other circumstance right
okay so we know we have an accumulated
PPS and an emission PPS and what we want
to do is we want to add those two
together for the final value that gets
written back right I'm sorry that's not
true what we want to do is only write
back the accumulated PPS because that's
the part that we're actually in a store
from last time
yeah when we output the lighting to the
actual lighting system then we use
accumulated plus emission PPS which is
what happens in output lighting points
sorry about that okay so what we want to
store here is we want to store our
accumulated PPS or our last PPS right in
last direction so these two values are
going to be equal to the ones we're
actually going to use so this is going
to be here we've got our accumulated PPS
in our direction and what we're gonna do
is we're gonna assume that those equal
whatever the ones we're going to blend
to are and then when we come in here to
actually store these values what we're
gonna do is we're going to do the blend
regardless in all circumstances but
we're just going to blend it with itself
in the case where the the thing wasn't
valid and that's just me simplifying
this routine because I didn't like
having to pass there again that's
something we might do when we're looking
at performance but right now we know
this isn't a slow part of the routine so
we can afford to just do it in a way
that's cleaner and easier for us to
debug okay shouldn't say cleaner it's
not really about cleanliness it's about
simplicity so if we come through here
and we're going to set the box storage
local index dot emit that's essentially
the last PPS value here so that's going
to it I don't think we need to actually
update emit c0 in this way necessarily
here because this value is not we're
right well okay so we do want it because
we need it to be picked up from
somewhere so I guess that's fine so we
know that this is this accumulated PPS
and in fact I suppose we can sort of
make this a pointer as well if you want
to but let's go ahead and just a little
bit more explicitly here so if I grab
out my accumulated PPS here and my
average vector to light those are the
ones that we computed on this frame and
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna update
them here the way they should be so we
know this one should be normalized at
the direction because it was an average
here we know this one needs to be
averaged over the number of samples that
were taken and right now we don't know
how many samples were taken so that's an
additional piece of information we're
gonna have to take
right so what we want to do here is take
the accumulated weight and multiply it
now that accumulated weight value might
be zero in the case we have enough
samples and that's fine that just means
that we didn't accumulate any photons
per second pass at this point that's
going to happen for services in the
world and that's fine and then we're
gonna normalize our direction to the
light because we know that we just
shoved a bunch of things in there and we
want the average we don't care what the
weight was because we have to normalize
it to a unit direction anyway right now
it may be that in the future we want to
not do that we want to use the weighting
of it to to and persist that forward so
that we know that when we take more
samples on a frame that we want to use
more of it and so on mmm yeah I'm gonna
go ahead and say let's not do that yet
because that gets into a little bit more
complicated like trying to see what we
should do sampling why serum and that's
a little bit much okay so if we have
last PPS here and last direction then
initialize to these two values we will
grab them out in the case where we know
that the previous values were okay and
then what we want to do is we want to do
a write back here that will produce the
final values that we need right
so we don't need to remember the average
direction to what we do again this is
just for the output routine if we did
output lighting points at the same time
not output let me point sorry if we did
output lighting textures at the same
time we wouldn't have to do that kind of
makes me think that that should be in
here
but again we'll just we'll deal with it
for now just it's not really that
important okay so the average direction
to light and the local index direction
that we're writing back those are going
to be this one's going to normalize just
the lerp between the old direction and
the new direction and that T update
there again is low because we we want to
take at least ten frames we're saying to
shift lighting over so because we just
don't think our our Sam place would be
good enough to update it any faster than
that without too much flicker so here's
that direction a projection to light
update this will update both of those
right and then finally we've got our box
storage last PPS value and again that's
going to look exactly the same so that's
just going to be alert between the
previous value and the new value so that
will just slowly move our expected
photons per second through the surface
and our expected direction to the light
source slowly over time towards what we
are seeing as the current accumulated
value and off we go right now
again I'm not sure this is really the
best way to sum these things because if
you imagine what's happening here it's
not
well you know yeah and I'm not gonna go
too much into it
point being we have a set of samples we
have samples from last frame samples
from this frame samples from next frame
whatever I'm not sure here that we're
waiting all of those samples as well as
we could be for our results here so take
that with a grain of salt I guess is
what I would say because it's it is a
little confusing to really know what's
supposed to be happening there right so
the other thing that I'm going to do
here is again I'm gonna set up the
emission values to be something that's
more understandable here so the emission
PPS I'm going to set for this light
index s so
and as you can see here so what I'm
trying to do is say all right I want to
remember what the emission value was for
this because I know that my initial PPS
and my accumulated PPS are not
representative of that the initial PPS
stores whatever amount of emission
particles per second we're supposed to
happen plus whatever the emitted ones
were and I know my accumulated is going
to be something that's based on all of
the averaging that's happening and so
what I want to do here is remember that
so that later when we come through here
to output the actual value I want the
color of the surface to be the
accumulated point photons per second
plus the emission photons per second
because that is actually coming at the
eye as well right
those emission emitters are coming
directly out of the surface in addition
to anything that bounced off the surface
so then if we say that we have that
information output I think we're good
here this same value is going to be used
up here like so and I think that's all
we really care about there all right
so again the only reason for storing it
there is because we don't want to
recreate it but we can recreate it so we
don't really need this you know this is
so we're just doing that to try and make
sure that there's less bugs look I don't
want to compute the letting in two
different places if we don't have to if
we can just store an array then it's
fine and so on and so forth right so
okay so then we go to compute light
propagation now we've got an update this
routine to be more reasonable now the
nice part here is that the blend amount
and the rate count and the power and all
this stuff I think goes away now I think
we just don't care about any of that it
doesn't matter so it can just be deleted
all we need to know is how many samples
we want to take which is the rate count
and that should be sufficient for our
purposes these values are all actually
VIII's here and we don't need total
added and removed we don't need a
complete sample to return anything to us
because it's not about that anymore and
we certainly don't need any of this
either so let's go through this now and
update it to do the thing that we wanted
to do this is there's no source omit Ord
estimate any more of those aren't things
neither is this so what we're gonna do
now I'm gonna stick with unidirectional
for now but again
I'm going to say that we want this
transfer to be bi-directional in the
future so off we go we come through here
we sample the hemisphere we find a path
that says that these two points can see
each other and then what we want to do
is we want to go ahead and record
samples for these points that tell us
how much is that tell us how the photons
per second should be perceived here
okay so accumulate sample is still I
think our friend the angular fall-off
still wants to be there the light power
is not relevant anymore
so that goes away I believe so it is
strictly the angular fall-off in
question the weight is just the angular
fall-off times that light color and I
think this is what we're talking about
here
right so we want to sum up the value
here we want to sum up these two values
and so actually when we're looking at
what we're summing into all of this I
think we should just pass the sample
index right because this is going to be
the surface normal is going to be just
the points normal right so I think we
can kind of not do it quite so I think
we can make this much more concise I
guess is what I'll say so the surface
normal if we just pass instead the
lighting solution here then what we can
say is the solution points for the
sample index is the surface normal that
we're talking about here the angular
fall-off is going to be the surface
normal on the normal to light right and
the normal to light will still get
passed in the weight is the length of
that light color there and that's good
and then all of these are are going to
be pulled off with a solution right so
the solution accumulated weight is going
to be plus equal something the solution
accumulated EPS is going to be plus
equal this and the solution cumulate our
average directional light
it's gonna come through there as well so
so this is really gonna be computed here
we can just use that since that
distributes those are the same answer
right so the wait times the neural looks
the light you can just get from lengthen
the color sample they're the accumulated
per second is just a sample color and so
that's the sample that we're taking for
particle four sorry for photons per
second and so now the question is just
what is the accumulated weight well if
we just want to average all of our
samples together it would just be one if
we want to use the angular fall-off to
say that some samples are more important
than others or something like this then
we would set it something else I'm going
to set it to one for now
and we can wait those differently if we
want to in the future okay so we don't
need this just need that so we just past
the destination sample index we pull all
the values off of that and then we just
need to pass the service not the service
in just the light color and the normal
to light and that's our cumulate sample
so that's how we would do that I'm not
sure if we want to pass an additional
scaler here because it could be
optimized potentially that way we'll see
in a second but looks pretty good so
let's go ahead and move accumulate
sample down here yeah into what we're
actually doing so we now know the the
right the sample that we're accumulating
is is this one
and so we want to pass the solution of
the death sample index and then we want
the light color which is you know this
mythical omit C value and I'm going to
change that to basically the transfer
PPS that's like how much we're trying to
give it and then the normal to the light
is going to be the sample direction that
when we know exactly so that's how we
will accumulate our sample this is not a
thing at the moment although we may want
to do that as a measure in the future I
suppose of what the total light is but
let's see what's going on here source
some test some I think all we really
have to do is some clearing here so
before we start the the sample stuff has
to get cleared so emission initial so in
here we need solution accumulated PPS
needs to be set to nothing and in
addition to accumulated PPS to be set to
nothing accumulated weight needs to be
set as well
all right so let's go ahead and update
this routine here when we do this this
is gonna be our transfer PPS here I
guess we call this C we want to change
this to be bi-directional eventually so
it shouldn't really be transferred PPS
but we'll call it that temporarily so
when we come through here right we're
gonna sum up the total weight that
doesn't change cuz doesn't it's just
crude producing a weighting value for
each of these points and then when we
come through here and we loop through
these we're basically gonna say this is
how the the the source emits e right is
what we're grabbing from that's now
gonna be our solution not accumulated
initial PPS so that's the previous
frames photons per second plus the
emission so that initial PPS that comes
in that's how much this doesn't happen
anymore
that's how much we're talking about here
and so the transfer PPS is either the
moon color or I think it's this contribs
ear right that weighted contribution of
how much of that has you know it's been
equaled out now the other thing we can
do here
so actually I guess now that I think
about it I'm looking at this to do that
says is there any way we can get rid of
the second loop and the answer is isn't
there it seems like there is because if
we look at what's happening here we're
summing up a total weight value and that
weight value is going to divide our
contribution right but we could instead
just multiply by the raw weight value
whatever this value is here right and
then multiply the entire thing by the
inverse total weight later because it's
a constant so what we should be able to
do here is say that the transfer of PBS
gets some directly right I mean I don't
see why not
if I just take the the weight value here
and I say sum the values multiplied by
the weighting value and some of the
weight when I'm done I will have the
inverse right and I can just take the
transfer PPS and multiply it by the
inverse total weight and I'm done right
I mean I don't see any reason why I
can't do that maybe I'm missing
something but so it does seem like I
don't know why I thought I needed two
loops I guess I was just kind of out to
lunch or maybe I'm missing something
there but that certainly seems fine I
don't know that we need that at all
anymore
and this is mr. fantasies all right so
now we've got a bunch of debugging to do
and like you know validating kind of
what I just did because it's sort of
we've made a bunch of changes and we
need to now like step through them and
get them you know I put in what we said
on the blackboard just my first pass at
how to make that work but it's not gonna
be correct right as you can see so we
have to now like actually go make this
you know a debug it make sure we don't
have any weird bugs in here which we
probably do and then B we need to like
turn the dial and make sure that we've
got all the weird stuff out of it right
good news is obviously there's no
framerate issues here so you know we're
pretty much okay in terms of Perth I
think so it's really just going ahead
and getting this to be computing the
thing that I wanted to compute all right
so I'm going to go ahead and turn off
optimization and we're gonna step
through this and start to make you know
try to make sure that everything is is
working correctly
there we go all right so I'm gonna come
through here and first thing I just want
to look at is what's happening to my
solution buffer so this is where all of
the operations take place so obviously I
want to make sure that these things are
all set to something reasonable right so
here we have set p1 and so we don't
expect it to be any change there the
points are what the points are but all
this stuff is different so let's see
what our initial PPS is this should all
be 0 basically there's none from
previous frames and that so only just a
few places where there's emitters should
we see anything same is true with
accumulated weight that should all be 0
and it is same with accumulated PPS that
should be 0 right and that is getting
set there which is good and the same
with emission PPS that should be set to
0 everywhere other than where the
emission is occurring right um so I
think that should be pretty good you
know I I imagine that if we look at this
right if we look at a mission there
should just be like some little place
where the emission is set to something
of course it's hard to find here should
probably be setting this to the smaller
number so we can have a better chance of
actually finding the people who are
emitting
I'm gonna go ahead and just make one and
then I'm gonna look at the emission
array I don't know how many points we
have 1849 so there we go so here's a
bunch of 1.5 emitters I don't know how
we got emission values is 1.5 that's not
supposed to be it's supposed to be 0 to
1 great work guys
you crushed it I'm gonna go you know
what
I'm gonna go ahead and say that that's
just not allowed and we're gonna fix
everywhere that is doing that because I
don't know how oh no no no
false alarm
that's post multiply so we're all fine
totally fine everyone relax all right so
we knew our emitter is set here if we
look at how many of these are set to 1.5
I'm assuming that's for a snake right
should be one more at the end for our
box and all the rest should be zeros
there we go all right so that's exactly
what we would should expect that's good
average direction to light should all be
zeros and days and so off we go now
we're going to do our compute light
propagation function we're going to come
through here and let's just take a look
brief look at how this is working as
well and we also got to check the output
part so we've read out a point and we
try to find someone to transfer with in
this case we did we come through here
and we compute a total waiting value
which is based on the you know I should
also the same time and probably since
this is our first frame probably
whatever it hit has no light on it
anyway so I'm guessing transfer but yet
it is a zero so the total weight is this
is the total weight it's going to divide
out something that was already zero so
we'll just get zero and no one cares
well then go into the sample
accumulation so we need the sample
direction you know that's where we're
going to get the light we have the
transfer value which is nothing get the
sample point index in the solution we
come through here and we say all right
the surface normal it's gonna be
whatever the destination samples index
normal was and that's exactly what we
expect right totally fine we've got the
angular fall-off which is the normal to
the light source and so there's our
fall-off factor we've got our sample
color now which is that's how much we're
actually going to add in here for the
particle seconds that are being added
flux wise again it's nothing the weight
is also nothing for changing the average
direction to lights the average
direction to light will not change based
on this value we have the accumulated
weight which again is just going to go
up by one so it should just be one
and off we go now the accumulated weight
value in this case I guess accumulated
weight will always be the Ray count at
the moment so in theory because we
always count like the moonlight as the
thing you hit you can't hit nothing we
can't actually get rid of that
accumulate accumulate weight value in
the future we can make accumulated
weight just be a constant right it
doesn't need to be it can just be the
number of samples that we take per point
unless we adjust that value in an
unpredictable way we could just get rid
of it because we know it's just rate
count and rate count could just be a
constant so again we come through here's
another example where we have the moon
color coming in so the moon color now
has a very specific transfer value we're
gonna come in here look at the angular
fall-off the angular fall is actually
pretty high in this case why is it high
well the normal to light is very it's
very pointy compared to the normal right
so the normal is pointing direct
directly to the left
perfectly left but the light value is
more upward than that so we're going to
go ahead and get some transfer but it's
not going to be a lot of transfer okay
so that looks fine right that's
basically what we wanted to know there's
some things in cure that we want to do
and in fact I'll add one more comment
the thing that I want to do just so I
don't forget
probably something to make our sampling
more uniform than it is right now would
help us so we probably want a stratified
sampling scheme we'll talk about that is
later but it's just something that makes
sure that we don't sample in a very
biased way due to randomness on a
particular frame it's a way of sort of
making your num random numbers less
random to improve things anyway so when
we do all those accumulations that seems
for you Oh oops
so at the end then we need to go look at
the output step the up it phase so let's
go ahead and do that so we assume that
we did our light propagation now and now
we're gonna grab the there we go look
count 24 so now we oh that's just a typo
well that's very bad no wonder we
weren't getting anything sensible at
first that's a pretty big initial bug
that's not supposed to be there valid is
only there to see whether or not the
read original values were useable so I
don't know what's going on there yeah
that was just that was just dumb
yeah that was just straight-up down
furthermore this valid really should be
done per per time at this point and I
think we should just go ahead and do
that because again we're gonna have to
figure out how we want to do that valid
bit a little bit real later but I'm just
going to go ahead and do it here all
right let's take a look at what the
results are now that we've got rid of
that stupidity they're so kind of
ridiculous actually so still kind of a
little bit nuts so let's go ahead and
step through this and see what's going
on here
so these also need to get clamped which
I didn't do so we should probably also
do that but I'm gonna skip that for the
moment
oh but you know what no I'm not gonna do
that right now
so I don't forget uh you know what no
I'm not I lied because they get clamped
in the shader I believe am I wrong about
that so here in the Z bias program and
would expect to see the light that is
getting clamped know so they don't they
don't get clamped so they probably
should get clamped in the shader rather
than not
so I think I'm just going to go ahead
and say that they'll get they're gonna
get clamped in the shader so in here
whenever stuff happens and we end up
taking whatever the surface reflectance
is I'm then gonna go ahead and clamp
that so I'm just gonna make sure that
that value can exceed 1 and it won't
cause weird color overflow artifacts
right which may have been why the whole
thing turned black before I'm not sure
no it's not muscle just overflowed and
some other weird way all right so I'm
just gonna leave that in there because I
want to make sure that that's something
that ya can can overflow if it wants to
alright so let's go ahead and and check
this out now that it's actually gonna
enter the part of the loop that we care
about there so we're gonna go ahead and
take for any particular point here we're
gonna use the accumulated PPS value
there's how much light it thought it
received here's the direction it thought
it was coming from and it's gonna go
ahead and
so on the first frame Oh
that's garbage as well not doing great
on the on the mind slips today so I want
last I want to use the last direction
here to do the valid check right so this
actually should be something more like
that um so yeah
that looks more reasonable to me and I
also think there's another thing we
could do here which is if we don't get a
valid normal we could set that normal to
something else as well I'm gonna ignore
that for now all right so that's a
little bit better right okay so now
let's step through here and look at
what's going on so when we check the
valid value it should be false on the
first frame and is so now it's going to
set the omit value which is the stored
value from the previous frame that we
use it's going to set that equal to the
accumulated particles accumulated
photons per second oh and this is also
backwards
Wow there's just a lot of bugs today a
lot of stupid bugs
so ya don't know what was going on there
but obviously when you want to normalize
something you don't multiply by the
weight you multiply with the inverse of
the weight so that was multiplying by
four every time no wonder everything was
instantly perfectly bright so I'm gonna
go ahead and say that the inverse weight
is zero and then I'm gonna say if the
accumulated weight and again we don't
really need to do this because the
inverse weights gonna be constant in the
future I think if everybody gets the
same number of Ray's cast but if we do
if we switch the bi-directional that
won't be true anymore so I'm just gonna
keep it this way we won't need to do
this if zero Chuck because there's no
way you'll ever get zero samples but you
could get more than the average number
of samples as well so I'm just gonna do
the full thing for now but in the future
we will simplify this a little bit so
now I think about it yeah this is
so at that point we should be okay the
accumulated weights
the accumulated weight is greater than
zero then we do the divided assuming
that's the case we then multiply out the
inverse weight that gets us the
accumulated PPS that we want let's step
back in here because I've made so many
mistakes in here now I want to really
check it out that's the correct weight
1/4 right so now we get an accumulated
PPS and a direction value out of it's
the last PPS and last Direction values
are going to be set to those we're going
to have a not a valid so we're going to
blend between them and that's what we
get here the T update looks right last
direction and direction should be the
same and last PBS and PPS should also be
the same I don't know why it's not hover
Valentino's okay so I think that's about
right in this case here
I will say that I think our moonlight
needs to be significantly less bright as
compared to our our individual spotlight
if we want to see anything I'm gonna go
ahead and change the moonlight value
there should just generally do these as
v3 so I can multiply them yeah
so how great is that debug light as well
uh that's 1.0 f so that should be so
something's a little off here because
that should be significantly brighter I
guess it's because it's very unlikely
that you'll hit it is the problem
because that should have been
significantly brighter than the
moonlight already and the fact that it's
not is a little concerning so we
probably still have more work to do here
also I think that flicker is way too
fast right now so I think we're also our
smoothing is not correct so I think we
got some some work to do here
right
[Music]
you
all right so let's think about this a
little bit more let's try to let me try
to just let me do a few things here so I
want to test a few things now the first
thing I want to do is I want to do the
standard test we were doing before where
we don't update the average direction to
light so I want to set here D is always
going to be equal to solution points
point index service normal so I don't
want to see anything that has to do with
the average direction to the light
that's just gonna get set so we can just
see the difference in emission value
right and so what you can see here if
we're looking at the difference in
emission value also that's not an
optimized mode well okay I guess when
you use a small scene it's very fast
yeah that's like 60 frames second when
you use a small scene just kind of cool
I guess
interesting
so again I think we've got bugs here I
don't know for sure but I'm just trying
to now isolate them out so my suspicion
here is that this this looks like too
much variance but I'm not sure okay so
if I smooth it out considerably more
than that it does dampen it quite a bit
but it's still flicker is quite a bit
more than I think it should that's a
hundred frame smoothing I really should
not be able to be seeing that like this
I don't think so that to me seems like
we've still got
that to me seems like this lerp is not
working properly for whatever reason
again because that means it should take
a hundred frames to change the light
from one value to another right to
between two different ones and so they
can only move by like a very small
amount per frame I would think now maybe
we really do have that much noise in the
system but it seems a little unlikely
hard to say but so if we take a look at
what's happening here just want to make
sure we're really doing it
so the accumulated photons per second
value that we're putting in there he's
alert between whatever the last one was
and this one however if the valid value
I guess so I guess it could be if that
valid value was was turning on and off
that would do it so I guess the other
thing we can do is force that valid
value to always be true again and just
see if that is an additional source of
noise there does not appear to be so
even at at such a small blend rate that
flicker persists let's see if we drop it
even lower
so I guess the fact that I can drop it
low enough - I can't eventually drop it
low enough to the point where you don't
see the flicker suggest that the
blending is working okay so maybe that's
all right
maybe that's all right so let's set it
to something reasonably low and I'm
gonna put a note in here go and so the
next thing I'm gonna do is I'm going to
try casting a few more rays as well so
our weight counts pretty low right now
and so the fact that more raise also
seems to reduce it does suggest that it
is just variance in our in our sampling
as well so that also seems good so I
guess now my main concern is I'd like to
address the brightness level because the
brightness levels seem a little odd to
me
at the moment and I'm not sure why that
is so I'd like to get a better handle on
that going forward supposing we set the
max light emission to something high so
let's say it was 50 we should get a much
brighter scene right and we do so let's
set it to 25 there we go
so I'm okay with that so far so I'm
going to set this down to something more
reasonable and I think now we're
starting to get I'm starting to get into
a position where I feel like we can we
can converge here I think now what we
have to do is try to get our samples
more stable but I'm feeling pretty good
about this right our lighting values
seem to converge much nicer now and they
don't go off the charts or do weird
things anymore and if we change this to
bi-directional that'll get us twice the
samples sort of for free which would be
great right it means that you know for
16 samples we're really getting 32
samples and that's nice so I think this
is good I'm pretty happy with that
because we just now we just got to get
our noise down a little bit and I think
also you know putting in a real I I
don't know what our what our current
like we don't even have a real random
number generator in there right so we
should probably also take a look at that
and and do sampling that makes more
sense right
okay let's go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A
yeah I'm pretty happy with how that is
actually I don't even know if we just
we're doing this multi-threaded we'd get
a lot more rays and we might just be
fine
like we may actually be at the point
where this is just gonna work without
reducing the noise much at all to be
honest you know I'm saying to you
because if you imagine this we're
running at 60 frames a second which we
easily could do this many if we just
multi-threaded it even on the CPU forget
GPU I think we'd be in reasonable shape
we should improve our spatial hierarchy
level as well as a separate issue
so the risk oh is that color banding I
see hope that's just ramping on stream
no I think that's probably actual color
banding you see we have not turned on
like any differing I don't think on the
GPU so and and we may need well okay I
don't see the color banding yes I do
so right in there you can see some color
banding and I assume that that is just
from the fact that we are not that we're
not getting like good differing we need
to like set up some things on the GPU
better to get differing in there because
I can definitely see it in here right
and and I don't think there's any
different going on in there I'm at can
actually check for you so if I open up
like paint or something for
if on here yeah okay that's didn't
want to do that so I guess I don't have
on here who knows so if we take a
look at you know somewhere where there
was more banding it's kind of hard to
see when the image isn't moving but
so there's no diff there there's there's
definitely no differ so what we probably
need to do is we probably need to set up
differ in the hardware to get rid of the
color banding that's not just a stream
artifact it may look worse because of
the stream but I can see it it is there
so that's just a question of that's just
a question if we've got to get it we've
got to get different output
check zero what do you think of game to
them at frameworks like unity do you
think in triple-a game can be made using
it it depends what you mean by triple-a
like obviously like if you don't
consider unity but you said you know the
Unreal Engine obviously that you know
was because Gears of War right is a
triple-a game and that's and that's made
in the Unreal Engine so you know I I
think unity may be a bit of a stretch
these days I don't really know if unity
is quite there yet in terms of really
triple if you want to make assassin's
creed or something I don't know that
it's gonna happen in unity but the
Unreal Engine has definitely been used
to make to ship triple-a games before
and that is a available framework you
probably can't ship something that's too
different from Gears of War right
because it's the engine is set up to do
a particular thing and so you need to be
doing that sort of that thing but you
know at least one of the engines out
there has been used to make a triple-a
game and so you know that that it is
possible to make at least a certain type
of triple-a game with it
unity I've never seen a triple-a game
made in unity maybe there is one but I
don't know what it is
why sampling rates can't be evenly
distributed to eliminate the flickering
wouldn't be fast the phrase um the
problem is that yes first of all I think
we will be able to do much better than
we're doing right now the problem with
it is that you don't know what evenly
distributed means so let's suppose
you've got a situation like this where
here is a bright light here and there's
no light here right or more to the point
let's suppose you've got a bright light
here but there's something in the way
and then we've got a situation here well
what you need to know is you need to
know how much of the light source is
occluded by this blocker and the only
way to know that is to find where these
points are right and so the way that we
do that because this is such a
complicated problem when you have a full
3d world geometry you're trying to
analyze is to just shoot a bunch of
these rays and look at the percentage
that hit the light source well that's
always going to be wrong always right
and how wrong it is just depends on how
many rays you shoot so when you're
talking about shooting so few rays like
if we can only afford to do 16 or 32
rays or something right per sample point
you're just not covering enough of the
hemisphere to really get accurate
percentages and that's where your noise
comes from because every other every
different frame you're getting different
percentages back
I'm watching a favorite of the backlog
you seem to return values and fungus by
parameter pointers even when you're not
returning anything else
ie void funk in our in star return
instead of in funk in art is there any
particular reason behind this I can't
imagine it maybe stops a pitch can you
give an example because it's not really
most of the time we do return the value
if we can return the value right pretty
much everywhere that's how we do it so
the times when we have to take an input
it's when it's gonna be something that's
expensive to return and we don't want to
do that or when we needed multiple
things right so most of the time we just
take inputs and return the output right
so I don't think that's an accurate
statement actually this is what I'd say
long billion are there any light effects
that you can think of we're assuming by
directional ray sampling would give
janky results
maybe subsurface scattering no so
bi-directional is always correct no
matter what the case is you can always
do it correctly the question is just
what are you actually going to do with
the bi-directional evaluation photons
can always travel like the reverse right
so I don't think there's any case where
they couldn't but I don't know there may
be something in particle physics that
says that some certain case cannot be
reversible but I you know I don't even
know about that because I've definitely
heard things from quantum people that's
like well we don't yet know whether time
always goes forwards right or stuff like
that meaning like you could imagine a
photon doing the exact opposite of what
it did so as far as I know at least in
lighting that we know about in terms of
computer graphics I don't think there is
such a thing as a forward path a photon
can take that a photon going the reverse
couldn't also take now remember the
probabilities are drastically different
and you that's why I say you know
a different computation so the chance
that a photon will take the reverse path
and the chance that the phone took the
forward path are completely different
that is true but the fact that they
could have taken the path I think is
always the case it's just a different
probability but you're accounting for
that when you do your summation usually
you know Big Mo fo one says but if
they're rays are the same across frames
the flickering would only happen around
moving objects would that be less
offensive during gameplay so if the Rays
are the same then yet what you do is you
get really really bad flicker a rat in
certain places and no flicker in other
places and that's not really a good
trade-off right you don't want some of
your lighting to be very accurate and
some to be incredibly inaccurate that's
not so good so what you want to do is
something that minimizes the inaccuracy
everywhere so you get a consistent
amount of flicker if you will and then
you try to reduce that amount it's the
best way I could say it I think
oh and one thing I should say though is
along those lines you will notice this I
put in here
I did say talk about removing some
randomness I do intend to remove some
randomest but only some so what the
stratified sampling stuff is about is
saying well okay let's suppose we want
to take an integral along this
Hemisphere right and I know I've got to
do random shots well what I want to do
is I want to partition it up into some
parts and treat them as sub integrals
right so I'm gonna shoot rays randomly
in here in here and here and here and
here and here and here and only average
along those right and so the way you do
that is you just say okay every frame
I'm gonna shoot you know one two three
four five six seven rays and I'm gonna
constrain each ray to be random within
its sub region that's called stratified
sampling and that's a way of reducing
the variance by saying alright look we
do know that we need to be random to try
and pick up what's going on but we want
to try and reduce the randomness by
keeping it within certain buckets so we
know we aren't for example on some
frames just always sampling everything
here and nothing out here which would be
a perfectly reasonable thing to happen
with pure random rays and so this is
basically like going more towards the
the blue neue style sampling it's
supposed to white noise style sampling
for example matter of fact would it be
possible to cast cones instead of rays
not into our geometry there are ways you
can do cone tracing into geometry that's
better than ours you know we might be
able to do something like Cohen tracing
in the future with our spatial hierarchy
and that might be an interesting way to
go but we haven't quite gotten there yet
in order to cast cones and have it be
any more efficient than casting rays you
need geometry that allows you to
intersect a cone with it and return a
color and that's very difficult to do if
you just have a bunch of sample points
so what we need to be able to aggregate
those sample points up in
to larger areas so that when a cone hits
them you can just return just that one
value and we just haven't done quite
that yet so it may be possible in the
future to cast they may not be not cones
per se but they are like cones in that
they are using coarser geometry as it
gets further away to reduce variance and
yes we may be able to do that with the
spatial hierarchy yeah
do you currently do any form of ambient
occlusion yea the lighting itself is
actually solving for the ambient
occlusion we are not doing a special
ambient occlusion pass to do we're not
we have no hack in there for ambient
occlusion at the moment right so we're
actually solving for real ambulant
ambient occlusion no hacking so so just
to be clear because sometimes people
have a special hack for ambient
occlusion exactly right it it's a like a
screen space pre pass that just you know
guesses at what the ambient occlusion
might be in that area we're not doing
that but we do get ambient occlusion as
part of the Ray casting so it is solving
for that right that makes sense
Kirito so you could use a blue noise
like source to select possible cones and
shoot random rates inside each of these
cones exactly or you don't even need to
blue noise the cones you can just use
fixed cones that has some consequences
as well you will see it a little bit so
I don't know exactly how we're gonna do
it but yes I mean if effectively that
what do you think about buying an IP
that is practically abandoned by the
publisher developer for a game that has
about a hundred players online at
maximum this is an online game I've no
idea I'm a game engine developer I don't
know anything about that pilot poop
how much does each new light in the
scene reduce performance there is no
reduction in performance for lights in
the scene it's flat rate so you can have
as many lights as you want there's no
performance change it's purely based on
the amount of geometry that there is
off topic do you feel like you still
have the same passion for this product
as you did back when you first began or
do somebody's feeling more like it's a
chore um I guess I don't know I feel
like that's a pretty broad question if
that makes sense for the actual
programming no I still like it
I guess is what I would say
right that's like about the end of the
questions
so it's good I'm sure it's best for
maybe to some extent like reflections
Triple A games this but our rate caster
tracer is really such a performance hit
that they aren't used on our complex set
of geometry it's like Call of Duty or
just in games without geometry so yeah
ray casters and Ray tracers just aren't
really used because of the amount of
geometry in most games they're they're
not common what is common is using Ray
casting in situations ticket to figure
out something about light transport by
doing the ray tracing on something else
that's not the actual geometry in the
game so for example there's screen space
ray casting and that gets used a lot
like you said reflections and Triple A
games will do stuff like screen space
ray tracing and that's basically a way
of saying well it's just too expensive
to retrace our geometry but it's not
necessarily too expensive to retrace the
pixels that we have because there's a
fixed number of those and we can sub
sample them predictably and so forth
right so you know that can happen
there's also stuff like pseudo radiosity
stuff like enlighten or whatever it's
called I don't know that's a tech that
got licensed by like frostbite and stuff
and so you know there's there's that as
well for real-time radiosity sort of
stuff that happens in a number of
engines games that can oftentimes will
bake lighting but baked lighting is sort
of a problem now for other reasons so
you know originally you always baked
lighting pretty much period and the
reason you always baked lighting in was
just because you couldn't do it any
other way
nowadays pure baked lighting becomes
less likely largely for artists
turnaround time light baking is a slow
process offline as well and so people
have been looking for ways to speed up
the you know having real time or close
to real time lighting is not just
something that allows the game to
respond to changing lighting in the
environment it's something that helps
artists produce better art because if
the artists don't have to sit around
waiting for the lighting to be
recomputed then they can see their
changes more quickly and produce better
artwork so actually in terms of ray
tracing the lighting in sort of a slow
offline fashion and using a baked that's
actually becoming less common for other
reasons right that may have nothing to
do with the actual runtime performance
of the game and so schemes that don't
require that that don't require slow
offline bakes are actually becoming more
popular not because of the game runtime
but actually because of the asset
creation time do you have any good
sources for learning about making
lighting solutions uh no not really
how would we implement fog can we
simulate different media in where the
light properties um yeah I don't know
that you would really want to yeah I
mean yes you could but just I'm it's
good it's gonna add more noise right is
the problem so I guess what I would say
is you have to remember that the
something like fog like participating
media is requires you to take light that
passes through it and randomly pick a
point in the traversal region to bounce
the light out randomly that's just a
huge source of noise right so if you
actually wanted to simulate fog with
this system in some way that was
actually utilizing the system to fully
do the fog I think it would be way too
expensive I mean we're already fighting
to get the variance down just without
stuff like that in there so I would say
if you did want to do fog you might have
to do something less rigorous than that
and say look all we're gonna do is when
light passes through a fog area we're
just gonna add light to the fog in that
area period that's all we do we don't
bounce the light at all so the fog
doesn't contribute to the lighting
solution it only receives light from the
lighting solution that seems plausible
right and similarly the degree of
attenuation in light that happens when
it has to pass through fog that could be
done as well those two things I think
would be fine however random scattering
of light due to fog I don't think is on
the table I just don't think that's
feasible so I think you could integrate
fog into the system and do some
interesting things I don't think you
could go all the way with it that's just
my guess
alright that's about it
okay thank you everyone for joining me
for an episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
the series at home you can always peer
to the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with the source code so you could
follow along at home that's about it for
today we'll be back next week when we
will look at changing to bi-directional
transport and stratified sampling just
to see if we can get our variants down
per frame before we go ahead and
optimize ourselves some more with
possibly doing maybe multi-threaded or
GPU or at the very least taking a look
at our spatial hierarchy stuff and
improving that because we threw it in
there and we've never really gone and
given it the full sort of attention that
it's gonna need to be good but yeah
pretty happy with the light I'm liking
it
I like the current one that seems really
stable I'd like to reduce the variance a
little bit but it's you know honestly I
don't know if we optimized it it might
just be fine even the way it is right
now so we'll have to sort of continue on
with the other parts of the lighting
that it that need to get addressed I
think all right thanks for joining me
and I will catch you guys on the
Internet
take it easy everybody