start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade hero the show we
could a complete game live on stream I
of course I gotta move this headphone
down apparently yesterday we did some
work to implement a sort of state
restoring state saving and restoring for
live code editing in loops now that
we've put in dynamic allocations as
opposed to just using a single block
allocation which used to kind of just
read and write out but we have not
debugged it yet so really all we are
trying to do today is just go actually
do the debugging work and make sure
that's all working properly that's all
so yeah let's get started today is day 3
44 as the little counter sort of says
here if you want to start with today's
code that I am starting with you can go
to day 3 43 alrighty then there we go
let's take a look at where we were at
now really what our problem was is we
didn't have any specifically crashy
things uh to deal with it's just that we
have a problem where when we go to
reload it looks like we get into some
kind of a state where the game is still
running but it's not really running
properly so although we must be saving
and restoring our blocks to a certain
degree something slightly off is
happening so we end up ruining the game
when we go into a loop and you can kind
of see what happens here if I click the
loop thing you can see the game sort of
freezes here but unlike what we would
maybe potentially expect during a normal
fries we are actually still executing
fairly reasonable code so we're not
actually frozen in the sense of like
some obvious loop that we just got stuck
in if we break at various times we're in
completely different parts so what
appears to be happening is we appear to
be still running the game just fine but
something about our state restoration
that we did now no longer allows us to
actually risk
actually restore proper functionality to
the rendering so it's as if our game
really wasn't still running effectively
as far as as what's present to the
screen even though for some reason the
code is actually running right and and
so yeah I mean we haven't actually
stepped through any of this code yet so
the first thing I just want to do is
take a brief look at stepping to the
code the other thing that we need to do
is is we have to verify because there's
a couple of things we haven't quite
implemented yet for example handling
allocation and deletion inside the
recording block which may be happening
for all we know so it's not one hundred
percent clear that that couldn't be
causing a bug but in theory it should
crash if that had happened but anyway we
have that problem of having that freeze
we should at least up through the code
and make sure we have some idea what's
actually going on right and so let's
take a look here here's the the stream
out you can see it happening here we're
going to loop through and see what the
blocks are that we're writing out I just
kind of want to get a feel for how many
of them we write out and what they are
you can see we have sort of our base
pointer and our size here that's a 64
Meg chunk that it's going to write out
which in theory it's writing out here
and yeah let's take a look at what bytes
written is as well oh well that's not a
good sign I wonder if we're getting you
some kind of an error here ah there we
go well it looks like that is a pretty
obvious reason why things are not
working properly um we didn't use the
right handle so yeah that maybe we
should check our um maybe we should
check our return values here one thing
that is kind of true and I am guilty of
this a lot is that I tend not to be
super careful about error handling in
parts of the code that aren't
user-facing so for example this is
purely debug feature so I don't care how
robust it is so I tend not to do stuff
like check return values of right file
or whatever you know what I mean but it
you know one of the downsides of that
maybe it saves
time but it can also cost you time
because if we had just done that if we
had put in something that would at least
do a cert that that was coming back true
or something or that we wrote the amount
that we thought we were going to write
that would have caught that error for us
without us having to look for it now
granted maybe that doesn't matter
because it wasn't like we look for it
for very long but it's just worth noting
that that's the kind of thing that can
happen sometimes even though you don't
actually care about a particular piece
of code in terms of robustness and so
you don't do that error checking it may
be that you still want to put the error
checking in just to give yourself the
benefit of not having to debug something
that doesn't that you know could have
been called for you so now that's
actually getting written out in both
cases which is what we would hope so
that's all good and of course we can't
check that one because msvc refuses to
show it to us okay so now at least where
we are writing that out oh and hey that
turns out that was our only bug so good
so now we've got our loop left coded in
working properly with dynamic
allocations and that might be fine like
again this is not a feature that anyone
is going to run in the actual game it's
strictly a thing that we do for
ourselves so that we can implement
things if we want to if that makes sense
and I guess what I would say about that
is you know it kind of depends on on
what we want to have happen I suppose do
we want to make sure that we can always
use loop live code editing even in
circumstances where it might be a little
bit touchy or you know I don't know what
what I will say is it's a little bit
weird there that it got a lot slower the
second time through I am a little
curious about that like the first time
we ran this it didn't do that oh you
know why it's because now we're actually
seeing the rights before we weren't
actually doing the rights and now we
were that's that's probably why so
anyway that's that and now we're doing
those now we're sort of working probably
there we have two comments all we're
going to do we also have sort of a
situation here that we might want to
take a look at which is how fast it is
to do those state for stores
and that's sort of a separate issue but
the first thing I want to look at here
is I just want to look at how big those
files are so if we I think this coat
yeah so here's our loop edit one input
right there you can see it that's the
file the state's stuff I don't think we
actually do anymore so we could actually
delete all those files so if we have
these these loop edit you know sit
things here and we want to have those
actually work efficiently 363 megabytes
for one of these a lot of that is
probably in the asset store right our
asset storage system right now allocates
256 megabytes as its block of asset
processing and you know if you thought
about that it's like well does that
really need to get saved and restored
anyway in fact the whole asset system
really wouldn't have to get saved and
restored at all the asset system itself
isn't you know entirely sort of it
serves itself properly in terms of a
cache so it doesn't really need to get
saved and restored if it didn't get
restored when you did the loopback it
wouldn't actually matter right it
wouldn't affect anything so if you look
at how much receiving their to the loop
edit yes it's a lot less than it was
before before we were saving out a
gigabyte or something like this because
that's how much the total block was so
the fact that we're only saving out the
blocks we've actually allocated so far
it does help a little but we're still
saving out a bunch of data we don't
actually need to save out and so it does
raise the question of whether or not we
would want to do something a little
fancier here in terms of what stuff we
want to save and restore and what stuff
we don't want to save and restore so if
we were to take a closer look at this
for example let's say I go to the asset
system itself I'm going to take a look
in here so if we were to go to the asset
system itself where we do allocate game
assets you can kind of see here that
that if we yeah if we just take a little
bit of a second to look at the allocate
game asses call you can see that what it
does is it's actually kind of grabbing
one giant block off of the arena it's
given here and all it really needs is
that for
then on it's not going to do anything
else right because it allocates its own
memory and does its own stuff so if we
wanted to we could take the asset system
entirely out of the equation because it
also doesn't really do anything other
than it doesn't have any other sort of
like hooks into any systems or really
anything else in particular it's doing
and it can probably be treated for the
most part just like sort of a separate
system that doesn't need to be really
worked with in any in any more specific
of a way right so we probably could take
that out of there now it's a little bit
iffy if we do that the reason for that
is I'm not sure exactly how that would
interact with our we've got sort of
threads that are operating inside the
asset system there and those threads
obviously are doing sort of asset load
work so you can take a look at what
happens inside load asset work calls for
example like one of these guys you can
see that the way that that's working is
inside here we have to do stuff which
may be touching things in the asset
system which means that if we were to
have these like these tasks saved and
restored for some reason which is sort
of what would happen in a suit to a
certain degree if we were loading across
the save restore boundary we would get
into a situation potentially where the
asset system would be out of phase
because its memory wouldn't be getting
restored but the memory for this other
set of stuff would be gang sword I don't
know if we really care about that too
much because again probably other stuff
will break at that point anyway meaning
what we probably want to do when we do
loop live code editing is shut down all
threads then do the loop point and then
like we want to wait for drain out then
like do the loop point and then go
forward from there so it seems like it's
still probably a reasonable thing to do
to say let's take maybe the asset system
out of that let's just take the asset
system out of the general pool and let
it just do its thing right and so if we
wanted to do that what we could do is
say well we've got these memory Rena's
maybe we can just say on the memory
arena something that has to do with like
don't you know we don't want any
allocations that come from this memory
Rena to actually be save restore right
we want them to like it bypass that
process and not be involved well we
could do that pretty easily because the
way that we sort of structured the code
right now where we have these sort of
like memory blocks is we could inside
here say okay maybe like there's some
flags on this memory block and the flags
on the memory block could control things
like whether or not it was going to get
saved out right something like this
that's the wrong place I meant there
there we go those flags the memory block
would say hey this is you know some
extra information and so when we go to
write it out we could you know when we
go to allocate it we put the information
in the flags for the person who did the
allocation and then when we go to write
it out we could check the flags and say
hey if this is a block that's not
supposed to really be saved in restored
then just don't do it and save us the
trouble so we could say all right so
there's win32 memory block flags right
and we can just say just probably call
it mem flags went through two men flags
and something like that win32 memory not
not restored or something not not
restored is probably my best one so far
let's just call it that lets say and so
what we could do here is when we
actually pass stuff down to the
allocator right because when you know we
we know when we're getting an allocation
call right they have to call this
allocate memory thing so what we could
do is have it passed down flags here and
when it passes down the flags here those
would go to our allocator and we'd be
able to set them on the memory block so
the memory block would know so like
right here we could just say okay the
flags there's the flags
right and then we would be good to go
now in this case where we do the
allocations here we need to know what
flags to pass and so presumably we can
pass those flags however we want
presumably they would just be stored on
the arena but i guess i would point out
we could also pass them in some sort of
other ways i suppose but i think that's
what we want for the most part so i
think what we want to do is just say
let's store in the arena itself up here
let's store in the arena itself the
flags that we want to pass so these will
be the allocation flags and then we you
know by default those would be
initialized to 0 which is what we want
because we don't actually typically want
much of that to be happening but in the
case where we wanted to take a specific
arena out of the allocation pool then we
actually could write and similarly the
pushed buffered here for per frame
arenas I think that would not want to be
saved and restored either because that's
just a temporary thing per frame so we
probably don't want to restore that
either so we just set it to not restored
here and and leave it at that so now
what we should be able to do of course
if we run things now there'd be no
difference right nothing particularly
odd would happen if we did that right we
still get exactly the same behavior
because we're not actually looking at
that flag so we don't have any yeah we
don't have any expectations about what's
going to happen there because we're
never looking at that flag anyway but if
we have right file here then we would
just put in here the fact that we don't
want to save this block at all so if the
source black flags happens to equal
let's see here
where did you go there we go so if the
source Black Flag's happens to set if
this source blocks flags happens to have
the not restored flag set then we just
don't write it out now we don't have to
do anything else to it because when we
read in the blocks it will just won't be
there so it'll naturally leave it
completely alone so now we know if we do
this we'll have like one that's going
through there right OOP how about I make
that be the right order there we go if
we do that we'll now at least know that
one block is going through that and
that's just our that render that
temporary memory Reena for the rendering
stuff and that's all fine but what we
want to do is take that bigger block out
of there right because again we've got
this sort of loop edit one input HMI
it's still really large probably much
larger that it actually needs to be and
and that's also what kind of causes that
hiccup there during the state recording
you know you can see how long that that
was taking so what we might want to do
again now is go into the asset system
and we could just pull the asset system
out of that out of that process entirely
so what we can do here is say alright
the asset system is going to have we
know that it has its own memory or
rather will have to have its own memory
so we should be able to go here to where
are you yeah here we go we should be
able to go to this this that's not it
there we go the asset structure and just
say alright since we know that we want
this thing to have the the its own kind
of memory pool that's outside of
everything else what we can do is say
all right we'll put a memory arena in
here for the asset system's memory and
we'll call it may be non restored memory
and then what we can do is say all right
in the non restored memory we're going
to have the asset system when it gets
initialized instead of using the arena
that's passed in in fact we could just
take that out entirely the there could
be
no actual arena passed into the asset
system the asset system could just sort
of generate itself from whole cloth
because if we take a look at what's
actually happening in the arena here you
can see that it's really not used for
pretty much anything other than the
asset information itself so what we
could do is say all right forget about
that right let's say that we have a
memory arena and it's just going to be
the non restored memory from the game
asset school itself and then all we have
to do is instead of doing a push truck
we just have to do a bootstrap right
we've start to do the same thing that we
were doing before and when we do this
then we will get the situation where the
the memory arena does it sort of
bootstrapping and it sort of creates a
new arena for the allocation and makes
that arena be something that's inside
the asset struct itself so that's about
it for that we don't need this anymore
but what we do need okay what we do need
beyond that because now this should work
just fine but it's still going to be an
arena that's attract arena so if I do
this I'm still going to have it going
through the standard arena process where
it's getting written out and so I don't
want that to happen so what I need is
some way right I need some way
specifically of going in there and
setting that arena to not record its
memory and I would like it to not record
the game assets truck itself either so
in the bootstrapping process I would
like to have during the bootstrap a way
of setting that thing and so if we take
a look at the bootstrap push size here I
would like to be able to pass like we
passed the minimum block size as well
I'd like to be able to pass the flags
here too I'd like both of those things
to be able to be passed now I do like
how confusing that is where you
kind of got these two things here that
are sort of like just numbers and plus
the office it looks like it could be
something you know that could get messed
up so I might want to do something like
memory bootstrap Rams so it's just a
little clearer what's going on here's
the allocation flags here's the minimum
block size like so and then what I can
do is say all right when you bootstrap
you pass the memory bootstrap grams and
that way that can get set up properly
and the way that would work is okay when
you do a bootstrap here right we'll set
both of these location flags to be
bootstrap Rams occasion flags bootstrap
grams minimum block size and there we go
now I just need some way of getting a
default in there and pretty much none of
these other ones who do bootstrapping
are going to want to really set anything
beyond the default so probably what I
want to do is take exactly the same tack
that I took with the other part here so
you can kind of see what we did with
like no clear and these sorts of things
and there's the default arena prams what
I want to do is do like a default
bootstrap programs as well
and while I'm at it let's move this up a
bit and why I didn't call that arena I
don't know we go and so all i want to do
there is i want to take the bootstrap
rams and i want to set them to the
whatever they should be by default and
in this case we really don't have to do
much because we already make zero work
correctly with them so as long as I just
clear the bootstrap Rams first that
would be the default and that's fine so
what I can do is just say like all right
the bootstrap Rams is going to be
default bootstrap Rams and that's it
nothing further to be done and then
everything should compile properly but
like i said in here we want to actually
pass them so in this boot strap push
struct here i'm just going to say like
okay i want to pass some params the
params i want to pass here are just like
a non restored arena right and what that
would be is just something you know as
part of the bootstrap params settings
that would be maybe i should type get
these guys somewhere down here there we
go that would just be something that
essentially takes the default whatever
the default is and sets those sets that
particular flag so i'm going to go ahead
and say non restored arena and i'm going
to make that at the default oops
bootstrap ramps i'm going to set the
flags equal to
you know now I think about it why did I
make this a win32 memory flag when you
have to pass it in that's just where my
head is today when you have to pass it
into something it can't be win32 it's
going to have to be in the platform
layer right it's part of this thing so
it's really a platform memory block flag
pants platform every nap story so don't
know I did that all right so anyway the
allocation flags being set we wouldn't
need to touch the other parts of it and
then I just need to change these places
where I had erroneously labeled it as
win32 so let's go here
so now the asset system is not being
included in there right so during the
save and restore the asset systems 256
megabytes allocates which is again not
really necessary to restore or at least
we hope not or is it I may be very wrong
about that so it looks like we do have
something we need to restore from there
which I suppose we could but that part
which is not necessarily not necessary
to restore wasn't being restored and
except for that one problem it means our
loop edit code our loop edit sort of
size we have to save out is dramatically
reduced now the in-flight generation
count thing this was strictly to allow
us to do some stuff that we don't do
anymore originally when we first did
handmade here we had the asset system
set up in a nice way that there was a
predefined time when assets got flushed
out so that they wouldn't be flushed out
when they're being used for rendering
unfortunately we then decided to try
doing the ground chunk thing which
really was way more work than it was
worth because it required us to have the
asset system know when things were in
use and when they weren't and this is
all that really was for now why the
asset system itself is tracking that I
mean this may just be a case if we could
still preserve the feature and just move
those out to somewhere else right and
that wouldn't really be a big deal I
also don't know yeah I believe the same
thing is true for most of these things
right like we had to do a bunch of
things here that really we don't
probably want to be doing but that came
in as a result of the fact that we
wanted to support this process that we
no longer actually want or need so it
may actually be a good idea to just get
rid of that that might be
right because I'm really not sure I'm
really not sure that we want to keep
supporting that if we didn't support
that there's pretty much no chance that
we would ever have a problem because we
know that we'll always have enough asset
memory that we'd never page out
something that was being used on this
frame right so really all of this stuff
is really not necessary at that point
and it does sort of mean that we're
having a lot of complexity there that we
don't actually need and I don't know
like what the best way to deal with that
is but it does you know like just might
my feeling about that is I would rather
not have that be the case right that's
just what I that's just what I would
prefer and you can see that the only
reason we need it right is during a
choir asset memory we go and grab things
and all we were doing here is we're
saying like oh you know the the asset
memory if you're going to take something
don't take and from an asset who's still
being used by someone but really we
don't need to knew that anymore because
the only person you could be being used
by is the current frames worth of memory
right and so it just feels like a really
not necessary thing that makes sense so
the question is the other question I
suppose there is could we could
generation has completed be made into
something a little bit simpler now that
we know we don't have multiple threads
doing sort of asynchronous render tasks
that are unrelated and i'm not sure i'm
not really sure
but I'm going to take a look at this so
let's say we were to get rid of this
code who actually uses it at the moment
obviously begin asset lock and asset
lock if we just said there's no asset
lock although this we probably do need
here potentially but if we just said
there's no asset lock who actually uses
this stuff so begin generation just
increments the ID ID n generation just
removes it from the list of people who
are currently using the lock who else so
result can presumably in this case if
we're just for testing purposes result
can just be 0 and in terms of generation
has completed we could also just always
return true because we could just say
yep you could always use memory from any
one you get right all right and so again
there's really you know there's no
chance that that would be necessary code
at this point and again the reason is
because all that code the only thing
that code was actually doing there was
no point to that code at all other than
to prevent you from evicting an asset
when something in the renderer might
have been using that asset right that's
the only reason that we were doing it so
we essentially had a beginning end lock
sort of a not a real lock but a sort of
conceptual lock where during the
rendering of a frame you would basically
have to ignore any asset that was being
used
on that frame until the frame rendering
completed so yeah so that's the current
state and I feel like I'm not sure
whether I want to try and preserve that
functionality or not I i guess i would
say that in general I I like it
conceptually because it does seem like
the kind of thing you might want to
include so I'm just wondering could we
perhaps just have that be stored in
something that was you know just
allocate that from something that was
going to get restored and then we
wouldn't have to worry about it for
example we could put that in the
transient state and and leave it at that
right I just don't know I just don't
know let's take a look at what would
happen if we did put it in the transient
state I'm just curious so let's say that
we put that over in the hat in the
transients day and we can always against
ill delete it after that so I'm just
going to take a look and see i am going
to
snip this out yeah and place it in here
very well and now i am going to does
this get cleared by the way yes and now
i am also going to change all of these
calls back to doing what they were doing
before but i'm going to have them get it
off of the transient state and I'm not
thrilled about that back point are
according to the comment but since it's
already there I will use it
use of undefined structure yeah well
that's probably true I agree with that
question is can I put this somewhere
else handmade asset begin asset lock
identify are not found oh because these
guys are all in line as well yeah so I
guess not this is that stupid see thing
that I absolutely hate which is having
to deal with its kind of vagaries in the
sense i suppose i could make sure the
trans date is known about here but I
don't really know that does seem a
little bit squirrelly again it's this is
one of those things that programmers
should literally never have to deal with
but unfortunately C++ being what it is
you do so if i have the transient state
I suppose I could just loft that up
somewhere else and have the asset stuff
be defined after it in theory this isn't
really pointing to very much else so you
know I could just pre declare the game
asset pointer and then we would be done
the asset system itself of course
getting included right here so you know
literally I could just do something kind
of squirrelly like you know that not my
favorite thing but you know what are you
gonna do task with memory
can also be moved up and so now we do
have there's a little bit more that we
haven't done here there's the begin jet
begin generation stuff oops in
generation that I did have to comment
out before and so now that also has to
get commented back in again nothing
particularly weird happening here other
than just I have to use that pointer
there it is
next generation ID I looks like i did
not move one of the things I should have
moved next and in fact there it is
alright so let's go back to the
transient state and put that in as well
and I think that's just about it
and just a pro tip should probably set a
pointer before you use the pointer just
something to think about I don't know
that this actually needs to happen here
though because in general if the trans
States cleared we don't need to clear it
again right it'll just get cleared so I
think that's mostly all we need and so
now the locking should be restored saved
and restored which I can't think of any
real reason not to continue supporting
it I guess why I say it's a little bit
of code complexity that definitely
doesn't need to happen and so we may end
up pulling it out at the very end you
know when we get further down the line
or like okay the games like you know
roughly where it should be in general
and now it's time to go maybe clean up
some of them code stuff that now that we
know everything is what everything is I
can still see cutting it but at the
moment anyway we might as well just
leave it in there because I don't know I
suppose it helps us potentially in some
weird circumstance I can't think of I
can't think of any way could ever
actually help us because either you have
enough memory to store all the assets
for the current frame in which case no
assets going to get evicted on that
frame anyway or you don't in which case
you can't read to the frame so it just
doesn't seem like the kind of thing that
we actually need it it's really only
necessary as far as I can imagine in my
head it's really only necessary for the
circumstance where specifically you know
that what you want to do is have
multiple renders running concurrently
and so one render could could be sitting
there chewing through lots of different
asset requests moving through the least
recently used pool while another
renderer is still kind of sitting there
hasn't touched in the asset a while but
it's still pulling from them doing some
background rendering that's the only
time you actually need anything like
this to a
so yeah that's about the only thing I
can say about that all right so now we
have a situation where we're certainly
much nicer like you can see here the
loop live code edit file is now like for
that loop was 32 megabytes you know so
even though probably we don't you know
we definitely don't need to store a 32
megabytes of memory because you know the
memory some of that memory isn't
changing and stuff like that one of the
nice things about it is that now we do
know okay we're not saving memory for
stuff that we just don't care about
getting Satan restored and before we
were now at least we're only saving
memory for arenas that we actually
thought think are participating in stuff
we want to loop live code at it and that
seems like a nice win now that's just
about all we need to do with with this
system like I said we now have a sort of
a question about whether we want to go a
little further with it and see about
handling memory block restoration in the
case where we malloc and free something
essentially or a virtual a lock and
virtual free in this case something in
the middle of the recording and I don't
know that we actually ever have that
happening now in theory we should crash
if we do so in theory that means that
during the memory during the sort of
test runs we just did that wasn't
happening now that makes a lot of sense
why that wouldn't necessarily be
happening and the reason why it makes
sense that it wouldn't be happening is
because the only thing that would really
be getting allocated indicated during a
frame at the moment is just like
temporary memory or something right so
it's very unlikely that we would have a
block that would whose persistence would
change across the recording boundary but
that won't always be true so in theory
that is something that we might want to
care about because otherwise our loop
live coding would kind of like crash
someday and we would be unhappy now what
we'll need to do here is if we allocate
memory look if we want to support this
if we allocate memory what we need to do
is no okay when we allocate memory if
we're going to go back to the loop point
we need to get rid of that memory right
that's what we would need to do and if
we D allocate memory than what we have
to do is just not actually deallocate it
right the second one's pretty easy to do
all we would do is when we go to
deallocate the memory we would just say
if we're in the middle of recording just
don't free the memory in the case of
memory that we allocate what we would
probably do is say well okay if we
allocated memory that's inside a record
block let's set a flag on it to let us
know that actually when you go to
restore the pages delete this page and
pretend that you freed it right seems
pretty straightforward so it feels like
we should at least nominally implement
that because we might as well I can't
see why we wouldn't
yeah I can't see really any reason not
to so while we're recording right while
we're recording when we allocate memory
what we'd want to do is anytime we're
recording or playing back if we allocate
memory we just want to market that if we
jump back to a record point free it
right so we just need to know are we
recording or are we not and so really I
just need some way of determining that
and then we would know hey if you're
going to allocate this page make sure
that you free free it later right and so
they need clear we'd have platform you
know memory in addition to not restored
it's like allocated during recording
something like this and technically I
don't know that we would want to expose
this to the platform layer because it's
sort of just a implementation detail the
win32 side of things so I might figure
to do on here that's like you know maybe
you know and in fact maybe we don't want
to do that maybe we want those Mary
black flags to be more pure than that I
don't know and since we've got plenty of
padding in that struct maybe I just
won't even bother putting to do i'll
just do it a different way so i'll just
go here and say you know there's just
you know two of these be 30 tues on here
use up one of those you 64's of the pad
and just say one of those is allocated
during oops allocated during loop or
something and so if its allocated during
looping then that's one that would just
get freed and so what we could do is
when we do our restore so you know I'm
pretty sure that's in here somewhere um
let's see
so we've got em didn't put playback
right link acute and include playback so
if we end input playback we would want
to we wouldn't want to free anything
allocated during the looping because
that's something that's now going to
persist so what we'd want to do here is
clear that flag right we want to go
through and clear the the flag off the
memory block like so let's see 132
memory block block equals new state we
actually got past that state memory
Sentinel next block block block next all
right so in this case we're going to
loop over the blocks if we're going to
say allocated during looping was false
so we just clear it don't actually do
delicate the memory because we want to
keep the memory around we're going to
continue playing the game from this
state we want to keep it around so if we
begin the input playback then at the
point where we begin we would want to
deallocate all of that memory right so
we'd want to say like deallocate all
looping blocks when we go to begin input
playback because we want a clean state
there right the same would be true when
we go to I guess the only other time we
really care about that begin to play but
we want to delegate all of them and when
we begin recording input I guess we
don't have to do anything because in
that case our memory state is our memory
state so when we begin input playback
that means we're hopping back to the
thing we want to do locate all the
blocks that were created during looping
when we ended but playback we just want
to clear the flag so we wouldn't
accidentally
free them during a later loop session
right and I'm trying to think if there's
any particular time other than those
where we would need could do something I
don't think so so the other thing that
we'd have to do is if we would have free
to block we need to free that block if
we end input playback so when we end
input playback like we do here right
we'd want to set allocated during
looping but then we want to do like free
during looping and we'd want to actually
free the block right so I think that we
actually do want to do that
so something like this right so there
I'm just saying okay a 72 Raider we're
going to iterate over these blocks we're
going to move to the next block
regardless but what we want to make sure
we do is if we're going to free a block
we don't want to touch that block
afterwards so we want to make sure we
have a way to do that so then we'd have
to hear that's like free during looping
right and yeah so I think that that's
all we really need to do there now if
something was free during looping and
we're looping back to it our deallocate
all looping blocks call which it looks
like we only ever do once so I guess
that's just going to actually be this
this call has to do the corresponding
operation right so in here we would loop
through all the blocks and then we would
say allocated during looping is is what
we would actually need to switch on
right so in that case we do this and the
free during looping is the thing that's
actually going to get cleared
so I think that's it and we could
probably structure that a little bit
more cleverly by just past like having a
single thing that takes a mask you know
what I mean so if we wanted to we could
be a little bit more clever there and
collapse those two loops down to be like
a you know a basically a in fact let's
just do it let's just be clever their
internal like 31 32 free blocks by mask
removal call it clear blocks by mask I
don't know what we call it exactly so if
you pass the win32 stayed in and we do
essentially this exact loop if we
imagine having a mask here and turning
this into a flag right that's like loop
looping flags then we can just say ok
there's a win32 memory block flag and
that's like winter to loop or mmm
allocated during looping remem free
during looping right and what we can
then do is when we pass in a flag here
we can just say tell me what you want me
to look for when I free right so what I
do is go ok in the case where we don't
free it we're clearing it but in the
case where it matches the mask then we
are going to free it and we'll check for
the entire mask
just in case we want to look for 22
flags or something like this and I think
that's all we would really need to do so
then what we can do is in here we'll
just actually make the appropriate calls
so here we'd say win32 clear blocks by
mask we passed the state and we'd say we
were trying to do allocated during
looping to false and free during looping
is the free condition so that's that and
then in the other case we want to do it
the other way around right where did
that go where are you mr. looping t'en
here okay did I just remove it I must I
did I I just cut it out didn't I alright
well that's not very smart so we did
win32 clear blocks by mask at the top of
and input playback but for some reason I
guess I cut it out of here for no reason
whatsoever
because end input playback needs to have
it but so does begin input playback all
right it's just me having a little brain
part they're all right so I think that's
what we're looking for in terms of
clearing and now I just have to make
sure that I'd go and set these things
properly which at the moment I'm not
actually doing right oops that's it
correct again all right so let's go
ahead and and do the rest of this so
let's take a look at the deallocate
memory call the deallocate memory call
it we need to now pull out into
something that D allocates the block so
that we can have free memory block so
that we can have somebody else call it
besides this routine this is all we
actually need to do right it's all there
properly we just need to actually call
it or have it be callable as a separate
function
there we go okay so I think now we're in
good shape the problem is this will do
literally nothing at the moment because
or it'll completely destroy the entire
world because we aren't actually ever
setting these flags or at least I didn't
think we were now on apparently we
actually are probably we're not actually
clearing that I should double-check that
we are or aren't whereas our win32
memory block
i log
see here and made bitmap memory sighs
blah blah blah there we go although
those flags should be cleared I mean
because virtual Alec will give us back
as erode page it's required to so we
should be able to assert that our
looping flags are set to zero so that
means nobody should ever get freed here
oh hi that's that was probably just an
infinite loop I was like that shouldn't
have done anything
so I guess now that i think about it is
virtual Alec allowed to give me back the
same page I thought bitterly Alec had to
be zeros Oh up wow it's been a rough day
I can tell you that here there we go so
that was how I just the infinite loop
there i would assume let's double check
to see if that's true oh and not to
mention the fact yeah i'll tell you some
days you just shouldn't be programming
and that is today to be certain so let's
see here what I want to do there is I
need to check for the actual block
Sentinel which I was not doing so let's
go ahead and fix that
much better so now that's okay but we're
not setting those flags at all so I
think the only other thing that I want
to do here we're almost should be almost
out of time as well is I want to have
some idea of whether I'm input whether
i'm recording or playing back or doing
other things like that and if I'm during
one of those things that I need to set
my flags accordingly so essentially what
has to happen is during allocation when
I would do a deallocate or an allocate I
need to be able to mark the blocks here
in the appropriate fashion so what I
want to do is say all right when i
allocate memory if i'm going to allocate
memory always have to succeed obviously
because I can't not allocate something I
have to hand it back but what I want to
do is say if I was going to if this was
going to be something that was inside a
loop I need to set it with that win 32
mm freed allocated during looping flag
so I want to do is like is in loop right
then I would set al Qaeda during looping
otherwise I had set it to nothing right
and then the same thing is going to
happen for the free what I want to do is
say you know if win32 is in loop right
then I want to go ahead and check and
this should probably take the global
win32 state logo 132 state if we are
then we're going to set it
be free during looping and if we're not
then we're going to free us normal so
now we just need a way to know right we
need to know whether we're looping or
not so we essentially need some function
here that's like hey are we in a loop
are we not in the loop and I believe
that technically there's two ways right
that we might be in a looping condition
if we're recording aura for playing back
they will both jump back to the
beginning so really what we need to
check there is we need to check whether
or not we have a recording index or a
playing index right and if we have
either of those then we are looping I
believe that would allow us to handle
gracefully the condition where somebody
does something during the loop with the
memory blocks that's about it for today
timewise
and thank you neil for putting in ! ! QA
for me I still have not on this machine
I keep meaning to but I just haven't had
a chance to like do the whole thing
where I get hex chat set up to log to
the twitch stream so that I actually am
senior Tory on there if I try to type
anything into it now it's like you're
not I'm not me so it won't allow the QA
the pam QA thing
so
yeah I we should go find out what the
black dot is as well the black dot is
pretty cool I don't know when it started
showing up but we've never gone and
checked down what the black dot actually
is if you run the game usually the black
dot is there but I think it may have
been remember we have a bug still on our
to-do list that i postponed for
occupation points they are not getting
created properly at the beginning or
people aren't put placed on them
correctly at the beginning so I wonder
if that killed our black dot i really
liked our black dot i wish the black dot
was back it kind of reminded me of like
the Atari 2600 adventure game where you
there is that like secret black dot you
could get but I guess it's gone now
unfortunately one nice thing about doing
this different memory new stuff is it
now loop live code editing starts and
loops really quickly it's like very it's
it's mostly instantaneous now even on
this hard drive which is a 7200 rpm like
physical disk drives not even STD so
that's kind of nice
Neal I'm scared to look back at my own
library reload not even looped editing
after I stopped using it for a few
months probably 10 plus hours plugging
ahead of me yeah I mean some of this
stuff is obviously things I mean like
anything else the whole reason that
people reuse engines is because
low-level code is is hard work right and
typically you want to kind of keep a
code base up-to-date that does the
things you wanted to do and it is you
know you don't generally yeah like you
said if you kind of like leave things
lying around they do tend to atrophy
unfortunately besides you I what things
are a must use our must use oh I besides
you I what things must use threads and
games just started learning threads and
I'm curious there are some things that
somehow run slower threaded than single
so that's usually not I I would not
recommend thinking about threads in
terms of what does and doesn't use them
threads are just ways of taking
advantage of extra processing resources
usually in games because I mean there's
two fundamental ways that you can that
you can two fundamental reasons why you
might be using threads one reason is
because you want something that runs
asynchronously and you just don't want
to have to deal with parceling out time
to it yourself right so you just create
a thread and let it do something and you
just count on the operating system to
like switch the context so that that
thread gets some time and run that's
fine for stuff like when you're waiting
on the operating system because
oftentimes it doesn't necessarily give
you a choice but I don't super love that
as a solution for things in inside the
game proper and the reason for that is
you can usually be a little bit more
reliable by not using the operating
systems thread system and hoping that it
switches threads for you in a reliable
and fashion that doesn't you know cause
frame hiccups or something so usually
the way that the rest of the fred's
thread stuff works in a games nowadays
is by more
like a job system where you have like
some number of worker threads and you
don't create a thread per job you create
a will work order per job and those
worker threads just are constantly
chewing through whatever jobs are
available and so typically I think a lot
of times on modern game engines what
you'll see is you don't necessarily have
like oh we went and put the UI on a
thread or something instead you just
have lots of work that needs to be done
those are from different systems the
physics has worked we've done the
rendering has work to be done the entity
system has work to be done you'll see
those like getting put into these little
work orders and then those work orders
are getting executed by worker threads
as fast as they can and they aren't
separate threads necessarily right so I
think there's really no answer to the
question what gets put on a separate
thread it's whatever can be parceled out
in efficient work orders nowadays is
something that is totally something that
could be threaded the problem with
reading things is once you have multiple
threads touching a piece of data it
becomes much more difficult to ensure
that you don't have bugs that have to do
with the order in which the threads do
things you know on handmade hero we
haven't had to wrestle with that too
much because we've used threading to a
limited extent and so we've been able to
kind of compartmentalize the risk in
terms of what has to happen there when
you start getting into systems that have
like lots and lots and lots of different
pieces that are all doing threaded work
you tend to have to be a little bit more
systemic about it and start to have like
a concept of like resources or something
it's like what does this work order need
in terms of resources and let me just
like not allow other things to be doing
you know let me only run this like like
don't ever even take this work order and
start working on it if those resources
are being used by some other work order
or stuff like this right there tends to
be sort of more systemic stuff like that
just because if you actually tried to
find grain lock everything well that's
going to be more efficient because you
can be more clever about it and only do
exactly the locking you need and you
know
be lock free in places you don't have to
be and all that other stuff it's just
really hard programming and the chances
that you want to write all your code
that way and can do it in a way that
doesn't have bugs are just real low even
if you're a very good programmer it's
hard right and so that's why you don't
just write things as threads like whole
cloth all the time I'm sorry as
multi-threaded all the time and so
usually you go one of two ways either
you've got some light multi thread
locking stuff that you've hand coded
because it's very efficient and it works
well in whatever kind of like we were
trying to do and handmade hero or you
are multi threading a huge set of things
and then you tend to have to
systemically do it somehow right and
that somehow can take for all kinds of
forms like you know maybe it's like
something that's built into your
language like I think go for example you
know has a bunch of sort of primitives
that are like hey write your threaded
stuff this way and then we can guarantee
that it won't cause a problem if you do
because now we have like serialization
for those things or whatever or it's
like if it's in C++ you've got some like
utilities trucks around that like you
say I'm going to begin doing work on
this thing now then n doing work on this
thing now and the only way to like get
back a pointer to the thing at all is by
going through that so that you know that
there is a built in synchronization
happening there or something you know
blah blah blah blah blah hopefully that
answers that a little bit more
for the moment I have a thread job
system it's for rebuilding a mesh for a
big match it takes like 20 milliseconds
so I thought maybe it would make it
faster but not that much maybe like
thirteen percent faster well usually
things don't get faster when you thread
them unless you actually have a plan for
why they're going to get faster right so
for example if you know that you can
break the work down into a certain set
of pieces that you know don't have to
talk to each other and don't have
dependencies then you'll get that much
faster typically a modern hardware you
know depending on the circumstances
certainly there's other factors but you
know so like for our renderer on
handmade hero is kind of that way and so
for the render on handmade hero we do
get quite a bit of speed up by having
more threads but if you if you know
depending on how your mesh building code
is written it depends entirely on how
separable that is and how much of it can
run in parallel without locking and all
that sort of stuff right
all right I don't see more q colon so
I'm going to go ahead and close things
down there we go all right uh let's go
ahead and close that thank you everyone
for joining me for another episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along at home you can
always peer to the game on handmade here
org and it comes to the source code so
you can experiment follow along at home
if you have questions you can go to our
forum site if you want to support the
video series we do have a patreon if you
want to know when we're going to be live
we have a schedule bot and if you would
like to catch up on old episodes we do
have an episode guide that has time
coded links brought to you by the
fabulous midlo so check that out as well
that is it for today I'll be back here
tomorrow 8 p.m. pacific daylight time or
standard time I don't know which one are
we in right now do we know time in
Seattle we're still pacific daylight
time so mm we'll be back at 8pm pacific
daylight time tomorrow hope to see
everyone here for that I will ya the
handmade hero the handmade con speaker
list got posted today so check that out
if you haven't already you can go to
handmade Conda org actually no you can't
that's a lie i don't think i've posted
it up there yet you actually have to
just go to Molly rocket com that's where
it is at the moment that is about it and
I hope see you back here tomorrow at 8pm
until then have fun programming and i'll
see you guys on the internet take it
easy everyone