hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here the show recode complete came live
on stream we are well I don't we're
going to do today but we might do some
memory profiling or we might just not
I'm not sure I care about it I might
save it for some time later so I don't
know what I'm in the mood to do I'm
going to do whatever I want to do which
is basically what you should do it cuz
you know with not like we don't have
plenty of things to choose from that we
can do to move the engine forward so I'm
going to go ahead and get to it today
270 so you're going to want to go ahead
and grab 28 269 source code if you're
trying to follow along at home that's
really all I have to say so where we
left off let's see here where we left
off is we've kind of got our debug
system doing most of the things that we
wanted to do and i made like a little
nice kind of like headline like a heads
up thing that so when the debug system
is completely collapsed it kind of just
shows us a quick little little piece of
information that tells us like the frame
rate and those sorts of things so this
is a little sluggish everything is kind
of slow because I had to reboot the
machine those of you who were watching
this live know that like Windows decided
to kind of poop out on us but it's back
now and so I think we're all good looks
like we're running correctly so here's
our little line you know when we drop it
down we then get a bunch of information
that we can look at if we want to and
all of that is fine and dandy so I don't
know let's just like I said do whatever
I want to do I can be whoever I want to
be it's it's a free world in a free
country so let's go well some countries
so that's where you're watching it from
to lesser and greater degrees depending
on where you're watching from it's a
pseudo free country here in the US so
you know you can make sort of a game
that you want to make as long as you
don't try to publish it unlike the apple
store or something because then you
can't make the game you want to make you
got to make the game that they're going
to let you publish which is a different
game probably but doesn't matter point
being here we go into handmade
good world mode I'm gonna see like okay
so you know we've run the game right now
and maybe it'd be a good time to sort of
like get get this stuff a little more
under control because I now kind of know
I finished off how all the design stuff
works and I now pretty much know how all
of these things are supposed to work and
I much to the chagrin of people who are
really love smooth scrolling there is
not going to be any smooth rolling in
the game at least you know if we want to
make it smooth scroll when you go from
screen to screen that's okay but this is
not going to be happening in the game at
all because there's essentially no
there's everything in the game has to
have the concept of like a room that
you're in and so even when you're on the
out like the in the outside part of the
world it wants to be more like a
traditional game where you go from
screen to screen and not you know you're
never going to have that sort of i'm in
between two screens kind of a thing so
for example if we go up here you're
never going to have the thing where like
this where i can walk between these two
segments that's never going to be a lab
like you pretty much have to walk to the
edge and then hit hit edge and hit this
and then you can be in another room and
go right so that's just that's just how
the design work so that's just it's
non-negotiable I'm afraid but you've
seen how we did the scrolling stuff so
if you are making a game that does want
to be more about smooth scrolling and
that sort of thing you know feel free to
do that but we're not going to be doing
that here so anyway what I kind of
wanted to do I guess is maybe we should
start thinking about cleaning up that
that sort of code there that world code
and if you remember when you go into
world mode the way that this works is we
sort of have this concept that the first
time through you know if it hasn't
initialized things right it initializes
them and so when we come through here in
fact I guess I don't really even
remember exactly how we decided to
write it up or when the world gym
happens i guess now i think about it
world jen i guess still happens out in
does that still happen out in the game
state stuff i wanna because we kind of
pulled this stuff out but we haven't
really looked at it in a while so we
kind of have this this this sort of
state where I were I don't remember if
we pulled out the world Jen stuff like
you know add wall was a thing right
where did that end up going so here it
is and it's in this particular thing
play world and yeah so it looks like it
looks like what we do is when we call
yeah so we pulled it out to the extent
that when you actually say we're going
to play world it does the world generate
in here right and that's how that works
makes a bunch of random stuff for you
and then you start playing so that stuff
to get pulled out so that's all good so
anyway first order of business here is
ground chunks are not a thing ground
chunks are gone so we have to pull the
ground chunks so they're they're going
to go away and one of the things that's
nice about that too is that'll let us at
some point we want to clean up the
renderer since I don't think we're ever
going to be rendering in a background
task anymore which was something we were
doing before this will let us not have
to worry about that situation which i
think is kind of a nice thing because
yeah we had to make a bunch of
concessions to make the ground chunks
work and so we could pull those
concessions back out again and simplify
some of the code in the future in ways
that would probably be nice so I'm going
to go ahead and nuke the ground chunks
ground chunks are gone goodbye it wasn't
really all that nice to see you actually
so I'm going to get rid of all of these
and I'm going to get rid of the ground
chunk like storage and all that stuff so
anything before where we had ground
chunks uh has to go now those should
have been in here somewhere in they
should have been stored in in the state
somewhere i'm assuming they ended up not
getting moved over
get to the storage yes oh they're still
in here you can see them in the
transient state so those grand buffers
are going to go away and they're not
going to be around anymore here's our
low priority queue stuff for processing
and now that I think about it I don't
really want to delete the low priority
queue entirely I don't think because
that's how we load things as well yeah
so those those I want those to remain I
don't know if they need to be there
necessarily but i do want those to
remain so it's just the grand chunk
stuff that i want to get rid of so these
are gone we don't have the concept of
them anymore so so goodbye to you and
you did indent that over and let's see
ground buffer count this is the stuff
that recompute those ground chunks in
the case where the X people got reloaded
and I don't want that either so all that
stuff should be gone and now when I run
this we should be good although of
course we you know we could go fix that
texture thing today to is another thing
we could do that might be fun so now
when I run this I should see exactly the
same thing but now that ground chunk
stuff is gone which is kind of nice so
all right so what I would like to do now
is start to kind of pull this this world
rip stuff together a little bit more I
want to kind of tighten this stuff down
I just want to kind of go through
everything kind of get it ready for a
game code implementation right and this
game like I said design-wise oh I don't
have my mischeif come on mischief
mischief mischief here we go
once this takes a little bit to load
because we've got a lot if that makes
sense we've got a lot okay so what I was
trying to say was so hmm what I would
what I need the game to actually be able
to do now is I want to be able to make
it so that there's the concept of a room
and that doesn't necessarily have to be
baked in to any sort of data structure
or anything we could have different
sizes if we want to like zoom out or
zoom in since we can do that with the
camera pretty trivially right but there
is going to be an actual grid so there's
gonna be like this actual visible like
very obvious concept that there are
individual squares and as I implement
where of the game I think you'll kind of
see why that is but i need to actually
have this concept of grid squares and so
things are not really going to be
allowed environmentally speaking there's
there's this very heavy prioritization
of of that grid and so i'm going to want
to sort of pull back sort of gather back
a little bit of that ability to sort of
specify where things are in terms of a
grid basis and I so I'm going to want to
do something where I say like there's a
int you know 32 or whatever that is the
grid square index and be able to talk
about those so that as the world is
generated I know where I'm talking about
in terms of these grid squares and I can
make them okay and then we're going to
do some stuff for drawing later when we
add another art pack to the game but for
right now I just need some way of
drawing where those grid squares
actually are so what I'm going to do is
I'm going to make their be I
think actual I want to make their be
actual grid squares so there's actual
entities and the you know there's grid
entities so that I'm not sure how to
explain this so I actually want to make
an entity for each grid square and that
entity would have liked how you get
information about that tile right and I
don't the reason that I want to do that
at the moment is because I I want to be
able to push the combinatorial aspects
of the game as far as I can and so
although it's going to be mean that
there's a lot more entities than there
should be because there's going to be
like hundreds of entities on the screen
that wouldn't necessarily have to be
entities per se because we could
compress them down and talk about them
in a more simplified fashion right um
I'm actually not going to worry about
that because I just want to make the
decision in this particular game that
it's more about having a wide diverse
way in which things can interact and
react and so everything is going to be
simulated including like the ground and
so because I want to do that I'm just
going to say up front that I'm going to
accept the inefficiency that that brings
because this is an important part of how
the games going to work and anything
that flows from that requiring more
memory like you know maybe this games
footprint has to be bigger maybe it's
slower and like can't run on his lower
and plat for us because we're simulating
to what stuff who knows whatever it is
I'm just making a decision to make that
you know I'm making the decision that I
want that to be the way that it works so
I'm going to go ahead and start to make
that change and again this is not really
a big change or anything this is sort of
like how we had it working initially
when we just start out with a towel map
thing and all I'm doing is I'm sort of
making a tile map with the entities so
that they can still kind of be arbitrary
and we may even want to play with that a
little bit in the game as we go forward
we may want to make it actually
eventually so that
you know uh not everything is a regular
grid like we could then make irregular
grids out of entities and still the game
works the way it works or whatever right
that could be a thing but I want to be
able to recreate those grids so what I'm
going to do first is I'm going to go
into that world mode situation here and
I'm going to look at the ad wall which
is this is the thing that we were doing
before and I'm kind of looking at how
this stuff got added and this stuff I'm
going to start to probably hit a little
harder I'm going to like start to
streamline this and make this a little
bit more real because it's all kind of a
little bit so I go dishes i think the
word i've been using it's a little bit
like underbaked right okay so here is
the code that creates this you can see
that the code creates but it creates
things per screen already and you can
see that what it's doing right here is
it's a sort of calling code to create a
room and that room is passing the
parameters that are based on how many
tiles there are and that sort of stuff
right and we have the concept of the
tiles / tiles / width and all that sort
of stuff I don't know where where is
that stuff tiles / there it is being 17
by nine and all that and so when we call
the function that creates the standard
room the reason that we're getting you
know this this as our room is because I
set that 17 by nine to be the the whip
that I wanted so we end up with 1 2 3 4
5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 15 16 17 right
123456789 now in this the way that we
were doing this we had a bunch of things
out here that were like space entities
and these other sorts of things and
those entities were we were sort of
playing with how we were going to
represent the movement of the player and
again it was it was kind of useful to do
that sort of stuff and again like I was
kind of showing the basis of that and as
the rear scan exploring how the engine
work that's a good thing but now that I
know specifically like I've solidified
exactly how I want move into work
the way that movement actually works in
this game / the design is that you move
from a cell to another cell always so
your your dude cannot stand in between
two cells the game doesn't actually
allow that to happen if that makes sense
and you'll again that stuff will sort of
get to as you get a little bit further
down into the implementation but what
that means is that I want or rather I
need to represent how you move from
place to place in a way that's more
specific than just a vector that I add
and I allow the player to move around
it's going to be a little more
complicated than that and so again
that's what I'm going to start working
with now so the first thing to do is we
have this concept of entities I don't
know if you remember it's it's been a
long time obviously but hey if I
remember you should remember so we have
this concept of entities and there's
types in the entities i think is it in
sim region where we have the entities
yeah and we have some things here that's
like like space and what we said is that
space is a carved out area where you can
move well that's actually not going to
be I don't think necessary anymore I
don't think we need to create extra
entities which are spaced entities which
are what you know telling you that you
can go somewhere what I said I think I
want to do is just there's the causative
an entity that and I mean in some sense
we are keeping it it's it's but it's
floor right in others the entity type is
now like a square you can stand on like
a standable thing and so instead of
calling this space which is not really
indicative of what I actually am trying
to say what I actually would call this
would would be you know floor or
something or something like that right
and or a standable I don't know any
typos or play like you know a place you
can stand what would that called perch
placement a node graph I don't know I'm
just going to call up floor because even
though a lot of times it just
grass or something that isn't
technically a floor will know what I
mean all right so let's go ahead and
actually make this happen you can see
here that we call add ground identity
for the standard room and we make one of
these edit e space things that's not
going to be useful to us anymore because
I want an entity in each of the tiled
positions that that creates the actual
conceptual floor so what I actually want
to do here is I want to do a like a for
I loop to create one in each of those
positions so what I'm going to do is you
can see here we get like this position
here for the AB style x y&amp;z what I
actually want to do is loop over with
you know using an offset that takes
whatever the standard room size is and
does that that 17 by nine thing to it
right so let's let's do offset x 0 right
and I guess technically if we wanted to
do these rooms as if they were centered
rooms which maybe we do right we would
start the offset off if we were talking
about 17 we would start the offset off
as being negative 8 right and we would
let the offset X get up to eight so that
way we would create 17 but they would be
a balanced 17 if that makes sense so I'm
going to go ahead and create those here
you can kind of see it happening like so
and what I want to do now is I just want
to say again the 17 by 9 so 9 would be
the same it would be you know negative 4
24 and we'll see if we will you know
we're probably parametrize that in a
little bit but you know because now
we've got that kind of fine in two
places but that's again not really a
concern of mine at the moment because
I'm just you know just going to sort of
push through this code once and make it
be representative of how the game
actually works at its core so when I do
this out standard room here we go i'm
going to do this add got identity bit
here and I'm doing the standard room
collision thing standard room collision
is really presumably now
entered floor collision right and
standard floor collision I don't know
that we really need standard for
collision in the way that it was before
in some sense this entity doesn't really
have any collision because you can't
really run into it it's just a floor
tile that you can hop too and there's no
way to like bump into the floor tile I
don't think mm I don't know maybe that's
not true I it depends I guess how we
want to look at it but anyway that very
least would be standard for collision
not standard room collision and when we
say that it's traversable what I don't
actually want that 22 probably mean the
same thing as it does but it's a good
it's a good name right and in some sense
maybe that traversable is actually a
very good name for the entity type that
we're talking about here it could be
that this entity type is a traversable
in fact it's just a thing that's sitting
there and so I don't know like should it
be a flag maybe it should be a flag I
don't know that's it that's a tough
decision that's a really tough decision
and I'm not sure I guess technically
since we had a flax from there ready
maybe I'll stick with the flaxen just
say when you make something you tag it
as traversable then it's going to be a
floor thing that you can stand on and
that seems fair enough yeah I would say
ok so we have our ab style x and i'm
going to Pat like add in that offset
right at this point and to be honest I'm
not sure why these are you 30 tues
because I thought that we had centered
the world around 0 and so I don't
understand why the tile values aren't
like plus and minus e I like you know
I'm saying like I don't know why they're
you 30 tues
don't don't understand why I guess I
only go up or down with them but I don't
like that's not something we're going to
want to keep so that probably has to get
changed in the future all right so let's
take a look at standard room collision
here's the make simple grounded
collision thing and this is this is
going to be just one tiles one tile big
right that's that's all it's going to be
for now and standard floor collision
well standard floor collision is the
name that I made for this thing and I'm
going to have to change these ones up
here so we actually have like let's see
wall collision floor collision room
collision and I I guess I don't really
need to call it floor either standard
really because it's not sized in any
particular way anymore so okay so when
we add standard room there is no way to
return a single entity anymore because
there's a bunch of entities that are
created for that room and so that's just
not going to work we just we're not
going to be able to give that back if
someone wanted it they're going to have
to be a sad panda because they're not
going to get it so anyway I'm going to
go ahead and fix up these last parts
here and so when we draw one of these
floor tiles I'd like to be able to see
it and so I think what I'll do here is
again we'll just use the same thing
we're doing before we'll do a push
wrecked outline on the collision volume
so that we can see where its volume
actually is and I just want to see what
that actually ends up doing for us so
yeah so now we're creating a ton more
entities so we're going to have to
reduce the number of screen counts we do
because right now we still have some
hard coded stuff in there we were like
this is the maximum number of entities
you can have I think we'll probably get
rid of that a little in a little bit as
well what is this ground chunk rendering
ground chunks are gone I deleted ground
chunks
goodbye all right uh so yeah so anyway
in here I'm just going to make it so
that we don't create very many screens
at all you know we'll just do the one
we're starting on for now and then we'll
increase it a little bit but that way we
don't have to wait for anything weird
like that so okay so now you can see I'm
picking these and hey we did create them
so that's nice right and that's all good
because this is you know I can actually
see them there in fact if I want to I
can even use our little system here to
sort of show where they all are and
that's all great right fantastic okay um
so I would like to draw them perhaps a
little bit more permanently though uh
when I do the drawing here I want to
actually I guess I'm not at the moment
drawing the the floor things I think cuz
yet because it's turned off I do want to
actually draw these always I just want
to draw them with actual art but for now
we'll just draw the collision rectangles
which seems fine but yet but there we go
so now we can see them all and that's
much better but we're still not really
doing what I wanted to do yet because
what i want to do now is I want the are
the character to move specifically you
know from from one of these together and
to understand Winnie's on a particular
one and not right so basically like the
character should be aware of that fact
and should we need to start considering
these things differently than we were
right there not traversable in the way
that we were thinking the before
traversable before we're like empty
spaces and that you could move through
continuously as part of your collision
and that's not really what I want to do
if that makes sense so what I would like
is what I'd like to I just need to think
through how exactly I want
these to be used for starters I probably
will want these to be able to have
different elevations and so that's going
to be kind of shouldn't say probably i
know that i want to have different
elevations the only question is how
meaningful that is in terms of like
whether that one can be so high that you
can't go to it if it's next to you if
that makes sense so we'll see you about
that in a second but that that just in
general again is something that I kind
of have to start thinking about more
through the pipeline so the way that we
did collision volumes before right is we
have this concept that a thing
references a collision volume and that
collision volume has stuff in it and so
the way that we were doing movement is
just by saying hey if something's
collision volumes say that you can move
into them then that's like a walkable
region and that's how this that's how
this dude is moving right that's how
that's how I'm moving around here if
instead we were to say oh when we create
that room like in here if instead when
we did add standard room if we didn't
always add this like let's say we did
something where we said like if offset x
is less than negative 3 or something
like that or maybe greater than negative
3 then we add the flag then we would end
up in the situation where you couldn't
move into those squares even though
there's not an obstacle blocking you you
just can't go and so you see that happen
here look I can't get any further it
passed this past that boundary right
that's not something I can do and the
reason for that right is because if we
select this guy I guess there's we don't
have a good any good selection tools for
when there's entities on top of
each other i'm not sure what we would
how we necessarily fix that but what's
happening there right is when i when i
try to move into this region i think
what i like is i don't really know but i
guess what happens currently is you can
go up until you would hit the end of it
with your end that's what it looks like
right because negative 3 would be what I
what did I say so it goes to negative
where's the midpoint 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 so
8 on either side and this would be the
midpoint so negative 3 this would be 0
negative 1 negative 2 negative 3 yeah so
essentially essentially it looks like
that's the way our our thing was working
before and I think I could keep doing
this that way and we could make it so
that it worked that way but I'm not sure
that that's useful I think what I
actually want to do is say that
traversable 'he's just have a point that
you can stand on right and when you are
moving you go to that point and when you
want to go to the next one it looks to
see in that direction if there is one
for you to go to go to if that makes
sense uh that's what I actually want if
that makes sense so that's actually some
work right in order to to make that
happen that's going to be more
complicated but what that means is also
that like the way that we do movement
the part that is people colliding with
other people or obstacles that still
makes sense but the part that we did
that was moving through empty space I I
don't think does anymore because we're
it's not about moving through empty
space is about moving between specific
points and so yeah so there's that
ok so again so now if I kind of come
back to that what I'm going to do is I'm
going to say for you know for the sake
of like pushing this slowly forward I'm
going to take a look at the way where's
my sim region doing my sim region again
I'm going to say that the Samana t I
like that the category regular butter I
like that we that introspection stuff is
so funny I don't know why it was called
regular butter I wish we knew all right
anyway so pure and cemented e what I
want to do is say okay if this thing if
this entity has one of these collisions
volume groups the like I could just
probably use that same concept like
these collisions volume groups there we
go these collision volume groups are you
know they have a series of things that
tell us how the thing collides what I
want to do is say well maybe in addition
to that there's also liked the concept
of traversable points
is it able or herbal don't know anyway
so if we have one of these at the moment
it's just going to be a pee but I don't
know we might want more information
there at some point but point but point
being if we have one of these and
there's a traversable there then you can
move to it and if not not and so that's
sort of more what I was thinking and
again yeah don't know how good of an
idea this is or if it's a good idea at
all but I'm just thinking that that's
how I want to implement it as a start
and so that way you know we could have
things and say that there were multiple
points like a single entity that moves
around could have multiple traversal
points on it that you can move between
if that makes sense but you know it's
always a specific set of points that you
can actually stand on and like I said
most of the time this is just a grid but
I figured we might as well implement it
in a way that allows us to build nan
grid things if we want to because it
like for example you know if you're
moving along these these things you know
maybe sometime you know you want to do
like a little like snakey little path
like this or something and that just
might be fun to be able to do that
instead you know just something to think
about so so I'm going to say that
there's this set of traversable than
anything that is has one of these clin
value if so you can have collision
volumes for things that you cannot move
through but it can also have traversable
which are things that you can stand on
our points that you can stand on and so
then I'm going to go ahead and take a
look at the collision routines which I
believe her in here
in move entity so you can see in here
the way this works it's kind of annoying
a crappy code that we kind of played
around with but you know until we want
to actually sort of rewrite the
collision texture I'm gonna leave it the
way it is we're not going to fuss with
it we're just going to leave it in it's
sort of all in its it's sort of
prototype II state but the hero i'm
going to delete this because we don't
really need to break when it's the hero
specifically at this point oh well you
know what I'm sure we'll probably use
that again actually so maybe we will
maybe I won't delete it even though it's
not necessary at the moment so when we
do this stuff and we've got these
iterations that we're going through so
what I actually want to do here is what
I actually want to do here is I want the
there to be some sort of conceptual way
that this this code works that's largely
semantic so I need this and like I said
it's going to be contra key I need this
function to still work with the
collision volumes but I just need to
pull out the part where it I need to
remove the part that's talking about the
traversable right so the part where it
looks to see if something's traversable
which is like here I i need to to remove
that right and let's see this is if it's
traversable and can collide so we all of
this stuff let's see how we're doing
here so this is all just kind of
refreshing my memory of how we did this
handle events based on area of lapping
collision loop you
and so here's the ground stuff so yeah
so get entity ground point now so this
is going to be very formalized because
now what's going to happen is the
entities ground points are always going
to be specifically tied to that that
information about the traversable 'he's
so you're always going to be standing on
one of those and when you're moving
between two of them you're going to be
like that's an actual thing that's known
so entities move between two of these
points and they can't change that
traversal really right part of the rules
of the game are like when you decide to
go from one square to another you have
to touch that square you decided to go
to you can't like even if you steer and
decide to go down like you know I was
going left and then I decided to go down
if you've committed to that square
you're still going to touch you're going
to technically go through it and that's
just like I said part of the rules of
the way the game works so so yes if
you're always doing that there is no
such thing as like gravity really or Z
freefall you're always going to a
particular Z so in some sense yeah
gravity is not really a thing at all in
fact we can really get rid of this this
stuff can go there's no such thing as an
unsupported entity there's no such thing
as as being in free fall it's just plain
not allowed so yeah so we're going to
get rid of this gravity goes away and
that is supported thing that has to go
away as well so I don't even know was
that just a flag that was set up here is
supported as you support it that's what
it was so Z support is not here what
does this say does it make more sense a
flag neckla collides non-spatial yeah so
some of this again some of this stuff is
going to go as well a traversable also I
guess technically we don't really need
that flag because it's just that would
just be if we want to optimize because
really it's just if you have a
Percival point then you do you know so
the concept that something's traversable
is known from looking at its collision
group so that just seems like it's not
really an issue anymore so yeah so Z
supported I'm going to go ahead and get
rid of this stuff so ground plus equals
like all of this stuff where we take the
ground and we we change that stuff this
this is all not this is this is not
allowed anymore all of this is gone so
let's see blah blah blah blah blah blah
blah blah blah that's that's going away
and yeah so the isset reversible thing
basically I want to neuter all of this
stuff because that's going to kind of
get handled in a separate phase so I all
I really want this cousins active
routine to do anymore is I really just
want it to collide if there's you know
two entities that are trying to move and
they hit each other that's the only
thing that this routine is supposed to
be doing at all and so I just want it to
like handle that case it's not supposed
to check whether you can go stand
somewhere you can always go stand there
if you don't run into an obstacle in the
way so that concept that we had before
about also defining the space which you
can move and the ground area like that's
that's no more that's not that's not how
we want this to work anymore so yeah so
is set entity traversable and this thing
and can collide what I don't know is
where do we handle the things that
aren't traversable like where do we
handle colliding with things that are
non traversable right oh here we go it's
an or so yeah so what I really want to
know is I really want to know the can
collide thing right I really just want
to know can collide so if it's can
collide then we go through and we do the
volume test we see whether or not we
would hit this thing right and that's
all good
I'm not sure where the traversable part
was exactly so we go through the volumes
we say for each test volume we do our
Minkowski dilation we see whether or not
we would hit the walls of this thing
here is the traversable part okay so we
say if it's reversible then we allow
ourselves to to go through it I guess
and that's the part that we're gonna
have to change this case is no longer
really happening right so really all
we're doing is this one case here which
is the case where the thing is an
obstacle okay and we also need to make
it here where I think the tmaxx is all
we really have to do with the tmaxx
before we were computing the furthest we
could go by using that t max value so
now we just have to assume that the
furthest you can go is all the way right
so we really as long as we just set t
max to always be one I'm assuming that
that will solve the problem that we what
we use to do is we use the collisions
are to figure out how far I could go
through movable space right and that's
going away now so now this entity flag
traversable bit that actually I can get
rid of because now what we're going to
do is when we create that rounded
collision or ground identity whatever
collision what I want to do is take the
floor collision and add one of those
points that you can stand on so where I
do this make simple grounded collision
what I need to do is make this one's a
little bit more specific and so what I'm
going to probably do is is go get that
code make simple grounded collision oops
I'm going to take this and I'm going to
make like another one of these that's
that's fancier so make simple
traversable or make simple floor
collision something like that and and
there we go so I don't really know what
the tile depth so this was making like
an empty area with a certain height to
it and the floor is actual to extend
downward a bit right it's not supposed
to extend upward anymore so I'm not sure
exactly how we want to do that but I
guess tile depth and meters is the thing
to pass here probably and when we call
this function make simple for collision
what I'm going to do here is say that
that dims eCos out the bottom so what is
this Dogma not world arena change using
the fundamental types arena etc oh ok
well we Creek recruit we recreate these
every time though so why am i
complaining about that I don't know why
we would need a fundamental types arena
I guess just so we don't like why
wouldn't you just create these every
time you started the game I don't know
that seems like a stupid to do but i'll
leave it for now because we're not
thinking about that stuff right now so
maybe it wasn't as stupid as it sounds
who knows anyway so this volume stuff at
the moment i actually don't need this
thing to have a collision volume now
that doesn't mean i won't want it to
have a collision volume in the future
because like i said i want some of these
to be like higher up potentially than
others and things like that and so you
know we may go ahead and do that a
little bit in the future but for right
now i don't actually want that to happen
so let's
let's go ahead and make this happen
there we go so here's my traversable
point what's the total volume hmm i
don't have a total volume here i want to
include the Traverse little point in the
total volume well I don't know so I
guess what I would say is the total
volume is still going to be that
dimension and the offset p is is at this
point I think going to be 1 point 0 dim
Z in the sense that it's displaced
downward right I guess I don't know what
the offset p the ossipee would be up so
from the carpenter so it's actually
negative it goes like down or I guess
given the way that we wrote that if it
point 5 is the amount we do it be 0 so
it would be entirely below it right I
think that's how I love to go read let's
go see how that's actually listed but
anyway so in here I would then say okay
I want to do my traversable 'he's that
first reversible is going to be at the
zero zero zero point right it's that
middle point so I really wouldn't even
have to initialize it but that just
gives me that one traversable that I
wanted right and I'm going to go draw
these so we can see them no binary oh
right stop key so in here where we do
volume count and we draw the volumes out
for what we were doing so let's see
where was that that was in the floor
right so where we draw these out here
i'm also going to do a thing where we
draw the traversable sand what I should
do is I should pull this out into a
thing that's like draw collision volume
I don't know why it's not that way as as
is we'll probably do that in a second so
here's that traversable point and wish
we had more screen real estate all right
and I'll just make this called
reversible index so what I'll do here is
I'll do a push wrecked that just
basically draw like a point at wherever
this thing is and so I think I just do
whatever the volume whatever the
reversible p is I don't know that I want
to do anything else with it and then
we've got the volume dim XY that's what
I want Oh what's not a volume it's so
really this is just a dim so I don't
know what the dim should be you know
some number and then we would draw this
as a point you can stand off oops
so yeah that's not great I'm continually
moving upwards everything else was fine
but i guess that ground point bit was a
problem hold please I don't actually
know how we recompute where the ground
point for the entity is but let's check
player Delta eg and let's see do we have
a dot Z coming in anywhere here I can't
see where I am
so what exactly do we do with this
ground handle overlap at ground testing
the index can overlap entities overlap
handle overlap what does the handle
overlap do pray tell that just does
stairwells I'm going to pull that for
now because we don't have that concept
at the moment so let's just simplify
things a little bit here and say that
handle overlap is going to go away for
the moment so this all goes away and now
we just the figure out why we're getting
that movement upwards I assume it's just
an offset like you saw what I'm talking
about right like see I'm floating
upwards not good so let's see so what is
the position that we actually except we
take entity DP and updated so now we've
got the velocity that we're going to try
and then I assume through here we've got
the TMNT max and when we get out to the
bottom we take our team into max we take
our player Delta and we move the player
by that amount so where is the player
Delta getting a Z displacement from
would be my first question
because i'm not sure why we would ever
get anything into the z-component there
like that doesn't actually meet a whole
lot of sense to me
I'm going to go ahead and just check to
see if player Delta is the thing I'm
just going to say player Delta Z equals
zero to see what happens if we prevent
any amount of Z motion at the moment all
I know if it still does it okay so
apparently that was it so we are getting
Z acceleration in there for some unknown
reason okay so anyway I think that's
probably about time to stop for today
but I guess I've got a couple more
minutes left so I'm just going to look
into this where we're getting that Z
motion where we're getting that from so
we come in here and we are passing in an
acceleration so I guess the first thing
I would check is is the acceleration
ever being set to something positive so
if I was to zero out the Z acceleration
would I still get the upward motion my
assumption would have been yes because I
don't think we're ever telling it to
accelerate upwards right so what that
says is that it's nobody's ever
accelerating anything upwards but we're
still getting some upward stuff anyway
so where is that coming from so here's
some we're doing some multiplication of
the DDP here to to normalize it and we
take it multiply the MU spec speed if we
started out with zero here then we're
not going to get any we shouldn't ever
get any other zeros here same thing with
this if we never got any pot n Easy
velocity we should never see any of that
happening so I'm not really sure what
the deal is with that and then through
here obviously still like none of this
stuff seems like it should generate Z
and so what I'm wondering is do we
somehow have velocity that's pointing
upwards somehow when and where is that
happening
so the first thing I'm going to say is
let's go back and look to see when we
have handmade world mode I'm going to go
take a look to see what happens in our
movement code here do we ever specify
some kind of upward motion if DZ is not
equal to 0 DZ equals what
hmm the entity so this looks like there
was some jumping code in here it looks
like but oh my seriously you know what
that is the fact that the space bar
starts the game and causes the hero to
jump still is where that velocity is
coming from because we didn't put any
hysteresis on it so it will trigger that
it'll actually trigger the jump code
that's what we're seeing that's
hilarious so right now it's this this is
the code that is the problem it's one
initial jump that I'm doing essentially
so like space far to start was like
being interpreted as a jump that's
hilarious all right well at least we
know at least we know all right so I'm
going to call it for now we're going to
go to QA anyone has any questions hit me
no queues going to be an early night
Colonel dragon so how will this tell
based movement work we still be able to
move freely within a tile or will the
character actually snap to a tile to to
be to be demonstrated later it is
actually neither of those things if you
con when will we sort out the coordinate
system uh probably like what I'd like to
do is I'd like to sort of clean up the
sim path thing and then I'd like to
clean up the storage which is when I
assume the coordinate system stuff can
get can get store sorted as well
for godin is it possible to get access
to the source code if I lost access to
my old email account on not so there's
two things that you can use for access
one is the link that you got when you
when you purchase originally and the
other is your email address but if you
have neither of those two things then
there is no way for us to know if you're
someone who purchased it so we can't
actually determine whether right like we
don't have any way of associating you
with something else if you have like
even a paypal reference number would
probably be sufficient maybe for us to
dig it up but you need some piece of
information that nobody else could Forge
that proves that you're a person who
purchased the thing if that makes sense
so usually you're going to need either
the link or the email but if you happen
have something else like a paypal but
proof of purchase kind of a thing that
may be okay depending on what it has in
it
midlo how about stairwells dirt reversal
used to be seamless as far as i remember
now that the rooms are locked have will
stairwells work what will happen is
you'll move between them still and it'll
run between them you but you can't
change direction on the way down or up
and that's very intentional actually
because most of the time when you go
down a thing you're you won't be able to
get back up again like it's like you
gotta commit so so that's actually by
design
the I burley any plans on changing
vigils to do code instead of the full
IDE i believe the full debuggers
included well two things 1 i'm not sure
why we would but two I actually at least
on the Linux one that people were
talking about it didn't have even close
to all the features like they didn't
show disassembly and stuff like that
apparently and so I don't if I don't
know if there's like a Windows one
that's better or something but someone
would have to verify that it's like
better in some way otherwise i'm not
sure why we would long billion what are
the benefits trade us in having each
tile be an entity so the reason that i
want to every tile to be an entity was
because i want you to be able to do
anything to a tile that you could do to
anything else right like you know i
don't know how far we'll push it in
terms of when we're actually trying to
like for lack of better term tune which
is again not really my job description
but when we're trying to make sure that
the game is like playable and fun I
don't know how much of it will use but
obviously like let's say you have a
ground tile and there's the concept of
some spell or something that causes
things to levitate or that makes
something heavy or that turn something
into water we just want everything to
work everywhere basically and so if you
want this to happen the floor should be
able to react to everything just the
same way everything when else does so it
should participate fully in every
transaction that occurs if that makes
sense so having them be entities that's
a bonus and the other bonus is we can
create our levels out of non grid
patterns if we want to whereas if we
force it to be a grid we could never do
that so I'm just deciding to go that
route instead because I mean one of the
things that's true as computers are very
powerful and so you know in a 2d game
sometimes it's a good idea to try and
use that horsepower to do interesting
things because you're not using that
horsepower to
3d rendering fancy photorealistic stuff
so you want to put that horsepower
somewhere you don't just want the game
to run at fifty thousand frames a second
and be boring right and so what I'm
going to try and do is like focus a lot
of that energy on entity simulation so
all of those cycles were not spending on
3d calc stuff we put into the sim yeah
so but as far as the trade-offs are
concerned if we had made it in a grid we
get to compress a lot of that down and
if they aren't entities because then we
could just store the minimal amount of
information we can store it in a 2d
array and it's much more compact so
we're not wasting as much memory
bandwidth we're not wasting as much a
testing time there's a lot of stuff that
we can eliminate if we just assume that
everything is always a grid so basically
we're giving up a bunch of optimizations
is what we're giving up Toby Peters are
you al kidding your image on the heap or
stack heap right could you even allocate
enough on the stack so part of the
problem with that question is that heap
and stack like when you say on the stack
you mean the stack for function calls
and the answer is no we're not
allocating on the stack for functions
called function calls but sure you could
allocate them on the stack for function
calls if you wanted to for some reason
but you don't want entities to be
tracked on the stack for function calls
because their lifetime has nothing to do
with the stack for function calls if
that makes sense right we don't allocate
them on the heap in any real sense of
the word because the heap is actually a
layer down from virtual Alec right
virtual Alec isn't really the heap
because there actually is a thing that
is the heap and they keep we aren't
using that's if we were calling keep a
lock or something like that right so
there actually is there's there's the vm
there's a virtual memory system which
you might call the heap then there's the
heap which is built on top of the ritual
memory system we're not using that and
then there's the stack which is also
built on top of the virtual memory
system and we are using that because we
kind of have to
see does it automatically in something
we can do about that right so we're
we're allocating stuff is we have
essentially our own stack that is not a
function sack it's just a regular stack
that we use in memory and wii virtual
alec a block of memory and we just
allocate from that stack and that's what
the entities are right now
hey Mark Hughes
BTN games says he asked q where is your
Q BTN games
do you foresee complications with the
new greed entity flora system and the
texture slats given that you want a
variable height / traversal entity like
I said before I knew to the texture
splats so that's not how it's rendered
anymore that's why i deleted the ground
chunk that those were the grand chunks
dude in basement handle RB ne1 r or l
our confusion over Atomics who is
written all are and what is this
confusion over Atomics if modern CPUs
usually reorder or merge rights how do
they use memory mapped registers can you
even bit bang a serial protocol with it
yet I mean the the important thing to
remember is that the CPU is as strongly
ordered as you need it to be because you
could put in fencing and stuff like that
so the complete answer to that question
is it depends exactly what you're doing
right first of all certain areas of
memory like pages of memory are marked
in specific ways so for example some
memory is right combining memory some
memory isn't right combining memory blah
blah blah so most CPUs when they're that
have a memory management Union that
memory management unit knows information
about pages that are mapped so it's not
like the CPU behaves the same way when
it's talking about a page that's mapped
for hardware io versus a page that's
mapped for just use by the CPU right so
first of all the MMU will do different
things depending on when it when it
knows that it's a special kind of memory
that's looking at and then the other
thing is the CPU obviously can be
instructed to put barriers and fences in
between things so that the reorder
window will not reorder things above and
below specific markers so you know you
can put it in mm fence command or
various things like this that will say
you know this is not supposed to
move any store commands above this you
know thing in the reorder buffer or
anything below it so when you are are in
a situation like an OS or driver writer
past you know will find themselves in
when dealing with the hardware you have
to know your CPU you have to know your
memory subsystem and you have to you
know take into account all of it right
and do it correctly in the old days
obviously was really easy because
old-school CPUs there was none of this
there wasn't a cash you know so and
there was no such thing it's like out of
order execution
long bullion what is the plan with
rendering when the hero walks behind a
piece of terrain that is on a higher
level and obscures the hero I don't know
to be honest I'm not sure what I wanted
you to render that I'm not sure how
often that would ever actually happen
but I don't know I'm not sure how we
want to render that Jim's 0 will this
system fix the collision areas getting
stuck in each other if stacked example
two heroes loading at the same position
when we do our final collision detection
we will make sure that stuff works but
right now i'm not actually i'm not
actually trying to improve the collision
detector I'm just changing the game to
work the way that the final design wants
it to work it's not trying to improve
the quality that makes sense
all right not much cues today so I guess
that's good let's go ahead and shut down
alright thank you everyone for joining
me for an episode of handmade hero it's
been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow along
at home you can always go to the game on
handmade here org the handy dandy
pre-order button and it comes with a
source code so you can follow along with
with it at home we also a forum site you
can go to which will be shutting down
this weekend for two days while they
test it's going to move to a handmade
network and they're going to be testing
it this weekend before bringing it back
up again so yeah so go check out the
forum site but be aware that sometime
friday night i'm guessing they'll be
shutting it down and then it'll be back
on monday for our stream we also a
patreon page you want support the video
series we have a tweet bought the tweets
the schedule at you if you want to know
when the series is going to be live on
stream and we also have this little
handy dandy button which you can use
which tell you the next time it's going
to be live of course in this case it is
actually alive but it would give a
little countdown camera normally that's
about it until then until tomorrow which
I guess well you know what tomorrow's
Thursday so I won't be here so I'll be
back here friday i'll be off tomorrow
i'll be back here friday until then have
fun programming and i will see you guys
on the internet tickety's everyone