hello everybody and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete-game live on
stream we have done a bunch of work with
our renderer to make it a lot more
efficient in hardware really has nothing
to do with renders in general it was
mostly just a case of hardware really
doesn't like texture changes if you're
on certain types of cards other types of
cards don't mind and so we kind of
needed to have a solution to that
problem and so what we did is we started
using texture arrays and we have much
much better throughput than we did
before we still get other issues in the
renderer that we'll have to address some
at some point that have to do with
performance right now we're using way
too much memory due to our the way we're
handling our back buffers right now
we're doing some stuff with def peeling
and multi sampling and stuff like that
that's just it's a little too piggy
and so we're probably gonna have to do
some work to make sure that those things
are a little bit more frugal and we also
are doing some things right now with
respect to texture usage that are absurd
for example right now everything's a 512
by 512 texture but we've never updated
the fonts to for example be packed into
a single texture so right now like every
letter of a font I believe will get its
own 512 by 512 bitmap into which it will
pack a little tiny character in the
upper left corner is what what is
actually happening as you might imagine
that is not particularly useful or
necessary so we will want to do some
work ship wise on that sort of stuff
down the line however I don't really
know that we care about it at the moment
especially because you know if we take
up 50 of our texture slots with random
characters or something it doesn't
really affect our ability to develop the
game we're still getting totally fine
frame rates and everything else and the
only thing that we have right now that's
a bit slow is lighting which of course
we can always turn off for development
if we need to and
we will eventually improve that anyway
so that's really not a big deal so I
would say let's just leave it for now
it's in a good state it's a pretty
reasonable system I think what we want
to do now is focus on the asset system
and the asset tagging and we have a
pretty clear path for that really what
we just want to do is iterate on it
until we think it's in a good place and
the way we're gonna do that is right now
our world is very barren we can create
rooms and hop around them and do
whatever we want but what we cannot do
is really decorate them much because we
just don't have we don't have an answer
for how we want to bind our input assets
to what we see on the screen and so
that's really the challenge that we have
to face and this is actually I would
actually argue this is one of the most
difficult things in game programming and
the reason why it doesn't appear
difficult most of the time is because
most of the time people don't really end
up solving it and we're not gonna solve
it fully on handmade hero either because
my my feeling is that the actual
solution to it which i think is the more
appropriate one actually involves such a
huge step forward in terms of game
development systems and things like that
that it's impractical to consider on a
project where we only code two hours a
day two days a week so put that aside
and just say that asset binding is a
very very difficult problem and most of
the time the way to solved much like
np-complete problems is you don't really
solve the problem you solve an easier
problem that gets you most of what you
want and you accept some of the
compromises so that's really all we're
looking for and again it just has to
work in order for our game
to run and do what we need it to do it
doesn't have to be perfect in order to
ship in fact if things had to be perfect
to ship we'd probably never ship
anything so anyway we know that we're
we did the cutscenes as well and those
all seem to be working we double-check
those so here's the game running just
fine
but as you can see everything is just
cubes blank cubes and we don't want a
game full of blank cubes what we want to
do is put things on the cubes and in
addition to putting things on the cubes
we also want to be able to put items in
the rooms and that sort of stuff right
because we've got little items that we
can put in there but right now if we put
an item in there it would just be
another Bank blank cube or something and
we do have a fairly kind of poor system
right now for picking some assets and
that's how we made like the hero pick
pick the head asset and so on and we can
you know do some stuff here in terms of
training the hero and so on but it
really isn't that good and so what we
want to do is we want to now actually
create a real answer to this problem
right we've got most of our stuff
working in a pretty reasonable way and
so what we would like to do here is we'd
like to come up with some kind of an
answer as to how we're really gonna do
this and I feel like the best way to do
it is to actually try to make an
orphanage filled with the stuff that we
think should really be there and also
fix the hero the hero still using the
old assets we have new assets for the
hero that are at the right perspective
this is kind of at the wrong perspective
so all those sorts of things really want
to happen at some point here and I think
now is that point right that now is the
time that we want to try to get that all
working we should probably fix our debug
system to snap these to the corners to I
don't know when we lost that snapping I
think we changed to like pixel
coordinates at some point rather than
like percentage based coordinates or
something and we lost a little bit of
something there so anyway that's that's
really what I want to do and I feel like
the things we can focus on in the short
term to try and like drive that because
we've got a few things here we can
really clearly focus on one of them is
get the right sprites for the hero the
other is the walls provide a really good
opportunity for working on the asset
tagging because there's actually some
fairly complex stuff that has to happen
with those wall textures if you look at
what we've got in terms of what goes on
to the walls art wise right in the
handmade art directory
we've got example assets from Anna that
are what things you know testings and
what you can see here is right like
there's these textures that have panels
and those panels are semantic like this
is clearly the beginning of a run this
is the middle of a run this is the end
of a run and this is for one like
isolated one that doesn't have a run you
know and so and like that's for the top
and these are for the bottoms you know
and so if we looked at something like
that we know that the assignment of
those is has to be like coming from the
procedural generator because only the
procedural generator is going to know oh
you know I wanted this to be a
continuous run of this wall so each one
of these things should be that way and
furthermore like you know the procedural
generator probably wants to think in
terms of should these things be
staggered Heights are all the same
height so that they look continuous or
not right and all of those sorts of
things are pretty important for getting
getting it right you know so we want to
come up with a very good system for
describing those things that makes it
easy for us to do what we need to do
here now if we look you can see that
we've got a couple different types of
orphanage blocks as well these are like
floor tiles for example and these are
stone floor tiles right so we have two
different types of floor tiles there and
then these are like wall tiles you know
and here's an example of a forest simple
forest ground tile too you know we've
got
trees we've got furniture to place right
and so we want to we want to try and
conceptualize what's the easiest way for
our code in the generator to articulate
things into the world that will then
select the right assets and the most
primitive way of doing that would just
be to explicitly say what the asset is
you know and maybe that's what we go
with there's the notion of having some
matching we have some of that in there
now and finding the balance between
those is going to be important sometimes
you cannot articulate the entire thing
and the hero would be a good example of
that
the hero is an entity in the world but
the hero can turn right so if we were to
just say explicitly what the hero is
then he couldn't turn because the
parameter of what direction hero is
facing could be used
you just have explicit bitmaps right so
it might be fine for a wall to have that
but it wouldn't be fine to hear that
that extending it a little bit further
it might also not be fine for a wall to
have that why well let's suppose we
wanted walls when we hit them to show
damage well if damage if a damaged wall
is a different asset from a wall then if
all you know about the wall is that it
is having this particular texture on it
you wouldn't know what texture to look
for when it got damaged so you can see
how raising it up one level and saying
well I'm going to specify a class of
possible things around this wall with at
least one parameter which is how damaged
it is gives you the ability to specify
something if the generator that is what
you wanted to say but then have a match
occur later on in the pipeline that
allows the
is to put more things in they can show
response to some parameter does this
make sense and so again this is why I
say this is a very very sensitive part
of the pipeline in other news I'm
wondering why we're having weird I think
this might be a fog based issue there's
some kind of weirdness with like if you
look at this all of the alpha blending
looks totally right
you see I'm saying it looks perfect
really really good right
and remember this is order independence
and that's pretty awesome that the
render is doing that it's great but like
that is wrong and I think it's because
it's getting fogged I feel like the
Alpha is getting fogged wrong you know
I'm saying to you and I guess I can
prove that by the fact that this looks
fine even in the same exact way and the
only difference here is that the fog is
turned off so we've got a fog bug you
know what why don't I go and love that
in our fancy github
all right there we go I've had to learn
how to use github because I released the
meow hash as open-source and it seems
like people all use github for that sort
of thing so I had to learn how to use
github which was a real treat let me
tell you but so I sort of vaguely know
my way around it now it's not pretty but
for example I at least know the basics
like I can make new branches put stuff
in there merge them in and comment and
all that stuff so I had to learn to do
all that stuff reluctantly but it does
mean that I can at least use the hand
made here oh one more now which of
course I never really did I just made a
script that would update it and I never
looked at it again more or less but I do
sort of know how to use it now and it
can least use this stuff reasonably so
there we have it
so anyway what I want to do is focus on
that for the next few weeks because that
will take our game from something that's
very prototype looking to something that
actually starts to look quite game-like
the difference between something that
looks like a prototype of something that
looks like a game is is art I mean
people ship entire games where the
gameplay is terrible so it's not
gameplay that differentiates a prototype
from a finished product sadly but art
definitely does so you look at this
screenshot and it clearly looks like a
prototype because everything is fairly
blocky
I mean granted you know you know
Minecraft are the best-selling games of
all time doesn't look particularly
different than this but that's a
separate issue I suppose you can't
compare things to Minecraft sort of an
anomaly most of the time if you look at
a game that looks like this you know
that it's a prototype because it clearly
doesn't have much art in it
so really what we want to do is take our
game from looking like a prototype to
looking like more of a an actual game
and that just involves having you know
art assets in place and looking like
they belong there so that's what we're
gonna try and do now and we want to try
and move that as far down as we can to
something that looks you know if not
shippable than at least on the way to
shippable insane so I'm gonna go ahead
and build the game here just to make
sure everything is still working
properly looks like everything is oops
don't ask me why I've got two for coders
open I guess I got a little overzealous
there all right but if you recall the
way that we were doing this previously
is that inside the asset system we've
got a bunch of different ways that this
sort of stuff works but we have these
things called asset vectors and an asset
vector basically has a tag count and the
tag count is something that's specified
in the hhas here so we've got this
notion that any individual asset can can
sort of depend on or specify a series of
parameters right and on top of that we
also had a type system so we would say
something like okay you know this thing
here this asset shadow or asset tree
sword rock grass tough stone those sorts
of things right all of those things were
also a sort of orthogonal way of
selecting things so you could also say
in addition to saying here's some tags
and each tag has a parameter so you know
if I said well let me let me actually
load up the tags here they should be
here somewhere so the tags are things
like smoothness flat it's facing
Direction Unicode code point font type
shot index primacy blah blah blah blah
blah right and the difference between a
tag and a type is a type is just a
category of objects you basically say
look this is what I'm looking for
whereas a tag is a thing that says
here's a parameter like I don't just say
that something is flatness I say that it
has flatness of 0.4 right and then when
I go to pick an asset I say here is a
type of asset and here is the time right
and and so on
sooo that was sort of the way that we
had things going and I mean you know
it's it's ok we could keep going that
way it's just it's a little off it's
just not quite right I and so I want to
try in take the approach of
snuffleupagus oriented programming which
we've done before I and snuffleupagus
oriented programming if you'll remember
SOP is when we basically say look we all
really know what we're doing here we
don't have a strong opinion about how we
want this code to work but we know that
we want it to work and we want to work
well so let's start on the side that
uses the system and let's see what we
would type in if we imagined that we
have the perfect system on the other
side so just every put it out of your
mind how it works
it's magical it's just gonna appear
somehow with pixie dust and unicorns
snuffleupagus just comes and saves the
day it's fine what would we write in
that case and then we use what we come
up with there by focusing on the
imaginative perfect system to then
inform our design of the actual system
which we then have some idea of what we
might want right so it's kind of a way
of generating some requirements when you
don't really know what they are yet
right you know sometimes you go into
piece of code you know exactly what it
should do and so the goal is just to
write a piece of code that
satisfies those things that you want the
code to do
other times you're dealing with a much
more conceptual and abstract in this
case that's exactly we have we know we
want some way of talking about these art
assets that works well for the code we
need to write for the gameplay but we
don't really know what that would be we
don't know exactly what the best type of
code would be calls would be for this
system so this is a way of us getting
insight into what that should be is just
imagine we can call anything we want
anytime what do we end up typing in so
let's pop into the world generator code
and try some stuff so here's the couple
things I might try first of all I'm
gonna take a look at code that generates
a room and I'm going to say for the code
that generates a room I want to do the
basic step that I was just talking about
just a moment ago which is let's figure
out how we might state that we want to
put those orphanage wall blocks in there
so you know this stuff how would I say
that I want to put like these on the
floor and maybe I randomly want to pick
you know different ones of these because
these are just tests imagine when Anna
actually does them eventually those
these will probably somewhat different a
little more than that maybe or maybe not
like maybe we just that's as we don't
want that much variance I don't know but
point being you know we want to be able
to randomly pick from some of those we
want to be able to make these work
properly where we have depending on
where is in the run it selects the right
panel out of the art right so let's see
how we're gonna say that and how we're
gonna include that in the entity and
then based on what we've come up with
there then we'll have some idea of what
to code on the other side when the
entity goes to actually render so there
we go all right I think how much time
you have left half hour is that right
when did we start we're at 12:30
oh no no we've only been doing four and
we thought we've got an hour hour and a
half hour and a half all right
so in here when we go to place a room
and again this is just some basic
generation code we made it's nothing
particularly special but what you can
see here is we we then have sort of some
code which will go in there and for
example here it's doing some some work
to sort of put rooms in place but I
think this just puts the rooms there
right yeah I think so so this is
probably the code I really want to look
at because we don't really need to deal
with it at a higher level we can deal
with it right weren't actually spotting
down the tiles so this for example is
where we're we're sliding down those
tiles and you can see us adding in the
pieces here and you can see us just kind
of what we randomly do is slap down
something asset grass here which is
probably pretty meaningless and that's
just what we called the the the cube
type that was that was there right cubes
at the moment don't even get textures on
them in our system we have the ability
to do so we just don't even use it so
this is what generates all of those
entities and what we want to do is be
able to generate the correct wall tiles
for each of these so what you can see
here is inside this inside all this
generation code mostly what we're doing
is we're putting entities on and the way
that we're putting entities into the
world is we start by adding an entity we
end by placing it somewhere and in
between right we often do stuff like
this where we add pieces to the entity
and the reason we have this notion is
that an NV is sort of a logical
construct that we think of as you know
there's a wall here or there's a player
here but that individual semantic
construct that we're programming with
may itself be composed
smaller pieces that we don't think about
separately other than to produce the
visuals and so that's what the idea is
behind the piece is a wall could have
two different pieces to it like if there
was a weird floating I on a pedestal or
something right that always just wanted
to be talked about together because they
never really were able to be separated
or anything like that but you want to be
able to control their animation or you
know how they're rendered we've got this
notion that an entity can have multiple
pieces and so the piece concept is
really what encodes how an entity's
visuals are presented and so we want a
way of specifying those that's actually
what we're trying to do here we want a
way of specifying those such that we can
capture the specificity that we were
talking about with the texturing right
so that's that's where we would need to
encode what parts of this we were
expecting to have happen right um so
let's say that I wanted to move over to
[Music]
let's say that I move over to the entity
system here and we've got the definition
remember the entity system will be
finalized later so this is kind of we
can do whatever we want here we can
literally just do anything that comes to
mind we don't have to think about doing
anything well we can just throw anything
in here and this will be dealt with
later that's intentional very
intentional so you look at this one of
the things that it looks like to me sort
o'the right is
we've got these entity pieces here it's
called it's called any visible piece you
can see that it encodes a few things and
they're not that bad honestly it's light
index still used it's not I don't think
it was they're not that bad right
we know that it's got some color we know
this got an offset from wherever the
entity is we know that it has an asset
type which is how we select I don't know
really why it's there I think that's how
I would normally do it right so we've
got our vector here and then we've got
sort of our flags and type down here but
so we have our color our offset and
we've got our dimensions the dimensions
probably should be three dimensional
rather than two dimensional if we're in
keeping sort of with the fact that now
things generally exist in three
dimensions we can always just ignore the
Z for things that are flat but I think
we probably want three I think we want
everything to sort of be conceptually a
cube even if we don't render it as cube
especially because we may need to absorb
light and stuff within our final
lighting we want to kind of know what
that is so I'm going to start with just
some basics here I'm gonna make this
into three-dimensional which shouldn't
really require much because now in here
where we're doing ad piece we can just
force people to specify
three-dimensional things and they can
just specify the final component as 0 if
that's actually what they wanted so in
here where we're adding a piece will
just say look there's the dimension and
it's fine then you hear where we're
doing this sort of thing instead of a v2
where we just do 0 and the height for
those sorts of things
of course I don't really know why we
specify it that way but I guess we do
you know we can just put this thing here
for now like so and for this one I guess
in here we can just say radius radius
radius it's kind of sounds like kind of
funny there and yeah same here so in
here we we know that we've got the ball
height I feel like that should really be
in Z though so I kind of feel like these
should probably be more like that
honestly like we kind of want to go
through and clean that up into making
everything actually specify things in 3d
uh so you know that's that's roughly
what we're looking at here when we go to
actually render these things we would
also like to render them a little more
sensibly there I'm gonna take a look in
here I think we've got entity rendering
where we go through the pieces here
right here so you can see here we we
kind of do our our nonsense where we
where we fuss with it a little bit you
can see where we do our dimensions we
actually kind of control that stuff by
picking out the pieces that we wanted
and so what I point out here is like
when we're doing a cube now we could
actually do this correctly so X Y Z like
that we could have this now be specified
in its entirety that lets us use full
three-dimensional specification for that
which I think we want for lights again I
think should really just just specify
the dimension again like so seems good
to me and so really these folks just use
the Y which is fine because that's you
know if we want to just encode a single
dimension for flat things that's fine
too but it just seems like that's a good
thing to just start with getting
ourselves properly properly set up for
that now since we're back in the game
and we don't really care about the
cutscenes much I'm gonna
pop back over to handmade that's EPP and
I'm just gonna go ahead and turn back on
the little we've got this little thing
that instead of actually playing the
intro cutscene what we do is we force
the game immediately to pretend that the
player one has started so that we just
boot directly in which is a lot easier
so anyway this is this is just exactly
the same as it was before or should have
been you can see that the lights are a
little bit larger I think because before
I guess we where did we add pieces for
lights so much they shouldn't really
have been larger let me look at where we
were
you really care about things so add lamp
when this calls add piece light this
stuff is kind of old and pretty out
pretty worn out at this point because
it's gone through a lot of revisions so
when it calls add piece light it just
passes radius and an offset and the
radius gets spammed in here so they they
really should always be the same size if
we're doing it correctly and so I want
to see what's going on there when we
push a light in here we're passing the
piece dimensions so are they always
cubes yes
they are all right so I take it back
all right so that's all well and good
let's take a look now at how we're going
to fix the part where this doesn't have
any texturing on it so if we go into the
renderer we've got the push cube call
and we're calling that directly what you
can see about the push cube call is it
kind of specifies textures very
explicitly here and we don't really want
it to do that because we would like to
control where those textures are coming
from now we did do a little bit more of
that and I think yeah so this was our
answer right is if you want change what
the layout is you can actually do that
by using a set of tables that allows you
to pick different cube layouts now I
think I think we probably don't want to
have to specify that entire thing each
time so we probably just want to build a
set of those and the other thing about
it is like I said kind of later on is
this is just a big waste of time anyway
we could make it more efficient by
having this be generated in like a mesh
shader of some kind right because we
know that the assets for cubes are
always laid out like this so really we
only need three pieces of information
which tile to pick at the top which tile
to pick for the sides and which time to
pick at the bottom you could argue it
six pieces of information like which
tile for each side and then the top of
the bottom but at most you're talking
about six IDs and each ID is just two
bits right so six IDs of two bits is 12
bits even if you padded it out to 16
bits you're talking about one 16 bit
value per cube is all we actually need
to send down
but at the moment we really don't have a
way of sending down a 16-bit value for a
primitive and having that get expanded
out into different texture coordinates
per vertex right that's the domain of
something like a mesh shader or the
earlier incarnations of that geometry
shaders and again I don't really want to
go down that road but what I might want
to do is I might want to say let's what
if we do use a scheme like that for
encoding it at the higher level pass it
down to the lower level and then even
though we're gonna blow it out here at
least then we would be ready to do a
better path by just directly encoding
the 16 bits later on right so maybe
we'll architect for the good thing now
because it gives us an opportunity to do
something nice there and we'll kind of
go from there so I think what I'll do
here is say ok let's encode in here a
u16 that gives us that layout
flexibility i and we'll make something
that kind of works that way so let's
look at what that would be like we would
be passing a render a texture down that
says kind of what the texture is in
general and then in addition to that one
we would be passing down a u16 that says
like the UV layout right and I mean
maybe we can leave that in the same
place and we can say default cube UV as
an actual thing here as well scuzz we
can say that there is a default cube UV
i and
default cube UV layout like so and we
could just say in fact we could just say
that that's 0 is always the default
right that gets us out of that business
entirely right I and so what that would
be is that would be like an encoding of
where we want each which tile we want in
each case so for example we could say
encode queued UV layout like so and then
in each case here we would say alright
there's gonna be you know a top index
there's going to be side index and this
is probably like it's got a wind around
so we'll probably do something like this
maybe I'll do top bottom and then side I
don't know I feel like maybe that's
better so you see what's on top you say
what's on the side so it's on the bottom
I suppose to be correct and order it
would have to be more like this so it's
bottom side side side side type sorry
east side
and I'm just gonna go around
counterclockwise compass right so
basically the same thing you get if you
did sine cosine right so here we would
just specify which sites we wanted I'm
going all the way around and then we had
the bottom of the top so to encode our
cube UV layout we would just pack these
values into a new 16 so the first thing
I would do is I'd say I want each of
these things to basically be packable
into two bits right and assuming that
they are you know we're okay so you know
let's make sure everything fits
assuming everything fits then let's go
ahead and pack them together so then
we've got a results and the results just
going to be all of these things board
together right we're just gonna smush
all the bits together but we need to
make sure that they don't overlap so we
want to slot each one in every two bits
so the bottom index will just naturally
slot in there at the bottom and I'll
write it this way so it's clear what
we're doing but we're not actually going
to modify it right the next one will we
need to leave the two bits we add for
the bottom of next so it's got to go up
by two right then the next one that's
got to go up by that two plus another
two to leave room from the side index
and so on right so we're just gonna
slide each value up two bits at a time
excuse me
look okay so we basically put two bits
two bits two bits two bits two bits two
bits and that's all packed together it
gives us our result and that in this
particular case this u16 our inputs
allowed to be just regular integers we
want to cast down to make sure that it
comes it goes from a 32-bit to a 16-bit
there right so that encodes a cube UV
layout so then what we need is a way to
decode a cube UV layout and I think
really the only person who needs to do
that is is really the the push cube call
itself so for the moment I think we can
weld that right right in here actually
and so we can go ahead and kind of work
that into the specification so here's
the bottom piece and I guess I should
change us to do and say if we eventually
have mesh shaders in the renderer we can
actually save a ton of bandwidth by just
encoding the 16-bit cube layout directly
and expanding in the shader because
that's really all we need to do so if we
look at this bot stuff here what we can
see is you know we we had a notion of
this stuff before the cube UV layouts
this stuff right so you can see exactly
what it was previously and what I'd like
to do here is just start by assuming
that it actually is the same right so
we'll start by just initializing these
guys like
this so this is what the bottom would
have been before I believe oops
so that's how the bottom gets picked
so mmm you know not us realized too so
if we think about this we actually have
we actually have more bits available
than we're using right if we were to
think of this slightly differently so we
could also say in addition to the
encoding of which tile we're picking we
could encode the orientation of that
tile so for example if we wanted to take
the top and point it in a direction you
know what I mean we could do that now I
don't know that we want to do that but
we could so I don't think there's any
point in encoding the bottom direction
because you can't really see the bottoms
ever they're really just there for
lighting in fact we could probably just
not even have them as far as we know so
really we would only care about the top
and the top could have another two bits
that just said which of the directions
it was facing so I might do that
something like that so basically we
could just say look if the top is or you
know I guess it's more like well like
that um so we're basically saying we'll
spin that top one around because we
might as well do it because we've got
that that extra space so that way we now
are using 14 of the bits and you know I
don't think there's really much else we
could in code you could flip you could
do a 180 rotation on the sides I don't
think the art would work that way so I
can't say that it makes sense to do that
speculatively the bottom I don't think
matters so I think that's pretty much
what we're looking at that's a pretty
flexible set of information there so
let's just leave it at that
so we encode that cube layout now what
we want to do is encode the rest of this
stuff the bottom really doesn't matter
but we're gonna I guess relining to pick
one thing that you know may be a mistake
is maybe what we really should do
instead of packing them this way is move
these up here and just have twice as
many options for top tiles you know what
I mean because I just can't think of
when we're ever gonna use like you know
what's the circumstance where we can
ever see the bottoms of tiles I mean we
we can see them when we do this but our
game you know is always gonna look like
that and there's just no way to ever see
the bottom face of the cube
I mean I'm trying think of the case
where we would care what's on the bottom
but I just I can't can't do it
so I guess in some here's here's gonna
be my fairly poor rationalization so
'hammied hero is a learning project and
so as such the decisions made in it are
not exactly the same as they would be if
it's a game that's just some game I made
or whatever right we could in theory in
the future want to do rate racing like
let's say Nvidia r-tx turns out to work
three or four years down the line and
just turning on rate racing makes a lot
of sense
well maybe we want to have some mirror
tiles that show the reflection of things
that are on the ceiling right if we
didn't specify anything on the ceiling
we couldn't do that so adding
reflections does seem like something
that would be educational at some point
even if someone else did it not me
meaning someone took them a hero
codebase and added that in there so ok
I'm gonna leave them in there there I
don't know that I'm gonna encode the
rotation for them though because I don't
know that we care about that but you
know we'll we'll see maybe I'll do it
just because it's symmetric and we have
two extra bits right like you know we
could we could say that there's a bottom
index and a bottom facing index like so
and it would be free for the most part
to do right if there's the the encoding
then it just means we've got this
instead and hey now we use all our bits
right so that does feel kind of nice
it's nice to have used all the bits you
know time saying so that's good so I
think if we just said well let's go
ahead and and encode it and we'll treat
the top and the bottom the same and
we'll go from there if that seems ok I
don't have a problem with that and off
we go all right so let's take the bottom
and the top and just weld those into
place here temporarily and then we'll do
the sides so oops so I'm gonna grab this
back there I'm gonna grab this up there
let's grab these so and the first thing
that I'm gonna do is I'm going to the
sides because the sides don't actually
have rotation right so the bottom and
the top kind of reluctantly the bottom
but definitely the top need to be
oriented and that's gonna be a little
bit different how we write the code but
as far as this one's concerned all you
really need to do is offset it by like
also it laterally right so this is the
exact set of of coordinates that we will
use in all cases right you just go ahead
and get this stuck in there this is the
exact set of coordinates that we'll use
in all cases except for
act that we will slide them over so the
only change that's happening here is
that it will slide relative you know by
0.25 as we go
wait a minute
that can't be right
oh I I see we encoded them this way I'm
like what that doesn't make any sense it
makes slightly more sense now and really
I don't I probably shouldn't even do
what I'm doing here I only need one of
them so I'm not sure why I'm bothering
with this in fact I'm not going to
bother with this it's just grab them
like this all right so that's what a mid
panel looks like and we just need to
slide it back and forth right so what
I'd like to do here is be able to set
the the mid results and I you know I'm
just gonna try and look at where we've
got these there you can see how we're
pushing the claws on like this right I
feel like those kind of want to be
arrayed so we can just kind of treat
them as an array I'm guessing I don't
really know how we want to do that
exactly
I mean one way we could do it is just
like this right and each of these is
just a copy of that with a different
offset in fact a kid mister like this
because I don't know that I want to
overcomplicate it the ones for rotation
will be a little more complicated so
we'll see maybe I want to overcomplicate
those but each one of these should be
pretty straightforward if we know what
the cube layout is from this parameter
we know that all we have to do to
extract one of the facing sides is shift
down by however much that side is right
then get rid of everything but the
bottom two bits
so we're slide it over get rid of it we
then have a number between zero and
three that says how far over we want it
to be right
so that's decrypted at that point into a
number between zero and three and since
we know exactly how much we move over
each time we can just multiply that out
that gives us the offset that we need
and we can do it the exact same way for
each of these that is if you actually
managed to get the right number of
parenthesis right so we can shift down
mid x0 by four then mid x1 by six and
other than that the rest of it remains
exactly the same and these would follow
suit in exactly the same way right so
really trivial to decrypt those and then
use them as offsets on the x-parameters
to to basically initialize everything
right because the Y parameter is always
the same so we don't really need to fuss
with that at all
that's not necessarily true for the
bottom ones right those might because we
want to have the potential to encode
rotation those are gonna be a little bit
more finicky but for the moment that's
basically what we're talking about okay
um so I think the only thing I don't
know is whether these are encoded in the
order that we want them to be though so
let's make sure we wanted this to be the
eastward facing right so let me rephrase
these this is the one facing down the
positive access this is the one face
down the positive y-axis this is
negative x in this
is negative Y so it's plus X plus y
negative x and negative Y it's what we
want to see right so here's the one
facing down the positive x-axis assuming
that I've got this right that should be
zero and it is the one facing down the
positive will actually be one the
negative should be two and the three
three so those are exactly what we
wanted that we already did obey that
convention and again that's just using
cosine and sine as the rule so that
everything always obeys that same rule
so we can lock this up a little bit and
just say well we also know that our top
X and our bot X are also computed the
exact same way so this computation here
is also identical and what we could do
is get out the top and the bottom
equivalently I believe the bottom was
encoded at 12 and the top 0 right
there's the bottom and there's the top
and yeah so I think that's all we need
to do to make those slide over properly
is is use that as the offset now again
we now have sort of this other issue
which is we need to figure out how to
rotate the top and the bottom
around and if you think about what's
gonna happen there really the only thing
that's gonna do is it's gonna cycle
these parameters so all you would do if
you're rotating one is you're basically
shifting over which one is T 0
which one is T 1 and so on so that T 0
is now T 1 T 1 is now T 2 T 2 is now T 3
right
so I don't really know the best way to
do that but I assume it looks something
like this
so
assume that I capture one of these
setups into an array like so pretty
straightforward yeah
so I basically say early and I've got
four coordinates that make up a tile and
off we go
well then hopefully we all agree that if
I was to take one of these tiles and say
you know that the BOP tile is gonna be
you know a pointer to
well it's gonna be hard to actually
phrase that correctly um let's just say
this so assume that I read these out
like so
right and maybe I do this it's not the
best way to write it but you know what
are you gonna do right so hopefully we
can see that this would give me what I
needed and furthermore I could do the
top the same way I would just have to
offset the the Y as well too to get it
there oh sorry I got a switch this to
the top well cut pasted that right so if
I take the version I used for the top
and use it for the bottom I'm sorry at
the bottom and used for the top all I'm
doing is is looking for higher up in the
bitmap right but that's that's all that
happens here these are the same as these
offset by 0.75 and that the rest of it's
the same right to 525 I think so if we
want to rotate these what we could say
is well if I want to never fetch outside
of this array no matter what I do I can
just end this with 3 right hopefully we
would agree that that makes it so that
it can never get outside of the 4
elements that are there because you
could either be 0 1 2 or 3 and all the
top bits are knocked out so I know I'm
always gonna be those so what that means
is if I then go and decode the facing
direction right like so I'm just going
to take the
UV layout and shift it down by two to
get the up sorry this is the bottom face
this is the top face if I extract those
two values I know now know which of
those facing directions I am right now I
could end it with three here but I don't
actually need to because I'm gonna end
it with three here right so I think
we're pretty good to go there because
the only bits we care about at the
bottom two we don't care about the rest
cuz they're all gonna go away no matter
what happened up there
so I think what I can do is just say all
right bot face +0 bot plate face plus 1
bot place plus 2 dot place bot face plus
3 and I think that just kind of gives me
my answer right it allows me to rotate
around what those movies are and I don't
have to think about it much harder now
the thing I don't like about that is it
does look like a lot of code the
indexing into an array part I don't love
so what I'm curious to know is there
some way to directly decrypt that value
in some other way right because we now
have a value here that we could use so
if we wanted to look at what this was
we've got zero two five two five zero
and zero zero two five two five right
what we're basically saying is that 0
maps to 0 1 maps to 0 2 maps to 0.25
just write this out for you here and 3
maps to 0.25 right I mean that's what we
actually said for the y coordinate
for the x-coordinate we said zero maps
to zero zero 1 maps to 0.25 two maps to
0.25 and three maps to zero so what can
we conclude from this you know well
we'll start by expanding it a little bit
this is the bit pattern right so what
you can see here is actually the
y-coordinate is trivial all we needed to
actually do is just look to see whether
the second bit is one if the second bit
is 1 it's 0.25 if the second bit is 0
its 0 so we don't need an array for the
y-coordinate we're done the x-coordinate
on the other hand is a little bit
trickier right or is it if we were to
take these two bits together what we
could see here is well these two bits
lead to 0 if they're the same and they
lead to 0.25 if they're different XOR
them together right so what we can do is
we can eliminate this sort of semi
expensive stuff but I don't know and
again I'm sort of thinking my header
towards what I want this on a GPU CPUs
are fine the table lookups table lookups
are oftentimes the best way to do things
on CPUs GPUs I don't know you you're
starting to get into finicky territory
there so I don't know that you would
really want to be doing a lot of stuff
like that although in this case a table
is so tiny that probably it's fine here
the bit patterns are so easy it seems
like - well just be done with a direct
bit
it seems like reasonable to me so if we
look at this here we can take what this
bit pattern is gonna actually end up
being and so if we know that the Y is
always whatever the second bit is then
it's really just if we take this this
bot face here what I can do is I can
encode bot face in this case here right
I can shift it down by one so that that
bit is is lined up right and then I can
just end it with one that gives me for
that particular face a 1 or a 0 as to
whether or not we want the well it gives
us whichever one we want right it gives
us a 0 or a 1 which which we can then
just multiply by the actual value we
wanted like so right and so each of
those can be encoded in a pretty simple
routine here right I can basically say
you know cube decode Y and we can say
rotation like that or maybe I want to
say you know face and offset something
like that so it's just face plus offset
and there's the value right supposed to
be you also might want to do this for
like what's the constant or well no we
wouldn't have to because we just put it
in there so I think that's all we really
need we just say cube decode Y and we'd
say that it's the bot face and 0 like so
and then we don't need the tile look up
anymore at all right oops
so now the only question is what do we
want to do here right and so now we need
a cube decode X which is basically the
same exact function it's going to take
bot face in the exact same way I and so
it's gonna do the exact same thing so we
have effectively the same function the
only difference now is that it needs to
be able to do an XOR so instead of
shifting it down being the only
operation that we're doing what we need
to do is take that right which is this
right here this phrase right here and it
needs to XOR with itself
yeah I'm saying so basically we need to
take the face plus the offset XOR it
with the face flips the offset shift it
down by one and then that will tell us
what we actually needed to know right
all right leave that will come in there
all right perfect
so let me also obviously here we got the
wall UV will start UV will end UV so
these are just ones we are going to want
like those were ones we defined up here
and we can now encode those into fact
that'll give us a good test so now all
we need to do is finish that off for the
the bottom cube as well so inside and
then renderer here and we don't need
this anymore we can go ahead and encode
this the top ones the exact same way so
if we grab this and say here's our you
know our top version
it just needs to use the top face and
we're done now you'll note that the
bottom face is probably not really
correct I guess I don't know how we
decided to encode those UVs
so so we probably want to look at that
at some point I don't know when that
point would be because I don't know
who's ever gonna use orientation on the
bottom like I said but you know it's
there the top on the other hand we're
gonna see right away so that one will be
an easy easy one to play with and get
right but there we go so I think that's
actually the encoding for everything and
now it's just correct
I believe so let's take a look here this
is in the renderer test so that's in the
renderer testbed so that's this and what
you can see here is we have wall runs
going right and so in order to preserve
those wall runs we want to do here is we
want to do wall start and end we want to
get those correct right so I believe a
default wall UV is is actually not zero
it's gonna be the one that's in the
middle so I think it's actually if we go
into the render here and look at the end
code so in code cube UV layout this this
one right here so if we want to do
encoding for these right what we want to
do here say all right here's our own
coatings here's our wall UV
we know the bottom we don't care about
the bottom facing we don't care about
the side indices all the slides are
gonna be the same they're gonna be the
one that's two over and then the top
again we don't really care but it has to
be zero for now because I don't think
there are any other tops in there at the
moment so that would be the wall UV the
wall start UV is gonna be the first one
in so that's gonna be this and the wall
muv would be the final one over so that
would be three and now we can actually
use the test bed to debug that code so
that's good I need to delete these and
then I don't want to pass addresses I
just want to pass the actual value all
right and so now this gives us a good
way to debug that so now we can step
through and and and try to get those
correct it looks like we've got our
bottom and top reversed but otherwise I
looks perfect actually
oh and you know why because we didn't
add seven five so that's actually
exactly what we'd expect on the top
you'll remember the y-coordinate so in
cubicle black it's just just two two
five there so you need to offset it by
the fixed offset to put it up to the top
so that may be it let's see
yeah so let's suppose we wanted those
runners to go the other way on one of
these so let's suppose we wanted to
encode facing direction for the top just
to see if it's working since we have a
convenient way to test it here in the
renderer test so let's say that on the
end UV and only the end UV let's try
rotating 90 degrees oops
let's try rotating 90 degrees that will
end the top piece of the wall end so
what we should see is it go like that
yeah and it is right so that's good
and similarly you know I could do a full
rotation along on the wall one so then
we would see to counter facing but still
90 degree rotating versions of that same
bitmap is what we should see going along
the wall run now so that one should be
facing that way and this is facing that
way yeah let's make sure those face
effects are actually correct I don't
really know how to pause this in any
particularly good way but what we can do
is take a look at the block orphanage
here so if it is just used with no
modification the bright side should
point down so what that means is in 92
rotation the bright side points this way
so you know just look at the bright side
right I mean you know what let's do the
dark side instead dark side starts
pointing up that way so with no rotation
which I believe we did on on the wall UV
I'm sorry on the well start UV it should
point up which it does so I think that's
pretty much all we needed to really know
but I'm just going to double check again
so on the wall and UV right what we had
was it should be rotated once which in
this case actually that
rotation looks backwards to me
that rotation looks backwards to me so
going around the incrementing by by
forward by one is not actually what we
want we want to subtract by one there so
there is one other thing I should
probably do now that we're incrementing
these these probably do want to be
ending so that they won't carry right
because we could get a situate well I
mean they can't really carry yeah but if
we want to do subtraction we're gonna
have to okay I think all right so yeah I
think that's all correct but it looks
like we kind of want to go the opposite
direction I guess
let me see if that makes sense to me I
want to make sure I've got this right
get a lit up Milton here
it's time we got left half an hour
so what we said is we said like okay
here are our coordinates it was like
zero zero 0.25 0.25 0.25 and 0.25 right
so it's drawing that set of texture
coordinates hopefully for all I know we
did some weirdness in there when we
actually have cubes but it's in theory
in theory doing that in fact let me just
even check to make sure that that is
what it's doing
it's yeah I mean it's definitely going
around the in the counterclockwise
fashion okay so if this is the order in
which we are doing it and we have a
particular orientation that we're saying
so we're saying this is the starting
orientation when done in that form if we
wanted to rotate this so it was pointing
that way right so if this is 0 this is 1
or let me do it with ABCs if this is a b
c d then rotating it one that way right
if we want to rotate it we would assign
D to here a to here right B to here and
C 2 here so it is true that it is minus
1 though the value you assign is
whatever the value you were going to
assign minus 1 so I didn't do that
properly right what I want to do in here
is actually this
and I think that will still do the right
thing because I believe that the binary
wrapping that goes when you go from zero
to FFF will still produce the correct
bit pattern cuz they'll still produce
two ones in the bottom which is what we
wanted when you wrap so I think that
should still give us the correct result
with only that change okay so with the
rotation just make sure this is correct
so the walls start oh sorry it's
actually not quite that simple i negated
the wrong parameter its face that
actually wants to be negated so it's
really a subtraction is it this way
right offset is always correct it's
really just face that subtracts it away
so that was right I bet I'm like that's
that's not gonna be correct that's gonna
be correct because face is the thing
that's the rotation parameter and the
rotation parameter is the thing that
subtracts so let's try that one more
time so again no change and we should
have the dark point facing upwards it is
a rotation of one and the dark point
should be facing to the left right which
it is and then a rotation of three and
it should face it back the other way and
it is so I think we're good I think
we're good so I'm happy with that
okay so again this is good because now
we can encode that very very easily
right now we can encode what we want to
put on cubes in a very concise manner
that's easy to pack into anywhere
doesn't cost us hardly anything and if
we find that our bandwidth usage is
getting too high it gives us a
convenient way to eventually send that
down imagine all of this and all of that
going away
it would just send down sixteen bits to
the GPU which could then expand it out
using the same logic right so that could
save a ton of bandwidth there I'm sorry
I'm a little sick so I'm losing my voice
slowly but surely I could make it
another 30 minutes so um so yeah that
all seems good
I think that's just a straight-up win so
let's get back then to what we want to
be able to use that for which is to say
that we would like to be able to encode
that so now it would be pretty easiest
easy for us to encode that so if we take
a look at the visible piece structure it
would be pretty free now for us to
encode that as a possible parameter here
for for anyone who puts a cube into the
pipeline they can now specify how they
would want that to be textured we know
that only cubes would need it non cubes
wouldn't need it so we may want to kind
of introduce down here something that's
just going to be extra parameters for
physical pieces that really don't have
to be stored like separately so only
cubes would need a cube UV layout right
and similarly something like a I think
like a light value you know could store
its emission there so basically any
pieces can each of the types of pieces
that might be involved like cube or
light can can store something extra in
here if they need to and other that can
be overlapping because we don't need to
store it for everything so if we look at
that that should pretty much do it
because that completely controls the
that part of the the layout process so
if I was to go and say now let's when we
add a piece let me add a cube piece
let's have them specify the cube UV
layouts in addition so in any that age
there isn't I thought there was wasn't
there an add piece where do we put those
in room gender well I guess that does
make some sense all right
so inside here where we do an ad piece
to an entity and when we're going to put
in one that's a cube which I guess we
don't really differentiate much I do
think we kind of want one of those right
so we kind of want one where we say
here's a cube so I don't know I mean I
will see how we want to do that but when
we do an ad piece we should get back the
piece right or do we not we should
because you may want to make changes to
the to that encoded version so I feel
like ad piece should actually return to
you the piece you know I'm saying like
you should be allowed to to fuss with it
I would think
oops so I'm just going to go ahead and
make these all return that information
to you in case you want to specify
something in there like so and then the
code for specifying the walls can easily
just set those you these as they wish so
let me think so there's one of the thing
that we would possibly need so I don't
know it's hard to say but
akiza's we could also support mirroring
so like instead of allowing the bottom
to rotate we could pack into those bits
to mirroring so a mirror bit for each of
the sides if you want to flip that way I
don't know that we actually need that
for any purpose I can't think of a
particular reason why we would but it's
worth noting so I'll just throw that out
there in case we'll see if we hit it I
guess what I'd say is if we ever hit a
case where we want to be able to flip
things then I would say what we do is we
cannibalized those top two bits and
they'll become the way that we do that
because the bottom doesn't really need
to be spun sorry that's not the top two
bits that's the second two bits in we'll
switch those to be mirror bits I think
that's about it for that so now we move
on to the tagging part which is kind of
the more difficult part there right
because now the room layout code could
just set whatever cube layouts it wants
or anything in there so now the problem
becomes well what are the actual ways
that this entities this visible piece is
going to get picked right and the way
we're doing it currently is we're
basically saying look there's an asset
type and that asset type is gonna tell
you which texture type to look for and
then you're going to match tags the rest
of the way down
so what I will say is I do think there's
something to be said for retaining what
amounts to a two-tier system one where
you select sort of the channel of asset
you're looking for and then the other
where you set where you use information
about the entity to pick an asset from
the set
so I think what we would want to say
right because just thinking it through
it does make sense to basically say this
visual piece is an is an orphanage wall
so don't ever select anything other than
an orphanage wall and here's the part
you know here's the which part of the
orphanage wall it is but then you could
dump like ten different orphanage wall
tile sets in there and they could have
stuff to do with like how wet it is how
damaged it is how burnt it is whatever
all of those things could all just be
fed into the system and if there was
artwork to reflect any of those things
then that is what you would get right so
it does seem like that one is pretty
straightforward and we don't really need
to go particularly far afield to figure
out what the right situation would be
there and so adding something into a
table that basically says this is an
orphanage wall piece
is probably what we want and then
anything that further specializes on
orphanage wall piece you know off off
you go
so I'm trying to think in addition to
that I'm trying to think of ways in
which this will be problematic and
really the only one that comes to mind
at the immediate moment is that the act
of searching through the information
available to find the best match is
itself fairly expensive so if you take
you know the set of entity properties
that are currently you know on that
entity and you want to send them off to
be matched against the asset system you
probably don't want to do that for every
wall tile every frame because as you get
more wall bitmaps let's say the artist
just goes nuts at some point and decides
to draw like 30 different bitmaps for
this particular type of wall tile that
means you're gonna search through a list
matching a vector on 30 things for every
wall every frame right I mean every
visible wall but you know still that
seems unwise so I would suspect that at
the very least that information has to
be cached and only updated when the
entity properties change I would assume
now maybe that's not true
it's hard to say I mean one thing that
is true is it's completely paralyzed
Abul you know all eight cores of a
modern CPU could all be sitting around
doing nothing but matching stuff every
frame so if you really thought you were
gonna get some leverage out of it in
making it more dynamic and responsive in
terms of as the environment changes the
graphics change along with it
then it's not entirely out of the
question that you could do a bunch of
stuff with that however it does seem to
me that you know caching would possibly
want to be on the table and honestly I
don't think that's really a big deal
because we need to cache the lighting
information anyway and we want to cache
the letting information only for things
that are recently visible and so I think
it's been in the back of my head for a
while but what I want to do is have it
so that there's basically an entity
cache that's used that's like an a least
recently used sort of discard scheme
that just stores transient entity info
so basically stuff like lighting and
what the latest matches were for that
entity for bitmaps could just be in
there and that's a scheme that's gonna
go in regardless
[Music]
so it seems safe you know it seems safe
to me now if I go look at the file
format stuff here and I'm just gonna
look really quickly that's sort of how
this stuff was being done so the way
that it is encoded in the file is basic
category is you know just encodes
exactly the thing that I just said which
is stuff like you know what is this
thing oh it's like a basic wall piece or
something like that and so I think we
can just say that that that's gonna be
that's going to be something that we
just defined to have meaning in our
world and we go from there
and so it really does seem like we would
be fine with that and off we would go so
let's take a quick look here was our
original asset type buys ID for v-0
right this is what all this stuff looked
like and so if I just briefly moved that
forwards into file formats here and
really I guess what we want to do is
talk about the category now there's just
going to be some concept of an asset
category right so there would be a thing
that's like something like this and
these are like legacy things right so
this is all legacy stuff here
that maybe if we do a full asset rebuild
at some point we would just get rid of
we could leave asset and none in there
for now right so here's all the legacy
stuff and so I think what I want to say
here is look let's start with some basic
stuff here let's call this like you know
maybe this is like it's like wooden drop
wooden drywall is what it looks like
basically right um so I don't know how
far we want to go down with this but you
know if we want to say that basically
like there's a certain type of
construction it's wooden drywall and we
basically say like here's an interior
wall right I guess this is really just a
wall
if we just hmm
use basic categories like that and rely
on parameters to get us the rest such as
damage
you know dusty miss moss eNOS those
sorts of things
I assume that's good enough so basically
what we would say on here is you know
the basic category is here and we go
from there right and these would remain
in effect but now we can like import
these three things in there right
and then for forest you know we would
have
something like this
I mean possibly it could also be that we
really want the grassiness of something
to sort of be a parameter so we may want
to do something a little bit differently
where we would say something like you
know that's sort of like a field and we
would have a grassiness parameter right
but in terms of the blocks we have like
that would kind of say which one we
wanted and if we imported those assets
in and assigned them that way and had
some tags to describe those then I think
we're basically where we want to be and
so I think that's roughly what we want
let's see here
I think we're just gonna basically
update this enum and there's probably
not a lot more to it than that
and now I like that naming better
because asset type was not a
particularly good way of talking about
assets because the type of an asset
makes it sound like we're saying bitmap
or sound whereas category lets us know
that we're talking about sort of like
you know a genus like you know is it an
animal is it a wall is it a you know
treasure chest type of thing you know
what's the actual category of it
so distinguishing between a type of
asset which may be a physical thing in a
file which may be the asset system
always needs to know about a basic
category is more of a matching
information like oh you can restrict the
matching to this thing you know a priori
kind of a thing right seems a little bit
better let me just
so yeah I think this is reasonable so
we're really not it looks like honestly
we're not gonna really have to change
things much it looks like we more or
less had the right idea at least for
this particular version so really I'm
just going to rename that old version to
a more sensible name then type and think
that maybe all we really need at least
four walls and floors seems like that
should be fine and then we'll try it
with something harder like a monster or
the hero
and we'll kind of go from there
[Music]
and really this is just boring busy work
there's nothing to say pretty much just
exactly what it looks like just kind of
changing the nominator a little bit all
right so now that that's done what we
should be able to do is tomorrow and
I'll stop it there
tomorrow we should be able to go build
import tables for importing things like
those block files so tomorrow we should
be able to basically change this room
into something that has proper walls and
a proper floor and unless we hit a snafu
there that should be what we do tomorrow
and it should be fine we should also be
able to make it so that if you walk out
here into what should nominally be like
the other part of the world we got to
eventually do our final camera code too
once you get out here it should be a
forest right and and then there's oh
right we need downward as well so we can
get dungeons right we've got dungeons in
there right you can go underground and
stuff you can see them so we want to
want to make all that happen - so
tomorrow we should be able to do all
that and that'll get our art importing
seeing if that works roughly the way we
think it should so and we can again just
keep iterating on it so it's good I'm
gonna go ahead and go to the Q&amp;A now
in the render tests the corner blocks
that are on the side of the building
have their diagonal beams reversed due
to sharing their texture with the front
blocks you have a plan for handling that
yeah that's actually so that's just
because the renderer test isn't encoding
that information into its database right
so if you look in here we just have all
of them use the same UV right so all the
sides use the same UV if we instead in
here actually encoded different kinds of
wall starting right then you know we
wouldn't have that happen so you know we
could if you wanted to make the renderer
test app a little bit more fancy in that
sense then if you looked here you could
you could go okay in the test scene
we've got the test scene element and
it's got these sort of parameters as it
grasses a tree is it you know it's a
wall whatever right um you could decide
to make it more explicit here and it
record what encoding you wanted as well
so for example suppose you did that and
then you did this
and now we said hey right that would
give you the ability to encode that
information and then use it later now as
I'm typing that I'm kind of glad you
asked that question because it again we
wanted our renderer to kind of be
something used outside and so what that
suggests is really this you know should
be a thing where we you know do
something a little bit more like that
because we'd rather have people use an
explicit encoding where it's not just a
you 16 because what if later we decide
we really need 32 bits to encode our UV
layouts for cubes well now everyone has
to change their code rather than it just
working so wrapping it in a struct again
because we did decide we wanted the
renderer to be a little bit more of a
first-class citizen something that is
possibly useful outside or being used by
multiple people eventually and so on I
think we want to continue that idea and
and not sort of cheese out when it comes
to making additions to it so you know it
would look something more like this
something like that right so then when
you say encoding uvl you're actually
doing this and when you pass a UV layout
cure what you're actually passing is
something like this so you can sort of
pass something if you want to you can
you can ignore it and it'll just
automatically construct the one that's
nothing but otherwise you can you know
create one here but it's always make
sure you're actually talking about
layout and not accidentally passing some
other thing right and so that seems
pretty good and let me just go ahead and
quickly update the code for vex think
that's a worthwhile change right and so
here where we talk about UV layout all
of these are actually just the encoding
on the UV layout right so that's easy
enough and then everyone else who passes
something in just kind of has to deal
with that now I don't really want to do
the render test just yet I'd rather work
on him maybe he rows one first to make
it well alright I'll do the render test
first
whatevs so here we just need to know
that we're checking the type field
instead of the well you get the idea we
just need to use the type field instead
because we've now said that there's an
actual struct here right so now what
we're saying is well the scene elements
in this case right equals a particular
element type you can see here we're
doing like the wall here and here we're
doing some other part of it you know
blah blah blah right so in this case we
can just do this although we're gonna
wanna do something fancier in a second
here right
and then actually so I guess we can even
do it well I might as well just encode
it here so two retaining the exact same
behavior we're not gonna fix anything
but just encode the exact same behavior
if we were to put the UV stuff here then
when you place a rectangular wall you
know here's the encoding for the basic
wall stuff what we would say is that as
we come through here we're going to want
to set these elements to something in
particular so we need to do this so
we're setting both of these to whichever
one of the element types that we would
have here it's just gonna be wall in
this case because now we don't set that
anymore and then we need to set the UV
layouts right for each of these
right so it's actually this statement
here and we don't need this anymore
because it's not changing so really this
statement here is the thing that's going
to control how these cube UV layouts
actually work right right
but it's even a little bit more
complicated than that because some you
we're gonna have to switch the Y's as
well but for right now we won't do that
right for right now we're just gonna do
the same one as we did before right and
we're not going to do anything else
fancy so we're just doing the basics
here and so for these these are just
element wall so they would be well I
guess I can actually do it exactly the
same way since they're both the same
right so that will set you v's as well
now and these of course are now a real
type right so again not doing anything
different here I just think it's
something that was done at runtime and
actually just recording it now into the
database of the test renderer if you
will um and please random in an occupied
scene test element type and so here I'm
just gonna go ahead and set just the
type there and in here we're just gonna
do that although actually so in this
case we don't need to check for all of
these anymore right we could just check
for if it's a wall cuz that's the only
one we actually needed and then what we
can do is anytime that we're pushing one
of these when we look at like the type
and look at what we're pushing we don't
need to change anything here right
because now this is encoded in the
database itself so what we can actually
do is say the element cube UV layout
just gets passed directly there and now
we don't have that sort of switch
determination okay so here we would just
say default cube UV layout because we
don't care what it is for light and
there's probably one another place where
that needs to happen as well yeah so
here we wanted that although we actually
now know what that is
so we Winx cube we want the cube UV
layout so we can actually just fix that
piece of code to actually do that now
cuz we know we're going to want that
eventually and our energy piece and have
that too
so basically that just cleans up that so
that now everyone is always correctly
talking about QB view layouts right and
so now if we look at the renderer test
right
now what we want to do is actually so
that's kind of interesting wonder why
that did I set that wrong or something I
probably did so anyway so now we that we
have each one of these able to be
encoded directly when we actually go to
lay out the world what we can do is
sorry encode the layouts correctly for
every piece now right oh right because
there must be well oh right so this is
why right we want to be able to set that
wall UV to the wall to not the default
in the case where we're in the middle of
a wall run because that one doesn't get
any of those pieces right all right so
now we're back to the original behavior
but it's all going through the data set
rather than you know anything else so
let's go ahead and fix the problem you
were talking about I believe the problem
timeout is that one right there for
example right and so what we want to do
is set the correct things on each type
of the various cubes so for wise you'll
notice these don't ever get that we do
need them to set I'll show you why in a
second but let's just focus on these for
now
so what we want to do here is maybe
change a little bit the way that we're
doing this so what I want to do here is
say look here's the wall UV and instead
of considering there to be a wall start
and a wall and UV instead what I'd like
to do is actually just talk about the
encoding here directly right so what I'd
like to do is say we're gonna include
into like the wall start or something
right we're gonna encode the entire
thing here and the same thing is going
to happen
here right and the reason I'm doing that
is because they're going to now be
different right they're laid out this
way
okay we're we're instead of always
setting it to the same thing no matter
who you were they're actually going to
be different now and so I want to encode
for every piece an actual unique set of
values so that I can do that more
explicitly now I don't know that we
actually want different rotations here
I'm gonna leave them as one for now
because it was kind of a little bit fun
so maybe we're gonna do that but you
know let's talk about that a little bit
later alright so let's take the min x
case so the min X case has two cases
there's the one at the top and the one
at the bottom on the far sides it's the
left side of a wall the topmost or the
bottom most one so why goes that
direction generally in our system so
that means the min Y is the one that's
closest to us so if we think about what
sides need to be on there will the side
facing that way it doesn't matter and
the side facing that way it actually
doesn't matter so it's only these two
right here that we care about the one
that's that way if we think about what
it needs to be on there that needs to be
the three that needs to be the one
that's gonna like start or run going
this way and the one that's facing us
needs to be a one because it's gonna be
the one that's facing that way and so
that's how we would encode that one
right and so let's look at if that did
the right thing in the renderer test now
so let me run the renderer test and you
can see it's kind of coming up on this
wall here again we didn't change the
encoding of that but here we did change
so that's poisoning the still point of
entry so we didn't screw it up we want
to see this side right here and you can
see now that that's facing the right way
but that one still isn't right because
we haven't touched that one so we now
are our lower left corner wall is now
correct if you will but our lower right
corner wall isn't and that's really the
one we want to work on what the heck
happened there I didn't even know you
could do that
okay well um yeah that seems wrong are
we missing our top Oh looks like we are
how did we that's how sorry I
accidentally deleted that these both
need to be set to wall okay so anyway
let's go back to our lower right so this
is our lower right case and so again if
you think about it two of these don't
matter so the one facing that way is
like interior we can't see it so it
doesn't matter what it is and the one
facing up we can't see either so those
two are just irrelevant and so that's
this one here right and this one here we
don't care about so it's this one and
this one are the actual ones we care
about so this one here is the one facing
out that way that's going to need to
start the run so that's a 1 the other
one is a 3 because it's starting a run
going back the other direction right now
in neither case if we looked at the max
Y run so we only did those those first
ones there excuse me but this side
should now be correct
and it is so you can see it there right
alright so we've done those two corners
now let's talk about the far corners
perhaps which are the ones that are on
max Y so the maximum wine maximum X
right if we again go around the horn so
the one facing this way is an end tile
that's actually correct the one facing
up should be a start tile I believe so I
think this one should actually be a one
these two are interior right yeah so the
min X is the one on this side again the
one facing up so if we were looking at
this way it's actually an end so that's
this I'm sorry that's not facing up
that's facing up so the one facing this
way we don't care about we can't see it
the one facing up is the end the one
facing to the outside is a start and so
it should look like this so I believe
that's everything that we needed to get
there right and so now I think if we
just were to look all of our exterior
walls would be correct I don't think we
would have any any more that are wrong
and that's why I did that cube UV
encoding the way I did it right is I
knew that we had to do this at some
point and so I made it so that you could
explicitly encode which panel you were
picking for every single side right
and so now like we just really shouldn't
see any where it's where it's bogus
hopefully
that looks right
and so now the only question would be
like you know what do we want to do with
interior walls right like what do we
want to do because you'll notice we
haven't set any of the interior wall
pieces to anything at all right like the
interior wall pieces are are basically
just always blank and so if we wanted to
have those interior wall pieces also
have the correct beaming structure to
them we could do it right let's tick
when this piece rotates interview by the
way to make sure we've got all of our
themes correct yeah looking good
so those interiors you can see those are
all white with no beams and maybe you
know you want beams in there and so
let's suppose we've wanted to have the
beams in there what we need to do to
check for that is we need to look at min
X like minus 1 and max X like minus 1
kind of situations right we need to look
at like one inset so here what we would
need to do is repeat this case again
right there's just a lot of special
cases but that's just the way it is so
if we were one out or one in then what
we know is that certain ones now are
going to be visible so let's say we're
one in from the end then we now know
that while most of the time everything
is just a blank wall right
so most of the time we're just gonna set
- oops that's not blank well that's a
blank wall um so on this each one of
these will only have one visible strut
and it's only an only one so the rest of
them should be they should be blank so
if we look at one in from the left
so min X plus one is one in from the
left then we know that the only thing we
want is the the southward face right
should start a run so it should be one
of those
similarly if we're on the oh sorry no
that's backwards that's on the max why
that's the farthest one on the closest
one the one in it's only going to be the
northward face and that northward face
if we switch around is going to end the
run right it's gonna look like that now
if we're on the max shrunk in so we're
on the this end if we're on the earliest
then it's the Northridge face and if you
think about it that's gonna start the
run and so parallel wise if we look at
the farthest went out we're gonna want
the South face and that should end the
run right so that will make it so that
now we have proper interior beaming on
the left and right sides not the tops
and bottoms because that's the other
path so if you look through here what
you can see is now if we get the top
well we're not gonna be able to see the
top are we we need a free look mode here
we've got to get to a place where you
can actually see the tops of one of
these hopefully we'll pan to one in a
second here but now we should have it so
that that that there's a strut there
okay and the fact there isn't a strut
there would suggest that I'm totally
wrong about that not great
I'm gonna need if we keep down this path
I'm gonna need a way to do that a little
bit better so on the max why that's
right we're facing northward facing left
we're facing down facing that should
have done it
aha
sorry about that missing an else clause
there although I don't think that would
have done it it would cause this to
clear in some cases but not the one that
I cared about I don't think
Oh God alright so maybe that was the
problem we didn't even get a thing
compiled did we right there we go um
let's take a look one more time that
missing else should have created more
bugs I was wondering why it didn't and
the fact I guess we just didn't compile
would have been why I wasn't paying very
close attention there yeah okay so now
there are the beams I can actually see
them in the from the right there so I
think both beams are correct on that
part of the interior now and so now we
just need one more which is the vertical
beams right so that that looks right so
now we just need one more which is the
vertical beams also I really don't know
what we want to do about the roof
thatching like the the tops I'll leave
those as zeroes for now cuz I don't know
what else we would do there necessarily
but yeah they is what they is so all I'm
gonna do here is just special case
this one part here and so all we need to
do is the same thing we were I don't
know why Fargo to do that so all we need
to do is I special case the Y's and do
them in the exact same way as I did the
X's so assume that they're just a normal
wall like they were before and then all
I'm going to do is say well okay so for
the case for the case where the Y is one
in from the min right which would be the
first in there or one back from the max
I'm doing a run of X's here
right from min to max so if
vx
wait wait a second
what did I do here I'm I'm a little bit
confused so I do a loop on the X's and I
place the X's
oh okay sir I guess I've been
programming a little too long today
I forgot my cut and pasted this code
from the thing about I'm like what am i
doing that shouldn't work of course it
shouldn't I just cut and pasted it and I
have to update it this is the code I
should have been looking at and it works
just fine it uses min and Max I'm like
it should be Y with min and Max X well
parenthesis it was if you actually
looked at the actual code never mind
that
all right so what we actually want to do
here is this we want to make sure that
this stuff is presented correctly so in
here we've got the min X and the Max X
the min X and the max X and so we just
want to do the exact same thing here
that we were doing before where we just
say look let's make sure that we put the
right beam on the right side so in this
case we've got the minimum Y which is
close to us one up so we're talking
about the two like bottom left bottom
right interior pieces right the min x is
the one on the left so that one is going
to have its first one right here be a
start
beam right and then we've got also on
the other side so the bottom right on
the interior right don't care about
anything up till the the one that's
inside facing so the one that's facing
into the interior the building that's
gonna be the end of a run right and so
then here we also have the exact same
thing happening where maximum Y is the
top right one in so the interiors there
so the minimum X is this one that's that
first one that's that's facing in that's
gonna be the end of a run there and then
similar we're gonna have the exact same
thing I'm in here the other one that's
gonna be an end of a run on the other
side I'm sorry beginning of a run on the
other side so I think that should be the
complete set I believe
[Music]
also have to make sure you close your
brackets or braces I should say if you
actually want your code to compile and I
think that should be it
and by the way that's code we can we
needed to do that because we actually
need to do that exact same code in the
actual game as well so it's not wasted
work we'll just duplicate that logic
when it comes time to do that inside
handmade hero because we want to be able
to do those interior runs properly as
well that make sense
looks like that one on the interior was
wrong looks like I had those backwards
on the why the oh you know why because
you can't have something that's only one
long because you can't put both struts
in so I don't so it's not wrong it's
right it's just that one was too close
together but you can see it now right
it's all kind of built together when we
use the new for a coder update um as
soon as the picker thing is working it's
too slow right now but it's when it is
fast I will be updating all right I
think that's it for today we've done
quite a bit
but that all looks right you know like
the beams look good there right
alright I'm gonna close it down
all right thank you for for joining me
for their episode of handmade hero sort
of pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along series
you can always peer to the game on
handmade hero org and it comes with a
source code so you can follow along at
home we will be back tomorrow when I'm
going to start putting that same stuff
that we were doing in the render test
we'll just put that into the game proper
which I think will be really nice
because then we can start to define
areas of the game better and start to
kind of bring them more into like a to
give a little more of feeling of
exploration and sort of feeling of the
actual gamey environment which is always
kind of nice so that'll be fun see you
back here same time same place until
then have fun programming and I'll see
everyone the Internet take it easy
everybody