hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete game
live on stream this is going to be yeah
I mean we're kind of the point where
there's just tons of things to do is
talking about this in the pre stream we
don't really know exactly what we're
doing today because we got tons of stuff
we could do on the game now pretty much
everything is available we've got some
bugs we can look at we've got a bunch of
features we can start adding now there's
just there's tons of things we can do
and so one of the things that I think
maybe I'll start with because it's it's
sort of what we had been working on a
little bit beforehand is like getting
the camera back into a place where all
of the features that I want her in there
in fact I shouldn't say getting it back
to a place I should say getting it to a
place because we never really had all
the features I wanted possessed a render
test made here um
and so yeah you know if you take a look
at what we did with the camera you know
you you can hop around now and we
totally fixed all of the problems with
the camera interpolation being incorrect
from frame to frame we had we had just
written it poorly the first time I think
we didn't really think it through right
or something I don't know what happened
it was very simple when I went back and
looked out I was like oh we just have
some very simple stuff to do um and so I
would like now to go in and because the
camera is working nicely in this you
know for the interpolation I would like
to maybe say like let's continue going
on with the camera and let's try to get
the camera to a place where it's like
you know it maybe isn't shippable
because we don't know exactly what we
need in its entirety for shipping but an
arguably shippable camera meaning it
doesn't have obvious problems so for
example let's get scrolling in there
like I shouldn't be able to do that
right this was a room that was opposed
to scroll so and we never added
scrolling the camera so let's get
scrolling working let's also make it so
that for example we've got our specials
working nicely and our room highly
working like so so for example let's say
I go up and hop on this square
maybe it's oom Zin when I'm talking
you know if this is a talk to this
person square for example let's make it
so we can do a zoom in on that so stuff
like that that's what I'm looking for
and then finally and very importantly as
we go to start working on our like
polishing up how the art is rendered and
so on like fixed like we're gonna want
to work on our Z bias stuff and our
sprite layering and all that kind of
stuff as we're polishing that up we need
that debug camera to be back and right
now the debug camera is not there right
we don't have a debug camera setup right
now and so we need some way of doing
that and like as far as the debug camera
is concerned I probably I don't know if
I really like the way that it works
right now like it's a little weird but
I've had it for this whole time on like
you right click the button and it went
into debug camera mode and it was weird
it like stored a separate thing so I
think we've also want to in addition to
implementing sort of like a good debug
camera where we can move all around and
focus on whatever we want I think we
also want some kind of like you know a
feature that that some kind of a good
idea of how we get in and out of it you
know
and and what it's supposed to do so you
know we'll kind of like talk about that
a little bit and figure out what we
actually want there and and how we want
that to work um so let's try to figure
out like scrolling for example for
scrolling I think what we want to do is
maybe think about just setting the
location of the camera based on the
position of the entity that that it is
following and so you know in if we look
at where the camera is like update
camera for MV movement in this code here
I'll move it over here so it's not
behind ahead one of things you can see
is in here we talked about the room that
we found that we're inside and you can
kind of see that happening here and if
we
look at that room function what we kind
of see here is that the we set the
target PE of the camera based on where
the room center is and I think what we
want to do here is specify some idea
about what the maximum size of a room is
that we want to focus on and then if the
room is any bigger than that size then
we actually take the center of a sub
room size that can slide around inside
the larger room right so we're just
saying look we know that rooms are any
size we want like we want the game to be
able to generate any size room where
room in this case can be any thing
really and so we want there to be a
notion of like free-roaming or not and
so there's you know now and now that I
think about it too you know another way
to look at it would be the room itself
could also tell us that so if we wanted
to set it into sort of a free scrolling
mode maybe that just is the way it is
and and let's let's look at what would
happen if we did that because I don't
really know if I like that or not and so
it might be interesting to kind of see
what would happen there so for example
if we look in here you know we've got
this
this entity coming coming in you know
what I mean and that's like here's the
person you're following and so in here
we kind of pull out and say oh well you
know we've got the simulation center and
so on you know blah blah blah if we were
gonna follow an entity directly what
would we do and if we look here you know
the target P for example we've got this
target offset Z and the camera Z right
the target offset Z could remain set for
the room but what we could do is say you
know in the case where we're scrolling
right if we were scrolling and you know
special camera maybe is maybe even
special camera could could be
oh you know what it looks like we
already do this cam review player there
you go so it looks like when we create
this room you know we can set up a
special camera that's you know
intentionally set up to handle this if
we just set that we would scroll so
let's see what that looks like
so if we set view player up inside the
gen room code here's our room creation
and when we set this up we've got the
ability to set these flags right so you
can see here you know we've got camera
behavior as a thing that we can set and
so if we want to we could say like cam
room camera behavior equals something
and so when we actually specify this
stuff it seems like we would want to say
well when we say get camera offset Z for
dim you know we might want to say like
that this function here can look and see
if the thing is bigger you know if it's
if the the X count gets up above a
certain amount which is whatever we can
thought you know actually find maybe we
set some flags here to say what that
should be you know what it should do you
know something like this and so we could
just say all right you know set the
camera behavior here in that case and so
when you go generating a room of this
size we would just say like oh you know
or in that's that special behavior you
know the the like view player
and so in either of those two you know
we just say look follow the player along
I think we actually want a view player X
and a view player Y a separate so I
don't really think we want to do it
exactly that way but let's just see what
that does at first make sure that code
is actually like working at all and so
if I hop out here and I leave yeah so
you can see now like I'm able to kind of
like I can I can smoothly hop around and
it will follow me it's a little bit bad
because it's actually like following the
hop and so we probably don't you know we
don't really want exactly what this is
doing which is following with no
hysteresis like so we want probably we
want a way to make this a little more
stable
I'm guessing than it is right because
that that nonlinear movement is not
gonna be fabulous
you know it's just a little nauseating
in my opinion so we'd like it more
stable than that but that's basically
the right thing and we probably want
here also to say well like I said we
want x and y so like a hallway can be
tracked along Y and and not X or vice
versa so you know I think we probably
want something like this where we're
just saying like take specific elements
and use those don't you know don't
scroll or not scroll scroll or not
scroll based on a particular like a
specific axis that you're looking for so
here's the cam that camera behavior so
if I do a view player X and if you
player Y instead I'm just gonna change
these flags here that seems like better
right
so there we go
we're already set up inside room Jenna
deal with that because you can see we
were already checking the X count and
the Y count anyway so it seems like
that's what we want we may also want it
to be tracked earlier than that like the
13 might be already something where we
want to scroll it not entirely sure but
let's say we come out here right you
know this this kind of wants to scroll
how big is that room 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9
10 11 12 13 so that's actually Wow okay
so I guess I guess these are just kind
of not really quite as far out as they
probably should have been I don't really
know what I want to do here
I'm not sure what we want that ramp to
be I also don't know why we did this
this way but I guess it's because
there's sort of different levels of zoom
it's gonna play around this a little bit
and see we also already had a multiplier
in there
[Music]
I do think maybe we want to be able to
be further out than that so I'm actually
fine with that I'm going to continue
boosting these numbers a little here we
probably want to tune each of these I'm
guessing eventually to be pretty
specific
that seems better
and the thing I like about this is this
would allow us to create large open
areas where the player can freely move
around and that aren't room based and so
we would have the freedom to do both
things right we can have room because I
want room based encounters
we're like the doors lock you know in
standard fashion and so it's kind of
nice like this this feels really good
actually
when you come out to the hallway you
know you're moving kind of through here
and then when you come into rooms that
are shorter it locks in on it and that
feels like really good and here it feels
good to to be locked in the center but
you know but you don't actually have a
locked vertical so it can scroll here
and I mean so that actually feels pretty
good too so the only thing I would say
is that it seems like I don't know I
don't know how many across we really
want to have one two three four five six
seven eight nine ten eleven so you know
it might be something where the X
distance is a little less than I was
saying you know maybe maybe it's more
like this
this dude is super in our way right here
I'm gonna say that the main hall can't
have a person in it until we fix that so
if you look at what we were doing there
inside create orphanage right we place
we allowed things to be placed in
various rooms and we said that the main
room could have an orphan placed in it
and then it went ahead and placed an
orphan in the doorway because we don't
really have any intelligent placement
code it just starts looking for empty
squares and puts things in there and so
that you know blocked our entrance right
so now like the main room there yeah you
can tell that works really nicely to see
its roles and why right I'm just like it
should and you know we could hop in here
and then it kind of zooms in on that
area and then you know we're outside now
and I can walk around through there and
you can see one really interesting thing
like I sang one of the things I really
like about this is as I'm hopping around
here my like my I'm actually crossing a
room boundary there so this is actually
two rooms but you know they're they're
seamless as far as the as it would
appear because when we set the scrolling
to be arbitrary like that you can just
hop around a non room based world so
even though you know we can create
things still thinking in terms of rooms
because that's how we like to do it in
the code for like placing different
elements and welding together and all
that we don't actually have to do that
and as far as like we don't have to
actually do that as far as like outdoor
regions up here to the player they can
feel like their large open expanses if
we want right now what we want to do in
terms of
rendering stuff that's below us is still
pretty tricky right if we look at how
much stuff is on the screen right now
it's quite a bit and you know in the
future there wouldn't probably be a lot
of that I mean maybe if there was a
cliff or something but generally
speaking you know you only kind of
really see like if there's a hole down
to the the next level or something there
but yeah like if we look and just say
what's what's our what's our damage here
you know like how bad is the situation
what you can kind of see is that like
you know like let's look at our our
thread view right you can see that that
it's all just the lighting so really if
we just and maybe we need to back off on
our lighting complexity too and just do
simpler stuff you know who knows but if
you look at what's going on there if we
just weren't lighting we wouldn't really
have a problem still even with stuff
like this where there's tons of things
in here and so you know as entity sim
gets added to the mix we're gonna have
to do some better work to make sure that
stays opto but that's not that hard
that's gonna be pretty easy I think so
my opinion there is that like we just
have to address the lighting and make
the lighting do the right thing there
you know what I mean and and I think
that's most of what we gotta do we
certainly can can shoot less Ray's right
like you know we can always make the
lighting crappier for the moment or
something but you know we really need to
just come up with a better solution to
the lighting long term and I'm not sure
what that is and it may require moving
it to a GPU based solution as well you
know I really couldn't tell you
so here's where we're doing our ray
count and we're sending 16 of those I'm
wondering like what happens if we just
use super crappy lighting for now just
to avoid having any problems with with
speed based on lighting it would look
horrible right it's super flickery but
then we don't really have any issues
with with the frame timing anymore and
we can make that larger it looks like a
disco doesn't it kind of
it's like disco time discotheque pun
intended um so yeah I mean we just
really need to get better lighting
solutions in there and I don't know
exactly what that you know will entail
but something better than we've got
because again like we're not even
simulating the lighting all the way like
you can see we're kind of getting that
like we would have to simulate the
lighting all out through there if we
wanted to draw this and it's just just
wait we just don't have the capability
of doing that you know and so that's
really you know that's that's really our
issue and I don't know when we're gonna
address that or how excuse me
so let's figure this out here let's do a
couple a couple things let's go in and
make our room Jen also allow us to
access everywhere in the game at the
moment like right now for example we
don't have like there are transition
points that we don't properly handle
that like we don't handle boundaries
going downward you know what I mean so
the connection system here it just all
it does is say we don't you know we're
we're going to not put a wall if there
was supposed to be a boundary connection
there but we don't actually have a way
of doing if we were supposed to go down
and so in the set in the case where a
connection goes down I would like to put
in a stairwell so like when we did that
and granted this code is you know I
haven't worked on it much so it's kind
of janky but when we actually place the
room along the edges we do you know we
do have
the up-and-down concept in there so you
know we do have a way of saying that
that should happen and it is being
picked and then when we create one of
those Delta's like when we create the
the connection we check to see if it's I
guess we check to see whether yeah we're
really not do anything particularly
interesting here we just check to see
where we're gonna connect and then we
connect for Zee
here it is we say intersect these two
volumes then take the halfway point
between them right so it would have been
placed in the middle of the room if
there was a downward thing and so I
don't know exactly how I want that to
work but I guess like I mean I guess I
want a hole there so in here I'm
thinking we kind of want this to be
expanded for when we do a connection we
would like it to be expanded by by one
all the way rounds I want to do and we
have this in there before so when we
create this entity and we take the
visible piece we've got this color
setting right and we set them all to
something arbitrary here but I'm going
to turn that off so that we can see like
essentially a color coding of what
everything in the world is walls and
floors and connections and so on and so
I think that if I do that and I come out
to the outside here we should be able to
see when we get to the place where these
are connected we should be able to see
the connection and we can right so
here's that room and and you know
there's a connection I believe and
there's the connection between these two
rooms so I think that that's like the
down you know the the passageway that
goes down and
there's a few things about stairwells
that make them a little bit tricky well
there's a few things about this in
general that make it tricky so I don't
really know what we want to have for
stairwells in general I suspect we want
stairwells to be like any other door you
can just you go up or down in them and
it's fine I don't know if we want the
concept of falling through something but
either way if we want to have to like an
up and down connection that's on the
same room we would have to be careful so
that the stairwells don't like overlap
each other in some kind of bad way or
things like that
[Music]
but I don't know I mean so anyway if we
were gonna put in a stairwell it needs
to be a little bit more thoughtfully
arranged and maybe you know I guess what
I'm saying is when I actually go to
place one of these stairwells I think
maybe what I would want to do is hollow
out the stuff around it so when we
actually create one of the downward
connections like I might want to say
something like if this is an up or a
down connection meaning you know like if
it's a box index up for a box index down
kind of a thing I might want to have
essentially a way to do like a Minkowski
sum on here essentially to expand it out
just to grow it a little bit so it's
like a little bit bigger and occupies
more area so for example like maybe I
would say something like you know add
radius here and in most cases you don't
have any add radius so the connection
most the time doesn't do anything but in
the case of an add radius here we would
do you know that so up and down
connections would grow by a certain
amount so after you create what the door
would be we would say add radius to and
we would say you know that now I don't
know that we haven't had radius true for
these but I think these are actually
these are rectangle threes that don't
have
they need to implement sort of non
floating-point versions of what we were
doing with rectangles before so I think
in terms of the world Jen you know
there's there's a I think there's a
rectangle type that we use in here I
don't remember what it is though
where's door Jen volume I don't know
where Jen volume is so Jen volume is in
Jen math and you can see that it's got
some basics here but doesn't have the
ability to add right so if I just have a
gen William add radius to and I've got I
guess I would need to actually pass this
in as an sort of a gem like it's a it's
a gem v3 right it's the radius and so in
here it's right it's pretty simple
here's the results it just equals
whatever this is I guess we're doing
this like this so when we pass this in
we would just say okay the result in
this case is going to get expanded in
exactly this way so the min0 equals the
radius zero
and then the max has the same thing so
it just puffs it by that much all right
so to create one of those Jen VIII's I
don't remember what we've got for that
looks like we would want something like
this so here I can say that and this is
really just a you know a simple utility
function to make sure those can be
bundled together so I think that's all
we would really need there and so in
here we would say that add radius
function is a gen b3 and in here we
would just say okay except that way um
so that's all I'm really talking about
there I don't think we need to do
anything else to it other than that and
I'm gonna go ahead and run the code now
and make sure that that created a larger
door for me
oops why did I accidentally set the
all right so going up here now again I
should be able to verify that the I
should be able to verify that the
location here is it's now large see see
how it's like a square now you know I
mean and so I want that to be I would
like that Square to be the downward
motion now you know one thing is it's
not centered it looks like it added it
for some reason it looks like it it's
shifted backwards a bit I don't know if
that's that maybe because of where it
shows to align them in terms of where
the underlying level is so I guess I
don't really know that that's wrong but
when we play with the generator more
seriously later we'll have to make sure
that's actually something that happened
correct like I'm not sure if it actually
is or not so what I would like to do now
is just have some way inside the rim
generator of detecting whether you're on
a stairwell or not and so you know I
need some way of of having of looking at
one of these connections and knowing
that it is or isn't a downward
connection so the derp mask
I assume the derp mask though so looking
at this it's the dermis is just gonna
tell us which ways it could have
connected but it's not gonna tell us
necessarily which way it did connect I
don't think I don't know if we update
that to actually say which direction it
goes
so when we finalize a connection yeah do
we set that
hmm not really you can see us doing the
room connection here you can see us
saying get the other room it's basically
saying if the room if the other room was
placed then we can place us and if you
could go the direction then it looks
like you kind of do and so then we do
this place room it seems like at that
point we want to like lock the
connection down to the direction it
actually went you know so we can say
look this is the way this direction went
and I guess I don't know
hmm
I guess I don't really know what I want
to do there but it seems like in here so
so here's what I guess I would say
inside world Jen
we've got Jen room connection and it
seems like that's probably where I want
to put that so essentially what I want
to say is we've got the directions in
that box thing so we've got like the
west east north south up and down you
know and so it seems like I want to say
which direction is this going
so in general neck ssin we would say
like placed direction or something and
when we actually put something down we
would shove into the room connection the
direction it actually went right so we
would say something like okay you know
[Music]
when we do could go direction and we
pass it you know this nonsense here and
we do the like get der masse from room
and the result equals der bassant s mass
so there's like the test mass there and
we get the surface mass from the DIMM in
the side that gets passed in here right
we want to then write this back in so
this here is the direction mask I guess
I really just want just the direction
though I don't really want this you know
what I mean so what I really want to
know is what's the what's the surface
index so I want this right so I think
what I want to do is say look look if we
placed this room we know that we placed
it along a particular connection a
particular room connection and so we
want to actually go back and rewrite
that room connection so you get this
room con here right is the thing we're
looking at so we want to actually take
room con and when we place the room we
want to set room cons waist direction we
want that to be equal to the surface
index value in question right so like
dim inside and that should be one of
those box index things you know I mean
it's one of these
uh why it doesn't return one of those
I'm not sure seems a bit weird but the
only thing that doesn't really work here
is that the opposite side of our room so
the the room that we branched off from
we don't actually know who we'd never
looked at the room connection on that
room and we didn't do the opposite one
of these so we really need to do like
other room con once we've placed it like
it's the other way round
and it's not- side because I think side
is just zero and one so it's it's really
not side here so it's like it's like we
whatever the other thing of side is the
side is either zero or it's one so it's
you know it's that I don't know if we've
got a function to do that already we
probably should so there should probably
be a function in here that's like
it's interesting that surface index is
an S 32 but mask is at U 32 not sure why
that would be but anyway this is that
you know what I mean
so the problem now that we have is just
how do we you know how do we talk about
that other room how do we get the other
room connection and so you know if we
look at what we've got here there's a
bunch of stuff going on here's how we
add those in right and and here's how we
connect them right we create all these
and so what we don't really have
anywhere here is something you can you
can see us even here we will look at
like the connection and get the other
room what we don't have is something
that spins over the connections to find
the one that goes to a particular room
right you can see we don't really have
anything in here that that wants to do
that so we never you know we never get
there we never get to that type of stage
but it's pretty easy right so if we go
to get other room here and we just have
something that's like get room
connection
and we say all right you know from this
room to this other room get me the
connection that was linking them
together that's a pretty easy thing to
do because either there is or there
isn't one we just have to loop over and
see whether there is so we would just
say okay here's the test connection we
would do from room first room connection
test testicles test next and then in
here we would say well you know if this
test and you know we've got inside the
definition here for each one of these
room where is it room connections right
we've got the Jen connection and then
the next value there so for each one of
these things we would just say if the
test connections has the two room in it
then we're good then we're good to go
right so we can just do it this way
and that's really it so that allows us
to get from a room to the connection
like which connection would would have
linked it to some other room that we
know it's connected to so when we're
inside world gen and replacing rooms now
when we do that room placement here we
can get the other room connection pretty
easily because now we know once we
placed it we can say here's the room
that we placed we know we want to be
going to this other room right and it's
it's specified already because we've
we've done this this work here where
we've we've picked that what that other
room actually is already so I should be
able to just say other room and once
I've got that we're done now that's
actually constant throughout the routine
so assuming that we want to actually
make that happen we should be able to do
do this you and I mean and I think
that's it so at that point we can now
set these so that each person knows what
direction they're going and they can
look at their side of the link to see
which direction the exit is for them I
don't remember whether the which way
these go but I think we're talking about
the opposite way so I think I've got the
sides reversed there potentially it's
ready to stretch there we go
so in here for example when we say could
I go this direction here's the
connection here's the other room and
here's the side so that's the the
direction I would be going from this
room I assume so I think if I'm not
mistaken that that means that this and
this are like backwards right like side
is actually talking about which way we
would go from the other room not us so I
think
this is the way that they're getting
used side is how we would be coming from
the other room to us not how we would go
from us to the other room but I don't
know we'll double-check that because
there's a lot of information flowing in
here and it'd be easy for me to get that
wrong I guess I could look at this and
see it says that the connections door at
which is the max value the max value is
going to be the minimum of our room if
it is positive and it's going to be the
minimum of the other room if it's the
negative direction is that right so if
we were going this way right if we were
going towards if we were going to the
left then we're saying that we would use
our there minimum as the maximum value
of the door and if we were going to the
right then we would use our minimum as
the maximum value so yes the the side
appears to be saying if I was going from
the other room it's that direction
that's what it seems to be saying inside
box I so I want to know why this gets
surface index
why isn't get surface index returning a
box surface index I want to know like
what would be the problem if I did that
can someone tell me because I don't see
why I don't know why it was that way
so I think it should be that way because
that that is a known indexable value and
if you wanted to stick it into you 32
you could just go right ahead but we
know it's coming out as one of those and
we've asserted it as well so we kind of
know what we're guaranteeing to the
external code so I feel like calling it
a box surface index makes perfect sense
all right so now inside rim Jen we have
a lot more information we should in here
be able to say like you know this is a
stairwell and in here I could say like
stairwell equals room con placed
Direction equals box up or down and now
we would know if there's a stairwell I
just don't want to place anything
probably at the moment so if it's not a
stairwell so I'm gonna like if this
whole block out
uh we would we would do well to have a
way of remembering our last position and
just starting there you know what I mean
because it's gonna get really tiresome
if we want to debug things in the
generator to like have to hop all the
way out every time you're in I mean like
I have to do that whole hop and like it
didn't work right and so now I gotta hop
out here every time so I feel like that
would be a nice feature to have as well
like I feel like we would want something
like this thing right here so if we
imagined having a magical camera editor
which I think we can all imagine and I
wanted to just have like you know
this something like this you know what I
mean
you know I don't know what that should
look like exactly but you know but
something like that it would be cool and
so let's just put some stuff in there as
a reminder that we want this and then
maybe I'll do it seems plausible right
so maybe in here we have like devmode
what did I call it maybe something like
that and so maybe that's the f2 key
actually and editing assets is maybe the
f4 key or something I don't know trying
to think of what else we want there yeah
I don't know anyway so if we imagine we
had some magical camera editor thing
there then that would be cool and we
could bind that to an F key so it's easy
to get to it's like a quick access
situation and so you know something like
this
that's weird
I wonder why it's having trouble getting
a asset ID all right maybe not so for
some reason dev mode camera didn't show
me anything why not we should come down
here to camera editor oh right we've got
sort of a you know is it an editor
function thing that happens here will be
nice to just bracket that and I suppose
I could I suppose I could do something
like this if I wanted to it's not the
prettiest thing in the world but it
would work and then we just say this
um so yeah and I guess in some sense to
this stuff can kind of be moved a little
bit into because we don't really have
undo and redo for the camera per se
although maybe we will want to that's
kind of a little bit a little bit
weirder but in terms of the asset editor
as far as yeah like you just look at
some of the stuff and I'm like gosh what
sort of stuff should this be so I'm kind
of thinking maybe what I did there was
kind of dumb
maybe we actually don't want that at the
moment anyway you know maybe we do want
to do that just for editing assets and
then the camera is actually we wouldn't
do that here you know it would be here
or something along those lines I mean
you can't quite do that because yeah
gosh I really I really don't know what
the right way to do that is
I guess I'll keep it the way it was I
guess I'll keep it the way it was
because I could imagine putting in undo
for the camera you know there we go all
right so if we do it like this
all I really want to do here say well
the HHA stuff probably needs to go down
into the asset editor though right
because that stuff is not applicable in
this case
so that would want to go in here I think
like so
and some of these things that are that
we're actually down here probably want
to get moved up because they're kind of
more general Yakubu generally applicable
and then yep so I don't know exactly
what we want to do there
see how that goes so now we should be
able to have like a camera UI there
which I really don't know what we
exactly we're going to do with but we're
gonna do something with it probably so
that's the camera that's the editor that
hij editing right and you know we may
want to kind of break that out too so
that like the HHA stuff has has two
things like I don't know we got a lot
work we could do on the editor to make
that better but I'm just saying I want
to remind myself that I want some of
this here so we can save and load our
start up locations easily so that we
don't have to hop all the way out there
every time because that's gonna get old
real quick so that needs to happen when
we do the camera stuff so inside here I
want to know why I didn't get a
stairwell like I want to know why this
didn't happen and because we sort of
know we know that this must have been
happening because we were getting that
color change right so we had to we had
to have been on a connection or we
wouldn't have been getting the color
change that we were seeing here and so
the fact that we're not that it's not
selecting this we must be getting this
hit properly but for some reason the
stairwell term is never evaluating right
but we should be evaluating it and I
don't know why we're not when we go look
at the world gem here and we see what we
were setting it to so when we do our get
box service index we use dimension here
and it's it's the direction we're going
right for that it is the direction the
connection is going so it should
evaluate to box index upper box index
down I would argue it doesn't appear to
be or something else is happening but
because there's an
enough stuff going on in that code I'm
not gonna try and guess what's wrong I'm
just gonna step into it and see if
there's something I can see in there
that that lets me know what we did wrong
so inside world Jen what I'm going to
look for is when we go to lay out that
room there is a clear-cut case when we
do this so I'm just going to say let's
look at the downward directional one and
the upward directional one we know that
those should both produce a result that
has box index up or or down set and
we're not getting either of those
working properly so let's see why so
when we set one of those and we come
through here we should be able to place
the room in theory right it looks like
here we did yeah so we place the room
along the edge here oh wait so we have
two ways that we place the room
whoa
so we have a place room and a place room
along edge and I guess place room along
edge hold on a second
well that explains it we have a place
room in volume which just puts a rim
somewhere we have a place room along
edge but it looks like we actually don't
ever call a place room so that's why
this was just in the wrong code right it
needed to be in place room along edge so
here's our place room along edge code
because remember we were playing with
different ways of placing rooms so we
only actually ever use this one so when
we do add radius to here's where we
would actually need to do the work of
place in one of these things when we get
here we know a couple things so we know
the connection and we do know
so we do know the direction we're going
so it seems like everything's fine
so in here it does seem like if we got
the two connections we would be okay so
the rooms place direction and the room
other rooms place direction right
they're going to be these we need to
know which direction we were going
and looking at the relative x-axis here
and that's tough it looks like that
would tell us what the direction we were
talking about was going to be all right
so rels e axis is the axis of travel you
can see that here because we do max door
and min door right these are not
directions of travel they are just you
know the where along the edge you are so
it looks like we should be able to say
like rel z axis is the axis in question
here and then the sidedness of its form
in door and max door I'm not sure it
doesn't look like we know that like all
we do here is we just intersect the two
volumes to find out
[Music]
where they should go
to be completely honest with you since
room volumes don't overlap
why does intersect get called there that
doesn't make any sense
shouldn't that produce nothing like
shouldn't the intersection be for the
min and Max of the door should be
nothing right
that doesn't make any sense so if I have
two rooms and I intersect them and then
I get yeah and then I get eight actual
volume back for the door I have no idea
why that would happen the intersection
along yeah that's that's just puzzling
so I would like to see what's going on
there
I got I got no no idea how we wrote that
so what happens in intersect
it does exactly what you would expect
and presumably these rooms are
non-overlapping so when you get that
back you should get nothing so when you
set the dorm in and door max ah it flips
it perfect wow we were clever I'm like
why did we do that that makes perfect
sense I thought I looked for that I was
like maybe they flip it and then I
thought they didn't but they do okay so
that's all good so the fact that we flip
it there again means that so we don't
really know what direction we're going
is the problem so we must have that
information up here so in the surface
index where we're doing this like you
know r LZ axis min is the thing that
tells us which direction we're going it
looks like and I think we don't get any
other information so in the case where
we're going from the base room and we're
going from the base room to us right
then if we're going west then that would
be negative so min rel z-axis min is
actually the one for us it looks like so
it looks like it's it's this that
appears to be the case so we'll have to
double check that but what we now need
is the these two room connections
because I don't think we have any room
connections here yeah we don't
so what we need to do is we need to call
this function get rim connection - and
we're gonna have to use that to generate
the these two so you know we're gonna
have to do room con and I guess
shouldn't believe that and other rim con
and so for the room con that's us we
need to do from our room to the base
room and then we need the opposite and
we need both of those and then we can
set their place two directions so I
think that's what we need there and and
we should be good to go
in theory but I don't actually know it
helps to edit the right function right
it's not surprising that we didn't get
what we wanted when we didn't actually
edit the right function so let's go
ahead and move out there and see what's
up
so now we have the you know the hole
there that's what I wanted and I want to
be able to like go down right I want to
be able to go down to the lower level
stuff and so I was gonna what I was
gonna do here is just place some stairs
in there when you were inside that
doorway I don't know how useful that's
gonna really be but we'll see so I'm
gonna get rid of this now and put this
back in there and I'm gonna look and say
well I probably want to place people on
stairwells for the moment so I'm gonna
prevent you from adding things to the
stairwell but I am going to look here
and say okay if it's something that it
should have been on a stair then I'm
gonna move it down you know so on here
we say like wall height blah blah blah
right and we're putting the P offset in
there I want this to actually be done
differently so you know if it's a
stairwell it's one thing otherwise it's
another thing you know and so the
stairwells I think I'll do where we have
we probably still want the unilateral in
here maybe you know maybe maybe I even
do that and then I'll say okay if it's a
stairwell I'm gonna do some nonsense
here so I'm gonna like move it down by
some proportion to where it is in the
stair so like there's a tee stair value
and I'm gonna move it down based on like
what your tees their value is or
something and so you know we'll move it
up to a meter downward or two meters
down I don't know what our floor to
floor distances even are in the world
because it's been a while
what's the floor height
so AB style Z gets modified by the
tyldum so it actually is set up in here
right like we're actually setting it up
here it's tile depth in meters so it's a
1.4 so you know that's the most you
would go downward and so T stair
probably wants to top out before one so
you know in here we would say all right
the stairwell thing if it is a stairwell
the T stair is gonna take and I could
even do this
in here we're gonna say t stare equals
zero and we would say that the T stare
equals you know this in this volume it
can map ourselves into it so we can
essentially say well the tile Y value
you know that we are - the the minimum Y
of that divided by the Y range is what
we need for our T value right so if I
said you know here's the Y range okay
I'll keep that caps I that's just the
Conville max Y minus the convo min Y and
off to go should absolutely do that
okay
left of dot why
ohso volumes are dim aren't they so this
is actually easier it's just this right
what's the problem here so the volume
has a min and a max OS oh I see so it's
just I will say having a dim there seems
pretty weird
we don't actually ever store the dim
it's just min and Max so shouldn't that
just be II probably that's a really
weird way to write that if you ask me I
also don't know why these aren't gen
VIII's like shouldn't this be this I
mean that's how you should do it and
this seems bad let's fix that
so everywhere in here I'm just gonna do
like min X it's gonna be min x-men X X
is gonna be maxed out X min Y is gonna
be MnDOT y oops
okay max wise we matched that Y and
Maxie
yes I forgot Minzy all right so let's
see what else we got here
and Wiseman got why what the I keep
hitting the T button which opens the to
do thing I wish that didn't work inside
there hold on a second I got to make
that not work inside there cuz it
happens to me all the time
then why because min got why okay all
right so in here these are just gonna be
dot YZ so like if you have a min bracket
it's just a min dot u bracket and I mean
and then if you have a max brackett it's
just a max dot u bracket so now those
are accessible properly and and they
match the way we do our vectors which is
what I wanted
so again max in this case is that and
min is the same so I'd also like to get
rid of dim so we'll do that at some
point here I really wish I had the way
to just like all the replacements I just
did in the other file I want to execute
them now right and I've been waiting to
update my for coder till we have the so
we have the ability to use jump and it's
almost there but it's not quite there
yet and so I'm hoping that happens to
him because there's a lot of features
that I kind of want to add and I just
have been putting it off because I want
them to be based around having a jump
ability which doesn't quite work yet and
so I don't know when the next for coders
coming but I'm hoping it's soon oops
got those capitalized on
so I think we're good now and so this
part here like the dim again just it
seems really weird and so that I feel
like there must be some reason we did
that and I want to make sure we don't
keep doing that so I'm gonna delete that
so yeah we'll see
so I want to let me make sure I didn't
destroy everything by doing that okay so
I want to go in here and and I don't
really want that dim value in there cuz
I feel like that would be easy to make a
mistake this should just be an e right -
that's how we've been doing it so you
just access the elements if you want so
that dim value okay so no one was using
it so that's good so this is really what
it should have looked like and
furthermore once it looks like that
right it should just look like this and
the same is true up here there's no need
for the extra level so now we should be
basically done with that and I just
wanted to make it so we could hop around
down there so like I said as we start to
work on the camera more we need to be
able to check what happens if you go
downward or upward and so I wanted some
way of doing that you can see it sort of
goes down a little bit there but not
quite enough
so yeah part of that is just that this
should start like +1 right so it would
be that and then the max minus the min
is inclusive which means that you know 3
&amp; 2 would just be a span of 1 so even
just
this also like both of these need to be
plus one in a sense I mean maybe we
don't really want to talk about that way
so maybe we want to do this and then
when we're doing the T stare
displacement maybe it's something like
well it's it's really one stair step
down yeah I don't know I don't know how
I really don't know how we want to
parameterize this I think the way we I
think we do want to do it this way so we
essentially say look it's a uniform set
of steps so you want to start on the
first wing and you don't want it to
finish so you want it to look like that
I'm pretty sure that's what you want and
then you just say what's the total
height you want to do and that's what
you get yeah that seems good and that
would allow us to connect like we just
need to make sure that actually allows
us to hop all the way down which I'm not
sure if it will or not we may need a
stairwell to be a little longer
vertically as well in order to actually
hop down them um and looking that I
don't know why that doesn't go down
further as well it seems like it's
so I don't know if the tile dimension
yeah I feel like the tolerance isn't a
radius so I feel like this t stair value
should give us a value that's properly
goes up to 1.4 as a downward
displacement which would bring us to the
next floor height right I mean that's
what should happen because when we
actually go to get where this thing is
it should in theory right I mean there's
the tile dim I mean I could just say
look that's the tile dim it's right
there
so whatever the downward distance is in
general that's what you would use with
the T stair value and then this T star
value should be smoothly should be
smoothly varying
so I want to know why it's not see what
our to stare values are
so that's exactly what I would have
thought they should have been so why are
we getting such little displacement
I mean that just seems really strange
right I mean that's I would have thought
we would have seen a much more dramatic
downward motion for such a big
displacement but for some reason we are
and and that that doesn't really make a
lot of sense um all right so we've got
some figuring out to do I don't really
know oh so at that time it did work
correctly for some unknown reason and it
did create a stairwell down all right I
must have run it prematurely
that's weird so looking at this when I
want to go down there right I need now
some way of making it so that the when I
hop down the stairwell I can I could hop
till things that are that low below me
and I at the moment can't like the the
restriction on the hop distance is I
think too much there let me see what the
let me see what what we're actually
looking at there in terms of how we
decide to do that
so here we see get closest traversable
with the hop target
hmm
so I guess I'm not sure why that
wouldn't let us hop there are we for
some reason not placing a traversable
location on it I mean in theory we
should be here right so when we come in
here and we add the floor tag
we're presumably going to add that
traversable because you know
so I'm not sure why that's not working
let's take a look at get closest
reversible and see so looking in here
that's a long Rey here's the one we'd
actually be be looking at here
sooo you can see here we sort of have
the problem of we want to be able to
pick what the closest reversible is and
we don't really want to we do want this
to be in effect right we want to be able
to hop to lower traversable x' assuming
that they are not too far outside of our
range so once we create this two-point
structure you know we do want this to be
set probably this way for things that
can go up and down like that and we
would say well you know you you can't go
more than like half a meter or something
you know what I mean so we'd say well
alright however much this thing is
however far away it is we're gonna clamp
why we were um I'm not really sure why
we decided to do it quite that way with
clamp above zero there's a lot of ways
we could have done this but we're
basically saying look once we take the
delta between these two things we want
to say let's not worry about the Z as
much we want the closest thing in x and
y but the Z as long as it's within like
a general range that's allowed we're
gonna we're gonna let you hop there so
we kind of want to take that to Point C
and just say look it's yeah it's it's
that far that's how far the Z is and
we'll just say like
this is not a closest distance this is
just a straight-up requirement it's got
to be within this within this bracket so
if the two point Z is less than whatever
our bracket size is like half a unit or
something then we go and you know not
exactly sure how we want to do that but
it's something like that so you know you
can you should be able to go to one of
these if it's within that bracket now I
don't know how far that bracket actually
should be why I can't hop there
must be some other bug here
what am I doing wrong there when we're
searching for the Z we should be able to
bound the region in which we're testing
the Z and that should have still
included wherever that traversable was
right we shouldn't have had any problem
with that so I'm not sure why it didn't
why it didn't like that it seems to
really not want to go on those stairs
and I'm not sure why cuz they should
have traversable x' and in fact if I
drew them I would be able to see them
right I mean if we basically said I want
to see the traversable x'
you know show me the traversals you know
I can see that they're there and I know
I can hop around down here
but I'm not sure why I can't get up onto
that I said why I couldn't get on to any
of these stairs I I don't know why gosh
so there's a bunch of weird things going
on there let's let's go debug that so
when we search through all of these
queries we are testing all of the
entities you can see our to do here of
like we probably shouldn't do that but
we're testing all of the entities to see
which ones closest and in theory we
should be able to bias it to always use
x and y closeness primarily and then Z
is just more like a clipping like we'll
clip out anything that's not you know
within a certain range of us right so in
theory we should have been able to say
like you know in fact we don't even
really need that we can just say
look if you know to point Z is you know
greater than or equal to some negative
bound and less than or equal to some
positive bounds then we know we can take
the distance
not counting the Z right so then when we
do our test distance squared when we
take the length squared of to point here
it should just give us the XY distance
not counting the pitch downward so it
won't be favored hopping down a stair
just because it's further to go you know
to go Z downward then it would be to not
and so I have no idea why it doesn't
like that you know what I mean that
doesn't really make a lot of sense and
so I would like to know why we're having
that problem and you know what I could
do to to save ourselves the agony inside
world Jen I can just put us in a
different location outset so when we do
all this generation and I'm like what's
the start room or where's the hero get
placed or whatever right the result here
for initial camera P we can change the
hero placement for that right so I think
what I would do there is say let's take
a look at the forest so you know in the
orphanage forest entrance
I can't probably just say this
and then force the placements to be
there instead right or maybe not
can I not do that we are generating a
forced entrance are we not yeah
so we should be able to set the initial
camera P here to be the hero room like
this right I mean there's no reason we
can't do that but for some reason it
doesn't want us to do that let's find
out why
so it looks like it couldn't actually
add our entity for some reason like it
wasn't able to actually put the hero in
which is interesting I wonder why not so
here's the place where we actually do
that oh well I mean that's why get
closest traversable in this case I guess
we we need a way of telling it in here
not to do this clip if that makes sense
so I'm curious this get closest
reversible where it's st. reversible
search unoccupied
interesting enough we don't obey it
do we or I guess we do
but nobody passes that in does the other
person who calls us pass it in there's
two places where it's called I was like
if there's a couple of places where it's
called
weird
so in here where we say traversable
search unoccupied we say if the
traversable search on occupied occupied
flag is not set we can do this or if the
occupier is zero meaning there's no one
on it we can do it so that means in
general where we when we search
interesting so yeah we don't search for
that interesting interesting interesting
so normally we check after the fact
right you can see them check in like the
brain for the the various things hereit
they check afterwards ok so really I
feel like that should have been set that
this flag should have been set on me on
the other one but I guess that's neither
here nor there anyway so I'm gonna say
something like if we're gonna clip Z
then we do this otherwise we don't so we
say you know if this was not set we can
just do it if it was that we have to
look here right and I probably don't
want to do this
in that case either you know what I mean
so the two point dot Z equals zero that
probably shouldn't happen unless we're
gonna clip the Z
so we'll do that and off we go
all right so in say I would argue in
here this this really should have been
passing that I feel like yeah so I think
we're good now that's just a little bit
of a weird thing that was happening
there and so then inside the geckos
traversable for these inside the brain
when we ask for a hop I think that's
where we want to do the handmade clips
e-version and I want to know why it's
not working because I have no idea why
it's not working it should that should
have been something very unintuitive
what's happening here because I should
be able to hop to that one so why can't
I you know what I mean
so I want to see what's going on there
cuz something's messed up severely if I
can't hop to there because like at some
point if I set the if I set this large
enough
there should be no way I could possibly
not and cap it like capture the distance
between this one in the next one
right so the fact that I can't still
can't hop down there is absurd
something's totally busted so let's take
a look at let me just switch to debug
mode now and let me see what's going on
there
so in this case now I'm like forced
going that way right and I could I think
here's a question can I do this if I
want to turn on loop live code editing
can I just do like l-l yeah maybe now
is the frame temporary arena not marked
as unrestored I think it might it might
not be yeah it's not so the frame arena
probably in order to make loop life Co
didn't be okay the frame arena probably
has to do that because it's actually you
know persisting across and so it
shouldn't probably be restored because
the temporary it can't reload it's
temporary at that point at least that
would be my assumption I can't think of
any reason why you would want the frame
arena to not do that so I think in here
we want that frame arena here we want
the frame arena to be set to that mode
so gamestate frame arena Flags actually
don't remember what the flag is but it's
something like do not restore is
actually that's in the platform isn't it
it's the non restored memory pool that I
want to emulate here it's yes so when
you do when you create it you do a non
restored arena so it's really this I'm
assuming I can just set that I don't see
any reason why I couldn't so inside the
arena where you've got the allocation
flags I think I can just set that so
like that memories not restored so let
me see if I can make sure that that
works properly
oh but you know what the gamestate is
gonna get restored so that temporary
free lasting outside the frame is is not
great right because the gamestate
yeah the gamestate has to line up with
the arena temporary that's tricky so
here's what I'll say I think what I want
to do there is make it not do that so I
think what I'd rather do is just set it
that way and instead of n temporary
memory like instead of this I would say
let's just clear it every frame because
that way we can just say cuz we don't
really want that participating in save
restore ever that would just be bad so
we'd rather just do this I think because
everything else seems to work just fine
there
all right so why would that be unhappy
and also we don't care now whether it's
restored or not so shouldn't this be
okay now I guess I'd have to think about
that so since it's in the game state and
we will restore its pointer maybe this
has to happen we'll see but I feel like
now we should be able to get this to
work but because that is a sticking
point I'm not sure how we would have
that happen so it doesn't want to do the
clear right
[Music]
but I'm not sure why let's debug that
too so free marina's we I do think we
want them to be non restored because I
don't see why you would want that right
and it's cleared always at the outset so
that's just how that happens so I just
want to know why I want to know why it's
having trouble with that restoration the
gamestate structure itself will have its
state restored right meaning like
when we come in here the frame arena
this game state struct so you know this
will have its state restored and for
some reason the current block pointer
gets borked there when we go to clear it
you know this memory is garbage but I'm
not sure why it was because it should
just be set to whatever it was on that
frame
I guess one question is what happens
when we what happens when we rewind our
arenas here so when we're reloading the
process when we're reloading the state
for replay we do have a problem where if
we free a block what's gonna happen to
that block when we reload it later so
here we go when we begin recording we
come through here and we look at all of
the source blocks that we've got and we
write them all out and then we finish
right when we need to play it back we
load them all and we load them at their
locations why is that that is what this
is isn't it
why does it say that
so it seems like that should be fine
what I would say there is it is a little
bit weird do we just never deallocate
locks or something
because there is a little bit of
weirdness there like in terms of like
watching what gets allocated during
looping and what doesn't so when we
begin recording our input here you know
we're saying like okay go through all of
these and look at what the memory blocks
were at that particular time and you
know we saved them out
hmm I'm also not sure what that final I
guess that final null is just what lets
us know we're done so here we keep
reading till we get a base pointer of
zero yeah I don't know I mean that seems
like that would be fine the win32 clear
blocks by mask
I guess what I would say is when we're
loading these back in how do we do the
mapping so when we come in here and we
say like here's the saved memory block
so to get that thing how does this even
work because do we just prevent all
memory block memory block freeing during
that process I guess we do
so what happens when I do a winter it's
your allocate so in here we presumably
set yeah allocated during looping right
so we know whether this thing was
allocated during looping or not I'm
gonna go ahead and say that this creates
sort of a problem for us because if the
looping flag is sets this but we are an
on restored piece of memory then this
should really not be set because it's
gonna be allocated or freed during
looping but it doesn't matter
right so where's the non restored memory
curious like what are the what are the
memory flags we can set they're not
restored so when we record the input if
something is not restored then it
doesn't get written here right but
what's kind of busted is that when we do
a free by mask this is not good
right I mean I guess we I guess it's
okay cuz non restored would be set there
maybe but those are looping Flags only
so it seems like you really don't want
to actually do this because if something
was a non restored block then you really
don't want it to be cleared right so I
feel like that's just a bug in this
system where we want to make sure that
when we're recording you know we play
back what was supposed to happen and
that's all fine but when we go to
cleared the allocated blocks we need to
make sure that anything that was not
supposed to be restored should not get
cleared you know what I mean so I feel
like this has to respect that flag or
something
you
I'm also not sure when we call win32 end
input playback why we would anything
that was freed during living we don't
know that we're actually at the end so
this seems questionable to me
no it's it's okay because we're not
talking about future ones it will just
free the ones that have been yeah okay
now that's fine so I think the problem
here is just yet like that freed during
looping and the allocated during looping
Flags I feel like that has to be
respected it has to respect it has to
respect the non restored part of things
right so if the memory type here you
know I think we want to do something
more like this where we say if we're in
the loop and we say that this is
supposed to be restored then we're gonna
do a looping allocate but otherwise
we're not because it's a non restored
memory and then in here it would be the
same way so if the memory block in
question has flags that indicate that we
wouldn't restore it then we don't want
to do that so win32 block flags or it's
block block Flags I guess I think
it's that I think that's what we
actually want to have happen there and
so that should happen and then now I
argue as I said before this should be a
non restored memory piece right so I'm
not sure about that because that's a
fairly complex system now we should
probably pull it out and get it a little
bit more tested but yeah so now that
frame arena is not causing us problems
which is good I also want to make sure
we're not getting a memory leak in there
because that's pretty tricky now because
it's like doing sort of this behind the
scenes saver store stuff so that looks
leaky right to me
so I I think we're still I think that's
still bad in that I think that memory is
still not quite right so let's see here
yeah you know that frame arena is
supposed to have sonication flags set to
not restored it's supposed to be able to
clear itself
and I guess the other thing that I'm not
sure about is sewn on was the other
problem with non restored memory he's
like guess you really can't the arena
itself has to have its stuff restored or
not restored as well and that's another
part that seems busted like we would
need some way of we would need some way
there of having the arena get like we
would need the arena's actual data
itself to not be restored to you know
what I mean so if you look at what would
have to happen here like this needs to
be that and it needs to be bootstrapped
so they its allocated in itself right if
that makes sense
because otherwise like you wouldn't yeah
like it just wouldn't work so we kind of
need to do something where the frame
arena itself is put into the non
restored memory so that it can always
actually be like non restored I know
that sounds weird but there's no other
way to do it because otherwise the data
for which blocks are in it is getting
restored but the blocks aren't getting
restored and we want the whole thing to
be non restored it's just it's running
along with the frames and it's just
supposed to be that way you know
so inside the memory system it's where
we do a bootstrap off roots right on
that so inside here where we do a
bootstrap push struct this we should be
able to call directly and the struct
size is just going to be the size of the
memory know the offsets zero the params
are non restored arena
what's the sort of bootstrap trims
dime-store arena I think that's all we
need right so I think that's good and
then in here right we just need the
frame arena is now pointer always so you
don't need to take the address of it but
everything else is fine so that keeps
everything in non restored memory and so
I feel like that should work and we
should be able to verify that no one is
touching that memory don't really know
what Chuck arena does I don't remember
writing that all right that's a nonsense
call so we just cleared it
so let's see here moving on let's see if
we can make that a little more stable
now and it should I want to be able to
actually have it so it doesn't leak that
memory - so when we are see here so
frame arena why isn't that getting
initialized so in here frame arena
that's supposed to be allocated here so
if not game state oh that needs to be
set up right away so as soon as we get
one of those we need one of these
and why are we not
initializing that so here's the game
state here's a bootstrapping it
there's destruct
there's the frame arena nope Wow
that's kind of dangerous
that's just zeroed out the memory of
that thing okay so if we clear a memory
arena
oh wait no that that is what should be
doing right so it should be calling this
all right so what was the problem
yes that wasn't so dangerous so what was
the problem here come down here sit
clear the marina's fine
oh so in this case if we were the one we
really don't want to clear up to that
point so I guess now we really do want
the temp them to right so here we would
want to do n temporary memory all right
so this is kind of tricky to get
something that allocates across the
frame boundary when you do your restore
not so simple there might have been a
better way to do this if we added
support in the system for it more
directly I suppose so there is that so
we need to make sure we don't free the
actual storage for the arena itself that
seems okay and so I want to make sure to
let me let it run in optimize note I
want to make sure that that's not leaky
like I want to make sure that that we
didn't like mess up how we're managing
that memory pool there because it's very
subtle much much more subtle than
anything else we are ever doing so it
looks like that's loaded everything and
that's gonna load I don't see any
leakiness there so let me just see what
happens if we do this okay so now we're
super stable
so that's good all right so that's good
so now I can actually do the thing I
wanted which is to see what was going on
with that error there and so maybe we
can even do a thing where all right so
if I do loop live code editing here so
we were just stuck in this loop we're
constantly trying to search for that
thing
so I find I want to do the debugger
action a lot to do so I'm going to
recompile live code edit into debug mode
so now I think that's what's being run
right and now going to sim region and
then check forget closest reversible in
debug mode and see why it's not finding
a traversable in this case right so I
want to see inside execute brain here oh
this is what's gonna happen
we're gonna search for the hop target so
if we look at where the where we're
looking to go like this is where we're
looking to go right I want to know why
we're not properly considering the Z
values there or like what's happening
right look what what's going on inside
get closest reversible such that we
never get there you know what I mean so
two points is the you know target under
consideration and in theory right like
these Z's we should get to a point where
these Z's are more reasonable right
so there's one with like a really steep
like these these are all like wickedly
far we kinda feel like we're gonna need
something to narrow this down for us
like does it ever get here
that's kind of weird
so we do get in here and if we look at
what the two-point value is so it is a
value that's that's close you know in Z
it's close enough so what happens here
when we do that we zero out the Z value
we do the length squared of this thing
so that's just going to be the X and the
y values and so we look at what that
distance square it is and we look at
what the closest just to the square it
is right so we're going to take that one
you know and that that looks like it's
operating basically how I would have
thought it would be operating you know
so I look at the test distance squared
there you know there's an even closer
one right
if that's the hop target what's the
actual target so this is slightly higher
than the target anyway this should end
up being something like like we should
end up having one here that's really
close let's see which one's get closer
so there's a zero that's still quite a
bit far away and why here's one that's
like lower down than it and we are
accepting that move so that's like to
the left a little right
I'm also going to set a breakpoint down
here so here's one that's right in front
of us I mean that looks pretty good
right however it's z-value oddly enough
is the same as the hop target so that
would suggest that it is it actually how
is that possible
that that seems like it should be
impossible
are we accidentally searching from like
back some other location that's not
where we're actually hopping from or
something I mean we were taking the body
position and we're adding the target why
how was there one with a Z that matched
our search Z like that just doesn't add
up for me right because what we saw
there was that the traversable was like
at the same place something's fishy
there's something we're kitten we're
getting closer here but something's
weird is good III don't know what's
going on but it's not good right I turn
off the loop so something is happening
where it actually thinks those points
are at the same Z level
also there's some weird stuff happening
with Z as well the actual like C bias
that's a real puzzler and I have no idea
what's going on there because we
shouldn't have seen like that debt was a
totally bogus value it says if there was
a traversable right there and we know
that there isn't because we're drawing
the traversals as the purple squares
there so if there was one there we
should have seen it and I don't get why
so how is what's going on
I'm super stumped right now and I don't
have any way to debug this so I'm gonna
have to do something to simplify this
down I guess what I can do is only add
traversable x' in just those two
locations and nowhere else in the world
so like you know I could change this to
only allow traversable schemes just that
one room and only just in that location
[Music]
maybe so here's the one other thing I
want try so let's suppose I didn't move
the stairs at all there's not moved I'm
assuming I can still hop on them right
is that true so I can still have a cross
them just fine
if in here I set them to some smaller
amount so they're just gradual
that's allowed if I set it to slightly
more now I can so it's like the values
that we think we're multiplying by are
not actually the values or something
you know what I mean it's like it's like
we're somehow setting like this stuff is
not actually in the same space as we
think it is right because the difference
in Z between these if it was one point
out the entire difference here of the
entire stairwell is only one point four
right
so how we could actually have this not
pick that up I'm not sure
and there didn't seem to be anything we
could set this to that would make it
work either
that's just really really weird so
what's the value that we actually have
to do before it can't do it that's just
so bizarre and like that's right at the
edge where the random the amount of
randomness involved actually makes it so
I can't hop on these two stairs but I
can on this one so is ours stair height
way higher than we like how is this
possible it doesn't make any sense this
value here we know what it is look we
know it's 1.4 how is this happening this
is so bizarre it's like complete
ludicrousness something really just
absolutely bonkers it's happening here
and I have no idea what it is that's
gonna drive me nuts so
a value of 0.25 is how much we are
saying we're moving by all of the tiles
in dim Z which is supposed to be 1.4
that's point three five right it moves
up and down by another point five so if
you pick the absolute maximum you could
do it would be I guess it would be 0.35
plus well even that think about that for
a second how is that that's almost the
entire floor mat I must just have the
floor I must be this value must be much
larger than I think it is what did I do
wrong there
so tyldum Z what's what's going on here
so when we actually set this oh I'm in
room John I'm like why can't I find
anything um so when we actually do this
here then we say typical floor height
what does that do
so inside begin world Jenna's presumably
where we would set this up I looked at
the wrong value this entire thing could
have been avoided if we just looked at
that so really this is probably some
other larger value for the tile depth in
meters okay so what is this value
when do we actually set that pass it in
so the typical fluoride is 5 this entire
time so I just misread that value I
don't know why all right well that was a
waste of time although I guess we fixed
them the loop live coding so I'm happy
that we did that but ok so when we want
to do the Z range there inside sim
region this should really be more like -
right my lord
ok that was just unfortunate all right
so since that was a bit of a disaster
there I'm gonna go ahead and say let's
also do one more thing which is let's
find out why are we not is there a
reason that we we don't go down and kind
of zoom further in to like is that
actually how far away we should be from
here you know I guess maybe it is but I
can't quite tell if we should be or not
and we need to set our alpha clipping so
that when we come down here it clips
away as well so I'm not sure what we
want that to be set to exactly but like
our clip or Alpha clip your clip plane
here needs to match that
you know
how far out is that stuff now
seems like the answer is very far out
so the Alpha clip here is based on what
and that's a little strange cuz
shouldn't the Alpha clip value be now
we'll see so is the Alpha clip stuff
it's based on the same setting as this
or not look I'm not sure what the Alpha
clip params actually refer to there in
terms of when they kick in so yeah I'm
not sure but it does seem like those
should have been parameterised off of
the near clip plane but doesn't look
like they were so I'm not sure if that's
like actually just something that kicks
in in some other way you know what I
mean
and it seems like that's also wants to
be measured in pure Z as well kind of a
separate issue but this is pretty good
now I can actually explore down here and
so you know to that I think that leaves
me in good shape for tomorrow because
then I can go do the camera stuff now
which is what I wanted and I can work on
the clip see the fog and the debug
camera and get that all looking proper
but this is much better now and I can go
up and down the stairs and like you can
see that look we want the clip C to clip
things in a the the near clip plane in
the Alpha clip those should actually be
measured off of the camera Z this is
actually should be measured off of a Z
of the world Z and this should be
measured off of the world Z - probably
so this is probably not what we actually
want similarly I don't know to what
extent we care about this it's like this
should really be doing like there's
there's a bunch of stuff we want to hear
so in terms of getting the camera Z I
don't think we want a fog based on the
camera Z I think we actually want a fog
based on the world Z I think and the
Alpha clip we would want to do the same
thing I think I don't really know but I
think this stuff is busted like we want
to change that measurement in the actual
shader and get that stuff to work
properly
I also think it seems like maybe we
should be like the camera doesn't seem
to be moving very far down in here and
so it seems like maybe it's a little bit
as far as Z is concerned it seems like
it's just confused about how far off set
it should be and I don't know if that I
don't know if that's because when we do
the room Jen and we get how far away
we're supposed to be like maybe this is
doing something dumb they're like we
shouldn't really let it get set to such
high values ever I'm not super certain
about that and it looks like that would
be more of an X count thing that's
happening there so it looks like it'd be
one of wear one of these
then one of these but so I'm not sure I
want to see 1 2 3 4 5 ok so that is
gonna be a larger than 15 room so I'm
wondering if maybe these should still
like this maybe got up too high too fast
you know what I mean so I want to take a
look at that I think maybe the the
displacement of the camera was a little
too much
because that still seems like like
that's still a little too far away I
feel like so I wonder if you know maybe
this should have been like this I don't
know it seems like those values are just
not right because especially because
this room at this scale doesn't even
really need to scroll much right so it's
kind of weird
the way that was set up sorry I keep
going here I know I'm supposed to be
finishing this dream but just you know
sometimes it's easy to get obsessive so
I think for the Alpha clip here I guess
I don't know what that distance wants to
be exactly in terms of where we start
clipping but I guess we want to clip
something like I don't know
almost
um so that seems really nice and let me
turn off the movement points to because
we don't really need those
and so yeah seems like that works pretty
seamlessly now first I don't really know
what happened there
so it looks like that range needs to be
maybe a little tighter we probably also
want to make it so it's the camera
follows someone up and down the stairs
so you don't get that problem but yeah
that seems pretty good right um let's go
ahead and do brief Q&amp;A and then I'm
gonna bow out until tomorrow
I mean if we really want to make this
spooky we could turn off the moonlight
too right like
trying to load the complete set of v0h
SAS data set with the latest github
handmade hero cope it doesn't work so
did you did you actually use the HSA
editor right did you actually do HHA
edit - rewrite and move them all - v2s
like I did like you got to do this those
are v-0 so you got to do rewrite and
then the HHA in question like you know
that and then you have to do to update
them will ship a complete version as
soon as I'm done with this but we're
kind of in the middle of that now so I'm
not going to constantly update those
files if that makes sense
but so you need to use HHA edit to bring
them in I will probably soon try to get
to the point where we rebuild all of our
assets with one call because we can do
that now but what's the status on the
Rattler ask Alan I have no idea I
haven't seen it had just clipped into
the wall for sell corrected you plan
doing a z-buffer tricks to keep sprites
from being hidden by three of John -
yeah we already actually did that but we
had like when we updated our sprite code
I'm kind of holding off on that to
decide exactly what goes on here so if
you look inside the entity code here we
do our computation of where everything
is and then we do the push bright call
here on these the scaled axes and then
if you go into the push bright call you
can see that it doesn't use an easy bias
right now if we did use some Z bias it
would work temporarily anyway so for
example if we just
you know said that and and allowed there
to be some Z bias and there we could set
that value to something that would fix
it right but you can see like there's a
bunch of stuff we have to account for in
this case we have we want these to be
proportional to how much is actually
going on and we need to like set them
per sprite so that sprites stack on each
other and other kinds of stuff like this
right we also don't want to use that for
fogging probably hard to say but you can
you can see we sort of already did solve
the problem
in a certain sense but we haven't gone
and spent the time to tune all that to
work properly but the renderer does know
how to do it so it already has the
ability to work with that code
ooh oh I forgot we got it we gotta get
rid of the head thing there oh man we
actually have an area that would have
more than 4,000 ice enemies mm-hmm we're
getting into beef beef territory I guess
ouch
but anyway yes so that that's what's
happening in there um so what we want to
do eventually when we go to clean that
coat up is we're going to decide like
how this stuff is actually gonna get set
and we're gonna pass it in from outside
can you explain a between keep alec in
virtual AK and for what scenario they
are appropriate yeah so I guess I
couldn't really tell you why Hiep alec
exists really so here's the function
that's are being asked about you've seen
virtual lock we don't call this one and
I wish I knew what the point of it was I
really don't it's basically giving you
access to a malloc style thing you can
do heap Alec and you can do heap free
and it will actually try to handle
allocating and freeing memory for you
and I have never really used them every
process in Windows has one of these and
I just I don't know what the point of it
is I'm assuming that the point of it is
maybe for the operating system to be
able to interchange memory with you on
the heap but it never really does that
there probably are some calls that do
but this is basically like a little
memory allocator that runs in there
backed by virtual Alec right so this is
kind of like a utility you could almost
think of it that allows you to do Alex
and freeze on top of a virtual Alec that
you didn't have to call yourself that
the process actually manages for you and
to be honest I don't know what the point
of it is I really don't I wish I could
talk more intelligently to the reason
why windows thought it should be in
there I'm sure they had a good reason I
don't know what it was at the time
virtual Alec on the other hand is
actually the thing that interfaces with
the memory page table for your process
and that's what you actually need to use
to allocate memory so
when you call Heep a lock and keep free
you're not actually gonna be mapping
memory pages in you're gonna be going
through an intermediary who old map
pages or not so it's like a 1 removed
right you're gonna say allocate some
memory it's gonna say okay do I need to
virtual alt or not if I do I will if I
don't then I won't right I might just
give you a portion of memory are already
mapped so for our purposes we don't need
that really so because we do these calls
very infrequently so we use virtual a
lot directly because that's the thing
that actually sets up there we go that's
the thing that actually maps memory
pages in your process so it's the actual
memory allocator in some sense you could
say that gives you a page directly or
set up pages so this is really a thing
that this is what actually maps pages in
the virtual address space of your
process and says I'm actually use of
memory now virtual acts like a utility
that would work on top of that and I
don't really know why you would want to
use it you'd want to use it if the OS if
in order to interact with a particular
OS function it was going to want to take
a keep Alex page that they can free or
something right what kind of allocation
to use for assets well there's a couple
kinds so there's texture memory that
gets allocated for assets and we move it
into there then we use for the storage
of the actual like things that don't go
into texture memory like sound we just
use a you know we have a set of virtual
Alex that allocate pages for us and we
put them in there so they're just
virtually a locked and then pushed on as
like a stack what is the on lamp very
I'll represent so we have like I turned
off the the putting of lights in the
world so it doesn't do that right now
like there are no other lights in the
world besides the one that you're
carrying and the moon but
if you actually looked at the code for
rooms you can see that like we had some
code to set up some lamps in the corners
of rooms and so if you actually like
turn that back on then each of the rooms
has like a lamp a bright spot in the
corner where there is a lamp that's just
putting light in there right so now when
we walk down here it's not dark like
there's lamps in the corners they're
just there's no point to it I mean we
were just playing around and so that's
all that is and the lamps were like
variably colored you can see how some of
them are like more green or more red or
whatever right that that was it
it doesn't do anything else and so you
know it turned out that just wasn't very
interesting so I kind of turned it off
and forgot about it
yeah and that and that was it
all right close down
thank you everyone join me for an
episode of hand made here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you can always play the
game on handmade hero org and it comes
with a source code so you can play
around with it yourself I will be back
here tomorrow and I think we'll play
with the camera a bit tomorrow that's
what I wanted you today but we kind of
had a bunch of other stuff that kind of
came up and so I wanted to go I was
marching and doing some of those other
things and also setting it up so we
could walk downstairs and stuff so that
way we can look at the like camera alpha
and other things like that that we might
want to edit so we'll be back to do that
and we'll probably also want to start
down the road of doing the text files
for asset metadata too so we've got
plenty to do this weekend hope see you
back here for that until then have fun
programming everyone and I'll see you on
the Internet take it easy everybody