hello everyone welcome to handmade Hero
show recode a complete game live on
stream we are probably and I am loath to
say it I know that it's a bit it's a bit
dangerous in there it's dangerous to go
alone we are at the point where I kind
of would like to start looking at the
lighting and getting that into a
shippable State we did a bunch of work
on it we got something that's alright
but it's not quite there yet it's not
quite something that I think we could
ship reliably it's too slow and it has
some issues I think it would be hard to
use to light our sprites the way we want
to so I guess what I would say is I
think now might be the time to go in and
clean that up and one of the reasons I
say that is because we're getting pretty
close to what I would consider a
graphically complete looking sort of
game and the big problem right now is
that the lighting just isn't isn't there
and two things one you can see our
sprites aren't lit so they look stupid
all of this stuff is lit properly and
the sprites aren't you hop into a dark
area you don't get darker right and
that's not a huge problem to solve like
we could take our current lighting
system and solve that but it's not ideal
to solve in the current system so
looking at how we want to change that's
one thing and then the other thing is
it's just too slow like we already
you're just doing a sub-region you can
see here that's not quite big enough
because you can see the edge of it when
we zoom out a bit in things where we
want to be zoomed out a little bit more
so that's a bit of an issue but also we
have the issue that in general even even
in this sort of smaller state in a fully
optimized build on a modern machine this
machine is pretty fast it's not the
fastest but it's pretty fast it's
sucking down like all of our time and
it's sucking out so much time that even
things that kind of need to be optimized
like render ground cover is made to look
small and insignificant
by comparison I mean here's 1,600 calls
to a relatively inefficient routine and
that's only taking 4% of our time and
why is that when it's so piggy
and the answer is just my
Lord compute light propagation just eats
all the time why does it need so much
time
well because it's actually using the
entire CPU we've got a you know I guess
six is it six here one two three four
five six we've got six additional
threads including the main threads so
all the cores of the processor minus 1
which we leave for you know handling
sort of servicing other stuff at the
time like OS garbage and stuff like that
we're using almost all the resources of
the CPU and we're still getting a pretty
lousy throughput on e not even in like
particularly large swath of the world
and so you know that's not the kind of
thing that we really want to have in
here and furthermore that's before it
even has to do anything we before we've
made any accommodations for lighting our
sprites so it's a bad situation it's
it's not something where we just really
don't want to see this it's gonna create
problems for us and we need to be more
judicious as we go here ok so let's talk
about some like where's the slowness
coming from you know what's the what's
the actual problem I don't remember yeah
we're not really printing out much in
the way of stats right now but you know
what's going on like why are we so slow
and what can we do to speed it up you
know we got issues right we got we got
issues too much time spent in the
lighting even though we've thrown all
the CPUs at it so first of all let's
start with a couple basics it's not a
parallelization problem where we're not
locking or anything else we've perfectly
segregated if I remember correctly the
Lightning computation such that it
actually fans out to all the processors
with no
King so it's not the kind of algorithm
where a problem is just a subtlety of
the multi-threading or something like
that
we're multi-threading it pretty well I
mean obviously you can always probably
do a little bit better but it's pretty
darn clean the way that's being
multi-threaded so the issue you know for
us is beyond the multi-threading so we
can I think we can safely put that aside
and say that's not what we're looking at
here okay
think to GPU versus CPU so the operation
that we're doing which is our ray
tracing here we're doing entirely on the
CPU side obviously for these kinds of
operations GPUs have a lot more
floating-point power backing them up we
could probably get a good speed up by
switching from the CPU to the GPU but
not as good as the kind of speed up that
we would expect if we were moving a
traditional rendering operation over the
GPU and the reason for that is just
because the GPU is not as good at
arbitrary calculations involving
arbitrary memory walking as compared to
the CPU cpus are set up for that GPUs
are not at least until you get to for
example the RT X stuff like with Nvidia
where the chip is more optimized for it
and you use very specific algorithms
that are designed to minimize the degree
to which the GPU gets hurt by that fact
so could we make some headway by milla
GPU yes that's I think that's true we
would have to probably modify our
algorithms a little bit but that
wouldn't necessarily be in the end of
the world and we definitely could get a
speed-up by moving it to the GPU however
that would extremely high that would put
a very high load on the GPU
we're already demanding a lot from the
GPU because we're doing a lot of high
quality fill work we're using
to do order independent transparency and
things like this and multi sampling all
stuff we're kind of wanting to use our
GPU for actual rendering and so using
the CPU which we do not need for
anything else really
you know our game doesn't do physics
simulation in any kind of really
extensive way and so we're not really
anticipating putting a high stress on
the CPU for other things we don't have
thousands of characters walking around
on the scene or something like that you
know we don't have a lot for the CPU to
do and we've been pretty efficient with
our CPU usage right we haven't done
stupid stuff well we've done some stupid
stuff but not stupid enough uh and so
utilizing the GPU has some downsides
which is to say that we're leaving the
CPU kind of not doing much at all and
we're putting a lot of stress on the GPU
at that point and I don't know that
that's necessarily the best way to go
either right so there's some issues
there I think that are worth keeping in
mind however that algorithmic change is
worth understanding and it's worth
understanding that there's more we could
do
algorithmically with our CPU version as
well just in terms of how we're like
associated raised and casting them and
things like that there's probably more
we could do there as well right okay so
that brings us to the final point which
is the one that I actually want to focus
on today which is do i realistically
think our problem is just
implementational like that like how did
we actually type the code in versus are
we just fundamentally doing some things
wrong in the algorithm that if we fix
them we would get a lot faster without
really having to worry about particular
details in the implementation themselves
and that's really the thing that I want
to focus more on because I think the
answer there is probably yes so I guess
what I'm saying is I think our approach
should be improved first because I think
we can by doing some things smarter than
what we're doing right now
and if we improve the approach I think
we may get to a point we're doing it on
the CPU is actually fine and we don't
have to worry about it anymore at which
point we don't have to worry about
improving the algorithms and
transferring them to the GPU which is
more error-prone
and requires a much beefier GPU because
when we go to optimize our renderer for
lower you know whatever our lowest end
system ends up being it's gonna be a lot
harder to do if we've got to have a huge
ray tracing pass on there in addition to
everything else we're doing right so I
think the thing that I'd like to focus
on first before we do anything else is
I'd like to figure out what we're gonna
do algorithmically different from what
we're doing right now and I think just
based on kind of a you know more passing
familiarity with what the state of the
art is in the higher-end rendering world
so not handmade hero but you know you're
writing the next doom or the next you
know Grand Theft Auto or something the
next battlefield six or whatever and
you're just you've got a whole rendering
team you're sitting there doing
everything you can to max out the visual
quality of this game that you're working
on looking at the way that they do
things I think there's one pre major
change that we can make that would
improve our quality a lot I think for
the same amount of work that we're doing
or maybe I should say a little bit
differently it would improve the speed
at which we can arrive at roughly the
same thing we're looking at now while at
the same time making it easier for us to
light our sprites cheaply and and so I
think that that's probably the thing I
would I would focus on and I do think
earlier on I didn't really
I didn't really consider this as a way
to do things
largely because I think I didn't quite I
didn't quite have a handle on how you
would do it in real time as opposed to
pre-computed but I think I kind of get
that more now and so let me talk a
little bit about this and it's it's not
a huge change from what we're doing
actually but it's it's enough of it
makes enough of a difference just
because of a subtle change in the way
you think about what you're doing it
does have a pretty I think or could have
a potentially large effect on what we're
doing so let's talk about it okay
so what I'm talking about is light
probes and you see them around a lot and
the question is can they work for us why
am i mentioning them what would be the
difference between what we have now and
them why do I think that this is the
thing that we should investigate as our
first attempt at making our lighting
solution more shippable and less
experimental okay so what a light probe
is honestly you could even use that term
to describe what we're already doing in
a sense although I'll say why that the
term is traditionally applied to
something slightly different so let's
talk about sort of like an hours versus
there's kind of a thing in terms of
light probes and with an eye towards why
theirs is better than ours I think and
then we'll also say because I was aware
of light probes when we started and will
say I'll also talk about why I didn't
immediately choose to do them and and
sort of why why I think that maybe even
my original reasons for not doing them
or not warranted okay so the way we
currently do things is we sort of do do
light probes in a sense what we do is we
have services in the world right and
those services because we're sort of
going for a tiled aesthetic tend to be
kind of cube like they're not exactly
cubes it's not like minecraft they're
arbitrary
betray rectangular right rectangular
prisms it can be any sort of shape and
they can be rotated as well and all that
but they are fundamentally rectangular
solids so we know that we've got sort of
these quad phases you know like this
sort of thing and we know that on each
of those quad phases what we're gonna do
is we're gonna put sample points down
right that's sort of what we were doing
is putting down these sample points
right and I believe right now we're
doing that I think in a fairly
structural way like this sort of thing
but there's really no reason for that we
could perturb them and make them random
our algorithm doesn't depend on the
placement of these things but it is the
kind of thing that we haven't
investigated yet so we're really I think
doing a regular sampling on there at the
moment correct me if I'm wrong on that I
don't remember where we stopped with our
experimentation but so when we send one
of these things down we're typically
collecting lighting information on the
actual services that are bouncing around
and then what we're doing is you're
saying for each one of these we treat
this sort of plate effectively as like a
collector so that we're gonna send rays
out from it and we're gonna see what
they hit and when they hit something
which itself is gonna be another one of
these things right we're gonna send some
of that light back so we're gonna
basically collect that light by moving
it back to sort of flavor this tile and
then when we go to render what we'll do
is whenever we're rendering a particular
location with a sample from the points
that are on the surface that we're
sampling and we'll color that in right
now this is actually exactly like
basically everything about what I just
said is exactly the same as what a light
probe really does do for any real
definition of the term light probe but
there is one thing we did which i think
is probably a mistake
in our system that we didn't really
consider changing and again the reason
for it I'll go into in a second it was
mostly just because I didn't really
think about how you would be able to
overcome a particular limitation of the
real-time nature of what we're doing
because it importantly understand is
light probes traditionally are not
dynamic
traditionally in games light probes are
static so a light probe is something
that you pre compute and you stick it
it's somewhere in the world you do a
like a real ray tracing on your world
when you like bake the game and what you
end up doing is you just use those light
probes at runtime without really ever
updating them much right and so they're
they're not really a real-time construct
or at least they weren't but turns out
you can make them real time and that's
really the reason I hadn't considered
them so anyway I let's talk about theirs
for a second so what were light probes
what's the difference between what we
were doing which is basically a light
probe actually and what theirs is well
the main difference is separation of you
know reflectors and collectors is I
guess the way I would say it and the
important thing to understand here is
that we even in our system we do
actually have totally separate
conceptualizations for what is a
reflector and what is a collector we
have points that collect information for
our lighting and our you know our
occluders our reflectors are these big
cubes right and we do treat them
separately but they're always in the
same place right so they're separate in
our implementation but they're not
separate in terms of their actual
spatial distribution our reflectors are
always these rectangular solids and our
collectors are always on the face of
them and they're tightly coupled
together
right and that I think was our that was
our mistake that I think that
fundamental misunderstanding
we're not misunderstanding I guess just
fundamental bad decision that we never
experiment that our way out of I think
is wire lighting is not where it should
be so let's talk about what I mean by
that let's say that instead we went with
a more traditional lie probe approach
what would that look like well what it
would look like is in the world you know
we've got sort of maybe a little dungeon
area here and we know that there's tons
and tons and tons of these reflectors
everywhere right
you know it's tons of cubes all over the
place right well we had to distribute
collectors proportional to the number of
a reflectors that means that even if the
optimal lighting sampling for this area
would just be to strew a few lighting
sample points in this whole region and
blend between them we were instead
massively over sampling these areas
right just taking tons and tons and tons
and tons more samples than we needed to
okay now maybe it would have been fine
to drastically under sample those by
placing a few strategic points and just
collecting from there while still using
the same number of reflectors but we
can't do that with our technique because
our technique always just by default the
way that it worked was there isn't a
separate notion of a collector that
exists outside of a surface right and so
that is really the key problem and the
reason I think it's the key problem is
because it prevents us from placing our
collectors in the most optimal most
minimal fashion right because we
whatever you built as the world you're
locked to distributing your collectors
in that that dense
that arrangement and it means even
stupider crap like we more or less don't
even know whether we should place
collectors on the bottom of a cute look
we could go in there and start removing
them from interior points right that
would be one pass but it still just it's
not it's not enough right and I think we
almost sort of talked about this I said
when we build the world and one of the
reasons we switched over to world
building and didn't do any more
experimentation with lighting was
because I actually said even this
statement I said yeah we need to start
having our world place these points more
strategically even for our own technique
and I think I was right but where I was
wrong was that we should have separated
these things more dramatically than we
did right from the start all right okay
so in the there's approach what they
actually do is they place collectors
just evenly spaced kind of throughout
the world in the interior regions so for
example whereas ours would have taken
let's say from a side view whereas ours
is placing the collectors kind of this
sort of way right theirs is placing the
collectors like that like in the
interior the other really good thing
about that is you can see when we go to
lighting sprites you can see why that's
more handy too because the collectors
are existing in places that are more
central to where the sprites would be as
well so that they're not just always on
the surfaces which might not capture
some of the things happening in the
height and furthermore you could choose
to get more fidelity by placing say more
of these throughout the volume if you
felt like you needed more collection
right okay
so why didn't I do that to begin with
right would be another question and the
reason is because I failed to understand
a relatively obvious thing in hindsight
but when you're thinking through
algorithms like this it's pretty hard to
know everything and really like
understand it all if you've never
already solved the problem right and
again this is not my this is not my
field right I don't work on lighting
it's not something I do so it was as new
to me as it was to you well possibly not
as new I mean I had written ray tracers
before and stuff like that so the
fundamental Cubs were moving light
around maybe was not as new to me but
you know the computation real-time
computation of lighting inside a game is
not something I ever worked on as a
problem and so it was completely new to
me and that's again one of the reasons
why the understanding isn't necessarily
there to just do the right thing right
away okay so the thing that I was
getting hung up on was the you know the
real-time computation of it so in my
mind I was like well if I actually place
a collector here that's you know and
it's hanging out in the middle of
nowhere how do I actually compute its
value in real time because the only way
in my head I was like the only way I can
really get lighting samples into this
thing is I've got a light source
somewhere I've got a shooter ray out
from this thing bounce it around a bunch
of times ray tracing style and
eventually get back to the light source
that's a nightmare I'm like that's gonna
take forever in real time that's never
gonna converge frame the frame or even
cross multiple frames that's like a very
expensive operation forget it it's not
gonna work right so I was like oh our
collectors and our reflectors have to be
the same surface so that we can sort of
do a more radiosity thing where light
sticks to things every frame and then
gets reradiating out right got to do it
that's in my head you and I'm saying but
actually there's a really simple obvious
answer as to why you don't have to do
this that I just didn't consider and
what that is is it's just like you know
duh use the probes during casting now I
don't know why I didn't think about this
I think it's just because in my head for
some reason I was like thinking that you
can only use approach the real-time
lighting and that for the raycasting
stage but duh
don't do that just use the probes all
the time that way you just send out one
probe cast you take the point that you
hit and then you do the actual summation
using the existing light probe state to
figure out what that lighting value
should be
that's all you actually have to do right
and so that allows you to do the exact
same thing I was doing which is having
all of the surfaces have an incremental
state that you can sample you just do
the same thing you do during the
real-time lighting right very very very
very simple and I don't know why I never
thought of it I literally never thought
of it because the only reason I thought
of this this time is I recently saw a
paper in the journal of graphics tools
called you know bla bla bla and
something indirect light computation
real-time something something right and
I was like ah they're doing real-time
ray tracing of light probes in this
paper and I'm like let me go read the
paper and see what they did for this
problem because I'm like this is the
thing that's like stuck in my head as to
why I didn't use light prayers I'm like
I don't know what to do and I just get
to that part of the paper expecting
something important and they're just
like during computation when we hit a
surface we just use the existing light
probes from the previous frame to
compute the lighting
and I'm like like why didn't I think of
that right and again it's just like
brains aren't as logical as you think
they are right a lot of times it's just
like you're randomly trying to think of
ideas and sometimes you hit upon the
right one and it's very simple and you
think I'm so stupid why I'm think about
that bits like that's just not brains
right it's just not brains and that's
why reading papers so useful right
because there's so many more people
trying so many more things someone's
gonna figure out the answer if it's out
there but it's not necessarily gonna be
you so read the paper right and so we
really don't need to know anything else
like that paper is a good it's a good
paper actually it's mostly about more
about GPU tracing of light probes but it
has the answer we actually wanted and
it's not even a thing they actually
cared about it I think it's something
that I I could have really read probably
previous papers and figured it out right
but it's like this is just the one I
happen to see I was like I should go see
what they do cuz like obviously they
know something I don't but it's like
barely right it's like it's it's
something I should have thought of so oh
well you know life goes on you can't win
them all but given that is so simple to
do
I think that makes it sort of
overwhelmingly a good idea to sort of
move just very slightly
I mean basically not that big of a
change over to their system because that
would allow us a tremendous amount of
opportunity for speed increases in two
ways one it simplifies the description
of our collectors so we could get rid of
that expensive stuff we're doing about
seeing like which one of the points
should get which amount of return and
stuff like that so we can switch our
collectors to a more standard just
straightforward like Cube collector kind
of a model or something right
and not have to have like these like sub
points on the cube and garbage like that
so that's great and it also then allows
us the really great sort of fringe
benefit of letting us have our
collectors be spaced as arbitrarily as
we want
throughout our volume without them
having to have any particular
correlation to the rest of the the rest
of the scene they give me place by any
algorithm we want and they can be
completely D correlated and so that we
can basically just fine-tune that as
like a separate lever if that makes
sense right alright so so again just a
small little mental block there and I
think there's potentially a lot that's
unlocked by just realizing just sample
the light probes when you're casting and
that just gives me a huge tool I just
didn't have right
all right so that's all I really want to
do but there's a lot of complexity in
there that we need to start addressing
so there's gonna be a lot of code it's
gonna be several weekends so don't fool
yourself it ain't gonna be quick and the
reason for that is there's just a lot of
additional things that we're gonna have
to work out as we go and one of those
things I would argue probably the most
important thing is one that again we
probably want to go read some papers on
after the fact to probably get something
that's gonna be a little bit better than
what we do because you know what we do
is it's not gonna be as good as the
whole graphics community working on on
this problem there's a lot of good
people doing a lot of this stuff and so
they're gonna come up with better things
but I would like us to try it in
handmade hero fashion
I always think we should try it
ourselves first because that's part of
the learning process you wanna learn how
to do things yourself as well as learn
how to take information from other
people and implement it and so we would
not try things first and then follow it
up with a look even though in the real
world we might say like we know we're
not gonna come up with the best thing so
we'll just go read it right that's a
difference between educational stream
and a stream where we're just trying to
be as efficient as possible with how
long it takes us to implement the best
possible thing and so specifically the
part that I think we that's new and we
would have a deduce anyway for our
sprites so it's not really a big deal
that we're having to do it because we
wouldn't I'd do it either way but we now
have to do it right now it can't be
delayed because even if we don't light
our sprites we're still gonna have to do
it that is given a set of light probes
in the world we have to figure out which
light probes we use for any given pixel
on the screen or if we want any given
object etc etc we need to figure out
which light probes to sample be
there could be up to eight if we wanted
to you know if you imagine these light
probes being strand and we wanted to
separate into a volume let me grab my
tablet back here for a second so if we
were to for example say be in a
situation where we had light probes in a
volumetric pattern like this right and
we want to sample something the lighting
in here we might depending on how what
our speeds profile looks like and maybe
graphics card settings who knows we
might want to go so far as a sample from
like eight probes right and do a cubic
you know so a trilinear interpolation to
figure out what the lighting should be
at that point now we may want to mostly
just do four because since we're a
mostly planar game we can probably
optimize it and only really look at
things like a trilinear sample when
we're maybe going up and down stairs we
could do optimizations like that so we
might want to stay with a bot with with
four probes most the time but either way
no matter how many we do it's at least
four could be as many as eight we're
good and want to take those samples and
we need some way of figuring out which
ones to sample because all we'll have
especially if we allow a relatively
arbitrary placement of these all we're
gonna have is just a giant
one-dimensional array of probes I mean
that's it right and so that's really the
thing that we've got to deal with here
and I don't really know how right I
didn't read that part I haven't looked
at how people are doing that cuz I
wanted to think about it and do it our
ourselves on the stream and then we can
just correct ourselves and see like
what's the more you know what's better
than what we did right but
that's the main problem because
everything else about this scheme is
something that we've already implemented
and we're just going to tweak a little
more or less right we're just going to
change our algorithm to separate the
collection and reflection phases or
descriptors that's really all we're
going to do and then we're pretty much
good to go so at the moment anyway we
don't have much to do with to get to
light to a more traditional light probe
model but this part is completely new we
don't have a way of doing this and if
you think about it it's relatively
tricky because you know the naive
approaches would just be probably bad in
both ways so you know naive approach one
then ayiva proach this would be one like
some kind of grid you know what I mean
so basically like you just got this grid
lookup and so you've got to space these
things in a particularly regular way and
the reason that so it's it's like it's
too many
you know probes in the wrong places
right so if we just strewed probes
through the world in a regular pattern
well the lookup becomes trivial but the
it's not putting probes where we want
them so we would much rather have a way
of placing the probes in a pattern
that's more amenable and allows us to
place them flexibly to concentrate them
in areas we want and not in areas we
don't write so you know that doesn't
necessarily mean it's out it just means
it's kind of questionable right two
would just be like linear search right
and that's just not going to cut it
either because that would have the
graphics card or somebody plowing
through on a pixel-by-pixel basis if we
wanted to do per pixel lookup or
sampling heaven help us that would
implies some really nasty sampling of
like you know potentially like a
thousand of these things you know that
we're looping through every time and
that's obviously unacceptable per pixel
now whether it would be acceptable in
some non per-pixel ways so like we look
it up you know per element or something
and so an entire element just loads into
the constant store the eight light
probes to sample and then it renders the
thing yeah okay
you know then something really naive
might just work you know we're burning
some cycles we don't need to burn there
but it would work and furthermore it
would become not particularly bad
because we could use a spatial partition
right to speed that up really trivially
because if it's only happening once per
element the spatial partition doesn't
even have to be good it can just be real
basic you can chop that down to like 20
or 30 and then linear search and refine
right so you know that method seems like
I guess what I would say is it seems
totally doable even though it's naive it
just may not give us as good a lighting
quality as it could because we can't
transition from one probe set to another
probe set for things that straddle the
probe boundaries so for example if we
have a relatively large sprite that's
sitting you know kind of like that
what we would like is for it to switch
as it crosses this plane we'd like it to
switch to starting to use these probes
as it moves across in much the same way
that we would by linearly filter a
textile as we move across this axial
boundary we want to switch to sampling
from the next set of texels over we
would want to do the same thing here and
so the problem with these is this
creates a burden on our world placement
and management and probably on our
lighting as well because there's too
many probes being placed and so it's not
optimal
this means like no per-pixel right so
this is like bad placement potentially
too many this is no per-pixel
right you know we could definitely do
something naive if it wasn't per pixel
but if we wanted to do something per
pixel or forget it it's not gonna happen
right so so that leaves us with the
question okay
let's analyze our our situation here and
figure out if there's something we could
do you know some way we could get
ourselves to a point where per pixel at
least seems plausible meaning we could
make an argument that we wanted to
sample per pixel the lighting and so you
know GPUs are very fast nowadays there's
some lookup work we could to certainly
scheme one could be per pixel right I
mean if you think about you know there's
a reason I wrote this on this one only
if it was something as simple as just
look at the world coordinates of this
pixel and you know convert to the eight
cells and look those up directly in a
like 3d texture to get yourself a
problem you know or whatever no problem
right so we do we know that there are
things simpler and simple enough that a
reasonably fast graphics card could
definitely do them per pixel and the
question is just can we make a scheme
that can that isn't as naive as just a
grid lookup
so that we can get the benefits of
something that has good placement but
that doesn't actually require you to use
some really complicated lookup that's
gonna be too pricey right um and the
answer there is I don't know the answer
is there I'm not sure right if we look
at the back of the envelope calculations
on stuff like that you know we've done
some of these you know before if we
looked at having some kind of a voxel
oops to 6 by 2 to 6 by 2 to 6 if we
lookup texture on the card that we like
you know update periodically it's not
the end of the world right a 64 megabyte
texture which would be and in fact we
don't really need that it probably like
a 32 because we would only need a 16-bit
index you know so if we had to write
like looking at our lighting transfer
information it wouldn't be the end of
the world to send down a 32 megabyte
texture every frame that was the
lighting location and furthermore if we
needed to compress that further we could
actually generate that texture ourselves
probably on the GPU directly using a
more efficient list so for example if we
wanted to we could probably send down
just a linear array of our light probe
locations and then we could have the GPU
spam those light probe indices using the
location by rasterizing a single
primitive per light probe load
patien thus creating like a voxel fill
right so we could if we want to even use
the GPU itself to voxel eyes for us
which would allow us to send out a more
compressed representation if that if
that 32 megabytes was proving onerous to
transfer for some reason which it
probably shouldn't I mean the bandwidth
to the graphics card is pretty good but
you know you don't want to stress it out
too much
for obvious reasons so you know I do
think a direct lookup isn't out of the
question because what we could do is
rather than trying to pack all of the
information into an actual voxel which I
think might be too expensive for us to
do what we could do is just pack our
look up that the minimal amount of
information necessary to look up into
some other structure into the voxel and
you know maybe that would be sufficient
and I suppose now that I'm thinking
about it a little bit more sort of a
little bit more directly it does seem
like that would be pretty easy to do you
know we already had a scheme in here
earlier on where we looked up lighting
in a voxel pattern right so it's not
it's not really something far fetched
one of the problems that will definitely
have is just you know figuring out how
that voxel is partitioned and aligned to
make sure that we get good use out of it
but as long as we create you know I mean
if you look at the world as it stands we
probably wouldn't need to place sample
points like inside a given volume here
we just the lighting fidelity is not
supposed to be particularly good it's
just was to give a reasonable
approximation to the lighting so if we
think about it it probably isn't
particularly difficult to imagine the
lighting just being no more dense say
than inside one of these tile regions
like a normal room region here you know
we wouldn't have more than eight light
samples in the densest case you know
what I'm saying and if that were so we
can see pretty clearly one two three
four five six seven eight well how many
and we let's zoom out let's get the
biggest possible view here that we can
and so we look here what have we got
like one two three four five six seven
eight nine 10 11 12 13 maybe so figure
something let's just say something like
60 across and so even a 128 voxel that
was screen oriented right would have
more than enough fidelity to record the
amount of lighting we would really
require and Nyquist wise if we bump that
up to tip t6 which is the calculation I
just did were more than covered depth
wise I don't know but I would say
probably the same thing 60 deep tiles I
mean we're not trying to have that much
field of view here so that should be
more than enough as well so I would
think that if we use sort of like a
screen space kind of voxel and if we
wanted to you know we could just like I
said rasterize that and the GPU every
frame even so just using a light probe
list that we already were sending down I
think we've got a good shot of that so
my assumption is that maybe voxel lookup
because we know that a graphics card can
do that really easily you know what I'm
saying take this method and combine it
with this method so we're just basically
saying use a voxel and into the voxel
just write the closest light probe to
that voxel right I think that might be
good enough
yeah I'm saying and so let's just try it
let's just try that and what we can do
for starters right is we can draw all of
this stuff mostly CPU side really slowly
and just get it working in an
environment where we can debug it and
then when we're sure that everything is
working within a reasonable degree of
satisfaction at that point we start
moving these things to the GPU one by
one and we can still leave lighting CPU
calculation CPU side using the exact
same techniques that we're using right
now and I think that would probably do
it right so I think I hope I hope that
gives us what we need all right so let's
start down there we're not going to get
very far today we don't have a whole lot
of time what do we got an hour and a
half maybe
no just an hour I think so we're not
gonna get very far today but like I said
it's gonna be a multi weekend project
that's fine lighting is very complicated
it's probably the hardest thing there is
to do in graphics and so you know to be
expected loading up handmade Hiro just
gonna do a quick builds here make sure
everything's up to date and correct
looks like it so I'm gonna go ahead and
open up our lighting routines here and
just start to kind of get a little bit
more I'm gonna sort of work towards
there slowly so I think the first thing
I want to do is I'm just gonna more or
less like turn off lighting in the
actual game and I'm gonna focus on
creating the lighting probes themselves
as the important part of the problem and
I'm going to ignore the gather for a
little bit because we need to sort of
take it
one step at a time so if I go to the
OpenGL renderer first and we start to
pull out like I'm going to go to the Z
bias program if we start to pull out the
part where we're actually sampling
things here you can see our fragment
code and the way this is working you can
see the fetch and sum here where it's
summing up the lighting what I'm gonna
do here is I'm just gonna have this stop
doing that operation
so rather than sampling from these
pieces of light information that we had
I'm actually not going to do that
sampling and we're gonna revisit that
later when we're ready to go right
so this lighting disabled part of things
that I'm just going to turn that on and
we're going to just require that the
lighting be disabled all the time as we
go so in here where are we here here we
go lighting stable so I'm just gonna
hard code that now so lighting disabled
is always off in our shader it's never
gonna do that summation and so when I
run the game we should now see that
everything is always full bright
everywhere right so we are computing the
lighting still so that I'm not actually
setting lugging disabled to true because
the rest of the lighting is actually
running and you can see that here
compute like provocations still doing
its thing but while we're at it we're
gonna turn that display off so that it's
not interfering with our ability to
visualize what the world is actually
looking at looking like from time to
time as we send down like colors for
things which will help us potentially
debug stuff right so the next thing I
want to do is I want to introduce an
entity a special entity type into our
system that we can use to do light
probing
and this entity would just be literally
a light probe nd so as we kind of walk
around in the world I want to be able to
draw out like I want I want the room
generation code right to be spamming
down some light probes that we can use
for light sampling and at first we can
do that in a pretty haphazard fashion we
can even just spam them every tile that
doesn't have a wall on it can have our
light samples in it and we can just go
from there
now one of the things that we don't have
right now and I don't know why I thought
we had it a while back but we don't
actually seem to you can look here and
even if I expand everything out I'm not
seeing it in the lighting we used to
have a way of displaying like and it's
yeah just I don't know where it went
we used to have a way of displaying some
statistics and those statistics are
pretty important I would like to see
lighting information displayed here and
it's not so I'm gonna try and go in and
get some of that back because as we
create this sort of new pass on the
system I really want to have some way of
making sure that we can measure it as we
go I don't want to be completely flying
blind here I don't want to not know how
many samples I have how many collectors
I have versus like we had that
information at some point we got rid of
it and I know I want it back right okay
so here in the lighting system somewhere
we're pushing some information and we're
just not pushing that particular piece
of information I don't know why so here
you can see for example we've got debug
values total cast initiated total
partitions tested all of this crap is
stuff we want and I'm not seeing it so
that's that's what we want to do and I
think the main reason is because we kind
of got rid of right went in there we're
not opening up the lighting bracket as a
thing that we should be sort of storing
it as
so I'm going to go ahead and look for
that particular debug output just to see
where it actually is so let's see here
that is not what I'm talking about where
is it here it is so you can see here
we've got some nonsense about the debug
lighting block with you know this sort
of stuff here I and this is what I want
but it's not where I want it might be
the right way to put it
so what I'd rather do and I don't
actually know if this is the right way
to do it but it seems like good enough
at the moment it's a Miss gonna stuff
this in here and I'm going to like
display my loops my lighting information
as part of this system right so where we
were doing this stuff here I'm just
going to go ahead and open that up
and I'm gonna put that in here right
like so
and I'm gonna start building up like
what we're printing out in terms of that
information I think that part right
there should just work probably and now
we should be getting those stats but
there's some other stats I'll go gather
up as well just so we can output those
into the lighting okay so there you can
see more what I was looking for right
now we've got like how many times we're
recasting rays how many partitions of
our sort of octree let's not an octree
it's more like a bounding volume
hierarchy of our BVH what are we testing
here how many partitions forecast are we
visiting how many leaves
how many partitions per leaf all that
kind of stuff right so you know
essentially what we're looking at here
is well we can probably speed up this
stuff because it's gonna be a little
simpler than it was before
but really what we're trying to do here
is maybe get this number down right so
total castes initiated we would like to
get that number down at least by maybe a
factor of two so that we and and really
where that's going to come from largely
is reducing the number of samplers that
we actually have to cast hopefully
that's what we're trying to do anyway
so again just want to collect that data
so I can make sure that we actually are
reducing the number and not increasing
the number so I'm gonna go through here
and just see I don't know where else we
have a debug value out I may already
have that number I'm not sure so yeah
you can see lightbox counts like this is
what I'm actually looking for here I
don't know if I can just add those over
there so we can have it all in one place
that would be nice I'm not sure if we
can or camp I'm gonna try and just see
if I stick that in here so do we know
this information at this point I'm not
sure here we do oh we don't we don't
have the group we don't have this so we
need that that group there compute light
propagation where does the group come
from
it's just the render group there
and that information doesn't actually
look like it's yeah coming so um I guess
I'll just get rid of that I don't know
we may have that in the lighting
solution anyway yeah so box count is
that right so I think we don't really
need that so I think we're okay
seems reasonable all right so let's take
a look at what we're what numbers were
actually seeing here so if I look at my
lighting you can see here what the
numbers are that we're actually pushing
through the system so we've got 445
boxes I guess that are coming into the
system via the lighting volume here and
again that lady volume is not all of
this right it was just the visible
region so forward in 45 boxes if we
looked at how many there would actually
maybe be in this area that comes out to
sixty ninety seven points I mean I don't
really know but just eyeballing it
getting that number down should not be
hard if each one of our lighting samples
and we I think we can get away with
fairly few maybe just two per tile
possibly even just one per tile but two
per tile maybe if we got down to like
two per tile roughly
I mean I think let's say we got it down
to like two per tile which I don't think
would be too bad if we if we got it down
to like two per tile then I think we're
looking at something more like three
thousand points maybe which is you know
cutting that in half because each the
point we slept a sample in each of the
directions although actually if we treat
each one as a single point we may be
able to get that even further because
they're not really points anymore
they're they're sort of omnidirectional
so when we cast we can cast in arbitrary
directions and for each cast we just
know which sort of lighting direction it
contributes to yeah yeah all right so I
think I think this should be pretty
reasonable so if we look at our lighting
solution at the moment really this is
the part that's going to change so this
point count extended point count points
initial PPS emission PPS this is the
stuff that really has to be changing now
for our immediate purposes what we
should probably be able to do here is do
the minimal amount of change by making
our lighting points now come from
individual light sample volumes and
those sample volumes would have exactly
one point on each of the six faces of
the cube in question right so let's
start down that road the first thing I
would need to do is I need to start
placing these things in in the first
place right and so you know we're gonna
have to have something where we can
place one of these things down so that
entities can have like a brain type of
sampler or something right however I
don't really know if I
want to quite do it that way and the
reason is because our lighting sampling
is really pretty sensitive to where you
are in the environment how you would
move around if we had a tile that was
moving up and down right we would
probably it was kind of floating we
would probably want the sample points to
float with it and the reason that I say
that is because otherwise it floated up
too high it might it's self occlude that
sample point by like entirely
encompassing it right now what we could
do is say that encompassing a sampling
point is fine
because you're not really gonna block
that sample point from shooting rays out
um is that true if we don't if we allow
you to shoot out of a volume then I
guess that's fine so I guess I guess we
can just do it this way right so if I
said okay there's a type of brain that's
just called a light probe right and I
place it in the world and that's the end
of it you know I'm saying I I don't know
maybe that will just work and I can add
those to the world right now so what I
would do there is when were in the room
gencode you can see here we've got two
things one is like generate apron that
puts down tiles and then the other is
generate room that puts down tiles I can
just place light probes and off we go
plus I can be even a little bit more
squirrely about it and say well actually
when I'm doing this room generation I
could place light probes more densely
areas where you would actually go and
then like I'm generating the apron I can
place them much more sparsely because
maybe we don't care if the lighting out
there is particularly good right because
we know it's just sort of like ambient
nonsense that's not really the focus of
your attention you know um so that seems
pretty good too so let's start by just
placing probes that are in rooms so that
we don't place them in the apron anyway
and we'll go from there so in here where
we place like where we actually put
things down I think all I'm really gonna
check is whether or not something is a
wall and I'm just gonna say like I don't
want to bother like putting probes on
walls yet we may need to do that for a
collective we may need to collect data
on the like up maybe above the walls or
whatever we may need to do some of that
so this is not a final thing but I would
like to sort of say this wall height bit
I want to know whether I'm on a wall or
not and if I'm not then I place one of
those things down so maybe I say like
okay the traversable here there's also a
like on wall equals false on wall equals
true and so then down at the bottom here
in fact this can also sort of be done
this way
so then finally when I get to the end
you know and everything sort of been
done I can just say alright if I was on
a wall maybe I'm gonna add an entity
here and that end ease the light probe
and the place that I'm gonna add it is
just sort of in like the center point of
this thing and when I say Joe should I
add one should I add two I don't really
know what I'm really considering there
is should I have like one low one and
one high one so that we collect
different lighting information that we
can use to sort of see what's the
difference between high and low I kind
of have a sense that maybe we do want to
do that and so you know maybe I'll I'll
really do that this should be not by the
way so I made me want to add two light
probes and one one high probe one low
probe and I want to add those in
locations that make sense based on the
positioning that I see here so what I'm
going to do is say that those those
light probes are going to be added at a
certain understanding of the base and a
teepee I would like to sort of take that
and say to the sort of the basis PE for
this thing is before I've done any of
this kind of like weird offsetting of it
like the random unilateral parts of this
for example and I'm gonna use that as
sort of my basis right so I want to add
these at the basis P but I want to
offset them by different amounts here
largely just Z differences where I'm
going to add these light probes I think
that's really all I need to do I'm gonna
pass the generator down here as
something I use when I'm adding the
light probes but other than that I think
we're good and so when I add this in
what I want to do is I want one of the
light probes to be low and one of the
light probes to be high the low light
probe you know is going to be
[Music]
you know I don't know what these numbers
should really be I I'm not sure but
we'll tune them in a second whatever
they should be you know they're gonna
look something like that right so
there's one that's like high and one
that's low you know what I mean
so we'll look at where they get placed
and we'll figure out we can even make
them proportional to the height to the
floor height as well other things like
that as we go but anyway in fact let me
just add that in there as well so we'll
basically take however high you know the
Z height is to these things and we'll
we'll multiply that out right so I don't
know something like this I'm not really
sure but this is just to spam these
entities into the system so that we you
know have a way of setting up an initial
sampling that we could then use for our
lighting and at first it's not going to
do anything right it's gonna be
completely useless but then as we go
it'll be more useful all right so in
here we've got where's our oh I don't
want that file I want an image and I'm
like where's all our underneath
dimensions so here we go if I want to
add one of these
saucy gentlemen right
I just I'm saying here it's the position
of our light probe I'm gonna add that in
like so I'm gonna set its brain ID to
the special brain ID for light probes
I don't remember what type brain light
probe and honestly I don't think there's
anything else we actually need it's just
the position in the ID and that's it I
think at the moment so that's going to
add a bunch of these light probes to the
scene in theory that should just work
but of course we won't actually be able
to see any of them right to actually
need the soap this is totally wrong
probably want it that way is this
redundant no it's not alright so that's
really all I wanted to do and I'm gonna
have to go past that region down
okay
I guess this is so I guess when I'm
looking at this to the brain slot thing
so when we had a sort of that's right
because brains are sort of allocated on
an as-needed basis and we don't really
need to allocate anything for this
particular brain so when we actually
look at this what we wanted to do here
is say that this is a special brain slot
not a brain ID and then I think we're
good to go there
okay so this needs to take the region
these need to pass the region down and
then I think we even added the light
probes to the system and that's a good
thing but we wouldn't see him so if I
run now they don't draw so you know
they're effectively not there right so
what I need to do now is have some way
to visualize those things and so inside
the world mode I'll probably go ahead
and have a global here for for rendering
that stuff if we look inside our
lighting we sort of already had this
stuff like show reflectors show
visibility that stuff so if we hop out
to the Global's here which is that's not
what I'm looking for here we go so if we
look at this stuff this is what I would
probably want to modify our global
controls for this sort of thing
why I haven't used these at all I don't
know we added them in there and just
haven't really done much of them so I
don't need I don't actually even know if
anyone's using these right now I think
they're probably old news at this point
yeah so really what I want to do is
change those into something we actually
care about now
so this global renderer lighting show
reflectors nonsense and I don't even
really need it to do
because you know we don't need to name
it anything weird like that either
because as you can see when you put it
in the lighting system now it just shows
up normally we didn't do the underscore
parsing nonsense that we sort of had
suggested we would do well we did it but
we don't need it
so what I'd rather do here is just say
let's make this a little bit more easy
you know a little bit easier to
understand so maybe this can just be
called global lighting and then here I
do like show probes something like that
and this way we have some understanding
of whether or not it's going to be
happening but we can also always like
turn it on and off and so if I go into
the world mode here you can see where
that stuff is you know being IFFT
upon actually I don't really remember
I thought we'd done some weird nonsense
with pound Defiance for these as well
but I guess we switch to not doing that
anymore too many things in handmade hero
anyway so if I take a look at what's
going on in the rest of the code here
you can kind of see where we do some ifs
on these sorts of things what I would
like to do is before we you know finish
rendering the world if someone asked us
right so if we had like you know global
lighting show probes I want to loop over
the probes in the in the world and draw
them now it occurs to me that since
we're already looping over entities
anyway maybe really what I want to do is
inside the entity system while we're
drawing the stuff say oh is this a you
know is this one of those right so when
we're doing stuff like drawing
traversals or drawing who knows what if
we're in global letting show probes mode
and
this entity happens to be one of those
special ones which I don't actually
remember how we like to test for that
it's I guess it's just brain stuff okay
so if we just create something here and
it's like is light probe and we test it
the same way we were testing before then
what we can do is say well special case
these guys when we see them come down
the pipe will push a little cube on
there right now that just lets us know
they're there and later we're gonna want
to do something better than this because
we're gonna want to actually show what
the lighting is but otherwise you know
we should be good to go
and in here I don't really want to do
anything special other than use the the
exact entity P so that we don't get
confused about where this thing actually
is right I also have no idea what that
3.0 is but it's probably the radius of
our cube that's true
um no I am incorrect the first parameter
with the v3 there is so that's the
Lighting Store and the Z bias all right
well that's fine
so anyway point being pretty simple just
gonna push this thing on there and we'll
see if we can see anything show up so if
I go ahead and run now here is the debug
display we can see all the cubes I guess
what I would say is the low ones look
pretty good the high ones look way too
high
other than that no problem so I think
what we want for high gather there is
maybe like not so aggressive if we take
a look at this maybe we knock that down
to just like 0.5 or maybe we knock it
down even further than that because we
really want fairly low samples in both
cases we just want a little distribution
so we can see the difference so that
seems a little bit better to me right so
I think that's good let me hop out to an
area that actually has also the Z bias
looks like it's causing a problem there
I don't know why close the game let's
turn that off
so there's all of our of our saucy
gentlemen if I hop along out to an area
that actually has some room stacked on
top of each other I could get a sense
for like what's getting probed there
which would be good so I'm just gonna go
down to the stairs and take a look so
here's the stairs and I'm gonna kind of
just take a look at where those are
getting added so that seems good but you
can kind of see because of the stairs
we're gonna probably want to fix that so
that the stairs have the sampling placed
more strategically on them so that part
needs to get updated there if you're a
stairwell I think that's the only thing
we really need to modify let me go ahead
and do that it's probably pretty
straightforward to just use the
stairwell modification so this here I'm
thinking maybe looks more like this
right
so that way we apply that before we look
at the basis fee for that thing that
would give our stairwells more of a the
lighting probe we'll follow the stairs
down because we don't really need
there's not gonna be things like
hovering up in the like higher area of
the stairwell hardly at all if ever and
so we don't really want the lighting to
be primarily sampled in the areas where
people aren't we want them a sample
primarily there's people are and then if
you're outside of that region where
people are well then we'll interpolate
and get a worse answer but we want like
most of the time where you're standing
where you're gonna be standing most of
the time is where we want the lighting
to be sampled right that's just kind of
an obvious statement okay so if we look
at how many lighting samples were strewn
eight were like sort of spewing out into
the world they're one of the things I
would like to know at this point is how
many entities
suppose we actually just took all of the
lighting that's in that entire gigantic
region
how many entities would that be like how
many light probes are in the scene right
now for every last thing that we saw
there right so if we look in here and
save for every entity and I assume the
active flag would stop anything when we
iterate all enemies how is that actually
working yes so that's a Turing of the
hash larkey so that's only the things
that are in the active sim region not on
the entity cache so that's good so let
me go through here what I want to do is
just take a summation and I'm just
curious like how many light probes we've
got because I have no idea right so tell
me how many light probes we have when we
go through here and off we go
right now I'm gonna go ahead and do this
even though I don't know if I actually
want to do it this way
in the end but so that I can facilitate
that summation I'm gonna go ahead and
sum the light probes even if we're not
showing them and then what I'm gonna do
is just output that piece of information
so inside the lighting I've got this bit
of sauce here I'm just gonna reopen that
lock and I'm just going to dump that
light probe right so the light probe
count now will just tell us like how
many there are in the entire scene let's
take a look at that
okay so just looking at that hopefully
that can give you an appreciation for
just how much better this scheme
probably can be even if we sample a high
and low which we may not even really
need to do I don't know but high and low
on every interior square gives us only
slightly more light probes than the
total number of boxes in just the
lighting solution region so remember I'm
counting everything now in here right
all of these interior points in the
whole thing not just that small
rectangular section and so that
potentially right there is knocking
things down to really much more
manageable number so coming out into a
place where we have a lot more on the
table so let's get to like a really much
more dense densely populated region if I
can here right so getting up to much
more densely populated region again it's
not even twice and in terms of its
comparison to the point count if we
multiply this number by six one for each
face of the cube we are still gonna be
below right so even just just that we
could in less computation cost we could
do our whole sim region
the whole thing we could do with these
probes at two per tile and if somehow we
could manage to get it down to one per
tile which we might be able to do I
don't know that might be unreasonable
because it might not give a good I I
don't know that we really we probably
can't let's just start with that because
we need some gradation from low to high
to give it some shading to so you can
see like the difference between those
two things
so we kind of want to have two I think
regardless and that's just just the way
it's going to go but I
you know what we also could do though we
could also not sample it completely like
we could have our light probes these
sort of longer and sample them in a way
that like takes a gradation into account
from high to low without actions and do
a completely new set of work but who
knows anyway so when we look at that
right that gives us a really good piece
of information here that suggests this
could be a pretty handy way for us to
improve what to improve our lighting
just in terms of sheer count right
because now we could simulate for the
same cost but less even cost we could
simulate the entire sim region's worth
of lighting so that's great okay so now
let's think about this a little bit more
twenty five minutes hmm
I'm not really sure what I can do in
only 25 minutes that would be
particularly productive because like
sort of the next logical steps of this
are going to be a little bit more fancy
[Music]
so I guess one thing I could do is build
the voxel that's not too hard and we
could start to verify that the voxel
that building the voxel is plausible
okay so let's think about this so if we
actually I guess the first question is
do we actually want to simulate the
whole sim region or not and the answer
is probably not right we probably only
want to simulate the parts of the sim
region that we actually care about
they're actually in view again just to
keep that number a little bit more
manageable however if we were gonna
let's again let's I'm gonna maybe start
with all sim region anyway though and
then just shrink it down as we go as
necessary if we were going to do the
entire sim region I guess one question I
have is what is the voxel density
necessary to keep the entire sim region
in it without actually having any too
light probes occupy the same voxel right
so what's the like size of a cube
necessary to make sure that that never
happens and we sort of already know I
guess in a sense because our sizes are
sort of based on that to begin with I
think they're based on tiles so if you
take a look
where we form that sim region I where do
we form that sim region
so sim bounds is what we're using and so
we do three times a standard world to
meant the standard room dimension the
standard room dimension is set in the
world mode so I assume okay here you go
so I don't actually know why we're not
using any strengths of the tyldum there
again just laziness or confusion but if
you assume it's seventeen by nine then
you're talking about three times that
much right so you're talking about
seventeen times three in this case which
is pretty darned low is that really the
sim balance
let's take a look
how many cross are we 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 18
19 20 21 22 23 just six twenty seventy
nine thirty
seems reasonable alright so yeah I mean
a 128 by 128 by 128 voxel would be like
way more than enough probably all right
so let's suppose we wanted to create one
of these
so in our lighting solution the first
thing we're going to want to do for
sampling purposes we just have to create
one of these voxels so that we can
sample our lighting and say look at this
particular location what's the closest
thing right and so inside our lighting h
insert our solution here we just have to
have one of these right and this has to
be whatever our voxel dimension for
lighting is so much like we have this
lighting data with nonsense going on
here I would say yeah like as we
solidify like shines this should go away
I do sort of agree that like some of
this goes away but we do actually need
one thing here because this is going to
be fixed it's like our lighting light
lookup voxel dimension right and so
whatever our light lookup voxel
dimension is honestly 64 might even be
acceptable here based on what it looks
like we've got so you know this is I it
looks like it's pretty straightforward
but anyway so if we want to make a light
look up here where we just say okay
we've got a light lookup voxel it's au
16 that's like light index or spatial
light index and it's just a voxel like
so if we want to compute this spatial
light index we just need to you know
create a empty one we then go through
and every for every like one of these
sample points that we have we flood fill
out
index into here right and that's really
all we need to do that's pretty
straightforward that's not too bad but
we do need some additional information
we need to know like the inverse index
dimension and we also need to know the
corner so this thing kind of needs to
you know it needs to have its its
understanding there I also think we
probably want to do something like this
and just put it in its own sort of space
that's also ii mean these a little bit
more clearly something like this and
then you're not going to confuse if
there's other things that might be
similar there right and then I can just
put this in there
uh or maybe just call this the spatial
probe index something like that and so
so I think that's all we would need for
that and assuming I named it correctly I
think what I can now do if I have enough
time is just sketch out the routine that
would take all of our actual probes and
splat them in here as necessary right
now we can't actually do that because
we're not getting light probes
specifically we're getting lighting
points which is not really what we want
and so we want to go ahead and actually
have some some understanding of probes
specifically so instead of point count
that's this is gonna be probe counts not
point count also I don't really know
what extended point count is
ah that's just so we can build light
looks up like hierarchical light looks
up so that when you do a cast you can
hit larger regions so I don't really
know if that's something we're going to
want to do but it might be and if it was
we would probably do it using this
spatial index so what we'd probably do
is actually build filtered versions of
these right so we would have like each
our light probe would kind of hmm our
light probe index would have like a 128
128 128 version and a 64 64 64 32 32 32
16 16 16 right and we would have to like
sort of filter these up as we go I don't
know if we're really gonna have to do
that but we might and so I do think that
that's I don't know something that we're
going to have to do right I guess that's
that's remains to be seen but will you
know we'll start out assuming well you
know what I could do there is one good
way I could start out assuming that that
we are gonna have to do that and that is
inside the light probe spatial index I
could record the power of 2 or something
other than the count right so we could
we could we could do this in a way that
would allow us to make these flexibly
sized you know we could we could do
something like this so we could do
something like that I'm not sure that
might be kind of a waste of computing
resources if we if it turned out we
never needed one but I suppose we could
always just do that as an optimization
later so maybe in our first pass we will
actually have something like this seems
reasonable
all right so let's suppose that we had
our spacial probe index here and we're
not gonna actually we're not gonna
actually do this sort of subsampling
stuff yet but we will consider it later
what we would need is some way of
creating this thing so we need something
that's sort of like you know add probe
to spatial index and that's going to
take something pretty straightforward
right it would be the index in question
that we're adding right so here's our
spatial index it would take the probes
light you know where in the world is
supposed to be so basically the infinite
decimal point that the light probe
exists at and then if we need one more
thing which is like the radius that you
want to use to kind of splat it down and
you know that's the kind of thing that's
we can sort of adjust conservatively and
it you know we could probably actually
solve directly for it by saying what the
minimum light spacing is but effectively
what's going on here right is we need
every cell in this voxel that anyone's
ever going to sample to return an actual
answer right so leaving leaving a cell
empty means that anything that is in
that area will just be unlit because
when it looks up into there and says
what you know what's the lighting
contribution here there's no probe so
what we want to make sure is that we
don't get into an under sampling
scenario let me let me just draw this
out really quickly because like I said
we don't really have much to do that can
fit in the time left anyway so I might
as well do a more complete explanation
so when we're actually rasterizing these
let's suppose that our grid is too fine
so here's the voxel
right this is our spatial index but the
world generator like only put probes
like here here here and here right what
we want to have happen is when somebody
in this region queries what's supposed
to happen we want them to get ooh you
know what this actually brings up a
problem that we're gonna have with
sampling because what we want you to get
is we want you to figure out be able to
figure out what these closest ones are
but actually if we only point to one of
them that wouldn't be sufficient would
it right I mean it would be so long as
that index also stores what the what the
other closest things were to it right so
you know if this thing always store is
kind of like that bit of information
that I suppose it does all right that's
fine so in here what we need to do is we
need to store at least how to get to one
of these things and we can always say
that if you get to one of them there's
some way to get to the rest of them
right but you need to be able to get to
one of them and if you got to get to one
of them then the problem that we have
here is that if there's grid cells with
nothing in them simply rasterizing the
light probes or filling the light probes
into the voxel for the cell in which
they exist isn't enough we need to fill
them into all the neighboring cells as
well that wouldn't have another light
probe that was closer so what we need to
be able to do here fundamentally is say
for any spatial location that you look
up we need the light probes to
conservatively have filled so that there
isn't any dead zone between two light
probes where you think there's nothing
but actually you should have been
sampling from some of them right so
that's the thing that we need to prevent
and in order to do that we need to
enlarge the region we fill by a
substantial amount potentially right so
what we're gonna do instead is basically
like you know work work this whole thing
in fact maybe we just have you pass in
effectively a rectangle P right it's
like the probe min P the probe max P we
fill that whole area for you you know
I'm saying so that seems like a good
thing do we have a v3 s rebound if it's
v3 you but we don't have a V we have a V
to you but not a v3 you we've got this
one that's sort of different we probably
should just standardize this one and
make this gen v3 a v3 you because that's
effectively what it does like if you
look at these these are actually things
we want you know I mean
like we want all these so in a sense we
may want to promote these gen v3 gen
volume that kind of stuff we may want to
promote those two first class math
citizens now because I think other
people can use them like this code in
particular right so I'm just going to
sketch this routine out inside any of
Sidra block and then we'll worry about
tomorrow starting in on it but
effectively what we want to do here is
something along this lines you know min
index max index right so we want map
into grid and then what we want to do is
loop over this entire set of things
right so we want to then do lookups into
our to our system
something like this
right so we're gonna do some kind of a
loop over each of the elements of this
thing and we want to loop each time
through I guess this part doesn't really
make a whole lot of sense does it but
each time through here we want to
reinitialize the Y any time through here
we want to reinitialize the Z so if you
look at what's going on there I probably
do want to just do this I can't really
put a declaration in there though darn
you for a loop I guess I could just do
it and then bind the value maybe we'll
do it that way so if I just do it you
know the old-fashioned way
then we're just looking at a
straightforward loop over all this stuff
and this is just flood filling that
entire flood flows the wrong word it's
block filling rectangle filling right
that entire region so the min P and the
max be here I'm when you're gonna work
over those I'm gonna fill the whole
region and what I want to do is I want
to say let's look up which light is in
there right so I want to do like find
out what light is in there to begin with
and then like if we're the more
appropriate lookup use us instead of it
right so that's the two things I want to
do so first I gotta get the spatial
index right I gotta like get the
sort of get corner light index or
something whatever we're going to call
that so when we asked for the spatial
partition what's actually going on there
it's gonna return us a pointer to the
cell in question and I'm gonna pass it
you know the XYZ so it would be like
that sort of thing and then when we
actually look at what that is we could
say look if the existing index equals
zero then we definitely want to use us
instead I guess I didn't actually pass
that here so the existing if there's
nothing in there then it should be us
otherwise we're gonna have to look up
that particular light and so we're gonna
have something like this
whatever the existing index is like that
and if you know it's we don't actually
know what the equation is going to be
here but if we're more appropriate than
we would still do it right and so what
we need to then think about is what is
the actual algorithm that we're going to
use to determine who is the most
appropriate light index and the answer
there is just I think whichever the
minimum corner is because if again when
you look at what's happening in this
diagram where we say okay you know the
worst case scenario for this algorithm
is we've got eight probes and we want to
sample all eight probes right so if we
imagine we've got a coordinate system
here
X Y Z then what we want to effectively
do is give you back this index if you're
anywhere in the cube I think right and
then from this index it needs to tell
you what the other eight are if you will
right so effectively you're getting an
index to sort of or block a sampling
block that tells you everything that you
should use for your actual sampling and
I think that's what we want I think when
we go back and do the you know look at
how this is going to go so what we want
to do is see compare effectively we want
to take and look along the axes you know
what we're outside we only have two
minutes I'm not I'm gonna talk about
this we're gonna do that tomorrow
but that's effectively what we're going
to do tomorrow and and then we'll move
on from there
into actually using the thing right I
think we're okay here if I just compile
so we left all right all right so I'm
gonna go ahead and go to Q&amp;A
how far along in the game are we what
percentages you say we're almost done
with the engine so I mean that's I guess
what I would say is we're almost a
hundred percent done with the part of
the stream that is the part that I
wanted to do right which is building a
game from scratch technology wise in
terms of what remains after that
normally you would say well it's zero
percent done because you have to make
the whole game then after that because
that's the game design part of things
and that part I will not like I'm gonna
go do a game but but that like I can't
at that point the stream is it's not
over but it's sort of functionally not
really something I can help you with
it's not something I can really teach so
at that point like hey I taught
everything that I can teach and now
we're just like building a game so we
can say that it can run a game right but
I can't really teach it because you know
it's not it's not really the kind of
thing that I do
concerning picking lighting probes could
you use some sort of proximity hash for
lack of a better term if there is such a
thing something like where the key would
be the location you want to select from
ideally collisions would be physically
close to each other in space or is there
a reason why doing something like this
would not be feasible although and I
think about it when describing sounds a
lot like a 2d array um you know
proximity queries always have to you
know that is what we're doing and when
you say proximity hash it's like well
the only way to really do a proximity
hash is to search some percentage of the
entries in the hash because there's no
such thing as far as I know as a
proximity hash where you just like fuse
the values together and then you always
get the right answer in your first probe
right uh and so you know proximity hash
really what you have to do is just
spatially hash and then do a search for
things in the neighborhood of the
spatial hash usually and so what we're
doing here is trying to be a little more
efficient than that on the lookup side
while being potentially more expensive
on the storage side and the reason for
that is we're aiming for maybe running
this thing per pixel and per pixel all
we're really gonna have I think the
bandwidth to do is one lookup into a
voxel to get the cube we need to
interpolate and then eight looks up
eight look lookups into the lighting
info that's already pushing it right
have you thought about fully Vox lies in
the world and tracing raised in voxels
face
alternatively what about selecting the
probes using frustum voxels like in Doom
2016 so two things one is no I would not
Vox lies the world in trace raising
voxels face the reason for that is no
one's ever actually gotten that working
so if you go look at like voxel cone
tracing and stuff like that it's just
simply not fast enough to do all your
lighting like it just it's just not we
need to be a lot smarter than that we
need you know and you could argue that
maybe if we just did a really low res
version that would be fine but I think
we'd get all kinds of artifacts so in
order to actually make that run with
enough fidelity I think it's just it's
way too dense and just forget it right I
mean it's it that's sparse voxel qohen
tracing it so you can only really use in
in like pretty isolated scenarios I
would say at the moment certainly on the
kind of graphics cards we're targeting
but as for selecting probes using
frustum voxels like Jim 2016 again not
really possible reason is because we
need our lookup to be based on where the
probes are actually placed the reason
doom 2016's system works is because
they're just looking for the closest and
lights so what they do is they say let
me create a voxel a frustum voxel eyes
frustum so basically clip space voxel
and then for each cell of that voxel
I'll just track all the lights that I'll
track the end closest lights and use
those right but we don't really want
that we want you to have the same we
want the voxel granularity to be about
the same as the probe placement and that
probe placement doesn't get sparser as
you get further away
right so so using the frustum I think
would be a bad solution for us even
though it was may be a good solution for
them is it possibly to share your theme
color hex codes probably
so I think that stuff is in misc
so I think this is them
I think that's what you're looking at
we'll light probes only collect from
hits two closest services and as such
would a love with a three-level set up
port I'll always leave the middle one
never collecting any light no so light
probes collect hits from all surfaces
would you think consider hanging the
project over to a games artist a chief
to the next parts no because I mean the
problem with that is there are almost no
good game designers like you know
there's there's probably like five good
game designers in the world or something
like that and I don't know that any of
them would be interested in doing it
right I mean if if I was gonna hand it
over to like Jon blow to do or something
sure but he's busy right so I don't
really think that's a feasible
alternative because I can't think of
anybody who I'd actually who would be
available who I actually think is any
good it's a number of good game
designers in the world it's like almost
none I would say probably most games
that I play I think are fairly and
competently designed like like they just
weren't thought through obvious stuff is
wrong
they don't have much understanding of
what the players doing or why it's fun
like they're just kind of like most game
design tends to be like mimicry like oh
okay you know this is what happened when
we shoot things in first-person so we
just kind of did that again right so in
terms of teaching game design like I
really don't know yeah there's very few
game designers that that I think are any
good and I don't I don't think any of
them would be
interested in doing it interest is the
wrong word maybe many of them would be
interested in doing it but simply don't
have the time right
have you read the recent Morgan McGuire
diffuse di probe paper that's the paper
I was talking about when I said I looked
into it too because I wanted to know
what they did for a sampling real-time
something I was like Oh duh you just you
just use the probes
or enemy component systems really a good
way for any system Jonas said that they
are not really nice but I want to know
what you think about them uh yeah I I
don't I would just defer to John on most
things about that he's because any
systems are just about enabling
designers that's the only reason they're
there and so the same thing I just said
about how I think most game designers
are bad John's one of the only really
great game designers who's also a very
skilled technically adept programmer so
I feel like he's the person you should
ask what an indie pretty system should
look like just kind of period because
he's the only person who a has the
skills to make a good entity system and
B is the user of an entity system right
so I would say take his word for it if
you don't have your own opinion right if
you're looking for someone else's
opinion he's the person whose opinion
you should adopt if you just want to
know my cursory opinion I think it's one
of those cases of putting the cart
before the horse
it's exactly like object-oriented
programming it's prescribing a solution
before you have described the problem
right and so the problem description I
would give for how entity systems are
supposed to work is that given a
particular game design they should have
made it as easy as possible for the
developer of the game systems to express
that design and any component system
assumes a bunch of things about a game
design and makes a bunch of things hard
and a bunch of things easy right that
split is not necessarily a good one
right
and so much like object-oriented
programming it gets the kind of thing
where it's sort of like prescribing a
solution without really thinking about
whether which problems you were solving
or whether you solve them in a way that
you should really be telling other
people to do without first caveat and
saying your problem should look exactly
like this if you're going to use this
solution right
can we do some yeah I programmed me for
the empty seas well we will do some I
mean not really probably anything that
most people consider AI but we will do
some for just controlling how re how the
NPCs left move around and attack e right
so when we when we're doing the game we
will be coding the stuff that sort of
does that
to use for code or outside handmade hero
I used to I don't anymore really I ended
up kind of writing my own editor and so
now I don't but I did for the past five
years or so basically what I found was I
just when I actually sat down and did a
bunch of stuff that I wanted to do in my
customization layer I ended up with
something where the whole editor was in
my customization layer at that point so
then I just moved it into my own
codebase because that lets me now do
other stuff I couldn't do before because
now I can like integrate it into all of
like my emetic code stuff and everything
so obviously I can just kind of go nuts
with it but yeah which by the way is
roughly what I would recommend one of
the reasons I really like for coder is
for exactly that reason it basically
gives you all the tools to build your
own editor right from the start because
you can have an editor up and running
immediately but all of the code that
you're writing is is in C and usable
outside of it so it's basically like I
think of for coder almost as like a
editor making tool kit and then if you
ever want to go really nuts you can
always then just separate your stuff off
from for a coder someday and go off into
the sunset but if you never want to go
that far you don't have to you can
always just continue to use for a coder
as your base editor and not write all
that stuff so it was kind of optimal for
my purposes and I think that's a really
great I wish more systems kind of work
that way because it would be awesome for
example to have like a 3d editor that
you could start with and then eventually
you just move on your own thing as
you've reimplemented everything that you
want or if you don't then you just don't
write so having that like C program
ability just a really big thing that
helps a lot and I really like it so
you sure that paper you mentioned about
light probes yes
so I think this is the blog about it
yeah so there's two things one is this
blog set here that you can get and the
other is the paper that's in journal
graphics tools nope no if this is it
yeah this might be it yeah this is the
Jade yeah yeah yeah the other is this
paper from journal graphics tools those
are ones I was thinking of anyway you
talked about Harvey Potter during
priests dream yes
you said that at a hit you will store
the result in the closest probe no so
you've got it backwards probes shoot
raise and record whatever they hit when
you hit you look up what the lighting is
in the closest probes that's what lets
you use your probes as convector errs
for the light but you don't use that to
say where to store it right
MTS mocks might you need extra
reflectors for the sprites to get better
collection around those areas possibly
but possibly not our for coders source
slices available to the general public I
think so
but you don't actually need a for coder
source license
well you might up until Alan releases
the changes that I I contributed back
the changes that I needed to allow you
to do kind of arbitrary rendering and
stuff but those he's supposed to have
mainlined at some point so once he
releases something with those in there I
don't know that you really need a source
code license right because you know it's
got the stuff exposed that it needs to
expose for you to build your own like
editing stuff on top right and so the
number of times I've had to do something
in the for coder source it was really
only one pass that I did to AB sort of
hooks out for things I needed but I
contributed those back and now they will
eventually be anyone will be able to use
them so I don't know that you would
really need to negotiate a source code
license that said I would assume that
Alan would be happy to do so you know
they're just going to be a lot more
expensive than licensing you know
it's just gonna be a lot more expensive
than licensing it as as an end-user so
you know if you're a company though
that's not something you should do I
mean in our case right we wanted one
because like you don't want to be in a
situation like if Allen just stops
working on for code or Sunday right you
need to be in a situation that you can
keep updating it so you know up until
the point where you're sure you're gonna
completely move off of it to your own
custom thing or something where you're
literally not relying at all on updates
to the core I mean if you're a serious
if you're a company you should license
the source because it's going to be
relatively cheap compared to the cost of
running a company and then you know that
you just have the ability to do whatever
you need and you can go in a different
direction if you need to or anything
else right but as an individual I don't
think you really need to do that like I
said I kind of already did that work for
you so you know unless you're thinking
of some particularly saucy stuff that
that's like well well far afield from
the kinds of mods I made which I you
know I don't know what other people I
guess maybe other people are thinking
the things that are really wacky
compared to what I wanted to do but in
terms of just being able to draw some
stuff to the screen with your own like
rendering primitives you know I
basically added some stuff for that and
it's not crazy like you can't yeah so
you know if you wanted to do like images
and stuff I guess that never made it in
there but but other than that I think it
was pretty good
more Jeff in case each episode soon um
yeah so it really depends on Jeff's
schedule but you know the hope was yes
obviously we just released one last week
well actually this past week everyone
said that on Monday and so we you know
we probably won't be able to release one
like every week but we do hope to have
you know one a month or something coming
out now
why only PayPal and credit card payment
methods for him here
what other payment methods did you want
what do you think about a purpose-built
editor as opposed to a general-purpose
text editor could work directly with a
binary for any other Khanna creation
tool yeah I mean like I said that's what
I did
oh Bitcoin so the reason that we did we
had Bitcoin the reason that we don't
have Bitcoin anymore is because the
transaction cost for Bitcoin ended up
being more than the cost of handmade
hero bitcoins doesn't work it's it's a
fundamentally broken system they're
trying to fix it but it's not good
and so the Bitcoin providers that we
were using to accept Bitcoin payments
just couldn't do them anymore so they're
just not available
wasn't our decision that just option
went away
Apple pay so I don't remember what the
reason is if Apple pay is not on there I
think it had something to do with the
fact that there were certain because cuz
I thought stripe allowed Apple pay but
there are some things we had to do that
I wasn't thrilled about
so Apple pay may happen but it may not
I'm not sure but Bitcoin we had and
Bitcoin just collapsed on itself and
doesn't work so that's why it's not
there anymore
cryptocurrency gonna take over the world
right can't buy a freaking 15 dollar
product with it but but no it's great
all right
why are you listed us rewind evangelists
in braids the reason I'm listed as
rewind event evangelist in braid is
because I think the story goes something
like John's original idea for braids he
had whilst reading or thinking about a
post I had made to a mailing list about
rewind so I really didn't have I want to
say anything to do with the design for
braids look on the witness I remember
talking with John about some puzzles
even some important puzzles and you know
I didn't really have much to do with the
design of that game either but at least
I had some discussions I remember having
about it
braids I feel like I literally had no
contribution to the game design
whatsoever even in a patent that sort of
passing sense of having talked through a
problem with the designer when they were
working on it or something like none at
all
but the reason at least I gather from
John that I am listed with a credit in
that game for some reason was just I had
made a post to a meaningless where I was
talking about how games in general
should just have rewind because like it
treats my time as a player as more
valuable in like look I don't want to
have to replay this section of the game
if I don't want to like why should I
it's I already did it once it's not
gonna change right and so a lot of games
in that time like this is you know
talking not about roguelikes but like of
like Triple A games where you just have
to do this set of things I'm like why do
I have to do this set of things again
it's I already did it you're just making
me do it as punishment for not knowing
how to do the final thing and off we go
and so it was just me complaining about
why games just didn't just have
rewinding in general because that would
just make it more enjoyable for the
player to play these Triple A games
which maybe he's just a statement about
the fact that the Triple A games suck I
don't know but that that email
apparently was somehow related to John
thinking up the idea for braids or maybe
it crystallized some aspect of it I
don't know you should really ask John
it's it's probably more credit than I
deserve the the only meaningful
contribution I actually made to braid
was a code contribution the collision
detector the rounded rectangle collision
detector in there is my code so really
the only credit I should have gotten was
like some kind of like additional
programming by kind of credit but
instead I get a very prominent credit as
rewind evangelists which you know I was
for that email but but I did I didn't
yeah I guess that's just a really
long-winded way of saying ask him I'm
not really sure why I had a credit I
absolutely 100% in my memory had no
design input to braid whatsoever even
even like a passing conversation with
John about a puzzle like I don't
remember a single thing that I ever said
to John about the design of braids that
had anything to do with designing braids
like as far as I remember he designed it
and I played it and that was it
what melius it was some game design
mailing list thing I'm not anymore
I don't even remember what was called it
sounds like you wouldn't be a fan of the
current souls like trend No
so I'm okay with games that are about
execution
for example I loved Ivan Hawkins and the
thousand-and-one spikes because that
game is about execution that is what the
game is about right
it's not about exploration it's not
about talking to NPCs not about solving
puzzles
it's about executing the line right and
getting really optimized executing that
that's what it's about it makes its
unapologetic right and so I'm totally
fine with no rewind in that game because
that's the game is about being it's like
it's like a being a gymnast right it's
about learning to execute exactly every
time and so I'm totally down with that
but the problem is a lot of games
legends of Zelda you know The Witcher or
Red Dead Redemption or you know maybe
not Grand Theft Auto as much but even
Grand Theft Auto even first-person
shooters Call of Duty blah blah blah
they're just not about that they're just
not about execution they're you know
about playing through a scripted
scenario and when I play through the
scripted scenario and the game is three
easy dudes and then a really hard dude
and I never die on the three easy dudes
and I die on the hard dude I don't know
how to kill and you make me play through
the same three easy dudes for no reason
every time that is just not and nothing
I do about those ever improves like I
don't you know what I mean that was the
big thing about a band Hawkins
was like you learned to refine your
movements to make it very unlikely that
you would die in all the places and that
felt really good right and that if you
don't have that aspect to your game it's
just frustrating and annoying right so I
don't necessarily have a problem with
games that are about that or like
roguelikes like binding of issac where
each run is unique totally fine right
because at that point it's like you're
not making me play through exactly the
same thing for no reason but if a game
is mostly about making me play through
the exact same thing for no reason I've
got a problem with it I never played
Dark Souls so whether I would levy that
complaint at Dark Souls I'm not sure but
you know hopefully that explains a
little bit more
all right I'm gonna wrap it up all right
thank you everyone for joining us it
upset a handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with
stories at home you can always go to
handmade hero dot-org and pre-order the
game it comes with a source code so you
can play around with it I will be back
here same time same place tomorrow I
believe so at that point we'll start to
look at actually implementing that
lighting we'll have a full two hours so
we can start to make a dent in it
but again it's probably not going to be
one day thing we're gonna have to spend
a few weekends on it for sure
letting is very complicated it's one of
the hardest things you can do in
graphics so we're gonna take a little
bit of time that's fine but just be be
advised
so we'll start taking a look at that
until then have fun programming and I'll
see everyone on the Internet taking
these everybody