hello everyone and welcome to handmade
here I'll show Rico complete game live
on stream we are kind of in we're in a
bit of technical difficulty land it's
true I my laptop my pet the power port
on my laptop fried itself and so I had
to kind of provision this laptop kind of
in hope that will work and you know I
think we're going I was able to read the
chat during the pre stream so I'm hoping
that everything's fine I don't
necessarily know if everything's fine
but we're doing the best we can under
the circumstances hopefully my laptop I
sent it back for RMA hopefully it will
get repaired and that is sort of a
separate issue so we're going to try and
go we're going to try and forge ahead
here with episode 203 and assuming that
today goes well I'll post the foot full
handmade hero schedule to the tweet bot
and we'll do the rest of the things for
the week if if it turns out to be too
much of a problem maybe we'll take a
week off and come back to it next week
with a repaired laptop hopefully maybe
but anyway where we are at is we were
working on a debug sort of rearrangement
of the debug display and we basically
did all the work for it that we did not
actually get to the point where we you
know we just kind of finished at the
very end of stream so we did not really
get to the point where we could actually
test it out debug it and fix it no that
sort of stuff so that's what we're going
to do today just get that working now I
did have one thing that was stupid on
the last dream last week was a bad week
my laptop died my credit card got stolen
my laptop died at well I could card
number got stolen i should say the
actual physical card never got stolen
but you know how it is with data
breaches and such everyone has your
credit card number is just a question of
when they'll start to use it credit card
got stolen and i like injured my foot so
it's just like bad and so i feel like i
did not do it for a good job talking
about something I was just like totally
out to lunch when we were talking about
trees here in an order in and out of
order walk so I do want to take a quick
second just to like address this and
maybe explain it correctly because I
totally explained it wrong I think on
the last one not that I really remember
what I said
but just pretty sure it's just wrong so
I'm going to kind of correct i'm going
to try and correct that ok so what i
said was that if you're doing a stacked
reversal of something then you're going
to get a breath first thing but that's
not really true what's actually true is
that like the type of stack determines
what's going to happen with your
traversal and i'm not sure why i like my
brain was just frazzled so i just didn't
quite see it that way even though I've
written this kind of code many times
before you know sometimes your brain is
just not on it's not on you know there's
really not if she can say about it so if
you take a look at kind of the case that
I was looking at before we got kind of a
tree and you're going to walk through
this tree then if you think about how
the stack sort of traversal these things
go if you have some kind of stack and
you're going to be pushing things on to
it so you kind of start at the top and
you like push things down as you go then
if you push the first thing on to the
stack right let's say we've got ABC you
know d e f g h right then there's
different ways that we could visit the
nodes in this tree and so you know one
way is we could do a depth first walk of
this tree and that would be like if I
was to do it in this order right as I
come down so it would be like a BD right
so I'd come down this way first all the
way down then I can't go any further so
I come back up and go to the other side
and then be an e right so then I come
back up that's very top because I can't
go any word from there I come down to
see than F then down all the way that
side which is G and then H right like
that so bab Dec fgh now if I was to do a
breadth-first I'd end up in the order
that I sort of said it in terms of the
alphabet right if we do breadth-first we
do all the ones at this level then all
the ones at that level then all the ones
at that level then all the ones of that
level right so we do like a b c d e f g
h in like alphabetical order right
that's how i actually labeled them
originally and the difference between
these two is actually just how you
operate on the stack so like if i push a
onto the stack as a start right because
we're always going to start at the
the tree then really what just the only
thing that determines what the order is
that I get is how I choose to pull
things off of the stack so obviously
there's only one thing on the stack at
first it's a so when it gets pulled off
we're it's going to push his children on
which is B and C right and so then the
question is hmm excuse me the question
is when I pull these things off if I
want a depth-first traversal versus a
breadth-first traversal breadth-first
traversal it mostly depends on what i'm
going to do in terms of who gets pulled
off first right so if i pull off see
meaning i pull off from the top of the
stack then i will get a breath first I
mean I sorry i'll get a depth-first
traversal because if i pull off see i
will then push sees child which is e
right hmm of course it would get pushed
in place like this comes off the sack
right this guy technically came off the
stack if that makes sense traveling have
a good way to draw this may be like this
so a comes on the stack we need to then
pull a off the stack so a comes away
right then we push its children on which
are B and C right then we pull the top
one off the stack would you see and we
push its children on which is e right
then we pull it off the stack and we
take its children which is G and H right
then we process H it has no children we
process G it has their children we
process be it does have children DNA
right and you can see as we did that we
went all the way down first and then
came back up so in order to do the
breadth-first traversal you actually
pull off the front of the stack right so
instead of the top you use the bottom so
you push a on you pull a off that
doesn't change there's only one thing on
the stack but then it pushes B and C on
instead of pulling see you pull be right
so becomes off the stack and the stack
pointer becomes here right so that goes
away then you push on a right you push
on bees children which is de right and
then when you go to pull something you
pull see next because you're always
pulling off the front of the stack so
that goes away right and you
see that that's what does that in order
walk for us so we always pull things off
in the order they were pushed rather in
the opposite order of what they were
pushed and so that's just like a FIFO
first in first out versus a LIFO last in
first out right sort of view of the
stack as a cue right as a thing that
sort of processes items and so I just
want to correct that because that was
just totally wrong my explanation of it
yesterday or not yesterday on friday
thursday now i guess we need to do a
friday stream on thursday was just
totally wrong so that's like a hopefully
a little bit better a little bit clearer
and it end more importantly not
erroneous way of thinking at it because
basically like with a stack it's not the
stock doesn't force you to traverse it
in one way hmm and I really shouldn't
say stack I said more q if you have a
queue you can't reverse it in either way
if you have a true stack meaning you can
only pull off what the top like that
because technically a stack usually if
you say stack you can typically only
pull off the top it typically gets
called a queue if you could pull off
either end right or or not the end you
push on even if you only pull out one if
you can push if you can push on one end
and pull off the other it's typically
called a queue if you have a true sack
actually a true sack also only traverses
in order you in-depth order usually it
does that it does depth-first not
breadth first so that was just just like
I said just a flat-out wrong for all
intents and purposes of what we were
talking about so I'm not sure again
wives think I just kind of frazzled I
guess I'm not sure why I was thinking
that but yeah just getting old probably
the bottom bottom line so anyway if we
kind of go back to him a hero now it
doesn't really have any practical
significance to us in the terms of the
code we wrote necessarily but it's just
important to understand that so that
people aren't confused when they go to
like work with stuff like that so if i
remember correctly we sort of have
things done but not really working
properly like we had done all the code
work
but we weren't quite there yet and so
like if you look we're not drawing
anything here like the game is running
and the debug system is obviously active
but we're not seeing anything right and
and so where are where is our hierarchy
is the first question so what I want to
do here is I want to go ahead over to
handmade debug and see if I can get a
bead on exactly where our hierarchy went
right so let's go ahead and see when
we're doing this this debug stuff what
we're actually looking for here so let's
go ahead over to see here and region
debug and interact a lot to debug
drumming menu there we are I'm going to
go over debug draw a menu and just see
what we've got so we do enter debug drum
a menus loop so we do have a tree right
so we know that at least the tree itself
is not busted and if I look here it
looks like the group is actually set up
there it is right so we've just got some
problem with our traversal not
surprising because we haven't tested it
yet all we did was type it in so if we
look here we are setting the depth of
this thing to we're setting the depth to
one and we're pushing on sort of the
state of the iteration here inside this
while loop Jimmy inside this while loop
we are obviously over a depth of zero so
we'll proceed we grabbed the first thing
off the stack and the first thing off
the stack is going to be that first link
right and it looks like it is the
central or at least it thinks is the
Sentinel right so that seems to me like
that would imply because it looks like
this code is correct it looks like it's
setting these two things properly to me
right because I'm seeing that that makes
me think that maybe it just wasn't built
correctly like it it looks like maybe
the drawing code is not necessarily at
fault at least not yet and that the
problem is actually that the thing
that's supposed to build this is not
actually building it right and so as a
result
when it goes to draw the tree it just
finds it that group contains nothing so
let's take a look at what happens when
the tree gets built at the beginning of
the program and we'll just see if we can
spot what is happening there let's find
out all right here we go so in here when
we first start creating the stuff you
can see here when we begin variable
groups and that sort of stuff I meant to
set a breakpoint and we might actually
start a little bit above this because
this is actually the first place we do
it right so maybe let's start here and
see what happens here so we'll go to the
root group will say to begin a debug
variable group and yeah debug ahead
variable adding our group we know that
works because we saw the root group and
here it is we're going to add ourselves
to the group depth that that looks wrong
to me so wait a minute wait a minute
everyone what are we okay so how do we
when we grab off the group stack what
are we actually looking at we're looking
at the group death itself alright well
honestly that's that's correct so
alright that's fine so we set ourselves
to be the top person on stack at that
depth so off we go when we call begin
variable group now we're going to see
what happens when we try to add one of
these guys it looks okay so basically
the problem is we just yet we just have
it so that it doesn't actually call
debug add variable to group that's the
problem that's pretty much it right we
want it to be doing this and it's not
so I think that's it that may be that
may be the primary source of air my
voice is rough I wish I had a drink I'll
be honest with you drop forgot my drink
never good situation so okay all we
really need to do here when we do debug
that variable is now we just have to
make sure we're calling the right one
which is the one that actually takes the
context and does its thing right what is
happening here oh this was of course our
hmmmm excuse me this is of course are a
little problem of we still have that
weird compile you know we we set all our
compiler variables thing so if our debug
stuff fails we can't actually we get
like a null file here right which is not
the best situation to begin yeah I don't
really know I said that's something we
kind of want to to fix this was kind of
a thing that's on our list to do it's
pretty easy for us to recover from but
it's just kind of annoying and stupid
oops delete tangle um but for now since
we're working on something else I'll
just go ahead and fix it myself this is
pretty basic let's see I'm fine search
for quote make it 0 go back to the
beginning there we go all right yeah so
for now let's go ahead and just see what
happens with our system as it stands
again let's okay so this is good so now
we've gotten to a point where we're a
little bit further down and so we're now
actually eating over variables it looks
like we've still got a bad situation
though we've got a link to an actual
null pointer which would never actually
be possible right that's just purely
erroneous so that just means we're not
quite initializing all of our stuff
right and we have to figure out exactly
where that's happening so I'm just going
to go ahead and look at the tree and
just see for myself
exactly where it's happening so if we go
in I'm going to take a look at this
debug variable skin I'm going to come in
here and take a look at what happens to
that group again all right so we're
going to do big debug ID variable there
and add ourselves to the group add some
of these guys in fact I guess you know
what i'll do i'll take a look at it kind
of post build and i just want to see
what the look of the tree is so here we
go here is the debug state route group
and if i take a look in here i could see
the VAR group which is what it is I look
at that and so the far on this VAR on
this VAR group here that looks correct
right because that should be no because
this is just a sentinel if i come to the
next one well so that's not correct
right it's got another one and the VAR
pointer is no but the VAR pointer should
never be no on these guys so something
is a little bit busted there so let's
see what's going on with that when we do
debug at variable we add advert to group
oh so this is the problem when we add a
debug variable we were never actually
even setting that right we never
actually like are basically our thing
that makes that thing never bothered to
set it so that's not great okay so this
is looking a little bit better now it's
still not great right we can kind of see
that's it's it's it's not quite right
yet but we're getting closer right we're
definitely getting closer and it looks
like to we even have all of our stuff is
kind of working here in the sense that
like all of the the sort of zooming
features and that sort of thing work now
we do have a problem that those things
aren't stored anywhere because we
haven't implemented the cash for our
data yet but the rest of this stuff
seems to be roughly correct right and
that just did a save that just did it
right out so I'm going to look and see
what this and so this worked as well
right you can kind of see that here we
actually did write out all our variables
as well which is kind of nice so that
part was working as
okay so we still need to do some more
work here this is obviously not working
correctly quite yet so let's go ahead
and and see if we can tidy that up art
it looks like we're not really handling
expand and collapse or any of that stuff
and I think that makes sense because we
didn't actually when we implemented this
sort of inorder traversal stuff here we
did it the same way as we did it in the
in the handmade config and so it's not
actually doing any checks I don't think
you know for basically for when it
should and should not descend to
children if that makes sense so if we
look here we've got right hand made
config we've got debug drumming menu
down at the bottom of this guy if it's a
VAR group you can see we pretty much
always push even if the guy is collapsed
which we don't really want to do right
so what we'd rather do here is say okay
we've got handmade give our gut h we
know we were storing these in our view
write debug view and so we knew that we
had the concept that this thing was
collapsible or whatever it was and so
what we want to do is we want to go
ahead and test that right we want to do
a thing where we go like okay I get the
collapsible out of the sky right it's a
view which we already had and so
assuming it's a group we only want to do
it if the view expanded always for now I
guess is the one that will look at this
I think that's the one that we were yet
that's one of the we're modifying at the
moment we want expanded always to be
true and if it is we will descend if not
then we will not right sorry no go
so now if i run this everything or
nothing should be collapsed right but of
course we can't ever actually i think we
probably won't ever actually be able to
do this because when we do the
recompilation step right that will
overwrite our static our debug view
dummy here so I don't know how effective
this actually will be but you know we
could do we could for a minute sort of
just for testing purposes go ahead and
make a single one of these it's actually
in our debug state stuff so we can take
that out of the equation right so we can
basically just say oh there's a debug
dummy in here right and then this guy
just returns the debug state dummy that
way there's no static variable and we
can actually see what's going on right
so that'll work a little bit easier okay
so in theory I feel like I feel like hmm
I see it for a second but then it goes
away and I'm not entirely certain why
that would be that doesn't make quite
the right amount of sense to me so I
want to take a look at that why that's
happening so when we do debug and
interact we set the expanded always
equal to knox may notice that should
only really be happening on that dummy
that one time although oh you know what
the problem is the dummy is kind of
overloaded so everyone's writing to it
including people who are writing the
position of things to it so that
actually makes perfect sense so I think
Babel what we should do rather than
trying to hack it is like actually
finish our implementation of get debug
view for that seems like probably the
smartest thing to do all right so what
we need to do for get the about view for
is we need a way again what we're trying
to do here is store the state of the
interactions with things in such a way
as to make sure that we always we only
store any important piece of state like
whether something collapsed or expanded
but we don't store it hard coded with
the particular variable itself so like
for example we were having this trouble
where we had two different copies of
like a tree of some
kind right or two different copies of
like a bit map viewer and one of them
was supposed to be sized like
differently than the other or something
like this right so we want to be able to
store those two things differently so
what I want to do is I want to just make
it so that whenever we have one of these
things whatever it is whenever we have a
debug variable we can have as many
states sitting on top of it as we want
right so anything that's like you I
state gets stored in sort of the
separate cash so that you can have as
many of them as you have like trees
right and so when we call get debug view
for what we want to do is say for this
particular debug variable and we
probably also want to say for a
particular debug variable link right so
for a particular link what's the what's
the state and to that since the link has
the variable pointer in it I probably
don't need to pass it so when we call
get debug view for what we're actually
passing here is going to be the inner
link right but we've already kind of
gotten rid of that so I need to kind of
cash it here like so so think that's
basically it let's see what else we've
got here so when we went to our get
debug before here and we do our expand
always right so in this case again we're
going to be have to have to pass a link
here so for the most part probably what
we'd want to do is we'd say whenever
you're interacting something you don't
interact with a variable directly you
interact with the link of that variable
so now our interactions rather than
being phrased on bars will always be on
links since those are the things that
will actually store the you know sort of
the synthetic values and stuff like that
so we'd say the link right equals that
and then we just go ahead and
dereference off of that so debug
variable VAR e quills think bar so
so then the debug get the debug view for
something all we'd have to do there is
say like okay pass the link now instead
and then these interactions are pretty
much the same they don't really have to
change much they just have to instead of
writing far as they're running links so
we're just changing with level we're
restoring really so that's good now
let's see here really know what this is
doing that's that's fine just kind of
make making a slight modification there
so yeah in debug interact this is
probably debug variable link again but
in this case we don't really know I
guess whether it's a bar or not until we
get a little bit lower down right so
something like that ok so I think that
should take care of it yep okay and so
now we're just interacting with links
instead of bars and so that gives us
like kind of a separate thing up the
hierarchy right and you can see that
it's still it's all working just fine
and so now we have to do is actually
implement that cash so we're not all
writing to the same state and then we're
good right so let's go ahead and do that
or at least attempt to do that so we
need to do get debug before we pass that
that link variable right and let's see
here let's see here
so in this case I guess I'm kind of
wondering though if we have the links
why am I not just storing it on the link
that seems like what I should have been
doing right that's kind of why would I
yeah this may have just been more of the
frazzled miss right I don't really need
this anywhere do I I can just modify I
mean correct me if I'm wrong but I
should be able to store this in the link
itself like I already have that piece of
information I mean there is one problem
with it and the problem with it is is
that if we wanted to not use the link so
much if we wanted to have iterators that
don't actually have links on them and I
guess that's something that we kind of
have to think about you know if we
wanted to make this a little bit more
flexible so that you're kind of going
through something and didn't actually
have to have the link yeah that does
that does kind of argue a little bit for
it like basically if you have links and
that's just a way of saying here are
some of the variables that we're talking
about then that's all good but if you
don't want to have any links like let's
say you were iterating over something
that doesn't that's not explicit we're
just iterating over say the members of
an entity or something and we want to
make those editable but we don't want to
actually announce them as individual
links in any particular way you know it
makes it a little bit it makes it a
little bit trickier right and so it
seems like more what we want to do is to
just have some notion right like you
know a debug view tag something like
that or debug view ID right where we can
just say okay variable links will have
these right like there's a way to get a
view ID from a very ruling
us ways you could generate them without
that you know like using a pointer to
something or using whatever so that you
can identify the particular thing that
you're talking about right and so I'm
just going to go ahead and say that
that's the way we'll do it you know and
maybe like we have something like
something like this where it's just got
you know let's say it's got two pointers
or something in it and that constitutes
the debug view ID and that's the thing
that we would actually be looking up on
for the most part right okay so we say
we'd pass one of those things and let me
go ahead and and and make that happen so
we just say like debug maybe that's
maybe that's just debug ID even yeah so
a debug ID from link or something like
that right and then that would just be
something where you can immediately get
one of those it's trivial to get one of
those where I'm saying okay I've got a
debug ID gonna return one of these so
curious debug you know variable link
here we go there's the link and all I'm
going to do is just take whatever the
pointer is for that link under say that
that's the entirety of the ID right and
again this is just some way of making
sure that I can uniquely identify one of
these things right so there's my value 0
is going to be equal to the link pointer
the result of value one is going to be 0
right so just leave it cleared for that
so that's really all we need for that
kind of thing okay so that way we've
kind of got it set up to look up on
anything we want right and that's kind
of handy so then when we do when we're
interacting with things we can now go
one step further and say that our
interaction system does not actually
require you to interact with the link it
just requires you to interact with
something that can be identified by the
debug system right and so our
debug interaction would just be like
we're interacting with a debug ID right
and and probably I would say maybe
everything every debug interaction has
one of those so we still do pass the
variable because that's the thing you're
interacting with but then we also have
an ID that allows you to disambiguate
the circumstance under which you are
actually editing that particular
variable right and i think this sets us
up for doing one more transformation
that we want to do that's going to be
cool right okay all right so anyway
that's probably that's probably the
right thing in my opinion and then this
doesn't have to do the thing that I was
doing before so we can revert this code
basically back to sort of the easier way
that it was working oops like this and
that's probably better do-do-do-do
do-do-do-do yeah and so this will just
use the debug state at interaction ID
and this
debug state interaction link would
actually just do this oops bar bar
alright so that's how that would work
but in order to make that work cleanly
we want to take one more step right so
right now we're kind of ad hoc with our
assignment when we do like item
interactions and stuff like that so
probably what we want to do is something
more like this we want to say like VAR
interaction and we want to do something
where we pass out the type of
interaction and then probably like this
so actually pi I'd even say like more
like VAR link interaction something like
that and we'll pass the link in right
and that is going to be something which
creates one of these debug interactions
basically a mento rank of that thing
grab that out where it takes whatever
the thing was whatever the type of
interaction that we wanted to do right
so debug interaction type it takes the
debug variable link pointer and then it
creates the item interaction that has
all of the like book ID all of the
information filled out properly there we
go right so it fills out the ID it fills
out the type and it fills out the bar
and then we can everything go through
that and so then as we sort of play
around with different ways in which
those if we r you know if we decide to
change kind of how that's packed up
there or what's in it we can do that
without having to worry that like about
all the places that's being done so
again this is just standard a
compression a little compression that
we're doing here to sort of take that
variability out of the equation you know
I'm saying so this is a bar link
interaction here again right so I'm just
simplifying it down into
something a little more straightforward
so everyone's calling through that again
debug interaction i can put pretty much
a search for it so this is a that's not
one of them it's a different kind and so
that's that's a size interaction that's
a VAR link already that's of our link
interaction i tear interaction it's
happening there I think we're good looks
good to me all right so then all we need
is some way of looking up into this cash
right so that we can get our debug view
of whatever the thing is we're passing
debug IDs now so we kind of have a way
of looking it up but we don't actually
have like anything to look it up in
right so we have sort of this is a
straightforward map right we just want
to map one thing to another so I'm going
to use the hash table that's a pretty
easy thing to do right and we've written
those before on handmade hero and we'll
just use whatever the value is now we
know that these values are pointers so
the thing that we probably want to do
with the hash table right is we'd
probably want to ignore like the bottom
bits of them for the most part like you
know pointers are pretty much always
going to be at least aligned to a D word
boundary so we probably want to like go
ahead and ignore those bottom bits so we
probably want to look more at like you
know we probably want to shift shift it
down as we do our look up so I guess all
I'm saying ok so then what we would do
is we'd say we have some set of these
debug views right and can see them here
it already has annexed in hash on it so
if i just come in here and i say all
right give a view this is my view hash
get rid of the dummy and the view hash
is however big it is we don't really
care and like i said any time you write
a hash function the most important thing
to do we've talked about this it's the
right better hash function
you have to have at least one of those
in any shipping game you're only allowed
to fix n minus 1 hashes in your game
some hash table has to ship with that to
do and the full and the fully known
belief that if you spent some time
looking at it you could probably make a
hash function that worked alright so in
the case of view hash in this case I
just need to hash index here and what I
need to do is when you call get debug
view I need to find it in the hash if
it's not in the hash I need to create it
in the hash right so I need to basically
grab the hash lot from whatever our hash
index ends up being and then I need to
kind of loop to see if i can find this
thing so it's probably something like
this where i'd say like debug view well
actually I guess I've got it right here
look at the above you result and I do
something like this where I do a debug
view search equals hash lot while the
search is working we do next in hash so
we just go through the chain and if we
do not find it right then we need to add
it but if we find it then we're good so
if whatever you know debug IDs match or
debug IDs or equal if the one that we're
searching for in the view ID that you
know whatever this guy has here I assume
these debug did I store it i didn't even
store it did I so assuming that the IDS
match so we've got the view ID we're
looking for the search ID that we're
looking at if they match we're done with
our search if not then we need to insert
it so if result is not acceptable here
we need to do a push struct on it to add
one in so we'd say that in that memory
arena we just need one of these debug
views and then inside there we just need
to set the parameters for this so we
know that we have the ID
calling it view ID it's obviously a view
ID in there I probably don't need to say
that and then I've got anything else
about the debug view what is that
actually why is there a tree pointer
that that was just there I think to
disambiguate so we don't actually need
that we don't need any of these in fact
really all we need is the settings I
don't think we need anything else yeah
so assuming that the IDS match all we
really need to do is just set up the
next and hash stuff the type right
whatever the type of debug view is and
so we're going to have to probably pass
that in as well so we do get debug
before we would have to pass in what we
were looking for because otherwise we
wouldn't necessarily know how to set it
I soon well you know what I guess that's
not necessary to either we could defer
that so we could say diva hbu type
unknown or something like that maybe and
we'll see how that goes in a second so
we could set it to unknown we don't know
what it is and then we just say like
okay whatever the next in hash value is
is going to be what's in that slot right
so we know whoever was in the hash left
to begin with and then we set the hash
slot to point to us so typically just
making a chain again just making a very
straightforward hash table so now we
need a way of getting that actual hash
index right so our hash index would just
be again the standard thing it's just
going to be some way of computing a
number we can use for indexing like I
said we've got the ID we've got two
values in the ID you know I have no idea
what the easiest way to do this would be
but you know you take them and you
multiply them together or something a
fantastical like this which is probably
very stupid and just to mix them in and
then we would say like I was saying
before I think we probably want to
ignore the bottom bits of them because
you know
they're going to be pointers so there's
nothing there that could be any
information in those bottom bits that
would be worth you know that would be
worth looking at it all so yeah I don't
know again not particularly great we
could also i suppose add them together I
don't know that we we don't really know
anything about the pattern of these
values so I guess I don't even really
know I'll just leave it like adding I
don't I don't want to pretend we have
some idea of what's going on here so if
we did the hash index that way we'd be
fine I think and then we can go from
there so we've got a oh we already had a
view hash look at that look at that it's
already there that's crazy um and so
yeah so let's go ahead and you know
we'll make these guys 32-bit values and
then we just need a way of comparing the
hashes which is trivial right I mean old
AR is just two pointers right so if I
have to debug IDs so then the result is
just going to be if the values equal
each other
yeah alright so that's all good that
means to be an address that needs to be
an arrow and that needs to go away and
so I think that gets us our debug views
relatively cleanly but let's see so now
our stuff should work in theory at least
and it does actually appear to which is
kind of nice so we're getting there
that's kind of nice I'm pretty happy
about that I'm pretty happy about that
how that's working out kind of hard to
grab this I got to make those little bit
bigger alright so that's working all
quite nicely now actually we got to put
in our indenting again but that's about
it so now we do have a way of creating
multiple things that all go you know
creating editable things that actually
store separate settings for themselves
which is kind of cool and and so we've
got you know maybe about ten minutes
left in the stream or more actually
probably like 50 ms left in the stream
so let's go ahead and push forwards a
little bit more on that lets fix our
indentation first of all because I'd
like that to be working properly I don't
know why that actually broke you
completely honest with you because i
feel like the depth value should still
be getting use it's not so Howard our
begin element rectangle stuff was
supposed to at least in theory was
supposed to be doing that part for us
was it not like it's supposed to be odd
so our layout element here our layout is
supposed to have a depth on it and we're
not using it that appears to be our
problem right so that's a little bit of
a mistake it's true so we're going to
have
to make something that that actually
acknowledges that that layout depth
right yeah that's a bit a mistake so
when we come through here I guess what
we need to look at is since the depth
since we are using the depth of this
stack properly I think it would probably
work to just say that they are the same
but we probably want to clean that up a
little bit we'll talk about that in a
second that's why that was not working
so there we go and so the depth is
actually one less than the action up
because we always have something on the
stack right even if it's the first one
but that looks like it's working pretty
well there so that's good yeah although
debug camera distance should be a scalar
and it's not so we're not setting the
value properly on that guy let's take a
look at that yeah and also we're not
actually setting the values right I mean
shouldn't that add up should have done
something well that worked fine
and that works fine so why did our debug
camera Oh probably because the distance
is zero because it's set to false so why
is our debug why is our why is our
scalar value no longer a scalar value
can we talk about that I would like to
know Dewar's debug camera distance so
where is our real 32 ro32 debug variable
type real 32 set so right there why are
we not getting our real 32 why is our
realtor to not working so there and it
was actually printing out as a boolean
as well so it really looks like it is
not the proper variable type right so
that's kind of odd so I don't know
what's going on there so I'm just going
to take a look rather than try to guess
I'm just going to look and see why
that's the case like what's going on
there so it's passing a bool it thinks
bool is actually the matching type for
debug camera distance I don't know why
that's the case so what is debug camera
distance
it's undefined all right fair enough if
it's undefined its undefined it's that
because if we went into variables that H
oops i mean config doubt h that should
have been as point zero so if I was to
do something like debug camera distance
point zero like that is that really the
entirety of the problem perhaps since
it's doing its using the type to
determine it that is the problem all
right well that's always good use debug
camera all right ok so that's all fine
no need to panic debug camera it's
working yeah ok so that's all fine no
real problems there ah so what now
what's the next logical step I think we
want to do now is get our tear-offs
working and test those but I don't know
if those are working anymore i think we
come to this out right so now we want to
do to create a tear-off we want to be
able to kind of do this thing again
right and we want to be able to pull
something off of the menu and create
another version of that thing that we
can interact with right and so what we
want to do there if we're going to yeah
if we're going to implement that I'm
trying to think if we want to do try to
do anything clever I don't know if we do
or not
I think we should try to do something
clever so let's try to do something
clever with that here we go so when we
let's first just do the basic thing so
we have our debug interaction where we
tear the value off we now need to make a
tree for it right well let's just let
compile errors tell us what's wrong here
first of all so our debug tree right
that's going to have to do basically
same thing was doing and when we make a
group for these guys we're now going to
have to do something where we actually
use these calls directly like we're
doing before screen to call debug ad
group right we need to do debug let's
see diva begin variable group probably
something whatever that's doing debug
add variable so we need to do this so we
need to do this again like we were doing
it before we need to make a thing where
we can do debug variable like a drupe
group something like that right that
just does this this stuff without
anything else it doesn't do that right
and it just uses the context state so it
just creates one of these but
initializes it right and that's it I
guess I should also say should probably
do it without the context that's the
whole point of this so we can add a root
group this way and I guess we need a
name for it obviously so there's the
name for it and then we want to be able
to add a variable to this thing right so
we wanted to call add variable to group
we want to pass it what group data to so
that all works exactly the same ways
does we want to add the tree and then I
think that's pretty much it right now it
would be nice if these two things were a
little more coherent so I think the way
that I'm going to do this is I'm going
to call debug a drupe go this way we
were doing it before and I like that way
so I'm going to keep doing that where we
caught we basically like call down to
the lower level one do the add that way
and then all we do here is you know fix
up the rest of this stuff so we'd call
debug add variable to group
right and hmm excuse me use whatever
that Depot group actually is and so
that's going to be that's debug add
variable can be this guy right here
right that's the that's the one okay so
deep effect add variable to group it
will just do this even that's a little
bit more than I want so I feel like
actually I should probably do this where
we do debug add variable there I
actually want internal void debug add
variable to default group or something
like this where it just does this part
and that way I can call that directly so
I can just say okay I've got a context
add this variable to the context
whatever the context thinks it should be
doing at this time right because then
this all works and that's all fine and
so then here when we do debug add route
group we can then called ego by a group
group and then debug add variable to
default group and it will always kind of
reuse itself properly in the chain debug
variable group and that's just going to
look like that all right
so I think that should be fine should be
good let's find out what happens we
actually do this so I want to clone the
sky so I have cloned Tim right and now
in this so far we have not actually
differentiated these guys so it should
behave exactly the same way as it does
before right that makes sense but now if
we want these guys to be expanded to be
able to expand and contract properly see
if I can do this why is that copying the
whole thing like we have some kind of I
think our ter interaction is slightly
off there though let me see add tree
root Cooper's new user group contraction
bar so if we're doing a tear value yeah
i wanna i just want to take a quick look
at that I feel like we may have the
variable wrong on that clear interaction
so that looks right we're tearing the
value and that's the value that we're
tearing off so I'm not entirely sure why
the tree is getting that is displaying
that whole thing did we do something
dumb when we do the main menu thing were
we grabbing something that's not
actually the trees root or something yes
fantastic why are we doing that that
doesn't make any sense that's what we
actually want to say the least so that
would have been kind of annoying uh to
debug because we'd be like what's going
on it's like well what's going on is
you're an idiot okay so let's go ahead
and delete that that away and now we
should actually be low tear off specific
values not the whole tree so there's one
let's try this one there we go but like
I said they're still tied together right
and so we want to do is untie these now
and that should be a simple matter of
being able to disambiguate them now what
we can do is we could deep copy the
hierarchy but that seems like a pain
because now in theory we don't really
have to because since the state is
stored externally we can actually tear
off whole hierarchy is just fine and
with that state start extremely all we
need i don't know why i've got two of
these open I don't even want to know why
that's happening we won't ask now that
we've got them sort externally all we
need to do is make our debug ID be more
expressive about what is actually being
compared right so all we need to do is
when we make one of these debug view IDs
we just need something a little bit more
expressive that says like what tree
you're iterating them in or something
and we won't actually ever have to clone
it because it'll automatically just
flown the state but won't have to clone
the tree if that makes sense so if we do
that
all we would need to do is when we
create these guys a debug variable link
let's just say that when you do that you
have to tell me the tree as well right
so when we do debug ID from link and
we're trying to create these
interactions you just have to pass the
tree as well all right so for our link
interactions we know the tree right we
know the tree here oops Stefan wrong
order and we know the tree here as well
right so yeah so now when we look at
this when we pull this off you can see
that in theory they should behave
totally differently and they do right
because now the state is being stored as
a look-up on not only which one of these
guys you are right but also which tree
you're talking about and we could extend
this a little bit further on the hot
interaction side right because you
notice we we highlight function like
this and they both highlight now that
may be actually a good thing we may want
that to be the case that seems kind of
helpful in my mind but if we didn't want
to do that we could we could make that
not happen either by just comparing
those debug IDs at the head end right
that makes sense ok so we've succeeded
in our first stated goal which is to
isolate that state so that's kind of
nice and that might be a good place to
end for today I'm really to be happy
with that and hopefully everyone knows
what we did there right what we did is
we separated the state out in the
something that can you looked up on some
key values so that now when we produce
our interface we're now no longer come
worried about having to store any
particular state for something just as
we need it we go please get me a state
storage for something that's in this
tree that has this site that has this
you know whatever pointer or something
and then we can
just kind of go hog Wow the nice part
about it is it doesn't use it if this
tree was giant you know if it was like
billions of entries we would never
actually be touching or storing any of
the state for those entities right in
that tree we're just throwing the state
for the ones we actually have ever seen
before and that's actually pretty
important because what that means is we
can have trees that could be infinitely
large like let's say and this is
swelling I want to do you know maybe
tomorrow or the next day let's say we
have something that has an unbounded
number of things in the tree like very
very large that could be like all the
world chunks or something like right
right that you could drill down into or
who knows what we wouldn't have to
create storage for all those things we'd
only store them as we came across them
and that's really like kind of what I
want right all right so I think we're
getting there we'll go to a brief Q&amp;A
assuming that the laptop is working
which I don't know if it is but we will
we'll do that you'll try to do that as
best as I can
pure design question in giba in debug
I'm sorry get debug view for your method
is named such that it's a query but it
appears to be a command in some cases in
that it change in state of the system
I've heard that you typically want to
avoid this do you agree is there a
reason you did this um so I guess what I
would say is I don't normally tend to be
too I don't tend to care too much about
that naming scheme wise I don't tend to
assume that the name of something tells
me whether it will modify it or not but
I would not mind someone who want who
felt strongly about that like if if
that's the way you tend to program is
that you trust that you will name your
things based on whether they modify
something or not and you then use that
to sort of speed up the development
process because I will I often do do
something that looks like this I will
often do that and so I am totally fine
with that I like I said I'm i'm not
particularly fussy about it but i will
often named it that way if I think I'm
in any danger of forgetting in this case
I know the debug view 0 is cached behind
the scenes so I don't think of them as
something that needs to state that
because you never don't do that at the
moment but it's it's totally fine
do you think learning all the algorithms
and data structures ISM is a must or is
it okay to learn them when the need for
one of them arises or is it one of those
things that you have to learn beforehand
or to know if you need them or not I
would say that I would say that the
basic algorithms and data structures are
probably something you want to kind of
learn at least learn what they do you
don't necessarily to learn how to write
them like you don't then learn how to
write a b-tree but you should know what
a b-tree is and why you might use it
because yeah learning how to implement
them lazily is totally fine but learning
what they do is kind of a must because
otherwise you wouldn't know if you
needed one like you wouldn't know if
you're in a circumstance you're like I
don't know what to do here you can't
just go learn the one that you need
because you don't know which one you
need right so you can't possibly learn
it at that point so I would say just
getting a broad overview of like what's
a b-tree what's a hash table what's the
stack what's a map you know what are all
these things and some of those are kind
of cross way like a map is kind of
conceptual thing where's the hashes of
implementation things so you know kind
of mixing words a bit there but
understanding just kind of what your
options are it's kind of important this
is basically it
and unfortunately I can't really answer
in sohbats question because I don't
understand it quarter Tron a b-tree is
not really a subset I'm sorry binary
search tree is not really a subset of a
b-tree like a binary search tree I mean
I I guess I guess you could phrase it
that way a binary search tree I guess is
kind of you could say it has to you know
two branches at each part where's Abby
tree has n you know I don't tend to
think of them as really being subsets
though because the b-tree is kind of
very different in terms of its
implementation but I could see why
someone I could see why you would say
that and that might be a reasonable way
to think about it yeah about your memory
allocation way back when shouldn't the
amount of memory you allocate depend on
the size the world chosen by the user as
it is it is fixed at compile time if I
understand correctly um so we sort of
have a dilemma there right and I don't
know how we want to solve it we will
talk more about memory allocation a
little later on but the dilemma that we
have is technically we set up our game
to kind of handle arbitrarily large
worlds right so in some sense if you
just want it to be ridiculous about it
you could say that the user should be
able to make a world that's as big as
the memory in his machine so a 32 a user
with 32 gigabytes in his machine should
be able to make a substantially bigger
world that someone with only four
gigabytes right
the problem with that is it's will it
would be very very difficult to write an
algorithm that predicts how much the
degenerates a world within a certain
size of memory right and I don't know if
we'll be able to do that if we can then
yes what we probably will do is will
make it so that at startup it takes a
look at how much memory you have and
then it like goes all right when you go
to make a world it will only allow you
to pick maybe you know a world that's
the size that could fit in your memory
footprint you know we could do that if
we can if we can't do that then we have
to do is pick some size of the world
that we know is reasonable and that fits
inside whatever our system requirements
are and that's the biggest you can make
the world you know
elvin I would like to be a tools
programmer game tech writer like you but
I'm still learning things so I'm not
fully qualified to work as one I'm
thinking of working in a simple game
company where the qualifications aren't
so hardcore maybe they use unity or
whatever and at the same time do my
private Louisville stuff self-learning
good idea yes no I would say it does
sound like a reasonable idea to me
there's a lot of work that goes into
making a game and only a certain portion
of that is like you know the programming
and so if you're interested in making
games it's very important to kind of
know about the whole process and have
some experience with the whole process
so you know working on at a company
that's making like a game and unity or
something may not be very good practice
if you want to be a tools engine
programmer kind of guy but it's still
very valuable because you will see the
process of making a game right and the
process besides the unity part is
applicable to any game no matter you
know the like how artists work on the
game how the game designers work on the
game how production works working on in
a team environment like that all of that
stuff is the same on a Unity game or on
a custom engine right and so getting
experience making Unity game is is not
at all a you know inapplicable to making
a game yourself and also getting
experience making a game in unity or
something would also inform some of your
decisions because you will see firsthand
what are the problems with unity where
does it break why is it causing us you
know issues and what do we like about it
like where is it a good tool what you
know what do they do right and that
would allow you as well if you wanted to
then go work on your own engine stuff or
do your own things it would inform those
decisions like what do I want to do that
unity isn't doing or you know or if you
want to use unity on your project what
do I anticipate the problems being and
what might I right to alleviate those
problems right so it's definitely I
think good idea the only thing I would
caution about it or not really caution
about it but more or what I'd say is
there is one option that's one better
than that if you can if you can get it
which is if you can work at a company
where you are maybe not doing anything
in particular hardcore you're just doing
game scripting or working on a simpler
thing but there are harder core
programmers they're making engine stuff
that would be even better because then
you can see how they are working as well
and that could be very educational for
you so if you can find a place like that
that's even better but those are you
know much harder to find good game
programmers are hard to find and good
jobs where you might work nearby or in
collaboration with a good game develop a
good game programmer is hard to find so
I appreciate the fact that you know it
start and chances are if you know if
you're trying to get your first game the
game is sure you're going to be working
out seeing that just has you know they
got some unity and maybe who knows what
they're doing and they don't necessarily
know what's going on in whatever else
right
what are your plans for streaming once
you complete this game I don't have any
plans for streaming that's this is all I
was going to do just make the game and
then the stream is over Abner cumbre
you've discussed using blender are you a
3d modeler of some sort more
specifically what operations do you do
with that software package yes I do i do
know how to do 3d modeling I can do
production 3d models III do not really
have much in the way of production 3d
model painting skills so I would not
necessarily be the best texturing guy
nor am I a good rigor but as far as
modeling concerned I can definitely do
that as for what i'm using it for at the
moment i'm using it for essentially
previz it's for working with the artists
i've been using blender to do previz so
i can sort of go like okay here is what
we're trying to do with this particular
thing here's a mock-up of it in blender
and this what everyone's on the same
page on the team on the current team i'm
the only person with 3d experience on
our current game so that's why i'm doing
that unhand me hero i'm not and handmade
hero yangshin knows how to use 3d
packages we don't use it a whole heck of
a lot well she doesn't use it a whole
heck of a lot on him a hero but but she
has 3d experience as well I don't know
how extensive it is but but she
definitely knows I'd like to see a
blender pre stream demo okay I mean any
particular reason you can just go online
right now and look up any number of
blender videos that show you
introduction to blender because they are
doing a short off our streams show
people how you do things like
metaprogramming that you won't get to
touch on it hammer here not really
because this stuff anything that's
that's anything that's relatively
straightforward to explain on a stream
in a reasonable amount of time I am
doing in handmade hero so anything that
I'm kind of leaving out is generally
stuff that you know would need many
hours of streaming itself to cover if
that makes sense
roots 2d hey love catching the stream
when I can what language you recommend
is a beginner programmer looking to get
into game development I don't really
know obviously like if you're serious
game programmer C and C++ is pretty much
the only thing the industry really uses
Syria in serious land but it's not a
great language that story to start out
in if you're talking about more like
just light game programming then C sharp
tends to be pretty common for that
because a lot of people use unity and
c-sharp is like the scripting language
in unity now whether any of those are
good things to start with I don't know I
I feel like probably if it's you know
your very first time doing any
programming at all you know you're going
to want a language that's really easy to
experiment with that's very simple that
just lets you play around you know like
my I didn't write my first program in c
you know i wrote my first programming
basic which is not really around much
anymore but at the time it was you know
exactly that it was a program language
meant for beginners just so they could
sort of like get an idea of at all
what's going on so what the best
language is for that nowadays I really
don't know you know I don't know it's
it's it's such a different world
compared to what I grew up in that I
don't really have a good I don't really
have experience with beginner tools to
know which one of them i think is like
really the best one to start out so i
would say you know that's probably
something you kind of have to search for
a little bit but yeah you know like like
maybe something like a game maker or
something like that probably i'm just
guessing and i don't know but probably
has like a very rudimentary scripting
language in it that's designed to make
it easy for people who don't necessarily
know very much about programming to
experiment and that might be you know a
good way to just kind of get your feet
wet but but I don't you know I don't
know
I really just don't another one might be
you know just to play around with with
something you know like I'm trying so so
the thing that I thought I guess I would
say is if I work if I were going to go
find it if I was going to go spend some
time like researching it try to find it
like what what do I think the best one
is probably think I would look for
something with a debugger like I don't
know if something like RPG Maker game
maker people are suggesting RPG maker on
here or whatever uh if you can find a
very simple straightforward you know you
know a language design three dinners
that has a debugger that would probably
be the best because that would be
something that allows you to look at how
your code is working and that really
speeds up the learning process one of
the problems with a lot of like easy
languages is they don't necessarily have
debuggers so i would say probably try to
find a language I don't never used game
maker so I don't know but you know if it
has a debugger and if its language is
relatively straightforward that you know
that might be a good thing you know its
design for game development you know
it's designed to be easy for games but
but I don't know
alright stream is over it's over people
okay not doing that yet okay thank you
for joining me for another episode of
handmade here it's a pleasure cutting
with you as always it seems like the
laptop is working well enough to answer
the chat so I will go ahead and post the
full schedules the week and we will do
it as normal now for those of you who
would like to chat about a special
episode that's up coming on Friday stay
on the stream for a second after i
finish this episode and we will chat
about it until that happens let me just
conclude the normal stream and say that
if you want to follow along the source
code at home please remember that the
source code does come with all
pre-orders of the game so if you want to
play around that you can always
pre-order the game on handmade hero org
and it comes to the source code which I
upload every night so you can always
play around the latest version as well
we also have patreon page montfort the
video series we have a forum site you go
to ask questions you have a tweet bout
that we've scheduled you when I know
what the schedule is going to be which
hopefully will be this evening since now
i'm pretty sure that we can do all the
weeks ones so that should be the best
way to keep up with the stream except
when we have reared technical
difficulties like we did this weekend so
anyway yet we'll be back here tomorrow 5
p.m. pacific daylight time and we will
be here all week at 5pm until friday
when there will be a special stream at
8pm i believe is the correct time and so
if you want to talk about what's going
to happen the special stream stay on the
chat for a minute and we will chat about
it until then or i should say until
tomorrow for anyone who's ducking out
have fun programming and i will see you
guys on the internet