hello everybody and welcome to handmade
hero share we code a complete game live
on stream today I think we really just
have to fuss a little bit with our we
built sort of a customized multi sample
buffer resolution scheme last weekend
but we only just got everything finished
up I guess we did it on Sunday we tried
this we only got everything finished up
by the end of the stream we didn't have
a chance to actually play with
algorithms for doing what we were trying
to do we only had time to get it you
know the pipeline setup for doing it and
that kind of thing so today I think the
only thing we really want to do is try
to figure out if there's some kind of
custom resolution scheme we can use to
make that work it's an almond milk day
today so yeah this is going to be one
where it would be nice to have drawing
so I may just try to draw without the
cursor it could be fun who knows we'll
see anyway let's go ahead and get
started here so let me show you where we
were at last time I believe we left it
so that we were booting into the the
multi sample resolution version of the
game because there's a hint you can
toggle on and off oops let me do that
again I meant kind of desk
but we aren't really doing it right yet
are right the wrong term here because we
don't actually know what algorithm we
would use all we know is that we might
be able to do better than the default so
I believe this is our custom
multi-resolution resolved here that's
happening and what you can see is if I
turn it off so this is this is I'm not
going to turn off the custom one I'm
just going to turn off multi sampling
right so if you notice when I turn off
multi sampling right we've done a really
good job I think at this point render
wise because everything is looking
really good and I'm really happy with
what we did and you know I think it's
ready to put the art in there happy with
all that so the only thing that I
thought was really objectionable was
these sort of jagged lines on the
geometric primitives for the ground
right and like I said even though we're
going to be texture mapping stuff onto
that ground those hard edges I think
what still remains you can imagine you
put a texture on this or other stuff
you'd still go sorry I just now there's
some ground cover stamping sort of stuff
that we're probably going to be doing
and so I feel like you know maybe that
would hide these edges so it might be
that we're you know going a little bit
too far in terms of trying to create a
bit of quality but I don't know I I want
to at least have some confidence that
you know let's say this was a dungeon
area and this was some kind of a stone
tile well there's not going to be any
fringing of that it's just going to be a
hard edge on the on that tile and I feel
like that's going to cause problems if
we don't have a way to smooth that out
if we just want really high fidelity or
high quality rather on the on the
graphics there so we can't turn on multi
sampling and what that will do is
that'll sort of help smooth out all
those edges and that's nice but the
problem that we get with that is that
the resolve the multi sample resolved
leads to poor results with the depth
feeling and this is somewhat
understandable because death feeling is
requiring you know the whole concept of
depth feeling is assuming that you have
one pixel per def sample one color value
for the pixel one depth sample for the
pixel and so when you move to a multi
see if this game the problem is that you
end up having up more than what right
you end up having multiple color and
depth samples per pixel and in order to
move to the next step
in the in the scheme you know for desk
you language each peel in order to move
to the next step in the scheme you need
only one you need to have some
understanding of which what the
particular sample was and furthermore
there's not really a way to do this with
you know well I shouldn't say there's
not a way to do it i if we wanted to
just persist the multi sampling through
the entire scheme we end up in sort of
an unfortunate position and the reason
that we end up in an unfortunate
position that is that the whole point of
multi sampling versus just over sampling
is that you only pay for the over
sampling at the edges of things so the
whole point of using multi sampling is
that on cards let's do it smartly you
will not be paying for over sampling in
here for example because since one
geometric primitive is covering this
whole thing you will not pay for over
sampling here you might write along this
diagonal because this diagonal is
there's two primitives right there right
one triangle one triangle that form the
quad but inside the triangle you will
not pay for multi sampling because the
triangle covers the entire pixel so it
runs as fast as it would more or less
than if you weren't multi sampling and
so that's an important speed win
especially on modern hardware this this
piece of hardware is nuts it's from a
decade ago so it's not particularly good
test case but just in general I think
what we would find unless I'm very much
an error we would have to test fit but
my assumption certainly is that what we
would find if we went through and tested
the two types of methodologies is that
multi sampling would be significantly
faster than over sampling and over
sampling would just be if we rendered it
a much higher resolution than we were
planning to use say
a you know we were planning to use 1920
by 1080 and we just render at two or
three times that resolution Meany in
both dimensions and then downsampled and
that has the benefit of just working
correctly with gut feeling because
you're now just one depth sample per
pixel still all the time until you
finally smush everything down the whole
pipeline runs in a higher resolution it
runs in 4k or something right and then
down sampled but again that will just
literally be at least if not worse you
know n times slower where n is the
number of pixels that there are and
where m is the multiplier on how many
pixels there are so if we were to double
the resolution in X and Y for example
which would just be 2 X in either
direction that's 4x more pixels so it
will be 4 times slower to run in that
and at least theoretically the multi
sampling version will not be 4 times
slower it he will be a little slower but
not that much because it's not you know
most of the slowness does not come for
doing more pixels because it's actually
not doing that many more samples
especially because our primitives are
very large in anime hero so there's not
a lot of edges on them but the point
here is basically that you know when we
are doing the the main bulk of those
things although we are not going to pay
for the more pixels we are going to pay
for the more memory bandwidth because
the multi samples multi sample buffer is
larger than a non multi sample buffer so
we will be paying a cache and memory
bandwidth cost one way or the other so
it will get a little slower it's not
free but it's not 100% the cost of over
sampling in fact it's probably not even
close so I do think we want to at least
try to get multi sampling working
instead of just going for something like
over sampling which would be quite a bit
more expensive but work properly to the
scheme so what we try to do to
ameliorate some of the problems here
that we see with the
with the multi sampling specifically
look up in the trees I don't know if you
can kind of see what's going on there
let's say I move over here so you can
see it move a bit but you can see a lot
of kind of like it's not leaves it's not
really traditional z-fighting but it's
like I think a form of z-fighting
right where the depth buffer itself go
ahead make a place where we can zoom in
and out where the depth buffer itself
during that sort of resolution from
multisample to nan is like picking you
know values that that exhibit this
problem that sort of fight back and
forth about who's the closer pixel and
so you end up you know we what we want
to do is pick something reasonable when
we do our resolve and not have that kind
of problem occur and again because
everything else is looking pretty good
you know I'm not seeing a lot of
artifacts in anywhere else so you know
when you do the multi sampling it looks
like we would just pretty much have what
we wanted if we could just figure out a
way to stop that sort of nasty effect
from happening with the with the resolve
so we have the the custom resolve
working here right here is a custom
resolve right here that I'm on and if
you take a look at this custom resolve
what we have is we've got the color
buffer and the depth buffer oh and you
know what before I forget let me do one
thing that people were asking for
apparently because we switch to using
sampler ms multi sample right sample two
DMS because we need that to do the
custom result and the the multi sample
the custom resolve functions are only
available in shader one-five-zero so
really we kind of need to specify that
version when we do the multi sampling
now we only need it for that shader so
thankfully we can still if you run with
multi simply turned off you could still
run in version one three zero if your
card only supported
three zero right so that's kind of nice
now the graphics card should have
complained about that but I guess this
graphics card compiler doesn't really
check that I didn't have ever checking
for that so since the card happens to
know to be same sampler to DMS
it's just worked even though we had
version one three yo it's not supposed
to but it did other people who compiled
on more stringent cars probably on
NVIDIA driver or something got that
error so they just let me know so
hopefully that'll help them make sure
that that compiles properly on their
machines but shader compiler not their
regular compiled stuff obviously
so you can kind of see here what we're
doing our resolve loops over the sample
count we look up the various samples for
you know we're looking at the same pixel
we look up each sample we look up the
depth sample and the color sample and
then we need to output something so what
we're doing right now is just a
straight-up average I'm sorry a straight
up a pic of whatever the closest depth
value was right and the problem with
that is when we pick the closest depth
value what we're essentially doing and
let me see if I can I'm gonna try was
going to try I know it's a bad idea I'm
just going to try to do a drawing I it
without the really having a drawing
program of functioning drawing program
I'm gonna try it because you only live
once here I'm saying alright so let's go
ahead and load okay so here's me doing
an offset drawing sit here so what day
is today today is day three eighty seven
so day whoa now it's on oh that's
because it lost connection I tell you it
like we just really need to go into
Milton and fix whatever the bugs are
here like you can see that when it loses
focus like when my when my program when
seamier when when this happens it
appears to lose focus right and you can
see that now it's locked on properly and
I think that's
because now it's not getting tablet
input it's getting like mouse input or
something right and then when I real
aunt it you can see when I relaunch it
it's back again right the pressure
sensitivity has returned it's getting
tablet input but now the offset is back
right it's very strange and so I know
that's fixable I just don't know what
the problem actually is all right so
this is going to be some of the worst
writing you've ever seen from me and
that's saying something
there we go
all right so the problem here that we're
you know experiencing is we have inside
our pixel we've got a few sample points
right I think in our case we actually
have eight so there's quite a few of
these bad boys in there right that's
eight right there
one two three four five six seven eight
so at each of these samples we have a
color and a depth value right now
remember in cases where a pixel was
entirely covered by a single primitive
we effectively only have one sample
because all eight samples in the multi
sample buffer will have the same depth
and the same color so in that case is
trivial because pretty much whatever
scheme we pick will produce the right
answer which is just that answer right
so the case that we're concerned about
is the case where these eight samples
have different values now some of them
may have the same value and some of them
may have different values and we have to
figure out what to do about this so I
think the problems that we're seeing is
for example in our trees we've got a
situation where remember we have the Z
bias program happening and what the Z
bias program does is as we go up the
drawing disease even though it's a flat
white card that's camera aligned so the
Z relative the camera should be the same
whole way we don't use it the same out
the whole way what we actually do is we
artificially boost the Z value get it
make closer to the to the camera which
in this case I guess is actually making
it less right because if you remember
our convention for Z here is that the
lower depth is closer to the camera so
we actually subtract from the Z value
and make it get closer right and so what
that means is that down at the bottom
right in here we're starting off at a
certain Z value and ending in another V
value in here there's like those shadow
is there down at the bottom here right
the three shadow those shadow pixels
therefore are all at different Z values
what that means is that where we hit the
edge now I just want to pull in the
darkness just want to say one more time
multi sampling when you're inside a
primitive just writes all the samples
normally if there isn't some reason for
it not to so I just want to be clear in
inside the primitive in here there is no
problem or you know where I drew it
right here for example no problem it's
only on the edge and the reason that the
edges the problem is because we're the
edge of the primitive is that's where
multi sampling takes a because remember
the point of multi center needs to
smooth primitive edges right so at the
edges what happens is we're going to
write all of these samples and some of
them right will go to something else and
some of them won't right so some of them
will go to our primitive some of them
will go to something else the problem I
believe we're having and we did some
work to verify this last weekend so I'm
fairly confident and although we haven't
proven it beyond the shadow of a doubt
pun intended is that these samples here
when they're written at the edge for the
three sprite they're all going to get a
different Z value right because remember
our Z shader is now operating our Z by a
shader is now operating per sample so
the Z value of each of these is going to
be slightly different so I think what
happens is when it goes to do the depth
feeling it goes out okay
well what's the closest one well the
closest one obviously is going to be the
highest one up right it's going to be
that one so it's like oh okay I found it
that's the closest one put that into the
depth field buffer then the next round
of depth feeling it goes well what's the
closest one now well the closest one now
is now a multi sample from the same
primitive so instead of P
away the primitive what we actually did
is just gathered multiple samples and
think of it since we're at 8x over
sampling and we're only deaf peeling
away four layers we basically just end
up in a situation where all of our deaf
peels record the same damn primitive
right and that's just not helpful
because what we want to do is we want to
peel away primitives so we need to do is
try to come up with some metric that
inside a pixel will discard values from
the same primitive unfortunately I don't
really know any way to do this directly
right what I want to do is say write all
of the samples with the exact same Z and
color value if you're coming from this
same sample right from the same
primitive and I just don't know how to
do that right in other words what I want
it to do is I want it to just I want it
to write the same value for the Z that
it would write for the entire pixel and
because there is no way that I can find
to do that like I was unable to find any
way to force it to always write the same
Z value for all the edges just generate
what you like don't interpolate Z per
sample that's all I wanted right I just
want it to not interpolate Z per sample
just and this would be I think fairly
easy for it to do it's not available
right and barring that you know if it
wasn't going to write Z per sample then
just a well okay you know here's a
question for you because I thought we
tried this
because I thought we tried this didn't
last weekend I remember us trying this
where we wrote we overrode what the
sample Z was right we said we passed
down a sample Z and we said all right
here's the Z that you're going to use
and that way it wouldn't take multiple
samples for it I thought that's what we
did and I don't and I guess you know now
I'm thinking about I I can't remember us
having any luck with that
and I feel like there should have been a
way to do that but I guess now that I
think about it I other than relying on
centroids and stuff like that I guess
there's no real way I guess there's no
real way to force flood all the samples
yeah I just don't know I so it leads us
in the nnv opposition I mean that's what
we want and I feel like if we were in
you know I feel like there must be some
way to do that I wanna I want to pull a
graphics one of those softer graphics
gentlemen aside and just ask because I'm
sure they would know I don't know claim
just be like hey all I want to do is I
want to make sure that all of the Z
values generated from a single
invocation of the fragment shader always
have the exact same sample value Z
values of the samples because that's all
we wanted right
I don't even care the color values can
be different I don't even care about
that I just need the Z values to be the
same so the depth feeling will work but
yeah all right so what we need to do
here let's just try this technique
anyway even though really what I want is
not this but if I recall correctly we
tried to make that to convince the
graphics card to do that and it wouldn't
do it so if we look here and we're going
to do a this text will stretch to grab
out our depth values what I want to do
here is say well okay I we're averaging
the colors together for this hmm
and really I don't know that that's what
we wanted to do because this is this is
Jimmy picking a single depth value but
averaging the colors which doesn't make
a whole lot of sense so that's probably
should get fixed but what we want to do
here is is let's let's say that we just
want to pick a representative sample so
what I want to do for picking a
representative sample I think is I want
to
pick a sample that's going to be the
farthest back sample of the clothes
samples right and this is kind of a
weird thing to say but what I'm assuming
right is that what I have here is I've
got two primitives and let's say I'm
looking from the top down here as to the
cameras up here and I'm looking down and
I've got two primitives all right like
this now the problem is because again of
the Z bias in this case but we would
have this problem if we had other
primitives and we do sort of have other
primitives like the sides of the cubes
the problem here is that they're sort of
on an angle right they're slanted like
that so I'm looking down at these two
and effectively my pixel right if is
sort of talking about picking out sort
of a shaft you know along the camera
direction now mind you it's not parallel
because this is actually a perspective
projection so technically actually if
you know those are really hard to do
drawing without having a cursor okay
there we go
it's really more like that right because
as you get further away the the sort of
range encompassed by a pixel is getting
larger certainly but what you can see
here is that you know I've got samples
from this guy and then I've got samples
from this guy now if you think about
what that means it means that if we had
some way of figuring out right because
remember I just want to split the
primitives I just want to do that if we
add some way of figuring out which we're
from which we would be okay for
death-dealing purposes what I want to do
is pick the furthest one back right okay
so we're
right here so what I want to do is I
want to pick like right there right so
if I had a sample that was at the edge
of that that's what I want to pick
because I know that when I def peel
again the next time mmm
now I will only get samples from this
further away thing I won't accidentally
pick more samples from this primitive up
here that I was basically trying to
remove right so yeah so that's just
that's just that now I you know one
thing we could imagine doing and the
reason that I'm not doing this is just
because again it's just it's much too
costly I think but you could imagine an
easy way to solve this problem would be
to just have another buffer right and
the other buffer destroys the primitive
index that'd be it because then all I
would do is as I step through these I'd
go oh what primitive are we on okay that
you know if take the closest take the
furthest back sample that's from the
same primitive index as me right and
that's easy but we don't really have
that so what I'm going to try to do
instead is say well maybe I can build
like a little mini cluster here of depth
samples and so basically say if the
depth sample is further back but not too
much further back then we'll use it if
it is too much further back we will
assume that it's from a separate
permanent right this isn't going to work
perfectly right because as you get to
things that are at the exact same Z it
will fail but you know again we're just
trying to minimize the artifacts here so
maybe this is will be will be good it's
frustrating to not be able to have the
graphs guard do the sort of relatively
simple thing that that would solve its
problem but that's graphics cards for
you and maybe if we ask like I said a
graphics person
if there would be somebody to do it we
could say it for multi sampling require
a much higher shader mode in a much
better graphics card and then only
enable multi sampling on those cards
because again multi sampling is like a
feature that it's a higher end graphics
feature for our game it's not required
you can just have those sort of
polygonal edges in the game will work
just fine it just doesn't quite look as
good and so that's just you know that's
just the trade-off there so if I was
going to do that what I need to do here
is say like okay here's the vertex code
fragment code for it
I don't need to change anything in the
vertex code because I'm not again this
is just drawing a full screen screen
cloth so all I'm going to do is just
change this rule here so what you can
see is I'm going over each sample I'm
getting the color and getting the depth
so what I want to do now is say well
okay let's defer picking the color here
till till maybe after this right and
what I want to do is say okay you know
and I could even defer the whole thing
right I can defer that this little thing
so let's take a look here and say all
right I'm going to grab the depth and
what I want to do is I want to take the
depth and go from a closest step scheme
to a further steps game okay
so I'm going to start off by saying the
closest of the furthest death rather is
the one that's right at the camera right
that nobody could have so everything at
first going to pass so what I do is I'm
going to take a look at the depth right
and actually I suppose what I should do
is say let's start with sample index one
and you know what I could do it just say
let's just get that that depth in here
to begin with so what we're going to do
right is we're just going to say let's
get the color
[Applause]
let's get the color let's get the depth
so we start off here with a valid color
in depth right and you know since des
isn't used anywhere I'm going to call
this depth I don't think we need to be
more specific
so I'm going to say that we just have
color and depth here there we go and so
that just selects the very first sample
and uses that as the seed value so we
start on whatever the first sample
happens to be we're on that depth and
off we go
so now we come through the rest of our
samples we fetch the depth value of
whatever sample we're on and now what I
want to say is well if this depth value
is further away or if it's closer I'm
going to take different actions so let's
suppose that the coat that this depth
that we get back is and you know what
since I don't really care about
averaging colors at this point and they
actually move this all the way to be it
right I may say something like
[Applause]
get rid of all this and just say that
we'll pick a result color and we'll have
a depth right and if we just are picking
one color what you can see here is that
we will be squaring the color and then
square rooting it immediately so we
wouldn't need to do that so because
again the only reason we need to do
gamma correction is if we're going to
operate on the colors if we just pick a
color rather than combining them which i
think is fine because again all we're
trying to do here with multi sampling I
well you know what no that's not true
because since we have polygon edge is I
guess we do need that never mind
take your back we do need to actually
average them we can't just pick so what
we could do here let's see what we could
do here say all right if we were going
to treat the combined color after the
fact because I think that is sort of
what we would have to do I guess you
could try to clear it in the meantime
basically what we're trying to do is
find sort of a depth range if you will
that is the depth range that we're
willing to accept for this particular
pixel where will average the color
values together right so I'm going to
write this out in that unoptimized way
first and then we can always sort of do
something smarter later on so what I'm
going to do here is say here's our
sample indexers our sample count we're
going to loop through these we're gonna
get these texels right like so so what
I'm going to do is going to say if the
depth of a particular sample is greater
than equal to depth min and less than
equal to death max
then we're going to accept it okay we're
going to fetch it we're going to do the
operation on it so we're going to start
out with zero we're going to sum like so
we're going to remember how many of
these we did so we add the color we
remember how many of those there were
then at the end of that we will do an
inverse of the sample count and we'll
multiply the combined color to get that
right and then what I want to write here
is I want to write the the DEF max again
this is different than what we're doing
before rather than picking the closest
we're picking the furthest but only the
furthest within a range so that we're
trying to do that picking of primitives
okay
so that's about it then we have to again
square root and again in an arch in an
sRGB mode that would happen
automatically so right now we're doing
it ourselves okay because remember we
don't our art assets currently are not
processed correctly so they're there
they don't have the right thing working
there all right so now what we need to
do we can get rid of combined color and
depth up here and we can just look at
our depth loop itself so we have a dip
them in and a depth Max and so what we
want to do here is I think probably just
initially feed the depth min and the DEF
max the same way right so we'll
basically say all right let's fetch
these
so we start out with the first sample
and we say let's just assume that the
death range is whatever that sample says
it is right then we loop through the
rest of our samples we get whatever the
depth value is for that particular
sample and we say alright if the depth
you know it's the minimum depth value
and maybe I'll write this the opposite
way around that I normally do just to be
a little bit clear if the depth we get
is less than the depth min right if it's
a coming if it's closer to the camera
then what we want to do here is say well
how much closer is it if it's way closer
we need to reset our min and Max right
and I suppose that means we could just
do this in one well okay so here are two
cases right so we have depth in depth
max obviously the depth can't be both so
I guess what we could do here is just do
that and say okay so if you're closer
than the minimum we know you're a new
sample that's in front of all our old
samples if your further the maximum we
know you're a new sample behind all of
our samples so all we really need to do
is figure out what the correct action is
to take here right do we widen the range
or do we reset the range hopefully that
makes some sense
all right so in the case where we're
closer right what we know is that in
that case the desk man is always going
to become the depth right because we
know that we are going to reset the
range to be whatever the closest thing
is it's going to have to include that
because we're obviously want that close
sample but what we want to do here is
see just how much the difference is
right so there's a difference between
these two and we want to see how high it
is so we want to subtract depth min from
death to get a distance value and then
we want to see if that distance value is
greater than the fresh
old if it is that we're going to set dip
max as well right so if the difference
value that we're tracking is greater
than some modicum right and we don't
know what that is
so we're going to set that probably up
here like down to fine
yep threshold 0.01 app or something like
this right
so if the difference value crosses that
depth threshold then what we want to do
is we want to set the depth max as well
so that's basically saying this sample
with so much closer than the other
samples that we're assuming there's a
whole nother primitive in here and let's
move to tracking that primitive instead
of the other primitive right and then
similarly if we have in here we got
depth is greater than depth max we want
to do exactly the same thing so the
depth the different value here is groups
[Applause]
that way around right because guess in
this case is the higher value so what we
want to do is say same thing if the
difference is greater than the depth
threshold then we wouldn't do anything
right so I guess it's not quite same
thing we really want the other way round
if we are within the threshold then we
expand the deck max right now this is a
little bit wrong okay and the reason
that it's a little bit wrong is because
it produces sort of results that are
based on the order in which the samples
were taken so we're going to do this way
but then I'm going to talk about that in
a second so don't let me forget so now
we've got to get this thing compiling
unfortunately can't see it with real
indentation which is not the best thing
and maybe I can reapply paste it in here
I can I need just like a CPP file so
here's that invented properly his name
looks like we're missing a closing if
we're missing a closing one right here
handy that indentation is what you say
so now we've got a debug that we're
going to have some compiler bugs in
there so let's go ahead and run that our
compiler bugs a go oh well or not so
yeah we can't really effectively see
step through this so it's a little bit
hard to tell but you can see we've we've
definitely not done a correct job
because we're getting all sorts of weird
artifacts there so let's take a look at
what's going on here and step through it
and see if we can't figure out what
what's going on so here's our jessamine
depth max they're initialized at the
start to the same value all right so
this way we have the starting range so
then I'm going to pull a depth value out
of the samples I'm going to say if it
was less than the minimum then I want to
see how much less than the minimum was
so I'm going to take the difference
between the minimum depth and it minimum
depth is going to be like greater
because it's a little bit further away
so when I do this subtract I'm expecting
a positive value here so if it's greater
than the depth threshold then what I
want to do is I want to move the whole
range up to this point so I'm going to
set the death-mask you look up and in
either case I'm going to take the depth
min and set it to depth right because I
always
want to pick that okay if that was not
true meaning that if instead of being in
front of the men it was something else
Chuck to see if it's greater than the
max if it is greater than the maximum
what I want to do is take the difference
there between and again depth is the
higher value now if it's further away
and if that is less than the amount that
we want to consider then we're going to
expand the range to include it okay so
then we come through and now that we've
produced a range definite ended up Mac
what we want to do is produce the color
value so we take the combined color and
we assume that it starts at zero we take
the used sample count and assume it's at
zero as well because we have not
accepted any samples yet and then we
then loop through all of our samples we
take the depth value okay that's
obviously wrong we take the depth value
at this particular sample so that was a
bug that would cause the bug we saw so
that's good that probably fixes that
particular but if the depth value is in
the range that we are allowing we will
fetch the color value out right we will
then adjust for RGB we will sum that
into our combined teleTracking and we'll
remember that we had one there at that
point we will then grab the you know
after we've some dildos up we will grab
the maximum depth value right and that's
going to be our fragment that we will
then look at the inverse of the sample
count factor you know we could do is
write this here to make it a little
clearer so like there's our depth now
we're going to write our color so I take
the inverse sample count which is just 1
over whatever how many we used and then
we're going to take the result color and
we're going to make that just be the you
know the adjusted combined color so the
combined color has n colors in it we're
just going to divide by n to produce the
average we then square root that to put
it back into gamma space
and we write it out alright so we fixed
one bug there hopefully that bug was an
important bug and we'll see so looking
at this here we're definitely doing
something wrong
first of all we still have the artifacts
or at least some of them but we also
aren't getting smoothing along our edges
so we must not really be allowing the
range to be proper I so I want to check
something here I want to change this
depth threshold to be like really big
right so this should basically just some
everything and I want to verify that it
does and so if you look there it does
look like that is sort of what's
happening right you can kind of see that
we are now getting smoothing along our
edges so yeah
Unitas had an interesting idea
I mean rinse I don't know how
interesting it is but I wonder what
would happen for depth peeling purposes
if we just always took a particular
depth sample meaning if instead of if
instead of trying to process the depth
values if we just took samples zero of
the depth it wouldn't quite produce the
right thing because sometimes that would
be from a different that would be from a
further away primitive but since you've
already averaged the color together
because you multi sampled it might work
still not great
gasps we really just want to be able to
do the thing that I was talking about
before which is just take the average
color of all the things that have the
closest Z value and then the closest Z
value and we just want to force the
original pixel shader at the fragment
shader for all the primitives to just
write the same Z value for all of the
samples that it writes in that pixel
right that's really all we want it to do
but unfortunately I just can't figure
out a way to do that because that would
be so perfect that be exactly what we
want I think we would have no artifacts
in that case but in this case we
definitely have plenty of artifacts so I
really don't know what to do about that
I also don't know why this wouldn't have
been a reasonable death range I'm a
little confused about that it seems like
the depth values are not what I would
expect them to be because like look at
that that I must have something wrong
there because that's a huge like
remember the depth value should only
range between zero and one right I mean
we're pulling these values out of the
death buffer they should only range
between zero and one so this is like a
tenth of the entire depth range and yet
it doesn't seem to work
maybe that's because the non-linearity
of the depth range I'm not sure but it
is a bit weird right so really you know
if we take a look at how we wanted this
to work right really what we want to do
is just track you know the depth min I'm
going to delete this because I'm not
really sure there's anything worth doing
in here so I'm going to save depth new
news
you know really what we want to do is
there's just this right I mean you know
I could do it like this right all we
want to do is say you know if you give
us the minimum give us them into a
sample that's going to be the one and
then when we come through here we just
do that
right I mean that's what we really want
and that I think would just work I must
say my something up there but that I
think would just work if we knew that we
would always write the same values for
pixel here we've got depth min let me
just make sure I did this right you go
through all the samples we say depth min
oops
that's bad there we go
so this just always takes the minimum
sample right and then it a ver ajiz
everybody who was at that minimum depth
sample and the problem that we get with
that obviously is that because we're
still writing different Z values per
sample we end up in a situation where
those test values are not all from there
they're not all representative right
they're not all giving that same minimum
value but I contend that's what we want
right that's what we actually want to
have happen and so again the problem
that we see is that in here right where
we're actually doing this doing the work
this is this is the shader that's
actually getting called multiple you
know per sample what we want in this
case is to be able to set our frag Z
in a way that won't vary per sample and
yeah I just don't know how to convince
it to do that I think what we tried to
do before is to say centroid and that
was you know supposedly something that
would create you know that was
supposedly something that would create a
value that was going to be constant
across the pixel I think we looked at
the documentation on this and it wasn't
as clear as I would have liked but
basically what we ended up doing is
passing a different Z in and overriding
it right so you know I think it was
actually frag depth that we wrote here
and
[Applause]
and basically what we did is we said
okay we're going to have an input Z in
that input Z is going to be something
different right so the only real thing
we needed if I remember correctly to do
that right was we said okay we do we'd
say if we have a frag depth coming in
from if we have a devalue that we want
to use for all the fragments coming in
from the vertex shader that we can force
to not interpolate for sample then what
we'll do is we'll say okay the frag
depth is going to be that the frag Z for
comparison is going to be that as well
and then everything else just runs as
normal right because we can produce
multiple colors that's fine we just want
to you know make sure that we only ever
produce one V value for everything that
we write for this primitive whatever the
primitive is right I and so in order to
make that work we just needed a thing
that was like centroid you know in f/32
input Z and this just needs to output it
[Applause]
right that was it and so we had to
produce a Z value and the V value had to
be you know transformed and all that
good stuff
so whatever the Z value was that we were
actually using in this case it was the
modified Z right we take that modify Z
we'd have to make sure that we actually
did our divide right just like it would
do and then we needed to put it into the
range 0 to 1 so that was going to be a
negative 1 to 1 range
[Applause]
but that's it right and so if I remember
correctly we tried that and it didn't
work right
cannot construct this type void
I guess it doesn't like just this
instant
oh no I see what it's looking at somehow
we get to my colon in there I mean a
regular coal instead of stomach that's
your half so this is a version of that
code right that's doing in theory
writing the same z-value per pixel right
so there - every sample inside a given
pixel should have had the same one I
think and again the problem is again
with any graphics card thing like this
it's very hard to figure out whether
that's happening now if we play with
this a little bit more because again I'm
just you know I'm just kind of shooting
in the dark here I have no idea but one
thing that I need right or would want is
some way of seeing how many unique
samples we actually got in that case so
what I could do is say you know if we
wanted to we could produce a shader that
sort of just tried to count the number
of unique samples that we were getting
and draw that somehow so you can imagine
how we might do that right if we if
you're it out this entire block and
instead of doing that block we just
implemented a little thing that does
counting and again this is strictly for
debug so it can be absolutely horrific
what I could do is
[Applause]
just just make it N squared because why
not right so I'm going to pick up step a
and this B so this will compare right
two loops it's a loop from zero to
sample count and then from whatever the
current sample we were on to the stamp
account I'm going to do plus one because
I only want to compare against different
samples and I'm going to do minus one
here because obviously I don't need to
do the last sample compared with itself
so well loop over every single one and
what we'll do is we'll say if def a is
not equal to depth B we'll do unique
count plus one so that will basically
give us a counter it says how many there
are
we'll say the result color a equals one
and then the result color are those we
wrote clergy equals there's no color P
and then what I'll do is just say the
result color B in this case equals the
unique count and I want to multiply that
unique count by something that will
boost inside because it's only going to
go between zero and eight right
well it will at least be I guess we
would say the unique count starts at one
because even if all the values were the
same
we would still want one right
if we're actually talking about that
value so if all the values were saying
we'd never increment this so if there
were two values in there that were
different we would increment it there so
this is how many pairs there are that
are different right so it says you know
is this value is it how is it different
from all the rest of the values is this
a different value traveling if this is
the best way to count this concept so
let's think if there were three
different values in here the problem
with that is we count how many pairs
were different and it's not how many
different values there actually are
right
so I think what we actually probably
want to do is break out of that loop as
soon as we find one so if we just loop
through and say okay if we find a
difference then this color is a unique
color right there isn't another one
where I should say it differs from other
colors in the buffer we go to the next
one
of course we we would still find it yeah
this is not doing exactly what I want
also we don't want mints in here so what
I really want is something that's more
like okay I look at this color well it's
a death value I look at this depth value
and I want to make sure that I count
this depth value if it's new but if it
already equals something else in the
depth buffer then I don't want to count
it so I think really the correct way to
do this would be to sort of do it the
other way around which is to say that if
I've seen something in the depth of her
up to this point that is the same as it
don't count it so I think the correct
way to do this would actually be to say
well the first one's obviously unique
let's go through it I should just yet
this is the better way to think about it
it just gets clearer
[Applause]
so I think this is that we want to do
something more like this so we say okay
for each color we assume that it's
unique get false inches other so we'll
assume that this color is unique we take
a look at the depth that's all right we
assume this depth sample is unique we
take a look at the depth we then loop
through all of the other thing colors we
depth as we've seen so far starting at
the first one coming to this one and we
say if they're equal then this can't be
this is not unique right that's the N
squared way to count the unique colors I
think right I think that's proper so I'm
just going to see what happens there in
this case again the maximum value
therefore can would be the sample count
so what I want to do here is basically
divide by the sample camp
and multiply by the maximum color value
right which is one so this this here
would give us something that gets
brighter based on how many unique
samples there were at least that's my
assertion boolean expression expected
[Applause]
okay um so here we can sort of see you
know obviously one thing that we expect
to see which is that you know this is
happening mostly on the edges right
which is what we want because multi
sampling is only supposed to happen on
the edges so the fact that we're seeing
multiple samples on the edges is is kind
of what we would expect right
unfortunately this doesn't really tell
me whether we're seeing two at the edges
or one or whatever so what I would
rather do here I think is maybe be a
little bit more explicit so let's go
ahead and set result color to one but
let's take a look at unique count and
say something like if unique count
equals one then the result color RGB is
going to be something like that and
let's just say two three and greater
than or equal to four like that right so
if there's one sample we're going to
call that uninteresting if there's two
samples we're going to call that green
if there's three samples we're going to
call that yellow and if there's more
than four or four or more we're going to
call that red right okay
um so you know what I'm looking at here
is all green so what that suggests to me
is or what that says to me is that
unless I wrote the loop wrong we are
actually getting only one outside only
two depth samples at the at those
locations right which is a interesting
start okay but I truth be told I have
absolutely no idea why that would be in
a lot of these cases what I would like
to do is find out is that actually valid
for this area right here for example so
we're you know these two things these
two triangles what I want to know is are
there two samples at this on the longest
line because the two triangles
themselves are abutting and we're
getting samples from either of them or
is it because we're still writing
multiple different Z values per sample
for a single permanent and what I could
do there is just like I don't really
know I don't really know any way to
figure out what I want to figure out
hmm
[Applause]
hmm I say so if we take a look at what
I'm actually looking at here right
that's anywhere the depth samples vary
it alright so we're counting how many
times we get any variance in the Deb
samples so for example we should be able
to prove a couple things about this so
for example if we came here and said
well alright let's suppose that we set
the input Z to the same value all the
time so the fragment Z that we were
going to write is just going to be 0.5
and there's nothing you can do about it
so basically like the values are just
always the same right and so we should
see here right is we should see that
everything is black and the only
possible way you can get non black is at
places where you're going to see through
to the literal background right where it
was literally just to the background and
that pretty much looks like it here but
it's a little bit hard to tell right we
probably need to be able to flick
between modes here which I suppose we
could do
[Applause]
so here's some of these crazy parameter
things here I'm not sure we probably can
if we want to just put these in the
OpenGL renderer right so if we wanted to
we could do a thing where we were like
[Applause]
something like this
so when here I could say something like
[Applause]
something like that and then when we're
in here looking at this when we do
resolve multi-sample I suppose what I
could do is say well okay you know if
look you simply see bug move this up to
the top so let me just do it as a knot
and then in here we would just say
[Applause]
and I believe we do we capture those
settings right it's just current
settings
[Applause]
so in theory that will force a a
recompile or it should have but doesn't
appear to have
I guess one thing is we do have that if
changed so we need this function here to
include it so remember right now we're
writing arbitrary Z values so our sort
is completely busted because it has no
information to work with so it's just
kind of order based at this point so
then if I come in here and I turn on
debug in theory this will actually turn
on debug so that's definitely good to
recompile but it doesn't look didn't
look like it actually did recompile
although that may be because
[Applause]
we do recompile consult another example
where do the settings the settings do
get snapped there and when I pound to
find make sure I actually did this right
when I pound to find multicentric debug
do actually do that right so that looks
roughly correct let's give that shot it
didn't delete the program I wonder if
that was confusing I don't think it
would have so something else appears to
be wrong there I'm not sure what right
like I would have expected that to work
let me let me go ahead and see what is
actually happening in that compile step
it looks like that compile step is not
properly making that switch between the
two different kinds
all right so the first compiled holds a
sampling debug is off but that's exactly
what we would expect let's take a look
here we turn it back on so now my the
assembling debug is one the format
string let's just take a look at what it
is to make sure that it actually
produced the right thing oh all right
now not only just I wash so here we go
it's multi-symptom debug is one oh hi
that's good but we actually use the
actual whole use the actual value i
define
so now we can flip between these and man
does that compile take a while or for it
to settle down right but at least I can
see that I can verify that it is what I
expected right which is that the only
place the fragment values differ is
where the background showed through
because obviously that's got a different
V value right so you can see very
clearly that that's what was going on so
I'm relatively satisfied that that's
okay
so at least we know that like our
counting is working at least to a
limited extent correctly right where
it's not completely busted it does work
a little bit so now if I actually set
the input V like I was you know supposed
to be setting it so doing the actual
taking the actual Z bias value and
dividing it so now if I take a look at
that and go okay now where am I getting
the different values from and I turn on
the multi sampling debug here you know
we see that it's happening at all of the
primitive edges which again is roughly
what we would expect that have happened
yeah so the only question I really have
here is
I'm trying to figure out if there's some
way that I can verify separately and I
don't know how to do this but I'm trying
to fear if there's some way I can verify
separately that along the edges of a
particular primitive
we are getting the same values
hmm so I do think there is something I
can do for that
so you'll notice when I'm flat on all
those go away which is good so if we
look up here so here's here's what I'm
going to do so I'm going to propose and
I don't know you can food you think of
this so I look up here what am i what am
I looking at with these dashed lines
right well that's the top of the tree
which touches the edge of the texture
map so it's the edge it is on the edge
so when the alpha value is positive
which is in this case we're getting
multiple samples there now one reason
we're getting multiple samples there is
because the background is included but I
can take the background out of the
equation right I can instead say okay
when we're doing our counting don't
count the background so inside this loop
when we do depth the DEF a right what I
can do here is say alright if depth B is
the background or just a is the
background skip it right so
for cutter indentation fighting me okay
if def a is not equal to 1.0 and depth B
is not equal to 1.0 right so basic
saying if I take backgrounds out of it
and they're still not equal then we will
consider it to be a match I'm sorry and
they're still equal then we'll consider
your match if either that's the
background we're just not going to count
it right now I don't know that I did
that comparison correctly
so that is very bizarre I must have done
something wrong there oh right I I guess
I want that the other way if either of
them are the background it's not unique
it's not a unique sample we don't care
about that at all right
I suppose that's not quite fair though
[Applause]
because that doesn't handle the case I
where we have something unique across
the Becker so I just need to get rid of
any sample that is no actually guess
that is that's right I think I am right
[Applause]
right so I need to say if either than
equals 1 so if islands the background or
they are equal to each other then this
isn't a unique pairing that we're going
to care about
even weirder
[Applause]
so now a theory I have taken the
background out of the equation
and what you can see here is that it did
eliminate those tops right so what that
means is that we're not getting multi
samples when we only have one primitive
right if that's what it looks like so
now let's see if that really is because
we did the same centroid thing just
trying to verify the best centroid thing
worked so here's that centroid bit the
input V so I'm going to come here and
say well our a we've got the frag V frag
depth all this stuff if I was to just
stop oops if I was just stop doing that
right so I'm going to I'm not going to
use the input C at all I'm just going to
use allow it to do its standard multi
sampling so now do I see multiple
samples up there because I should right
I'm expecting to
holy moly so now everything has multi
samples and I do still get the ones with
the edges all right so that you know
appears to be at least it appears to me
that that is doing what we wanted right
and if that's the case then I'm not sure
why we're not getting the anti-aliasing
so now we have to go figure out if that
if that really was the case you know
what am I missing here because something
is going wrong we don't get any blending
when we try it this way
but we should because if that primitive
edge you know like if those primitive
edges are writing the same value the
whole way and I guess another way I
could do that right is I can just focus
on this guy right here so let's take a
look right there's no you can see right
there there's there's absolutely only
one sample right there along that edge
and yet it is pre clearly not anti
aliased so if i take a print screen of s
guy right and i go into paint and zoom
on in there
it's pretty hard to tell maybe that
isn't alias there's so much blurring in
there it's very odd blurring you know
what I think that's the stretch blur
that's the blurring from stretching this
up I'm going to have to go into the
super slow mode that's one-to-one
because the the blur at the end is
making it so I can't really tell let's
see here there's going to be bad for the
framerate the Scotch card cannot handle
this at all
very old graphic card cannot handle high
resolutions
[Music]
all right so let's take a screenshot
there or at least I try to take a
screenshot there and if I seated can you
stop doing whatever you're doing we have
more than one version of Visual Studio
open I don't know we just did all right
doesn't matter anyway so let me go ahead
and take a look at that
hopefully I captured it oh great it
captured it with that big in the middle
all right let's try that one more time I
really got a switch to a machine with
the modern graphics cards is nuts trying
to develop on this thing we also have to
make our camera interpolation code not
the frame rate dependence you can see
it's oscillating the spring of the
camera is oscillating there
so theory this is one-to-one so let's
take a look and yeah you can see there's
like no blending at all so unless the
counter is broken we know that there's
only one set of depth samples there so
if there's only one only one depth value
across all the samples there so what
that suggests to me right is that we
should be able to do our primitive thing
properly I oh and you know what I just
thought of at least one reason why we're
not getting the smoothing there although
this it doesn't really help fix the
artefacts that we were actually trying
to fix so boys realized is so when we
take a look at this we're always going
to get that depth range right we're
going to do that that depth I'm sorry
we're going to get that minimum gap then
we have some everything has a minimum
depth we then need to make this be
something that composites with other
things so the fact that I was tracking
the used sample count is actually wrong
we want it to be darkened based on
samples that it doesn't take so the
alpha value gets reduced right so what
we actually want to do is always use
that always use the full sample count
[Applause]
right is what we actually want there
because what I was doing before is
saying well if we only had three samples
in this primitive and the rest were
forcing behind it well let's just forget
what the color was of those three
samples but that's defeating the whole
purpose of the multi sampling across the
edge what I wanna do is say if they only
have three samples and there were eight
sample total so I want to take 3/8 and
make that be the resulting color for
this thing right and so you can sort of
see that now at least doing that
operation but it's not summing up
properly and you can see that because
you're getting those bands in there
and that's a little bit more puzzling
because the theory you know if you got
three samples on one of them you should
have gotten sighs a samples on the other
one so they should add up properly right
but of course that only is correct if
the Alpha part is correct
and I suppose that the part that we're
not really dealing with here correctly
consider modifying the Alpha value here
right when the combined color comes in
if we're summing up the alphas
I still think that should probably work
correctly right because if we sum
everything up then we screw it the color
because the problem is we're trying to
produce premultiplied alpha here and I
guess I'm not sure this is that classic
problem of life gamma correction is so
awful it's because premultiplied alpha
and gamma trypsin just don't work
correctly together really and you get
into the situation where like okay so in
this in this case right I've got a
compliant color value that I'm you know
I'm loading out premultiplied alpha from
test from texture maps and such and when
I get those values back I'm summing all
of them up and so the question is at the
end I'm going to have a different alpha
value than what I started with for any
individual sample how do i reproduce the
correct premultiplied value that would
have been what those were if they had
been summed up just as regular colors
and then mapped back and I'm not sure
like in this case the in sample count
thing right it's going to reduce the
total alpha whatever it is at and the
colors you know is that should that just
work I can't quite tell
I mean I guess I can experiment with it
a little bit I could say something like
well when you lose the color value go
ahead and unpromoted alpha you know that
would look something like like that and
then when you're done so when you
produce the average value do it back
[Applause]
doesn't really seem to change the
results though
although you know what I just are we
still act did I accidentally still do
before I go down that road did I forget
to turn off the M let's go on so I don't
know I am not sure why we're getting
that I'm going to switch back here to a
lower resolution and I really just do
not know where that's coming from
so two things one it would be nice to
fix this and then see if we could get
any more improvement on what we were
doing however I would point out that
even if we do we still end up in the
same sort of problematic position where
we would have to depth fields executing
across the scene right across the two
triangle scene so I do also wonder here
whether this isn't just a just an
absolutely impossible task that we're
trying to do here right you know maybe
if you're doing desk feeling the only
way you can really smooth things is by
over sampling and that's what you should
do I don't know
I really don't because obviously you
know we turn off multi sampling all of
our artifacts are gone so we have a
really nice renderer in that case and so
all we want to do is smooth those edges
I wonder if the correct thing to do is
just to draw at a higher resolution and
down sample it right and it gets rid of
all that complexity I mean we could try
it right I think all we have to do turn
off the multi sampling and then Astra
high-resolution right there's 2x over
sampling it's a box filter so it's not
going to be great but you know we'll see
what does it look like right
so let me go ahead and take a sip print
screen of that
and there you can see some of that right
sampling going on there it's not great
smoothing I'll be honest it's kind of
somewhat nonsensical smoothing even I
don't know how its producing those
values this don't even look like proper
box filtered values to me that looks a
little bit wrong I would be lying if I
said that that looked at all correct
are you zoomed back out
because if you look at this lime what
you should see here is even stepping you
know this should be the same range of
color value because you go down and what
you're seeing instead and I can zoom
right in on an obvious case right here
is one pixel of one color one pixel of
another color and then the same color
the whole way down I guess I could
convince myself that that was just
because that's the corner so maybe
that's correct because you know you've
got right here to right here your if you
imagine what that looked like beforehand
there was an extra line in the middle
and so you're getting capped about yeah
okay yeah that's that is I guess that is
correct never mind
so that would be with 2x over sampling
let's try 3 X again this is going to get
really slow this graphics card is not
really good enough for what we're doing
here
ah and now I think about it that's not
going to help is it because when we do
our down sampling once you get it's not
it's not going to do a bit wide enough
filter we would have to implement our
own sort of process of sampling it down
twice so the only thing we really can do
is is to X because that the bilinear
filter will do yeah which is not great
so if we wanted to try the over sampling
approach we'd have to do something a
little bit more clever and so in here
where we're doing our let's take a look
here so we here where we're kind of
doing our final operation this is the
part after the DEF peel is done so it
does all the def peeling there we would
need to
make this final stretch be something
that's sort of operated in the loop so
we'd have to you know well wouldn't
really have to operate in the loop we
could just make a single sampler that
takes lots of texture samples so it news
that it does a down sample by a certain
amount and so you know rather than just
doing by linear filtering it could take
significantly more samples who have
wanted to he could take 16 samples right
it could take 16 by linear samples even
if you wanted to so we could make it
take a lot more samples if we wanted to
and then we could render at a higher
resolution unfortunately yeah on this
card
it's just going to be way too slow what
we could do however is run the lower
resolution and like for example you know
if we still just ran at 1920 by 1080
right and then down sampled - hmm a much
lower resolution that would work at
speed on this card and then people with
a higher-end graphics card obviously can
just run it 1920 by 1080 and would be
over sampling like 4k or something like
this hmm yeah so I really just don't
know I guess we have one more thing we
could try tomorrow and that is a little
confusing but we could try to figure out
some way to make it work which is we
could try to do something where we have
the multi the depth peel buffers
actually work in multi sampling mode
which maybe is something that could
happen I'm not really sure how that
would work so I don't know all right so
we've tried two things we've seen you
know a couple different results but we
don't really have a good answer yet I
guess I'll go to the Q&amp;A for now and we
will see we will see I don't know what's
the best what the best approach would be
let's see gee bouzouki says I can't
compile the code it's saying paste
written what is pasted in here but not
having support for this makes no sense
because they have a r9 390 which is a
newer card than you have you tried what
we did in today's stream which is
setting the setting the version number
to pound 150 instead of pound 130 have
you done that yet I did that on today's
stream I don't know if you caught that
for ostrich I haven't really followed
along with how you've implemented
peeling but what if you separate out 3d
objects and run them through a different
shader that doesn't do peeling well we
need the 3d objects to go through the
peeling is the only thing we're doing a
depth free pass without multi sampling
help I don't think so because that's no
different than just doing the multi
sampling and then during the resolve
picking one depth value because that's
the depth free pass would be picking one
depth value right it would be picking
the closest death values so as far as I
know doing a depth free pass without
multi sampling is the same as what we're
doing now we're picking diff men right
you
flying flower what you think about SSM
peg SSM says video compression thing in
your opinion sir a better way to
implement a video oriented program i
sorry that does not sound like a
question for me sounds like a question
for somebody who does video stuff
cheaper caleb if you want the same depth
for each multisample couldn't you write
the depth as a separate vertex shader
output with centered interpolation that
is what we did right that's that's uh
that's exactly what we did that's this
right here and it works so we can
actually get that the problem at least
from what i saw was that if I went to
then use that information I still end up
in a circumstance where when two
primitives abut each other they're going
to have different V samples across that
scene and I don't know really any way to
resolve that right like there's nothing
I can do about that particular thing so
it seems like kind of like almost to the
point where we've got something but I
can't uh I can't really figure out how I
would get any further along that line
yet so here's what's running currently
right and so in this case you can kind
of see that that well
you can see the situation right here
we're like hey all around the edges now
we don't get multiple desks ampuls so
that centroid sampling worked great
unfortunately at the scene between two
triangles you do get multiple samples
and that's not fixable in any way that I
can think of right
what do you think about essences unless
you do not want to just simply sample if
you want the same we do the center
everyone it works
subversion okay so this is Dee Mizuki
asking it's all question okay good I'm
glad changing Japan 150 works and yes
that's the version of the sampling
language are trying to use so which
version of GLSL is the pout when you put
version pounds something at the top of a
shader that's saying this is the version
of the sampling length of the shader
language I want to use and although this
graphics cards driver which is an older
ATI very old decade old at this point or
whatever it allows you to use sampler to
DMS in the actual shader in version 1 3
0 it's not supposed to so what happened
was we had had the version at 1 through
0 and then started using Stamper tuna
TMS it just led us it's not supposed to
so your car probably has a more
compliant driver which air is out in
that case so changing it to 1 5 0 is
correct because that's the shading
language version that actually includes
sampler to DMS without extensions Sergey
well of surged RGB oh its Sergio hey
Casey sorry about the cursor but could
you try creating a new canvas to see if
it still happens I missed the start of
the stream but people told me that it
only happens with welcome input is that
true yeah actually it does appear to be
true so let me show you so here's the
mouse I'm just drawing with the mouse
right now and you can see that it's
totally in the correct position right if
I draw with a cursor it's sorry with the
welcome it's offset
so I don't I mean I can try creating a
new camp i but it doesn't seem like it
has anything to do with the canvas
because it's just the difference between
mouse and there's just a bug between
mouse and and Wacom tablet so the Wacom
tablet mapping is wrong fry to where it
thinks the the cursors what I think is
happening there probably is that the
Wacom tablet has a higher resolution
than the screen in the mode that it even
showed that when we went to the Wacom
thing when we first popped over here it
showed this thing was like the whole
area right know how to get that to
happen again
so I don't really know how to make that
happen again to what it was but
hopefully if you went on the now yeah I
guess and of course thank that's not
doing now I don't so I don't really know
yeah I'm sorry I wish I could give more
information about this because the new
version feels really awesome actually so
I would really love to get it working
properly and that seems to be the only
thing here and I don't remember it being
it didn't seem to fix it when we did we
did do a new canvas when we first tested
it I don't remember that having anything
to do with it but yeah the the drawing
feels really snappy now so I feel like
there's just something wrong with the
mapping and everything else is pretty
great actually this is also happening I
don't know if you can see this on the
screen but when you scroll around it
jumps weirdly and I don't any kind of
field like that might be the same kind
of bug because that offset again is like
maybe fighting it's like using two
different offsets occurs right it looks
like the exact same bug almost it's
offset by a similar amount right and the
other thing I would point out is the
offset changes so up here the offset is
very close so it's correct at the upper
corner and gets less correct as you get
further down right so it says if it's
taking this region of the cursor and
mapping it to the whole screen so it's
deadly just like a scale it's like some
kind of a rectangular scale problem like
the Wacom tablet is giving you back
something that's in a different
coordinate space and somewhere it's also
probably giving you back some scaling
factor or rectangular scale rectangular
remapping that you have to apply I guess
right and that's not getting applied
properly but I have no idea since I
don't know very much about the Wacom
drivers I have no idea where that data
would be or what the likely culprits but
something like that is happening
Nicholls hi Casey do you have a few more
good scientific programming papers to
get me started on a good habit of
reading long stuff for coding I do
remember those from papers I loved in
the rasterization bridge one maybe there
are some lighter reads to begin with so
I'm not sure one here's one that I might
recommend I so and this is will be
relevant to handmade hero because when
we when we do a real random number
generator we will care about this so one
thing is this I think this paper is
probably an accessible one um sometimes
it's hard to know how accessible
something is I guess when I read it
originally I wasn't a sort of looking at
that exactly but this is Melissa
O'Neill's paper on / muted conventional
generators I think that's what that
stands for
I always forget the snappy acronym
Tuesday's their pet is what they're
called right permuting where is it well
anyway it's your paper on taking like
linear congruential generators and other
sorts of like low quality random number
generators and turning them into really
high quality random number generators
with very easy operations and it's a
pretty great paper because it's like a
very good way to generate random numbers
for games because it's extremely fast
and it's very very random for lack of a
better term compared to other things so
you know we'd be doing this on handmade
here eventually for our random number
generator
I feel like this paper because fairly
long it's 46 page paper she took the
time to actually describe everything in
accessible terms
she doesn't slam you with a bunch of
equations and then just let you figure
it out like she's got a lot of text in
here that's just like let me explain to
you what I'm talking about which is
great and so I feel like this would be a
pretty good paper it's a pretty obvious
topic for most people like random number
generation is very easy to understand
the concept of at a base level right and
all of the stuff she's doing she
explains and pretty good like English
basic English descriptions before giving
you anything specifically mathematical
about it and you know includes plenty of
diagrams math sort of stuff it also like
I said happens to be a great paper like
just the actual technique happens to be
great so feel like this would probably
be a good one to look at um that'd just
be my guest you know and it's got you
know code in it right which is another
nice thing if you're trying to be more
accessible you know she's just like
here's the you know here's the actual
piece of code and talking about right
instead of like obfuscating it behind a
bunch of equations which she could have
done right and I mean then she has
equations in here and she could have
left it at that but she doesn't right so
I would say that might be a good one to
start with like I said it's long and
detailed so you know if you're willing
to put the time in it's explained very
meticulously there's not a lot of hand
waving or you know go figure this out
yourself from these equations it
actually talked says what it says
it's a really good technique so it's an
interesting thing to read about and
useful and it is about a topic that you
know you should be already familiar with
so you're not coming in cold so I would
say maybe that's a really good one to
start with I don't know
oh and again I guess I should well you
saw me how you searched for it
type in PSG's space O'Neill and you'll
get you know her homepage or the paper
or both on the front page of the Google
hit so that should be it's easy to find
it that paper house 1955 coming longtime
no news uh we're still just not quite
ready to release press stuff yet we've
been working on it but we yet it's it's
a little it takes a long time we have
one programmer for a very ambitious
project like this so we're hoping that
stuff up pretty soon
but it's still a little bit off so
shouldn't be too long I guess it's what
I'd say we probably will release some
screenshots first is what I'm guessing
but you know we'll see if thread
behavior is considered to be completely
random can we leverage it to our random
number generator um
thread behavior is not completely random
I don't really feel like that is a
reasonable thing to say
I think thread behavior goes through
lots of different permutations of the
order in which things can happen but I
really don't find it random necessarily
I mean at the bottom line windows
scheduler happens on regular interval
updates so I just don't know that that's
a good source of entropy if you're
looking for a source of entropy for non
cryptographic purposes you know there's
one built into your processor so you
know that's going to be easily as good
as thread behavior
remember that is not what we want there
I don't remember the mnemonic for it
already Rand that's what it is um so you
know if you really want some kind of
hardware randomness RT R and is probably
what you want it's basically like a you
know nominally cryptographically secure
random seed you could use unfortunately
it's probably not cryptographically
secure like there's probably like you
know the NSA backdoor in it or whatever
but we don't care about that in a game
right we don't care if the NSA can
predict what the random you know we
don't know we don't care if the NSA is
really good at binding of issac because
they can now predict like you know which
item drops you're going to get so you
know if you really just wanted Hardware
you could do it this way and that's
probably a lot more sane than trying to
use some kind of thread behavior to do
it which I think you've run into a lot
of problems with because it's not so
random
Cubert Caleb isn't PCG less favorable
than something like X or shift for games
because the stepping function can't be
sse optimized um well like I said it
depends on exactly what you're doing
with it
but PCG an extra shift PPG is just an
additional step on X or shift right so
if you just build your game with X or
shift and you have parts where you want
to have better random numbers right
which I would argue world Jen is you
know if particles maybe we don't care an
X or shift is fine or whatever right but
if you have a situation where you want
to do like world generation like you
know when you're actually doing the
rogue alike parts of your game you want
those random numbers to be higher
quality and I doubt you care how SSE
optimizable they are right so if you
find that X or shift with the
permutation step which is what PCG is
right PCG just extra shift to the
permutation step if you find that for
some reason the permutation step is too
hard for you to optimize then you know
you can just not do that in the few
cases in the game where you're really
performance bottlenecking on your random
number generator but the world
generation part of your code is probably
not bad right what I don't know is
having not tried to do an SSE optimized
version of PCG where is that permutation
step
sorry I don't really remember where in
this paper the XOR shift+ modulation
step is I think I already passed and
unfortunately no here it's right here
so I guess the first thing I would ask
is what is the inefficient part of this
as far as SSE is concerned
is it because it's a variable is it
because it's a shift I guess the problem
is that you can't in like sse2 you need
the shift to be in a immediate it has to
be a fixed value is that the part that
you're concerned about
the 64-bit ad I don't know how hard that
part would be I don't know I did did you
look at the 32-bit I thought there was a
32-bit state one as well or maybe
there's only 64 64
so here's the thing she doesn't list the
32-bit one here but the 32-bit output
and state one would not have a 32-bit
state vector so it would only be the
variable length shift that would be the
problem but I do agree that the variable
length shift is a problem since it took
Intel forever to add that in
let's see Tec how come there are
different V values on the diagonal on
the same sprite it's a tan epsilon issue
or do they miss something it's not an
epsilon issue that's just correct right
and that's why it's a problem that's why
I was saying that's a problem I'm not
sure how you get around it can just not
a bug or a weird like floating point
inconsistency it's just correct when you
have multiple samples from a sprite
whose V value is changing along the
diagonal right the only reason we're not
getting different Z values per sample
inside the interior of the sprite is
because we did that centroid to force
them all to be the same but otherwise
they would vary because that sprite
member has different Z values as it gets
taller as it goes upward it gets higher
and higher zero closer and closer to
values will actually be lower Z values
but yeah so the problem is multi
sampling kicks in when you're on the
edge of a primitive and of course that
diagonal is the edge or primitive if the
edges of the two triangles and since
each triangle is covering different
samples those the actual sample value
there is just what one of the samples
right and if they don't both pick the
same sample then they're going to pick
different Z values right and I don't
know that you can ever force like I
don't know that there's any kind of
graphics card magic to force it to do
something other than that you know you
would need time that forces it to pick
sample zero and always use sample zeros
location which maybe you could do
somehow
I don't know
but it's a problem so we'll have to
think a little bit about what we want
our solution to be to that or just move
on and leave it because it just it's you
know we now know that like our non multi
sampled version is what we want so we
could just move on and say look we'll
leave it to the saucy graphics
gentleman to tell us someday what the
right way is to integrate multi sampling
into this pipeline are not necessarily
multi sampling but some sort of edge
smoothing and we'll just punt for now
because it's not going to affect the
rest of the game it's an option right
it's an optional thing you turn on and
so we can just make that be something
that we punt for you know for later all
right so I'm going to I'm going to wrap
it up already bit over time here
all right so let me close this up thank
you for joining me for an episode of
hand made here oh it's my pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow the series at home you
can always peer to the game on handmade
hero org and it comes with the source
code so you can play around with it at
home we also have forms that you can go
to if you want to ask questions the
patreon page if you want support the
video series a schedule bot tweets
schedule at you so you know we're going
to be live and an episode guide where
you can find past episodes with a great
annotation search feature right now -
that has recently be added that's
awesome so that's a great place to go
check for more information that's it for
today I'll be back here tomorrow at 12
so so noon Pacific Daylight Time hopes
different back here for that will either
decide to pump the multi sampling for
now or if I happen to have some other
idea want to try we'll try that idea
so we'll either move on or we'll try
some other idea we'll see what happens
but otherwise pretty happy with the
renderer the Deaf doing part works great
so it's really just that that polygon
edge smoothing is about the only thing
that I think we really have to worry
about it all all right soaps the air
from back there tomorrow till then half
of programming I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody