hello everybody welcome to handmade Hero
show recode a complete game live on
stream we are gonna be doing a bunch of
surprise streams all throughout December
here and well I guess late November in
honor of Krampus laughs which of course
is the Krampus run as you know Krampus
plays a big role in handmade hero and
one of the things that is celebrated
regretfully only overseas as far as I
know we do not have we do not have a
Krampus loft here in the US that I have
seen definitely not in Seattle that I've
ever seen but basically what it is is
it's a bunch of people dress up like
Krampus and they run around the streets
chasing little children around because I
don't know it's you know they want to
scare their children I guess for some
reason it sounds fantastically creepy
and exactly the sort of thing that I
think would be cool and so we have
always sort of structured something
around Krampus time for handmade hero
and I think it's December 5th
traditionally so it's coming up here so
here we're getting a bunch of streams
extra streams and we're not necessarily
gonna be doing anything out of the
ordinary on these streams it should just
still be normal programming although we
may do a couple crazy things because we
have more streams maybe we'll do some
handmade ray at some point maybe we'll
do some other stuff I don't know we'll
see but for today we're just gonna do
straightforward handmade hero because we
had a bunch of stuff we wanted to do
that we were in the middle of so we're
gonna jump right into that and let's
talk a little bit about what that is so
if I load up our sort of current state
of handmade hero then as you know what
we did the previous couple of weeks is
we've done a bunch of work on art
pipeline stuff because we have a bunch
of art we want to put in the game and it
works pretty well now except for the
fact that we don't have annotation
really ability oh that's that's a little
surprise for later if you are wondering
why the PHP interpreter is is runnable
on here
there's gonna be a little surprise with
that at some point as well but we'll
talk about that later so what we want to
do here is take a look at the annotation
stuff that we need and figure out ways
that we can make those annotations
editable in-game and specifically what
I'm talking about for example we tried
loading in cap our asset data here at
what you can see is although our
pipeline works just fine loading in all
of our art assets now we don't have any
ways of doing stuff like saying how big
the cat should be so it's way too large
and we don't have any way of properly
snapping the cat together we're so like
the hat head piece goes on top of the
body piece and so on there could be ways
of doing this externally if you have a
different tool chain so for example if
your artists work with something like
spriter
or something like flash then you can
potentially use those file formats have
data in them that you might use for this
purpose but our our our art assets are
just made in Photoshop which means there
is no bone data there's no skeleton data
that we can look to to give us that
information as a result we need to sort
of augment the data that comes in with
that information so we need the ability
to make those point definitions and
those size definitions ourselves since
Photoshop really doesn't do it and so
what we want to do is just have that
ability we added the ability to specify
those things to our file format what we
haven't done yet is make a way to
actually edit them but we have done a
bunch of work along those lines you can
pick things in the game now so I can
select things and we even made it so
that our little debug UI here that we've
been using for various things is now
sort of accessible outside as an actual
editing tool as well and so we're sort
of poised to allow editing in these
things that we have not actually done
the implementation of it so what we need
to do now is we need to go implement
some of that UI so that we can actually
edit that those elements of our art
assets that that you know just don't
exist anywhere
there is no existing data we can load so
we have to create it ourselves which is
fairly common in games it's it's not
unusual at all that a game cannot rely
entirely on our tools or the source art
tools in this particular case in
question to produce the complete set of
data that they need so augmenting art
with data specific to a game that is not
cut like commonly set up in the art tool
from whence the data arrives that's not
really unusual it's actually very common
so I'm gonna load up oops no I'm not
because I'm gonna spell it wrong I'm
gonna load up handmade in-game editor
and just zoom down to the bottom there
and show you kind of what's going on
here inside asset editor we wrote the
code already that would sort of layout
this stuff we say like here's the
alignment points for this thing and you
know here's some editing operations you
might do on them and then we also have a
UI kind of starting here right here in
Wi you can see we sort of got the
beginnings of a system that would allow
us to edit these things but a lot of
these functions all we did is we just
stub them out so you know this code
compiles but when it actually goes to
run any of the the things that would do
the work it really doesn't end up doing
anything and so our primary job is going
to be meant to make it so that these
things actually work and allow us to
actually edit the stuff in question and
there's two ways we can really go about
doing it and it's unclear at the moment
anyway which way we really want to do so
our job is kind of twofold is to make
sure that we pick a good way and then to
actually do that way and if we take a
look in here and we look at what we had
for the debug UI well we can see on here
is we've got sort of layout stuff that
already was written to do a lot of the
things that we might want to do so you
can kind of see here when you call one
of these debug UI functions not the WI
functions with debug UI functions they
were capable of producing information
that actually looks if you you know take
a look at here you can see that it's
not particularly specific to the debug
system anymore so I think what we want
to do here is kind of merge these things
in and really it's this part right here
that makes this specific to the debug
system and so figuring out how to maybe
make that not be the case anymore so
pulling this out of the debug system and
making it so that it can operate in both
realms might just be the most effective
way to go because we kind of just need
the same stuff in both so there doesn't
seem to be a lot of reason why we would
want to implement that stuff twice so
what I'm going to do here is I'm just
gonna look through the debug state and
see what is actually getting used now
you know you can see here a lot of this
stuff it's very generic and it would be
really easy to pull it out it's not
specific to debugging at all it's things
like the font scale and the font
information these sorts of things really
pretty basic and so I think unless I see
something surprising further down it's
really the like interaction tracking the
render group these are things that would
be common to both systems for sure and
just you know just looking at them here
really does seem like we could totally
pull this out of the debug system so I
mean I think that's sort of a no-brainer
in terms of at least these functions so
I think that's kind of what I'm gonna do
I'm gonna follow the same pattern that
we used on the previous stream where BCA
said look let's take the debug state out
of this equation let's find out what
breaks will repair it in the debug
system and then we'll move it over to
the other UI system so what I'm going to
do is exactly that I'm sort of gonna say
look let's get rid of this line here
let's see what has to happen we're gonna
assume we'll get this because this is
the thing that we knew that we needed to
do stuff like draw text so what I'm
gonna say is let's go ahead and
and just merge this over and then force
the debug system to use it right so I'm
going to ice it out of there put it in
here we're gonna call this a dev UI
layout and deal with the fallout from
that and we're gonna call this here
where we've got sort of the thing that
we were back pointing to we're gonna
call that the context so we're gonna say
again just step by step
extra cating that piece of code from its
original context in which it was created
we're basically saying look what are its
actual connections to debug system sever
those and now we'll have both systems be
able to use it by just passing the
actual data from the debug system that
was necessary in in that way both
systems can just keep that kind of data
and feed it upwards rather than having
this system be sort of inexorably tied
to the debug system because as we saw we
actually did a pretty nice job writing
it originally we didn't it wasn't you
know spaghetti like it wasn't
intertwined in there in a way that
really makes it difficult to pull out so
it turns out it's actually pretty easy
so our goal here is going to be yet to
extricate that out and then also here
just say let's go ahead and grab all of
this code and so essentially what we're
gonna do here I think is nuke this file
because mostly there isn't anything in
here that actually is specific to the
debug code you look and I just don't see
very much of that in here that there
really isn't yeah like I'm just not
seeing much in the way of debug specific
code here so I think we may be able to
just kind of say look all this stuff
comes over and then these fight these
files may just go away we may not have
them anymore in the first place right so
we're gonna drop those in here and then
we're gonna deal with the fallout so
let's take a look at where all the
errors start out again a big thing is
just going to be renaming here obviously
we've sort of got some things that we
changed the name of so in this case here
we've got sort of some stuff that's
gonna that's going to change but that's
you know pretty basic so I can go in
and just do a bulk rename on that and
that won't really be a big deal so
anywhere that we saw layout before I
could change that to a dev UI layout now
and that should be you know pretty
simple here right so let's just take a
look so a layout element should probably
be a WI layout element as well that's
probably true so you know just to be
clear because layout element let's be
honest
doesn't really scope it down
particularly much doops that one this
we're now into the code that actually
already had that so you know we probably
should do the the modicum of work there
that's necessary to just sort of make
sure that's named in a way that makes it
unambiguous about who we're talking
about layout pretty generic term so you
know how it is
so in here where we've got debug IDs are
equal that really should be WI because
these these are dev IDs now I believe so
I didn't know we forgot to rename that
but it looks like we did so if we take a
look here at where that's happening in
in sort of the debug ID space here we
probably just want that to be placed
somewhere more specific so let me see
dev ID I don't know where we've actually
got that defined here we can say there
if that's something that people want to
be able to do we'll just say you can do
it okay so that should take care of that
now let's go back to what I was doing
before so again in here we kind of have
this notion of an interaction that's
currently the one that's being used and
that's something that I think we want to
pull out into that context right so what
we want to do is we want to say that
inside I mean you know it's permanent
state really so I think we probably want
to say that this is the permanent State
that's sort of being kept you know for
the most part so I don't know we could
you know if we wanted to be really
discreet about it you know we could do
this and have another one in there I
just don't know if we care so it's okay
to be a little piggy here I think I'm
not really assuming that there's gonna
be a whole lot of wastage there really
so I think we could probably say hot
interaction here and then you could just
say look if you know what the context is
that you're using just pass me that and
we'll check it off there and off we go
right I think that should basically do
it and then all of these things here for
text our app and get text size and so on
I'm not sure what we want to pass in
there but chances are when we look at
what's going on here you can see that
these are sort of cracking routines that
really were just getting the WI context
anyway whether we want to keep those or
not I don't know but I suspect we
probably don't I think it's probably
fine to just add an arrow for the people
who are calling these so I think we
could probably say is look let's just
make this be something that passes the
context in the first place and then that
way first of all this is not necessary
so I don't know why that's even there
but then what we can do is you say look
like pass that in and off we go
and if we really want to make a helper
function later for that fine but at the
moment I don't really think it's
necessary so don't think people are
calling this so often that we need to do
that that they couldn't just use this
format for their call you know I'm
saying all right so that's you know just
the easiest way to deal with keeping
these functions usable in in both
contexts pun intended I suppose and I
think that just continues to cascade
down through a lot of these so a lot of
these things where you were taking a
debug state nowadays you're just taking
a context because the context has this
stuff explicitly right it's got the
scale in it it's got the font info in it
and so any of these things that had to
happen here will just work
I'm gonna move this over to the front
just to keep a consistent ordering for
it you can see here these are basically
similar routines that just use the font
scale to modify whatever the font
parameters are so that having them in
two different formats just made
using and I'll update our type Naumann
clay char here - while I'm at it
someday we'll just go through and like
change everything the f32 because that's
my new mine that's my jam
I'm done with our ours done F is the new
are soo anyway this looks pretty much
intact right that's just going to remain
the same as it was all of these I think
same thing so we really get down back to
here again where we're doing this begin
layout action and again that's gonna
probably take a context now and just
replace that debug state with the
context there so something like that and
when we look at what's going on in here
this all should be still the same right
so all that stuff I think ends up being
pretty clean that we have in here and
layout and I assume we also had a begin
layout in here somewhere I don't know
where that was originally dude did we
have one I don't even know where that
was maybe we didn't I don't know so we
maybe not didn't have that one so maybe
this is all just fine and layout isn't
gonna do anything so that's fine too so
all of this stuff seems pretty
reasonable so far yeah so we're gonna
have to change couple of these things
how they work eternally we'll look the
errors guide us there I'm just looking
at this stuff and it all looks again
pretty pretty clean the tool tip buffer
stuff that's probably going to be
something that gets moved up a bit so
you know tool tip buffer is just a
string we already have that type so we
should probably while we're at it change
that around because that's not really
necessary either I mean you can see
right here that it really is just one of
these so that's a good
so that's really I mean right look
familiar
so we really don't need to have it work
this way we could probably just reuse
this type and have everyone who does
counted memory blocks just use that as
we sort of go so that I'm not gonna
change yet but I'm going to probably
change it before long and again we'll
get to there we're gonna get to there
all right so let's jump back to the
error hunt now I'm gonna go take a look
at this B 32 here what's the problem I
cannot cover argument 1 so interactions
are equal is what exactly it's okay all
right so so that dev UI interaction
looks like it's getting actually copied
in there so I guess what we're saying is
this is actually not a pointer so let me
dump just remind myself if that's the
case is that actually what restoring it
is so what we probably want to do is say
look this stuff here is what we need for
a lot of the stuff so we're probably
going to want to import that over to
here right because we're gonna be moving
this the things in here that are
specific to the use you know to the
stuff in here that's specific to user
interface is gonna want to migrate out
so a lot of these things that were
previously welded into the debug system
will move out to the UI and the debug
system will just retain its actual
information about debug stuff and so all
of this will probably come through like
you know something like this and we will
move the input processing that was
happening here
into here slowly but surely
so okay that answers our question about
whether that should or shouldn't be a
pointer it shouldn't be so that's
confirmed so we should be able to kind
of move on from there these we renamed
because they're not debug fonts anymore
they're just fonts that are used in the
UI and that's fine
again here just cleaning up things that
were accessing the debug state no longer
need to do so pretty basic so here we've
got the WI context being pulled out
right instead of the debug state and so
the layout like so can just be accessed
same with a debug state was and then we
can access any of the other things it
does mean that we've got sort of in the
WI now we want to pull those again those
things that are basically all of these
things here that we were using before
all of that probably lives over here now
right and can be made with this system
rather than the debug system and
probably a lot more of these will - you
know I mean as we come through you know
this is obviously all debug specific
this is debug specific debug specific
probably maybe not hard to say not debug
specific write debug specific and so on
so really what we'd be doing is you know
pulling out a few these probably the
tooltips maybe I don't know it's hard to
say but basically pulling this stuff out
that should be you I and not debug just
moving that out one by one I think is
all we really need to do here and it'll
be a little bit of a slow going because
there's so much of it to extricate but
that's it's easy work right it's it's
it's just shove one code at that point
so we're going to just pull these out
here the render group is arguably
something that maybe should just get
pulled out you know at the outset
because anyone who's drawing is going to
do that we don't really need to keep
talking about it over and over
again here so let's just grab that in a
more direct fashion here's all those
push Rex now I'm just looking through to
see if there's anybody else who's using
it doesn't look like there is so in here
what I'd like to do is pull that out
right same way and just make sure nobody
else here is doing anything there I
don't think they are again debug state
in this case is is really just the
context in all these cases I'm trying to
look to see if we've got any other debug
state stuff going on here is a different
function looks like that's the first
time it's used ok so again since we're
gonna need the dev UI context here we'll
pull it out from the layout and then
we'll just use the context everywhere we
were using the debug state before should
be fine the render group doesn't really
get used much here so I'm ok with that
still being sort of pulled from from the
pointer in this case see starting
baseline why um so you know look looking
at that I feel like and maybe I'm wrong
but the starting baseline y-you can see
here we've got to get baseline situation
here and this is font scale times the
baseline that just looks like it's just
this call being reimplemented for no
good reason
um so we probably either forgot we had
it or we implemented this before we had
it and so really that should just be
that call and so I'm gonna go ahead and
and put that back on there oops did I
accidentally delete a parameter there
yes I did
okay I see what happened so what we need
is just that get baseline context um and
then I think we're good there we go
so now you can see it lining up properly
okay so the rest of this is pretty clean
it looks like let me just
REM highlight I'm not sure why that was
the old style of implementation either I
guess it's been a while spin this code
maybe for coder didn't have it at that
point we made it I'm not sure but
looking through here yeah I don't see
much else again this this is the get
baseline call again so it looks like we
definitely thought we had to keep doing
that at least back at that point but we
really don't
so there we go
and again this stuff here looks like
mostly things that you know should get
converted pretty pretty directly so I'll
go ahead and do that the render groups
get pulled out there tooltip' transform
also something that we have now yeah I
can really pretty basic stuff here just
just basic boarding nothing particularly
interesting and that'll looks pretty
good all right let's keep going here
we'll just use the arrows to kind of
skim so the render group in this case it
looks like we store a pointer to that
rather than the actual render group in
question so we don't really need to do
the aunt address there I guess we will
keep it that way we could make it so
that it was actually stored directly in
there but out know that we want to we'll
think about that a little bit later on
so yeah keeping going here you can see
we've got this debug line buffer thing I
don't
much about what we did with tooltips so
I'm just gonna try and take a look and
see what we were doing it looks like
here we just create sort of some kind of
a temporary holding cell for these
things basically and I'm not really sure
why we did it this way or who even cares
about it I mean especially if are these
things capped I don't know what the deal
is with this so I don't know much about
this but what I'll say for now is we'll
just keep it as it is we'll say that
this thing is just a deaf you eye line
buffer for now and we'll maybe revisit
what this wants to be a little bit later
on so we'll just say like you know
because I'm pretty sure all this thing
is for is for tooltips like that's all
it does and so it probably I can't think
of a time when tooltips tooltips are
just per frame so really you you don't
need it to be fixed size like this you
know it could just be created on the per
frame memory stack so you know again
this might just have in a case of like
early on in the dev stream we don't have
a lot of tools so we do sort of the poor
person's version of it right so I don't
know we'll see how we want to you know
how we want to deal with that a little
bit later on okay moving on let's see
here so here's the way we draw one of
those things and they pretty much pour
it directly over I think default
cliprect
in this case probably again wants to be
something that's in the UI system itself
I can't see or think of a reason why it
wouldn't be basically all this stuff is
over here now right doctor we can kind
of get rid of it so I do wonder if we
maybe want this to kind of be like this
you know what I mean
and so you just snap the pass in there
as opposed to doing a pointer to it it's
kind of hard to say but it seems like
that's probably a good idea I don't know
it might not be and this stuff can go
away here and just be replace by this so
effectively what we would have is
something like this right and you know
this this context it's not really a
context per se it's more just like the
UI
another thing we could say is that it's
just that and so it's more like this you
know what I mean because this is the
central UI structure it holds the
permanent state and so you more or less
just can do that the UI layout might be
a better place for this render group
because this is sort of permanently
stored stuff and this is what you
actually do per pass and so this there's
a strong argument one could make for
moving this from here to here just to be
a little clearer about what's going on
so I think we should probably consider
that when we're done with this pass
through the code so moving on I'm just
going to change these here I'm gonna
change everywhere that we saw a dead
view I context could just be WI all
right
and this will change back to that so
where we saw contexts I'm just going to
rename that
and I think that's it okay let's see
here so not really much to say here
again I would like to think about moving
the render group around so we may want
to change that a little bit in a second
here but that's again a separate issue
sort of let's see dev UI context again
that's gonna sort of change to just be
WY just in case there was any one or
those there let's see here what else we
got going on okay so we know that's
gonna be coming from there now instead
mouse text layout so I guess that's the
tooltip one and so I guess we create
sort of two of these things
two of these layouts that of course
would be a reason not to have it welded
in there although it would be an
argument in other words it does seem
like maybe this is the correct structure
right so when you're going through all
of these things and you're gonna render
something and you need to do a render
group right you probably need to pass it
this way and I'm just trying to think if
that makes good sense you know we kind
of got away with not doing it here
because what people kept doing is they
just passed the UI and they expect the
render rib to be in that
and you know I feel like it maybe maybe
that wasn't the best idea
I feel like though I don't know it's
just a really tough it's just a really
tough call I'm gonna leave it the way it
was because I just don't see a lot of
benefits to doing it it just I feel like
it probably is a little bit wrong and
that's okay anyway so if we are going to
look at what the mouse layout was here I
think that may be a little bit janky so
what I think I might do instead is say
look you just passed me the one you want
so you know you tell me where you want
this thing laid out and I'll lay it out
that way rather than grabbing it out of
here which doesn't feel quite right to
me because why would I have to know
magically where that layout existed
right so that feels a little bit better
coming through here so this right here
the dev's Mouse text layout that's gonna
be a dev you I layout now right and now
we should move on to stuff that was
calling this stuff
um this is just the WI which I now have
put up here and I'll try to gather those
things together a little bit better so
you know here's all the stuff we were
using so you know we've got this layout
the tooltips in the WI right and that
I'll kind of goes together in terms of
stuff here that's you know UI related I
could also sort of gravitate that more
towards the bottom by sort of doing this
and this stuff maybe is what migrates
over eventually so you know you this
stuff will move because just looking at
it here right like all of these things
are debugger based so this stuff this
stuff is all rightfully part of the
debugger and it should remain inside the
debug system and then I think this stuff
here is the UI so these will remain
because it's how the debug system
accesses those UI services or at least
something like this or mean it may get
past this as well because we might want
to unify our editing and debug you I at
that point that seems totally reasonable
too but basically we want to look at
moving this stuff out as we go
now I don't really know what selected ID
count selected ID was for because I
don't remember us doing a lot of stuff
with selection per se so I couldn't
actually say like I don't know that we
did we do stuff with selecting things I
don't think we did yeah I'm not seeing
much there so I don't I don't really
know that that's getting used for
anything anymore
let's just see so we had something like
that I just don't know how we ever
produced one of those we've still got
the logic in there for it
I'm just not sure what we ever do with
it
so it kind of looks like we just you
know I'll be honest it looks like we
just we're supposed to be able to hold
down the shift key and multi-select
is that true I mean it doesn't seem to
do anything we'll have to go see what
that does but that probably would go in
the debug in the UI as well like
multi-select mine as well I mean
probably I don't know since we
implemented it we might as well keep it
so we'll play with that one a little bit
later on when I actually have some idea
of what's going on there right okay so
in here when we're doing oh I see what
that was for that was for multi
selecting things in the world okay I get
it
yeah you can see here this was if this
was if you wanted to use that in like in
in the game like as something where you
want to be able to select stuff that way
which again I don't think I'm gonna use
because I don't really want that to be
tied into the debug system I want the
world asset editing stuff to be stuff
that you can do whether video bug
compiled it or not so we probably won't
use that but you even so okay so once we
have the debug state you know you can
you should be able to do this pretty
directly I think and go from there
what did we actually call this just WI
yeah so I think that's all we need to do
for now on that debug ID interaction is
actually dev UI the interaction really
but we don't really need to rename it at
the moment well we can deal with those
sort of renaming a little bit later
again this is just basic stuff that's
reaching into the state and playing with
a little bit and that's actually fine
alright so render group in this case is
probably something I just want to pull
out here so I'm just gonna say like
render group render group and that comes
from the debug States the the dev UI
right and so we can just get that
anytime we want and now where we were
doing the render group that can just be
passed directly here we'd have to worry
about because we didn't do the arena
occupancy stuff so that looks fine let's
see here so UI transform that's just
gonna be from the dev UI as well so
maybe what I could do here is just say
look the WI is going to get pulled out
I'm gonna try to anyway
and then inside here we can just grab
these from it the tooltips I don't know
because those are gonna have to get
moved out as well so we'll have to
actually do that at some point first and
there because these are not actually
available right now right cuz they're
actually still in here somewhere
I think yeah so I think we probably want
tool tips to be sort of universal right
cuz like they're gonna be handled by the
you I always so again I think that just
kind of gets moved up you know what I
mean
so probably the tooltips end up
something like in here because they're
going to be things that you always can
access inside the UI
so let's see uh when we're doing the
pressing cure for profile bars looks
like people tend to set the next hop
interaction pretty directly all the time
I only know to what extent we want them
doing that seems better if they were to
make a call for that I'll leave it this
way for now because I don't really need
to upgrade this system at this point but
it's a little janky the way that that's
being done so just I figure I just point
that out for the time being the render
group here I'm going to go ahead and
again pull that out at the top because
it's usually something that people want
to be able to use so there's render
group and you know we we probably want
the WI as well it's something like this
and then everyone can get that as
necessary all right so these are off of
the UI now I really wish I don't want to
have it go to the errors for this see
also thing what are you gonna do so yeah
in here we're gonna get the tooltips
from the UI that's going to be off the
UI as well
that's gonna be off the UI - is this a
new function though yet is so we need
the dev UI to be accessible here and I
think we're good to go
oops text that's gonna take the UI get
text size it's gonna take the UI I
really hate that I hate these little
note jumps they're so frustrating they
make it impossible to just quickly go
through your code and fix the basic
errors um let's see so I need to add
something in for coder that skips those
there may already be something actually
I don't know if I have to turn it on
because it looks like you could skip
them by looking if you saw note : in it
you know what I mean and I think it
might have something like that already
actually it gets saw something that I
just haven't put it in mind but I don't
like them uh all right so let's take a
look at tooltips here so that's again
just coming off of this nothing special
happening there again just looking at
the UI the render group pull out here
and the UI as well
all right uh like we're making some
progress here
check your render group yep you're right
um that all looks fine nothing special
happening there look look at how many
times it makes me look at stuff that's
totally irrelevant it's like just go to
the next actual thang and fix okay there
we go
actually this should be pulled out
directly way we've been doing it so only
those should really be involved here and
I think we are mostly good there that's
all the regular debug stuff all right so
this is not a thing anymore we don't
have layout we have dev UI layout so I'm
going to preemptively change it to that
since we know that's what it actually is
going to be and then this stuff looks
like most of this can flow through okay
I'm gonna pull out the renderer oh well
I already did it looks like here
previously just looks like people aren't
using it for reasons I couldn't really
tell you but yeah you can see them right
they're not using it right
so looking everyone's capable of using
that just fine
go that all looks good pretty basic
stuff nothing weird happening here
[Music]
yeah it all seems totally fine yeah
all right yeah so I don't see anything
weird here
[Music]
I mean that all seems good so I need to
make sure that all these people who were
taking a layup for are gonna take a WI
layout now because we renamed that just
to be clear about who was doing what and
when
so this stuff here needs to have that
placed in there but other than that
there's really not much going on here
this is all pretty generic does look
like we need the WI here but otherwise
is pretty reasonable all right so let's
see that's off the UI that is actually
this so it looks like cuz this is gonna
need the debug state so it looks like
this actually will have to be passed
here right so we're gonna do a draw
elements gonna need to that's gonna have
to flow through there
in addition which is a little bit of a
pain in the butt right but that's just
that's just the way it goes
um not sure oh that's just because that
doesn't work on there anymore this Saul
looks reasonable what is the problem
here
Oh so begin element rectangle may be
something that takes a regular layout or
not does it no it's got it doesn't look
like that so ah it's just that that's
fine
so yeah anywhere that was doing a layout
element would have to take a WI layout
element which is fine it's a pretty
basic change all right so again really
non glamorous stuff here
pretty basic but it'll have to get done
to pull this code out if we want to be
able to use it sort of in the general
case so that's all fine that's all fine
too not much to do there god it's so
hard to just fix code when it does this
look at how many there are right
it just says all of this stuff it's just
I gotta find a way to make that not
happen it takes so much longer I'll have
to look last gallon about it I may have
already fixed that on my not to see I
haven't updated this for coder in a
while I don't remember it being this
owners on mine so I think I may have
already fixed this because it probably
would have driven me nuts when the
compiler does that so let's see again I
have to jump through 50 million things
to find out where the next actual error
is which happens to be here that's all
fine
you see skip the notes myself
God go this is another one let's get
baselines right that all looks good
debug draw elements needs to take the
debug state all right um so we're
getting down to it here like a lot of
this stuff is non UI related right most
of it in fact so that's pretty cool
render group is off of the WR what else
we get to begin layouts I think only
needs that it doesn't need the debug
state anymore
I don't really know if any of these
other things need anything different I
don't think they do so I think that's
pretty much just all there is to it
right let's see here undeclared
identifier layouts correct you are you
renamed that otherwise I think we're
good
that looks fine
so this stuff here we we could
potentially share or we could decide not
to share it and I'm not sure which of
them we want to really do because again
we sort of we've got a lot of different
ways that these interactions can work
and I'm not 100% certain how we want to
start sharing those out that's going to
be the hairiest part of things for sure
because there's just lots of different
ways to try and make those systems happy
you know what I mean so I think at the
outset what I'll probably do is just say
look I'm gonna leave these as sort of
doing their own separate functions for
the at first and then I'll probably try
to make them come together a bit more
after that that's my guess anyway and
we'll see how it goes because I don't
know that I really want these the actual
logic here to be miscible like you know
I might want to keep them fairly
separated so the video bug stuff gets
compiled out completely and so it's a
little hard to say how we're gonna want
that data flow to go there's a lot of
ways that it could go but you know we'll
see
um so again yeah not really anything
interesting to say here just manual text
modification and of course it's
impossible to actually update code
because the compiler just really wants
me to know about hundreds of other
places in the code that are completely
unrelated to the air what are you gonna
do by the way did you know this other
piece of code that has nothing to do
with your error still has nothing to do
with your error well yes I did thank you
for telling me
um just didn't quite hit them all here
nothing else to do there all right so
let's see most of these are probably
going to be these now too
so we will do that
and now it looks like yeah so I think
now we're basically done so now what
we're gonna want to do here is
previously where this stuff was being
set up we probably want to roll this now
into the UI system proper so that
basically we you know all of this stuff
right is just handled in the UI setup
and you don't have to worry about it
separate from the rest of the of the
system so like probably what we want to
do here is say okay inside the WI system
you know probably probably in here let
me see kind of jump around let me see
what what did we do for do we ever
initialize those we didn't really
alright so probably what we're gonna
want to do here looking at the endgame
editor right it never really gets an
init call and I think we probably want
it to have one so I think what I'll
probably do is say alright you know
there's gonna be in an it here and all
of this stuff can go into it right so
all of this here except for the push
font
I think that all just kind of wants to
go in here so I'm gonna grab most of
this stuff out
so yeah like just looking at what's
going on I'm gonna have to stay like
pretty much almost all this the global
with global hype part I'm gonna leave
because I don't really know yet where
that's gonna use so we'll take a little
bit of look at that but may it's gonna
pull all of these out into sort of more
of a UI start and end thing because
we're probably going to need these UIs
to link up to each other like I said
they're gonna have to you know we don't
want them fighting over who's processing
user interface or input so we're gonna
need that to be a little bit more
systemic so yeah just looking at this
stuff here this won't have to happen
because it's already gonna be happening
here and maybe this is just something
that gets pet will get passed down to
the debug system when debug start is
called will try to look and see where
that's actually happening and be a
little bit more careful about it but
basically what it means is this won't
have to happen they're looking through
here
yeah the pushing the sort barrier on
there does that actually do something
cuz I don't think it does yeah okay say
we don't use that anymore
so that's over so I think
I mean I think that's mostly it so if we
I think we're pretty good to go there
you know it's gonna want to do its
layout stuff here and so I think I
should kind of just be able to wrap this
stuff up so let's take a look at where
that's actually getting called you know
who's doing the actual distance batch
right and so it looks like we're calling
debug game frame end here and then we're
doing the start and end that way right
and the render commands are coming in
here but the question is like how is a
UI happening exactly so I assume that's
getting called in win32 right probably
yeah
so since the game memory gets passed to
that it's definitely a little bit tricky
to link it up because what we would like
to do is have the UI be accessible in
both places
right and I just don't know how we would
do that in order to keep the debug
system completely isolated it would seem
to me that we wouldn't really be able to
have it tie directly into the existing
UI
and so that seems difficult like there's
a couple different ways that we could go
about doing that one way is we could
make it so that the the you eyes don't
connect they're completely separate you
eyes they happen to share all the same
code but they don't ever share any state
and then you either put yourself in
debug mode or you're either in debug
mode or you're not in debug mode you
know what I mean and when you're in
debug mode none of the other UI stuff
works so you just have you know it kind
of like takes over the the interface and
that's all there is to it
and that seems reasonably compelling
because then you just don't have any
conflation of those two things but I
can't really say what I think about it
otherwise like I don't know but I think
what I'm gonna say is I'm gonna leave
them separate for now and maybe what
we'll do is we'll maybe have it so that
the debug UI stuff takes over when
you're in that mode so that these two
things don't fight with each other now
maybe you never really have to worry
about them fighting because their mouths
based interfaces anyway and so they'd
only fight with each other if they were
overlapping or something I don't know I
mean it's just it's hard to say I'm not
sure one way or the other how I think
that should go so but what I'm gonna do
for now is just say look we're gonna
have an init function like an init UI
and it's gonna set up all this stuff
when you actually go to do a render pass
it'll do this stuff
more specifically although I think we
could just make it so that this happens
yeah it could happen to begin layout I'm
not sure so we'll we'll see what we want
to do with that in a second but at the
moment we don't care about that part of
it so I'm going to port the rest of this
stuff here's you know how this stuff
would go we we can do this one at any
time right and this one here for font ID
we kind of need to figure out which font
we want and remember it so that but
that's you know again easy enough these
things I think have to kind of happen
every time in order to make sure the
font remains loaded because if we stop
using it then you know it will get
purged from the asset system eventually
when it runs out of space so that stuff
all seems pretty basic this has to
happen every time as well this stuff
does not so all of this can kind of just
be set up one time I believe because it
doesn't actually depend on anything it's
just Z offset nonsense that we're doing
for sorting there and let's see so this
default cliprect
is also all of this stuff this is all
the per frame stuff so this is setup
that would happen every frame but this
is setup that wouldn't so all of this
stuff as far as the in-game UI is
concerned
why that stuff can kind of come in here
yeah so I think that's good and it'll go
through all of these things and
initialize them except for this because
this is these are basically like per and
all this stuff isn't so I think that's
pretty good
and again like if you look at how this
breaks down it feels sort of like the
Devi I layout itself would be the thing
that would store these other elements
like the render group part and all that
but the thing about that that's a little
bit weird is that it's you still kind of
have two levels of that because you
could have multiple layouts that you do
inside a single render group that's
using you know the same font and all
that stuff right and the same tooltips
pass and everything so it's really more
of the case and you know maybe maybe
it's like this right um but it's still
the case that like these things here are
really sort of a dev UI pass sort of a
struct because they're not really a
layout because the layout you might do
multiple times right and so that's
really kind of confusing and I don't
know whether we want to bother having
another one of those like it doesn't
seem necessary so it's kind of like
we're breaking we'd be breaking up the
structure just to be pedantic about it
which I don't want to do
but it is worth noting that it's like
definitely a different thing like this
stuff is different you know so it's
we're storing some stuff in here that
really doesn't probably want to be in
there if we're honest about it right so
we initialize it and then every time we
want to you know begin a frame we have
to call it to initialize this stuff and
so then that's where this code goes
right so inside here now we're where's
the the font ID looks like we didn't
save that we want to do that as well
right so we want to be able to like you
know get the font ID get the font info
and the scale set up the transforms and
all that and nice stuff
we want to be able to do that and get
all of that correct and then we also
want to initialize this stuff probably
so you know I mean we don't really know
what this stuff is we'll set it to
nonsense for now and we'll zero these
out just because I have no idea what
else do we do with them
so all of that stuff would then be
initialized properly at that point and
then we would need somehow in here you
know - every time we're gonna go to
begin a frame you know we're gonna have
to call this stuff and presumably we
would also need an end UI frame thing
here as well now the thing that I don't
know is do we want to just link it up to
an existing one and that I think maybe
is fairly compelling that's why I was
saying I think this render group should
really maybe have been a pointer you
know I don't know but it seems like it
would want to because you just want to
tie it in with existing render groups I
don't know there's any reason to have a
separator group it's really hard to say
I just don't have a strong feeling about
it so again I'm gonna leave it that way
I don't know that that's really there
isn't a strong argument for it but there
isn't a strong argument against it
either it's just kind of like hey it
doesn't seem quite right and so you know
that's that's where we're at so that all
looks fine the width should have been
getting pulled out here from the
commands but it doesn't look like it was
I assume that's because of this right
and so if I come through here I can now
get rid of most of this because this was
just set up for this purpose so I'm just
gonna do that and then get rid of all
this
so when we go to do update and render
editor I also again want in here to be
able to do and initialize editor now I
want to be able to do this because I
would like to do that like I said and
then I also want to be able to call one
of these and as far as assets are
concerned here I don't know I mean I
guess we'll keep passing that down seems
okay so yeah so we'll initialize the UI
that we're using and again we've got a
couple of different ways we could do
this we can make the UI actually and
maybe we should just make the UI be
something that the game has in general
in which case actually this becomes a
little bit different right in other
words we could just say alright in hand
made that H we're actually gonna stick
the it in here right so there is one of
these actually I guess it's like that
you know what I mean
and then it will actually initialize
that and instead of initialized editor
being something that does this stuff for
you instead what's happen what would
happen is it just gets a UI to use when
it's trying to do its editing right so
it would be more like saying yeah okay
you know you're gonna initialize
yourself great good for you
when we call you here we will pass you a
WI to use and that'll come from the from
the game state and then you'll just use
that UI rather than making your own
thing so in here where you do a WI
layout you'll do a begin layout and
you'll do it on this UI and that'll be
the end of it right oops
so then all this stuff will just flow
through there pretty straightforward
nothing fancy and it also means that
this commands doesn't have to be passed
down anymore right because it's not
setting up any drawing which I think
it's what we want that seems a little
nicer to me that means in here the
initialization actually occurs in game
update and render when we actually have
to initialize some state so in here when
we say like oh we don't have anything
set up then what we would do here is
call the initialization functions at
that time so we'd initialize the editor
and we would initialize the layout I'm
sorry the UI as well so King State WI
and game state editor would both get
initialized here the assets would get
passed down I think in both cases
they're not really necessary cure but
I'm gonna say that since the editor
edits the assets may be the case that we
roll the assets indirectly right here
and then we don't have to pass them down
anymore that seems a lot more sane
because if you look at how long how many
times we've had to do that it seems like
a lot right so I think a more sane thing
to do here might just be a mutt might
just be to say look that's just you know
there's only one place these things
could come from we don't you know have
some kind of an idea that were some time
some that in some point in the future
we're gonna have like lots of different
assets like pools running around that we
need to like know which one we were
talking about or anything like that so I
think this is a little more
straightforward
that just seems a little bit better
oops
this one um I may keep because it's sort
of actually talking about the assets
more directly and that maybe would go
into the actual asset system so I'm not
going to touch that one at the moment
all right what else we got okay so looks
like for the UI frame stuff so we have a
left edge and a right edge and stuff
like this
so I assume we want to keep tracking
that like the default clip rect however
I think is also probably just tells you
that information so I'm not sure to what
extent that's really all that relevant
so I may say honestly I'm not sure I
care about that stuff at the moment
we'll see we'll see what I think about
that going forward all right
so an in-game editor I'm gonna say like
look it it's the ass that's among other
things so it's going to keep the pointer
to that and I'm gonna initialize it
these don't need to pass the assets
anymore it just needs to pass the assets
same here
[Music]
okay
so I guess going from here now I need to
start merging these things together in
terms of their functionality as well so
yeah like looking at begin UI frame B
this stuff here this needs to get called
now in a sort of more centralized
fashion so in here where we were
previously doing like you know hit test
stuff and update and render editor so
you know I don't really know exactly how
we want to treat the UI stuff as it
flows through but at the moment you know
I'm just gonna do it only around the
part that we actually care about so in
other words this is sort of where that's
gonna happen so I'm going to do begin UI
frame here and then I'll do end UI frame
here and so this will i don't know that
i don't remember if assets needs to get
past that but let's just say that it
does so i'm just gonna let that control
how this works this beginning UI frame
part won't really do anything in
particular at the moment it'll just say
look i'm gonna say what return anything
particular just it'll just set it up to
go and that looks fine and so this will
get the UI and then other people who
want to use this you I could use it so
we could call other editing things here
and we could even Brack and bracket more
of this we wanted to and have it so that
you could call different people I mean
there's a lot of stuff we could do there
I don't think it's particularly good
idea so I'm gonna leave it as sort of a
separate thing that happens outside and
then like I said I'm not gonna try to do
anything fancy there I'm gonna let the
debug system call it separately and use
its own sort of debug stuff now debug
view ID up CBP is now dead letter so
it's not something that's going to be
use anymore so I can get rid of these
two files as well and I don't know that
we yeah we do have a retired directory
so those are just gonna go in there and
not be around anymore so that's starting
to look good I got to get rid of the
debug UI include files so that I don't
forgot any others all right
and then the debug system itself has to
actually call these when it wants to use
them right so the debug system wants to
be able to just you know wants to be
able to utilize the same system and so
the stuff that it was doing to end the
frame in here also has to be the stuff
you know anything that was happening in
the end frame part of things has to be
done here as well so just looking at
that
I think we're basically just talking
about just this stuff here
so think that is basically it probably I
mean it looks like it anyway so I think
that's what we would be doing the mouse
text layout stuff I don't really know
what that was for because again that's
old debug stuff looks like it's stuff
that was happening at the cursor
position or something weird like that oh
no we're just using that for picking so
yeah I don't really know what the point
of this stuff is actually I have no idea
what the what the stuff is doing here
and so I'm not really gonna play with it
right now anyway and I don't care I just
want to make sure this stuff works okay
so we're gonna make sure this gets
called on both ends so it'll you know be
able to finish this up properly and draw
the tooltips and whatever right but then
we also need to call this so when we
were going to do all this stuff before
look inside debug start or whatever we
want to be able to do this here as well
right so you know
so we'll begin the UI frame can end UI
frame here so this can be used and then
in here we would just need to do when we
do our debug in it we would also need to
be able to do the same initialization
for the UI system right so for the debug
States WI system it's got to do it this
way now where it gets the assets I'm not
entirely sure right it needs to be able
to get those somehow Jimmy and I'm not
sure how it would be getting them when
it gets initialized you know what I mean
and so like I think maybe what it was
doing was every time it would run it
would wreak wery for a new font maybe
and I'm not really sure we could do that
so if we wanted to we could move that
query so that it happened every time
that way when you initialize one of
these you don't need assets to
initialize it
the advantageous part of that is if you
updated the font it would update
properly by you know if you added a
better font match can't say that's
particularly compelling and I guess I
don't really know much about how
debugging it actually happens either so
I mean it looks like it just gets the
assets by asking for them right so it
seems like you could just call that and
so maybe we try it yeah okay so not much
left to go over here again a lot of
changes necessary to make these things
sort of separate working systems that
can both share all the code but again
only an hour or two of work is really
not that much at the end of the day so
it is a lot of changes but it's also not
a lot of changes so I'm gonna take a
look at the line buffer stuff here just
see what's going on there it looks like
it needs whichever layout we're gonna do
and so like I saying before we need to
kind of know what layout the tooltips
should have I'm guessing that we
probably just want to use something
about the mouse location to figure out
where we want those to be and it
probably also depends on sort of where
you are relative on the screen which we
at the moment don't really do much about
and possibly we should you know we
should possibly take a look at where we
are in like readjust maybe draw a line
buffer does that I don't actually know
if it does so that's kind of a separate
issue but we could go ahead and look at
what like last mouse pee was that I'm
not sure where we were setting I suppose
that's also something that should be set
here like the mouse
is going to have to be handled here as
well right
yeah so we're also going to have to sort
of start trucking that a bit separately
so for example in here we're gonna need
the mouse position that we're using for
tracking because you can see like
there's a delta mouse value that needs
to come through that needs to be made
more systemic up here and I'm not sure
exactly how we want to do that but it
probably doesn't want to be in here
anymore right
so you know when you go through and
start doing a pass on the UI it probably
wants to be something that's tracked in
the UI system more explicitly and more
directly so probably something like you
know like this maybe like this and so
when you do one of these you pass in the
mouse key or whatever right and probably
we want to make that be a little bit
more involved so maybe when you go to do
one of these things we actually do a lot
of this checking for you so you know and
also that's more like that and so in
here we when we go to do the
calculations of everything we can we can
compute it here right so we'd like set
the new mouse position to be whatever it
was we would do the subtraction and that
would actually be stored right so all of
that information is preserved so
similarly all this stuff here probably
would also all of this would all get
rolled in there
right and so you know we would want to
sort of have all of this stuff get taken
into account weed reset the mouse stuff
we do you know this the unprojected all
that stuff I think that's basically what
we launched so here we would do this and
this and before we did any of it we
would do that so that would get us the
complete the complete set of user
interface parameters there that we would
need the alt UI stuff the whether or not
the mouse was transformed and how far it
moved in either case I don't really know
if the unprojected to quite do it the
way it's doing it there but we'll keep I
mean that I mean the weather the Delta
wants to be in the original Mouse space
or in the unprotected space hard to say
but at the moment we don't really do
anything fancy enough to care so
so I wonder why
what is begin layout taking such that it
wants to of those things Mouse P and the
upper left corner okay it's weird but
fine since the UI has the mouse B I'm
not sure why we really need to be
passing that down anymore but I guess
we'll look at that a little bit later
too a lot of the stuff could start to be
cleaned up I mean all we're doing is
really breaking apart the code here and
putting it in various places and a
little later on we may find that there's
a bunch of stuff we can do to improve
how things are working right since we're
gonna call this couple or use this
couple times here I think I'm actually
going to do this and because you can see
how many times it gets used I'd rather
just be able to refer to it a little bit
more conveniently okay um ah sorry I
guess I did that in the opposite order
so since this is actually stored here I
guess I have to more do it like this
oops this stores it into the UI
structure and then this is a way to
reference it more quickly right so I
kind of have to go backwards with it if
that makes sense there we go
and
all right so the draw line buffered now
what we need here is some way of making
a layout for this so we kind of need to
do one of these here which is the mouse
layout or whatever it's called there
right and so the mouse layout thing just
has to do I don't actually know to be
honest with you that and layout does
anything I think it doesn't but we'll
cross that bridge when we come to it so
begin layout again don't really think
that this needs to happen at the very
least you really don't need to pass at
the mouse PD because we're you know
that's gonna be known by the UI system
either way so at the moment that can go
away for sure and I think we could even
get rid of it here this doesn't really
need to be saved so really it's just the
upper corner that's the only thing that
we need to do here and again I don't
know where that's gonna be but let's
just say it's going to be here for now
so we'll deal with that in a second and
layout I don't know anything about so
we're gonna take a look at it here looks
like it just takes the layout in
question like so and it doesn't really
do anything with it so then I think we
can move on to this I don't know where
we're gonna put this UI so we're gonna
pass nothing at the moment but we're
gonna figure that out a second the rest
of these things yeah like you can kind
of see we're gonna want to pass all this
stuff down so probably what we want to
do here is maybe something like this
and then looking through here almost
done with this very large pass and we're
probably still not out of the woods yet
we got a lot of stuff we want to now go
through cleanup but it you know we're
pretty good right so let's take a look
at begin UI frame so it needs the input
and I think this doesn't need these
anymore right
because assets should not be passed here
all right so that's all good we got more
to do
begin layout doesn't need to pass mouse
key anymore so everywhere in the debug
system it was doing that doesn't really
have to do it we call debug in it we can
just pass the memory well although can
we how does it normally get the assets
preto so it normally gets them by
looking at the game state that's stored
off of the game memory and then if it
can get them it can get them all right
so it could easily do it that way now
again I don't really know where like
whether I could call that whether I can
call this this way it's a good question
what I could do too is I could say look
game state oops game assets assets gets
passed here so they can utilize the UI
and then you know maybe that back here
we kind of do it like this and pass it
in this way right
all right so beginning you wanna frame
doesn't take what oh it needs the input
to be half that hopefully looks like
only debug end gets the input which is a
little unfortunate so we'd like to have
that at the beginning right
I would think hmm so I think I'll just
do it I think I'll just add it cuz I
don't know that we care anything
particular about that doesn't even
really change the the way in which these
things are called I'm also not sure the
extent to which like why is width and
height something that's passed in there
it's not used here so really that should
go away too probably
so it should look more like that and
these don't need to be here also does
that in init do we care about those much
either I mean they're pretty much just
used here I'm not sure this is a good
way to do this anyway so I think we'd
probably want to get rid of that too
there's just a lot we could clean up now
which is nice all right so I'm debugging
here when we're calling this in order to
get the render group that's gonna want
to come out of the dev UI other than
that not sure what else it needs to
really know looks like this I don't
really know what this was for I don't
know what the draw trees part was that
actually something we were using
it doesn't use that layout so honestly I
think this is just nonsense because this
was just all that was was the thing for
doing the tooltips and we don't need
that anymore
so I'm pretty sure we're just down to
this and off we go
so I'll go ahead and grab UI here and
that seems good all right so now I think
we're back to just debugging and I think
we can implement most of the calls that
we wanted now surprisingly I would say
very surprisingly all of that just
worked which is nuts kind of even the
tooltips worked all right so you know
some days you get lucky I don't know how
much time I have does anybody know how
much time I have are we in the QA where
are we in savate what time did we start
this thing what I start at 3:30
probably so we got like 8 minutes maybe
so let's see what's going on in here I
don't really know let's just take a
quick look at what's going on in here
with like these ends section begins
section begin line all this nonsense
right so we now can merge the start to
merge these things together
and so like with the begin line and end
line stuff like we've got now ways of
doing some of these things because we've
we've now opened up access to like all
of the things that we had already
written
so like you know these end element
advanced elements all that sort of stuff
so begin row an end row is really begin
line end line right so we can just say
that that that's what that is and now
everywhere that we were calling
beginning ends we should be able to just
do this and now this this can be calling
into the system that actually does
something right because like I said we
we already wrote it and then when when
we want to do stuff like labels and
stuff like that we now just have to look
at see what do we actually have here for
for element drawing right and how are we
previously doing that so you can see
that we have the ability to do these
basic text elements here so presumably
if we wanted to do some of the stuff
that we had like a button isn't
particularly hard we could probably just
implement that that way trying to think
of what else we got here label F so a
lot of these things I think could be
implemented in terms of basic text
elements and some jumping around and
Squinkie miss
[Music]
I mean because you can see right I mean
here it is
so button is just action button so let
me just go ahead and make that and the
only difficult part is we don't have
interactions for these action buttons
yet
so if we just do this you know I gotta
do a little bit of work here to actually
wire this up but if we're talking about
something like this
we've already got a label as well so I
think you know if we just define this
interaction somehow we probably can make
it work so that we can get buttons
working in short order
oops that's not what I want to do so you
can see we've already kind of got the UI
appearing there right as I move around
here and so we're off to an okay start
but we we just need to now actually put
put some of the rest of the stuff in
there right let's go in and try to get
the rest of those in there so for the
other things in here like you know the
boolean type size that stuff I don't
actually know to what extent you look in
the renderer here
so I don't know to what extent we need
to look at like frame based memory here
I don't think I don't I don't know to
what extent we have sort of support for
this but like you've got you've got this
frame arena right that can stick stuff
on it and I don't know to what extent
any of these things need that like
they're dumping the they're dumping
stuff on here that's basically yeah so
you know they're just dumping lists of
drawing is on there so I guess we don't
even really need to save any of this
stuff so for the most part we can just
use local buffers to print out what
these things are and then be done with
it I think so it's actually pretty easy
to do so yeah so I mean I think you know
and it's not necessarily the best way to
do it but I think you could really just
do this
it's you know I'm Sam and then print it
out in here now we need to actually
thunk through to this because we are
they're passing us an F as well in here
and so we kind of need to do this
version of it only because we have to
use the VA list so we need to do like
you know VA start VA end kind of a thing
I don't remember exactly how that goes
so we'll just look at it here there we
go and there we go so that and then once
we have that we can just call the label
function afterward so that gets a little
closer as well
and so yeah that's almost the rest of
the UI and now we just need some of the
other editable types in there which I
get again I could throw in pretty
quickly I think they're not actually
editable but if we were just wanted to
see them right there just like they're
all like that and I think that's it so
you can see that this will come together
pretty quickly actually or at least I
think it probably will so yeah not bad
we'll go ahead and go to a brief Q&amp;A and
then it seems like we'll be in good
shape for next stream to go ahead and
get the rest of that UI done
looks like we are question free so that
makes pretty easy
all right
you forgot no questions we can wrap it
up
all right thank you everyone for joining
me flips on a handmade here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow on series at
home you can always pier the game on
handmade here org and it comes with a
source code so you can play around with
it I will be back for the next surprise
stream sometime I can't say when at a
surprising time but you can always check
the watch schedule I do put the the
surprise ones on there you know within a
couple minutes of when they're gonna
start as well and the Twitter feed also
gets updated so I think probably
probably pretty soon we'll do another
stream and we'll just go through because
I want to get the UI stuff done as well
and then we can start playing out the
art assets a bit which is also kind of
fun
so hooks to you back here for the next
price dream till then have fun
programming everyone and I'll see you on
the Internet techies everybody