hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are going to basically
read some stuff we wrote today we made a
little utility that creates its what a
you know would sort of effectively be
hand created font assets for importing
into our game but it's just why bother
writing you know why bother doing all
the work of creating them by hand when
you could just write a program to
extract them from TTFN that's exactly
what we did but we wanted to keep the
process of exporting you know want to
keep the process of importing I should
say our art assets into the game as
uniform as possible so everything comes
in as a PNG and then there's just a text
file with the markup in it that says any
additional information that needs to be
in the PNG and this is basically a
correction from originally I just kind
of stuff stuff in the file name that was
an attempt to simplify beyond what you
would normally simplify in a normal
asset import path it just didn't work it
was too cumbersome and you couldn't be
expressive enough in that and we were
gonna have to have text files anyway to
like store things like alignment points
and so I just changed that and said look
the PNG names are just random names we
don't care about them anymore
and we're just gonna have like a import
file that just says look here's the PNG
to import and here's all the settings I
want you to set when you load it in
that's been much better
we're totally happy with that and now we
can basically build our entire game
packages just from those kind of import
lists and really anyone could use that
to build their own sort of packed packed
and annotated file that has all the
additional info you invariably need
whenever you take bitmaps or something
and put them into a game that's always
kind of the bane of a game developers
existence is that art tools are usually
designed to just create an asset
Photoshop just wants to make an asset
and it doesn't have a lot of ways for
you to like link that asset to other
assets and create things that artists
understand cleanly about how that thing
will be related to the game so you
almost always need to have this kind of
game specific markup that you write in
the mill utility yourself or things like
that or kind of in the middle in the
game engine itself like we do that
always ends up happening and you need a
good place to store it
think we've kind of worked that out now
and I'm happy with it so I think all
that stuff is basically done but for
fonts it's kind of a little bit
different because for fonts we do have
all the markup it's the one art asset we
have where the input file actually have
stuff like kerning the things that we
actually need to know and so we don't
want to go have to respec I'd all that
by hand that's the opposite of the point
we were trying to do with everything
else and so what we did is we just made
a little utility called HH font and all
it does is just extract fonts from you
know a font file through windows and
then it dumps those out as PNG s it can
be loaded just like other bitmaps into
our engine and packed through your asset
part pipeline just like they normally
would be it then spits all of the
kerning information out into a text file
as well so that's good too but we never
made anything that actually reads those
font metadata's in so that's the last
piece of the puzzle because we've got
everything else we've got mark bitmaps
with arbitrary alignment points in them
we've got it loaded from sprite sheets
as necessary if we want we've got
streamable and non streamable sound
playback so you know you can import and
chunk up sounds into chunks to be loaded
separately we tested all that and it
works great so all that stuff is done
but what we don't have is a way to
import thoughts automatically at runtime
like we have everything else and so we
want to get off of that old test art
packing thing that we had that we wrote
at the very beginning Panama hero and
now into the nice uniform art pipeline
so we can finally put a stamp on it and
say okay we're done we can build any
assets we want for the game now and it's
all uniform and clean and can be redone
at any time so if we wanted to delete
all our packed files we can just rebuild
them you know which is what you want
that's where you want to be and this
will be the first time we can really say
that because yeah before that we didn't
really have a lot of ways we could do
stuff like that which makes it kind of
made it kind of an incomplete art
pipeline all right so there's two things
I want to do today the first thing I
want to do is just finish up a little
something I even made it to do for it in
here
loading loading I don't know it's maybe
the certificate are um so this by the
way was a good bug that somebody
reported that we do want to look at I
could put that up for looking at later
today but right here I just made a
little note that says hey when we're
writing pings remember we talked about
the fact that right now we didn't write
out multiple rows as separate chunks and
so there's a hard limit of the number of
bytes in the ping data chunk can only be
16 bits worth of length that's just too
small it happens to be fine because
we're only writing out fonts and the
fonts happen to be small but it's
probably worth our time to spend the
extra hour today to make sure that we do
something smart when the size gets too
large because we might want to use this
ping writer to write other things right
and so I'd like to go in there and do
that just to make sure because then that
way our ping writer can write pings
anytime we want and so if we want some
that saves a screenshot or who knows
what we want we'll be able to call that
ping writer and just know that it will
work and not have this weird like hello
I didn't write the ping moment and it's
like oh right
I remember now it's because we didn't
support pings that are as large as you
know 1920 by 1080 so that's just a dumb
limitation to leave in there and so what
I'm gonna do now is I'm just gonna try
to work around that limitation now at
the bottom here this is our little ping
writer
it's just crappy you know we just kind
of kicked out whatever would work but
it's fine for our purposes we don't need
something that's a good ping writer we
just need something that writes a ping
at all now what you can see here is the
error that we're seeing it's this or not
that we would see is we get this to do
here if we want to support larger than
128 by 128 we need to multiplex this
that's the correct comment it does say
exactly what the promised and we'll go
into what that problem is in a second
but what I'd like to do first is I'd
like to provoke the bug so that we can
see it failing then that you can all see
what I'm talking about literally and
then fix it that way we'll know that
it's fixed if I just kind of
shuffle the code around and say I fixed
it I don't really know if I have or not
so it's better to have a case where I
can obviously see the bug that we've got
and then after that we can definitively
say that we fix the problem right or at
least have some evidence we fix the
problem so what we've got is this HH
font utility to you know extract these
fonts that's a good way to test the ping
writer it's the only thing we've got
right now that actually does any ping
writing so what I want to do is I want
to call this with a set of data that
should make it produce font bitmaps that
don't work okay so if I if I go into HH
font that's CPP and I look at like well
something that did work here's an
example of something that did work
liberation mono 20 okay so let me paste
that in here we've got liberation mono
20 I just want the test care set that's
the only care set we've defined so far I
def hht and desu pinged ER are going to
be W temp font and W temp font so I just
want I don't know test out hht or
something like that right and I'm gonna
hit return oops and I'm gonna spell this
correctly there we go so anytime I run
that it should create this directory
with the fonts unpacked into it right so
if I delete everything in here and I run
this I should get the extraction and
when I look at what's in that those
extracted files
I should see something correct so for
example if I just open up 119 here with
I should see you know the correct
pattern with the Alpha and all that good
stuff Windows of course can't display it
very well because Windows is awesome but
if you load it up in a real package you
can see it's exactly what we expect it's
a white character on a transparent
background with alpha set you know
roughly what you would expect that looks
probably what we want so it looks like
the ping is writing correctly let's
delete that and let's try to do the same
thing now for very large so let's say I
do 256 which well we might let's do even
larger let's do 512
as far as I know that should immediately
expose any bugs we've got in the program
that we're kind of counting on things
being small to work and we'll see so
there's the extraction it extracted
everything and then we can take a look
at what we got so 119 is should be the W
again right because it was the W last
time and it should just be a bigger W
but what we should see is that it's
totally not that right and you can see
that we get almost literally what we
would expect the height and width of
this ping are stored in the header file
and obviously that header file I've
started my header file it's good in the
header section that will still just work
so knows exactly how big this thing
should be to 64 by 241 is probably the
right dimensions for the glyph that got
extracted
what it won't be able to do is store all
of the pixel information and what you
can see is it seems to have done exactly
that it's got some pixel information in
here right like obviously but it it most
of it is gone right like most of the
thing isn't there now there's no alpha
in here either I'm not sure why that is
that could be some other bug or it could
just be related to the fact that when
failed to load everything this is
how it kind of crapped out right so I'm
not going to consider that alpha a bug
yet but we may have to investigate
further about why we're not getting
alpha extraction on larger images it may
have something to do a to with how we're
calling Windows right we don't know if
it's the source or the ping writing so
we want to take a look at that later
okay so I'm going to delete all these
and say that's a good way to have oak
the bug or provoke the bug you might say
this line of code will do it or this
execution line I should say will do it
and so let's go ahead and try to fix it
by changing the way that we're writing
out that ping so if I that's not what I
want if I flip over to the ping writer
here what you can see down here is I'm
gonna get rid of this comment because
we're gonna have to fix this this also
we correctly throw out what it was that
and so what you can see here is there's
an Allen and an N 'ln and
be final type here this is the two of
those two things that one means this is
the final one and zero would mean to go
another round if you look at what we've
got here you can see that we're writing
out essentially one I'd at chunk right
and then one be final with a lenin and
end 'land for the entire image what's
supposed to happen is the B final type
is supposed to be 0 for every time we
send a chunk of data and then one on the
last one so the fact that we hard-coded
this to one means we only get to send
down one Len and one inland that means
we only get to send down one 16-bit
worth of length so 6 5 5 3 6 that's the
maximum number of bytes we can we can
push into the data section right and
that's simply because of this Len and
Len so what we need to do is we need to
create a situation where we're going to
repeatedly send down multiple sets of
this to make sure we can so to make sure
that no matter how many bytes it takes
to specify the image we will break it
into 6 5 5 3 6 worth of chunking and
then a last chunk that's whatever the
residual is right and we need to send
all of those down so we're gonna have to
now start setting B final type to 0 for
each of those that we need to do there
and then one at the final one right so
that's what we're doing now okay so how
would we go about doing this well for
starters we need to stop thinking of Len
and end lin as the actual amount we're
sending out that's not what it's going
to be what we want to do first is
compute a total length that will tell us
the size this thing actually needs to be
so before we cast it to AU 16 here we
were computing the right amount it's the
width times 4 which is the number of
bytes in a single scan line of this
image right a single row
plus one bite and that bite says what
the PNG filter is remember this is just
how P and G's are packed in it's always
set to zero so we don't actually use
that bite but it just needs to be there
because the ping is gonna read it and
needs to see the zero - no that's not
supposed to filter we then have a height
value right that's how many of these
we've got so we need to multiply that
out and that gives us a total length
this for all of the cases where the bug
would have hit is going to be larger
than 65536 so each of these here has to
be essentially done in a loop where the
Len and the n Len are going to be like
repeatedly done right we need to keep
doing those over and over and over again
so the first thing I want to do is like
compute a chunk count which tells me how
many of these things do I have to
actually write you know I'm saying like
what what are we doing here and so that
chunk count is pretty easy for me to
come up with because I already know what
the maximum is it's 6 5 5 3 6 I don't
think there's any other limitations on
Len so it can use the full 16 bit range
right well so it's 6 5 5 3 5 I should
say right because I don't think it adds
1 to the value so it's not it's it's not
0 and you know be honest with you I
don't know why they didn't add 1 to the
value so you would never encode one of
these blocks and set the length to 0 so
would right maybe they needed that to
encode as 0 by 0 paying because that was
the only way you could do it it's a
little weird if you think about it like
I'm not sure why they didn't just add 1
to the value because 0 is not a length
that you should never be specifying but
I don't know they didn't do that so what
that actually means is the maximum chunk
size is actually 6 5 5 3 5 I believe
right so let's say maximum chunk size is
6 5 5 3 5 so what I want to do is take
the total length and I want to
divide it by max chunk size right that's
gonna tell me how many chunks there are
without considering the residual I
probably want to say how many chunks
there are including the residual and so
what I'm gonna do is just add the max
Trump size minus one here to just say
look round that up right so you know if
if you were going to use even one byte
over that number of chunks round it up
because I'm going to need that residual
chunk so this is the total chunk count
here and then what I can do is say now I
know that whatever I'm writing in here
whatever I'm going to write in in a
series and we can see what that actually
is right it looks like this right this
is the part that has to get repeated so
I have to write out a be final it has to
be 0 if there's a if there's a chunk
after this one or one if it's the last
chunk we need to write unto Len in an N
Lin nobody knows why the heck the end
Len is there but they decided they
wanted both and Adler checksum and the
length checksum that I got nothing I
guess it's just weird paranoia I mean if
you think about how many check sums are
in here the lemma in the end Lin or a
checksum pair the Adler 32 is a checksum
of the whole thing and then the entire
block also has a CRC check how many
times gonna check the same data ping man
I don't know but that's what they do so
anyway in here what we want to do is say
look we're gonna repeat this stuff so we
have to write out a zero we have to
write out a line we have to write out
the B final type tool and the inland
right so that's what has to happen now
it's a little bit complicated and the
reason that it's a little bit
complicated is because we don't really
want to only write lines we'd rather
just be able to write arbitrary data I
don't know if we're allowed to do that I
think we are meaning I think we're
allowed I guess I'm saying is I don't
know whether I need to make sure that an
entire line is included within one be
final I don't one one of those
blocks right I don't know I don't think
so and I think we would have maybe
mentioned that in here probably if you
had to do that so I guess I'm a little
hazy on whether that's true or not if
you look at the way like our ping reader
works we would not care because we're
just building data out of this that we
then filter and we don't really care how
the filtering happened meaning this only
occurs once we've ingested everything it
doesn't happen on a line by line basis
and so I can't imagine that there is a
restriction there but just be I just
don't know and so I feel like I should
look and see if there's any restrictions
on that I'm just not sure so I'm gonna
look here and see about that particular
part of it
[Music]
I mean I don't see anything
I don't see anything obvious it calls
that out so I'm gonna assume temporarily
until we are proven other till some
improves this otherwise or like you know
the thing doesn't work loading into
or something
I'm gonna assume that I don't have to
keep lines together so I can I can break
the data stream in the middle of the
line because I assumed that that is
allowed the reason I assume that is
allowed because if you didn't do that it
would mean that a ping couldn't store an
image that was longer than 65536 pixels
long in uncompressed mode because
there'd be no way to actually write a
line that was you know twice that long
so I'm assuming you can break a line in
the middle because otherwise would be a
pretty hard limit on the width there
wouldn't be a limit on the height but
there'd be a limit on the width so I
think that we should just assume that
and so what I want to do here is I want
to figure out how I can best write this
out and it's a little bit harder than
you might expect because in order to
insert the zeros in we need to do some
fancy footwork if we wanted to we could
create a temporary buffer and maybe
that's the easiest thing to do because
we don't care about the speed
particularly much we could create a
temporary buffer copy the stuff in there
with the zeros and then just write it
out in chunks I'm gonna leave that
possibility open if this gets too
confusing I'll try to write it that way
first but if I feel like it's getting
too out there I might back up to that
because since we don't really have a lot
of reason to care about the speed of
this thing at the moment anyway I don't
necessarily know that I want to do it
that way
that's just my sort of that's my feeling
on it anyway but we'll try we'll give it
we'll give it a quick try and see okay
so we know that we're gonna have this
many chunks because that's the total
length of the of the image will get
encoded by that many blocks of 65535 we
know that we're gonna have to write out
essentially this u32 here is
for the adler 32 checksum so this part
here like that this whole thing is
actually how we're gonna have to figure
out how these rows go right and so the B
final type the Len and the n Len are all
things that have to go like like row
over chunk over head so we kind of know
that there's this thing called chunk
overhead that includes this right this
all of this stuff oops sorry didn't mean
that sorry and then that I so we know
that we're gonna have to write the total
length of the image and we know that
we're gonna have to write the I dot and
we know that we're going to have to
write the Adler checksum so it looks
like that but then we know that we're
going to have chunk overhead which is
this and I'm gonna put these as you
sixteens here we know that this is the
chunk overhead the B final type is what
are you eight yeah so we know we're
gonna have the B final type and then the
the Len and the n line and so we know
that this is gonna repeat every time we
have a new chunk so we have to do this
to figure out right what our total chunk
overhead will be the whole time we have
to multiply the chunk count by that
chunk overhead that'll give us the
length that it actually will come out to
be in the end right so then we can
actually start to work out how we're
gonna write this thing now we know that
we're going to be in a loop and we know
that we're gonna be in a loop loop until
the chunks run out right so we know
we're gonna write the number we said we
were gonna and then we know for each
time we hit the Len what's going to
happen there is we've got something like
a length remaining that's going to be
initialized at the top of the loop and
say look we need to write out however
much we think we need to write out right
so we computed this ahead of time we
know we need to write that much out each
time through here we're gonna have to
sort of clamp that amount
as necessary right so what we can say
first is all right look let's just set
the length equal to the max chunk size
right I and then what we can do is say
if that length is greater than the
length that was remaining then we'll
clip it to the length that was remaining
right that way we're only saying right
out 65535 unless that would be more than
we have left and if that's more than
have left we'll clip it down then we can
compute the in line as normal which is
just the you know ones complement of the
length no idea why that's in there but
it is okay
we'll then go ahead and do a struct copy
to write those out here's our B final
here's our length here's our inland what
I want to do is move the B final down
here because we're going to be writing
out to different kinds of B final we
need to say if the chunk index is the
last chunk so basically if chunking if
chunk index plus 1 would be the chunk
count like we're at the end right then
I'm going to write out a 0 I'm sorry a 1
because that's final otherwise I'm going
to write out a 0 because we got more
chunks coming so we need to set B final
conditionally then we can write it out
all right
so at that point I think ooh this is
what is this
wait a second why is our Adler 32
checksum at the end of the end Lin is
that right that has to be wrong doesn't
it
is the Adler through checksum on every
single one of these for some reason I
thought the Adler 32 checksum was only
at the end all right back to this back
so where does this go
at sexual value of the uncompressed data
excluding any dictionary data computed
according to adler 32
so I don't really know where that's
supposed to go
because it says it's the checksum of the
uncompressed data so if that sounds to
me like we would need to sort of roll it
meaning we need to sort of keep the
Adler running but we need to keep it
running in here so I think that makes it
makes us need to do this a little bit
differently we kind of cheese doubt on
this right because we we sort of had a
way to sort of cheat because we were
writing it all out in one that's not
gonna work anymore so I think we need to
roll that Adler checksum into what we're
actually writing your and I'm saying so
I think what we want to do there is have
a way to just push the adler checksums
ourselves i think that's definitely the
case
so this way of doing the Adler not gonna
work so we're gonna ignore that part for
now and I'm gonna come back to that in a
second again that also kind of argues
for us doing the the temporary buffer
copy is annoying as it is just because
that would allow us to just do the Adler
on the whole block and we don't have to
like piece mail out the Adler correctly
or whatever so yeah but anyway so let's
take a look at what we're doing here as
we write this out I'm ignoring the Adler
part of things cuz that's just not gonna
happen so that's that's out of here
we'll solve that in another way in a
second looking here at the B final type
out struck copy inland and I write this
is not gonna fly anymore the Y height
sort of stuff because we can't loop over
anything predictable here we've got to
pull chunks out of the image as we go
based on however much the size remaining
we have left right so what we need to do
is keep the Y value and the x value as
sort of running
values that we kind of you know continue
to process as we go so if I grab the Y
out here and say we're gonna start at at
this X&amp;Y
right that's sort of where we're
processing this then as I come through
here I can pull out the pixels at that
particular location and at you know push
as many on as I can as we go now we have
a problem here which is that the X of 0
and y 0 this is not really quite going
to work because we sort of need to be
able to specify that we're on the about
the actual like for lack of a term
negative 1 so we could there's two ways
we could do that one is we could say x
equals 0 is where we write out the
filter the other is that we say that the
x equals negative 1 is the point where
we write out the filter and I don't know
which of those we want to do but
probably best to keep it all in you 32
maybe let's say and so what I would
probably say is okay as we write this
thing we look to see you know we're
gonna we're gonna do some kind of a loop
here I guess we probably do a while loop
on the length remaining so we're
probably gonna do something like this
right yeah before I can do a while loop
on the line' there oh and also as we go
here this length remaining when we're
done with it we need to say all right
we've we've processed that much all
right so we're gonna do a while loop on
the line' here and we're basically gonna
say look we're gonna keep writing until
the line' is gone so what i want to do
is again not sure exactly how to write
this code well but we'll see if the x
equals zero then i'm going to need to do
an out strut copy on the single byte
that's just the no filter byte right so
I've got a no filter here I need to
write that out and so I'm going to write
that out like so I that's
only if x equals zero right and then
we're gonna move x1 forward otherwise if
X is not equal to zero then we're gonna
try to write some amount of the row
however much there is left in the row
we're gonna write that much out or if we
can only write on a portion because we
don't have enough left in the current
chunk you know we'll deal with that
right okay so this is how much we're
allowed to write out we've written out
one of those here so now we can you know
we can essentially do that reduce the
length by one move the X by one if we're
not in here then that means we can write
out an actual row now this is also where
we would push the adler so like we would
need to do something like this
right and we have some kind of a like
right something's gonna happen here so
we need to append that one byte that
we've got and maybe it looks like that
like here's the one byte
no I'm saying so we need to do that and
then we also need to do a I guess what
do we have what do what do we call the
stream out it's what is it it's not out
struct is it just like out sighs yeah so
we can do an out copy to do this and we
would do and add their 32 append of the
same thing right so we're going to have
like some length that we're gonna do
here like a roll in and a row pointer
right and then we're gonna do an out
copy here of the same data something
like that and we have to compute what
those are but we're gonna want to do an
out copy to the stream and then an
append of the adler checksum then at the
very end we're gonna want to do an adler
32 to like produce that value we're
gonna want to do an end on some
intermediate struck so do you see what
i'm saying about how we had to redo that
because you can see we're pushing pieces
in we can't use the old trick of just
take this range of
in the output stream because we can't
actually there is no continuous range
it's the uncompressed part that's
getting checked summed so it doesn't
include things like the B final type the
end line in the Len it's just the parts
that actually contain the pixel bits and
that no filter bit that's just because
of the way they picked out the way they
were going to use the z lib part in PNG
right so that's just something we have
to do it's not pretty but we'll live
with it
so once we've got that then we know we
can also do this here where we've got
okay x plus equals the Roland the length
is minus equal to Roland
keep these symmetric we could also do
this right so that's you know another
way to make sure that part is is a
little bit more symmetric so we'll leave
it like that
we couldn't even do it a little bit more
like this if we wanted to something to
think about we could say all right
there's a rollin there's a row pointer
and and that's all we would really need
right and so then when we come through
something like this
we can say oh the Roland here is one the
RO is the address of no filter right
which is just some value we'll leave up
here I guess I don't even need to leave
it up there and can put it right here
just needs to still be around but when
we go to write it and then we don't
actually have to do this right so we can
basically say look we're gonna write out
something each time through this loop
and that something will be given by this
size and point at you by this in the
case where we're just writing out that
zero byte we can do it like this in the
other case now we just need to figure
out what are we actually doing here
right and then we know that will do that
advance so I think that's all fine and
furthermore when we actually do this
part we should also be able to do okay
if x equals the wrap amount then we can
do something like that so we can include
the
app checking here where we can say oh
alright if you were going to overflow
you know if you were going to move on to
the next line by doing that and the way
we would do that is say well whatever
the width plus one is well that gives us
our X right now the other thing I would
say here is X is probably not a good
term so I might call this B instead the
reason for that is just because X
implies that it was actually a pixel
it's not it's just a bite we don't care
about pixels in this loop at all we're
just thinking of roses bytes the only
reason we care about rows at all or the
Y value is because we have to every row
insert that zero to tell it to shut off
the filter right yeah I wouldn't have
done the PNG spec that way just as an
aside a lot of things dumb about the PNG
spec but this one's particularly done
the reason is particularly dumb is if
you don't want any filtering what you
would rather do is just have two bites
that you insert every time you have a
set of rows and the bite is just how
many rows you want to specify the filter
for and then what the filter is so you
just say like two v60 or something
or two d50 as the maximum you could
specify and then every 256 rows you just
write that again the reason I say that
is because it's really unusual to change
the filter every single line most pngs
just use like one or two filters for the
whole thing or even just one filter for
the whole thing and so you either want
to turn the filter off entirely or trim
to a specific value most of the time or
like for different blocks of lines would
you put the chances that you change it
every line are probably pretty low and
now you end up inserting all this stuff
and just makes it weirder another corner
there but doesn't matter if PNG is not a
very good compression format anyway so I
don't know why I'm pointing out that but
that part's probably meaningless what I
just said
nobody cares anyway so if we go back in
here let's just take a look at this so
we know we need to reset the the B every
time we hit the end of the of the cap
the end of the row here so I'll leave
that in there that seems fair so all I
really need to do now is figure out how
big I'm gonna write out one of these
role ends here and in order to do that
what I would need to do is and honestly
you know what I could I could make this
even a little bit simpler what if I just
did it like this it's not really simpler
in terms of what's actually we've
generated just in terms of reading it um
we could just assume that we're running
out no filter and then we'll just say
look if we're not then we do something
there we go so to figure out how long a
row is well this is the longest a row
could be right actually sorry this is
the longest a row could be because we
don't include that that plus one there
that's that's happening in here right
that's the longest a row could be so
that's the longest we could write out
but of course the B value that's in
there is going to take away from the
maximum we could write out for the
particular row that we're on right so we
effectively need to do something where
we say look let's subtract away the B
value but of course the B value is off
by one because the zero we're not
including in these particular rows so
what we need to do here is say oh yeah
well whatever the B value is that you
know we +1 to get ourselves to the max
when we do then we put the B in there
subtract that off that'll remove this
one and however many bytes we've written
in this row so far that gives us back
the correct role and then finally the
row here Jimmy it's just gonna be based
on whatever the Y value currently is
right so we know because we know we've
got the pixel values that came in here
right so we know we've got these so the
pixel values again is just going to be
okay let's take the pixels plus y times
width that'll get us to where we need to
be to offset by the B value once we're
at that location
to add however far we are into the
stream but again it's also offset by one
right I think that's all we really need
to do to write out a full row the only
difference now is remember we can't
always write out a full row because we
may have not enough Len left to write
that out
so if rollin is greater than Len we need
to clamp that down to be Len
otherwise we're fine I think that's
roughly what we need makes sense
now I don't know if we want these Adler
32 nonsenses to be happening in multiple
places so I don't really know how we
want to do the Adler 32 part of things I
might suggest to the suggestible
listener that we do something more along
the lines of like put throw this into
the hash stuff just because I don't know
we can and say when we're doing like
hashing nonsense there's also this disc
wrap here and so we would have something
like alright there's an adler 32 you can
say begin adler 32 and it will like
start you off with those values you can
then say adler 32 append and that will
allow you to push some number of things
on there like so and then you can say
add and I would start end and it will
like you know pop out the final value so
we already have the code we need for
this looks like this and then
I think we're pretty good now whether we
not want this thing to be nd and then
swapped or not is hard to say because I
don't know if Adler thirty two builds
that in or not I'm guessing that it
shouldn't be so like my thinking is that
this should actually not be there and
then what should happen is in here when
we do this this is the people who
actually are doing that cuz Adler 32
probably isn't specified in nd in this
I'm not even going to bother to look cuz
I really do not care but I think that's
the way it should be because I'm I'm
assuming that's the ping spec that's
saying write it out this way and not
some part of Adler 32 itself that
literally mandates you must do it this
way right that's my assumption anyway so
I think we just want to do this where we
say all right
here's how you you know add stuff into
this thing right and off we go make that
a little more explicably
I think that's all we really need and
then that way we can just say all right
those Adler 32 values there that are
that we were computing I think those
wait what did we want those to be those
have to be computed in 32-bit space
right pretty sure that's actually the
case yeah right because we we have to do
the mod ourselves for six hours ago so
we want to be able to do this I think so
we if we kind of chalk that up in there
is there oh that's that was the age file
my goodness all right well it's one heck
of an h-file I'll guess I'll shove that
up at the top in case we ever want to
break that out
okay so that's about it I'm gonna go
ahead and just break these out here so
they're a little bit easier to see also
if we wanted to we can store that it's
two sixteen bits because if you look at
what happens here they don't actually
need to be 32 bits anymore because you
know you're only actually using them as
16-bit values for storage because if you
know if the only thing these can be is
mod 6 by 5 to 1 they can never be larger
than 16 bits I'm not going to bother cuz
who cares but it's just worth noting you
know just as a thing to look at all
right so now if we want to actually use
this code what I would say is all right
first when we start at the outset of the
chunk writing we're gonna want to do
that adler 32 here i'm gonna want to
create my start right like so and i
guess we'll just think that's what I
call it everywhere then we come through
here are all of our pins work that way
and then finally at the end we end right
and then it looks like the role ends
subtract here because this is Len is 16
right this subtraction
needs to also be only 16 since I this is
always clipped to be no longer than this
that should never be a problem but just
pointing it out so that's a sketch of
the routine it turned out to not be that
bad there might be some like bugs
working in here so we'll try to work
those out in a second here but this
isn't so bad that I wanted to fall back
to just creating the temporary buffer so
let's just not just seems better not to
these are also already putting things
into a stream which is already wasteful
so it's like why compile compound the
waste I guess
might be one way to think about it
anyway
we could have a by the way for like this
right here we could just have this be
like an out append because we don't
actually need to copy so in fact let's
just do that this out copy doesn't need
to be an out copy the reason for that is
because it's in a buffer that will
remain until after we already write the
stream I think I mean I don't know I'm
just leave the copy room now but it's we
don't really need to write so it's worth
noting we could do that if we were in a
speed scenario later on we don't
actually you know we could just append
that and then let it write it out that
way all right so what we want to do now
is we want to debug this probably we
don't really wanted to bug it this way
cuz like crashes and stuff right they're
just gonna it's just gonna roll over and
die or do something in fact it looks
like it's it's stuck in one of our loops
there right so you want to do is open up
the debugger for this so that's what I'm
gonna do and I want to keep this command
line because we want to be debugging one
that's big so that it'll hit all the
cases we're trying to get I'm gonna load
up
h/h font here but again this needs to be
changed it needs to be changed to this
new line here that's gonna be like a big
big font here we go
so that should be good all right save
that off and so now in fact I can even
just stop and break this into wherever
we're we're we're stopping here so
here's some the append chante code
let's see ups behind my head there but
our Adler append out copies so what's
our role in here
is zero all right well that would do it
what's our be vet whoa so we got him off
by one in here it looks like we came in
here at some point presumably because
you know we would have done the one
first thing we would have done is just
rode out one zero with the no filter we
would have advanced by one and
subtracted the length by one this
wouldn't have fired we would come back
in here we would say if B is greater
than zero then compute the role in by
saying four times the width plus one -
however far we went which was just one
so would just be four times the width
was our role in it wouldn't have maxed
that out so we would have written this
out and so we would have added four
times the width to B that's the problem
right so I think what I want to do is
just pre compute that value total rollin
here because we're using that twice we
might as well as compute it once and
that gets rid of that hopefully that bug
there we go
all right let's run it again all right
so that time it completed which means we
fixed that sort of Miss computation
there but we don't actually know if it
actually did anything useful so now we
have to start looking at the actual
output files and see if they have
anything useful now that looks a lot
better so it looks like we're properly
chunking that up because now like
windows can read it and it displays it
oh so helpfully as white-on-white let's
go ahead and open up and see what
it looks like in here now
what you can see and again this is I
don't know whose fault this is exactly
it's probably not
writer it's probably the font extractor
but you can see that there's no
anti-aliasing on the font there should
be at least a little bit of a fractional
pixel if you were to imagine what the
line is that crosses through there like
let me draw one for you what you can see
is there should be some partial pixel
coverage happening
you know on these sort of border pixels
there and it's not happening if we
assume you know if you assume that maybe
it was starting looking at where it's
starting maybe somewhere around there
let's say and drawing to somewhere like
dare or whatever you can see that there
should be a lot of fractional pixel
coverage and we're just not getting any
of it that says to me that either
Windows is just screwing with us because
it's Windows and it never does something
good or there's some stuff we didn't
specify so you can see here like when we
create the spawn there's a lot of
garbage that we specify with it who
knows if we specified the right stuff
here and then when we're creating like
our Dib section and all this nonsense
all of this stuff like what the
background color mode is all of these
things we don't really know to what
extent those have been set properly
right so it's probably worth our time to
go speelunk it's just a little bit to
see if it would be possible for us to
ask windows to not be terrible at
everything every day all the time for no
real reason other than laziness so let's
see if we can figure that out by taking
a look at like what settings are in here
if we look at these values what have we
got these are just what font mapping
that that really doesn't
very much
[Music]
all right so here's a bunch of nonsense
we've got so it looks like this is
probably the case that we're hitting
right like apparently it got too large
so I'm not really sure
it doesn't really look like there's any
way for us to force it to do that
so I guess what I would say is we we
don't have really any available options
here for getting Windows to do something
smart I don't think but we've got you
know I don't need to work on the import
thing today it's not like I made here
actually has deadlines so you know maybe
we would just move on from here but what
I would say is let's let's try and fix
this let's see if there's a way to work
around what we nose is doing here's what
I'm gonna suggest since it looks like we
can't anti-alias large fonts what I'm
gonna recommend is maybe we just use our
own down sampling or something like that
right if we look at extract font right
and we go down into the guts of this
here when we actually call this function
we pass it just the pixel height and
when we create the dc4 that we use max
lifting which is computed directly off
of these values right so I think
I think we should be able to pre-filter
the bitmap like real me this Batman
thought man we've got a pixel height if
we said give me four times the pixel
height like make this thing real real
large right the rest of this code I
think would work fine right it would
sample the thing as a as being large and
then all of the values that we write out
here would be off by a factor of four
but we could just divide them or
multiply them by the inverse of that
right and then we should be fine the
align percentages are already a
percentage so that doesn't matter
so I think we could just make this work
that's my current story and I'm I guess
gonna stick to it probably so yeah like
for example
if I just create something called scale
or ratio and in all of the places where
I ever actually write something out
which is very few right I just multiply
that scale ratio I think that just works
this horizontal advance table is the
only thing that actually says that the
font itself has some stuff that probably
we would want to maybe write out like if
we write this stuff out because I don't
think we're currently writing any of
that out but if we do we just multiply
it by that scale ratio and so right
so that seems reasonable to me and if we
did that then if we asked her this thing
at sample pixel height instead of pixel
height then that would allow us to get
really big copies of the font we could
shrink them down and when we shrink them
down we would be able to produce the
anti-aliasing it's not as good is
actually anti aliasing unfortunately but
it's probably better than what we're
getting right now which is no anti
aliasing which would look really but and
so just thinking about that like let's
say we were to do this then what we
would need is when we do load glyph
bitmap here right after the text out W
we would need to like scale that thing
down and just take you know the larger
image and like smoosh it right uh and
that actually isn't particularly hard to
do in place so what I could do is just
say hey yeah let's just loop over all of
these here and we'll say like something
like this so if I was to just say like
scale the thing that you started with so
whatever that you know what is it called
bound bound height and bound with so
just go over the whole thing figure out
how you're gonna do the bound with bound
height whatever and in fact you know we
could even do this a little bit
differently because then once you come
in here you want the bound within the
bound height does this pitch how do we
do we know what the pitch is here
that would just work
and this would just work so I think this
would just all work
it's very dicey because this code was
kind of just all written in line there's
not a lot of structure to it right so we
may have some nasty debugging work ahead
of us but we could clean up the code too
if we wanted to and just like you know
break it into sections with clearer
inputs and outputs so that we could be a
little bit more certain of ourselves and
that would be fine
but yeah if we wanted to I really think
we could just say right after you do
this we're gonna knock these down so
that the the bounds that we're actually
using for these things we're gonna we're
gonna knock those down and produce a
loop over a scaled version of this thing
which can be whatever multiple of two
you want there right or I guess it could
be any even multiple pixels
we're knock those down we're going to
loop over it and we're gonna ingest
however many pixels are actually in like
one blocks worth of that scale so we're
gonna do like a you know Y offset equals
zero y offset is less than scale y
offset kind of thing right so we're
gonna loop over a block of values there
sum them all up and like average them
right like the crappiest possible filter
for now all right and then output that
as the actual new pixel value makes
sense so when we read in here like what
are we actually extracting just looking
at it here we're just what are we
actually looking at
we just we just look at the red value
right so what we can do here is say look
just sum up the red values so we've got
a pixel we grab the red value
we're gonna have an accumulator we loop
over all of these and we accumulate each
low byte of these things I don't care
about that
all right there so we're gonna go
through those and just just accumulate
the red value when we get to the end
we'll have the average red value so we
can say a cume divide equals scale time
scale right so we produced that you know
we go back down to sort of our rounded
value we may want to do a thing where
we're actually rounding cuz that's and
that's really a truncation which may be
a bad idea like we may want to we want
to do rounding rather than truncation
we'll look at that in a second but once
we produce that accumulation value now
we can do is write that back out as the
red value so now what we can do is say
like okay that accumulation just write
that back out to the pixel so you know
whatever the the best location is here
would get that right once we've done
that compression of course we want it to
look at we want it to look like this I
guess we want to look at at and if you
look here it's like going I don't know
why it's going from the bottom up you
know it is but I have no idea why it is
that's just really strange so I don't
really get the point of that necessarily
but I suppose we can just keep doing it
so that we don't mess with anything
right
and so if we have the row pointer there
and here's our pixel pointer then as we
go through here we can just in fact I
can just do it like this I can just
write the pixel value out that way
and we're all good so all we really need
to do here is take samples properly and
that requires us to like offset the
pixel value as we go so what's gonna
happen there is we need to take this
pixel value here and say like in fact I
can do it as the sample pointer I can
say all right we're gonna start sampling
at the pixel obviously each time through
there we need to end literally do this
right each time through this loop we
need to move it right the way we were
gonna move it so as we as we step
through we need to go ahead and say for
each Y we need to move the sample back
how you know to to the the previous row
each time through the y offset right to
grab four of those so I think that would
just work now the thing we're going to
run into here is we're trying to
compress four at a time in each of our
dimensions so these things themselves as
we go we needed to have we need to have
like advance the pixel pointer by that
amount
so in these when we're looking at like
this we don't you know normally we would
write it out this way and move forward
and the sample could use the same one
but it really can't here I don't think
for that reason so we need this to be
more intelligent about how it's working
and so I think we kind of need a
separate separate one here like we need
this and the reason all I'm saying is it
because we need to write these out
packed but we need to read them in
strided right
so we need to do something like that
right so that each time we we jump scale
scales worth of rows so I think that's
what we want to do there and then when
we're coming through here to do sampling
this value has to be more like that and
well actually I guess now I think about
it what we could do is just do this no
we can call this I don't know what to
call that right so as we go we would
start where the sample is and that's
moving four lines at a time and then we
would inside that scan all four lines
and all four columns accumulating them
together to give us what we actually
want and then we can figure out what the
accumulated pixel value should be from
that I know it's pretty messy so in
order to make this work we need to tell
this routine what the scale value
actually is and so
in here we need that scale value and so
that's is just gonna be the thing that
we actually specify here that's also
gives us a way to do this cleanly which
seems good and then yeah now we just
have to debug it because we did some
really stupid stuff in there
and off we go we can also turn this off
now probably but I don't know that we
want to because since it is willing to
anti-alias fonts for us it can probably
anti-alias small fonts for us better
than we can because it has the TrueType
font in there so we probably want to
turn scaling off when the actual sample
size is small that's my guess
so I think we want to leave that
anti-alias:on and then just try to
figure out when that's gonna happen so I
would say that from this we could look
back up here and say all you know the
where's the where's the value there I
don't know where did it go
I quality right so that I quality value
which is this thing we could make that
look like this it's like the iPhone like
that and sooo this way I've got the
ability to turn this off so what I might
do is say okay you know if scale is
greater than 1 i quality equals 0 so
that way if we're doing downsampling
will turn off quality and that way in
here I can do you know like to do Kaycee
turn off scaling below certain pixel
Heights and that way we can play with
that and tell Windows to stop doing its
anti-aliasing for things that we want to
do the anti-aliasing up and tell us to
stop doing interesting things we want
Windows ooh the entire thing off and
hope that that goes well
so now we've done it we probably are
gonna get complete garbage out of it in
fact
why am I seeing nothing that's not why
would it be corrupted oh dear what did
we how could we okay so that is a little
bit strange how did we manage to get a
corrupted version of the data it
shouldn't it just be garbage it
shouldn't be corrupted should it seems
weird
all right so I have no idea why that
happened we'll have to take a look at it
because I I guess we've got some bugs in
this that we haven't worked out yet
because I'm not sure why we would end up
in a situation where the output got
corrupted let me try one thing first to
make sure this still works okay if we
just have a way to nerf it so if I can
say in fact if I can say that can we
just turn the scaling off and not break
anything right that's all I really
wanted to know so let's see if I say
scale equals 1 can I make the can I make
the program work ok so that works fine
what I don't know is so like is this
sensitive like can I make the bug that
we get garbage happen in other
circumstances like if I call this you
know 800 with that with that output
corrupted p.m. geez so it seems like I
did something weirdly bad there but I
don't know why we would have how that
would have happened exactly
hmm so let's try to figure out what's
going on so let me first set the scale
up to - so we're gonna down sample by
two and now in theory I guess when we go
to run this thing we crap out somehow
right you look I now I like the pings
themselves are just garbage so how are
we actually ruining the ping just by
doing that I that that's kind of fancy
so I want to start by jumping into the
ping the ping writer just to see what
are we getting that's so bad well that
would do it all right so it's because
they're just zero zeros that seems not
good at all so let's go ahead into HH
font and see what we've done wrong there
in terms of scaling so here we are in
lewd glyph scoot down here okay so we're
gonna step through the image here
reading the rose and obviously I did
something super stupid here that's kind
of fine because we should be able to
figure out what what's going on so here
we are looking at the pixel and the
sample we're going to write out the
pixel here using the accumulator
so that's gonna sample off of this that
seems fine so that seems fine unless I'm
missing something that seems fine
now whether there was anything here yet
we don't actually know because there's
probably a lot of blank pixels there and
then we're going to write it out to this
pixel we're gonna do that bound with
times that that seems good
ah so the problem here is that sample
inter never gets advanced so I missed
one of my readers you can see here that
sample inter gets set the sample and the
row gets advanced but we never actually
move it so this samples four pixels but
then once it's done and it goes to move
on to the next one here this has to get
moved right four pixels forward in order
to read the next set of pixels so that
actually was correct I mean what we saw
was the correct output from that bug so
let's try it again and see what else
we've got because that that was
obviously just wrong
still nothing so you can see like no
width no height right so we're still
busted so something more has gone wrong
than just that let's keep looking in
here so my sample in err sorry
Wow bad day today it's not sample in er
that's the one we were moving around
it's sample yeah there you go try one
more time
there we go all right so now we're at
least getting plausible values back now
that doesn't mean we've actually done
this correctly there could still be
plenty of problems for example it looks
like that works it looks like we're
squishing too much from what we should
be but let's take a look and see
otherwise do we at least produce
reasonable pings and reasonable images
it looks like we did and they are
properly anti-alias now well properly is
a pretty bold statement that doesn't
actually look very good so I'm not sure
how properly that is the fact that we're
double squishing on X that seems like oh
that's why got four hardwired into my
brain all right so now I think we're at
least scaling these down properly it
looks like and so now yeah there's our W
now that may not be very good
anti-aliasing but at least it gives us
some anti-icing let's take a look at
what the quality looks like not really
sure how about it look it looks okay and
don't forget this is gamma
already which doesn't do properly
so it's hard to really assess there I
think cuz it's I don't know how it's
necessarily triggered an alpha how do i
how do I make a black
need a new layer fill with foreground
color alright um so yeah I mean you can
see looking at that it's not really what
we would want for anti-aliasing quality
wise it seems a little off still to me
looking at that sampling I'm not sure
exactly how we're getting those results
per se but it could be also just the 4x4
sampling or the 2x2 sampling so we'll
jack that up a little bit
another thing I want to know is when
we're actually writing this out here are
we editing these values at all it
doesn't look like we are so the alpha
switch so we should be able to inspect
that alpha properly because the pre
multiply nature of it isn't really
happening here because we pre-multiply
it in the game import so let's crank it
up to 4x over sampling and see if that
improves that at all but it looks like
we may still be a little bit off in
terms of just the sampling quality there
I'm not sure what's going on there but
we can try cranking it up even further
than that too if we want to obviously it
starts taking longer and longer because
it's doing a lot more work there I don't
remember where's the W there is 119
so that looks a lot better yeah I'm
saying
so if we actually look at this
one-to-one which is here
it's it's only better it's not perfect
and again it's hard to say to the way
the W's going here because you know this
is I don't really know to what extent
is like reliably doing the display
of an anti aliased thing but like if we
have no anti-aliasing versus
anti-aliasing and we could probably do
some testing of that so let's say I go
in here and say look I want to just do
one you know don't don't over sample it
there at all
and then I run it I should be able to
open the 119 again as a layer so should
be able to load that in and I shouldn't
be able to see the difference between
those two so there is what Windows was
giving us back before and there's what
we have and you can see it's a lot nicer
right I mean even just there it's like
super jagged and now it's much nicer
right so we're getting there I would
like to see the difference what if we
crank it up even more
I mean we're starting to get kind of
absurd here it's gonna take a long time
for this thing to run because it's doing
a ton of work and a completely
unappetizing but you know let's just say
we let it chunk through that because
remember we have to run this once who
cares how long it takes as long as it
eventually finishes and then we can look
again at seeing you know let's yttrium
port that 119 again we can look at the
difference and see to what extent that
seems smoother so there's you know oh
and you know what I could do too I could
probably make an easier way to flip
between these if I took the new layer
group thing here and we have
kind of duplicate a layer there we go if
I put this into a layer group then what
I could do is turn the whole thing on at
once right so there is the Windows
version which is crappy
there's the version which only does 4x
and there's the version that does 8x
right I don't see a lot of difference
between those two those look the same to
me so I think what I would say is 4x
seems fine all right so now we've got a
way to over sample these things the
question is when do we turn it on and
the answer is I have no idea when to
turn it on don't know when windows the
size stop doing its anti-aliasing so I'm
not sure when let's try to figure that
out because I like I don't know if we
can I don't even know if we can ask
Windows if it's going to or not like I
don't know how to ask Windows were you
planning on actually getting off your
lazy butt and anti-us in this font or do
you just decide to call it a day
right and so I'm not sure which one it's
gonna do like and I don't know if
there's a way to ask like to query and
say hey you know I asked you for
anti-aliasing I know you're Microsoft
Windows so you don't really feel super
compelled to actually anti-alias
anything so you know what what was it
heads or tails today when you got up in
the morning and we're deciding whether
you're rasterizer wanted to go to work
um and so I'm not sure if we can
actually get that information out by
using some kind of a query we might be
able to but I don't know I just don't
know I can't think offhand of what I
would ask
yeah there might be something in here
but I just I just can't nothing's coming
to mind so I'm gonna assume I can't ask
and I do some quick testing on this
machine cuz this is where we will be
generating fonts
I'm gonna see if I can determine a rule
of thumb for when we would want to pick
ours in and turn theirs off this won't
be a really reliable way to do it
because it's only being tested on one
install and we don't have any way of
knowing whether Windows will follow the
same rules on this install it might be
that depending on the DPI setting or
something like that
that it could change it and so it's not
gonna be reliable in that sense so what
I want to do here is try to get that
sorted out at least a little bit what
I'm gonna do is I'm gonna set the
scaling back to 1 so that means that
we're asking what is not to do it and
let me do is I'm just gonna run this a
couple times here and I guess I want to
run it actually for the command-line
probably so I'm gonna run one of these
msai go ahead and generate it deny
recompile that there we go so I'm gonna
say go ahead and generate it I'm gonna
look at the result and see whether or
not it was anti aliased so in here I'm
gonna you know open this up with with
the and then I'm gonna play with
the font size to see so we know that
it's not doing it at that font size
let's just do kind of a little bit of a
a binary search here and say well is it
doing it like at a really low value like
how about 32 you know how's it doing at
32 so at 32 it's definitely doing
something right that's a that's a thing
that happened one thing that's
interesting here is I don't understand
if that's 32 and we're not scaling right
why is this bitmap only 19 by 17 that's
like half the size that it should
actually be and I'm wondering what's
happening there
aren't we supposed to pass this negative
am I wrong about that
there we go well it's a little bit
better I thought you had to pass if you
could pass negative for the pics like
it's still only 20 there's no chance
that the sender's are twice as big are
they well they could be if this was a
lowercase W I don't actually know if it
is is it a lowercase W the reason I
passed that is negative for those of you
just joining us way back in the day I
think we looked at this you can see the
documentation on this this is device
units whereas this is character height
so I started cell height versus
character height so I thought that
negative was a better representation of
getting if I want characters that are
roughly this pixels I think that
negative is the is better right and it
does seem like it sort of is okay back
to our story let's crank it up to 128
see where we're at so it's still
anti-aliasing all the way out at 128 I
can't say it's doing a fabulous job
necessarily but it's looking okay so
let's go ahead and crank it up again
oops
2:56 still happening right still
cementing their double it again
all right so somewhere between 256 and
512 it craps out on us
let's see you know house 400 no good 300
so 300 it's still doing it so 350 anyone
wanna are people bettin on the screen
here or is anyone taking bets on when
the met what the magic value is on this
particular install of Windows still
happening so we're getting close because
we know that like 400 didn't do it but
350 did so like where what are we
talking about here windows 375 375 it's
off how about 365 how about Office 365
have you considered a subscription to
the world's premier office suite that
maybe sometimes occasionally lets you
log in but most of the time it just
doesn't because Microsoft's
authentication servers are busted
all right so 365 no dice so what do you
think 360 355
Wow so is it like 350 exactly we're
getting close folks
fifty-four I don't really need to know
it to this level of precision it's just
at this point we've come so far so
they're there you have it somewhere
between 353 and 354 Microsoft's like
that is where we turn it off at 353
pixels high
we need anti-alias this font at 354
pixels high with that it's just
ridiculous nobody ant know who wants to
see that nobody wants to see an anti
aliased font that big that's just that's
too big
353 is reasonable but 3/4 is totally
there's no way anyone wants an anti
aliased font that that's that's that big
I mean what would you why would you do
that right
nobody nobody wants that nobody wants
that all right so I'm gonna go ahead and
say in here I'm gonna say like actually
no this is not really to do because we
did it
right I think that's what we decided
so the changeover points 543 to 544
right
so let's just say that 128 is our is our
changeover point so we'll basically say
here look if the pixel height is less
than 128 then it's 1 otherwise it's for
maybe the better way to do that would be
to write it this way so we're like look
if it's over 128 then we super sample
otherwise we don't write I'm gonna
consider that a solved problem there
because now we know we'll always get an
anti-aliasing on I on at least the art
machines we're talking about and we
won't have to worry about Windows like
suddenly deciding to you know to poop
the bed on us and just like crap itself
and piss itself all the time when it's
trying to actually make these fonts
right so we should be able do now is say
look give us font that's 500 large that
should just work when we go over here
and look at it if we open this up we
should be able to get a correctly you
know subsampled w there it looks like we
do when if we want to drop it down to
some really small font like 20 y 20 high
we should be able to do that too
and open it up and that should also have
anti-aliasing from windows directly
which hopefully is higher quality
because it's got the TTFN outlines it
should be able do a better job there who
knows maybe he does maybe it isn't so
there we go and I'm gonna call that a
day I would say we solved both things we
ended up trying to solve I only will
actually wanted to solve one of them but
but the other one seemed we're solving
tomorrow we'll do the reader and then I
think we're good to go let's go ahead
and go to the QA brought to you by in
savate your your choice for deep
learning and AI excellence
[Music]
in Sopot of course is our sensory and AI
technology that monitors the stream and
will eventually take over the world in a
Skynet like scenario perhaps your
certificate for a large font it aliasing
thigh you know that's a good question
like do we have that you know do we
actually have a certificate for these
fonts is it signed what if what if our
font license expires in extract font max
okay so X 13 pixel says extract font
match systems X value is set using text
metrics TM overhanging if the material
should only have plan to Maxis y value
um
well so what we decided to do there is
we don't actually know what that value
meant so we just decided to add it to
both because it can't hurt right so we
just said screw it add it to both it can
be as big as we want it to be right as
long as it's not under science if it's
oversized no one cares that's why we
also had 56 so I'm fine to just leave it
like I don't want to know whether those
things I don't want to know what my
girls I was thinking I just want it to
happen right with this only work for
mono spaced fonts no it works just fine
with non monospace fonts what is the
difference between the freetype and
TrueType fonts do both do the subpixel
rasterization um I'm not sure exactly
what you mean by that do you mean the
difference between a TTFN and an OT f
three types like a library for
implementing fonts right it's not a font
format is it there's an open type format
is that what you're referring to there's
also an Adobe type 1 format and a true
type format are you just asking with the
difference
is oh whoops
did I did I make a dyslexic here I did
it's 353 to 354 thank you I've read the
sequel
did you try the cocoon editor could its
behavior be achieved and for coder um I
I didn't actually try it myself because
I'm not sure that I really care about
actually using it but I did go and read
about like what it does um as far as its
whether it could be it it can be
achieved in the for coder it's kind of
like a difficult question because for
coder allows you to program it using C
so sure you could implement the kind of
composition based parsing that it does
but you'd be doing a lot of work because
for coder by default doesn't have those
primitives so I don't know and
especially if you wanted those things
I'm not sure why you would use for coder
instead of just using coding Nate
connais because I mean if you already
have an editor that does things the way
you want you should just use that editor
right
didn't msn say something about small
fonts - yeah if it gets too small it
says it won't anti-alias them that we
don't have to care about because we
won't be getting fonts that are too
small so that i don't really worry about
but the two large fonts i do because we
may well want some large fonts for
certain circumstances I don't know and
so I really didn't want to be in a
position where if I asked for a font
that was a particular size if I wanted
some large letters or something I don't
want to suddenly get crispy edges so I
just wanted to make sure that we don't
leave did that there wasn't like a time
bomb lurking in there that would would
screw us up
did you not check 500 and it worked no
it didn't it doesn't anti-alias at 500
Windows doesn't we do but Windows
doesn't that's how we knew I did a 512
size font and it didn't get anti-alias
that's how I initially noticed the fact
that the anti-aliasing wasn't working
and aeleus wasn't working
so if we have no further questions
github bug report oh you just mean
too many things open here no bad wrong
ah right okay well actually we should do
two things on the github since no one's
asking any questions in here this is
done now right
so that's good and then we want to fix
this I think this is correct
we haven't actually I mean I looked at
this actually a couple of days ago when
it was first filed and I think it's
correct because if you look at what
happens here we do an is number on this
thing and so we wrote we you know we try
to enter this loop but if the tokenizer
was a dot if that's what we were at his
number would fail and we would never
enter this loop so this is correct
because otherwise we never get in here
right so I do think that's correct I
think what's happening is the reason we
don't notice it is because we never
parse fractional numbers at the moment
that start with a dot
I'm guessing or we just skip them so
it's like wrong or something I don't
well let's take a look I'm not sure what
I'm not sure why we should have noticed
this so it's a little bit weird oh oh I
know why I know why because we don't
write them out as those kinds of numbers
let's let's take a look
yeah so that's why we just wrote these
out as raw values because they're just
edited so we would never know we never
actually use that code code path oops
that's why um so yeah I do think that
should be fixed the way you suggest the
idea here is that when we come through
here and see this dot in order to do
this part of the routine we want to do
in advance cares to skip the dot and
start parsing the rest of it right so I
do think that's correct
so at least that is now a little bit
more logical so we come through here we
see that it's a dot we skip the dot and
then we just look for any numbers and
say that those are going to add
fractional values to our thing it's a
crappy parser anyway I mean it's not
very good so it's not like this is super
critical either way but I think that
should work are there any plans for new
hammock on we don't do handmade con at
the moment but there is if you go to
handmade con-com there is a list anytime
people run unofficial conferences we try
if they sort of our low-level
programming
oriented we try to stick them on here so
there is one potentially that may
interest you
it doesn't have details yet but at
Seattle Center in November
abner coin Bray is running one and he's
the guy who organized handmade network
as well so he's got a lot of experience
organizing stuff in this space so put
your email address in there I don't know
anything about it yet because you know
the details haven't been fleshed out but
it's apparently booked and the space is
booked and it's you know going to happen
and so if you are interested in that put
your email in in here and you should get
a mailing when there's an actual like
here's what you know what's gonna be
happening at the conference and so on
I followed your suggestions and use
Roboto and droid sans' for my desktop
they look good thanks for that Joe any
other suggestions for the good-looking
font um no I don't think so
that's that's just what came to mind as
some fonts that are reasonable Roboto is
a pretty good fun um you can go you know
it's not perfect but you can go to like
this and if you look at trending
sans-serif fonts I mean hey there's
Roboto right at the top open sans is
pretty good you can find fonts that are
popular with designers pretty quickly I
don't I don't have a lot of those
suggestions
right
but that would get you started
Oh
all right seems like we're all good no
further questions
no further questions
alright let's go ahead and close down
thank you everyone for joining me for
those for the handmade hero it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along the
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero org
and it comes with the source code so you
could play around with it we will be
doing the importer for fonts tomorrow
which is basically just reading that
text file that we output to move all
those piece of font information into
like a packed resource the way that
we've been doing it it's just reading it
from a text file so it shouldn't be too
bad but it is a little bit of busy work
got to do it get it checked off and then
we can basically sign off I think asset
importing because that would be
everything that means you can generate
everything from just source files and we
can also at that point maybe think about
what we want to do for some font stuff
pick some fonts and check them in there
to the source directories I probably
want to do some stuff like that as well
I'll be back here tomorrow after doing
that same time same place until then
have fun program everyone and I'll see
you on the Internet
thank you everybody