hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show where we code a complete
game live on Twitch no library's no
engine it's just you know the old
fashioned elbow grease style of game
development right before your very eyes
of course we've already kind of gotten
past a lot of the stuff that's the elbow
grease we've we've already sort of done
a lot of the work on like rendering and
and entities storage and all that sort
of stuff we're kind of getting to the
point where this might start start to be
some semblance of an engine we're at the
point now where we're even thinking
about maybe in a week or two here
starting optimizations on the renderer
so you know it's getting down to it I
think originally I had a ballpark that
we'd spend about 200 days which is
roughly 200 hours so that breaks down to
like you know five weeks of programming
time basically five weeks of full-time
programming time and five weeks of
programming time is like nothing right
like five weeks of programming time is
is nothing and so I was thinking well
five weeks to make an engine sure why
not
right seems a little ambitious but it
should work and so far it looks like we
might actually make that like we were
only halfway through our time budget for
stuff that I was thinking you know we'd
want to do and there's just not a lot of
stuff left to go we've got you know some
renderer work to do probably do 20 30
more days of render stuff I'm guessing
something like this and then we're back
to just kind of a little bit of list of
features that really aren't I don't
think that heavyweight there's stuff
like just um you know Titan doing a real
collision detector and you know maybe
doing some debug code that sort of stuff
but they're really just wasn't that much
on our list so I don't know I'm feeling
pretty good about it
I think the 200-400 breakdown is
actually not going to be too far off
potentially which is 200 hours of coding
on the engine and 400 hours of coding on
the game which roughly breaks down again
to you know something like five weeks of
programming time to build the engine and
then something like ten weeks to build
the game right so it's like a three
month for a month kind of
so we'll see we don't know where we're
gonna be but that's roughly the thinking
and it seems like it's going okay so far
if you would like to follow along at
home today
today is day 106 so go ahead if you
pre-ordered the source code you should
have a zip file unzip 105's source code
a 105 source code from the zip file and
that is what you want to start with
right here right now so that you can
code along with me and it'll be like you
know it's like riding up a tandem bike
yeah I'm saying but you're on the back
bro I'm in the front all right so we
left off don't ask me why this happened
yesterday in the Q&amp;A people were asking
if we could reflect actual images
instead of checker boards and I'm
assuming there were people who weren't
here when we implemented this stuff and
explained how these were just images and
we put checker boards in them explicitly
for the purpose of having something we
could see the lines in and so we ended
up bleeding some ground into our bottom
bitmap here and that's why our bitmap is
no longer reflecting a red checkerboard
it's reflecting this patch of ground
that we grabbed but that's just totally
that was not at all what we were
supposed to be doing that's just some
stuff that people asked in the QA and so
what we were supposed to be doing I
think I might actually turn off that
little that that stuff for right now
actually I think I might just go in here
real quickly just well we're talking
about it and turn off the coordinate
system test stuff that we still have in
there so in here I'm just going to go
ahead and put that back to any of 0 just
to get that out of the way there for us
and so now we're back to just having the
actual game graphics which is what we've
wanted and today what I want had said
that I want to do and what I think that
we probably should do is to start
getting our z situation straightened out
because you know that's kind of the
whole reason that we dove into the
renderer is we were kind of like well
you know what we have to start nailing
down our Z because that was one of the
last things in our engine architecture
that wasn't quite there so I don't want
to do now is I want to start changing
over I think what I want to do is just
flat-out change over the render
so that we're going through the
coordinate system draw instead of their
main draw now this would probably tank
our frame wait quite a bit I don't
really care about that right now because
like I said we're gonna optimize the
renderer so I don't care about that but
what I'd like to do is get it so that
we're drawing the world through
something that can scale it and the
reason that I'd like to do that is
because once we can scale the world we
can kind of see how things stack up on
each other and zoom and that sort of
stuff and so I want to see how bad it
would be if we just started going
through the coordinate system drawing
call to draw everything so let's go
ahead and try that out right so if you
take a look in handmade render group
right we have our draw rectangles slowly
call there's really no reason we can't
call the draw rectangle slowly call with
our bitmaps right because we've got you
know essentially what we have here is
our push buffer processing stuff is you
know it's basically like a stream
processor right it reads out of the
stream it sees what's coming into the
stream and it says it translates those
into actual code you know it basically
says I'm reading this buffer and I'm
gonna do operations on it so it's pretty
free for us to just say okay we used to
render a bitmap like this but maybe you
know we actually want to render a bitmap
in a different way and there's nothing
wrong with that right we can just go
ahead and call a different function here
draw a rectangle slowly for example we
can go ahead and call that instead so we
can pass the output target and then we
just have to fabricate these other
things that we actually want to have
right so we know what some of the stuff
is right we know what the the bitmap is
that we're doing we know that we don't
have a normal map or any of these other
maps at all right pixels two meters I
believe is something that we were just
sort of computing here right because we
didn't actually have that so there we go
although what I might do is just let's
just get that out into a variable so
it's not getting spammed everywhere
pixels two meters there we go
and
go ahead and put that up at the top
there we are
so pixels two meters yeah
pixels two meters is now precomputed
which is what I wanted and that's just
the inverse of our meters two pixels and
so now we've got mostly everything we
need we just need the placement of this
thing right we just need to know where
it's going to be now the origin we've
got it's that px py bit so if I just
pull that outside in fact these can all
be outside if I just use that P that X Y
there would tell me and I know that the
x axis and the y axis are just the
standard axes right
I know exactly what those are for now
and then the color value obviously is
something that that's been passed in and
so if I want to its close to me address
there we go
I can now in theory I think call through
call through the slow path and go or not
that was awesome
so just realize something this has to be
the entire size of the thing in pixels
which I just remembered so if this is
the entire size thing in pixels that
will draw everything as one pixel and
you can actually see the little pixel
dots in there we could make it a little
bit better by making them a little
larger there you go you can see
everybody's little tiny okay sometimes
the bugs are more fun
you know then sometimes the bugs are the
most fun thing I guess is what I would
say all right sorry I lost my train of
thought there what I was trying to say
was that these the x axis and the y axis
currently we passed those in with the
entirety of the scale of the thing that
we're drawing baked in and so what that
means is we would have to use the bitmap
itself to to sort of get that with in
that height that we need right that we
need to specify so I believe we can just
pass that along I don't think we have to
do anything special
for that what's the problem here sorry
there we go
so I pretty sure that's actually not
really a big deal there you go and you
can see that our frame rate is super
slow now right
that can just give you some idea of how
expensive that calculation really is
it's fairly expensive right because
right now that routine is so in totally
unbiased it's just yeah it's pretty
rough but at the same time what is kind
of interesting about it is even so
looking at this currently this is still
not that bad like for how ridiculous
that function is with what it's doing
right now in terms of how inefficient it
is this is actually pretty good and
again this is why I say I'm kind of
surprised and this is a five year old
computer right I'm kind of surprised by
how fast it really is without having to
do any real work it's kind of crazy so
at the end of the day this I think bodes
pretty well for us in terms of our
optimization because really like getting
it from here to be something that's
real-time I just isn't I don't think
that bad and you have to remember also
we're doing some really stupid stuff
right now even if you don't even talk
about how unoptimized the code is
there's also another part to it which is
that right now we're Matt we're not even
like bothering to pre clip our sprites
so for example you know this head is
actually running over all the pixels
that are in this entire giant rectangle
right because we're not even we're not
even clipping our sprites to just be the
region that's actually filled with valid
pixel data right so we could actually
improve things quite a bit probably by
fixing that as well but at the moment
like I said not a super concern to me
because I'm really only concerned about
what things look like not how fast they
run I'm I'm fairly confident that we'll
be fine with that so what I like about
this now is now that we're going through
this path what that means for us is
we'll be able to
scale things up and down which i think
is a pretty important thing for us to do
actually I feel like that's good hmm
as I spilled water all over myself
I feel like the scaling is a good thing
but I do have one sort of I do have one
thing that I'm not entirely certain
about in terms of how you want to deal
with the scaling or whether we even want
the scaling or not and what that is is
I'm not currently certain when I do the
scaling I don't actually know whether I
want to scale each individual sprite all
the time or whether instead I would
rather do it so that we draw into a
buffer and then scale that right and
just to sort of give a little bit of a
perspective on on how that's working
this is what I'm sort of thinking
through so the thing that I'm not sure
about is let's take for example the
ground tiles right so the way that we're
doing the ground tiles right now is we
essentially have round tiles that you
know we fill in with ground data right
and and by the way when I'm saying
ground tiles
I mean ground like like floor right not
like beef so we're not talking about
ground beef here when we say ground beef
tiles that would be a very different
thing we're talking about things that
are on like the ground okay so when we
do these you can imagine that if we
wanted to make it appear like we have
multiple height levels right so looking
from the side we're doing this if we
wanted to make it appear like the things
that were higher closer to the camera
right like here's the camera looking
down things that are closer to the
camera if we wanted to make them appear
as if they were scaled upward there's
two ways we could do that one is that we
could render the ground tiles into a
buffer first that is basically the
ground buffer right and then scale that
up right the other way we could do it is
scale each individual ground tile to
make just a bigger set of ground tiles
right
and there's good and bad aspects of
doing these two things first of all as
you've seen scaling is more expensive
like something that allows scaling is a
little more expensive than something
that just does a direct rectangle copy
so one reason that we might want to go
with this method is for speed because if
we just did
blitz directly into this buffer and then
did one split that scales up we might be
able to make things faster however on
the other hand we have to remember that
it would incur one whole extra copy from
the but you know from one buffer to the
other right which if we were able to
make this version fairly efficient might
actually end up being a lose right and
especially since memory bandwidth tends
to be a real big problem and maybe
computation is not such a big deal in
certain circumstances we don't really
know where that trade-off lies and so
the other thing that I think a little
bit better about going this way with it
is we don't incur any problems with
scope so if we were to say scale down so
let's say we were doing we were making a
small thing so here's the screen right
and there's a floor that's off in the
distance that we're trying to render
this becomes problematic if we actually
wanted it to fill the whole screen right
and the reason it becomes problematic is
because if we wanted to fill the whole
screen like so right that would mean
that our starting buffer would have to
be huge it would have to be like 9 times
the size of the screen in order to scale
down to something like I've drawn here
right because it has to be this big
right it has to be the size of the
screen when scaled down and so if it was
you know if this is actually how big a
screen size thing is you know then that
means that you'd have to do something
way way bigger than the screen as the
original buffer to shrink down so I
think it argues for not doing that sort
of post pass kind of thing it argues for
for actually rendering things the size
that they're supposed to be directly and
not going into an intermediate buffer
now that said I do think we may need to
do some stuff with intermediate
buffering and I'll talk
what that is in a second here so let's
say that we're going to allow some
number of ground levels right so let's
say that we do something right that
looks like I don't know that looks like
this and the way that this works is in
fact I'm gonna going to draw it a little
bit differently so let's say that we do
something looks like this and the way
that this works is this is the level
that we're actually looking at right so
this is what we're looking at and this
is the next level down right and this is
the next level down from that and so
what we want to do here right is we want
some way of as we move as the character
moves like lift there's a stairwell in
here and they move up the stairwell
right remember we're looking down from
the top on this if they move upwards
what we want to do is we want to make it
so that oh I guess I drew that in the
wrong place
sorry if they move upwards so that this
will become the new level that we're
looking at right so we're going to move
our camera view up we need some way of
of having that new level come in right
so we want to do something there like an
alpha fade or something like this where
we can actually fade it in on top of of
the underlying geometry right and maybe
you know what I think instead of trying
to explain to you what the problems are
with doing that I think maybe I'll just
implement it we can just implement it
right now the stupid way and I can show
you why the stupid way is a problem
before we talk about ways to fix the
stupid way so let's do that really I do
need to at some point remember to ask
yangshin to draw us a stairwell so I can
just put a stairwell in here instead of
having to constantly pretend that we
have a stairwell which we we currently
don't have so anyway what I'm going to
do for temporary purpose is is I would
like to
make it so that we have instead of
moving the hero in Y with the with the W
and s keys or you know what I'll do I'll
just make it so that when you hit the
spacebar instead of that being a jump
which we don't actually need what I
might do is oh wait you know what I
don't even need any of that I'll just
use the arrow keys because we've got
those bound as well I'll just use the
arrow keys to basically give me a way to
move the hero in Z just up and down
right or not even the hero just the
camera even right I don't even care
about the hero where the hero is I just
want to be able to move the camera up
and down so that we can see what happens
when it zooms kind of in and out if that
makes sense so what I'm going to do here
is we have that that sort of action
button thing right we've got these
action buttons and what I'm gonna do
right now is I'm just gonna kind of take
out that code that was sort of when we
were in there testing sort of ability to
fire things and that sort of stuff and
I'm gonna go ahead and make some code
here that just looks at whether that
that initial button is up or down and
I'm just gonna make a little a simple
little thing that allows me to move the
camera up and down because we've got a
camera we've got the camera P right and
I don't even remember exactly how we're
doing it I think right now we just we
actually just have the camera track the
player right but I don't actually
remember what we really did for that it
looks like that's not it it looks like
that's handled entirely in the sim
region so let's take a look there sim
region PPP yeah and so basically the
camera
we just got an entity that the camera
follows and so all I'm gonna do is when
we do the drawing here I'm just going to
introduce a synthetic offset to the Z
value that I can control so I can move
things up and down basically and that'll
be you know that'll be it so you know
look right here when we do basically get
entity ground point I'm just gonna add
in a Z offset
which basically you know literally it's
just gonna be for our testing how the
zooming works right so we'll go ahead
and make that just some temporarily a
variable that's in here so in game state
there we go got Z offset and I would
like to make that controllable by these
keys so I'm just gonna go ahead and do
something like Z offset plus equals I
don't even remember what our time value
is here I think it's DT for frame or did
we actually bake that out into a DT we
don't still right here what's grab that
and so I'm just gonna take whatever the
rate is of the zoom and I'm gonna
multiply it by however many seconds have
elapsed and so we're gonna put those in
here like so and in fact you know what I
might do I might just make it work like
this so we'll do this rate and we could
set the zoom right for in and out and I
don't really know let's say we go up a
mirror per second and then when it ends
when we're doing action down we'll go
down a meter per second something like
this and I feel like that should allow
me to go what happened here
oh is this
just cuz I added oh that's cuz I added
something again sorry I'm a little
little out of it today I forget every
time that if you add something to game
state you have to restart because we
don't handle that another live update
all right so in theory we should have
something that goes a little too quickly
there but now we've got something that
zooms us in and out right and so we've
got two things that we want to do one is
I want to change the scale of these
things as we zoom in and out obviously
but the other one is then I want to talk
about that alpha situation since that
was kind of what I've done to on the
blackboard right so as we zoom these
things in and out we need to start to
think about this I also want come on
make this rate a little slower there
let's go ahead and that's lower although
you know what that might just be because
our coefficient is too huge right if you
remember we never really did we said
we'd postpone it till today but we never
because we never quite got to the get
entity basis P stuff right where is that
get render and basis this thing is still
translating the meters to pixels this
this factor here we have not really
thought through at all
and so really one one meter per second
is probably fine actually now that I
think about it it's probably this value
that needs to be smaller and we'll have
to think about what we actually want
that value to be that's the value that
controls how much sort of scaling we do
based on Zemo motion and so I feel like
that's probably gonna be something
closer to what we want for the time
being right so as you can see the
positions of the things are being scaled
the sizes of the things however are not
being scaled and that's pretty
straightforward really what we've done
here is we've created our Z fudge value
says how much we're going to scale the
positions of things but we've never
scaled the size and so that's actually
pretty easy for us to handle you know
when we sort of go through this after we
sort of figure out exactly what we want
to do with these tests and then we kind
of come back
we can do it potentially in a little
more clean way but for the moment it's
actually pretty easy we just have a
scale that we could have here or since
we don't we know that we're always
scaling uniformly for the zooming
basically this Z fudge is just our scale
value so if we were to scale the size of
the sprites by that same thing the same
thing that we're scanning the positions
by it would line up right so this Z
fudge here I'm just gonna go ahead and
say that when we do Oh what's up with
that mark place when we do get render
entity basis what we really want to do
is have that return us a scale as well
as a placement right so there's a
there's a like an entity basis P or
something right something like this here
or a result which is going to have the
position and the scale right and that's
that's really all I want to do so I'm
gonna return that instead here here we
go there's our results so what we want
to do is is put the center in there and
then put the scale in there and the
scale is just the Z fudge there we go so
that when I get render render entity
basis P that's actually going to be the
entity basis P result there we go and
that's the I don't know we'll call that
basis or something and so then when I do
my drawing we have its basis dot P is
the actual place that I'm drawing that
at right and I need to fix the other one
here too right well actually I don't
even have to it's just that although
technically we should fix this one for
scaling as well so we'll do that in a
second anyway so you can see that
nothing's changed when I've done that
everything's the same but now if I
actually take that scale value and say
well now we kind of know these are our
two basis vectors right here's x and y
what i want to do is go ahead and take
that scale right and I just want to
multiply that the width and the height
so that it changes with the scale as
well right and now you can kind of see
as I shrink the things down we're
actually getting a real shrinking
instead of a fake shrinking there right
like so
now we still have obviously more stuff
we got to do to make that work right and
also our ground chunks are not are not
playing along but we're you can see how
that's kind of putting to good use the
code that we wrote over the past few
weeks where we can do our scaling now it
makes it nice so that our trees you know
our trees have kind of a nice little
less killing effect I can see however
that there is a bug we thought that
there probably was one we were going to
go through it with a fine-tooth comb you
can see that we're getting a problem
with with sort of when we when we zoom
in you can see that the the actual
popping at the very top of that tree
right and I don't actually know that may
not actually be a bug that may just be
the way the sprite is constructed one of
the things that I talked about but we
haven't quite covered yet was that we
always need one pixel of emptiness
around everything in order to make it
work properly and we'll talk a little
bit more about why that needs to be
later on but I just wanted to call that
two attention I know if you can see that
it might be too hard for you to see
because of the way you know video
compression is or whatever but it's
there all right so why our ground isn't
scaling I suspect is because we're not
actually giving it a proper Z value
would be my thought and so I think right
our Z offset which we kind of added in
here we need to add that to the ground
chunks as well when we render them
otherwise they're not going to scale
right and so if we go into the ground
buffers when we're actually doing that
thing and we do our push pit bitmap we
do the push back with the Delta we need
to be able to to put in that camera
offset there as well right and so now I
think with that in there we should get
them we should get them scaling although
for some reason
no we don't oh because that's actually
not the way that we have our base of
stuff working this was the thing we
talked about yesterday so we said that
our Z fudge is only based on the base P
never on the offset P I know if you guys
remember that right there is this whole
situation with because we're in 2d we
talked about this literally yesterday
because we're in 2d we wanted to make it
so that the position and scale of things
would change but they wouldn't lean if
they're stacked on top of each other so
if you basically have like you imagine a
snowman made of three of three pieces
right his ground point will scale his
things will scale but the placement of
these guys on top of him will not change
so he remains perfectly vertical even
though the perspective would have
potentially have actually made him look
like that right we decided to keep that
sort of straight up-and-down scaling and
so what that means is I can't pass a
cure I have to actually go ahead and
make it be in the basis itself which is
again not a particularly big deal it
just means that we have to do our our
bases push here right so basically every
time we do one of these we've got to do
that push the zooming the basis is going
to have a placement which is I guess the
Delta now that I think about it there
really isn't any offset for this thing
so the offset for the bitmap is actually
always going to be zero in our basis is
going to capture all the information
about where we want a place that's
actually how the renderer is supposed to
work at the moment right and so this
this p-value is actually supposed to be
the Delta so that's going to be Delta
Plus again that that Z offset
here we go oops guess I need to pass a
non offset here there we go and now
we're closed
we're closed but we've still got
something odd happening which is that
our our scaling of positions doesn't
seem to quite properly line up right you
can kind of see as we scale our stuff is
not where I would have expected it to be
right as we zoom in things scale kind of
counter to each other and you can see
this happening with everybody right
there they're not scaling about the
right coordinates and so we need to kind
of go take a look at how we're doing our
bitmap alignment and stuff like that to
figure out what's going on there right
and I suspect that part of that has to
do with the fact that we translate we do
translation and alignment in this you
know kind of ad hoc way that happens at
the head of the rendering stuff so let's
go let's go take a look at that and get
that straightened out this is good I'm
really glad we're doing this this is
basically like this is one of those
weeks that I'm just happy about
everything because we're taking a bunch
of stuff that we haven't done properly
it haven't thought about very carefully
and we're you know fixing it basically
so okay so let's go in and take a look
at how our coordinate system stuff works
in terms of when this that scaling
occurs and who it is applied to just so
we can figure out exactly why it's it's
not quite doing what we think it should
do and just again I hopefully people can
see that in fact you know what I'll do
right now I'll turn off the ground
chunks entirely because they're not
actually necessary and the other thing I
could do too is let me let me quickly
just fix those those rectangles as well
because those need to be changed so the
rectangles need to be scaled obviously
so we can get the basis P here like so
and that's going to be applying the
scale to the dimension of the rectangle
right like that oops okay so as you can
see like when we scale stuff in fact you
know maybe I'll just even turn off these
for a second so we don't have to fix
everything at once I just want you to be
able to focus on the stuff that I'm
talking about so you can see this
scaling here right as we scale and
what's particularly strange about this
right as we do it is you can kind of see
that for some reason we get a lateral
motion on on the characters right you
can see that like as I as I move around
here everything's still the same as it
was for the most part but when I do the
scaling I move to the side right it
doesn't make any sense right like that
should not that's visually totally
nonsensical right oh you know what's
kind of cool about this this is kind of
awesome
I totally forgot but now that we have
the ability to scale out we can see our
sim region pulling stuff in from the
worlds as we move around right these are
the things that are in the simulation
set remember and so that's kind of cool
right that's that's pretty neat all
right anyway sorry I got a little head
of ourselves there so what I want to do
is I want to go figure out why we're
getting that lateral translation and
it's hard to say who is at fault there
because you know we don't really know
who's scaling properly it might be
probably the case is no one's scaling
properly and they're just kind of the
trees are at a particular Z level and
the guys at another Z level and whatever
and so it ends up looking a particular
way but really I think what's you know
the scale is not happening in the in
sort of a coherent way we want the scale
to scale around the center of the screen
and neither of these two things seems to
be scaling around the center of the
screen to me I guess is the way I would
say it and so what I want to get to is
when we zoom in and out like this I
would like to see the center of the
screen be the point that things shrink
around and everything should appear to
be stable relative to each other just
scaling so off we go okay hopefully that
all makes sense nothing particularly
weird going on there so let's take a
look when we are doing our scaling we're
already centering everything about the
screen Center right because we're
starting at the screen Center and we're
moving by whatever the entity XY is ah
and then there's the offset X Y which is
obviously a constant that's you know
apply it on top of that I'm interested
to know also what happens if we turn
that off by the way right yes so that's
that's actually our problem as well if
you take a look at it in terms of why
these things are sliding relative to
each other is that that offset right
there so what were we trying to capture
with that the offset X Y it's kind of a
little bit odd because my understanding
was that the offset X Y should have been
the thing that the entity that was
allowing things like ah okay I see so
the offset X Y is the thing that's
supposed to allow different parts of say
the hero to be you know at different
levels right so for example if his head
was supposed to be higher than his body
that was the thing that we would use for
that but what I forgot is actually our
current state of the hero
is that he's actually all on the same
level these sprites are not clipped yet
so they're not actually offset from that
ground point so the reason that doesn't
actually do anything in terms of thing
is because the actual values of the
sprite were all the same right so I can
turn it off and he still looks okay but
if I go ahead and rebuild this here you
can see that that actually does change
things I believe that's because the
offset XY of the entity basis excuse me
he is still getting set right it's
actually still a value let's take a look
here who is setting that value now that
I think about it who's setting that
offset so when we render like the head
these offsets are all set to zero so I
guess the only thing that we're actually
using this offset for right now is the
bitmap alignment that's it right the
bitmap alignments actually the only
thing that that's getting that's that's
going in there and so since that bitmap
alignment is in there I'm trying to
think of why okay so that bitmap
alignment here's what's going on this
actually makes sense if I wasn't having
such a slow day I don't think this would
be really that big of a deal but here
you go so what's happening here is that
we've got you know a bitmap and we've
got a point that we're using to place it
and we have the offset that says where
that is right and so actually the way
that this works we actually do it in the
reverse order if you think about it what
we're doing is we've kind of got a
displacement that says well I want to
say that the guy is here I want to say
the tree is here but the bitmap is
actually a rectangle so I need to move
to a new place so that when I draw it
right it will it will still line up you
know I'm saying and so this value here
actually definitely does
need to be multiplied by that that Z
fudge value so this definitely wants to
be in here because as the dimensions of
this change we would move less far out
right
if this rectangle gets twice as large
this displacement has to get twice as
large and so on so this is the thing
here not using the offsets Z value is
correct because we wanted to keep things
straight up and down like that's like
the Snowman example but we do need to
scale the offset because as we change
the size of the bitmap that offsets
going to differ so I believe that that
was just a mistake that we made that we
didn't want to make and hey now you can
actually see when we scale it looks
properly right it looks like what we
expect and I can go ahead and turn that
ground back on now
let's take a look where that one hello
mister ground pushed back so you turn
that crown back on and there is the
ground again and again this is kind of
fun I don't know this is one of those
things I don't know it's just kind of
fun if you take a look you can see now
sort of our world stuff happening as you
kind of move in you can see it filling
the ground chunks as necessary and that
sort of stuff which is kind of cool
right that's that's like I know it's
just kind of nice be able to zoom out so
you can kind of see what's going on in
the world so when we zoom in here
right I think everything is now
relatively stable looks pretty good to
me
yeah I feel like we may be - oh that's
kind of hilarious
so our jump is still active and as you
can see our hero gets bigger as he jumps
which is pretty hilarious
yeah that's pretty hilarious I feel like
we want to make that jump probably into
some kind of an offset although I don't
know it's kind of funny to see that
happen I don't know I don't know how we
feel about that maybe we do want him to
get bigger that's pretty hysterical dude
yeah as he jumps he gets large that's
funny um so yeah so back to what I was
saying originally it's been a pretty
scatterbrained day here I apologize for
being so so out of it um so basically
what I wanted to show was some problems
with alpha feeding right we talked about
this and kind of you know curse early at
the beginning episode and I wanted to
say well what happens if we need to
start having a level above this one
that's gonna fade in and out so what I'm
gonna do is I'm just gonna take the
level that we have right now and I'm
gonna show you what happens if we do the
stupid way of doing alpha which is to
just draw the sprites and you'll you see
this actually this drives me nuts you
see this in indie games sometimes and
I'm always like oh don't do that when
you have a situation where you're trying
to fade out something um off what's what
times sometimes what people will do is
they'll actually just set the Alpha
value of the various components right
and so you can imagine what that would
look like here if we went into the
renderer right and let's say that inside
this this entity basically thing right
we had some kind of a thing oh sorry
that's the basic key result that's not
what I actually wanted I meant inside a
render basis thing suppose we had you
know we were to introduce something like
an alpha fade value right or or maybe
even do it in a slightly different way
maybe we just have a thing where we can
sort of as we're pushing things we can
set kind of a you know
a global alpha value or something like
that right and so at the outset that
global value that global alpha value is
is gonna be one right and and I'm
actually remember right here there we go
so that global we've got 15 minutes on
the on the bonus clock right so I'm
gonna go ahead and take those so our
global alpha value is 1 and then every
time we get an alpha push on one of
these bitmaps I'm just gonna take the
Alpha and I'm gonna multiply it I'm
gonna go ahead and multiply it by the
global alpha right so I'm just gonna I'm
just gonna flat out have this global
modulation that I can do to make the
alpha value be there right and so now
what I'll do is I'll just say oh okay
you know as i as i zoom in and out i
want to be able to make that that sort
of global alpha I'm going to set that to
be something proportional to the Z
offset right so when we do the render
group you know I'm just gonna say render
group global alpha that's going to be
equal to game state Z offset and I'll
clamp it from 0 to 1 like so and I want
to basically do like let's say 1 minus 2
Z offset so you know it starts out
everything's full alpha and then as I as
I as I change it I want it to to differ
and so here's what happens as i zoom in
right do you see what's happening there
now what I'd like you to look at most
importantly right is take a look for
example I'll put the hero in a
particular position maybe right about
there okay and as i zoom in on him watch
what happens as he disappears okay you
can see through his sprite now into the
background and same is with like the
trees and stuff and so instead of a
fading out effect you get sort of an
effect as if everything turns to mist
but it doesn't actually feel like I'm
fading out this layer it feels
like everything's turning into like a
weird ghost version of itself right
now you know maybe that's fine if that's
what you're going for but usually that
just looks amateur hour especially if
there's stuff like you know you
shouldn't be seeing stuff
perhaps behind some of these things you
know it might be that the art there
wasn't set up for what that's supposed
to show or whatever and you just it's
just not good right so in order to fix
this particular scenario right we want
to be a little more conscientious with
how we do our Z layer stacking I'm
guessing that probably what we will want
to do is do an off-screen composite
first of each slice of our world that
might be fading right and so essentially
if you know we go back to this diagram
what I probably want to do is have a
render buffer that's going to render
that top part that might be fading out
or fading in right this part so you know
if you actually think about maybe how we
bucket this let me go ahead and say
something like this there's a render
buffer a that will take whatever's in
here then there's a render buffer B that
will take everything that's in here and
then a render buffer C that will take
everything that's in here which is
things that are fading in now a and C
are actually mutually exclusive because
either we're going up or we're going
down and so we don't need both the fade
in and the fade out layers right because
this later is fade fading out if we're
going up and this layer is fading in and
and same if we were going down we'd have
the opposite this one would be fading in
and this would be fading out so we only
really need two buffers right at any
given time we need the main buffer and
then one of the fade buffers right
whichever way whichever one we're in
between we need to run there but what I
think I'd like to do is actually have
those two buffers so that we can do the
fade in and the fade out properly right
and so I don't actually remember where
we left it if I if I turn off our ground
buffers for a second let me let me see
where we're at here if I turn off the
ground buffers for a second
and I I just have this if I want to get
a second layer in here I feel like we
have the ability to do that I feel like
if I switch between these I feel like I
should probably make this official at
some point huh we go if we if we do that
that gives us the ability to have
multiple world layers right if I
remember correctly let's see if that's
actually true I don't know if it is hmm
so here's my guy so yeah if i if i zoom
wow those things are really high up
there though my goodness what exactly is
the Z value on those things hold on a
second that would suggest that our Z
multiplying this is really far off so
that's something we're gonna have to
take a look at in a second that's again
this coefficient here which is
controlling how much of that sort of Z
happens right so that looks a little
more more sane there right yeah so part
of the problem too of course
when we're looking at this is we don't
really have much oh hey there's our
secret stairwell right about that so we
can actually go up to the next level we
got to turn off the ground buffer
rendering as well because the ground
buffers take a long time to render now
since they're going through the scaling
paths as well which we really probably
don't want to do but yeah
so things are a little wonky now I'm
going to go ahead and and turn the
ground buffers off entirely and really I
just don't want to spend the time I
don't want to spend the computational
cost to generate them it's basically
what it boils down to because until we
do again the renderer optimization I
really just don't want them taking up
any any time at all really so I'm just
going to turn off our ground buffers
entirely like so right
and then you know we should be good to
go so now when we're rendering this
stuff again it's a little bit weird for
me to work with because it still got
that this notion right of a it's look
out this weird notion of Y displacement
for Z as well as Z displacement for Z
which I don't actually know if that's
such a good idea it's a little bit it's
just been very confusing for me as
someone who comes from a place where
they normally only use 3d coordinates
it's kind of hard to always wrap your
head around what's happening there right
and so like you can kind of see what's
going on here with the with me playing
with these Z values you can basically
see that that that value changes how
spread out our stuff is based on the Z
difference from wherever the player is
right now there's some stuff that we
probably want to fix about that and
maybe now is as good a time as any to
talk about it but I'm just kind of
playing around this here because I want
to see sort of how it how it feels right
and so it's still that's yeah that's
just that's just very strange so I feel
like this wants to be a different value
and I think we may want to put in
something which which does a little bit
more of a real perspective transform
there so let's let's think about this
how much time I got left I got about
five minutes left all right so all I'm
gonna do right now is I'm gonna go ahead
and and take that alpha value thing out
right the global alpha I'm gonna go
ahead and set that to zero like so
and I want to take a little look at this
right and I'm trying to decide what I
want to do in terms of the Z offsetting
2y right because the Z offsetting 2y if
you remember this is what does that
right this this term right here is what
does that so if you could imagine you
know if we turn that off
then we would have only Z offsets right
so this is what the world looks like
with only with Z just being treated as Z
know Y at all and so you know when we
come if we come in and out of that or if
you know if I walk my guy up the secret
phantom stairwell you can kind of see
what that ends up looking like in terms
of just raw Z offset values and it kind
of feels to me like like it's another
situation where really because of the
way the 2d 3d stuff interacts it's
almost like we want there to be scaling
for the guy for the world based solely
on like the Z layer that you're in but
not on fine-grained Z motion that
happens like inside inside that frame
right so if you're jumping or whatever I
don't think we want your guy to get
bigger right we want him to just do a Y
jump not a Z jump right but when he
walks upstairs between two worlds that
two Z layers that's where things should
probably scale that's just my feeling
about it I don't know but just looking
at how things are going
that kind of is what I feel intuitively
like what I want to see happen if that
makes sense
go ahead and change this down a little
bit so that that looks about right to me
so if I walk down these stairs to the
next level I mean that looks like about
the amount of parallax that I would
probably want from stairwell you know
from from an upper layer and a lower
layer right I mean that looks kind of
like what I might might want to see so I
don't know we'll have to percolate on it
what to think about it a little bit but
it's starting to get more towards what I
actually want to see happen right yeah
yeah so that feels that feels kind of
more correct to me that feels like what
I would expect and so I don't know
it just it seems to me it feels like if
I had to guess what I'm leaning towards
saying here is we basically want
everything to be about a Z slice and the
Z slices get scaled but inside a Z slice
things don't generally scale I mean if
we want like a special effect sometime
to make it look like something's coming
up towards you or something you know we
do that but on the whole we wouldn't we
wouldn't generally have that happen
right and that seems that seems like a
good thing to me
so I'm gonna go ahead and say that
that's where we'll that's where we'll go
tomorrow that's I think that's what I'd
like to say tomorrow in terms of
starting to clean this stuff up further
I'm gonna put that in here so let's see
discrete slices and the render action
understand Z slices and so we're gonna
say that that's definitely true and what
I'm going to say about that is I'm going
to say that computing Z slices are what
control the scaling of things whereas Z
offsets inside a slice are what control
Y offsetting right
and I think that's really gonna be the
way to make things work with the kind of
weird mixed 2d perspective that we
expect to have in a game here right and
we're it's slightly uncharted territory
right cuz most games just don't do this
stuff like most 2d games just don't have
parallax stuff that you can walk between
it's very unusual to have that right and
so we're kind of in a place where we're
having to make sort of an artistic
decision about what we want to have
there it's not it doesn't really have
anything to do with technology and
that's a little tough but you know I
think this is a pretty good compromise I
feel like this would look kind of neat
you know if you're in a world and you
look down you saw like a you know we
have like a pit and you could look down
into it I feel like that's gonna add a
little bit of niceness to the game and
so I think that's what I'd like to go
with and so we'll just assume that we'll
do that with the fading and that'll sort
of be how we'll start working on the
renderer tomorrow how we'll start
working on it something that basically
does exactly that levering so yeah I
think that's good
I'm happy to leave it with that for now
and tomorrow I guess we'll start on that
slicing and we'll put in the fading so
that we can kind of fade layers in and
out and we'll and we'll maybe try to
make that Z slice stuff maybe we'll try
to make that a little more explicit like
maybe we'll try to force the game to
basically say to the renderer here's
these slices 0 1 2 3 4 or something
right like instead of just passing an
arbitrary Z values so that we can sort
of start to think about them discreetly
because we're probably going to want to
do that for in terms of bucketing things
and sorting and stuff as well all right
so I think we are going to go to the QA
let's do that
there you go and so anyone who wants to
ask a question please put Q colon in
front of it so I will see it and yeah
let's do some QA got probably about 15
minutes left yeah yeah ended on time
pseudonyms every 3d did I see that
correctly that the ground shadow jumps
along with the hero yes did you I don't
know you might have missed yesterday we
turned off that the stuff with the
ground shadow jumping along with the
hero because staying on the ground
because we we want to do that a
different way
basically it was being done in this
really hacked way before that we had
just hacked in there and it still got
propagated out to the renderer and so
that's like gone that's gonna be done in
the future when we do our shadow stuff
we're gonna handle that in the actual
game code was that we decided to do that
so the off topic but can you quickly go
over the concept behind move speck why
not have every entity have their own
velocity drag etcetera values instead
just for organization well it's also
it's not just organization it's it's
really more just because right now we
didn't actually need to put it in the
entity so we hadn't done that yet so
having it as a move speck just allows us
to do whichever one we want so right now
they can shave share those move specks
but in the future we could just move the
moves back into the entity if we wanted
to have every entity have a unique one
right and so I suspect actually in the
end we probably will have n if every
entity have a unique one but we haven't
really focused on that stuff yet because
that's really more of the game code
stuff that we're gonna do after the
engine's done is the jump a real
mechanic or just for making the system
robust it's just it's naughty it's not
even for making their system robust it
was cuz somebody asked about it in a
stream someone had said can you make the
guy jump in a QA so we just threw it in
there it should just be removed it like
we should just get rid of it at this
point because it's not gonna be in there
eventually
why don't you pre compose hero bitmaps
into a single bitmap at initialization
so there would not be fussing with
pushing pieces because well so we're
gonna do animation probably not too long
after we get the render stuff working
and we want all of those pieces to move
separately a big part of animation is
having the pieces kind of move
separately so they get some
and they get some feel in there and so
we really don't want them to be baked
that's why I specifically asked yangshin
to draw them as separate composable
pieces and there's a number of other
reasons to do that too but that's the
big one is for the animation when you
are walking up a staircase with a
character suddenly snap back on why when
you transition to the next D slice
so I don't think so so I think we'll
just move him smoothly up Z like we are
now so that'll be basically the his Z
slice position because all the Z slice
positions will be still floating point
they'll be like between 0 &amp; 1 1 &amp; 2 2 &amp;
3 right so when you give your Z position
coordinate it's going to be in terms of
slices or something like this right
we'll figure out exactly how we want to
do that in the next in the next few days
if I'm not mistaken with your way of Z
scaling it's going to be hard to support
large in Z structures such as tall walls
that should be aligned across different
Z levels
imagine a multi-story house or so so I
agree with that because since we don't
currently shear things right you
wouldn't be able to have those things
line up however I'm not sure how much we
care about that because a multi-story
house you're only seeing the levels at
you know when they fade in so I'm not
sure how much we care about that as a
bug right you know essentially there's
no way without doing actual 3d mapping
to have those things line up and still
have things get bigger when in the
foreground and further in the distance
so we can't have to make a trade-off do
we want to do the scaling and break
continuous vertical walls so that they
don't line up properly or whatever or do
we just not want to have the scaling and
I think the scaling is gonna be a bigger
win then the bug is of never be of never
being able to make sure that vertical
walls will line up if that makes sense
so that's my hunch if they're going to
be pits ledges in the game how are you
going to render those well we already
are basically rendering those right so
if there's a pit here all you know the
ground we turned off the ground buffer
but if there was a ground here we just
not render the ground where the pit is
that's it right so there's really hardly
anything to it
I wonder how the ball would work with
the zoom in so if you want the ball to
if you want to do the ball zoom really
zooming and the ball don't I mean we
already had control over however big we
wanted the ball to be right so the only
thing zoom is doing is changing that
scale so you can see what it would look
like to to scale the ball up just by
scaling the ball up right like all you
have to do is come in here turn this guy
back on so that we'd get the ball right
and if you want the ball bigger you just
say okay you know give us give us the
bigger ball right like so oops that's
displacement not what I wanted
try that one more time there we go so
you can make the ball like as big as you
want it to be but it doesn't necessarily
you know I'm not it's not really gonna
be any different that might be a little
too large right and so you know the
other problem with it too is remember
this it's actually moving the reflection
location so a super large ball also has
the problem of out sampling our map for
it so you know we've got we've got some
other stuff that we have to finish first
of on the normal mapping code before we
can make things arbitrarily large
because we don't really have a plan at
the moment for what would happen if you
were trying to do reflections for stuff
that's outside the map and we didn't
really tune the parameters to make sure
that wouldn't happen etcetera etcetera
so I'm assuming that it's not quite
perfect in that sense right but yeah
I will say that does look kind of
strange I wonder if we still have a bug
in there that we just weren't seeing
because we didn't have I don't remember
exactly where we left it but it
definitely looks like the reflection
changes in a way that I wouldn't
necessarily expect that I can't remember
that may just be because it's traversing
more of the space in Z right and so yeah
so I don't know and that could also
argue for not doing that translation but
but I don't know yeah so I have to look
at that that guy more but really the
zooming that has nothing to do with it
it's just the same as when we were
changing the size of it before what
games do the bad fade out effect you
mentioned uh I think the most recent one
I remember or I think this was was one
that I was playing was hatoful boyfriend
like and a lot of those sort of those
like visual novel games for lack of a
better term that's how they do the fade
outs it's really super janky looking but
I was trying to remember that may not be
the one I apologized to the people who
made that if I'm saying it the wrong one
but I think that was the one that I just
saw just recently
how will the staircase be scaled when
you are moving up and down it well I'm
not sure I understand I mean it'll just
get it'll get scaled with probably the
lower Z slice would be my guess
and I mean presumably when we draw the
staircase you'll bake some perspective
into it
so the scarecase will look you know like
this kind of a thing so as the hero
moves up it it's already got that sort
of scaling based in so it shrinks but by
the time the hero get to the top the
hero has grown in the staircase has
shrunk so these the same relative size
kind of thing so I'm assuming that'd
just be fine I don't anticipate any kind
of weirdness there really
it's a first how could I not know how to
fully fund everyone knows how to feel
but in fact I just seed garland Oh bloom
saying at the bottom everyone knows how
to flow boyfriend friend it is it is I I
have no idea why this happened and I
don't pretend to know anything about it
other than for some reason somebody
decided to make a Japanese dating sim
game where all of the people who you
date are pigeons like that's not slang I
mean they're actual pigeons they are
birds for some reason I have no idea why
slow seven have you seen heard of
huniepop then uh I think I've seen it on
the steam like best-selling page four
four like I don't really know what maybe
maybe visual novels or something like
that but I've never actually played it
so I don't really know anything about
that one
I did play hatoful boyfriend I mean I
played 15 minutes of had a full
boyfriend but I did play I did like to
watch the game
however I think this is a wrap because I
don't actually see any more questions so
I think that's about it right anyone no
all right
well thank you everyone for joining me
for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always I was a little out of it today
not sure why sometimes after coding all
day and then handmade here I don't
necessarily have my full coding brain on
it depends on the circumstance but
nonetheless we kind of did get some
stuff straightened out I think we're
getting pretty close to to getting our Z
stuff kind of where we want to be and so
I think tomorrow we can go ahead and
start trying to work those slices in
there and I feel like what we want to do
with that is like start to get the
ground buffers working on slices and
then you know so that we can kind of
have have ledges that look down into
lower things and see those kind of
clearly and then also start to use that
to do sort of that reflection mapping
picking properly so we know that like
okay this ground is the ground buffer
that we use for you know doing the
reflection mapping or that kind of stuff
right so you know I think we pretty much
know what it is we got to do here we've
got a couple more days of getting
everything lined up properly but we're
in pretty good shape so hopefully you
come back tomorrow and join us for that
when we go ahead and start the
implementation of getting those slices
kind of formalized and working properly
it'll be the same time same place
tomorrow 5:00 p.m. on right here on
Twitch if you would like to follow along
at home with the source code you can do
so by pre-ordering the game it comes
with a source code you can download it
every night I uploaded after I finished
coding we also have a patreon page if
you want to support the video series
that's a easy way to do that there's
also a forum site that has anti episode
guide and place to ask questions and
porce to Mac and Linux good stuff like
that and finally there's a tweet bot
that tweets the schedule at you so if
you want to know when the streams gonna
be live it sometimes we change the times
and sometimes there's you know days off
or something like that that's the best
thing to do is just subscribe that tweet
pot cos it'll always tell you you could
always go to its page if you want to
check it out so that's about it I hope
everyone has a good evening and I will
see you guys back here tomorrow for some
more handmade hero take it easy everyone