all right hello everyone and welcome to
handmade hero show where we code a
complete game live on stream and we need
to
uh you know move things around
it's basically what's going on here um
we are sort of in like a little bit of
an interim area uh the code is
you know pretty playable right now for
engine feature stuff but we just need to
like
put in the sorts of things that i don't
normally do uh like you know
combat and those sorts of things these
are usually someone else's job
and not really something i'm
particularly
you know
well versed in so i don't have much in
the way of opinions about it but as you
can see right now um what we did on the
last stream is we sort of cleaned up a
little bit of how we're gonna
handle this stuff
and we
we made the gloves
because they used to be
um like things like the glove and also
uh like this this thing out here you can
see um there's like this skull thing
those were like floating creatures so
there were hopping creatures and
floating creatures and like the floating
creatures
were like the glove and the skull the
big skull uh and then there was this
little like skeleton thing here that we
had that hopped around and the hero
those were hopping creatures
and hopping creatures like move by a
transaction like base movement so they
basically query a square to see if they
can move into it and if they can they
will move into it and if they can't they
won't so it's it's like a very like
it's it's sort of almost turn-based it's
it's not turn-based
because it's happening in real time but
it has the same sort of semantics as if
you were just taking turns
uh at the frame level but it's it's
basically that right
um and we sort of didn't really have a
plan for what we wanted to do
uh you know what i mean we we
we didn't really know
oh sorry i forgot about the audio maybe
that's what we were gonna do today
oh yes i can't hear that i'm sorry i
tortured you
um
we were gonna move the audio to a
separate thread that's what we were
gonna do today
should we do that
i'm gonna do the movement first uh let's
do that let's do that next week i'm
gonna turn let me just turn off the
sound for you there
um
and uh and that way i won't i won't
torture you with that
so uh
there's two things that are happening
there and i guess i don't know exactly
how we would want to turn them off but
uh probably the easiest thing to do
would be to just not bother updating the
sample buffer
right
um so you know like the
the output playing sounds thing i should
probably put on a headphone so i can
make sure i don't torture you guys with
this
hold on a second
um
let me just see what happens here if we
just when we do the output playing
sounds thing we just don't actually
bother
so
output playing sounds
is
this code right here
gets called from here
uh and i just don't know can i do this
if the thing is i i may have to clear
the buffer because it may be garbage
right
um and so we'll hear what happens if it
is
nope
so that's an easy way right uh to just
if zero around that and
um you know one of the things i've done
recently that i kind of liked
um is i introduced a thing that's like
capital temporary like that
um and what i do is i'll do like if zero
and then you do temporary so that you
know that you didn't mean to do that
permanently it's just kind of a nice
thing
and you can put that on anything if you
just go into
like the place where you have the rest
of your stuff like your assert macro or
whatever like wherever you have your
sort of things that you do um you can
define like temporary as nothing
and then you can just put temporary in
places and if you then search for it
um you can find all the places where
it's used this is not a case sensitive
search here in fort cotter i don't think
so that's why you get a couple other
things but basically you get the idea
right
uh so i kind of liked that i probably
should have used that for a long time i
just
never really did for some reason um
but
it is something that i kind of liked
so yeah i don't know if i don't really
want to move the mixer today i don't
think that's what i wanted to do
that is what we sort of said we're going
to do last week but i think i'm like nah
nah i'm not going to do that today
um so what i wanted to do is i wanted to
just get some of the movement stuff
working better with like how these
entities are gonna move around
right now moving the hero actually feels
fine
um
you kind of just hold down the key
um till you get where you're going and
then you let go
and it feels fine
so i don't really think we need to do
much with hopping like we'll probably
clean up the code that does it
because we're kind of working on that
system now and we we probably want
things to be a little cleaner
for our own
uh purposes right
and we want to do a trailing edge
triggers of things like hopping so for
example the the
these lighting up before you land on
them right that's because the
transactional movement system currently
fires that event
when you start the hop right to take a
square
rather than afterward does this make
sense
um
so we really don't want uh to do stuff
like that so we want to clean up that
code a little bit but in terms of how it
feels right now it actually feels fine
it feels totally fine to use like i feel
like i could play it like this maybe it
needs some tuning um once i actually
start to do like combat maybe i'll feel
some issues there that i'm like i
probably should clean up this or that
but at the moment it feels pretty
reasonable to use so
really what we're talking about is like
things like the glove
so for starters i need a way to move the
glove around with the hero as the hero
hops around
and just make it you know like i want
the glove to basically just follow
wherever the hero is
um
it should just be locked basically like
i want it to feel more like an action
game
i didn't like the physics-y feel of it
before i was like yes this is kind of
interesting but not quite what i was
going for so what i'd like to do is i'd
like to have the glove be like right
next to the hero right uh at all times
and then i want to have it so that if i
when i actually do like a attack which
is like what i'm doing now
the glove kind of sweeps out a
prescribed pattern i guess
and you know maybe like
the me one of the things i had sort of
toyed with on the last stream is maybe
that pattern is sort of like
dependent on what glove you're using
like maybe some of them just go out one
square like a simple little punch like a
jab but then others maybe do like a
sweep like a pattern
um
you know so like the glove is basically
sweeping out like patterns on the tiles
um
and different gloves have different
patterns
you know
like if you think about it
like suppose that the gloves
just have
like some stats right
and the stats are like how fast like how
much damage does it do when it hits
things
how fast
does it go
right
um
and
and which set of squares does it go
through and you know
um
the other thing you could do is say
that's per square
so like
when we do
you know like i don't know i'm just
sketching this out here i'm not a game
designer this is not my freaking job man
somebody else should have to figure this
out uh
not me
so
yeah like engine programmers are not
supposed to have to be responsible for
this stuff so you know
someone else should have to do this
but the point is
so suppose the entity
right it's
like i kind of had this this idea last
time i think i called did a like a move
queue right
and
the idea behind the move queue was just
that you would stack up some things in
here so like for example if you were
going to
go ahead and
uh
do a a punch it would like add in the
punch
uh
squares that th that glove whatever that
gloves sort of move pattern is it would
add them in
and then it will trace those out
and that's just a given like that's it's
like you're it's it's sort of
it's a little bit dark soulsy although
you know i would i probably i don't love
that kind of thing so i would pr i would
probably add a thing where you can
recall the glove in the middle of a
punch
right uh i pro and and maybe like
sometimes you can't so maybe there's a
little bit of a dark soulsy thing for
certain parts of the move
uh and so basically when you get these
gloves we'd have different like code for
the gloves where we'd say well some of
the gloves put in like this pattern
something this pattern and maybe each of
these you know has other stuff
associated with it even so
you know when you put in a move queue
entry you have things like is it
interruptible but maybe you could also
have things uh right like
you know
a damage value
um or a speed value
right
um
i don't know
maybe those are f32s i don't know how we
want to do this uh
where like
you could imagine
that
as we do the gameplay it might be fun to
be able to create gloves where like the
first two squares don't really do any
damage or not very much
but then like the last square does or
something like that you know what i mean
um
so things like that
you know what i'm saying
uh
basically giving you ways to to make
choices when you're when you're sort of
kidding up
and also to like sort of provide that
kind of binding of isaac you sort of
feel where you like want to
have the runs be kind of
sometimes dramatically different like oh
in this game you know i had a glove
that's very like short distance but high
damage
and in this other one i had one that's
like you know very wide circles but very
small damage over the whole thing and
then another one i had one that like
basically couldn't do any damage like
near me but it could do a lot of damage
far away
right and so you know those would change
sort of the hopping patterns that you
have to use like how you're kind of
trying to move around and how you're
trying to like um
play against the enemies and that seems
like the kind of thing that's pretty
important in these sorts of games where
you're like hey we want to play randomly
generated dungeons
and
have like a different experience every
time that's not like always exactly the
same
uh if that makes sense
so yeah
um
yeah yeah yeah
let's see
what i would do is
[Music]
in the brain code when you go to do an
attack
i guess there's a question of what we
should do if the
like
just trying to think of like
what the actual gameplay would be
you
punch
it adds the things into the move queue
the glove is now in strike mode
so so let's do this first because i'm
not really a game designer right
uh
what i would mostly want to do is
do the
the most straightforward thing first and
then i guess try to feel how it feels
when i'm
doing it and see what happens
so like if you
for starters when you do an attack
it'll just always complete the entire
attack and you have to wait for the
glove to return to you right
so basically like you won't be able to
recall the glove is the first thing
we'll code we'll see what that feels
like and then assuming that i don't
fully like that because i i don't think
i will
i'll want a way for you to probably
recall the glove early
or at least for some gloves i would want
you to be able to do that so like you
know maybe some gloves that are very
powerful you can't do that so it's like
part of the downside of using you know
a particularly powerful glove or
something is that it can't be recalled
that's fine and whatever
um but
i
went will use what it feels like to not
be able to recall it to guide us to how
you will because i guess i don't know
how you would do it like for example
if you try to do an attack it puts the
attack in there while the glove is slow
motion
do i if i hit another attack like i try
to hit attack again
does that recall the glove
like would that be how you recall the
glove
and if you do does it also launch the
attack you requested or does it not do
that right
um
you know uh
does it just like cancel the attack
if you push an attack button but while
the glove is still out it just recalls
the glove and so you double tap
to recall and
restrike
right i mean there's just a lot of
different ways you could do that and i
don't i'm just having trouble like
envisioning what it will feel like so i
just want to do it
you know what i mean
and see because you may want to be able
to recall the glove without
launching a new attack
right
um
like you could imagine
you don't want the glove to hit
something it was about to hit so you
recall it and you don't really want to
attack anything you just want it to
cancel right so it kind of feels it
feels to me like you want the ability to
cancel
without
like
like oh i i sent this glove out to to do
a wide punch but it's going to hit this
barrel that explodes and i don't want to
do that yet because like the enemy like
hopped away and i want to like recall it
but i don't want to re-punch in a
direction i want to save the punch
because i want to time it for something
that's about to happen
right
so it feels like at least four
responsive gloves like gloves that don't
you know have the downside of
uncancelable or whatever right which
which would probably be a thing as well
for gloves that are supposed to be more
responsive i feel like you're gonna want
like more meticulous control and i just
don't know like
yeah i just don't know what you would
push
like i don't really want a separate key
but i don't know maybe you need a
separate key
i don't know
but it's too early to worry about that
let's just get the basic thing working
first and then we'll start to we'll
worry about that
and hopefully we'll be able to kind of
get a feel for what it should actually
be like you know what i mean um so we'll
see
all right
well
um
yeah and oaks let me say one other thing
what if a glove has like aftertouch
right like what if one of the gloves
one of the properties of glove can have
is you can like
chain attacks on the glove so like i can
i can do like an up and then a right on
the glove and it'll do it
like
without coming back to me right like who
knows what other stuff there might be
that we want to do so yeah the more i'm
thinking about it the more i think like
i don't think like hitting an attack
button
should recall the glove
pretty much ever
um
you know what i mean
i guess
all right so let's just do it i don't
know i really don't so we're just gonna
try it here so if we look at some of
these you can see we've got like these
attacked uh nd sword stuff
so i don't really think that's quite how
we're going to
want to write it uh the d sword thing
is sort of correct like this v d sword
thing here
uh
and attacked as two values are plausible
as what we want but it's d sword is not
really the word for it what we're gonna
want here instead
is more like two bases like
we're gonna wanna say okay
we have these movement patterns for the
glove and they're going to be written
probably like as if they go i don't know
like
up and down or something or to the right
then we're going to rotate those
patterns depending on which way you you
asked to to attack
the glove is going to rotate its pattern
into that direction right
so we're going gonna have a thing here
where we would do like
it'd be more of like an attack x and
attack y
that's which kind of square you know
which
um
movement direction we have for each of
the of the squares right that's more
what it would be
um
there's sort of another thing here and
in fact the move cue maybe
it may be more like this
and one of the things that's kind of
annoying about handmade hero is because
we originally did something that allowed
arbitrary like geometry if that makes
sense
um we don't really have a grid per se
so even though like the game looks grid
based it's actually arbitrary like those
squares could be completely
arbitrary
and so we kind of have this annoying
aspect here where this is not an integer
it's actually just a floating point
value
that says where you would want to go
kind of and you like have to sort of
look to see what you would hop to which
really sucks
but there's a lot of things that really
suck about sort of the way we did things
uh that's just the nature of the beast
and also being on stream where you don't
have very much time to fix things
so you know that kind of sucks but point
being the attack x attack y and attacked
values now there would be a slight
modification
for how we were doing things before so
when we look at those attack values
which are like this little thing here
and it kind of looks at like which but
buttons you pushed
um
i guess i don't know what you would do
if you push two attack buttons at the
same time
uh you know i guess we just else clause
this for now um although actually you
know even that's not really that
necessary because it's just it just
changes which one you're going to do
you're going to only do one of the other
uh so we don't really have a good
a good idea about like what we would do
there you know we don't really know like
like if you push two buttons at the same
time
i don't think
i think we just flip flip a coin right
like uh
i don't i don't hmm
like i don't know if what we expect to
do there is too
so you know what i take it back i i i
guess we do sort of know maybe
i'm going to maybe i'm going to maybe
call that a
future topic there because in theory if
we were going to do this where you
could
rapidly cue in things like you don't
have to wait and you want to do a like
upleft attack or whatever
um
i could imagine wanting that to be
a
like
i i could imagine wanting this to
actually be an event cue that you read
so when you look at game controller
input here you actually like look
through and see
now the problem is that you know the
super crappy x input stuff
which is like really really lousy
um
doesn't really give you a good way to to
say like what's the order in which these
buttons were pressed
um
you would have to just like pull at a
high frequency i guess
which makes like no sense because the
thing's usb so there's nothing to pull
it like sends it to you across a wire
it's really dumb
uh but that's just next input for you
so
yeah i don't know
we're gonna do it like this for now but
i do think this is a little bit bad um
or maybe a lot bad
uh as the case may be but we'll see
so if you push the up button then
you know the x in this case would be the
normal
um well
so i guess we have to decide how we want
to encode these
you know i think everything encoded as
if it's faded as if it's facing
rightward is probably the most sensible
thing just because that's how like math
works in circles angle zero
right produces a vector pointing to the
right
so we might as well try to keep with
that convention
uh so really action right let's order
these and let's order these in circle
order just to make it easier on
ourselves so action right um we would
expect that encoding to be the normal
encoding right the one where x is x and
y is y no
change
for up which would be the next one and
down would be last so it'd be it'd be
right up left down
for up we would now expect whatever was
previously the x should now be the y
right because now anything that was
going out from the hero in the rightward
direction it's rotated up so that it's
facing upward
so now that will be y x
um
i'm sorry y
on the other hand which was kind of
going up and down
up
y before is now going left which is
negative x right so again we're just
rotating around the circle this is
basically like sine and cosine
right you know what i'm saying
um so if
if you look at like
what these values are they're just the
sine and cosine of 90 degree angle
increments around right this is sine and
cosine of zero this is sine and cosine
of 90 degrees
uh now we want 180 so now you're flipped
around so now the x that was previously
going out to the right is going to go
out to the left and the y which
previously would have gone up is now
rotated around to face down right
again just sine and cosine is is always
all we're doing here right
uh and then the the final for the
uh
pointing downward
again so now like the x
uh
for for whatever is going in x is now
again going to go in y this time it's
going to to go downward
uh the y is going to come from the x and
again to go downward uh so i believe
that's everything let me make sure that
i've got it right i may have missed one
or i may have i shouldn't say missed one
i may have
bogarted one of them
all right so this is going out to the
right uh and up
right right and up it's it's that
direction
um right uh and this one is is uh
i mean it's really just
two axes that look like that right
it's like an l
so that's that
right now we need that we need to rotate
it
this way
so if we want to rotate it
we now get our y is coming out negative
x that's correct and our
uh our x
is
coming out
uh as y which that is exactly what we
expect yeah
rotate it one more time x is going out
negative x
yup and y is coming out uh
negative y
that's
also what we'd expect right
um and then finally rotated to facing
down
uh we go to
um
[Music]
x going out negative y and y
going out
regular x so that there was one error
there i thought that looked wrong and i
was right
i think that's it
um
that looks good to me
so then what happens is when we know
that we have an attack that did get
pressed uh then we're going to have to
uh
actually insert moves into the move
the move
cue
of the glove
if
it actually did attack right
so in that case
we need to say like all right if you
attacked
um then we need to do some like logic
here if that makes sense
uh and we
we need to push things on to the move
queue
we
we sort of have like
like a couple things we probably want
so
the move cue entries
which are here
uh they they would stack up as
individual movements
but we probably also want
like we might uh
we might want what is going on in the
chat
e of course enum is in c
what are you talking about
enums are in c
pretty much anything you see in handmade
hero is in c
except for
operator overloading
is not in c
and function overloading is not in c
we may use a thing for like profiling
that has a constructor destructor
there's like one thing
i don't think we really use anything
else you would have to add some type
defs
like like you know
this you would write these
like this
but other than that
that's basically it so pretty much like
it it would not
if you had operator overloading in a c
in c
uh
you know you're pretty much home free
for handmade hero would not be very very
difficult right
um
so yeah but enums are
have been in c for a very very very long
time
so uh back to our story so in here we've
got kind of two concerns we have one is
we need to like push moves on to the
move thing so like you know if you
imagined
right you've got like
some kind of like push move call
you know that you're doing here
and like whatever the weird pattern is
that you want the glove to push
uh
you would do that so you'd basically say
like okay we've got the attack x
uh the attack y
and
you know we've got
some movement that we want to do
whatever that is right it's like
we want to go out one
uh
and
or something like that and then over
i don't know
maybe something like that
so you'd go out two squares and then
over one square and then you'd return
right
i and all i wanted to illustrate here is
like so there's two things there right
one is the squares that it's going to
move along
but the other one is while you're doing
that
what if you want to chain moves together
so like i do that and i want to queue up
also after it finishes that i want to
queue up another move
that
tags on the end if this if this glove
has like double tap
right
um if that makes sense
so
double tap
is
double tap is a little harder because we
we need to decide how we want to store
the fact that
we
probably only want
a limited number of over like we don't
want you to just daisy train attacks
like five in a row
we presumably want the glove to have a
number
that is
the number of double taps it can do
before returning right
so presumably
we need some way of doing like a roll
check here like we probably want
like a
uh
there's like individual moves but then
there's sort of the overall move
like a move group count or something
you know
and so
you would do a thing where you do like
move group count
you'd increment
and then you would only
reset move group count when the move q
went all the way down to zero and the
glove like returned so it would it would
really be more like
you know if
glove
um
returned to hero or if
uh
glove
with hero or whatever right so so
you would have this kind of thing where
you
you can cue up two moves or something
uh and then any taps you do after that
just won't they're like ant
and you have to wait for the glove to
come back all the way back to you before
you can do something else
right
oh
oh man
stretch it out something like that
right
so i think we want to be respecting both
of those we want both of those things we
we don't want um
to just think about individual moves we
want to think about groups of moves and
then
in you know individual moves
so
um
i guess one problem i have is i'm not
sure what i would consider returning
you know like i said since i don't
really write this kind of code like
this game design stuff
i don't normally do
so i guess the question is what do you
consider
having returned to the hero anyway
like
is that a
two-stage process probably is it like
okay there's a radius
um
and if the glove is less than that
radius away from the hero and there's no
moves in the move queue
then it has returned
even if it hasn't made it back to like
its resting position it's it's the
radius at which you are allowed to like
start it going again
i mean that sounds
right
ish
um
maybe
i don't really know
again this is not my job
this is this is what game designers are
supposed to do
a lot of times they don't do it
like a lot of game designers are lousy
but it's their job
and you know it's not my job
so
lousy or not it's not my job
so i would say uh yeah there's probably
a radius there and you know i don't know
what we want to call um
this stuff but
there's probably going to be like
basically like stats that we want to
start having for various things
you know what i mean
like uh
we
we could just dump them all in the
entity structure
which
it seems probably less like what i would
want
um
because the stats
the stats are probably hand authored
right again this is where being game
designer would be good but
so in a roguelike
you
don't
really want all of the stats to be like
independently
rolled do you like like when you create
the gloves i mean i'm just trying to
think about like binding of isaac right
um i'm just trying to think of like
roguelikes that i've enjoyed you know
and if you think about that like
the the items are just the items like
there there aren't
there aren't like
randomly created items in the game
it's just it's just
it's just like a set of items that
somebody designs right
like you don't
you don't have like when you play
binding of isaac the items are all new
every time right
you play the same game with the same
items every time
there's just like
different
items that are the the set of items that
appear in that dungeon are randomly
selected
from the pool of existing of items that
exist right
so
so that suggests to me that i would
probably want like an authorable bank
of like here's all the items
like here's all the different gloves
right
and the gloves have their like stats on
them
and
then yeah like if you then if you pick
up modifiers
the modifiers like are combined
with the glove stats
but they're all all of this always comes
from like a group like a
like a
[Music]
a bank of static
yeah
integers are not more efficient than
floats by the way floats are far far
more efficient than integers
like
by several orders of magnitude usually
pun intended i suppose
um
like good luck finding a fuse multiply
add for integer
on most chips but you now almost always
have a fuse multiply add for float
not to mention the fact that you don't
have to shift correct for a scale
um
so
yeah i don't know
um
i i don't like i said this is not my
this is not my area i don't do this kind
of code
uh
so i'm not sure where this stuff would
go
like we could just stuff it in the
entity but it may make more sense to
have the entities sort of have like
basically like a just a like almost like
a
uh
asset id
you know what i mean
um where the asset id just says like
this is the stats
that i have
this entity has
and then you know we iterate over
if you've if you've collected items the
players items like
uh you know
affect
that
so i don't know like i said not my area
of expertise i would have strong
opinions about this i'm sure if i was a
game designer um as an engine programmer
it's just not something i think about
because it's like you know it's a it's
preferences it's like
what what would what does the designer
want right like what does the designer
think is good there so uh that's that's
tricky for me i don't know but you could
imagine like
um some kind of a settings thing where
we basically said like okay you know if
we imagined
sort of the stats that determine
uh
that these sorts of things can do
there's like a
there's like a max move group count
thing which is you know this would be
how many
moves can cue
back to back without returning
um there would be some kind of a damage
multiplier
i guess it's a base damage value like
i'm just thinking like the glove right
so
it strikes me that probably what you
would want here for the gloves are like
different type move types
so
um
because you're gonna need a way to like
explain this
you know what i mean like okay so i'm
just trying to think about it uh here
visually right
so suppose we create a glove and the
glove
has a pattern of squares that it's going
to attack
that pattern of squares
it would be very easy if that's all i
needed to communicate to the player was
that you're going to pick up this glove
right
and it's gonna do like
zero damage to this square one damage to
this square and two damage to that
square
right like that's what the glove does
um that's easy to articulate because
when you go to get the glove you could
just do a like you could do a thing that
basically says like zero one two or you
know
uh
empty
green red right i mean you could think
of many ways that that could be drawn
that makes it very obvious
you know
but
the part that
would be very confusing to try and
articulate later
would be
okay now i want items that affect that
so so now the designer wants to come in
and go oh and
and like you know when you have that
that sort of pattern well the final
strike if you get this item you have a
20 chance of getting double damage on
the final strike or whatever right like
that's the kind of thing a designer
would do
well how do you articulate that to the
player because you all you did was just
draw this thing for the glove this item
is unrelated to the glove so how do they
articulate to the player that this item
affects this square of this glove right
so to me it would make more sense i
think to say that there are basically
square classes right so maybe there's
like three colors or three symbols or
something so when you get a glove
it has like you know diamond square and
circle or or a b and c or one two and
three right
um and those are the different square
types and so the glove has a base damage
for each of its square types
um each of the three square types or
something
and then items can say how much they add
to each of the square types
you know what i'm saying
um so basically like
i don't know if that i don't know if
that makes more sense right to
if you understand what i'm saying
but
and that way you can have like
interesting gloves too that invert the
normal pattern like you could have two
gloves that are exactly the same except
they have invert assignment to where the
squares are so like the same items would
do opposite things to those two gloves
right
like um if normally
the
c-square is the far square and the
a-square is the close-square you could
have a reverse
like a inside-out glove or whatever
right and it flips them around
you know what i mean
um
[Laughter]
frizzy i like that
yeah
um
[Laughter]
uh that's actually exactly what we
should do the glove has six slots
and if you fill them all you can snap
your fingers and half of the world
dissolves that's a very good idea
was it six or five
for some reason i thought it was five i
didn't pay very close attention to those
movies to be honest it's six
i don't know
um
so anyway yeah i think that's how we
would probably do it so maybe we would
have a thing like
uh move square
type
you know
um and
we would just have some of those
you know
so there would be like
um
sort of like an equation
and you know probably these equations
would be pretty standard
like
like they're just going to be like these
affine things so we're like you know
maybe there's like a stat eq
where you basically say like hey there's
the elements of the stat equation
and there's three of them like x squared
x and affine like
x to the zero
um or something like that so maybe we do
more like this where we were
anticipating that these are fairly
standard
and we basically look look there's just
like the damage for those squares and
you know maybe there's other kind of
study cues that go in there
who the heck knows i don't know
uh and so
then you could you could multiply these
together in fact we could say that these
are just v3s
um
that is probably the easiest thing
you know
something like that
uh so you could basically take these
things and just multiply them together
uh
so you know if you have a thing
where you're
uh or or add them you know however you
want to do that i'm trying to think of
like what the most straightforward way
to do that is
i'm trying to think of the most the how
you would want to represent that well
how we have to just write the code and
back it out it's probably too
presumptuous to actually put it in here
right
um but so you're going to have some
random stuff like that kind of thing you
know what i mean
uh and the reason i say like we probably
want to make this
something that we have ways of composing
is because there's there might be a lot
of these right
like you might have things like okay you
know this
this happens in is is there a poison gas
cloud or is the are you in the water or
whatever right and
you would probably probably need to have
like
random expressive things that are going
on in here
so we would have some kind of a damage
thing and that would be evaluated
separately for each type of move square
so when you are in a particular phase of
the move anything that you hit
in that square is going to have a
different thing done than things in the
other square right so there's just going
to be like a
kind of a trade-off there right
um and i like that that seems good
and then the question would be like
i
i guess what else we would need so
there's there would be like stats there
would also be like move
patterns
again i'm just trying to sketch out like
thinking about what we've got
we have move patterns and those are
going to be like any set of things that
is
um
supposed to be used with the move cue
and
presumably the things that go in here
would basically be like
hmm
so the things that go in here are gonna
then be yeah this is gonna be kind of
annoying so we're going to have a thing
that actually happens as
you
evaluate stats against entities and
the question is like what kind of stats
are we going to have is there just going
to be a single damage number or are we
going to have like status effects
um
something like binding of isaac has no
status effects
right
i
and i guess i don't have a strong
opinion about that
it seems a little bit unnecessary like
it might just be like too complicated at
that point
like because now you have to think about
like what the move patterns are
and now you're also thinking about like
status effects
that are gonna happen
i think the reason that i don't know
that status effects make a lot of sense
here is because
the problem with status effects is they
assume you have the ability to like
actually equip
let me just talk this out
right
so the way i would say is
status effects are
not going to be
things you can
adapt to right so would just be like do
you end up getting a weapon that has
fire damage or not
right
normally the reason things like that
would be interesting in games
is if you can have like a more balanced
approach because you you know you take
multiple weapons with you
and you like plan for that or whatever
or you're like oh i'm going into the
area that has like a lot of poison
creatures so i need to be able to wear
my poisoned
um
resistance necklace or whatever right
in
a
binding of isaac style game you don't
have you only have one attack right so
you don't have the ability to do those
sorts of things
and in this game i don't think
however
okay that said you do have the idea of
hopping on the tiles and so maybe that's
where that comes from okay so i would
say we probably do have that actually
so we are going to have a bunch of
things here so so basically the move
pattern
whatever the move pattern is that we
load up right
um the move patterns are going to have
to have like basically all of this stuff
in there so we say the move pattern has
which square type each thing is
right
and where those squares are
and presumably that's basically like
a thing that
maybe gets copied directly i don't know
if it actually would or no it wouldn't
because it gets transformed first
so there's a move pattern entry
um and a move pattern and these are the
things that we would actually have to
have for an individual glove we'd load
this out of here and we go and we don't
really know what has in it because until
we get further down we don't know all
the things but we know at least
it's going to have a concept of a move
square type which is just like you know
i want to be able to mark those
uh so like the l shape we were making
now i want to be able to mark like the
ones that are close
as a different type as the ones that are
far for example that's the thing i would
like to have
to experiment with in the gameplay if we
end up deciding it's not that
interesting we can pull it out but i
want at least try it uh before i would
decide that
so uh
the move pattern entries you know
there's some entries
in this thing and i don't know how many
we have max i haven't thought about that
we'll set that to whatever we actually
want
but then we've got like uh each thing in
the move pattern is going to have a um
a type
and
a
delta
right a normal a normal delta so a like
rightward
delta or whatever i don't know what we
want to call this like a facing facing
to the right
um it would have a rightward delta
rightward
normal delta
canonical delta
right
um
and i think that's all there is in a
move
pattern
um
i guess we'll throw in one more thing
for good measure which is is it
interruptible
and maybe
we would do something like
that is the interrupt typical or hubble
it's typical
so
so in general i guess i would say we
we have move patterns
right they
look like this
we
know that we're going to have something
that happens here but this could be we
have no idea how this is going to work
uh this is just gonna be something that
like we
start writing some code to evaluate
these and some stuff happens right
um so whatever happens there happens we
don't know
we probably need some things in the
stats for like the speed of the glove um
[Music]
and i guess i don't know
tk dev uh your suggestion is not
useful
um
so i guess what i would say is
i don't know what we want for speed
stuff because again that gets down into
the stat stuff which we don't really
know what we want to do
but i think this is roughly what we need
so we need something where we can have
patterns
those patterns will get copied into a
queue
um
the queue will have computed
what we're actually going to do
based off of like something that we have
no idea what it looks like that
basically gets like um
you munged down right so there's gonna
be like gameplay code in here that i
don't know how to write or what it looks
like right because it's it's it's
entirely game designery stuff like
how how do you want to compute damage
right like it's
it's not really engine stuff it's more
just like what what is
gameplay stuff for that right
um
so what we want to be able to do there
is just say
okay we've got the patterns patterns are
stored separately from statistics right
patterns are just
here's the flags
like
maybe that's only ever can it be
interrupted or not
but maybe there's other things that are
important here who knows um like maybe
for example another one would be like um
like you could imagine putting something
in here that's like uh ephemeral or
something
did that
f fm
mural
again we gotta check the spelling here
yeah uh
so
in here right you could imagine also a
thing that's like this is allowed to
phase through things and not touch them
or whatever
so you know again these are both
completely experimental i'm just saying
these are things we want to try in the
game design but the point is that's
where they would go so in the move
patterns we can specify like oh
here's like a pattern and it can do
whatever random crap
nothing in that specifies any stats
because stats are some other thing that
we don't know how to do right now
um this is just saying here's the
pattern and here's what the types of
squares are
i like
would they be
in one of several classes maybe there's
only two classes maybe there's five
maybe there's ten we don't know that's
just like game design that we hope we
won't screw up later
that has to do with the stats
uh then we have the actual move queue
and the move queue itself
is basically just a way of taking a
pattern you would combine it with the
stats that we don't know what to do
about
you would produce some value for each of
the squares and then the squares then it
just goes through those squares and the
gameplay gets evaluated on each one
right
um so i think that's
i think that's roughly what i wanted
this part i don't know right like this
part is gonna have to come
through like figuring out
what is happening with monster attacks
right and we're just gonna have to like
grind away at that
at some future date so i don't i don't
know what this looks like this
it makes perfect sense right um but
i i don't know
um i have no idea what's going on out
there also we have no idea what these
would be but you know abc seems fine for
getting started
all right so i think that's all i need
and um
so when we do like these push moves so
that's how this would work right so we
would basically imagine we're going to
get these move patterns from somewhere
there'd be like an entry count in this
thing
and you can imagine we would basically
have a move pattern here and we'd just
make one of these as if we got it from
somewhere which we didn't right
um
this would be like the attack pattern
right
uh and the attack pattern is going to be
three things long and it's gonna have
these in it right
so these um
these uh these moves
uh there's
i don't i don't know like i'll just
assign them each a different square type
for now so that we can if we want to
start playing with that later we can
um but then we have like the
the type the delta and the flags so the
delta
are just these
right
uh and the flags
we don't know but i'll just set them to
interruptable for now because we know
we're going to want to play with that
um and so
you know and you know i could even say
like let's set it like this
so
we can actually play with that as well
right we'll just see what happens so you
can't interrupt it in the first square
but you can interrupt it before the
other squares or something
i don't understand how the pattern is
involved oh uh rational quarter i have
some i thought you yes so what rational
coder said like
i totally agree that you don't want to
go too far ahead but like you kind of
have to sketch something out that you're
going to type in because i don't
have anything in here right there's
there's nothing for like how gloves
attack so i have to make something up
to start with um
and
i know i want to try the pattern thing
so that's what we did
uh we don't have to do it could get
removed but
i don't understand how the pattern is
involved in the gameplay what is the
function of pattern uh it's how a glove
punches
so basically like when you when you do a
glove punch
some gloves are just like they punch one
square out other gloves will punch like
and do damage out
like two squares or three squares away
right
um
and
more importantly
it won't just be gloves
like the the um
[Music]
the
enemies we would all would be the same
encoding
so basically that what we're typing in
for gloves will also just be true of
monstar right so monstar will have you
know
different attack patterns
that they execute
based on their like sort of random role
of like oh it wants to attack now so you
know or whatever
that kind of stuff
um so so these would probably be unless
they really suck
uh they would probably be what we'd use
for everything
everybody just does
like
they have moves they queue
and
probably like
the monsters can't really interrupt them
much
so like part of that part of like
playing the game is probably knowing the
monster patterns right and knowing like
oh when a monster is executing this
pattern
you know he has to do these three things
so if i punch at this square
that's like a good move right
um
and like yeah a lot like a chest move
right so sort of like a real-time chess
moves right like this is how the night
works and this is how the bishop works
and this is how the
pawn works or whatever
and
um
you
you don't have like turn taking but you
do know once someone initiates an attack
that you are familiar with you know you
have that predictability that like it is
this attack so you can counter that
attack
you know
so if we are going to attack uh then we
are just going to try out this little
thing we've got this fake attack pattern
here
and so then uh what
oh someone's unhappy too many initialize
or
oh you're right you are sir
this needed an additional
i guess maybe i'll do it like that so
the indentation is okay
um
so if we assumed that we had some kind
of a place where these things were
coming from right rather than being
defined directly inline this is what we
would get back so then we would have a
little thing here where we just loop
through and say uh you know okay for
each of these
this is probably move count and this is
probably moves
right
and you can see like this would we'll
just once we get this right you know
once or or at least close to right
um you can see this will just become a
generic routine right where you'll just
pass the attack pattern and it'll like
push the transformed version on
right so
what we would do here is we'd loop
through these we have the attack pattern
we pull out like one of the moves and
now we just translate that move which is
encoded in like canonical form
into
whatever the actual move is
so like in our move cube
um maybe i'll call this source right
um
and then i've got a desk which would be
the
[Music]
the translated version
so the delta equals the canonical delta
right so we
we know we have an attack x and attack y
so we just transform
[Music]
the move
from its canonical form
direction right
uh by just doing standard you know
standard transform right
uh the damage is the part we don't know
so this is like
hey this is the temporary thing i was
talking about right
we don't know
um so we can just throw that in there of
course well four quarter won't like it
so we'll put it before the semicolon
um
so we have a damage we have a speed and
those are the things like that like the
stat system is gonna have to supply
eventually like i don't know what these
are so we'll just
set them to just random values here and
we'll figure that out later
um and then we've got our flags i don't
know why this is called interruptible
still supposed to be called flags forgot
to change it
and so now hopefully you can kind of see
what i was talking about right so this
comes together pretty nicely so
basically these are the kinds of things
we would define like these little attack
patterns
and then when we go into the
actual
uh to issue like an attack for a monstar
or uh you know well it doesn't matter
for anything right
um
we translate them from their canonical
like pattern into an actual like correct
facing direction
um for the for the entity
and
i think that's basically it
right
so this has to be predicated on
a few things like
you have to have room
so
if the entities
move cue
if the move q count
for the entity
plus the
the thing that you're trying to do
um that would have to be less than the
size of the actual move queue so there's
probably that's never going to actually
be a thing
because presumably
we simply will always set this value in
fact we may just want to do this
yeah
what what is
what is happening
ryan
ryan what is this
can somebody go ask ryan what that what
is happening right now
so oh it's showing me
the definition of a cert
but it's it has grabbed
like the entire
thing
or something
yeah okay so you can see like it's got
this heads up thing down here i guess
where like i'm on
if i'm on a function
[Music]
it shows the prototype of the function
that's kind of cool i didn't know that
was there
and then i guess it's just it's just
failing look at that
look at how fancy
i seriously have never noticed that it
does that
i gotta set the color is probably better
because you can't read it but
um
that's kind of nice isn't that that
seems kind of nice
anyway
um
so
the point is
ignoring all that uh move q overflow is
probably something we want to
warn on
in debug because
we
this
move group count thing
is the gameplay restriction like hey if
this glove has two aftertouch then you
can queue up two moves
but you should never run out of space in
the move queue because the move queue
should just be set to
if the maximum length of an attack
pattern is eight and the maximum amount
of time of
after touch you can have is three then
the move queue should be 24 long right
we we should never you should never
actually
um
end up in a in a place
where you
um
where you overflow the move queue that's
probably just a bug right
so what we'd like to do there is it just
set that properly and so i'd if this
ever tops out i'd rather get told about
it
in development mode than it just
silently handling it and moving on
because it's a subtle gameplay bug at
that point
right um as opposed to like a crash or
something so you'd never really know it
would just feel like something didn't
quite happen and you might miss it so
i'd rather have that like be loud and
and stop everything
um
so we've got uh
another condition here which is that
um you would have to the move group
count
uh
also why is this
what's the error here
oh it's not entity it's glove
um
so what we want to do here is just
make sure
that we
always
have enough
um like the move group count for the
glove
we want to make sure that the movement
move group count is always less than
whatever our magical like way of saying
what the stat is
we don't know what that is but like it's
gonna be a thing
um
and like this is where we now get into
the part that i was saying like i don't
really know what we're gonna do
we need to evaluate we need to have some
way of evaluating what the stats are on
things and
i do not really know um
so i don't really know
um
[Music]
should the if just be the assert no
because if if we did screw that
counting up we don't want the game to
crash or something right
that would literally just corrupt the
entity table
you know what i'm saying
so so no definitely not you want to
bounce check that
uh that push
um
so yeah
now we are at the part where we got to
think about how yeah how we were going
to evaluate the stats we don't care so
much
about what we're evaluating because we
don't really know
um but we do have the problem of
how how are we going to when do we
produce like the aggregate stats for an
entity because like
we're gonna want to sort of have the
stats for the entity be based on things
that
may be very like
game play
squishy right
like oh
you
get a plus one damage modifier for the
next five rooms
and
i
get plus plus one to move square b
damage
uh
or like
the the glove is
interruptable always
for
this period of time or whatever you know
um
when you want to add those kind of
roguelike nonsense things
uh you need like some kind of a coherent
place where that happens and presumably
we want to not do it just in time like
presumably we want to do a thing where
we
where we just like evaluate everything
at the head of the frame
[Music]
and produce one set of composite stats
for the entity
i'm guessing
you know
like i don't know my assumption is just
like there should probably be a thing
where we assume that
at the start of the round right like
before brains are
like
evaluated so before like you know you or
the ais sort of like
put in the commands for that frame
i like i assume what we would want to do
i assume what we would want to do is do
that i don't know
like i said i don't have stronger pants
values because i kind of have to make it
up as i go along because i don't do this
type of code normally
but like
so you see this i mean this is basically
the structure of the game update loop
right
so basically brains run first
and they
you know control what's going to happen
on that frame like what things are
trying to do
um
and then
we do update and render entities to like
flush everything out
i could imagine doing like
uh before
like uh one more loop up here right
that does
that does the
compute what the entity stats are for
this frame or
slightly differently
at the tail of this so when we do update
and render entities
and we loop through all the entities
we produce the
[Music]
statistics for the next frame at the at
the end
right
um
if that makes sense
i guess i would say
the
the latter thing sounds
i mean
i again don't really have a strong
opinion about it but i think what i
would say is it seems to me like
probably the smartest thing to do here
would be to put that where you do update
and render entities because you're
always going to want to look at these
stats all the time for all the stuff
you're doing right
and so presumably you just want to
compute it
that time
now
i feel like this is easier said than
done because we sort of now have to
address how we want to handle a bunch of
things that current or previously
we just haven't really looked at
like for example we don't have any
opinion on how we want
our
like how do you even get power-ups or
items or things like that
right
um
and i don't know i might want to think
about it uh how much time are we going
for
all right it might it's going to be
pretty short today actually because uh i
got a bunch of stuff i have to do before
tomorrow so
i probably won't go very long um i don't
actually know what time it is but
what time is it
2 30.
um
so uh so i do think we kind of have like
two separate we have two separate things
we have to sort of do we've got to do
the move q stuff which seems easier
like i've mostly got that
how i think that would work
but the stats thing
[Music]
is harder because even just the things
i'm thinking about right now i'm not
sure what the most
like sensible way is of doing those
sorts of things
uh in here right like
again it's a case of like i'm sure i
would have a strong opinion about that
had i done this kind of code typically
but i don't
so like if you imagine what happens in
here
you
you figure at some point you're going to
pick up an item
and
the question is just
um how does that item
how does that item get its stats
conferred to you so
let's take the simplest possible case
and work from there because that's you
know
we don't want to over complicate things
um
i would say
imagine like we want the hero to pick up
a hat
so
there's a hat
and the hat
is
swappable so if the hero picks up a
different hat
they drop the hat they currently have
right
so they can only wear one hat at a time
and they pick up different hats
throughout the game potentially so you
know one of the hats
gives you plus one damage and the other
gives you plus one speed or whatever
so you want while you're wearing hat a
you want plus one damage while you're
wearing hat b you want plus one speed
and you just want them to be able to
switch at any time like when they hop
over
a different thing it should switch and
your stats should change
um
i'm too tired today
gary sleep
and i didn't have any coffee
well that's not true i had decaf coffee
but that's same as not having coffee
um
so the question is
those are obviously have to be entities
so because they're going to exist in the
world
and you can drop them and they get drawn
right so the hats are obviously entities
the
uh
the entity system would presumably just
need a thing that was like i'm carried
by
and
and then the question is just like how
do we efficiently
how do we efficiently say that you add
your stats into the person who you're
carried by
one way that comes to mind is you just
have like a ping-pong buffer where you
basically say like entity stats
ping-pong in this thing
seems like over-complicated
but you have
you know
if you don't want to do multiple passes
i'm not sure what else you do
because if you're going through all the
entities and you want to go through the
entities only that one time
you know like you you only want to go
through them
of course are we already you know could
we just do this when we initially do the
unpack
so i suppose i don't really know
um
there's sort of the world unpacking
process here right there's
begin sim simulate and sim
and
we we operate with entities like in the
cache
right
and the sim
so like
since we rebuild this thing every time
i guess the thing we could do here
is
we could just say
okay we clear
hmm
i'm just not sure i'm just not sure how
you want this to work
when we add the entity to the hash
that's means this that the entity is
gonna get operated on this frame
um
[Music]
we
we could clear
a stat holder at that point
and move
i mean
like here's the thing i was thinking i i
don't know if i think this is
particularly good
so here's add entity to hash
um
and when it goes into the hash
at this point you could do a thing where
you said all right
the entities
like active stats
um
you could do something like this
where when the entity gets brought into
the working set of entities for a
simulation
it basically says hey okay we're gonna
take all the accumulated stats for the
entity at that point we're going to
move them
and say that they are now the active
stats for the entity that will operate
across this particular frame
um and then we clear out the accumulator
then when we update all of the entities
when we go through the thing calling
update entities
we just say
that
if you are someone who affects another
entity you accumulate at that point
right so it's like one frame
that you know
every frame you recon you recompute the
stats as part of the sweep
and then the next frame those stats take
effect
you know what i mean
anyone
no
that's just that's just a vague guess
right
that's just a vague guess
so in the entity struct
uh we would just have
like whatever the stats are
um
that we keep
which you know again we really don't
know what that looks like
there would be a thing that's like
accumulation stats
uh
and
active stats
that are just things that you work on
there
uh
and then
we have the base stats up here right
and so basically like every time you
you kind of just like work through that
have you considered dynamically
calculating stats based on the current
modifiers
i mean that is what we're doing
do you mean every time you go to look at
an entity's stat for any reason you
recompute all the stats on the fly right
there
is that what you mean like the
like when you need want to ask a
question about the damage you go iterate
through all the entities that might be
affecting the damage and you compute it
just right there
um
i mean you could do that but that sounds
kind of
risky right like as things start as more
things start to happen on the screen
you're suddenly potentially recomputing
the same thing like many many many times
right
and furthermore you'd have to create
acceleration structures specific to that
because like how do you even know which
entities might affect it so you'd have
to start keeping like a list
like here's all the entities that
are currently potentially affecting this
person's damage level right
i mean and why bother
you know like why bother when you could
just
while you're sweeping over all the
entities which you know you're going to
do to do their update anyway why not
just have them
[Music]
dump stats into anyone who they think
they affect at that time
and that way there's really no need for
additional
thought
to it
probably right i mean doesn't it seem
just more sane to not do it that way to
not to not have to have
ways of quickly coming up with these
values
just in the moment
so that you don't have to care
they never get stale well they might i
mean they might actually be
you you still have the order dependency
problem right so if you compute the stat
when you ask for it
well
what if a one of the other entities that
would have affected your stats hasn't
updated yet that frame
and you so when you go look and see oh
that entity is gonna have it says it has
five damage or whatever so you add that
five damage into your computation then
you get to that other entity in the
update step and oh it turns out it died
so it shouldn't have contributed right
or whatever
so
you really aren't
it's not really more correct
it's just different right it's just a
different order of operations but it can
still totally be wrong
in exactly the same way this could be
wrong because you'd have the opposite
problem here
where it's like well
you're going to use
the previous
like
you're going to use
the
[Music]
post
update state of the entity on the last
frame always
right
and never
the post
value from this frame
maybe is
better or maybe is worse but at least
it's consistent whereas the just in time
one you have no idea it just depends on
the order of updates of the entities
right
in fact as i'm saying it i think there's
actually a good reason not to do it the
way you're suggesting because that would
always be order dependent like which
order do you update the entities and
determines what the outcome is of that
of those stat roles we're using the a
definitive set of stats that get
computed on the final frame seems a lot
better because at least then it doesn't
matter what order you ask the stats in
you know
so i think i'm kind of skeptical of the
approach that you're saying now that i
think about it
i think that sounds more error-prone not
less
whereas if you update the stats every
frame
in a
double buffered way basically then you
know that the stats for any given frame
are what they are they don't change
based on where you are in the entity
update order you don't suddenly use a
different set of stats halfway through
you know
so i think i think i would say that it
does seem like that's something you
would want
i don't know hard to say uh but
seems like it uh
this
is not really necessary because hey is
that the only a tan two
how many a tan twos do we have
sadly we do have
looks like we do have one atoms in there
i see what we did here we just we just
wanted to be able to do the orbit and
pitch values
reverse engineer them from where the
camera currently was which is you know
it's noble
um anyway
so
this thing is just
the d sword y d sword x thing right
so the facing direction here i think
we could probably just write down
um
but it is just the attack x vector so i
think i think this can just be subbed in
for this
moment we shouldn't we should just set a
separate value for that and not do it
that way
um
sort of a separate issue but
uh let's go back to what we were looking
at here
so we do want the glove
stats um
and maybe since we're going to be
referring to these like lots of times we
want to just call them instead of active
stats maybe we just call them the stats
it's that stats is a
function
it's it's in c time
i like that we're loading c time as part
of the uh
dev
bell biv devotes set here
um
okay
so
i think maybe we just call it stats
because that's what everyone uses and
then there's like a stats of hume
right uh
and then the base stats are like a
different thing right or whatever blah
blah blah
so in here we would do something like
this uh
i'm i'm not gonna say that it's gonna
look exactly like this because
it's probably not
uh but it will look something like this
right when we add the entity to the hash
we would have like uh
maybe like the get or or um
advanced
entity stats or something like that
and so we would call
a function here
that was just like advanced entity stats
and i'll grab that out and put it here
when we see that we do the little double
buffer swap
so we're good to go
uh and that maybe goes into the entity
side of things
right
so
there's this
and
i guess
then anyone can look at what those stats
are
like so
and choose to make decisions about it
um
in
fact you could even sketch out what this
looks like at that point
because now you could say
well
whatever the move pattern entries
square type was
you could do
the glove stats
um
damage for that
move square type
right
so glove stats speed for that
move square type
and and now it's actually sort of
a thing
um i'm going to get rid of the
coefficient thing for now because hey
like
i don't really know what we're doing
here so i'm just going to say it looks
maybe like that
um and then we'll figure out how the
coefficient stuff would work later like
we'll figure out how to get something
fancier in there
when ready uh the entry count
thing for attack pattern
it's actually move count
[Music]
um
same
here
and then the move cue entry dest
this
is actually the glove move cue
first of all this should be a star we're
writing to it
so there's
that but the move cue
it's just whichever
is
actually this value
and each time we push something on we
want to advance that volume
all right
so i think that's basically it the
glove with hero following
stuff is sort of like a separate issue
now and i don't actually know what we're
gonna do with that so maybe we'll save
that until next time but i think we're
more or less where we need to be
so i think that was good uh i'm sure
this isn't great because like i said i i
don't write this kind of code
for a living so
i don't know
but
that looks like a solid enough stab
and
now we can go set some stats and try to
like actually implement the move and
attack stuff in some way and we'll just
we'll see what happens right
um
i would say that if we just take the
delta between these two so if we just
said like
hey there's a glove distance
uh that's just like the length squared
um between
wherever the glove is and wherever the
body is
um and if the glove distance squared is
less than you know whatever
i don't know what it is
something like that
then you're
you're back with the guy
you know what i mean
um
now this would presumably only happen
when there wasn't anything in the move
queue
uh
so right you're only going to reset it
if there's nothing in the queue and
you're back then you do this
um and off we go now there's
probably a few other little things in
here like okay if the move q count is
zero
um
and you didn't attack
you would want the glove to like find
its way back towards the hero
so
like the actual target like basically i
think we do next time is like okay now
we're gonna actually start the movement
code because we kind of know how
everything is going here
um
you know
like set a return move when there's no
moves in the queue
um or
where
does
does the movement
code
live for that i don't know
so i think that's basically it
um i'm going to say that's it for today
because like i said it has to kind of be
a short day
that was a little
it was a little bit like okay
let's just try to poke around in here
and see what the heck makes sense but
that seems good
i'm relatively happy with that uh and i
think it'd be pretty easy for us to put
that
to like use the same stuff for multiple
things so i think enemies can use that
as well
and it'll be reasonable so
all right
that's about it
um i'ma wrap it up
thank you everyone for joining me
and i will maybe find someone to raid
maybe
um
i guess we'll see if john is streaming
of course he's not
um
[Music]
well
uh yeah
i guess we're
we don't know so you're gonna have to
find your own thing
and i'm sure you will
and
and i wish you the best of luck on that
stream take it easy everybody