hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero show we code a complete game
live on stream i am going to
well i am going to go ahead and
see what we want to do today
because i think mostly uh
the only thing i wanted to look at that
was a hangover from last week
was just the fact that uh i wanted to
make sure that
we had a good answer for how brains
would work
in cases where we didn't want them to
activate if only some of the parts of
the brain
were uh together and
i guess like that's sort of the topic
for today i
don't know how much we want to do with
that or don't want to do with that
because it kind of depends
um on how far we want to go with it so
what i'm going to do
is oh oops
what i'm going to do first is run the
shell
there we go um so i
i don't really know uh exactly what we
want to do with it
and really what i'm talking about here
is just the part of the code
where like if you look at at how we're
doing doors right now
so or well how we're doing anything so
what happens is
we gather up entities based on what
to which brain they belong
uh and then we run the code on them
right
and i don't know to what extent we want
to do uh
i don't know to what extent we actually
want this to to happen
but the problem that we're seeing is
this means that things like
multi-entity systems get constructed
per frame and then disbanded right so in
other words what happens is
entities are the permanent thing that
gets stored they get placed out into
you know the world and
when they get pulled in if the
particular region that you're simulating
only contains some of the entities that
were part of a unified structure
it doesn't actually matter the brain
will still run and can do stuff to those
entities
now i don't know whether we want to
change this design
because we haven't really gone anywhere
on it it just is what it is like it's
you know there's not much code here
right if we were to rewrite this code it
would be hardly anything
so there's really not much that we have
to do uh
and you can see here this uh mark brain
and
actives thing right you can see this
thing
is already designed to sweep over the
brains and s
and mark uh and and pull entities in
from the inactive region if if there is
a brain
and there are entities that are active
or not it will like activate entities
that were not there that it will
activate entities that were in the
inactive region
of the sim uh
automatically right so we'll pull them
in
so the problem that i see
is even with something like this it
doesn't really help
because no matter what you do there's
always
there's always going to be that regional
split where you basically say
all right if something is inside the
active region
then there will be things outside the
active region wherever the split is
and we're always going to have this
happen
i guess you could say well you know what
now that i think about it
this feels like though if you assume
that one of them has to be
active
yeah so so if you assume that one of
them has to be active which this does
this looks and sees are any active
then we make all of them active right
so i guess my only question is does that
just mean we needed to check to see if
they were
active first okay
yeah you know what this may just work we
may just have not really done the full
code now that i
think about it
interesting interesting okay so let me
run this by you real quick first of all
i want to see
where we actually do this is it in world
or sim region or what
because mark brain actives um
has to be called by somebody in order to
do something
i don't see it being called here
so all right so
you riddle riddle me this batman
um because i i think this
maybe this this thing that we did maybe
really did solve the problem now that i
think about it
uh and and maybe it's just a case
of it of
when we did it we didn't quite think it
through all the way we we were like sort
of thinking
halfway about it um
and we didn't quite like internalize uh
what actually needed to happen right um
and so it's entirely possible that
we can actually
use this system i'm trying to think of
whether i should do a drawing here
i probably should do a drawing um
do y'all mind waiting one second because
i think i can probably use
the starco galaxy setting setup to do
the drawing
real quick hold on
okay let me see if i can use the star
code galaxy setting for the setup for
this
uh because i i probably can i don't know
you might as well check it out
let's take a look um
all right
so the only question is if i'm doing
this here
is this mic set up to hear me well
enough so can you hear that okay
let me go check because i haven't done
level testing of this in obs
when i record star code galaxy actually
record quite differently
than this setup but i think it can
stream so let me check
how's that audio is that audio any
better hopefully that's a little that's
i just boosted it a little bit
okay
all right so let me just explain really
quickly
what's going on here because this can be
kind of confusing and
again this is pretty experimental stuff
all the entity system stuff we've done
has just been entirely off the cuff like
looking for interesting things to do
because i feel like that's just an
interesting thing and it's probably
something that you know most people
they just kind of do weird stuff like oh
we implemented an
entity component system and then we just
shove everything through it but people
don't generally think about like what
they actually
should be doing to try and make a good
architecture for programming entities
and so we're just trying some stuff out
because we want to see if we find
anything
interesting as a result so here's what's
actually happening right
we have entities in the world and for
example let's say we have the door
like the stuff with the door so we'll
have something where we have you know
a a room let's say that's kind of out
here maybe something like this
right and then we have like one of these
things has like a blocker so there's a
door
like this right here is a door
you know what i'm saying so if you have
a door here
and you've got some stuff in here that's
dependent
that like opens the door so let's say
there's the tiles like we kind of were
making those tiles you hopped on
and these are kind of wired to the door
so
when you you know when you step on all
of these the door opens
that itself is sort of that is what the
brain
is in terms of the actual like gather so
there's a thing
called a brain right and these are
created
every frame so on a particular frame if
you have
a door right a and then some tiles b
c d or whatever then what happens is
when
on a particular frame each of these has
a brain id in it that says i belong to
brain 4976
it's just a number it doesn't exist
anywhere it's just a number
in each entity that says this is the
brain i belong to on a given frame
when entities are gathered the entities
are gathered
based on their brain id and put into
brains that only execute for that frame
so a b c d get put in here into slots
right and then on that frame just just
on the frame the brain
executes and it uses everything that's
in there
right that's what happens
but the problem is since the world
system is designed to handle literally
arbitrarily large worlds so you could
put worlds
so vast into it that no one could ever
play them because they would just take
too long
it's designed to handle that what that
means
is that we never simulate the whole
world at once we only simulate a region
that you're trying to update at any
given particular time
because there would be no way to even
fit the entire world in memory
potentially if you really wanted to
scale it all the way out
it's designed to literally be able to
like page to disk if you wanted to
right so uh
this section here where we've got uh
this room with the door
well you know the player is going to
approach that you know and they're going
to be
in some other room right and maybe
they're coming through
here so maybe the player is here right
um that's not player player that says
played
okay so the player is here and they're
coming through the door
we're simulating a region around them
and so when we
do that gather maybe we do something
right
where we only gather part of
uh the system and really i probably
should draw it like this to show this
particular bug
so maybe let's pretend that actually
instead of the door
a being there maybe that's not the door
right maybe the door is actually down
here right so this is the actual door in
question
so instead of the dorbing up there the
door is here it's still all part of the
same brain though
uh just like before so when the player
comes in here
the problem that we might have and that
i think we were having
although we didn't really try to track
it down is that when we gather
up our simulation region so this here is
is the region we're going to simulate
we always run the run the risk of
gathering
an entity whose components
are on like some of whose components are
on the other side
because remember a brain is just a thing
that gets assembled per frame to do
activities
and so what would happen is if you only
gathered a
then b c and d aren't there and of
course brains don't exist in any
capacity other than temporarily for that
frame
as a result it means that the brain
itself
only sees a and then goes oh i'm just a
door that has
no dependent tiles so i guess i should
unlock because nothing is preventing me
from unlocking
right same thing would happen if say you
got just a little bit different and so d
and a were both there but b and c
weren't then
if d had been stepped on but b and c
hadn't technically the door shouldn't
open
but it would because it would look and
go oh i've got one plate the plate is d
is it down yes okay then i'll open right
so the problem that we have is this
partial gather
and we knew it was a problem before we
weren't thinking about doors
what we were thinking about is entities
like snakes so for example let's suppose
that in the exact same kind of scenario
we have maybe a situation where there's
a snake here right
so there's a snake where we've got like
a bunch of entities
and they're cut by that sim region well
what will happen is it'll move these two
somewhere but these will stay behind
right
so same exact problem just a different
way that it might manifest itself
door that opens when it shouldn't open
snake that moves its front half not its
back half
or vice versa right that is
that is what we mean when we're saying
uh that this partial gather creates this
this problem of brains not being
filled in right
okay so if you imagine that and just
keep that scenario in your head what we
did to try and fix that
is say oh okay instead of pulling things
in in this way we already know that we
kind of have
an exterior region around the actual
simulation region anyway
for things like lighting and whatever
because we need
light to be able to propagate like into
the region and stuff like that
and we need to be able to see where the
light sources are and furthermore
we may need to like uh do some stuff
where
we know for example that someone who's
trying to hop in this direction
will or won't be able to hop so we need
people to hop out of the simulation
region and then just kind of freeze out
there and stop being stimulated but they
have to be able to cross it otherwise
they'd all kind of
be like pinned in by this weird border
so it's possible to leave the region
because we know there's stuff in the
region and what we do is we basically
have that region be marked as
inactive and this region be marked as
active
so what happens is we actually know we
will never really get a situation
because snakes and doors and tiles
can never be so long that they stretch
across
the active and inactive regions right
nothing's ever going to go
all the way off uh from inside active to
inactive because we just set that size
to be the size of our largest entity
you know so what we did is we said oh
okay well if there are some entities
that are
active right in the brain
we will mark everything inside a brain
as active if any of them were active
right which makes sense because then
it's like oh if these were inactive and
these were active
we'll just say oh make all these active
so the brain is complete
problem is as far as i can tell we never
put in a check to say
don't run a brain unless the brain
itself had someone active in it
the brains are just running all the time
they're never looking to see whether
their entities were active or inactive
so what we did is we said well we
guaranteed that everything in a brain
would be active if anything was
but then we never checked to see whether
anything in the brain was active at all
which means that even if all of the
stuff
is outside the region so even if we were
going back to this case where
a is here and the tiles are like going
up off the region like that
if they're all inactive we still run the
brain
so we actually know that we shouldn't
run the brain we even looked and said oh
it's all inactive
but we never actually turned the brain
off
so i'm thinking the only bug we actually
have here
is that we're running brains on inactive
entities and if we were only running
them on active entities i think we
wouldn't have the bug
so my goal now is to just look and see
if that's the case
because if that's the case we really
don't have a bug
in our architecture we have a bug in the
sense that this is happening
but we wouldn't have a bug in our
architecture we just have to fix that
check and say don't run brains
that are inactive they don't have at
least one active entity because if they
have one active entity then the brain
itself is active
right because all of them will be marked
active
that may just work so that's what i'm
gonna go check
okay how did that go was everyone able
to follow that
right
okay
all right yeah the light board is even
more magic than you think it is you just
haven't seen some of its advanced
features
uh why have more than one brain so the
reason for that is because
uh so let's suppose you have like
multiple entities
that are separate right or multiple
creatures that are separate
but they're actually multi-entity so for
example
you have like two monsters each of which
has like
a is a snake and has lots of little
pieces
so the brain is the thing that
coordinates the motion of those pieces
you want
one brain per creature right
because they're thinking and moving
independently they're not related to
each other
so what we do is we create each one of
those
brains to handle each separate creature
so they run
as a unified creature that's that's all
we're talking about
and the bug is that we're allowing
brains to run even if they're only
if no thing in the uh brain is marked as
active
that means it could span outside of the
inactive region and there could be
entities missing
what we need to do is just make sure we
only run brains that have active
entities and then they can never be
partial because
no entity can be long enough to extend
from the active region
to outside the inactive region
i know it's a little confusing
um okay so what i'm going to propose
here is you see this mark brain actives
thing
so here's the thing that does execute
brain and
what i think we want to do is something
like this
right so each brain is either active or
inactive
and then what we would do is we'd say we
go down here and say if
the brain is active
then we mark it as such if the brain is
inactive
then we mark it as such
like that so i think that's what we want
to do
um you know don't quote me on that right
but i think that's what we want to do so
if we do that
then we will never execute a brain that
doesn't have all of its entities in it
pretty much
if i'm correct about that behavior and
so
in here we should then be able to
just add
that
so i think that might work um what we
need to do is
probably construct a good test case or
at least have some way of verifying
whether it works or not
i can go hop around right now and sort
of like inspect
whether if i can see the bug happen
then i know that didn't fix it but
that's not really particularly
conclusive
especially if i see if i don't see it
happen
because this is kind of a wonky bug uh
to have so
you know you don't really know if you've
actually
put it in a situation where it should
happen um
so we'll see so i think this one is
correct because there
are no there are no tiles so that one
should open
uh oh
that dude just stepped on all of the
tiles
okay so no stop okay
so that one is not down so that's good
that one's down but that's because the
dude these dudes open all of our doors
so that looks like we still have a
problem right because that
that was not down but the door was
so i think i'm gonna have to create some
way of like constructively testing this
so we can see what's going on
um if that makes sense although i
like i said it's pretty tough i don't
really necessarily know
if everything else is working properly
so it may have also nothing to do
with the thing that i was just talking
about which i do think we definitely
want um it's just a question of of uh
of whether or not this
we definitely need to solve that problem
it's just a question of whether or not
has anything to do with this particular
problem of doors being open that
shouldn't be open
right all right so first things first
let's remove these little hopping guys
because they're triggering these doors
for us which is not
good like we don't actually want
them to be doing that
so in the play snake call here i'm just
gonna
just i'm just gonna turn that off right
uh and then the other thing that i don't
understand is i'm not sure if dora from
a to b
always has place tile pattern occur in
it i'm not sure
i understand how we're seeing some of
the stuff that we're seeing so there's
there's another
sort of weird problem there that i'd
like to address
so we'll see so now there should be no
hoppers so we should be able to see
just raw what's going on like no one can
open doors for us now
they were like opening all the doors
which was not what we had wanted
so if we go in to here
the first question i have is how is this
door
like what is going on with that door so
what you can see here is there is a door
and it's down which is right because
there are no tiles in this room right
there are no tiles
the problem is i can't understand how we
placed a door
but no tiles so door from a to b
is kind of busted i guess because you
can see that the door
uh that door is clearly
these tiles here right
there the door went down quote-unquote
door the stand-in tree went down
but you can see here there is a door
that got placed but
no tiles and so i don't understand how
that's possible because
door from a to b right is set to true
in only that one place as far as i know
and yet
uh oh well
well maybe that's correct because
it goes from prevroom to room
so if we're back if we're back placing
it
then i guess the problem is this
actually needs to be that
in other words if it goes from pre-room
to room then draw from a to b
means that the tile pattern should be
placed actually
in the in the previous room not this
room
right okay so that was just a bug
in the request the room generator was
operating i think
uh exactly as as intended
it was just telling it to place the
tiles in the wrong room
there we go so there's a door i hop and
now it should be open
and it is um this one has a door that's
closed uh
which is good and
so now it's open and my goal here is
just to see
if i can find any evidence that doors
open on their own
right um so we don't know
yet
it looks so far so good and maybe that
other bug had something to do with it
maybe
no here you go so here's one that is
open but there is no
right there there was no tile hopping
that happened
right um
okay so that's very reliable as well
that one has been wrong
every time and so i
assume we can take a look at what's
happening
to that particular door um
i assume we can just step in and see
right uh so i'm guessing
that i should be able to just make a
like i should be able to just set a
break point where the door
actually gets um opened
and see why it triggered because i
should
i think be able to
um
i should be able to just look at least
to see whether or not
the whether or not that makes sense for
the door to have opened
so switch is set for example
um i should be able to like
uh
i should be able to to stop right here
right because that's what unlocks a door
so if i switch to a debug build here
i i think
i think i should be able to like stop
every time a door
gets unlocked um and we should
in theory trigger that should trigger at
some point
when i'm not doing anything meaning
we'll we'll hop along uh
on the tiles and we'll unlock the door
and that should trigger
and we should be able to watch that
happen but then at some point
if our theory is correct we
will be doing nothing like that we'll
just be hopping around in empty sp
like on an empty set of tiles just
moving around
and we should have that situation occur
uh sporadically right
um that's the theory
anyway uh and and i
you know the only other thing that could
happen is
we it never triggers which means that
somehow the door is getting
created in the unlocked state which
would be a totally different bug that
has
i guess nothing to do with what i'm
talking about and we were looking at the
wrong place
so we'll see but if i hop down here you
can see
me kind of just you know hopping along
and when we hit this third one right now
um i'm sorry fourth one rather uh we
should see this
unlock run and you know uh
it should only run once uh
and so that's what we expect
no issues so far uh everything
that all looks according to plan
so there that's wrong
this is what we kind of wanted to see so
we should not be unlocking a door here
but we are
uh and it looks like it did oops it
looks like it did happen
when it does look like it happened
precisely when the region changed which
seems to suggest that i'm right about
the fact that it's the brain
that's the problem so the first thing
i'm going to do though
is just take a look at the switches and
see if any of that's true
so you can see it does seem to be
exactly what i said
so it's the door is
somehow inbounds or getting gathered
right
uh but there are no tiles being gathered
for it if that makes sense
um now how this is in the active
region and the rest are not even in the
inactive
apron i don't know so i'm wondering if
the active inactive thing
is like not working properly or
something let's take a quick look to see
which flag is the entity active flag
because maybe that is just broken right
um
so active would be set
um to four
which is set so it does think it's
active
right um
[Music]
so somehow
that doesn't make any sense somehow it's
included
in the active region but the inactive
region
does not extend far enough
to encompass the other elements
that it depends on
and i don't know if that just means we
need it to be a slightly larger
apron
let's take a look
another possibility is that we just
don't handle
entity flag active correctly
at the moment right
um so that's just the brain code that
we're looking at before
so here we can see a setting and
clearing the flag
as to whether or not uh the entity
is is in the update bounds
right so that's good
that's all good so it looks good to me
so the only question is like what is
this
how are we defining the updatable bounds
so it may just be that those are not the
right size
um but what i what i might want to do
there is have a way of seeing those
bounds
better
[Music]
so that i can visualize this uh so so
like
actually let's do that first um i i will
look to see
what those are uh real quick
but
i mean correct me if i'm wrong but it
doesn't look like the updateable bounds
are even
any different
right so we may have just kind of
accidentally disabled that as we were
doing stuff
because it doesn't look it doesn't look
like we actually do anything there
so that's probably the issue
is that we're just not doing that
anymore um
so let's take a look and see if we can
draw that a little bit better
so
[Music]
oh no i'm sorry we have to pause for a
second i think i hear the puss
hello puss come on in it's okay
it's okay sorry i i closed the door
it's okay puss it's cool
it's cool you want to come up
you can come up come on up
the puss wanna the puss wanna come up
she was outside come i mean out not
outside in the world but outside
uh the room do you want to say hi to
everyone on the stream
do you want to say hi or do you just
want to cuddle what do you want to do
here you can come up you can come up
here there you go
okay okay that's a good plus
um so what we have
now is uh
fairly solid evidence that that the
reason that our our
uh solution wasn't working is because we
don't actually use an apron anymore
i don't know why um probably when we
were just like
doing the entity cache stuff
we just stopped playing with the
updatable bounds thing um
and forgot to like put that back in
so i don't know why we did that um
that's just what happened
and so we probably need to fix that by
making sure those bounds are larger um
and uh and we'll see what are you what
are you doing puss
what do you what are you what's wrong
what's going on
what's going on what's going on
what do you want to come up do you want
to come up just come up on the shoulder
you
you like being on the shoulder just go
up there yeah yeah there you go
go ahead um
so i think mostly uh all we really need
to do there
is is draw that first
and make sure that this appears to be a
reasonable explanation for the problem
first because i'm not sure if it really
is
um and then just enlarge that
and deal with any issues that come from
enlarging that
um i think that's all we really need to
do
um it's going to be a little bit hard to
visualize it because we need to draw
entities that are outside it which we
don't currently do
um
yeah let's do this first
before i do anything else um it's okay
puss
it's okay no no
no no just just stay calm you don't have
to type right now
uh casey's typing oh my gosh no
oh boy no no stop
puss no no
that's my finger okay
hold on a second
the puss may have done some stuff all
right i tried to close the editor and
not save any changes so that the puss
wouldn't uh add any code to the project
she
she likes to add code and she's not
really great at it
to be honest with you um
just just not not fabulous um
okay uh
okay puss calm down please you're moving
the microphone
puss okay
uh so i'm gonna switch back to
release build and just use the uh
debug camera to kind of pull out and see
what's going on
okay puss what are you doing you got to
make a decision here we got to do some
programming we're not done yet
what do you want to do what do you want
to do
why don't you just sit down why don't
you just sit you can sit on my lap while
i'm programming
why don't you do that what do you think
unfortunately you can't stay on my
shoulder because i don't actually have a
way to type
while you're on my shoulder because you
tend to slide off you know
and then i get scratched as you try to
like
hang on okay
uh so if we
[Music]
use the debug camera to zoom out here um
i just kind of want to see where this
line
occur like when this occurs
does it seem plausible uh
you can see this is the active region of
stuff
right um and
if we kind of it's a little bit hard to
see because the
upper area is all filled in here
um but
so in theory when i hop across here that
should have triggered the break point
and the question is does that make sense
that it did
um and if you look
at the actual setup for it
it's hard to say because i it to be
honest
it doesn't really look
like it should have um hold on a second
let me
really quickly just
because it doesn't look like the door
should have paged in quite yet
at that point right
looks like the door should have been
slightly up from there
you know what i'm saying
it was almost there so so maybe
i guess maybe i could believe that
somehow that was there and just not
being
drawn but it didn't look like it was
there it was right on the edge though
so i mean i could believe it
um but i don't know so let me take a
look
also that did brain break point did not
trigger
that time
which was weird
a little bit disquieting um
so yeah i'm curious to know what happens
if i change
those uh bounds so
where we actually do the um updatable
bounds um i'm just curious what happens
if this is actually an enlarged region
right uh and and
i guess the idea is the sim region
bounds are the whole bounds
and the updatable bounds are supposed to
be a subset of those bounds
right i mean i think that's what's
supposed to be happening here
so like
so like i assume that the add radius 2
part of things
you know that should get shrunk down
and maybe the bounds enlarge so it could
actually be that what we would want to
do is
more like this
you know
and then the question is just how big uh
that should actually be you know what
i'm saying
but like if we imagine just temporarily
uh that we added something here
i don't know what it would be exactly
but we added something
uh substantial right
i'm just curious if this will work or
not
uh
so if we did something like this where
we take the updatable bounds
and then we we basically pull in like a
larger subset
um
i'm wondering if that would work
i don't know what it means but i can't
convert all the argument types because
they're rectangles right so it should
just work
it's good to do it that way
i'm not sure why it says two overloads
like
that's a rectangle three and that's a oh
right forgot not using integers
there we go so i'm not sure what this
would look like
um presumably it would stay the same
visually
it might get a little slower because it
has to unpack more entities although it
doesn't appear to have actually made any
frame rate difference whatsoever
so that's good um
and then like in theory
this now has the inactive apron now we
don't actually know
um because we again have to probably put
in something so we can actually see it
a little bit better um but in theory
this appears to just be fine so we can
enlarge that region we're going to have
to figure out how much larger we want it
to be
um here we're coming up on the door that
was broken
uh there's one more
yeah and and so now it's not broken
anymore
so my theory again is just that that's
all that was happening
is the brain you know the brains were
causing a problem there
i don't really have an iron cloud proof
that that's the case
but it looks like just having that apron
is what
fixed it right so it was exactly what i
thought it was
as far as i can tell um
all right so the question is how big
that apron should be
and i'm not really sure um
it it probably wants to be like one
room's worth
you know uh but i don't know
yeah so i think that's probably fine
you know i also think like let's let's
do a couple things here so first of all
let's make that apron size be like one
rooms worth
um which i believe we sort of have
the concept of
probably in world mode
so it's called standard room dimension
you know um
so i feel like what we want to do here
is like have that apron
be applied in here so when you go begin
world change
it can add a room to all sides
you know just to make sure it catches
everything
on the other side of it uh and standard
room dimension
is initialized somewhere
yeah you can see it here it's basically
just our like arbitrary
calculation
so i'm not sure like how if we want to
just feed that
forward i guess um
[Music]
what we could do is say begin world
change
takes that like
both sets you know it could take like
the simbounds
uh and the like
apron bounds or something where
you get both of those things and it just
sets them
both here so the sim bounds go in here
and the apron bounds go in here right
and then people just have to like update
this
to call the right thing
and i think that might be good the
reason for that is that like
this code doesn't need larger bounds
the editor code just uses that bounds so
i think this one
would be the thing you know begin sim
would
would take
would take two different ones and that
way they could they could each do
what they want to do rather than having
um yeah you get the idea
so you do simbounds and apron bounds on
that
and then i think uh
we would be in good shape so
this has the simbounds here and it would
also
create
the add radius 2
and here we would say work world mode
um standard room dimension
right so that just means like unpack
a much larger area than you would have
for the apron bounds
and again my main concern here is just
like
putting too much stress on the unpack
um
putting too much stress on the unpack is
mainly the problem
you know uh and and i and i don't really
know
[Music]
um
i don't really know like how bad that
would be
you know maybe it's always fine
maybe it's not uh
yeah so i don't know um that's that's a
tough call
and for now i guess we'll kind of say
like okay
you know um
let's just throw this in there at the
moment
um
oops i gotta fix my four coder
i i keep saying i'm gonna but i never do
um it's it does weird
deletion things so
i think that's all we would need to do
for this
uh again i just don't know
i i don't know to what extent we want to
standardize on this or
or what like
if we look at where simbounds is
computed here you know that's
this is it um doing its its dependent
calculations and you can see here like
we could say okay the apron bounds is
the thing
we can also have this be a
like a standard number so instead we
could do like
a apron radius
like that um
and then we can set that
where is that getting set
it's weird it's sometimes it's kind of
hard using two different editors
is hard to say the least
so standard apron radius is just gonna
be this
uh and i don't know what it should be i
don't know if it should be two times
this
potentially like it may be that we want
that to be doubled
right um
and
that like i said i'm just worried it's
free from a simulation standpoint
because none of that stuff gets
simulated it's it's just sitting there
not doing anything
so we don't add any actual cost
in that sense
um but what we do
is uh where's the world mode
shouldn't there be a world mode
structure
here or is it mode world
there it is um
so my problem is just i don't actually
know
whether we
are going to put too much stress on the
unpacking and repacking of the entities
every frame by forcing it to go through
this incredibly large list of entities
right um so i don't know
it doesn't seem to have a particularly
deleterious effect on anything
um
and you can see that it's not nothing
but man it's not even one percent
so and and it's single threaded
at one percent so you know i mean
yeah i don't know i i i guess we don't
have to really think about that
particularly hard
so i believe at this point now
[Music]
we should be in good shape
that'll is standardized now
um
yeah i think i think that's it i think
we're good
seems seems reasonable
okay um
that doesn't apply anymore right
because the game state is not in here
anymore
so i think that's all good um
so i think that's that's all good
wasn't the to do they're actually
describing the bug uh which to do
i'm not sure which to do you in which
which function are you talking about
i can check it out uh anyway so i think
that's all good uh what i would
like potentially
um i'd like to do one other
thing maybe
um
[Music]
which is that when we generate the world
uh handmade world mode around 300 okay
well you know what uh here in handmade
world mode i'll just look at the to do's
so i don't think that's actually true um
i think we're okay with that
okay so i think we're all good
um so what i wanted to do in the world
uh when we do the tile stuff so in well
first of all
let me also go ahead and in world mode
let's uh take a look at that uh
place snake call because now we should
be able to re-enable our snakes
i'm sorry not uh in world gen
in place snake
wasn't there a place nick
there it is um
we can continue dropping the snake down
also why don't our snakes have multiple
snake pieces um
we do now unlike before
we do allow uh multi-piece
entities so in like this
place tile pattern call for example uh
the same we could do the same thing that
we did
like this for example
um so in here we could do
like basically this and
we could just say like a
segment counts
and
i guess the only thing that i don't know
is
how this would like so these things may
need the ability to say
which index they were and and honestly
that's
probably should have been in here
instead of in the counting code
so we should probably fix that
as well which i'll do so
in here when we add the snake entity
we just need to now have a thing that
adds
adds the the like
i don't know what you want to call it
the um
the hopping part right
so in here i think what we would
probably do is say
okay so you know
the there's snake head and snake body
and we should be able to get that to
work now so
this would go when you do play snake
i assume you would do this
uh like that
so you add a brain for the snake it gets
the brain id
in the the gen entity right so in here
there's like a brain
id equals right
and it places the entity and then it
goes on
to
and maybe i'd differentiate this by
saying this is the head
of the snake
so this is the thing that adds the
snakehead you know
i'll be completely honest with you um
it's kind of annoying that these things
don't work
more directly but you know whatever
uh anyway so in here you know this says
okay
you know uh add the particular brain id
so i believe
we get the gen entity here in in the
genetic callback right
um no
yeah so so this like kind of sucks like
this thing should
get you should pass it the generator
thing right because it needs that
and when you if you call this directly
you should still have to probably pass
it
the data you know from one of these
things
that would make the most sense i think
at least that's what i think so maybe
you would do something like this
maybe that like here's the specification
um there's all this garbage
right um and
there's like the spec
has that and it has
the brain id um
and the brain in index or whatever
right so that stuff all just goes in
here
and then when you create one of these
entities uh
you know maybe that just gets assigned
automatically even you probably don't
even have to do it in here
in fact i guess now that i think about
it why pass it in maybe that was just
dumb because it can just get assigned
so i guess i don't really even need to
do that i can just put it in here
and say there's like the brain index
and the brain id right and those would
just get
set on the outside thing
so so you would never have to do uh
that stuff
right so maybe these just don't
work that way these get set up in here
and then that doesn't have to happen
that seems plausible to me
um so that way
inside like place
snake
that would happen
right uh and in any of these other
things
like there's there's a monstar here
i don't know if anyone actually ever
calls it
i don't think anyone does let's
let's if zero these out for now and
report them later um
and so i think it's just that and and
the player
or the orphans i guess none of these
have brains at the moment
so that's fine and in fact you wouldn't
actually need this or that
because they will now happen
automatically
and nobody else is doing anything with
brains anyway and okay so that's all
great ir i would argue
um and so then when we actually call
these
uh so when we call the actual entitygen
code all we have to do is is just
actually do
that work where we so you can see
there's like a gen
entity p and a gen entity at traversable
here
right um
[Music]
i want to say that this gets in space so
i want to say that this code kind of
sucks
because we probably always want to call
gen entity at p right
because then we can do this
oh well i right like i feel like this is
kind of
putting the cart before like there
should be a unified way to call this so
that it takes the gen entity thing
and does the assignment of the stuff
that needs to get assigned
so
i don't know we'll see in a second so if
we go down here
to the stuff that uses the gen entity in
in the room gen
anyways we can at least do it there
which i think would be correct so you
can see here like
if you say if it's a switch do this
extra
[Music]
uh stuff right
um
but actually we shouldn't have to do
that
so what we should be able to do is move
this now
down here right when we do
the place tile thing
in here
we would set those up as part of the gen
entity
so we'd say this right
like that so now all of that happens
nicely in there and this part just grabs
these
out of the gen entity itself
that is probably how this should have
worked because now everybody can have
the brain assignment thing work the way
it should
we would then just make this place
entity
bit happen out here
and then i think we're good yeah
so now
the room switch brain
just gets pulled out and the only
problem that we have
is we don't know
how the like i mean i guess we just do
this
it's kind of janky um
but we don't need switch index anymore
and so door index is the only thing that
we actually need
and
and so really you know what we would
prefer is if these things were part of
the pending entities that got placed
you know i mean that would be
nice um so
maybe we need to put this into
this part of the code here you know
um
so that it can correctly get the the
right wiring
right because it probably should be
but that's the only thing that's a
little bit weird right
um
that that's the only thing that's a
little bit weird so
uh and if we didn't do that
it's it's still actually pretty simple
to make this work even that way
so um when we do place tile pattern
you know we could do it the other way
around so we could just do this
when you do play style pattern you pass
in the room switch brain
you know what i mean uh and then when
you call place tile pattern
you just say like oh yeah
um there's like a brain that goes in
that slot
and the brain just goes here and then
this goes away uh
[Music]
i guess that is still there but
tour from a to b door from b to a
this doesn't
all right now i think that's fine um
and so when we do this we would just use
the brain
in question on from this connection
right um
maybe i want to do it this way
just to make it a little bit simpler on
us
so we just have that uh
we just have that set up and i think it
would just work
my only question there is like why this
probably wants to be
just off of the world not the grid
because there is no grid and we don't
need there to be one
so it's probably just that um would be
my guess
yeah right uh is is the
generator not have that
in there there is one what was the
problem
oh room switchbrain
i gotta fix my four quarter this is just
so annoying
okay so
it just takes forever to do anything um
at the moment which is really annoying
all right so if we you know
take care of the rest of this stuff
[Music]
this is going to be slightly different
so in here there's going to be
add snake body and add snake head
like so this
is just going to be head
and this is just going to be body
like so and
um that should really be the end of that
when we place the actual snake down um
i assume the brain goes into slot zero
although i don't actually know
yes i assume it just goes into slot zero
because i'm not sure
why it wouldn't um
[Music]
and so it's just gonna add the snakehead
in there
the brain id is what the brain id is
and it's going to place the entity then
it's going to go through here
and just do like a segment count
and i assume we want you know at least
one
of these but for now we'll oops
for now we'll just do four that's fine
we'll do a segment index zero segment
assess and segment count segment plus
plus
there uh so we'll add
some number of segments and here
the only thing we would change is that
now when we
uh when we create these like
segments
it's going to be the segment index plus
one right so it's everything after
i don't think we need to do anything
here
uh this
looks fine
i i think the append entity stuff sucked
if i remember correctly um
[Music]
you're always passing the previous one
so i kind of feel like we probably want
that to
not suck the way that it's sucking at
the moment
so we may want to fix that uh
as well like this is just a pain and
is not good right so
easiest way to do that i think would be
to change append entity slightly
um so i'm going to hack it for now and
then i want to replace this
so
i think that's what we're talking about
right
i also don't know if that makes any
difference either
okay so we need to look at that because
that's not great
um
but most of this stuff is kind of jank
anyway so maybe that's the next thing we
do maybe next weekend we'll start
improving our placement code
so now uh yeah we gotta have the
connection has to have that
gen connection has to have that um
room switch brain looks like room
connection
we accidentally added it to room
which was not correct it's actually gen
connection that's supposed to have it
um like this
the thing about that is it's probably
the wrong
one though um
[Music]
so because you need actually both
directions
would would potentially have a different
one so i may have been right
like it may be that that's what you
actually want
you know what i mean um
and then you need to just pull out the
correct one
because it's you can't use the same one
for both you could
put it in here you know if you wanted to
um
and really that would make more sense
but like if you look at what happens in
connect it doesn't
return those to you you you know they're
both they're here
and and maybe answers yes so if you
think about how this would work right
it would go in here uh and you would say
look there's a door
and this is the brain for that door
like that
so if there's a door brain id you're
supposed to use it right and the problem
is these add room connections
we don't get those back so when we call
connect
we don't actually get back what those
room connections
actually are and we would need them
you know what i mean and it'd be really
easy for us to do that
we would just need connect to actually
return like a structured thing
that you get back right
and you know and or
gen connection just tells you what your
room connections are
is the other option i suppose um
but it seems to me like you probably
don't need that i don't know
i mean maybe you do maybe you just do
this
right uh and then when you do that
uh connect call it's it's literally just
like that
right that's the connection from a to b
that's the connection from b to a
and you just do that you know
and then things get a lot simpler if i'm
right
because then you just do this
uh and that should work right
uh
what did we call that doorbrain id
so you just say from a to b there's a
door brain now because we actually have
that connection and then in here
you don't actually do this at all
right um
instead you just say well
it's just is
the room con doorbrain id
there right and now we know
that it's going this direction because
we're looking at our rooms connections
so that's actually like way nicer
and it's way clearer what's happening
there
so that seems good um
do we not have an is valid on brains
so helpful
um
so whatever like
here's is valid and here's the
the brain id
i mean i guess it's just that
all right so that's a tremendous number
of changes and so i probably broke
everything
um but now we can start to actually
like go through this and and fuss around
with it right
uh and try to get that working so let me
first of all go to debug mode and we can
uh
start to pull apart what i just did
and we'll go from there all right so
[Music]
i'm not sure why i did not
for some reason it's not showing me
where we are actually
getting suspended
oh it just looks like looks like a call
to zero um
where did my call stack go
it went away um so it looks like we're
just
we're dispatching into a null handler
right um
it appears to be what's happening so a
callback
into something that did not get
initialized right
uh we should probably make it easier to
trap those
because like
once you jump into xero it's hard to
unwind the stack
sometimes uh if you don't have special
code in the debugger to do it
which i think remedy doesn't
so what we should probably do is guard
around the creator call
you know what i mean so when we actually
call uh let me actually see if i can
search this yeah okay
i wish yeah uh
boy so
i wish i had my editor right now but
we'll do what we can so in here we
uh we're almost certainly like
dispatching
like in here we're probably doing
something where we're not
uh specifying what the thing should be
or something like that so we're doing
it oh yeah right there i mean that's
what it is right
um and so you know the only thing i'm
saying is maybe we should have a thing
that asserts so that before we jump in
we can see
like what it was or something like that
um and so what i was thinking is like
inside room gen before it actually calls
uh the dispatch code when we're actually
looping through the
pending entities or something like that
when you call gen entity at traversal
that kind of thing
uh maybe we can put in a cert in here
that says
that the pending entities like creator
call
is not zero and again
the only reason for that is just to make
it oops
uh easier to debug right
so now if i run it i'm hoping that you
just write and so you can see
it's just a way to like help the person
who maybe like stumbles across that
later not knowing what you were doing
right then it was really easy for us to
debug
right then because it happens to be what
we were fussing around with but like you
can imagine if that just happened
out of the blue why that would be bad
because it would mean
uh that you would literally have no idea
who jumped in there and you'd have to
start doing a branch and
bound like debugging process to find out
who jumped
to zero and why right so it's just a
like
to help make that less painful
um for people who are you know doing
this
in the future right uh is all we're
talking about
so uh let's see where we're at okay so
we're running the placement code just
fine now
uh so you know we're good here
where are we at time we're we're about
15 minutes till the end of the stream i
want to say
i don't know if that's right uh but so
let's just take a quick look here and
see if that
um if that fussing
defest us and
and we'll see
okay
all right so i think that's all good
um
uh i gotta unlock this door real quick
uh so it looks like the body this
snake thing doesn't seem to have the
correct body like it looks like
everything worked
fine though like it placed the snake and
the snake is hopping around
uh so it's just an asset like we have to
label those assets properly
um looks like uh but otherwise we're
[Music]
good
that looks broken so somehow that let
someone hop
on there oh yeah okay cool
i see why that would be um so we want to
fix that bug
that's a definite bug and an interesting
bug
yeah oh that's very interesting okay
um so anyway uh all that seems fine
but uh other things we gotta fix uh and
so let's fix the asset problem first
because i don't really even know
um what even is getting set here so
i i need to really quickly just see even
what is the
body stuff for that snake
and i i don't i don't even know uh
because we haven't really looked at that
stuff
hardly ever um so if we look at
at the skeleton stuff
uh what is that even
i don't even know um
so it'd be character skeleton
um is what that actually
is and in terms of those pieces
like the snake body piece is just going
to be
whatever the other thing was so
when we place the snake it's gonna be
body and head
for oh so i think it all it was is that
we didn't ever
set these up right um
so it may just be that
setting those tags right
so i think that's all good uh we're
gonna have to add some stuff to quickly
teleport us to places in a dungeon
because pretty soon this is gonna get
really old
um we can use hot code reloading
which we have right to fix basic things
but
world generation you can't reload
because the world
was already generated right so reloading
that code doesn't help
so we're going to need ways to like
inspect the world more quickly
in the future all right so that appears
to be working
there's like little skeletons in there
now
right um
and the only question i have there is
they don't seem to be setting their
direction
which seems wrong um
which i don't actually know are they do
they even have
i think they do so i feel like they
should be setting their direction and
aren't that's the only thing
that i can immediately see
being weird and so let me just fix that
as well since we haven't looked at this
stuff in forever
so here's the snake code and i might
just pull that out real quick
just so it's easier to see
uh and i don't even know
like it doesn't need half of this stuff
probably
but
okay uh so there's our snake
code and so what does this thing even do
um
looks like it needs the entropy
how does the sim region not have entropy
why why would that
be the case
that's pretty weird because you would
think that all game
entropy would just come from the sim
region
that's pretty strange but okay for now
uh i'm i'm not upset about the fact that
that comes in off a separate pipe
but it's a little weird
all right so this thing does this little
hoppable nonsense
um
[Music]
and yeah it just doesn't it just never
does that
so yeah um so we need to set the facing
direction
of these guys and it looks like the way
that works
is like you would look at the delta
between these two
so yeah this could be done probably way
more efficiently
like blowing an atan ii per seems kind
of stupid
for that you know honestly
um
so that doesn't seem like it's necessary
but you know
so i don't think we want to be doing
that long term
because it's just dumb uh but it's fine
for the moment because there are so few
of them
so we really just need a segment delta
and
uh in this case the segment delta
uh is just going to be
like this this person's location
and the other person's location right
so we we already sort of have this
uh traversable reference thing
and there was the thing that like
tells us where it is
you can see it here right so when you do
get sim space traversible
um i
think that's all we would need
to do so if we did
this
we would just say okay there's the sim
region
in both cases and
all we're doing here is saying whatever
the like occupying and came from
things are that's how we would do the
delta
right so the delta's just
wherever we
wherever the last occupying thing is
yeah you can see this right so
we're just gonna say like okay we're
going
to the last occupying and we're coming
from the one we're on now
and i think that's all we would actually
need
keep doing that
i think that's all we would need um
and once again i've stupidly made it so
i have to hop all the way down there
okay so now they correctly like orient
themselves
in the direction that they should right
um
which is good they're they're a little
bit scaled
down but that's fine i mean they're not
really supposed to be used for this
they're not actually snake segments i
just
used a random skeleton thing for them
um so that's fine
okay um so i guess that's good for now
uh we have to fix some bugs and we have
some to do so there's some stuff we want
to do there and
uh we'll deal with it tomorrow or maybe
not tomorrow uh next weekend but i think
that's all good
and it's good to have the snakes back in
now as well
um all right so we'll do a brief q a
because i think we're right on time
um
ah