hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here the show recode a complete game
live on stream right here on Twitch we
actually use no libraries
no engines no n berries and nolé engines
so we're completely engine library free
and all combinations thereof here on
handmade hero and right now we are in
the middle of writing our own asset
processing system why shouldn't a asset
prostitution asset loading system we've
done a bunch of the work over the past
week and we just have a few more things
to finish up before we can actually call
our asset file system a replacement for
loading regular files off the disk
randomly which is what we were doing
before I'd like to get right to it
there's really not much to discuss we
all know what we're doing if you've been
here for the past couple days you know
what we are doing here on day 150 if you
would like to follow along at home with
and you are one of the fellows who has
pre-ordered the source code on handmade
hero org wait a minute why does that say
twitter.com handmade hero that's some
kind of that's some kind of link foo
right there there we go handmade hero
org if you've heard the game on handmade
erode org what you want to do is unzip
day 149 source code that's the source
code I've starting with right now and
that will allow you to follow along with
me at home if that is the sort of thing
that you are into all right so we
already got a test file writ written out
that has all of our assets packed into
it so really all we have to do right now
is actually start using it and in order
to start using it as you can see if we
actually run the game right now we've
essentially got no assets loaded because
we commented out the sort of debug code
we had written to fill our asset table
at runtime so all of the stuff that we
had working with the little hero in here
and the trees and the grass lawn stuff
is not working because it can't get any
assets it doesn't crash which is nice
because our system is pretty swanky that
way but it would be nice if we could get
some of our bitmaps back and of course
the music is not playing either because
that was also one of the assets so what
we want to do now is we want to again
take
more steps toward getting everything
loading off of the asset file we did
yesterday we got the tag array going and
so I'm gonna go ahead and finish up the
other arrays here and we've got two
different other arrays that we have to
actually handle one is the assets right
themselves so let's go ahead and spin
through the assets like so assets asset
count asset index and we're gonna be the
exact same thing here as we did in the
tag array we're gonna pull out two
different things we're gonna pull out
the source which is from the HHA assets
array right and we know again where
those are because all we have to do to
get something in the file if we want to
figure out where the assets array is all
we have to do is start at the beginning
of the file which we've loaded into
memory so we know it's at this address
in memory and jump ahead however far
that the header tells us that particular
array where that particular rail is it's
gonna give us the byte offset into it
right so we can do that I guess we might
as well while we're here also do the
asset type so let's do asset type so and
just get all of these things sort of
prepped and ready so that's gonna be
asset types right so then when we spin
through here
I guess I should leave this to come up
for a second so then when we spin
through here we're gonna have the the
source and the desk right assets assets
so we're gonna be reading from the asset
definition here and then we're going to
be doing something at the destination
with the destination here right let's go
ahead and compile that make sure I
didn't make any mistakes there oops
tag index is no good I think I might
just change that to index let's go ahead
and do it this way so I don't have to
keep changing that there we go
and then we can also we'll also want to
do the same thing when we loop through
the asset type array so we're gonna go
through here and go index equals zero
index less than this time we actually
want to use the header right we want to
use the in fact I don't know to tell you
the truth we may really want to always
use the header
you may want to do header tag count here
header asset count because we may later
start concatenate these things together
so maybe it's a little bit cleaner just
mentally speaking even though we're not
gonna actually deal with this at all at
the moment something you know to think
about so in here right we've got our our
stuff loading now and we just have to
actually do something with it so we've
got our HHA asset type source here as
well there we go and then the desk in
this case is going to be a little bit
different so we're gonna have to play
with that but now that we've got all
that compiling we have our loops that
are spinning through the data that we
actually have so if we want to actually
process these guys right here what we're
gonna have to do is look and see what
what do we actually have for an hhhh a
asset right and you can kind of see the
structure here we've got what the tags
are and those are going to translate
directly right and in fact what I could
do here is also have the asset struct up
so we could take a look at what the one
that we want in memory is right so
there's that so if I want to copy these
right I'm gonna want to first set the
first tag index and I'm gonna want to
set the one pass last tag index like so
right I want to handle those by just
copying them directly from the source
because it's the same data either way
right so I'm gonna go ahead and copy
both of those but then I need to you
know do two different things depending
on whether I've got a sound or I've got
a bitmap right so what I want to do is
take a look at the source and see what
type it is remember we store in here for
each asset in the file we store which
type it was so the type ID is going to
tell us I don't actually remember where
that code is wait that's the asset I
pray that's not what I'm talking about
oh so we don't actually know this is
interesting we didn't actually store
this in the file we only cuz we didn't
actually we don't actually need it when
we actually go to load something so
that's kind of a little bit tricky there
right that's interesting
so maybe I won't actually do what I just
said maybe that's maybe we don't want to
actually
have to actually switch on that because
we don't really need to do that so maybe
what I want to do is just go ahead and
actually take that data directly so if I
look in here I've got my asset and I've
got the bitmap info and the sound info
right
but those bitmap info and sound info
were these old things that we didn't
actually that aren't actually
representative of what we're actually
gonna store for the the stuff now so I
wonder if it's better for our asset to
literally just be one of those HHA
assets like could we do that could we
just have our assets actually just be
the HHA assets directly and I don't
actually know if we can or can't another
way to look at it would be if I want to
take a slightly more baby step I could
do it this way right what would that be
like if I did it this way so let's let's
let's find out what happens if I
recompile that right so if I take a look
here when we do asset sound info when
we're retrieving the sound info right
that would no longer retrieve the actual
sound info that would retrieve retrieve
instead where is that the HHA sound
right get we return this stuff and the
hhhh a bitmap would be would be that now
we could still if I wanted to actually
instead of returning I could actually
build that on the fly but I don't think
I'm going to so let's just see I'm just
gonna see what happens if I actually do
it this way so if I did HHA sound well I
guess that would actually just work
I believe don't really have to do
anything just change which struct it's
returning really so that's pretty easy
and the assets
what is it dot sound assets ID value is
that not why would that not I thought
that's what exactly that that's exactly
what that would be oh right because it's
HHA dot sound yeah so there we go and
then we've got the bitmap same thing
would be happening here right this would
actually be HHA bitmap
it comes back let's see file name that's
true
file name is not going to be that
because we're not actually going to be
calling this anymore
so we will have
I have to actually deal with this this
is essentially not inflected to do
actually do loading here
so what else we got assets sound info
this is again HHA sound like so and
that's going to come out of the HHA
information again to do kc actually do
loading here what else we got
see first tag index so these is just
it's just going to be that right it's
just going to use those directly same
thing here using them directly it's the
thing that came out of the file what is
this first tag index is not a member of
asset oh this is the copy so this this
is not actually this is just the copy so
all we have to do for the copy is just
block copy the whole thing over right
like so alright so then we got asset
sound info that's actually gonna be a JJ
sound now and still should have most of
the stuff that it that it would normally
have prefetch John Craig vary from u3 to
- sound ID that's actually ok because
that is a sound ID right so I can do
something like this next idea to play
although I also could just start I
should probably just actually use sound
ID and bitmap ID in the actual file
there's really no reason not to do it
that way
so inside file formats we could say that
the the bitmap id sound ID stuff there's
no reason I couldn't actually do that in
handmade file formats right because
they're fully specified right so that
seems pretty safe if I wanted to do it
that way that seems like a pretty
reasonable thing to do so I could just
say that sound ID and and off we go
right so then these guys go away yeah
and these just have to actually be done
like this right binary equals
next to the play dot value I guess I
don't even need to use the dot values
anymore on those guys there we go
one thing I do want to know about though
is I'm not sure so I feel like we do
have one other thing which is the whip
over height thing but well we'll take a
look at that in a little bit all right
so back to the story back to our story
as it goes
so as we're loading these things all we
would be doing is putting those those
sources over just copying the the asset
information directly into the thing that
we were going to use there right and
what we're gonna have to do temporarily
in order to make all this work
yeah although we don't want to do this
in the end we won't actually be using
this but what we do want to do too is
have a little u8 star here which is like
hhj contents right we want to store that
because we're gonna need to pull stuff
out of it in the future after the
initialization phase right
so we're gonna actually need to remember
that base of the file and that base of
the file is gonna tell us right where we
can grab the assets out from so we go
through here and we're you know we're
copying everything on I think everything
set we just need to now deal with the
asset type array and remember that asset
type array is a little bit different
than the other arrays in that it just
actually stores sort of a table that
tells us what type of asset we're
dealing with and then where the range
actually was right so what we're gonna
have to do here is our destination right
our asset type so our destination is
actually going to come from a lookup
that it works with the source the
sources type ID right we're gonna say go
to the asset type array and grab out the
entry that is for whatever the one that
this this thing that we're reading out
whatever one it corresponds to right and
so one thing that we would be doing here
generally speaking because we might be
loading a data file that has asset types
we don't know about yet if we're loading
data file from the future I don't think
that's particularly relevant necessarily
but what we want to do is say if it's
less than the asset count that we know
about right that's gonna be a pretty
important thing right
we should probably merge these into the
file format right probably wouldn't you
say that seems like a pretty reasonable
thing to do I don't know though we can
do that later I suppose but anyway you
know we've got that asset count we're
just gonna say we want to make sure
whatever the type is it's less than the
actual asset count that we understand so
that we're not trying to access some
array that we don't know about right and
so then for now I'm gonna put to do you
know support merging eventually we want
to support merging us like that for
right now we're only writing out one
file so we don't really have to worry
about that for our testing so what we're
gonna do here is just go ahead and oops
what was that create that file what
we're gonna do here is just grab
overwrite whatever the asset type stuff
was originally the first you know first
asset index and one-pass lacet last item
asset index we're just gonna go ahead
and overwrite whatever was in there and
we're just going to assume that there
wasn't anything right and we could
assert that that was true right we could
say assert first asset index equals zero
and one pass last asset index equals
zero so that there's like nothing in
that array or whatever so that would
allow us to load everything right and
presumably we'll step through that and
see if it worked
but what's gonna happen then is all of
our slots are still initialized to not
actually have anything in them so once
we actually go to load something right
when we actually do a load grab here I'm
gonna take these guys out right and
recompile oh right but I commented them
out so that's not good anything so once
we come in here right you can see that
we're doing this debug load bitmap work
right what we want to do now is be able
to produce the same results as debug
load bitmap but without actually ever
using the bitmap file just using our
asset file right this is where we used
to load the bitmap file
straight away and do all the work on it
we don't want to do that anymore so we
have work bitmap and that is a loaded
bitmap right that's a that's a loaded
bitmap struck right so that's the bitmap
and what we want to do is we now want to
go ahead and reproduce whatever that
actually had on it to do all the loading
right so how do we do the loading in
this case well we don't except to load
the data because we're sort of cheating
right we already know that we've got all
of the data loaded because we you know
sort of did that for testing purposes we
just loaded the whole asset file in
which is not something we want to do
eventually but that's what we did for
testing purposes so all we really have
to do is go find out what's in loaded
bitmap and how do we reconstruct that
from the data that's in our asset pack
file right so here's the stuff that we
actually need right so we got to fill
out all of these right we got to fill
out every last one of these in order for
our stuff to work properly because the
code is relying on all of these being
valid so how do we figure out all of
these things from what we actually have
in the bitmap file right so let's go
ahead and do that if I come over to
handmade asset we we know that the we've
in theory got the the pit map info
itself here right so what I should be
able to do is just use that that HHA
bitmap structure to figure out all the
things that I need and assuming that we
actually saved everything that we need
that should be pretty easy so here's the
HHA bitmap
if I want to figure out the align
percentage that's pretty easy because
it's right there right it's just it's
literally just stored in the file for us
because we knew that we were gonna need
that so we you know we've got it right
so there it is so that's pretty trivial
how about the width well the width is
right there it's the dimension the
zeroth dimension right oh good thing
we've got the height same thing and we
already said that our convention for the
pitch is it's always going to be the
same right the pitch is always going to
be exactly whatever the pixel size is
times that that first dimension right so
that's already specified then we've got
the align percentage oops I put that in
the wrong place then we've got the width
over height and we know that as well
right because we we know what the
bitmaps width
is it's that and we know what the
bitmaps height is it's this right but
those are integers so I want a
floating-point divide here so I'm just
gonna Lock them up to floats to get that
nice floating point actual specification
flipped over height and then finally for
the memory where's the bitmap coming
from well the bitmaps in that file right
and if you remember we've got this data
offset thing here in the asset itself so
what we need to do is we're gonna need
to pull the asset here right so we got
to be able to do this where we have the
HHA asset or whatever so we're going to
actually need to grab that out as well
from this thing right so we've got the
asset there and then we've got the hhas
at bitmaps a week we've got both of
those things
so the HHA asset has in it the data
offset which says where the bitmap data
was which means that if we were to add
that data offset to our base pointer
which we know where that is right it's
the game it's the the work assets right
it's the it's that thing right there we
stored in at the HHA contents right so
that's the base pointer for the file
that we loaded into memory so we know
that the bitmap is just going to be at
the offset that we said it was so that's
all we need to do to really say okay
there we've quote/unquote loaded it we
don't have to load we don't that you do
the work of loading it because we loaded
the whole thing in before so really all
we're doing is just pointing into the
data that already existed right and
that's pretty much it that's really all
we need to do so once we've got that
then all we have to do is fix the oops
all we have to do is fix the sound
loading to do exactly the same thing
right so let's go ahead and do that
here's the how the sound was loaded and
I don't remember what this loads I have
no idea
looks like loaded sound right so what we
need to do is we need to patch all these
things up in exactly the same way that
we patched up the other stuff right so
now what we want to do is say ok we've
got the sound like so and we need to set
all of this stuff up right so we start
by saying we've got the sound sample
count that's going to be equal to that I
believe we just stored that directly yep
yeah like so that's info sample count
we've got the
the channel count which is also the
exact same thing right and then we want
to probably assert that the sound that
the channel count that we have here is
going to be less than the the array that
we have to put stuff in and then we're
just gonna go ahead and copy out that
data I'm not copping out today I'm sorry
just point to that data so we've got the
channels right for each channel that
this thing has we will set the pointer
to the sound samples equal to whatever
the data offset is in the file and how
do we figure out what that is right well
we start by saying that we know the data
offset for the samples right sample data
offset is going to be whatever the asset
thing said it was right so we've got to
do the same thing that we did up there
which is we still have to remember what
the HHA asset was because that's what's
got it in there and maybe that was dumb
maybe we should have lowered that data
offset down one I don't know but yeah it
doesn't it's not really gonna matter in
any way the point being we've got this
and we've got that right just like we
had before so now we know that we start
wherever it said the data offset was
right and this is gonna be equal to that
same thing we did before we're gonna
take the pointer to the base of the file
I guess you know what why did I cast
that before because we had already set
it up to be the correct thing okay I
didn't cast it good so we're all good
nevermind I take it back
right so what we're gonna do here is
we're just going to start at the base of
the file we're gonna go however far we
think the samples are right
starting at the the correct sample as
indicated by the file for this sound
asset and then we're going to do is
we're gonna move forward by however much
there should have been in this sound
channel right so we know what the sample
count is right we know that the sound
sample count is specified and we also
know how big each sound sample is it's
that big so that's how far we would go
and with that we'll just work to get the
channels cascade
one after the other right so all we
really need to do now is just say all
right that works sound the thing that
we're trying to fill out right loaded
sound all we need to do is now actually
sort of write into that instead of using
the the debug load like we used to and
that should really be just about it I
don't think there's anything else that
we would need to do got to change that
to an in sixteen there and so that's
that's everything now we've probably
made some mistakes when we did that so
we're gonna have some debugging to do
but basically what we've done now is
write all the stuff that we need to do
for testing out that asset file right
and running off of it instead of the
bitmaps and so on or it might just work
the first time that also happens
sometimes in game development and you
never know so yeah our game is back and
that's good to know everything appears
to be there
sounds are playing the sound is
streaming properly the music still
playing so everything appears to have
worked just fine who knows why just the
way it goes sometimes all right well you
win some you lose some and we won some
today so that's always good makes up for
those times when everything goes wrong I
suppose so what do we need to do now
well what we need to do now is remember
the fact that we're loading the entire
asset file at startup which is not at
all
what we would like to do right what we
would rather do because we'd like to
stream our assets and we already wrote
all the code for streaming assets like
we've already got it threaded and
everything all this stuff is set up for
it so what we would like to do is only
load the parts of the asset file that we
need at any given time instead of
loading the whole thing right and that's
gonna involve some work with our
platform layer because at the moment the
only thing we put in the platform layer
was just the ability to load entire
files at once right and we'd like to
stop doing that okay so first things
first let's just briefly run over this
code slightly and see if we want to just
flat load some of it right I was talking
about the flat loading before
and so what I was thinking is I guess we
might as well not over complicate things
since we have asset tag here right what
I'm thinking is maybe we just make it so
that the asset tag is just used directly
the same as it is on disk because I
don't anticipate there being a lot more
stuff happening with asset tags in terms
of annotation that happens at load time
so I'm thinking that maybe we delete
asset tag and we just use HH a tag in
here right so we go ahead and do that
and then everyone who was using asset
tag uses HH a tag instead right if that
makes sense now we could actually I
suppose do that in two different ways
one is we could leave the name asset tag
if we'd rather have that be a thing or
we can switch it to HH a tag I don't
have a personal opinion on that I think
I'm gonna use this notation so that we
can see which things are in files and
which things aren't I think that might
be what I'm gonna try here and if we
don't like that we can always change it
but that's my gut inclination at this
moment in time right so that's what
we're gonna go with so there we go
that I just changed the name there so
now we're just using the asset tag
struck from the file and there it is so
that's all good and now what I'd like to
do is now that we're just pointing to an
array of asset tags what we can do is
once we load it when we do this thing
here what we can do is instead of
allocating space for it we can literally
just use the stuff we loaded out of the
file right so so this would be that and
we'd never have to loop over this at all
ok and so I'm gonna go ahead and delete
that and I believe the to do that says
decide what to do about flat loading
because that's exactly what we're doing
right now so now I run and as you can
see we no longer process the tag array
at all right we no longer a loop over
the tag array but everything still works
because the data on disk is exactly the
data that we want so we can just point
straight into it after we load it and be
done question - can we do that with our
HHA assets well if we take a look at the
way we've done it we've split up our
assets into the asset in the asset slot
and so there's really no reason why we
couldn't do that we could just decide to
go ahead and vaporize asset and then it
becomes HHA asset like so right so let's
go ahead and try
as well can't think of a lot of reason
not to do it so let's go ahead and do it
that way
that would look like this these are now
long no longer have to sort of access
that thing right again do the same thing
HHA asset now and those and we no longer
need to allocate this this will just
point directly into the asset array like
so and again that would get rid of this
entire loop and that's all very nice and
now let's see how we're doing oh good
right and so basically what we've done
there again is just remove two
completely unnecessary things from our
code which was the translation of the
file data in when we really didn't need
to do it right so now what we do is
we're just doing one load to load in all
that stuff and we just point directly
into the buffer after we've loaded it in
right so that seems all all fancy and
good all right so now that we've done
that there's a question of what about
this one
and the answer with that is remember
that one is not something we can flat
load because it's actually going to be
variable right it's going to be
something that we have to sort of
process because it's stored in a
different way it's set up to allow us to
say which things it's adding to so it
doesn't just flat load in there and it's
worth noting that these won't quite do
exactly this flat load in the future
potentially we may allocate a bigger
array of assets than we actually have
because we might have multiple files to
load right so we'll maybe take a look at
that in the future a little bit as well
right so there we go now we're flat
loading those so let's go ahead and push
forward on not just loading the entire
file at once right because right now
what we do is we load that entire file
at once and that's not really what we
want to do what we want to do is
something you know a little more
little more piecemeal we want to be able
to say look this is a giant asset file
it has everything in it I just want you
to load a piece of it any given time and
I'm going to process just that piece
right so now we need a more this is the
part where we define our more realistic
file API the one that we're actually
going to be shipping on so we need to
start actually thinking about it and if
you remember correctly I kind of put
this off when we were doing things we
were building the classroom layer for
precisely the reason that again always
right the usage code first and I knew we
were just nowhere near being ready to
write the usage code so I didn't want to
do anything like that but now we've
arrived at a place where we can write
the thing that actually uses the file
API that we want for our asset loading
and so now is the time to start to think
about exactly what this API should look
like so what am I gonna do right what am
I gonna do now anyone out there who
didn't say write the usage code first
I'd better be a first-time handmaid here
a viewer because you always write the
usage code first that is how you start
at a good place with any API design you
always always always write the usage
code first and I can pretty much tell
you from experience that almost everyone
who designs API is inside their own code
or else we're never follows this advice
and that is why all api's are awful so
right the usage code first what do we
want to do here well let's imagine we're
actually doing the thing that we do want
in the final shipping game right so we
have multiple asset files why do we have
multiple asset files a we're trying to
fit under the fat32 limit so we had we
had to break our giant 16 gigabyte asset
set into multiple chunks thing one two
maybe we had to patch something so we've
got a big asset file and a little tiny
asset file that patches some of the
assets in it or something three we
shipped a DLC that may or may not be
there right so the person may or may not
have ever downloaded the update to the
game and that would just be an
additional file that would come in stuff
like this right so we might have
multiple asset files and what we want to
do is load and merge them right so
what's that going to look like well
we're gonna
something right like a list of files to
load from the operating system right and
in fact I guess we could even do that we
could even sort of speck out what that
API should look like as well we could do
something like you know let's say
platform directory or a platform file
entry or something like this file
entries you know or platform file group
let's say I'm just going to say we get
back a file group we say platform you
know I would like you to get all files
of type right and I pass HHA or
something like this so it's like I want
you to give me all the HHA files that
there are right just give them to me and
again we're not going to be more
explicit than that because this game
doesn't go searching through directories
or anything like that there's just
there's the directory where the game
data lives we're assuming that the
platform layer understands where that is
because it's where the excute Abul was
or it you know it knows because on that
particular platform everything goes in
one particular place or whatever like on
a console for the DVD or what you know
who knows but basically what you do is I
want you to gather all of these files of
type and maybe they're even in different
places maybe the you know like you're on
a console and it knows it gets some from
the hard drive and some from the DVD or
whatever all that stuff we don't want to
care about that in the game because
that's platform specific right what we
do want to say is get us all of those
data files right and we could even have
specifiers for what these are but for
right now we'll just use that string
we'll say we'll pass look like what the
extension would be let's say right so
then what we want to do is we want to go
through all of the files in the group
right we want to say for each one of the
files in the group so we want to do like
platform file you know or probably just
something like index right equals 0
index is less than file group file count
you know something like this plus plus
index and then what we would do is when
we
when we get here we're just gonna say
that we can open any one of these files
that we want so actually you know what
we've got another thing that we want to
do here and again you can see what I'm
doing right I'm thinking through how I
want to use this API and I'm writing the
code that would be the best case for me
as the user of the API first and that's
always where you start so I'm gonna go
here and say that we have an asset file
right and an asset file is going to have
to have some kind of handle that
associates you know that that kind of
tells me right if you will what that
which which asset file I'm talking about
right or something like this something
like this okay and that actually reminds
me that is gonna be kind of interesting
I'm interested to know now that think
about it how we're actually gonna do
some of the loading thing I'm thinking
about an interesting problem that we're
gonna have in the future and I'm not
sure exactly how we would solve it it's
gonna be it's gonna be to see we get
there anyway so I have an asset file and
there's gonna be something like a
platform file handle right there's gonna
be something there that I would use to
reference this file right then I would
say I want to load something out of this
this file whatever right and then in
here I would have at the very top I
would say I've got something like an
asset file count right or a file count
and then I've got an asset file files
right and however many files I opened
there's gonna be an entry in this asset
file and it's gonna have an open handle
to every single one of them right so I
guess really the first thing I would do
is once we get all the files of that
type right I would then fill out this
part of the assets structure right I
would say this is how many files we have
this is the files themselves right and
it's gonna be a push array Reena
file count right and asset file right so
we go ahead and push those on we then go
through every single one of them right
one at a time and we're gonna open them
right we're just gonna open them up and
as part of opening them up you know I
don't know maybe we also in here just
because maybe we store the header right
which gives us all of that information
that we actually need right all of those
offsets and stuff that we actually you
know might might want for loading things
out now it's kind of a little bit
extraneous it's not clear that we
actually really need that to be
persisted so I could do it locally but
you know it's really no big deal so I
think I'll probably just store it for
now and that way we always can kind of
refer back to if we want to or stuff
like that so I push the array on there I
go through here and I'm gonna say for
every asset file right I'm going to take
a look right here we go there's our file
index this could be file index so I go
in here and I take this file and what I
want to do now is I want to open the
file or try to open the file right I
want to see if I can if that makes sense
so that would just be some kind of
called the platform layer which would be
like you know platform open file right
and what we would do is we would pass it
I probably I guess just the file group
and the file index for now I don't know
maybe we would want something a little
bit different than that maybe we would
want something more like file group you
know file group names or something or
files and then we just do it like this
you know I'm not sure something like
that maybe I don't really know but we're
gonna leave it this way for now I think
that's the way we'll we'll do it excuse
me so when we open a file we may get the
file handle we may not so we're gonna
want a way of saying you know platform
is valid or platform file handle is
valid right we're gonna want to be able
to say did it actually open right
did it work and there's another way we
could do that too right we could
actually go in and do something slightly
different but I don't know so well you
know what let me talk about that for a
second we'd want to we do something like
this right we'd say flat pilot is valid
and if so we'd read the header right
we'd go ahead and read the header we'd
say platform read data or read file data
or read data from file right and we
would pass the file handle I'm sorry
that's no that's right we would pass the
file handle we passed the offset we
passed the size of the thing that we
wanted to to actually read which is the
header right in this case and we'd pass
the location that we wanted to read it
to right where we wanted to put the data
so if we were to actually do it this way
now we've got another thing we've got to
do this as well right we need to see
whether this succeeded because maybe you
know in between opening the file and
reading the file it didn't get it or
maybe the files like been truncated and
the petyr's like not they're all there
or something right and we'd have more so
there's more errors here and that sort
of stuff right so what I think I'd
rather do is just not
that and say that we just do this right
files you can just do all the operations
that you want on the file and then at
the end all you have to do is say
platform no errors or something no file
errors and pass it a handle and if
there's ever been an error on that
that's like hasn't been cleared out then
you know it's considered an error this
is basically like you know do we have an
invalid code path yeah I know if we do
come on looks like we do so yeah so you
know if there were errors at all then it
wouldn't do any more processing and it
doesn't matter whether the error was
here or here because let's be honest we
don't care we don't care where the error
was all we know is we didn't get back a
header and we don't really need to know
when that error occurred because we
can't do anything different about it
anyway right there's not like there's
some magical thing that we're going to
be able to do if we can't open the file
we can't open the file right so in here
we probably want to assert and then we
also probably eventually have some way
of notifying users of bogus files right
we might want to be able to put up you
know when we have a little bit more of a
UI or something that comes up message
boxes or something we might want to
notify the user like hey there was an
HHA file in here but it's busted
which is probably not what you wanted
maybe you should check your download or
tell steam to like reinstall the game or
do whatever you know do something to try
and restore this game to working order
because it's probably not working the
way think it is right so there's that ok
so that's the way I would like that to
work if we actually got the stuff ok
then what I'd say is what we want to do
here
we want to sum up the total counts of
things right because we have tags and we
have assets so what we want to do is we
want to actually sort of sum how many of
each of them they're going to be right
and the same is probably going to be
true for the asset type array as well
like that's a thing that kind of has to
get merged so we'll have to see exactly
how we want to do that in order to do
like our layout
this will be kind of interesting to do
we'll probably write a very inefficient
one first which honestly will probably
end up flipping because there's only
gonna be like three or four of these
files at maximum any time anyway
probably so the efficiency is not gonna
matter but it would be interesting file
it would be interesting problem to think
about for extra credit if there was such
thing as credit on him a hero of how you
might set up these things to be merged
in a in a expedient fashion let's say
it's just something to think about
hi okay here we go
so when we actually determined that
there are no errors what we would like
to do is we would like to sum up some of
these things right so we would like to
go ahead and and sum up some stuff so
we've got you know the tag count and
what I'd like to do is start the tag
count at 0 and sum up how many we have
total in all the files right and the
same is true of our asset count right
I'd like to start at 0 and and sum it up
ok so inside here once we know we have a
header what we could do is also in there
try to validate the versions right click
in here which we may want to do is a
separate thing just so we could report
the error a little more cleanly right so
do something like this probably check
both of these separately even right
so assuming that it's a version that we
understand and you know and it's a an
actual file that we think we understand
and here we would have again
notification stuff to some degree and
not sure how we want to do that
eventually but maybe yeah we'll think
about that pretty far down the line
assuming all that stuff worked out okay
then we would just say that you know
we're gonna sum up how many there are
right and I probably also want to mark
the file you know one thing that I would
want to do is say that the file handle
itself had an error in these cases mark
platform mark error or something like
this platform file error and I would say
you know what this thing gets messed up
okay this one we already this is this
one or is Lux in the case we're checking
Matt well you know what I could do
that's pretty interesting actually hmm
I'm actually thinking that maybe we
could do that slightly differently as
well because we could instead do this
right
we could do it this way and then we
don't ever have to deal with more than
one of those right and these would
eventually you know be some kind of an
error message that we would put here
right it would be like magic HHA file
has an invalid magic value or something
like that you know or HHH file is of a
later version or something you know who
knows we put some we'd we'd make this
probably go through some kind of system
that we report errors eventually but you
know something like that just to give
you the idea that way the aerosol go
through the same system so we only check
the error once eventually at the end and
then we desert here you know if it was
wrong the asserts obviously won't
compile into the game in the final
release version so the user would never
get an assert but we would get one so
for our debugging purposes it would stop
us immediately and we'd be able to see
what the problem was at that point
because obviously we shouldn't ever have
this problem this is this is problems
that are happening only when there's a
corrupt files or bugs in our fire
reading code so that's what that would
look like right
and that all seems pretty good right
that all seems pretty good so let's see
a couple of the things we may want to do
there but let's see so if I do that I do
all that reading right I think now I'm
got enough information to actually
allocate the arrays properly right
I've got asset slots and tags right and
these are all going to be push array
stuff oops these are all going to be
push array
to create what we need in terms of
storage so we've counted up how much we
need to store the data from all the
files and then we are going to allocate
basically blocks where we can put all
the data right so if we want to do that
after we finish we need to actually load
the data in to those locations so then
we would have another loop through our
files right and I guess I should
probably change this to be that so then
we would have another loop through our
files where we would actually work with
them and you know what we might want to
do here too we might want to do
something along the lines of begin
platform begin all files of type right
or get all files of type begin and then
platform get all files of type end right
because the OS may require resources to
do this so it's kind of like you know a
thing where once we've opened the files
we don't need it to waste any more
resources on that list of files so I
just want to give the operating system
layer the opportunity to deal with that
gracefully right so in here we do push
arrays to get the slots that we need and
then we just go through and actually
load all of the data out right we load
all the data that we actually want to
load into the locations where we want to
load them right so we'd have like a set
index and/or asset count here right and
tag count here and then at the end after
we loaded them all we would want to do
an assert that the asset count equals
the assets asset count make sure we
loaded as many as we said we were going
to load right and so this gets back to
sort of the the sort of strange thing I
was talking about before
give me I'm gonna do this in a very
inefficient way what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna say since we care about organizing
things by asset type I'm going to say
that we have an asset type ID right that
we loop through all of the asset type
IDs that we actually have first right so
we go through all of the asset type
things we have like so so I go through
every asset type ID and for every asset
type ID I go through all the files right
and I look to see which files have
assets of that type right and I can do
this in a super janky way which is what
I'll do first this whole thing is pretty
janky and this is what I said like it'll
probably still execute extraordinarily
fast anyway because there just won't be
very many files and so I don't know that
we'll ever fix it but point being you
know it's something to think about it'd
be interesting to think about how to
write this in a way that wasn't
brain-dead right in fact I might do to
do exercise for the reader how would you
do this in a way that's scaled
gracefully to hundreds of asset files
right or more or however many so what
I'm gonna do here is say alright so for
every asset type ID I want to go pull
out all of the assets in the file that
are of that asset type ID and put them
so that they're continuous in my array
so I'm like I'm ik merging right all of
them together if that makes sense yeah
so hopefully that's you know relatively
clear so if I want to do that what would
I do here the first thing I would do I
probably would need HHA asset type right
asset
type array I would probably want to
actually load the asset type array for
each asset file and really we don't need
to keep this around so I should probably
be putting these in a transient a fully
transient arena but that's something we
haven't really gotten to yet so I should
do something like here to do if we ever
do thread sacks then there are asset
well actually gonna put it in here right
if we ever do thread sacks asset type
array doesn't actually need to be kept
here right that makes sense okay so when
we come through here and do this little
dance right what I'm going to do is say
I've got this asset type array I'm going
to assume that in here we would load
that array right so I'm gonna assume in
here that we would go ahead and and and
load it in I do something like platform
read data from file from this file
handle it would be at the file header
location writes a file header asset
types right and the size of it is going
to be however many there were times the
size of an asset an hhas s type right so
it would be like file header asset type
count right so something like that and
that would read into the asset type
array and the asset type array I guess I
should make this a size right that's it
type array size it's gonna be this guy
how big it is
and in it goes right so what I need to
do is I need to allocate space for the
asset types and of course I can't do
that till I've actually read the header
in right I can't do that till I've read
read the header in and again if I want
to I can sort of do this in all in an
entirely incremental way right I can say
that the file header I can just make
sure that the file header itself is
zeroed at the beginning I assume you
have a zero struck do we and actually
remember if we ever implemented that
you're a struct yeah
so we can just make sure that the header
is zeroed at the beginning we can then
do the read we don't have to check to
see whether the read succeeded or failed
because we don't care we can then go
ahead and set the asset type array right
to be whatever that size is right so we
can just do push array like so and off
we go so we would do asset type of race
size or strike push size rather HHA
asset type we do a push of that size
from whatever our arena is which to be
honest I don't remember what it actually
is just the called arena there we go so
that would give us face we'd then read
it in and that would be that right so
off we go yeah I guess I can't really do
much compelling here we're getting close
to the end of the stream so I should
probably go ahead and nerf some of these
guys out so we don't leave ourselves in
a non compounding state but we're
getting closer so I'd read those in and
then in here when I loop over them right
I would go ahead and say okay for each
file I'm just gonna go through its asset
array and see if it has any of this type
right so I'm gonna do something like you
know if if the source type ID equals the
asset type ID right and we could we
could call this like desta type ID right
desk type ID then I'm going to do the
block load of its assets into this
location right
really pretty straightforward if that
makes sense very very simple and there's
one other thing that we probably would
want to do actually now I'm thinking
about it as we do this interesting which
is we would want to do a tag tag base so
remember the tag arrays are by index so
all of the assets in one file are
assuming that their tag array starts at
0 but it won't start at 0 when we
actually concatenate them together so
we'll have to rebase the assets tags as
we go through in order to make them all
line up in the tag array that's kind of
annoying when you think about it because
it does mean that we will have to touch
the assets trucks onload which I would
have preferred not to do right if that
makes sense I would have preferred to be
able to just flat load it and be done
but it looks like there would be one
thing we'd have to touch which is to
slide the offset for the tags over
basically now there is so so that could
mean that there is a better way that we
should do our asset stuff although no it
still in me then it would be variable
size so I think that's probably still
gonna be the the easiest one for us to
do but time is of the essence here so
I'm gonna go ahead and and if zero this
out for now so that we don't we don't
leave ourselves in a non compiling state
and what I'll do here is just kind of
nerf the things that we added and so
that we don't have that problem ok so
there we go I'm just gonna leave us in a
compiling state here there we go working
nicely so I'll just keep writing this
for the next three minutes or whatever
till the stream runs out and then
tomorrow we'll pick back up on how we
want to do that sort of rest of the
merging and that sort of stuff all right
so as we go through the files again we
put this file now I'm just going to go
ahead and in that file we've got the
asset type array so I'm going to go
ahead and say that we've got you know
that source and the source is going to
be the file
acet type array should probably also say
that we're only going to process files
that don't have any errors
so if flaps worm file note what was it
platform no file errors if this handle
has no errors then we will use it
otherwise we will not write and it's
arguable that we maybe shouldn't even
have included it in the asset file list
if it had an error
maybe that's the smartest thing to do
but I'm just gonna I'm just gonna for
now leave it this way so when we get in
here we're gonna go ahead and loop
through every asset type index right so
this is basically the index from the
source right the thing we're reading out
of that's gonna go from 0 to however
many there were so this is in the header
this is asset type count right we're
going through them and for each one of
those we have our source and basically
if that source is the right type then
we're gonna do the block load right so
we're gonna load the that set of assets
in so that'll be another platform read
right that'll be platform read data from
file like so so we do platform rigidity
file and we would take however many of
them we're going to read and we would we
would want to kind of slide if you will
the we want to make the our range for
the dest we would want which is where is
our desk where we haven't done our desks
yet right we've got this asset type
right our desk we want the desk here
maybe we should do desk type and source
type that this desk type is going to be
the array that we're actually trying to
fill in right assets asset types plus
desk type ID right and that's our desk
type so our desk type for as we started
off is going to be because remember it's
got the first asset index and it's one
past
last asset index right so what we're
gonna do is we're gonna have our asset
count we want to start it off assuming
that it's like at the asset count and
then as we go we're just going to kind
of widen it out to fit you know wherever
in fact you know what it is it's really
just this right it's just gonna say one
past last index is whatever the asset
count is now so the asset count will
like increment as we load each
individual asset right so yeah all right
so we've got a bunch of work to do there
but we'll do it tomorrow
for now let's go to the QA and go ahead
and well let's go ahead and just you
know ask some questions so if you have
questions about what we did on tonight's
dream please go ahead and ask it now put
Q colon in front of it so I can see it
and answer it
of course I don't see any questions
everyone understood every last thing I
did tonight perfectly which is good news
everyone just knows how to do it
sorry if this has been answered what's
your general rule for making a variable
a pointer versus not so usually there's
two reasons for making something a
pointer the first reason is if you are
afraid that the copy' the cost of
copying it around is going to be too
expensive
so to give you an example right let's go
ahead and take a very simple case if I
were to make a function here
boy 2 and I had another function boy bar
let's suppose that I had something here
that was like a struct that they were
both going to talk about my struct right
so I wanted to find some data that both
foo and bar are going to operate on if
it's very small like this then if foo
has a my struct right and it sets part
of it to be equal to something and now
it would like bar to use that thing yeah
the question becomes should this be a
pointer or should it not be right that's
sort of like the thing that you're
asking right because in here you know it
uses this or something like that right I
don't know what it does with this value
but maybe it does you know some math
right so let's start thinking about this
particular problem and I'll go ahead and
compile this even and we can step in and
see what happens right so let's let's
first take this incredibly simple case
let's step in and see what happens so
here we go okay well you know what I got
to actually call it we won't be able to
pin to it if I don't ever call it there
we go so let's step into it here we are
so what's going on in the compiler at
this particular time right what's
happening here well if we look at the
disassembly we can see exactly what's
going on right here is the number five
right that's this and here is a pointer
to this structure right it's saying the
location of the structure on the stack
right here it's gonna copy the five into
there right it's gonna if this is it's
using this is like a target saying put
the five in there right so there it goes
it's moved in there then what's gonna
happen is it's going to move into ECX
which is a register the what is at the
location obstruct right which happens to
be that five it's gonna move it in there
and then it's gonna call bar okay so in
we call bar it's going to grab excuse me
what's in ECX store it to the stack
because it's trying to save the
variables here it's doing it's a little
standard dance because normally we're
running without optimizations right so
after wastage here it's then going to
load do you would point destruct which
is this right here right it's basically
you know it's taking the value that it
got past its storing it to the stack and
that's immediately reading it right back
from the stack right again the optimizer
would not be doing a lot of this stuff
but we're in an optimized code right
then it does the add of five which is
this five right here to our system five
to get 10 right at least it should be 10
and then it's storing it back out that
value back out to the stack
it's interesting you can see right the
the debugger is viewing what is on the
stack so until it actually moves it back
out to the stack it doesn't show it in
the register once it moves it out to the
stack you can see it so the debugger is
always inspecting the stack basically is
what that's telling you right so what
did that do well what it did was it
actually copied this by value right it
actually copied the whole thing okay and
so that's what's actually gonna happen
if I don't pass this by pointer so one
thing that might cross your mind is how
expensive is it to do that what if this
were very large right what if this were
32 things long right and we only use you
know and maybe we use all of them even
right so we're gonna use all of them or
whatever and we're gonna initialize all
of them so pretend we were doing a loop
where we English lies and we don't
really have to do that but pretend we
did that right so we actually want all
of them so now what happens when we do
this right so here's this
assembly and right we go through here
it's loading in it's actually trying to
figure out where to store this thing
right it has to do that offset of six so
it's figuring out where that's going to
be it's going to go ahead and actually
put it the value in there and then you
can see it gets to this thing right here
this rep mob s right and what it's going
to do is to see that a th there right
that ECX at a th that's actually if you
if you look at how many we've got we've
got 32 and they're 4 bytes each right so
they're 128 bytes so we can see is it
loaded in a th is the O X 80 right it's
it's 128 what it did is it said I got a
copy 128 bytes right now right because I
got a copy all that stuff onto the stack
for calling this guy because he wants
the whole thing so that's gonna full-on
bite a copy of 128 bytes right now right
that was it doing it and that doesn't
get any better right like I mean that
could be huge right that could be 4096
or something like this right or I guess
let's do 1024 which times 4 will be 4096
a whole page of memory right here we go
we come in here take a look at the
disassembly what's it doing right well
what it's doing is this copying 4096
bytes every time you want to call this
function right there it is so yeah doing
a lot of work so why might I want to
pass a pointer time number 1
the thing is large so what I'd rather do
is this right what happens if I do that
right well if I do that oops well if I
do that now when we look at the
disassembly it's not gonna bother
copying it it's just gonna send the
pointer right so in here when we do this
right you can see that rep mob is gone
that thing that does the block copy is
gone right so all it does is it takes
the address of the thing which is this
right and it's gonna move the address
into the register that it's going to
pass right that's all it's going to do
so
that we call bar bar grabs that pointer
out now and now from now on it's just
gonna use the pointer to access the
struct right and be done so it's much
more efficient now to do that so that's
the first reason you might pass a
pointer because the thing is large but
there's a second reason you might pass
the pointer right there's another reason
you might need to pass the pointer okay
so let's take a look at a different
scenario I'm gonna unwind this a little
bit back to where we were before before
we had a big thing so before there was
any reason to pass the pointer and
remember you know it can actually be
yeah
well nevermind I'm not gonna bother
saying that so anyway off we go what's
another reason to pass a pointer well
let's suppose that this code actually is
going to modify X right well what
happens if I just do this if I just do
this then what's gonna happen I mean
think about what happens in this code
right I'm gonna set X equal to 5 I'm
then I'm gonna pass it in fact you know
what I should probably point out you
know right here I want to find out what
it thought what you know what X actually
ends up being right well if this is
going to modify X when I come in here
and I set X equal to 5 and then I call
struct to have it go ahead and you know
increment X by 5 when I come back what I
will find of course is that my struct
still has 5 in it and the reason is
because if I pass something by value
it's passing an entire copy and this guy
is working on the copy but a lot of
times that's not what I wanted I wanted
that function to work on the struct and
I want to get back the results of that
right so one way to do that is obviously
to have a return value of my struct
right so I can do this so everybody's
doing by value this is the functional
style you might call it right I pass in
a struct I get a new struct back then I
just overwrite my old Struck's contents
with the new one right but again that
could be very inefficient if this struct
is large all these copies the optimizer
optimizer may not know how to do that
efficiently so another thing I can do
say you know what no we're all operating
on the same memory so I'm just gonna
pass you a pointer to struct and then
when you modify it I will see the
changes because it's the one that I'm
using to we're both pointing at the same
place right so here we go we set it to
five we call bar and now when we come
out here our struct is set to ten
properly because we were both looking at
the same struct right so hopefully that
answers the question usually it's very
unambiguous whether you use a pointer or
not if the thing is large or you're both
trying to operate on the same one you're
gonna use a pointer if it is small and
you don't care you're gonna pass my
value because usually it just more
efficient since you don't have to pass a
pointer that then gets you don't have to
pass the thing which tells you where the
thing is you could just pass the thing
and that's always going to be a little
more efficient than doing that
indirection right
SSS McGrath says I don't completely
understand your aversion to using the C
standard library is this just at HMH
thing for teaching or do you just never
use the standard library
I just never used the standard library
pretty much that started with granny
granny was the first thing I shipped
that did not require the standard
library and could be compiled completely
without it and you know I the current
code base that I'm doing at work doesn't
use the standard library at all either
so the next game the game that we ship
hopefully next year will not use it
either so the reason for that is twofold
one is I don't trust it and the reason
that I don't trust it is I've had lots
of bad experiences with it for example
you will call some math function in the
standard library and it's doing a ton of
extra work it doesn't need to do right
so I don't like the idea of maybe
calling sine or maybe calling a tan and
having it do a bunch of ridiculous stuff
that's not what I wanted right I want to
know exactly what the code is that I'm
calling on every platform and I want to
be the same right so I want to implement
it myself I want to implement atan2
exactly the way I want it and then I
want to know it's always a tan - I don't
want what some new library maintainer
thought a tan - should be doing I don't
want what the sea standards committee
thought 18 - had to do I want what I
think a tan shoe should do and I want it
to do the same thing everywhere and I
want it to be only what's necessary
right so that's one thing the second
thing is I just don't like the API like
I said I don't like their file API
I think it's written incorrectly I I
don't like a lot of the ways they've
structured things it's incomplete
there's a lot of things that the file
API doesn't do properly globbing for
example like you can't iterate over the
files in a directory that have a
particular name or something with that
right so it's just it's it's not even a
good standard library it doesn't have
the features I actually want so I know
I'm gonna implement half of it anyway
myself because doesn't have the things
that I need and so at some point I just
looked at it and I was like oh and then
one other thing is unreliability
linking the more stuff you rely on in
the standard library the more Microsoft
screws you by shipping really unreliable
side by side assembly dll lineup
nightmares I mean I can't tell you how
many times people have sent me
executable stuff like a game they were
working on and I go to run it and it
doesn't run because the proper MSD Siri
distributors were installed right if you
don't link with the Saint with the run
so you run time I were you never have
that problem now of course I've told you
other ways you can get around that is
just lick with it statically which I
highly recommend people do if you're
gonna use your mind right but that's
just an example of the kinds of
annoyances that happen or I want to link
with it and I don't have the C runtime
library dot Lib installed on the machine
in the right way because when
Microsoft's compiler got installed it
didn't do it right or the path is set
wrong or whatever it's like forget it if
that's if you'd ever linked with the and
stuff you just never think about that
again so yeah and that's something I did
recently with the current code base is
the first time I've ever done it the
current code base uses new link
libraries whatsoever the only one is
kernel32 on Windows so that I can get
get Brock address everything else is
done dynamically so I literally don't
even install the platform SDK I just the
only thing I do is I I lick with
kernel32 and I copy and I saved kernel32
Lib right into the source tree so there
is no in there are literally no source
paths involved in building our latest
codebase and let me tell you it has been
awesome because I go to a new dev
machine and there's no BS right there's
no fudge it's just it builds right there
is no way it can't build you don't have
to call VC VARs all you don't have to
like set a path you know I saw the
platform up to install what version of
DirectX blah blah blah is like none of
it it just builds and then from now on I
will never think about that right which
is great so
how and where will users savedata be
stored so that will be a separate thing
that will deal with a little bit later
and that is entirely platform dependent
right so we will basically define an API
when we get to the point where we have
actually user data to store we'll define
an API at that time remember always
write the users code first so when we
get to the point where my save user data
will do that and the platform will be
the place that besides where it's stored
because you know if it's running on
steam it's gonna want to use like cloud
save if it's running on a console it's
gonna want to use whatever their thing
is if it's running just a standard
Windows it's gonna want to use the
windows
you know app data or whatever you know
wherever the latest places they say you
have to store it you know you want to
basically just have that be pushed
totally to the platform later because
every platform is different so the main
code will all it will know how to do is
issue commands of like here's my user
data please save it or whatever you know
or update it all right we good
think we're good I'll really quickly run
through the non topic topical questions
well keeper are you using this is a Das
Keyboard 3 after I got extraordinarily
mad at the bus keyboard for which many
of you saw on stream how long have I
been developing games I've been
programming for 30 years I've been on in
the game industry for 20 let's see how
and what sorry why brown switches over
blue I just I don't like the heavy
clicking I I grew up my favorite
computer to type on growing up was the
amiga computer and it had a softer touch
keyboard I still haven't found anything
that I'd like to type on quite as much
as that keyboard but blue blue switches
are a little too hard for that Brown are
closer let's see what do you have in
your arms those are my wrist braces they
keep me from getting tendonitis I find
so I always use them and that do I like
dogs or cats I'm fine with either I just
I die if I'm gonna if it's gonna be my
pet it's a cat I don't really dogs are
too needy for me
Russell abyss how far do you think you
are in terms of stream days from
implementing game logic in terms of play
versus platform my ballpark was
somewhere around day 200 would be where
it would be because I've been days are
roughly an hour so if you think about
how long that is like 200 hammy hero
days is 200 hours so divide that by 40
that's 5 work weeks and 5 work weeks to
build a complete engine is not very long
but we've been making pretty good
progress and it does seem like probably
about there so you know day 200 day 250
something like that I just got to RPI
twos what do you think about the RPI -
in general I have not seen an RPI - I
only had an RPI 1 what do you think
about Intel I NDE
sorry I guess I I don't know what that
is
is it something integrated native
developer experience is that is that
what we're talking about I yeah I I
guess I don't know what this is a cross
architecture productivity suite that
provides developers with tools support
and IDE integration to create high
performance C++ Java applications for
Windows well I mean I guess I've never
tried it so I don't know but I'm not
sure what it would really do for me I
mean the only thing I use ms dev for is
the debugger so if it had like a really
great debugger or something maybe but
you know otherwise I'm not sure what
what I would be doing with it all right
looks like we are done with questions
which means we are done with the stream
so let's close this down
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
it has been a pleasure coding with you
as it always is and I'm pretty happy
with where we're getting here we're
almost done with the asset file stuff
it's looking pretty good and again you
know it's pretty cool when you think
about it the limited the very limited
amount of time that we spend on things
you know we'll spend like 20 30 hours on
something and have a crazy list of
features like we do streaming sound
overlapped with you know on separate
threading for with our sound mixer that
does pitch shifting and volume panning
and all this other sort of stuff like
all going through the asset system which
is all streamed and loads you know in
the background and all this other star
stuff like if you think of how short we
spend on most of our things we get a you
know a lot of features in there so I
think we should be pretty happy with
that because you know a lot of things a
lot of times you'll get a commercial
game engine that can't even do some of
these things and we have been pretty
consistent at being able to do some
pretty powerful stuff so far so I'm
pretty happy with how little time we
have spent doing any individual piece of
this and yet we've gotten some pretty
industrial-strength stuff out of it so I
think that's pretty darn cool and sort
of validates what I tend to think about
things which is that making stuff by
script making stuff from scratch really
isn't that hard once you kind of get the
hang of it and it's something that you
always could build on going forwards and
and know that it works the way you want
it to you know so anyway that's said we
will continue with the asset file stuff
for a couple more days getting it
running smoothly with the win32 platform
layer and also making sure that we can
load multiple asset files and merge them
and so I hope you'll join me for that
we'll be back here again 5 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time tomorrow same time same
place
here on Twitch in the meantime if you
want to file a look at home come follow
along at home with a source code you can
pre-order the game on handmade hero or
it comes with a source code this handy
little pirata button here so if you want
play around experiment with it yourself
you can do that we also have a forum
site we can ask questions
get an anti episode guide you sports mac
and linux that sort of stuff we also
have a patreon page while support the
video series you could subscribe there
and we have a tweet bot which tweets the
schedule so if you ever want to catch
the scream live or you're not sure when
it's going to be the tweet box the place
to go for that and it will keep you
informed thanks everyone for joining me
and I will hope see hopefully see you
here again tomorrow until then have fun
coding and I'll catch you on the
Internet