hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here the show we code a complete game
live on stream we did some bugging
yesterday and I think we are now at the
point where as far as I know we don't
really have any outstanding bugs in our
art pipeline stuff that we've done which
means that we are kind of free to import
stuff into our game and decorate the
world and add entities to the world
which brings us to sort of the port part
where we have to really start engaging
with the the the gameplay more again
which is not really something that I
like to do because I'm not a game
designer and I feel more comfortable
generally speaking when a game designer
is at the helm and so you know we're
kind of at the part in how we're oh and
if I don't remember the end of last
stream we loaded first we have a giant
cat for some reason so there are some
technical things we can do right now
like I said I kind of wanted to do
alignment point stuff so we can do so we
can add some stuff to like you know we
want to line the the head and the body
and stuff like that and we can add some
technical stuff in there but we are kind
of getting up to that point where it's
stuff I feel less comfortable with I
don't like doing game design oriented
stuff I'd much rather be in a situation
like on the witness or something where
John blows doing the design and I'm just
programming something that's a lot more
comfortable but you know we'll muddle
through it we'll be fine and we'll focus
on the technical issues of it as we go
so what I want to do here is I want to
take a look at just what we want to have
happen naturally and then I want to
augment our current system to provide
that thing so what I want to be able to
do and we're ignoring the fact that the
hero is a cat currently but what I want
to be able to do is place you know
throughout the world right now we've got
a couple different cats in the art set
three of them we've got a brown tabby
named Fred we've got a great tabby named
Molly and we've got a ghost cat named
Hannah who's a Behrman and we would like
to place them in the war
old somewhere right we would like to
when the game starts up you know we'd
like to place three cats around these
three cats around the orphanage and we'd
like them to just be available for the
cat and you know for the player to come
to and you know maybe when the player
hops up to it we want them to interact
in some way like you know maybe they
purr or something like this right so
they're they're kind of a set dressing
for the game and maybe they have some
gameplay ramifications later as we get
into it we'll see but basically the idea
is we want to be able do that simply and
so the question is how do we make it
easy for us to accomplish this task that
I've just stated what are the current
technical barriers present in our engine
that are going to cause that to not be
fluent and easy for us to do and how do
we break down those those those barriers
right so again the goal is we're sort of
taking again a snuffleupagus oriented
approach here I want to go make a thing
that lets me place cats in the world
easily I want that to be as low a
friction as low overhead as possible so
I'm going to go into the system and try
to do so and then when I do it I'm gonna
see what problems arise and try to solve
those problems with improved engine
capabilities now in terms of like one of
them like I said is already just the
alignment fact and there's also the
scale fact right there's a lining and
scaling and stuff that's why our cat is
like huge and the head is not right so
we know some of the things we're gonna
deal with but we don't necessarily know
them all so I'm gonna go ahead and place
some cats in the world and then we're
gonna address all of the issues that we
see and then we'll we can use that to
also place monsters in the world and so
on right we're gonna build up our
repertoire so that we no longer have any
friction associated with this because
remember what we're going to be doing
you know 50 days 50 day episodes from
now as we've got the world up and
running all of our work is going to
revolve around these sorts of things
generating entity structures in the
world and programming those entities to
do things is the entire
of what gameplay programming is and so
we want to continue and we want to start
a trend now and continue the trend of
refining the systems and interfaces to
those systems that are involved in that
till it's very low friction to
experiment and change because that is
what will determine whether or not our
game is any good in a world where we had
a designer right and that's what I'm
trying to prepare you for right in other
words if you were the engine programmer
or one of many engine programmers
hopefully on some engine programming
team that is what you are trying to
accomplish because it doesn't matter how
good your gameplay programmers or game
designers are if the systems that they
have to interface with are very
laborious and onerous to work with then
they will not be able to iterate fast
enough on the design to make it any good
and this definitely you see this in a
lot of places there's a lot of times
where technological limitations prevent
a game from reaching its true potential
in fact this is a little bit separate
from the point I was making in terms of
NNE placements or things like that but a
very good example recently was Red Dead
Redemption 2 for those of you who played
it that game would be 10 times better
than it is if it had had a solid
technical program programmer on the UI
system
it's a incredibly clumsy game to play it
feels awful you end up accidentally
shooting people you were trying to talk
to and all sorts of other ridiculous
things and again that's part I mean you
could argue that's the designers fault
and to a certain extent it is but it's
also a technology problem because if you
provide good quality technology for
constructing user interfaces it's more
likely that you will arrive at a good
one
whereas if everything has to be
microprogrammed by people who are maybe
not necessarily even strong programmers
because they're more on the design side
you will end up with janky stuff so
again can't say why that happened but I
noticed it I mean it's a game that's
gorgeous I don't have you seen it looks
beautiful and it's just a lot of fun to
kind of ride around the world but oh my
god when you go to actually do something
it's not the interfaces mind-bogglingly
bad and I just
like that's a great place where
technology you know a little technology
and dynamic response to the environment
and allowing the controls to very
smoothly transition between meaning
different things that we're all very
intuitive would have helped a lot so the
player doesn't have to remember like oh
if I wanted to take my saddle off my
horse I hold down the left bumper and
the right trigger at the same time and
then I push up on the d-pad and then
it's just like oh my god right like it's
it's so weird and so I feel like a lot
of times you have to be aware of what
you give people to work with will a lot
of times determine what they end up with
and while you can blame them for that
the blame actually should be spread
around a little bit more because it's
also the underlying technology making it
easier difficult to represent certain
things oftentimes that shows through and
I suspect that at least in the Red Dead
Redemption case my gut instinct is that
there was a little bit of blame to
spread around there that it was not just
the design team's fault but also
probably a certain amount of programming
at fault
that wasn't exposing a rich language for
talking about how the UI could work that
leads to a very janky manual 15,000,000
button mapped kind of solution so don't
know purely hypothetical but you know I
always hate to see good experiences held
back by things that probably could have
been fixed so anyway let's go ahead and
jump into the world generator and we'll
talk about this particular thing that we
would like to do here so inside handmade
world mode with absolute world gen we
know that we can create rooms and things
like this and we have things like room
specs so when we go ahead and create a
room it has a pointer to a specification
that tells us about what that room has
to have any
now there's a couple different kinds of
things that we need to address here some
things have to do with with room
specific stuff and some things have to
do with characteristic stuff and some
things cross both boundaries if you
imagine specifying a room as we are
specifying room right now there's a
couple different ways you might want to
talk about that room one way we might
want to talk about that room is to
generically say that certain types of
things happen in the room for example
let's say that rooms in general just had
a 50% chance of having a cat in them
always that would be something that
would go in something like a room spec
because you would just be saying look
every time I have this type of room
there's a chance there's a cat in it so
roll the dice and if you roll it the you
know the dice comes up this out of cat
if there isn't don't add a cat right and
that's the kind of thing that treats
stuff as non-unique monsters are a good
example of something it will probably
most the time follow that pattern like a
non boss monster a non-unique monster
will normally follow the pattern of a
room just says it tends to have these
kind of monsters in it it expects the
room generator to then roll some dice
effectively and come up with which
monsters are actually in the room but
doesn't matter which ones are in any
particular sense it just matters if they
adhere to a certain pattern of
population right but that's not true for
something like unique characters so for
example if we want each of these three
cats to be a unique cat which was the
original idea in the game was that these
are three unique cats Hannah Fred Molly
they should only occur in one room so we
can't very well add something to a roo
spec that says there's a chance that
there might be a cat here because even
if we did that we would then still have
to have a structure on the back end that
check to make sure it only added each
cat once which therefore leads to a sort
of backwards phenomenon of rolling dice
every room and then picking a cat from
the available set of cats or none if
none is still available what this does
is it heavily biases the random
generation about where the cast will be
placed towards rooms that are placed
early in the placement sequence which is
not something we actually specified
right because think about it
say we said there's a 50% chance as a
cat in every room well there's only
three cats so after six rooms all the
cats are placed and the other thousand
rooms in the game will never have a cat
you're gonna see that bias and players
are gonna pick up on it and it's gonna
feel weird and it's gonna be bizarre
it's not gonna make sense it's obvious
that there was a technological
constraint they're causing something to
happen that was not supposed to happen
doesn't feel right
so what we'd rather do is place on a
more holistic sense where we say okay
there are room specs those say things
that are generic about the room and that
don't have cross room concerns meaning
they don't depend on what happened in
another room as to whether it can happen
in this room so we'd rather have
something that works in sort of a more
holistic sense and can say we're gonna
place three cats after we figure out
where all the rooms are then let's reach
in and place the cats say at that time
when we have complete knowledge about
the entire world and can make an
unbiased decision about which room the
cats will go in based on information
that we now have about the actual
structure of the world and this makes a
lot of sense especially because
especially in case of the cats they are
things that inhabit the world and the
world does not really respond to them in
a structural sense meaning we don't have
any plans or I don't anyway for saying
well if a cat is in a particular room
then the room and the things around it
should be structured like this right now
you could imagine a circumstance where
that is true and that would create a
more complex structure for the world
generator to have to understand and work
with but in this case we don't have that
situation the cats are more like just
inhabitants of a world that is
constructed based on rules ancillary to
the cat's and so you can think of their
placement as something that's more about
looking at the world and figuring out
where we think the cat should go rather
than building the world around the cats
which makes them sort of a perfect thing
for this sort of secondary placement
phase that's about analysis and
placement so what I'd like to do now is
add that phase into the world Jen
something that allows us to cleanly
think about placing unique items and
characters in the world in specific
locations only once put that in have it
actually place the cats and then push
that down to the final part which is any
kind of cleanup we need for the asset
system like say those alignment points
or scaling information that we then want
to add the asset system to make it easy
for us to actually create the entity
which is a separate issue right so I'm
going to go through that whole process
today hopefully we'll get through all of
it but we may stop a little bit short of
setting the alignment points because
that's sort of another step that's a
little bit more involved so we can maybe
talk about next next weekend so here's
the structure for generating a room and
if we take a look at the world gem code
right now it's not particularly good
right we just sort of started sketching
things out but we you know we do play
some rooms in here and then if you
remember how this works we've got sort
of the create orphanage thing and so I'm
gonna go ahead pull it over here so my
head isn't blocking part of it and what
we do inside the Creed orphanage call is
we just create a bunch of room specs
that are specs for rooms that we want to
have exist here there's such save slots
and the bedrooms and things like this
and inside those room specs we have a
simple setting does it have stone floor
or not which we actually respect so if
you look we just do that as a test to
see if you actually look at what happens
when we generate the world here you can
see if I kind of move upwards here that
the bedrooms which are these right here
actually do have stone floors just like
we said that they should and so that's
actually being respected as the one and
only current specification for room that
we really use and there could be a lot
more there I'll see as we start making a
richer description of what constitutes a
room and what goes in a room so what we
want to do now is we want to say well
okay so if that's the stone like the
room spec stuff and you can set things
in there we have a good place for that
we now need a good place for talking
about when we generate these rooms you
can see us generating them here you can
see us setting the size of a lot of them
and you can see us connecting them we're
sort of creating a bunch of rules about
how these things have to be connected
and then they get laid out right we then
at the end of this would like some way
of saying how we might want things to be
placed right how we might
want entities to be placed in those
rooms so for example inside the bedrooms
we may want to place particular
characters from our character set right
we have all the orphans who live in the
orphanage and we may want some way of
placing them into the world they would
for example each live in one of the
bedrooms or something like this or you
know in the kitchen or the tailor's room
right the tailor orphan would live in
the tailor's room and the Baker orphan
would live in the kitchen for example
and I live is probably the wrong word
what we really mean is stay is is there
when you're walking around right baking
or doing something they probably don't
live there or maybe they do there's a
bedroom there I don't know but point
being we want some way to place people
into specific rooms probably and the way
that we would probably do this is at
some point after we've created this
stuff like for example inside create
orphanage we do all this stuff to create
the orphanage we also have things like
dungeons and we create the dungeons
right and so when we're doing these
creation things they return results that
we can use and so you can see in here
when we create the orphanage for example
or the forest or the whatever right we
can see us here we create these sort of
results from the spec generator this
sort of says stuff like oh you know I
here's the orphanage here's some
important rooms that I created and we
might eventually specify all the rooms
we created in here right so after you
call Corrine on it you can think about
it in other ways I think that's how we
would like to purchase because when we
call create world we'd probably like at
the end of create world when we've
created all the rooms in the world we'd
like to go through all of those sort of
structures and start tapping into them
to create various or to place various
things that we might want placed right
so I'm just gonna start by sketching in
what something like that could look like
so
for example in here if we have the the
orphanage what I kind of want to do is
take a look at some of the other I want
a way of reaching in there and placing
the cats as we go and there's a couple
of different ways that I might want to
do that right one way to do that would
be to do it in line with create
orphanage if the cats are always inside
the orphanage but another way to do that
would be to do it outside because what
if for example sometimes the cats are
not in the orphanage like maybe once in
a while one of the cat cats wanders off
into the world and then that cat doesn't
place itself in the orphanage places
itself in some other world location
right so if I was to say look let's
actually record a lot of this
information in here maybe you know maybe
we want this as something that we can
actually record so you know I'm gonna
say let's say there's three hero saves
slaves slave slots four bedrooms and
then there's some specific other
elements in here that we you know have
talked about for example I if I was to
upgrade the orphanage structure to look
a little bit more like this so it
actually records all of the rooms that
it hasn't it then anyone who wants to
touch those rooms specifically or place
something into them specifically can do
so so if I grab this and fill it out at
the end I'm again just sort of guessing
cure but I'm thinking that might be a
nice way to propagate that information
out words exactly as we have been you
know the entire time so here's our save
slots here is the front hall it's so
then the other thing that I want to do
here is I would like to be able to
access these things as in multiple ways
so I'd like to be able to access them in
ways that allow me to randomly pick from
certain types of rooms
as well or do other sorts of things like
that and so one of the other things that
I can do is I can make you know I can do
a lot of different things here but
another way that I can do this is to
make one of these right where I can see
Jen orphanage
and I get back a set of rooms and I can
if I want to actually just give them I
don't know exactly I'd say that it's not
really rude type it's more like a room
ID maybe might be the right way to look
at it and when we talk about these room
IDs what I could do is say oh you know
what instead of doing it like that let's
instead say that we've kind of got
something more like this where each of
these sort of rooms can come back in a
set of rooms and we just say what if
type of room is so we can do random
picking on them or you know who knows
what else right I'm not sure the best
way to place something like that there's
two ways we could do it one is to set a
room type and the other is and list the
rooms another is to actually just have
rooms by ID yet even another is to just
have giant list of these things hmm I
say and I don't really know I don't
really know what's the best one would be
I mean you can see sort of what I would
like what I'm going for here anyway is
I'd like to place three cats and so you
know what I want to do is inside here
where we say you know the same sort of
thing where we're like look this is
where the starting room is it's the
hero's bedroom or whatever so startling
happens there and generates the world
just go outward you know in here I would
like to to sort of say let's place some
cats you know
so in fact I guess I wouldn't quite do
it that way I'd probably more do
something like this place cat and I want
to pass something there that lets me
pass where you know sort of the the set
of possible locations that we might want
to place the cat but you know then I'm
gonna pass which cat it is and so inside
the sorry I should say file formats
inside here we've got these tag types
and I can say like okay I would like to
place you know the Berman cat in a
particular location I'd like to pass the
tabby cat and I'd like to place the
brown cat I want to place each of these
cats and you know off we go so I'd like
to have a way of placing the cat
somewhere and I'd like to be able to
have it picked from a set of locations
fairly reasonably I just don't know what
we're actually going to be passing here
so when we write this routine you know
you can imagine how I would want to be
able to write it also I suppose there's
probably some kind of a gem placement
thing here or maybe even just an entity
you know that comes back I'm not sure
how that would go well it's not gonna be
an Andy it's gonna be the request for an
entity right because we wouldn't
actually place the entity itself until
we actually generate everything right
it's cuz we want we're just saying that
there should be an end to be here not
you know what I mean so anyway what we
would like to do now is have some way of
you know discussing where this thing
actually goes and
we might want a couple different ways of
saying that obviously if we knew exactly
what room we want to put them in we
would just pass the room but since we're
sort of saying we would randomly want to
put them in a set of rooms we want
something that's going to be like the
series picker
here and you know the world generators
got a set of and you know in Tropic
serious that it can use for this so we
know that the world generator would come
in here and that we would use the
entropy from the world generator to pick
randomly from some set of things right
we would want to do a random choice over
some set of rooms like you know a room
count here something like this where
we'd say look pick a random room out of
a set of rooms like so find out what
that room is something like this and
when you found out what that room is
then we are going to add an entity to
the world to that to that room right you
know I'm saying something like this and
that sort of allows us to I guess this
should really be asset tag ID like that
this is sort of what we would want to do
and so the question is how do we come up
with this structure you and I mean I
my gut instinct which is often wrong but
is always the place to start because
what else where else are you going to
start I is that maybe what we would like
to do is just maintain picking lists in
the world generator and then you
randomly pick from a picking list so for
example let's suppose that every time
one of our generation routines that's
creating structures in the world creates
a room where it thinks a cat might want
to hang out it would create a cat
placement record that is saying you
could place a cat here if you were so
inclined right then when we go to place
a cat or anything else a mini boss or a
boss monster or a treasure chest or
whatever you could imagine that system
being somewhat generally useful meaning
you would just say all right every time
the generator generates something that
could be used for a particular purpose
it adds it to the list of things
and I can't say I can't say I can think
of any particular reason not to do that
it seems okay
I guess what I'll say is I'm gonna
experiment with this a little bit and
just see how I like it I may not like it
and I reserve the right to therefore
stop doing it at that point so I'm gonna
call maybe I'm just gonna call this a
Jen option and a Jen option I think at
what I want to do is something like this
where you basically say okay I've got a
Jen option type and the option type is
gonna be like this thing that says like
Jen option you know cat or something I
apologize for this being kind of a
little bit ill-formed but it's
ill-formed because I don't really know
what I'm gonna do here right but like
imagine something like this where I just
sort of made some chains of stuff and I
mean I guess I could also make them be
the actual array so they'd be easier to
pick from
it's pretty hard to say what I'm
thinking is you know if you if you've
got if you've got an array you can
pretty easily pick a random element from
the array if you've got a linked list
it's much harder to pick randomly from
it because I mean on the one hand you
can sort of do it in an efficient method
by randomly sorting the thing ahead of
time and then just taking the first one
but that random sort is a little bit of
an issue in and of itself
hmm
and the other thing that I think I want
to be cognitive is when you're placing
these things you don't want to place
them all in the same place so when you
place like a cat somewhere you kind of
want to talk about an option having been
overloaded to a certain extent which I
guess you can sort of do
I'm just gonna go with it I'm gonna say
arbitrarily speaking maybe there is a
gen option array and maybe that has an
option count in it and maybe it has the
options statically and maybe I have a
set of those like so and that's just all
purely hypothetical right so that's what
I would have and inside this the gen
option would really just be a pointer to
a room and that room would be the thing
that gets whatever we're talking about
here right uh and I might furthermore
try to flag that out so that we have a
notion of what is in the room so we
would have like something like this
where the options picked in this case
get Ord in from the set of options that
are available
you
and I think that works reasonably well
at least my first inclination right so
basically every time we pick one of
these things we randomly select one and
then we see if it's suitable and if it
is we are in the flag here that seems
okay to me
so for example Jen option cats would be
one maybe Jenna Jenna option orphan is
another you know like we we put one of
the orphans in here maybe Jen option you
know trying to think of what they would
be you know they'd be like you know a
mini-boss or you know those sorts of
things right so I think we would put
sort of this stuff that we place around
in that way would create the options
would be sort of created in the list and
then we would pick from those options
and fill them out seems okay to me I
don't know maintaining the arrays that
the generation goes on seems like a kind
of pain in the butt because you want to
be able to both pick quickly from them
at random and also just add to them
which there is no really good data
structure for I mean there's better ones
probably than an array but you know
maybe depends on what you're optimizing
for whether you're optimizing for
picking or adding but I don't know so
I don't know
that's something it's hard for me to
really get too excited about it because
I'm just not sure yet
but that's roughly what we're talking
about here so what I would say is you
know there's gonna be something here
which is like oh yeah maybe we'd do
something like maybe we would do
something where we pick the option I
just can't decide if you should remove
it or not you probably do so we'd
probably do something like Jen option
you know pick option and it probably
just returns the room so we're like give
me something I just want you to give me
something that I can place this thing in
I'm gonna look at it and and maybe
there's a corresponding one which is
like hey this I'm gonna tell you that
this thing is now an option for placing
that thing so I can pop an option off at
random and I could push an option on and
those two things both have to be able to
occur pretty much at any time I'm just
gonna say it's gonna be ugly cos gonna
waste a ton of memory because I've got
to make like these arrays and stuff it's
not compact but I guess that's just
gonna have to be okay for now and if we
really need to do something more
creative later we can you know as
necessary so then when we want to do
something like place cats we would
really just do something like oh oh
right so I need to know what cats what
room the cats in so I just do a pop
option and I say you know I need you to
give me
place for a cat can be you know and
maybe we do something a little bit
saucier where we also say like you know
require and or or you know allowed and
disallowed and so what we saying here is
like well we're gonna pass you a bit
vector that basically says here are the
things that have to be in there and here
are the things that can't be or
something like that right
I mean really I guess what we can say is
a more complete version would give us
the full flags so it would say yeah you
know what I don't really want to do it
quite that expressively
yeah I don't want you back aggressively
so here's what I'm thinking I was
thinking oh you could pass some stuff in
here that would kind of let it
discriminate and determine what room it
wanted to place them in but I think
that's gonna be a lot more touchy like
it's gonna involve inspecting the room
and fairly complicated ways eventually
so that just doesn't really make a lot
of sense so I think what makes more
sense is to just say look give me one
the most important option here right
like here's the gen option type that I
want I'm gonna pop these off and I'm
gonna pop them off in order probably so
I think I'm not in order but I'm gonna
pop off potentially multiples as I look
through and try to find a room that's
suitable so really it should it's gonna
be a little more complicated and pop
option what it's actually look like more
is like an iteration if you will so it's
gonna look more like this it's gonna
look like struct Gen option iterator and
what you're probably going to do here is
is inside this place calf thing you're
gonna say like for you know gen option
iterator begin option search or
something or iterate options and you're
gonna say I want options for someplace I
can place my tap and then you're gonna
iterate over what comes back and maybe
this is known to only work this way like
maybe we don't really need anything else
so it's just gonna be like yeah we
create one of these iterators we get
iterate over it this will give us our
options for each option we can look our
selves and we can say all right so
here's the room that it's saying we
should put it in here we could do to do
KC check this room to see if it meets
our other criteria whatever those happen
to be and then we can either
well I guess in what we would do here is
just say all right now we're done right
so we would say like finish or something
right
I don't know something like that so this
way we can iterate over a number of
random choices looking at them and the
system understands that we're doing that
so it won't keep picking randomly and
giving us back and like searching
through rooms we've already searched
through right it'll always pick new ones
until we run out of rooms to pick and so
I feel like that would be the key right
so we'd have Jen entity results and we
would return the results here and in
here we would place the entity and so
this really is just an if one but
someday we're saying it would actually
look at something and then it would
place the entity in the room and I think
that's all we really need there right so
we have our room index and room choice
stuff is not necessary anymore that's
going to be coming from the system we
can iterate over all the options where
we might want to place a cat we can do
additional checking to figure out
whether a cat really belongs there and
that and yeah that's that's the end of
it right
seems reasonable to me so this goes
inside because you know if we didn't if
for some reason we didn't find this room
to be acceptable someday when there's an
actual criteria being evaluated in here
then what we would do is we wouldn't
finish so we'd keep looking for new
rooms right so I think that's how we
want that to work and so really this
looks like this and then each of these
is just sort of a service call that
allows us to complete that iteration
cleanly and just makes it easy to use
the semantics of it right okay so there
is no pop option there's only a way to
add an option and to iterate over
options and then the system is
responsible for doing something
meaningful with it at that point right
and we'll figure out how I want that to
work but I pretty much already know how
I would have that work but we'll kind of
look at that in a minute so that seems
reasonable and we'll stub it in for now
so here's the results right and what I'm
gonna do is just say all right let's
just assume that this just always pops a
room right now and so it's totally
broken doesn't actually do at all what I
wanted it to do yet right so it just has
a room on here and so the result of this
function is just is the room valid and
in order to advance it it just sets the
room zero and when we go to finish this
it also sets the room to zero and so
there really isn't so this is you know
I'm gonna put this in here not yet
implemented for real
so really I'm just stubbing this out and
not really making an actual function out
of it and we'll talk about that well
we'll actually implement it a little bit
later so when I iterate options here
what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna pop
the first option off of the option array
so I'm gonna go ahead and say that if
well first I'll get the option array in
question which is here so I'm going to
say alright this option array is
whatever the option arrays are plus the
type that you asked me for I'm then
gonna say that the array you know it's
got an option count so if there are
options in the option count then I'm
going to pop the back one like so and
I'm just going to grab it so the room in
this case is just going to be the
options and we're gonna say that the in
here when we get the Jen option array
it's got a pointer to the options the
first one that will the last one in the
list we're just going to take whatever
that room is and use that makes sense so
that is that is sort of the stub out
that just says well it doesn't really do
what it's supposed to do meaning it
doesn't really allow us to pick multiple
rooms or randomly pick rooms or anything
else yet it just kind of gives us one
room and places it we're gonna get it
working with that and I'm gonna come
back and change it to allow that to work
better right so that leaves us with push
option push option needs a way of
creating something meaningful here in
terms of option arrays and again this is
gonna be some pretty tasty bad code and
that's okay
because I don't think this is going to
be a particularly important part of the
system anyway but we're just gonna
basically just add
these in blocks of a hundred or a
thousand or something and call it a day
right we're not gonna do anything else
interesting here so what I'm gonna do is
the same thing I did before I'm just
gonna grab the array in question and I'm
going to check first to see if the
maximum option count has been exceeded
so if the option count is less than the
max option count and I'm kind of writing
that only semantically this is the case
where we could add it but if the option
count is equal to and greater than
should never happen so you know and
really it should just be that that is
never the case because that's just
totally borked
so assuming that the option count is
equal to the max option count means that
it's full and we can't add anymore that
could happen either because we've never
allocated any of them or it could happen
because we've used all the ones that we
have allocated so what I want to do
there is say that the max option count
is going to get increased by some amount
that amount is just going to be a
hundred because I pulled that out of my
butthole and we're just going to use it
then what I'm going to do is say that
we'll reallocate the array so we'll
basically say that we have a new option
amount right new options is going to be
equal to an array that's pushed onto our
temporary memory and all we're gonna do
there is say inside our temporary memory
that we're using for scratch let's just
go ahead and grab a we'll just lemongrab
out one of the you know a block of this
mini however many we want we'll
lemongrab that many gen options again
really piggy and wasteful memory here
why is because we're not even going to
return the old array back to the system
for any particular use right so it's you
know
we're only using it a generation time
however so it's not clear that we'd ever
really care and we will flush all this
before we actually start running the
game when we would might care about the
memory overhead so it's probably not an
issue but we'll see so anyway we're
going to increase the option count and
then we we need to copy the old array of
options so we just say okay we've got
whatever the option count was we need to
copy our array of options I I do have a
copy right yeah we're gonna our old
array of options to our new array of
options and then we're just gonna make
that the new array that allows us to
push as many as we want on and we'll
continue to grow again don't know that
we really care about this one way or the
other but we'll find out later whether
we need to be saucy err here or be more
efficient right maybe we do maybe don't
so now that that's done we can just
actually place a cat the problem would
now be that we don't have a way of
recording that we want specific entities
to be placed into those rooms so we now
need some way of having that being
notated in the world generator as
standing structure that you know works
with whatever's in there so inside here
where we have a general we kind of want
a way of attaching entities to it cuz
like right now you can sort of see by
the way that means all of this is not
necessary anymore so I guess that means
that was a waste of time sorry about
that
maybe we'll still use something like
that later I don't know but probably not
because we did something else um so
there's really only these two
go ahead okay so essentially what we
want to do here is we want to expand the
notion of the of the room idea to
include entities that have been placed
specifically in this room and which must
be placed in the room right meaning that
the the outer scale system said hey this
you gotta put this entity in here you
don't get a choice so mister room
generator thingy go ahead and do that
right
so if we say general room entity but
really we can just say entity probably
because this doesn't even stick to the
room
these can just be in the rooms as a
chain I think and so they would just get
placed in here and these entities would
just kind of stock up and then we tag
them you know we would basically have
some set of tags in there and those tags
would get carried forward as a way of
specifying what the enemy was I'm not
gonna have a variable list I think that
would kind of be a waste of time
so instead I'm just gonna say that we
have a sort of a gender the tag here and
that just has whatever the asset tag ID
would have been and the value of the tag
and then there's just gonna be some
number of tags that entities can have
you know maybe it's eight
maybe it's sixteen I don't know but
we're just gonna place that many of them
in there let's say it's 15 because why
not because then we have a next this is
a balanced entity at that point it is
exactly 16 times 8 right because we've
got one 8 byte thing
and 15 8 light things so it's 16 times 8
light things which is 128 bytes 2 cache
lines everyone's favorite number of
cache lines because it's actually the
minimum number I think Zeon's pulling or
something anyway doesn't matter so we
can place these throughout the room when
we can just stack we can place them
throughout rooms and stack them up and
then when the room Jen generates them it
will place them in there some are
reasonable hopefully lots for a way to
do that specific thing meaning how we're
you know planning to actually make that
work right so let's see here
if we were to do that then we've got an
identity call that we'll have to work
with that that system see here ok so
when we call that identity call that's
going to return one of these entities
it's not really gonna do anything
specific it's gonna place it presumably
in a room but I don't know whether we
actually want to do that or not I feel
like you'd probably want to do something
more like this where you just said okay
you know place an entity in a room and
then that inserts it into that list you
know it's more of thing so that seems a
little bit more sensible to me all
things considered so then we were
basically say alright the room first
entity equals this entity and of course
we need to preserve that list so off we
go
those get stacked up into the room
everyone's happy to add an entity no big
deal right here's the entity as a
results that's just a push direct on the
temp memory cuz again this is all just a
temporary infrastructure we use for
analyzing the structure of the world so
we just want to grab one of these in
there we then want to take a look
well I think it just automatically
clears it so really that's it because we
wouldn't do anything else
and then I don't know it would be a lot
easier for us I suppose if we had some
extra stuff in here so I might say you
know maybe there is a tag cap and maybe
there's a Flags field you know I don't
know these really don't need to be quite
so large but you know I'm just saying
maybe we do something more like that and
that way when you add tags it's just
quicker we'll see so anyway then we've
got the notion that we want to add tags
to these things so when you add a
particular tag to an entity again you're
just passing the same set of stuff in
here's the entity you want to add the
tag - here's the asset tag ID and here's
the value and so that's just going to
make sure that the entity in question
only has a certain number of tags so
it's gonna want the tag count to be less
than the array account of the end of
these tags and then it's going to say
okay then the tags are added to like so
in this case I should probably write it
this way because we want an actual point
of the tag and then I'm going to take
the tag and set the ID and set the value
that pushes the tag on so now we could
play some of these put tags on the
entities put them in particular rooms in
this case we're going to do that right
here so we're gonna place the entity
like this and we're not going to pass it
there so that's all we're doing and once
we're done with that see here it's like
Europe bedroom
we really just have to go in and make it
so that these things actually get placed
in the world meaning when somebody
actually reads that list and sticks the
entities into the actual room you know
other than that not much else we have to
deal with see here okay uh here's our
option tiny just wanted to return that
in case people want to fuss with it
after the fact and off we go okay so now
we have the ability to place cats which
is something everyone wants to be able
to do especially shelters and there's an
important difference here which is that
one of our cats is a ghost so this is
Hannah and she's a ghost so we're gonna
add the ghost tag to Hannah because she
died she died a few years ago it wasn't
great anyway so once we've added these
entities in we're now almost done with
the system for placing entities
throughout the world kind of however we
wish and then the system can respect
those in different ways we still have a
couple things we haven't done and that
is adding options for when rooms can be
placed or when things can be placed in
various rooms so I feel like cats
probably wouldn't be in the hallway and
I don't know that the cats are going to
be in the save slots but otherwise they
could be in a lot of these places so I
would say I want to do what did I call
it a push option I'm gonna call it add
option instead I think so I'm gonna say
i want to add an option for the main
room to have cats in it right and the
other ones here would be maybe the
bedroom a b c
and D maybe maybe the tailor room maybe
the kitchen I don't know if I want them
to be outdoor cats maybe only one of
them is an outdoor cat I'm not sure or
maybe none of them are so I don't know
but I think that's mostly it in terms of
where they should probably be I at least
here right so I'm gonna add these
options here where we base say these are
rooms that the cats could be in and that
seems reasonable so then inside the
world gencode right we had a push oops
push option I'm gonna call that add
option instead and I'm gonna grab this
stuff and put it up above because we're
all this stuff gets used right
actually could be even higher than that
I think this is kind of like you know
it's like this kind of thing so I feel
like it kind of belongs more up here so
anyway that means we can add options to
the world right and I think I like that
syntax better too I think I like it
better this way so I'm just gonna make
it reversed but that seems good so that
adds those options and then it will pick
those options to put the cats in and so
I think if we run this actually it will
in theory place the cats at least once
we debug it
oh and that a search should be greater
than or equal to sorry I'm sorry less
than or equal to right it should be
assert that it's really a cert not the
thing that I was saying for so now it
should maybe in theory wants to debug it
it'll place the cats we won't actually
see any cats and the reason that we
wouldn't see any cats is because the
actual entity list never gets processed
by the room generation code so we will
have to add that it looks like for some
reason we didn't get any cats that's
really disheartening because we would
like more cats right so let's find out
why I'm also going to switch the debug
mode to make it easier for me to step
through Visual Studio doesn't really do
a very good job of stepping through
release mode code unfortunately so let's
go ahead and and oh I know why
I don't even really need to step through
it
we expanded our array we never actually
put the thing in it so we still need to
do this right so this allows us to add
an option and then we can make that
option be the room in question yeah I'm
saying I'll probably return that in case
we add framers to it that someone who
adds an option wants to be able to touch
so that should add our cat like our cat
request records so there we go we placed
Hana so now all of our cats are like
recorded as being somewhere in the world
but we inside the room generator now
need to actually put entities in when
they're requested so you know I'm gonna
take the simplest possible way right now
and we'll again we'll add much like this
route this is completely on worked on
the world generator is starting to
become a little bit more real like
there's actual logic in it and it's sort
of starting to look more like a thing
that's a real system for doing what it
does the generate room is still just
garbage and so I'm not gonna spend any
time on this part here yet because we're
gonna we're gonna do this whole part
much more seriously at some point when
we get to actual room gen stuff we care
about and so this I'm just gonna do the
stupidest possible thing which is to say
that here when we do we've got on lamp
right on boundary on connection so on so
on so anytime we add a traversable right
here I'm going to add an entity if we've
got an entity to add right
so the entities that you add to a room
will just literally stack up along the
top row well in this case would be the
bottom row of the room and that's just
where they'll go because again I don't
care and I just want to make sure that
the higher level codes working
eventually then we'll get into room
shaping which will be like a different
thing that we'll do when we get there so
here when we do the traversable we know
we can put it in the honest reverse well
if we want to so that's exactly what I'm
gonna do we'll start out by opening at
the start we know we've got a particular
room we know we have like a or a you
know an enemy or a pending entity let's
call it so we know we've got that first
entity it could be zero but you know
we're gonna check so if we're not on a
lamp and we add the traversable here
we're just gonna say look if there is a
pending entity we're gonna add the
pending entity and then we'll advance
the next one so if we want to add one of
these entities into the system we need
to add whatever the type of entity is
that we're actually looking at here
right so in the case of the cat we have
to actually add the cat so again we've
kind of got some there's probably an
additional piece of information that
we'll add to our gennadiy which is like
what the generator call is that adds
this thing and I'm not sure how I want
to do that but I don't really care right
now because that's not really yeah again
that's something that we can kind of
address later when we have more stuff we
care about because there's really no
information at the moment about how we
might want to do that so let me just go
ahead and jump up here and take a look
at what happens when you add in these to
the world right looks like this so what
I want to do is I want to be able to add
entities and then I want to be able to
add tags to the entities that come from
the list of tags that we specified there
uh you know it kind of occurs to me I
feel like we already okay here we go
so here's like for example the code that
adds a mon-star so if we want to add a
monster you know would look something
like this
so I'm pretty sure all we really wanted
to do I'm pretty sure all we really want
to do is just make this a little bit
more generic and then we just go from
there like if we want to add a Monstar
like it is a little bit harder because
like things like snakes that occupy
multiple squares are going to be harder
for us to place so we'll have to think a
little bit harder about those but most
things since they only occupy just the
one square would be really easy for us
to place so I'm gonna start with the
simpler case and we'll have to kind of
grow it out to work on the harder case
but if we look at what happens when you
place it entity it looks actually quite
simple so we've got like the world
position P and the standing on place
that's occupying right and so it looks
like you can kind of just do this where
you say this is where the thing is going
to be in the world and this is what its
going to stand on so it looks like we
kind of already know the end of the
position right it's this thing and so
it's going to get placed down here by
that call or this thing's a would get
placed down here by that call anyway I
don't know why we would have to specify
a P if we already specify a standing on
that's a little opaque to me why that
would occur
[Music]
so we'll have to think about that a
little bit more because I don't
understand why you would need to do that
and maybe you don't really need to do
that but that's sufficient so in this
case if we have a pending entity we're
just gonna like place the pending entity
here and off we go
I yeah I mean the other thing I guess I
would say is maybe we want to leave that
up to this system and if that's the case
then what we'd like to do is really have
something like this so we know that this
is what we would place or how we would
request the placement of an entity this
will do that addition and add the
various pieces here like so I don't
really know how much more of this there
would be for cats probably just the Buy
in the head but this is what it would
look like I don't really know that it
has hit points either but you know we'll
cross that bridge when I come to it so
this is a brain cat as well I'm not
going to add a brain to it at the moment
but eventually we probably would and
that is pretty much all there would be
for adding cat that means although we'll
call this directly here because all of
our entities are cats
we will then just make this a more
abstract way of specifying which what we
actually want to place a little further
down so here's how all of these
functions should I believe work and so
then we would say you know entity equals
add cat I don't know that there's
anything really else this is like the
place entity add cat I don't understand
the else we do other than spam the tags
on there so in here we wouldn't need to
do the occupying because that gets
in here and we wouldn't need you to
place entity because that gets done in
here so really all we would be talking
about is adding the tags that exist on
the pending entity so we'd really just
do something like this where we take
that array and we just say all right for
every for every one of these we just
push them on now looking here you know I
mean it's really just pretty basic right
we would just say here's the genin of
the tag if the pending entity tags plus
the tag index we would then just call
add tag on the place entity and we're
just effectively copying these over so
that adds all of those tags to the
entity and after they've already been
placed and in terms of adding the cat we
just need to pass it the traversable
which like su passed like that don't
actually know how you pass that to be
completely honest with you that we'll
have to see but looking at ad cat here
right we need to pass the other things
that we do know what they are so the
region the P and the standing on I just
don't know how you get a traversal
reference because I honestly don't
remember how you make those traversal
let's try and find out
[Music]
not seeing a lot of information there so
you've got an entity reference which
says which the which entity we're
talking about here and then you've got
an index which is the one inside the
entity so it's pretty easy to make one
of those but I don't know again like
that systems kind of old and we haven't
really done a lot with it so I'm not
sure how that wants to be done I mean I
guess it would be done like this right
where you say the traversable reference
is just zero zero and the entity that
we're talking about here is is this one
maybe and again I'm not really sure
the only reference in this case I guess
looks like that and the only thing I
don't know is so the entity ID though is
not filled out in this case which is
less good because we don't really know
what that entity ID would necessarily be
although I guess we can just fill that
out as well is there a way to just
reference an MB but don't we have a
function to like make one of these stuff
needs to get overhauled
so no that's kind of seat-of-the-pants
there don't love any of that stuff I
feel like that stuff could get cleaned
up quite a bit now but one thing that
I'm so placing one of these things would
work like this and this call will be
something that I think we then turn into
a function pointer so when you play
something you could just say this is the
function I would like to create my
entity at you know at such time as we
actually go to create it in in practice
right um so now we probably love to step
through the codes somewhat to find out
if these entities are getting placed but
it looks like they are right because if
I go now in here you can see that we've
got Fred is there right although there's
some really weird stuff happened I think
with with I don't know if that's
z-fighting or some other weird thing
that's happening with them let me go
ahead and
you
so some weird things happening although
and it looks like really most of it just
that he like he's not structured
particularly correctly so he's kind of
flattened on top of each other which is
not particularly great there but it
looks like we've placed two cats for
some reason we're getting both threads
which is not correct right we should
have been getting so there's a Hana but
we should have been getting a gray tabby
and we're not getting a gray tabby so we
got all three cats placed and that
system does seem to be working properly
except for the fact that we're not
actually singing one of the cats ah you
know why because it's one is a grit it's
because we didn't pass those tags we
just said tabby so actually that's our
fault right so when we go to place this
tabby here what we really wanted to do
is probably specify in here maybe even
take this out so we may want to do like
a place cat and say that it's you know a
Burman and then here we want to say
that this is a gray and here we would
want to say so so now we've got one
ghost firm in one brown tabby and one
gray tabby and I guess technically we're
going in the right ad active order it
would look like that
that's a volume that's an entity and so
now we are correctly I think doing all
of the entity placement there so when we
start off in the world here we do have
so there's one ghost Hannah there's one
brown Fred
and then there's well no no we're still
we're still wrong there yep typos abound
the code can only be as good as the
parameters you pass it folks
um so let's try more time so there's a
Molly there is a Fred and hopefully
we'll get a hand up here if there's a
Hana so that's good and at this point
we've got that envy placement stuff that
seems to be working roughly the way I
would want so really what we need you
now is just expand that slightly to have
the notion of a call in there that's
gonna be specific to the type of entity
being placed so in here where we do Jen
entity we're gonna have some kind of a
callback which is like you know type def
entity star and I guess I'll do my
standard defined trick here which is
just this is like an entity generator or
like this is a create Kennedy call
something like that you know I'm saying
and so one of these is just something
it's anything that returns an ende and
takes the same parameters as our place
cat call right where is our place cat
call nope I'm sorry not place cat add
the cat so it's basically that so you
pass it a sim region in the world
position and traversable that should go
on and you know that's what it does so
that
is going to be on the entity struct it's
like a thing that we then have gender
identity and then like this is the
creator and so when we we make one of
these we're just gonna say look that's
the function that you actually want to
call and so in place of calling add cat
here what we're gonna do instead is call
whatever the pending entity said we
should call to create the thing and
that's what's going to create it so now
if we ran this we would just crash right
because there is no that is not it's
just a zero right so we would try to
call a zero so in order to restore the
functionality but now we've made it so
we can do whatever we want we just need
our fleet I'm sorry our add cat call
here to be a Jen entity Jen create
entity call add cat like so so that it
fits the particular function prototype
they're looking for and then inside
world Jen whenever we do a place cat we
just need to make sure that the thing
that gets placed when we place cat knows
that the thing should be a cat so I'm
gonna say that the add entity called
generally speaking to encourage good
behavior takes a create entity callback
that's what needs to do the entity
creation and so that will always be set
so we don't end up jumping into no-man's
land okay
so we then need our calls like add cat
to be things that are generally
available and since that's sort of since
we have like world Jen room Jen I think
at this point we need entity Jen right
so I think we need like in the code
directory we need like handmade entity
Jen dot H and dot C here's our H
here's what see and so all of this stuff
should really go in there in my opinion
right so all of this lamps familiars
blah blah blah blah blah right whatever
that is that all goes in here and this
stuff is given like primacy over when
we're doing the Chen stuff there's an
M&amp;E Chen the codes in here and the same
is true in here right and then we can
move similarly this stuff here out see
where did I have that stuff right here
so this stuff that was previously you
know stuffed in there is now its own
sort of space that can exist outside of
it now everything should kind of be
properly bucketed so we can think about
what we're doing at Yin time
um so that allows us I believe to just
make whatever we want so we can make
things that add whatever random stuff we
want to add and it will just work which
I think concludes the placement series
of things so now I think we're on to the
proper construction side of things which
is to say that that does not look like a
cat because the head and the bite well
first of all it's enormous
start with that the head in the body
aren't lined up right blah blah blah
right so now we're kind of we need to
work on the entity construction part of
this process right so that's something
that we kind of want to work on here so
let's pop over doing that and this is
where I said I might stop today but we
got about 50 minutes left so we might as
well just start with some of the light
treatment that we might want to do here
and we can then move on a little later
to whatever we want to do that's more
serious later right so we can start with
some basics which is that well you know
the scale of cats is just going to be
the scale of cats
so really you know whatever this is
supposed to be here just is what it is
so at some level we don't really have to
do much work because I think our system
already allows us to make things as big
as we want them to be and so if we just
scale these things a little bit
differently we would end up with cats
that are appropriately sized right and
similarly if we float them a little bit
above you can see they're kind of
interpenetrating there if we make them
higher up off the ground that'd help as
well and again I'm not really sure what
we want to do about that necessarily but
for right now what I can do is elevate
elevate them up off the ground so we can
see them so this will be both of their
pieces are just kind of floating above
where they are I should probably
instantiate them in our room it would
make them easier to see but so there you
can see me walk in there there you can
see a more normal looking Fred right and
there's a couple of things that we want
to be able to do there his body I'm
sorry that's Molly
so her you can see that the body is now
a more reasonable size the head maybe
isn't exactly and so we might want to
adjust those two things separately and
just kind of get the relative sizes
correct and I could even position them
correctly after that but that that once
we get to that that gets more into the
sort of align point stuff that I want to
talk about separately which we can then
go from there
so let me go ahead and do two things one
let me raise the head slightly above the
body because it should be right and two
let me make the head a little bit
smaller than the body because you know
it should be and there's a couple of
things we may have to do we may have to
respect sizes a little bit more then
we're doing right now so I may have to
go look and see how we want do that as
well because these two things it's hard
to say I don't remember if we're
respecting sizes correctly in things so
let's see
about that anyway so looking in here
right I feel like the head should have
been raised up a little higher and it
wasn't I'm not sure why right that
should place the head higher up because
that's a Z offset I thought so like that
for example it should be clearly above
and the fact that it wasn't clearly
above is a little odd so I'm wondering
if maybe is that not being used somehow
and again this entity stuff we're gonna
have to go and and cleaned up because we
it's kind of always been an afterthought
so now that is you can see that it's got
a Z offset now right floating up there
so I'm not sure why that wouldn't have
been sufficient I think even one point
one should have been enough to see it
floating above and I guess part of
that's you know the Z obviously is
modified by the Z bias program and so on
so there's that but we'll see so anyway
yeah so that seems a little bit more
correct now and so yeah there's the cat
and it seems fine
certainly more fine than our current cat
giant weird hopping cat that is not
supposed to even be a cat so I think
mostly the stuff there is now about
aligning things in particular ways so I
think that's a good place to stop for
today just trying to think if I should
if I should bother going further into
that
I don't feel like I should
and you can kind of see like we're
getting some different weird things
they're like different sized things so I
think we want to respect size more I
should probably go do that maybe I could
do that in 15 minutes just to get the
size stuff being correctly proportional
to the sizes that are in the files so
that's something we would like to do and
yeah so let's we can think about that
but you know we're kind of opening up a
bunch of things we can start doing now
and I'm not sure which of them we want
to work on first but one of the things
that I would like to do maybe is just
see here about inside like inside the
actual system that that renders the
entities I'm thinking also you know if
the things a ghost it should get alpha
or something I mean just as an example
and we probably wouldn't quite do
exactly that in the future but you know
something to that effect so when we go
to do an entity render here what I would
like to do is look and see you know if
this cat is a ghost then it's going to
it's going to have its alpha affected by
that so one way to do that here would be
like say hey you know we did whatever
this match vector here is tells us if
it's a ghost or not so we could do
something like I don't know if there's
an alpha value that comes through here
probably not so you can see there's
probably a color right here and what we
could do is say look color it's going to
be x equals whatever the tag value is on
ghost for this entity so match vector
and the ghost tag
so just looking at whatever that is one
- the ghost tag is going to multiply
impure so if something is a ghost tag
you know it would ghost out now I don't
want it to become completely invisible
when it's completely a ghost I want to
maybe be you know just a little bit
invisible when it's a ghost or something
like this so well you know it'd be
something more like that so that way in
theory now ghost cats are translucent I
mean that's what you would expect a
ghost cat to be I would think I don't
really know but let's just assume and
and now they are right and I think
that's better because you know if I go
into a room when I see a ghost cat
that's what a ghost cat should look like
in my mind a ghost cat shouldn't look
like a regular cat because ghost cats
are ghosts for a reason
so again just some little things like
that that also should be taken care of
and so anything that's a ghost in the
game should probably have some effects
on it that's just a simple effect
throught now it's probably not the one
we'd use in the final but it's close
enough for now
so yeah I think we're down to a line
points and sizing looking at sizing I
think is the first thing I would want to
do so the thing that we've got that
currently happens with sizing is when we
push an actual sprite on here here so
what happens here where we do the bitmap
dimension stuff right you can see us
sort of playing with it here we don't
well there's a lot of things we don't do
when we go to push a bitmap on what you
can see happening is we use the bitmap
dimension to figure out what the aspect
ratio should be to make sure that we
always get the aspect ratio correct
right and this is a good thing what we
don't do is figure out how big this
thing should be based on any bitmap
dimensions right and that is potentially
a problem and potentially not it really
depends on how you want to look at it so
if we imagine that most art assets in
the end would want to be scaled up to
maximally put detail
into the space available for the texture
then really what we're talking about
here is some intrinsic value that tells
us how big this thing would have been
relative to other things its size right
relative to other things sizes I should
say so what we're really talking about
is we want to have something in addition
to the width over the height which tells
us how to correlate those two things we
would want something that tells us how
to correlate the incoming size of the
thing we said we wanted versus the size
the things should be according the art
assets right and this is just a way of
saying look if I say that something
should be 1.0 in terms of scale well
something that was small at a scale of
1.0 and something that was large at a
scale of 1.0 should come out to
different sizes that's really the only
sane way to have the game treat art
assets uniformly but have them come out
different sizes based on how big they
should have been in the input
so right now we don't have that piece of
information and we kind of need it right
we need something that tells us what
that was otherwise we can't really
process it and if we look back at our
file formats right then what we have is
we have a dimension of the bitmap which
says how big the bitmap is in terms of
storage area and then we have an aligned
percentage right we should also have a
width over height here but I guess we
just get that from this dimension so
nowhere in here do we actually store any
information about how big the thing
should have been right we just don't
have that information and it would be
nice if we did have that information
because we liked ideally have a way to
adjust sizes of things based on whatever
their input size worth maybe or maybe we
just want to be able to do that sizing
after the fact right
that's my thinking anyway
so I feel like we really want an
additional piece of information there
and that additional piece of information
is like a scale factor that gets applied
that's what I'm thinking
so roughly what we would do is we'd say
all right what was the input size and
this well actually no we probably
wouldn't do anything what we'd probably
do is we just import the data as we
imported it and then we would size the
thing ourselves on import till we
adjusted the size to be what we wanted
it to be you know what I mean
that's probably what we would do and
then we would just say look that's the
sizes so the alignments and the sizes
would just be things that we adjust when
we first import that asset in and then
the asset even if it gets updated we'll
just retain that size every time you re
imported right so I think that's good
[Music]
and I think that's probably what I want
to do I'm not going to tackle that now
so I think we are towards the end so I'm
gonna go to the QA and we will tackle
that stuff next weekend when our goal
will be to place I guess most of our
entities into the world as examples and
get their sizes and appearances to be
correct
justice would or could you add the
values the cat pieces into the two big
data lists and from there drag the
values to liven at the cats I think you
already made those features long ago yes
that is actually probably roughly what
we are going to do something along those
lines do you have a video where you talk
in depth about the construction of meow
hash I didn't find it on YouTube no I
have not put anything on you know hash
video wise but it's pretty
straightforward if you look at the code
are you offended that we named our cat
Miura Tori no I'm honored I love cats
cats are awesome so if there's a cat
named after me I am pleased
can you talk about some of your plans on
the AI amenities and what options you're
considering
so there's not really gonna be any AI on
entities so entities are supposed to be
arcade-style if that makes sense so
they're generally supposed to do
patterns that the player can like
predict so to the extent that there is
AI if you choose to call it that it
really is an AI so much as its pattern
execution so the entities are supposed
to kind of like do specific sets of
actions that the player predicts like it
knows you know that this kind of entity
when it sees you like charges at you or
whatever and you know that like this
other kind of entity like randomly
weights amount of time and then like
bounces at you or something right so
there shouldn't be any like AI in the
game that's you know doing something
that could be considered like
intelligent because that's would ruin
the feel like the feel is supposed to
it's opposed really like Arkady like an
arcade game not like a like a immersive
like simulation feeling thing offended
if they missed the opportunity to name
the cat per Ettore I'm not offended but
I do agree that that would have would
have been a step up right purgatory is
great cat see per Ettore also great I
mean who could argue with that
and again the AI thing just to be clear
on that it's that's a stylistic decision
it's not a technical decision it's just
the type of game that you're making if
you're making an arcade game you
generally don't want to specify a lot of
things that like the goal of artificial
intelligence generally is to sort of
confound the player to a certain extent
meaning it's supposed to feel more like
you were playing against a human right
so it's supposed to make decisions that
maybe you don't necessarily exactly
understand or maybe do things that might
be considered clever or or respond to
your behavior and those are not things
that I want in this game meaning like
nothing in this game should be like
learning about what you are doing or
taking actions based on expectations
about what you've done in the past and
those are the kind of things that you
would normally consider AI and this game
is not supposed to feel that way it's
supposed to feel like the things in the
world are very like simple simple
organic beings that just have a
particular reflex right they're very
like innate and they just only do
exactly what you would expect them to do
and the difficulty in the game comes
from you trying to look at a particular
screen go these are the patterns that I
know will occur so I'm gonna do this
because that's the most effective way to
thwart those patterns or accomplish the
objective I'm trying to accomplish given
that I know those patterns will happen
right and of course is not always
possible for the player to really be
that thorough about it because as you
get enough enemies on the screen their
patterns become fairly unpredictable to
a certain extent as well so that chaos
is fine - I know I'm not saying the you
know we have to keep it to the player
could perfectly predict it's going to
happen or anything but generally
speaking it used supposed to be case
that like if it's just a player and one
or two entities they should not have to
guess about what's gonna happen there
should be should be very clear like oh I
know these things patrol back and forth
and I know this thing will charge at me
when it sees me and you know it that
should be the the way that the player is
reasoning about the world that should be
very consistent and if that's ever not
the case it should only be like one
maybe there's like you know a specific
type of entity that's that was smart if
we ever did any AI at all it would only
be like very specific for some I don't
think we will because I can't think of
any reason why I want that in there but
you know it would be a very isolated
incident if we put in anything that
would be considered like an AI style
thing
see you're fairly optimistic in your
ex-patients a serious thing don't expect
to be done for two years what are some
of the topics if taken long as expected
actually nothing's taken longer than
expected and the two years is right on
target the only thing that I messed up
was when I was computing the two years
because I said two things I was like 600
episodes is how many we're gonna do so
it'll take two years for some reason in
my head I was like thinking 300 ish days
a year of episodes so 600 is two years
but we only do either five or two
episodes a week depending on the
circumstance which means that it's more
like five or six years to get 600
episodes so we're more or less exactly
where I thought we would be which is to
say that we're on Episode four 85 and I
said there'd be 600 I still think that's
roughly how many they'll be you know I
might be more or less if there were 700
episodes I wouldn't consider myself that
far off in the estimate but that's just
the reality of doing it this slowly you
know normally you program you program
many hours a day here I get four hours a
week it's just not very many hours so I
would say yeah there was really no
optimism was pretty realistic and so far
it seems about right I don't we'll see
where we were at on days 600 if I was in
the ballpark or not you know maybe we're
on day 600 and we're nowhere near done
you know
how did you approach redrawing small
parts of the screen in an immediate mode
GUI
well immediate mode really doesn't have
anything to do with whether you're
redrawing the small part of the screen
or a large part of screen right it's
just how you decided to iterate so in an
iamb GUI right
you're just you've got a structure and
you have a way of looking up where you
are in the structure that is code rather
than data right so at each branch where
you go I'm gonna draw this panel now you
can just do a lookup to say do I need to
draw this panel now and the answer is no
you just don't touch it
right another way to say it is you do it
exactly the same way that you would do
it in RM GUI they're really not
different they're just different API is
to the same system right and I'm GUI is
a different interface but it doesn't
imply a different structure you could
create a complete in fact I've often
said you can take an RM GUI library and
create and I'm GUI interface out of it
I've actually done that I did that once
for a QT app where you could I am you
know have an IM interface and then what
would do is it would build the structure
out of the IM calls look at the
structure that existed in QT and modify
all the things that it needed to to
basically sync them together right so I
am gooeys an interface paradigm it's not
an implementation paradigm the
implementation can be anything you want
and if you want something that's more
retained in terms of implantation
because you decided that's better you
can just do it it's really not
complicated the goals you seen are
trying to inspire the next generation of
game engine parents how successful do
you feel the series has been on that
front remarkably successful far more
than I thought it would be actually I
receive emails so I had to I kind of
buried my email address because I was
getting so many emails from people about
the series and them going into game
programming or getting a job and getting
pregnant cuz of the series that I just
got overwhelmed by them so I buried my
email and even with the email there's
only one place got the email now and
it's in like the it's a business email
I still get email routinely like every
week from people who are like I got a
job doing like Louisville programming
after watching the series and this sort
of stuff so it's been like way more
successful than I thought it would be
which is great I think I mean it's hard
to know how necessary it is to have low
level programmers in the world but from
my perspective we need a lot more of
them so having people getting into that
and getting jobs and doing it for a
living I think is really good
personally toxification could you please
explain again what does volatile do sure
volatile is a pretty simple concept but
it's very widely misunderstood largely
because people I think so in that same
way that like low level programming is
not very common these days people tend
to think of things dogmatically or in
terms of abstract concepts they've been
told not in terms of what something
actually does and that makes it very
difficult for them to understand
something like volatile because volatile
is not really an abstract concept it's
very concrete so volatile tells the
compiler that the piece of code it
happens to be compiling at that time is
not necessarily the only one that will
modify the value in question and that is
all it does so if I say int X and the
compiler is compiling code that
references X the compiler implicitly
assumes that the piece of code is
compiling is the only thing that is
touching X so if it compiles the code X
plus equals one it assumes that the
value before and after that statement
are whatever X was and then whatever X
was plus 1 right
if you insert a volatile so you have a
volatile index instead of a regular
index now when the compiler compiles
that code it assumes that the value of x
after X plus equals one is arbitrary who
knows what it is it knows that it will
write back the X plus equals one to the
location where X belongs and then it
will have to read it again to find out
what it is
the next time X is referenced right so
volatile is a way of preventing the
compiler from making assumptions about
the values of variables that are marked
volatile and it tells the compiler that
every time you operate on a value marked
volatile you must read it into a
register and write it back out again
after you are done because other people
are simultaneously modifying this thing
that's all it does so it's imperative to
recognize that when you were doing
multi-threaded programming you need to
use volatile in a lot of circumstances
because you need to tell the compiler it
cannot rely on the value of this thing
being the same as it was because other
threads are touching it but it's also
imperative to understand that that is
the only thing that volatile does
volatile does not synchronize access to
that variable so you must still use
locking or locked operations in order to
access that variable because otherwise
you can get race conditions if you don't
know what you're doing right so volatile
is one tool in a set of tools necessary
to make multi offender code work
properly and it's crucial that you
understand what it does and does not do
if you're doing a lobster point if
you're not doing multi-threaded
programming you never need to know what
volatile is ever it's completely
unrelated if you're not doing much
started programming however
multi-threaded programming can sometimes
mean things you don't think it means for
example if there is hardware in a system
and that hardware is sort of effectively
executing its own threads and can modify
values in main memory that is the case
where volatile might be important right
so you may have liked its give me very
simple let's suppose there's a keyboard
controller that operates asynchronously
on a particular piece of hardware right
so you don't have to call a function to
read from it or do anything else that
would clue the compiler in that it could
change you just know that the main
memory contents may spontaneously change
to reflect the fact that a key was
pressed right well there's another case
you need volatile because if you don't
tell the compiler that this memory range
could just be spontaneously changed by
somebody then the first time you read it
it may just think well I know what it is
and I know that no one's changed it so
the next time I read it I don't need to
read it again I know it hasn't changed
because I'm looking at this piece of
code on compiling and I can see we're in
a loop here looking at the space of
memory and I know that no one's touched
it because I'm looking at the code and
no one touched it right so again multi
thread can mean more than just the
threads you write it includes any type
of execution unit that exists anywhere
in the system write an interrupt handler
a asynchronous piece of hardware a
separate bus that can reach over and
touch main memory all of that stuff
would induce volatility and things that
have that characteristic must be marked
volatile in order for the code to work
otherwise the compiler may accidentally
compile out work that it should have
compiled in because it thinks something
can't change when really it can
hopefully that makes some sense
Poul future with explaining the Maya
question I aimed less at the
implementation but the thought process
that goes behind it do you know of a
good resource to read up on how hashes
are generally constructed how you design
them so they produce low clearing rates
and how do you quality check them
actually no I don't so the interesting
thing about hashes is they really aren't
well understood in my opinion so
basically there's two types
Tosh's there's cryptographic and non
cryptographic there's some work that has
been done on cryptographic hashes that
has to do with things that you might be
able to do in terms of proving their
strengths and that in a sense is a way
of looking at hash design that is
systematic but the kind of hash that
meow hash is which is a practical hash
non cryptographic there really isn't
much known about good ways to implement
those because the definition is bizarre
the definition of what makes a good hash
for non cryptographic purposes is one
where the data that isn't expected to
hash will not collide right because
fundamentally speaking what you're
talking about we talk about a hash is
you're talking about compression
function it's a function that compresses
compresses a large amount of data
usually into a small amount of data so
it's something that takes I don't know
10k of data and represents it in 128
bits we know from information theory
that there is no way to represent 10k of
data any set of 10k of data in 128 bits
which means that all hash functions are
equally bad I'll say that again
all hash functions are effectively
equally bad why because information
theory tells us that every hash function
is exactly as bad as representing its
inputs as every other hash function now
I'm not an information theorist so
correct me if I'm wrong on that but
that's my read on information theory
there is no way to construct an
arbitrarily good hash functions they are
all equally good or bad however you want
to look at it they all have exactly the
same arbitrary provable quality which is
to say that all of them are bad at
representing data because there's no way
to represent 10-k data in HoN 28 bits
right um now I should couch that a
little bit to say that it's not really
true because I could write a function
that I call a hash that just returns
zero and obviously that's worse than a
hash that actually returns all 128 bits
worth
data so what I should say is there is
sort of a way to assess a hash function
and say that some hash foot patches are
objectively bad because they are unable
to produce an even distribution from the
distribution that comes in right
meaning that all of the messages that
come in if almost all of the possible
inputs to the hash all map to zero
that's objectively a worst hash function
than one that can actually produce a
message that maps to all possible 128
bits so there is one way you could look
at hash and say there is a quality that
you would like to get which is that you
want to use all possible 128 bits worth
of output right because if you don't use
the complete range of output then your
hash is objectively worse than a hash
that did but assuming that your hash can
produce all possible values of the
128-bit 64 bit 32 bit whatever the
output of ash is assuming that that's
true then they're all equally bad and
the reason that they're all equally bad
is because each one Maps the input
message space redundantly somehow onto
that 100 set of 128-bit values whether
one of them is good or bad for a
particular purpose just depends on which
set of messages you will input to the
hash because I can always take a given
hash and pick messages that will collide
right and furthermore the number of
messages that will collide should be the
same for every hash right because you
know that the total number of outputs of
the hash is 2 to the 128 that means that
that the number of collisions for every
hash that can produce the full range of
128 bits of output is the same they all
have the same never collisions so the
only question is do they have the same
number of collisions on the data we care
about so that's what I think makes
hashes particularly hard to read to
reason about non cryptographically
because non cryptographic hashes are
about what are the chances that the type
of data you will feed too it will
collide and we have no idea who knows
right I mean the way to look at it would
be we'd need to take a large corpus see
what the sorts of structures of the
messages are that are in that corpus and
then say which hashes do a good job of
spreading those out very diffusely so
that changes that are likely to occur
between two similar messages will result
in different 128-bit values I mean
that's really it so there's some
properties that we can say probably are
ones we want generally speaking we would
want a bit that changes in the input to
change all the bits in the output or as
many of them as we can make happen right
we want messages that are the same but
in different orders to produce different
hashes you know things that we can
generally say are true about the kinds
of inputs that we're feeding it that's
really all I can really say there's not
a lot more that I feel like you can
really say in the abstract about non
cryptographic hashes cryptographic
hashes are much more well understood in
a sense and the reason for that is
because they have a real model for what
they're trying to prevent a
cryptographic hash is trying to prevent
someone from spoofing a hash value
so what they're trying to do is look at
how difficult it is to work backwards
from a particular hash to a particular
input or set of inputs that's actually
much easier in my opinion of a problem
statement because you actually have some
idea of what you're trying to do an on
cryptographic hash is both easier to
make by accident than a cryptographic
hash and harder to define rigorously
there is no attacker in a non
cryptographic hash we don't know what
their motivations are and we
certainly don't know how to look at a
function and tell what a non
cryptographic hash really needs to do
right and so while it's true we could
just say well a cryptographic hash this
probably has to have properties that
would be good for non cryptographic
hashing so in that sense they're sort of
equivalent in a sense that's really not
true like we don't really have any real
reason to think in that way it just kind
of happens that if it's hard to figure
out collisions then therefore it must
also be unlikely that they could happen
by accident
I guess right but it's just really hard
and I think that that that problem is
you know it's just non cryptographic
hashes are just a really ill-defined
problem because by definition their goal
is to make it unlikely that particular
corpuses will collide and that's just
not very well-defined it's just an
intrinsic property of the corpus you
could you could you could almost think
of non cryptographic hashes a lot like
image filters they're good if they work
good on the images that you have you
know I mean that's what they are and
they don't end it's very similar to
compression like I said compression is
good if it happens to do a good job
compressing the input and that's all you
can really say about it there's there's
a few little parts of it that follow the
same thing as like the hash where you
can look at them and say well given that
we want to encode some set of symbols
then we can say things about the
optimality of the encoding and the same
is true for hashes if we decide that we
want
generally speaking modifications of bits
to affect all the bits in the hash we
can then say how good a particular hash
is at doing that but that doesn't speak
to whether the thing is effective for
the particular corpus really right and
so it's just a very it's much like
compression it's just a very ill-defined
concept and there's a lot more black art
to it I think
then then science really although
obviously there is some science to it
exactly like compression so that's what
I'd say all that being said I'm not a
hashed construction guy I happened to
figure out a good hash it was largely
luck
looking through the rest of questions
here do you happen to know how different
embedded C programming is compared to
simple C programming they're basically
the same except for you have more hard
Hardware constraints like timing number
of cycles that you have to do things in
the amount of memory is tightly
constrained and so on but in other ways
they're a lot more fun because you know
exactly what you're doing and I like
that one of the most annoying things
about program windows is specifically
that I don't know how much memory I have
to work with B I have no idea how cycles
are counted or how they're going to be
applied see I have no idea when the
operating systems going to interrupt me
D I have no idea what else is running on
the system and blah blah blah blah so
embedded program is actually a lot more
satisfying even though it's more
limiting because sometimes those limits
are very refreshing you know what's
going on and a lot of times you have a
lot more control or system so I would
say that it's six of one half-dozen to
the other there are some parts that you
don't get to do like can't just allocate
huge blocks of memory and party on it
like we can on a Windows machine because
you always have just gobs and gobs
memory to work with but you do have
situations where you know how much
memory you have and you do you can make
decisions about it's reasonable you
don't have to show up and go well there
might be this much there might not be
this much I don't know the operating
system might be doing this it might be
doing that right that's where we're
adding a fun section of handmade network
to be a viable short-term solution hami
Network us already funded by a fund it's
right here the handmade hero fund or the
handmade fund I should say allows you to
contribute and we have been funding
things CDBG would definitely be next on
our list the problem right now for it is
I don't think we can provide any
realistic amount of money to them that
would really help at this point the
handmade fund just isn't big enough for
that you know right now we traffic in a
few hundred dollars it would need to be
several thousand dollars before we could
really provide anyone what would amount
to be a living wage for doing things
like CDBG so we have this option
available there just we don't the level
of contributions for stuff like that
just isn't that large so
that's good I understand Thanks I just
wasn't talked about the volatile I just
wasn't sure because the wiki says do not
use it for inter thread communication um
yes so I guess what I would say about
that is there's a lot of misinformation
floating around there about volatile
that if you want one of the main reasons
to treat stack overflow as a purely
random resource that may have some
things to think about but never taken as
actual answers if you look at the kinds
of things that are said about volatile
on there they're almost all wrong yes it
is true that volatile doesn't solve your
inter thread communication problems
because that's not what it does it is
also not true that it isn't for inter
thread communication it absolutely is
volatile is a crucial component of inter
thread communication and without it
internet communication won't work I if
you're trying to say - - you tap two
threads that need to share access to a
particular piece of information you had
better be marked volatile otherwise you
can probably just compile it straight on
out right so it's crucial to understand
what it doesn't it doesn't do is a very
important tool for multi-threaded
programming it's just not the only tool
and so I think a lot of times when
people get confused is they've been
warned about volatile not doing
everything for them that's not the same
as saying it's not necessary it is but
no it doesn't solve the problem it's
just one part of the solution to an
inter thread communication problem
Lori master a really good lossy
compressor is a decent hash function
absolutely that's 100% correct you could
think of a hash function as a very very
lossy but hopefully good lossy
compressor
you mentioned many times you're not a
game designer and that it would be ideal
if Tom Flo would design the game do you
plan on having him on an episode or two
to talk about gameplay related stuff
specifically relate to the zine he seems
to be very pressing I imagine proper
game design does not just happen like a
dare to yeah so no I am NOT putting up
doing that and specifically because
that's not really the hard part of game
design so you know the extent to which
John could contribute abstract guidance
to the game is stuff that I can that I
could do myself because that is not hard
that's more like game criticism or game
reviewing and game thinking about games
and that's actually stuff I'm
comfortable with the part of game design
that is hard and the part that for
example John excels at is the actual
work of experimenting and deciding on
experiments in the game and that is not
something that you do by having someone
just take a look at something and make
some comments right that's not what that
is and so I think it would be great if
John did streams where he shows how he
does game design work in that way that
would be a wonderful educational
resource but it would be in depth and it
would be involved it's not a two-day
thing it's a many day thing showing lots
of hard work being done just like the
engine work in handmade Hiro it's it's
significant it takes a time investment
very specific expertise and skills and
it's not something you can just drop by
for a day and do that's not what that is
we're pretty much the end of screaming I
don't know if there's any Martin's there
are attackers for non crypto hashes hash
table lookups can lead to denial service
attacks when attackers can control the
data coming into a system well so I
would classify that as a cryptographic
hash though like if you have an attacker
it's a cryptographic problem to me so I
don't think of that as being a non
cryptographic hash if you're using a
hash for purposes related to data that
an attacker can control then you have a
cryptographic hash scenario right that
that is what that is
so it's no longer appropriate to be
choosing from a non cryptographic hash
period that's my opinion on it obviously
Martin's your opinion may differ and I
would totally respect that but that's
just not the way I think of it if that
makes sense so I almost think of the
definition of a non cryptographic versus
cryptographic hash is are they suitable
for use in a case where there's an
attacker and so attacker in this case
means anyone who can cause damage to the
system by controlling an input to the
system and that totally includes data
coming in for a denial service attack
right
I don't know if that makes sense but
[Music]
mash is based on a es so in a way it
uses crypto Tec yeah so the way to think
about that would be AES is the cheapest
instruction on a current CPU that can
mix bits and that's what uses it so it
definitely uses crypto tech but doesn't
really necessarily use them in a crypto
way and so while it does take advantage
of the S boxes in order to get
propagation of bits out from individual
bits 128-bit lanes I have taken no care
to try and make sure that that happens
in a cryptographically secure way so it
is assumed at least by me although I
have not undertaken any sort of attempt
to prove it
but I don't believe that there is
therefore any cryptographic security to
it because the way in which the AES bit
mixing is used in male hash is not
cryptographically secure in fact I'm
quite I'm fairly sure it's good
graphically insecure meaning that
someone wanted to reverse the me on hash
process probably could or could at least
in some circumstances and so it's not
equivalent to the way that AES is used
in a cryptographic scenario at all
alright let me just stick last questions
here
there's too many questions the SMS or
github repo talks about percentages of
bias and distribution for a hash what do
those mean so it depends on what exactly
you're talking about in any given part
of a hash test suite but generally
speaking what we mean by bias and
distribution is that you have an input
to a hash and then the hash outputs its
hash value usually it's compressive but
sometimes it's not so sometimes you can
hash eight bits and turn in 228 bits
right the meow - for example supports
every size from eight bits up to 2 to
the 64th right so who knows
but generally speaking you're typically
hashing more with a data hash anyway so
you're typically Aisling at least a few
k maybe a few megabytes even or even
gigabytes depending on the circumstance
and your training in 220 bits so what we
talk about when we talk about bias and
distribution is that if you look at that
input if I want to talk about a specific
bit in the input and I change that bit
right then there's a question about how
those bits might correlate to other bits
to two bits in the output right so if I
change a bit in the input and I look in
the hash output and I see that like only
one other bit changes you would say that
that has a lot of bias or that the
distribution is very bad for example
right because it means that certain
ranges of your inputs produce very
predictable range than your outputs that
makes sense whereas if I flip bits in
the input and just random bits change in
the output that seem to have no
correlation to which bit I'm flipping or
no predictable one anyway
you would say that that's very unbiased
right or that it has a very good
distribution if I feed bunch of inputs
in and they all come out totally
randomly I can't find any correlation
its distributing very well right so
basically the idea is just to say that
depending on what you're measuring and
bias and distribution could be used in
different ways when you're talking about
hash so I'm not it depends on exactly
where they were using it but generally
speaking what you're and
is that set of correlations I have a
certain set of inputs I'm going to make
a structured series of changes to those
inputs I'm then gonna look at the
distribution of hash keys and see our
hash outputs and see whether there's a
bias to them well distributed outputs
imply that there is not a bias right
because a well distributed set of
outputs should not let me identify
correlations to things I'm doing the
inputs whether that's flipping bits
changing the order of things right and
so on Jonathan Blow mean offender mark
that one should never use the standard
i/o functions but always use OS specific
i/o functions I do not know why and I
can't stop thinking about why it could
be do you know why he could be talking
about Junichi bearing thanks you would
have to ask him for his motivation for
saying that but obviously there's a lot
of reasons not to use standard i/o
functions and the main reasons not to
use Sanrio functions usually are because
it's an extra layer of indirection that
could do all sorts of things you may not
want to do number one when you're
actually creating a data stream of some
kind
most of the flags that you're provided
by a standard i/o don't map exactly to
the i/o flags of the actual hardware
that's underlying enough the hardware
operating system that's underlying so
for example if you're going to call open
or F open you will have a much more
restricted set of options that you could
use generally speaking then if you call
create file on Windows which gives you a
lot of other options right so that's
number one is in direct mapping that
reduces functionality number two there
may be buffering or unwanted
transformations of the input or unwanted
copies of the input that are unnecessary
introduced by the layer so if you call
for example F open and then you use F
right or if read you will oftentimes be
going through an intermediate buffer
which just adds an extra copy for no
reason that is not necessary right and
so typically speaking you don't want to
do that for no reason because unless you
actually want the buffering you're just
wasting the CPUs time and making your
i/o slower for no reason number three
you
using resources that don't actually need
to be there so if you take a file
pointer that's opened by F open or a
file descriptor open by open that's
necessarily maintaining a table or a
structure interior to the C runtime
library that itself then has to maintain
a pointer to the operating systems
version anyway in order to issue the
real calls so essentially what you're
doing is you're creating a management
layer that's using up extra resources
and taking extra time extra cash space
etc etc for doing nothing other than
forwarding your i/o functions to the
correct actual place right those are
some reasons don't know whether any of
those were the ones that he was thinking
of but they might be all right thank you
everyone for joining me for an episode
of hand made here it has been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to follow along the series at home
you can always pair the game on handmade
hero org it comes to the source code so
you can play with it yourself and well
learn from it add features do the sorts
of things that you might do with
experimental programming that's about it
for this week I'll be back next week
when we'll take a look at getting our
assets structures having the correct
sort of alignment and sizing stuff in
them that we want so that when things
get important to the game they look
correct for multi-part entities which is
really what we're missing at the moment
in terms of placing entities that's
about it
hope see you back here for that until
then have fun programming I'll see you
everyone the Internet
take it easy everybody