hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero the show recode a complete game
live on stream we are in the middle of
doing some some debug interface code and
really what I wanted to talk about today
is we haven't done anything in our game
and you know honestly we probably for
the most part won't ever have to do
anything in the game because of its
nature as a game that deals with the
concept of sort of focus or UI
interactions and the reason for that is
because this is an action game and as a
result you know I want the game to be
very direct control so I don't want a
lot of modality I don't want a lot of
things in the game that are going to be
about the sorts of stuff that happens in
typical UX design sorts of situations I
want you to be wired directly into the
character and off you go
so we don't really have much that we're
ever probably going to do in the game
that will involve this sort of thinking
but I wanted to take the opportunity
here in the debug system to introduce
this this aspect of the thinking because
the debug system itself does have some
modality of operation to it that we can
use to sort of discuss these issues
which are relevant in general UI
programming and by that I specifically
mean stuff like you know I'm moving the
mouse around and you know I click on a
thing and release and that toggles like
a boolean value you know button it's
like a radio button like on or off or
something like this or a checkbox right
but if I like hold down on that that
thing and drag maybe I like tear off
that thing and I can move it to like a
different place on the screen or
something right I'm making this up but
the point is you can see that there's
sort of like an interaction model there
where things are not hardwired the act
of clicking doesn't do only one specific
thing
the act of clicking initiates a
potential series of actions and what the
user does subsequent to the click will
determine what actually happens with the
UI element with which they are
interacting
in games typically in an action game
those things play out over time as a
consequence of interacting objects I
punch the barrel and it explodes which
sends a thing flying or whatever right
that is a cut the consequence of a
series of physically sort of like of
game code triggering events and so on
that are outside of the users input in
that way whereas in UI coding it tends
to be inside the users input model
meaning they are controlling that series
of events and only by looking at what
the user did can the system understand
what was actually trying to happen so
what I wanted to do is again like just
take a little bit of time this is not
something that will ever cover in
handmade here or later on to cover that
now because I think it is an important
programming topic and I wanted to just
say a few words about it so let me go
ahead first and motivate this just by
pointing out where we are at so if I run
things here you can see that we kind of
had a situation where we started making
a little bit of a debug output sit you
know thing here and some of these things
these debug outs of things are like you
know stuff I can expand or collapse like
this right and we haven't done anything
particularly fancy certainly but that's
you know where we were at and some of
these things even we're like different
kinds so like there was a 50 of value
and we wanted to make something where we
could start interacting with that value
and where we left it if I click on this
right
it just goes to an assertion here
because we haven't implemented any way
to interact with those because we all we
had was stuff where you can interact
with my click either it could like
negate a boolean or it could you know
expand a treeview element of a group but
if it was any other kind of item that
might have like you know a value range
to it we didn't really have any way of
interacting with that thing and so if
the reason for that of course right is
because we haven't talked about at all
about how we might do user processing or
any of that sort of stuff so all we just
had was just a click and that's all we
we could do so what I'd like to do again
is like talk a little bit about the
structure here and then start to
implement some things so that we can
have a more coherent concept of how we
might deal with interaction in the debug
system and we won't go too far with it
because again it's really not going to
be saying that's going to be in the game
so we don't
it's probably not even something that I
might even spend any time on in reality
here but because this is an educational
stream I thought it was a good
opportunity to talk about this a little
bit and I think it's something people
should kind of have a reasonable
understanding of right so here we are
here's day 196 and this is sort of like
UI input processing all right so you've
seen me do some very rudimentary input
processing and it's the kind of input
processing that a lot of people
associated with the i''m GUI style stuff
right which I am constantly asked about
and in general what what I mean by the
type of thing people associate with it
is they often associate I am doing stop
processing with like single like single
execution model I guess I would say
right and what that means is if I have
something like a checkbox and I've got a
thing next to that checkbox and what I'm
going to do with this checkbox is I
click on the checkbox and it checks it
and I click on them again a bit like I'm
checks it or something like that
right that's the interaction model I
have then typically what ends up
happening is in I am GUI you will see
something where they'll do like you know
or they won't even do if checkbox like I
said it's a checkbox they'll just call
checkbox right and then inside this
check box routine it will do something
where it decides you know is the mouse
in here and has it clicked and if it has
or not it'll like toggle the check on or
off right then that's the most basic the
most straightforward way that you could
possibly implement this thing you know
what I mean
now there's a problem with this way of
thinking about things and that is that
it makes it rather difficult to decouple
the way in which things work with should
I say this it makes it very difficult to
to decouple the interactions from the
specific thing that is on the screen
right
so for example if what I wanted to do
instead was I was had some kind of a
selection paradigm so I wanted to like
select this thing and maybe I had like a
tool box over here that was like my
check box tool and I had my selection
arrow tool and if I was on the arrow
tool when I clicked on this it was
should select it and when I had my check
box tool right I wanted to like check it
or whatever you know then what that
means is every possible tool that I
might want to implement or every
possible behavior that I might want to
implement has to get stuffed inside this
check box routine which means that the
person who implements the checks box
routine has to be the person who knows
everything that might ever actually
occur here right because the the
interaction cannot be written outside of
the thing that it actually that in
outside of this actual call everything
kind of has to happen inside there right
and so I just want again wanted to point
that out that is sort of the thing that
you've seen me do so far and I don't
consider that I am gooey at all I just
consider that to be one very simple way
of implementing interaction processing
that really has nothing to do with
whether your immediate mode or not and
specifically the reason that I say that
is because I am GUI the immediate mode
part of I am GUI is only talking about
the fact that these things are announced
by the code and it does not talk about
the fact that the thing that has
announced had to be checkbox right
instead what could have been announced
here with some generic thing that's just
saying like I have a boolean right it
has this information about it and I'm
not going to say anything about how I
want you to process it as a UI element I
may just be putting these things into a
batch right as part of the I am pass
through that buffers up all the
information about what ended up on the
screen and then it could have a totally
separate set of code where people have
implemented different tools which will
then scan through this batch and do
things right because there's nothing
inherent about the immediate mode nature
of the UI
requires you to not do this right the
immediate mode nature is just about the
fact that the calling code it doesn't
have to save like a pointer it doesn't
have to call a create function to create
some kind of a widget it just announces
the things that it has and it just does
them in a passive it's done now what it
announces on the other hand is totally
up to it and again that's one of the big
reasons I say like most people don't
seem to conceptualize I am GUI the way
that I had intended not that I really
care but that's just part of it so what
I'm going to kind of show here as we
develop our debug you a little bit more
I'm going to current try to show you a
little bit of how you might structure
your code in such a way as to avoid this
kind of a thing just because I'm
assuming that everyone could find
reference to how you do this and I've
already shown how to do it a little bit
in the code so for example if we go into
here to handmade debug oops so you know
we've got a pretty obvious situation
here this is an example we've got these
debug profile things on the screen that
we had been printing out and if you
press the left mouse button it would
just take whichever one you were over
right and it would do an operation on
that right that makes sense and so if
you look at how this code is structured
it's very immediate mode meaning this
thing right here goes through all the
counters it does a bunch of operations
on those counters but all it does when
it does that processing is remember who
it would have been interacting with
right like who is the person that it's
interacting with then at the end at the
very end it goes okay now I'm going to
just do whatever I want to do UI wise
and I'm going to use whatever came out
of the immediate remote pass as the
information about who to do it to and
what you can see if like what I'm trying
to say like
said kind of here when I was talking
about this what you can see there is
this is totally decoupled from the part
where you're actually doing that
processing the thing that knows what to
do with the UI element is a completely
different part of the code than the part
that actually drew it on the screen and
recorded the fact that it was there and
that's the way I tend to like to
structure my you is because with that
structure it affords you a lot more
possibilities for writing things that
work across UI element or in a broader
sense with the UI elements then if it is
baked directly into the operation at the
time because we could have done that
remember I could have done what press
was pressed I could have done that right
here right instead of storing the hot
record I could have done that right here
but I chose not to and by comparison I
think we did it the other way in one of
these other ones here I can't remember
though let's see here
no I guess looks like I did it looks
like I did it that way in both cases I
did the debug stayed hot variable thing
here as well all right so that's okay
so I think it was only when we had baked
in here which we had when we had it in
in here before I think we did at one
point I think that was the only time
that I was doing it kind of in the older
in the in the sort of like more direct
way which I don't super love right okay
so that's the way that I'm going to
continue pursuing to do things but I'm
going to take it
slight step further right now that we've
got this and what I'd like to do is I'd
like to have a notion of the place in
which these operations occur and I'd
like to have a notion of what operation
is occurring so that we can make these
things like I can make things like some
way to interact with those real very
with those with those like floating
point variables or whatever else right
so here's how I'm gonna approach that in
here when I do my draw G bug menu I'm
gonna assume like we've sort of ad hoc
done so far I'm gonna assume that what
that does is that produces a piece of
information for me which is what the
mouse is over at this particular time
right and that won't necessarily be
something that I will use but it's it's
a piece of information that I want to
have and so if I go in here and we see
what how this is kind of working already
I've got this hot variable thing right
and hot variable gets set by draw a
debug menu right now what I do is I just
take that hot variable I see whether or
not it was pressed whether the mouse is
pressed and if it was I do the operation
to that hot variable I want to again
move like sort of one step past that and
say that I have two things I have the
hot variable and I have the interacting
variable right and I might just say this
like hot interacting with write
something like this and these are going
to form the basis of my UI system so the
hot variable is the one that comes out
of draw debug main menu in here it will
set the hot variable like so and in fact
I don't even know now that I think about
it I don't even know that I want to set
the hot variable I think what I'd rather
do is actually just have this returned
to me who is hot or something although
you know what I guess I don't really do
that let's do it this way
we'll have the hot for April how the
attract available and I'll put one more
in here which is like next top and then
these guys they just so we set next time
right and I'm gonna make this systemic
so I'm gonna say at the start of our
debug you know at the start of
everything I clear it like I was sort of
doing here with the hot record we then
do stuff whatever the stuff is that
we're gonna do and that can set the hot
record anyone in here can can do that
operation of setting the hot record or
hot variable I guess in this point in
this case and then at the end we will
use that information to decide what we
want to do with it right okay so here's
how we're gonna do that and I guess I
could also do something here where we
just kind of pull this out so it's a
little easier for you guys to keep track
of what I'm talking about
right so I'm gonna grab this I'm gonna
put it in here and this is just going to
call it be like interact debug interact
and that's gonna take the debug state
there it is right nothing particularly
odd going on there obviously it's all
good so now I clear the hot thing always
at the start I do my interactions
whatever they are right and then I come
back through contract
debug state and I'll put past the mouse
key in as well and I guess I'll also
well that's all I should really but I'll
put the input is as well
all right so inside debug interact at
the moment we're doing this thing with
the left mouse button so we'll just
leave it that way but what I want to do
here is I want to start by entertaining
a few more concepts right so the first
thing I want to know is what is the
actual thing that I'm doing at this
moment
am i interacting with something or am I
not and so at the moment we'll do
something a little more straightforward
in fact you know it let me I don't
really want to keep dealing with this
summer's gonna put that up there and do
this so what I would like to do Vmax
will let me do this that'll be there we
go what I would like to do is say okay
first I'm going to check to see if I'm
interacting with something if I'm
interacting with a variable then that
means my I have a very specific thing
that I'm doing at this time and I want
that interaction whatever that act
interaction is to have primacy if I'm
not interacting with the variable right
then it's not such a big deal that means
I'm just kind of moving the mouse around
and everything's fine so if I'm just
moving the mouse around and everything's
fine
that implies to me that whatever the hot
variable was whatever variable I'm over
should become officially hot if you will
right but if I'm interacting with
something it should not be what that
then means to is once I'm in that state
I would like to say that if I start
interacting with a variable the way that
that's gonna happen for now is I'm gonna
click down on I'm gonna push the mouse
down on it right and so what I want to
do here is I want to test to see if you
know I'm gonna use went down as a thing
I'm gonna say if the button went down on
this frame then I would like to start
interacting with this thing otherwise
and I guess what I could do to here is
say you know
kinda wanna test a couple different
things so I don't know maybe I should
actually do this a little bit more
explicitly because I'd like to know a
couple things so I could say something
like if if you know clicked you know I
could I could have a click thing where
if they clicked down and up inside one
frame by itself otherwise I'd say you
know if it went down right so I kind of
have two different different sort of
ways I could think about that
so if I click something or if it went
down then I've got different things I
might do I'll leave this one for now
because again like I said I want to kind
think about that one a little bit more
but assuming that it went down so I just
started track this thing then what I'm
gonna say is okay whatever I was
interacting with or whatever I was hot
you know whatever I was hovering over I
would like that to be what I started
interacting with right
and similarly I'd like to say for now
again if whatever the button is that I
was interacting with there if that went
up I would like to go ahead and say that
whatever I'm interacting with will
return to zero I'm gonna if the zero is
out for a while I'm just gonna talk a
little bit about how this this works and
we're gonna keep kind of we're gonna
keep flying on this a little bit more so
first I need those utility functions
that I have there oh and I forgot I pass
this guy bunch of things but I didn't
actually make them exist just try that
again let's go ahead and get our game
input in our mouth feed
and get rid of cencon all right and so
what I'd like to do here is I guess for
went up all I really need to know if if
it ended down right if it didn't end
down then then we're not attracting
anymore
went down I guess it's really simple -
that's just did it end down and so
clicked all that really all I really
need to know for clicked I suppose is if
the half transition count is it's
greater than one you know handle puts
inside a frame all right so what must
have wait to slice there we go I don't
know why I left that in there but I did
so if this is the logic for a button I'm
gonna make a little bit way for we can
draw it so so we can see it and I could
actually I suppose just also print this
out I could just make this be a piece of
debug text that we use so I could do
something like this
yeah I don't know if this actually will
work I don't remember if we actually
finished this stuff we didn't really
integrate it into our current thing I
think it's debug text line yeah if I do
a debug text line can I actually see
what's happening here
interacting hoops like so and not all
right so let's see what happens there
yeah cuz I can see that right there so
there it is so if the mouse goes down
you can kind of see how it becomes
interacting right and as I move it
around there it goes and then when I let
go comes off right like so all right so
now that I've got that I want to go
ahead and make you know the most
straightforward change here I just want
when i compare like what the item color
could be you can see that i'm using is
in a rectangle for that now imagine just
from what you could see here if i was to
go in and and want to edit one of these
and i click and drag on it and now as
i'm dragging around it highlights all
the rest of this stuff right you see how
that's happening i wouldn't want that to
happen right I want this thing to stay
highlighted that I'm interacting with
and so that is a classic example of the
thing that I was saying that I don't
want in here which is that a decision
about what should be displayed or done
is being made in line with the actual
immediate pass and that's not what I
want right what I want to do instead is
all the only thing that the immediate
mode path should be doing is determining
the information that will be used later
so in order to draw something as being
hot I exclusively want the rendering
code to test things that were set by the
controlling code by that interact thing
so I want to look to see if the variable
that we're talking about here was said
to be the hot air
variable by the actual UI interaction
code right so basically what I've done
there is I've pulled that out into the
way that I said I want to do things
instead of the way that we talked about
before and so if you look at what's
happening here right now when I interact
with something you can see that it locks
that hot thing in so now the interaction
goes on as long as it goes and only when
I let go of the mouse does the heat does
the hot things stop right
so again just pulling that out and
putting that into the interaction code
so that it can be decoupled its separate
in a way that allows me to iterate on it
as sort of its own separate thing that
doesn't require specifically being
coupled to each individual drawable
thing right ok so if I continue down
this path what I would like to do now is
I would like to say ok if the half
transition count you know if someone
clicks on something inside a frame you
can kind of see what I've set up here
here's the beginning of the click here's
the end of the click so what I'd like to
do is be able to do those two things if
there is a click a whole click inside a
frame I'd like it to do both of those
things right and so there's two ways I
can do that one way I can do that is I
can just make functions right and maybe
that's a good way to do it so we'll try
that so you know we'll do something like
begin interact or something and then
debug and interact something like that
and what I can do there is say all right
this is debug begin interact and this up
here is going to be debug and interact
like so and then what I could say is
well you know if I get a click inside
one frame then what I would like to do
is I'd like to just go ahead and process
the mode right I just want to do
whatever would have happened now you
know again this was kind of because we
chose a simplified model for the
we the user-interface thing happened
here we could even go a little bit a
little bit more hog-wild right we could
do something where we actually count
down that number we actually like to go
go further down that number so we know
you know if the thing ended down or
whatever we could sort of say all right
however many of the half transition
count however much the half transition
count was let's get it down to zero or
one so we could do something like this
right so we're gonna say this is how
many times the button went up or you
know up or down we're going to say that
until you know as long as it's gonna be
above one I want to process a click so
if the user was like wailing on the
mouse button i gona process clicks right
and then would have gotten to the end of
that presumably I would then want to
also say okay now we're down to zero one
clicks if the if zero one transitions at
that one transition what I may want to
do is if it ended down go into the
actual direction there right it makes
sense so that seems pretty
straightforward right I suppose so I
could do that the other thing that's
interesting is if I was already
interacting with something maybe I want
to to support that case as well right
maybe I want to support the case where
I've already interacted something and
the users wailing on the button for some
reason that we don't necessarily know
what it is right and so I can go in
there and also presumably do that right
I could say something like all right I
want to do this sort of a thing where I
just go through like how many
transitions were there you know and I'll
do you know you you could even imagine
do it doing it this way where I don't
even actually have any sort of logic to
it I could do something where I'm
literally just
switching the order right that would
process all of the clicks that come
through by doing ends begins instead of
by doing begins ends and then at the end
it would still do the closed processing
so you could do that pretty
straightforward and really it just is
you know yeah it's really not that
complicated it's not particularly
interesting the other thing I suppose I
could do is I could make it so that I
actually I feel like you could even
collapse this a little bit more
straightforwardly right if I just said
inside the loop for every transition I
could just say well whatever the
transition was going to be now no and
yeah you know what you can't really do
that I'm gonna take that back so I could
do something like that I don't know if I
really want to I do it real life it's
really necessary if you have a standard
event system for passing things in you
could see that you just do a for loop
here and you do these inside of the for
loop but we went with a simplified
system that just passes a single known
state down and doesn't try to do
anything more fancy with it right so
it's hard to say but either way it
doesn't really matter I don't think very
much for our particular purposes because
if since it's only people code but it's
something to be aware of all right so
yeah if we have that now I've got the
ability to sort of know exactly what's
going on here in terms of debug begins
and ends interacts right and the other
thing that I would want to know is I
want to know every time the mouse moves
so after we've done all this stuff right
or maybe perhaps we even want to do it
before we want to assume that Mouse
moves happen before the click it's up to
us to decide again since we aren't
looking at them sort of in some kind of
event order that's been serialized for
us on the platform side we kind of go
scare like okay we can do it in either
order that we want so maybe what we do
here is we just say all right we also
have debug you know I guess you know we
could just say this is our debug move
interact right here and so if we are at
the point where we're interacting with
something if we're not interacting with
anything I don't think we really have to
do anything if we are interacting with
something we would process the mouse
motion in a way that would interact they
would do whatever that interaction is
right and so this is basically like
mousemove interaction right here and
this is like you know quick interaction
that makes sense so for the mousemove
interaction we really only need to know
whether or not this thing whatever the
thing is that we're mouse moving on is
something that we would actually
interact with with the mouse that way
so whatever the interacting variable is
and I'll pull it out here into a into a
more simplified name so if we take a
look at whatever the VAR type is there's
only one thing that we actually interact
with at the moment in a way that we
would drag and that would presumably be
one of those variables that was you know
a real 32 or 32 or something like that
so I'm just gonna take a look at just
that one I'm gonna say okay if we were
moving the mouse I want to interact with
one of these and I want to interact with
it by changing whatever it's very
whatever its value is right so I want to
be able to say whatever the real 32 was
I'm going to take like some kind of
mouse Delta and multiply it by it and
I'm just gonna pick something random
here I'm gonna say zero point one for no
real reason whatsoever and then I'm
gonna take whatever the mouse Delta is
so I want to do like a demas be kind of
a thing like that and so the first
question would be well where do I get
the the DMS P again I'm gonna have to
difference it with the previous frame
right so the D mass P would be something
like whatever the last mass P was and I
would take the current Mouse B and I
just look at what's the Delta between
those and that's what I'm gonna use
again to drive those kinds of
interactions right at the end of
everything I would obviously need to
take whatever the debug state is I need
to remember what that last mouse key is
whatever the last must be I process was
I need to know you know so in order to
like figure out what I should do so in
somewhere in the debug state I'm gonna
have to have that piece of information
so again I'll put that here
with last mess P just so it's clear what
it is alright um okay so at this point
we're sort of getting a little further
but in order to get at that real value
right I have to be able to open these
guys up so I need to implement at least
one more thing which is I need to put
back in that boolean processing for
those guys you know and so what I need
to do is that would be an end
interaction I assume so
on end on interaction ends I want to do
the stuff we were doing before which is
this so when I end the interaction
I know that I've clicked already so what
I'm going to do is say okay whatever the
variable is that I was interacting with
which is of course this one and I guess
I should double check yeah this should
probably so there's one other thing we
should do here and it's the next thing I
was going to do something yeah like 50
minutes I got played a time okay go so
I'm gonna do it this way first and then
show you and then switch it up a little
bit in a second okay so what I'm gonna
in in the interaction I'm just gonna
look to see if the if I had an
interacting variable right and assuming
that I did have interacted variable I'm
gonna get it out I'm gonna look at what
type it is and do whatever the thing is
that I want to do on that type then I'm
gonna clear it so we know we're not
interacting with it anymore
okay so off we go and I should now be
able to open things up which I can write
and see me doing it there
and now I'm gonna see about interacting
with one of these guys so I'd like to
sort of change that variable oh right
and I should probably allow our debug
end interact to allow things to pass
through that now don't need to be
interacted with oops yeah otherwise it's
gonna keep complaining so yeah if I open
up the camera here now we can kind of
see I can edit this value right like so
I probably shouldn't have tie it to the
Y probably should have tied it to the X
because it's kind of a little bit stupid
I suppose the way that I did it but hey
we got what we wanted anyway which is
that we can edit our debug camera and
you know zoom it in now and you can see
that we have the problem I was talking
about before which is why I saying I
think we probably want to make some
system that allows this to not have to
be not have to be compiled like it is
currently because that compile step by
the time Visual Studio is done compiling
we're waiting a long time it would be
nice for that value to just update in
real time right because there's no
reason why we couldn't do that so I
think at some point we probably should
do that but now we've got the ability to
modify these these debug variables and
it's pretty straightforward right so
that's all good so let's take this a
little bit further and look at this a
little bit more closely so right now
there is it a little bit of an odd thing
which is that if I were to click down
out here
right so I flicked the mouse down and
now I move up now you'll notice that
things get kind of a little bit strange
right it's kind of unusual what happens
and the reason right is because we are
not able to go into an interacting state
if we are interacting with nothing so
when I click down out here it's like
okay that the hot variable was 0 so the
interacting with is still 0 and so it
doesn't consider it having started
interaction but I really did if I click
down here and drag I should not then
start interacting with the very first
thing I hit which is what happens like
imagine if I do this right you see I
picked that up by just like rolling into
it with the direct so what I want to do
is I want to have some way
of having my interactions be a state
separate from the storing what is
actually being interacted with right and
so in order to do that I'm going to want
to introduce some kind of a notion of a
interaction state that's separate from
you know whatever else I might be doing
so in order to do that I'm going to use
an enum you could also use a callback
for this depending on how you want to do
it in other words I could do a type def
here for a function I'm going to do I
think I'm gonna stick with an enum for
now this really six of one half-dozen of
the other and I tend to prefer enums
over callback so most of the time so I'm
just gonna do like debug interaction
drag value and debug interaction let's
let's go a little hog-wild here you know
let's just let's go nuts let's say we
have debug interaction drag value and
let's also say we have debug interaction
well toggle value maybe I don't know
empty bug interaction ter something like
that so I'm just making some things up
here and we'll have debug interaction
none and now I have some notion of
what's going on in terms of interaction
and so what I can do here is I can kind
of reverse the way that I've set this up
and I can say something like alright I
want to know what I'm doing right now so
I want to know what it is that the the
code is how the code is interacting so
I'm going to set up a thing here where I
just say I've got a debug interaction
and this is my interaction I'm going to
look at that interaction and say if I am
actually interacting at this time I'm
going to do one thing and if I'm not I'm
going to do another and so that keeps it
roughly the same way that we were doing
it before meaning the else Clause is the
clause or what I'm not into
knocking at the moment but I might go
into an interaction and you can see you
know that sort of doesn't change
anything here and I'll go ahead and
delete these who don't really care about
this the moment then up here if I am
interacting meaning I have an on it's
non none then I have various things that
I might be doing so what I want to do
now is I actually want to do these will
end up being sort of double switches
right these will basically be I've got
some set of things I might do where I
want to switch on whatever the
interaction is that I'm doing whatever
the interactor is right so I'm just
gonna use I'm going to switch on this
interaction and I suppose now that I
think about it really I don't need the
if anymore
I suppose that was premature to say that
I can keep that I don't really need to
keep that right I can switch on the
interaction I can have the case of debug
interaction none that's just what I've
got down here right that's what happens
and then I can also have the rest of my
values happening here
all right now if I'm dragging a value
then the only thing that I really know
how to do is just do this particular
type which is real - it's real for 2q at
the moment so that's fine but let's
continue on reporting the rest of the
stuff so assuming that I have an
interaction none I might want to change
my interaction and begin interact or and
interact we'll we'll deal with that
obviously assuming that I was trying to
toggle a value or something like that
again I kind of want I kind of want this
click interaction thing to be shared I
don't really want to have to keep doing
it that's sort of why I was saying I
would like them to kind of be common
yeah it's such a hard choice it's such a
hard choice really I'm gonna go back to
keeping it the way it was because I want
these guys to be shared processing and I
don't want to have to duplicate them for
every time so like I say guys my first
thought when I said when I said future I
was premature to call it premature let's
be honest because I do actually want it
this way so I would like to be able to
say like okay I know that I'm doing an
interaction so now there's just some
code in the movement thing that says
what I'm going to do in that case right
and and that's you know that's how that
goes so then I've got one in here which
when we're doing the drag value does
that the rest of these guys don't
actually care in fact I could almost say
that they don't actually do anything at
the moment
and then I've got sort of the other
things that might happen at the end of
that interaction at the moment something
like this then what I'd like to do out
here is say like okay when I do might
begin interact what I'm going to do is
I'm going to actually take a look at
what the variable is I'm going to decide
what I would like to do interaction wise
so I will take whoever I'm doing the
interacting with and then I will also go
ahead and take a look at its type and
I'll see what kind of interaction I
think is that I should do and so looking
at these guys right
I know how to interact with only a very
limited number of these so I know how to
interact with a pool 32 I know how to
interact with a real 32 but at the
moment I don't really know how to
interact with oh and a group at the
interact with anybody else
right I have a guys I don't have any
idea so if I do one of these guys then
what I would do is say okay and you know
what I could also say here I could also
say that interacting with only gets set
in the case where the interacting with
type is known so I could do something
like this where I say okay if debug
state interaction then I said it right
otherwise I don't something like that so
for the pool case I want to do a toggle
value that's the interaction we want for
the real case I want to do a drag value
and I suppose in in the group case I
would also want to be a toggle and I
could call this a different interaction
but at the moment we know they basically
mean the same thing right so when we do
the end interaction again same thing I
would want to basically say well what
kind of interaction am i doing so I
would say you know and I would also
assert that this is true because of I'm
interacting I better have one of these
now so I'm going to say whatever the
interaction is and I could still do this
part I guess whatever the interaction is
I want to do a different thing depending
on the circumstance so here is case use
case
and here's the case and so if I'm doing
a drag there's nothing that I have to do
at the moment since since we could get
rid of that one if it's a toggle then I
know I want to look at which type the
variable is and toggle it and yeah
basically that's about it
terr value we haven't gotten to yet so
we'll talk about that in a second right
okay
so off we go or not what did I do wrong
did I set the debug interaction
incorrectly debug interaction
hot type debug and interact interacting
with because it asserted and said I did
not have it interacting with variable so
somebody cleared my interacting with you
no way that Oh duh I also have to set it
back to none at the end of this right
okay
there we go all right so in theory we're
sort of back to exactly where we were
before and we can still do the same
stuff that we were doing and off we go
right but now when I interact with
things in theory right in the middle of
my sentence even obviously we still need
to check to make sure we actually have a
variable otherwise it's not going to go
well okay there we go one more time so
now what I was trying to say is now that
we have the notion of what interaction
we're actually doing then if we click
outside and move in we should be able to
avoid this sort of thing that right you
can kind of see like it moves on here
and off you go
right so what I want to do is I want to
make it so that we have the ability of
spcialit interaction so what I'd like
to do is specify some kind of
interaction that's just not doing
anything like the person click that side
and and they're you know just they're
just screwing around I guess or
something like that and we could do that
in company of ways we could make it
legal for one of our values to be
something that you do right like I could
make it legal to drag as a null or
something if I wanted to but I'll just
make something that's like you know that
there I'll just make an actual type for
it I think is what I'll do so when you
begin interacting here what I'm going to
say is like if it wasn't a hot variable
then what I'll say is like you know the
debug state interaction equals some kind
of like you know no oblem right it's
just like it doesn't do anything and
then in here when we come through I'll
just do something like okay that's some
kind of special case thing when the
interaction is a no op
we'll just get rid of that it doesn't
have to do any of this stuff it doesn't
have to rewrite the config file doesn't
have to do anything so now I can have
that happen and when they do that it
just doesn't do anything and then when
they let go it starts going again right
so I'm moving it out and it doesn't
happen like so and then I let go and
then back and back it goes right okay so
that's again pretty straightforward
nothing particularly weird there
everything works back it's the way we
planned it and the highlighting works as
well and all that other good stuff too
right but now I want to do a slightly
different thing I would like to be able
to have other ways of interacting with
the same piece of information right and
I think I had about 10 minutes on the
clock so I'm gonna go do it to 1810 so
what I'd like to do is make a way to
like clone a menu item or something like
this right and so what I'm gonna do I'm
gonna do something kind of a little bit
weird right but you know I like doing
things that are kind of a little bit
weird so I want to make the concept of a
group I'm going to expand that a little
bit I'm just gonna say that you know the
debug variable group can maybe be in a
location right like I can have a place
you know a place where that exists right
so it's like it's uh it's it's it's you
IP right it's where it where it is in
the world in on the screen if you will
and so if we talk about where a variable
group is on the screen then what I'm
gonna say is okay you know these if this
variable group and and I guess to be
fair maybe I should make it so that that
that's sort of more of a first class
citizen you know maybe I want to do
something more like a debug variable
like it's because the groups kind of get
nested inside each other I want to talk
about like a debug variable sort of
collection something that's like
a hierarchy rate a whole hierarchy right
and what that is is that's the route
group you know what I mean for this
thing and the location at which that is
drawn and they'll probably be some other
things eventually right that we would
put in there and so what I'll do is I'll
just change this so that we have some
bigger notion of what's going on there
oops like maybe now I also in here I
would do something I'm like okay
whatever the debug variable hierarchy is
you know that thing in and of itself can
maybe we can have as many of those as we
want or something I'm not sure exactly
how we would want to do it but for the
moment I'll just say we've got one of
those right like that and we'll just say
like okay the state hierarchy route
group equals the context route group but
then we also give it a you IP hierarchy
copy so and that's going to be wherever
was that we were drawing this so it's
like it's this stuff right and I think
we might want to do that outside of
debug create variables let's see here
and maybe bug and you know I could still
to be honest with you I could still do
something where I did something more
like this I could still leave the debug
group in there which seems like okay
like here's the route group and maybe
the route group is just something that
always has everything in it and then
everything else we kind of play with
separately something like that
I could see that so we'll do it this way
all right
so after we create these variables sit
here create variables then I'm going to
do some stuff where we sort of set this
group up a little bit more I don't
remember where we actually set left edge
yeah we set it up we set it up in here
which to be honest I'm not sure why we
always set it up in there that's kind of
odd but doesn't matter anyway
so that's where we set it up so I'm just
going to go ahead and use it there so
left edge and debug state at why are the
two things I actually need to know to
set up my hierarchy so the hierarchy
this guy I know that the group is just
going to be the root group and I know
that the location is just going to be
what we already computed right and then
when I actually draw this thing I'm
going to just draw it you know let's see
where we got him a config menu there it
is instead of passing this thing or
instead of this thing using the route
group instead this thing is going to use
that hierarchy right so it'll do
hierarchy group first child like so and
for the add X at Y it'll use the UI P
like so says and that's a good point
doesn't it's not what should get the
exact same thing or not did I not
initialize that properly I'm just trying
to exact like literally the exact same
thing I was doing before and I set the
group and the uip I set them to the @y
in the left edge which should have been
correct and the route group is should
still be initialized unless I maybe did
something stupid there which could be
the case let's double check label there
we go so yeah I still set that group so
I'm not sure what was the problem there
why am I not seeing anybody where did
everybody go
I guess we're gonna find out by stepping
in let's find out where everybody went
debug draw in here am I never calling
this function
let's see here I am calling the function
set set break point where is code for a
break point no no no almost there
okay that's what I want so let's see
what these values are and why we're not
seeing what I want to see at X at Y does
seem reasonable bar is a group ground
chunks is there something not reasonable
but oh oh dear did I flip did I flip the
tube can I do something relieved right
there somehow
yep gotta love it well that explains
that that was anticlimactic
to say the least okay so I want to stop
now because I'll do the rest tomorrow
but I just wanted to make sure that we
could draw two of those and so for
example you know if we wanted to draw
more than one of them now we can just
have multiple characters and draw them
so tomorrow I can implement another
debug function which is just to be able
to like tear off one of the menu items
and put it somewhere else for example
which is just kind of a handy thing to
be able to do and just kind of will
start to show a little bit more about
how to manage the interaction stuff but
we have a little bit more ways to go on
that so yeah so at the moment we'll just
have to hold off on that and leave it
till tomorrow for now let's go to the QA
anyone who has a Q please put aq cool in
front of it and I will do a I will a it
I just want food once you finish making
the game you you do a live playthrough
yeah I mean I'm assuming that actually
while we are making the game we will be
doing a bunch of playing through it as
well right because I mean we're getting
towards the end of the code we can do
that doesn't involve playing the game
right we've got a few lighting things to
do and maybe a little collision
detection stuff to do but after that
pretty much everything we do is going to
involve playing the game because you
know right after that the we're into
world Jen and at that point you know we
got a walk around the world and start
playing with things in the world and you
know we can't really do anything without
interacting with the game so we're gonna
be at a point where we're pretty much
gonna have to be playing the game all
the time and you know we'll try to keep
it to a minimum on stream in the sense
that I don't want me sitting around
playing around all the time and to be
honest I don't really know quite how to
manage that that well I mean I'll try to
do the best I can because it's been
relatively easy for us since we've been
working on code that's primarily
structural and like architectural
implementation wise it's been pretty
easy to keep it so that we don't have to
do a lot of of like running the game to
to work with it and I don't know so I'm
hoping that maybe using the loop live
code editing that we implemented you
know will well because you don't want
the stream to just turn into me just
basically have to play the game a ton to
get to various places and say okay maybe
we should try this one thing and then
there's like five seconds of programming
so I'm hoping that maybe you know I
don't know
besides that we're getting close to an
episodes how long do you think until you
start on the game proper I don't know
like I said I thought 200 days was a
pretty good estimate or I should say 200
hours or whatever was a pretty good
estimate and I don't think we'll be that
far from that I think we're gonna go
over by a bit because I want to do some
lighting and see that list no where is
my list where is the list so yeah I
think you know I've got a little more
stuff I want to do in here you know
we're doing this part now we did this
part we did this part but we've got GUI
you know the GUI the diagramming and the
gooey stuff we haven't finished it we
got to do that this is just a single
debugging thing so I don't think that
would take very long particle systems we
actually did although we didn't do you
know maybe everything we could have done
with what we actually already did them
so really would just be if we did
something in the renderer so really this
is mostly what we're looking at here and
then I think after that I feel like
we'll we'll have to do I feel like
everything else is gaming
there's nothing else really in here that
I can that I can do without being gamey
like we can't write a save game system
well I guess we could do we could do
this multiple sim regions well but even
that I can't really do until I actually
have a bunch of entities interacting I
wouldn't feel comfortable probably
implementing this so I would say
probably what we would do is start in on
on constructing - basically - do these
two right here we was starting and
constructing a few game play pieces to
nail down how we want the collision
detector and the Z stuff to work
yeah III don't really see anything else
in here that we can do with that game
without game stuff I mean even even
something like pathfinding I wouldn't
feel comfortable actually implementing
pathfinding prior to having the game be
gay me so yeah so I would say I would
say pretty much just the stuff up here
this stuff is all gonna require game
game to be gamey and you know we don't
we won't go hog-wild so you know I feel
like we will want to still nail down a
bunch of these things to a greater
extent before we start like cranking out
entities like just doing like it before
we're right here where we're like okay
we're just we're not thinking ever about
the collisions of section protection
anymore for the most part or something
like that but I don't even really know
that because it may be that we're
constantly kind of going back and forth
a little bit but yeah I'm pretty sure
I'm pretty sure that basically like the
only things that we could finish before
game applying things this is up above
here
does this mean any proper orangie is
around the corner
probably not around the corner because I
don't think like I said I probably
wouldn't try doing too much world gen
which is where we care about the RNG
before we have like a few rooms of
gameplay working well right so I feel
like we're still gonna do this part
first when we come in here probably not
this like this part is probably more
like that right but we're probably gonna
do this first which would be like you
know guy and some enemies in a couple
rooms fighting and things like this
right so this this part I feel like does
not have any orange enos to it for the
most part so would probably be like that
and then maybe
I would actually say this probably if
we're being realistic looks like this
because the entity system I don't really
know why yeah why some of the stuff was
laid out the way it was I feel like it
probably looks more like this maybe like
that's probably a little more realistic
that'd be my guess it's funny that we
said animation would lead into rendering
but we did the renderer first so that's
not true but yeah I also don't know what
stars are so yeah I would say that is
maybe a little bit more realistic in
terms of how things would probably go
but I don't know like I said it could go
either way it's possible that this could
go up here games are very hard to
predict schedule-wise best if you're the
only programmer on them so I don't
really know ElkY 144 did I already
covered the minkowski difference on the
stream I don't remember when we talked
about the collision detect detection I
definitely did talk about the Minkowski
sum I mean there really is this thing
isn't a bouncy difference there's a
mikowski addition of the inverse or
whatever and I don't remember how much I
covered of that we covered enough to do
growing things by other growing shape by
other shapes which is a Mackowski sum
and I don't really know if I don't
really know if I talked about the
difference I don't think I would have
because the only reason you talk about
the Minkowski difference in the sense of
like subtracting a shape from another or
summing the inverse
something the- the only reason you
probably talk about that is if you were
trying to find the origin for like a gjk
kind of a thing and we didn't talk about
that so could you explain the difference
between how our I am GUI is often
implement and how you think it should
work again it went a bit faster me um so
this is just one of the what things one
of the many things but like one way is
the way that I wrote it here in the
debug one right which is to say that the
interaction code is separate from the
patent the pass that does the drawing so
these are like out here there this is
the drawing right DUI driver menu it
doesn't do any interaction itself
instead all of the interaction is
deferred to later by using the hit
testing that happened in the IM pass
later on somebody will actually do the
interactions and basically it's it's
splitting those two things apart that i
think is was the part that i was trying
to talk about so we could have shoved
these in there right we could have
shoved these into directly into here
when we do or is in rectangle who could
have done it here and i just don't think
that's a very good place to do it
because i feel like it makes it harder
to decouple and make it's harder to keep
the code organized with the parts of the
code that you want it to be organized
with it's in some sense it's just a
stupid artifact of the way that you know
procedural stuff works but
I just find that I'd like to pull those
two things out but that was the only
part I was trying to elaborate on
let's see a bur 173 would you ever
consider doing a 24-hour stream that was
create X app or game from start to
finish in one stream I mean I guess it's
not that I wouldn't consider it it's
more that I'm not really sure what would
be the point of it so I mean I would
probably consider it and then go that
doesn't sound like a very good idea I
don't know I mean like I just don't know
what would be gained by doing this
unless it was like you know like a
publicity stunt or something I suppose
where you're just like 24 hours can you
create this in that time or something
you know
not really singing anymore questions so
I guess we are done I guess we are done
all right let's see let's go ahead and
see close please okay thank you everyone
for joining me for an episode of
handmade hero it's been a pleasure
coding with you as always if you want to
follow along at home you can always
pre-order the game on hammer you're
gonna come to the source code so that
you can follow along with what we're
doing and if you want to play around
with it that's a good way to do it we
also have patreon page from ask about
the video series we have a forum site
you can go to ask questions get
annotated so a guy and a tweet box which
tweets the schedule at you if a track
gets stream live and if you are
connected stream live you can do that
tomorrow again at 5:00 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time I will be back here and
I'm gonna make a little thing so we can
tear off menu items again just to kind
of show how to do like different
interactions in one place and that sort
of thing and then after that I think we
may be kind of done with that part of
things so I'd like to do is go ahead and
move on to a couple of our two do's here
maybe get the things working updating in
real time
and and then integrate in our little
profile logging system so that we can
you know get all the UI in one place and
be able to kind of maybe start to use
that to interact with and scrub through
our debug events which I think would be
nice so just kind of start to pull
things together and now that I've shown
all the different parts of it try to
start to pull those things together so
that we can kind of wrap up the debug
system and be relatively happy with
where it's at in terms of you know
having something we can use during the
stream to debug stuff when we have stuff
we need to debug or tweak things that we
need to tweak so that's about it thanks
for joining me I'll see you guys here
tomorrow until next time have fun
programming and I'll see you on the
Internet