alright hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Shiro the show where we code a
complete game live on Twitch no engine
no libraries because you know what it's
just it's old-school day up in here all
the time you know what I'm saying like
we kick it old-school
none of the crazy rap music's and heavy
metals that the kids are listening to
today with their you know ridiculous
hair and their there are other things
you know it's just like that's that's
not you know that's not how do we roll
you know we don't we don't try to put on
rollerblades and go like criss cross
through the cones or the other things
that the people are doing in California
you know that's just not how we are here
this is old-school traditional
programmer values here on handmade hero
and so you know with that said off we go
if you have pre-ordered the game and
want to follow along with the source
code you can go ahead and check out that
link that you should have gotten your
email and today is day 89 so you're
gonna want to unpack day 88 source code
that's what you're gonna want to do
because that's where I am at and so you
know do that so that you and I will be
aligned will be working on the same code
because otherwise we will be divergent
and despite the fact that that appears
to be some kind of an awful young adult
novel that is currently not sweeping the
nation because it probably wasn't very
good i I feel like we should avoid that
in terms of our code base all right so
let's take a look at what happened on
Friday because some stuff happened on
Friday and it kind of changed everything
around a little bit so what happened on
Friday is I just kind of finally got
sick of not having a renderer and so we
just started pulling things out into for
lack of a better term a renderer and
honestly I kind of felt like it was the
right thing to do because once I started
doing it I was like yes we should
probably be doing this so I think what's
probably gonna happen here is either
we're just gonna go ahead and write the
renderer this week and next week or
however long it takes probably longer
than that if we write the whole renderer
so we'll take a couple of weeks and
write the renderer
or will at least take a week and write
enough of the renderer to make it not be
bothering me anymore
so yeah maybe we don't write the whole
renderer but we write enough if that
makes sense I don't know which one will
do it remains to be seen you know maybe
we get up a good head of steam we'll
just write the whole thing but I think
at this point it was getting annoying
enough that I just decided to make the
call because we've just got a bunch of
crufty code in there that was sitting
around doing ugly stuff because we
didn't have a renderer and at some point
you just kinda have to say let's do that
yeah and similarly we had another thing
that we might consider to be a blocking
factor which is that in our ground
rendering code which we had kind of
started to want to make into more of a
thing so we could have multiple ground
levels and stuff that was kind of a next
big milestone that we wanted to kind of
hit we run into the problem that we
don't have scaling at all right because
we don't have a renderer and so how are
we gonna test out render you know
rendering of our ground pieces if we
can't scale them because maybe we want
sort of lower levels on the on the
screen to be shrunk right so they look
like they're further away or something
like that
and we want them to kind of be able to
do that smoothly as we go up and down
stairs or other things like this if
that's the case then we need some way
even if it's not a very good renderer or
it's on a very fast renderer we at least
need something right in order to test
that and get a feeling for whether or
not it's going to be workable for what
we need to do right so I think that's
where I'm at and so I think I'm just
gonna go with it until we hit something
that that suggests that we need to do
something differently so let's talk
briefly on the blackboard about what's
gonna happen here just so everyone's on
the same page and you know just at the
head of the week here we can kind of get
a little bit of a kind of a an over an
overview it is day to night 89 yes so
what I want to be able to do with this
renderer is I want to be able to have
the game code right I want to be able to
have the game code issue a bunch of
essentially instruct
that are going to tell the renderer what
to do but I don't want them to actually
be executed right away okay in other
words I want the game to be able to
issue instructions so when we're coming
through here and it wants to render
things every time it wants to render
things what I want to do is I want to
put it into a buffer okay so I want to
put it into a buffer here where it says
like okay you know render the head of
the thing and then render you know this
particles or something right that are
here I want to basically build up a list
of things for the render to do and I
called this a push buffer and the reason
that I called it a push buffer is just
because you keep pushing things on to it
it doesn't like shrink or anything ever
right it just you keep pushing on to it
non to it non to it and eventually the
renderer actually renders the whole
thing and then discards it entirely
right that's just how it works
so why do I want to do that well there's
a couple different reasons I wanted to
do that and I'll briefly say what they
are
the first reason and probably the most
important one is that I want to be able
to sort okay
so I want sorting in here because what I
want to be able to do is I want to be
able to take all the things that we're
gonna get rendered and I want to be able
to think about them in terms of what
order I want to do them in and in order
to do that I need to see them all now I
could try to structure the game so that
it went through and actually did
everything that it need to do in the
order in which it had to be rendered
right we could do that but that imposes
a lot of constraints on the game and it
makes the game do a lot of thinking that
I don't really want the game to have to
do I would like the game routines to be
structured so that they're about making
it fast and flexible for us to do
interesting things and so that they're
optimized for doing a lot of off-screen
calculations as well like I was saying
and so what I don't want to do is build
the whole game architecture or just
around how you're gonna render it now
that may sound like a weird thing to do
not the what I'm suggesting but the
thing I'm suggesting against that may
sound like a weird thing to do to ever
build the game entirely around a
renderer but that wasn't that unusual in
the old days because when system
resources were severely constrained
think Atari 2600 ColecoVision commodore
64 in those days it may have been the
case that you literally
could not make the game work if you ever
wanted to do something like queue up a
bunch of render commands and then
execute them right
that's simply nonsensical because you
did not have the kind of system
resources it would take to do that
efficiently your game would run awful it
wouldn't have enough memory to run it
would be too slow you know who knows
what would happen but that simply wasn't
on the table nowadays we have the luxury
of having just this incredible amount of
Korus power under the hood and so what
we can do is we can make different
trade-offs there now I don't advocate
making the trade-off of let's just write
a bunch of crappy code and use all the
CPU to allow us to run crappy code you
know I advocate against that very
strongly because I'm tired of running
really lousy stuff run machines all the
time which is typically what people tend
to be shipping these days so I don't
advocate that but what I do advocate
doing is trying to figure out where you
can make those trade-offs for the
betterment of the game code as a whole
right and this is one place that we can
do that because there's a bunch of
things we can get if we do this if we
allow the sorting first of all we allow
the game code to be structured in a more
efficient fashion and it doesn't need to
have that sorting logic baked into how
we structure things so all of the stuff
in the game can get more efficient and
more flexible because of that so that's
a plus and the other thing that's a plus
is it means that we can sort things
essentially on if you will we can sort
things differently depending on the
circumstance and so let me explain a
little bit what that means right so
let's say we then want to take this push
buffer and do the rendering and so this
is comes to the next big benefit here
which is the output target right so the
output target is where this push buffer
is actually going to go eventually right
so OpenGL is one place it could go right
direct3d is another place it could go
right mantle is another place it could
go so like trying to think if there's
anything else really
software are api's I don't think so you
could imagine some console API here like
it's like a you know whatever the the
x-bow nor the ps4 is doing your son like
that and then finally our software
renderer right that we right okay and
this software render the
like the different versions of this
right you could imagine maybe there's an
SSC two versions when we do now maybe
there's an EDX version maybe there's an
AV x2 version maybe there's a neon
version for arm-based processors so
there might be different software
renders and so one of the things that
this push buffer does allow us to do is
to the sorting you can almost think of
more as processing right so don't think
of it just as sorting think of it as any
kind of process you might want to do it
allows us to translate this push buffer
into the most efficient thing for the
target without having to rewrite all the
game code right so it does provide a way
for us to get a layer of portability
that makes it it makes it possible for
us to optimize for a lot of renderers
blender targets without us actually
having to to rewrite the game and while
again that's something that sort of
sounds a little bit like well isn't that
kind of cheesy like don't we want to try
and make things optimally efficient
again there is this this concept of what
will you actually end up doing right you
know if you go to the extreme of sort of
the we want to make everything efficient
philosophy it's kind of untenable just
like the extreme that we're at right now
today in most software where you don't
care about performance at all and you're
just like I don't care I don't think
about it I didn't know how memory works
it's a mystery I get back these
reference counted things and I don't
even know where they come from
right just like that the performance
extreme is also a bad decision because
if you actually wanted to make the most
optimal thing that ever existed in you
know in the history of humankind for
this particular platform you would never
finish it right because there's always
more optimization to do so what we're
looking for all the time right is the
right balance we're looking for the
right balance of something we can
achieve that we will actually have time
to do in the course of the project and
that efficiency that that actually
causes it to be a good high quality
product that when you run it you feel
good it's reliable it's fast it's not
wasting your time it's not stuttery it's
not ugly and so on right and so push
buffers allow you to have a
nice balance there in my opinion it
allows you to insert this sort of this
this thought if you will this thinking
in between the output target and the
game that allows you to do optimizations
in a nice space so you could almost
think of it as an I are an intermediate
representation for your render language
like it's sort of like a compiler has an
intermediate step and this thing should
be designed basically for two purposes
it should be designed to allow the game
to quickly you know this should be a
fast pipe here so it should be quickly
describe what it needs to describe in
terms of rendering and also minimally
right it should we want to minimize
because again we want that balance we
don't want to be super piggy we don't
want to put the pig hat on I've got it
here but we don't want to put it on we
also want to be relatively minimal we
don't want the game to be spamming giant
stuff into this push buffer every frame
that's going to cause a performance
problem for us so we want to be able to
quickly and concisely represent the
things that it needs to represent in
order for rendered to occur and then
what we want to do is write good highly
optimized ways of taking this push
buffer and turning it into one of our
output targets either OpenGL calls
direct3d calls some other API I don't
know a console if we ported to one or
our software renderer which will be the
first thing that we do which will be
written presumably will do the SSE to
one because that will run everywhere so
everyone will be able to follow on home
and let's be honest I don't even know if
I have a BX I don't think that - I don't
know if I have a BX in this box it
probably doesn't have it I'm not sure so
anyway that's what we're going to be
doing we started doing the push buffer
stuff and so I'm going to kind of - here
I'm not gonna spend much time maybe
three more minutes talking on the
blackboard and then we'll spend the 40
minutes just kind of working with the
push buffer and showing how we want that
stuff to work and kind of getting things
set up for a little more of our renderer
stuff to happen okay so that push buffer
that's that's how this is going to work
and we've already kind of done the work
on Friday of getting a sort of semblance
of this started we have these output
targets here we don't really know
anything about them I happen to know a
bunch about OpenGL and stuff like that
and I know something about software
renders as well so you know I'm at an
advantage here certainly compared to
people at home who may be a new
experience with this before but in
general I'm trying to take the tack as
if I don't really know much about it
because there are ones that I have no
experience with I don't have I don't
even have a machine that runs mantle
right now I don't think and so on so I'm
still thinking of it in terms of like
yeah there's output targets here and we
don't necessarily know everything about
the arbiter grits we're targeting we
don't even necessarily know what they
all are because a lot of time the game
ships we could end up with a surprise
the chrono scoop could ship Vulcan right
and we want to target it we don't know
anything a bad Vulcan right I've never
even seen the spec for Vulcan so again
what we're trying to do here is set
ourselves up for success so that we can
rapidly adapt to new targets and get
reasonable efficiency out of those
targets without having to rewrite our
whole game because that would be bad
okay so that's what we're trying to do
and then our push buffer is essentially
going to get handed in our first phase
we're going to be doing our software
target here so our software target is
going to essentially be doing what I
would call I kinda just decided this is
what we're doing at least to start GPU
rendering or I should say maybe more
civically GPU esque rendering right and
what that means is we are going to be
writing a renderer that works the way a
GPU would roughly now obviously it's not
exactly like a GPU would work but it's
similar and why are we doing that the
answer is because there's really no
reason for us to ship a software
renderer right
we literally there's no point in
shipping us off for render these days it
just doesn't make any sense right but at
the same time knowing how a GPU works
I mean GPU is simple it's just a CPU
just it's it's just like a Intel
processor at the end of the day just has
a few different trade-offs in there but
it's very very similar it's just you
know kind of purpose-built for a
specific task instead of with more
general tasks right what's very
important to know when you're working
with UVU's is how they actually
function and so what I think is the most
interesting thing for us to do with our
software render cuz I do want to show
you how that whole pipeline works is to
write something that works essentially
the way the GPU actually does work what
that means is we're gonna be a little
slower so we'll be a little slower than
if we didn't write then if we were you
know a hundred percent CPU focused okay
so we'll be a little slower than that
because we won't take any shortcuts that
would only be that would structure the
algorithm so that they run specifically
for a CPU and what a CPU wants to do
right we won't do that but what it does
mean is that we'll get like basically
all the insight out of it right so we're
gonna maximize the degree to which we
get insight into how games are actually
running today because that's the biggest
takeaway I think and it's the thing
that's the most meat immediately
applicable to everything so when we walk
away from this we'll say ok we kind of
now have seen how everything in a GPU
works roughly at least the parts that we
care about and we have some idea of why
shaders look the way they do why they
have the performance characteristics
that they do that sort of thing right
and so what that means in practice
really the primary thing that that
implies is that we are not going to be
doing a scanline renderer right and so
there's kinds of renderers there's
there's two kind of ways you could look
at a renderer working and and they look
like this right so here's my pixel grid
I know it ain't great right here's my
pixel grid again okay so one way to do
it is to say alright if I'm going to
draw something like a triangle right and
I've got that triangle here there it is
one way to draw a triangle would be to
say let's figure out what sort of scan
lines the triangle touches or something
right and I'm gonna then go through them
and figure out what the span is of this
triangle on every scanline right
basically which pixels it spans if that
makes sense okay that one it wouldn't
actually cover so I'd probably be here
right something like that so you
basically figure out which pixels it
touches by doing it in iterative scheme
where you first figure out how much to
step each edge every way as you go down
and you start with a span that's however
wide it is and you exactly rasterize the
rows you need to rasterize right you
know that's the old-school way of making
a software rasterizer that's the way
software rasterizer is typically worked
back in the pentium days when they work
the common thing that game shipped on
we're not going to do that even if that
turned out to be the faster way to do it
today we're not gonna do it that way
that doesn't mean it would be but that
we're not going to the way we're
actually gonna do things is by actually
it's it's called it's an implicit
surface rasterizer essentially instead
of explicitly you could think of this as
an explicit rasterizer right and this is
an implicit rasterizer instead of
walking the pixels that we want to fill
what we're going to do instead is only
get a rough approximation of what they
would be on some boundary and so let's
say that boundary because this is
probably what we actually will use is 16
pixels in a square so it's a 4 by 4
right it's 4 this way and for this way
and what we will do is we will try to
determine which four by fours it might
touch on the screen right so instead of
being explicit we're more doing some
bidding to figure out roughly what 4 by
4 is it touches and then we will
evaluate every pixel in the 4 by 4
regardless of whether the triangle
touches it or not so if the triangle
actually passes through it like this and
these pixels are never touched and
similarly it passes through it like this
and these pixels are never touched it
doesn't matter we will actually compute
the results for all of these pixels and
then we will simply mask away these
pixels here and fill only these right
now there's a lot of reasons for doing
it this way hopefully a fair number of
them will become clearer to you as we
actually implement it I don't want to
kind of go into them all now but this is
how GPUs work nowadays they they do this
sort of they do this sort of the scheme
and so that is what we will be focusing
on which means that our renderer will
look something like push buffer here
right here is the push buffer goes into
some kind of a pinning phase right which
is going to figure out where on the
screen stuff lives of all of our
triangles right it is then going to go
into a 4x4 selection right so it's gonna
pick what four by fours need to get
filled for any given triangle or
whatever the primitive is this is for
primitives here now right and then we're
gonna have a four by four you know
basically I don't know what you want to
call this it's not it might be weird to
call it a rasterizer but I'll call it a
rasterizer but basically something that
actually does the calculation for the
4x4 right and this will be written
essentially so that on SSE right on sse2
which will be our minimum target that's
four wide which means it calculates four
at a time that means we will be doing
four times basically the pipeline for
sse2 we'll be doing two times the
pipeline for AVX because that's eight
wide and we'll be do or you know I'll be
honest I don't remember their naming
schemes and one times the new avx-512 I
think it was called Baby X 256 or
something I don't even know Intel's
naming schemes mystify me I never know
what I'm talking about I know the
instructions I'm thinking of but that's
it so there's another one that's 16 wide
I think that's coming out in skylake so
like the end of this year or sometime
this will be a thing that that's on
desktops and so this cindy pipeline will
actually be able to do the entire 4x4
rasterization in like just you know a
list of instructions that looks like
it's just pop rating on one pixel is
actually doing the full hole 16 by 16
right so this will be quad pomp this
will be double pumped and this will be
single pumped and that's roughly what
we'll do and this right here is
essentially where our shaders will come
in right this will be what what
where we write sort of what we want to
happen per pixel and we will have
basically that working in a way that
allows us to run it at one of these
granularity is depending on the platform
I don't know if we'll ever do an
implementation 480 X 2 weeks or 512 our
cells actually but what we will do is
set up the code so that it essentially
is already working as if it was IV X 512
and it just quad pumps the SSE to part
of it that's probably how we'll set it
up all right so that's what we're
building okay and we're starting with
this part and we'll maybe sort of
cautiously start to work our way down
until we get to this and right now we're
working primarily with rectangles right
and because we're a sprite engine I'm
thinking that probably we will be
exclusively rectangles meaning although
we may think about things in terms of
triangles on a rare occasion I'm trying
to think in my head if we ever actually
want an actual triangle and we probably
don't which means we can save a lot of
fussing through the pipeline by just
dealing with rectangles explicitly and
that actually includes this because as
you will see when we get there it is
actually almost the same cost to fill
rectangles as it is to fill triangles so
we will essentially save ourselves half
the work by just filling rectangles
explicitly if that makes sense and
hopefully it does make sense to you okay
hopefully we're all on the same page
we've got a good 30 minutes left here so
I'm gonna stop the blackboard session
because we can come back to it later
when we start to get into some of these
things in more detail so right now I
just want to take the rest of this time
to start looking at our push buffer and
start thinking about how to make this
into something that's nice and clean for
the game side to use and maybe extend
its feature set a little bit even though
we have no backing for it to allow it to
express the things that we're going to
want to express and when I say that I'm
kind of explicitly talking about things
like scaling and rotation which we have
not been doing because we want to be
able to push those through the pipeline
so that they can actually be used in in
the the subsequent stages right and
right now the game has no way of even
asking for scaling or rotation so it
wouldn't matter if we had a back end of
the renderer that could actually handle
it
it doesn't matter the game can't ask for
it so that's another thing that we kind
of want to look at so let's just start
get our feet wet it's a Monday I don't
expect much from myself let alone you
guys on a Monday you know we're all
sleepy so so I don't blame you I don't
blame you I'm tired too I know you've
been out partying that's just how it
goes it's totally fine let's not get
hung up on it okay let's just take it
easy so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to start pulling some of the stuff
out we've got some stuff here draw
rectangle draw rectangle outline draw a
bitmap draw Matt right you can see it
all there I'm gonna go ahead and say
that stuff is coming in here so we can
look at it all just you know kind of
have it all in one place we can pile
make sure nothing's broken there we also
we didn't break anything
oops did actually no I did dead end
there we go
you know what I type Ms dibs so often
because at work I have a batch file that
will do that for me I'm wondering if I
should just go ahead and make ms dev dot
bat here in the misc directory and just
say you know what Devin there you go so
let's see if that works now he gone the
MS dev lovely alright so that was what
it used to be called they changed the
executable to Devon nobody knows why
they just did I guess they were they
wanted to make sure everyone had to
learn a new thing to type and really it
was really worth it because now everyone
knows it's dev M not M s dev so good
decision guys anyway let's go ahead and
take a look at where we're at to make
sure everything's fine it looks fine to
me we're just kind of in doing that
cache filling there so that's totally
fine and
yeah I don't think there's really
anything that we need to worry about
here it looks like everything was left
in a workable state so let's go ahead
and start playing with this okay so here
we are in here may render hoops EPP
that's got two functions in it here we
are in h this has the stuff that we were
working with so we have a render group
here and you know what we've got piece
count it's still in there but I don't
think we use that anymore why am i a
misaligned let's rotate that over there
there we go so piece count is there I'm
gonna get rid of that because I don't
think we need that for anything I don't
think it actually is used so I'm just
going to vaporize it and get rid of it
there we go
and so what I'd like to do now is go
ahead and say well let's look at adding
multiple types of commands in here
because that's something we're
definitely going to want to do we're
gonna need something that allows us to
kind of interleave commands or do sort
of more fancy stuff with the commands
that end up in this push buffer so I'm
gonna try to expand things to that
effect so first of all let's make this a
a push buffer entry or maybe I should
say it will be a render group entry that
might be a little bit smarter because
hey it's a push buffer is kind of the
implementation of it it's not what it
actually is so that's fine and so that
way I can sort of change that that sort
of name there which doesn't make sense
entity visible piece is not what it
actually is so I'm gonna replace any
visible peace with render group entry so
that we can kind of have that taken care
of there we go
and same thing here just replace that
anywhere that exists where else we got
it you got it here okay so this is
another thing too I'm gonna pull this
out again into that render group and and
there's really this is strictly just for
my own personal benefit of being able to
look at things in one place this is this
is an organizational thing has nothing
to do with the code it's it's purely
organizational so I'm gonna call this
you know render push buffer or something
or a render group you know render
group to output I don't know something
like that and then I'm just going to go
ahead and say that all the stuff that
was happening in there that's going to
happen in here and we will pass now we
will see what it actually is that we
need to pass to make that work obviously
we're going to need the render group
itself that's you know thank thing 1 but
then we're going to need some other
stuff like the output buffer and things
like that so let's see so screen Center
X screen Center Y those can be
determined from the buffer itself let's
see what else we've got here meters 2
pixels that obviously is something that
we can do directly off the render group
because we're restoring that although
that's probably something that we'll do
in a slightly different way a little bit
further down but that's yeah a little
bit a little bit further along in the
process if you will
there we go render group screen Center
will solve in a second and draw a buffer
same thing alright so basically all we
need here is that draw buffer so let's
go ahead and grab that draw buffer out
of things it's just a loaded bitmap
right and that's the target that we're
drawing to so we're gonna go ahead and
and pass that as well right there's that
sort of the target we'll call that the
output target for now so that output
target is this bitmap and the bitmap is
going to I think give us everything else
we need because that's what we're
drawing to there those output targets
and then that screen Center we can
compute pretty trivially by just doing
it off of the output target rank so
there's the output target again the
target let's take a look if there's
anything else that needs to happen I
don't think there is
so this is our draw buffer and this is
also our render group get passed here
and now we should be again nothing
should be changed we should see exactly
the same stuff and again this is just a
simple programming step you'll notice
and I want to keep emphasizing this I
know you guys have heard a bunch of time
so I really can't emphasize it enough
you'll notice that no design work is
happening here the design is happening
organically and that's really really
important under
like basically I have some stuff that I
want to do and I'm just pulling things
out and letting what was already in
place as a structural set of
requirements for the code guide what
lives where and who does what when right
I'm just and I'm making these sort of
incremental steps that's a really
important skill to learn it's a really
important skill to practice because it's
what keeps you out of the bad habit of
over-designing overthinking not getting
anything done sitting there drawing
things you know class diagrams or things
like this which are all just basically
totally useless like you really want to
focus on write the code that works and
then start pulling it up and cleaning it
up and making it into nicer pieces using
those compression steps that's just kind
of like pull things out make them
simpler pull things out make them
simpler you know that's sort of
leveraging that's the way to do it it
works really well you've seen it work a
bunch of times really well in the stream
and it's gonna keep working well for us
so I really want to emphasize it's
really the best way to go if you take
anything else away from handmade hero
please take that away it's it's a really
valuable programming thing I wish I'd
known a long long long time ago and in
some sense it's something everyone
starts out doing like I used to do it
instinctively until a bunch of C++
nonsense you know books and stuff and
people essentially taught me out of it
by telling me that this was better code
was the other way they're wrong it's not
so please you know follow your instincts
because your instincts are good don't
follow the books because the books are
lousy and so ok so again we're in a good
place here we've got our render group to
output working and so now what I want to
do is introduce a different type of
command so that when we're going through
the push buffer we can have commands
that are kind of interleaved now again
this is somewhat inefficient because
because we have different commands we
have to look at each one to see what we
need to do but remember that's why we're
focusing on trying to be concise with
these commands so that we're not
constantly like we don't want to have
like triangle or rectangle be
necessarily the have have a
this we don't want anything that isn't
relatively expensive to render to be in
the push buffer as a single item if that
makes sense like we don't want to fill
the put like let's say particle let's
say we had particle effects so tons of
rectangles that are drawn with the same
texture we wouldn't want to push each
particle into the push buffer because we
have to keep deciding as each one goes
there to say what is this oh it's a
particle call some particle code right
so we want to do is aggregate those
things up to the point as far as we can
basically right and so something like a
bitmap blip we can actually probably
make that one entry because that's gonna
require switching what texture we're
using potentially and things like that
so we can we can think about that as
being appropriate for a push buffer
because maybe there's a hundred thousand
of those on the screen that's not that
big of a deal but things were there's
going to be like 10 thousand a hundred
thousand of them it's not an option to
put them in the push bumper individually
because all of that testing to see what
they are will kill us so we have to be
careful what we do we'll start right now
with just doing something very basic but
you know keep that in mind that we're
gonna have to do some things there that
allow us to that the proof that will
prevent that switching overhead from
becoming any kind of dominant factor we
don't have to think about it all the
time but we have to think about it a
little is I guess the way they would say
it so when we when we grab out an entry
here right and I'm going to change the
word piece to the word entry so that
it's a little more clear what that is
there so when we grab out one of these
and we're looking to see what we want to
do with it right when I do that what I
want to do is I want to say okay let's
see what type it actually is so when we
grab an entry we're actually going to
we're going to see what type it is and
then based on what type it is we're
actually gonna do different stuff right
so we might have a render group entry
that's going to be a clear right oops
sorry it's going to be a clear we might
have a render group entry because I
spoke of that one before
that's going to be like a rectangle
which is you know like I've seen before
that we kind of know
is where a lot of our sprite puddings
gonna come and then we'll have other
stuff here right now we don't know what
that stuff is going to be but I would
we're gonna handle basically everything
that we possibly that goes through there
we want to make sure that we handle it
so what I'm gonna do here is introduce
another one of our in Falco path things
which is invalid default case and what
invalid default cases is it's just a
macro that lets us know that the default
case in our switch statement is not
allowed to ever happen right it's just
not and so if it ever does we want to
assert because basically the only things
that should ever get pushed on here are
things that we can handle and if there's
something that we don't want to handle
for some reason we should add a case for
it and note we're not doing anything for
that case we're just not handling that
thing like let's say it was something
that was only applicable to OpenGL or
something like that right okay and so
then what I'm gonna do further is I'm
gonna say all right that base address
right is actually going to go up
whatever we're advancing by it's
actually gonna go up by a different
value depending on what's in here right
so they're gonna kind of be compressed
now that may not be the fastest option
at the end of the day but I just wanna I
want to make sure we support it so that
I'm gonna do that for now we'll see we
will see what we want to do at the end
of the day for it because there's other
stuff we could do there we can do it
this way the other way we can do it is
by having some pointer chasing happening
there again I'm not sure which one of
those we want to do so we will kind of
leave it open and we'll see we'll sort
of see what happens when we get to it
all right so when we do this what we
want to do now is say we've got our
render group entry so let's say render
entry clear is a thing that we have and
we're just gonna cast right are we're
gonna we're gonna basically cast
whatever the entry was to be the thing
that we know that it actually is now
after that type this is this is
basically a discriminated Union if you
will and then we're gonna have a
rectangle that's another option here
and that's gonna be done like this where
we have render entry rectangle so and
then we're gonna act on those and so
what we want to do here you know what I
could do too is I could just actually
call this entry as well like so and
actually make this the type list entity
entry or something like that so when we
know that's type we turn into entry so
then at the end we will take whatever
the size of the entry actually is right
and we will advance by that thing
like so so there we go okay so now if we
have these two now instead of making
render group entry the vast thing I'm
actually going to make it so that
there's two types there's a render entry
clear and a render entry rectangle and
right now rectangle we know what that
looks like for now at least it looks
like this and then we've got a rectangle
entry clear that is a different one and
and that's going to be some other thing
presumably what render entered clear
will be was just an RGBA that's whatever
we want to do our clear to right and
then of course everything needs
essentially one of these at the top of
it like so we'll call that well we can
actually call that the header I suppose
like so on and in fact I could call this
render group entry header which might be
a little bit clearer I could also call
it typeless render group energy I don't
know it's not worth thinking about too
much so we'll just leave with that and
so we're gonna have an enum here which
is going to be the type who's going to
be the render group entry type and the
types are going to be the two kinds that
I have right so I've got clear I've got
rectangle okay and so what I'm going to
do in here is in that header I'm going
to have the type there I'm going to have
a in addition to the type there was
something else that I wanted to have
what was it
maybe there wasn't now that I'm thinking
about it am I am I did I misspeak do we
only need the the header for some reason
I was thinking in my head just moments
ago I'm like well we'll put the type in
there and then we'll put something else
and then for some reason I'm not
thinking of anything so it may literally
just be the type that may be the only
thing we actually need all right I take
it back take it back maybe it's a Monday
I just forgot what it was in a minute
I'm gonna be like oh yeah we need that
thing but there we go
all right so what you can see what I've
done here right is I've essentially made
it what's called I've made what's called
a scrim innate immune yin all right and
I'll put that up here so you know I'll
just say okay render group entry is a
discriminated Union right and
essentially what a screw native Union is
and furthermore it's it's a you might
call it an efficient discriminated union
or a memory efficient discriminated
Union right maybe a compact
discriminated Union so Union as you know
is something we've used before in actual
see where we do like Union and we say
okay you know we've got a Union it's got
the render group entry header
yeah I'm sorry it's got the red we have
to clear it's the clear we got the
render group entry rectangle or whatever
sorry so rectangle right and what that
does is that makes it so that the size
of each of these things is whatever the
largest one is so they'll all fit but
what I want to do oh and and I should
say that's a regular Union a
discriminated Union right is one that
stores what type it is it discriminates
essentially is what there's a type field
that discriminates among the the
possible types that it is so that's
called the discriminated union typically
probably from category theory I don't
actually know where that term comes down
and furthermore what I'm doing is I'm
saying I'm gonna actually compact these
down so that instead of using like the
largest size possible so I know that
they all fit and not having to and and I
can always advance by the same size
every time like base address would
always be
equals the size of whatever the Union
the whole Union size is I'm actually
gonna say I'm gonna look at since I'm
already looking at the type is I'm gonna
advance by whatever
I know its size to be and there's
actually a reason that I'm doing that
it's a little forward-looking but it's
basically so that we can push
arbitrarily sized stuff on the push
buffer and I think that you will agree
with me when we get to the end of this
that that turns out to be a really handy
trick but we haven't gotten there yet so
no need to really go into it now anyway
so essentially what we're doing here is
we're making one of those unions and I
guess like I said maybe we really don't
need that header I don't know I'll leave
it on there for now but might be that we
only need the type so with that in mind
we now have the ability to sort of walk
through these however we want to and
process them differently so in the case
where we get it clear we can actually do
the clearing operation here in the case
we get a rectangle we could do the
rectangle operation now we know what the
rectangle operation is it's this right
but you can see this already had a
discriminated operation in it it was
looking to see whether it had a bitmap
or just a regular rectangle so our next
step after we get this working with the
clear is basically going to be let's
pull those two out so now we have the
concept of two different types of
rectangles we can also add rectangle
outlines in here right so now that we
have types we can start to kind of go
nuts with having as many different sorts
of things as we have render operations
which is exactly what I want so let's
keep going with this let me go ahead and
compile so what we have to do now is say
that push piece push piece is actually
doing something slightly different
we've got push render element again I
kind of set us up for success this is a
little bit of the just the experience
talking I kind of know roughly how these
things go so I'm not having to go
through all the steps I would have to go
to to determine what a good architecture
of every bush buffer is I kind of know
one that I like that works but you know
it's not that much different if you
didn't know you just have to go through
more iterations of trying things out but
you'd be programming in roughly the same
way yeah you just wouldn't have that
benefit of the look-ahead that you do
when you've done it before
and it's hard and there's nothing you
can do about that that's just
variants and the more experience you
have the easier it becomes because you
can make better decisions right so
anyway what I want to do here is say
when we push a render element we're now
going to push not only the size of the
render element we're also going to push
the type of the render element and you
know what I should do here I should
actually do this here I'm gonna do even
get another trick this is the full
ridiculousness
of the world you know this is a real
ridiculous trick I'm just going to show
it to you because why not right so what
I'm gonna do here is I'm going to do a
little trick which is like you know
we'll prepend something to the type name
itself to make the identifier so our
types in our enum are the same as our
structures only with this prepended to
them okay and then what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna define push render element to
be a macro the macro is gonna take the
group and it's gonna take the type to
push on okay makes sense and then what
that's gonna do is that's going to call
our actual function it's gonna pass the
group straight through it's gonna take
the size of whatever that type is and
pass that but then it's also gonna go
ahead and take that render group entry
type prefix it's gonna paste it on to
the type game okay you see how I'm doing
that and what that allows us to do is
that allows us to make a nice type safe
way without having to pull in crazy
templates for doing any nonsense there's
there's no fussiness there oh and to
boot up again I'll cast it for it there
so we know it's the same so now we know
we're getting back the right type and we
also know that we're setting the type
field to the correct thing in that step
right so now when we call push render
element all we have to do is say which
one we actually wanted to have right in
this case we wanted to get a rectangle
out of this and once we've done that we
know that everything else will be taken
care of for us so in here we've got that
type we were passing in so when we get
the push buffer result out we want to go
ahead and call that a at least the
a header rank if that makes sense you
can think of this as returning a header
because we know that no matter what we
allocate it will have that sort of
header on it if that makes sense
although I suppose we could go one level
deeper and allow things that don't have
that header on it to be inserted there
that's something we might decide to do
and if that was the case we'll put put a
push size above this one level deeper
again not something we have to worry
about right now so we do that when we
push a render element on when we do this
result here when we grab the result
again we're going to be casting it to
this just so we can sort of access it
and then we're going to say all right
the type equals whatever the type is if
we want to support running out of space
it's actually very easy we just do one
if at the head end of things to make
sure that we actually got one otherwise
its discarded we essentially forget
about it and that's really all we need
to do if that makes sense
it's really pretty straightforward
that's the the underscored one there all
right
so oops what happened there oh sorry
gotta have a paste operate in the right
place there there we go my bad
alright so grabbing out the header right
we'll just do it like this render group
entry header right that gets us our
header and then we're just going to cast
the header to whichever one we want like
so we change the names of these types to
be like this so there they are so and
again oops
like so so now we've got those
straightened out and I believe things
probably will still run just fine they
do and so all we've done now just make
things a little more convenient for
ourselves again to put ourselves in a
more regional position so let's go ahead
and do that next step so let's do one
where we've got sort of bitmap which is
our old call and rectangle which is just
like a solid rectangle right let's pull
those out into two separate cases so
we've got these two cases here I'm going
to pull those out into two separate
cases I
got one which is rendered bitmap I've
got one which is render rectangle and
we're gonna look at these two together
so what we're gonna do is say assert
that this one has a bitmap and draw the
bitmap like so the other one is going to
us essentially just draw it as if it was
a rectangle and now when we look at
these two things we're gonna have two
separate versions here we're going to
have the bitmap version right and then a
rectangle version which doesn't have the
bitmap at all okay those are the two
ones that we're going to have and then
we're gonna compile that right now when
we push this on a push to do a push
piece call we've sort of got two
different pushes to do now we've got the
push piece call that that pushes on a
bitmap and we've got the push piece call
that pushes on a rectangle right and
these right here are the ones that do
rectangle pushes this one and this one
and then we've got the bitmap one which
is here so what I'm going to do is I'm
going to go ahead and sort of I'm going
to take this one step at a time we have
a little more stuff that we want to do
to it but I'm take this one step at a
time so first I'm going to do is I'm
going to still call the push piece
function for the bitmap like that and
it's gonna get called here as we can see
oops
tangle entry bitmap so and inside why
does that not have what did I do
this is bitmap yeah so that should work
except for now we should hit an
assertion the assertion we should hit is
as soon as we try to draw a solid
rectangle and that entry bitmap is not
filled in right and you can see what
that smell so now we have to do is make
it so that when we actually call that
one in particular we will actually push
a rectangle on not something else so
let's take a look at how the when that
push rect ever actually gets used if
that makes sense I can actually see cuz
the five-minute warning is blocking me
the moment which is not what I what I
was hoping for but let's take a look
about push back so we draw hitpoints
we've got draw stare well we've got a
couple of these here we've also got sort
of any space that was drawing rectangle
outlines so when that gets called I'm
just going to duplicate this code for
the time being
duplicate it like so and then we will
take a look at what we can do to make it
so that that's not being duplicated in
that way so there goes the bitmap right
off we go and then we have that a line
which is not actually in there for the
rectangles okay so I think that should
do it for our rectangles and they are
still being thrown as you can see
there's our rectangles they're
underneath the guy as we would expect so
that's fine but we've got a bit of
duplicated code there and there's some
stuff that we want to start to take a
look at in terms of again pulling that
out and like you can see all of this
stuff here kind of being common right
and similarly when we do the push we're
getting that same we're getting a lot of
sort of duplicated code there right so
what I'd like to do is I'd like to kind
of compress that down into something a
little more sort of useable for the time
being at least even if we don't stick
with it what I'd like to do is say okay
there's going to be a shared piece here
there's going to be sort of a render
entity basis or something like this for
lack of a better term where that's
actually kind of gonna gonna have the
basis this offset the offset Z the Z see
that stuff that really is about
positioning it relative to an entity
right I'm gonna pull that stuff out
because it's really sort of a
positioning scheme that has very little
to do with what the shape is that you're
actually drawing right look none of this
has anything to do with the shape that
you're actually drawing like the bitmap
or whatever or the rectangle it's it's
much more specific furthermore we could
also compress these our GPAs down to the
which does seem like a good idea as well
so you know in fact I could even pull
the dimension out there we'll see if
that's a good idea
it might not be a good idea but we'll
see if it's a good idea all right so
let's go ahead and do that then these
guys basically get a new notion of basis
and their basis is actually doubly and
directed right so they've got an entity
basis like so it's not actually in
directed because it's built straight in
but you get the idea right so there we
go now um I also want to do here
what else do I want to okay so then I
can take this stuff and go all right all
I really ever got out of this stuff was
that center bit right all I ever got out
of it was just centered that's it really
so I just need to be able to call my I
just need to be able to call something
that will take one of these entity bases
and do all these computations for me
right so what I want to do is just
introduce a function where you basically
you know you do something like compute
entity offset or compute basis offset
and you notice we've got a little
weirdness here to half dim the half dims
a little odd because what is entry a
that's the Alpha why does this guy never
use the dimension of the bitmap oh
because it's baked it's actually baked
in okay so that's actually that's
actually something we should take care
of as well I probably did this a little
bit too soon all right so let's do this
let's do this into her so I might go
about five minutes over we started a
little bit late so I don't feel too bad
about it so what I want to do is when we
do a push rect call I don't know if you
can see here where is where is that push
vertical oh you know what that's good I
moved it out so we do a push rect call f
did I not pull it out where is pushback
oh it's in the H bar that's right so
when we do a push rect call and these I
could probably move out of the
faul now as well but don't we need to be
in the H file so you know what they
probably shouldn't be let's get them out
of here alright so if I do my push wreck
call I take a look at my push read call
right really I think what should have
happened is we should try to do the
offset we should bake in whatever
whatever that was that we were doing
that made it different from computing
the entity offsets from everything else
right so in here we're doing this thing
where we take the center and we offset
it we really want to make it so that
this is just sort of this coordination
point and they both draw from the same
one so instead of doing a center minus
half dim in a center plus half dim what
we want to do is kind of bake that out
over here I think that seems like a
smarter thing to do to me if that makes
sense
so what I'd like to do is I'd like to
suggest that we go ahead and say well
whatever the meters to pixels was right
we're gonna go ahead and compute that
half dim here right so the dim will just
come come out that way
and then what we're going to do do we
actually when we do draw a rectangle
Center plus half dim center - half dim
yes so this will just turn into
something which instead of using the
half dim actually uses the full dim if
that makes sense like so and I'm trying
to think if there's anything else do we
actually need
where does dim actually get used in here
because I don't actually know so dim
entry bitmap so dim only really gets
used for the rectangles right like so
and so really yeah really what we could
do is we can we can totally sort of slap
this down into something a lot more
sense of sensible so we'll do the meters
to pixels here - to do our dim call
which will actually have here as well
and again we'll start moving things
around a bit here so we'll do it that
way so we'll do basically rp+ empty dim
and we'll start here so that that is
more what I want to see right Pete of X
P that Y like that this is more what I
want to see so they're all based off
this
same point essentially so now we've sort
of gotten rid of the notion that the
other one's different
and then this half dim here when we when
we compute our offset we'll just
subtract that half dim away or of course
I guess we have to do it the two
different ways because of our of our
whole y flipping thing so we have to do
something where we do 1/2 10 dot Y and
our half-game X we want to basically
subtract the 1/2 dim X and add the half
dim why I believe right because of the
way that we're we're flipping things I
don't actually know if that's true I
don't remember what was it what was the
way that we were doing it here let me
take a quick look so I don't remember I
want to make sure we're basically doing
it exactly the same way that we were
before so it was just minus and plus
that's all it was all right here we go
sorry like I said Monday it's a bit
difficult so in here I guess we've
already done anything that we would have
needed to do in that sense so it's just
minus and plus all right I'm gonna leave
it that way and say that that was the
way that it was going to work for now
yeah let's go ahead and let's go ahead
and assume that that's correct for now
well debug it in a second all right so
if I've got that I don't need the v2
there anymore I'm gonna take a look now
at just pulling out that computation and
all that's going to do is like compute
some kind of a entity base for us it's
gonna take one of these guys the render
entity basis right it's gonna be like
get render entity basis P or something
like this it's going to take one of
these which was what entity basis and in
both cases we'll compute that right like
so and then what we'll do is it'll just
do this right so it'll do literally this
chunk of code right here and just in a
duplicated way presumably and so that'll
return a v2 I guess is what that'll do
and let's see render interfaces peak
we'll take one of these oops
I'm going to the basis
like so and so call that entity basis so
and we will also pass it the vendor
group render group that and we will do
that there we will return the value that
computes and we just need to go ahead
and change entry to entity basis that's
mostly all we actually need to do there
and then vaporize this stuff make sure
it's all kosher okay okay so we need
that screen Center X screen Center Y
that's got to be in there so let's go
ahead and pass that screen Center like
so and then in here we will go ahead and
pass vendor group oops
render group and screen Center now
screen Center is probably actually also
known all throughout the pipeline so we
could also choose to sort of bake that
in a little bit further but that's
something we'll get to a little bit
later we also need to take the address
of these and bases here like so and
these are V twos not the threes all
right so our entry it says we don't have
a dim that is a mistake and this was
actually supposed to be pulled out to
just be in the rectangle because I
realized it was only in the rectangle
there where we were doing that so off we
go alright so we've got an empty basis
now we've just got to fill it out again
here are the members of that right and
peace is no longer have dims at all
right if I'm not mistaken those are just
gone and then we also have in here our
render group I guess it's just called
group in here should probably call it
the same thing everywhere but sometimes
again but I'm talking on the screen
stream it's kind of hard for me a lot of
times to concentrate as fully on the
code so the code doesn't come out as
good as I would otherwise I apologize
for that
I do the best I can so alright probably
made some mistakes there but let's see
where we're at
all right so I think we're in good shape
that all looks correct so I guess we can
stop for now we're only a little bit
over so we can go ahead to that Q&amp;A
we're you know we made some decent
headway there we're gonna want to to
keep pushing forwards on this pulling
things out making this a little bit
cleaner you can sort of see it starting
to clean up a little bit and it will
continue to get cleaner over the course
of the week until we've got a really
really nice push buffer system the specs
everything out that we want and then we
can sort of focus our attention to
actually how we turn those into more
efficient drawing calls and add some of
those features that we need like
rotation and scaling which is kind of
where the more media pixel finnicky work
happens all right q : before the
questions please if you could just put Q
:
before your questions so I can see them
and the other thing that I would like to
do is again if you're new to the stream
our post stream questions are for
programming what we actually have been
working on so please keep your questions
confined to that if you want to just do
general chatty questions or off-topic
questions I'm totally all for that but
we do those before the streams so come
back about 15 minutes before a scheduled
start time and ask away I'm happy to
answer them there but I skip I just
flat-out skipped most of the time
questions that are not about the
programming here in the post stream
because I like to concentrate on the
actual code if that makes sense
and student in 73
he's a very frequent viewer I guess I'll
say of the show he is sort of our
resident math expert it would seem from
most of the comments that he makes are
very they're not the kinds of comments
that somebody who doesn't know a lot of
math would ever make
he says warning there may be lots of pre
stream questions today so I guess I'm
glad I warned against that I don't know
if what that means exactly but yeah so
I'm not sure when you meet a bug in the
game and are able to recreate it will
you get a bug line in the programming or
how does it work I'm not sure what that
question is asking exactly but when you
get a bug typically there's two types of
bugs there's ones that are very easy to
track down and you quickly know where
they are so you go find them and fix
them other ones are much more
complicated and you have to spend time
creating situations that allow you to
deduce what's going on and then you can
fix them but I'm not sure what a bug
line is so sorry about that
is it worth aligning render entries hmm
so here's what I'll say at the moment no
probably not and that is because all of
our render entries will already be 8
byte aligned anyway right because
basically you know you've got these you
sort of got these render entries things
and they're all gonna have pointers in
them so they're all gonna be a byte
aligned so you're pretty good to go but
when we start pushing things on that are
more variably sized we will probably
align those because we don't want to
probably leave things on a byte on odd
byte boundaries or anything like that
alignment past that
probably not but I don't know I mean
really the answer is we'd have to test
it you never know with alignment
sometimes it benefits you sometimes it
hurts you if you spend a lot of time
patting things out for alignment and
then but that ends up taking more total
space you may find that your memory
bandwidth or cache pollution or
something becomes that eats up any games
you could have gotten from any sort of
alignment win right what is mantle
mantle is AMD's direct Hardware access
well direct narrowly direct more direct
graphics API for accessing their GPUs
any recommendations of some reading
about GPUs rendering rasterization
except for a Google search for once when
someone asks that question because I get
that sort of question a lot like do you
have any good ideas for reading about
blah and I'm always have to be like no I
don't know where this image is I do
actually I absolutely do and what you
want to do is go to Fabien x' blog when
I grow up I'll be an inventor
this one right here Fabien blog is
Fabien Gazin he works at rad
he's like definitely one of the best
programmers I know or have ever known
for that matter and if he happens to
have written in a blog entry about
something much like I said if Raymond
Chen writes a blog entries about Windows
programming you probably want to read it
if Fabien writes an entry about
programming especially graphics or
optimization you really want to read it
and in this case we are lucky enough
that he has written one about the
graphics pipeline so what you can do is
you can go in here and there's a
graphics pipeline one I would highly
recommend clicking on that and if you
can set aside some time for going
through these you can start here on port
1 and he will set you up for
understanding a lot of the stuff that
has to do with why graphics works the
way it does right it's really great it's
it's gonna be even probably more
then he knows more than I do about it so
it's gonna cover probably even more than
what we will cover so if you can spend
the time to dig into some of this and
understand it you will probably a very
happy camper now regrettably is a 2011
trip through the graphics pipeline which
means that it is a little out of date
and graphics does sort of change over
time but to say the very least
it will certainly give you the
perspective you would need to understand
a graphics pipeline from 2015 because
they don't change that much and it will
give you the right perspective so that
you'll be able to read other stuff that
tells you how it's been updated and
understand what they're saying when they
tell you that right so very very very
important blog highly recommend reading
it and this series in particular for the
question you were asking is definitely
the one to read I can't think of
anything else that's even close although
there may be some that I'm just unaware
of but that's that's the one and if you
actually mean internalize all of this
you'll probably know more about the reax
life with them than I do I don't think
I've read all of these in the lip at the
level of detail that I probably should
have so you know I would I would highly
recommend them
why use pointers over references there
is no difference between those two
things pointers are just a superset
right so the reason I use point instead
of reference is is that pointers or
references do exactly the same thing
there's no in especially when we're not
using any C++ features really we use a
little bit of C++ suite but we you know
our coding style is very C like we don't
use a lot of C++ isms a pointer in a
reference both mean the same thing
there's no difference between the two of
them in terms of what the CPU is gonna
do it's not telling it to do anything
differently and so pointer is a superset
of a reference because the reference
can't be assigned to something else
right a pointer can be changed to assign
something else a reference can't be
although my understanding is they they
change that recently I think I have want
to say I want to say that the new C++
spec actually allows you to change what
references point or something I don't
even remember it's kind of silly
so yeah references they don't do
anything so I don't use them they're
kind of a useless language feature
honestly they don't actually do anything
so I don't use them because you know why
add complexity for no reason you have to
use pointers you're going to use
pointers because pointers are very
important to do a bunch of things that
you want to be able to do like
arithmetic and references can't do those
things and so they're just kind of a
weaker pointer so I don't like to use
them
about mantle were you aware AMD drop
development for it and put a lot of that
manpower to helping push Vulcan no
actually I'm not aware of that yet I
mean I I well I was aware that they were
trying to help with Vulcan and trying to
make mantle sort of be a basis for
Vulcan and so on I did know they were
doing that but I didn't know they were
dropping support for mantle yet are you
sure I mean I I don't follow AMD very
closely sorry AMD people no offense I
just don't so I had no idea for all I
knew you know Vulcans not a thing yet
right so for all I knew I assumed they
were still going to do mantle at some
point but maybe they're not
the push buffer is an abstraction layer
relying on memory for communication
instead of a bunch of functions if I
understand correctly is that how you
prefer API design in general the answer
is yes I I do prefer API designed to be
memory based not function based and the
reason for that is I feel like it's
better SPECT it's more flexible it has a
bunch of important aspects things you
can do for it such as tracing capture
and stuff like that and so API is that
are based on functions tend to be hairy
they tend to be complex they tend to be
difficult to document whereas API is
based on memory layout tend to be the
opposite of all those things so yeah
it's what I prefer certainly for
anything like a renderer there are other
times when maybe API is make more sense
become a stay P has make more sense
because you have kind of a sprawling
concern like the whole game for example
has pieces that have api's in them and
you wouldn't want to turn those into
memory api's because they're just it's
gonna be too complex for that so I guess
I should say I prefer that kind of API
design when you have a problem it's
straightforward like rendering is that
has very well-defined ins and outs in
that way any more questions about the
code anyone anyone not seeing any so I
think we're close to wrapping up I would
say yeah
all right well I don't see any more code
questions so I guess we are done here
yeah seems good I think that basically
the push buffer stuff should be
relatively clear again no mystery here
we we need it for two reasons we need it
one sort of to support that multi target
stuff I like to use it to support the
multi target stuff but also for the
sorting and sort of organization all the
things that are coming out of the game
so we're going to try and push towards
that one thing that we'll probably try
to do relatively soon after we get some
of these more of these divisions in
there a little bit more as we'll try to
add that sorting in and that'll actually
fix a bug that we've had for a while
right if you remember our little dude
here he goes behind trees sometimes
depending on the order in which the game
happens to traverse those entities so
that will fix that bug for us which is
kind of nice you know it's just nice to
kind of have that taken care of for us
so that's good so yeah so I would I
would say that we'll get like a nice
benefit out doing that and then soon
after that we'll probably get another
benefit to which is that our integer
snap coordinates which kind of cause you
can see a little shimmering and the two
in the trees they kind of have that sort
of stopping pattern which you see a lot
in games nowadays actually I've seen
like a lot of 8-bit games or sort of
demake style games having this kind of
ugly jitter we'll be fixing that pretty
soon as well too because now we'll have
a real renderer that can deal with that
stuff properly it makes a big difference
and so we'll try to take care of that as
well
so anyway good stuff on the horizon I'm
excited to get the renderer taken care
of as well so let's go ahead and save
our state here on the blackboard will
close down our compiler in our editor
and we will close down for the day I'll
double check to make sure there's any
other questions
see if there's anything else does not
look like it all right so thank you
everyone for joining me for another
episode of handmade hero that pleasure
coding with you as always I am excited
to do some renderer works this is going
to be a fun week I think it's it's I
don't know getting stuff on the screen
graphically is
he's fun so tweaking with that it's just
it's a lot of fun
so anyway I'm excited to do that it just
kind of emerged it's just where the code
was going so we're going there that's
just how it's gonna go so I hope you'll
join me tomorrow again 5:00 p.m. Pacific
Daylight Time again hope see here on
Twitch same time same place if you would
like to follow along the source code you
can always preorder on handmade hero org
the game if you preorder the game you
get the source code during the whole
development so you can keep downloading
it playing with it doing whatever you
want right up till the day we ship and
if you want to do that you can do that I
have my hero org you can also if you
want to support our video series this
educational series you can subscribe to
our patreon always much appreciated we
also have a forums page and the forums
page is where you can ask questions or
find ports Mac and Linux there's also an
episode guide on there that's pretty
cool catch up with past episodes there's
a tweet bop tweets the schedule so if
you want to know when the video series
will be live that's the place to go so
definitely check that out and yeah I
hope you guys are gonna have a good week
and I hope to see you back here tomorrow
for some more renderer action
take it easy everyone