here we go hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the show we code a
complete game live on stream we are back
for an exciting Monday after last Friday
when we implemented Hardware display of
our game so now we're actually going
through the GPU to display our game I
thought that was gonna take longer than
it did it turned out to really not take
very long at all which means here we are
on Monday
and I don't necessarily know what we
should be doing there's a number of
different things we could do like I said
there's a number of things on our list
that we want to do and I'm not sure what
the the most logical one is and so
there's a I guess what I would say is it
feels to me like probably the best thing
to do is since we had some momentum on
the GPU stuff and people don't seem to
be minding to much that we're doing GPU
stuff I think maybe the most convenient
thing for us to do would just be to
actually look a little more seriously at
the GPU stuff and maybe show how to make
our renderer go through the GPU so that
we can basically pick which one we want
to do whether we want our software
rendering or whether we want our GPU
rendering because really that is
incredibly incredibly simple to do
there's really not very much work
involved in it especially because we
don't really even have to take a step
into shaders to do that a little later
on in our game we probably will have to
do that because as we decide to add a
little more lighting and stuff
we'll probably want our students just I
want probably just really need for the
most part shaders to do what it is that
we're gonna want to do and so at some
point we'll have to do that but even
with just what I've taught so far you
can pretty much forth the entire game
except for one thing so there's really
only one hard thing that stands in our
way of making that work and that thing
is how to get the textures like
basically the bitmaps that we're using
for the game like you know our little
sprites it's how to get those down to
the card in a in a efficient fashion
and so if you recall how our
architecture works at the moment we
don't have to think about that because
what happens is that when we find that
we need an image or predict that we're
going to need an image on a frame that's
coming up soon mmm choosing we really
don't have to do anything other than get
it off the drive and then put it in
memory in a location where our render
can get it and that's a very
straightforward operation because it's
entirely on the CPU and there's no need
to communicate with the graphs card
about anything there all we need to do
is have a flag basically on our side
that says this thing has finished
loading you can now draw with it so that
the renderer doesn't try to draw with it
before it's actually finished loading
that's that's really all we had to do
now when we go to doing this on the GPU
all of the rendering stuff can pretty
much stay exactly the same as it did and
the reason for that is because the
amount of of command throughput that
we're going to have is just not that
complicated in a 2-d game like this even
if we have thousands of sprites on the
screen that's just not a really high
amount of traffic to send down to the
graphics card but for our texture data
there is a lot of data we're a 1920 by
1080 game we've got a lot of full screen
layers in like our cutscene for example
so even just for the intro sequence
alone there's a lot that we might have
to manage there and we don't want to
have a stuttery framerate while we're
doing transfers of stuff like those
plates and so we need to insert an extra
stage in our asset streaming to be able
to stream textures to the graphics card
in some kind of a reasonable way and
that is not always as easy as it should
be there's nothing inherently
complicated about it but unfortunately
GPUs were not designed to do it
originally that you know textures were
typically not streamed in real time they
were uploaded during like a loading
screen and so nowadays when you're
actually trying to stream the api's
aren't really set up for it so you have
to kind of go through some extension
mechanisms to really do it and not all
cards
support it well some are very buggy with
it there's sort of this concept of
fencing you have to use to sort of do
stuff like know when something it's
finished uploading this there's just a
lot of complexity there so I think maybe
you know just what I'm leaning towards
is maybe what we do is we poured
everything over and we just let our
frame rate be very stuttery at the
moment when something needs to be
download of the card we just do it and
we accept the fact that it's stuttery
right maybe we do that and then what we
can do is look at that as a separate
issue and choose to address it at
whatever time it is that we feel is
necessary we would have to address it
eventually if we can't really leave it
that way it'll have to get fixed at some
point but that's probably the way to
keep things easy enough to understand at
first without having to force people
into too much of a GPU understanding
right off the bat because the rest of
stuff is is relatively simple so I think
maybe that's what I'll start doing today
and that way we can sort of get that
working and then we can kind of get all
that going maybe this that's what we'll
do this week and then we'll sort of end
with having the ability to switch
between the two renders and then we can
turn on vsync which is one of the
reasons I wanted to be able to go these
paths and we'd also then then have a
path that we would know would always be
fast enough to run at 60 frames a second
1920 by 1080 so we can also test with
the GPU so it doesn't force our hand at
forcing us to optimize our software
rasterizer if that's not what we want to
do in the short term right which let's
be honest I was never expecting to
suffer a renderer to run 1920 by 1080 by
64 and sorry that was totally crazy that
it ended up actually tuning that and so
you know I don't necessarily want to
sort of insert into the stream this
constant need for us to go back and
optimize that when that's really was
never supposed to be a thing was most
mostly educational the reason we're
doing it just happened to be really fast
so anyway let's go ahead and take a look
at that now today's day 2:38 so you're
gonna want to if you're falling along at
home if you preorder the game on
handmade
you're gonna want to start with day 237
source code that's what I'm starting
with today and just to sort of refresh
your memory about where we left off here
is me running the game and you can kind
of see that this is exactly what we
would have expected it to look like only
now it's running through a graphics card
instead of running through you know a
software renderer and you can kind of
see that that everything still works the
same way that it did now if I remember
correctly I think there was a bug in my
in my float conversion because I feel
like if we let this guy run
didn't-didn't we get to a point where
there is a bug in the radix sort or
something and I'm guessing it probably
wasn't actually in the radix sort is
probably in my my float to int
conversion code but I just feel like at
some point here maybe when it gets to
the next scene it we have an assertion
that the sort order wasn't correct
that's just my recollection and and I
don't I don't actually know if that's
true but I felt like that was true mmm
well I don't know maybe we have to get
to a further out scene I'm not sure I
just felt like that was true was that
not true well I mean well I'm sure it'll
it'll crop up again if if I'm if I'm not
mistaken
next time we kind of leave it running so
I guess I don't have to worry about that
for now cuz you know next time we sort
of preview our our cut scene it should
happen if it's gonna happen so I don't
know what's going on there well that's
interesting so in this sort we have two
things at the same Z level and you can
see that Santa Claus has has moved
behind the background there's not good
right so now that we're sorting in Z we
kind of have to deal with that although
we could also have a way for cutscenes
and stuff like that to turn off the Z
sorting entirely if we wanted to since
we don't actually
see sorting for this that's worth noting
so it looks kind of like maybe I'm wrong
about that I don't know it I thought
there was a bug but maybe there wasn't
we'll see if it crops up again and we'll
take a look at it if it does okay so
here we go let's go ahead and and talk
about what we're gonna do here so right
now you can kind of see what happens
where we have our rendering we we have a
very sort of properly in my opinion
walled off renderer in the sense that we
don't really count on very much about
the renderer in the external code so
really all that happens is we called
like you know tiled render group to
output and stuff like that that's really
all that happens so we we push a bunch
of stuff on that are like you know
instructions to the renderer to do
something specific and then we call like
this tiled render group to output and
then we call and render and that's
that's really all there is to it
right so it's not it's not super
hands-on and that's somewhat intentional
because the idea here is that I've kind
of known all along that you know the
renderer is something that may want to
be swapped out for example in the exact
case that we're talking about here where
we have a software one and then we also
want to have a hardware one right and
even if you didn't want to have software
and hardware you might for example have
two different Hardware ones for example
people ask about Vulcan or direct3d and
that sort of stuff well if someone was
going to port the renderer to one of
those other one of those other API is
you know you may be on a driver that
doesn't support say Vulcan yet and so if
you have a Vulcan path you may still
need to have an OpenGL like fallback
path right or similarly if you have like
a DirectX 12 path you may need a
fallback path for machines that don't
have DirectX 12 right maybe you're
running on Windows 7 which doesn't run
DirectX 12 so it's just kind of one of
those things that if you're a
professional game programmer you have
probably gotten into the habit just by
nothing other than experience of keeping
the renderer
sort of separated out even before you
get to the point where you really need
to now is it essential to do that at a
time no it's always fine to sort of like
again use a more compression or an
approach and like start separating it
out at the time that you need to but
because that's just something that I you
know I'm just well aware of I just tend
to write renderers from the start at
this point to be fairly modular in that
sense so it's already set up to be
pretty reasonable as as it as you know
it's something that can be swapped out
but it's not quite there yet right we
haven't done the work of really truly
separating it out and so what I'd like
to do now is start to move you know
start to extract it out in its entirety
so that we really can choose which you
know how we want to actually render
things whether we want them to be
hardware or software based and so
there's a couple different ways we can
do this and it depends on how much code
we actually want to share now you can
kind of look at our render group in here
and this is all the code for the
software renderer right but if you
actually take a look at where the the
work actually gets done you know we do
our sort entries for example and then we
go into sort of this do tiled render
work thing and the do tiled render work
I always fail at searching for that
because it's wrapped in the Emacs can't
find it because it's wrapped in this
platform work queue callback thing but
really this thing right here render
group to output this is where all the
time is spent right it's all of the time
is spent going through these things and
calling one of these rendering functions
and specifically for our purposes
obviously we optimize the expensive one
so draw rectangle quickly is really the
one that we're spending most of our time
and almost everything goes to that path
okay and what you'll notice about this
is really all of the stuff that actually
determines what the game looks like on
screen goes through this function so if
we want to render to a piece of hardware
instead of rendering to you know instead
of rendering through our software
renderer really all we have to do is
produce a new version of this
function that instead of dispatching to
our software renderer dispatches to say
OpenGL so I'm just gonna literally start
by doing exactly that thing so I'm gonna
go ahead here and you know we're gonna
open up Winton if you handmade and I'm
going to make a new file that's like
handmade OpenGL render group and really
what this is and you know what honestly
I don't even know if that name needs to
be that long I'm just gonna call it
handmade OpenGL and we're just gonna
start with that and say that we'll just
put whatever opengl stuff is in there
okay and so here is our render group to
output call okay and I'm just gonna
literally translate this into something
that that will I think will work with
opengl and so what we can see here is
that this entry coordinate system thing
that was always a test thing we don't
really need that at the moment at all
right that's not doing anything and so I
can I can literally just leave that case
and not do anything with it okay
we've got this guy here which is how we
draw most of our sprites we've got clear
and we've got rectangle so far that's
all we actually have to deal with in our
render it's really it's it's very very
straightforward right it's very simple
and so if we take a look at what happens
now does this does this sort entries
thing ever even get called it doesn't
does it so it's really just so sort of
oh well it kind of gets used right here
I guess so anyway if we take a look at
what actually happens in this routine
it's not really particularly difficult
to imagine replacing this very small
number of operations that we have to do
with their equivalents in OpenGL now
clear right we've already seen how that
works so there really wouldn't be any
thing magic for us to do about clear we
could literally just come in here and do
exactly what what this says we have a
color value here right and and we know
the target width and height so really
everything
that we might want to do here is it's
really straightforward for us I'm gonna
go ahead and and pull this out here
temporarily just for another reason it
looks like a butt so if I wanted to
clear we just need to know what the
color is and then we do the color buffer
Bickler that's really it and of course
the color if we go look at what the
color actually is inside handmade render
group dot h we've got that clear entry
where is that guy it's just a v4 so you
know literally we can just pass this
thing down exactly as it is and we
really shouldn't have to do anything
else okay so passing that down and
clearing that would be a complete
implementation of the clear command
that's it so that's nice and now we're
just left with two ways to fill a
rectangle one way to fill a rectangle we
have to actually do it with a solid
color and the other way we have to do it
with a with a with an image right so the
image one's going to be the hard one for
the reason that I was talking about
before it's because we really don't have
any notion at the moment of how we're
gonna background load those things so
that's gonna be an issue but we'll cross
that bridge when we come to it
for now what we'll do is let's just say
that we draw both of these basically the
same way so we're gonna draw them both
as solid colored rectangles we'll just
do that for now and then we'll kind of
go from there all right so if we start
by doing that let's see if you take a
look at what happens here the this is
our rectangle our rectangle goes from
here to here and it's in this color so
if that's what we're trying to do if
this is essentially our min P you know
what I'm saying and this is our max P in
terms of where they are on the screen
and here is our color that we're gonna
do for our rectangle if that's what
we're looking at then again we already
pretty much learned exactly how to do
this in fact we really learned already
how to do all of these things right you
can kind of see how I was doing these
here with this DL begin
angles thing we already sort of have
exactly the code that we're doing for
this so we could do that exact same code
with with really no effort right we
could just go ahead and say all right go
ahead and draw some triangles here and
instead of like negative P P that sort
of thing instead of drawing it that way
let's just use our min px right and our
min P Y that sort of thing and then this
would be our max px
Sabir minge-y I mean essentially it I'm
just doing negative P with min P is all
I'm doing and and P with P with max P
right that's all we're talking about and
and that's it now there is actually even
a I don't know that we actually want to
do this but we can you can you can even
if you want to when you're passing a
vector there's a FV style call like
where you pass a vector where you back
to just pass a poor nerd the floats I'm
not going to do that because we mix and
match a fair bit here so I'm not going
to bother doing that I just wanted to
kind of point it out but it's there you
can actually pass vector a step in jail
that way just as a rays of flutes
so we have our min P we have a max beam
in P right of 1 0 we have max max min
min Max Max and min max that looks that
looks right to me so that would draw our
triangle now we do have one problem that
you'll notice here that weeds with that
we'd have to solve fairly soon which is
that this brings up the coordinate
problem again which is that we this is
remember we talked about the unit cube
all of these coordinates are in the unit
cube and we don't have yet a projection
matrix that will actually give us
something that would correctly map us
into the unit cube for these coordinates
that we're passing which are actually
screen space coordinate that we've
already transferred so that's a problem
but other than that this would do
exactly what we would want it to do
right
and so in both cases for four rectangles
we could do exactly this in fact we
could really do the same exact thing we
could just have a function up here which
is like rectangle vertices or something
like this and or I guess I should say
just rectangle opengl rectangle I don't
know something like this and we could we
can just have this be something that you
pass these two and then we can just use
it right so we can say okay there's a
min P there's a max P there's a color
and that's it right and so that's pretty
straightforward the color value we would
probably just do like so because the
entire thing typically has a color value
that's not interpolated so that's
roughly what that would look like and
off we would go so there's our Open GL
rectangle now there's a number of
reasons why we probably won't end up
doing it exactly this way and the reason
for that is because this is just a lot
of function calls and stuff and when we
get up to higher numbers of primitives
we're gonna want to do these in a more
efficient way and in fact open jail has
more efficient ways of doing it that
we'll look at a little bit later and
basically what they involve is packing
all of these things into one buffer so
we just write out a big buffer and then
we just say hey Open GL take this whole
buffer as if it's a bunch of vertices
and draw it that way right so you know
don't be don't be deceived although this
looks like just a lot of business
happening here and it's like wow that's
a lot of function calls going on for
every rectangle or whatever yes that's
true but really we'll be able to flatten
that down into just one function call
sort of as we after we get everything
working and want to start just
concentrating on cleaning up the the
usage a little bit more so don't let
that bother you too much it's really not
an issue but it's usually best to kind
of leave it this way when you're first
learning because you can see exactly
what's going on it's a lot easier you'd
have to worry about what is OpenGL how
is OpenGL parsing your buffer and did
you pass it the right sort of waited to
decode it and all that's
there's a lot of business that comes in
with the parsing that's why you may want
to not you know just not quite do that
at first that's why I'm not showing that
as the first thing we do so we can do
this this in both cases here we have the
entry color I can now convert this to
basically doing the same thing that it
was doing before but calling our OpenGL
version of functions so there we go
there's the opengl rectangle for that in
this case we have essentially the same
thing but we've got to do a little bit
differently so here's our entry P I
believe our entry P it's like these two
vectors are what stretched to the other
side so in this case we probably want to
actually compute that max P and can I
guess in this case maybe we do say both
of these so we've got our min P is going
to be the entropy and our max P is going
to be you know sort of the things
stretched or sorry displaced by these to
get to the other corner right so there's
our min game and then entry color is
still the same so so really if you know
if you take a look at what this what
this turns out to be here I guess I also
don't know why why do we pass no pixels
to meters to that function does anyone
know
what is that use for absolutely nothing
all right I think that was only for when
we had lighting and I guess we still
pass it for some reason that's not
immediately clear but it looks like that
can just completely go away great so so
there's I mean at the risk of of sort of
being overly dismissive of how hard it
is to get us off for to get a hardware
renderer working hey since there's just
a ton of hardware there to do everything
for you really honestly this is
basically what what it looks like and so
we really just have to do a few simple
things to start with we would have to
obviously set up the viewport to be
based on whatever the output thing was
here so but really that's about it
there's there's not really a whole lot
more to it so we have to do that to get
ourselves set up correctly for drawing
but other than that it's really not that
complicated so let's talk a little bit
about the things that we're not doing
yet so we're not doing the texturing so
we need to do this part right here so
that part's not done our rectangles are
basically done it's just our texturing
isn't done so we need to figure out a
way to do the texturing part of it so
that's one thing but the other thing
that we need to do is like I said we
need to now establish a screen space
because what we did before again was
just actually give it coordinates that
were the unit cube and that doesn't
really help us when we actually have to
start drawing individual rectangles at
different places on the screen so what
we want to do now is we want to be able
to set up our matrices so that our our
projection matrix when OpenGL actually
uses the projection matrix that
projection matrix actually Maps our
coordinates into the unit cube for us
from our screen space okay that that's
what we would like that's what we would
like to have happen okay so how do we do
that
well if you've been paying attention to
our maths and you know maths the plural
of course coming from the Britain then
you should actually kind of already have
an idea of how we would do this this is
not really a mystery and it's not
particularly complicated sometimes it
can take a little while to get right
because hey there's enough sort of fuzzy
things around that that could be
possible but in general pretty basic
here is how this works right as I told
you before in OpenGL what happens is we
have a point in clip space and that gets
computed from the points that we pass in
right so our actual P gets passed in and
it's multiplied by M projection a
projection matrix and an M Model View
right and like I was saying before
although we haven't really covered this
much in hand-made here oh these are
actually multiplied together so for all
intents and purposes it's just one
matrix it's just like what we do know
there's really just one M and since we
have set our modelview matrix to the
identity matrix which means it doesn't
do anything essentially our entire
opengl fixed function pipeline operation
at this point looks like this okay this
is all we're doing so we're literally
just doing a P prime equals M P the most
basic vector transform you could
possibly do you know we're multiplying a
for this is this is a four element right
this is a four by four and producing
another four and remember the reason
it's four is because it's X Y Z W it's
got that synthetic coordinate now in our
case we don't use Z right we're not
actually using Z because we've handled
that so this is Z is always zero right
for all intents for us we don't care
what it is and since we're transferring
points W is always 1 so really we're
just talking about XY 0 1 is the vector
we're always transforming and M is this
matrix that we can set up to be whatever
want so we know that we're trying to
produce a P prime here that has the
structure that looks like this we want Z
to stay zero or really honestly we don't
care it doesn't matter what Z is at all
to us to be honest so we don't really
care what what Z actually is beyond just
respecting what OpenGL needs it to be
and trying to think of how to to say
this essentially there's a step that we
have not talked about that occurs after
you do your transform and that is if you
are trying to do the perspective stuff
that we covered a while back what
happens is whenever you transfer them
you end up with something in the the W
coordinate and OpenGL will divide the
vector by whatever that value is so if
the W coordinate is like three or
something it will divide this out to
produce a one so it will divide
everything by three the reason it does
that is that's the hacked way and hacked
may be a strong term there's a little
bit of mathematical rigor to it but the
reason for that is if you remember how
we did our divide by Z thing to sort of
get the perspective so that things
shrink as they get further from the
camera that's how they work that in
there because remember a matrix
transform is always linear and dividing
by Z is totally not linear right just to
be completely clear if even if I was
just to talk about the single variable Z
that's Z to the first power
that's linear right and we're talking
about something that is now doing Z you
know to some kind of a of an inverse
power right it would be Z to the
negative 1 power it'd be 1 over Z which
is in no way to the power of 1 so
basically the way that they hack that
into the pipeline to make it sort of
still feel like it's all matrix e is it
just it's specified that after you do
this matrix transformation you do
I'd buy the W coordinate to
quote-unquote renormalize write or
reimagine eyes those coordinates where W
is always going to be equal to two one
it's I don't really know what to say
about it it's it's not we could kind of
go into that in a little more detail but
I'd rather just kind of leave that be
for now because it's really it's more of
a topic for when you're starting to
think about how to do 3d transforms with
these and we just don't have that in
hand made here we've already talked
about how to handle the perspective with
Z and so really it's just kind of a
topic that's super not relevant here so
point being we're gonna leave that
bottom part we're just not really gonna
think about that much we're just going
to assume that we come out with a 0 &amp; 1
here and we're gonna make that be true
so it's really just the X and the y that
we care about right and this part that
has to be in clip space like I said clip
space is this sort of synthetic
coordinate system where a negative one
is over here this is negative 1 negative
1 this is 1 1 right
thank you I shouldn't bother drawing
that there and so it's sort of this this
this dimension to cube right that's
that's it's sort of radius 1 in all
directions you might say and what we
need to do is we need to map the entire
visible screen into this space which
means that in order to do the coordinate
system we want where our coordinates are
currently like 0 to width of the screen
or something like that that's what we
have we need to essentially divide and
displace our values so that 0 ends up
being mapped to negative 1 and width
ends up being mapped to 1 right that's
what we actually need to have happen
here and it I agree it's kind of stupid
that we have to do that because OpenGL
is then just gonna turn right back
around and remap negative 1 and 1 to 0
to width so we're literally doing this
for no other reason than to shoehorn it
into the GPUs concept of what the
graphics boat pipeline is supposed to
look at look
like oh well life is hard but a small
price to pay to access all the power on
the GPU so you know who cares so anyway
so that's what we actually have to do
and so that's what we have to setup our
matrix to do so what we're essentially
doing here is we're saying okay we need
to set up a matrix and we can really
think of these matrices in in ass more
simplified fashion when we don't care
what those bottom values and we don't
have to do anything the bottom values if
we know that we're inputting something
that looks like this and we know that
we're outputting something that looks
like this right then it tells us some
things about this matrix that allow us
to sort of by default fill in some
values so we don't have to think too
hard about a bunch of the different
values for example if this has to be
equal to one well the X and the y value
that's coming in here obviously can't be
multiplied by anything because if they
were we might be we might end up with an
on one value here so essentially all we
want at the bottom is just something
that reproduces the one so we want to
knock out all of these terms and just be
left with the one technically we could
put anything we wanted here because this
is OE zero but it seems like better to
leave it zero so that we know even if we
pass the Z coordinate we'd still get a
one okay so we know that we want this
this to come through a zero we don't
want anything in there at the moment not
that it really matters so since this is
a zero and this is a zero I feel like
maybe we just treat that as a pass
through so that again would be almost
exactly the same it's just the identity
matrix kind of portions here so that way
we just take whatever is in here and we
pass it through here right and that
seems fine and then furthermore this
value we never want to affect these
values so we're essentially saying that
when it whatever it gets multiplied by
in these remember because it's going to
be it's gonna be x times this location Y
times this location plus you know this
times this location plus this times this
location you can kind of see that we
already know that we don't want our Z
value ever to affect anything so even if
it wasn't zero we want to make sure that
it doesn't actually affect our x and y
for the time being because that's not
something we actually
wanted that happen so really what that
means is we're left with just some very
specific places here we're left with
essentially something that looks like
this right something sort of like this
and what we can sort of see about the
equation as this comes out I don't know
can I erase there we go
what we can see about what happens to
this equation if we assume a priori that
this is what it's going to look like is
that we'd have ax plus B y plus e right
if I just doing the multiplication here
right ax B Y e and then I was gonna just
do the exact same thing here CX plus dy
plus F right there we go so if you take
a look at what happens there these are
our equations that we know we're going
to have as a result and so we can using
these equations sort of back figure out
what our what values we want to put in
for these coefficients in our matrix to
give us the transform that we want so
what we know now is we want write ax
plus B y plus e right that's our x
coordinate we want that equation to
essentially be something that takes in
right we're trying to produce a function
that takes in an x value and outputs a
new x value such that this was in the
range from from zero to width and this
is in the range of negative 1 to 1
okay so what we know is that for example
since we're not rotating things we can
pretty much say one additional thing
since the Y value doesn't have any
participation here like it doesn't
matter what the Y value is for our
computation of the X we can also say
that like these terms similarly the X as
now becomes 2 might we could say that
these terms also are irrelevant right
because we don't were not rotating
anything so we don't ever need the Y
component to move into the X space or
vice versa
so we can also kind of get rid of these
all right so we're back we're down to a
really really simple equation we're
basically saying f of X you know equals
ax plus B here in this case and we're
saying F of y equals dy plus F in this
case we've got a little bit of too many
FS here but oh well life goes on in fact
this is probably a G it's a separate
function right so we've got these two
functions and we just want something
that does this mapping and it's pretty
easy for us to figure out what that
would be right because this mapping
defines exactly what we want
we know that for X for example our f of
0 we want to be equal to negative 1 and
we know that our f of width we want to
be equal to 1 and that's two sort of
equations we have right and we only have
two unknowns a and E so if you write
this out right if you write this out
just substituting if x is 0 then we
would have a times zero plus e equals
negative 1 and that immediately just
tells us that e equals negative 1 right
because that term goes away so there
we're done we solve one term right and f
of width equals one well then we know
again multiplying this or rather
expanding this out we would just have a
times width plus e equals 1 we know that
e is negative 1 right yeah sorry it's
right up above there not sure why I'm
forgetting so we have a width minus 1
equals 1 or a width equals 2 right and
hey guess what you divide this out and
you get width or sorry a equals 2 over
width right so that lets us know exactly
what our what our function for for f is
in this case and it allows us to fill in
our matrix exactly what we wanted our
II in this case is a negative one RA in
this case is a 2 over width and you can
kind of see why that is right it's
because we're trying to expand it to a
thing that's 2 units wide
right remember our unit cube is 2 units
wide we're trying to expand this thing
as 2 units wide we're trying to get rid
of the fact that it goes from 0 to width
we want to be 0 to 1 or so we can map it
as a unit interval right so we're
dividing by with to normalize this to 0
to 1 right we're multiplying by 2 to
blow it out to a 2 wide thing and then
we're offsetting it by that one to make
sure that we shift it back over so that
it starts at negative 1 instead of 0 so
you can you can see that we solve the
math purely algebraically but it makes
concrete sense when we look at it over
here and hey big surprise these
equations are exactly the same so you
know we don't even have to solve the
other one we know it's just going to be
2 over height and minus 1 right so that
tells us exactly what our matrix looks
like now our matrix is just this matrix
right it's the 2 over width wow that's
really bad handwriting 2 over width 0 0
0 sorry negative 1 0 2 over height 0
negative 1 0 0 1 0 and 0 0 0 1 okay and
that's the thing that will compress us
down into that unit cube so you know we
probably don't want to jump right into
trying that right away because hey we've
got all this other work over here too
like we don't even know how we're going
to call this function this handmade open
yield function so what we can do instead
is we can jump over to the stuff that we
already have working right because you
know we've got this thing over here
where we've we've got this code working
where we're drawing stuff we should be
able to test it over here because you
know we probably we only got like 15
minutes left we probably don't have time
to get all the rest of stuff working
over there today right let's test just
that one piece over here
and get that working in something that
we know works so let's shift this
remember we fixed this by just directly
passing the coordinates to the unit cube
let's go back to doing it the way we
were doing it before let's go back to
doing it with in fact you know what we
could do we could just use the min P Max
P thing we were doing over here right we
could just take this open jail rectangle
thing exactly how it is here it hears
that like so let's get rid of that so
there's our Open GL rectangle function
and I guess we you know at the moment we
could still leave the color thing in
here I suppose we could just say that
the color is you know all one's just
white so we can still do exactly this
thing and now we can specify our min P
and our max P like so so we know our min
P is just going to be 0 0 and we knew
our max B is going to be buffer width
buffer height I believe I'm sorry window
width window height is that correct no
that's not correct that's not correct at
all we actually want it it's in it's in
terms of the buffer I believe right at
the moment there's some aspect ratio
stuff we would want to do here I'll fact
I'll mention that to do decide how we
want to handle aspect ratio black bars
for prop so yeah it's not really that
it's actually the buffer within the
buffer height right because that's
that's the actual size that we're trying
to fit into the display so I believe
that would be a more correct way of
looking at it probably but you can it's
six of one half dozen the other it
depends on exactly what you're trying to
do so you could pass either there and it
would just have different behavior when
you when the window isn't the same size
as the back buffer if they're the same
size it won't matter so anyway that's an
example of that and now if we run it
we'll go back to the old bug we have
right where we've kind of got this thing
where you know we're drawing in the
wrong place and we're drawing like I
know you can't probably tell exactly
what's going on there
but we're basically drawing like one
pixel of our of our bitmap right weird
it's like totally wrong because it's
huge
remember the whole thing is specified
from negative 1 to 1 and we're passing
like 1920 like we're passing something
that's that's that's like a thousand
times the screen size as the coordinate
you know over in the corner not not what
we would want right so let's go ahead
and try to fix that with our projection
matrix so we have load identity here
what we're gonna want to do now is learn
one new OpenGL call which is a way to
load something other than the identity
so what we want to do is do like load
matrix call and there's a couple of
different ones of these which I'll kind
of show you now they basically are the
same as sort of the other ones where you
say what you are you you know what kind
of matrix are you passing let me find
something here that's a documentation
for it the service is unavailable okay I
don't know what that means
I don't want Stack Overflow I want like
a spec page please how about this is
this that doesn't seem to be loading
here we go all right
so here you can see geo load matrix D
and G load matrix F the two flavors of
this and again like I said it's kind of
almost like a Hungarian notation sort of
a thing it's not really as bad as some
very notation it's it's actually kind of
good because in this case unlike
Hungarian tation which is completely
useless
this actually differentiates these two
functions for a calling program like if
it was in C where you where you can't
overload functions that's kind of there
to prevent that right so it's not bad
like Hungarian it's not superfluous like
Hungary notation is we're not passing
doubles that's what the D stands for
we're passing floats so we're going to
be calling load matrix F right and as
you can see it's expected to pass a GL
float here so what we need is we need an
array of floats that comprises the
matrix so we need our projection matrix
here and we need to specify
the actual matrix that we just talked
about now here is write the identity
matrix so if we wanted to you could sort
of imagine this being the identity
matrix like so that would be what that
would look like and I guess I could
probably do it like this because we
wouldn't be able to use those
initializers there so there's the the
matrix and when we do GL load matrix F
we can basically just pass at a pointer
to any array of 16 floats and it will
just load that in place of the current
projection matrix will replace it which
is what we want but as soon as we start
to do anything more complicated with
this matrix we run into a particular
problem now what we can do right off the
bat is we can put in our terms here like
I said where we had kind of our our two
over width right and our our two over
height that and I don't know if we have
our math supported here I don't remember
if we do or not but we probably want to
use a safe ratio one here just because
remember there's nothing that says that
our buffer width might not be zero it's
some weird kind of unusual case so you
know we might want to go ahead and take
a little bit of a precaution there to
make sure that we don't divide by zero
in that case and just go nuts go haywire
so those will be fine no matter what we
do but we then need to put in our
negative ones here and there's a problem
with this that we'll talk about in in a
second
that that's why I can't just literally
think of it like that necessarily okay
so we don't have math in here can we
just get math in here is there any
reason we can't just include the math
library square root is not found where
is square root normally found dare I ask
intrinsics looks like in transics
and so you know like if assuming we did
all our math right and assuming
everything else is fine you know we
would expect this to just work with the
projection matrix s so but of course it
doesn't although that looks broken for
other reasons so don't take that with
the slight grain of salt but point being
this is wrong already even before that
at least if I remember correctly and the
reason for that is because of an
encoding issue and let me explain to you
what that encoding issue is when I draw
this you notice I'm just drawing out a
matrix the way that you would see it in
a math book and that's totally fine
we all understand what this is and I
kind of showed you something that tells
you how this matrix works because I
showed you matrix multiplication I said
oh we kind of go like this and we go
like that we take the X multiply the X
the y by the Y positions you know Z by Z
W by W and and we go like this what that
means is you now know the structure of
this matrix and what its values mean by
looking at it because we've defined the
operations on it and it's all clear
what's going on okay so there's no
ambiguity when I show you this and
furthermore there's no ambiguity in math
because math writes things such that
column vectors multiply this way if you
wanted to multiply the other way you
could write a row vector right I could
write a you know sort of a vector that
looked like this and then if I was doing
multiplication that way you would see a
a different type of equation emerge
right it would be x times the x position
here the Y times the Y position here the
Zetas loosen here and it would go by
columns the multiplication write the
column the matrices columns would get
multiplied in here not the rows right
and that's a pretty important
distinction to understand now in math
you have both of those things in math
it's just matrix multiplication is
defined anytime you have two
matrices because the vector is just a
small matrix right vector is just a
matrix that that only has a 1 for one of
its dimensions but math is defined just
fine as long as the number of columns of
the input matches the number of rows I'm
sorry of the left-hand side matches the
number of rows on the right-hand side
right
that's all it cares about it doesn't
care about anything else as long as that
was true which it is in both cases right
we're fine and the and it'll just
generate a different sized thing as the
result if you add more right if I added
more in here we would just generate a
bigger result but the math is still
defined now it breaks down if I don't do
that if I if I tried to do it where I
was just doing two elements here it
would break down because you'd multiply
this by this this by this and you get to
hear me like I don't know what to do the
math is not defined anymore what does it
multiply there's nothing to multiply it
by right similarly I couldn't get rid of
these two same reason I also couldn't
get rid of just of these because then
these would have nothing right right but
as long as it's defined as long as the
number of rows in in the left side and
the number of columns on the right agree
we're fine so the map just works and the
map is clear and we all know what's
going on there but once that math has to
happen inside a computer we have a
problem ok these are just arrays they're
just memory locations they're just a
series of floating-point values that
come one after the other there is no
rigid rule inside the computer about
which way you were specifying your
matrix for example when I say you want
to multiply a matrix times a vector well
OpenGL or anybody else doesn't know
whether that means right that I've got
this happening right and my matrice
defined that way or whether I've got
this
happening and my matrix is defined this
way right and you might ask well what's
the difference the difference is where
these values would appear right and
furthermore we don't know how it chooses
to store the things in this matrix
whether it's going to store them like
say this way so this is the first value
this is the fourth value then we go to
this one's a fifth value and so on or
whether it chooses to store them this
way so there's all this ambiguity in
here and you have to make sure that you
get it right okay and so the way that it
looks if we write it out in C to match
the math if I remember correctly is not
the way that open gels fixed function
pipeline happens to work open eels fixed
function pipeline I believe goes down
considers multiplication by columns so
it says if the vectors were silently row
vectors actually and and so it goes like
safe ratio zero zero negative one the
negative one would actually happen over
here right now I'm gonna go ahead and
verify that cuz like I said it's been a
long time since I've used the fixed
function pipeline and so you know I
could I might very well be
misremembering that fact but I believe
that you need to put those in there now
I'm going to take a little shortcut here
or rather just a little I'm gonna
condense this just a little more cleanly
so you could read the matrix a little
bit better
okay so now you can kind of see it a
little more clearly but I believe that's
the way it has to go now I'm going to
hope that this documentation has it but
let's take a look here and and yet you
can actually see just right from this
definition so cure they've written it
out in math form for us and take a look
at the indices right it goes straight
down the column there's the 0 the 1 the
2 the 3 right which is exactly not how C
would interpret it right so they are
assuming that that the things go in
columns which means it has to look like
this so this is really the more correct
projection matrix for for what we're
doing right and so now as we get well
okay so there we go
so I guess there were no other problems
we got exactly what we expected and I
just wasn't sure there might I thought
there might have been one other problem
in there but anyway now we've got
something which actually takes screen
coordinates in and produces what we
would have expected so now we're
basically out of time
but we've done what we wanted to do here
and so I think we're in perfect position
for tomorrow to basically have our
render reported over because if you look
at what has to happen again very very
straightforward really all we need to do
is just go ahead and set up this same
thing so we're talking about about
literally calling this exact same stuff
essentially as the preamble to to what's
going on here this would literally just
be like the output target window with
output target and au height and then
we've loaded in we'd literally do
exactly the same stuff and and then we
would be done and so we're not that far
from actually having a fully implemented
Hardware renderer just at a very basic
level really all we're gonna have to
deal with this is just doing a little
bit of the integration to make sure we
can call this function from the right
place and that swap buffers will happen
properly and that sort of stuff and then
deal with that texture bit but that's
really it so hopefully you guys
understood that I know there's a little
bit of major stuff in there and maybe
you guys aren't as
couple of major series we did kind of
cover them but maybe we need to cover
them again if that's so you know let me
know but for now let's go ahead and go
to the Q &amp; A so I can answer any
questions that you guys might have about
that let me see if I can kind of get
here I don't know for actually I think
we're working
are we working sometimes the computer
decides to like stop paying attention to
the chat I need to get this machine
using the automated Q : thing it's not
using it I'm still got to read the chat
manually on this machine which is kind
of annoying that Alright
in Sopot was pretty great there by the
way
who rocks 998 what key part layer to use
oh just normal the normal US standard
u.s. keyboard layout Huber Caleb will
hand made up in jail B including the
platform layer or game layer it will
actually be in the game layer and the
reason for that it although it's it's
sort of technically a third tier in
between the two but it doesn't go in the
platform specific layer because it can
be shared between multiple open
implementations of OpenGL so you don't
want it like welded the reason you don't
weld it into like the win32 layer is
because then you have to rewrite it all
again for for mac even though it's 99%
the same so typically you end up having
the handmade opengl thing as a separate
platform clean you don't want to use any
platform stuff in there and that way you
can reuse it and and so you like wiggle
swap buffers that will still live out in
the platform layer but all the generic
opengl will live in a file that can be
reused in multiple platforms
I see no other cues Elven jumped in a
bit late
so are we using the fixed function
OpenGL API right now or will we write
our own matrix struct at some point I'm
not sure that's an ore question I think
the answer to both of those is yes right
now we're using the fixed function API
when we switch to using shaders I don't
know that we'll have our own matrix
struct but we would we would obviously
be passing the the shader will do the
transform at that point so technically
it's our matrix at that point and we can
use it in whichever order we want but
that's kind of a separate thing that's
neither here are there AHS method wrist
brace is recommended for programmers in
general or just something you've had
issues with I'm not really qualified to
ask him not really a physical therapist
I think it probably depends on the
person q for Caleb if you include
handmade OpenGL in the game layer won't
that force you to include when is that H
and all the OpenGL headers in the game
layer so no to be clear remember
everything gets built sort of together
right so it doesn't really matter for
our purposes what is in what layer
because everything gets built is one
giant file so the important part really
has nothing to do with whether or not
you put it before or after the Windows H
right because you can easily just put it
after Windows out H that's where it
comes right that's pretty trivial the
the important part that I want to sort
of hammer home is you just don't want to
use any non OpenGL calls in this file
because if you use Windows specific
calls like let's say we put wiggle swap
buffers in here then all of a sudden the
Mac port can't you
use this file even though otherwise it
would have been able to and so the idea
is you want to keep your OpenGL file
even though it is platform specific in
the sense that it's calling the OS you
actually don't want to make it D
platform specific because you want to be
able to reuse it in all of the different
platforms so basically what will happen
is like the win32 platform file will
pound include the handmade opengl dot
CPP file and so will the Apple one right
that's how you do that
grizzly ninja was pushed before
rendering primarily in the software
under because the real Hardware renderer
works that way due to GPUs
no it's in the software renderer because
of sorting remember we never would have
been able to implement our sorting if we
hadn't have gone with the push buffer
style and so really in a 2-d game where
you know you you're gonna want to sort
for transparency reasons to get better
compositing and stuff and potentially
for performance as well you gotta do
deferred you gotta wait you gotta just
buffer and then render later because
otherwise you can't sort and you need it
you need sort right pics 1234 will the
game be given away to dev viewers for
free no it is pre orderable in fact on
handmade arrrgh
it's right there
off-topic have you worked with talk to
or met Andre lamothe before no on all
three counts I in fact have not even
ever read something by Andre Lamaze so I
literally have no contact with Andy
laughing anyway other than that I know
he wrote some books that is that is
really all I can could say about what I
know about under the moth Lost TGM I
feel uncomfortable ooting points
represent representing pixels have you
ever had problems with OpenGL and
floating-point values like passing them
to shaders or text words so I'm not sure
exactly what you're saying but I'm gonna
I'm gonna take a guess maybe what you're
saying and you can correct me if I'm
wrong but are you basically saying that
you're uncomfortable with knowing what
will happen when you pass a
floating-point value in terms of where
it lands on on the pixels themselves is
that is that what you mean or or do you
mean something else if that's what you
mean
that is not only would I say that that's
very normal I would actually say that
probably the vast majority of
programmers have no idea what happens
when they pass floating point
coordinates to OpenGL and a lot of times
they get it wrong and I think honestly
the that that the fault of that is
mostly with the OpenGL materials don't
start with a really clear diagram of how
texture coordinates and and pixels work
together and how pixel coordinates work
together that stuff is all very
rigorously defined and at least nowadays
as far as I know all graphics cards
properly obey a rigorous specification
for where for what exactly it means to
specify a floating-point value and have
it map to pixels but that wasn't always
the case so one thing we could do on
handmade here at some point maybe I have
to schedule something for this is to
actually talk about that we don't really
have a lot of occasion to need to know
in our particular case but that's not to
say that it wouldn't be good to to cover
it because it does happen it does come
up
do you use any element buffer or vbo in
your opengl wait where did that go let's
see to use any element buffers or vertex
buffers in your opengl if no y so the
answer is that we will be using vertex
buffers in the opengl code and the
reason for that is because the function
call overhead of doing GL vertex calls
is not really
we don't want it there's no need for it
we're just the way that our renderer is
set up it just needs to stream a large
number of rectangles essentially out
into to the graphics card and say I need
you to draw all these rectangles with
these textures and so there's no real
need for us to do that now unfortunately
for us and we can try to take steps to
avoid this but I don't know to what
degree we'll want to but unfortunately
for us we do have a problem which is
that the majority of systems that we're
probably going to run on is certainly at
the low end do not allow you to set
textures out of a buffer you can do that
on say like an video hardware you can do
fully buying this graphics where you're
literally just specifying like what
texture
drawing with on a per element basis but
you can't do that in the general case at
least not yet and so we will have the
problem of our vertex buffer scheme will
not be particularly fast or at least
it's not as fast as we might like it to
be because we won't probably bother
packing our textures into texture pages
like maybe we will maybe we won't but it
depends like we could have our asset
Packer do that potentially but it's it's
hard to say right there's a lot of
downsides to doing it as well in terms
of the streaming and and all these other
things so it's unclear like what we want
to do with that but we will be doing
vertex buffer objects just because
there's no point in having the function
call overhead for building the the
rectangle stuff but but it won't be
really that much of a speed win because
a lot of our time will be spent
switching textures I would suspect
that's my guess anyway at the moment
we're not using them yet because I only
just barely taught people how to do
OpenGL at all so before we switch to
using those we will have the pipeline
working in fixed function with no buffer
objects and then we will switch it over
but it's purely an optimization as well
there's there's no difference like it
doesn't do anything different it's just
an optimization to get rid of the
function calls
did you do your own geo ortho call when
you set up the projection matrix also
thanks for all the matrix explanations
so not really I mean yes and no
basically this is the equivalent of a GL
ortho call so sort of we did but we we
didn't reach GL ortho because GL our
throw slightly different so you can take
a look at geo ortho I just wanted to
show you how to do it cuz geol ortho is
just a utility function doesn't do
anything right I mean look if see if I
can find something as a better laid out
version of that oh nice good that's good
does somebody have the actual one that's
not all typeset all messed up this one's
all messed up the typesetting is all
messed up yeah
well I mean the type sings all messed up
on that so I couldn't quite point you to
it but essentially what's happening here
is we're just doing the our own version
of GL ortho that doesn't actually need
to bother with the z-coordinate
right normally GL ortho actually still
does depth like it still has to do Z
it's also support z-buffering and
z-buffering is of course the thing where
you actually track a depth value per
pixel it should probably call it death
buffering is the probably more correct
term but in order to support that
feature which we don't need and aren't
using they need to have the ability to
actually generate proper Z coordinates
and do proper homogeneous coordinates
there for the Z so their matrix is not
gonna be the same as this it's gonna be
basically the same as this but it's
gonna be a little bit different right
and so if you look up to you Laura
though and find a place that actually
has it type set properly you will see a
matrix that looks very much like our
matrix but it's not quite the same the
reason for that is it's not passing
through these values the way that we are
it's actually putting things into the
the values that we'll get used for doing
def buffering
let's see
trust if there any other q questions
I don't see any
I see no further questions so I think
that's it
and hey look the stream has ended
alright well I guess that's just that so
that's all there is to it go ahead save
this so we can wind down alright thank
you everyone for joining me for another
episode of hand made here it's been a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along with code
at home you can always spiro to the game
on handmade hero org and it comes with a
source code so you can play around that
at home but but that is not the only
reason to go to handmade here org
there's also a forum site you can go to
where you can ask questions there's a
patreon page you can go to to support
the video series and there's a tweet bot
that you can subscribe to to know when
the videos serious is going to be live
if that's your thing that's about it
really
yeah double check that tweet bot for the
time for tomorrow but I can tell you
ahead of time it's 5:00 p.m. Pacific
Standard Time right back here on Twitch
so if you want to follow with getting
the OpenGL renderer running which I
think we're there really isn't that much
more to do we will cover that tomorrow
and probably the next day just to
probably about two days would be what
would be required so yeah hope to see
you back here for that until then have
fun programming and I'll see you guys on
the Internet
take it easy everyone