hello everyone and welcome to handmade
hero sure we could complete game live on
stream
i am going to go ahead and take a look
at the code that we wrote
last time um did this machine reboot
sometimes windows reboots machine it did
not
i always have to check to make sure that
windows did not reboot my machine
um because sometimes it just likes to
reboot your machine and you can you know
it wants to
right you can see it really wants to so
i'm probably gonna have to do that soon
and then you know then it undoes my subs
to drive which
which you know that i hate anyway
if you remember from last time what we
were doing
is i just wanted to uh
i just wanted to make something that
would do a
do like a door and so i wanted to make
something
where if i uh hopped into a part of the
dungeon
it would uh have like a blocker there
and then there'd be something you would
do and the blocker would go away so
if i run the game currently you know i
can hop
out of the sort of starting area here
that we set up
there were some bugs we wanted to look
at by the way there was um
like something in this corner that
doesn't exist remember that
um so there are some things with level
generation
like maybe it's putting an orphan there
that we don't have tags for or something
right so we want to take a look at that
probably but anyway
uh don't really care about that at the
moment because i want to do some other
stuff
we'll tackle that when we come to it uh
so if i come down here
and we take a look at this part of the
dungeon i think i just set
every dungeon room to have a door in it
and we didn't really have any door
graphics yet so we just stuck a tree
right as you can see i can't go through
the tree at all
right it's not possible and so what i'm
trying to do here
is uh today i just want to make it so
that there's a way to open this door
right so if we take a look down here you
know you can see that there's
stuff on the other side of it right uh
and
i would like to go ahead and make a way
to open the door
because that's going to be a pretty core
thing for
how you play the game because again the
point of this and
i say this can't say this enough not a
game designer
don't have strong opinions about that
not saying this is
correct or anything it's just from a
strictly implementation standpoint
the way that this is supposed to work is
it's supposed to be sort of like a zelda
or a
binding of isaac game where you'll hop
into a room
such as this one and you will have to do
something
and then the door will open and you can
go through it right
the only difference that i suspect uh
that i will probably do here is that i
don't know that i want
um those games will often lock you in
meaning when you hop in through a door
it closes the door behind you
until you do something in the room that
we may not do
so so i don't know that i care about
that aspect
of those sorts of games but the aspect
of the games
where you where you have to do something
in the room in order for the door to
open like kill the monster
or whatever those sorts of things i do
want i have some specific things that i
want to add for that
so that's mostly what we want to do here
is is create something
where that will occur and the way that
i'd like to do this
is i want to make a thing
uh so you notice this this dude hops
around
on squares there's a reason for that so
the way that you open doors
in rooms uh and this will pretty much be
exclusively true i believe is um
it will be sort of cubert style where
there's things on the floor
like there's tiles here and you have to
like light up the tiles by hopping on
them
and then the door will open right so
what i want to do is create a new type
of
thing where there's
some number of tiles in the groundwork
of a room and if you hop
and and they start out in like a down in
a
in a unset state so they start out
like on not lit up they are dark
right and when you hop over them they
light up right and
when you have lit up all of them
they will become that they will
become activated effectively and the
door will go down
and maybe
again this is really more of a designer
type question
doesn't it involve us we're just doing
the engine
maybe we want also the ability so that
that becomes the locked state of the
world now
meaning now what once you have
successfully
done that pattern
you you can't undo it so so if you then
go
and hop onto one of those tiles
again they will not change state right
whereas before that maybe they would so
me before that
maybe we have it so they would and
this may just be a property of the tile
so it may be that each individual tile
uh when we create them has uh properties
so like
maybe one of the tiles is you hop on it
sets it you hop on it again it unsets it
another one is you hop on it sets it and
then it never unsets it
right another one might be that you hop
on it sets it
you hop on it again it sets it to a
different color you hop on it again it
unsets it right
there could be like a bunch of different
things like that
um and there could also be ones where
like you hop on it once
uh like they could be numbered one two
three four five
and like if you hop on one two
three four five it works if you hop on
like one
three it clears the sequence right
so you have to hop on them in order
would be another one and i just want to
be able to have it
like the engine goal is if you imagine
there was a game designer
like you're handing this off to john
blue and he's gonna design a bunch of
stuff with it
it should basically allow him to drop
into this code and do whatever he wants
meaning we want it to be like very
flexible so that like the designer side
can do whatever they want
and they don't have to do a lot of work
to like change it so so i want it to be
like fairly
full-featured in that sense um and so if
we look
i think what we'd probably want to do
here is make this be a brain
and so it would probably be something
like this where we have
like a brain um
i guess these are switches i don't know
what these are called
um but these are basically like the the
switches in the floor or whatever
right uh and
you know i don't know how many we would
have 16 might
be a bit much so i don't know that we'd
ever use that but since we're basically
saying like look there's 16 blocks of
these sorts of things
will just it doesn't hurt us to use it
because we're already saying that's sort
of the size of these brain
things anyway um so when we go
in here um
also i can put that in down here
let me grab these brain switches drop
them in the union
uh so if we want to make one of these
now it should be pretty easy for us to
do
we just say all right there's a thing
which is a type brain switches uh
and you know maybe i'll say like these
are environmental brains or whatever
like these are you know this is not a
monster it doesn't move around
um but it is a thing that's in the world
right
and so what i want to be able to do now
is in the entity
system you know if one of these things
is a switch
then it's just going to have a brain id
of switches and that'll gather up
and what we want to do too is in here we
would like to do a thing
uh where we maybe
have some data that has to do with
switches like are you set or are you not
and i don't think we have anything
really like that in here right we've
we've
got some things in the entity but
there's not a lot of it
um and so i probably want a thing in
here uh
for switches and so i want maybe
something in here that's like
um you know switch properties
uh and then also like maybe a switch
state
and this these i don't really know
like i said we're just gonna kind of
feel our way around in here
if i was a game designer i might have
stronger opinions about how it's going
to go
i don't um and also the advice that i've
mainly seen given from people like john
blue who i trust
on game design is that your game design
process should be very experimental
anyway so
i would assume that again the most
important thing when
working on this part of an engine is to
not
box yourself in like do whatever is the
most flexible at the time
like just type in the code that you
wanted and don't overthink it
because if you try to do a lot of like
overt structural things you're just
going to box yourself into a particular
game design and that was not the goal
the goal is to experiment with the game
design and feel
like feel out if it's good and make
changes to it that help you get towards
good
so again i'm not really qualified to
give game design advice but all the
advice that i've seen from people like
john who i trust
or daniel ben murguy is another person
who i trust on these sorts of
uh questions they seem to think that
like
it's the experimentation that produces
the good game design so
so don't box yourself in like don't
don't try to design a system first and
then make the game
just let the system be fluid and allow
yourself to do whatever random crap you
think of at the time do that and you'll
get a better result than if you try to
do like
what's my entity system like don't think
that way because you'll just produce a
very generic game
at the end of that so in here i'll just
make a new function for this that i'll
stick in and this is purely
organizational
it could just live in the switch
statement but i'm going to actually have
one in here where we we don't need input
for these right
um i i don't even know if we need the
sim region
honestly um we might not uh we might
just use the brain
um but i'm gonna put the sim region in
because
well you know what here's where we'll
probably need the same region at some
point
these switches need to uh
trigger things like opening a particular
door
and i don't know
i mean i guess we don't really need yeah
we i don't even know if we need any
queries i guess i'll just leave it out
for now
i feel like eventually we would want it
to be in there
um but but i i guess i just
can't think of it so don't you know my
main thing is that you know i'm not
going to pass something around that i
don't
actually care about so you know we'll
add it if we need it
so if we see one of these things where
we have uh
you know switches i'm just going to go
ahead and make a function where we
process logic
involving these switches um and i'm
using the brain system here which i
actually kind of like
um i don't know if it's a good idea or
not uh because
it was very experimental but you can see
how it's kind of
becoming sort of a nice thing for us to
have
uh which is to say that if you look at
what happens in here
we have these switches and
i want to think of them in a group so
the brain is really nice because it
gathers them all up for us
right so it automatically just gathers
all of the switches
that are involved in a particular uh
like room and it will bundle them
together for us which is pretty great
right
so i don't know that seems pretty cool
um maybe it's not
but i don't know it just seems pretty
neat
uh the way that that works anyway
so when we come in here we've got uh
this brain switches
thing right and i'm just gonna say like
well we've got
uh the switches version of this brain
is there's really not much in it other
than just the switches
uh and really these are going to be all
the tiles that we care about and so i
think
if i'm not mistaken we can just kind of
go through
them one at a time and see what their
states are so if i go
uh back in here and i say
uh and and i just look to see
what the various things are i should be
able to just
run through the switch states and see
what they what they are right
so if i just go ahead and say all right
uh my
switch or tile index and i'll just say
uh
loop over all of them
uh and in each of these
i can look at the particular tile in
question like so
right and
i think uh what i
would need to do here is i would need to
have some way of knowing
like that this traversible has been
hit and we may need some like edge
triggering
so basically when we actually
hop onto the thing that's a trigger and
standing on it
won't like keep re-triggering it i'm
gonna do a simpler thing right now
uh which is to just look to see whether
or not
it's actually uh being stood on at the
moment
um
although actually i suppose this
maybe that's better handled on the
actual transaction
so maybe i won't do that i don't know
i'm not sure what i want to do
there uh
i'm not sure what i want to do there so
what i'm going to do at the moment
is i'm just going to go ahead and say
that we're going to do it this way
and what i would like to do here is i
would like to be able to grab
out the particular
so i'd like to know like which door it
is so what i might do
what i was thinking is there's like
doors that are
uh there are doors that are controlled
by the tiles
and maybe i want those in the brain as
well
you know what i'm saying i don't know
if that makes sense or not but it seems
like it might so it could be like
this kind of thing you know what i mean
so there's like there's things that get
unlocked by the
by the tiles and then the tiles you know
what i'm saying
so i don't know i i you know i don't i
don't know
how i feel about that or or what you
know
whether that's good or not but something
like this and so you know we would go
through the tiles we would see what the
tile states
are uh and then at the end we would loop
over the things that we unlock and
unlock them
right
and so for things like doors i don't
know that we
actually need a separate type for those
though or
really anything at all we could
potentially just get rid of them
right um because they kind of but but we
probably want to animate them in some
way
uh so i'm not sure like exactly again
how we want that to work because we
haven't really worked in this part of
the code much at all like we haven't
really added these kinds of
gamey things um so i kind of need some
way here
of making like
uh making it like
take me like a like a like a basically a
transaction that goes to nowhere
would be the way to think of it right
so in other words like
this function
where we do the transactional occupy
okay so there's where we need the same
region i was like yeah
well we need the summation so like where
we do the
the transaction occupy i'd say okay i
want
like the uh the unlocks
id
uh that we're talking about here
like so
yeah so for every unlock
i just want to go and
have it go to nowhere basically
right so excuse me
so i don't the the question about how
this works exactly
um
i assume what we would want to do and
i just don't know but i'm assuming what
we would want to do
is make a dummy traversible
that's basically on the door so that
when the door is supposed to unlock
we just transactionally occupy it to
like a traversable that's like
hard-coded to like be like wherever the
door if it should go up or down i don't
know
or to the side
we just place a traversible there that
it's supposed to go to
i guess um like i said i'm really not
sure
i'm really not sure um
well you know what i don't really want
to think about that right now i just
want to implement the switch stuff so
let me implement the switch stuff and
then we'll come back to this and decide
how we want to do that because
we're just going to need something we're
going to need to decide like
look we're going to put in like an
animation control basically that just
lets the door open
and i have no i haven't really thought
about what that
should even look like on the screen so
we're gonna have to make some decisions
there so what i might do is say
i'm gonna skip transactional occupy
right now
um i might just do a like to do
to call that and what i'll do instead is
in here where we do
uh the the the
the one that you're actually uh coming
from
so where you were previously
excuse me uh
like yeah so the problem here is right i
want desired
for now to just not be anything so what
i'd like to do
is is basically this so uh
you go in here and you say i want to get
the traversible
for this oops
for unlocks current
occupying right
uh and i then just want to say like
it's not there anymore right so then
i
am i doing this right
where's the occupying there it is
so like these um so basically what i
want to do
is i just want to say like yeah the
occupying one
uh is now gonna be nothing so we're
gonna get a traversable
for that one uh we're gonna clear
it out because we're not there anymore
right so we're just clearing this out uh
and then we're gonna say like
ours
uh is gonna get cleared is like we're
not on that anymore
right
okay so excuse me
so that would unlock uh the door
by basically just removing it from the
occupier
and i don't actually have any other
like ideas about how i want that to work
so i'm also just gonna say
like look just make the z value
b go down by by one
um or you know what right now let's make
it go up by one just so we can see that
it happened
you know what i'm saying uh and and
that's all
so that's what i'm going to do and again
it's not good
i just don't know what i want to do here
so this is just a placeholder so i'm
gonna put
uh something around here where we like
say like
look we don't know what this is but we
know it's probably not that
that's what we do know so then when we
have the tile indexes here
and we loop over all the tile indexes
here's where we want to check what their
states are
and so
i again don't know what we want to do
uh for these but for now i'll just do
is it state not zero is all i'm going to
actually do
right so in here we have the switch
state
and in here i'm going to do like you
know switches
set and actually i guess i'll assume
it's true
right
and what i'll do here is say i'm going
to assume that this switch date
that all of these are true and if the
switch state
is not true
i'll set it to false so that way when we
come through here i can just say look
don't unlock
unless the switches are set
something like that again not great
but we're just sort of starting in
on the entity side of things and so
we'll have more opinions about how this
works
later right we'll we'll have a stronger
idea of what we want to have happen
there
so now what we need to do is say okay
when
there's a transactional occupy we
probably want to see what happened there
um i'm not sure how i want to set this
up
uh precisely but
you know the yeah cause like the thing
i'm not entirely certain about
is how exactly would we
want to
the thing that i'm not certain about is
how we want to know when you've hopped
on a thing
because there's lots of ways we could do
it one way to do it is that when you
actually call transactional occupy
that would process things that happen on
that
another way to do it would be inside the
brain these things just
just check right
so for example inside the traversables
here you know you've got
uh the traversable point stores who's on
it
and i don't
know you know you could do something
like this
so inside the traversible point where
you've got who is occupying it
uh you could have like who occupied it
last you know what i'm saying to you
so there would be like an occupier and a
preview of occupier and you could just
look
to see if those were different and the
interesting thing about that is it would
also let you see like who just left
or who just arrived it would give you
that information
i think i like that better
i feel like that gives you more
information about what you want
so i think i'll stick with that
so if we look at transactional occupy
um in here what it's doing is it's
setting the occupier to the entity id
and so what i might say is like okay so
there's a prev occupier and we just
every time you switch this thing
right you
you move it over
so basically you would take and say when
i switch the occupier
to this thing i change the previous
occupier to the new one and in here when
i clear this out
uh i do the same so if if the
you know
if the place that's if if the uh the ref
that we're actually
setting if that's getting cleared then
the previous occupier
for that one also gets saved
right
that seems like what i probably want
and when you sent this yeah so the the
weird thing is that if desired is not
like i don't quite understand why this
has to
exist because if you want to remove
something from the system entirely it
seems like you can't really do that
which seems bad so i would assume that
you would
want actually in here
like
when you look at the reference to a
traversable here
it seems like you would want that to
just work
like if this is zero it should be fine
i don't know i think i would prefer that
and maybe that's stupid but
i think i would prefer that so basically
like if the
desired occupier uh
oops
like if this comes back no i guess is
what i'm saying
that seems okay
meaning meaning i guess i don't know why
we can't just
do this
like get the dest if there is a dest
then we clear it out right
get the desired if there is a desired
then set it but either way
um
this happens
right so as long as
this is not true
we we definitely do this
uh so yeah
something this is a little more
complicated but
maybe there should be a null traversable
and everyone just gets set onto it or
something but you know i'm just trying
to
see how this would work
um so i think that's okay so we
basically say all right we're gonna do a
transactional occupy we get the
destination
that we're set like destination's a bad
word here it's
we probably want to call it something
like the mover
right because it's the person it's the
mo it's the
reference that's being moved right um
so i might say like look this is the
movers reference
so the movers reference we will get
we get it and we update it
like so
right and then we go and say
where we do we want to go and we get the
we get that one if it exists so it might
not exist
right it could just be zero if it exists
then we look to see if we can move
right if we can move we do like so
um if otherwise we don't if we can't
move
right then then we would do this right
and
since we only want to update
where we're coming from uh in
the case where we succeeded this should
probably go in here
right meaning we don't want to clear the
place we're coming from
unless we actually were able to move
which i think this does
right so i think that allows us to
keep both of them um
properly
yeah also
where's the sampling lighting
generator thing there it is
okay um
[Music]
so i think that's okay um
and now i just want to create some of
those
uh and i can play around with them right
and since i
did that update also i can get rid of
the hack
uh so now this can be proper right
so now i can say okay
in transactional occupy we'll move this
[Music]
we'll move this guy to nowhere
whatever that is to null space
right um so we'll just say look this
this guy
goes away he's he's gone and i'll i'll
leave this
like weird like set the position up
thing and that's just
my way of trying to figure out whether
it works or not so i can see if it
raises i mean we can hop
through it because it'll that will be a
trigger that will show us what's going
on as well but just be easier to see
so we'll try this and now what i need to
do
is i can actually handle the switch
state stuff in here
so what i can do is say all right uh if
the tile so the tile has it
has traversables right and we know that
there's just going to be the one
because each tile that you hop on is
only supposed to have one of these
right so we would say okay there's a
traversible
and i just want to take a look at this
traversible so i want to say
okay the
the previous occupier in the occupier
oops
if you stepped on the thing these will
be different
right and so what i'm going to do
is say if
they're different and the occupier
is valid right
uh then i want to change my switch state
or something you know what i'm saying
uh and the only question i have here is
what should happen next with these
but i think what i would probably say is
after that
then they are like considered processed
right and i don't know if we want that
to happen
as a sweep like something that happens
at the end
i don't know um
and that's just whether or not we want
to look at that any other time
right uh and i don't know
so in terms of is it really true we have
this exact
problem before i thought we'd looked and
to see if entity ids
uh had it at an r equal and i thought we
wrote it
oh it's is equal is it is equal
we have is equal and r equal what the
heck
all right
i don't know how i feel about that
i think is equal is officially getting
the boot
um
i don't like is equal because it's
not things you don't say that in english
right is valid because it's one thing
are equal because there's two things
right that's just
just english you could argue that
english is not a particularly
well-designed language and you're
probably not wrong
but we are programming in it
and much like we don't get to not use c
syntax because we don't like the way it
was designed
we don't get to not use english just
because we don't like the way it was
designed
okay so now we need a few more things
first of all we need to create these
switches but also i probably should have
some way
of making the switches uh
show that they're down so maybe i'll use
the z trick for those as well
so maybe i'll do something here where i
do like
okay the tile pz minus equals
something right so it'll like sink down
into the floor
just temporarily and again we'll have to
decide how we want to handle
like what we want to show in terms of
animation or
like glowing we will want real stuff
there
um so for now i'm just going to do some
random crappy stuff but we'll figure out
what we want to actually do for reals
later
so then when we go into uh room gen
when we set up the door right we had a
thing
uh in here that sets up a door
and you can see that happening
somewhere in here right here
right so in here where we've got like
doors
we're actually creating these doors uh
this is where we would need to create
like a brain for this particular
set of switches you know it occurs to me
that we create a brain for the room
maybe that's where that should have been
what the heck is special brain slot
so it's literally just the zeroth brain
slot
right
so i guess what i would say is no it
probably shouldn't be part of the room
because what if we want like
one brain for like what if we want like
two patterns
in the same room that doesn't seem like
the kind of thing that would be all that
far-fetched
so we probably don't actually want to do
that
so i'm going to say let's create a
different one
instead right so i'll just
create a brain at the top of this thing
uh and like
i don't even remember how
i don't even remember how this thing
happens
so in here for example you can see
there's a no brain
so there's a brain id and a brain type
right
and inside the entity
you want to be able to set those both
right and i assume they do get set
yeah so
we know like
we know that this is pretty obvious what
that's set to
um that's just set to switches and then
whichever one
of them it is but
i don't actually know how the brain id
was supposed to be set because i don't
see any of these here so i'm assuming
that you just call that
um on the actual sim region
or world right because it generates
brains
you just ask for new brains right
like this so i'm assuming what we would
want to do is when we go
at the top here uh we would just
create one of these and we could be
frugal and say oh we don't want to
create
any brains for rooms that don't have
them but who cares
it's literally just a number right
it doesn't matter
it doesn't take up any actual storage
okay so we want
to talk about the sim region
which is what in gen region i believe
uh off of this because we need to
it looks like ad brain works well
actually i guess you only need the world
so actually i don't even need the sim
region never mind
uh so in this case we only really need
the worlds
although maybe i should go through the
region anyway because i mean i can
because we do have one
uh
but it would just be gen world there
right
um
so it's that right there so so maybe we
would just do it here
so in here we just grab the region that
we're
using and we say we need a new brain
i don't have any plans for how we're
going to do this stuff
yet so i assume what i would do is just
randomly pick
a particular location just straight up
out of the blue
um
so in here where we create
this entity that's the
a tile right and so we just need
something here which is like
is this going to be one of the switches
right
um and we'll probably want to do this i
guess the way we would actually do it is
maybe
using the sort of placement thing
i guess um because we'd want to have
little patterns that get like
dropped down into the room
so it might almost be this thing that we
would do
i i really don't know um
where we try to find a place to put an
entity group
and then when we slap it down yeah so i
think this might be where we would
actually want to do this
so maybe we'll do this uh
we'll do that in there actually later
right now i'm gonna do a more hard-coded
thing
uh and so i'll just take a look at the
edit tile here
and and this relative index i believe
is all we would really need so i could
just do something where i say
like look if this
um and in fact
i don't i don't have any idea what this
is doing
does this color even get used
oh it does
and we stopped using it here but anyway
um so if the rel index uh
x equals i don't know 10.
uh and the real index y equals
five let's say
um i really gotta update my four coders
that stops happening
drives me nuts um i guess
and i and i i really just don't know
i just want to see what tile that would
be
and this is called what again tile
so now uh i want to see if
if i go into a room that's sufficiently
large
will i see a highlighted tile anywhere
and i don't i don't seem to
so that that does not seem to have
worked at all
am i missing something there
because it seems like
like that should have worked
so i don't know why that didn't work
exactly let me take a look at what that
that rail index actually is and we'll
step through the debugger because i
assume that rail index is what we
actually want
so like when we look at um iterate
as planar tiles here uh
i assume this will update that
yeah so like this should work right
um
so i feel like that should have set like
one you know just
just one but it should have set one of
the tiles
to be uh
offset like that
because it or not offset uh to be bright
cyan
and it does not appear to have done so
so
maybe i'll just take a look at what
happens there because
i don't understand why that didn't work
let me just see does it ever actually
trigger that code
um as a starting point
all right so in here
i'm just going to look to see first do i
ever hit this code
so i do hit this code right
for some unknown reason it doesn't seem
to have any effect
i mean it could be that i just can't see
it i
don't think that's highly plausible but
let me
now that i know that it's actually
firing um
i could also change some other aspects
of the tile to see if that's the case
um maybe we're not using that
uh color anywhere it could be that we're
not
that would be weird but
you can see like oh no there it is
there's the yellow when i said cyan i
was
obviously totally wrong it's actually
yellow i don't know why i said cyan
i guess i was reading it bgra for some
reason
so okay so it appears to have worked
after all because there's the tile
right you can see its reflectivity is is
yellow
so let me try something slightly
different here just to make sure
so if i go into the room gen again
and let's suppose that i
instead set its reflectivity to like
nothing
so it's like just not there um or very
faint
right
uh and then i'm also gonna say that like
the entity
brain uh in this case
is gonna be that that brain
that we created for the room
yeah so it's going to be the room switch
brain
and the particular slot in question is
just going to be like uh the
tile slots
so this thing right
uh and
i guess you'd do
this so i say i want the indexed brain
slots
for the switches
this is the doors zero
we probably want an actual counter here
so we can make more than one but at the
moment i don't have a count or
i'm only setting it for one tile so you
would do this
and then
in the when we create the door
we would do the same thing so like down
here
uh when we check for like the door
back and forth bit so like there's a
room a room b
door thing this thing we would just say
like
same thing only this one is in the
unlocks
right um and this one
we could pretty easily since we know
what's going on we could say like
the door index is 0 here and the door
index
goes here right
um and we could also like assert
that the door index
uh is is less than the number that we
have
right so brain switches
i don't know if you can you probably
can't
c plus is always disappointing so i
don't know why i'm even bothering to
type this in
but assuming that you did this
hey i don't know if that actually worked
or c bus plus produced something else
but like i just wanted to say hey can
you tell me how big that array would be
normally um so anyway again
not really sure that this helps us at
all at the immediate moment but we'll go
ahead and see
if any of this code now works so there's
the darkened one
you know what i would uh like to do is
oh that was good so we got a crash in
there which we probably didn't
quite do that transactional occupy right
so we'll take a look at that in a second
but what i was going to say is that lets
us know it triggered
i was going to say let's also set the
color to something
so that we can tell so anyway inside the
brains
here
[Music]
let's also say like tile uh there's
pieces
for this thing
uh and so what i wanted to do was maybe
say
well let's suppose that
there we go let's suppose that the
pieces for this thing
are
going to have their colors changed as
well
so there's the color
and maybe we'll just do like blue
or something
okay and then our transaction occupy
seems to
not be correct for zero moves which is
the kind that's happening here
so when we pass the null space as the
desired
so to this thing right uh
the question is like what happened here
something
evidently screwed up and we can
i don't know try to figure out what that
is
let's take a look at get reversible
so it should it looks like it should
allow us to
um produce you know
null pointers you know what i mean this
should work
it should return the null since this
won't set it'll set this to true
um then when we go in here it'll say
give us the move
person back so we got that it'll
swap up up it will swap
the occupiers around
and then complete i don't see where the
code goes wrong there
so unfortunately i may have to just go
ahead and run this in debug mode
real quick to see what the heck happened
there
we should probably add a flag to turn
lighting off in debug mode
when we want to because uh the game runs
just fine
it's only the lighting that's super slow
in debug mode
um what i really would like is a way to
just tell it optimize that one file
but of course you can't do that very
conveniently it's
real pain in the butt um
in msvc unfortunately but anyway
so i'll try hopping onto that tile uh
and we'll see what happens although i
guess
i don't know if i can hop onto this
particular tile
is this um
oh so actually i don't know if that's
true it might be fine we just forgot to
check to see if this is valid
that's all because there may be no
unlocks
so so never mind that was probably the
only problem
famous last words
um okay so
assuming we go hopping along here
i don't know there's the other tile
um so it's set
and
okay so so basically this seems to work
fine
um right and the main concern we have
here is
is we'll just we need to
oh man this dude like already opened the
freaking door
dude that's our door oh
i like the fact that since it gets lower
each time eventually
it will trap him in there because he
will hop onto it
and it will be too low because i just
set it down
from where it is every time you hop on
it
[Laughter]
that's funny um
that's pretty great so this dude's just
screwed like he's just
that's he's just down there and he's
never getting back up
that's great um but in theory you know
i will be the person who who normally
hops on those things
um like so so what we would need to the
ma the only real thing we need to worry
about
here uh is is like
do we need to is is how do we want to
make it
so that these uh
the the animation is synchronized
also why are there no doors on these
lower levels
oh there are some
i don't know where how we were setting
that value
um so yeah the idea here is just that
like
we know ahead of time what will happen
and so
that uh it triggers immediately
uh and like well you can't really see it
here but
you know this must be an item room
that's why it's
yeah uh so yeah it must be the case that
like
that those rooms don't get doors or i
didn't set those for doors
i don't know how did we decide that
that has nothing to do with it
so here's where we set this thing
so i really don't know i mean i'm not
sure
this is a bit weird because like yeah we
you know these don't
have doors these ones don't
um
ah okay so there's some kind of weird
nonsense where oh wow okay
so i guess what can happen here is you
well you know i don't really know
but i can see why there's like some
weirdness there so i don't want to
draw any conclusions from that because
this code is is kind of crazy
actually interesting um
so anyway yeah what i was trying to say
before is just that like the
that all seems to work fine and let's
just try making some more of them first
and we'll see what happens but really
the main problem now is just fixing
the fact that um
there's not enough like there's there's
not animation synchronization between
those
so like when i hop it immediately makes
the door open
before i've even landed on the tile
because the game knows that will happen
ahead of that's great
um since the game knows that will happen
it it starts the animation ahead of time
so that
is an interesting question like how do
we want to trigger those
uh animations so that they happen
more in line with when the actual hop
finishes and i don't know how we want to
do that
yet at the moment what i want to do
is in the room generator i would like to
figure out how to
[Music]
maybe make a few more of these just for
testing
and i also i guess so
let's see so
so assuming that i i use a switch index
here and i and i increment it
i just want like a way of looking to see
uh what these are so so maybe like i'll
just do a square for now so i'll do
like you know this sort of thing
so i'll say look anywhere
uh in this square is fine
that should create four switches on the
floor
right
in theory
uh and so to get out the door you should
have to hop on all four yeah
so that's fine um
yeah so couple things uh
since we want the switches to light up
uh one of the problems we're gonna have
here
is that this probably implicates the
renderer a little bit in the sense that
we want those switches to like
actually glow now it's pretty easy
to make them so that dude stop hopping
on my switches you know what let me just
let me just make it so that they don't
do what they're doing right now
so yeah so what we want to do here
is we want to go ahead and say
if there's an occupier on here we set
the z
down but if there isn't we set the z
back up
i mean one way to do it would be this
so if you went from having someone on
you to not having someone on you
right uh and and then the opposite
which is a total hack but i mean at this
point i don't really care because i'm
not i don't have any strong opinions
about what we're doing in here
oh i think i've got this wrong though do
i
no no that's that's correct um so like
in theory that would make it so that
they would
they would go down and then up right
probably
um so the other problem that i think we
would have here
is i do suspect we might get errors
so one of the problems that we never
really solved with the brain thing
because i like the brain thing but there
is kind of a critical flaw in it
and we we kind of think about it and
that is that
the opening like opening the door
right all it's doing is checking to see
if for a given simulation region
if there is a door right
and it will just take all of the
switches that go with that door
that are in the region but if you
imagine taking a simulation region that
included the door but none of its
switches
it would immediately unlock right
so the problem is i think you end up in
a situation where
you don't know how many switches there
are supposed to be
for this door because the brain is just
collecting them and nobody bothered to
write
no one no one actually keeps that that
number
right so what i want to do to see
i'm just curious if that's happening
what i want to do is
maybe say look
when you do the pz for the
um for the door
maybe let's make that be like really
not much so we can still see that the
thing is like halfway submerged in the
ground or something i don't know
um
you know what i'm saying
oh and the other thing is we have to see
this needs a state
as well so we would need like this
so we don't keep doing it right
yeah so this needs one of these
so that way we can just say look if this
thing already got unlocked we don't
unlock it multiple times
because we don't want to play like
multiple sounds or like displace the
thing multiple times or any of that
stuff
so i'm just curious to know if i now hop
through here
like do i see doors that are unlocked
that i didn't unlock
and for the for for whom the switches
are not down
would be the other way to say it
um so there's the door dude um and now
you can see it sunk into the floor and i
can hop through it
um so this one didn't have a door
because this is a special room
right uh so this is
unsurprising and and fine like that
doesn't matter at all
um so sunk into the ground as we would
expect
not sunk into the ground yet sunk into
the ground now
uh sames
so there right so i do think this bug
exists in practice right and i think
that's something we would need to figure
out
how we're going to deal with right the
brains
need to have some
some way of coping with that and i don't
know
um
that's a tough one
there's obviously simple ways to get
around it like the door could be set
to how many switches it needs to have
set and we just check against that value
and that fixes the problem but it
doesn't
it doesn't fix the problem more
generally
and i wonder if it's just one of those
things where like look this
is a problem with with this whole way
that you do brains and it just can't
really be fixed so you just have to work
around it
um and i and i would like to be able to
i would like to know which it is right
like is there some more clever way of
doing the brains the way we're doing
them that
makes this not a problem or is that like
always a problem
uh and i and i just don't know
so that requires more thought like that
requires me to think
pretty hard about what i want to do with
those things and
i just don't know um
yeah i don't know
it's neither here nor there we know a
hack that could fix it and the other way
to fix it would just be to not use
brains
right you you just have brains be actual
entities that have to get paged in and
they
keep with them state you know there's a
whole bunch of things you can do and i
don't know how we wanted i don't know
how we want to deal with it
um but that's you know that is what it
is
so one thing i would like to do maybe
just see how hard it would be
to just move this into the thing that
actually just does placement
so in the fine place to put entity group
thing
um i was wondering if maybe this
would work so when we do gen
entity at traversable
i'm wondering if we're going to use this
to put patterns in so
when we call this you can see this thing
calling the creator function which gets
the region in the base hash
if we were to just pass it instead
so this this looks like searches right
and so if we just made a thing here that
was just like
um
[Music]
do you see what i'm saying i know this
is kind of a little bit confusing
but if we did something like this where
inside the gen entity thing um
if this thing just had like a flag
that was like gennady like is switch or
something
you know what i'm saying where we just
tested it
and used the same process for everybody
i don't know that that's a good idea but
like
if you just did that i'm wondering
if you then can just use this system and
go from there and and i don't know right
like maybe you can maybe you can't
um but if we then said all right so
uh we take the room switchbrain thing
and we put that down here
when we start to do like doors and crap
like so um and then we
take out this part of the code that was
monkeying around
with the you know with with the
the cube layout stuff all that thing we
take that out
and we just say all right if we want to
add a switch we do that here
like this
i wonder if that if that just works and
so
the structural entity is this one here
so i think
you could just say
that we grab the entity this way and we
modify it like so
i think that would just work
and we will want to do stuff like change
what it looks like there i suppose
but otherwise i think that would do it
and so uh if we then create
when we're making a room that has a door
uh like inside the world gen code
and it places one of these door for me
to be things
then what we would do is place one of
those like entities so much like we do
play snake
here we would do like place tile pattern
or whatever
right and
again i don't really know what this
looks like
but we would say place tile pattern and
we would do like add entity
and the the function here
would be like nothing at the moment
right and the
[Music]
gen flags would just or in the thing
and that would be it i don't know what
place entity does in this case i guess
it just adds it to the list of things
yeah so so we would literally just do
just this and maybe we would do
something slightly differently here
later i don't know um
but it would literally just do that and
i'm wondering if that would do placement
for
us
um that way when we improve that routine
to do lots of different kinds of
placement
we'll just get we can piggyback on top
of it right
so i don't know what that would do or if
that will work at all
uh it doesn't look like it did so i
guess i'm
i'm wrong um but
oh wait no that's false we only added it
to rooms with doors
so when i go down here it should be the
case that only rooms with doors have one
of these things so there's the door
but doesn't look like it because there's
no switch right
and the door is unlocked so it didn't do
anything
oh but this one did
huh that's odd so it was able to place
it in that room but it wasn't able to
place it into this room
i'm kind of perplexed by that
so that's weird uh i don't understand
why it worked
in everything but that first room
also these guys are too uh
crazy for their own good they're hopping
all around uh
so that's odd i don't know what's up
with that we'll have to look at that
later
um but the reason i cared about that
is that in theory like um
in theory this thing where we like
add
conversations here you can see this
thing
like appending entities to the group
this this place of the orphan and this
like appends entities
to the um
you know you using a a mask
so i assume we can just do this like
where we do
[Music]
chains like
something like this
and this could be random as well uh
in fact sure
presumably there's a good entropy yeah
so we just take this entropy here that
we're using
and we say look there's going to be
between you know
two and eight tiles or something again
it doesn't matter
we're going to go through all the tiles
that we would want to add here
we'll add them like so
uh and then when we do
place orphan here when this does it you
can see it does like instead of place
entity it does append entity
[Music]
right
and so i just need to do like if tile
index
else you know what i'm saying
so that way i can i can do this nonsense
uh and i guess this needs to return the
head end
right so
um and now that i think about it maybe i
should maybe this should just be
well
let's do that
so basically like we we take the first
one
and we we consider that the one we made
and then for all the rest of them
we do something different and in fact
this this could actually be how we do
that
all right so that seems fine
and all we would really need then is
like this thing
would need to be randomized so i don't
actually know
where those box masks come from at the
moment
so here are the box masks you can see
uh you could say what do oh
so i guess we don't even really care so
so maybe we just say look
it doesn't matter
for now
okay um so again i'm not sure
if that's right
and this code probably needs to be
improved because now we're going to
start to do
things that have to be gamey so it's
going to need like more awareness
of what the heck is going on
but
i'm going to see if that lets me place
tiles
automatically so that at least it's all
going through the same system so that as
we improve that system
it will be okay i don't know why that
assertion
so that looks like
it looks like maybe it was not able to
place
these i should start with something a
little bit more just to make sure i
didn't screw something else up i should
start with something a little more
obvious first
probably um
so let me just see
uh um if i do something more modest
first
so it looks like it's it's really not
able to do this and i'm not sure why
so um i guess we'll take a look
yes um so
in here it looks like the problem there
is that it's not able to actually
place this thing right so when it's
calling place room along
edge it couldn't do it
right so if we take a look at
oops place room along
edge and i run
so here we are
you know i'll be honest i don't actually
i don't see how this could affect that
though
i mean obviously it must be
because if it wasn't why did we stop
play but
that code isn't supposed to actually
look at this yet is it
so who is actually faulting out there
like because because we don't ever tr we
don't try to do that
until we actually go to the room
generator which
if it failed it wouldn't actually even
matter would it like it wouldn't
like if this failed
who cares
like why would that even cause a problem
nobody nobody faults on that
so did did i do something boneheaded
there then maybe because it
right it doesn't look like that should
really be a problem
so when you're doing these identities
here
um and you push these things on
right it should just kind of work
and let me look at a pen entity to see
what happens here so
you know you pass the parent first which
is what's happening
the dur mask on the child and that seems
fine
i don't see
[Music]
i don't see anything weird going on
there
so i'm not sure i see how this is
possibly how this is screwing anything
up
by just appending these
like room entity groups shouldn't
shouldn't cause a problem
do
so i'm not seeing a lot of obvious stuff
here why this would be a problem
right
i can't say i see like i don't see what
the
i don't see what the weirdness is
that's that's a real strange one
because this should not be tied into it
at all and so the only thing i think of
is that by creating something in a
particular location that
previously wasn't having something
placed in it
maybe that means that someone then tries
to look to see if there's nothing in a
particular location and finds that there
is
is like the only thing that i can think
of
that would make that happen but i'm not
sure i don't know who in here is
actually doing that
and if i look at like place room along
edge
like nobody actually generates these
rooms till they're all put down right
so so like nobody even uses these
during that pass so the only thing i can
really think of
is is just the act of using that entropy
yeah it might just be that because this
code is kind of crappy
we haven't really done a good layout
that that is guaranteed to actually
complete
it might just be that we had entropy
right so in other words
if that were the case you would expect
to be able to do this
and without touching the entropy do that
and then it would just work
yes perfect so basically it does
actually work the only problem is that
now it can't place
that actual group so yeah so basically
we just we're gonna need to like improve
the way we're generating these layouts
right
and that's fine um
because we kind of knew that was the
case anyway
if we look here at the gen room tile
query stuff uh
it's unable to place this entity group
in
whatever this room is right
and if i look at what the entity group
says uh
i can look here and see
it's 4 just like we expected i
don't know why it says
next direction used 0 probably because
it hadn't actually found anything
but i don't
i don't know what that actually expects
it to do in append entity
so in allowed directions for next
these are all set to zero
which is not
what it should have been
so those should have all been set to
like
those should have been set to like all
four bottom bits
right so
why is that
why is that not setting those bottom
bits
maybe it is and then when it tries to
place them it can't
and they get cleared
so let's see
it just looks like it does a greedy
search
right so it looks like it just does a
complete
really slow bad greedy search at the
moment
why would that not work
let's take a look and see why that's
failing because i
don't think it should right
because it should for some reason these
are zero and this doesn't clear those
it just uses next direction used right
so it shouldn't
it it should not have that problem
so that's busted um so let's take a look
at why
why is append entity not properly
setting that that
that allowed directions um
i can't i can't think of where that
would be
so here we are in playstyle pattern and
you can see us calling append entity
here
uh looking through here right we would
expect the parent now to have those set
uh and that that is what we would expect
to see
right so those should always be set to
in all cases uh i would think
and uh let me go ahead and jump forward
to where these like like in here right
and i'm just going to see if i can stop
on one where we're actually doing
one of these placements
just to see this is not one of them this
is
so here we're trying to you can see that
allowed directions for next is properly
set to 15
uh for one of these guys and it should
be
for long oh
oh they chained together
okay
oh
what the hey okay so i don't like the
way this works at all but you can see
what happens here this is supposed to go
like one after the other
which is dumb
so i mean the hack for fixing that is
pretty easy is pretty simple
right it's just that but
i want to fix the way that works i don't
like that at all
um that's too cumbersome to use
in my opinion so that just worked just
fine
uh and now these things should be
working but
let's clean that up let's make that what
we do next weekend
we'll clean up these like layout
placement things um
and get these working better for for
some kind of structures that
you know that make sense gameplay wise
these dudes hop on be hopping on all my
switches
i want to hop on the switches yes so
this works fine now
um and like i said i think we just want
to clean this stuff up a bit
now that we're going to actually care
but like it's just putting it in the
first available space
each time which is all it's knows how to
do
all right um so i'm going to put a
little to do in here
and be like to do
turn this into a list of some kind
so it works cleaner but more broadly
speaking we're going to have to now
uh take a look at what we want to do
uh for actually trying to get placements
to mean something right
yeah so regarding the question is it
worth having the renderer check if it's
running in debug mode or not and drop
the number of learning samples to make
it more playable
uh yeah i do think that's a good idea
what i would prefer
is a separate switch for debug on
lighting
but i don't know uh
[Music]
i don't really know how you want that to
work
more broadly um
mainly what i want is just two switches
one for optimization and one for
optimization on lighting because i want
to be able to run
in essentially three different
configurations all debug
debug with release lighting and all
release
and unfortunately the compiler makes it
really hard to do that
like ideally you'd be able to just
bracket your code with pragmas it said
turn on the optimizer here
but don't think you can do that msvc you
can do the opposite
so you can have a thing that you bracket
the code with the thing that says turn
off the optimizer here
but
follows i'm pretty sure that pragma
optimize can't
turn the optimizer on
it can only turn the optimizer off if
it's already on
so you can like turn the optimizer on
in the switches then you can turn it
off for a region and back on again but i
don't
know that there's any way to turn on
optimizations that weren't already on in
the switches
if there are please let me know i
believe llvm
might be able to do that but i don't
think msvc can
the door switch stuff only allows for
switches to trigger doors that are in
the same room
or can this work for triggering things
in other or multiple rooms etc
um so basically uh
so basically here's the thing that we
don't know
at the moment the brain stuff uh
just all the brain stuff does
is it gathers up things that are
currently in the simulation region and
simulates them
so that they can work together right
and i use that for a way to make the
switches because it seems good because
it can just gather things together but
it has problems
like the fact that if you happen to
simulate something that
cuts off some switches from a door then
it wouldn't behave properly
so i don't actually know
what the best solution to that problem
is
there's lots of other ways you can do it
right
but
i just don't know which way i want to do
right
and so the problem with having switches
unlock a door somewhere else
is that if you did that you would need
some way of having that
thing whatever this the the permanent
switch status is
would need to be something that can
persist until you get over to there
which it doesn't currently do
right um
and so like i said it's really it's it's
very easy to
there it's there's many ways you could
fix that problem
i just don't know which ways are good
right and so that's really the issue
um it's mostly an issue of me not being
sure how i would like it to work
so
i think it just remains to be seen you
turn it on and then wrap the entire
compilation unit in a pragma
turning it off then turning it on again
when you need it uh yes i think you
could
which is um the only way you could make
this
sort of work but again i just haven't
been motivated to try to do something
quite that squirrely
all right
thank you everyone for joining me for
the episode of handmade heroes and a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow the series at
home you can always pre-order the game
on handmadehero.org and it comes with a
source code
so that you can play around with it uh i
will be back here next weekend at which
point i will take a look
at how i want to deal with some of the
brain slash entity placement things
because now we're going to want to do
is basically create like different sorts
of room
types and stuff like that and so we're
going to need to actually think about
how we want the code for placing stuff
in rooms to actually work
the sort of stuff we have in there right
now that just like does a greedy
placement
doesn't really work for gameplay
purposes so we kind of need something
that's going to be
um more geared towards how we want so to
be placed for gameplay purposes
that may require just custom coding like
we may not want a generic
kind of thing for that so we'll have to
see what we want to do
and and basically i guess we'll just
sort of we'll wing it for a little while
and make some rooms that we think are
sort of what we might want
uh and then we can see whether there's
stuff we can pull out of that or not
uh we'll start that next weekend until
then have fun programming everyone
and i'll see you on the internet thank
you everybody