hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream we are really going to
just be continuing the work that we did
last weekend we implemented the
beginning of octahedral light Maps for
our game I guess I don't know that we
want to call them at people light maps
we maybe we should call them octahedral
light probe maps or light probe storage
and we need to sort of push forward on
that there's two things that we want to
do today if we can one is to sort of
debug the code a little bit because we
just kind of threw it in there it's
probably typos there's probably mistakes
and the other thing we want to do is we
have to tighten up the actual meaning of
the map and how it's used so right now
what we did is we just threw in a
packing of the maps that I think is ten
by ten right now and that is an 8 by 8
map plus a one pixel border around the
map obviously there's a one pixel border
on each side which ends up being plus
two so that's why it's not nine by nine
it's ten by ten because this is a one
pixel border all the way around but at
the immediate moment we're not actually
doing that we're just using the full ten
by ten and so we also need to kind of
tighten up that idea and move to
actually properly aligning all of our
ways that we work with the texture to
sample into it properly so right now
it's not really correct the way that
we're doing that so we want to kind of
tighten that up today so accounting for
the one pixel offset and all that and we
also need to copy right we need to place
the proper values into those border
pixels so that's another thing we have
to do once we do all of that work we're
going to have to then and this will
probably start tomorrow because they
don't we'll probably need all of today
to just make that stuff work once we do
that we also need to do one other thing
and that is we need to start
streamlining the process of working with
these maps and probably moving to some
kind of scheme where we just only have
one of them in memory and update it
directly and that sort of stuff because
there's a lot of business going on right
now and we're not gonna be able to
afford that like these octahedral maps
are actually pretty big they store the
light mapping for the probes at a pretty
high resolution compared to something
like the low res voxel version we were
using before and so in order to sort of
move towards a an actual finished
version which is what we're trying to do
here I think we probably want to change
to a system where we're directly
operating on a single octahedral atlas
and every time we take a ray cast we
just blend that in directly I don't
actually think that'd be that hard to do
and so I think that's probably what we
want all right so I'm gonna go ahead and
get started if I go ahead and switch to
handmade hero here what you can actually
see is that if we run the game and mind
you we're not actually doing any
lighting right now so if I go ahead and
switch over here to remedy and load up
the renderer here we're not actually
doing any use of the lighting so you
kind of see that the game itself is
unlit at the moment and that is
intentional but we are actually writing
into the light map it's out the storage
for these probes it does actually it
actually does exist so we have those
probes stored and at each location in
the voxel we are saving out one of those
octahedral maps so what we want to do
here I think is start to view that we
viewed it inside the actual the capture
like we looked at render doc and we saw
that but we'd like to be able to see
that light map more specifically and
right now we can't so what we might want
to do and I guess nowadays I suppose
since we did the work of doing
reloading I could probably just leave of
the actual renderer core we can probably
leave this up and just and just work
with it here if I go to the renderer the
opengl side of things when we're
actually in the middle of the render
loop here and we do bind these images
and send down the updated voxel
information we should be able to just
draw what they look like directly on the
screen you know having some we know like
what their dimensions are right so we
should be able to go ahead and actually
just like draw the to light map textures
so that we can see what they look like
and if you go and look at what we've got
here as far as that's concerned you can
see that we've got you know a thing at
the end where we resolve our def peels
so at some point right we finish up in
the use program begin use program and we
finish up by doing a bind frame buffer
and doing a final blit to the screen and
that final stretch is the thing that
does that right you can see we have the
color handle here and we do all this
nonsense right and I think if I'm not
mistaken we should probably be able to
when we do that final stretch we should
be able to put some debug code in here
that just goes ahead and outputs our
octahedral light map out to the screen
in some kind of way that we can
visualize and so if we take a look at
the final stretch call so if I if I look
at this final stretch what you can see
here is there's just a thing which says
look here's where we're gonna put it and
here's the texture lookup that we're
gonna have and so I think if I'm not
mistaken I should be able to literally
just do some extra passes here right so
when we do the the use program begin use
program and through this line of code
here I feel like the GL draw arrays call
that we're issuing here after the bind
texture I feel like we should be able to
just do that more than once right so you
know we've we've
found an array this this draw triangle
strip here it's gonna draw one quad
right and the quad it's gonna draw is
whichever one we've lined up as being
the active quad so I think and let me
just double check this is true I think
it's whatever sort of texture array
we've armed and I don't know so let me
see I don't see us explicitly putting
that in here so I'm assuming and this is
kind of taxing my memory a little bit
but I'm assuming that you know in the
the the use program begin news program
and sort of things
we're probably setting up that program
information so like if we go look at at
where that is on here let me see we get
resolved exceed lighting we don't have
one for that one right and so when we do
the use program begin for the final
stretch program which it looks like yeah
just looking at it so it's gonna be like
one of these common calls here and if
you look you can see that if there's a
you know we we've enabled these vertex
attribute arrays right and we don't
actually set anything other than the
offset so we're not actually specifying
an actual array anywhere we're just sort
of turning them on in here and so
whichever one is is whichever one was
last in there is the one that we're
gonna use how come I can't oh because
I'm already in there so my question is
just like when did we setup that for
that whatever buffer has the for for the
triangle strip whichever one has the
four pieces in it at some point we had
to actually enable that one and I'm just
not sure when we actually did so you can
see here we set up the frame buffer and
all that stuff oh here it is here it is
so this GL bind buffer screen fill
vertex buffer fat right there so if we
take a look at that screen fill vertex
buffer I'm gonna go ahead and pull that
out so if we take a look at the screen
fill vertex buffer like right here you
can see that we've got one that just
fills the whole screen with whatever the
map is and we sort of want basically
like a debug version of that so that we
can draw whatever we're looking at you
know so we want to draw our octahedral
light information into a map using some
pre coded coordinates here and we know
the resolution of our octahedral map
because we sort of packed it in a
particular way so we know that it's sort
of long and it's it's sort of wide and
not it not as tall as it is wide it
would normally be because everything in
it is a symmetric dimension right it's
all ten by tens and it's you know the
lightness so I think it's 32 by 32 by 32
s worth of 10 by 10 s so it's a cube but
we had to like unwrap the cube so we
unwrapped the cube in the width
direction so we effectively have instead
of 132 wide we have 32 times 32 wide and
then just 32 tall of these 10 by tens
and so we kind of need to make a version
of these vertices that we can use that
will just have around for this the
purpose of doing one of these light map
debugs
and so in here I'm just gonna say like
light map debug buffer or something like
this so that we can generate something
that will fill this properly and and
look at it and if you look at what's
happening here you can see this fills
the whole screen by starting off at the
X that's so this is the left edge of the
screen and 1.0 would be the top I guess
so I don't really know why we chose this
whining but we did and then we go from
oh you know why because it's a it's a
try strip so we had to do try strip
order so we started off in the upper
left corner we went down to the
left corner we go over to the lower
right corner and we go up to the top and
so we still basically you know want to
do essentially the same thing probably
but we're looking at something that if
you look at it if we look at its aspect
ratio oops I promised I wouldn't use
calc in a more speed crunch we're
looking at something that's 32 by 32
across but only 32 high right so it's
aspect ratio is 32 to 1 so we want to
actually have a height that's going to
be proportional if the width of this
thing was to right or 1 I don't know
whether we want it to stretch all the
way across or only half the screen maybe
we only want it to stretch on across
half the screen so if it was negative 1
to 0 let's say then we would only want
it to be 0.03 1 to 5 high right and we
probably want like two of these so that
we can do the depth map and because we
have a depth map and a color map so if
we did it that way we would have two of
these one for each right and so if we
just go ahead and think about how we're
gonna make these work we can just say
all right let's suppose that we're just
gonna go and do negative 1 to 0 so we're
going from the left edge of the screen
to the middle and then instead of going
to 0 to 1.0 let's just go to oh you know
well I mean you know there's no point me
type in the sand we'll just create the
actual value which is like the height
value here or maybe we'll say the top P
or something and so I want to start at
negative 1.0 and then I want to go up
exactly that 1 over 32 so that gets me
you know up to the top of the where
where it should be
if the aspect ratio were correct for
this thing so then here I'm just gonna
call this my top P or tough why might be
a better way to say it right
and that would allow me to draw things
that wouldn't occupy the whole screen so
that I can just slap some debug stuff up
there and I think that's all I really
need to do I want to have two of these I
suppose I could just do this right which
is to say that I'll put another one in
here that goes from zero to one and they
can just both sit there and I'll just
use different parts of the vertex erase
should be fine right
and once I specify this I think I'm good
to go so I don't know when this gets
sent down it's OpenGL in it so it should
only have to happen the first time which
I think is good I guess that does you
know do we actually call up and chi'lan
it again I don't think we do so I take
it back because this is initialization
time we don't rebind these buffers maybe
we should because then they would work
during a reload but so anyway I'm gonna
go ahead and and recompile it this way
I'm gonna need some place to remember
that light map buffer so you can kind of
see in here we have the screen fill
buffer is is gluant we remember so we're
gonna want to remember the light map
debug buffer as well has an extra
capital u there and I think that's all
we should really need and then we can do
at the end we can use that buffer tube
lit the two textures and onto the screen
and see what they look like so now
inside the OpenGL code here we just go
down where we were using the program
here we can do it inside here because
we're using the same program so we don't
need to redo that so we can just do
effectively like something like this
right we should be able to say all right
let's just rebind the the vertex array
that we're using so it here where we did
the bind buffer we'll switch to our
light map debug buffer and then in here
where we do our bind texture stuff we
can say all right we're not going to use
this anymore we're going to use our
light map values our light map textures
and so we know that those are or should
be yeah right here so we've got the
Atlas handle for the colors and the
Atlas handler handle for the depth like
so and we're gonna need here a way of
picking out different ones so I believe
this is the initial element index I'm
gonna double check I assume it is so I'm
assuming all we need to do is that but
you know I don't remember the specifics
of the drawer raise call at the moment
so I'm gonna go ahead and look at up on
docks GL to make sure that I'm not
totally wrong about that because there's
other things that could be could be an
offset a byte offset or whatever right
so it's a gluant for the first and it
says starting index right so assuming
that we're doing a drawer array is
Collin not drawing an indexed array is
called and it should just be the fourth
one of the vertices and that should draw
both of them I think so let's take a
look and see if that does anything for
us and we'll go from there
all right so we are actually seeing some
of the information on here but you'll
notice that it doesn't it's not doing
what I had wanted it to do right it's
clearly drawing on the full screen and I
wanted it to draw on the I only wanted
it to draw a part of the screen so
looking at what's happening there you
can see doing an array buffer bind here
of the light map debug buffer and then
me trying to do my two draws and I'm not
actually sure why that would have
happened like I feel like that should
have worked okay but I'm not I'm not
sure why so let's go ahead I probably
just passed the wrong thing or something
so let me go ahead and look at the call
that actually initialize those so if I
go to light map debug buffer and look
here at what happened let me just see
what the problem is
so we Jen the buffer we
bind the buffer we send down these
vertices and these are the UV
coordinates so they shouldn't have
changed these are the positional
coordinates and
I'm not really sure like I don't
actually see why that would immediately
be a problem it looks sort of like it's
not actually using the bind buffer here
so I'm wondering if for some reason I'm
not finding it
oh so here's a question it may be that
you can't swap a bind buffer without
recalling the vertex attribution calls
I'm not sure about that
we could test it pretty easily so I
suppose I just should but then we'll
have to look at why so I just gonna see
if this is true if I use program end
here change the bind buffer and then
restart the program I'm wondering
whether or not that changes anything yes
so that does right and you can see those
textures are down in the correct place
now so that's a little weird and I guess
I don't know why so I kind of want to
take a look and see is that actually
what the expected behavior would be and
maybe it is and that's fine but I'm just
a little bit weirded out by that so does
that imply that basically these calls
are gonna bind that buffer whatever
buffer was active at the time and it
doesn't matter if you try to switch the
buffer out it won't actually take a new
one that appears to be the case which is
a little bit weird because these calls
don't actually need that right they're
just these are just specifying a vertex
format but you know I don't know it
looks like maybe that's exactly the case
it doesn't matter I'm fine with it that
way but anyway now we can sort of see
when we run the game we can see that
we've got both of those textures down
there
and I you know if I had to argue I'd say
that does look about 32 times longer
than it is wide now we have a problem
which I can see here it's just it's too
much data right that it's so tiny that
it's impossible to actually see what's
going on
in that texture so I guess I'm not sure
that this will actually help we may need
to look at like a subset of it right
like we may need to just focus on a part
that's that's significantly smaller so
that we can see anything I'm not sure
what the best way to do that would be
but anyway we now have that part working
so if I actually go and change what that
you know what that amounts to so that we
maybe make it a little bit higher and
change the UV coordinates I don't know
that seems like the only thing we could
really do here to help so if we wanted
to do that what we could do is draw like
a fairly significantly a much smaller
subset of this thing so what I could say
is like all right there's a UV dimension
and we're gonna like shrink down how
much of this texture we're drawing right
so I'm gonna go ahead and say maybe this
will be something that specifies both of
these and then I'm here I'll just say
like look UV well these are the zero I
guess is an offset so maybe we'll say
something like this UV min UV max so
that I don't have to specify each of
these individual coordinates so I'm
going to just say all right this is UV
min X in both of these and then this is
UV max X and then this is UV min Y in
both of these oops sorry
human X in both of these and UV max X in
both of these and then in these we'll
just have UV min Y and she that's max
sorry give you even why max Y you've
even in Y and each of these is just
going to be
adjustable now oops and that way I can
say look we're gonna pick out a smaller
subset of this thing and I kind of I
think I want to focus mostly on the you
know center of the thing because we're
gonna be trying to center the voxel
around us so I want to try and pick a
location in the map that has something
to do with the center now we know we
unwrapped it XY wise so I guess it's
pretty hard for us to really pick out
the center in any meaningful way but we
can at least do up-and-down we can pick
out the center so we can pick out the
center Z at the very least so maybe we
say look the Z Center would put us
somewhere like let's suppose we went
like that so we had like you know or
maybe even something like that
so we're just talking about a very
narrow part of the map and then if we
wanted to here like let's suppose that
we were doing sort of a square so if we
were doing a square part of the map well
we know that again this map is going to
be 32 right the the UV coordinates are
normalized from 0 to 1 but the map
itself is not uniform like it's not
square right so if we wanted to have a
part of the thing that would correspond
to this it would have to be 32 times the
span here in order to get a square part
of it out and so if I take a look I
guess that means I want to know
where's P crunch so if we said look we
have looking at this it's 0.1 so 0.1
times 32 is too much so I guess we want
this to be even smaller right so maybe
we say something like look it's it's
something like this so now it's just
point O to maybe even that so now it's
just like 0.01 right Supes so it means
that we only need to cover point 32 in
the x-direction to capture that much Y
right just I'm making this up as I go
along
right but basically that means like it's
point one six radius so if we were point
O 5 minus 0.16 right and 0.05 plus two
point six the problem is that straddles
the boundary so I think we probably
actually want to be more like that I
mean it really I don't even know where
we want to be in the map XY z-- but you
know off we go
so we can do something like that and
then all we would do here is just say
look at that point the top Y is gonna be
zero so we're gonna actually draw a
square now and off we go
so I think that's all we really need to
do to see a more representative part of
the map unfortunately you know like I'm
not sure again because it's a lot of
data there I'm not sure how to display
it at the moment in any particularly
useful way you can see now we're looking
at a more perhaps zoomed in in the
region of it it looks a little weird I'm
not sure why we're seeing the kind of
stipple we're getting there it may be
because the format of the texture we're
like I don't know why we're seeing
exactly what we're seeing there so we're
gonna have to look at that a little bit
more closely it looks stretched as well
in a way that doesn't make a lot of
sense to me so I think these are not
quite correct at the moment we are now
drawing a square though right because
top Y is zero
I mean well let me put it this way if
you look at this thing
it should be roughly square of course
it's not really I guess that's because
the
this is not quite a square this is
sixteen by nine so as these will be
sixteen by nine as well so let me make
those square uh for lack of a better
term because again these are also
coordinates that are the coordinates in
this case are also going to be
interpreted normalized over the screen
which we know is sixteen by nine so we
would want the them to have a 16 by 9
aspect ratio for these coordinates as
well so when adjusted they'd work out so
what I probably want to do here is say
alright where are we going to in X so
we've got like a max X here and this
width when we do this max X or maybe I
could even say this is X dim right so
I'll just write these in terms of some
starting location and then like an
addition so well actually probably more
like that and so now if we did X theme
equals one we get back the same thing
but if we do X them equal something
that's aspect ratio appropriate we'd
shrink these down to a square so that
we're at least looking at the the right
aspect ratio for a square slice of the
texture and so in that to that end right
and maybe I want this to be even a
little bit fancier so maybe I want this
to be like 1.0 minus X 10 so that like
the middle of the screen is a gap you
know what I'm saying oops and so then if
I said all right let's make X dim like I
said one if I did that correctly
[Music]
there we go I should get the same thing
and then if I change it so that I'm
actually looking at a next M of a value
that's properly adjusted for sixteen by
nine then what I should be able to do is
get those to both be squares that are
bound to the edge of the screen so
there's a square on the left side and a
square on the right side that are at the
edges of the screen but don't extend all
the way to the middle and in order to do
that like again I know that this is
going to be proportional to sixteen by
nine right because that's the resolution
that we're rendering at so I know that
the if I assume that we're doing one you
know zero to one on why I want to do
something that's 16 times but divided by
nine that in X and I don't actually want
it to not sure how to say this properly
so we know that on the screen we're
drawing one in Y but that one in Y is
proportional to the nine and we have
something that wants that is going to be
interpreted proportional to the 16 right
so this is going to want to be inverted
I need to draw this out because I'm
explaining this very poorly you know
I'll be honest I don't know where the
pen minute there it is
all right so if we have our screen and
it looks like this then what we're doing
is we're specifying coordinates that are
interpreted on a screen that we know is
sixteen by nine right
and right now what we're doing is we if
we specify one here and here which is
what we're doing a length of one right
then what we're gonna do is this length
is going to be effectively one times
nine
right and this length is gonna be one
times 16
but we want them to be equal right so in
other words we want to take and say look
we know we're doing one times nine and
so we want to say what would the value B
for our width where width times 16 is
going to be equal to one times nine
right so if the width times 16 I'll just
write this in math now
so if 16 W equals nine then I want W to
equal 9 by 16 right does that make sense
and so if we look back at what we're
doing here that's why I was going to say
like we invert this and I was trying
explain why and that's why because what
we're actually doing it although it
seems like the X should be 16 by 9
because X is the 16 side and Y is the 9
side what's happening is they're getting
multiplied by those values when they
actually go to get rendered so we're
trying to like undo the multiplication
right we're trying to reverse the 16 by
9 multiplication that's happening during
rendering as it blows it out to a screen
of that size so in theory if I invert
that fraction I should now get something
that does the correct like fractional
difference between those two and there
we go so now we're drawing actual
squares and now we just have to figure
out why we're you know we're obviously
not putting very good we're not we're
not properly selecting those UV
coordinates at all at the moment
and we gotta go see why I may have made
the same mistake when we did the
textures like I should have had a wider
version in Y right like I think what I
did is when we yeah so look here this is
the wrong way round right I needed to
make it so that this was taking a like
larger section and I think I probably
did it the opposite way that I should
have right it needs to take a smaller
section because the texture is bigger I
think that's again not explaining it
very well but we're trying to grab a
piece of a texture that's very wide but
very short and when we go to grab it
what I did was I said like oh we're
gonna grab a point oh one size slice in
Y out of the texture or in V depending
how you know why are V depending on you
want to think about it and so I need to
do one that's 32 times larger in the in
the X direction because the texture is
three times larger but it's the opposite
stru right because the texture is 32
times larger that means that whatever UV
coordinates we pick we're gonna be
getting 16 times more up sorry 32 times
more of that thing then we would have
gotten with the same slice in Y so we
actually want it to be 1/32 of the
amount we pick here so actually I could
definitely have done this the other way
round and said oh all right so if we
take a point 1 there it's not going to
be x 32 to get the other one it's gonna
be divided by 32 to get the other one
and that's the value we're actually
gonna use there right um so that's
actually what I should have done and
that was just me kind of having a brain
fart I often have that problem like it's
it's just you're thinking about the
ratio one way but the ratio actually
think goes the other way because you're
you know it's being multiplied by that
thing so you're like undoing the
multiplication and
if you do the multiplication the same
way then you're actually like doubling
the problem or squaring the problem when
you look at it so I think that's now the
correct way to look at it
and we might have to try and find a way
to grab enough of the image now to make
it make sense obviously that's a pretty
small section of it so maybe we'll try
to to to make that a little bit wider
let's write this proportional so let's
just say like V span and let's say that
we want a V span of like well we'll
start with the whole thing
we'll say 0.5 and then we'll narrow it
down as we need to go so we'll say 0.5
which means that this is - the V span
this is plus the V span and that would
take the whole thing and then we can
just do you span and the you span like
so can just be proportional to the V
span in fact of the way that I said so
it can just be the V span divided by 32
and that should give us a proper square
subsection of it assuming I don't
accidentally capitalize the letter and
once we have that we should be good to
go
right so let's go ahead and run it there
we go so now we can actually see part of
our light map here and I'd like to try
and get a part of it that we actually
visually see you know I can see there
that we're getting it what I might do
because there's no reason not to is if
we go back and you take a look at what's
happening here where we do the gen
before bind buffer here if I were to
just move this out so you know let's
suppose that I just took this thing and
I said okay you know here's here's the
part that gens the buffers and in fact
you know what let me just do it this way
so if I just said all right here's the
part that gens the buffer so here's one
gen buffer call here's another gen
buffer call
these two I can just run anytime I want
so if I was to move these into the part
where we do our change settings call
this if I did these here then I believe
I would just be able to like you know if
I do this I believe at that point I
would just be able to hot code reload
this part because it would run anytime
we reloaded the code right so I'm pretty
sure that if I start off now with a
fresh compile having moved that into the
part where the we do it every time we
change the settings if I run it now and
then I go here and start mucking with
those values I think they should update
right in real time so if I wanted to
change the V span to like zoom in on
this let's say so let's say I doubled
the V span I think after that compiles
done it should just like change in when
we run it and you can see that it did
right so there there it is so that will
allow me to kind of focus in on a value
that a part of the texture that I want
to see and so since we have the UV min
Max part of this happening right what
I'd like to do is change this to a
vector equation so I can basically say
like UV Center here or something and
then the UV min max can just be like UV
Center mine you know minus UV span and
I'll just make those two values be part
of a vector right so if we look at what
that would do I just say UV span
[Music]
that's the dimension there you either
use man and the Beast fan bound into a
vector and then the center at the moment
is 0.25 0.5 so if I delete this out and
I just make this UV Center plus UV span
and minus UV span like so now we can
just set the center to look at whatever
part we actually want right and if I was
super motivated I could even make that
just be like a debug value or something
that we move around but we've never
really gotten the debug system into a
particularly good place so it's more
annoying than it should be but let's
just try this so let's suppose I look at
apart slightly to the left does that
move this into focus a little bit more
for us so that that's in the center and
you can see now it sort of is right and
as I move you know through this thing
you can see how those octahedral
lighting results are kind of being
modified as I move around see I'm saying
and I want to zoom in probably just a
little bit more and Center it just a
little bit more so you know you can see
it's kind of like needs to be moved over
the right a little bit more and it needs
to be moved like up a little bit as well
so you know probably want to do
something like that I guess I don't know
or am I going the wrong way on why there
aren't V I should say yeah I think I am
so let's say that's 3/5 and instead of a
point 4 or 5 we'll say like five
and still so probably want to say that
not sure exactly what that center value
for X should be there there we go that's
pretty darn close so you're looking at
that part you can kind of see how it
goes right
as I'm hopping through it and I might
want to zoom it a little more on that so
if we took the V span and doubled that
to zoom in on just the center part of it
I think that would probably be good
right so now we can really look at that
octahedral light map and you know
looking at it I guess what I would say
is it's kind of hard for me to to really
tell it's not obviously wrong but I'm a
little nervous that the unwrapping is
still not quite correct right like I'm
not sure about that it's nice that we
can see it certainly but I'm just I'm
just not necessarily sure that that
we've got that unwrapping right and part
of the reason for that is you can just
see that there's sort of some weird I
mean you know it's possible that those
are in the right place with that that
doesn't feel quite Congress to me it
seems like it's always kind of out on
the corners maybe a little bit more than
it should be I'm not
I don't work with octahedral maps it's
the first time I've ever looked at them
so it could just be my unfamiliarity
with them that this is what they should
look like generally but I I don't I
don't think so
I think there's probably still someone
ramping bugs in there all right
but either way that's good like I'm I'm
pleased with that because you know we're
we're in a pretty good shape here as far
as like being able to see at least
something that that's going on I will
say it's not completely wrong like it
definitely looks like ok but it's it's
just I'm not 100% convinced of of the
accuracy there and there's a couple of
things that we can do sort of to fix
that and here's what I would propose so
I think what I want to do before I
correct any of the errors that we have
yet like not using the border and so on
I want to go test that octahedral
mapping carefully and so what I'd like
to do is I'd like to go and right into
the octahedral map using the octahedral
unwrapping of the map in such a way that
I put each octant of the octahedron on a
separate color so I can then look at the
octahedral map and actually see whether
my sphere octants are going into the
locations that I think they should be
going into and more importantly whether
they're at the place in the map that I
think they should be based on those
quadrants I think that's something we
probably wanted to do now in order to do
that I want to be able to turn off the
blending on these maps so when we go
look at the that code there it you can
see we've got sort of this stuff for
real like hey here's you know whether
this thing is linear or clamped to edge
or whatever else and if you look at this
what I would like to do here is do the
same trick I just did because I want to
be able to switch these between
blended in linear anytime I want to so I
don't want to have to restart the game
to turn off blending on my light map so
if we take change to settings and we go
in and do basically exact same things so
exactly like this here where we set
those textures you can see here for
example we're setting some min filter
mag filter stuff for like you know MIT
maps and whatever I want to do exactly
that same thing for this stuff excuse me
so I want to go ahead and and bind the
the light color Atlas and then I want to
set its parameters here right and I want
to go ahead and so that this is really
only doing just it's not setting the
parameters it's doing just the actual
creation of the texture that we don't
want to change and then I'm gonna do the
same thing with the depth handle and
that way we can play with these as much
as we want we can change what they do
and how they do them so if I want to
change one of these I can easily do it
and what here what I'll say is maybe
we'll have a blend mode here so we'll
say like okay there's like a Atlas or
light blending equals and I can just do
you know maybe I should say light
sampling and that way I can just change
that one variable and then all of my
sampling will change anytime I want it
to so if I go ahead and run that what
should happen now is any time the that
code
anytime we recompile that code we should
change the blending so right now you can
see it's very smeary it's doing linear
sampling so what I want to do now is see
if I can make it so that if I switch to
nearest this will turn into a pixelated
display and it did so that's better for
debugging you know I'd rather see the
pixelated version so I know like what
kind of resolution there is in there and
I'm not trying to figure out what is a
pixel and what is just a blend between
two pixels so that allows me to see
specifically what we're storing and
that's what I want now by the way I
should mention this entire time the
reason this one over here is completely
red is because we're not using the depth
channel at all right we're not that we
have a depth texture for our light
mapping and we're just not doing
anything with it that's intentional and
we're you know we're gonna leave it that
way until we actually get the rest of
this working so I want to go do bug this
part now and see what I can see about
that so if we go to where I'm actually
writing into that in the lighting test
you know I'm I'm just dumping down some
values based on preconceived notion of
where a light would be and you can see
in here right so if we take a look at
where we're writing into it here's the
light voxel information where we where
we put that stuff so for each one of
these what I'd like to do is say all
right when we do a write in here we're
gonna do a unit vector from octahedral
here and what I want to know is for each
one of these and I can't really test the
reverse yet because I'm not really doing
the reverse version but for this when we
say unit vector from octahedral what I
want to do is let's turn off the part
where we actually do any lighting so
let's just turn that right on off and
what I want to do instead is place some
code in here that will set the light
color to a known value so for example if
I was to set this to let's say blue
right then I should now see all blue on
the left side of my image right so there
it is and obviously we're not setting
the depth to anything at the moment so
it's just gonna come out black over
there and that's fine too so now what I
could do is say all right let's take a
look at when we get back the unit vector
from octahedral here let's see what it's
telling us these sample directions are
and so if I was to create like a pretty
simple sort of little like decoder here
and I said take the sample Direction and
take a look at the absolute value of the
X right and if the absolute value of the
X Direction is greater than the absolute
value of the Y direction and the Z
Direction right so it's the maximum one
it's it's the maximum value of the
values that we have is that parenthesize
properly know if it's the maximum value
that we have we'll set it to one thing
right if it's if it's not you know we'll
check the other way around and then
we'll check the final way right so this
is basically saying like we'll just look
at which one is highest and so if the X
is highest then what we'll do is we'll
set the X equal to we'll set the red
right channel the green channel or the
blue channel based on which one's
highest and now what we haven't done is
differentiated between the positive and
negative quadrants which we would like
to do but for right now we're not going
to do that we're just going to look and
what we see if we look here is I don't
know you know I'm not sure I could
really call that correct but at the same
time it's not obviously wrong either
right like it's a little bit hard to
tell so I'm gonna go ahead and finish
that part and see I'm gonna different
differentiate between the positive and
negative halves of these so I'm gonna
say look if sampled or X is less than
zero right then I'm gonna do dark blue
otherwise I'm gonna do Oh actually you
know what well no
right so now dark will be positive and
I'm sorry dark will be negative and
light will be positive of each of the
values
there's the green version sorry blue
version here and off we go
so yeah so if the absolute value of the
x-coordinate is greater than both the
absolute values of the y&amp;z then we will
color it red and we'll use a dark red
for negative and a bright red for
positive if the Y is greater than the X
and the Z then we will do the same thing
with green and if the Z is greater than
the X and the y then we'll do the other
one right and I could have just done an
else here I suppose because we know that
basically like you know I mean maybe
this is the smarter thing to do right
so we'll just get a blue in the case
where you know neither of the other two
were true at that point we should be
able to see if this thing looks like an
octahedron or what right and so looking
at it here you know that that's not
correct you know this this doesn't quite
look like an octahedral map to me and so
I think we've got a bug somewhere now it
doesn't necessarily mean that we have a
bug here you know for all I know this
thing's writing into the thing wrong you
know what I mean like this could be
wrong right I'm going to look at the
octahedral mapping first and see but I
guess
one way to test this as well would be if
we now that we know that we're not
seeing quite acht quite an octahedron
what I could do is just say look well
let's see if we're actually writing into
this thing and the pattern we think so
if I set the light coordinate here what
I could do is say look we know we've got
two T X in the T Y and we know they're
based on these values so let's just see
what happens if I do TX /
whatever this thing is right and and in
fact you know what I don't even need to
do that because we've already got it
it's the O XY here that we're feeding in
so let's just draw the yo XY and we'll
draw the O XY as sort of a you know in
red getting increasingly bright from
left to right and blue I'm sorry green
getting increasingly bright from up to
down and so if we look at that what we
can sort of see here is like at least
nominally it sort of looks correct now
there's some issues here so I'm not
really willing to say that this is
correct because if you look at what
we're getting if we look at these values
a little bit more closely and you know
we could zoom in even further on this
for our purposes here so like you know
let me go over to where we're specifying
the the zoom so in here let's let's say
that we want to keep this span around
for a little bit but I'm gonna go ahead
and zoom in like way in for a second
just to visualize this more carefully
right all right maybe not that far
try that one more time so what you can
see about this is I'm expecting or was
expecting to see a 10 by 10 right and if
I look at the red I see 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
8 9
ish I mean you know 1 2 3
yeah I think you could make an argument
pretty easily for 10 there you know what
these are from negative 1 to 1 though so
I guess I need to do this so maybe
that's all that was
hold on one second
am I wrong about that right these are
negative one to one so if I undo that
transform that doesn't look right at all
the green is like Fulbright oh yeah
sorry about that
all right so if I look at this right
what I'm trying to say here is I see
this value looking like what I would
expect so 10 across but this is not
looking at all like what I expect and so
I've got some kind of a bug in there
like I'm not understanding what's
happening with like the T Y value and
I'm not sure why right and pun intended
and so I need to figure out what's going
wrong there and it could be that this
packing here is wrong and it's kind of a
mess so I could totally see that being
the case so maybe we need to take a
second and actually figure out what the
heck we want to do here for writing into
these packed versions a little bit more
cleanly but it really looks like we've
got the Y wrong because our X values
line up exactly the way I would expect
them to and our Y values totally don't
they look doubled up so it looks like
for example if I had to guess it looks
like we're advancing the wrong amount
for the next sheet or something so
basically like we're we're not going
where we should go for any particular
cell right so if you look at what we're
doing here this L index C is supposed to
pick out like a particular pixel so that
has to be able to map directly from a
particular voxel location into where
that would go
in the texture right I mean that's
what's supposed to be happening here and
we don't have to care about Elland XD at
all because we're not debugging that
texture and it's just the exact same
look up with a different variable anyway
so I think what we want to do here is
figure out what this equation actually
should look like and try to make sure
that it's actually right instead of
being kind of messed up which appears to
be at the moment so if we take a look at
what our parameters here actually are
these parentheses don't really do
anything right so so this is what we're
actually looking at these are our actual
you know parameters and if you look at
how much we're going for each sheet in Z
we're basically saying look it's we're
doing one entire voxels sheet times the
size of each of the the lightmaps
and that seems like it makes sense for y
we're going let me rearrange this so for
a while sheet we're moving down
essentially that's saying we're gonna
move down one complete dimensions worth
of little squares right which also seems
reasonable for X we're moving by this
dim and that
I'll be honest this doesn't really make
correct sense so no I mean I guess that
does I mean yeah it does
so basically like we start out moving by
just however wide it is because for each
X voxel we have to go one whole sheet
right
and the TX there is you know mmm that's
moving by pixels so we go up one level
and we now have to move by whatever the
dimension of the voxel is but we also
have to move by the dimension of the
actual squares right so you're gaining
like both of those on the voxel side of
things I don't think this would have to
do it because we're not packing them
that way
40y we need to move down by whatever the
dimension of the thing is times the hot
dim as well right I mean that does make
sense for each pixel wide we wise one we
need to go so that does seem right but
again no you know what it's gonna be the
this dimension is going to be sort of
wrong because you still have to move
yeah you know what I mean just looking
at I still and I still I still don't see
the bug there I mean it looks alright to
me because another way to say this would
just be look this is the amount we're
moving in y-you know we have to compute
a y-coordinate and an x-coordinate the
x-coordinate is ya is going to be
obviously just like if you're trying to
move a pixel at a time which would be
this then it's not it's going to be
unadulterated just happens by you going
ten pixels over right so as far as X
motion is concerned we are literally
just talking about this right that's how
we move in X and so anywhere that you
ever want to be XY z-- is literally just
that there's nothing else that happens
in X right for Y motion we kind of have
a weird situation because Y motion is
actually going in X in a sense because Z
is how we laid out our sheets so in
order to move in why there's two things
you have to do and you is because the
actual squares are laid out in the UV as
a square it means that when you move a
pixel Y you have to actually just go by
the entire length of the texture right
and so I think that's the part that's a
little confusing so in order to move the
entire length of the texture well Z
moves by the entire length of the
texture by using hot dim times ktem
right the entire length of the texture
is going to be the x times the Y times
the ox
dim right so it's going to be it's going
to be to move one pixel in Y you do have
to move by the total number that there
are times how many each the size of each
one to get one y over and you're going
in X at that point right you're going
laterally and then in order to go an
entire Y sheets worth of those like t y
yeah so the part that I'm Trever back my
head around so T Y actually needs to be
doing this totally differently like this
is not
this is still not correct let me just
make sure I got this right
so
this is definitely correct this is
moving by the number of those that are
on one entire x sheet and it's moving
that number over that is wrong so this
is the part that's wrong
the reason it's incorrect is because
there are many Y's next to each other
and we need to account for those so
actually this would only account for the
number that there were in X so we're
really that is actually what has to
happen right it needs to account for the
number there are an X and the number
there are and Y so yeah I believe that's
actually how this needs to get encoded
and well actually that's not true so I
believe that's the first part of how it
asks get encoded right that has to
happen that's how you move in into Y if
I nerf out these for a second because I
want to think about this separately I'm
curious is that now actually at least
properly stepping through and I don't
know how would I see that for some
reason I don't see this doesn't seem to
be changing it all which seems odd
because given the fact that I'm
manipulating how we're writing these out
I suppose that maybe because it's
writing to a different area or something
so let me restart here and just see what
we get we should get like nothing ill or
something right yeah
I'm gonna take the whole V fan just so I
can see where that's writing now all
right and so now I'm not seeing anything
on here I'm gonna try the upper corner
of that as well so when we're looking in
here I'm gonna look when we take the UV
span I'm gonna I'm sorry when we take
the UV Center I'm going to re set the UV
Center to be like the UV span like so so
this would take the corner of the
texture the mid corner all right and so
here you can see writing into the
texture and now by the way it looks
correct right so if i zoom in on that
now from where we are I'll go back to
the zoomed version and it's only writing
one row which is how many I thought it
should right now we can see that we're
actually writing we're you know our
indexing is correct to this thing and so
then if I go in here and say alright how
do I start extending this out two more
of these so that I could fill the next
row I've got to make sure these things
are indexing correctly so let's start
with why now and remember no matter what
I do to Y in theory I should not be able
to fill in another row because Y exists
on only one row so each time we move in
why I need to go hot dim times acht dim
over right and this I think is wrong
because this is not part right like
think about what this is doing I'm
saying I'm stacking these in the Y
direction I'm sorry in the X direction
so that I have one row and then the next
row is just next to that row on the same
row right so even though these are
multiple rows logically I'm packing
multiple rows together so I don't
actually involve this part at all right
moving by the voxel just moves by
however many of these things you had to
do to get to the next one so we're still
going in Y at that point and we don't
square our X our X pixel value like that
oops so now if I look I should still
have the same thing and I do which is
actually good and so now all we need to
do is move in Z and so Z is the first
time we're actually gonna say look
alright we need to move we know that
each row is hot dim times hot been long
and we also know that we need to skip
over the ktem times the ktem because
we are moving by entire squares now so I
think that's the entire equation that
was a real Mindbender it shouldn't have
been but it was just because I'm not
used to packing a voxel into a square
like that and so that looks much more
valid all right so now if I can go back
thanks to our structured art we've
eliminated one of our problems here now
if I go back and take out the line where
we switch UV centers I can go back and
look at the place I was looking at
before and hopefully now I'm gonna see
the same thing so now everywhere should
look like these little squares and it
kind of does and that's what we wanted
so now having gotten that bug out of the
way we can switch back to looking at the
view this way and see if we see anything
different now with setting our
structured colors up here right so I'm
entering this back on and turn this part
off like so and now I should get
something in terms of where the how the
octahedron looks right and so if we look
at how this is structured yeah like do I
think that looks like an octahedral map
I mean it doesn't obviously not look
like an octahedral map but I'm not
really super confident
what I'd like to start doing because
it's hard for me to see which part of
which this is I would like to go ahead
and make it so that I'm actually gonna
try to use the correct sampling here so
when we go through and we're looking at
T X T y what I want to do is actually
only write into the places where we were
supposed to write so instead of doing
this I'm gonna actually do this right
and that way we will no longer be let me
rephrase that I want to write only into
the interior without using without using
the edge pixels that we left to because
we're going to copy those in later so
when we actually go through these I want
to effectively write into just the
narrow part here so what I wanted to do
is say look let's create something that
only fills in the interior square like
so and we're never going to touch those
edge pixels right those edge pixels are
going to be like a totally different
thing right and I'm then gonna go in
maybe an add a pass that actually fills
them right so now I can see what this
thing actually looks like right to see
to what I sent it looks like an
octahedral map at all and one of the
things that I'm noticing curious just
looking at it it kind of looks like
maybe it's sort of like an octahedral
map but it's sort of off like I wonder
if maybe the input here is a little bit
off
I mean I'm not entirely sure
I might go in and step it through this
code and look at what these oxly values
are just to satisfy myself that there's
no funny business going on but it looks
it looks a little off like it shouldn't
probably have its center line like that
its symmetry looks a little bit broken
and while the fact that it's an eight by
eight means that its symmetry isn't
going to be perfect and that's okay it
does make me a little concerned so I
just want to I just want to kind of get
that I want a little bit more assurance
that there isn't something busted there
before I go any further I'm gonna go to
debug mode in remedy I'm going to ask it
to stop the code at the point where
we're passing on those values and I just
want to see what the ranges of the
values that we're passing right and I
want to satisfy myself that they make
sense so I'm gonna go to the watch
window here I'm gonna see what we get so
negative one is what I would expect
stepping through these yeah exactly so
I'm missing my last value right and I
guess I'm not sure oh it's you know what
this is the problem right there
so I was right I mean to the extent that
we can call me being right today I mean
I was wrong when I wrote the code this
is supposed to go up to this value and
include it right so we want this code to
actually still look like it did that was
just kind of an oversight in which
values we were supposed to be
considering so you know if we're going
to the light color lookup squared dim
minus one here we would need to
actually include that value if we ever
wanted this part to actually work right
and so I think so I think that means
this needs to subtract three right it
needs to subtract the two that we've
pulled off the edges and then one
because we want to divide out to one
exactly and so I think that's what we
need to do in order to get this lining
up I think right and that's starting to
look actually a lot better I know it
looks a little worse inside here but
it's it's more symmetric now and these
are gonna be rounding error issues
anyway in here not super concerned about
those at the immediate moment this is
starting to look correct because these
blue parts here right just in terms of
how this is set up the way that the we
probably want to try and color these a
little differently I guess is the way I
would say it because the way the
octahedral mapping works is it's going
to have you know things based more on
whether or not you you know X or u plus
V is greater than 1 or less than 1 to
say whether you're outside of the octave
so it's not gonna produce a knock that's
gonna produce more like this
checkerboard that we're actually seeing
so that's actually fairly encouraging
all right so I'm gonna go ahead now and
verify that I can actually produce sort
of an octahedron so what would we do
here if we wanted to actually produce
you know an octahedron let's start by
switching between the 0 the sample
direction 0 in one case right so let's
say that our light color is going to be
you know 4 on the top of that of the
octagon or the bottom of the octagon
we're gonna set our blue channel to 1 or
0 or something right
so I'm gonna get rid of this for now
and I'm gonna just just set the sample
oops set the light C equal to a positive
or negative there and then what I'm
gonna do is say look let's see which of
the X quadrants were on let's see how do
I want to do this yeah I mean I think I
think I can set these to just be you
know I mean I guess what I'm saying is
can I just do this can I just look at my
my quadrants and take a look at the
light that way because that should give
me something roughly resembling an
octave octahedral map and we'll see
where it goes so if we take a look here
at what we're filling in you can kind of
see that's a little bit wonky so you
know we've got something that roughly
resembles an octahedral map but it's not
quite so the actual sample directions
here if the X was positive I measured it
on it this way
so yeah we take a look here if the X was
positive we're gonna see red and what
we're seeing here is that for some
reason as we get up to the top the X is
not positive and I'm not sure why is
that because the X is zero there you
know perhaps I suppose we can figure it
out maybe by doing that just to see what
we get there yeah so basically like the
X is positive what we're seeing is like
the X is positive here in the octahedral
map but also all through there and here
and I'm not sure that that's correct if
I remember correctly the way that like
you know if we just looked at the blue
you know like let's suppose that we made
it a little easier on ourselves and
knocked out the red and the green if we
just looked at the blue what we would
expect to see is only the this part
would be in and the outside part would
all be out basically right and that
looks correct like that seems right to
me
so that part of the octahedral mapping I
mean seems right to me for the other
part of the octahedral mapping let's
just take a look at the X so now what
we're saying is this is the X side of
the cube and I don't know that I believe
that those should be set like that
the X is 0 through here so I guess maybe
that's okay like we're saying that's
actually equal to 0 literally right
so I guess I might believe that too and
now if I go through and just say like X
and Z if I take a look at the Y I always
try to see the same thing basically like
this top part yeah so I can believe it
I'll be honest I could believe it I
could believe that we've got it going
now I don't want to say that with 100%
confidence but I'm willing to believe
that's more or less a correct octahedral
map at that point so let's go ahead and
turn back on our actual lighting so that
we can see what it looks like now that
we've done that amount that limited
amount of debugging and we'll see how it
goes
there we go all right so why can I not
Oh cuz we're in debug mode my bad debug
mode is very slow still because entirely
the lighting good all right so now let's
go ahead and take a look at how this
this these maps look we may have to zoom
out a little bit now on them and I'll be
honest that looks a lot better right you
see it kind of moving around sort of as
if a light source were unwrapped into
that octahedral no I mean I feel just a
lot better about that in terms of the
likelihood that now we're actually
mapping the octahedral properly right
I mean I just feel much better about I
think you know those I thought there
were bugs in there there were now it's
looking a lot less like there's any bugs
like that doesn't look super bugging me
I'm gonna pop out a level here of
resolute zoom on the so so you know go
back to maybe sort of the further up
looking at a larger cross-section of the
map there and just see if that seems to
continue to make sense so you know I'm
I'm thinking that's not bad I'm thinking
that's not bad right
I'm pretty happy with that let's go
ahead and go do a quick QA but I think
we're good for today right Myra am I am
I right on time so wait what would we
use sir if we start at 12 no no wait
we've got more time what time do we
start here nine three mister okay okay
okay no I've got more time so great so
let's go ahead and finish up the writing
side of the code and because now what we
should be able to do is go in and do our
copy right so we should be able to do
our copy back where we say look let's
just take those corner pixels and copy
them in the other thing we could do is
actually use the lighting now which I
guess we could do maybe we'll throw that
in because we have a little bit of time
maybe maybe we'll do that if if we take
a look at what would have to happen
there in our Z bias program we basically
need to do the same stuff that we're
doing in the main app right we need to
be able to sample the lighting in the
fragment shader which is gonna take a
bunch of work right so if we take a look
at what's going on in here and you know
I really wish we could see this as
actual code you know regular code it
would be nice I feel like we could
probably make that work in for coder at
some point but basically something where
we could just say like look just indent
this like normal code right like you
know take a take a look at what the
value is here and we could say you know
hey for coder if you see a here doc
that's basically that right indent it
normally because it would help a lot
right for us to be able to read this
stuff and there's no reason we can't
just do it that way it's just a question
of for code or just needing to know that
which I don't know if it's possible or
not and on the gallons watching today
but I do feel like that's something that
would be cool to have at some point
yeah anyway uh so if we take a look in
the main code here what's gonna happen
is we do a you know a some like call to
get the lighting and then we multiply by
that lighting and if you look at what
happens to the sunlight call we just
don't do anything currently right you
know nothing happens now we know our
voxel uvw and our relative position in
the voxel and all that garbage right
so we basically know how we would go
about starting to look up this stuff but
what we don't know at the moment is like
how we actually would go about taking a
voxel sample for each of these and what
we're going to have to do right is we're
going to have to produce our own manual
sampling of the you know we're gonna
have to take eight samples ourself and
blend those eight samples together now
that's not horrible or anything right
it's it's not bad that we have to do
that but that is what we have to do and
so if we go in here and start to do that
what we would need to do is find what
the the eight corner voxel locations are
two sample between and in order to do
that we would take this voxel UVW
multiply it by the number of voxels per
side to figure out where we are right so
when we take the voxel relative P and
multiply it by the inverse dim what
we're gonna get is like something where
we want to basically do like a floor a
multiplied by the size and floor to
figure out what voxel cell is like the
bottom corner of us and then we're gonna
want to find the like upper corner and
so on now if we just pass the voxel
dimension in here which we can do right
like we can just do a pound define for
this right we can just say like pound
define light lookup Fox lignin and
that's just that's just a
you know a value we should be able to
multiply to find what those voxel
parameters are and then we should be
able to take those samples using like a
utility function so if we want to in
here we should be able to say something
along the lines of all right voxel you
know address or voxel I or something
right that's just gonna be whatever the
UVW was times whatever the heck this
thing is right and I guess since we're
in shader land we can actually just do a
straight multiply like this and it
should just work I think that gives us
the actual voxel index and when we have
the voxel index what we want to do then
is find the corners right so the corners
are pretty easy to understand right
there just like this sort of thing right
so we've got that oscillating down and
if we just pick out each possible
additive permutation so going 1 in X 1
in Y and 1 in Z in the voxel if we just
do all the permutations of that that's 8
right 2 to the third we get eight
permutations those are the eight corners
of the voxel that we need to look up
we've done this before it's nothing
special right so if we want to take our
light samples at each of those locations
then we need to actually have some
utility if I'm just going to take a
voxel index look up where the light
actually should be and give us back
something we can actually use right now
because we're gonna want to look up two
things we're gonna want to look up a
depth and a color and we want both of
the things then we want them both to
come out I'm gonna go ahead and say we
probably just want to do something where
we actually call the sunlight function
we want to call like a function on each
of those so like we want to do like a
like an accumulate call or something
like this right like we want to be able
to do something where we're summing up
these as we go and what we're going to
use here to figure out where in the
voxel we actually go is gonna be like a
voxel look up UV that's for the the
actual sub square and that's gonna be
based on the normal we're trying to
sample we don't want to unwrap that
every time so we want like an octahedral
on you know we want to do that unpack at
some point and we're gonna want to pass
that into the accumulator so that it can
sample based on the direction it's
supposed to actually be looking you know
I'm saying it's like what's the lighting
in that direction ah and I think I think
that's mostly all this would have to
look like right and so each of these is
going to want to do a sample into the
voxel it's gonna give us back like a I
guess we could do the accumulation here
where it's just gonna give us back
whatever the lighting was from that
thing and we're gonna multiply it by
some weighting value right like we're
just gonna be doing like well what's a
voxel it's it's one of you know if we're
summing these things together
oh well no we're not we're gonna need to
do the trilinear blend now that I think
about it so we're gonna actually want
this to be getting the values out of
these from a try linear blend it's not
going to want to do the accumulation now
there's a slight issue here which is
that when we're doing the blend I'm not
sure I'm not sure where we take the
depth into account because we'll have
depth and we'll say I guess could we
have seen it or not and you know I don't
really know we should probably go back
and look at the original paper for how
to do the sampling there what they think
a good way to do it is but I'm just I'm
trying to figure out how this code
should work ideally what we would do is
we'd get back the depth we get both back
both of the things I'm just not sure how
you actually structure that in a shader
like in C we just create a struct and
we'd return it in a shader you can sort
of do that but I'm not sure to what
extent you can actually do that Oh duh
you know what we'll just use a v4 so do
RGB and we'll stick in the a we'll stick
the depth that way we don't have to
worry about can you declare structures
and shaders in in GLSL 3 which I don't
know if you can eventually you know in
later shader versions you definitely can
- don't know about 3
all right so we'll just say like this is
sample s 0 0 0 right and this way we can
just write down what these are so we're
saying like look it's something like
this I guess so we've got all the
samples coming out that way and this
will just be like
so we'll get all the lighting out that
way and that'll be a fairly simple
lookup once we have the octahedral
unwrapping it's basically just figuring
out where in the voxel you are or where
in the texture sheet you are pulling out
the value and giving it to us that's all
it has to do and it could do both of the
samples and pack them together and then
all we need to do is actually do our
lerp so we have our vox uvw here what we
don't know is where you actually are in
it so when we actually do this light
lookup voxel dim times the uvw here
right this thing when we do this vox i
we want to floor that but if we also
want to know you know so I guess this is
actually how you would sort of do it
right we would get the I Vic 3 out of
that but anyway so you want to floor
that and this is actually going to be we
want both of these so we want to store
what the offset was where we were in the
actual texture there and so where we
were like in the actual voxel and so I'm
gonna like call this like Vox relative
or something so we've done would say Vox
our you know - equals fox I so that way
we have the relative coordinate and the
like absolute coordinates we know like
the fractional part and the non
fractional part right we'll put the
unwrapping here when we do this we'll
have the information we actually need to
look up into the light location I would
think and we can probably do this in a
better way because these would all be
fixed offsets so we can probably as
compute those offsets ourselves and
speed up this routine so this this is
not gonna probably the way we want do it
eventually but just to keep things a
little bit simpler and then we'll
actually do the blend here so we're
gonna call this the result will return
this result and here in the result call
what we want to do is
is actually take all of these values and
and blend them together right so it's
gonna be one of these heinous lerp sorts
of things but we can do it sort of in in
stages right so we can take and create
some interim values here and I don't
really remember did we define the lerp
ourselves I don't even remember how we
did this stuff yeah we did so we made
our own lerp ATB so we can just go ahead
and write this the way we would normally
write it because we made a macro that
turns it into a shader speak as
necessary so we can make these lerp and
basically what we're going to do is
remove one dimension each time I mean
that's all we're doing here right so s
zero zero zero we want to remove the
variants on Z so we've got two right and
in each one of these is just going to do
each one of these is just going to do
one of these right so that would remove
one dimension out each time and which
dimension we're going to use right so
well it's just Z so we know that the the
Vox our Z is the value that tells us how
much Z we should blend right how much we
should blend to the the next z1 and then
we can do the same thing to take the the
last dimension out of it right so now
we've got the same thing we've got you
know 0 0 and 0 1 and 1 0 and 1 1 and
that would you know be removing the Y
dimension and then the final one for the
light sample is just blending those two
together on X and then we've got our
result if we want it now eventually
we're gonna want to do more stuff here
cuz we're gonna have we're gonna
actually want to do the reflection
probably in a in a smarter way
or you know whatever the diffuse blend
and and all that nonsense
so I don't know exactly what we're gonna
want to do here with respect to that and
if we look at how this is working right
so this is the reflection vector but you
know if the surface is very diffused
it's just gonna be reflecting general
lighting so we may want to also do some
things where we control like the MIPS
sampling of this thing so we've got a
bunch of stuff we're probably gonna want
to play with for right now though let's
just say we're gonna take the reflection
vector and we're gonna unwrap it and use
that for the lighting so we would need
our octahedral where we say look we've
got a unit vector and we need to put it
into octahedral space so we're
effectively gonna have to do this right
now in order to do this we don't have to
do it as badly as we were doing it
before right we can actually be a little
bit more clever here because we have the
ability to do like swizzles and stuff so
instead of having to do the stuff we
were doing before we could do this more
compactly if we want to so first of all
we can do here where we say like here's
the ox right so we take the one norm
that's going to be taking the R vector
and then we're gonna say all right let's
go ahead and divide that out that gives
us effectively the result so that's what
we wanted and then all we really have to
do is say oh well though we do have to
do a thing where we we take whatever the
the when the Z is negative right we have
to then say okay let's update the XY to
be equal to this equation right
so then what we need to say is our ain't
if the Z is negative we're going to have
to take the sign of the thing that we
were talking about before it doesn't
matter which side the signs will be the
same because this won't change the sign
so we can take the sign either of acht
or of our I don't think it matters which
one and so maybe we'll take the sign of
our might be the better way to do it
and then we want to take the absolute
value of the octahedral sample so that
should be acht I believe and this should
be what we actually want to produce
right so we want to take the absolute
value and then we want that sign of I
don't know that we have an ability to do
sign of in the way that we would need to
right maybe I might have to put this
back sign of in this case is supposed to
produce positive or negative it's never
supposed to produce zero and I don't
actually know what the definition of
sign of is there like I don't really
know what GLSL defines that to be like
what is it so if we look
yeah like sign up doesn't really help us
because or the one that they have the
sign call will will incorrectly produce
zero when we didn't actually want it to
do that right
so I guess we will have to implement
that ourselves unfortunately I don't
know and we can look in fact I think we
actually saw this if we go back and look
at the actual values that rupes in the
reference version so we downloaded the
light probe part here and in the
supplement that gave the code right and
the code for the octahedral wrapping and
unwrapping was in here did we aim you
know what I think we maybe had to look
it up in yeah I think we maybe looked it
up in here
yeah so this is how they implemented it
right and if you look at what they did
you can see that they had to write this
themselves and so I don't think they
would have done that if there was a
convenient if the GPU actually had a
call for that thing I don't think they
would have done that so my assumption
here is that we just have to write it
ourselves right because it doesn't look
like there's any way to do it otherwise
so they need like sign of you know we
need we need to do it ourselves
like this
and I think that's just the way it's
gonna have to be right so I don't know
if they've got sign of if we define sign
of in here so we have sign and we
defined that as sign and our sign of is
not that right and it doesn't work the
same way so we kind of need that to be
like that this is actually sign or zero
in a sense and we don't really want that
so let's see what else we got here
all right let's try to debug that shader
we got a few minutes actually so we
don't really have any minutes left but
let's just try to get the compile errors
out of it how about that so let me go
ahead and take a look at what the errors
are here in the program of this this
will be what fragment errors absolute
value let's go ahead and get that
straightened out sample lighting that's
true we haven't done that yet
so here's sample lighting maybe
something like that seems reasonable not
sure we're actually gonna put in here
but I suppose right now if I just stuff
it with white we will at least not ruin
our rendering because it'll just light
with nothing all right what else we got
undefined variable Vox eye is that true
that is true I agree
all right and so now in theory we've
actually got this set up and so tomorrow
we'll go to QA for now but tomorrow we
should be able to move over into
actually sampling these and seeing what
we can get out of them pretty happy with
that we're in good position we had a
bunch of bugs I knew there were bugs we
got rid of them so we'll be in good
shape to like get some more bugs out
tomorrow because now we're gonna have to
get the lighting sampling working and
I'm sure that'll be a little bit buggy
too but we'll we'll get there slowly but
surely all right let's go ahead and go
to quick QA I don't got any
up the cooter was asking if I could show
the octahedral map with linear blending
sure let me go run it again all right so
here's an active object let's get to a
position where it's relatively good so
there's a you know there's an octahedral
map area you can you can pretty much see
that it's you know doing something
probably correct I mean you know I'm not
confident we completely debug this thing
yet to say the least but I'll go in here
now and I'll switch from you know over
to the linear so if we go down to how
we're doing our our filtering so here's
linear in a second there you go and you
know there's not a huge difference right
obviously it's just it's just smooth it
I mean it's pretty small texture so but
it's exactly what we would expect to see
and we'll switch back
can you say a few words about octahedral
mapping there's not a lot to say about
it if you just go back and read this
watch the streams where we implemented
it it's pretty easy to understand but I
mean this is the diagram this is it in a
nutshell it takes a sphere it Maps it on
to a square you can think of it as first
sort of shrink wrapping the sphere onto
an octahedron so to tetrahedrons one
facing up when it facing down and then
just unwrapping so that the top part of
you know the part that's facing up the
top hemisphere comes into this middle
part here and then the bottom part is
just unfolded so that it has somewhere
to go right that's it um kind of off
topic have you ever been at a point
where you thought that programming might
not be the right thing for you yeah sure
and I would say I currently think it's
not the right thing for me I really love
programming I think it's it's awesome
and I love doing it I still pretty much
enjoy anytime I'm actually programming I
would say that doing it as a job is just
a really bad idea these days there
there's absolutely no interest in the
current computing landscape there's
absolutely no interest in doing a good
job there's no interest in trying to
make good computers there's no interest
in trying to make good operating systems
there's no interest in trying to make
good tools and so I would say probably
95% of what I do is just cleaning up
other people's crap I get to actually
program things that I actually wanted to
program so rarely and it's really really
sad and so I would say that that I don't
think I ever really had much of a doubt
or and still don't that I love
programming and love doing it you know I
think you could make the analogy to to
probably any other industry at some
point that industry becomes like so
distorted and useless that you know it's
it's not really about the thing that
it's nominally about and I guess I would
say if you loved cooking but the only
way to get paid cooking was to work at
McDonald's then at some point you might
be asking yourself why you're doing it
right because it's not really cooking I
mean it technically is like technically
if you recommend Alice you are cooking
but you're not really doing the thing
that you would call cooking if you were
talking about it separately and so
that's the modern programming industry
right the modern program industry is all
programmers effectively are now working
at McDonald's they like to pretend that
they're not but they are and so what
you're doing is not programming it's you
know taking a chicken patty out of a
freezer it's already been fried you're
putting it into a microwave and pushing
a button and you're not even putting in
the time you're just pushing the button
that says chicken patty out it comes and
you put it in a wrapper the wrapper is
on a stack that you grab and then you
hand it to a customer right and so at
that point you're just like I mean so
yeah you could try to and and I do try
to then say all right I'm gonna go spend
the time to build my own like you know
I'm gonna go learn to be a carpenter so
I can build an actual place that's not a
McDonald's and then I'm gonna
figure out how to build like a stove and
put that in there and like all this
stuff right and start a farm to actually
make the ingredients so that I can
actually then cook again right and you
know I tried to do that but at some
level it's like kind of a bit Sisyphean
and at some part when you're right in
the middle of it you kind of go why am i
doing all like I don't really want to do
all this stuff you know I don't want to
write an operating system or I didn't
really want to write a standard library
or something or I didn't want to or in
case of you know someone like Jonathan
Blow it's like maybe he does enjoy
making a language but it's sometimes
it's also why the heck does he have to
make a language like he's one of the I
mean I'm one of these like the greatest
game designer of all time I mean he's
certainly from my perspective the tubes
got to make a programming language I
mean good on him for doing it but come
on I mean how much wasted intellectual
power is going to this stuff because the
people who were supposed to be doing the
stuff just didn't care right or suck and
so at some level it's just really it's
really sad and so I definitely feel like
I'm in that place and I you know I am
and not a game designer or any of that
stuff so it's not like my talents are
being wasted like they are with John's
maybe and waste is the wrong word cuz he
probably will design a cool language but
it's like a ton of potential there's a
ton of games you won't play because you
know the people who make all of this
stuff suck and John's spending his time
figuring out how to do stuff like get
Visual Studio to install properly and
replacing the programming language you
know I'm saying and so I think it's a
really depressing time to be a
programmer it's horrible if you actually
care it's a great time to be a
programmer if you just want a job
because there's a ton of jobs and they
pay really well so if all you want to do
is make some money it's a great time to
be a programmer if you really love
programming it's a terrible time to be a
programmer that's how I'd say
have you ever used or heard of spherical
gaussians before I have heard of them
before I have never worked them before
was exactly the same aspherical
harmonics so my understanding is
spherical harmonics versus spherical
gaussians the difference there is
basically what's the basis function that
you're going to apply to the sphere to
project your functions on right so you
have some lighting functions I mean
usually they're discrete so it's calling
a function maybe it's wrong room you
have a lighting set of lighting samples
and you want to project those onto the
sphere and potentially compress them
circle harmonics are you know Fourier
style so they're gonna be like sine
cosine lobe shape things that are
defined over the sphere right circle
gaussians although I've never looked at
them I assume are just Gaussian
functions on a sphere right because why
not I mean you can you can use any basis
function you want they don't even have
to be orthogonal right you can define
anything you want as functions on a
sphere and you can decompose functions
on the sphere into those basis functions
so my assumption would just be that
that's what they are but I've never
looked at them before so I don't know
you know I wouldn't be in a position to
talk about trade-offs between say why
would you use a spherical harmonic
function instead of a spherical Gaussian
function because not having work with
them either myself I I just don't have I
just don't have any intuition for you
know where they go wrong I'm sure
there's reasons why you would use one of
the other otherwise you wouldn't have
them but you know I'm the one person
asked i remember we moved away from
manual try linear filtering on vox
samples because it was a lot of texture
bandwidth how is this better than the
old approach so actually this is really
pretty interesting as an approach I'm
pretty excited about it
so if you remember correctly we were
previously saying that we had our so
previously we're saying look we're gonna
have to have six textures and each of
those textures we're going to have to
sample
our selves right so we had each of the
six directions was sort of I think what
we had stuffed in there and I it was a
lot of texture bandwidth to blend those
first and then look at the results it
wouldn't be a lot of texture bandwidth
to just blend the thing first and
produce one vector sample and then
return it right but even doing that
would have required us to sample at
least three of the directions and blend
them together
the thing about octahedral Sammy that's
so nice is the texture card does that
first blend for you so imagine you're
gonna do one trilinear blend well you
know that's going to be for lips to lips
one lerp right
now if you had to do that on six
directions that's six times those seven
lips right six times seven is twenty too
much stuff on the other hand if you
blended first well now you still have to
take at least three samples of each of
the voxels blend those together and then
do the seven lips right and so you still
have three times seven with the
octahedral sampling it's just one times
seven you look up and you let the
bilinear blend do the lerp do the first
smush down for you right so it is very
nice it takes out one entire step of the
process for us which is great both in
terms of making it simpler but also in
terms of of less work like less actual
GPU work so it's faster to I would think
do you think step back step X times 2
minus 1 could be faster than our current
sign implementation I would seriously
doubt it I mean you know I'd have to
think pretty hard about it and obviously
you'd want to time it if you actually
cared about the performance of that
particular thing but you know if you
take a look at that where was it as a
biased program here if you take a look
at what we wrote
so that sign up function right is
compare and then select so you're
talking about two instructions to
implement this
whereas what you're talking about is 3
it's at least step a multiply and
subtract so pretty sure it'd be hard to
beat this is there a reason you think
step x 2 minus 1 was faster maybe I can
answer it better that way why is the
depth not red squares I think that's
just cuz we haven't actually touched
that part of the routine I can go ahead
and fix that for you if it's bugging you
I don't I don't mind I agree that might
be kind of annoying so if you take a
look here you can see we've got the
original set of vertices X stuff here
and then we've got this one I didn't
really look at what this was set to it
looks like it's drawing in the right
place so let me just see if we got the
UV x' set up correctly here looks like
we do so I don't know if it's possibly
possibly a problem where we didn't
submit the texture properly or dimension
it properly I'm not sure we should look
at that because this looks like it's 16
by 9 again which suggests to me that's
something's a little off right but I
don't know I would I'd like to look at
that a little bit later if you don't
mind I'd rather not get into it now
because it's the pre but yeah we would
like to fix that
it doesn't look like it's anything
obviously wrong so I think it's probably
there's probably something broken about
it right I think you just didn't play
the fix oh right that's a good point
we're not actually writing into it
correctly yet are we so so we wouldn't
expect to be right like this oops so
this code here right this is correct but
this is not so I'm assuming that if we
just did this maybe that would be
sufficient I don't actually know that
that's true maybe we might have other
problems in there but yeah if we just
changed it to octi dim here that that
might be all all that's wrong I don't
actually know so yeah I think that was
all that was wrong since we don't right
into those pics fit yeah so that was
that was it thanks for reminding me that
we were not writing anything into there
yet but we were using the index is wrong
so even though we were just writing read
it was it was incorrect do you have any
opinion on potential new computing
devices or platforms ie mobile
operations of tablets and devices or
anything interesting going on no I
haven't seen anything interesting if
anything it's less interesting because
there are things that devices that are
made to be more locked down usually what
do you think of Carmack working on
general AI I don't really have a thought
on it I mean Carmack's even older than I
am so at this point I feel like at the
point in the career at his at the point
he is in his career I mean you know how
much programming do any of us have left
he should just be doing whatever he
wants so I think if he's interested in
doing AI that's what he should do I mean
you should do what's interesting to him
you know
I mean already you know made a bunch of
significant impacts on the world not
just the programming industry but you
know I mean he's more than made his mark
he should just be do he should just be
doing whatever he wants
if he elects he should be doing it some
people already mentioned this but it'd
be cool to see more handmade chats talks
with guests as siddur estimate of the
data compression topic Charles yeah I I
do agree with that I probably wouldn't
do it though is the bi-linear sampling
from the octahedral map exact then or is
there some distortion due to the way we
are mapping the sphere in two dimensions
yeah I mean of course there's there's a
distortion the distortion is
specifically the projection
it's the projection from a sphere to an
octahedron so so I'm not I'm not sure to
me about that it's I wouldn't
necessarily say that the bi-linear part
specifically is a distortion because
it's hard to claim that by linear in
particular is distortion but just the
map itself is a distortion right so by
definition the octahedron itself is
under sampling certain parts of the
sphere and over sampling other parts of
it and you know I don't I don't know
that there's any particular reason why
you would blame the bilinear for being
somehow worse or whatever right
we'd ever consider doing a tutorial on
testing for something like a library
where it's important to be thorough yeah
I mean there probably be some parts on
testing in the course when I release the
course math Damon says I thought ours
might be scalar but was just a guess I
thought ours might be scalar but was
just yes I don't know what that means
I thought ours might be scalar I'm sorry
I don't know everything in this in this
shader is scalar so I'm not sure what
that means can if Allah says what other
than the games at my rocket are you
working on referring to the cleaning up
other people's mess you said earlier
maybe I misunderstood well I mean but
everything right so anything you're
doing today when you make a game is
cleaning up someone's mess almost
exclusively like the amount of time you
spend on the game is almost zero or
vanishingly close to it I mean it
doesn't matter what part you look at
it's someone else's mess you have
artists how do they make stuff well like
in our case they make it in Photoshop
Photoshop sockem pleat disaster loses
most of the information you would
actually want but there's not much we
can do about it it writes out a file
format that's garbage that doesn't have
a lot of the stuff that you actually
need it doesn't really allow you to
clean the annotate things so all of that
stuff is tiff we have to work around we
work on file systems that don't properly
track changes so I have to write tools
that do all of that work you don't have
any way in most things to cleanly like
set up you know servers or stuff like
this using shared net shared drives
networks don't work properly we have to
keep our machines disconnected from the
internet because otherwise Windows 10
ruins them all the time
our Wacom drivers I had to recently
figure out how to get Anna's machine to
stop pausing for several seconds all the
time it turns out it's because Wacom
drivers we're trying to spy on you now
and they send information back to HQ and
of course our machines aren't plugged to
the Internet so that was causing a stall
like I mean all my I spend all my time
working around the fact that nobody
makes anything that doesn't suck anymore
right and you know eventually someday
maybe I'll have made enough stuff that
like and in some cases I do you know
like I do think we've made some progress
at Mali for example like nowadays I'm
completely insulated from anything
Microsoft does like it doesn't matter
what Microsoft does Microsoft could
completely crap up everything now and it
would be okay we don't use their SDKs we
don't use any parts of their IDE we
don't even really need their compiler
although we can use it but we kept like
a isolated copy so we don't update it
right and so like you know I'm working
on getting us to a point where less and
less things are important but it's hard
right and so most of the work that you
do nowadays just does not involve
programming game it's working around all
of the disastrous crap that has been
crapped out and is getting worse by the
day whether that's Photoshop or Windows
or the compiler or you know the debugger
thank God you know George wrote a new
debugger otherwise I don't know what
we'd do
probably I'd be writing debugger right
now right it's like it's that bad and
what and the editor was the same way I
had to write my own editor basically and
you know thank God Allen made for coders
so I had something to start with right
but it's ridiculous that that's the case
I mean it's ridiculous that Emacs is
what it is now right and I had to switch
from it because it's such a pile
quicksearch says step X might be
hardware-accelerated it works on v2 and
his branchless not sure how impactful it
actually is so I think I would just take
a second to say you're probably not
thinking about shader code properly at
that point so first of all everything in
a shader is hard for accelerated right
so really what we're talking about is
what is it doing nothing works on a v2
there's no such thing as v2 s on a GPU
what a v2 actually is is just two scalar
ops right and so it's important when
you're looking at scalar is to
understand that scalars themselves are
not so a GPU goes wide by looking at
multiple pixels at a time or multiple
fragments it doesn't go wide by working
on vectors right so when you say v4 in a
shader it's not operating on a v4 it's
four separate scalar operations one for
the X 1 for the Y 1 for the Z 1 for the
you know W and what's happening is it's
doing 16 or 32 of those at a time
because it's doing 16 pixels at a time
or 32 pixels at a time right so there's
no such thing as if something that
operates on a v2 it's all just scalar
code and it goes wide by going pixel
wide right it's not operating on a v2
there's that's no such thing so what
you're trying to do is minimize the
number of actual operations that have to
happen it doesn't matter how wide they
appear to you because skate shaders are
always full width they never go under
the width of a you know a 4 by 4
fragment or a 4 by 4 fragment block or
whatever they're doing right so take
that one part the second part where you
say branchless again doesn't really
apply to shaders so the way that shaders
is there predicated there are such
things as branch testing in shaders but
they're only to test around large blocks
of code and only if none of the things
that are being processed go through that
block so if you have something where
you're either doing one thing or another
thing always so every possible thing
that goes through this code will either
get a negative one or a one based on the
value that is always branch this anyway
what it will do is it will say here's
the values for the one thing so one one
one one one one here's the value other
thing negative one negative one negative
one negative one and all it will do is
say issue the comparison which then
produce a mask value and the mask value
just says alright I've got 16 pixels so
I'm sixteen wide for each pixel I did
the comparison and just built the mask
zeroes for ones that worked ones for
ones that are sorry ones for places
where it was true zeros for worse false
right and then it just uses that mask to
and to select right between the two
possible outcome values so it's always
branchless to do the question mark
operator right all you're doing is just
saying it converts it and then does a
select on the two values one for each
pixel so what we wrote is both
branchless and full-width already does
that make sense it screws you understand
that difference because you don't want
to think about v2s as of unit of
computation in a GPU because it's not I
think it's important to remember that
did you get any traction or 30 million
line problem video in terms of people
line to collaborate with better
programming of the Harvard directly from
software people sure but never from
anyone hardware side I enjoyed your talk
on epi designed by see that it's 15
years old to have your thoughts changes
it's still the model you follow yeah I
mean I might have a little bit more to
say but honestly I in a rare instance of
foresight I would say that pretty much
everything I said in that talk is just
right I mean it it seems to just be true
I don't know if it will ever be wrong
because it's just like yep they just
seemed to be fundamental principles at
some level and you know you might change
a few things about some of them in
certain languages where you have access
to a few features right so you know in
places where closures or something are
more common you you may end up thinking
about the flow control part a little bit
differently right but for the most part
I think that just I got lucky and it
turns out that those things are more
timeless than a lot of the things that I
mean probably look back that I said are
probably just nonsense but that one
seems pretty pretty relevant we're gonna
find concrete resource on QT lighting no
idea
I don't really know even what that means
you mean just like if you wanted to
apply the lighting equations but not in
three demand that software generally
sucks what do you think you're letting
get to you too much there's something to
say about staying positive side the mask
yeah you know if I had a paycheck I'd
stay positive but at least for the time
being where you know it's very stressful
for me trying to manage lots of projects
and and looking back and realizing that
I'm spending most of my time trying to
clean stuff up that had nothing to do
with what I was trying to do it's it's
it's no it's it's not I don't really
know of a way to stay positive it's
point where soon the major changes you
have made to four code are worth
mentioning I don't I'm sorry don't know
what that means
I streamed when when Alan and I were
doing the the four coder jams and and he
put in all the changes like all the
changes I asked for that I worked with
him on and and I did some of the changes
and then submitted them back there he
did them all so the new for coder has
all the things that that I had changed
so all the stuff I do on stream now is
all in for coder now like the jumping to
functions and highlighting by type
correctly and all that stuff that's all
in there now all the hooks are there I
don't know if the default has
implementations in the custom part for
all of that but you can do it so is it
possible implement the idea of a dynamic
language without garbage collection sure
I mean what what difference does garbage
collection make to die Nant to dynamism
when is the CE course coming out I'm not
sure hopefully soon like I said a couple
months hopefully it'll be on steam
you'll be able to buy it I don't know
what the price would be like I said I
pretty sure will be less than the course
of cost of like a triple-a game so you
know something less to six something
less than sixty bucks but I don't know
how much
can you elaborate on the issue si made
with tying type strongly with operations
yeah I mean it's just you can see it as
a problem when you start working with
intrinsics right like if you want to add
two things together did you want a
saturating ad or an unsaturated ad or a
signed ad or an unsigned ad you know
saying that a thing is an signed or
unsigned type well it's not stored
differently so really what you're saying
there is when I do an ad or a subtract I
don't care which one it is because they
should be the same on signed or unsigned
but when I do like a multiply I want you
to do a sign multiply versus an unsigned
multiply or something like that or when
you do a great when I do a that's right
I'm looking for when I do a comparison
like greater than or less than right
it's got to be changed so like certain
operations have to change or shift would
be a better example so I want to do a
shift well did you want an arithmetic
shift or a logical shift right and so
it's just not appropriate because
depending on the algorithm you don't
know just because I said I wanted to
think about this thing is signed most of
the time well sometimes I don't and it
just I would rather be able to reclaim
Lee read code without to put caste
everywhere that I'd rather just be able
to say look this is a sign shift this is
an unsigned shift
that's what I'd rather say and then if I
want to say default this thing to always
using this kind of shift maybe that is a
nice time saver but I don't like the
idea that everything always got tied to
the type because it doesn't actually
work that way in practice when you're
actually trying to optimize code you
know I don't know just it's hard to
explain but how many people pre-order
the source code I don't know it's send
I'll makes it really hard to figure that
out you have to go in and like spend
seven years waiting for it to like sum
up values and stuff it's not mini it's
it's not I don't think it's any it's not
more than like 10000 I'll put it that
way so it's not that many more than I
would have thought I mean it's you know
I don't know might be like 7000 or
something it's more than I would have
ever thought before the game was out but
yes it's not like particularly many know
if Sindel can do is to be shady is there
a plan to switch platform so people will
still be able to get it if something
happens um I don't really know what to
do about it to be completely honest with
you I might try to move it to steam I I
don't know it's been very hard to find
good distribution platforms so I really
just don't know I wish there was a
better place to but I would like to move
it off of Sandow
I wouldn't call sundial shady I would
just say send Al's kind of more or less
defunct I mean they just they are pretty
antiquated now in terms of the features
they support it's just it's just not a
good e-commerce platform so I don't
actually know what to do about that
longer term I would like to use epic
store Steam or something like that
because that handles distribution much
more cleanly it has a much better
downloads it keeps it up to date for you
you know send L doesn't do that
send al can't keep it up-to-date it also
can't handle huge stuff you know I don't
know so you know someday I might just
knock on the door of the valve guys to
be like hey man is it ok if I do this
because it's not really a game right now
and I don't really want to call it early
access because it's not right I only
allow the pre-orders because people want
to be able to follow along with the
source code and it's not early access
it's not a game that I expected to be
playing right now right so I don't know
but I could ask them to what extent you
know they could tell me something that
it would work there
I don't know but yeah I'd like to move
to something better I just don't know
how and if we did that it would be
pretty easy because I could just issue
everyone on send out a steam key to go
unlock it on Steam or something right
and I think that would just work for
everyone who is able to go use steam I
don't know what I do about people who
couldn't because it's possible that
certain people can't get access to steam
who could have gotten access to a cendol
download but
what are the challenges is finding good
distribution platforms I mean it's
pretty obvious right I mean you want an
online store to function relatively like
steam I want to be able to have an
account somewhere I want to be able to
buy something I want to be able to have
it installed on my machine and kept up
to date automatically I want that thing
to handle taxes properly and payment
methods properly right compliance and
filing and remittance or that you know
and then that doesn't exist steam is
really all you got
the epic store may be to a certain
extent but a fourth episode doesn't even
run on Linux and Mac as my understanding
I don't think so I don't care about Mac
anymore max over like I've officially I
based on what Apple's done lately I've
said like apples over like I will never
support Mac ever again
but Linux is an open platform I think it
should be supported especially at
something like handmade here where we're
teaching how to program I want to
support Linux so I want something it
runs on Windows and Linux you can buy
something on there it distributes it out
keeps it saying keep track of that you
owned it all that stuff and there and if
that's it as far as I know it's team
farms there's literally no nothing else
so you can either put something a theme
or you can and that's it and even steam
isn't perfect because steam itself also
doesn't really support an easy way to
get into the ecosystem so somebody who
doesn't already run steam it's very hard
to sell someone something and then just
have it download steam right they first
have to like create a steam account and
go through this process you really want
it the reverse way round you want it so
they can just go to my website hit by a
handmade hero and then it says alright
here's you download steam here's the
download and what would you like your
username to be that's what you want it
to do but it doesn't have that right and
so that would be really nice as well
because especially we're talk about
selling other things like you know we
saw
comic book at Molly rocket well no one
buys comic books with that in that way
right like they don't first open up
steam to buy their comic book or even
have one of those right so you you need
the same you have the same problem you
know yeah HIO it has its own issues as I
mentioned at the start of the stream
where I couldn't even buy for coder
today because it said my credit card was
declined and then I called my credit
card and they said it never even
attempted to charge so each i/o is kind
of a bug riddled mess I guess I would
also say I don't know to what extent
HIO actually handles tax compliance
properly but I suspect not really the
same is true of Gumroad so Gumroad
doesn't handle tax compliance properly
they can trim it like so there's a
concept called merchant of record and
basically if the place doesn't order a
merchant of record ability then you just
don't want to use them so Gumroad
doesn't itch thought IO doesn't send out
doesn't you basically just don't want to
use this because it means that you will
have to handle the tax compliance
yourself now some places claim to sort
of do something for you like Gumroad in
inter Toyota oh I believe both claim to
handle that Moss and they do but the
problem is VAT Moss is only one of many
taxes that you have to comply with and
they don't comply with any of the other
ones Gumroad
in particular doesn't handle sales tax
in for state sales tax properly they
claim to sort of handle it but actually
it's incorrect so they violate I checked
and their way of handling it violates
Washington state law they don't even
know that but it does and because
there's certain RCW requirements about
how tax has to be listed on invoice so
this stuff isn't a joke tax compliance
is incredibly complicated there's very
few people who do it properly if you
don't want to be basically breaking the
law it's very hard
right now I'm doing most of it myself
with sundial and it's just not worth it
I'm happy to give valve 30% to do that
for me what I love to pay epic only 15%
or whatever it is that they take to do
it for me yes but currently you can't
you can't just put stuff on the epic
store that doesn't work yet
so you know Amazon would be great if
Amazon had the ability to do digital
distributions well great they don't so
it's not really an option but if Amazon
had shipped a quality client like Steam
which it's crazy to call steam a quality
client because steams not that good but
hey it's way better than the stuff
that's out there otherwise you know so
I'm hoping at some point these things
get into some kind of a war I would love
to see steam versus epic really get
heated because I think the quality would
go up dramatically and then I just use
one or the other or both for everything
and that would be fantastic
we're just that's not the world we're
living in I don't think GOG lets you put
anything up there but games does it
you might be able to get permission the
people at Epic or running the adjuster
are good people yet no I totally believe
they are good people I emailed Tim
Sweeney actually about this while back I
basically said like hey you guys should
do direct ecommerce here's the reasons
why he never applied so probably just
went in the trash I mean he probably has
so many emails he's not gonna bother
looking at one for me no steam doesn't
have any requirements to put DRM into
any program at all most games on Steam
now just don't even have DRM I think
it's mostly like big Triple A games it
would but if you buy an indie game on
Steam I think most important that box so
like for handmade hero we just wouldn't
check that box right so you know we just
install the source code along with the
game and if you just hit the open local
files door it would just open up with
all the files right there just like it
is right now and download the zip so
steam totally works for handmade hero
purposes and I just wouldn't check the
DRM box and there'd be no issues right
it used to be this team was DRM that I
really didn't like that they got rid of
that so I have no problem with it now
like Steam just works and anyone can be
on it now 100 bucks right so I think
seems great I wish they didn't take 30%
I think it's maybe a little bit high at
the same time like YouTube takes 50% and
twitch takes 50% so they're not the
worst right so I don't know
yeah I like I give Tim Sweeney like
major major props for doing the epic
store because as far as I'm concerned
like he really just it's just a giant
headache for him I mean they do not need
the money even a little bit right like
fortnight made infinite money Tim
Sweeney does not have to care about a
single dollar ever again right but he
did the epic store anyway and I honestly
truly believe that he didn't do the epic
store because he wanted money I think he
did the epic store because he really
didn't like the fact that people didn't
have any other options but steam I mean
I really do think that's why I did it I
don't think he did it because he needed
the money or not needed the money I
wanted the money because for tonight you
know made so much money that there's
just I mean in he and he was wealthy
even before that so I really just think
honestly he did it just to do something
good which is crazy I think that's what
they did and so I think that was awesome
I mean that's like if it ends up being
the case that the epic store becomes
fairly reputable and people use it and
it becomes you know more refined and
works well and all that stuff I think it
would create a really strong incentive
for both epic and valve to improve the
quality of digital distribution models
and that is awesome because valve
totally was not
I mean steam is basically exactly what
it was when it started it just has not
had the kind of attention paid to it
that it should have had and I think
pretty much the reason for that it just
doesn't have the competition right I
mean there's an plenty of incentive
there for valve to maintain it there
isn't really any incentive there for
them to push it forwards and explore all
the possibilities and like make great
improvements because everyone has to
sell their game on Steam so it just
doesn't matter right
is there anything I've seemed to improve
totally yeah there's so many things you
can improve on steam the steam Kline
itself is very hard for non you know
expert users it's it's just really
obtuse I mean I get lost in there
sometimes trying to figure out what the
heck I'm doing and look where my stuff
went the usability needs a massive
overhaul like a massive massive overhaul
the purchase flow is terrible if you
don't already have steam getting you
onto the platform doesn't work they
really need a smooth end-user purchase
flow so they need to have it so that if
I put up my website and I'm selling
handmade hero and somebody who doesn't
have steam comes and buys it it should
be like they click the button it just
pops up a little thing they put in their
credit confirmation just like it is now
then it says great here's your download
and you download steam right there and
it knows what you purchased and it comes
up and has you creates the account right
it should be super smooth that's not
what happens right now you have to
create a steam account first you have to
use their website for the purchase it's
just there's so many things that they
could do to make it a much stronger
ecommerce platform and they're not doing
those things and again because they
don't have to write
all right last question what are your
thoughts on undefined behavior I think
if you have a spec that has undefined
behavior in it then you don't have a
spec full stop so like the fact that C++
and C call those things specs but they
have undefined behavior in them I
wouldn't call them specs I'd call them
ideas about how a language might work I
mean not to put too fine a point on it a
spec should have literally no undefined
behavior and I know that people think
that maybe that's sort of an absurd
thing to say because oh wait well what
about you know when you want to be able
to support something like floating-point
operations but you don't know what kind
of floating-point operation thing
there's gonna be your if you don't know
like what the kind of hardware is that
implements this thing and so
optimization bubble-butt know that is
not what that means undefined behavior
is a cop-out where you haven't specified
what the programmer can expect when you
easily could have for example instead of
saying that a unsigned 64-bit integer
overflow in C is undefined behavior say
when you put that in a piece of code the
compiler will generate the code that
would work if it simply did the basic ad
that the Machine normally does right now
it's not overly specific behavior but
it's not undefined you have defined what
the programmer can expect but whenever
you say a behavior is undefined you've
made what is effectively an unworkable
spec it's not a spec right and so as far
as I'm concerned if you produce the spec
with undefined behavior as a specified
category you're not done yet I don't
consider it a specification I consider
it an aspirational fantasy period
because there's never an excuse friend
just finding if you can always specify
what the programmer can expect even if
you can't tell them what that is ahead
of time you can tell them how to know
when they actually go to use it because
you can just say it will do whatever the
underlying machine does or something
right you can always say that you don't
have say unbind because undef' I
behavior gives the compiler vendor the
opportunity to screw you and guess what
they always do always is there an
advantage to having undefined behavior
no there's no advantage whatsoever the
advantage that is claimed is more
flexibility for the compiler vendor
that's never good flexibility in a
compiler vendor is horrible because it
means that from version to version or
from compiler to compiler the programmer
doesn't know what's gonna happen that's
never good
all right I'm gonna head and wrap it up
a lot of windows open today huh thank
you everyone for joining me for another
episode of hand made here outs and a
pleasure coding with you as always if
you would like to follow along this
series at home you can always go to
handmade hero org and preorder the game
it comes with the source code so if you
want to follow along at home you can do
so I will be back here tomorrow for a
little bit of fun with the ocular number
we'll finally get to sort of play around
it I think that'll be interesting and
I'm pretty happy the direction it's
going I think we're getting to the light
at the end of the tunnel here I'm pretty
happy about it so hopefully we'll have
some good lighting soon and maybe we'll
see the first it's the first little
glimmer of that tomorrow that's it for
today hope see you back here tomorrow
till then have fun for everyone and I
will see you on the Internet take it
easy everybody