hello everyone and welcome to handmade
Hero show recode a complete game live on
stream I am going to be looking today at
the sort of structural code that we need
to add for the new ray caster that we're
hoping will have much better performance
characteristics than the old one it's
been kind of a battle like this is
pretty tough to do CPU side only CPUs
are just really still quite slow in
terms of parallel flop stuff they're not
horrible but they're not nearly where
like a 20 80 is you know so we'll see
but I think we can do a reasonable job
we're already running real time with the
old one and the idea here is just to get
us up to more like a 60 frames a second
frame rate instead of a 30 frames a
second frame and so we're looking for a
2x speed-up here if we can get one we
don't know if we can but we have a lot
of fat left to trim I think because we
have the red cursor I also would speed
up the diffuse the specular to diffuse
conversion which is a pretty expensive
process right now and we didn't think
through it much we optimized it like we
put in a simple optimization which is
just to use for wide through it so we
did do that but we didn't actually take
the extra step of thinking about
optimizing it algorithmically so I think
there's probably more we can do there
that we're not doing now in terms of
keeping that routine running as fast as
possible especially because we know that
given the way the dot product fall-off
works that specular only affects diffuse
in a specific way and so there should be
ways that we can be more intelligent
about our waiting and not have to do as
many flops because we're probably doing
roughly 2x as many flops in that routine
as we actually need because a lot of
them are zero and so if we could do it
in a more sparse like if we could make
it a sparse computation instead we
probably could save a lot of actual
multiplies now that may not be directly
possible but again we'll see when we get
there and we know that that takes about
a quarter of the time so if we can get
this down to X or so and the
one down 2x or so I think we'll be in
really good shape and I think those are
both potentially possible so we're gonna
go for it and if we do then we'll be way
under six we'll be way faster than 64
and second will be safely under it I
think and we will continue to be even
more safely under it because all of this
is perfectly paralyzed Abul there's no
thread communication whatsoever and it
scales to as many threads as you want so
on future processors with 32 cores 64
cores as AMD basically as Lisa sue
continues to save us from the collapsing
Intel behemoth we will presumably be
able to scale very very well and get a
lot of ray tracing essentially for free
we will do no work our game will just
run faster all right so let's go ahead
and take a look here yesterday I think I
made some really great improvements
personally compared but that's really
more of a statement of how bad it was
before to the down stepping code here
where we actually have to do the work of
switching to scalar this is now much
cleaner this is a much better way of
computing those normals than we were
doing before I'm really happy with how
that turned out I know this can be
better but it's now I think within
striking distance so you know I think in
probably optimizations for this code
will not yield any practical benefit at
this point because it's down to so few
operations and this isn't this part does
only occurs after everything's done any
way that we don't really care so I think
we've gotten out of the weeds on this
there's still an open question as to how
we want to handle the actual sampling
and we'll probably take a little bit of
a look at that at some point as well but
for the most part I'm pretty happy with
how this goes and mostly it's just
waiting to be debugged now I think it's
structured relatively well and I think
I'm also excited to see how our min come
our this this is some this is some
pretty fun john was talking about the
hackers delight and I was thinking about
this when he was talking about that as I
thought this was pretty good
where we do our H comp we do one shuffle
for one instruction and one min posi PU
sixteen so it's two instructions to
figure out which Lane the the raycast
float that we wanted is in two
instructions for that seemed pretty good
to me
like I don't know I I don't know that we
could have done a better job than two
instructions for that maybe we could
have I don't know but I thought that was
pretty darn good so we'll see if it
really works but I thought it was pretty
pretty good stuff all right
anyway let's take a look now at the the
grid raycast
code and just talk about what we need to
generate so there's two pieces to the
puzzle one is this part here which is
called walk table and walk table is the
thing that says for any individual
location in the grid how do we know what
we should recast to along a particular
array and this code is a little bit of a
lie right now so this probably is not
gonna work yes we can pull directly out
of a walk table no we can't then
immediately access the spatial grid
nodes from there that's not a plausible
thing that can happen what we actually
need to do here is we need to do some
kind of arrange check and we just need
to step through the we need to step
through the space until we like by using
deltas basically right so in other words
we're on a particular grid spatial grid
location we need to each time we need to
like go okay where do we actually want
to step to and we need to look that up
so one way to think about that would be
we have like an initial so we have an
initial grid index something like this
so it's it's like you know whatever this
is we don't know how to find it right
but we're gonna try and find that and
that's something that would presumably
be passed in here so we would start with
an initial grid index
that we're probably going to get passed
from the parent in here we will go
through the walk table as a delta so we
would say okay we need to take our grid
index and we need to add whatever is in
the walk table to it so it'd be
something more like a post like a post
increment where we just go to the next
thing now the thing about that is that
would be great except we don't really
know what to do at this point about the
when we get to the end right there's a
couple of different ways we can try to
make this work the problem we're gonna
have is if you imagine we've got this
voxel and we just want you know we've
we've arranged it
memory is obviously one dimensional so
we've collapsed the three dimensions
down to one dimension by doing rows you
know then we stack the rows then we
stack the rows of rows right to get a
three dimensional thing mm-hmm and what
we'll find is evidence use me what we'll
find is that going off of the top or the
bottom of this structure will naturally
work with just one range check because
if we go below zero that will wrap to a
very high number or if we go off the end
that will be a higher number than the
total number of things in the table in
the in the spatial grid and so one range
check which is are we less than that max
number that will give us the termination
condition we need right however what we
don't know is when we wrap around a some
other boundary so the stacks will rat
will would be checked by just that one
condition but if we go off either end so
we go off like the left or right side or
the front or back side of this voxel
that will still wrap around to a valid
value right it'll just come back on the
other side
it's much like you know when we're doing
bitmap work if we write off the right
side of the bitmap we come back down one
row below it on the left side of the
bitmap or one row above it depending on
that whether it's top to bottom or
bottom to top right and so the problem
that we face here is we actually need to
bounce check this thing in a lot of in
in several dimensions right we we need
to have a way to bounce check it into
multiple dimensions and so what will
happen for us here is when we actually
look at this we would need many range
checks here we would need to check off
the left side off the right side off the
front side off the back side and then
just the the total bound and doing all
of those ifs inside our main loop here
yeah it's not on the interior of the
loop but it's almost right it's the the
next worst thing that's just really bad
and so I think the way that we want to
solve this problem is instead of doing
any checking here which would be inside
the loop I think we want to just do the
checking once outside the loop and then
we just adjust this walk count value to
say what it's actually going to be so I
think what we really want is when we go
down and look at the Ray casting here so
when we would ordinarily do the grid ray
cast what we want to do is have
something where like the walk count here
get set specifically by looking how far
can this go before it hits one of the
boundaries and then it sets the walk out
that way we do the if checks once per
ray cast rather than once per node right
so that's a potential savings of you
know six seven eight times the number of
ifs that were reducing out of the out of
each ray cast and that to me seems like
way better right so I think that's the
clear choice there so that
just this should just propagate through
and we would send that walk countdown
which means that this part here when we
pass the sample Direction is not really
gonna quite work the way that I would
have expected I mean we still could do
that here but you know I mean I guess we
could we'll just modify them when we
pass them down right so that walk offset
in this case when we set the grid index
here and and in fact I suppose if we
look at what we would be doing we could
almost just do a test on the termination
condition as well so we may want to
restructure this a little bit to in fact
what we may want to do is this so we
basically just have a walk off set and
an end at walk off set that way we can
just do something like okay there is a
walk index there's a grid index and it's
just going to loop directly using this
light sample direction and again this is
just about removing things from the loop
to D complicate it right and so this way
we can presumably just do a test now
I'll be honest it's a little bit
difficult for me to reason through and I
apologize I should know this and I'm not
sure that I do so if you take a look at
the way that this is working so at the
end of loops there's a thing that
happens typically it's called macro op
fusion so there's there's different
kinds of fusion that happen in a
pipeline one is called micro op fusion
the other is called macro op fusion that
involves smishing things together that
would normally happen separately and
when you're constructing loops if you
actually care about performance which
we're gonna start too soon in other
words we've got RV tune set up we're
trying to make this routine fast so you
know normally you're writing a loop you
don't have to think about this
particularly much because you're not
thinking about trying to you know
extract a ton of performance for it from
it but in this case we are you want to
make sure that the the end of your loop
is the place where the test is gonna
happen and you want to make sure that
that test fuses with the loop jump and
what I mean by that is if you take a
look at the assembly language code and
and I can I can show you the god bolt
here because it's kind of a it's you
know it's a bits a mellow day here at
and handmade hero so if we were to go to
God bolt and take a look at what a loop
looks like when you actually compile it
right so let's suppose I don't know I
don't really need this to be called
square but you know let's just say we've
got a count in here and I don't know
yeah like a float that comes back
something like that and maybe we've got
a float here as well that's like stuff
so if in here I do a while count - - and
then in here I do a like star stuff plus
plus and I do result plus equals so this
is a basic like I'm just doing like
basic summation you know where I'm
trying to sum this array that I've been
passed in and returned the value I don't
know why no it's fine I thought that red
meant like air or something
but so if we actually tell like I'm
gonna switch to clangs I don't know GCC
very well we could also use em SVC maybe
we will since that's what we're using on
the stream right now so if we take a
look at
if we take a look at the assembly
language code that gets output for this
routine then what you can see here is
this is our loop right and the
instructions here are this piece of code
is summing the float right so this is
adding a single like a floating point
value and it's a memory op so it just
goes look xmm zero is is holding the sum
so xmm zero is result right we're gonna
add whatever we point to with RDX which
is this stuff pointer here we're gonna
move RDX forward by four which is the
size of one float right we're gonna sub
ECX which is our loop counter so ECX is
count here and then we're gonna jump if
not equal to and so this sub instruction
here is basically saying look we don't
we've never talked about this and
hammering here I don't think but when
you have a sub instruction this is just
x86 assembly
it's just how x86 assembly works sub
instructions they when they hit zero
they actually will so if you do a sub
and the result isn't zero or you do a
sub and the result is zero
it sets a flag differently in the
processors condition table that I don't
know what you want to call that
condition register whatever you want to
I don't know what the right term is for
that I apologize I didn't program very
much x86 assembly this is old
bread-and-butter stuff and I just don't
I just my brain on the terms but
basically depending on whether it's zero
or not it'll set a flag and when you do
a jump immediately after the sub that
you know that that flag is still set to
whatever the sub set it to because
there's no intervening instruction which
means that now you can do a jump not
equal to to basically say look if this
thing set the flag that said that this
thing is equal to zero or if it's set a
flag and it's not equal to zero right
then we know that we can do a jump right
after saying jump equal to zero jump not
equal to zero
right and we'll jump based on the result
of the sub what that means is that the
operation to update the loop counter and
the operation to test the loop counter
can be done in a single instruction this
sub instruction and the jump if not
equal to can be one instruction so
instead of three instructions sub test
jump it's only two instructions that's
great
efficient assembly language is good but
actually what happens once it gets into
the front end of the chip is that it
actually doesn't even do that as two
instructions
I believe it does it as one because of
what's called macro op fusion a sub jump
is actually an instruction for all
intents and purposes through the chip
and if we can get some kind of a micro
architectural analysis here I don't
really know how to use gob bolt so I
don't know how to add oh here it is so
if I switch this to clang temporarily
which should look basically the same
like the code that's generated shouldn't
be like wildly different there we go so
if we look at the code that's generated
by clang here and we what is happening
okay so when I said it wouldn't be while
I just and I was wrong they decided to
unroll the loop whatever so they
unrolled the loop and they did a totally
different way of doing this routine
which is not what I would have wanted
them to do and holy cow did they spam
out way too much code which is not
really what I would have wanted them to
do in this particular case but oh well
so
it doesn't really matter cuz the comp
jump and the sub jump will do the same
thing that I was talking about I just I
want this to uh how can I convince this
to do the thing I wanted to show it to
to show I mean I can still show it but I
just talked about the sub and I wanted
to show the sub but I can't really make
it do that um so like one way to do that
would be like to give it an offset it
didn't know it could trust so for
existed be clear I'm sorry I knew what
it was doing here and and maybe you
didn't so what they're doing here is
they said look we know that we're going
to have a pointer that will tell us
where to load out of the array that's
what stuff is and what happens is they
said well look if we're gonna use that
pointer anyway and we're gonna be adding
the pointer eight to the pointer each
time we might as well just pre compute
where that will end and test that right
so presumably if I look up here
somewhere they will just do an ad with
the total number that's in count right
and that's how they'll figure out where
this thing is going to end at least I
assume that's what they'll do let's take
a look so they're comparing EAX with ECX
so EAX here is computed where that's a
comm here it is so they load the count
into EAX here right which is gonna be
like this integer and then I'll be
honest I'm not familiar with al what is
that what is I don't even know if I've
ever seen that before I'm not sure what
that refers dude that's that's a new one
for me like I said x86 assembly not my
strong suit
so anyway coming through here where we
actually process the
X is we align it to okay so we align EAX
first by saying we're gonna knock out
the bottom three bits of it right so
it's now aligned to eighths yeah
and then we clear we then add the first
one
so whatever the first thing is in the
loop I guess oh and we jump here in case
man there's so much preamble
why did they do all this what were they
thinking this is by the way again
not an expert on this topic but this is
all worst code than the than the visual
studio compiler people asked like why
don't you always use this is not good
code at all this code sucks in my
opinion the visual studio code was
exactly what you want and this is not
this just generates a ton of
instructions and it doesn't do anything
like this doesn't help you at all as far
as like it like this literally would run
slower or the same speed and it why did
it do all this I have no idea but anyway
so yeah I don't know
here we're compiex so here's where we
actually produce where did they actually
this must be a good trick where they
actually produced what EAX should be and
they're come they're doing the low part
of it the only the 32-bit part of it
probably because it's an int so how did
they actually oh there it is I missed it
it's right there they
take adi which they produced up here and
they move it into EAX there so basically
they just they just computed where they
would stop a stopping value for this and
then they use that so they don't have to
do this up this code sucks like this is
just bad period I don't think there's
much argument about that like I don't
know why they did that but that's just
not good and I don't understand what the
heck happened there to be completely
honest with you like if you take a look
at this code here this is exactly right
I mean this is basically one and what
let's see how my cycles this is so I
mean this is basically two cycles per at
maybe one and a half cycles per and like
did they actually get better than that
after all of this no I mean they
definitely didn't this is dependent
right so i don't really think i mean i
guess they amortized so I guess they
amortize that dependency so maybe that
is faster this unrolling this loop was
not a bad idea that part I agree with
it's just I don't think this this didn't
get faster so you could have still done
the sub the same way and not done any of
this right or most of it because all you
really had to do was just do the one
quick test to see how many of these you
were gonna do right so yeah I just I
don't understand that weird
transformation I'll stop complaining
about it now anyway
let me see if I can add a tool though
here and and it's possible that maybe if
I switch this down
something lighter okay there we go well
though they still do the same trick I
don't know so I'm sorry I can't really
figure out any way to get this to still
use a sub here but it's fine
anyway you the point is I wanted to talk
about the the fusion that happens at the
end of the loop here so basically if I
add in here the micro architectural
analysis and let me remove this you can
see it I'm gonna put that light over
here cuz we don't need the source code
while we're doing this so if you take a
look at the micro architecture analysis
here then what you should see in here
assuming that you can't actually fuse
these let me see where we've got here
did they actually say fusion anywhere
No do they do they say it they don't
they don't say it I got nothing so this
is kind of a failure and I apologize I
just if we looked at this in Ayaka I
could show you the part where it says
the what got fused and what didn't
unfortunately that's I don't think in
here anywhere so yeah all right this was
a waste of everyone's time and I
apologize let me just say what normally
happens so when you do a comp jump or
anything else that sets a flag so a sub
jump would also do it and this is why I
say I don't understand why they did this
because the sub is free but I don't know
maybe they were trying to save register
because they just do that by habit or
something when you look at this comp
jump what will happen is the comp jump
will actually get fused together into
one comp jump instruction and so when
you normally look at things like how
many instructions you can issue per
cycle this won't count as two it'll only
count as one right and so that's pretty
nice because it means that you can issue
it more instructions per clock assuming
that it's available for issuance and it
also means that when it actually travels
through the pipeline because of the
nature of how jumps work you actually
don't pay extra my crops for them either
so it doesn't get blown back out on any
any point in the pipeline into more ops
they stay fused together forever it's my
understanding and handled by the front
end so basically you're essentially when
you do a sub and then a jump or a comp
and then a jump and I believe comp is
true sub is the one that I'm more
familiar with in x86 but when you do a
jump that jump like a subject
you're basically getting the jump for
free it's not really there it's just a
freeloader on the sub that the front end
will just do right and so it's kind of
important to remember that when you're
constructing loops you don't ever if
you're actually trying to get
performance out of them you don't ever
want to create a structure for your loop
that makes it impossible for the
compiler to generate a good post amble
like that that's all and so like if we
were to take a look at how like this
loop was set up you know
and all I wanted to say was when we loop
through here if we're going from from
and - I want to make sure that it
doesn't get confused and I don't think
that it would right but if we do like
first you know last or something and
then in here we do like for INT index
equals first you know last index oops
index not equal to last plus plus index
or something right then I just want to
make sure that you know the compilers
don't have trouble with that and you can
see right that it doesn't like it's
still just going to do a comp here on
that now that's a little bit cheaty cuz
it's a plus plus index so again I want
to start to complexify this just to
prove the point at all to myself which
is like let's say there's an offset
table and so in here it's actually like
plus equals you know offset so as we
come through we've got more work to do
so then you can see in here now this is
what clang does because it can't it
can't mess with the AUSA's because it
doesn't know what's actually happening
so in here you can see it does the adds
and then it does a comp and jump exactly
the same way which is good that leaves
it there it can't unroll the loop if
that's okay we can't unroll our loops
they they we don't know who were
processing next so it's not really
unreliable in that way
there wouldn't be much you know benefit
to it and we have a lot of math ops so
stacking up math ops isn't gonna help to
give you shadow room here so you know
that's all I wanted to verify and if we
take a look at the M SVC output for it
as well I'm assuming it'll be roughly
the same let's take a look so there it
is so you can see here also yeah comp
jump same same thing these are all
pretty straightforward
I guess I'm not sure how optimal that is
because I don't know how many ads stack
up here but I'm guessing this is more or
less free
so I'm guessing like this is basically
one cycle of total op time is that right
this part here so it's it's two cycles
total I want to say because we gotta
wait let me see
Hey look it was already on ad so when
you're in here I'm just curious sorry
I'm rattling so when we do an ad on ECX
to memory so that's going to be the
here uh if we take a look I don't know
why I needed to click on that I just
need to look here so if we take a look
at the total cost you can see that it's
one micro up on that seems high Wow
one micro up on any of these four ports
1 micro up up on one of these two one
Micro up on any of these ports and 1
micro up on port 4 but like is that
really how bad an integer ad is like
holy cow
that's pretty pretty brutal right is
that really how bad it is because if you
take a look at like what an ad looks
like in Oh
duh that's the wrong order sorry it's
this one that's if you're adding to
memory this is if you're adding from
memory I'm sorry about that
this is that's exactly what I expected
to see so happy so this means that
basically we're gated on the memory but
we can issue two of them so if you take
a look at how this is gonna go right we
got four ports that can issue an ad
we've got two ports that can get the
memory for our ad and so if we take a
look at what happens and here we can say
all right these two oh well and there's
only one of these because this is
actually the other kind of ad but still
so this and this can obviously happen
together so that will just occur this
and this could also happen together
because those are immediate so they
don't need it so that would be fine so
this will all issue in the same
instruction and then this will have to
wait for that to finish so this and this
yeah so I'm gonna say something now that
is above my paygrade and like fabien and
Jeff
thank God don't watch the show but I'm
gonna go ahead and say that this looks
dumb that just looks dumb to me right
because if you oh wait no no no okay no
nevermind I saved myself from
embarrassment
I forgot we changed this to having to
load the offset number so this is fine
because I was going to say if they just
done this as a sub then they could have
issued this independently but we're not
doing it that way anymore we actually
need to load this part in so it doesn't
count
so we do have to wait so we're fine so
this will all issue in one instruction
and then this will issue as soon as it
can but even though it like I was trying
to think of like how it could slip right
in here
these can't fuse so this is for these
are four instructions on the one cycle
they'll issue and complete and then we
have to wait anyway to the next cycle
because we can't issue any more
instructions but this will happen on the
next cycle and go right while that's
happening it will start to issue some of
these presumably it would probably try
to issue these three while it's doing
this like on the same cycle it issues
this right so it'll get some this will
be like a one and a half cycle loop
throughput kind of routine probably
that'd be my guess so I don't know
exactly I forget how you get clang to do
its little dance that's kind of crappier
than Ayaka but at least it still exists
Ayaka kind of got sidelined but if you
look at the if you look at the LLVM MCA
code here it tries to give you an
estimate we need to put in those little
those little doodads LLVM MC a marker
defines
where do they go where do they go where
do they go is that how we do it yeah so
you got to do this nonsense here but
this is just how so in order to tell
this thing like where to actually wear
the loop is I think you got to do this I
don't know if you put it I don't know
where you actually put it for loop
analysis
do they have an example cuz like for
Ayaka for example you you do like
basically that and that's just so you'll
get the loop post the jump right cuz the
jump the loop jump will happen here yeah
so anyway if we take a look here we can
say you know what are we actually doing
right reciprocal block throughput and
you can see yeah like we're at one point
two cycles per block and again the
reason for that is because if you look
at what actually has to happen
this part here it blocks because these
two things are serially dependent you
have to wait for this one these have to
finish before this one can go so you can
then grab some from the next loop but
not entirely right if you didn't have to
wait if if this here did not appear here
then this whole thing could issue one
cycle per loop and again that's because
you get four cycles per instruction on a
skylight core but these five these two
fuse so you end up only issuing four and
so you would be able to do one whole
loop per cycle but you can't because
this EDI is a dependency so you actually
can't do a perfect issue you have to
grab some from the next loop and it's
this constant like slight stutter so
that's why the reciprocal blah
throughput here is 1.2 right not one I
don't know if anything I just said made
sense but that's what happens you can
also see the port spam and hopefully
this makes some sense because I showed
you that thing about hey you can issue
ads on lots of ports so you can see here
the load ports or spammy because people
are loading all over the place right and
oh sorry those aren't the load ports my
bad they are 4 &amp; 5 you can see the load
ports happening on the to memory ones
here in here and their spammy because
again both of these instructions issue
could issue on either port and we're a
stuttery loop because we take we first
the first time through we issue these 3
and then these 2 and then we grab this
one and we like we we start to do this
like weird like you know beat pattern so
it's spammy rather than just one one and
then the ads can issue all over the
place they can be 0 1 5 and there's one
more I think good issue ads usually can
issue at least 0 1 &amp; 5 but the integer
adder was I thought it had another one
and six so 0 1 5 &amp; 6 so you can see
those getting spammed here so that's all
this crap right so those 4 ports are
getting spammed with the actual ad right
this ad gets locked because probably ad
SS is only on 0 &amp; 1 maybe I don't know
if that's actually true let's take a
look
yeah it's only on zero and one right so
that's why you don't see that spamming
out to the other ones because it can't
go there so you know this one's gonna
hit these two in a beat frequency based
on the offsetting of the routine and
then you know that your scaler ads are
gonna spam out further because they're
they have two more reports they there's
four integer routers only two floating
point adder z' so hopefully that makes
some sense I'm sorry that this parts
behind my head but you only need to see
that I mean that there's nothing over
here that you care about so again that's
what happens why I can't find the micro
op fusion or Makarov fusion stuff listed
here I don't know maybe it doesn't do
that yeah I don't understand like why we
can't get that information kind of
bummed about that
um I mean maybe maybe Kampf doesn't fuse
maybe only sub fuses right and that's
why it's not showing it I don't know
so normally you would want a tool like
this to tell you about fusion it doesn't
seem to do that and maybe that's because
comp doesn't fuse or something I'm not
an x86 assembly jockey so you know my
I'm the wrong one did say like hey it
should or shouldn't fuse but yeah it's
just a bummer sub jump does fuse let's
put it that way and add jump does fuse
with immediate but it could be that
register register comps don't fuse yeah
sorry anyway that was disappointing and
depressing but you get the idea anyway
back to our loop so what I want to do
here is just have the walk off set and
the end at walk off set be a test like
that I'd like to be able to check the
end of the loop for fusion and make sure
we're doing that in a way that's
amenable to it because there's other
ways we can write this obviously and
then at that point well I guess this is
actually grid index now I think and
we look up the new one each time wait
that's not no no no sorry it's still
walk index so we start with the grid
index somewhere I'm going to call this
initial grid index and then I'm going to
have end at grid index and that way we
can just say that we're going to start
the grid index here
I guess this would require us to
increment the walk table pointer though
but I suppose that's fine so the grid
index just always would start at
whatever it tells us to start at we
would want to check the grin act index
isn't you know wherever this is and then
we would want to do a grid index plus
equals walk table plus plus right I
think I think we want something roughly
like that so we just read out of the
table for whatever our update is and
then this just tells us when we actually
stop hmm and again I don't know if maybe
what we should do there is just awhile
sub so you can see why I'm a little bit
weirded out by that I'm not sure it
really makes sense so maybe we just want
a changed my mind didn't like the way it
looked so I think what we'll do here is
actually send an account so we'll just
do like walk out - - as we're doing
before the grid index will get
initialized to some initial direction
and then we just go as as we go as far
as this thing tells us - so that way we
know this is a sub jump at the end of it
and I also think we can change this to a
do-while so there's no preamble so this
way it'll only have the end of the loop
and it won't have the beginning which is
good and the grid index here we'll just
get initialized to some thing I think
that's what we want I think that also
means that this is not what we want and
so I'm going to change this back to just
beer a direction walk table
and walk out so we loop on the walk
count hmm we pass in like some of this
information about like where we're
starting and so on and off we go and we
can pack that information together if
there's weirdness in the calling or
anything like that but that all seems a
little premature so I think that's a
good enough set up I'm pretty happy with
with how that looks and this hmm
unfortunately needs a preamble so the
problem that we're gonna have here is
that nodes can very well be empty and so
if a node is empty then we want to skip
it so so I think the hardest part about
all of this that we're going to end up
hitting is just how we tell how far this
thing has to go right yeah
so just thinking it through the walk
count is gonna be by far our biggest
problem everything else now can be
completely pre-computed so everything in
the walk table can be pre computed and
it'll just be stored in the H file so we
literally won't have to do anything for
that we'll just load it and that's it so
the problem is I see it is that the walk
count at the moment is unfortunately I'm
not sure how we're gonna generate that
because what's going to happen is when
you're inside when you're going okay I'm
at this grid location I want to cash
this Ray and I know there's this many
entries in the walk table you and then
need to figure out where you would stop
walking in order to not rap to not
exceed the bounds of the table and I
just don't know how we do that
I mean one way is to use a another
lookup table but boy does that seem kind
of expensive but like you know you you
want some way of you want some way of
figuring out
yeah let's do it on the blackboard I
don't even know this is gonna be the
heart this is gonna be by far the
hardest part of this routine I think
well it's not this routine it's the
hardest part that happens somewhere else
that makes two in order to enable this
routine and I don't know so here's the
problem
so here's what we're talking about if we
said okay here is you know voxel grid
right well you know what we can do this
on 2d and make it simpler so here's you
know some voxel grid thing and I'm gonna
cast rays from here so let's suppose
that we were building walk tables so
when we built the table what we did is
we said well we imagine right that we
are at the far corner of this thing and
the raid erection is like whatever here
so what we do is during the pre
computation that we generate the H file
we just say look we know that it will
cover these elements of the grid right
so into the walk table we say well how
many were there 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11
12 so then we know that the walk table
for that Ray is 12 long right you know
I'm saying so then you come to the
actual runtime and you say all right
Here I am and I want to do my ray cast
well only the first three are valid
right because as soon as you finish you
can't go outside of of that so the
question is what do you do about that
all right all right all right okay okay
okay better idea we make a skirt of
exactly one grid square around the
entire thing and into that grid square
we write a special value that lets us
know that we're done then we don't ever
have to do this because we just know we
hit the end and that way we never need
walk count at all
that's the answer
by far definitely better than what I was
saying so this is not correct this is
not what we do we do not have a walk
count - - we simply say that when we
load up the spatial node we just break
so this thing here right lake is just a
infinite loop and what we do is we say
well okay in the event that we've got a
certain value in there we do one thing
and in the event where we've got another
value in there we do another thing and
that that if is not a new if it just
replaces the if we had before on the
loop invariant so when we grab the node
we say like look if one passed last
index equals like you know spatial grid
node Terminator or something like that
then we know that we've finished our our
walk so this you know tells us right
that seems good to me
that seems good
so we'll say like look if the start
index maybe is like not what we want
then off we go yeah okay that gets us
out of a jam because now it's trivial
and we don't care so we just put a skirt
around the whole thing like an apron
around the outside and whenever we hit
that apron we stop so that way we don't
have to do any complex checking
whatsoever
we literally just point at the table and
go that is great that is very good okay
happy day sunshine so that's great that
means now we just have to think about
this part we don't have to do this which
is very good and so then we just have to
start thinking about exactly how we're
doing what we're doing here right so
here we've got our rady stuff and this
part I guess I guess I don't care about
most of this at the moment but what I'm
gonna do here is I'm gonna actually pull
this out into maybe an array temporarily
and this is just so that I can keep this
code cleaner while we're testing and
then eventually this code will probably
go away because we're gonna if this if
our routine actually ends up being
faster it might end up being slower in
which case we're sad but you know that's
always possibility we're gonna do this
we're gonna remove all this code if it
ends up being faster so we don't really
care if this is a little ugly at the
moment so we're gonna inside here we're
gonna build the components into an array
and then we're just gonna loop over them
so the transfer PPS array will just
start as that for the moment and then
we'll have a ray index equals zero right
index less than four plus plus rate
index and this will just serve as our
temporary here right
so we clamp the moon der - the Ray
direction so our rady equals rady ray
ray index so we grab that out maybe I'll
call that this ray D like so so that
produces our transfer PPS for this
particular pass and then we need to pass
to grid cast the things you know give
unto grid cast the things that our grid
cast and render unto transfer PPS that
which is transfer PPS is so this is this
ray D and then we've got to send some
stuff down that's actually like what we
need ray index D D D and grid ray cast
now needs the following information in
addition to ray D so oh and the Ray
origin so where is that coming in it's
right there
yeah it'll be nice to finally figure out
what's going on here so we can get rid
of a lot of this code there's just way
too much code doesn't need to be here
but we can't really do anything about
that at the moment because we need to
test all this stuff so it's the nature
of test codes very ugly and modern
program layers don't make it easy
it's unfortunate anyway so we need
initial grid index walk count and walk
table so like so and if I remember
correctly now what we're saying is the
walk count goes away because we're just
using the apron to determine whether we
stop or not so we really just need the
initial grid index and the walk table
that tells us like the offsets right now
the walk table in this case is really s
16s I mean they're sort of Delta's so
you know we might want to say that just
to be a little bit clearer about what's
going on but that's basically the idea
so now in here when we do a radial that
doesn't actually have to happen it's
here the walk count isn't going to be
used and the walk table I guess isn't
offset into here so I guess what we
could we could actually still pass this
as a walk table offset I guess
but I don't think we want to so I think
that's gonna go away too
yeah so I think that's what we want
there and I'm gonna pound to find this
thing to be something I don't really
care but something that wouldn't be used
at this point we've got a bunch of stuff
to do down here it's it's wrong
and I don't know what happened here oh
that was an old vestigial romaine it
looks like from the get component call
so there's the inner product there's the
clamp there's the moon pillar so I think
that's all good
so mostly our problem now is we have to
figure out how we're going to pass these
two values down so we've got a initial
grit index and we've got a walk table
and what we need to do now is we just
need to build the things that are
actually gonna provide this data now the
problem is this is gonna start to cause
problems for us because of the way that
this gets passed down it's not great
because we kind of wanted this thing to
be welded into the raycast but doesn't
really work that well with the raycast
unfortunately so if we take a look at
how this is going you can see here where
we do the sampling sphere it's this part
here that we actually kind of needed to
know about right so we get the sample
directions out and then we do those two
ray casts right
hmm stretching now mind you I don't
really know why we're doing this it's
not super clear that we needed to do it
this way but yeah if you look at what's
going on here
so we have the loop there that would be
thunking down to the raycast call on the
raycast call does these Texel ops to
blend things together and that could
just as easily been done on the outside
but it wasn't and I'm assuming that we
put it in here just for convenience but
there's not a lot of real reason that it
should have been happening they're two
completely honest with you so I'm not
sure we actually need that or want that
we may actually want this to be move to
the outside at which point we could also
call grid grid raycast to produce these
values so it's a little Squinkie I'll
preserve it for now but we're gonna want
to unwind the meta here as soon as we
can
actually determine that we've picked a
good route you know I don't know that we
actually have so that's a little up in
the air but we'll we'll leave it at that
so when we actually grab our sampling
sphere information out here that's
really where this information needs to
come from so when we're passing down
like sampled or a and sampled Derby here
I think what I'd rather do is just pass
down the sampling sphere pointer and
that way people can get from it whatever
they want we don't use the sample sphere
of stuff here for anything in particular
so we shouldn't actually have to do what
we're doing here
like if you take a look here at the way
this is working we should just be able
to pass the sampling service down and
then get the sample direct like
direction out of it right so here's what
that actually looks like and you can see
that we've got like a array of sampling
directions you know what I mean
and since we know we need more than that
I feel like again this is kind of the
thing that we now want to start to think
about how these are going to get packed
so we may just want there to be a
parallel array in here that you get and
so like what we know we need to load
[Music]
we know we need the initial grid index
and the end at grid index well actually
that's not true
we know we need just the walk table like
where the walk table is right because we
know what the initial grid index is and
we know everything else so we just need
the location in the walk table that we
would start right that's the only piece
of information we actually care about so
in addition so light sample Direction is
not super relevant so what we need here
is like in addition to this thing we
need in another array that's like how
many of these like where do we start in
the walk table so when you load a
direction out of this thing you go to
the walk table and get that however
again looking at that just thinking it
through
you also don't cast for rays at a time
anymore so that would also mean that
like yeah I guess the reason we set this
up is this previously
this previously needed to work we don't
need any this this previously needed to
work with with Ray bundles and it just
doesn't need to anymore so we really
just have this is all you load so we
need this like you know that will
eventually this will go away and it'll
be replaced with this thing does that
make sense so each sphere now rather
than having these pack together actually
has these packed together so that you
have Ray Direction walk table offset and
pad pack together as one 16 byte pack
right you load up the 16 byte pack
you've got everything you need and you
go from there I think that's it and then
you're gonna use that walk table offset
and the walk table offset actually can
be au 3 2 because there's nothing else
to put in here so we actually can have
huge walk tables if we need to but a
theory that should never be necessary
because the number of rays is not large
enough the number of different ray
directions presumably is large enough
but that's fine so at that point we
would just say alright that's all we
actually have then and we're gonna look
those up into this in the sampling
sphere right now in order to generate
that yeah so like
unfortunately we don't really have a
good way to generate that at the moment
because that's an another part of the
thing we're gonna have to write it right
but what we want to do is make sure that
the plumbing works here so what we want
to do is make sure that this light
sample direction part actually gets
loaded we also kind of have a problem
that like this doesn't really work now
because this is gonna be wrong so I
guess the other thing we might want to
do is you say look for the time being
maybe we do this that way we're not
stepping on anyone's toes so it's gonna
look something like that you know so
again the problem here is that we have a
light sample direction that needs to get
passed down and we don't at the moment
we we're calling ray cast to cast a
bundle of four rays and now we need to
do a separate call for each of those
because we're casting for a separate
Ray's and you can see why I'm not sure
this routine is gonna be faster because
it's just like pretty tricky to figure
out how this is going to work exactly
not tricky for tricky to figure out
whether it will actually be less
expensive or more expensive because of
the way that you have to you're doing
one ray at a time instead of four rays
at a time and you're counting on tests
against four things at once instead of
one thing at once
so you've changed which way the 4x goes
and so that means that the meta changes
there's just a lot of differences there
so it's hard to say so what we want to
do now though is go ahead and take a
look at the the way we're gonna pipe
this information through so if I take
the light sample direction here and just
pass this as a pointer perhaps
temporarily
and then down here I would say let's get
those sample directions loaded up and
we'll and we'll pass them down
furthermore I guess this actually
technically can just come directly out
of here so this can just be that and get
rid of this okay so we'll get this rady
thing and then the initial grit index
can come out of there as well
oops
not that's that's wrong I meant that so
the walk table the global walk table
here that we're saying we will
eventually have the light sampling walk
table that'll just be this and yeah that
also goes in here right so the only
thing we don't have right now is the
initial grit index and we know that we
need to be able to map grid indices too
we need to be able to walk map spatial
positions to grid indices this initial
grid index is something that should also
get passed down because it doesn't
change at all for the entire thread loop
basically for for that entire run of
that thread loop it doesn't change so
for the raycast it's gonna want that
value to stay the same and so that
should be a pretty straightforward thing
as well so when we go to what is what is
the complaint here ah yes so when we go
to raycast
basically what we're saying is like okay
the full cast call here where we say the
voxel center P thing that's gonna cast
everything for this voxel that
we plan to cast and so it knows exactly
what the and I mean we probably already
actually can compute it it to be
completely honest with you yeah so you
can see we've got the Z Y and the X here
so what we really want is this to just
know that value so when we pass through
here we've got the initial grid index
and that initial grid index is the same
for every raycast operation that we do
right so when we call full cast we would
just pass that down so it is initial
grid index equals Z plus y plus X and
when we're talking about the voxel
dimensions here right we just do voxel
dim and voxel dim so we would do the X
dimension here and it's and the Y
dimension as well here right if that
makes sense and since this is
distributive we can also do a little
fancy footwork there and just say you
know that's that so that's just hmm
map's us into the grid and I think we
probably want to make that systemic so
we probably want a thing here that's
like you know grid index from and we
pass a bunch of like you thirty twos
right
so that way we can change this
computation whenever we want and we
don't have to like worry about where we
put it in the code that's all that is so
I think that's everything and now it's
more a question of actually building
these data structures but I think that
everything is in the right like format
for it so hopefully that's good and man
there's a lot of code here that does not
need to be here but you know that's just
something we're gonna have to deal with
ok so if we do the light sample
direction what we want to do here is say
that this will be like R a bundle index
probably I'm guessing for our the offset
so like here are the sampling spheres so
we would say you know I don't exactly
know what we would do but we would say
for each sampling sphere we do we would
do salute it's not solution it's like
some global right yeah so it's just it's
just these and so we're gonna look up
into one of those for example this and
we'd have like a sampling spheres - I
don't know why there's a pointer to that
maybe so we could swap between different
ones but right look why is that I don't
even know why that's a thing I'm not
sure it doesn't make a whole lot of
sense of why we have that and you can
see here right like
so let's say we've got one of these
really we don't need this so we can just
do light samplings for Table two and
then we have der sample index here and
we're going to load out that light
sample Direction table and then in the
light sample Direction table we've got
sample directions like so same as before
and this time the difference is we just
be jumping up by for each time because
we're loading for out and that's all of
this crap is just so that it works the
same for the four wire or the one wide
cases which we all want to delete so
it's just messy right now and it sucks
but that's just how it's gonna be for a
little bit right so what we would say is
light sample directions sample direction
like and we would add to it whatever the
REA bundle index was and so we know that
the REA bundle index is getting
incremented in a particular way here
like a bundle index plus equals two
right and what we want to do with the
REA bundle index I probably should have
asserted that somewhere else and so what
we want to do here is we want to pass
into this routine like the pre off
setted tables that we're going to use
and so this for sample Direction plus R
a bundle index so now what we're doing
is we're saying well okay we really go
by fours when they go by ones right so
it's like this I'm sorry by eights when
they go by twos right and that should do
it
and again it's it's all kind of nasty
but that's that's the way it goes
so let's go ahead and look here what
else we got
that is the wrong thing this is light
sampling sphere - right voxel dim okay
so I think that's all we really need
there and we just need this is a u16 so
we'll we'll do a safe truncate just so
we can get a warning when if if we blow
that limit all right so now we've got
all the plumbing done and the problem
we're gonna have now is just we have to
generate this disaster and we don't
currently generate this disaster so we
need to write the generator code that
generates these and we also need to
write the sorting code that actually
puts all this stuff in place
so for example in here where we do is it
an end lighting computation I don't
really remember where we do it we kind
of sketched it out somewhere in here
yeah so here's like us sketching out
this routine you know I'm saying and you
can kind of see we did most of the work
but we have not actually done the work
of getting it to actually compile right
so we need the grid build to be done we
need to get this code working and then
we need to get the generator code to
generate the walk tables for each ray
and we might as well do that first
because that's something we haven't
sketched out yet so we might as well
sketch that out and then maybe we'll
stop there and next weekend we'll
implement we'll get those two routines
working so we'll do a sketch first
and here's where my memory should be
better than biz because this is a
routine I've written before normally
what I would do is I'd just go take the
routine that I already wrote and use it
so it's a bit of a bummer but I'm gonna
have to see if I can remember how you do
this because I remember it's not trivial
to understand so the thing we need to do
now is that actual build so we need to
do something that oops
if given a location in the grid and then
we want to do a raycast
in the grid so we're basically going
like this kind of thing right what we
then want to do is we want to say what
are all the squares that we visit in
that walk right so like as this thing
extends out like what do we actually hit
and in order to do that for the grid we
basically want to see you know I mean
it's it's basically like a brezin ham
line drawing algorithm you know what I
mean like we basically want to say we're
at a particular location and like one of
these grid squares will be the the one
that the line touches next right and the
question is which one is it
and then we just keep going till we
generate a movement of till we know
we've covered in all three directions
checking all three directions until one
of those directions has spanned the
entire length of the voxel because at
that point you know you've you will have
stepped out of bounds no matter what
right so it occurs to me when I'm
thinking about this too that probably
those tables were too big because we can
only move one well no cuz because we
want to do it with with just one value
so nevermind so yeah so looking through
the walk table for this I don't know
exactly how we want to do this we want
to we want to say that it's not quite a
present online routine because we want
to fill every one that you touch so like
if for example you were right in the
middle there or right to one side or
what to the other side we want to make
sure we get whoever the other pixels are
too so we really what we really want is
we want to say from the location that we
start at wherever that is we need to
first it's probably different on the
first one than it is on the subsequent
ones but you would go and you would say
how far in the radar along the Ray do I
have to go to hit each edge and
whichever one of those is less that's
the one I pick basically right
so you would basically say we know so
you'd know ahead of time how many grid
squares you travel along the Ray per
unit in each dimension right and I guess
you just say based on where you are in
the grid square you know that you're
gonna do
so and just to be clear our grids our
grids are always the same size - right
because that's actually important now
because the grid has to this this walk
table is computed for a particular size
of grid right and that's that's
important now we could do it we could do
this at run time we don't have to
pre-compute it actually if we don't want
to we could do it at startup because
it's pretty quick and maybe I will do
that and that would that's just so in
case we want to change our grid
resolution at run time we can that seems
relatively important right
so creating those seems like a good idea
and maybe we'll do that but what does
this routine look like let's start let's
start sketching it so let's suppose we
want to do this we need a couple pieces
of information so we need the voxel
dimension we need to know the light
sample spheres but those we kind of
already do you know we need to know how
big it is so how big a voxel cell is and
that might be it I think that might be
it and then of course we need the output
and we would return the count I guess of
how many there are just a check right so
when we go to compute the walk table
what we would then do is we would start
at the center so we would do that's the
center of a cell and then we would go we
need to travel somehow to see where
we're gonna end up and in order to do
that we have to take our voxel dimension
and I would sorry our cell dim and
figure out how far we go for a
particular ray direction and so we need
this to be inside all the Ray directions
right for each ray direction we're gonna
pull that out of somewhere the sampling
spheres then we're gonna say we need to
loop through until we've gone far enough
in one direction whatever that direction
is so it's probably something like this
so for each dimension we would keep
track of how far we go you know I'm
saying so then in here we would say
let's figure out which direction we're
gonna go and for each of these we would
say like which whatever dimension it is
like there'd be a best dimension we
would say that the span best dimension
increases right and if this if the new
span is for that dimension is greater
than the voxel dimension so we've like
we know we've gone like one more than we
need to go then we would say that we can
stop right so our termination condition
is just we've spanned the entire voxel
in at least one of the dimensions X Y or
Z so we know that no matter where we
started on the interior we would have
hit an apron before we got to the next
so we would be looking at now so then
the question is which of these best
dimension here right so we say like
where are we we're at this starting
location we then need to say like what's
the best dimension to go along and then
we need to like yeah we need to figure
that out I think it probably looked like
this where we just stepped the T best
each time and so the question is like
how do we determine what the T best is
you know what I mean and we need to
check each of the dimensions in turn so
maybe it looks like this
so we want to check each dimension in
turn and what we want to do is see like
how far you know where we would where
would we have to go to get to the seldom
and the problem here is we need to think
about it in terms of a direction because
we're either going we're going either
backwards or forwards right and I
suppose that one of the things that's
true about this is it doesn't really
matter which one it is
so what we might do is say the REA
Direction comes out of somewhere and
then the negation of which direction
we're going is like a separate thing so
we might just say let's simplify it by
saying we're always going forwards so
we'll say that negation in each case is
like forward and we'll loop through the
dimensions at the beginning saying like
if rady is less than 0
rady e
so we'll just negate it and set the
negation parameter you know and I mean
so that way we could always just assume
that we're going forwards so we can just
assume that we're looking for seldom
like we're looking to get to Selden so
what we need to do is say the REA
Direction element for the particular
axis were on we need to just do a
divided and we could we could turn this
around we don't care this is not a time
and this is not a per frame thing we're
doing just happens once it's set up so
we want to see how far we have to go so
the cell dimension II minus the place we
currently are divided by how far we
travel should be this T if that's the
best one so far
then this is the best dimension right
and that's kind of it now all we need to
do is have our increment ORS
so really negate was probably the wrong
thing here so probably this is actually
called step right and so when we compute
this we would just say what's the step
that gets us to where we want to go and
we would either fill in the dimension
index in question and it'll either be
positive or negative so we could
actually do this in the more positive
frame to brown right if it's positive we
take this step if it's negative we take
the opposite step in this case dim step
is just one at the start right and for
each dimension we would multiply dim
step by that dimensions span when we
pass through it so in other words for X
steps it's positive or negative 1/4 then
when we're done with that we would we
would multiply that by the dimension of
X right
I think that's it
I guess the whole routine probably
forgetting something that will find one
right step through it but that's that's
it and so there you go
we just need to output to desk and so we
would do that here and this is step best
Tim and that's it so we now need some
way of just recording that we haven't
gone too far so we might just say okay
dest in this case well you know what I'm
going to do this with an increment or
nevermind so we'll start at destined x0
and we'll do a plus plus des index or
I'll do it this way and that way we can
also do an assertion here the test and
this is less than max des count so that
way we know and I think that's it at
some point in here we're gonna want to
record where we started so when we pull
out the radio also going to want to do a
thing that's like hey this equals
destined X so like the walk table offset
is this offset right and that's it not
that complicated actually I might be
missing something but that was pretty
trivial so meh
I'm gonna call it there for today and
we'll pick up the actual implementation
next weekend we've got everything done
now and we just need to like actually
blow through everything in act and get
it all running smoothly and then we
cross our fingers that it's actually a
good starting point for optimization
because we don't really know that yet
what is this nonsense what am I seeing
here what are these what are these faked
screenshots from neh sale where he's
trying to claim that he got 889 35 on
slipways we that did not happen we all
know this is like this is like the king
of Kong when Billie something-or-other
faked his Donkey Kong Billy Mitchell
thank you George
this is like when Billy Mitchell tried
to pass off that fake Donkey Kong we all
know that nay sale has never had an
interstellar slipways that was four
stars I mean come on
Billy Mitchell's recently sued someone
yes so I wonder what the story is about
all that stuff it was so crazy right
like there's so much acrimony in this
community where the entire thing is just
like people keeping high scores and
you're like do we even care maybe we do
I don't know Billy Mitchell cares
obviously maybe you'll win maybe it
turns out it wasn't faked that's that
that it's like the plot twist I have no
idea
they clearly needs to be like another
king of Kong documentary because it's
clear that stuff's gone down that's the
problem with sometimes making a
documentary is you affect the outcome of
the community you're documenting that
definitely happened with king of Kong it
definitely happened with tiger King
already and it may it may happen with
flat earth as well right it's like
documentaries are not are not separate
from the story they've become part of
the story I don't know what I don't know
what happened with the Billy Mitchell
thing the in the king of Kong
documentary they don't they kind of
suggest that he may have cheated because
they sort of hint that well the VHS tape
doesn't look quite right or something
but they don't straight-up claim that he
cheated right but since then Twin
Galaxies claimed he cheated right and
now he's suing them for something right
or something right it's it's copy you
should go read about it's complicated I
don't know I wasn't there
can you explain more what a microp is
yes I can uh where's my blackboard here
it is alright so the modern execution
architecture of like you know of like a
skylake core sky like ish core so it
looks like there's now at front-end
there's like front-end nonsense that
happens up here I don't wanna use
nonsense that's dismissive front-end
[Music]
prep I don't know so there's like your
instruction stream that's like sort of
what we looked at before right and I
don't remember exactly what the
instructions we were looking at but they
were like you know add I don't know what
it was like
add a X or something D word pointer
brackets ECX or something I don't
remember what the instruction stream was
so apart I apologize but it's something
like this right and I was saying like oh
then there's gonna be like a sub sub EDI
or something I don't again I don't
remember what it was but it was
something like this and it was a Janney
to a label right and the label was like
up here so this is like a loop right and
it's gonna do this instruction this
instruction this instruction and then it
might keep going here or it may go up
here you know based on whatever EDI was
so it's three instructions and these
when we say in the word instructions
that's a very specific word here and
it's used intentionally these are
assembly language or machine code
instructions they aren't actually things
that process or execute as is they get
munched and in the old days
that was not really maybe as true you
know I wasn't a c64 jockey or a 68k guy
or any of that stuff but you know when
you had the old eight 16-bit 32-bit
microprocessors up until like the
Pentium error stuff typically like the
assembly language instruction was what
the processor executed so like an ad was
an ad and a and a jump was a jump and so
on and it was just one-to-one most the
time I think but that's not true anymore
like modern processors are way more
complicated so basically what happens is
sitting in a cache somewhere well you
know this is in memory or whatever
sitting in a cache somewhere it's
typically called the AI cache which is
the instruction cache but really you can
think of it as it's part of the l1
subsystem on the chip
it's the fastest possible memory style
cache these will exist somewhere in here
if they're about to be executed
so they'll inside the eye cache this
data the actual bytes that encode this
will be in here and what will happen is
the front-end is responsible for
figuring out based on what's in the eye
cache what the heck is supposed to
happen and nowadays that's actually
really freaking complicated I probably
didn't put enough space here so what's
gonna happen is each one of these
instructions has to be decoded into
operations that the CPU can actually
perform and for example this instruction
right here I have sort of semi
intentionally written this in a way that
makes it so that literally none of the
instructions that you see are operations
that actually occur
none of these are operations the CPU
performs none of them literally if I'm
remembering correctly so starting with
this instruction the CPU actually has
multiple things that needs to do this D
word pointer reference here this is a
load so it's a load from
memory and then this ad here is an ad
operation for like an ALU unit it's like
an integer ad so this is really to what
we call Micro ops because even though it
is one assembly language instruction
it's actually to my crops a load and an
ad ok this sub EDI is one you up
that's a sub you up and this J any label
is I guess I want to say it's a zero you
up I mean it's really hard to classify
what this is but the jani label is sort
of an on up and you could think of it as
one you OP that gets fused to this but
you would have to be more of a
optimisation guy than I am to really
know how to use that nama creature
correctly if you're a microarchitecture
person you know exactly what you should
say there I don't so I'll explain what
happens in the chip roughly to the level
of my knowledge but whether you call it
you up or not
I just don't know it depends whether you
think of my crops as things that issue
to al use or ports or whether you think
of you ops as anything the chip could do
and so I don't know I would think of it
myself as a zero you up instruction but
no no okay so the front end is
responsible for determining this and
here's more or less how that's gonna go
again I don't really know I don't have
the inside knowledge on how skylake
works so I don't know but what basically
happens is it's going to take the I
cache and it's going to go through
what's called sometimes a trace cache
but really there's multiple different
micro op caches so these are you up
caches
there are multiple different kinds of
you op caches in the skylake core and
which one actually operates is way
beyond me this is like has to do with
loops versus non loops and I don't even
know so there's a micro app cache and a
loop cache so like there's a you op one
and there's a loop one here which one
will happen in any given case I don't
know I would assume the loop cache will
happen here it's sometimes called a hot
loop cache I think again I apologize
Jeff and Fabien if they ever watch this
for getting so many things sloppily in
here but I'm just trying to give you the
basic idea of what happens so please
take all this with a grain of salt it's
roughly like this it's not exactly like
this so in here this instruction will
each of these instructions when we have
to start looking at it when we know that
we're going to actually execute it it
will get pulled into the eye cache at
least and then it will be decoded into
the micro app cache as my crops
so load ad sub and the non jump
instruction micro hop that doesn't
really exist will get decoded in here
and again I don't even really know if it
gets encoded as are you up or not I
think it does maybe I'm not sure there's
also saying that's made specifically for
relatively small loops that are running
very fast I don't really know why but
there are two of these and it might be
in both of them because it is a tight
small loop right okay so we have
secondary caching that will cache the
results of decoding these actual things
from instructions into you ops the front
end does that but the front end also is
responsible for actually issuing the
UUP's so while it's doing that which may
involve fetching from the cache if it's
already decoded or going out to the I
cache getting it and decoding it into
the you OP if it hasn't the front end
will then look and see what am I
actually going to try to do here the
front end will then try to issue you ops
from the cache like the load ad
here it will try to issue those to the
back end and the back end is this giant
nasty monstrosity that's got a register
allocation table which is the thing that
tries to remember what values are where
it has a retirement cue retirement
window and the front end is going to
start looking through these you ops and
it's going to try to shove them down
through the rat into the scheduler which
is here and then they're gonna go out to
the retirement window so what's gonna
happen here is first for everything that
you see like EI x and r CX and all these
things so you may like think like oh you
know like how many registers you know
does an X 64 have and someone says like
oh it's got like 16 general purpose rest
like no it has 16 general purpose
register names so you can name 16
general purpose registers it actually
has like 96 or more like it's got a ton
of registers it's just you can only name
16 of them and what that means is that
as you do ops on registers if you use
the register multiple times and
overwrite things in the instruction
stream the out of order execution nature
of the process or means it can be
executing many instructions from an
instruction stream at once so it renames
registers as it goes so that you don't
block up on the fact that you only have
16 of them and you're waiting for
something so really there's 16 names for
effectively scratch space I mean that's
the way to think of registers there the
scratch buffer of the processor
there's 16 free scratch slots at any
time the actual number of registers in
the processor is actually quite high
it's it's I don't know how many it is if
it's much much larger than 16 in
practice um so anyway what the front end
is going to do is it's going to try to
allocate a name for the result of this
thing so it sees this ad and it says
well I got a load ezx so
asks the register allocation table right
it's alright it's actually looking at
this now right I've got a load ECX from
a location in memory so go ask the
register allocation table where the heck
is the value of ECX right now because
it's not East in ECX oh there is no such
thing there just a giant table of values
and we just need to know where was the
last time anyone in the instruction
scream stream tried to modify ECX that's
what we've got to get so tell me where
that thing is and the rat will tell us
right so it tells us where that thing is
then we go hey scheduler we need to
schedule a port up for a load and that
goes on port 2 or 3 right so we're going
to schedule on port 2 or 3 a load into
this from ECX into a temporary location
right just some value we need it doesn't
have to have a name some value we need
and we're going to use the result of
that later right so that's going to go
into the scheduler and the scheduler has
off to the side like all the ports put 0
1 2 3 4 dot dot right and we know that
ports 2 &amp; 3 are the load ports so in
here the schedules got this load and
this load is gonna be sitting there as a
micro op right it's an it's a micro
upload it's sitting there as a micro op
waiting for ECX now again it's not
called ECX anymore because we got some
name out of here slot 73 is what was in
the ECX for right now so it's waiting
for slot 73 to be done when that slot 73
is done this instruction will become
ready right and will get executed as
soon as somebody has a spare port 2 or 3
so on a cycle when a port 2 or 3 either
of those are available the load up for
this if it's ready if we've if ECX has
been readied if 73 if that version of
ECX has been readied it will then issue
this
when this comes out of the pipeline some
number of cycles later in case of a load
it's like one cycle later if it's hits l
114 cycles later on L 2 or 300 cycles
later if it's a memory who knows this
load will then retire out to the
retirement window for micro ops so
somewhere in here this thing gets
retired and these go in order so this
will literally have like the load add
the sub and the jump won't be in here
the load the add the sub the load the
adds up right well that's not true the
jump will sort of be in here but it
won't be in here as a jump it's more
like a verify all right so hopefully
some of that makes sense so if you take
a look at what's going on here decoding
into my crops the microbes come from a
cache the front end issues the my crops
they look through the rat to figure out
where the data is and to allocate space
to put the data for the actual result
that result may have a name in the case
of a test destination register it may
not have a name in the case of a blind
load that just gets used those things
going to the scheduler the scheduler is
in charge of looking to see for any
register name that was assigned are
those registers ready if all the
registers for a micro op are ready is
the micro app is ready and it will then
issue on a port when a port is available
for it to issue when it issues on the
port it will go through the pipeline
however many cycles the pipeline takes
for that particular instruction it will
then issue out to the retirement window
the retirement window will mark it as
done and it will move to the next it's
like out like a pointer and it just
retires these in order right that's how
this works when we get to some of the
things I was talking about before I said
two phrases
I said Makarov fusion and micro op
fusion these are the two types of fusion
that occur why do we care we care
because there are you up limits and
instruction limits that apply in a
single cycle the front end on a skylight
core can only process for can only
decode right can only decode for
instructions I want to say don't quote
me on that so if you are seeing the code
for the first time add sub jump one more
it can decode those four I believe can
it is it only is it for sirs are only
for you ops you know I'm sorry I can't
remember I don't remember if there's an
instruction limit so I'm just going to
talk about the OP limits alright so the
you op limits are on a single cycle this
one I actually remember you can only
issue for you ops on a single cycle so
even if you know there's more than four
ports right remember there's 0 1 2 3 4 5
6 7 right so skylake had several ports
if we actually had you ops to issue on
all the ports it wouldn't matter because
the actual issuing so the scheduler can
only issue for instructions per cycle
anyway right so the reason we care about
things like you OP fusion is because in
order to actually get stuff through the
chip we have a for you OP limit so if we
can take advantage of micro op fusion
which is when to you ops flow through
the pipeline as if they were one you up
it means that we can actually increase
to like 5 you ops possibly even more
per cycle even though we only have four
you ops per cycle as an actual hard
limit
so you're basically cheating the
pipeline by sticking and extra you up in
there so in the case where you can get
you out fusion and you can say these two
you up use together in flow it's great
this I believe is an example of you up
fusion a memory op and a arithmetic op
that are the same so that worked
together I believe those travel as a
single pair of you ops that goes through
the pipeline as if they were one you up
don't quote me on that check all this
yourself but that's an example of
getting more than two more than one you
op through the pipeline for only the
cost of one now macro op fusion is a
little bit different macro op fusion are
not you apps at travel code in the
pipeline they're instructions that
travel together in the pipeline and sub
jump is an example of Makarov fusion sub
jump means that those two instructions
actually count as a single instruction
through the whole front end so for the
decode limit for anything that's
instruction bound you actually don't pay
two instructions you only pay one I
believe that's my recollection so
basically if there was something that
could only process for instructions and
I can't remember it's only for
instruction decodes for cycle I'm sorry
macro fusion means actually you can
process five instructions the reason for
that is because jumps don't really exist
so you have to remember front ends what
they're doing is they're filling up this
scheduler with crap they're just
throwing my crops into the scheduler as
much as they can so that the scheduler
can just have as many possible
instructions to work with as it possibly
can right because the more things you
have in the scheduler the more likely
the scheduler is to be able to find one
to put on each of the ports every cycle
right so you're trying to make sure that
every cycle the scheduler has four
things to execute and the best way to do
that is to fill it with as many things
as you can so what the front ends
actually
doing is when it sees this jump it
doesn't actually sit around waiting it
just uses the branch predictor so in
here you've got the branch predictor and
the branch predictor goes for this
address and maybe some other state who
knows guess am I gonna take the next
instruction or am I gonna jump and take
this instruction and then it will just
keep going
so the front end is just gonna run
through this as fast as it can
slamming crap into the scheduler right
ad sub ad sub ad sub ad sub ad sub ads
up it's just right and for the case of
this particular thing since these are
both cheap it doesn't pile up because
the the ports can issue that can execute
this just as fast the front it can
handle it but imagine you had something
more expensive like imagine instead of
an ad this was a div so that these
started to get really backed up you just
have like dibs sub dibs sub dibs sub
dibs up tips up those would just get
stuffed in here you just have like a
crap ton of dibs sitting in the
scheduler right okay
so then what happens is at some point
the branch predictor fails it guessed
that you were gonna jump back and you
didn't you kept going that's what
happened where the retirement window
flush comes in so then what happens in
here the more I said this doesn't really
exist well there's a verification though
that does so something in the retirement
oh and I have no idea how this works
somebody retire videos is just says
check check to see whether the flag was
actually set and it'll do that check and
if the flag doesn't match the thing the
branch predictor thought the flag was it
will then flush so it'll say like oh
crap
everything that was in this speculative
chain needs to get not retired right so
it will undo all of the operations back
to wherever it you know started specula
to be executing it'll roll those back do
not know how that is implemented no idea
but that's what will happen so you don't
really have jump instructions in here
per se what you have is abort like you
have like oops instructions that
say I screwed up let me roll back that's
why you talked about branch
misprediction penalty right and that's
why it's so high it's why it's like 20
cycles or whatever right it's because
it's gotta go like hey yeah the pipeline
was probably 20 cycles 10 cycles long
who knows how long the pipeline is
everything that was in the pipeline that
i issue specula past the branch which
could be quite some time it's all wrong
so we're in trouble if we were waiting
on a memory access to come back to tell
us that it could be huge right it could
be like 300 plus cycles because all the
stuff we issued every single operation
we issued well I don't know if that's
actually true because we may not even
have enough in the retirement in the
window for that I mean maybe there is
I'm not sure the R at the retirement
window may not be long enough for some
of these I don't know how long it is but
point being it can be way more than 20
cycles if we're if the branch mispredict
was on a memory load type thing was or
depended on a memory load then we go
through and we're like oh crap we did a
ton of work and it's all wrong you know
what I mean so
I don't think they fuse the instructions
anymore take a look at loop loop II and
loop any on you offset in fear they take
a lot of you ups what do you mean by you
don't think they fuse the instructions
anymore skylake fuses instructions all
the time I don't know if the new core
does the 10 nanometre core or the yeah
the 10 nanometre + cores or whatever
oh I see no right right right yeah no
I'm not talking about the compiler the
compiler is not involved here I'm
talking about the the core fusing the
instructions what if it is an HTML div
in the scheduler is that what web
assembly is like this web assembly
you know it's basically like the front
end it issues a div and then it has to
issue a wack t'v - like this is the
retirement window this is this is the
retirement window and yeah print
Department says they do even crazier
instruction yeah like my understanding
was that the instructions per clock
because it's hard to push the clock
rates up they're trying to get more
aggressive on instructions per clock so
my assumption would be that a lot of
like the ten nanometer core stuff like
ice Lake and stuff probably tries to do
even crazier crap right like the front
end because the bottom line is like al
use I don't think there's a lot going on
there like I don't know that there's
been much innovation in al use I mean
maybe there is I don't know but I don't
think people are coming up with like
brilliant new ways to add numbers faster
maybe they are but I doubt it
so the al use don't really get that much
faster
mostly what they're doing is they've add
intelligence to the front end and stamp
down more al use so if the front end can
look at more instructions and there can
be for a tour al use instead of two or
you know eight instead of four or
whatever you know all of that stuff is
basically there to just try to get more
performance out of not actually getting
any faster at any individual thing but
doing more things in parallel
so
all right I think we're all good here
all right thank you everyone for joining
me for another episode of handmade hero
it's been a pleasure coding with you as
always if you would like to follow the
series at home you can always peer to
the game on handmade hero org and it
comes with a source code so you can
follow along with it at home I'll be
back here next week and I will go now
and remove the Kickstarter banner from
our web page because kickstart is over
in fact there it is it's over I hope you
got in before was over if not well you
know don't be sad so that's it I don't
know if John's streaming today probably
not because you commented on the stream
just now but maybe he'll stream some
slipways so he can prove no said
probably not okay but I want to see
where the where is the proof that you
got four stars there my friend because I
do not you did not get four stars on
tough we all know that that didn't
happen nay sale just doesn't have those
kind of skills especially not after last
night where I had to bail you out when
the hordes were attacking yeah you
should have OBS tit at this point if
those are actually real screenshots then
you're better at slipways than I am by a
long shot so I should probably be
watching you for the pro tips all
kidding aside but yeah there really
aren't save games and slipways because
you just kind of play you know a 30
minute game and that's it there's not
it doesn't really persist like that
that's a very good point that's a very
good point although I think I streamed
mine I think mine was on stream so that
does that I do have the recording of
that on my harddrive here alright that's
it everybody take it easy