hello everyone and
welcome back to handmade hero it's been
a while
and rather than jumping right back into
programming i felt like that would
probably be ill-advised since
uh it's been a long time since we've
done a stream we actually moved
and so the streaming location is is
completely different now i think
everything's fine we did one test stream
and the internet held up reasonably and
the recording setup held up recently so
we're
hoping uh that that will be the case but
we don't actually know
so what we're gonna do today is a little
bit lighter than full programming we're
just going to take a look at some stuff
that came up on twitter recently
uh regarding how the front end of a cpu
handles
clears and i just wanted to kind of
go through uh the basics of this sort of
thing because
it's a good less so than just
understanding how
an xor clear works on a cpu um
because it is worth knowing that as a
specific thing
but also just understanding how to sort
of like read the assembly
at like a basic level that comes out of
the compiler and
understand whether or not it's producing
something reasonable
if you're trying to do like testing of
what it's doing
uh that can be kind of difficult and
so i kind of wanted to walk through one
of these just so you could
see what's going on and
get some experience with that process
so if you uh i guess the easiest way to
do it would be to like walk through
what actually happened so there was some
talk about
uh clearing values to zero uh this was a
separate thing
uh regarding like language design stuff
that i actually don't care about but the
part about clearing to zero
i do advocate i think zero clearing is
probably one of the most
under-appreciated things in computer
programming um
and in fact i highly advocate
like what i would call z-i-i is the term
that came up with a long time ago
zero is initialization it's to kind of
combat the raii
phrase um which i don't think is
valuable so resource acquisition is
initialization i think is
is a bad programming practice i don't
think it's good i don't think it leads
to good
uh program structure but zii which is
zero is initialization i think does lead
to good program structure and it's
it's actually not just about clearing to
zero
um clearing to zero is sort of a
separate thing
because you can imagine programs that
are just written exactly the same way as
they normally would be
but you insert a zero clear before every
use of a variable right so
you just assume that if a variable is
uninitialized it actually gets cleared
to zero or something like that
there have been languages that do that
there are also like extensions
to c plus do that i want to say i feel
like microsoft
actually introduced something like this
in some research structured programming
projects that they did
they have divisions at microsoft that do
things uh involving
compiler and error uh research and such
and they periodically do things like
introduce
static code analyzer things and they
actually try to deploy them like at
microsoft
uh to try and find bugs and things that
are like huge and unwieldy like you know
microsoft word or something like you're
talking about like legacy code base
um hundreds of thousands
thousands of developers millions of
lines of code probably right
and they try to deploy things and i
think they had some things they deployed
that in addition to stack last like
clear to zero stuff
i don't know so there's this is not like
new like clearing to zero is old and
not like anything that you haven't seen
before if you've been around a while
zii on the other hand is like actually
pretty different
i haven't seen it discussed much i don't
know if it has a history or not it's
just something i kind of came to on my
own but i know that other people
also kind of came to it on their own um
at least something like it and the idea
behind the iii
is just that you try to structure your
program
so that zero is valid right and that's
different than just clearing to zero so
an example of how that would work is
if you have only two valid states of
your program let's say one where
the value of a variable's supposed to be
three and another where the value of the
variable's supposed to be four
you would actually change that program
so that the correct values are zero and
one
instead of three and four and then you'd
offset the three
by two right so you'd add two to the
variable so you get three or four
depending on zero one
that way no actual ish initialization
is necessary for the default case
so basically zii means transforming a
program
as much as possible into the state where
all zeros
is actually the like starting run
condition
rather than thinking of some random set
of values that you want
as the starting condition and trying to
enforce that those actually get set
right and so um
again big proponent of this model it
it has a lot of advantages
number one it makes it much harder to
introduce bugs uh but number two
is that it's actually way more efficient
because rather than having to
keep all of this data on hand that you
use for initialization that you're
constantly like
pulling into the cache to copy into
things and having to like actually have
structured pieces of code that go
through and switch around
to know how to initialize things you can
literally just
initialize like giant sections of your
program
simply by allocating and zeroing a block
of memory
which which is way more efficient
especially because the first time you do
it you
actually don't pay for it because the
operating system usually has to hand you
a zeroed page to begin with
since security concerns on modern os is
means that they will zero the pages
whether you want to
them to or not for example on
a pc there is really no way to allocate
anything other than a xero page
the operating system will never give you
back anything other than a zero page
so you can't actually get a performance
win by not clearing memory
the memory will be cleared and it will
be cleared by the os and again the
reason for that is because there are
really significant security concerns
to the operating system recycling memory
because that memory
wouldn't necessarily have come from your
process or even if it did come from your
process
it doesn't really necessarily know
whether it came from your process
in a way that's safe to allow you to
reuse it so when you call virtual alloc
you always get memory that's zeroed
that's just a specification of the os
and the best of my knowledge there's no
way to turn it off um
you would have to be doing some kind of
kernel bypass thing or something
uh the average program that just runs on
an end user's machine
again to the best of my knowledge has no
way without like
special administrator privileges or
something of actually getting
a non-zeroed page so
so what i wanted to talk about now with
something sort of tangentially related
to this
that is just a programming model that i
think is good you've seen me do it on
handmade hero before
um i actually do it even more now like
in my
in the past five years or so overhead
course of handmade hero
definitely some things have happened to
my programming that
uh i think make it better i mean you
never really know whether you're getting
better getting worse right but
um and i actually apply zii a a lot more
now than i did so like if anything i
feel like it's on the rise
in terms of the number of places where i
find it useful
um the other big one would be
multi-threaded like i feel like i'm 10
times better at multi-threaded now than
i was starting handmade heroes so the
multi-threading stuff in hammond hero is
kind of crap but you know
you're always learning there's nothing
you can really do about that you're
always going to look back at programs
that you wrote and go wow this is
garbage if you don't it's usually a bad
sign because it means you've kind of
stagnated right so i never really beat
myself up over that sort of thing i just
go look
if i can't look back at a previous
project and find something i did stupid
then it must mean i stopped learning
because no one's a perfect programmer
and so if you look back and you say wow
this is all great
uh it's probably not a good sign right
it probably means you haven't been
pushing yourself
very hard and that's usually not good so
anyway um what i want to talk about
today is tangential to this
uh again uh i talked about this a little
bit on the pre-stream but i'll talk
about it again
um on twitter a fellow named jesse meyer
from
nasa uh was responding to some of the
stuff
regarding zii with some stuff that
doesn't really have anything to do
with zii structurally it's just about
looking at the performance
something i said about clearing to xero
being free in a lot of cases
and i don't actually know why he was
interested in this but he maybe just
wanted to look into it a little bit
and so he posted some test code he was
trying to
run and you can see it here it's
basically a piece of code
that creates a little fictitious
matrix type here so four by four matrix
uh homogeneous
uh 3d matrix like the kind you would
normally see in graphics programming
and he then allocates a large number of
these
so you can see here that he's got um
a what 10 million matrix alloc he just
allocates a flat block of memory
he does a clock and he then runs through
the memory
and he does some setting of it and he
did it in two versions one
has this zeroing commented out and one
has
it commented in you can actually see
here uh it
with the zero removed so he was trying
both of these
now um there's some things i want to say
ahead of time about this because
so if you look you can see on the
command line here
that jesse was using dos which means
there's certain things that are not
necessarily
at play that would have been at play if
he was using
linux and i want to mention that real
quickly because a lot of people don't
know this
um i've actually been bitten by this
multiple times so i want to just point
it out
because we're coming from das it can be
uh
a little uh disquieting
so the first thing i want to say is when
you're doing a benchmark
and it looks like this and you do
a malloc of a large block of memory
and then you do a timing run
one of the problems that you will get is
that if you actually structure your
timing loop like this where you do a
beginning
end and then you do the whole thing
inside the beginning and the end
you can run into really significant
performance penalties
that are not accurate that don't reflect
the actual performance
of the routine inside because of the
fact
that the operating system is under no
obligation to actually have mapped this
memory yet
so on windows usually what happens if
you call malloc
it's going to thunk through to virtual
alloc for something this large
and it's going to give you back a very
large piece of actually committed memory
usually um and then when you run through
it
you're not really page faulting
necessarily right
you're writing through that memory and
it probably already got
set up in the memory
mapping tables so that's all fine
and this was on windows so it was
probably fine
but again to avoid any kind of secret
surprises while we're talking about this
kind of
profiling and this kind of looking at
detailed information how the processor
works
it's important to remember that on linux
that is not true
so on linux if you allocate a very large
block of memory
um well i'm not exactly 100 sure all the
things that
malloc might do because malloc is
actually a runtime library component
but the equivalent to virtual alloc on
linux is
memp so it's mm map
you can look it up in like the in the
man pages
mmap is exactly like virtual alloc in
terms of what it does it sets up memory
mapping tables
for your process so that you can create
pages of memory that you're going to use
but it operates in a very different way
than virtual alloc
uh when you call it by default what it
will do
even with the kinds of settings that you
would normally pass to virtual alloc
is rather than ever actually allocating
any memory for you
when you ask it for something like this
like 10 million
matrices it will actually only allocate
4096 uh bytes
it actually won't even really allocate
4000 isix bytes what i should say
is we'll map a phantom page
a zero page um of 4096 bytes
it will point the complete range
that you asked for at that one
at that zero page and it will set it to
copy on right
so what it will do is when you actually
touch a particular page of memory it
will go
and map an a real page
at that time that you first touch it
and when i say touch it i mean write to
it
so if all you ever did was read from it
you would literally never map any memory
so for example
on windows if you virtual alloc
16 gigabytes of memory with a commit
like so if you actually
you know use mem commit um not mem
reserve you're actually
saying hey i want to actually map this
um it will actually allocate 16
gigabytes of memory and if the machine
doesn't have 16 gigabytes of virtual
memory
to spare because the page file isn't big
enough or something
that will just fail right
on linux as far as i know and again i
don't program links
that often so you'll have to forgive me
there may be certain configurations that
interfere with this or certain behaviors
that will change
but generally speaking if you try to mem
map
16 gigabytes of memory on linux as far
as i know it just works
because it never actually allocates any
memory so
the only time that i would think that
there could be any real
way that that could fail meaning it
would actually return like a zero
is if you tried to allocate so much
memory that it was outside like the
bounds of mappable memory
completely like it like if it if it blew
past the 48-bit barrier or something
like this
where you were into a range where it was
impossible to even
map the memory but at no
time as far as i know does linux
actually look to see whether it
actually has enough virtual memory left
available to give you
that memory it's only going to do that
later when you actually write to it
and whether or not this is a good idea i
suppose is debatable i think it's
horrible because i care a lot more about
reliability
than i care about like weird performance
tricks like that where you're like
getting a little bit extra in the case
where
an app doesn't really need the memory or
something so
i really don't like that but you know um
linus and dave can fight that out
because i'm not really experienced
enough with os's to come down
definitively on one side or the other as
an
as a system programmer or anything like
that but as an app programmer i really
don't like it
suffice to say it happens so you need to
be aware
that that is occurring and even though
in this particular case
we don't care about the failure state
for example
the case where we're asking for more
memory
than the machine can actually provide in
the mapping
and uh if we were to actually touch them
all we don't care about that because
this is a test program we're not
shipping it to an end user or anything
like that so if it fails it fails we can
work around it
but what we do care about is the very
odd
access pattern and performance pattern
that will occur
the first time you attempt to write to
the memory that you've allocated and so
like i said
in jesse's case he's using windows so
probably this wasn't a problem
for him and his timings probably weren't
affected by this
but if he had chosen to run this on
linux
he would have been and the reason for
that is because
rather than the time taken to
pull these pages in and give them actual
virtual memory addresses for real where
where they're really mapped to real
pages not to the xero page
normally in windows this will probably
happen on this line which is before we
take the start clock
but on linux it will happen inside this
loop and it will specifically happen
every time we cross one of those 4k page
boundaries unless
linux is set to a larger page size i
assume linux can be set to 64k pages or
two meg pages or something but i don't
actually know again i'm not really a
linux programmer so i don't
no but point being usually 4k pages is a
safe assumption on a lot of machines but
it could be more
every time you cross that page boundary
you will actually page fault and this
clocking
here will actually measure the page
faults
so runs 1 through 25
or run one through 24 i should say
will be reasonable runs runs zero will
actually be
totally wrong and since this clocking
here
is actually taking that into account
it's worth noting that when you're
trying to do things like examine
performance
you really don't want to have that
happen because page faults are so
expensive
that they may easily dominate the
measurement time that you're actually
seeing and the actual cost of the thing
you were trying to measure may be a very
small fraction of that
leading you to believe that there's less
effect
on the time of the program than there
really is
so usually when you're doing this kind
of timing what i would recommend
depending on what you're actually doing
there's two approaches you can take
the wild west ride into town
with guns blazing cowboy time
fun fast way of doing it is you actually
put the clocking
and usually you use more accurate
clocking than clock usually you would
use query performance counter on windows
um but you put that inside
so inside the for loop you put the
beginning end in here
and what you do is you take the smallest
time so you initialize outside the loop
to like the lowest time is
infinity right the highest value
for the thing you're tracking then
inside the loop here
each time you do a begin then you do the
4i over the entire end then an
end you take the difference between the
two of them
and you if it's less than the previous
minimum
you use that one furthermore
what some people do is they even put
they they keep the it looking like this
basically
and they put the foreign loop around the
outside but rather than
being a four-eye loop they use a while
loop and what they do
is they do a four-eye of 25 runs or
something like this
and if it goes down from the if
if inside here so i'm not explaining
this well you put the clocks on the
inside of this thing
so you run it 25 times and you do the
thing at the end
inside here you do clock begin clock and
you check the time if it's if it's
lower you keep it but then you've got a
while loop on the outside
that says if during any of those 25 runs
i found a new minimum
run it again so basically that's just
keeps running as long as it can get a
lower time value it just keeps running
and that's basically like a hunt for the
minimum
kind of routine a lot of times you want
to use that's why i call it the wild
west way because it's not a good
measurement
of what the routine will actually cost
in practice
because it's kind of the best case
scenario it's finding the best case
scenario of whatever this thing is but
it's a good way to find out what's going
on in the processor right because if
you're trying to figure out what the
minimum possible execution time is for
something when all the stars align and
the casters in the best possible state
and the branch pictures are the best
possible state
and everyone is just happy and wonderful
what is that time hunting for the
minimum is the way that you get that
right
so in this particular case again this
this uh this particular way of running
it
is particularly except susceptible
to the page mapping problem and like i
said the reason for that is just because
since it's timing the entire set of runs
rather than say hunting for a minimum
i if you ran this on linux you would get
totally screwed
uh on windows you probably won't get
that screwed right
okay so uh as i said there's a second
way that people often try to time these
things
and that is that you do basically the
same thing i just said which is you put
the clocks on the inside and then do a
bunch of runs on the outside
but uh and again you usually use a
higher uh higher perf clock than clock
uh if you're actually trying to time
stuff precisely but point being whatever
your timing function
is and then what you do is you take a
statistical
look so you like histogram and make
buckets for
how like where did i see the times
landing
right and you maybe ignore some outliers
like if the
operating system decided to swap you out
at that time so you're
you know you you would count like a huge
kernel transition in there for example
uh that's an example of a place where
you really don't want that
to count that time against your average
let's say
um or if you find you get an extremely
fast run and you've never seen
it and you never see a run that fast
again maybe again that was the case
where all the stars aligned and that's
really not a realistic
expectation of what will happen so a lot
of times what people will do is they'll
look at a statistical breakdown
right of what actually was happening in
in in the routine
and so that's one way you can um
that's one way that you can go in and
get another picture that's not just hunt
for the fastest possible
it's like try to get a picture for how
this scatters around
now in either case again it's never when
you're
creating a test case like this one we're
usually investigating
something specific about the processor
so i would probably recommend the hunt
for the minimum if we were going because
because again
what jesse was trying to do here was
investigate something the processor was
doing he's not really trying to figure
out like what this routine does in the
real world right
so taking a statistical breakdown of it
doesn't make a lot of sense
because it's already a synthetic test
case and we're not really trying to
figure out
anything about how it actually would
behave in the real world what we're
trying to do
is investigate something about the
processor so hunt for the minimum makes
a lot more sense in this case and that's
probably what you would do
if you were going to upgrade this to a
little bit of a stronger
uh analysis right for um looking at what
the processor does
probably not statistical breakdown uh
unless you were trying to capture
something else
if you're trying to capture sister
breakdown you probably need a more
complex test case
because this is so compact and so
straightforward
that it's unlikely that you're going to
capture a lot of weird things about
cache behavior
or branch prediction uh
or hyper threading or whatever like
we're just not going to get that
here so statistical breakdown doesn't
make a whole lot of sense to me but you
know
everyone has their preference okay
so with all of that preamble out of the
way which again
all of these digressions are intentional
because i'm just trying to give you a
full uh
the whole only reason i'm doing this
today is just to give people
a firm understanding to the extent that
they can get one
about how this kind of process works and
what to be aware of so
again like maybe this is sufficient
what's already written here
maybe it's not especially if you're
running on linux it would be bad on
windows maybe it's fine
if it's not fine you may want to move
these on the inside
you probably want to switch to higher
resolution timers a lot of these things
are important for investigating cpu
performance because cp performance is
subtle
right so you you need to be careful
about how you do it because even if
you're just trying to get
a vague understanding of what's
happening there's so many things at play
that sometimes you have to get a little
bit more
precise so it's hard to say but
this is sufficient for our purposes for
now what i wanted to go through
i tried to recreate this routine in god
bolt so you can see it
here i've not compiled it so i don't
know if i have a typo or something so
what i'd like to do
is i'd like to just compile this really
quick
on the actual machine to make sure that
i didn't screw it up right because i
just kind of typed it in
and i wasn't particularly careful or
anything
so i want to make sure that i don't have
any kind of like stupid error in there
that's going to make it
um so that i don't uh let's just uh call
this
xor clear or something um i don't want
to have anything in there that's really
stupid that's going to make it so that
we're looking at assembly code that's
actually totally wrong and doesn't
matter
right um because if i screwed up the
code and it doesn't actually work then
the assembly that we're looking at isn't
a reflection of anything at all it's
just fictitious
and wouldn't matter so i just want to
run it and make sure you know
get rid of any crash bugs get rid of any
if it prints out completely wrong values
or something right
so i just want to go ahead and compile
this here and run it and see what
happens
just so again i can get a feel for
what's actually going on and make sure
there's no obvious bugs
value check is one which is what it
should be so that's good and if i
actually go in here and do an o2 on this
um it should get faster and it does
uh so i think we're good like i think
i probably didn't screw it up too bad
and
that's really what would matter in this
case
so let's pop back over here because what
i wanted to go over was
nothing in particular about actually
running this code
i want to go over the assembly language
and so what i'm going to do
is i've opened up godbolt here and i've
got
that code basically exactly as jesse
wrote it
uh it's more or less the same i i maybe
changed some names and wrote it in the
style you're used to seeing on handmade
hero but other than that
it's basically the exact same code i
also included xmm and trin here because
i'm going to want to play with intrinsic
a little bit later on so i just put in
um the ability for us to access the
intrinsics as well but otherwise it's
basically the same code
and what i'm going to do is just make
sure that i have both compilers here
um i don't really remember how to do
this exactly yeah there we go
i always have a little trouble the
interface of godbolt sometimes
once i get it set up it's it's nice
um so i'm just going to pick an msvc
with an o2 here um and
so that we can look at both pieces of
code and
this way we have uh yeah you can kind of
see here
this way we've got an example of what
clang will output when we tell it to
optimize
and we have an example of what msvc
will output when we tell it to optimize
as well and
just looking at this i mean
this this tends to be what i see and
it's you know it's weird
um i i don't know like maybe
i just always happen to drop in and
inspect assembly
at times this happens but just whenever
i look at assembly
of scalar code or like code that the
compiler was supposed to make for a
simple routine
um msvc always seems
to totally beat uh
clang from what it looks like like it
just always look
msvc's optimizing characters always
outputs like better stuff
for my code and then the opposite is
true anytime they're intrinsic so
anytime i write like heavy intrinsic
code
not any time i guess that's not true but
a lot of times when i write heavy
intrinsic code it seems like clang
actually does better i don't know these
may be
a little bit um
again just like selection randomness
bias like i happen to see
certain times and not um but it's just
weird and when i look at this
you know you can kind of see um even
just from the start
what you can see here is that um
when when it's actually generating this
code like it looks like
it looks like msvc just
totally crushed it like it looks like
it's just using a rep
to move these guys and i mean i feel
like that's exactly what you would want
most of the time you know maybe i'm
wrong about that but i feel like that
would absolutely destroy
this nonsense which doesn't even look
like this doesn't even look right
just even if you were going to do
like i'm going to walk through both the
assemblies but
this just looks nuts i have no idea why
you would ever do this
and again i'm not really an optimization
guy so like
my opinion of whether this looks nuts or
not is maybe not the most informative
but i mean just like
at first blush i can't see why
you would ever want anything like this
code for this loop
it's just plain nuts whereas this
looks exactly like something i might
want for this loop
um so i i don't know like
i i don't know what to make of that
other than to say that it kind of
reinforces my opinion that clang has a
lot of weird
bad cases hanging around in it that that
just don't seem to happen
um for msvc and sometimes like i said
in certain circumstances it seems like
clang has a much more aggressive
optimizer that will do some really cool
stuff in certain circumstances
but on the average it seems to have
really dumb
problems uh that it that it always
screws up
right and this is an example of that so
let's walk through what this code is
actually doing
um before i start talking about xor
clears or any of those
sorts of things you can see we don't do
any clearing here all we're doing is
basically a glorified memsat
um so inside the loop and what you can
see here
is in if you're not very familiar with
assembly language
then the way to think about it is just
uh
the innermost loop of your code is
usually pretty easy to identify in god
bolt it's especially easy because you
can actually move over it and it will
show you
and it also has them kind of color coded
right so you can see when i move my
cursor over here it like highlights this
and when i move my cursor over here it
highlights that
so you can actually see the body of the
loop
in question um and you can even see
where the criteria for the loop are so
you see as i move over that you can see
that it's highlighting this uh piece of
code here right
and so one of the nice things about
godbolt and the reason i often tell
people when they're learning assembly
language to please and
um take a look at it it's a very nice
tool for this
and it's the kind of thing that you
would want built into your editor uh and
so they've you know it's too bad it's
not built into most editors but it's not
um and so when you're actually looking
at the code here it just helps because
if you don't know how to read a semi
language and you just had
um like especially on this side where
there's not labels
in this one um because of the way that
it turns into a rep
uh but you look at it as just a giant
wall of assembly and if you're not very
familiar with how to read assembly that
can be very
daunting and it can be hard for you to
figure out where you're looking at and
get any kind of foothold on it but when
you have
godbolt you can just move over it and
see where it's coming from
which makes it a lot easier for you so
um when we actually look at this code we
could see
what it's doing and let's go ahead and
walk through
what's actually happening so as you can
see
this particular for loop here has
evaluated to
effectively this piece of code so
this lbb02 label
is matched with this jump and what
that's doing is
that is what is creating the loop so
remember for those of you who are really
new to assembly language
for loops while loops do loops all of
that
stuff doesn't actually exist in the
processor at
all those are just shorthand notations
for
tests and go go-to's so basically like
um you can think of all
loops in c as getting rewritten first as
an
if and a go-to and then they get
translated into assembly language
is a good way to think about it because
that's what's actually going to happen
on the processor
so what you can see here is that's
exactly what occurs
this cmp instruction is doing a
comparison
it's doing a comparison between a
register rax
which happens to be where we are in our
copy
and this value which is how many things
in total
it was going to try and copy i mean it's
not how many things it's like how many
bytes basically um it was going to copy
and after it does that comparison it
does a jump and the jump
is basically saying look if this
comparison it's a jne which means jump
not equal to
it's basically saying look the previous
comparison you did
is going to set a bit in the processor
that says whether or not these things
were equal
and then we're going to jump if they're
not equal and so
what this does is it says here is a you
know what the compiler did is it
precomputed this value
which is if we go and actually do the
computation ourselves we should be able
to figure it out
we know we have a four by four matrix
um and each floating point value in this
case it's a float so it's going to be
four bytes long
you can see that that is 64 bytes
per identity matrix and we know that we
said we wanted a matrix count
of 10 million right so if we do 10
million
64 byte matrices there is our value
right and lo and behold that is exactly
the value
that we're looking at here right zero
zero zero zero zero zero zero six four
four six right so it's this value right
here right
so what clang did in this case is it
multiplied out how many bytes total it
was going to be writing
and it just makes rax be the pointer to
the matrix
and you can see here that each time
through the loop
it adds 64 bytes which is the size of
exactly one matrix
and so you can infer that this copies
one identity matrix
to the memory it advances the pointer by
one matrix
test to see whether it has gotten to the
end of the byte range
by looking at the total number of bytes
it was expecting to write
and if it has reached zero it will not
take this jump this is jump if not equal
to
so i'm sorry if it is reach zero if
there's no difference between them
right then it will just fall through and
finish
by executing the next loop check which
is this one out here
otherwise it will jump back and copy
another matrix
right so again not very difficult to
understand when you actually parse it
out it's just
advance the pointer check to see if it's
hit the end of the byte range
and jump back to the beginning now
you'll notice that it does take a little
bit of work to read this because
it's not doing the loop the way we wrote
it we wrote it as
going indices of index um
to matrix count not indexed to 64 times
matrix count so we
wrote this to copy a matrix at a time so
we use the index of
the matrix but in this case they
the compiler clang expanded it out so
that actually rax is a byte pointer
now you may ask why did it do that and
the reason that it did that is just
because it's a free transformation for
it to do
these are both constants so it doesn't
matter whether this was one
and this was uh 10 million or if it's 64
and 640 million
right those are both free uh more or
less
with with the exception of maybe no i
don't think there's really an exception
there that's just
basically just both gonna be free um so
it's a free transformation to do
and it gets rid of extra addressing that
might have to happen
in here or you would have to do rax
times 64.
so it's trying to reduce the complexity
of the addressing
used when it's actually trying to figure
out where to write this stuff
um so that's a transformation that it
probably will
usually apply because why not right
we need to have like an auto ban of rust
from the chat
uh anyway so if you take a look
at this um what you basically find
is that this is the part that we
probably actually care the most about
i'll speak briefly about what was going
on the assembly language here
just so that everyone's clear on it um
when you look at what's going on
these two instructions are usually what
are called
fused macro apps um or usually our
macro ops subject to fusion might be the
way that you would say it
so one of the things that you'll notice
and you see this actually
twice already just in this really simple
piece of code that we have here
is that usually what's going to happen
in assembly language
is that most of the time you don't just
jump around the code for no reason most
of the time you jump around the code
because you've done a comparison
and you're trying to skip over an if
body or you're trying to go back to the
beginning of a loop
as is the case here and so almost always
you will see
a comparison instruction paired with a
jump instruction
so what the processor actually does
because this pattern is so
common is that actually comp
jump even though it's not an instruction
is actually what the processor treats it
as
so this on modern x64 processors
will often be interpreted not as two
instructions
comp and then jump but actually as one
instruction
which is comp jump so the reason that's
actually
important is because when it actually
goes
uh to process this that will often
not count against you in your four
ops per cycle so on like a skylake park
for example which is kind of the most
prevalent part right now
although that's going to change because
amd is going to take over the world next
year and no one will be using intel
processors anymore because they
no longer are able to actually make them
um
at the moment when we talk about the
most common processor it's a skylake
processor
and it's going to fuse these into a
single operation which means it won't
count
against your four instructions that you
get through the front end
i believe it gets fused and can be put
through as a single instruction and
again when you're trying to
look at the throughput of a processor
one of the main things you look at
nowadays
is what's called ipc or instructions per
clock
and when you talk about the number of
instructions per clock that you can
actually do in a processor it's around
four micro ops
um on the skylight cores
and this is an interesting case where
you actually diffuse those
through the entire pipeline i believe
it's actually macro opt fusion not micro
objects i believe
comp jump actually goes through the
entire pipeline as one
meaning it's only counts as one in the
front end and only counts as one
uh in the back end as well don't quote
me on that because again i'm not
offspring it might be that it's only
micro up fusion which means it actually
counts as two in the front end
uh for certain parts and then it counts
as one um
on the back end but either way point
being these get fused together and don't
count against your execution time at all
as 2 they count as 1.
and i think part of the reason for that
is also that if you think about it jump
isn't really an operation
so comp is something that actually needs
to go through
an execution port it actually needs to
do work to figure out if these two
bit patterns are the same so it's taking
actual values feeding them into an
execution port and actually testing to
see
if they're the same jump doesn't
actually
do anything it doesn't have any
execution ports it's just a thing in the
front end that says
i need to fetch a different execution
set i'm going to fetch these
instructions rather than these
instructions
as the next things to pull into the out
of order window
and so what usually happens
on jumps is they're either completely
free as i was saying meaning the comp is
the only thing we actually care about so
the jump is either completely free
or it actually has a branch
misprediction penalty
if the branch predictor failed to guess
which way it would go
and we'd end up spending 20 cycles
pulling in the correct instructions
because we actually pulled in the wrong
set of instructions or something like
that right
so jumps get into branch predictors not
very
uh relevant to this particular thing but
it's because this loop is running so
many times that it's always going to
predict basically correctly because it's
always going to take this jump
uh except for the very last time that it
runs and so
it really doesn't matter that much to us
here but it's worth understanding what's
going on
so what will actually happen at the end
of this is we'll have an ad on the
scalar pipe
because this is a scalar ad we'll have a
comp on the same so this is actually
an ad and a dependent compare and then
it will do the jump these can all be
uh sorry these two will issue like i
said together
uh for free we'll get the jump it's only
the comp that we're worried about
and the ad is actually
again dependent so it's gonna wait this
comp is going to stall
waiting for this ad to finish it so
it'll be like one cycle on the ad
and then one cycle on the comp right and
the jump is free
so really what we care about um is what
we're going to start looking at up here
because
also typically when you're talking about
doing large moves and you can actually
see this happening here
xmm registers are the cmd registers they
are the wide registers
typically the pipes are separate um so
on skylake they're completely
separate in the sense that scalar
ads and um like
mob aps are not on the same execution
units at all
uh this is gonna be something that's on
a memory execution unit this is going to
be something
that's on one of the scalar arithmetic
units
uh and i believe there's
slightly different so it's
let's just go full pull on this
i mean it's a handmade chat after all
so uh here's our instruction no it's
just add
sorry i'm thinking
sse i was one step ahead of myself there
come back maybe i'll make there we go
that's what i need okay yes
all right so in this case we've got an
ad with a 64-bit register and an
immediate
um so if you take a look at what's going
on here we can actually pick out
exactly that one so you can see here
like here's an
an ad with an rs64 and it's probably an
i8 because it's only adding 64 so it
doesn't need
very many bits to encode that now i
don't know if i can get code bytes on
here
[Music]
um
it doesn't really matter because they're
going to be this pretty much same anyway
but point being
let me open it up um so here's the
performance breakdown for skylake x core
for the ad instruction where you're
adding an immediate to a register
and it doesn't really matter if we got
the right one or not because as long as
we're in the ballpark it should be
basically the same
and what you can see here is the port
usage
here tells us which of the actual
execution ports
on the skylake processor uh are going to
be able to use it and
see ice like canon lake skylake we don't
have isolator canon lake
nobody does because intel can't figure
out how to fab them
so you might have this if you're using
like a recent
uh laptop this i think got deep six
they printed a very small number of
these and then they just gave up
so this is the only thing you might have
if you have a modern laptop there are no
desktop
ice lakes i don't think i don't know if
they ever got that working
they may never have um so we ignore
these two
because these are not particularly
relevant right now for anything honestly
so we're really looking at this right
here and here's the port usage now the
port usage happens to be the same
so we really don't care but it's worth
noting that this is the core that you
probably actually have
right similarly this might be the core
that you have this one's a little harder
course it depends which one you have
this is the one i think is in this
machine i don't use the skylake x
because sky x has avx 512 i'm not
mistaken and this machine doesn't
so i believe this is just a regular
skylight core again same port usage so
it's okay
um and what this p0156 means
that's the list of execution ports there
are like seven
i think in a skylight core zero one five
and six can all
do an add right um and so it takes
one cycle not one cycle
it takes one of these execution ports
and it will do it on any of them that it
has
what this means is that if you have four
ad instructions
that are all independent you could
actually get them all going on separate
ports
and not have to wait right um so in
other words you could issue on port zero
an ad
on port one nad a port five an ad and
port six an ad you could issue
ads on all four ports at once that's why
they end up with a thing that's like
the reciprocal throughput here is 0.25
that's basically saying four per clock
right meaning it only takes a quarter of
a clock
quote-unquote to do an ad because you
can do four of them at once now any
given one
actually will take one cycle that's what
this latency
tells you but this thing is just saying
hey there's four ports so it's
effectively 0.25
right so again just trying to give you
a little bit of a flavor for what's
going on here right
um and so basically the cpu resources
that are going to get assigned to be
doing this
the ad can go to any of four ports
so what i was trying to get across there
is that pretty much no matter what
happens in this loop
unless it is absolutely psychotically
tightly optimized
and can only work with zero one five six
as its ports this ad will probably just
sneak
in there for free right the
ad comp is probably gonna end up being
pretty free
let's look up the comp as well while
we're at it
uh so this is an r64 versus an immediate
64. or that's a 32 right
i think it's a 32-bit immediate right it
was it was 640 million so that's
that's well within 32-bit range um so
let's take a look at this comp
um of the r64 register and here it is
the comp can happen on all four as well
right
so chances are this
is literally irrelevant to the root loop
runtime
it will just find a hole one of those
ports will be open
and it will just find a hole and fill it
so we can
almost say i mean once we look at this
we'll have a better idea of it i mean i
can already tell just looking at it that
it's true but i mean
imagine we were gonna imagine that we
had to focus on this a little bit more
closely
um this will almost certainly
just fill up execution port bubbles in
our routine
and we just don't have to worry about it
right
so this is basically free and we'll just
find
of those ports 0 1 5 6 it will just find
one to execute on
and execute on it in the shadow of all
the other crap
that we're going to be feeding the
processor right
okay so that's what's going on
at the end of the loop and we can more
or less ignore it completely
so now what we're looking at is just
this
what does this code actually do and to
be completely honest with you while i
think i know what it does
i have literally no idea
like i literally have absolutely no idea
why the compiler is doing it this way
there's probably an explanation and if
there's someone out there who works on
the clang back end
who's watching this maybe you can tell
me what the heck happened here
i don't know maybe there is a smart
reason why you would do this but i just
i don't know what happened here let me
walk you through it
[Music]
um
i i'm i'm struggling to figure out
i i mean the only thing i can say
because i've never looked at the back
end of clang before so i don't have an
idea of like how it could get
into get itself into this situation
um i
guess maybe the reason it it ended up
doing this is because it
was penalizing
uh yeah i'm sorry i just i don't know i
have no idea why it's doing this
i i wish i knew
um
i'm sorry yeah i think our only real
hope
is that somebody who works with the
clang back end
uh is watching the stream and can post
later to tell us why
you know how it got itself in the stairs
so let me walk you through what it's
doing
um and i i'm i'm sorry i just i can't
because that's not my expertise i don't
spend a lot of time looking at the clan
compiler back end in fact i don't think
i've ever looked
clanky power back in so i just i don't
know what set of heuristics went
wrong to get it into the state or if
this is somehow really brilliant but
my knowledge of skylake suggested this
is not even remotely good
um maybe it was trying to optimize for
another
i don't know if there's a way to
basically say like hey
what would you do if you knew you had a
monitor no so it just it seems to want
to do that even if i tell it it's a very
modern processor
um so i'm sorry
i've got nothing i don't know why clang
did that it's just seems just kind of
nuts to me so
maybe someone else can clarify that
later what the heck it was doing here or
why
i don't know but let me tell you what
it's doing and then we can go from there
so if you take a look uh what you've got
is
you have essentially a set of
instructions that are sort of uh paired
a little bit so you can see that you
know it's it's doing this loop
uh where it's going to do uh
four separate mobs right
and those moths are going to be moving a
particular constant value
into particular locations and what you
could see
is this value is a very specific
structured value it's hard to determine
what this actually is for a human
um because it happens to be a floating
point number now remember we're actually
moving um this pattern here
around but what we can do uh
in this case potentially is just um
if you happen to know what 1.0 looks
like in floating point numbers then you
know what it is but if you don't know it
can be tricky so i want to show you a
little trick
so you can figure out what the heck is
going on there if i was to do
this um
what you can see is that this value now
changed
right so that's a way of me
verifying that that number is just the
floating point in coding of 1.0 without
me having to actually go figure out what
the floating point
value of 1.0 actually is in binary right
is i can just twiddle some of these and
see if i'm right
and it turns out you know that i am so
this ox3f8 with the zeros at the end
is just floating point one
and what you can see is that it's doing
a move
so it's copying memory it's saying i
want to
write a constant so an immediate value
this value
and i want to write it to rbx
plus rax right these are two registers
we can infer i haven't even looked but i
can just infer
that rbx is what the base pointer of
matrix so this is what we got from malek
and in fact you can see it happening
right here there's the return value of
malik getting copied into rbx
so that's just the base pointer and then
rax as we already determined is just the
byte offset
of the current matrix we're writing so
you can see we'll do an rbx plus
rax and we're going to do that we're
going to do these writes throughout so
you can see
everything here is like rbx plus rax rb
express so all of our rights
are all just writing to offsets
of the actual matrix we're trying to
write
makes sense like that's what you know
that's what we're doing
um and what you can see here is that the
actual way that this thing works is
completely nuts
it's absolutely bonkers i
never would have thought to try this or
and now that i've seen it tried i have
no idea
why it was tried um and i can't imagine
it's
ever a good way to write this loop but
what's happening is
it's literally moving the one value
so this value one right
it's literally writing the one value
into the first
slot so the first floating point slot of
32 bits four bytes it's writing that
there
with a single 32-bit move so it's just
writing 32 bits or four bytes it's
writing it
here then it is
doing this load so it's doing an xmm
word pointer rsp
plus 32. now what is rsp plus 32 in this
case
well rsp is usually the stack pointer so
that's usually
something that's on the stack and what
is on the stack in this case
well you can see right here that what we
did is we did an xrps
on xmm0 and xrps is
packed single xor it's
i have a whole hour left so i think i'm
okay to just be this explicit
xoring your register with itself clears
it that's because xoring any two values
together that are the same
right so if i have two uh if if my two
operands to xor are equal i get zero
that's because if you do a uh
exclusive or it's baked into the name
exclusive or means it has to be
exclusively
or like it has to be one or the other
and never both the same
so zero one produces one one zero
produces one
but zero zero and one one both produce
zero
that means x or p s of x m m zero with
x100 will produce
zero everywhere even no matter what this
value is can be anything
and this is actually the topic i was
starting out with today which is xor
clears
and we're going to talk about what that
does the problem is the compiler never
used them in the loop anyway
but uh we'll talk about them at the end
because i wanted to
talk about what they were so we'll get
there eventually
so this actually clears xmm0 so xm0 is
just zero
and then what the compiler does is it
moves to the stack rsp
plus 32 plus 16 and plus zero
three copies of zero right
so it's saying all right i want to
store zero to the stack three times
right um and again this is why
i don't really understand like i'm
passing o2 here and i've passed o3
as well as an attempt those are supposed
to be
optimization flags as far as i know
maybe i'm just naive with clang and you
have to say it's something else
um but i don't
really know
i does anyone know
like is there anything i can ask this
thing to do
better than o3 i'll just stop real
briefly and ask chat does anyone know if
clang
does anything more than o3
anybody
because as far as i know that's as
optimal as clang is likely to get i mean
i can give it
like i said i can give it the benefit of
knowing the architecture
is better than the base sse2 but it
doesn't seem to change the code
so as far as i can tell minus o2 is
all it gets right um
like it's this is the code no matter
what i pass
right
so i don't know
so let me finish explaining what it's
doing and i'll go through all the ways
it's absolutely ridiculous and makes no
sense
so what it's doing is clearing this to
zero and storing it three times to the
stack so it's basically creating
three places on the stack where it
stores xmm0
and that xmm0 is basically just clearing
48 bytes right so there's 48 bytes of
zero on the stack starting at rsp
and ending at rs rsp plus 48
right so because each one of these is
storing 16 bytes move aps
is move aligned um for a
16 byte register right
which is xmm so clear a 16 byte register
write it to the stack at three locations
sequentially so we now have
three times 16 or 48 contiguous zero
bytes
set that up and so in here what it's
doing is moving the one value
then it is loading into xmm0
what it stored to the stack which was
zero
and coincidentally it is what xm0 is
so it's loading xmm0 here
in this line even though xmm0 already
is zero so this line does literally
nothing
it's a complete waste of time but it
doesn't anyway
then it stores the zero uh
to the next location so remember it
wrote 4 bytes
now it's going to write 16 zeros here
makes sense then it does the same thing
again
write the one load 0 again
and load it from a different location
even though these are all the same value
it still decided to load it again right
from a different location
as if this were different memory
then it writes it then it writes the one
again
then it does uh another load to load the
final zero value even though the whole
time xmm0 was zero
uh and then it goes ahead and writes
uh the final zeros and the final ones
right does this make sense you see what
i'm saying
i have absolutely no idea why it decided
to do that
someone was saying make it const
it's the compiler already knows that
it's const
right um
nobody else got visibility to this value
so there's no way
like i don't know so if adding const
helps that's just a compiler bug
but i'm pretty sure it won't matter
because again the compiler already knows
that it's const
right um so it just doesn't matter
right i mean that's not relevant um
people always thinks const helps and it
doesn't because the compiler either
knows it's const already
or can't can't count on it anyway
because of constcat so there's
almost never a case where cost affects
optimization it's pretty important
right um so you kind of have to
understand that like
const doesn't usually help optimization
almost ever
right um so you can see that this is
just really bad code and if you really
wanted clang to generate this you would
probably try to do stuff to fool it into
writing better code
because this code is horrible how is
this code horrible well first of all
it doesn't need even if you're going to
do it this way where you write a one
then write four zeros then write a one
then write four zeros and write a one
right none of this code
none of these lines are necessary xmm0
is
already zero it doesn't need to store it
to the stack at all
and it doesn't need to load it from the
stack at all so literally you can just
delete these instructions
they don't do anything right so that's
incredibly bad code and and this is just
a bug in the back end as far as i'm
concerned like that that should never
have happened right um
let's see what would happen if we move
these outside
of the function does it change it at all
so it actually produces better code if
you move it outside
so actually if it if it doesn't know
that it's constant
it produces better code actually
it's still not necessarily fantastic
code but it's a lot better code
right like this is way way better code
in fact this may actually be more or
less optimal
um it's probably as good as the rep mav
sq
that msvc was doing
um so like yeah
moving those outside helps a ton um
but i'm not done talking about this so
i'm going to leave them
on the inside for now um because i want
to finish talking about this so
obviously hopefully everyone understands
why these instructions are ridiculous
they're because it's loading zero off of
three locations of stack even though it
was already zero
and doesn't need to be loaded at all so
even if
you wouldn't even have to replace these
lines with uh sorry replace these lines
with xor ps
because you already cleared it it's
already clear so you don't even need an
xrps here you can literally just delete
these lines completely they don't do
anything
but even if you deleted those lines
this code is still not very good and the
reason it's not very good is because if
we look at what's happening with that
code
what we can see is that it's executing
so skip
skip the mav aps let's assume that we
got rid of those and the compiler wasn't
quite as dumb
as it is so suppose it just did the mav
and the mafia ups is so that's one two
three four five six seven
right so it's requiring seven
instructions
to move 64 bytes right
seven instructions to move 64 bytes
how many instructions should it take
right how many instructions should it
take to move 64 bytes
well if we assume that we're only on an
sse capable computer so we don't have
avx
then if we wanted to use move ups for
example which is the largest move
available on an sse target machine
move ups moves 16 bytes so to
write 64 bytes to memory we should
require four
instructions four move ups if we just
did
four move ups we would write the entire
thing
but because it chose to write the one
as an actual separate scalar move
we're creating seven instructions where
four would have been sufficient
scalar moves and wide moves
happen on the same ports
ports for memory ops are
not dependent on whether they're scalar
or not
in skylake so if we pop back to our uaps
table
we can see just how bad this is
so let's go ahead and take a look at
imav and what you can see
is that if you look at everything that's
written here
all of the mob stuff that we care about
is where is the mob that we care
about
oh right it never mind uh so one of the
interesting i was
looking for the r64 this is actually a
32-bit mob right the art the
uh it's gonna be a move quad word if
it's not so i've got that there's a
little brain front my part
so this is the part we're talking about
here right oops
i take that back
where is it where's the immediate move
so this is a move immediate to a memory
location right
it's
so i don't know where it is it may be
that it's
named differently in here
it may be because these are only
micro-ops so it's actually gonna do
a different one of these
but i don't see any immediates in here
so why can't i get the immediates in
here
what am i missing do i need to tell it
something else
because it should be in the base
instruction set and there should be a
mod for an immediate
but it doesn't look like there is
so this may be above my pay grade of why
the ups info table doesn't have
mauve on there
as moth these will be um
these are all on here where's my ssa
there it is
so these are easy to understand you can
see and the scalar move is the same so
port tooth to ports two
and three um are the ports on which
this can happen so when you are doing a
right
uh you can see that like if you're
trying to do
a move from a register to memory
or uh from reddit for from a register to
memory or from memory to a register
you can actually see uh what's required
by looking at the uh by looking at the
um
port usage here what these are i can't
say that i know
oh i know what these are so this must be
the nomenclature they give to
so okay you can see a register to
register move is free because it happens
in the rename
so these are probably just what the
names they gave to those front-end
micro-ops
i've never seen that before so i didn't
know these had a name but it looks like
these
are synthetic things at the upset info
people i don't know if these are
standardized
but these must be synthetic things they
gave to
um to basically say look
this is what the um
this is what we're calling the micro up
that
renames and it's weird to call it a
micro up but
it basically says if i have two
registers and i want to copy one to
another
that's never actually doing an operation
it's just renaming
that value by giving it a new name so so
then now that value has two names
in the front end rather than one right
in the register allocation table
um so that's probably what these
nomenclatures are we haven't really
gotten to the rat yet but
we'll get there eventually um so these
here are the two move ups this one is
moving a register into memory this one
is
is moving um a
uh memory into a register so this is
like a load
right and this is like a store if that
makes sense
um as you can see here the breakdown of
ports uh
you can see that port four is necessary
for
storing um and then ports two three or
seven can all be used for uh
for address generation so the thing that
actually determines like where this
thing's gonna get stored
that looks like what it's trying to say
here um and unfortunately i can't seem
to load that out of this one and i
don't know why um
i i don't really know why that is i
should be able to find
uh this here i mean this is sort of like
what it looks like right i mean this is
uh a move from a register to memory so
you can see it's the same exact
breakdown as as the mav here so it's
like
writing to memory looks basically
exactly the same but i'm not sure i've
never really looked up the mobs in this
upset info table and
i have to admit it throws me for a
little bit of loop these look like
exactly what i would expect except that
i didn't know that they gave names to
these
this doesn't and i'm not so i'm not sure
why
it seems so limited there and and
you know i would have expected to see
other permutations of moths and and
there might be a reason for that
it might be that there's like some kind
of a different name that they give those
and so you don't look them up by the
actual assembly language mnemonic
you look it up by uh something else um
and we can look in the intel and turns
this guide i'm not the intelligent chat
the um
intel programmers manual to see um what
it actually says
because it might uh guide us
a little bit better there so if i go
ahead and pull this up
and we look at mauve and here we can see
um
if there's yeah but i mean even just
looking at
at this right like i was expecting to
see mav q
in there as well right and you know i
typed in
um mav and and it doesn't even have mob
q
in there which which doesn't make a
whole lot of sense um to me i guess i
guess because it's only in ssc so that's
fine
um so maybe that's
uh part of it let's see here
no it's just not there well at least mob
q is there
i don't know um so let's say we look at
mob q
right um if we look at mavq that's a
64-bit write
um sorry 64-bit load from register to
register
right and so here's one that's like
writing 64-bits to memory
uh and you can see that's the exact same
thing same port usage
so i don't know why ups is weird there
if somebody else knows why
uh it doesn't have like here's here's
mob for example
here's all the permutations of mauve
there's like a ton of them
right you can see how many mobs there
are there's like infinite mobs
uh and i don't know why like here's a
mob for example
uh that didn't show up in the uops table
there right i mean
so i just don't know i i couldn't say uh
it might be just because they figure
well
we didn't want to list them all and and
we know that it's it's basically just
gonna be the same
uh port breakdown as this one is so just
use that one i don't know uh somebody
who works on upside info maybe can clue
us in on what's going on there
all of that i apologize for wasting so
much time on that but all of that was
just to say
mob and mob aps and mob ups
they're all banging on the same ports
right so it doesn't
benefit you at all to insert
32-bit moves in the middle of your
64-bit moves
there's no reason to do so
what's the problem oh the orange look at
chat okay re-say what the chat is
oh was the whole time there was another
page are you kidding me right now
where's the where's the oh it's behind
my head
i don't feel like that's the owl of
shame i couldn't see it it was behind my
head
no all right
thank god i thought i was losing my mind
i'm like what is going on
all right thank you chat
thank god all right so this is what i
was expecting to see
i'm like god i even thought in my head
i'm like haven't i ever looked at this
in your feeling like maybe i haven't
because it's just kind of obvious so i
wouldn't bother
i mean i don't know okay thank god so
finally here's this is what i wanted
this these are what i wanted so this is
moving amer
um uh immediate 32-bit immediate
to a memory location right
so we can find that one on here
uh and and this this is it right this is
oh no sorry uh this is
it right here right
32-bit immediate moves to a 30-bit
memory location
and you can see that the ports are 237
plus 1p4
right so it's going to take two
micro-apps one is p37 i believe that
first micro up is the address generation
so basically what that is
is this thing it's taking this rbx plus
rax and turning it into an
actual like location that it's going to
write to right
uh and then the one times p4 p4 is the
right port so that's the execution port
that actually
like once you have an address and you
have a value it's going to put it out
there
right makes sense um
so just so you know that's that's what's
actually
going on there right okay whoo
i'm glad i wasn't crazy because i'm like
what the heck i'm like where's all the
mobs there's so many of them
um all right so as you can see
this is all gonna hammer on the exact
same port so this is just a disaster
this loop is crazy slow for no reason um
it should just be four move ups's
because all it really needs to do is
have xmm0
one two and three have one zero zero
zero one zero zero zero zero one zero
and zero zero zero
one and just right right right right
right right right right
right right right right right so if we
want to help
out clang and say hey clang i know
it's been a bad day right
uh in fact i guess i'll just do it this
way to avoid confusion
um i'm just gonna say look
let's help you out here let's tell you
what is going on because you obviously
don't know and are very confused
about the world um let's create
three explicit register values that you
can use
like so um and then let's tell you
how to actually do your job so let's do
a well you know what i'll just put a
little if zero in here
so we'll get rid of this right
like so
and i'm just gonna try to store
the rows myself
right so you can see me trying to store
one row there
and i just want to store all four rows
like so
um and here is the new code that base
says all right i'm gonna generate
hopefully four registers xm0123 or
something right
each register will be set to one row of
the matrix and i believe
set rps is the way that you say that you
want to go in memory order
um let me just make sure that's true
before i lead everyone down a bum path
there
oh no it's not okay so it is normally
memory order is that right
i almost never use these functions
directly i always
have them like written in my own version
so no that's not it so set ps
oh no it is it is because they're in
opposite order
in the parameters so yeah it's set rps
if we want them in memory order which
which is what i wanted
um so here's them set uh to the various
rows of the matrix so we're not going to
use this we're just going to set these
up directly so the compiler understands
what they are uh and then we've got uh
this
storing here we're going to store each
row of the matrix
as as written right and then i'm going
to see
if that helps this thing out at all i
don't know if it will or if it won't but
we'll see
um and lo and behold yes it does uh so
if you look at what actually happens
with this piece of code it actually has
produced
exactly the right code now and if you're
wondering why
there's eight stores instead of four
it's because it chose to unroll this
loop
one time why it chose to enroll this
loop one time
um hmm
i don't know why it chose to enroll the
loop that may be because it's thinking
of a broad set of architectures so
when you issue
because this is free so the sub comp
jump is gonna snuggle up in here
and just be executed in parallel with
this
there's no way to issue four stores per
cycle you can only issue
two stores per cycle at most so
the fact that this is dependent the sub
comp jump
it should just nestle correctly where it
will do
if you had just had four it would do the
sub with the first one
and the comp with the next one and then
it would go to the next part of the loop
i don't actually know if there would be
any value at all to unrolling this loop
i can't
say that i would expect her to be so why
the heuristics
told it to do that it may be because
it's thinking about more architectures
than i
am so it's like broader it certainly
can't
hurt it's not really like gonna ruin
anything
that it chose to do that um
so like
i yeah i mean i wish i had an
explanation here
for that but but i but i i don't um
i i really don't know and you can see
that there's issues that it's created so
the fact that it chose to do
this means it had to do a little bit
more fancy footwork here than if it had
just done
what i told it to do and i think what i
told to do is honestly still better so i
still think clang is kind of
um wearing a slight dance cap here but i
don't know like me there may be some
reason to unroll this so i'm not going
to say i'm not going to criticize it
because maybe that's actually smart on
some architectures and so on like maybe
that's a good thing
so but point being now you can see we've
got it much cleaner this is
probably twice as fast as the other loop
was because rather than doing seven
instructions
it's doing four instructions per matrix
four instructions per matrix is almost
twice as fast as seven instructions for
matrix that's just kind of how that goes
so there you go
yeah and anyone who thinks that like the
o3 help it didn't we can put o3 on now
to see if it changes but it it didn't
seem to change at all what we were doing
uh we can leave it on though there's no
reason to have it not on there but it
basically does the same thing
so that's at least sane and
this is also why um
i tend to write things out explicitly as
often as i can
because compilers just aren't very good
a lot of people think compilers are
smarter than they are
they're not um that argument's been had
on twitter before
and the people who say the compiler
smarter than a programmer
must be talking about other programmers
because i come across this sort of thing
all the time and that previous loop i
will absolutely stake my reputation on
using seven cycles
to set 64 bytes is just plain dumb
um again i am no optimization god
and you shouldn't take my word for
anything optimization related but
that one is pretty blatant and i will be
shocked if someone
can point to me to something that
suggests that doing
that seven cycle sequence was better
than doing four mod
ups's i will be very shocked
anyway um getting back to
what was happening here if we switch
back to the other version really quickly
um i wanted to point out briefly what
msvc was doing here and why i thought
this was
particularly cool um so basically
there's a thing built into intel
processors called the rep instruction
and it's kind of a really neat
instruction it basically says
hey i'm going to be doing a dumb simple
loop
either i'm going to write the same thing
a lot or i'm going to copy the same
thing a lot
why don't you just do that for me and
one of the nice things that's happened
is as the intel processors have gotten
more advanced their ability to do
high performance reps has gone up
so nowadays calling a rep instruction is
actually
really really fast and you know that
you're going to get
really good throughput on it because it
will be smart and use
large block moves where it can so
actually even though this kind of looks
like stupider code it's just calling
some processor instruction rep and
sometimes rep gets a bad name on modern
like skylight cores actually rep
is a pretty darn good instruction and so
if we look at the ups dot info for
rap for example
um here is
this is an uh sq right
so
i don't know i don't know how to ask i
i've never looked up this on
uh
i've never looked up a rep move
so i'm not sure which one this would be
closest
um
because i'm not sure which of these
would map to a rep mavs cue this is just
my naivete with rep mods
um let's pick one
uh let's this would just be the bite one
probably right
um so if you take a look here uh
at doing this on skylake
here you can see um so you can see like
the cost
of the ports and it's pretty confusing
confusing
right um because the problem is it's a
loop
so it's pretty hard to determine like
what the heck is going on
in here when you look at the actual port
usage of it it's just like well it's
going to use one on this gonna use 16 on
this gonna use two on this 22 like
this is just you know i don't know right
um but in terms of the actual cost of
the uops
um for a given size
where the size gets put the way that you
use this instruction is you put the size
in one register
and like the value you want to move
another register or you set up pointers
and so on
when you actually do this rep
instruction here
it actually is very fast per loop it
basically will do the equivalent
most of the time on a modern core at
least as far as i know
of what i did so this rep mob sq will
actually use
the two ports to actually do two stores
per cycle
um as far as i know right
um and so this is actually probably way
better code than clang generated
when we didn't help it once we help
clang and we get here
i think these two would be about
equivalent but again
hard to say you'd have to time them and
find out
all right so finally let's get back to
the thing we actually wanted to know
so after all that i hope you understand
this assembly at least a little bit
what i want to do now is i want to try
to actually
determine what will happen
if we now do some kind of say dependent
clear so let's say we stop doing things
the way that it was done before because
none of this stuff is good and this is
by the way why i was trying to on
twitter tell
jesse to not do things the way he was
doing it is because when i saw the
assembly language code that he posted i
was like clang
is doing garbage here so i was trying to
say and i thought it was just because he
was complying with
with minus og but actually now that
we've looked at it compiled with o
three it's just clang is just bad at
this it's just it's just producing bum
code
so you don't want to do timings with bum
code you got to look and see if the
compiler generated something usable to
begin with before you actually time it
because
that code that clang generated was so
bad
that it's not a fair comparison of what
would happen if you clear registers of
course clearing the registers will
probably be free
because clan created a loop that's so
slow that you won't notice
right so yes clearing registers
happens to be free but that was not a
fair test of it right
um so anyway that's what i was trying to
say hopefully
um that's what you get right
um so anyway oh someone wants me to try
one more set of composers so before i
get rid of it we'll just try one more to
see if it
creates anything you wanted march
skylake so it knows it's using a skylake
architecture
and fast math yeah
i mean trust me this doesn't look like
any kind of thing that has to do with
any of that it's just super confused
right
and so really the thing that's confusing
it is that
for some reason the fact that this is on
the stack i guess
confuses it because moving these to
actually
to actual stored data it suddenly knows
more what to do oops
what just happened okay there we go
moving it outside it suddenly knows what
to do
right um this is again just an unrolled
version
of this loop that's not horrible right
um
it's not good uh but it's not horrible
right um
actually it's kind of horrible never
mind it just doesn't know clanks clang
sucks at this
let's just let's just stop talking about
switches clang sucks at this you
shouldn't have to set any switches
other than optimize to get this to work
properly the compiler has
all the information it needs it does not
need const here and even if we said it
didn't help anyway
it does not need to be static this is
obvious the compiler should be able to
figure it out and it doesn't that's
pretty much period
we're done playing with switches
okay
no you can you cannot leave it inside
and set it to static
if you leave it inside and set it to
stab set it to static
right you're gonna get uh
initialization garbage in there right i
mean maybe
you can
uh but i would i would worry right in
this particular case it
oh my god
what the heck did it do
that's even nuts
yeah don't do that holy cow
that's horrible
all right clang is nuts okay
just just it's nuts you got to write the
code yourself
that's what we did just stop telling me
switches
switches if if the compiler was any good
you wouldn't have to know what switches
to get it to output an obvious
copy from register right so it's got a
lot of issues
like i said this is what i find a lot of
times like a pile of clang
msvc output something sane clang output
something ridiculous
and i have to handhold it like this
that's just what i see a lot of the time
and that's what we saw here
your mileage may vary moving on
so let's suppose that we actually want
to do what we were talking about at the
beginning which is we want to have some
way
of doing a uh potential clear
so we want to see what happens if it
costs us anything in the kind of case
that involves clearing registers so in
here let's suppose we move these
uh into place and so we've got a thing
where we set them up
and then we write them out right and so
in here we've got the same loop right
this is fine it's unrolled for no
reason whatsoever but it's you know it's
fine it's not ridiculous
but now what i want to do is i want to
say look
uh if every so often
like maybe if
let's see um maybe we introduce
and um
[Music]
maybe i try to do something like this so
i say look if index
equals run
um then it's this and if it's not it's
going to be zero
and all i'm trying to do here is
simulate the case where we have
something to test
where we set the
matrix to the identity sometimes but we
set it to zero
other times right
so in this case sorry i'm not very good
with this web editor so i'm kind of like
ham-fisted when i'm editing things
because it's not
you know my normal editor config or
whatever but i'm working on it
i'm getting there right
um so let's say we have something like
this and we take a look
at what we end up with in here uh when
we ask
clang to do optimizations on this thing
so here we're saying is look we're going
to set these to zero and then sometimes
right we're going to
set it to the identity and either way
we're writing a matrix but sometimes
we're going to write the zero matrix
in fact most of the time and other times
we're going to write
uh you know
i didn't mean to do that i guess i just
saved a copy of that somewhere
so anyway um taking a look at what goes
on in this particular piece of code you
can see
in here if we want to look at uh the
the stuff that it did here um
it looks like it went again ahead and
kind of went
into uh a rather absurd way of
of breaking this down i'm wondering if
we try to do is outsmart us because you
can see these
let me see if i can make it even harder
for it
um in this case so
i'm trying to think of a way to make
this something the compiler doesn't
understand
uh you know what's a good way to do that
here so now we just have a function foo
right
and i'm going to make it read out of
this control structure so that the
compiler doesn't know
at all uh what it has to do
right so it has no idea
whether it's going to do one or the
other and we'll see
what it actually outputs here right
so if you take a look at what it
generated for the loop
um here's us doing the right
here's us doing the um
add so we're moving forwards right
here's us doing the comp
and the jump and we jump back to 11
which is here
and then what we do is we kind of do
like jumps around
uh kind of nonsense wise so here's us
oh wait no that's jumping out so
[Music]
this is the part so we fall through here
we jump to two
we do a test of
this we do the xors
if necessary otherwise we jump
to and then we jump to three no we just
jump
based on the comp so we xor our sum
we jump based on the com what what is
the point of this
look at how many jumps this thing
inserted in here
what did what did msvc do
hold on a second if i see if msvc is at
all sane so here's the comp
here's the uh
zero clear right here is the jump
over the yeah so like once again
like once again visual studio does like
exactly the right code
and clang is a friggin nightmare
i don't know why i can't imagine having
this many jumps in here could ever be
good
for anything they're conditional jumps
so these go through the branch predictor
even
um
yeah i mean
i mean that's that's the loop
right it's perfect it's exactly what you
want you comp
clear jump if you're not going to
overwrite
copy um
it's exactly right so msvc
output the exact right loop clang output
an absolute monstrosity i
can't imagine that's ever faster let's
see if o2
was more sane it's not
what is going on um
i just don't know why you'd ever want
any of this
this just looks like massive branch
prediction nightmare
right
so
i want to say and i could be wrong about
this
i want to say that there's some really
really really bad aspects to this code
so
looking at this code i could be wrong
about this
but this looks like code that is
absolutely abhorrently bad
and maybe this is again just my naivete
with optimization but when i look at
this code the first thing
pun intended that jumps out at me
is that if i'm not mistaken at least
on zen 2 which is like one of the
highest performance cpus
currently in existence if you have
multiple jumps per 64 byte block of code
every jump past the second jump becomes
worse so like if this is probably
like 164 byte block of code
and there's like one two three four five
six jumps in it right
um one of them is a straight up jump but
so maybe that doesn't matter but these
are all conditional jumps
so that many conditional jumps in 164
byte block is an absolute nightmare for
the branch predictor i think
i mean i could be wrong about that but
that just seems
really bad really really really not good
now
again some optimization like if agner
fogs up
on here and wants to tell me that that's
not true
that would be cool but this just looks
like garbage
this looks like exactly the right code
to me um
and so what you can see here is what i
finally wanted to
get to um and
it's not quite exactly what i wanted
because i wanted xor ps
for an xor clear but these are actually
functionally the same thing
so we can talk about that and this is
what i actually wanted to get to
by the end of the show and hey
thankfully we did get to it by the end
of the show
so let's finally talk about exo or
clears
um oh and someone mentioned there's a
there's a tuning parameter for
zen so let's see if it knows about that
nope i mean it looks a little better
but it's still outputting a heck of a
lot of jumps
i think it may have improved slightly
but i don't know
yeah i don't know real bad code
um so yeah
not great and uh and like i said i do
feel like
my experience with clang is it outputs
really stupid code a lot of the time
but like i said before i also find that
in certain places where it really counts
like in really intrinsic heavy like
crazy math code
i feel like when i've done clan compiles
it actually
produces the faster code and so i do
think they're
important things clang does that often
times you run it on your whole code base
you actually get a win
from clang but it's like i don't know
why
um i don't know why it's doing these
stupid things
it don't seem right um anyway
so let's talk about this because this is
the code i actually want to talk about
and this looks about right to me
so what's happening in this loop is it's
doing a comp on the control
right that's just seeing whether or not
it needs to write an identity or a zero
it has mob aps's to move xmm0 into one
two
three and four xm0 is just the zero
value you can see that it was cleared up
here
so that's just setting these all to zero
then it's going to just jump over the
actual load of the identity matrix so
this will load the identity matrix
in then it does the same set of mobs
one two three and four out to the matrix
right and advances again
exactly what we want this looks great
right and so now let's get to the part
that i was trying to explain before
which is why i was saying usually
clearing to xero
is free and in this case you can see why
it's free
because this piece of code right
doesn't do anything
mob aps xmm1 xmm0 here
is actually not going to ever go to an
execution port at all
it's just going to rename the value that
was in
xmm0 to also be the value that's in xmm1
modern processors don't have registers
the way that
that old school processors did when we
say that there's xmm0 through xmm7
or something there aren't actually
eight physical registers in the cpu
each holding 16 bytes that's not what
happens there actually is
is a much larger register table
with lots of 16 byte spaces
in it for values and then
there are eight tags
xmm0 through xmm7 that can tag
those values so all that's happening
whenever you see a register to register
move
is it's just taking the tag for xmm1
and attaching it to the value that is
xmm0 so that now that value
is tagged as both xm0 and xmm1
so anyone who reads from xmm0 or xm1 in
the future will get the same value out
of that table
right it doesn't ever actually copy it
to the best of my knowledge
right
so what happens is all of these the
only cost that you pay for them at all
is just the decode code space
cost right so those instructions still
have to move through the front end
like they do take up some time to decode
in the first place but for a loop it's
all in the hot cache anyway it's
probably actually in the loop cache
anyway so these are effectively free
they take
no execution ports whatsoever they only
take front end time
so the only time you could ever
ever pay for a mob
aps or equivalently in xrps is the same
thing
it's just re-tagging a location as zero
basically
it's processed in the front end um
any the only time you can ever pay for
those
in an actual uh execution cost
is two cases that i know of
one is when you are actually decode
bound so like the front end
is actually the thing that is stalling
your routine in our case we know that's
not possible
how do we know because we know we only
have
two possible stores we can do per cycle
there's no way on anything on skylake
that i've ever heard of that can ever
store more than
two uh stores per cycle
so if you can only do two stores per
cycle at an absolute maximum
um i wanna say i think you can i don't
even know if you can do
two you may only be able to do one um
store per cycle on skylake
we should look that up but point being i
i think you maybe do two reads and one
right
i don't know if you can do two writes
you can definitely do two reads
per cycle but
but rights i think is only one
don't quote me on that but but that's my
feeling is that you can only actually do
one right per cycle maybe
either way it's either one or two
depending whether it's reads or writes
and depending on whether my memory is
bad or good
um but the front end can process four
cycles at a time
uh four instructions at a time right and
since mob aps is not a complex
instruction it doesn't generate like
lots and lots of u-ops or anything
there's no chance that we're going to be
stalled on decoding
anything there's going to be lots of
spare decoder bandwidth here
because we're simply going to be mostly
waiting around for the store port to
become available
because chances are we're only going to
be issuing like one store
or two stores per cycle and if we're
doing two stores per cycle
then we actually have two spare
instructions
that we can issue every cycle in that
shadow
that we you know it doesn't matter so
the front end
we're not counting on the front end
pushing five
or six if they're fused i'm sorry
four or five if they're fused ops
through
uh to the execution ports because the
execution ports are what we're going to
be bound on
right um and you'll forgive me for not
remembering whether one or two but we
can look it up
chad is saying maybe someone looked up
skylake and it's only one so i'm not
wrong in remembering that it's two reads
and one right i guess
i guess but i might wrong either way
it's definitely not more than two
as far as memory ops it's either two
reads and one right or two reads and two
writes but i'm pretty sure it's like two
reads and one right
and that would the fact that when we
looked it up on us.info it said port
four
it didn't say like port four and
something else so if you could do two
per cycle it should have said
port like three and four right um so i'm
pretty sure that it basically is like
you know
reads on ports two and three and writes
on port four or something right so you
can only
you only have one port for rights you
know what i'm saying
anyway
so these are effectively free in almost
everything you do
and the reason for that is because it's
so cheap to rename
things compared to everything else
you're doing that you have to have
gotten down to like an incredibly
highly optimized really well working
system before they actually pay for them
now there is one other case where they
could have an effect
and that's code size or
like if the alignment is slightly
different there's all these weird like
edge cases you can hit
so i don't want to say that like
inserting mob aps is into something that
moved from registered register
never affects the performance because
sometimes it actually can in a weird way
but that's true of every instruction
that you could do
so that's kind of not something you
actually are talking about when you're
talking about how much does it generally
cost to do a thing because that's like
finicky stuff that may have nothing to
do with
like what the actual cost of doing thing
so mob aps and export rps in these ways
where you just use
an xrps to clear a register or use mob
aps to move one register to another
register
you're not paying for that it's not
actually
bit work being done by the processor in
the back end on an execution port it's
actually just happening in the register
allocation table and all you're doing is
renaming something you're either
uh or clearing like you're either saying
oh there's no value in here anymore it's
zero
or you're saying this value that
previously existed
is now also called some other register
name right
and so that's why i say for zii patterns
clearing to zero is almost always free
you really don't have to do this
this is what you do when you don't zii
right
when you say oh i'm i'm i'm optimizing
my code
right by doing this
so that
actually that that's not what i meant to
do
you know people will often be like oh
i'm optimizing my code
by doing this but you're not optimizing
your code by doing this
right um this doesn't actually
do anything other than introduce
a potentially unnecessary uh
operation into the code depending on how
complicated the code gets
in this particular case the code's so
simple that basically these two things
will
will evaluate to effectively the same
thing right
um oh no you know it's worse
there's an extra jump so i'm right even
in this case it's it's true
i was assuming they could probably smart
enough not to do that uh but it looks
like it's not
so what you can see here is actually
this just introduced an extra jump now
it's not definitely worse code
necessarily because this jump is
probably free because it's not
conditional
so the front end's just going to eat it
and it's probably fine
right so this is probably not necessary
um
necessary to worry about but what you
can see is you basically just ended up
with exactly the same code anyway
these are just clears so they don't cost
you anything
these are the things that you are now
doing a jump around right so it
reorganize the code slightly but it's
basically the exact same thing
so you haven't ended up with more
optimal code at all
it's either the same code or if
something was going on here that was
more complicated the compiler may not
have been able to figure
out exactly what it should have done and
it actually would have just gotten worse
right so this
is like an old way of thinking about
things when you think about
having to do this you're kind of
thinking about stuff
that's like a decade old or more right
this didn't change this is a better way
to write this code
is to just not do that right is to get
rid of this
and just always clear to zero because
there's a no reason
to actually make the compiler think
about
going down two different branches
because you really only ever have
one thing you might need to do if you
can start with zero that's just a way
to have the front end eat the clear for
free
so you don't pay for it and then you
have one branch to avoid
overwriting your cleared values but
that's all you actually
need to do right now this actually gets
a little more complicated because you
can actually make this
even more free than that so you can
write this
in a way that's actually branchless if
you want to
um and you can see like for example
just to finish off this is actually just
a value we could just use
right um so if we wanted to we could
actually just have a blend here
where we actually never do an if so if
we can
if we're concerned about the branch
predictor getting
confused about this we can actually just
eliminate it entirely and so this is yet
another reason why clear to zero is
often
pretty reasonable to do because
oftentimes what you're actually going to
do
in here is you're actually going to do
something
more like this so like
this is a totally common pattern that
you might see right
where i'm i'm now going to do
effectively exactly the same code
i think i have to tell it now that we
have uh sse4
does this is it sse4 sss e4
there's weird what's the name of that
thing
how do i get is it is it just sorry is
it just blend
i may need to tell it sometimes there's
it's this kind of nonsense
what is the what is the actual thing
that needs to be on here
you know what forget it
i'll just do it old school
so suppose i want to write this thing
out and i want to just make it dependent
what i can do is just do it
by like doing an and not right so
suppose i just make
a macro here that's for blending so i
don't have to type it four times
and i just want to blend this based on a
value that i load out of the control so
what i want to do is i'm doing the same
exact loop
loop i want to take this control um
value here and what i want to do is just
use that control value
as a mask right so let's suppose
that i just have uh a set of masks in
here
maybe these uh i want them to actually
be like set up properly i mean i don't
know you probably want to would do an
expansion here but just to make keep the
code as simple as possible
let's say we're loading the mask out of
here um
rather than lofting it up although we
can we can show how to do the control
i'm trying to keep it simple because
we're at the end of the
time period here but um so let's say we
do a blend here
and so we're going to do a blend of zero
and if the mask is true we're gonna use
uh this secondary value here right so
then what i do is just say okay let's
take blend and maybe i can
uh help fix this here
so here's my various
options that i have
and what you can see here is i'm going
to load out a control word here
and that control word is going to i'm
going to say is pre-expanded so i don't
have to do it but we'll
actually do the expansion if we have
time in a second
um so that it can still come from a care
and then what i'm going to do
is i'm just going to find a blend macro
here um
where we basically say look i've got an
a and a b and a mask value
and what i want to do is i want to
combine the two so what i want to do
here
is i want to basically uh or these two
together
um there is an actual blend command but
it only got introduced
in like sse4 um so
i'm not calling the the blend directly
because of that
uh that's the only reason so
uh if i want to bore these two together
i'm going to or
together an and and an and
not and it doesn't actually matter
which one's which in this case uh let's
just say we're gonna and with
m and and not with uh
with the other one i always have to look
up and not because i always forget
which uh one gets knotted in the intel
syntax
so i always look it up and see which one
it is so compute the bitwise not
of practice a so the first parameter
is the one that actually gets knotted
right so the m
comes first which is what i did so i
happened to guess right that time but i
usually have to look
so uh in this case i think i'm gonna say
i think i said
a is the one that happens if the knot is
false so i'm gonna i'm gonna switch it
that way so we not the mask for a
and then we use the mask for b there's
our
uh blend instruction so what that does
is just takes the mask and picks a or b
based on whether the mask is pop is ones
or zeros right
so now what we can do is we can take a
look at the code that's generated and
i'm going to just look
at the code on the msvc side because it
tends to be the one that's
less ridiculous um and so let's take a
look at where
this code ended up right so here's us
moving the control
word in um
i'll be honest i don't really know why
it's bothering to do
these rx rcx loads
from
[Music]
i'm not i have to stop and decrypt that
my assembly language reading skills are
not fast enough to know exactly why
those lease are there
um
because it looks like so it looks like
it's just using
it looks like it's just using those as a
way to advance the pointers
which i guess anyway let's not care
about that let's just ignore that right
now
um so what this is doing here right
because that's load effective address
so yeah just ignore those two for now
because those are
those are you like working with the
pointers so let's just look at what we
did with the ups so
first what we do here right is we load
in
excuse me we load in the control word
that's coming from rcx right uh we then
basically take xmm3 which presumably is
prepped
uh somewhere here yeah so we take xmm3
which is prepped with one
right um and we we load that into zero
we then and uh
we then and that which is exactly what
we would expect to do
we then move this as i assume is zero we
move that into here so again these two
are both free
now we then and it
uh with two we do all of the ands with
two
actually uh and then we do
oh so wow
actually if you look at what this
generated it was smart enough to know
that it didn't have to do the blend with
zero
right so it's not ever even doing the or
because it's just smart enough to know
that
so let's since we were just doing this
as a test let's just
make sure that you can see the whole
code path
this way it has to actually do something
that was pretty cool though right good
job msvc
noticed that as an or was zero but there
now you can see the ors
so it's just going to load those in and
by load it's actually just renaming the
registers which is great
so it's it's really costing us nothing
it's just doing an
and an or and or and or and or
right it's just doing ands and ors
and there's those and knots as well
right
um there should be
more of them than that shouldn't there
no there shouldn't because these are all
the same value
the compiler is so quick isn't it
it's it's really doing a good job with
the sub expression elimination there
right
so the oh you know what i'll do
here we go
there you go so here you can see um
the full case where it has to do it and
and
and not and an or for each one now again
this may
look like a lot of code right because
it looks like a lot more code than the
other one which just had one you know
four and then a branch and four
but what you have to remember is that
this now has
no branches at all this entire loop
executes branch free and all of these
things
execute together or an and
are simple one cycle instructions for
which there are many ports three
ports at least most of the time
um and so all of this stuff will overlap
so actually when you actually profile
this this routine may be
way faster than the other one depending
on the circumstances
because now there can never be a
mispredicted branch so whether this
routine or the other one was faster
would depend on
how random the control word was
basically right now again we can also
amplify the control word if we only want
to
load one byte out we can always do a
load and a shuff
to like blow that out um but there you
go
okay so i think i covered everything i
wanted to cover
let's go to a quick q a if anyone has
any questions
and this is jesse whose uh original post
on twitter motivated this
he says thank you so much for taking the
time to explain and demonstrate this on
handmade hero deep appreciated
my pleasure thank you for taking um it
seriously
like of everything i saw on that twitter
thread which is mostly just people
making stuff up that they didn't know
about you actually took the time to
write some actual code and learn from it
and that is like so important
so that that was why i did this because
i was like somebody actually cares
rather than just saying stuff on twitter
and when somebody actually
cares that is the person
that deserves to have their concerns
like legitimated and explored so
thank you for taking it seriously and
posting on twitter and i'm
glad that you found this useful if you
found it useful
uh so yeah
and yeah the lea so load effective
address there's just
so because i don't really do much
assembly language programming except
with um simdi
a lot of the vagaries of x64 or x86 for
that matter assembly language like using
load effective address to do
arithmetic and stuff are lost on me
because i never write that code really
right i'm usually just trying to look at
how to make sure this sort of stuff
works out okay
so i have a pretty good understanding of
how to make sure
all of the um cmd unit stuff lines up
properly
but like the cool tricks and stuff
that's like using load effective address
to do point arithmetic
faster than maybe you could do it with
something else i just
don't understand that stuff i'm sure
it's not that complicated if you went
and looked it's probably not that hard
to learn
but i've never done it and so i don't
feel comfortable
explaining anything that may actually be
slower than doing the equivalent now and
it may be kind of antiquated that it's
doing that
or maybe that's still the best way to do
it i have no idea so i
you know someone else will have to talk
about that
i compiled the code with icc the intel
compiler with o2 and it takes
3.5 seconds to run it is it really bad
um well it depends on what the platform
is i don't know and
again like i don't uh i don't really
have
a feel for how fast this thing should go
yet because we haven't tried test
running it or anything
i will say that the memory bandwidth on
your machine will make a big difference
because this is going to be out of the
cache so
if you look at how many bytes that is
this is the
total number of bytes right so it's six
four zero zero zero zero zero zero
is the number of bytes that it's going
to have to write if we did that
correctly
so if you take a look at the cache size
or typical cache size that you might
find in one of these processors
um you're going to find that like 256k
is like a typical l2 cache size for
example
um and so this is like way more
times than the cache is covered so
you're looking at l3
or main memory bandwidth most of the
time that's actually going to be
a big bottleneck so one of the reasons
that
if we were actually going to move into
like actually talking about this and
testing this
in a real scenario rather than just
talking about
what's happening in the registers as a
for educational purposes we would have
to acknowledge the fact that the amount
of memory that this thing is working
with at a time
will make it very difficult to assess
differences in the routine in the first
place because there's so much
memory getting moo touched here that the
cpu's memory bandwidth will really be
the bottleneck because
remember when i said it can do two
stores per cycle that's two stores to
the l1
or the l2 uh there's no way it's going
to get two stores per cycle to main
memory
because main memory isn't fast enough
for that right
um so you have to keep in mind the
the performance overhead of stores is
one cycle to l1 and 14 cycles to l2
typically
so depending on exactly what you're
doing you may be able to get
l1 or l2 bandwidth which may end up
equating to
something like two stores per i'm sorry
one store per cycle
uh sorry if i said two store circle one
store per cycle to l1
um you're not going to get you're gonna
get one store every 14
cycles uh to l2 and
you're going to get one store very
much less frequently than that if you
have to go l3 to
mem or main memory right so
the fact that we're doing such a huge
chunk of this thing
this is not indicative of how you're
usually using clear to zero
normally you're talking about something
local that you're about to use like i'm
initializing like an entity or something
and those are the cases where clear to
zero is completely free usually because
you're about to use it anyway
and you can go as fast as
l1 goes because you're all in the l1
doing stuff in the l1
when you're talking about giant clears
or giant writes
usually it doesn't matter what you do
because memory bandwidth is so slow you
can do several instructions that are
irrelevant and don't matter even the
branch misprediction penalty
probably doesn't matter because it's on
the order of 20 cycles
and main memory bandwidth is on the
order of like 100 cycles or something
so it's just worth noting that
these are the limitations right
uh someone has mentioned that older
versions of claiming generate better
code
uh it could be right performance
regressions are real
um and their test suite probably can't
capture everything so
you know if we go back to doing this
thing
which was where it was kind of
generating uh really bad code if i
remember correctly
yeah we can certainly roll back so let's
suppose we roll back to like an earlier
version of clang let's say clang seven
um looks the same we can roll back to
four
looks the same so for whatever reason
like clang's memory analysis here is
just it just rolls over and dies
who knows why just hit a bad case i
guess i don't know
i read that mixing sc2 and avx-2 will
incur performance penalty how would you
handle optimizing code if you want to
support avx-2 but also sse
for older systems would you just have
separate builds for each
um
so let me first take a moment to cast a
slight shadow of doubt on that
statement i don't actually know that
it's fair to say that mixing
sse and avx ii code
incurs a performance penalty because
it it does i mean that's not wrong
but it's more precise to say that
mixing v prefix and
non-v prefix instructions can have a
performance penalty
so avx instructions are prefixed with v
but so are sse instructions written
in avx so the sse instructions
themselves
have v prefix versions that you can use
and you
see them show up so here's the exact
same code when i say mavx
it'll all have v prefixes inserted in
front of it
so the code is actually completely the
same the only difference is now it has a
v
prefix and that's to avoid calling
v and non-v instructions in the same
path
whether that has a performance so
calling a v in a non-v
uh in the same path whether that has a
performance implication
i think depends entirely on the
architecture i don't think it's true for
all architectures but i could be wrong
about that right
um and
to the extent that you care about this
what i would say is
typically what i do is i isolate all of
the code
that is architecture dependent into like
one file
i usually call that like x64
underscore you know math or something
right
and then i will have variants of it so
uh
in that file i will have
if blocks determining which one i'm
using or i will just have
like avx underscore avx2 underscore
sse underscore as my files and then
pound
include f0 around which ones i'm going
to include right
and i will just create the code
for each path i will
write the entire path that way so i'll
compile
all of my sse routines
as avx routines and so forth
switching between so if you just have
the compiler outputting sse instructions
in your normal code and then you call
into an avx
routine that's going to have vp
instructions i don't think that
performance penalty is going to hurt you
because it's only the first time you do
it that you pay a transition penalty and
it's not that expensive
so the only thing you're really trying
to avoid there is like inside a loop you
don't want them both
but like if you occasionally switch
between the two i don't think it's going
to matter
that said allowing the compiler the
ability to generate avx code
is usually kind of good so what you
might want to do is just have two builds
of your game
and just have a little shim that starts
up and loads the right one
right so like build two dlls
avx avx2 or
three dlls sse2 avx and avx2 or
something like that
um or avx 512 if you're really gung-ho
uh and then just load the right one or
load them in series and wait for them to
fault and then switch to another one you
know whatever you want to do
right
someone asked if we could show what gcc
does yes we can
um where is it though
here it is
um so wow
all right um is that really what it does
so gcc's code is is terrible
um it did the entire thing with scalar
moves
try clang six
still looks bad um
playing six looks wrong doesn't it still
ah
still looks bad
ah okay so 03 made a big difference
for gcc though right that is the correct
code
so
so that's so gcc absolutely trounces
clang here at 03
for what it's worth
could you provide the twitter
conversation link that you are
responding to for the youtube video i
thought i
did actually at the beginning of it um
but it was jesse meyer posting
some tests he was trying to do right
here
um so uh this is what i
uh said you know because like i said i
appreciated the fact that he took the
time to do this so
i uh wanted to take the time to expound
on it
um and just say my thoughts on this
particular
uh topic
uh latest clang with well i thought i
did i think we did try the latest clang
with o3 um and yeah that's latest clang
with o3
so let me let me pause for a second and
also say one more thing before we
conclude
this isn't a tractable situation right
this is like really bad the fact that
everyone's like try clang six with o3
and arch this
it should produce reliable code for
reliablely written
simple pieces of code without having to
be some kind of a switch jockey
now in this case it never produces good
code so clang as far as i can tell will
never produce good code for this
period but this is one of the reasons
why i
think that fundamentally the model for
c and compilers is broken
it should not be a gigantic mystery what
kind of x64 code is going to get
generated when you do something as
simple as copy
from a known value to memory
right it should be like really
straightforward
and the problem is we keep introducing
all these
layers switches and optimization paths
and all stuff
just let's stop all that
if there's not straightforward ways to
optimize code from the c
code let's modify the c spec so that i
can tell you what i was trying to do
right and that's just better
right i don't want this to be happening
this is bad
right it makes the um person's job a lot
harder when they can't
reliably know that copying from one
place to another
if it's 64 bytes should just be
four mod ups's
that should just be like obvious and if
something other than that's gonna happen
you should have to be specifying all
kinds of like in code pragmas or
something to get it to happen
doing the obvious thing is way more
valuable than occasionally doing some
heroic thing
you know so
this is not tractable it's not great
right
is it possible the extra jumps clang
generates are a specter mitigation
why is it doing specter mitigation
nobody asked it to do spectre mitigation
in what universe would i care about
spectre mitigation in a game
right it's absurd
it's absurd if you want specter
mitigation you should have to ask for it
now i don't know if that had anything to
do with spectrum indication but if let's
say that you're right and it did it's
absurd that it was doing that by default
i'm trying to test this code and it's
doing spectre mitigation well that's
something i should have asked for right
all right um so if you want
to uh share this
god bolt as well uh here is a link to it
um it'll probably save it uh and then
we'll close down for the day um
oh someone says spectre mitigation is on
a hardware level um spectre mitigation
at the hardware level
is only in some processors right and
they had to do like
patches for it but again i don't think
that was spectre mitigation or anything
anyway uh but i'm just
saying let's suppose it was i don't see
how it would be but let's just suppose
it was
that's dumb anyway right it shouldn't
just be throwing spectre mitigation in
the middle of something that i didn't
ask for
so either way it's dumb right
um so anyway
so here's the godbolt link if you want
to jump to it yourself uh and play
around which if you're trying to learn
assembly language i highly recommend you
do
um and uh yeah
uh i guess all i can say is it surprised
even me how bad this clan code was
i really don't like that i guess i'll be
more aware nowadays to double check
anytime i comply with claim that it's
not doing something really heinous
uh to mems set loops basically uh so
now i know all right let's close it down
thank you everyone for joining me for
the first episode back of handmade hero
it's been a while
thanks for coming back and joining us uh
if you want to follow along this series
at home you can always pre-order the
game at handmadehero.org
we're going to start working on that
soon maybe next week but i want to start
off so with the chat and i did want to
address that
twitter uh thread because i appreciated
jesse taking the time
to actually do some testing and some
timing
so uh that's it for this week i'm gonna
do limited
uh since i'm working on star code galaxy
right now um
which is the upcoming code class i'm i'm
actually working pretty hard to try and
get it finalized
um since i'm working on this right now
uh there's gonna be limited handmade
heroes only once a weekend
just just to save my voice so i can have
a day off
um and not get too much laryngitis
um so it's limited schedule but i will
be here once a week just to say hi to
y'all
and to also um make a little bit of
progress on the game while we wait
and then after our starco galaxy is out
we'll start resuming
regularly scheduled programming uh so
thanks for joining i'll see you back
here next week until then have fun
program everyone
and i'll see you on the internet take it
easy everybody