start recording hello everyone and
welcome to handmade Hero the show where
we code a complete game from scratch
live on twitch no engine no libraries
just us in here writing every little
last piece of code so that after this
series is done literally we have we
he'll have done every single piece of
code that is necessary to run a game
from top to bottom no mysteries leaving
no stone unturned that is that is our
mission our goal our charge if you will
now we're trying something here today
that is new I don't know if it's gonna
work we'll see but basically like we
have switched to mischief for the
blackboard and what I did is I went
ahead and got the commercial version and
I'm trying starting a fresh blackboard
and I'm just gonna save it to the
directory and see if this works for
people who can load it up at home the
problem that I see with it is we were
unable to figure out any way to really
get this to work so that people could
view it with a free viewer and I still
don't think that's gonna be possible
because I tried using the free version
of mischief but the free version of
mischief doesn't even let you set a
background color for the canvas and so
people were very sensitive to the colors
I remember when we first started it they
people really want it to have a dark
background so that would match the
editor that we use so that wouldn't be
kind of like very jarring when they
switch between him so I'm afraid we got
to go with the commercial one the
commercial wants only 25 bucks so if
people want to view the art file they
can choose to buy it I don't know it
might load in the free version we're not
sure but we're just gonna go with it as
an experiment we don't really have any
any other choice at this point what I
can do periodically to solve the sort of
the problem is to do some kind of an
export where I could save it out to an
actual bitmap file eventually but this
thing's gonna get so huge I don't know
how likely that's actually going to be
so we'll see we're gonna go with this
for now because the best solution that
we found I can't say it's perfect but
that's basically where we're at so with
that in mind and starting today we'll
see how that goes we can talk about in
the forums again see what happened after
a couple days and again that file is
is now going into in the handmade well
if you have pre-ordered the game on
handmade hero org right you have access
to the source tree that source tree that
same zip file will now have inside the
misc directory there'll be this
blackboard art file and that blackboard
file will hopefully contain all of the
drawings that I do on the stream now ad
infinitum so there we go all right let's
see where we're at if I remember
correctly and you know programming all
day and then coming home and programming
on the stream I gotta admit I don't
always remember where I was in handmade
hero because I have a lot of other
programming that I have to do but if I
remember correctly what we were doing is
we were using a rock bitmap to basically
have a virtual sword for our guy and we
wanted to make the sword be something
that he could use to basically attack
you know another entity so really basic
stuff what's all we want to do and I
think we just did the part where we took
the sword and you could basically drop
it like that's it
and so what we wanted to do now is we
wanted to finish that off so you can
actually kind of throw the sword Zelda
style and when I say sword here I guess
I mean rock because we don't actually
have a sword bitmap probably should
check something like that and at some
point but we are not going going to at
this point because they don't have so we
want to go ahead and make it so you can
kind of throw that there and make it
into a valid you know projectile that
actually makes some sense so we did most
of the work yesterday I think for
actually doing that we might as well
just go ahead and get that working today
right so one thing you'll notice is it's
kind of ridiculous now when we drop the
sword like the whole point was not to
drop the sword the whole point was to
throw the sword so we should probably do
is go ahead and go in there and and make
that stuff a little more sensible now
all right so let's take a look where
what we when we actually did our sword
stuff here this is where we actually put
the sword into a location right here's
here's how that worked and what we'd
want to do presumably because we're
actually making the sword occur we're
making the sword appear here
we probably want to go ahead and give it
a velocity right because that would be
the easiest way to make it sort of sail
across somewhere so if we wanted to we
could we could make it have a velocity
by moving it into the high empty set and
setting its velocity equal to something
equal to the direction that you threw it
in and that would make it travel now
again the other thing that we said is we
might want to make the sword only go a
certain distance so that you can't throw
it infinitely far it will only go a
certain distance or maybe it like hits
the ground so maybe it kind of gets
thrown in an arc I don't know we'll have
to think about that but point being
distance remaining we kind of put that
in there just to see if we could sort of
initialize that to some number of meters
however I could throw the sword so I
want to go ahead and put that in as well
right so first things first let's go
ahead and set the controlling entities
distance remaining.i starting off to
controlling entity the sword entity
right which we have here let's go ahead
and make that sword entity have it have
a distance remaining and let's just say
that it's going to be I don't know three
meters or something like that maybe
that's too short we'll say five meters
and so as soon as the sword has traveled
five meters we'll just say that that's
as far as the sword gets to go and
that's the end of it right and so the
sword at that point we could also say
let's go ahead and set its velocity in
order to set up velocity we have to have
it in the high OD set and so one thing
that I could do here is excuse me one
thing I could do here again is is force
it into the high entity set we didn't do
that yet because there wasn't any
particular reason to do so but it seems
like now there actually is right and so
what's kind of weird about this and you
can sort of see the way this is going
it's kind of annoying again sorry I have
a cold so I'm still sniffily today
believe me there's no fun for me either
anyway the thing that I haven't been
liking very much about the low end
behind the thing although it's been
working relatively well for us in terms
of how it's actually functioning the
code is kind of annoying because you
constantly have all these weird like
pointers and indices and I don't love
the fact that there's so much typing
involved there I don't like the sort of
proliferation of that and so what I'd
like to do is finally maybe get it down
to the point where it's something that's
fair
condensable like it's something that
doesn't have to have so much kind of
janky miss there and so I went back and
forth with using this entity structure
and what I'm wondering is that maybe we
kind of need to just get that that sort
of thing to be more standard right maybe
just kind of figure out what the calls
need to be where this entity actually
happens and then you know actually start
using it because it again like the same
things going to happen here right we're
gonna have like a high sword or
something like this or you know here's
low sword right and and if I do it this
way and then I've got the sword and I go
for centimeter high right it's just
there's now there's a two Porter's to
the sword or two things like it's just
it's just this kind of ugly in annoying
right and so far we haven't really hit
bugs because of it for whatever reason
it just doesn't seem to be error-prone
but it just it resulted to its typing
and it makes the code harder to read and
that just is a constant drag on
development so it's just flagged in my
mind as something that we need to
address going forwards because I just
don't like it and I'm not going to be
willing to have that stay that way added
you know forever basically right so yeah
so let you know let's let's just assume
that we're gonna deal with that and
we'll think about it keep it in the back
of our heads and just know that that's
something that needs to get addressed at
some point so let's say we go ahead and
and do here we go ahead and force it
into the high entity set so it's gonna
be a high frequency update and now we
want to actually set its velocity well
we now already have this D sword thing
which is the direction we want it to go
in right so all we really need to know
is how fast we want it to travel what
its velocity should be right and I'd
only know how many meters per second a
sword should travel I don't know I feel
like maybe if the sword takes one second
or two seconds that seems fairly
reasonable so maybe maybe you know it
should go about two meters per second I
don't know we'll tweak that constant
we'll see but I think that if I go ahead
and set that I feel like that should I
feel like that should allow us to see
that sword sword in my sword I mean Rock
travel actually in a direction
after we launched it although that was
kind of unspectacular I just realized
that what we don't do yet is we don't
actually have any kind of update for our
actual for our actual sort so let's take
a look here are we actually ever dealing
with this guy where do we actually for
our move entity call right for our move
entity call there we go it looks like we
are only ever let's see move entity so
on our update familiar call we do move
it we don't ever have an update call for
our sword right so the sword itself will
never actually move unless I actually at
some point give it you know give it the
actual swords and say update it and then
it can do its move entity now I don't
know if we actually need and this is
kind of interesting point I don't know
that we actually need a special case of
updating the sword it probably could be
using something that updates generic
sort of projectile sorts of stuff but
again this is code that we're meant to
sort of suss out how we want the entity
system to work so for now I'm gonna
write everything explicitly and then I'm
gonna see what things look common to me
across entities and pull those outs as
we go right
again that's compression oriented
programming I think it's the same as we
go at this early stage when we're just
trying to figure out exactly what we
want everything to do so we don't build
our game on top of a bad foundation
basically so I think that if that's the
case then really all we need to do for
move entity I guess now that I look at
it we don't we don't have any
acceleration for the sword the sword
stays the same speed the entire time
that's typically how a Zelda style sword
would would work right so if I'm if I'm
doing that I think really we don't do
anything other than call the move entity
routine that we always called before and
that move entity routine should in
general just work now there's something
that that I got a check here I don't
know if we actually yeah so there's some
things that we need to do in here for
now I'm going to do it right here
I guess right let's see let's see right
here I want to basically turn off
collision detection on the sword for now
so what I want to say for now only and
we're gonna do something a little
fancier here in a minute but for now
only I'm going to say that if something
collides then it does this testing but
if it doesn't collide it doesn't do that
testing and that allows things like the
sword that are marked non colliding to
just sail through stuff because I want
to sort of think about what's going to
happen to them a little bit differently
right so let's go ahead now and finish
things off in here we kind of want to be
able to do update sword right like so
and we pass at the game state the entity
and the DT and I think that that's most
of what we would need for our sword that
was a pretty uninspiring sword through
but I think it actually did move but it
it's actually slowing down and I believe
that we still have a problem here and in
fact this is a good time for us to
actually start to pull this out because
we never actually did this with the
familiar with with the familiar and so
on we still have this this bad notion
where the players speed and the
acceleration and the drag and all that
stuff are actually just built in and
that's really kind of bad because each
individual object is going to want to
have its own things like its own dragon
that sort of stuff so the reason that
are stored sort of stuff going is
because our move entity just has baked
into it the fact that there's always air
resistance right which gives him the
same kind of like stopping as the player
has which is which is totally not what
we want at all we want the sword to just
sail right and so in order to fix that
what we would need to do is say that
these are sort of things that are
parameterised when the entity is is
being moved those are parameters that
control how this update actually happens
right and so the first thing I think
we'd want to do here is make it so that
player speed is no longer this kind of
thing that gets multiplied that the
acceleration gets multiplied by the
player speed right that's what we were
doing here and I think that's just
totally bogus we don't want to do that
at all what we want to do is we want to
say that we have some notion that the
acceleration has already been processed
by whoever it is that's calling us and
is the valid acceleration for the frame
and move entity is only responsible for
actually responding to that acceleration
right so that's the first thing you
wanna do right which is acceleration so
valid acceleration passed in and that's
pretty easy to do we'll do that today I
think and the other thing what we want
to do is in here where we have this drag
coefficient right we'd like to sort of
have some notion that the drag
coefficient was also something that's
passed in right and since this is
something that affects the acceleration
right and it's it has to do with the
equations of motion as well I think we
probably will want to pass in this value
the actual coefficient so that when we
change this into an ordinary
differential equation here which we'll
want to do a little bit later I think
that we'd want that to kind of just be
baked in here so that you can just pass
in a drag coefficient right and so what
we could do there's a number of
different ways we could do this I'm
thinking that may be one of the easiest
things to do would to be have some kind
of an entity spec right and so a move
spec something like this and maybe you
know the move spec has something like
the acceleration and the drag
coefficient right so this is the the
drag coefficient here right and that's
gonna be you know for the player that
was negative 8.0 F so this will actually
be something where we'll take the move
spec I guess we don't want it to be
negative we'll say that it's positive
right so we'll say the move spec drag
whoops you place that there and then the
player speed we could make the speed be
a parameter and then actually do have it
do this as a directional thing
potentially as well I don't know if we
want to do it that way it just kind of
gives easier way to pass in stuff than
having to have it roll its own so maybe
we'll try it that way we'll have a speed
parameter as well right and then we'll
also have a pool which is basically like
cap for I should say unit max accel
vector
something like this right I don't really
know what to call that exactly but
basically if we wanted to keep all of
this stuff as stuff that you could use
when you call move entity and it would
all be fairly common working stuff right
then what we could do is just say that
you know the stuff that we were doing
before is stuff you can just optionally
have this function do for you right so
if you want to make sure that your unit
that your acceleration is that maximum
unit length so it's based on what you're
doing is you're using it as a
proportional scaler like like with the
analog stick like what we were doing
it'll do that for you
for the player speed stuff it'll
actually do that for you as well right
and so this is going to be speed equals
that for when we actually move that out
there so what we could do here is say
that also happens right move speck dot
speed and then you also pass in that
drag and now what you could do is you
could you could have the entity and in
addition to the acceleration you could
pass in that movement spec which is
basically just a thing which says how
you know how this entity moves what are
its equations of motion and we could add
some things perhaps later that will tune
the the motion as well other things that
we might want to control right and so
now we know that if we were to make one
for the player you know it would look
like like this and unit max accel vector
equals one point now right our sorry
equals true and so if we wanted to call
this for the player now we could just go
ahead and do that in the move entity
call for the player right so here's the
one for the familiar and we know that
that was also using the one that the
player was using although probably it
shouldn't probably should be set a
little bit different than that but you
know we'll sort of get to that when we
actually are fussing with things of that
nature so there we go we can pass that
there we can go ahead and you know what
we'd probably want to have this be a
default to we'll make this be a default
mu spec something like that in fact I
like that a lot so we'll say that that
way we know that we've always kind of
got some kind of a default there so
let's
move speck default moves back like so
and put one here so we don't know what
the speed of the sword is exactly I
think oh we do we know that the the
speed is is zero it can't accelerate we
know that it has no drag and we know
that we don't actually need it to do any
of this stuff so that's that's just
completely not doing anything so we've
got the default may expect there we've
got our move entity okay and then we've
got the same same stuff going on here so
that's gonna want to use basically this
guy for now there we go
so alright so that's pretty much all
there is to that and again I don't
really know if I love that or not but it
just seemed like a sensible thing to do
just to kind of clean up what was
happening in that function and kind of
move it out into something that we can
deal with and so what happens here in
this in this default one is I just
wanted to make one where the default
things that should happen will happen
right so that the people if we add
basically what I want to here is if we
add members to this because their
physics parameters I feel like it might
be too hard to do I usually try to make
it so that everything defaults to zero
but in this case the defaults being zero
might not make sense because in physics
some things want to default to one some
things want is fall to zero and you have
to name things in very odd ways to make
that work and so in this case I just
kind of decided well I'm gonna go with
actually having some kind of
initialization here and so basically
most people will just initialize that to
the default spec and they'll go from
there so let's just verify that
everything seems to be still working our
familiar head is still following us
around which is good and there's our
little sword quote unquote sword off it
goes and so that's what we wanted to
have happen it's a bit slow for a sword
so I think to say the very least we
would probably want to make sure that
that sword goes a little bit faster in
the future so let's do that but also
what we now want to do is go ahead and
implement that thing where it can only
travel for a certain distance before it
goes away and so alright first of all
our DP is actually going to be happy
let's higher than that
and then our distance remaining what we
want our distance remaining to do
basically is to sort of act as like a
ticker and so what we do here I think
gives we'd say let's take wherever the
entity was and then we'll take wherever
the entity is now so we'll just say the
old position of the entity equals the
entities you know position at the start
and then we'll say the the distance
traveled equals the length of basically
this vector right here so it's going to
be the entity's current position - his
old position so that'll be the length of
that vector and then what we want to do
is subtract the distance traveled
basically from that now there's a little
bit of a bug in here and I'm not sure
whether we want to address it now or not
but we'll talk about it in a second the
first thing we want to do is say if this
distance remaining drops to zero right
so if the distance remaining falls below
the the if we basically used up all the
distance that we had to travel we want
to go ahead and make the sword disappear
right so we want to do is we want to go
ahead and change our enemy location we
want to change the reuleaux entity index
right for this guy change entity
position into your location so so we
want to go ahead and change its position
to essentially nowhere right so we want
to take want to take that low entity
soar dot low this is actually soared low
index I guess why do we have this
shouldn't be soared this is just the
entity and a lot of types of sword
it's just entity there we go so we go
and past that we have its old position
which is just where it was right and in
some sense it's sub sense I don't even
know why we're passing this anymore in
this this utility function because the
old position is just wherever it was
right so this is always going to be
entity
P right is that old position so I wonder
if we should just get rid of that now it
does seem like we should but anyway and
then the new position is nowhere right
the new position is it's just not gonna
be anywhere at all so I think that would
would basically do it the only thing
that yeah I guess we haven't done yet
because we haven't made a length for our
vectors we made something that does the
length squared but we don't have
anything that actually gets the length
but that's not very difficult obviously
because if we want to get the the length
of something and we already know how to
get the squared length all we have to do
is square root it right and square
rooting
something that's the length squared will
get us the link right so that's pretty
easy so we'll go ahead and return that
and off we go now
at this point you may be asking well
square root is undefined for negative
numbers you're correct it is but what
you have to remember is since we're
calling length squared there is no
actual possible way that it can produce
a negative number now why is that right
well the reason because if you remember
back when we talked about the math the
inner product is when you take a vector
well two vectors and you multiply their
components by each other so you multiply
the X's by the XS and the Y's by the Y's
now normally that could produce a
negative number quite easily as long as
one of these was negative the other one
was positive and the positive you know
times a negative is negative a negative
plus another negative would be a
negative that'd be really easy you can
imagine lots of ways that this result
could be negative and so you would end
up taking a square root of a negative
number which is not a good idea right
complex numbers not something we want to
have happening in here because we don't
even have any place to store we're just
storing a real value right but you have
to remember we are taking the length of
a vector which means we're passing
itself as both parameters to that inner
product which means it's going to be its
own x times its own X and its own Y
times own Y which means it's going to be
a square plus a square and any number
squared is always going to be positive
unless that number was comments
beginwith right any real number times
itself if it was negative it's two
negatives so you know negative times
negative is gonna be a positive if it
was two positives then it was gonna be
positive if it's two zeros gonna be a
zero so there's really
no way that can possibly be a negative
because gonna be one positive number or
zero plus another positive number or
zero which means that our square root
essentially can never fail in this case
right so that's easy enough and we don't
really have to worry about that too much
of course I guess we do have to worry
about the fact that we've never actually
defined our square root which it's kind
of odd we've never had to take a square
root it's right there
if I spell it wrong what happened or is
it that hand made math isn't in it comes
after it or something like this square
root let's see let's see where are those
intrinsic s-- where is hand-made math I
guess is the more important and made
yeah so that's our problem that needs to
go like that all right so we're we're
basically done here we're going to have
to that's that's totally wrong fix up
the typos here and there we go let's see
change in a new location converted five
from world position that's true that
needs to be address of the position and
that's done so now I think that should
move it after it's done traveling or we
might get an error so that's interesting
we hit one of our assertions that
basically says that one of the things
that we were passing was not canonical
what happened there what happened there
change entry location so old P and new P
oh so I think when we wrote this
function we never actually we never
actually did one for a new P being zero
so we've never we've never actually
allowed you to change entries location
from somewhere
to nowhere if you will so basically all
that assertion was telling us was well
actually don't think I was assertion
that was probably actually a no pointer
dereference but could be wrong with that
I think what we actually want to do here
oh no we actually it was an assertion
well we actually wanted you to just say
if both of them are valid and they were
in the new chunk then we leave the
entity where it is otherwise we process
it separately right and so that's I
think we just needed to just check that
there and that should be that should be
it I think let's find out let's find out
um hmm that's a little bit odd what are
we doing what is the actual assertion
there old P is valid so is it suggesting
that it's not actually valid I can't
actually tell ya I want to see what it's
actually complaining about access
violation writing location zero zero
zero what exactly inside that assert is
writing a location well you know what
that may just be that that may be a
slightly furious way that that's being
reported so let's let's actually step in
there and make sure that we actually
know for reals exactly what's going on
there so what's happening here let's see
let's find out so the new chunk P and
the old chunk P that old chunk P is
invalid so basically this is still
moving the guy after he essentially has
been moved to zero so what I guess was
probably the case here now that I think
about this is if we've moved him I
wonder if this is a case where we have
let's go ahead and see here if we're
actually moving somebody out and then
he's still in the hi entity set so while
he's still in that hi entity set he gets
moved again and then that causes a
problem I assume that's what's happening
let's let's actually double check and
find out if that's the case so we need
to be in the other file so what we want
to do is we want to see what happens at
the end here when we move the entity so
the sword we want to disappear at this
point we go in and say change entity
location we go ahead and we change it
everything's fine
the lwe entity is now outside of that
set and so our sword entity which I want
to kind of pay attention to now let's
see which one he is right entity low
index so he's nine two two zero five
right and we can always view him as well
by just saying the gamestate low
entities 9 to 2:05 like so there he is
and you can see that he's got an invalid
chunk X which is what we want because he
doesn't exist in the world at the moment
and so that's that's pretty good now
what I suspect is happening and I'll
just say this again because in fact
thinking it through I'm almost positive
what's happening so when we change an
enemy's location even put a to-do in
here about this before because I was
thinking that it probably should happen
you'll notice we said if this moves an
India to the into the camera Mouse
should automatically go to the highest
set immediately there's a corollary to
this is if it moves out of the camera
bounds
should it be removed from the high set
immediately right and basically
immediately is probably the wrong word
here we maybe don't want to be immediate
but we may want it to happen in some
kind of a more controlled way than
waiting for the next time that set
camera gets called right and so what I
believes happening here is we change the
send of these location and then in the
high set we don't actually do any work
to sort of ensure that it's that it's
removed from that high set and not still
getting updated in the high set as if
it's still in the location that it was
before we moved it right because we're
only changing that low P and we're
moving it out into the middle out into
non-existence that should remove it from
the high set but unfortunately it won't
right like there's nothing there's no
code that will actually do that because
the only thing that removes things from
the high set is when their high position
moves outside the camera bounds right so
I think there's probably a hacky not
particularly good way to solve this
problem right and that would basically
be to set the entities high position to
something super invalid right like you
could imagine setting it taking that and
just doing something like you know this
kind of nonsense right that would
probably do it for us but I want
something that's not going to be so
janky right I want to think this through
and do it in a kind of a relatively easy
way I just want to see if that's the
actual problem is that it's not getting
removed from that set I want to see yeah
so that
I assume and that is actually the case
so that's what I expected and so we have
to kind of think about that and this is
actually a very important problem in my
mind this is exactly the sort of thing
that we want to kind of look at a little
more intelligently because it's the kind
of thing it's the kind of thing that you
really want to get right or you're gonna
have lots of subtle bugs of exactly this
kind because having two frequencies of
up update for your entities is a complex
thing if you don't get the basics of it
right you'll constantly be fighting this
battle of bugs like this that that annoy
you and waste your development time all
right so the question is what do we want
to do here let's review how our enemy
systems actually working right and I use
the term Andy System loosely but the
enemy code that we have so far right we
don't really have any system per se so
what we're doing is we're spinning
through these high entities that we have
and we're updating them as we go and so
when we update the sword eventually it's
time for the sword to sort of get moved
out of existence and so one of the
things that becomes true here is it
shouldn't participate once it gets moved
out of existence it's possibly the case
that it shouldn't participate any
further in anything else that might
happen on this frame or on subsequent
frames so one thing that we could do is
essentially move mark things for
deletion or remove things as part of
this loop right that would be the
first-tier way to deal with this and the
example there would be some sort of a
control flow thing that tells us that
right so you could imagine something
like this which is like remove right
should something sort of highly in index
get removed right and so we'd set that
to false and then what we do is for any
of these people who have an update call
right you'd basically have a remove call
that would that would return to us
whether or not we wanted the thing to
get removed now that's all right
and what we do is at the end of this
right here we just process that out
I don't super love that as an idea
necessarily I think what I prefer
I would prefer something that could set
that on sort of a more global in a more
global sense perhaps something that
could do it so that it'll get processed
the next time through on maybe on that
camera call something like that right I
think that's really what I would prefer
so what I want to do is take a look at
that set camera call and see how that's
working right right now what it's doing
is it's saying offset and check
frequency by area right that's the
that's the call that loops through and
says who's still in the sort of the play
field it would be nice if that in and of
itself could just check to see whether a
high entity should or should not still
be around right and it seems to me like
that's a more sensible place to do this
potentially just thinking it through you
know something like this where we would
say you know if hi you know is alive or
something like this or or we could even
do it a little bit more straightforward
we could say that that that sort of that
low entity position we could say if it's
low entity position is valid right which
I guess do we we don't really know the
low entity position here so it kind of
bites an extra look up which I don't
love but you know we'll we'll sort of
we'll sort of do that for now and just
see we can always we can always put in
something to accelerate that later if we
want to right so I'll just go ahead and
do low entity low and we'll go ahead and
grab that guy off of here like so so
what we'll do is we'll say if that if
that low P is is valid that's that's one
reason but if it's not valid if if the
entity has moved out of existence
basically and its position is in the
ether then we're not going to leave it
in that high empty set now I don't know
if that's the best criteria for now but
that's certainly stronger I think than
what we had previously and I like that a
little bit better so let's take a look
at what happens there let's just take it
take a look at that we've got one other
thing that we kind of need to address
when we do that though which is that
when we're going through this loop if we
don't remove people right away then
they're still getting checked for their
current location
I don't reeled it that's necessarily bad
but it's something to think about right
mean this sword for the rest for the
rest of the Hyades before we get to the
end of this loop the sword is still
where it was originally which I don't
actually know if that's a bad thing but
with something we have to think about
all right and so I think that's also so
you can see that also solves the problem
just fine right our sword still seems to
be incredibly slow which is odd and I
don't know why that does not seem to
have gotten any velocity either that was
particularly weird if I do say so myself
I'm not sure why our sword would ever
not have velocity how did that happen
that's pretty amusing
let's take a look G sword we always do
give the sword some velocity right yeah
distance remaining five it's high DP it
can't collide with anything so it
shouldn't ever be able to have a
velocity that's not zero right because
we specifically said that swords don't
collide pretty sure anyway
when we did add sword right collides is
false so when we're calling move entity
on the sword
I would think there should be no way for
it to ever actually get into a state
where where it can't where it's velocity
would get clipped right because in
theory let's see hit high into the index
that can't ever set get high into the
index right it's always equal to zero so
it should never actually I don't think
be able to have a velocity that is yeah
that is zero so how did that happen I'm
very confused about that that's very
troubling that doesn't seem like a
doesn't seem like a reasonable thing to
have happen I want to know what I'm
missing
basically because if this always gets
set I'm trying to think if there's any
other way that it could get set with the
DP not being able to that but it's DP
should basically always be this I don't
know why it's DP ever would be anything
else yeah so that's that's a little
disconcerting so I'm trying to think of
what would be the best way to catch that
right like what's the best way to hunt
down how that happened cuz it obviously
happened I saw it happen so let's think
about this basically we get a low entity
there shouldn't ever really be a wait
yeah I cannot think of a way to really
have that happen gosh that is really
strange well let's take a look here when
an enemy gets forced into hi ah ha there
we go
so that could easily be our problem if
the entity was going to get moved into
hi by someone other yeah so basically
that is almost certainly where a problem
comes from right so when the entity gets
moved into a tie frequency space its
velocity at that point right it's going
to yeah is going to basically be
shooting its velocity at that point
would get zero so one question is is
there any way right that a sword could
have that happen it does seem like it
would be possible for the sword to get
placed down in low frequency like it
gets transitioned out of low frequency
and then transitions back into high
frequency somehow or something like this
right I I don't think that's entirely
out of the question and so I assume that
is exactly what happened so let's take a
look
move entity let's see if we can actually
make that happen
force empty into high so make any high
frequency so that's one way we could do
this to try and make that that case is
we could go ahead and do an assert here
or rather we won't do an assertion let's
just set a breakpoint
right we'll set a breakpoint where if
that entity low type equals the sword
then I'm going to set a breakpoint there
right so so if I'm looking at a sword
like so break here right equals five so
that way I can go ahead and just try to
make that bug reproduce itself and then
I can also see at that point I'd be able
to see the call stack
to see who it was exactly who was
causing that to happen right so anyway
so yeah so in this case I think we're
okay because this should actually be
called from game update and render which
is here so it's gonna it's gonna
actually call that there right there we
go and then it gets called a second time
that seems erroneous right that doesn't
seem right to me make entity high
frequency why wasn't it - see already
what what's going on here did it get
moved out of the high frequency set you
saw it happen didn't you
that seems erroneous to me let's see if
that happens every time that just seems
bad so let's go ahead and debug that
that seems like a bad situation I don't
think that should be happening
so basically when we make entity high
frequency right make entity high
frequency there's two cases that's
happening on the sword one is happening
when we're basically setting the camera
and so what we're doing is we're looping
through everything and we're moving it
here so I'm guessing that what must
happen is offset and check frequency by
area must actually be removing the sword
from the high frequency set for some
reason right because otherwise why would
that ever happen right so it must be the
case that like our low P is judged as
invalid or something where it happens so
I
gonna go ahead and say that this right
here is a case well I guess I could do
it and make it any low frequency right
low frequency so in here what I could do
is say okay let's go ahead and see when
we do this deletion yeah so we just do
this
if NC low and we've got our type and we
want that to be the sword
let's see who's moving that into the low
frequency set right so that happens and
then it yeah so so something something
is amiss in my opinion because as you
can see we've hit this twice but we
never hit the oh no that's not true
I lied we did we actually have to set
the breakpoint sorry about that
spoke too soon I'm assuming I was suing
that should fire but it didn't and I
realized because I didn't actually set a
breakpoint on it all right so there we
go that actually hits that breakpoint
which is what we expect and then it hits
this breakpoint all right so basically
we've got we've got nastiness and that's
good because now we can actually debug
our nastiest which is what we want so
the first time it end it enters into the
high frequency set that's exactly what
we wanted to have happen right because
that's where we actually forced it into
high and that's where we actually set
its state right and so that's all good
and off we go now the next time through
we find that we've set it to low
frequency and the question is why are we
setting it to low frequency like what's
the reasoning right behind that of
course Microsoft Visual Studio makes it
as hard as possible for that to happen
by giving you absolutely no information
whatsoever what we'd like to be able to
see is like what happened in here but we
can't unfortunately and so what we want
to do is say all right
it failed one of these things so let's
see if we can figure out which one it
failed yes thank you so much visual
for being absolutely awful at everything
that you do okay so let's go ahead and
see if I can set the next statement to
just be inside this routine actually you
know what I could do let me let me step
out of this first so let's go ahead and
well you know what this actually has the
things I need in it to some degree I
suppose and not really because they're
gonna get deleted uh Visual Studio
alright well let me see I guess what I
could do is trick Visual Studio into
being less of the world's worst debugger
and maybe only the world's second worst
of bugger by putting in some dummy line
that will allow us to still inspect the
variables we actually want to inspect so
here is our dummy line here like so and
maybe this can help you know as you know
people at Microsoft don't actually debug
any of their code so they don't actually
have to worry about looking at code in
the debugger so they probably never
occurred to them that people who
actually do debug code and ship it
without the bugs in it would want to
actually see the variables in their code
while they were stepping through it
that's kind of one of the things that
debugger sometimes do but if you never
launch it a bugger and you just send it
out the door however it is you probably
don't think about those things anyway
so let's see we got our dummy line here
so now what I'm hoping to do is when I
take a look at this make entity low
frequency I can now actually hopefully
step out here and since we've inserted
this dummy line I'll be able to actually
look at these values right so there's
the values that we actually have here's
our high entity here's where he is and
he's set out in the middle of nowhere
that is pretty darn clear right so
that's pretty telling and the low
position for him not not super sure I
understand why he's set out in the
middle of nowhere but he is and then his
low position is actually doesn't seem to
correlate with that at all to me right
am I wrong about that but that that
seems fairly
clear so he's failing this but I don't
understand why he is getting these
ridiculous values set
I'm not sure I don't follow why that's
the case so I want to figure out what's
going on there in this set camera call
what is the end of the offset for frame
and the offset per frame is nothing so
that's I guess what you know to be
expected we're in this first game update
and render through so I don't know
that's that's pretty bizarre let's find
out why that's happening so when we
first enter into the high space where
does the entity think it is entity high
let's see here and so moving into camera
space this is where it thinks it is at
zero zero right that's where it's
thinking the entity is at the moment
that's the camera space P right so let's
get out of here and double check that
we've made the end of the high frequency
here it is we set the low and the high
there so let's take a look here soared
like this let's see that low and high
like so so just taking a look here at
these values they all look very very
sane nothing particularly odd there I
will say if that's the offset negative 5
5 9 I am wondering a little bit is that
actually what it should be because I
guess I don't know exactly where that
well there might be that the cameras
there as well let's double check to see
what the camera state actually is so you
can see whether that's a sane value
right just want to make sure that that's
that's actually makes sense yes so
that's where the camera is so that all
worked out exactly as it should and then
we're going to come down here and we're
going to actually update the sword so
let's take a look at that call because
that's another thing that could do it so
if we take a look at our entity now like
so there we go okay so in here in entity
we still have reasonable
use for our high and our low values and
so I'm wondering how we end up with such
ridiculous stuff I'm guessing that
something happens in here that causes
that to occur so let's take a look
so inside move entity let's see what
happens in there when we do our movement
what's our DDP look like it's all zeroes
what's our new player P look like let's
take a look at what so let's just take a
look at what it's trying to do do play a
P that's a totally sane thing as far as
I can tell anyway so the desired
position so let's take a look what's
that player Delta what's the team in yep
all looks pretty good nothing
particularly out of the ordinary there
as far as I can tell anyway yeah so
entity hi P is totally sane values
totally sane values so now let's take a
look at what happens when we do our map
into chunk space when we Macan map into
chunk space we get another totally sane
value so that seems reasonable as well
and then when we go ahead and do this
let's see what happens here so we get
our new p or low end vp is gonna get set
so there we go
then let's take a look at that low
entity so and that's totally fine as
well so coming out of here this actually
looks all pretty good right nothing
weird actually happened to our guy so
I'm not sure why we ended up with such
ridiculous values there but we did
unless that was just a trick of the
debugger showing us wrong values which
could totally be the case obviously
let's go ahead and keep going with this
investigation because I'm not satisfied
that we have any idea what's going on at
this point all right so if I continue to
look at my low entities I could also
look at my high Indy's I suppose here is
the high any index is high in the next
97 so what I could do is
say let's also take a look at it here so
what I want to do is say I've got my
game state oh you know what I don't
think this has anything to do with it
but I just thought of something
particularly ugly that we definitely
probably that we that it's gonna cause
problems at some point although I don't
know if that's some point is anywhere
near now but I just thought of something
really gross I don't even want to say it
it's so bad the things I do for the
stream things I do for the stream all
right
no that's one high end of these is that
like that there we go
so this is our high entity and we can
delete all this stuff and just look at
our high D and our low entity for this
guy great so here's our sword our full
description of the sword using totally
hard offsets so we can just kind of see
as we go what's gonna happen there
so let's find out when that craziness
actually occurs here's the drawing code
that's fine so now we're gonna have to
step back into basically game update
render write game update and render so
we're gonna have to see coming through
here I assume we're still all good we go
through our controller index we haven't
done anything so there's nothing weird
that has to happen here let's see you've
got the low entities are fine yep
nothing weird there again this is all
fine and our entity is still totally
sane it's not in its rediculous state
that it was and so now when we come
through here and we're going to go ahead
and do our set camera call I assume this
is where we get the weirdness where the
entity goes haywire although I still
have not been able to determine why that
would happen we're gonna see if we can
find it
so we get the camera bounds let me step
into the check the frequency check and
then we're gonna go through and start
actually checking these and we checked
them and they probably should all be
valid I would say right
I would think they'd all be valid so I'm
gonna set a breakpoint at the end of
this function just let it run through
there and so it was able to go through
that no problem so that wasn't where we
got made low frequency so the first time
through set camera was actually not a
problem which is kind of interesting
right that's that's actually pretty
pretty unusual yeah that's that's
bizarre but okay so off we go and then
so when we finally do it I don't know
how long it has been since that has
happened that's kind of weird right this
happens at some point but we're not
really sure when it's not in the first
time we call offset and check frequency
by area it's in some time sometime quite
thereafter so I'm guessing that that
might mean that it's only when we do
that change location because the change
location call would cause that to happen
it looks like it was happening a lot
faster than that but I guess it wasn't
so if you remember right when we do our
update which is it's right somewhere
where is our update call update call
update call I wish I had a better way to
jump to functions in here I'm sure there
must be one by now I don't know what it
is in Visual Studio so it must be that
we're actually doing this
right Oh awesome
man I tell you I'm stream i'm always so
absent-minded so we still left this in
there why did i leave that in there i
said specifically that that was just a
quick hack and then like here's the
other thing we should do and then there
I go like totally leaving it in there oh
man that's hilarious
yeah the number of typos I have on the
stream is awful
I assume we've had some legitimate bugs
so far but man the time I spend on the
typos is way worse I don't know I kind
of need I need some kind of a thing for
for I got to figure out how I can talk
and pay attention to my own code at the
same time I'm not really sure how to do
that okay let's get back to where we
were before that ridiculousness all
right so there's the high frequency and
there it goes man that was so annoying
all right so that's actually correct
that should be low frequency so that's
fine I want to see if I can repair that
bug again without that ridiculous being
in there just so I guess because that
was probably the entirety of the bug so
lame yeah so there's one thing that we
are doing at the moment though that's a
little annoying which is I feel like I
don't know exactly how I was able to do
that but that's pretty cool we don't
actually ensure that we set the position
back to where it was so I'm actually
able to do kind of a cool hook shot
thing here sometimes like right there so
that means basically if you look at the
order it's kind of interesting so this
is something that we need we've been
needing to do for a while and that's the
first time we've actually had this
happen so if you think about the order
of operations here everyone's getting
updated in a particularly coherent way
except for this ridiculousness this is
totally outside of the we update the
player inside this this thing where
we're processing the input in a total in
a way that doesn't actually ensure that
things that should have happened to the
sword for example actually have happened
to the sword already so the set camera
call for example hasn't happened which
means that you could if you wanted to
end up getting the low entity of the
sword and having the low swords P B not
valid right but it still wouldn't
actually be outside of the high entity
set right because it hadn't got moved
out of there yet which means that its
position in high entity space this
wouldn't actually trigger anything right
which wouldn't move which wouldn't
restore its position I know this is
particularly a weird thing to think
about but basically you could think of
us as a bug in one of two different ways
one is that the order of operations is
odd and that's something that we have to
sort of work out because we kind of have
this done piecemeal here so one thing
that we do kind of want to do is collect
our user input and then we want to
update the player in a coherent way
outside here right so that's one thing
the other thing that we want to be able
to do is when we change a location we
kind of have this problem where if you
change a location and the entity has a
representation in high space we want
those to say in sync and right now those
can easily get out of sync and so the
question is how do we design our system
so that those don't get out of sync
right and that's kind of a tricky
problem again this is the reason why I'm
trying to do the having two different
sets of entity updates it's because you
can see it's a lot more complicated to
write the code this way than it would be
if we didn't do this and so I'm trying
to whenever I can I'm trying to pick the
most complicated type of thing you might
have to do and do it that way to show
how you work through all of the problems
that are involved in it right because I
want to show how you can make any
systems that scale up to huge numbers of
entities even if we could save a lot of
time by not doing that I don't really
want to go that route so I would rather
spend the time for exactly how to work
through those things so there you go so
I think that's what we want to probably
focus on next time I would say that's
gonna be our to do for tomorrow is to
sort of okay now that we have a real
relatively complicated situation
happening here where we can see the
consequence of things I would say
tomorrow's goal is to pull out this code
and streamline it so that we can have a
sane system for dealing with positions
where we're not going to get bugs in
terms of things moving in and out of the
high and they set like that like what
can we do
to basically increase the usability of
that system so I'm gonna put it to do in
here do for tomorrow basically what
we're gonna do is say now that we have
some real usage examples let's solidify
the positioning system okay and that'll
be fine for you tomorrow so let's go
ahead and go to the Q and a please
prefix your questions with Q : so I will
see them and if you could keep it to
stuff we've done today stream or on a
previous stream if you want to ask
off-topic questions that's okay for the
pre stream but not post stream so if you
want to a soft-top of questions come
back tomorrow 15 minutes before the
stream scheduled to start
that's 7:45 Pacific Standard Time 7:45
p.m. Pacific save time if you want to
ask off-topic questions that's when we
do it
he'll shame do you think that's the I
love shame I don't know I tend to not to
a love shame myself if I make a typo
because like I don't know I I feel like
well I don't know we could do a love
shame I'm fine with the a love shame for
that but that really wasn't much of a
bug that was just me having typed
something in and forgetting which is
really easy to do on the stream so I
don't feel like that was a legitimate
mental bug like I architected the system
wrong or other things like that but I'm
okay with Alice name for that I just
don't know how deserve it it really was
do I ever use GDB yeah on Linux I do do
you test more than just using asserts
sometimes it depends on what the code is
why did you create a struct for each
vector type instead of using plain float
arrays the reason is because I like to
be able to overload to have math
operators so basically if you take a
look at if you take a look at handmade
mat you can see that we actually do
operators for stuff like x and that sort
of thing and the reason for that is to
make it easier to read so let's say
you've got some code right and I have v2
a and I have v2 b or whatever right like
this it's much easier to read a times B
like this right let's say five times B
equals three plus a C right that's very
easy to read
the equivalent if you would just use
float arrays is very very difficult to
read it looks like this it's you know
mul or whatever you want to call it a
scale vector I think I've often called
it scale like that so it would look like
this these would obviously all be floats
so you would end up with float a to look
B of two like so float C of two and so
you do see that you'd have to multiply
it that way so five times B goes into C
three times a goes into and these would
actually I guess you'd do them temp 1
and temp 2 right look 10 110 to so so
you got temp one tip to you do those two
then you do an ad and you do see
temp.1 temptu right that's what the code
looks like so that's why you don't use
float arrays is because you know which
do you want to be able to read in your
code that or that right and so just
looking at them even without any
declarations on them you can see that
this is just really hard to read
compared to this
do you think version control would help
when you go off on a tangent for the
stream you can roll back hacks like that
not unless you're gonna check in like
every 10 seconds so no I don't really
think version control would help have
question but that hook shot thing
actually looked like it would be kind of
fun to play with I actually agree with
you so I should probably I was thinking
that when I was playing us like I should
probably put this in the game somehow so
I'll have to try and remember to add
that in fact I guess I'll add that right
now to my reminders file I have my game
player reminders file here and so I
could go ahead and do that so we'll say
basically bendable shot which allows you
to change direction of the shot once or
something like this I'm not sure how
that would work out in practice but I
agree it was kind of fun what are your
feelings on the vector multiply operator
performing a dot product I don't love it
I tend to use inner for that but given
the fact that like all shader languages
now do it that way no they don't
actually they do the Hadamard product
don't they yeah so I would actually say
double double bad I would say that it's
probably real dangerous to have vector
multiply perform a dot product because
shading languages I'm pretty sure they
use the Hadamard product if you use the
multiply operator so now if you're in a
shading language you're gonna read those
and think they're dot products because
your brains been like train to that
you're constantly like oh wait no and
the shading language is not so I'd be
real careful I would not I would not
have vector multiply perform a dot
product personally I don't think vector
multiply should even be defined I think
you should have to say which kind of
product do you want just to avoid
mistakes but if you were going to define
one I'd say you'd probably have to
define two the Hadamard product because
otherwise every time you switch between
shader and your code you have to do a
mental swap and you're gonna make
mistakes I think I know I would
do you keep your assertions for release
code if not at what point do you remove
them release mode by definition compiles
out the assertions so yeah I mean the
the final version of the code just has
that assertions compiled out the pound
if you pound to find the assertion to
not be anything and that's the thing you
ship why wouldn't you encapsulate each
entity type into its separate classes so
we haven't quite gotten there yet I
would say you're gonna have to come back
in like a week or two when we're
actually talking about how we want to
break down the immune system so I can
explain to you why you don't do that
we haven't actually made any system yet
so even if I was going to do that I
wouldn't have done it yet because it's
too early to start thinking about what
should be an entity class or what the
different end of classes should be like
sword or Pierrot or whatever so even if
I was a fan of object-oriented
programming and inheritance and stuff
like that I wouldn't do it yet I would
wait until I have more done and see how
things should break apart but even that
said when we get to that time I will not
be doing that because there's I don't
like that concept that you're talking
about just in general the concept that
like a sword has a sword class I
strongly dislike I don't think that's a
good program model I don't think it's
very efficient for game development so
so I don't do that even so but you'll
have to come back later if you want to
talk about that more because I'm that's
something we'll be getting into in a lot
of detail
and Tom Forsythe is backing me up on the
shading language thing that the Hadamard
product is the standard product in the
shading language so basically yeah like
I would say I would say it's it's pretty
darn sketch to overload the multiply
operator to be dot product because man
you're gonna be in a world for a world
of hurt when you switch between that and
hlsl or that and GLSL or whatever right
did you add the quick calc hotkey no I
didn't I probably should quick calc is
pretty cool what would I use I got a I
don't have many keys free is one problem
right so I don't really know let's take
a look at the dot Emacs file I don't
know what Keys I have free um let's see
here
yeah maximize frame could probably go
away I don't really use that anymore I
used those fairly frequently next let's
go to that I use I menu undo up case
word I don't really use nor capitalized
word fill paragraph I do though replace
in region start keyboard macros
all-important kill this buffer always
use those make that asking yeah so I
could probably use lose maximize frame
so all P could be quick calc that is
plausible because that's not really
doing anything so we could do quick cap
like so you val region so we could do
that so let's let's go ahead and try
that we'll try that out so yeah that
goes let's see how it works 3 plus 5
equals 8 well done max
is XML fair game in this project it's
not a library but it still might not be
handmade enough well it would be fine if
you wanted to like load and XML file by
writing the parser yourself
that's certainly handmade right I don't
know why we would ever want to do that
but you know the the handmade part just
means we write everything with no
libraries so as long as you parse the
XML file yourself using your own code
with your own partial that you wrote by
hand that would be legal by these
standards of handmade hero so it looks
like we are done with questions pretty
early in fact if I'm not very much
mistaken
yeah all right well that was good
looks like we got one more that don't
you feel that low entities have already
too much extraneous stuff in them and it
would be time soon to split them and
also things like the sword might not
need the low part at all so it's not so
much that it that it wouldn't be
reasonable to split it now because there
is a fair bit of stuff in there and we
could start to think about how you want
to do it my fear is just that we haven't
gotten far enough with the types of
things that are in there so what I'd
like to see is I want to implement a few
more things so that I know that we have
like most of the types of stuff we would
care about in there some examples would
be like I'd want to have some property
transference like I want to be able to
have like like at a minimum right I
think what we want to have working
before we start writing any system is
there's a blue flame in the middle of
the screen and if you throw the sword
through it the sword picks up the blue
flame property and then when it hits the
monster it does blue flame damage or
something right and a minimum we want
transference of those sorts of things
happening in the entity system before we
would start to break it apart because if
we break it apart now we'll probably
make simplifying assumptions that are
wrong
because we haven't put enough complexity
in there so I want at least a little
more complexity in there and since we
have no reason why we have to break it
up now right there's nothing we don't
really care about our memory footman
footprint right now right we care about
our memory footprint way down the line
and so right now it's way easier just
have everything in that until we get as
much stuff in there as we can think of
that might be different like is they
disparate things we can and then it's
time to maybe break it apart and think
about it
what will we do at 3 p.m. PST when this
game is finished this game won't be
finished for like 2 years because we
only do an hour a day so I think you
really won't have to worry about that
for quite some time
right I mean we've got a little bit more
work to do a couple more weeks or
something on entity stuff that we want
to do then we've got maybe a week or two
on animation prototyping then we got to
write the renderer right that's going to
take several weeks to write the renderer
and then we're gonna come back and we're
gonna write the entity systems and stuff
that's gonna take several weeks then
we're gonna have to write you know some
sound stuff for some a couple of weeks
you know we're gonna be it's gonna be
June and we're only gonna be starting on
the game code right or something like
that and then there's tons of game to
write we got to write world gen we've
got to write all the properties that we
want we've got to write a eyes for the
monsters I mean in an hour at night
right so we are gonna be program this
game for a long time right it's gonna be
Christmas and we're gonna have only the
basic stuff working we're gonna have
like you know very you know half or less
of the game implemented and then it's
going to be the next Christmas and we'll
have most will implement or something
like that and then we'll still have to
do ship up shipping versions of the
win32 linux mac layers there's a lot of
work a lot of work ahead so so buckle up
are you happy with the current progress
yeah pretty happy actually because we've
only done so we've done like 62 hours of
programming right which is less than two
full weeks and we've already got you
know basic stuff working pretty well so
I'm pretty happy with the progress we'll
see how long the renderer takes I'm a
little nervous about how long the
renderer is gonna take but we'll see how
we do hopefully we do the renderer in a
reasonable amount of time if that if
that works out then I think we're in
good shape but what am I not
more than memory footprint I was
thinking about unwanted side effects ie
code that deals with the transfer
properties ends up triggering hard to
debunk shenanigans with the positioning
etc yeah I mean it's true that things
are harder to debug for us now because
we don't have any systems in place and
we don't have any debugging tools in
place either and so those will be things
that will get you know a little bit
further down the line but it's okay to
suffer through those right now because I
think it's it's not that hard to debug
stuff but most the time I'm done bugging
stuff it's a it's a typo at the moment
and unfortunately there's not a lot we
could do to fix that so I don't think
it's worth it right now to be doing
those sorts of things it's always a
tough call to make but I think it's
really not worth it to be doing that now
because the work that you'd be doing to
split apart low entity is all gonna be
wasted because all gonna be wrong if we
don't get more stuff in there and so
doing it to try to eliminate bugs I
think is a bad trade-off call that's
just my guess that it do we have any
more on top of questions mmm I do not
think so all right all right good deal
okay ladies and gentlemen thank you so
much for joining me for another episode
of hand made hero it was a pleasure
coding with you as always if you would
like to continue this adventure with me
I will be back here tomorrow at 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time same time same
place right here on Twitch and I would
love it if you could join me if you want
to follow along with the game at home
you can always just pre-order the game
and it comes with a source code which I
update every night so you can go ahead
and follow the video series and code
along with me to your heart's content
and and that's a pretty cool way to
learn from the stream if you are trying
to learn low-level game programming and
stuff like that it's a pretty easy way
to get started actually if you are new
to the series there's a bunch of stuff
we have a patreon you can subscribe to
if you want to support us that's always
very appreciated and if you're new to
the series also want to know
when what the broadcast schedule is we
have a little Twitter bot you can go
basically cami here our casts all the
links you can go to the tweets section
which is basically like a little bot
that tweets out the schedule every day
which is pretty handy and we also have a
great site the news and forum site which
I highly recommend checking out
basically it's got the schedule on the
front page you can keep track of that
it's got an episode guide so you can
kind of go through and go through old
episodes so if you wanna learn how to
set up a dev machine to follow along
with it with a stream if you want to
learn how to program the Windows
platform layer or everything that we've
done is in here and and it really makes
it much easier to catch up by going
through there we also have a coding
resources page which has some cool stuff
if you're looking to program on a
different platform people in the
community have already done ports to it
ahead of like we're gonna be doing that
later in this series but they've already
done it so if you're trying to follow
along on Linux or Mac that's the place
to do it and then of course there's our
code discussion board where you can ask
questions and stuff like that and I
answer them and also other people there
are other experienced programmers who
hang out on the boards and they answer
questions too so I highly recommend
checking that out if you're tryna learn
for you it's a great place to go so
thanks everyone for joining me I hope to
see you back here tomorrow again 8 p.m.
Pacific Standard Time right here on
twitch so hope see you back here
tomorrow and have a wonderful Wednesday
take it easy everyone