hello everybody and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete game
live on stream before I get started
today just wanted to let you all know if
you didn't see it already because I
tweeted about it
we Mali rocket here are doing
kickstarter for printing our comic which
are pretty excited about
we had been pretty excited actually
because we are comic was accepted for
van calf 2020 which is the Vancouver
comic Arts Festival which is you know
just it's a drive away from here right
we can we can just drive up i five to it
and we had gotten it done in time and
we're gonna print it and we were pretty
psyched about this because obviously if
you do a comic your end goal is to have
a print edition that's what everyone
wants for any kind of comic or graphic
novel right but then of course all
conventions have been cancelled from
from now until the foreseeable future
I'm sure I don't think there's probably
gonna be a comics convention for many
months possibly even a year I don't know
I mean I don't know when it you know it
would be considered safe to have some of
the convention which is kind of like the
optimal case for virus transmission
[Music]
people get sick at conferences even when
there isn't a new virus going around
there's often things like pax flu and
these sorts of things that people talk
about so so we don't actually know when
that's gonna happen again so we decided
we still really wanted to print the
things so we made a Kickstarter for our
comic that you can take a look at if
you're interested if you like comics and
you like space or cats or cats and space
please check it out we have the banner
on the top of the handmade hero page so
either of those pages that you might go
to on hand made here at up or it's got
it up there and you could just click on
the banner and it takes you over here
it's got a little animated trailer that
you can see here that's pretty fun and
you can read all about you know what the
comics like it's an all-ages comic it's
it's good for everybody and also you
know if so if you if you have kids who
like comics or if you like reading
comics with their kids it's okay for
that to like it's not nothing
gritties is
in it it's it's just a fun comic that's
uh it gets a little serious at times you
know it's it's it's got some some stuff
in it I'll just I don't want to give any
spoilers but it's you know it's not it's
not just light-hearted fluff so you know
it is something that's got some teeth to
it as it goes but it you know again it's
it's totally g-rated comic and it's it's
we think pretty interesting so there's
two books book one is done and that's
the kickstart is four we're starting
work on book two now hopefully you like
it you can check out the Kickstarter and
the trailer for more information there
you go that'll be running for 30 days
and you can check on the progress of the
kickstart as we go we also have a bunch
of fun stuff that we planned for this
month because if we're doing a
Kickstarter we wanted some promotional
things to do and we wanted those things
to be fun for everybody so also on the
market YouTube here that does all the
handmade hero stuff we are gonna be
posting a bunch of stuff now we already
had some things on here like Anna draws
it that you've seen before that are kind
of fun that are art based and we're
gonna be posting a bunch more stuff like
that so today we're gonna be posed to
get time-lapse of Anna drawing now the
main character that you can check out
tomorrow we're planning to post a new
series we have that it's kind of a
comedy thing that's some an art comedy
thing so if you want to just stay tuned
to the Molly Rocket Channel it's you can
subscribe to it or just it's just I
think you can just literally type
youtube.com slash see Molly Rocket I
think that works yeah so if you can
remember that you can always go check
back there we hope to have videos all
month long of fun stuff for people to to
check out related to the Kickstarter so
that's coming too and hopefully everyone
enjoys that alright that is it for
business let's take a look at the
non-business side of things
let me sub stardrive and get started
here so we left off last weekend we lost
one programming session to the fact that
I was pretty grumpy about some stuff
getting said on Twitter as usual
uh so you know let's let's just let's
just ignore that that's what happens
sometimes and let's go ahead and open up
a handmade hero and take a look at where
we were at so we had a lighting profiler
that we made because we need to start
optimizing this we didn't really finish
debugging it and we didn't really finish
doing some verification for it we had a
bug in here that some people noticed
this was supposed to be that and it's
amusing that it didn't crash but
probably because the boxes were not read
properly I don't actually you know it'd
be completely honest I'm not sure how
that was working you think that would
have crashed we must have just gotten
lucky and the way that the things were
allocated we didn't crash but there's a
couple bugs in here so there's a few
things we want to do one of them we
already fixed which is that we weren't
using the array sampling here but anyway
the point is we need to go through this
and make sure that we're actually
getting reasonable results out of it now
and we may want to actually make a
little thing that sort of pseudo
verifies those results and what I mean
by verifies those results obviously we
don't really have a way to unit tests in
a rigorous sense of the word a ray
tracer without some reference ray tracer
so it's not like we really can say for
sure that a ray tracer is producing
accurate ray tracing results necessarily
but what we can do for example is we can
at least lock our results to a known
case so we're starting with this ray
caster and we want to optimize it well
how do we optimize it we're gonna make a
series of changes to it and see if they
improve our performance based on the
profiling information that we have right
well when we're doing that it's really
easy for us to introduce bugs into the
system and not know and we kind of don't
want that because we want to know that
our ray cast are still working otherwise
we might go down routes of optimization
thinking that we're getting faster but
really what we did is introduced a bug
and the reason that's getting faster is
because we broke it right so we probably
want to do here is like capture the
results of our ray tracer into a log
buffer somehow so that we know that
they're actually what we actually got
out of it and then at the end we can say
oh did we actually get the same results
that we think we should have gotten in
for the Ray tracer
so we kind of need to do all this stuff
this weekend to get us in a place where
we can actually start doing it so we
want to do that and we want to actually
get vtune capturing profile numbers for
us
so we want vtune to tell us what our
performance counter is and we didn't
actually get that far in that we weren't
actually able to do that interface wise
this is why I say I normally use what's
a thing called perf on Linux which is
just a way of running an application and
getting the performance numbers out of
it that's what I normally do let me just
run this really quickly and see what
we've got here I just want to make sure
that we're still running this
application properly so anyway the
problem that we have and you'll notice
it's taking a lot longer to run now
which is actually good because before I
think we were just totally buggy before
whereas now we're actually getting like
a real runtime of the thing so I think
that's actually also good too anyway
ignore that all of that let me let me go
ahead and drop this down to something
more like 64 here um so we wanted that
variation but the other thing we want to
do and we could take a look at this
today as well in fact we can take a look
at this first because it's something
that I I need to find how to do I'm not
used to using vtune to get my
performance profile results so that's a
little bit of an issue because I don't
actually know how to make vtune do what
it is that I want it to do which is not
to give me some weird like Intel speak
discussion of my performance I don't
care about that what I want to see is
performance information that I care
about and it's a little bit harder to do
that then you know I would expect so if
you go over here and we run vtune
amplifier right what we did the other
day is we said like okay you know we've
got this HH light prof thing we got it
running here and I just I don't know my
way around this interface very well you
can go into this thing here and like we
can pick a couple different things so
like microarchitecture and memory are
access are like the two things we care
about parallelism we don't because we're
already running fully parallel and no
with no internet communication so we
know that our parallelism is fine in the
game and that's not our issue or rather
if we do need to check it it's gonna be
something in the game code not the
lighting code that's the problem because
there's no locking in the lighting code
so we don't need to check that in our
test amp we don't care about the
Hospice's because that's not really the
kind of preferred sauce we're doing here
what we want is these sorts of things I
just don't know like when we look at
something here like this costume
analysis I don't even know what I don't
know how to even get something in here
right I want to be able to do that right
I want some way of doing that I just
don't know how to get YouTube to do that
right so the question is how do we get
it to do like one of those custom
analysis things I don't I don't have any
idea right I just don't know is it like
siding behind there let me just know um
so what I want to be able to do is
something like okay like give me a
microarchitecture exploit exploration
and let me set these right let me set
these here but it's grayed out right so
you know how do we set it so in prayer
if what you do is you just on the
command line you say these are the
things I would look for that's what I
was wondering you know how we do I don't
know you know is there something in here
I can set and this is yv2 no ease throws
me for though I never know how to get it
to do just the things it's supposed to
do I don't know you look in here I can't
see anything like I don't see anything
about that right it's just I don't see
any check boxes in here there's no check
boxes right what if I set to summary
nothing there right so I just don't know
I don't know I don't know how to get
this thing to do what it's supposed to
do I have no idea and I were probably is
gonna have to read the manual right I
mean presumably you wouldn't have all
this stuff here if you couldn't make it
go now one thing I'm not sure about is
whether or not the driver and this talk
to each other properly so you know one
thing that ooh does this have anything
in it so no so one thing that I don't
know is like is it just not does it not
have like the right permissions you know
so like for example in here when we go
to vtune do I have to like try to run it
with extended permissions which I could
do that didn't seem to work
try it again there it is run as
administrator' um so I don't know like
maybe the thing doesn't have proper
permissions that seems like a
far-fetched thing because it installed
its own driver so the driver should be
able to do whatever it wants probably I
mean I guess I don't really know but so
if we run it as administrator I'm just
curious like can I get access to those
things or something no so I don't know I
just don't know let's go ahead and see
if we can get some documentation on this
because I just really want it to do the
same thing I would do on Linux with perf
and this is why I don't use v2 mitts
because I always find I just don't know
what I'm doing I feel like this should
be simple you just check a few boxes but
it doesn't look like that's really
possible so let me click on this
documentation button let's see if we can
find anything all I really want to know
is how do I get those those performance
counters right that's that's all I want
to know I don't I don't really need any
of this I just I just need I just need
some docs say how to make this thing go
right
this is the profile itself not the
documentation for it right
contents analyze performance custom
analysis can I get this
it's actually it's actually that that
was actually what I wanted was right
there so this is the thing I want is is
come come here come here
that was here it was here this is the
thing I want I think maybe I'm not sure
not sure what they're gonna call you
yeah yeah these this is what I want well
I don't really care about precise events
could be this yeah there we go
yeah that's what I want I want PMC yeah
[Music]
install the sampling driver which I
assume we did cuz we ran their installer
maybe we didn't do that but it wouldn't
be able to it when we ran a micro
architecture house before it seemed to
think it was getting those values so I
assumed that it did this worries me
it seems like they think this is obvious
and I guess I'm just thick about how
Intel designs interface like shouldn't
it just have a section called like how
to set up a custom I mean am I missing
it
maybe analysis types would it say there
I just need something just tell me tell
me how to ungrate ell me that's all I
want is that so wrong I don't know I
guess it is is it in here
okay okay alright alright here it is
we've got a clue we've got a clue create
a new custom analysis type based on
available predefined analysis
configurations so we need to use these
things here okay okay
so you see you see we're learning maybe
I can make this do what I want so if I
go to microarchitecture exploration and
then I click this maybe oh yeah boys
look at this now we're talking
all right so let's name this you know
fruit salad x12 or something right Oh
where'd it go there it is so fruit salad
x12 for now and in theory now I should
be able to actually tell it what to
create you know like all the fruit in
one delicious salad so now we should be
able to play around with this hopefully
and get actual like information here I
don't know what that exactly means but
I'm assuming that that just allows us to
get the pmc from our app I hope I mean I
don't know um the CPU sampling interval
in milliseconds here these I don't I
don't think these counters wrap do they
so I don't know that the sampling
interval needs to be that high or I
should say low one millisecond is waking
our app up way too often like I just
want the totals right I don't care about
any of this stuff if you look at what
Jesus okay so if you look at this
there's a lot of stuff checked and so
okay couple things here
so a little word of advice here just
from if you've never used these kind of
tools before so performance counters on
x64 are things that you effectively arm
like you say these are the performance
counters I want to record and then the
CPU basically has little counters and
every time one of those events that you
armed occurs it will increment the
counter but the problem is there's not
that many counters I don't remember how
many there are if it's like 8 or 5 4
maybe it's four I think it's four I
don't remember I'm sorry it only has a
certain number of counters which we can
go look up how many there are but let's
say it's four what that means is that
when you see something like this and
like this is what I mean even if there
are eight look at how many are there's
so many things checked here right each
of these events it cannot actually count
those events for you because there's too
many of them
so what it actually does is it randomly
or systematically depending on the app I
don't know how this one works exactly it
will just pick four to count armed those
wait a millisecond which is what this is
wake back up change which four it's
counting and go back for another
millisecond right so what it does is it
goes well if you're in a tight loop I'll
just time four of them then time another
four of them then time another four of
them in time another forum right but as
it's doing that it means the more things
you've checked the less accurate any
individual one of them is because you
were checking it for less time right now
maybe they're uniform across the whole
run of your application in which case it
doesn't matter but if they vary at all
the more things you check the less
accurate they'll be over the same amount
of sampling time does that make sense so
when we take a look at all of these
things we probably don't want even
remotely all of these checked at once
because we have a completely repeatable
workload right so all we're doing
is making it worse for us because we're
basically introducing a bunch of noise
into our thing we could just do
something else which is like look man
don't wake up hardly never please at
least I don't care about any of this
stuff right don't do that just and I
don't know what the uncor I don't think
we're timing anything on the uncor are
we I don't know that we care about uncor
in this at all the uncor is the thing
that's off to the side of the CPU that
handles other stuff right it's not I
don't think it's implicated here in our
performance here so we can crank these
up I would argue and then just reduce
these down right like just get these out
of here and so I think what we can do is
just I don't know how to clear these
exactly do I manually have to do this
like I kind of want to just I just want
them to all be off right are you kidding
me right now am I really gonna have to
go through these and check them all
myself is that really what's happening
is that what's going on here that seems
what's going on I also don't quite
understand why are these listed so many
times I'm a little weirded out by that
dude does anyone know maybe I mean if
you're if you could explain this to the
folks I don't cuz I don't actually not
can't explain that I don't know why I
don't I don't know what's going on there
right so so that's a little confusing so
I'm gonna try I'm gonna try just
clocking down here right
good to do and I mean am I missing
something
I mean I'm missing something right
please tell me there was a way to clear
these it isn't what I'm doing I didn't
see it but like clear all there was
there was no clear all that that wasn't
on the table I guess I mean what what is
happening here but but as far as I can
tell you got to do this yeah does anyone
know it's just really the fastest way to
do what I'm doing I mean I know everyone
at home really wanted to watch me sit
around for 15 minutes scrolling up a
very long window unchecking a bunch of
things that I don't want it to count but
you know was there I so you know I'll
still do it for your for your
entertainment folks believe me but I
don't actually know there we go all
right um so when we look at this now in
theory you know if I save this thing and
you know what I'm gonna do I'm gonna
call this not for yourself I'm gonna
call this no counters template because I
ain't doing that again all right
okay so what's this button do save
alright so I'm assuming if I want to I
can copy this template by saying okay
like this clone button here like copy it
and then I can say like I've got two of
them yeah okay so here I'll be like you
know the ultimate fruit salad every
fruit you ever wanted all diced up into
one delicious salad and then on here I
should now have a completely clean I
hope slate of these things yes okay so
now what we can do in theory anyway is
start to add things in here that will
tell us what we're actually what's
actually happening at a hardware level
right so if we want to for example we
should be able to select like how many
you ops were actually executed you know
in this thing so I assume something like
this right so you can see here like I
mean this right here alone would be the
complete analysis for just like the
throughput like the you know how many we
doing but we could say look if we're
targeting like you know trying to get
three you ops through or for you ops
through you know something like this
would be you know sort of what we want
right this would tell us how many total
you ops were executed in fact you know
what we could just do this and say
here's how many cycles none were here
are so many cycles like one two and
three were and that alone would just
tell us something about our stalls right
so let's suppose we just ran that I
assume we can now get some actual
information I don't actually know but
we'll try it again vtune not my
specialty
okay so now this is a lot easier for me
I don't know if it's easier for you but
like the this is the same information
you can get out of perf so I'm glad we
did this because this will actually help
me make sense of what we're seeing and
the reason I say that is just because
look I don't know really anything about
how about how vtune works and I'm used
to using perf which is just a thing
which literally gives you this so you
say you list the things you want like
here and then when you're done you look
at how many each event triggered and
that gives you some information about
your execution right so what you can see
here is if we look at how our
performance is at the moment again if
I'm not very much an error in anyone out
there who's the vtune expert please do
correct me on the chat if I'm wrong but
if you look at what we're looking at in
terms of hardware events here what you
can see here is it looks like it added
CPU clock on halted ref TSC
automatically for us I assume I didn't
check that right because I don't
remember checking that one I don't think
so if we go back and look at the
analysis configuration you can see I
didn't check that so it looks like no
matter no matter what we do it's gonna
use put that in there and that's fine
because that's basically just the thing
that tells us look how many clocks
happened right look how many clocks
happened on this on this core but that
we were while we were doing our check
right so that's fine it's a good
reference number for us then in here you
can basically see how did we do so if
you remember correctly from back in
there we talked about this originally an
x64 core from an Intel from the Intel
side so which is what we're on right now
you can see right here it's a cable ache
process or
it basically looks like a front end and
a back end the front end is decoding
instructions feeding into the back end
the scheduler on the back end has ports
it can issue instructions to each port
can handle certain types of instructions
at any given time the CPU is only
capable of issuing four instructions on
a cycle so it will decode an issue into
the scheduled scheduler up to four
instructions on any cycle it cannot ever
issue more so that doesn't mean that you
couldn't issue more than keep saying
instructions I don't mean them I mean my
crops so actual thing is you can do
there are ways you could get more than
four instructions potentially executing
apparently if those instructions don't
actually really exist if they're fake in
some way so there's for example ways
that they can get fused together and
things so you can appear to be excluding
more than four instructions but in terms
of actual work so doing and multiply
that's what's called a micro app or you
up you can see it here right and if
you're doing a micro op a micro op is
something that actually can only happen
four times a cycle there's only four
micro ops can actually get issued per
cycle basically right
and again there's something called micro
op fusion which means that technically
actually some things that do normally
count as micro ops can get SQUOZE
together so for example you can actually
sometimes have micro ops where you
actually get five in a cycle we're not
gonna go into that but point being when
you're actually talking about things
like multiplies you're never gonna get
more than four per cycle and in fact you
can't actually get four per cycle cuz
there aren't four multipliers on the
chip so what you end up looking at is
how many ports can issue the thing that
you're trying to do like a multiplier
divide and how often are you actually
issuing things to those ports that's
gonna give you your actual throughput
analysis and when you look at what we've
got here what you can see is at least to
my initial estimation right what we can
see is our utilization is not actually
very bad it's actually between 2 &amp; 3 is
where we pretty much live we're never
really stalling out for that much so if
you look at how our throughput analysis
looks already we're actually not that
bad
now we can extend this a little bit
further since now I know CPU clock on
halted was the thing that was actually
happening that that they're gonna add
always let's just do 1 2 3 &amp; 4 right so
we in here oh boy how do i okay okay
okay so now we kind of know what this is
gonna be I can actually name it oops it
doesn't have to be named I ultimate
fruit salad why do I keep licking that
that's what I want alright this is going
to be instructions per clock simple oops
simple performance gather of IPC right
and so all we're gonna do here is we're
gonna say look you ops oops
you ops executed we're going to go ahead
and say
that I think so we've got one two three
and four that should be savable that
yeah okay okay so now if I do this I
should basically just have a way of
gathering what our instruction four
o'clock tends to be right so how many
instructions are we actually able to
issue on every clock and what you can
see here is that we get one fairly often
pretty much all the time so we're not
really stalling out the core completely
hardly ever we get to actually quite a
bit so not very often do we fall down
three is getting lower we're only like
75% of the time hitting three right and
in terms of four well that's only like
half the time right that's not bad
so looking at this what that sort of
tells me without too much further
exploration right is I don't think right
now our primary problem is that our loop
is set up poorly or something right it
doesn't look like we're spending a ton
of time recovering from branch which
predicts or you know going to the cash
out to the l3 or main memory or
something it doesn't look like we're
having a lot of stalls it looks like we
are issuing at least two often three and
some client half the time for
instructions for clock which isn't bad
now it might not be good enough we could
still do better than that probably if we
actually go in there and start to think
about these loops but what that suggests
to me if I'm not mistaken and again
please take it with a grain of salt
because I'm not a vtune person I don't
actually know if I ran this proof
correctly I'm just not a vtune person
I'm getting to be a better vtune person
right now on stream this is my V tune
education here um but if I miss if that
actually collected the performance
counters that I think it did and the
performance counters that are actually
labeled properly as to what I think they
are
then this tells me that our first thing
to look at is not going to be try to get
the data into this routine more
efficiently right because it looks like
we're processing our data pretty
efficiently it looks like what we're not
doing is trimming the ops so we're we're
flooding we're putting too many
operations into this core so what we
want to try to look at now is ways of
reducing the workload not getting the
workload in more efficiently because
those are two things that could you know
the two things we can look at are get
the work in more efficiently and do the
work more efficiently and the do the
work more efficiently seems more
strongly implicated at this point that
just doesn't look like there's a huge
amount of fat in there to trim on the
throughput it looks like there's a
problem with our algorithm all right I
was doing too much work so how do we cut
that work down right all right so that's
the basic idea here and in order to get
a slightly different picture of that
what I'm gonna try to do now and again
caveat not a great vtune guy gonna go
ahead and try now to to get it to give
me another piece of information which is
what I would look typically look for
next which is who's getting throttled
okay so if we go ahead and okay okay if
we go ahead and clone this again right
so we are actually you know what I made
one for cloning so so it so is it this
button yeah so if I go back to our note
counters template and clone that one and
I go in here and say change this to port
usage and this is going to be or and and
you know what I'm gonna specifically say
arithmetic port usage
checking see how overloaded we are or
checking see which ports are stalling
right so you saw me try using my limited
vtune skills to have it tell me what the
performance counters were on the CPU for
which types of encyc alums one you up to
you up three you up and four you up
right so we were trying to figure out
how many micro ops we were issuing and
what we saw is that we're doing a pretty
good job issuing you ops but I'd like to
know now when we're not issuing for and
when we're not issuing three because one
and two were fairly likely when we're
getting when we're not issuing three and
four just double check which ports are
stalling right so who's the port that's
overloaded okay
now if we look in this list right what
you can see here is we can actually find
out for each individual port 0 1 2 3 4 5
6 &amp; 7 we can actually see which ports
are getting these you ops dispatched
right now if I check them all which is
the information we actually want the
problem is that on that run we won't
actually know which one is actually
happening right so if you look at what
that information would give us because
when we're running it that's too many
right it's too many for our perf
counters now it may be that it's fine
because again this loop is a tight loop
so it doesn't really matter so I'm gonna
try and see if V Tunes alternating which
ones we're checking works there but if
it doesn't we can actually do what this
is actually called with just arithmetic
port usage and get rid of the ports that
are actually not implicated in our
algorithm much so and just to give you a
perspective on that as you people who
watch the show
frequently know we have this bookmarked
the ecstasy for you op table and if we
want to we can look to see for example
the types of things that we're doing so
for example we know that we need to do
things like shuffle how do I make oh
where it is um so we know that we have
things like shuffle you can see the port
analysis here it's on port five now
again I'll just restate this you know
this I've said this a bunch of times but
so when you take a look at the you ops
dot info this is telling you for each
particular thing that you might be doing
on your process or this is telling you
what the actual port is that will be
necessary for the ALU to complete the
instruction so if you take a look at
something like a pea chef with which we
know we're doing for broadcasts and
stuff like that what you can see here is
for there's different ways in which that
instruction may have to execute and
that's what's listed here so pea chef in
this case like a pea chef D a pea chef
hwp chef LW you can see that xmm lines
the ones that just have X mmm they tell
you what the port usage of that
instruction is so it says one you OP on
port five is the only way right that
means that's what happens when you have
to do a patient it will execute on port
5 . if port 5 is blocked so on that
cycle you shove something into port 5
already that's it you cannot put another
instruction into that pipe so that will
block port 5 or wait on port 5 period
right so what are these other things
well anytime you see memory in there so
you see that M eye is immediate by the
way so that's just telling what kind of
shuffle to do right so an X mm is the
register M 128 is saying that it's got a
memory operand right and Intel x64 is
not a RISC architecture it's a Sisk
architecture so it allows you to do
things like say in this one instruction
load something and operate on it in the
instruction bypassing registers
altogether that's something can do so
this instruction is a bypass register
instruction it says I want you to do a
piece off on this register using this
piece of memory right right here and
that instruction itself means that not
only does it do the P chef which is
represented here you see it's the same
one you up on port five it will also tie
up the memory ports right so what does
this mean well the memory ports are port
2 and 3 they are the things that can
actually do loads and when you see 1
times P 2 3 what that means is that it's
gonna issue 1 you op on port 2 or 3 so
that means it has two chances to get it
right if port 2 is blocked condition on
port 3 if port 3 is blocked condition on
port 2 so that means we can actually
issue two of these per cycle now we
couldn't issue two of these per cycle
because they require port five and only
one port five exists if this was p1 5
for example we get issue 2 total piece
chef instructions but since it's only
has that one the pea chef will block on
the port 5 but if something else was
tying up port 2 no problem port 3 it
could use right so we care about the
arithmetic ports and what are the earth
medic ports well as you can see port 5
is one we may care about because it's
gonna move our data around not
technically arithmetic but we need it
for arithmetic we have things like a pea
add write an instruction that's gonna do
a pea add that's adding things together
for example what's the actual scalar add
though
what's what's the it's PS or whatever
it's that bad PS that's it
um I don't remember the mnemonics as
well as I should I don't do enough
assembly language programming I wish I
did
so if we're doing something like an ad
write what you can see is the typical
layout of these things is it's going to
be used on ports like 0 &amp; 1
right so port 0 &amp; 1 do the heavy lifting
of arithmetic usually you can look at
the mole PS you can see it's the same
right so if I multiply I'm in there now
there's a div PS and that you could see
is on port 0 right so you've got a lot
of different things going on there that
that we care about but they're all like
0 1 &amp; 5 that's where we're gonna be
hitting for our Earth minik are if
arithmetic so if we wanted to we could
just do this
and say look here's our like
floating-point arithmetic stuff that
we're gathering so I'm just gonna call
this like our like float port usage
let's say China Sea which ah what is
happening no no don't change okay there
we go I don't know how to use B time I
said that already
I'm checking to see which loading or
this is a analysis of floating point
port usage and related ports right so if
we want to we can go ahead and say let's
take a look at that specifically tell us
how our floating point port usage is and
now we've got a way to collect the
information about that so if I run this
one now in theory we should be able to
see a little bit more information about
how our floating point ports are doing
right so what's happening there all
right so again if we look at this
particular piece of information and we
see like what the port breakdown is what
it I'll be honest if we look at that
that doesn't look
fabulous is that what I think it is can
I get a good night can I get a I can't
can I let me just grab this guy in
that's cycles per thread when you ups
are executed in port five and cycles per
thread when you UPS are executed port
one cycles per thread beautyreport zero
right so looking at that it's a little
bit confusing
[Music]
I'm not sure how to interpret that
information so let me make sure I'm not
just confused but here's what that seems
to be saying right and this is good if
this is the case it's good we did this
because we're learning something so what
we said is eight point six plus eight
point six I'm just adding up these
numbers plus seven point six is
twenty-four
eight out of 18 so that to me says like
alright the number of times so if I
subtract 18 from that the number of
times we issued three you ops should be
around seven is that what we saw let's
try and get this going there we go and
see it's it's not so okay so this is
good this is information we needed so
that suggests to me that these when
we're looking at what you UPS are
executed here maybe we're actually
shoving things into the memory port a
lot more or something so I want to keep
going on this a little bit here so let's
actually ask this question let's do
another one of these where I just say
okay you know cloned this one I guess
let's okay let's call this all ports
usage general collection of all
execution ports at once and we're just
gonna say look alright I clearly need a
little more efficient before I can
decide what's actually happening here
oops I should just search instead of
scrolling you ops dispatched let's just
go ahead and say give me everything just
to see how good that does if that is
able to actually give us reasonable
information then we can go with
right so click that right and then I run
this thing hopefully I don't I don't
know if that's gonna work I'm just
trying alright uh so if we take a look
at what's going on here what you could
kind of see is we've got the port usage
breakdown and a lot of the stuff that
we're issuing to is on port 2 which
means we're doing a lot of loads there 2
2 &amp; 3 are our loads so what again you
can hopefully see why I wanted to do
this what that tells me is that if we
look at the total number of hardware
events that we were talking about here
which is 17.8 if we add port 2 and port
3 together right that's actually like
this number right so we're we're loading
a lot right these two issue together so
that's not really a fair comparison
there might be a thing word that's like
which cycles have something issued on
either port 2 or 3 which would be a
better way to read that potentially but
what you can see here is yeah our port 6
&amp; 7 not super interesting 5 somewhat
interesting 3 &amp; 4 which are right ports
I'm sorry 4 &amp; 5 or the right ports is
that right
no just 4 is the right port I forget cuz
5 is the permutation port so it's not
that what's the right port please tell
me
love I just need a mop PS I don't know
how to search for that let's see
mop ApS that's what it is orb ups in
this case there it is so this is the
load which we know this is the store so
it looks like it just it looks like it
can do two or three or seven actually
but requires port four so I guess what
you would say is probably doesn't much
matter because port seven is available
for that anyway so it's really just port
four is the right port so this is what
we're looking at for writes here you
know I'm saying and it's pretty
interesting that those are completely
balanced but no that's where we're at so
yeah there we go that's the port
breakdown as we see it it looks roughly
like what I want but not quite there yet
so I would like to see a lot more zero
one five issue right then we're seeing
so I actually do think based on this
breakdown now that we're looking at it
it does look like we could be a lot more
efficient with the memory okay because
I'd like to see us issuing zero and one
a lot more than we are and now I don't
know that that's because the memory
isn't coming through as fast as I want
but it does look like we're issuing a
lot of instructions to do loads and I'm
wondering if we can get that down right
so I don't know I don't know right I'm
just guessing but you can see why now
that I hopefully again caveat if vtune
is doing what I think it's doing perf on
Linux does this and I and it's doing
what I think it's doing this I don't
know if it is or isn't so I just don't
know um for example I don't understand
why if you're only checking for like
four things why this is only two and
that's 60 I don't know that doesn't I
don't know what why these wouldn't all
be the same like
I just don't know what it's doing but
anyway it doesn't really matter point
being hmm like in one where we only do a
few like here those should all be the
same shouldn't they because I'm only
asking for four counters I know it can
do four so I don't know what that means
Hardware event sample count
I just don't know so I don't know what
that means because I think these should
all just be the same right these these
should all be the same number
I would think but apparently they're not
and so that's I don't know what it's
trying to tell me here but it makes me a
little nervous like I said not a vtune
guy don't don't know um
so anyway if we actually want to now
take a look at what's going on that does
suggest to me I would like to see how
these numbers change if I start to
compact the memory usage a little bit of
this thing now before we do any more of
this I think I've done what I want which
is I now have a way to take the
performance analysis hopefully get the
performance announce numbers that I'm
looking for mm-hmm so before I go any
further I want to validate that our
actual code is working right because
these may be bogus numbers it may be
that I didn't that I've got bugs in the
test harness that are making it so we're
not really testing it's like not walking
the tree right or something right so I
do want to go now do some a little bit
of due diligence just to make sure that
like we actually have some some belief
in some modicum of understanding that we
actually load and raycast
these things properly right so I'm going
to go ahead and take an OD here
take a note we're gonna OD we're gonna
OD this so we get a debug builds and I
want to just step through the code a
little bit more carefully
first and then I want to add something
that looks at the results of the code
and tries to validate them a little bit
so when we go ahead and grab the box
dump here and we get three hundred forty
three boxes and we set the box count to
that and then we do an allocation the
allocation is going to be 4 times the
box count times the lighting boxes plus
however much it took to to store just
however many were in the file so this is
just giving us a Headroom for our tree
we're thinking AF read those in and then
we're gonna go into test raycast
the first thing we do is build the
spatial partition and that should we
don't actually want that did that
actually call debug dump data hoping
that's just stubbed yes good that's like
we don't want it to overwrite our debug
data not that it would matter cuz I
guess it is gonna overwrite it with the
correct data but that's fine um so we
come through here and we should see
ourselves building reasonable bounds
right so if I look if the occluder
bounds here in remedy what I should get
is I should see these expand as we go
through right and and that is roughly
what's happening by the way you can't do
this in Visual Studio cuz the watch
window so bad you can see me just
watching these things expand right
people are always like oh you don't need
to do that you can just set a date a
break point it's like that's not why I
want a fast watch window I want it so I
can do stuff like this I don't care
about data breakpoints very often John
does though and I agree with him I just
don't use them that often what I want
though is this I want to be able to run
a routine and watch the numbers change
it's a computer that's what it does
anyway so we can go down here to the
root box and you can see us adding the
root box in here
these look valid to me if I actually
look at that root box value what I
should see here is that it has you know
a a valid child count once I split once
I run the splitter so
we can get rid of this root lightbox
thing we don't actually need this
anymore but anyway um so hopefully you
know this trial count thing that's - is
correct that's how many there should be
and the first challenge is that so that
looks reasonable um I don't know what
this is about calculate r FC reference
center what do we use that for do we
know what this is for so
oh that's the colors oh yeah I forgot
we're still doing average colors for
root boxes I don't think we do that
optimization anymore so we can actually
get rid of a lot of that stuff because
we're not really doing this anymore we
maybe should to be completely honest
with you like it's possible that we
should be doing that but I don't know
that we're gonna write like I I never
really came up with a coherent argument
of like how we would make distant boxes
properly produce good ray-tracing
results and the reason for that is we
just don't know how much light comes out
of an area in a particular direction
right now and we need to come up with
some argument for like how we would do
that so anyway if we go in here to
entropy index what we want to do now is
we want to develop validate that we're
actually casting something reasonable so
the Rea origin of zero is just made up
we don't really know where we should be
casting and so that's a little bit of a
bug in the sense that we probably would
want to figure out a reasonable location
but I don't really know like we could
save that data like we could save that
in the lighting dump potentially I
suppose other than that I don't really
know how we would do it so if we go
through here and also by the way that
reminds me
wherever that dump is
this should be set to false now cuz we
don't want to dump any more when we run
right anyway um so now that we're in the
raycast we should be able to just take a
look like what's the Rhea origin right
like where is this thing and I guess I
don't know that's a 4 wide right so you
know it's just zeroes
what's the raid direction there we go
there's probably a better way to look at
this but you know it's valid right and
so when we do a ray cast now we should
see ourselves walk this tree right like
we should walk the tree pushing boxes on
it
like so right and off we go yeah so I
mean I think we're doing a reasonable
job with that you know I think we're
okay and if we take a look at the
results in theory at the end of it we
should end up with a thing we can
validate to a certain extent right and
that is the diffuse Atlas should have
now I'm sorry the speck Atlas should
have something in it now
the problem is I I don't know that
there'll be much in it and the reason
for that is because you need some light
in order for that to happen and so in
theory there was some light but I don't
know if it'll last I get picked up on
one frame we'll see but assuming that
there is some light in the D in the spec
atlas at the end of it we should be able
to verify that that's working now
you probably want to put something in
the diffuse Atlas as well because
otherwise we're not testing the diffuse
Atlas atlas sampling it's a little
Squinkie right one way we could do that
is we could actually just do a capture
like we could when we do our debug dump
we could actually prep a buffer that has
everything about the light cast in it
and maybe that's look maybe that's
actually better right
because I'm just worried like thinking
it through I'm just worried because I
feel like we want to actually be able to
validate the whole thing to a certain
extent so I do wonder if maybe the right
solution here isn't to actually capture
the speck atlas the diffuse atlas sorry
the diffuse analyst at the start the
speck atlas at the end validate that we
get the update we expect I guess we need
them both spec is and a few sets start
and then spec atlas at end I think I
might do that um that seems a little bit
better and then we can validate them so
let's try that so if I actually go to
the lighting code so if we actually jump
over to handmade hero for a second and
in the handmade lighting code here I
where we're gonna do this this debug
dump data here this bit again like maybe
we just dump this as the spec Atlas
sorry I'm trying to think this through
so in end lighting computation here I
guess I would say hey there folks
maybe this actually happens here and we
dump like multiple things so in a
different in addition to the boxes we
would also dump the Atlas so right and
then I could just say solution
I'm sorry speck Atlas how does this work
again and there's a one that gets you
the entire size it's this so we just say
look I don't know tell me how big this
whole thing is dump it all right and at
that point we should have the ability if
we dump the diffuse Atlas and the speck
atlas to reproduce the entire thing
right so we can do you know source maybe
we call these like source so we do
source lightboxes source Beca atlas
source diffuse atlas that's what's like
coming into the routine and then we also
dump like at the end so when everyone's
like done right we dump those two so
here you know we also say like here's a
recap you know I'm saying to you does
that seem reasonable cuz it seems
reasonable to me like that feels like
what you would want to do because then
we actually know what the result should
be now there's a little bit more to it
than that because we need to know a
couple pieces of information too so I
might go ahead and say that there's like
actually like one additional thing that
we'll store which is like a lighting
debug dump struct or something I don't
know and in there we'd say stuff like
what was the voxel were actually trying
to cast and
what like the sizes of things were maybe
something like that could just dump this
piece of junk cuz I think that would
have everything right so yeah maybe we
just do that
maybe we just dump that and call it a
day so that would just take the size the
solution and dump the whole thing so I
don't know just a just a off the top of
my head
situation if we now run and made hero in
theory we get this back a complete dump
that we can actually validate which I
like better because as I make changes I
don't want to change the substantive
results much I would accept the little
wiggle room but not much right so if I
go ahead and say let's go over to win
through handmade and I run this now and
I go to the data for handmade debug in
here we've got this lightboxes dump I'm
gonna delete that I'm then gonna say
let's let's go to a situation we're
gonna test I don't know maybe one of
these bigger rooms out here like this
situation right and then I can go ahead
and say yeah let's strobe like capture
that so I'll go over to this variable
here just turn it on right
and now in theory we should have
captured that data in theory you know
who knows we'll find out so now if I
take a look at in this directory here we
go we've got a light box set we've got a
dump of that struct
we've got spec atlas diffuse Atlas right
we've got the results versus the source
we don't know if it worked but we've got
it so let's try now loading this stuff
in and running the routine the same way
that we are running it in the game and
the only difference would be we're not
gonna run it threaded right so if I go
into the lighting code for the game here
and we look at the set of things that
has to happen so what I want to do
inside the lighting prof. now is just
first I want to make something that
loads files because that's gonna be
necessary right so I want something that
loads files and I want something that
will do a test ray cast that's the same
way that we do the test ray cast in the
actual game itself so in here I more or
less want to just call and I guess to
some extent maybe I literally just want
to call the work function so in here if
we have this compute light propagation
work I think I just kind of want to do
that right so in here with build spatial
petition for lighting that gets called
directly where's my and lighting
computation
here it is so what I want to do is I
want to just kind of do this so I want I
want this to look the same right so I
want to go through here and say like
let's do this whole this entire thing
has to occur right so we want to do that
and the only difference is we're not
going to contemplate the multi-threaded
case so we're just going to literally
put like this exact thing in here so
we're gonna do this we're gonna do all
of this every last bit and then the only
difference is we'll never do that case
so we're just gonna run it on a single
thread but otherwise it's exactly the
same right so this right here should do
all of the light propagation that we
want everything works the only
difference is this lighting cue is
nonsense right so I think that's okay
since it doesn't do anything I should
just be able to call it with a zero so
that just means I need to make sure I
allocate one of these or a large enough
one of these on the lighting structure
but other than that it should be fine
and if I do it that way then now that
means we don't have to do this anymore
what I can do is run it multiple times
if I want to but basically like that's
the work I mean there it is right so off
we go this doesn't require any of these
things
I don't think which is a bit of a
problem because I'm not sure where
they're gonna get them from so if we go
to the that actual function where we are
doing the work
so this is a problem we have to actually
set this up so we want to do this
probably but to be completely honest
with you it doesn't make sense to have
that in our system if we look at why
we're getting this so if you look at
this command structure here if you look
at why it has to be there it's not there
for a very good reason because the only
thing it's actually doing is getting the
diffuse atlases out of it so I would say
a better way to do this would be to
actually just store those two things in
the work structure because they are
work-related right there are things that
have to happen for the work to actually
take place so what I would rather do is
say let's go ahead and keep these two
things in the system where they should
be which is here so get rid of that add
this and then when the work dispatch is
happening we can actually set these up
properly so the diffuse light Atlas
comes from a few scientists the specular
light Atlas comes from speck Atlas and
now everybody's more properly contained
like there isn't this load of garbage
happening right where we're passing
rendering crap down to the lighting for
no reason so that means the only change
we would have to make here is we just
have to make sure that those get set
inside the place where we were
previously setting the commands up so in
here right this just has to now be
diffuse light Atlas equals like diffuse
Atlas and now it should be fine we
shouldn't have any more trouble with
that I don't think anyone who was
previously doing that has to do the new
thing now but that should be fine these
are not addresses up anymore they're
just regular accesses because it's a
pointer and I think that should be good
what's the problem here work times
previous yes that's true there we go
okay oops so now I think we're set up to
run like exactly the same code which I
think we want because if I'm going to
start doing this performance analysis
for real I might as well do it for real
so what we need to do here is actually
load in the atlases because currently
we're not actually doing that and we
need to do that so what I'm gonna do is
take this piece of code here which is
the thing that actually loads files and
I'm just gonna load the files right so I
want to function here and the function
is just gonna be called like load entire
file something like this right oops it's
gonna take a file name to load it's
gonna do exactly this the same set of
work that this routine was doing before
and it's gonna load that file in to
memory now the problem is I'm gonna want
to know the size of the file probably so
well actually I guess I don't even
really need that so maybe we won't
bother
[Music]
you know what we're gonna do read it
this way
oops so we've got this thing called
struck buffer I'm gonna use it so
instead of returning a void star I'm
gonna return a buffer and what I'm gonna
do with the buffer is I'm gonna put in
the size and the pointer so that way you
get both back so in here this is gonna
be like result that count right and then
in here we're gonna do an F read into
result dot data right like that so now
we need to grab you know the stuff where
we actually open the file so like this
and we'll print the error message there
too so we'll load that in we'll get the
file out with the FTL
we'll get the designs out we'll have to
do our malloc so result data equals you
know Mal'akh so result that counts so
via see how big the file is allocate the
data copy it into memory like so I and
be done with it right I also want to do
a thing called exercise where if we want
to you can pad your results out like
it's like so and that's just if you want
head room at the end of your buffer
because you're gonna add more stuff to
it or whatever
so load entire file just gets all the
information we need there so now we can
actually do a thing where actually we'll
just load all of this stuff right so
we're not going to do this anymore like
we're not gonna have you specify these
files I'm sorry we're just going to load
them all in so we know what they were
because we dumped them right so we're
gonna go ahead and and grab them in the
same way that we were doing them here
with the debug dump file
so all of this stuff we're gonna grab so
I'm gonna go ahead and Lemongrab here
I'm gonna Lemongrab like all of these
like so and there's one more which is
like the results set so we're gonna grab
those two so in here if we then say what
are the files we've got buffer we've got
like source lighting that's gonna be
like load entire file
we've got source light boxes equals load
entire file
we've got source spec atlas let's load
entire file source diffuse Atlas equals
the entire file result spec atlas load
entire file and we've got result defuse
atlas entire file so that will load
everything we have and we might as well
F close these even though it doesn't
actually matter because we don't
actually care and we should print out
the right file name here and that seems
good so once we have all of these
probably do something like this
and just say hey like if there was data
in all of them something like this then
we'll give it a shot so assuming that we
get data in all of them we'll try
running the raycast otherwise we just
won't and it will already have printed
out some kind of an error presumably but
like we'll just say you know unable to
run raycast test due to missing data
just give us a clue if that happens so
that's everything now we need to use
this data in some way that's actually
constructed so the first thing that we
can do is we can move this stuff into
the actual routine where it actually
happens so what we can do here is say
all right the global lighting solution
actually I'm going to work that way
there isn't going to be a global
lighting solution instead when we set
all this stuff up here right and we go
to do our test ray cast with whatever it
is that we're going to test right what
we want to do here is say well we
already have a solution now so our
lighting solution is just gonna be like
our the thing we dumped right the struck
that we dumped out that's that's it
that's the lighting solution we're going
to use so the data from that file is the
lighting solution as it was when we
dumped it so that's what we want now if
we dumped it at their appropriate place
which I think we did t Update blend is
set to whatever TM date blend was going
to be set to so we don't have to set
that presumably the series was also
whatever the series was supposed to be
because that doesn't get set either the
sampling spheres we're going to have to
said to the samplings for table because
that's an address we don't have that the
Vox cell dim and the in Vox cell dim we
already know what they are so we don't
need to use those and that means that
the fundamental unit doesn't have to get
set so now we're using our actual data
which is good right that's what we
actually want to know and in theory we
can probably we probably should have
saved this data out but I think we'll be
okay if we just because we know what it
is so it should be fine so when we make
our light atlases here
and we're ready to go the only problem
is the setting the texels we need to
actually set these to the actual texels
that they were but we know what they
were because we have them here so we
should be able to do it and just say
look the source spec atlas is where
you're getting those pixels from right
and the source diffuse atlas is where
you're getting these texels from and
then i think you just run the code I
don't know I mean right so I think if we
just clean this up now that's the thing
that we can run and have a little party
with our friends I don't know
so anyway mm-hmm that does everything
except the light boxes which we haven't
used yet
excuse me so we can assume the
excercises zero in all cases except for
for example in the case with the light
boxes for the time being we need the
padding there now we don't need very
much padding I don't know how much
padding we need let's just say we need a
massive amount of padding who cares it's
just a test app mm-hmm so that'll
allocate way more memory than it needs
then what we know is the boxes here so
you know in this thing where we were
going to set up these the the solution
boxes here we need to actually like this
stuff right the box count will be
correct but the box pointer will be
you know I'm saying to you you know I'm
saying to you right the boxes are not
there we dumped the struct it all it all
it has is a pointer to boxes that
pointer points to nothing because we
just loaded a value out of a file it's
not pointing anything so we have to
redirect it to point to the actual boxes
we saved which that will do so I think
mm-hmm that should run the test now we
probably screwed something up but at
least that's the that's the idea right
so you get the idea let's run it and and
we're gonna have to set our source up to
be here yeah um so now let's go ahead
and and go in debug mode let's debug
this get it working and then validate
the results to see if we can get them to
run the right stuff right okay so in
test rate cast oh yeah we forgot to
allocate the work solutions that's
another thing that we need to do from
the lighting cuz that gets allocated on
begin on an it rather um so here's that
code so let's just do solution work I
don't know what this whoops I don't
actually know what that's called what is
that called it's called
works so I want to do a man lock there
to get a lighting work array so I'm just
gonna do a malloc size of lighting work
oops
work times oh and we need an alignment
here well we could use an aligned malloc
I don't know do can we just use push
array can I just use push it right here
I propped you know what I can't use push
it right that's a lie
I can't use push array because we would
have to have a platform allocator hooked
up so I guess I'll try and aligned
malloc maybe although what I could do
here is force it to be aligned by doing
something like using a line as right so
in what's the name of that thing in C++
is crappy nonsense all right so a line
as should work right so in theory we
should be able to do something like this
where we just say look a line as 64 well
actually no I take it back since we're
running single threaded we don't care
about false sharing here so actually we
don't care if this is aligned at all
that doesn't matter
nevermind we're fine yeah yeah we're
fine we don't care about this so we just
need enough of these to make sense and
if I remember correctly the calculation
for that was we just want this right
which we we have we know that number
right so I think we're okay now we've
got the works let's see what else goes
on in here so there we go we ran the
test case and running the test case we
now at the end of this the spec Atlas
array
of texels should be updated right so
what we want to do is try to validate
that we know that we've got like a
source here where we can say whatever
the result spec Atlas is that we were
looking at and we've also got our result
or I guess we should it's not source
texels it's it's the thing we want to
test against this is the expected and
this is what we got right so this is
going to be our texels so get texts get
light atlas texels so we just want to
get the light atlas texels of our spec
atlas right like so so what we can do
now is compare these so I'm just gonna
ask how many of these there are so like
how many texels there are in the spec
atlas and then I'm just going to loop
over them
and so all I'm doing here is reading in
all of the texels that we expected to
get and all of the ones that we actually
did get and I'm just gonna have a total
error accumulator right so I'm gonna say
we expected this oops
expect heed we expected this we got this
I'm subtracting the tube taking the
absolute values so I can just say this
is how much error there was we look at
how much there is and then we just say
look that's the total error right we can
also say total error protects 'el and
that's just going to be the textile
count that we have so whatever the text
of count is we can divide the total
error by the text account and that's how
many how much air there is protect so
now to get this routine working we would
like to see zero right so if I go here
and I run light prof we'd like to see no
error at all right and we sort of do
meaning that's pretty good it's weird
that we saw any at all because you would
expect this to run the same but we
didn't compile in release mode so it's
possible that it's just like optimise
some floating point optic ount for that
probably so let's try and release mode
same deal
so I'm not sure about that it's
incredibly low error to have if there
was something off
so the total number of texels is six
hundred and fourteen thousand and the
total error is only 324 per Texel the
error would be invisible that's below
the threshold you can actually see when
quantized down to 8-bit so let's just
for my own sanity let's just try
breaking something here so let's see
what the error would be if I actually
just like incorrectly like tracked
something so for example oh I know what
so let's suppose we do a different blend
so in here after we set the solution up
let's set the T update blend to one
forget it
let's just go go nuts right because
again this is the sum so we're only
blending 95% saz well so if we're gonna
our errors already dropped synthetically
some little just a little worried right
yeah so we got this is not right like
that should be like super Airy so I made
a mistake here not sure what the mistake
I made is but I made one
because I mean setting the ste update
blend to one should have given us a
drastically different result right
so what's wrong here we load everything
in do our raycast
we've set our sources up we test we load
expected texels out of result spec Atlas
which is like not touched right we don't
do anything with that we sum the error
and this should make us get like totally
hosed right
so at least that changes the total error
so something's a little fishy so let's
actually take a look and see if we can
figure out what's going on here cuz this
is a little bit busted I think it might
just be hey because that update is so
weird I mean like let's say I do this I
should be I mean I should be able to get
a pretty crazy error out of this right
seems reasonable not sure why it's imp
there we go so for whatever reason it
looks like that's just T update blend
equals one is not enough somehow to make
the error as much as I think it should
come out to be which is a little bit
weird so I'm a little freaked out but
we'll see we'll keep going so at least
now we have a way of validating and
we're not really in the ballpark here so
something's a little bit up and I'm not
sure exactly what it is we have our
diffuse scentless in our spec up atlas
set up in theory I guess one possibility
too is that I don't know if that if we
actually dumped those correctly like
maybe I dumped the wrong things so this
dumps the lighting solution this dumps
the light boxes as you would expect
that's the spec Atlas texels tested a
few set lists excells then it runs okay
so actually
no cuz okay so that will we're now doing
exactly that so we're actually doing the
whole thing too right
we're actually doing the this part as
well right so we're actually doing the
part where we fill in the everything so
everything is happening there's nothing
we're not doing now so again I'm just
not sure I'm not sure what we failed to
account for there or what our actual bug
there like what we're not setting up ah
we're not doing this we're not doing
this so that has to happen as well
right because the diffuse light Maps
probably aren't saved here they might be
nope they are so did a few suede maps
will be set up to the light sampling
spheres won't be so we have to make sure
those are set up but everything else
would be right everything else would
just be stored there's no other pointers
in here that we care about we restored
that one we create this one and we
update that one right right there so
we're running the exact same code using
the exact same settings and we're
getting the wrong results out why is it
happening
what's the secret and I don't know
[Music]
so we dump them down here does anything
happen to them in between I don't think
there is I don't see anything so I don't
know I know how much time do I have left
here to look at this I guess I have
eight minutes it's not very long so we
want this to work more exactly if there
was a very tiny amount of change I maybe
say it could be okay due to the
difference between the two compiles
perhaps but I don't really feel
comfortable with it the way it is now I
think it's wrong so I want to find a way
to figure out why we're getting
differences here between the two pieces
of code because as far as I know we're
running them the same way I think that
doesn't do a clear or anything so that
should be fine and those look both
reasonable
yes so I and I don't really see anything
else here that that bothers me much so
yeah hmm that's a puzzler
why wouldn't we get a similar results
here I don't actually know
what happens inside compute light
propagation work oops we look at the
work the solution the juice is not
specified okay we get the ant entropy
out of the work the entropy in this case
is just the random next to the series
that should be set the same in both
cases because that's the entropy has
something to do with it but that should
be fine because we're sending those this
stuff we don't care about because it
again came from the things that the
speck atlas we do have to have set right
but as far as we know we did we just do
basic stuff with the tiles here we do
exactly what we expect we run full cast
we update here I don't get it I don't
see the problem so you may have to start
on this tomorrow because I don't see the
problem unless somebody else caught it
why we shouldn't be able to get similar
results out of both of these so I'm not
sure why we're running this exact code
base as far as I know so now we're not
we're not really doing any test version
we're just running the exact code pretty
much identically right and we run each
work in series which I suppose is not
exactly the same but I don't know why
there shouldn't be any
oh well actually that's weird what
happened to my ah crap
alright so it looks like somehow I got
that accidentally removed I don't know
if that's the only problem but what you
know one thing I might want to do here I
guess is make this be something you can
call to eliminate that source of error
right I may do that make this right here
be something I can call to eliminate
that source of error let me see what
happens when I run this now oh and and
we'll get rid of the the intentional
working there so or did I already do
that yeah T updates not getting set
anymore
right yeah so unfortunately still wrong
right so that was not sufficient I guess
is that yeah so that was not that was
not the problem unfortunately so um what
I'd like to do let me go ahead and
remove that source of error though so
I'm gonna make something here that's
just called like internal void lighting
core right and what I want to do is I
want to try and make it so that this
exact thing like this here
this exact thing here I want to be its
own thing right and I'm gonna actually
put the debug dump for the output right
at the end of it so that way we know
that like it's completely self-contained
like so right so it'll do exactly this
it will take the lighting solution the
spec Atlas and the diffuse Atlas right
so it'll take those it'll do this work I
don't know where the lighting cue comes
from it's here yeah
and so when here what we'll do is we'll
say and it takes the lighting cue if the
lighting cue is valid will dispatch it
if it's not we just do the work right so
that way you can switch between threaded
and non-threaded just by changing the
parameter to this function right
and so in here when we actually call it
which is right here we would pass the
actual lighting cue so that it'll be
multi-threaded but in here when we do it
we wouldn't so instead of test ray cast
I'm just gonna call internal lighting
core we're gonna pass our solution our
spec Atlas and our diffuse Atlas and
then we're just gonna pass 0 so it won't
actually thread right and now at least I
know we're doing the same thing right so
that we can do a capture we can make it
do the right thing you know what I mean
everything will make sense so this part
of the code - I guess that can actually
just probably be there I mean I don't
know this part here where we we do the
summation
I think this just wants to be right like
we'll just return the work camp this is
how many units it used right um and then
I think we're okay so only thing I need
to do now is when we call that it
doesn't have a platform layer but that's
fine
I think we can just do like this where
is that platform where is that stuff
well you know what it's just this value
right so where is the platform got
update my editor one of these days
platform API
so now that that's used I need to have
it be somewhere right so in theory oops
in theory we're good now there we go so
tomorrow we'll debug that but then I
think we're good to go because we got we
got issues right we'll go ahead and go
to Q&amp;A real quick
is it still build on oh you just want to
if the build flag is it's Oh - right now
so that's that's Oh - here's our D and
they had exactly the same result so it
doesn't look like it's particularly
related to a floating-point precision
problem it's like a bug right capture a
single-threaded run I mean you mean just
to see if it's different does anyone use
let me just see if there's some kind of
weird accidental sharing in there
because I agree we should see if maybe
it's a sharing issue
so I mean you know this is a sharing
issue in the sense that these are not
necessarily particularly correctly
aligned I mean so but it shouldn't it's
not over over writing a value it's just
a speed issue potentially right but but
I don't think I don't think so
on your us in fact Abele in the stream
you were set to sky like rather than kb
like just in case that's why you were
seeing issues uh but they're the same
right they have the same port layout
like they don't they don't change what
what ports they are right I'm not sure
what happens if I check both of them so
there you go so the port layout between
kb lake and and sky lake are the same if
that makes sense
the ice lake is a pretty different
architecture i think so
that if you were on a nice Lake core
that might matter you know I'm saying to
you so you know hey it's issuing on port
9 what the heck is port 9 right Scotty
doesn't have a port 9 I don't think so
so ice Lake would matter but but sky
lake is KB Lake is coffee Lake it's all
the same ice Lake which has been a long
time coming
it still hasn't really arrived ice Lake
is still not here you have to go by like
a low-power like a notebook part to get
a nice late core as far as I know like I
don't know that you can get I don't know
that there's like a core i9 ice Lake
there maybe there is maybe someone who
keeps up with that stuff more than I do
you would know but ice Lake is like just
in notebook chips now as far as I know
cuz it Intel's had such a hard time with
it
it's their ten nanometer process which
is a pretty dense process and it didn't
really work like the process node was a
really bad disaster apparently so like
they can barely fab the chips is my
understanding and so ice Lake just
didn't materialize so they have notebook
parts that they been shipping this year
last year I mean but they don't have
like desktop chips I don't think I don't
know I don't think maybe there are I'm
not sure
so I don't know if they've ever actually
made a nice lake desktop chip that you
can actually buy it looked like I can
buy they may have ones that are like
very special purpose but I don't know so
yeah
we uncheck that this is such a great
site thank you to the folks who built
this I don't know why they built it or
what they hope to gain out of it just
other than being cool but it's awesome I
mean it's just great uh have you
considered releasing your secrets
earlier as a beta release just so many
because no sern courting uh I mean if I
thought I could release it now I would
it's not ready yet so I I will release
it when it's ready to be released but
you know it's of course it's people are
trying to learn from it I'm not going to
release something that's not right yet
how long I there's there's really no way
to answer that question because the
course is somewhat nonlinear and it's
actually very uh nonlinear and it
depends a lot on what knowledge you're
coming to it right it's designed to
cover everything and so some people will
have to start like at the beginning
beginning like they don't know what an
entry point or a function is right but
other people who you know maybe they've
programmed JavaScript for awhile or they
know Python or something right those
people don't need to spend any time at
all on that part of the course like they
know what a function is they just maybe
don't know how they work in C or some of
the things about how like functions are
actually implemented in hardware or
stuff like that so I think like that's
really what how long the course is
depends on what you need to get out of
it if you just are looking for certain
aspects it is a much shorter course than
if you are literally coming to it at
zero which some people might be right
bulbous is it bad on x86 to do online
pointers No so x86 cores for any of the
ones you're that in modern circulation
like skylake or anything else they don't
have any penalties for unaligned
pointers you can load off of unaligned
pointers all day long and it's fine
however that said there are a number of
things you have to think about when
using unaligned pointers there are still
penalties for example for pointers that
cross a cache line or that cross a page
boundary there are potential cases where
those can hurt you page boundary
definitely like so if a pointer crosses
a 4096 byte alignment
it's a problem right so they're aware of
that and the other thing that you have
to be aware about is aware of is what
your minimum target is so for example
let's suppose that your minimum target
is not a VX so your minimum target is
SSE like two three or four that if
you're if you have to compile code just
for sse2 then there is a real penalty
for unaligned pointers and that's that
they can't be memory operands SSE for
really bad reasons and it was really bad
I don't know why they did this they made
it so that memory oper operands fault on
unaligned I don't know why they did it
it was a really really really bad
decision they fixed it in a V X so if
you're compiling with a V X is a target
and you use V prefix instructions then
you can just have underline pointers
everywhere but if you are compiling
without a VX enabled so you're compiling
with SSE two three or four compatibility
then you have a problem now that problem
may not materialize is any actual harm
to your performance and the reason is
because unless you're actually executing
four instructions for clock you probably
have a free instruction for a memo in
there anyway right so it's unlikely that
it's actually that big of a deal
sometimes it can be though and you have
ten extra register free so it depends
how much you're pushing the boundaries
right if you're really pushing the
boundaries of the performance of your
chip it could hurt you if you're not
pushing the boundaries it probably
doesn't matter a lot of line pointers
are generally fine just be aware of the
limitations
do instructions with memory operands
actually use the earth we took units
before the data is ready no so an
instruction with a memory operand it
becomes multiple you ops so the way to
read this so let's take the one that's
on the screen right now so move ups with
a memory operand this is a store right
oh wait but that's just a move so sorry
I need something like we had before okay
so this is something that does an ad
right so this is an ad from memory so
it's going to take some register you
give it and then a memory destination
and it's gonna do an ad the ad is going
to happen on one port and the load is
going to happen on the other port so the
way that you see this here this first
thing p01 that's the ad port and this
thing here p23
that's the load port so what actually
happens here is when you do this ad PS
first it will I didn't say the whole
thing I'd say this equation this pseudo
equation the plus means more than one
micro op right
this means number of micro ops in each
term so this is 1 micro op issued on
port 0 or 1 plus 1 micro op issued on
port 2 or 3 right so what happens there
is when you issue these microbes I
believe that's what it is I don't think
that's cycles I think that's microbes
but it could be cycles that could
actually be cycles so I'll be honest I
take it back
I don't know how they issue like I don't
know if that's 2 cycles on port p5 are 2
microbes on port p5 it's probably 2
cycles so I take that back it's 1 cycle
on port 0 or 1 plus 1 cycle on port 2 or
3 it's probably what actually what's
actually happening there so I take that
back either way the point is these are
two separate microbes
so when you see the ad PS instruction
with a memory operand it actually
generates two separate things that have
to happen first the load then the add
the load will first get issued on port 2
or 3 the ad will not get issued until
the load is done does that make sense
so until the load actually comes back it
will never touch port 0 or 1 at all
until the load actually comes back is
the course gonna be useful for hardcore
fans of handmade hero I guess I would
say if you've literally watched and done
the and followed along by programming on
every episode of handmade hero no
probably not but if you just kind of
watch the series probably yes that's
what I'd say
I mean the reason for that is just we do
everything on ham here I don't know what
else we could possibly cover you know
what I mean I mean I've gone through so
much stuff is the course project-based
where throughout the course you make X
or Y project yes it is is there an API
to access the performance counters so
you don't have to use vtune sort of so
there's two things if you install vtune
i think you can use dll calls if you
have you vtune installed to do some
performance kind of stuff I'm not sure
but I think you can maybe don't quote me
on that but the other thing is event
tracing for Windows may provide access
to these counters may don't quote me on
that either if what you're asking is the
more general question of is it plausible
to say build this into profiling in a
game no it's a disaster
it has to be running as administrator
even to just query them and stuff like
this
it's a it's bad so I don't know of any
way to do what you actually want which
is to say I'm a developer I'm an adult
give me access to my CPU counters with
some expletives thrown in there it
doesn't I don't know of any way to do
that there is a long route to it which
is I think there's an open source
project that has like there's an open
source driver that you can compile
yourself and install that I think you
could then call to get the performance
counters I think don't quote me on that
but I think that would be about the only
way to do it there's no way to just make
an executable that does it you can't do
that because it has to run in kernel
mode
all right I'm gonna go ahead and wrap it
up
too many windows open
all right okay thank you everyone for
joining me for the notes on a handmade
here it's been a pleasure coding with
you as always if you want to follow on
the series at home you can always go to
handmade hero org and you can pre-order
the game it comes with the source code
so you can follow along at home we also
have a Kickstarter running right now for
our comic we're doing a print edition of
it if comics are your thing please go
ahead and check that out there's a
banner on every page of the website that
you can click to to head over there I'll
be running for about 30 days and it's
pretty cool so check it out we also have
a bunch of videos coming that go along
with the Kickstarter so if you're
someone who follows the the channel that
we do here at Molly rocket that has all
the handmade hero videos on it we will
be having a bunch of videos on there
starting today there's a time-lapse of
them now drawing going up on there and
then they'll be some other fun stuff
that we're doing probably some
additional streams too so stay tuned for
that stuff I'll be posting about them on
my Twitter feed and they'll also be if
you subscribe to the video if you
subscribe to our video channel I don't
actually know these days if you can get
notified like if you subscribe to the
thing I know there used to be like a
bell you could click on to get notified
I don't know if YouTube seems to
consistently be nerfing all that stuff
so I'm not sure what to do other than
just say look go to the videos tag of
our YouTube channel here's a trailer for
the comic there'll be more stuff getting
posted in fact I'm gonna post one right
after I get off stream now so check that
out there should be some cool stuff
coming on this channel all all this
month for like the next 30 days
so that's about it alright that's it
everyone
see you around see you tomorrow for the
next performance analysis stream
hopefully we can get the stream
validating and then we can move on to
trying to get it faster that's it for
today and I'll see everyone on the
Internet take it easy everybody