okay hello everyone and welcome to
handmade Hero the show we code a
complete game live on Twitch no engine
no libraries it's the complete set of
codes that's necessary to run a game and
we do this for both educational purposes
and also just because hey it's kind of
fun to do this kind of code if you're
the type of person that likes
programming oftentimes it's kind of fun
to get down into the guts of things
because it can be a lot more rewarding
and a lot more interesting to kind of
see how things work and also kind of
tinker with them right now we're doing
some work on we just started yesterday
on multi-threading our application and
the reason that we're doing
multi-threading we covered yesterday
basically the problem with processors
these days is they are out of places to
add speed in terms of clock rate that is
just they hit a kind of a thermodynamic
wall somewhere around the four gigahertz
range and so now a lot of the speed that
you get from modern processors comes in
the form of other things such as wide
registers like Cindy which we did
operations for a couple weeks back and
things like what we're doing now which
is multi-core where you can run several
different streams of execution in
parallel at the same time and leverage
that to make your application go faster
so what we're doing is we're showing how
to multi thread some of the stuff in the
renderer and yesterday I gave an
overview of what multi-threading was if
you missed that please check it out
because it contains all the fundamental
things that we'll be referring to
throughout the week as I show different
things and we also at the end of the day
yesterday showed how to create a thread
in win32 so now we need to do today is
talk about how we will actually use
those threads to do something useful for
us and in order to do that obviously we
need to start talking about how threads
communicate with each other and how they
know what work to do and that sort of
thing so we're gonna do another
blackboard session today possibly not as
long as a previous one but another
blackboard session today that talks
about the sorts of stuff we need to do
in order for threads to work together
and then again we'll pop back over win32
and show how we could do some of those
things in win32 and that should set us
up for at least by tomorrow actually
having the threads do some real work for
us maybe we'll get to that today but I
don't know sometime
the Blackbird sessions take a while to
really thoroughly explain things so you
know that that tends to eat up a lot of
time but anyway so here we are on day
123 so let me go ahead and and give a
little bit of a have an overview here I
don't know why we are locked in that
mode there we go all right now we're out
of it so yeah all right so here we are
on day 123 and let's talk about like
thread synchronization and also I guess
we might want to call it communication
right so where we left things yesterday
I showed how easy it was and 132 to just
create more threads so basically we
could create as many threads as we want
that's really not a problem and it's
obviously very easy for us and went
through YouTube to create as many
threads as there are processors in the
system will show a little later on a
little further down the line how to
query the system to find out how many
threads we should create and that sort
of thing but obviously it's very easy
for us to just go ahead and create these
threats but where we left it yesterday
it was not clear how those threads
actually start doing useful work for us
so we need to think about a couple
things now the first thing that I said
yesterday that comes into play here was
that threads and processes are not the
same thing right because remember we
talked about processes and processes are
different memory spaces so two processes
in order to share work with each other
have to do a lot of special things in
order to make that happen they have to
set up some kind of pipe between
themselves in the operating system or
explicitly request that the operating
system allow them to share certain
memory ranges so stuff has to happen in
order for processes to see the work that
each other does or to get the data that
each other produce that sort of thing
but threads are not processes threads
inside a single process all actually run
in the same memory space so what that
means and we showed a little bit of that
yesterday actually but what that means
is that our threads can all work on the
same data right so basically if we have
a bunch of data here like in the case of
the renderer
right we had our push buffer which is
what we need to operate on and then we
had like our frame buffer you know right
and then we had you know our bitmaps and
stuff and what that means is these are
all laid out already and they are
accessible by our main thread when we
create new threads those threads can
actually all read these just fine and so
if we just pass in remember when we
created the thread we were able to share
global variables with it and we're also
able to pass in one pointer and 132 it's
startup so there's actually plenty of
ways we can we can sort of tell the
thread hey here's where the data lives
right so it's actually pretty easy for
this thread to get access to all of the
information that it needs so we won't
have to do any real work to make sure
that each individual thread can see the
things that it needs to see because
unlike processes threads always have
access to all of the memory that's in
our process so that's not a problem but
there are two problems that do have to
do with threads okay so number one is
knowing what work to do okay because
once we have multiple threads of
execution right it's a nebulous problem
how do they know what they should be
doing right implicit in all of the work
that we've done in handmade hero so far
and if you've never written
multi-threaded code implicit in all of
the code that you've ever written is the
fact that you've never had to think
about who was actually executing the
code that she wrote right
you just wrote all the code line by line
and assumed that we executed in order by
one person right by one core that would
come along and executed in order but
once we have multiple threads that's not
the case anymore all of the code that we
have written could be executed by anyone
at any time and we have to start
thinking about how we would like to tell
each thread where it should do its work
like what is what are the routines they
should run what are the data they should
run them on we need some way of actually
making that work literally physically in
the code so that these threads know what
to do right
and again it's implicit in everything
we've done so far because our code just
started at one place and we just kept
calling functions right and that's how
all the work done
but now we have multiple people
essentially multiple of these places in
the code that are running at any given
time we have to fundamentally rethink
our model right for how code works
because now there isn't just one big
long chain of people calling functions
and returning and doing loops there's
multiple of these and we have to have
some model for knowing who should do
what work when okay so that's one thing
and number two we need to make sure that
people are sort of how should I say this
it's it's it's synchronization but it's
also the concept that different people
are doing different work at different
times so we need a notion of when work
is done right or visible because there's
a problem that I'm going to talk about
in detail now that happens with
multi-threading that you'd simply don't
have to think about when you're doing
single threading and it's very important
okay so I'm gonna expand on this because
number one is pretty I think
self-explanatory what I said it's just a
logistical problem and so we can look at
how we solved that a little bit later
but hopefully you understand what the
problem is the problem is all the code
we've written so far is just about us
calling functions that's not going to
cut it when we have multiple threads we
need ways of distributing work out to
these other threads so obviously the
easy problem to understand maybe not
super easy necessarily to solve but you
know it's clear number two is a little
harder to understand so now I want to
talk about what that is all right
so currently the way that we do stuff in
our code implicit is we'll do stuff like
function a we'll call it then we'll do
function B right and we'll call that an
implicit in this is that this will
happen before this so anything in our
code that had an order dependency the
only thing we ever have thought about
before is what we just put it before the
thing that it's that depends on it right
if function B needs to use the results
of function a we know we just need to
call function a before we call function
B done right but once we start talking
about multi-threading we start noting to
ask the question what if we want these
to happen on separate threads right and
more specifically just again
an example of why this might be the case
let's say we had something that actually
looked more like this right let's say
that we had you know multiple different
ways we wanted to invoke function a
right and then at the end of them all we
have function B which takes all of these
in right all of the things that these
guys did they all wire into here
eventually right so this is the results
of it this a 0 a 1 a 2 the results of
all these right whatever they are all
get wired in here now if each one of
these functions is very expensive let's
say function a takes you know a
millisecond to compute yeah so we may
look at this and go oh you know what we
want to do right we would like to be
able to have all of these things run
concurrently so I'll put a thread you
know thread zero will do the first time
thread one will do the second time
thread two will do the third time and
then some other thread and we don't care
that is maybe it's one of these guys or
maybe it's a fourth thread even we don't
care really right
we'll run function B ok so we assume
that we have some solution to this
problem right we've already solved it we
know how we're gonna dispatch these
things they get dispatched and whatever
there's another problem again the Coasta
related which is that we can't actually
whoever's gonna run this function B
cannot actually run until all of these
other things have been completed right
until all until we know that all of
these have been completed we can't run
this one which means that we have this
other problem when we do multi-threading
which is that threads that need to use
the work of other threads had better
have a way of knowing that those other
threads have finished right so these are
the two things that we kind of need to
keep in mind as we expand our threat our
code to be thread aware and to work with
threads this is what we will start to be
working on we are starting in a very
easy place which is the renderer which
is a very easy thing to multi multi
thread because we're just going to do it
in sort of buckets so we won't have to
confront some of the harder problems of
multi-threading that you know might
occur if you're working with a less
partition about problem let's say but we
will still have
do the basic work of doing these two
things and so we'll show how to sort of
work through that now the problem here
becomes a little more complicated or I
shouldn't say the problem becomes more
complicated what I should say is the way
that you have to solve this problem is a
little bit complicated the reason it's a
little bit complicated is because when
you are dealing with a multi processing
system you no longer even have a
guarantee about certain basic things
that you might have taken for granted so
what I want to do is talk about this
sort of fundamental model of how you
have to think about how threads work and
how they see each other's results with
an eye towards how we're going to do
this right so let's take this very
simple example well I've got some
functions a a and a you know and I've
got one should be here and we want to
start actually like thinking about how
we would actually implement something if
this is what's going on because really
if you think about it this is actually a
lot like what's going on if you imagine
that function a was like render one tile
right and function B was blit to the
screen then this is basically what the
first sort of thing we do have to do
with our render right we need some way
of a bunch of threads coming in and
realizing that each of them should be
rendering some different tile on the
screen and then at the end we need a
final thread to go oh okay everyone's
done now I can like sort of commit that
change out say like okay let's let's get
that out to the screen we know all the
tiles are there okay so what I want to
talk about here we'll talk about sort of
the first part of the problem right so
let's say I have all of these threads
okay I've got all these threads and I
don't care for a moment about melting my
CPU I just don't care I'm gonna just
full-on spin up all of the cores of the
CPU and they are going to just do what's
called a busy wait they're gonna sit in
a while loop just waiting for there to
be work for them to do okay so we're not
trying to be polite citizens here we
will literally just go ahead and melt
the CPU it will never go into a
low-power state it'll all be crazy town
okay so suppose I was to write something
like a for I loop right that just goes
forever so my threads you know you saw
how we create a thread gesture
they just start Xtreme like everybody
else so we have some threads here right
and what we all we want to do is be able
to basically have something occur right
which basically says if there is work
for me to do right if work exists for me
to do right then I do it that's it and
we just if there's work to do I do it if
there isn't I just go back at the top of
the loop and look again to see if
there's work right so it's just that a
full-on busy wait loop and we want to
see if work exists right well in a
thread right inside a given thread
having multiple threads is no different
than having a single thread in terms of
the capabilities that that thread has
our thread is just executing x64 code
just like everything else in our program
was executing xst for code back when we
were only thinking about programming one
thread and so what that means is this
operation here where I have to say does
work exist right that operation has to
essentially be done in the exact same
manner as anything else might be done it
has to be done by looking at memory
pulling things into registers doing
operations on those registers it has to
be done in a way that a CPU can just do
it doesn't magically get any different
because there are threads we have to
construct this out of the same
primitives and what I want to show here
is that that is actually a relatively
tricky problem okay the reason it is a
very tricky problem is let's say that
our solution to this is just to make a
pointer right out in space somewhere so
we've got some pointer here it is and
that pointer we will set to zero if
there is nothing to do or we will set it
if there is something to do to point off
to like the render buffer right so the
buffer is out here so all we want to do
is we want a thread to come along and
see if there is work there if there is
we want it to pick it up and we want it
to do it okay that's all we're trying to
do very very straightforward doesn't
even totally solve the problem we were
talking about all we're trying to do is
just that right so if we were to write
that right this code would look
something you know like if pointer right
Renne
Poynter okay that would work just fine
for a single thread it would loop
through I would just sit there and as
soon as we stuck some work in that
pointer it would come along and it would
render what was in the pointer right now
the problem is if we had more than one
thread who were sitting in this loop
right well multiple of those people
would come they would see that the
pointer was pointing to the work and
they would start doing it which would
mean that more than one thread would
start doing the same work right and we
don't want that to happen because if
we're gonna make a good system for
distributing work here one of the basic
things we have to do is make sure that
no two threads do exactly the same work
and like you know waste all of that time
right we want to make sure that threads
are always doing new work so what we
might think of is say well okay if we
see that there is a pointer pointing to
some work then what we'll do is right
away after we see that will set that
pointer equal to zero so that now no
other thread will see the work that
we're going to do right so we'll
essentially do you know we'll save the
point of ourselves so we'll kind of do
like work equals pointer right pointer
equals zero and then we'll call you know
render work so we'll clear out that
pointer as soon as we see it all right
and this is the part that I want to talk
about right here because while that
seems like it would work it won't
actually work and the reason that it
won't actually work is because
multi-threading introduces like I said a
whole nother set of subtleties that you
don't know let me think about when you
think about single threaded code and the
reason is because if you look at this
from the perspective of two separate
threads that might be sitting in this
loop waiting to do whatever work comes
there they would look like this right
both of them have an if pointer both of
them try to save the pointer work equals
pointer both of them try to set it to
zero and both of them try to do render
right like so
okay so the problem here and I'll just
put little braces around there as you
can see it so the problem here is that
if one or the other of these blocks
happens to execute is SEC essentially
all by itself we don't have a problem if
this thread here says if pointer working
this pointer pointer equals zero and
manages to get here before this thread
ever does anything we're fine but what
could easily happen because these two
cores are both running at the exact same
time and could be executing any of their
instructions at the exact same time is
they both could look and say if pointer
right and before this guy has cleared
out the pointer to zero
this guy actually advances inside the if
right and he goes ahead and takes a copy
and they both overwrite the pointer with
zero but it's too late now and they both
go and do the work right so essentially
what I hope you will sort of appreciate
when I when I'm what I'm illustrating
here is that actually given the
primitives that we've worked with so far
in C C actually doesn't really give you
any way to even create something where
you can guarantee that two threads won't
do the same work right in fact I don't
even think there is a way to do it in
any in C at all
without going to like C++ or some fuzz
C++ 11 or something
but as you know multi-threaded code does
actually work and people ship it all the
time so how is that happening the reason
is because x64 actually provides a
number of instructions that help with
this right so there are basically
special instructions that are designed
to facilitate the fact that you need to
write code that looks this way in order
to make multi-threading code function
properly and the way that these special
instructions work is they typically put
operations into a context where you can
guarantee that only one thread will see
a particular result and no two threads
will actually see that same result so
I'm going to give you a very simple
example
of that right now there is a function
that the x64 there is a instruction that
ecstasy 4 can do for example which is a
lot increment it's called a locked
increment you can access it by using
interlocked increment in win32 which we
may or may not use we can probably won't
actually use that one why was gonna give
that example and what a lot increment is
is let's suppose that I wanted to well
actually no what let me wash it out why
would I introduce that one when I have
the one that I'm that would actually
solve the exact problem that I wrote so
let's call let's do this one locked
exchange okay what a locked exchange
does is it says I would like to replace
a location in memory with a new value
and I would like to ensure that nobody
else will be able to perform the same
operation at the same time ok so what it
does if we were to change this here
right because you could look at what
we're doing here what we're trying to do
is exchange whatever is in pointer with
zero we're trying to put a 0 in and get
whatever was in there out and we want to
make sure that we are the only person
who can do that right we want to make
sure that when we do it nobody else will
be observing the value that pointer
actually is at that time before we stuff
the zero in there right that's what we
want to make sure happens so what the
locked exchange does is it says all
right I can do a lot exchange right and
I can say the location that I'm trying
to exchange is pointer and the new value
that I would like to put in there is
zero this locked exchange will provide
me the result which is whatever was in
the location pointed to by pointer right
at the time and it will put a 0 in there
before anyone else can observe that
result so if some other thread at the
exact same time he's also executing
locked exchange right so if we have
another thread that's also doing a lot
to strange over here it will guarantee
that one or the other of them will
actually get pointer what was in pointer
and replace it with a zero before the
other one gets the value so if the other
one will get that zero swap right
that makes sense so what we can do is we
can rewrite this routine to make that we
can rewrite it to make it work right by
saying okay instead of doing it that way
what we'll do is we'll say all right we
you know we have whatever the work
pointer is up here we've got work right
and what we'll do is we'll say work
equals interlock exchange write the
pointer and zero we can then say if work
happens to actually be valid then do the
work right and what this will guarantee
for us is that if work comes back with a
valid value as long as everybody else
who was ever trying to observe that
value didn't just cold read it because
other people could cold read it they
could do star work they could just look
at the pointer and they'd see what was
ever is in there but as long as everyone
else is also only doing it with an
interlock exchange we know that only one
person will ever be able to actually get
back the value because as soon as they
get back the value it will get
overwritten with that zero right so that
is how multi-threading code works
essentially in a nutshell the
synchronization primitives how they work
they are all based around using special
versions of functions that are that are
coded in X 64 to ensure that no matter
how many cores happen to be banging on
this piece of memory at any given time
they will all serialize themselves into
a line properly and retire in a
particular order that guarantees that no
two people will be able to do that same
operation so that's very good and like I
said there's other ones like ink
interlocked increment which will take a
location increment whatever the values
in it and return you whatever the old
value was it will guarantee that if
everyone is doing interlocked increments
you will only ever see each person will
see a unique value in the series right
so you can kind of produce like an
escalating series of integers for
example now the granddaddy of all of
these the big poppa right is a function
called interlocked well an instruction
interlocked compare
exchange and I want to mention this one
because this is probably the one if you
only learned ever how to program one
thread synchronization instruction in
x64 this is probably the one you would
want to use because it is crazy powerful
interlocked compare exchange allows you
to do essentially the same operation as
an interlocked exchange but it allows
you to do it predicated so in most
circumstances where you don't super care
about the absolute maximum performance
of the interlocked point right because
these instructions keep in mind these
instructions are on the order of like
100 cycles or something I don't even
know what they are nowadays but they're
not many right but if you were doing
tons and tons and tons and tons of these
right we're not probably gonna be doing
tons and tons of these you know we'll be
doing 50 of these or something or a
hundred of these right we won't be doing
that many so we don't super care how
fast the interchange happens to be
because our goal is to do very few we
want to basically partition the work
into very large chunks so we're not
spending a ton of time figuring out
who's supposed to do the work right
that's not really where we want to be
but if you are in that situation then
maybe interlock compare exchange is not
for you but in circumstances where you
have a reasonable a number of cycles to
spend doing your thread synchronization
interlock compare exchange is kind of
amazing because it lets you write
basically any old janky crappy code that
you want and still have it work I know
that sounds a bit strange but it kind of
is actually true why is it true well the
reason it's true is because if you take
a look at how this code was working
right you can sort of start to think
about I know it's a little bit hard for
you to conceive because you haven't done
a lot of monkey friend coding before
you're not really thinking through all
of the possibilities here and you know
whatever but you can sort of kind of
extrapolate that well ok if this is the
operation that I had to work with
interlock exchange well basically I have
to phrase every last little thing that I
might want to do as a single swap right
I have to kind of make this single swap
do all of the work so I have to prepare
things so that it all just spits through
there so it's kind of hard for me to
figure out like oh if this 3
wants to go look for things and decide
what it wants to do and then maybe do it
how do I boil all that down to like the
single swap it's a little annoying you
know I don't know maybe like complicated
work distribution schemes how am I going
to write them etcetera there's like
there's a lot of thinking that might go
into that and you might have to do a lot
of cleverness to make this happen right
interlocked compare exchange is not that
interlocked compare exchange is a thing
that lets you be super piggy you can put
on the pig hat for example I'll put on
the pig hat while we're even talking
about it because it basically enables
some pretty piggy behavior and and
doesn't really make it into too much of
a problem right so how does this work
well what this does is it's essentially
the exact same thing I just said it's
the same as the interlocked exchange but
what it does is it takes a value that
you are expecting to see in pointer and
if that is not the value that is already
there it does not do the exchange right
so basically what happens is with
interlocked compare exchange you can
essentially write code the same way
you've always been writing it you can do
something like okay you know if there's
work there no thread synchronization is
gonna look and see if there's work scan
like through the work you know figure
out the ones I want to do you know
rearrange some things in my own store
you know whatever do a bunch of stuff
here and then when you get to the very
end
right you can then go okay if
interlocked compare exchange right I'm
gonna call that ice interlocked compare
exchange to this cool acronym if
interlocked compare exchange do the
actual swap to move out the work right
and do some stuff and what this does is
allows you to go oh if some other thread
actually got there before I did and
replace the value that used to be in
work with some other thing now I'll know
because this won't succeed the could
exchange won't go through and I can
actually just not do any of this stuff I
was planning to do right and let this
come back around right because usually
like I said these are in loops waiting
for work
let this come back around and try the
whole thing again right so what you can
actually do with interlock compare
exchange if you don't mind being a
little bit picking is you can actually
write some pretty crappy thread code and
it actually can work thread safe just by
keeping it arranged relatively smartly
with interlock compare exchange whereas
if you are using one of the other
primitives that is not the case you
pretty much always have to be sly fox
and sly fox it around right because if
you don't have it worked out just right
if there's any work that you were doing
at all that that is sort of counting on
being done outside the interlock
exchange but not while the other thread
sees it you will end up with some kind
of the bad synchronization problem or
crash or anything else who knows
depending on what the what the
particular circumstance actually is
right so that that is basically that is
basically that for thread
synchronization so what we are going to
do is we are gonna try to use these to
build some way of us having our multiple
threads to do the work that they need to
do and there's only one of the thing
I've got I want to reserve a fair bit of
time to go back there so I'll spend
another five minutes now and just
briefly mentioned what other things
since we're on that topic and that is
simply sort of about reads and writes in
a multi-threaded context I want to just
sort of preload this we probably will
talk a little bit more detail about it
further down the line but what you have
to understand with threading is that
once this sort of concept is on the
table and we and you know I've done it
once for you here but we're gonna talk
about this a lot and you have to be
aware of where of it once we you know
our multi-threaded this is always the
way you have to think about things you
always have to think about things away I
was thinking about it here where any
thread could be at any point in its
execution at any time right so you
always have to think about what might
happen if two threads are trying to do
something with the same piece of memory
at the same time right and what this
means is that reads to stuff this
constants are always fine if I have a
bunch of threads that are doing work and
they want to read from some database of
values that never changes then I don't
have to worry a read just always works
rights on the other hand right anytime
two threads might write to the same
place you have a problem because if two
threads might write to the same place
you have to ask yourself which one of
the results did you actually want to
happen now if they're both gonna write
the same result that's not a problem hey
two threads could overwrite the same
value with a new value that happens to
be the same that's not a problem right
but once threads are writing to the same
place you have a problem and you have a
synchronization problem so that's
something you need to keep aware of
because obviously you know whoever
writes last will be the value that gets
stored there that's an issue right but
it gets even a little more complicated
than that and that is because once you
start talking about threads that are
writing to places where other threads
might also write even if they don't
really read from them you may actually
have secret places where they do in fact
read and the reason for that is because
the processor actually thinks about
things in terms of cache lines okay now
we haven't talked very much about cache
lines in the past because we haven't
really had to we've talked a lot about
the cache and we say things like the l1
cache and the l2 cache right and we
talked about these being things where
you know you go out to the cache and go
out to the memory
well the cache as it turns out is the
primary place where synchronization
happens in the processor meaning when
the processor cores think about
coordinating things themselves like for
example these locked increments and
stuff right interlock and pair exchange
and those sorts of things even though
those things appear to be operating on
64 32 or 64 bit values really processors
when they're thinking the cores when
they're thinking about this are thinking
about them in terms of who owns what
cache lines right and a cache line is
some size that's much larger than 64
bits right and it depends on the size of
the processor how big the cache line is
but you know it could be something like
128 bytes or tunafish these bytes or
find 12 bytes right there's some number
of bytes that come
a cache line and what happens during
these reads and writes is that
processors try to take ownership of
lines of particular segments of memory
in terms of a cache line boundary which
they then operate on and then commit
right and what this means is that you in
you know in your code may think oh you
know here's what's happening in my code
I've got this struct and there's you
know an int here and in a and there's an
int B you know in the code and you know
oh one of my guys is just it's just
reading and writing from this a and
another one of these guys is reading and
writing from B so there's no problem
it's fine I don't need to do any
interlocking I don't need to do any
synchronization I can just use standard
old C and read and write from a and B
all I want that may not actually be true
because depending on the processor and
depending on the situation in blah blah
blah blah blah you may be in a situation
where since you have not told the
processor about this these may be on the
same cache line which means you could
get crazy stuff happening such as you
know here's core one here's core two
right core one goes oh I'm supposed to
read and write from a so it loads in
this cache line into its cache and
here's a and here's B right and we'll
say that these are a 0 B 0 then the
state of this thing at some time and
core to happen to be executing some code
totally in parallel it's like oh I've
got to read and write from B so it loads
this into its cache right so it's got
here's our a and here's our B right now
they go oh you know what cool dude I
just got a modify a so I execute a piece
of code and I end up with a 1 so it's
like you know this is some other version
here I've got a 1 a 0 B 0 right and B it
still be 0 Core 2 goes oh you know what
cool dude I got this I'm gonna modify B
so now it's B 1 right later on when they
go to commit these cache lines to memory
right again depending on the
architecture and depending on all all
sorts of other things they may then go
oh okay let's just commit these guys
back to memory they commit them back to
memory right
and what happens is one of these two
cache line commits just overwrites the
other one right or something equally
heinous so you just end up with a 1 B 0
or something like this or you end up
with a 0 B 1 right so that's bad and you
have to know you have to essentially
know again information about your your
particular processor whatever on x64 my
recollection is that this is not
something that you have to particularly
care about right because in general I'm
pretty sure that it guarantees that
right always that rights are always
visible to other processors so it as far
as I am aware and someone on the stream
can connect me out this time wrong as
far as I am aware on x64 you never have
to think about weird stuff like this
happening right let me think about this
before I say that
I feel like that's correct I feel like
that's correct we'll double-check it but
I'm pretty sure that the way the x64
memory coherent works
it's that rights are always visible in a
particular order and so you don't have
to actually worry about that particular
case happening I believe I could be
wrong about that but I believe it's
buried in the Intel system architecture
manual
I remember reading this very carefully
when I first started doing both my throw
into programming and I believe that
unlike other processors which actually
you have to be more careful about this
sort of thing that Intel has a very
strong memory ordering model that
prevents this this actual pattern from
ever occurring it just knows it's smart
enough about those rights that it will
it won't do that particular operation on
the cache lines but again could be wrong
about that point being you have to think
about these sorts of things at the very
least again even if you weren't going to
think about them from the perspective of
just oh you know on some processors I
may have to think about this because
I'll get wrong results you still want to
think about them formant for another
reason altogether which is that if two
cores are starting to have contention
for a particular piece of memory again
that you know it's not free it's not
like the processor internally has some
magic way of making all these things
work out at no cost it's still all of
the synchronization still has to happen
somewhere so even if you're on an
architecture which guarantees that you
can do stuff that will not be a problem
as far as these kind of rights are
concerned you may still want to be aware
of it because you don't want to have to
processor 2 cores constantly pounding on
the same cache lines because that will
create synchronization work for the
processors where they have to constantly
talk to each other to shuttle their
results back and forth and that is again
not free typically so again just want to
bring that up there's things you have to
think about and so if you can most of
the time what you will want to do is you
will want your cache lines to you want
you want to think about things in terms
of cache lines and you will want to try
as hard as you can to make sure that the
primary were
that your cores are doing line up along
separate cache line boundaries so that
while your two threads are executing
either a you're guaranteed correct
results on platforms where you have to
make sure that that's not the case
you're guaranteed correct results
without having to start using a bunch of
synchronization primitives like the
locked versions right or on an
architecture which gives you strong
memory ordering and you don't have to
worry about getting incorrect results
you still may want to do it because your
performance may suffer if you're sitting
there forcing the CPU to constantly talk
and say oh hey I got that cache line
here you go oh wait I need it back I
gotta update the value oh wait you need
back ok great and they're shuffling it
around all the time right not free so
that's something to think about there
we'll be talking more about this because
there's things like memory barriers and
fences and all these other sorts of
things that happen in terms of write
coherence we'll be talking about that
sort of stuff
a little bit later probably tomorrow
when we get to when we actually have our
routine fleshed out and we need to talk
about how to make sure that it operates
correctly but for now we'll we'll leave
that all right so let's slip back here
I'll take off the pig hat because I'm
not actually doing anything piggy right
and let's go ahead and man that pick out
is hot I sweat when that pick out is on
I guess that's good you don't want to be
piggy so I guess that's a good penalty
for if we ever be picking in the code to
try to convince us not to be so piggy
all the time so all right let's open
this up here and let's go back to our
thread proc we created yesterday and we
got about 15 minutes here so I want to
kind of show how to actually start doing
some work with the threads very basic
but just try to get it so you can sort
of see how that's working right so what
I'd like to do is I would like to make
something and we'll just make a very
simple toy thing right now I want to
make something where we can make four
threads that each do some work and they
do different work ok that's what we want
to do and so what I'd like to do is
something where for example maybe each
of the threads prints out a different
string right after the fact so for
example we do these create threads here
this this great stud stuff here
right now we're passing a string I want
to make it so I can basically make a
little cue where I maybe put some
strings in and they'll print out the
strings something like this right so
what I'm going to do is I'm going to
create a little thing that's like thread
info here or something like this just
temporarily we mate we probably want
something actually like this eventually
but it's going to be just a little
placeholder for now and all I'm going to
do here is I'm going to put in something
like a logical thread index which is
basically just a value which says this
particular thread is number 0 or number
1 or whatever right so that we know what
they are and what I'm going to do is I'm
going to say that that win32 thread info
right it's gonna get passed in here - to
the function as that LP parameter so I
can basically and I can use this in the
future to pass anything else that I want
to the start of thread so it kind of
knows what's going on right so then what
I'm going to do is I'm just going to
create some of these threads right I'm
just going to go ahead and make this a
loop I don't know how many threads we
want I guess we said there were 16 cores
maybe I'll create 15 of them let's say
so I'll do a thread index equal 0
thread index is less than six 15 rather
and then we'll do thread index plus plus
and then when we're in here we'll do
win32 thread info we'll make that info
struct and then what we'll do is we'll
set the the thread the logical thread
index logical thread index we'll set
that equal to whatever number it was in
our in our array so we're going to
create 15 threads and then what we do
instead of passing 0 here
I'm sorry so tossing parameter which was
this this thread started thing we're
actually gonna pass an address of that
struct and so as you can see you know
oops it's no good to do that there we go
as you can see this will just pass
through to here so we can pick up that
thread info it's just we're just passing
this through to this routine right so
once we do that we then have a bunch of
these guys and for right now they're all
just gonna sleep right and so if I run
handmade hero now again nothing in
particular really will happen because
those threads will just sit there doing
absolutely nothing they're just sleeping
and our hand mate here runs as it
normally would would run right no big
deal and I and I exit but those threads
are being created so now what I want to
do is I
to take these threads and I want them to
actually look for some work to do right
that's what I would like them to do and
I want to make sure that each of them
gets the right work to do right so what
we're gonna do curious we're going to
have something like I guess maybe just
an array let's say something very simple
and what this array will be is it will
be it will be like a little mini queue
right it'll be like a mini queue so I'm
gonna do like a work queue entry thing
something like this and I'm going to
have in that work queue entry I'm going
to have a care pointer which is like the
string to print right and we can put
other work here that we wanted to do you
know anything like that
and then what I'm going to do is I'm
just gonna make this work queue entry
I'm going to make some number of these
right I'm just gonna make a bunch of
them I don't know how many I'll make
maybe I'll make 256 of them and then I'm
gonna have an index into them that says
here is the current count of them right
and so I'm gonna do an entry count like
so make sense and this is obviously a
you know this is obviously a value
because specialized zero start okay so
the first question is what happens if I
just start pushing things in here so
let's just write the code with no
thought to threaten thread
synchronization whatsoever and we will
see what happens right so first we're
gonna start up and inside each of these
threads what I want to do is I want the
thread to basically just go through and
do any work that happened to be there
right and so I guess what I should do
first is I should put push some things
on there so let me just do it like a
push string and and I'll you know put in
string zero right something like this
right
two three four right and what I'll do
here is I'm just you know again I'm just
going through and putting some in maybe
we'll do you know what I'll do ten of
them so there we go
we've got ten of those guys so we've got
ten strings in there and now what I want
to do is I want to make a little
function I want to implement this push
string so what I want to do is make that
so it just goes ahead and adds one of
these into these entries right so I'll
just go ahead and say we've got internal
void right forget you know I had a value
for this right just global right yeah
okay good mmm maybe not platform what is
global global variable oops okay I don't
like to use where it's static because it
means too many different things all
right so inside push string right very
very simple
it's taking some string that's gonna
push on here all I wanted to do is
basically say all right I've got a work
queue entry right it's gonna be whatever
the entries are you know entry count
plus plus right maybe I'll start here
that the entry count is less than the
size of this guy right so I don't want
it to ever overflow the array for now or
not the word I'm gonna push that many on
for this this test code but still and
then we're gonna have that string to
print is going to be equal to the string
that gets passed in there right so that
actually works now oops did that wrong
way there we go
so that actually works now and now the
strings will get pushed on there right
but we need to actually pull them off
and so what we need is we don't really
know where to pull these guys off right
so we kind of need we have the count of
entries but we don't actually know we
need like a second variable right which
is like the the last printed entry or
the or the next entry to print might be
the right thing right
so it's entry zero right now and
basically as long as this is below this
value we need to print out a thing right
so in here what we want to do is we want
to say okay if the next entry to print
is less than the entry count right then
we want to go ahead and end
print it so we want to go ahead and grab
it whatever it is will work queue entry
the entries equals the entries plus the
next entry print should say to print to
print or I should say X you know next I
need to do might be the better thing
because in case there was something I've
been printing in there so yeah next if
the next entry to do is less than the
total number of counts I'm going to pull
it off right and increment this value
and then I'm going to actually do the
output debug string for the entry write
print and while I'm at it
what I'd like to do actually I think is
I'd like to go ahead and actually build
a buffer here that actually has some
more information in it because I'd like
to know which thread actually did it so
I'm gonna call Windows and say why don't
you prepare this buffer for me right
which says like thread and it gives the
number right of the thread and then it
does the the string that that got output
right so I'm gonna actually create a
thing here so we have that logical
thread index there's the thread info
logical thread index right and then I've
got that entry screen to print it's
gonna form that up and then it's gonna
output that buffer to the debug console
right so there we go
and one thing - well I want to mention
that now you know it doesn't even matter
so there we go
we'll build that up logical thread index
oops sorry that's a pointer yeah and
we'll get this working right and again
we've done no synchronization now so
this code is totally not actually safe
but I wanted to show you the unsafe
version first so that you kind of get a
feel for where we're going with you each
of the changes right so off we go
I don't know exactly what is happening
there actually let's go ahead and close
that out so let's take a look so this is
pretty weird if you take a look at what
actually got printed there right I I
think I may have had a bug in there cuz
that's actually that's even weirder than
what I thought it would originally print
which is thread 14 printing
all kinds of weird things in that string
which should have pushed them all on
and I feel like that actually shouldn't
have printed something so odd that is
very strange if I do say so myself yes
if that is actually not what I would
have expected from the unsafe version I
would have expected if one thread
printed out all of the things I would
have expected it to Oh duh okay good I
thought I was going crazy there for a
second I forgot that I need to let these
guys persist so you see what was
happening there right
each of these thread infos I want these
thread and for us to persist so these
guys could use them right but what's
happening is I only have one on the
stack here right so what I actually
wanted I want this right which is you
know however many threads there going to
be or whatever right there's 15 I want
to do it this way so that each of these
still exists and these guys can continue
to reference them because otherwise they
just keep betting room so that's that
was discouraged that is just me that was
just just mental mental stupid dude
they're so we've got these thread infos
right so all I need to do is just make
sure that they all continue to persist
and then we're fine so no big deal but
that I was gonna say there's definitely
a bug in there somewhere because like
that even even though this is not the
safe code it should not be printing out
something like that
okay so let's let's give that one more
go here after we create all these
threads let's see
all right so there we go let's see what
we actually printed out all right so
here you could kind of see and in fact
this is this is now roughly what I would
have expected to see printing out you
can kind of see you know the results
that we end up getting basically thread
14 printed out sort of the three of
these guys here thread 13 printed out
these two thread 5 2 &amp; 0 &amp; 4 all got the
same string at the beginning right
and thread 1 got string 4 somehow right
so I mean you know again I have to check
to make sure I don't have any other bugs
in here but this is a totally plausible
thing that could have happened even if
there are no bugs in this code right and
it's totally wrong but this is what
happens when you don't take the proper
care to have your threads actually
synchronize and look at the proper work
right so what are all the things that
are happening here in three minutes I'm
going to say what they all are
and then tomorrow we will start actually
just fixing them all they're not
particularly hard to fix but you know
well we'll get started on it since we're
almost out of time so the first thing is
right here right so with our next entry
to do I'm going to pull that out into a
thing so I'm going to do like entry
index equals next entry to do plus plus
entry index right
okay so the first problem is this line
right is not interlocked right so two
threads could see the same value at the
processor level right this is what I was
saying before right this this thing
right here where I do the plus plus we
have not told the x64 processor that it
needs to worry about other people who
may be doing the same thing right and so
that is obviously going to create a
problem on the same line we have another
problem which is that the compile
doesn't know that this that multiple
threads could write this value right and
what that means is that even after we
were to take care of this right in
theory and this actually isn't really
true because it will you'll see it
automatically does this for us in a way
that will be clear in a second but if
the compiler is not made aware of the
fact that this value could be getting
changed by other threads it may just
optimize this out it will look at this
loop and go oh he's the only person who
changes you know this value or this
value or something so I can just hoist
it out or do other things with it and
and it's fine right and the answer is no
but it's not fine I need you to check
that value when I tell you to
you can't go moving it around or
changing what it actually does and so
there's a C keyword that we need to put
in there to make sure that it
understands that as well so that's
another thing that's problem right the
other problem that we have is here input
string so input string right this entry
count plus plus we've got another thing
here which is that these rights are not
in order right so if you take a look at
what happens here you can see what i'm
doing i do the entries plus the entry
count and then I have the string to
print that gets set there so first of
all what you may notice is as soon as
this value goes up right
as soon as entry count gets incremented
one of these threads could look and see
it right whenever this process this
processor core decides to put this value
out one of these guys will look and it
may see the entry count has gone up and
it will start doing this work and
loading this in if that's the case right
then I had better make sure that string
to print is already filled out because
otherwise it's going to go and get
garbage
right this value will be garbage because
it hasn't actually been written here so
the other thing that we need to do the
final thing that we need to do is make
sure that the rights to these things
happen in order so that by the time it's
possible for one of these threads to see
that entry count has been incremented
there is no chance that the work that
they are going to go and get has not
already been flushed out to memory right
I shouldn't say left out to memory that
that is not already properly notate
noted in the architecture however that
has to be notated in the particular
architecture that we're on right so just
in this very simple piece of code and I
hope this underscores just how important
it is to be careful when you're doing
multi-threading just in this very very
simple piece of code there are actually
three totally separate things that are
not correct that have to be rectified
and we will sort of talk about them in
order and technically there really is
one more and I'm gonna put in here which
is that the same thing that happens with
those rights there's the same problem
with the reads which is that technically
and especially if you're talking about
the compiler again certain architectures
guarantee strong ordering for different
things so this may not actually be a
problem on the x64 architecture at the
architecture level but the compiler
level it may be important what you have
to remember is the compiler is
technically free to hoist things like
these reads outside above things what we
want to make sure is that it never does
things like that so technically we may
want to also put in things that prevent
that from happening
okay so yeah again this is one of the
reasons why you tend to want to write a
few very simple primitives like a work
queue or things like this like sort of
what we're working towards in order to
facilitate your multi-threading because
once you start talking about threads
having to do work with each other it
gets very complicated and so you want to
typically solve that problem once in a
coherent way and not have to keep doing
it all throughout your code because
you're very liable to make mistakes and
you would rather only make those things
once and fix them once rather than
having them strewn throughout your code
that in a way that constantly causes you
bugs and headaches all right so with
that let's go to the QA and let's see
questions is your use of force semicolon
semicolon instead of wild one a
stylistic choice or is they benefit
drawback that I'm missing it is actually
just to shut up stupid compilers so for
some reason a lot of compilers if you do
this will complain at you right and what
they'll say is conditional expression is
constant it'll be a warning I probably
probably I don't actually know I can do
this - all there we go so let's see if I
turn on the the most strict warning
level here which of course I can't do
because the windows headers oh well you
know what well yeah the windows headers
are a problematic and I'm in that file I
guess but let me just take a look and
see if it has it here oh you know what I
may have disabled it even let me see if
I get rid of our warning disables
conditional expression is tough yeah so
that's the warning it's conditional
expression is not constant I disabled
that wording because it's the stupidest
warning but but that's why I tend to
prefer this is because if I'm running
code especially in another code base
like you know I'm working on the witness
or something and they don't have that
warning disabled I just try to make sure
that I don't introduce any spurious
warnings into the code right so I'll try
to prefer that that's the only reason
what's the problem with not being
interlocked and seeing the same value as
your to do suggests this one right here
so that's the one that we went over on
the blackboard in detail right it's that
we want only one thread we want only one
thread to actually see the value say
zero right because our goal is to do
each of these units of work once and
what we see already right is that's not
happening
thread five two and zero all did the
wrong piece of work here right which is
not good at all
and yeah I feel like again I feel like
there's still some some janky Nissen
here I got to see what happens let me
see what happens if I do only one of
these threads just want to make sure
before I start talking about this that
we're all good here yes you can see
these this with one thread it prints out
the number of zero to nine in order
right so each thing is being done once
if I make two threads now right we go up
here and they're still doing ok right 0
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 and thread one did two
of the units of work thread 0 did some
other ones probably because it had time
to do those before thread 1 got created
or something like this will step up the
number one more time and 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7
string 6 you can see thread one actually
got string 6 but printed it out later
just to the way these these guys ended
up happening having to go but again
still all good there so we're looking
out pretty well as as we have this but
again it's really just luck it's also
helped a little by the fact that the
there's a string synchronization this
output debug string actually
synchronizes because only one person can
write to that debug sync at a time so
you kind of have a low but synchronized
snip but what you can see is here is
once we get up to 4 you can see that we
got we got pwned right 0 1 1 2 3 4
four five six seven eight nine so we did
one set of work twice both red zero and
thread one both saw work unit one right
so what happened there here's what
happened there right
remember how CPUs work right they have
registers so here is core zero here is
core one okay here is entry count out in
memory somewhere okay
core zero says oh I need to do this
operation right oh I should say entry
count my bad I want next entry to do
right so next entry to do and next entry
to zoo in this case make sure I did the
right one so is the is the work unit one
right so next entry to do in this case
the value that's stored in this location
is one right so here's what happens core
zero goes oh I got a go check next entry
to do and potentially increment it so
I'm going to load it in here so now it
goes into a register right so inside the
register of course zero there's a one
core one goes oh I got a load that in
let me load that in so now in the
register of core one there's a one
because remember processors don't
necessarily operate on memory there are
such things as memory ops in x64
but a lot of times what they do is they
move something into a register do a
bunch of work with it and then put it
out so remember it's a copy it
effectively copied these values right
these odds that copied they got cloned
into the registers of the cores and then
does a test it says oh you know I don't
know what's entry count is this greater
you know entry count is maybe four at
this point or something who knows what
it is so it's like oh okay yeah you know
what I gotta increment this so it
increments it and it makes it a two
right core one goes oh you know what I
got to do that same thing increments
that and makes it
as well right they then go and they both
write out the value and they overwrite
this value with two and they both write
two back onto it so both of these cores
now think right that work unit one is
the one they should do and they both
think that they updated the value to two
which they did but what that means is
that work unit one is actually getting
done twice now by each these of these
cores each dozen right and that is bad
if that was rendering we just lost 1/16
of our performance because we rendered a
tile twice in we instead of having two
different tiles being rendered by two
different cores we rendered the same
tile on both cores so does that make
sense
do mutex is that I've seen used for
multi-threading code in other places
rely on those interlocking instructions
or are they something completely
different
yes mutexes are actually just operating
system primitives that are built off of
interlocked primitives in the end the
ecstacy for processor the ecstacy for
processor I I guess I don't
I can't think if there's anything else
that might be relevant there but on the
on the whole the mutexes are usually
built off of interlocked instructions on
the ecstacy for a processor but there is
also another thing called transactional
memory which is coming out Intel
processors now that's a different way of
doing it it's not really about mutexes
and then quite the same way but there's
there are some other new synchronization
primitives that do some slightly
different things but at the moment as
far as I know like mutexes in general
are just implemented on top of the
interlocking instructions what is your
opinion on lock liske use so I'll be
honest with you I don't really know what
people mean when they say lock liske use
a lot of the time I don't actually know
which which one they're referring to
like if someone says a lock Liske you do
they mean that they don't use any
interlocked instructions at all right
and if they do mean any interlocked or
not using any interlocked instructions
at all then I guess I would say well
it's interesting probably in some
circumstances
which is that if you if you care about
the speed if you if you have to queue a
ton of things and DQ a ton of things
then that may be worth it to you
right that may be something that that is
valuable right but if you don't then I
would question you know a lot increment
is really not very expensive out an
ecstasy for a processor so you know if
the complexity of that queue at all is
more than just the cycles of doing the
lock increment or whatever it ends up
being is it really such a good idea
because a locked increment queue is
really easy to implement and pretty hard
to mess up
whereas trying to do it without that
seems a little trickier but I don't know
so I don't have a strong opinion about
them I am not I do not try to do fancy
multi-threaded code usually I just do
standard work queue stuff and I make
sure the work queue elements are pretty
big and I don't I don't have to deal
with stuff like oh my god what if we
have to you know make this the
granularity of this multi-threading be
like millions of work units so a second
or something or weird stuff like that so
you know it doesn't tend to be a thing I
think about
what's the point of an infinite loop to
begin with it ends at some point doesn't
it well at some point not really I mean
you know we could very well make this
this loop be infinite for reals
like because the thread will get killed
in exit process so we may never really
care about having it closed down
so yeah in the case of threading you
really can't have literally infinite
loops what threading libraries do you
recommend and why I never use any
threading libraries locked increment is
so easy I find that I've always just
been able to use locked increment or
sorry I shouldn't say just locking right
lock compare exchange lock exchange lock
increment I just use those and it's
really easy to build a queue with them
so I don't I never use like as far as
I'm concerned using someone else's
multi-threading libraries is probably
just an invitation to inherit a bunch of
crappy bugs that are in there from them
because like I've seen boost and I'm I
mean I would not trust the people who
coded boost to write single-threaded
code for me let alone multi-threaded
code
what's better a job scheduler from where
each thread can get a job or separate
queues for each thread so basically it
depends on the workload so taking the
render as an example you might say well
why would you have a queue at all
because we know we have X number of
threads why don't we just have each
thread do a specific set of tiles and
that way they don't have to communicate
at all right and that's a perfectly
valid strategy and we may find that
that's a better strategy than what we're
doing I don't know I kind of want to
show the work cube version just for
educational purposes because it's more
general and applies to more things but
you know it could be fine to do it that
way but even in the renderer case it may
not be true that that is the right way
to thread it and the reason is because
different tiles may take different
amounts of time okay
so consider the following circumstance
right and so so just to give you just to
tie it in to your question right so
you're saying what's the difference
right between I have something that
looks like this right
q q q q q right and each thread pulls
from a different queue so when I go to
distribute my render jobs I take the
screen and I break it up into tiles oops
and I break it up into tiles and I
assign each of those tiles to different
threads right and they each get their
own queue so we like queue up tiles in
each of the thread queues or something
like this or better yet we do away with
this entirely and we just have each
thread knows which tiles it does and it
just iterates over them right what's the
difference between that and just having
one queue right where each of the tiles
piles into it and all of the threads
pull out of it right and just to give
you some nominal Eicher here this is
typically called single producer single
consumer right these are consumers of
the queue and these are producers of the
queue single producer single
Zoomer so basically like HQ only has one
thread writing to it and one thread
reading from it and this is called
single producer because it's the same
here as here there's only one thread
that's driving the house multiple
pre-consumer so this is this is single
multiple right and you can look those up
those are standard terms that you can
read about well the reason to prefer
this method is that what if say this
tile takes a hell of a long time right
so this tile takes a hundred
milliseconds and that that'd be too much
this Kyle takes ten milliseconds but the
rest of these I'll take one right well
what we'd like to have happen ideally is
we would like to have the rest of the
threads be able to do all the other work
while whoever unfortunately got stuck
with the 10 millisecond tile does that
work right because think about what
would happen in this queue case what
would happen in this queue case is one
thread gets say this tile this tile this
tile this tile and this tile right and
worse yet let's say that the 10
millisecond tile was actually up here in
our worst case right so now we got one
millisecond one looks like we'll mix
again so let's say this whole row this
whole column of tiles went to this queue
that means that as the first this thread
here he pulls off the first thing it
takes him 10 milliseconds he then still
has to pull off these other four so it's
still gonna take him another 4
milliseconds meaning that the total
frame time will be 14 milliseconds for
this guy all the rest of these guys only
had one millisecond tiles let's say so
they all completed in 5 milliseconds but
it doesn't matter that they all
completed in 5 milliseconds because this
guy took 14 so that means our total
frame time is still going to be on the
order of 14 milliseconds on the other
hand if this had been a general work
queue this guy would have gotten stuck
with a 10 millisecond guy yes but all
the rest of these guys would have been
done by other threads by the time he
completed right so our total frame time
drops from 14 milliseconds to 10
milliseconds in the single producer
multiple consumer case so when you know
that you don't have too many work units
like when you have on the order of a
hundred work units or something it's
usually
not worth the extra time savings in
terms of in queuing and D queuing that
you get from going with the single
producer single consumer because now you
don't have to do LOC increments or
anything right because you always know
that there's only one thread reading so
you can actually you can actually do a
lock free queue trivially in this case
but if you know that you have a small
number of work units it's almost always
better to go a single producer multiple
consumer because it means that you get
this free spreading of the work that you
would not have gotten in the case where
you've got this this queueing happening
sudonym 73 I think that the point of
lock las' is that it doesn't use an
operating system level lock if that's
all people mean by lock free queues then
that's the kind I always use so I would
say I'm in favor of them but i but it
technically you know you can have like
it's possible to do so just to make this
absolutely explicit so this is why I say
I never know what people mean when they
say lock free because there's two kinds
of lock free there's literally
completely lock free right there's like
meaning the processor its processor lock
free okay and that's actually possible
so for example in the single producer
single consumer case you could do a
processor lock free queue that's totally
plausible all you have to do is make
sure that you write to the index
variable on one thread after you've done
all the rights it needs to do and you
read from that on the other thread and
then you never have to do an interlock
right so that's actually possible right
then there's the other lock free which
means that no threads ever stall okay
and that's a very different thing what
that means that is like cheesy lock free
all that means is that you're using lock
you're using the processor it's got
processor locks in it right so it has
processor locks
I don't usually call that lock free
because it still has a processor lock
all it means is that you're not sitting
there stalling other threads waiting for
another proffer for this process to
finish right so the kind of thing that
we're writing here is actually locked
free by that definition because it
doesn't stall the other threads waiting
for one thread to finish D queuing all
the threads can DQ Simon
Dainius Lee using the processor locked
synchronization primitive primitives so
yeah this kind of lock three pretty
difficult pretty limiting I don't tend
to do it this kind of lock free pretty
cheesy use of the term lock free in my
opinion but this is the kind I normally
do so yes I am in favor of it
so Fabien says the terminology the
original term was non-blocking which is
more more useful for lock-free
and I would like that to be much better
because if that was a terminology then
that makes sense right if you call this
lock free and this non-blocking then now
I feel like that makes a lot of sense
but when you start using lock free for
this I just it's still doing a lock like
that's a lock it's not the processors
doing the stall for you in there so I
don't know but but yeah so yes so both
pseudonym 73 and Fabien said that
normally people when they typically say
lock free they're actually referring to
this case so yeah if that's the case
that the original questioner was asking
about then I that's what I tend to do
actually is it reasonable to synchronize
the receiving of network packets on one
synchronized thread sure I mean the
network card can't produce packets fast
enough for for an x64 a process for an
ecstacy for a court of choke on them the
xst for a processor can read much faster
than that so in order for you need to
need multiple threads simply to receive
network packets in if you were talking
about like a low-level thing sure it
would be fine right unless you had some
kind of amazing network card that was
like just crazy out super fast and you
were sitting right on some kind of fiber
link right but almost always in network
packet receipt case it's gonna be the
outbound link the inbound link rather
that's the that's the slow part not UD
queuing them now what is not always the
case is that the stuff that has to
happen with those network packets like
the crappy tcp/ip stack on Windows or
something or you know what you need to
do to actually process each packet that
may be a lot of work and that may be
slower than inbound and at that point
you need to make sure that you handle
them on multiple threads potentially but
the action will just
getting the packets off of the Nick like
you have to be on the world's most
amazing internet connection before that
is gonna outstrip in X 64 because X 64
could handle that no problem
later in the development cycle will you
go over threading for other operating
systems like Mac and Linux so it's yes
but there's really not much to it you
just it's the same as the wind three to
one you just call like this function
that's like start threading usually on
most of them so it's not that hard but
that won't be for a while because that's
only when we start doing ports
what are the advantages of having a
queue of jobs instead of creating a
thread every time you add a job well
okay so that is because we are not
queueing we are not queuing for overlap
we are queuing for performance and it's
porting to understand what these two
different things are okay so I want to
talk about these because this is I'm
glad you in fact I'm really glad you
asked that question because we didn't we
never really came right out and said
this okay so what I want to underscore
here is there's two totally separate
reasons you might want to thread okay
one is because you are trying to overlap
work all right and in that case let's
say that we just have we have 30 things
that need to happen right one of those
things is the UI for our application
okay and we're not a high performance
application we really don't care
we're Apple or somebody we don't really
care or you know what I shouldn't blame
app oh we're Android we're the people
who write Android so we don't care about
these experience at all if it's laggy or
whatever so we're just running the Java
VM and having a UI party and stuffs just
going nuts oeid right but we've got
these 30 things that we want to do and
we know they're all going to take a
second for something right a totally
valid use of threading is just a kick
off 30 threads let them go do their
thing and let and then we'll at least
know that that UI thread will get some
time now and again and it'll be Jack
tastic but at least run so the user will
still be able to do some input and it's
fine right so this is threading for
overlapping the goal here is not
performance the goal is simply to have
30 things that happen simultaneously and
not have one of them stall completely
while they happen right threading for
performance means we are trying to get
the maximum number of cycles of work out
of this processor as we possibly can so
if this processor right if the CPU has
16 cores or I should say 16 hyper cores
because we this processor actually has
eight cores I believe but they have to I
put threads each or something like this
you know something like that if the CPU
has 16 high per course but we create 30
threads because that's how many things
we have to do then what we are
essentially doing is we're forcing the
operating system to do our job queue for
us right these 30 threads will all go
into the OS scheduler right as if they
were a job queue that's what's gonna
happen now the OS knows absolutely
nothing about these threads it does not
know that they should be that we are
trying to have the maximum performance
possible it may think that we're trying
to interleave them so that they all get
a little bit of time it could think all
sorts of things it has to save all kinds
of register state right it has to do
interrupts to switch them there's all
this stuff that the OS scheduler has to
do if we instead were to create 30 work
units on our queue all we have to do to
DQ them is that interlocked exchange
right that's 100 cycles or something on
that order depending on the processor
right I think sometimes it was as much
as 300 cycles so I shouldn't say 100
something like 300 cycles but it's never
I don't think it was ever worse than
that let's put it that way we know that
we can totally beat all of this crazy
work the operating system s the doer it
has no information it will switch these
out multiple times potentially it'll do
register saving and restoring it will
have to you know it's using the
scheduled interrupt to do those things
all of this stuff that doesn't ask to
happen right we can save all of that
work by just doing our own job queue so
because what we care about is
performance we care about saving all of
the cycles that would be blown that
would be wasted and getting it down to
just that at most you know something
like 300 cycles that it actually costs
us to do this thing right and that's
really important and so what I want to
underscore there is there really are two
things that threading does and we care
almost not at all about this one there
will be once in a while where we do care
about this one and that'll be when we're
doing async i/o which will probably be
coming up shortly
actually once we got threads in there we
might as well get our IO asynchronous so
there are times when what we care about
is actually the overlap this because we
want to wait for like the disk to do
things or we want to do other stuff so
there may be other times when there are
threads either the operating systems or
our own that are executing on our behalf
we're really it's not about performance
is about overlap but for the majority of
the work that we do what we care about
is threading for performance which means
that we don't want to then go turn
around and give a bunch of that
performance away because the scheduler
because we're letting the OS do a bunch
of work and it doesn't have the
information necessary to do the right
thing all right we all done there looks
like we're out of questions and that's
good because we're also out of time
good good I'm glad this is a good
stopping point for today too because it
means tomorrow we will basically be able
to implement our work queue and yeah
start to actually do stuff because
basically it hopefully you saw you know
kind of when I ran this you could kind
of see how these problems that I'm
talking about we're not theoretical like
we actually did have exactly the kind of
problems that I was saying where people
get the wrong values and stuff gets
overwritten and it's not good
so yeah you saw what kind of happens
here basically our job for tomorrow will
be to fix that and then just kind of
abstract this out into something that we
can actually use in the game to
distribute our work at which point we
will have multi-threading in the
renderer now there is one other problem
we'll have in the renderer that has to
do with that cache line problem but we
can start talking about that a little
bit later that just gets into memory
alignment the fact that we need to make
sure that our loops don't kind of
overwrite each other's memory bounds I
didn't want to talk too much about that
before because it wasn't applicable in
single threading but now that we're
gonna introduce multi-threading we'll
will see this or at least we should see
it I think again until one of the things
I know it sounded kind of hand-wavy
today when I said it but this was
something that actually even when I
first learned multi-threading our first
I should say did multi-threading on
ecstasy for this actually surprised some
people that I programmed with who had
been doing multi-threading much longer
than I was because I actually went and
read the x64 manual x64 is a weird
processor multi-threading wise
it actually does synchronization stuff
that a lot of other processors just
don't do
it's got weird strong right ordering and
stuff like this that's like way better
than like there let me put it this way
we're gonna be talking about things like
memory barriers and this sort of stuff
the ecstasy for actually that I've for
what I've seen requires the least out of
you as a programmer in terms of
enforcing the memory ordering and
enforcement stuff happens so actually
when I say that we're gonna have this
problem or that we'll have to work
around this problem what I actually mean
is we will theoretically have this
problem and I assume that it will be a
problem Nexus before but since it's been
a long time since I read that for all I
know maybe the x64 actually just comes
in and is like nope guess what surprise
folks it's not a problem so I don't know
but in theory we could have the problem
so I'm gonna go over it as well and show
you what we would have to do to fix it
because at the very least for porting
sake we probably don't want to put
ourselves in a situation where we're
counting on all kinds of x64 stuff and
then all of a sudden it turns out that
you know you know people in the
community get that big contract from
from from Google to do an android port
of something and and then it's all
ruined because neon doesn't have these
or something at it so point being I want
to show you that either way and we'll do
that we'll take care of that so well
we'll be working on that tomorrow we'll
get the job keep going and then the days
forward we'll just make sure the
renderer is working kosher and we'll
touch up a few of those things memory
alignment that we want to make sure
aren't going to cause any problems
whether or not they do happen to cause a
problem on x64 because like I said
sometimes x64 can save you because it's
got it's got stronger memory ordering in
certain cases than a lot of other
processors do all right so I'm gonna go
ahead and close things down here for the
day close it up and also I think we've
gotten most of our blackboard stuff
we'll have to do one more blackboard
session on write read and write barriers
but I think we've gotten most of the
black boarding for from all the
threading out too so that means we
should be able to make much faster
progress for the rest of the week
because I won't have to spend the bulk
of the time drawing stuff we'll just be
able to do it so that'll be good too
so I hope you come back tomorrow and
join me for the next step in our
multi-threading which I think will go
pretty pretty smoothly hopefully but you
never know with multi-threading it's
complicated so yes please come back
tomorrow Android it'll be same time same
place 5:00 p.m. Pacific Daylight Time
tomorrow in the meantime if you do want
to follow along at home you can always
go to handmade hero org and if you order
the game you you get the source code all
throughout its development so you can go
ahead and check that off you want to do
the pre-order you could do that we also
have a patreon if you want support a
video series it's always much
appreciated we have a forum site where
you can go and ask questions and also
get resources like Mac and Linux ports
and stuff that the community do and
stuff like this and finally there's a
tweet bot which you can check out it
tweets the schedule at you and we also
have this live button which thanks to
some folks who contributed the
JavaScript code Reni Remy and Jakob
again don't know how to pronounce either
of their names but thanks to them this
now also is pretty accurate so you can
actually check the schedule for the week
with a tweet bot and and the schedule
for the day and stuff like that but you
also within the window of time when the
thing is going to be live it actually
says a little countdown there which is
pretty cool so thank you guys for that
it's been pretty sweet yeah
so thank you all for joining me I hope
you see you back here tomorrow until
then please have a wonderful day or
wonderful programming I should say and I
will see you back here then take it easy
everyone