hello everyone and welcome to hand made
here oh sure we could a complete-game
live on stream oops i'm a little
off-center
today actually let's get over here like
looking at the side of the screen today
we're going to be pushing the lighting a
little bit forward I think because
yesterday we took a look at the artifact
that I wanted to take a look at that we
weren't sure exactly what it was the
start of the stream but by the end of
the stream we were quite comfortable
with what was actually happening and in
fact it opened up an area that we might
want to poke at a little bit in the
future
effectively we found that the linear
blending of the octahedral light map or
bilinear blendering blending I should
say was not producing particularly good
results it's not the end of the world
like we could totally use them but they
weren't as satisfying as I thought that
they probably could be and they
suggested that we might want to switch
to a higher quality sampling of the
octahedral map now we have a couple
options for doing that and we sort of
played around with one yesterday and we
implemented it and got it working and
that was basically doing sort of a
squared fall-off instead of a linear
fall-off for the various interpolation
points and it definitely looked more
light like to me but it's still probably
not necessarily what we would want it's
hard to say there are ways of doing more
like we could do more taps we get sample
the texture more times so right now
we're pulling for pixels from the
octahedral map we could pull more right
so we could pull a larger number of
samples and get a smoother interpolation
of the lighting and we may want to do
that so we're just I'm not gonna look at
that right now because it's kind of a
second-order effect but basically we we
kind of now know there's there's like a
little tick mark that's like when we get
to the end of this and we take a look at
how the lighting is looking with the
full lighting solution in there if we're
seeing these artifacts because we know
that they're there now
if if they're objectionable at either
the squared version or the linear
version which only uses four pixels or
four texels from the texture map at that
point we may investigate some cubic
interpolation or something else that's
relatively fast but involves more like
nine pixels from the texture map or you
know worse yet 25 pixels from the text
texture map or 16 pixels from the
texture map and again normally I would
sort of bristle at the thought of doing
that but that's kind of an old-school
bristling because nowadays actually
texture samples aren't that expensive if
they're from the same place right
texturing off of modern graphics cards
anyway and again this is a totally
optional feature so the nice part about
it is on low-end hardware we could just
turn it off
and just use the one sample and you just
have more artifacts in the lighting
that's a great place to be because then
we could just say look if this is on a
fast card we know that lots of texture
samples from the same location will all
hit the texture cache very well so we'll
just go ahead and do 25 samples and have
a beautiful lighting solution or
whatever hmm that's a really great place
for us to be because in that scenario we
can just say look how hardcore is the
card we're running on turn on that
feature and now we just get better
results for taking more GPU time right I
got a saucy on my hands here on
second this is Molly beam many of you
know her she's an excellent puss she
likes the microphone she knocked it over
one time and I think that scared her a
little bit you want to say hi to
everybody do you know yeah everyone's
looking they can see you yeah I know
what you're up to today but you can sit
here if you want
just don't knock over the microphone
again alright so we have plenty of
options there and the so the good thing
about that is oh ok plus new are you
good what are you gonna do here what's
going on you're totally gonna knock over
the microphone again aren't you alright
we may have we may have made a mistake
okay plus what do we what are we doing
here alright okay so basically what we
want to do is we want to sort of just
keep that in the back of our minds we
don't really have to deal with it right
now because it's not actually affecting
our ability to see what the lighting
salute
to see what the lighting solution is but
we don't actually need to to do any more
work on it we may need to do some work
to protect our microphone from the cat
but we don't actually need to do any
more work to address that particular
lighting artefact because it's something
that we can just address as late as we
want to in the development cycle and
it's just throwing more GPU blending
time at the problem which is an easy
thing to turn on and off so I'm just
totally satisfied that that's a solved
problem if it needs to be and it can
just be something that gets better with
higher end hardware if that's what we
want so we'll just put that aside so
that leaves us with two things that I
want to do going forward the first one
is I want to get now the real lighting
solution in there because we've got the
ray caster and I want the ray caster to
start I want to start using the Ray
caster in the octahedral Maps and
debugging that I think that's what I
want to do today and then the step after
that is right now we're sort of
maintaining a separate voxel for no
reason that's just because of the way we
were sort of getting things working and
we don't actually need to do that
anymore we could just write directly
into the okay I think puts me start
typing into the chat window that's
probably going to be a problem
don't turn off the stream okay I'm gonna
put you in that window so that all you
can do is type into the chat hopefully
really hoping we don't have it hmm
push shuts down the computer situation I
tried to make sure that none of the
buttons that would shut down the
computer can be pawed with a one paw
click but it's not always it's not
always a perfect system all right so
what we need to do now is say let's
let's wire up the lighting we'll deal
with how to get the with streamlining
the voxel side of things later because
there's a lot of stuff we need to do
there that's just minutia first of all
we don't need to store it as floats
anymore we can encode the lighting in
something much more compact at the very
least we could do 16 bytes per gun we
certainly don't need 32 bytes relic of
doing now we're just doing 32 bytes per
gun because we don't want to have to
debug quantization issues right we want
to see what the solution looks like at
full float before we drop it down to
something less so we've got that we can
do we don't need the voxel intermediate
storage we can just write directly into
voxel so those are things that we're
gonna streamline in a second that'll be
that'll be like you know two weeks from
now or whatever so right now we need to
do is just wire up the ray caster and
get the actual lighting scheme in place
and I'm torn about how I want this to
work I was we built a thing that allows
us to query the lighting and the only
thing I really don't know right now I'm
not sure about is whether we should
query the lighting in some time shoot at
the light which is sort of a a way that
Ray Castor's often improve the ability
for lighting to get out into the scene
or if we just shouldn't do that and we
should always just choose sort of a
regularly uniform sampling and we just
let the light bounce the way it bounces
because we're not trying to buy us
coming from any particular thing like
yes there's lights but no we don't care
because we're just doing sort of
output of these lights into something
regular right and so so I don't know I
really don't we'll we'll have to play
around with that because I'm not sure
how we want to do it so anyway let's go
ahead and get started here I think I
want to do that sort of Ray casting
stuff today get that started and because
that way we'll try to hopefully get us
into a position where next weekend we
can spend all weekend
debugging the Ray caster and the
octahedral map interaction so I'd like
to get that like wired up and working
and just you know buggy right I'd like
to get to a buggy wiring of that today
so that next weekend we can spend all
weekend working on that so you can see
where we left off last time we basically
have the octahedral Maps working pretty
reliably in my opinion there are some
things that we're gonna have to address
going forward that are still artifacts
but that we know what they all are one
is when you move a light directly
through a light probe you get some right
you get some issues there I'm not sure
to what extent that will really cause a
problem in practice because in practice
I think we won't really have this
happening because the light this is a
procedurally done light right now and I
think once you're actually doing
hemispheres or a spherical sampling
you're gonna have so many inputs to that
system that I don't know that you'll get
such a problem when the when you just
have this one function that can move
through a singularity like that so I'm
not sure we'll have to address it but
you can see it sometimes happening we
get a like a little bright flash of the
light and that's what's happening there
we look at that and then of course we
have the sort of the sort of flower
shape here that's the interpolation
right and eventually Ike I said we might
want to try a bicubic to get that more
of a splotch that looks like that so
we'll sort of play with that but those
are the two artifacts that we have right
now but we know what they are and so I
don't really care about them much the
light probes here are being drawn I
don't know that I want to actually draw
them anymore so I'm going to turn those
off for now we may want to turn them on
so we can draw them the octahedral map
for each one of those at the location
where the
is I think we will want to do that in
the future but we probably won't do that
the way we're doing it now so I'm gonna
just gonna go ahead and turn that off
the base of the push debug box for these
we're gonna we're gonna get rid of so in
there or there but here so in here I'm
just gonna nerf this and I'm gonna let
this be a just a turned off path so if
we need it again and that way we're just
gonna look here and we can sort of see
some there's still some debug boxes
being drawn in here for things like
light querying and we can turn those off
eventually as well but for the moment
I'm gonna leave amongst I don't care and
we probably can start to turn these off
a lot of the time too because for a
while we're just gonna be working on the
ray casting and we now know that we can
see the octahedral maps just fine now
like so this like we know we're pretty
much sampling them properly as far as I
can tell and so we don't really need to
see these at the immediate moment so I'm
also gonna go ahead and turn some of
that off so I'll turn off the edge
coloring and I'll turn off the the
actual drawing of those of those as well
I should probably centralize a lot of
these switches so that I'm not like
dancing around with all this stuff each
time but either way so if we look in
here you can see we've got the light
maps being drawn in here we can just
kind of turn that off I'm not sure why
this is happening that doesn't really
make much sense that should probably be
out here there we go not sure why we're
doing that there was alright okay so now
we just switch back and we should have
essentially a fairly clean version of
the of the game lighting here right
and it's time to start making this
actually try to convict some light
around so what I'd like to do is just
switch over to the other routine and
start to try and make that routine you
know do something useful for us so if
you remember the way that we've got this
working is you know we kind of have this
thing set up where we can turn on this
test sphere and then there's also this
like checkerboard thing right and
finally we have this light transfer bit
and all of this stuff is kind of
nonsense now because you know like I
said we kind of want to be writing
directly into this thing instead of
doing what we were doing before but you
know either way it's fine we we can
leave it this way for now and then when
we streamline it will just streamline it
once everything's working and the point
here is this test light transfer the
checkerboard code is is not really still
working I mean we could make it work by
actually assigning to this but we'll do
this if we ever actually care about the
checkerboard the test light transfer
code is the code that we're actually
going to need now because the test light
transfer code is the code that actually
would grab out of the voxel storage
system and write to whatever we've got
here right so we're gonna need this to
be re-enabled and before I do that I
would like to take a look at the light
voxel cell because I think we want to
change the conception of how this is
working so what I realized I was
thinking about this the other day
actually just idly when I was sitting
around and what I realized is I think
we've been thinking about these update
steps
stooop stupid like we've been kind of
been stupid thinking about these
lighting steps because what I was
thinking is we don't really need to do
all this nonsense about total weight
accumulated and all that garbage right
because if you think about it when we go
to sample a location in the world and
we're going to write into one of these
octahedral maps what we could do instead
of any of the stuff that I have been
doing where we track weights and all
that stuff is just say look every time
we write into one just treat that
and update and blend it you know 95% 5%
blend it in right there because we want
the update rate to be based on how much
new information is coming in anyway and
the more rays we cast out of something
the more accurate the solution would be
on this frame anyway so we don't need to
do an accumulation pass and then a fill
we can just accumulate directly in
theirs right there's no reason not to do
that anymore so I'm pretty sure that
this is just stupid like I'm pretty sure
this is just not necessary right we only
actually need that and what we can do is
just update this directly which is great
because then when we want to roll all
this into a nice clean path once we have
it working well we can just do this
directly into the texture right so we
just store the texture and we just
update directly into the texture with a
light update and that's exactly what I
think we want to do so if we take a look
at what's going to happen here once I
start enabling some stuff we're gonna
have to deal with it but for the moment
right here's our test light transfer
pass we're gonna grab a light sell out
of here and then we're gonna do some
stuff well all right we know we need to
do a light C and a light D in this case
we can just grab those directly out of
here right so what we can do is say all
right the light C and the light D are
just gonna be grabbed directly out of
the voxel they're gonna be grabbed out
of the particular location that we're
talking about here
and so we can just do like you know T X
Y dy DX DX or something right and we can
get rid of this and we can write those
here right so we don't really have to do
anything else we'll just get that and
it'll work and everyone will be happy so
we can turn tests light transfer on now
in theory anyway and we should actually
be able to just use that now the problem
is we're not computing anything in it so
it we would just write and you can see
it it's just black right so you can see
we don't have any any actual data here
but all we really need to do now is we
just need to go ahead and say oh okay
let's make sure we actually compute
something here and put something into
these voxel cells right we just need to
put something into the voxel cells so
that we can do our lighting and so in
order to test that working at all in
fact you can also see here like look at
all this work we were doing before that
we just don't need to do like we don't
need to clear this either right we just
update every time we cast array we just
update on the right I don't know why we
weren't doing that before it doesn't
really make sense to me why we weren't
doing that before you know but we
weren't right so I don't know that's
just yeah that's just where we're at so
if we now want to go in and start with
this week it we can literally just get
rid of this like this is just garbage
now it doesn't need to happen at all and
if we want to go in here and do our test
cast we can just we can do that just
fine and we should be able to to use the
test cast case I don't know if we
actually care about running this test or
not but we should be able to do the test
cast case and actually write something
in right so let's see if we run the test
cast and we go to spam voxel this is now
not necessary right we don't have to
really do a spam voxel anymore we can
just do a single write into a single
voxel location and that should be
sufficient I think because we should
always be making sure that we yeah we we
don't need to interpolate outside of
things anymore so I think we should be
okay so if we take a look at the spam
voxel bit you can see here it was doing
the voxel slice and all this nonsense I
think I'm just gonna go ahead and say
that's you know not that's not useful
anymore we don't want to do any of this
right so let's just let's just nuke that
out or although you know what we might
want to preserve a little of this like
so this part here for example we
were computing which voxel were in that
one we might want to do although where
does that actually happen so there's the
vox i/o it's okay so it's just using the
vox i as a direct look up here right so
we might want to do is just keep this
part so we might want to basically say
like look this part here will actually
will actually keep and this spam voxel
part here we don't actually want right
we just want that so we can basically
say where are we trying to write to and
that'll find the location and then we'll
write it in and blah blah blah blah blah
right so let's take this out here and
one thing that I don't really know to be
completely honest I just I'm just not
sure is in the future I don't know if we
want to cast rays from locations that
aren't where the light probe is I mean
that's kind of one of those things that
I mean we might want to look at the
literature a little bit for that but in
order to accurately say what the
octahedral map is any particular
location you need to cast lights from
that location right but since we know
we're only casting that were only
interpolating from fixed locations in
the world and we're producing points
inside you know basically the cage of
eight of these things what I don't know
is do you want to just take samples
throughout that cage and splat them out
to the surrounding voxels as
contributions right so there'd be an
eight wide splat like like we were doing
before you know and I'm saying I don't
know if you want to do that furthermore
let's suppose we don't want to do that
because that's just way too much right
band but we don't want to do that
because it just it just multiplies out
our rights
so suppose we don't want to do that then
what I think we would be in a situation
the situation I think we'd be in would
be that do we still want to take inside
like further
neighborhood of one of these octahedral
maps do we'd want to take samples from
positions that are displaced from it at
least a little bit so that we can see
what other kinds of lights might be
getting there
as a result right and I just don't know
the answer to these questions at all
right I just have no idea so we may just
have to test that but for right now I'm
just gonna say all right we're just
gonna take this this spam voxel bit here
we're gonna say there's just one spam
voxel call we're gonna have like what
the location is that you wanted to spam
for now and we'll make that be a get
voxel index and I don't know that like I
said I don't know that we're really
gonna want to do it this way going
forwards but we'll leave it this way for
now so we have the light position it's
not really necessary anymore we would
just have what the light color is and
the light depth and that would be it
right so we do the spam voxel we'd we'd
do the large rush maybe we keep is test
case here for just for good measure I
don't know but then we would say look if
this where we're trying to spam if it's
inside we'll go ahead and figure out
where this is going to be where the
voxel center would be I guess we don't
even really need that anymore we would
go ahead and say look let's go ahead and
add to the the light see by doing a
blend and like I said we're just gonna
do the light update very directly so
we're gonna do something like this and
the way we're gonna do it is we're gonna
do it with a lerp so I don't think we
have it yet we don't have one so I'm
gonna go ahead and grab this particular
cell so we're gonna do a light voxel
cell I mean oh that was a sad Muse
what's wrong puss I don't know if you
heard heard the push she was upset about
that oh I guess oh you know what it is
she's just new and I I know what she's
mooing about now all right anyway let's
go ahead and update the light see and
light depart to just be lerp based so
what I want to do here is say we're
gonna take the light see and we're
using our lerp factor whatever we decide
that's going to be and the look that
would go in here so we want sort of the
blend factor to be something that we
remember and I and I feel like we did
that I thought that was in here so we
have that here and rather than a blend
you blend V I don't I mean maybe that's
fine because maybe we want to keep those
two coefficients so we don't have to do
the one - I don't know but basically
what we're be doing there is saying look
we want to do a alert either way
so maybe this is just gonna be I think
this is just gonna be a blend blend T
like T frame blend something like that
or a T update blend right I think that's
what we're gonna call that so I'm going
to take that T update blend and I'm
gonna use it here so we're just gonna
say go ahead and update from the
existing one to whichever one we've got
passed and write that back and we're
gonna be the same thing with the light D
and so that will just do those lips over
time right and that'll update that C
it'll update the D we have both of those
now and we can just move from there
right and we have a nice clean thing
where we just say here's where you're
gonna put the light in for now we're
only gonna spam one we don't spam all
eight and we're gonna use that as the
backbone of that least the test case
right so let's go ahead and get this
working this obviously has to be an
address of not sure what this cleaning
about it should have all of these
shouldn't it what's the problem could be
trying to match oh right sorry about
that so you know we forgot one more
thing we need the direction in the
octahedral map that we were going to
write so we in here we also need a txt Y
so we kind of need to say look what
direction were you going if that makes
sense so I guess that would just say
yeah that would just be a v2s right
which I don't I guess we don't have we
have a v3 s but we don't have a v2 s it
looks like we we have a v2 u I guess
which maybe is fine
yeah so if we want to convert this down
I guess then then what we would say is
yet where where are we inside the the
octahedral map at that point right and I
guess I hold on a second I got a wait a
second for that
all right so yeah what we want to do
here is we're gonna need the the
octahedral map lighting location so I'm
not sure exactly how we want to pass
that down v2u seems like maybe the best
idea but in the future I'm thinking so
it's gonna be a location in the actual
map so yeah I don't know it's it's gonna
be hard to say it would basically be
part of the voxel lookup as well so I
really don't know but let's just say
that this is the T offset for now and
then inside here we'll just say look
it's gonna be T offset Y T offset X
right so we'll do it this way for now
because I'm not sure how else we would
want to do that really but we'll see so
off we go and that has to be put that
array index has to be put on both sides
right we need to put it here and here
and that should take care of it I hope
so then what we're doing the spamming we
need to like fill this out properly so
this is an actual light this is in the
actual light propagation and so for this
I'm just gonna go ahead and turn that
off for a second because we want to just
look at the other one this is the one we
want to look at now and then as soon as
we get this one working we'll look at
the one in the actual ray cast code so
here's us doing just the test cast and
so what we need to do here is produce
the octahedral offset for this ray
direction
so whatever the raid erection is we
obviously knew it because we did a cast
d4 on it right
so we already knew that you know it's
this is the direction we're going so
when we know that we hit the light what
we need to do here is do the octahedral
conversion right so we need to take that
get the octahedral conversion and what I
would say here is we need the octahedral
conversion to actually be you know work
with with our bitmap so we kind of want
an additional we
additional layer of conversion here and
so what I think I want to do is take a
look at the one that's in the lighting
computation sphere test which is this
and we want this to be something we can
just call to get back the actual lookups
into the system now it's a little bit
weird here because we're doing this sort
of looping over the place to write in a
weird way and I don't know that I'd
really love that but for the moment
let's just say look it's gonna have to
it's should I have to take care of this
transform anyway so you know blah blah
blah all right so I'm gonna go ahead and
say we need like a utility function here
that's gonna get this for us and that's
gonna return the V to you that's the
offset right so like get octahedral
offset or something like that and we
pass in the Ray direction to figure out
what that is right so that's what I want
to do here and this is gonna require us
doing the inverse lookup right so we're
gonna want to call this function get
octahedral and we're gonna want to throw
that in here we want still the rest of
this stuff we want the well actually do
we don't need the light position
actually do we cuz that's not really
necessary so we just need the cast place
we need the light see the light D we
actually know as well actually
so it's this value right that's the so
we might as well throw it in there I
guess and off we go so I think that's
all we really need for the spam voxel
case right so now we need to do is
implement this actual function we need
it to work and in order to get this to
work what we need to do is take the oh
and you know what I should do one more
thing here where we were previously
doing the herb blend you herb blend V
right we need to set those
we need to change this to setting just
to the irradiance preservation value
right so this is the blend value we
actually want so this is just going to
be the the T update blend here and we
don't need this right that's just the
inverse one and we don't need any of
these either right so we would just do
like okay if we're accumulating we set
the herb blend view value to like you
know one I guess and when we're done
with this we actually I guess we just
set it this way if we're doing
accumulation we would just say look
however many there are the update blend
is just one over that I'm guessing yeah
okay that's what we were already doing
nevermind so it's just this right so if
we wanted to do an accumulation we would
just set the update blend to be one over
the accumulation count and then stop
when we're done right all right so if
we're in here doing the doing the the
rest of the stuff we just we just need
the oxygen offset now I think that's the
only thing we're really messed up on
right so we just need to implement this
function and let's go ahead and do that
so the first thing we want to do
obviously is to get the octahedral from
unit vector so that gives us a v2 right
and the v2 goes from negative one to one
and we just need to map that out into
our actual space so in order to map that
out into the actual offsets we know that
we're only gonna start at like one one
and in fact you know what we kind of
know what this is supposed to be in the
shader as well right
because we actually did this in the Z
bias program and we want these two to
kind of line up probably I mean probably
not exactly because they're probably
gonna be optimized versions of each
other but more or less you know
similar thing so if you take a look at
what we're doing here we're saying like
hey it's the you know 1/2 times the
interior UV dim C times the octahedral
so what we'd want to do here is make
sure that we're sort of looking these up
in a similar way right all right and
again we have to account for the fact
that the texture sampler is gonna have
the 5.5 offsets it's gonna be a little
trickier back to exactly how we want to
do this but you know we'll take it slow
all right so we know that this is going
to come back negative 1 to 1 so the
first thing we're gonna want to do is
we're going to want to so so in like UV
space right we're going to want to take
the UV and we're going to want to
multiply it by 1/2 to reduce the range
because it's spanning 2 now and we
needed to only spend 1 and then we're
gonna have to add to it right so you
know we could do it this way the other
way we can do it is like this six of one
half oops six of one half dozen of the
other right so we can add one to it
first that makes 0 to 2 and then have
the range that gives us 0 to 1 we could
alternatively take 0.5 and add it to 0.5
times the value you know we'll do it
this way for now but it doesn't really
matter so that gives us a 0 to 1 range
and now we need to map it into the
actual range of the light lookup dim
right so we now need this thing to line
up properly for doing an actual indexing
operation and in order to do that we're
going to have to make sure that we know
first of all what the dimension even is
right so we will make an f32 here that's
our dimension and we know that the
dimension is actually minus the pad
right we have a 1 pixel border around it
so we have this problem of needing to
subtract away this padding value
in order to make sure that we have the
right thing and then we also need to add
that offset that padding offset so we're
gonna have to kind of yet work that
through so when we go and start with the
actual UV with the actual index with the
actual I guess what it's call this eye
right we're gonna start by blowing the
UV out to the dimension right so we now
it spans the entire set of pixels but of
course that means that in the case where
the UV was actually one it's gonna be
equal to the dimension itself right so
in other words if we subtract two from
the light lookup square dim and the
light lookup squared dim is 10 that
means that's 8 UV can equal 1 so we're
gonna have 1 times 8 or actually 8 and
that would be 1/4 that would be off the
end right of our of our texture so in
order to figure out where to write we're
actually gonna need to be one more back
right we're going to need to be one more
back and then slid up 1/2 in order to
line us up with the actual pixel centers
I believe that would be where we would
want to be right so we'd want something
like this presumably which now gives us
an actual index but of course remember
the index itself also needs to be one
forward for the pad so we actually want
the half pixel plus the one for the pad
once we have that I think we're down to
more or less where we need to be right
we now know that the result is just
gonna be the rounded version of our eye
right so we're just gonna want to do or
you know what since we slid it up it's
just a truncation so we could either
round yeah if we slide it up then we
actually can just floor it right because
now we know that it already was so we
can just do a floor
we have four floor yeah so we'll do
floor here and I believe that would give
us what we want but we're gonna want to
check this a little more carefully
because I'm kind of just you know
pulling this out
oops
but that should give us in theory what
we're looking for
oh right and so that's the offset value
that we want and you know maybe we've
got some bugs in there oops I don't know
what's going on there oh I know what's
happening there we change the size of
the lighting structure so I think that's
what we want for getting the octahedral
offset that we're going to write to
again that's my argument that that's
roughly what we want so here we would
write that lighting in right here right
and in theory I guess if we didn't mess
any of that up but we probably did this
would actually work which is unlikely
right so let's see what we've actually
got well so actually something is
getting written here which is kind of
surprising actually so it doesn't look
particularly correct that's kind of
weird yeah so I have no idea exactly
what we're seeing there but it's
actually writing something into the
voxel which is kind of surprising all
right so anyway that's what we needed to
bug because basically this case for all
intents and purposes purposes is exactly
the same as the Ray casting case for the
full lighting it's just instead of
actually doing the voxel the octahedral
map sampling in there to do secondary
lighting this just does one straight ray
cast so if we get this working we really
only have one more small step to get the
final thing working and so that'll be
good
well small it's actually pretty big step
so we have one more major step they gave
me make it but that's okay one step we
can handle alright so what we want to do
now is try to actually make this thing
work reasonably debug whatever is going
on in here and make sure you know we're
getting some yeah make sure we're
getting some kind of reasonable lighting
it looks like in here we're just doing
the solution debug light P right so we
should just be casting from I think this
should just be casting from the the
light on the dudes head right I'm pretty
sure it's just casting the light in the
dudes head so what we want to do here is
just we want to go ahead and work on
this test case I think we're all good I
think it's still casting from that
because it looks like this would cast
from the closest light if we turn that
on but because we're not because that's
commented out we're just gonna get
lightly 4p so when we do our spam voxel
this is pretty much what we're passing
this is the hit distance we don't care
about that this is the light color we
want to some in there and here's the get
octahedral offset I'm not sure
so I suppose there's two things that
could be wrong and I'm not sure about
which one to start with so the copy
could actually be wrong which I guess we
should
visually inspect just to make sure we
didn't screw that up already but looking
here you can see us grabbing the cells
out
ZYX here and we're just gonna copy those
directly into the location in the voxel
that we thought they should go right and
I think that should just work I don't
think there's anything weird going on
there so that seems reasonable anyway
I mean don't quote me on that but that
seems fine and so then when we actually
do the spam voxel I'm not sure about
this but yeah again it's it's just doing
ZYX it's getting the voxel index from
the location that is trying to spam and
that all seems again pretty innocuous to
me hmm
so I'm kind of surprised actually I'm
not sure what's going on there what I
might do real quick just to get a better
sense of it since I'm not sure what's
going on is I want to see what happens
when I actually what's the probe test
function here work on test cast from
probes what I might do real quick is
just assume we always hit so let's just
assume we always hit a light I guess or
I should so just spam the voxel no
matter what if that makes sense just so
I can see what that does cuz I'm not
sure what that would look like
so it's really strange like it's like
the writing out to the voxel is somehow
yeah we've got we've got some kind of
weird bug they're like why would it
matter that I was right on top of that
thing it's like I'm only writing to the
one I'm standing on in some cases and
then not always right so I can hop out
here and it doesn't happen and it looks
really weird so we've got some kind of a
bug here that doesn't have to do with
like it probably isn't really I feel
like it's not really related to the
parts that I thought I was going to
debug and it's really just more about
this part here so that's kind of weird
if I go look I mean this does work in
world space which is what I would expect
right so the fact that we're passing
down the Caspi that seems right it
shouldn't it should not be localized
right it's just the it's just the
position and that seems right and we're
just writing in so you know I suppose
that could be the octahedral offset now
that I think about it though because if
it was based it based on the angle to
the light this would actually make a
difference right so if this were
actually borked I suppose that would
present a problem in theory so maybe we
have to maybe we do have to like take a
second to verify that this is okay right
know why this is done backwards here
wouldn't matter but just making sure so
just looking at this doing octahedral
from unit vector I guess one thing
that's a little bit of an issue is we
don't know what this even does we've
never tested this I don't think we
should take a quick check to make sure
it looks right
so yeah just making sure this is looking
up the same way we get the one norm by
summing up the absolute values of the
components which is the definition of
the one norm so that looks good right we
take the result as one over the one norm
times the input XY that seems reasonable
we look at the Z component of the input
and then we compute Oh X and Oh Y which
are the sine of the thing we just
computed which seems right and one minus
the absolute value of the inverted pair
so the Y goes into the X the X goes into
the Y and that seems right as well we
then assign those two to the result so
we now have that we overwrite the new
with the new version and we return that
so that seems good
so that part doesn't seem super
suspicious to me and if we go to
this part of the code here once we take
that UV which would be negative one to
one we immediately say let's offset it
by one so now it's should be zero to two
on both axes we have it sewn out zero to
one on both axes we take the dim of the
lookup we take the I value as the UV
blown out to that dimension offset by
the one pixel plus the pixel centers and
then we floor it again that looks pretty
solid right so I guess let's take a look
at that routine maybe we will do a debug
builds and just see like if I break it
up to get octahedral offset like what's
going on there
I could also spam some assertions
because even though it's kind of hard to
think about what you would necessarily
assert there are some things I can
assert so for example I could assert
things like you should be less than the
fifth pixel if the X was negative right
juju no I'm saying like in other words
we could we could assert that we're in
the right quadrant you know like stuff
like that so although we it's hard to
think about what we would necessarily
assert here directly we certainly could
have cert a few things that would make
sense so maybe we'll spam some of those
in there as well oops so here's our two
results and let's take a look at the
direction blown out as well so if you
look here right like you've got negative
x negative Y negative Z
and that does seem like that's a
plausible place for that to be I mean I
couldn't say for sure but it's not
completely absurd right things you could
never do with Visual Studio right I'm
just holding down the f5 key and
watching the values like Visual Studio
can't do that even a little bit right I
don't know if you remember what it was
like it's pretty pretty terrible it's so
stupidly slow alright so as the Y's
getting positive you can see us getting
onto the fifth pixel now which is right
because like pixels zero is the pad one
two three and four are the Y negative
the y+ are five six seven eight
right and then nine is the pad on the
outside oops
so again these seem sane enough like I
guess what I would say is it's a little
bit weird that I'm never seeing positive
x values because there should be things
to the right like do you notice oh there
we go okay I'm like there should be
things to the right and I wasn't seeing
any but there was some
I will say that by and large there
aren't very many so why am I not seeing
any positive direction X values I mean I
saw few but they were really rare there
should be more or less even like I
should see a similar number of positive
X directions unless I'm missing
something so I'm kind of wondering is
the cast Direction not what I think it
is I mean it sure looks like what you
would expect like is this light in some
totally random place or something like
is the light value weird
let's take a look so that's the light
position and here's that cast direction
so that's a little bit more balanced to
next I guess so I alright alright I mean
maybe that's fine I don't know I'm a
little weirded out by that but you know
a little weirded out is not horrible
so let's think how are we gonna do bug
this because we don't really have any
idea what's going wrong so I think the
first thing I need to do is make sure
that the copy can't be busted and so in
order to do that I suppose what I'd have
to do is inside here where we're like
spamming the voxel I would have to put
something in here that would tell me
like that would just write to the voxel
with some kind of known pattern you know
what I mean just to make sure that the
the C values and the D values here makes
sense so what I might say is like
suppose instead of doing this I was to
just say whatever the spammy location is
will translate into the color somehow
right so if we take this voxel I and I
said what's the maximum dimension of the
voxel and then I just set the color to
that that would be one way to do it
right I can basically say look take the
voxel I turn that into a regular v3
multiply that by a scalar that will
truncate me down so light lookup voxel
dim right so this will make it so that I
I stay inside the total values for
everything and multiply that down right
so that would just assign a color to the
voxel that should just be a gradient
ramp oh I don't need to be in debug mode
anymore that's just gonna be slow for no
reason
so that'll set that yeah that'll set
that color here we go
and let's try and get that working all
right so this just makes no sense right
like this isn't even seem to be doing
what I asked it to at all like that just
seems totally broken because that that
should be just setting the voxels as
they're set like throughout this thing
it should be spamming all the voxels
right and it's not doing anything even
remotely like that so we're not even
we're not even running what we think
we're running we're just we're just in
in no-man's land right now so let me
just test cast probe or test never
remember what this thing is called test
cast from probes so in test cast from
probes which is called here if we write
to that voxel
I would also point out that all of this
code is like garbage code now we should
probably delete like a lot of this stuff
just to clean things up so if we take a
look at what's happening in here right
we're writing out to the voxel then we
come through here and are we doing
something in here that's bad I don't
think we are so all we're doing here
right is taking our voxel and copying it
into the appropriate place inside the
actual external lighting voxel right and
this is just doing the edge copies so
that should not affect anything either
and that's it right so I don't know how
we're seeing what we're seeing here
because we should be blending this stuff
pretty directly right I mean I don't I
don't see how we're getting what we're
getting here so let me change to another
thing let's just do this
let's take the lerp out of this entirely
I'm just gonna say alright everything's
read every voxel we spam is just bright
red and I mean see how weird that is
it's like we're only spamming voxels we
land on how is that happening like
what's going on there why are we not
calling spam voxel anywhere else because
we're supposed to be calling it for all
of the light probes are all the lard
they're only like light probes right
next to the dude or something or are we
interpreting these in the wrong spaces
or something like that
is enlarged voxel like returning
nonsense
I don't know so we've got some kind of
nonsense going on here that's totally
broken and I'm not sure what it actually
is right so here's another thought let
me look at get voxel indexed real quick
I mean yeah that's that looks right to
me I mean I guess I don't know why that
would be suspicious at all it seems
totally fine I'm not sure why that would
be an error at all but I mean maybe it
is so it seems like we're not really
actually getting into this code path
much at all and that doesn't make a
whole lot of sense to me so what's
happening there why is that
failing let's do one more debug here and
look at why that's not hitting very
often or if it is why it seems to only
write into one of the things which
doesn't make a lot of sense to me
all right so we don't care about this
we mostly care about this here's our Vox
I I mean right here's our light see
I mean that sure looks like we're right
into a lot of oxal
so I suppose one thing we're not doing
though is we're not writing to the rest
of the octahedral map and I suppose that
would cause a problem right so maybe
that's mostly what we're seeing
we're only writing to the one direction
in the octahedral map where this
particular light source happens to be
so I suppose that would make sense right
so let's try this just to verify suppose
in here instead of calling get
octahedral offset suppose I hard-coded
this to actually just point upward
because we know that all of the ground
surfaces normals are pointing upward so
that's where they're gonna look for
their lighting like as close to that
right when we're looking down close so
let's try that first
so now yeah we're totally getting more
much more what we would expect right
all right so this seems better let's go
ahead and change this now to actually
doing in the spam voxel call let's
change this to actually using the
correct value well correct value is a
bit of a stretch here all right so this
is moving the light around and as far as
I can tell moving the light around here
should change the intensity of that
light see but it doesn't actually seem
to well okay I take it back no it
doesn't because this doesn't actually do
that it looks like right so I guess this
doesn't do attenuation here for whatever
reason because I I think spam voxel may
be used to do the attenuation so all
right let's add the attenuation Adam if
we have the length and the length is
here right so we want to do a clamp zero
to one on this thing where we basically
take the light color and we multiply it
by whatever value we're going to use
here for attenuation so we have the T
Max and the T max I guess arranged to
something I don't know what I want my
distance to be there but let's say
something like that and OH
that's what I actually want to do there
okay
all right so I'm pretty sure we now have
more or less of a handle on what we're
supposed to be doing here
and again we can't really make much use
of that of the REA Direction stuff
because we're only casting in one
direction so if we filled in like this
is this is not gonna work like with the
octahedral map much at all because since
we're only casting in one direction it
doesn't really help us but we're getting
okay we're getting there because we can
see what it would be doing if we were
only casting up so I'm gonna call that
roughly correct I think that's good
enough for now I don't know if we
actually care about what happens if you
run the Ray caster because the Ray
caster should not have broken in some
way so in theory that would be fine
still and that would just prevent you
again from seeing kind of around corners
so you know like when you are behind
things I'm guessing you shouldn't be
able to see it I don't know if that will
actually happen here though
yeah so in order to make that disappear
we would need to do this always so we
need to spam the voxel either way so in
here where we do the hid light what this
actually needs to be is like this right
so if we hit the light use it otherwise
dump it right because in order to make
the light go away we have to sum in zero
to any place we cast it and didn't find
the light anymore otherwise it'll just
stay lit forever right so I think that's
roughly what we would do I'm not sure
why that's so fast like the lerp until a
strip I'm not sure
that looks more gradual there
those don't look that gradual I don't
know let me set it I'm not sure about
that so I'm gonna set that T update just
really quickly I want to set that T
Update blend to be you know a bit
further down
and you know it fades out slowly but it
fades in awfully fast and I guess I
don't know why that would be is that
confusing to anyone else or just to me
hmmm I say so let's set it down even
more like I'm gonna set it down like way
down and just see because I don't I
don't really know what's going on there
so there is it fading out right I'm
looking at these two right here
I guess I don't know I'm a little
weirded out by that to be completely
honest with you I don't quite understand
what is happening there I I don't feel
like I'm getting the same amount I mean
I don't feel like I'm getting a uniform
sort of blend speed between decay and
attack there and I'm not sure why that
would be maybe the light is brighter oh
is that why the light may be much
brighter than then is is the light like
10 10 10 or something
where's the light see yeah okay that's
that's why right there right that that's
that's what it is it's it's that I was
gonna say I knew there's something going
on there so we were adding like much
higher values than one and which is fine
there's nothing wrong with that I just
wanted to know what was going on there
so now it should be much more uniform
between the two I would think let me
tune that and see if it actually is so
we are in here we're gonna set the light
see 2 1 1 1 then down here we're just
gonna blend it out so now if I set this
to more of a 10 frame sort of situation
and remember that's not frames anymore
it because we have multiple samples per
so that seems about uniform
I'll be honest still seems really
non-uniform to me I wonder if there's
another non-linearity in the ramp there
that I'm just not thinking about because
I don't touch that value anywhere right
so in theory we should be adding 1 1 1
or 0 0 0 right and we should be adding
them the same in each case right we
should be blending them into the same
rate whether we're whichever one we're
doing and I guess maybe you could argue
that the gamma ramp is what's doing that
maybe because the gamma ramp is going to
be nonlinear but no I mean because we
should still see at that point during
those darks you can see how slow it
moves to the darks and then it you don't
even see those darks when you do that
so that weirds me out I don't have an
answer for that I don't have an answer
for what's going on there I'm interested
to know
so do we touch the voxel in any other
way here like do we do anything else to
the light see where we like you know
muck with the value in some kind of way
per frame that we're not remembering
that we do
yeah I'm not seeing it I am not seeing
it
am I the only person who's not seeing it
like do you folks know I don't know
maybe you've already figured it out but
I don't know so that's troubling it's
not the most troubling thing in the
world but it's really weird and so I
would have expected those two things to
be the same and they are really
definitely a lot not the same at all and
that is weird right in both of these
cases we should not be able to have
really any values we can't these can't
be negative right because we're doing a
clamp 0 1 we're striving for 1 the
multiplying so that's going to be a
multiplier 50 to 0 in one and you know
if anything I would think they'll like
light should get brighter more slowly
because getting brighter is proportional
to the distance of the light source
whereas getting darker is always zero
zero zero so it seems to me like you
would think that it would be if anything
slower to get brighter and faster to get
darker if I was going to have to push a
bug in one direction
mmm
so I just plain don't know and I'm gonna
have to put this as it to do because
something's wrong so there is one way I
could see there being an argument for
why the color would I mean there is one
vague way this could work and not be
broken
I guess so since we're casting her probe
if two of the probes if it's like two of
the probes are zero and one of the
probes is not and then two of the probes
those other two probes switched to one
but they're all writing into the same
voxel that would do it gin i'm santi
so if we just did only the voxels
themselves or only did one light probe
per voxel etc etc that might explain it
so let me go see I mean sure
so here we're we're doing the light
probe garbage right let's just suppose I
knocked out one light probe per tile
because I can and then I ran it what
would I see now right I'm just curious
I mean it still seems totally wrong to
me
so not really getting a positive feeling
about that with new light probes we
should get nothing
I guess I'll verify that there should be
no lighting right and now if I turn on
one of these light probes let's say that
one the lighting should magically start
to appear oh no it shouldn't because we
haven't run the world jinn so running
with one light probe
yeah I don't know I can't think of any
explanation for that and that's really
bad I don't even know what we're gonna
look at to find that I guess what we're
gonna have to do is put in some test
code that allows us to like spam all the
voxels with a particular ramp color then
spam them back to see what that looks
like and verify that that looks okay if
that doesn't look okay then we're living
in bizarro land where somehow going a
ramp in one direction versus going a
ramp in the other direction
okay so wait a minute maybe I'm
overreacting though let's use this
awesome calculator thing that we've been
using I don't know how to make a new one
of these things area so here's the
thought for y'all since we know that the
ramp is nonlinear right because it's a
gamma curve that we're looking at at the
monitor so a linear change is gonna look
like a nonlinear change right so if the
curve goes the other way round which it
will that would explain the difference
very interesting okay so you know bear
with me here
what's our update function right well
our update function is we're taking
alert right so we're doing you know 1
minus T times a plus TB right where a is
like zero and B is 1 or something like
this right and so if we think about what
that's going to do this equations gonna
look different depending on the
circumstance what you get back so like
our final brightness right we'll call
that linear brightness let's say L if we
have 0 &amp; 1
here no I just want one yeah if we have
0 &amp; 1 here right this T value here is is
quite low and we're doing this over time
so it's gonna be a little bit hard for
us to this is like a recurrence I don't
know how we can do this easily because
we want to we want to do like a
summation of this over time for the same
value which I don't know again my my
knowledge of this graphing calculator is
not particularly good but the point is
it's
gonna be a curve that looks two
different ways it's either gonna look
that way or that way depending where
they were going up or down right
trying to think of how to show you this
alright
wait why does it say day 580 did I never
start the timer it's not day five idiot
I've bee 581 right Dave 581 anyone
anyone could someone on the chat verify
for me it's day 581 I'm pretty sure it
is yeah so we we never set this value i
sorry about that so this is just wrong
here there we go well remember to end 12
yeah anyway
so what we're effectively doing here
right is every frame we're applying the
linear blend so on a particular frame
like the value so whatever our you know
value is on or maybe let's say our value
is at time T plus one is always going to
equal a blend towards something so it's
going to be one - I shouldn't use T we
use F so on our frame the next frame
it's going to be equal to one minus T
times the current frame plus T times the
target value and this is either going to
be zero or one depending on whether
we're going up or down in this case
right we're either blending into a
bright light or a dim light so it's
whatever I mean doesn't really matter
what these two are right but the point
is we have the dark version or the light
version and we want to know the
difference in behavior of these two
functions right and obviously they're
going to do the same kind of a curve
going from one to the other but the
point is the actual place in the range
is going to be different so if we look
at what happens here on a particular
update step right excuse me on a
particular update step this value starts
off quite low like it's gonna start out
at zero and go towards one or it's going
to start at 1 and go towards zero right
and it's gonna update each individual
time now unfortunately for us this is
essentially a this is basically like a
differential equation right so it's like
a know de kind of a thing because the
value of the function you know V of of f
plus 1 is dependent on something like a
function of V of F right it's going to
equal some function here it's like
something that takes this function as an
put right so it's it's nasty because
it's it's if it's a function that
depends on itself and those are always
you know kind of unwieldy to deal with
right but we know that that is going to
produce if you take a look at what
actually happens if you look at the
values over time and again I there's
probably a way to do this in the
graphing calculators don't know how but
if you look at what the values of this
is going to produce over time what's
gonna happen is let's suppose that we
started at zero and we're going towards
1 what would we expect to see if our T
value in this case I think is like 1/6
right so I mean we could make that a
little easier on ourselves let's just
say it was point two it's not horrible
as an approximation but whatever it is
right so if we wanted to know what VF
plus 1 was in this case we want to know
what this part is we know that we've got
0.8 times in this case 0 right plus 0.2
times 1 right so that's just gonna be
point two and then on the next frame you
know this comes down here so we're gonna
have 0.8 because this is discrete right
we're not doing this continuously we're
doing it per frame as like a you know
discrete thing so in this case we're
gonna say all right now we've got point
eight times whatever was here right plus
0.2 times 1 again right so in that case
we've actually got 0.2 times 0.8 so now
we're at 0.16 right plus our point 2 now
we're at 0.36 right now what you'll
notice is the jump here if I did that
math correctly
yeah so if I did that math correctly
what you'll notice is this is not a
constant derivative right and that's
what you would expect from a linear
blend so if you take a look at how far
we got on this one we actually our Delta
was point two on this one our Delta was
not point two
right we didn't go from point two two
point four instead we went from point 2
to point 3 6 for a delta of 0.16 right
so our Delta's going down over time and
let's keep going so now we take our
point three six we put it in here right
and we have our point two again and now
what we end up with is 0.8 times 0.36
plus our point two right now we have
point four eight and give it the benefit
the doubt call it point four nine right
well now if we take point four nine and
- our point three six now we're even
less right so what that means is that if
you look at what this is doing on the
curve right starting at zero well as we
went forward over time so here's our
time axis here our actual value going up
you know if this was let's let's do this
so this is one so at point two point
four point six point eight one yeah so
we jumped directly up to there on our
first frame right so here was frame zero
is frame one hears from two right but
then in our next frame if we were going
up linearly we would have it there we
didn't at all right we were at point
three six so we were there and then on
the next one we weren't even at five so
we were there right so we're kind of
curving like that right as we go up
we're curving towards one using a
gradually decreasing speed of curve
right now when we do this in Reverse the
same thing is going to happen because
this is the same linear combination but
it's gonna happen the other way round
right so when we do the other one we're
gonna get the same kind of curve one
that starts out fast but then ramps
right it's just gonna be the flipped
curve because it's exactly the same with
just these two numbers slipped right and
so what happens is we move through this
part of the ramp quickly in one and
slowly on another and we move through
this part of the ramp quickly on one and
slowly on the other right if this were
linear perceptually then we would expect
to see it the same in both cases because
hey we're just you know it's it's linear
throughout so it'll appear the same
speed in either case it's just an ease
out at a different place right but
because it's not because this then goes
through the gamma ramp right which
raises this to the two point two right
because this then goes through the gamma
ramp were actually spending a lot more
time in one part of the curve on one
like this will then move this point
right drastically one way or the other
to think about which way it actually is
moving it right so when we actually look
at these two they should actually look
quite a bit different because one of
them is spending a lot more time in a
much more defined area of the color
space that we can see than the other one
I'm still not 100% convinced in that I
feel like it's a bit of a rat hole to go
down right now that we don't actually
need to but this is very interesting and
probably warrants further study what we
should probably do is make a few test
ramps using various things like one with
gamma 1 without graph their values and
look at their perceptual values just to
convince ourselves that we're not
overlooking a bug right because I don't
want to like brush it aside but that
does actually sound fairly convincing
because you can see like yeah you're
spending a lot more because you take the
same amount of time to transit between
the two values which we know would be
true in our case because when we're
doing that transiting the perceptual
result when you put it through the gamma
curve we're gonna be spending a lot more
time on one of them in an area that you
can perceive the shades of than in the
other one where you can't right
I believe that's what will happen but
again that's a little hand wavy because
we didn't actually we need to go
actually verify at some point that
that's the case
I don't know when we'll have time to do
that but we should because I think
that's a good thing to just understand
and it kind of eluded me for a second so
I kind of like would like to go do some
tests so that would sink in right if
that makes sense but anyway so I think
we're okay here I would like a little
more confirmation on that but we'll see
I don't know what this thing is that
we're gonna get rid of it so now we're
gonna try and get the lighting
computation actually do something and so
we need to do a little bit of work to
make that happen here right and so we
want something that's going to stop
calling the test probes version and that
actually just sends light around and
we've got a problem the biggest problem
is we don't know how to sample the
lighting here we need some way of
sampling the actual lighting so what I'm
gonna do is I'm just gonna go ahead and
turn off the test probe stuff and we'll
have to put in an actual voxel blending
call so when we call test casts from
probes we're gonna actually change to
compute light propagation which is this
right here you can see that we've turned
off the multi thread so we're not
multi-threading right here we're
literally
just you know we're not multi-threading
we're just doing this updates up here
and that's because we're gonna have to
partition our probes into things that
operate on certain parts of the voxel
right and so I don't actually know if in
the future we're even going to need to
use probes at all we might just be able
to use make sure our voxels are you know
sampled in some way that we only sample
things that are not occluded that are
not like inside I don't know exactly how
to say that but we may be able to get
away with just not using lighting probes
at all eventually which would kind of be
nice too but it's a separate issue all
right so if we go ahead and do the
platform work you call back stuff here
if we start looking at how this is
actually working and we look in here you
can see we've done the thing where we do
our ray bundles actually do elect bias
towards light replacement nonsense thing
here I'll leave that in for now but I
think we may eventually want to just do
completely unbiased
just regular sampling and leave it at
that I don't know so don't quote me on
that but again I'm not gonna rule it out
so after we do all of our sampling here
what we really need now is just a way to
do this
spam voxel we know that we can call this
stuff and we can we can use the light
direction so we know more or less that
we should be able to literally just do
this part here right so while this thing
does its ray bundle index stuff and you
know what now that I look at it this is
actually us to move on the inside anyway
so right here we're not gonna you know
this this is not gonna be doing it we're
gonna be writing in two different parts
so we don't want to do any of this this
this has to all happen in here right and
so there's none of this summing this
this is not happening like this is not
right at all this stuff here doesn't
doesn't happen this way right
so what we want to do in here is say
alright we've got the Rays coming in
we're doing a ray cast on this thing and
we get down here and we're gonna need to
compute you know whatever the transfer
photos per second are and all that
garbage so we do this stuff and I don't
see so this this looks like we're not
using this tool here so we we come out
and we have our transfer PPS right and I
don't care about any of this look we
don't care about this even a little bit
I think we can literally get rid of all
this so we just have our transfer PPS
and we have our emission direction as
well which I don't know exactly how we
want to use that we'll see in a second I
suppose but I think all we really want
to do is say look whatever the Ray
direction was here for our sub ray we
need that actual thing I don't know what
the emission direction part of this well
anyway so in order to get the octahedral
offset we would just be using the the
negative of the emission direction I
think regular just want the direction we
were looking at originally which is the
raid erection why the emission direction
is inverted here I'm not sure
oh right cuz it needs to look backwards
no that's that's fine yeah that seems
fine so anyway we're gonna need to get
the direction where we're going to
encode this actual thing and we can get
rid of this because we're actually gonna
be casting in lots of different
directions now so we should be filling
in the map a little bit more completely
hopefully maybe for lucky anyway so then
we don't need to compute any of this
stuff I don't think we just have the
octahedral offset that we want to pass
and so now we just need to send spam
voxel the correct information so first
of all we need to know where we're gonna
do it and that's here we then need to
know like what the actual color was and
I think that's the transfer PPS is all
we really need to pass there we have the
light D which is like the distance and
so to do that to look at that we need to
know how far away it was right and we
actually have that information but it
looks like we never extract it so oh
well it's this right it's the T hit here
so if I just do a get component on T hit
I think we would be fine or sorry T ray
right so I think we just need to get
component on that and that's all we
would really need
so I think once we get that out we've
got our light D as well and then the
test case nonsense we're not really
using right now but we'll keep spamming
it to false so I think that should be
fine let me see what else we got here
debt component cannot convert argument
so I guess there isn't a get component
call for tier a I guess we're just meant
to do this is that right or just just
that and then light C in this case was a
typo cuz we just need the transfer PPS I
think missing any parameters here
solution location light C light D oh yes
and then our octahedral offset there we
go all right so I think that's all we
really need there but it's not actually
gonna work because we don't have any
blending right now for getting the
actual like the actual values we need
for moving the light around we don't
have a way of actually of making that
happen right so that part's not done yet
and so that's I think the only thing
that we're currently missing and that's
gonna be the voxel irradiance stuff so
if we look here here's where this is
happening compute voxel irradiance at is
saying I need you to tell me what the
light is that comes in here so this is
the actual part we care about and we're
mostly good but the problem that we have
here is this part right here this get
irradiance it doesn't do anything right
like if we if we put this in we're gonna
have to like we're kind of screwed here
right we need we need this thing to
actually do the lookups and we're gonna
want to try lerp on the actual lookup
right so basically what we need to do
here is find some way of doing these
lookups for each of these so when we do
the like cells blah blah blah
and we have the field here that's not
gonna cut it
right so the trailer please to actually
have this thing welded in and in order
to do that we're probably going to need
to like encapsulate that into a function
right so what we're probably going to
need to do here is make this trailer
call actually call something that will
do a plant that will do like a you know
that will do the the what's the word I'm
looking for here it'll actually do like
the texture sample now I don't think we
need to actually use this for a macro
because we can actually just do this in
v4s and call it a day so I think that'd
be fine
so we don't really have to know much we
can just start with our reflection
vector I guess although is it do we
actually care about the reflection
vector in this case
so in this case again I think we have a
problem of we need to sample we don't
want a sample specular lighting here we
want a sample diffuse light transmission
and so we kind of want a sort of a
smooth value of these things right we
want to take a look more at at the
average values in these areas and that's
gonna be a more confusing puzzle right
so let's talk about that for a second
because this is something that I'm not
sure and we should look at the paper as
well but let me just explain to you what
the problem is here
and maybe we should save this for next
weekend anyway but oops
so the problem that we're fundamentally
going to have here is that we've got an
octahedral map and I guess I'll use the
grid to slap that down we've got an
octahedral map here and it's got a
border region around it right but if
fundamentally it's 8 by 8 so it's it's
it's this grid exactly and what happens
is when we want to sample the light
coming from a particular direction well
we can sample it just by asking like
what's the light in this direction right
and what that corresponds to is we we
know given that this is an 8 by 8 what
we know is then if we were to look at a
sphere right so let's take our sphere
here if we were to look at a sphere we
know that like this you know
subsection so an octant of the sphere
here would map to an octant here right
so well sorry back to a quadrant here I
don't have a quadrant I'm not sure how
to say that but boy basically what I'm
saying is this right so a triangular
region here maps to a triangular octant
here right and so what's gonna happen is
when we need a sample something that's a
fairly specular light so something when
we're looking for just what's coming in
right at a particular angle right that's
gonna get we're just gonna look up in
here and say what's the light and we'll
just take a sample we're done right but
what happens when we want to know like
more more about like this entire region
of what's coming in because that's we're
gonna ask for diffuse lighting
transmission and in order to do that
we're talking about a huge area here so
we're really gonna want to do is sample
like an entire subsection estate we're
gonna want to take a big sample like
that and average all of the light that's
coming in and yeah really a ver Ajit's
cosine weighted in a sense but otherwise
more or less we're gonna try and take
that you know summation and so I don't
this is the part I'm not sure how they
intended to it to be done and I don't
know because we didn't really look at
the paper for that and so the question
is what would we do I mean the most
massive way is to actually step through
a wide area of this texture taking
individual samples and multiplying them
by the cosine fall-off not a
particularly great way to do it right
so I'm wondering is there some other way
that you were supposed to sample it now
one thing we could do is MIT this down
so let's suppose that we took our 8 by 8
and we did a pass every frame that takes
the 8 by 8 and we then smush it down to
like you know some tiny texture we're
now like the entire triangle before like
one whole quadrant is just this area
here right or this area here in that
case so we map that down and then we're
just saying look now we're just gonna
take one sample in the smaller map that
will average together a wide right that
one thing will bilinear filter a wide
range of the stuff and yeah it's not
exactly cosine weighted so it's not
great but it's something right and again
don't really know I don't know if that's
a smart thing to do or a stupid thing to
do I would say let's take a brief minute
and see if we take a gander at the paper
what do they think you should be doing
when you're sampling that map right and
hopefully they actually said you know a
lot of times papers that they'll just
skip over things sometimes so it's hard
to say but in this case we'll just hope
that they maybe documented that part so
if we take a look at that original paper
that we were looking at for octahedral
map diffuse lighting just take a look
here and see
you
let's see we computer a blah blah we can
also handle a direct illumination from
extended area light sources all right
this is not really what I wanted to know
but here we go we extend the original
vision we were waiting a scheme of blah
which we maybe might need to look at
because who knows if that talks about it
and they're just importing that here
right we modulate experience by space is
bringing diffuse surface albedo in order
to compute one bounce of indirect
outgoing to do so radio okay so we might
need look at that to compensate for the
fact that the incident abuse irradiance
at a parable occasion does not account
for local clusion well that's not really
what we're talking about I don't think
yes I don't really see I don't really
see anything here that talks about that
to be honest so we may want to look and
just see what is on one of these two
right I don't know if any of these are
more explicit look let's take a look at
say this one here
because they may just not bother talking
about it because hey they talked about
it in earlier paper so they're like look
if you want to know how we're sampling
the light probes for diffuse just look
at our earlier paper right so I'm gonna
save this one into our Doc's directory
in case we need to look at it again and
we'll see so looking in here let's see
light probe light field probe structure
implantation details let's see layer 2d
texture array for shading applications
of the pre filter the light field
radiance additionally storing a cosine
witness okay well that's literally what
I was just talking about additionally
storing a cosine weighted incident
irradiance probe for all possible
receiving surfaces at X that seems kind
of aggressive though
you
let's see
so I'm still not really seeing here we
go here we go here we go this is what we
want so let's take a look at this well
at least I think so
we're a speciality visual starts to
compute direct light using shadow maps
in a pixel shader exactly as we would
have expected then on the same vegetto
we're a trace to estimate indirect
lighting using a monocle integration and
we trace n random raise according to an
important sampling distribution each
returns a sample incident radiance
they filled with skilled samples and
neurosurgeon the integral covers right
name is Cris indirect effects of
aesthetically a second higher-order
alright
this is a more performance issue not
sure we care about that would reduce an
opposition suitable for deferred for a
rescue do you know it's estimate of
indirect incident all right the limber
shins the part we're wondering about
our indirect illumination past traces
one ray sampled from each of these with
cosine waiting erase the result to loss
too noisy Lamberson and glossy incident
radiance buffers for Lamberson
reflection uh hmm
alright we compute in-store integrated
incident irradiance instead of albedo
modulated outgoing radiance this allows
us to denoise our numerical estimate
without blurring her by saying okay we
denies the incident radiance in a second
pass with standard cross without any
predictive temporal filters okay we
don't care what that really at the
moment
Juvenal is hence the benefits of
separating Lamberson and glossary terms
got parents the emission term was often
noisier sure but also spatially slower
varying as a result okay yep
I'm with you so far after I'm practice
we all do new to okay raise the sample
umber in reflection capture less
information per pixel than glossy
samples ie compare the left side of the
figure K estimated a function that
varies more smoothly sure Lambert's are
more expensive to trace to their
incoherence okay essentially random
clairs note however that complex
there's ability blah blah blah
so I mean this is the weird part here so
I don't really understand the cosine
filtered irradiance maps part because
what I'm trying to see how they're doing
is if I trace an individual ray out into
the world I only get back what's along
that Ray and that particular ray should
contribute to an entire hemispheres
worth of values in the irradiance map if
the irradiance map was already supposed
to capture the lambertian right that the
smooth hemisphere integral of a diffuse
you know reflectance and so how are they
blowing that out like how are they are
they doing a post pass on it to do that
or something
or how are they actually are they
writing to the entire 8x8 on every ray
with just whatever the Ray result was we
write back a splat it's actually
effectively right that's the part I'm
not sure I don't understand right so I
wish they would say that more directly
but it sounds like that's what they're
doing meaning on every ray it sounds
like they actually write back to a you
know a four by four or possibly even
larger inside the map which a we could
do
I mean it seems like that's what's going
on and you can see here their counselor
about so this is glossy sample
pre-filtering right it is tempting to
pre-filter the light filled prose by
constructing bitmap change to enable
cone tracing so if actually that would
eliminate the need for post filter and
glossy term however while it is trivial
to pre filter radiance maps the optimal
strategy for altering normal and
distance maps is not obvious sure that
makes sense
interesting here that they're talking
about the octahedral probes and saying
that circular monarchs might be
interesting
so I don't know I'm not quite sure I
think we'd have spend a little more time
reading this to really figure out what
they were doing there because hopefully
you can understand where my confusion
comes in it's just that I want to know
like I don't understand how they're
getting from a single race sample to
something that will actually affect a
number of directions in the octahedral
map right and so one way of doing that
is just producing the octahedral map and
then filtering it into something you can
use for that and then another way of
doing it is the opposite way round where
every time you cast array you just fill
it out into the correct place right and
I don't know I don't know which of those
two things they are doing it seems to me
that doing it in a single post Pass is
the most obvious thing to do to me
I mean that just seems like the thing
that would take the least bandwidth you
know so you'd write to the octahedral
map and then you'd have something that
just basically produces one octahedral
map form from another by basically you
know doing a read of a row writing it in
to the other row doing a read of a
column and writing it in that's the only
thing I can think of offhand so again
really not sure but it just seems like
we would have to do something like that
it's that that is the one part that to
me seems like I don't know what we would
do there and again
like maybe I'm just missing something
but it seems like yeah the other problem
that I think we would have there is
again if we move the entire thing to the
GPU which maybe we'll do then it's a
little bit easier because we have that
map available so that we can use it
while we're doing ray tracing but the
other thing that's a little bit annoying
is that if we built that map like
normally the weight place we would want
to build that down filtered map would be
on the GPU I'd want to just do the down
sampling on the actual GPU itself but I
don't actually know in this case if that
would work on our scheme because we
don't have a way to get it back from the
GPU and we do the ray tracing on the CPU
side right so again it seems it just
seems a little dicey I don't know where
to go with it and the problem too is
that using the mipmap version seems a
little dangerous because the mipmap
version is not cosine weighted it would
just be because you can't because you
omit map is the MIT map you can't have
it be cosine waited for each particular
direction because it would be a
different thing in each direction so I'm
not sure what you do about
I don't know I'm gonna leave that for
next weekend we're gonna to think about
that but that's the biggest problem that
I see in the scheme so far is it's
basically how do we produce a map for
the diffuse because while we can pretty
easily use what we already have we don't
have that secondary map right and so you
know like I said one way to do it would
be very expensive like if we did the
full version that that I mean just to
give an example if we were doing this
from the actual diffuse map version it
just seems really dicey right so yeah if
you imagine like a sample in this thing
so we do Lightsey you know it just it
just looked like this right so this
would not be that bad right it would
just be something looks like this
so we would first take ok what's the
direction we're actually trying to
sample in and then we would say what
that actual bounces oops I accidentally
deleted something I needed there didn't
mean to do that so this would be pretty
straightforward right we would just
compute our txt y-values by doing the
the octahedral offset right so that's
the direction we're looking in so here's
the actual values we want here's where
we're gonna look them up right so this
would be it this is all we would need
right that would just do it that would
just work move this up a bit though so
that would be fine and I have no problem
with that
the problem again is how do we actually
look this up right because this thing is
now the wrong like that's the specular
that's the specular value right and we
don't want the specular value we want
the diffuse value and so what we're
effectively doing here is is bouncing
around specular lights and that's not
going to do anyone any favors
and we can debug this just fine but it's
not good like we need the actual diffuse
light so what we don't have is a way of
mapping this light C value to a light
diffusive alyou basically which is a
blurring a cosine weighted blur of this
thing and it would depend on direction
so I don't know I have to think about
what that entails exactly but that's the
issue we've got right so we'll have to
think about that I'm fine with ending
here for today I'm gonna go ahead and
close this down but that's that's where
we're at right which is not horrible
right it's not it's not that bad but
it's it's still like a little bit of an
unknown so let's go ahead and go to a
brief Q&amp;A and and let's let's just
assume that next weekend that's our task
is to figure out a solid answer for that
and then we can start debugging going
forward and by the way we could debug
that using our other stuff as well
because then we could just change to
using a diffuse pass there and verify
that that worked in addition to the
specular right
is the diffuse component gonna be
computed on the GPU of the GPU then well
we don't know I mean the problem is I
think it has to compute it on the CPU
unless we move the whole thing to the
GPU and the reason for that is because
in order to do the raycasting we need to
sample the diffuse component right so
I'm pretty sure that's really their only
option because we can't get it back from
the GPU I mean we could we could start
round-tripping it but still since
hardware standards we've quickly had
considered doing a pass on the code base
to move to newer versions of OpenGL and
SSE I don't think there's any newer
versions of SSE we could actually use
reliably I mean I guess we could go to
SSE for but I don't think there's much
optimization really that I don't think
there's that much there that we really
needed it wouldn't really impact our
code much at all I don't think at the
moment we certainly can't use avx2
that's not available everywhere as for
moving up a version of OpenGL again at
the moment don't really need it for
anything in particular so probably not
but if we had something that we really
needed we could consider it but again
pass on the code base not really
necessary like these are really minor
issues right they just don't affect
things that much if we could go to an
entire other vector with maybe but we
can't we have to stay with four-wide at
the moment
Curnow pineal is like three point
whatever three point two or something
like that and so there's there's not
really like we don't really need very
much from open jail like it's just not
super integral to what we're doing
so we don't really have to use much more
than the basic programmable shaders
which we're using right so as for the
current version that's available I don't
know if five is available now it
probably is
do the papers say they compute a
separate cosine weighted radiance for
every probe where do they say that
information yeah again I think we need
to go read the paper carefully which
maybe I'll do in the intervening week
because it sure sounded like that it
sounded like they computed two maps one
that was the octahedral map of the
glassy so not Lamberson and one that was
the cosine weighted Lamberson map right
and at least in the paper we were
originally reading it only showed two
maps
it showed a depth map and a single
octahedral irradiance map so and again
this would probably be clearer to us if
we actually went through and read the
paper like it normally takes a few hours
to read through a paper carefully and we
don't do that on the stream so my
assumption is this would not be
confusing to us if we actually sat down
and read the paper proper like in
silence together right which maybe we
should do a stream where we all sit and
read the paper carefully but you see
what I mean
you
any pointers on reading research papers
effectively not really I mean just take
your time and read them carefully and
slowly work through the equations
yourself on a separate sheet of paper or
using a computer algebra system to help
you because I find that a lot of times
it's tempting to just blow past the
equations but then you have no idea what
the heck it's talking about so and yes
this is that was a research paper that's
that would be considered just a research
paper research paper is just any paper
by researchers right I mean there's no
technical definition for it some are
extremely hardcore and have a lot of
like technical stuff in them others are
like super fluffy and are like more just
like almost an opinion right so there
isn't like a there isn't like a a real
metric for does this qualify as a
research paper like they're all research
papers that's just a generic term it's a
paper where somebody's publishing some
research they did and that research may
suck or it may be awesome or it may be
super technical or very basic but it's
still a research paper it hasn't it's
not a statement about the quality it is
a statement about what it is Journal of
fluffy opinion papers they have those
it's called a liberal arts journal
alright let me go ahead and wrap it up
here alright everyone thank you for
joining me for this episode I had made
here oh it's a pleasure coding with you
as always I think we're down to one
final unknown thing in the lighting
system here we've got bugs that we're
gonna have to do and we got performance
stuff we're gonna have to do for sure
but I think we're down to just one more
thing where we're not quite clear on how
this would work and that's just how
we're gonna do the conversion from light
samples to diffuse which is some kind of
a down sampling operation basically and
we'd like to know what we're doing we'd
like to have some idea of what the
original intent was behind that paper
for example before we go do something
ourselves we could make something up but
it'd be nice to know what at least was
intended before we make something up so
we may do a little investigation there
but otherwise that's the main thing
we're gonna have to do next weekend
that's gonna be our big chore we can do
that without the ray convection stuff we
can actually just regress we can turn
off that go back to our sphere sampling
even and still do that diffuse pass on
it so we should have an easy time
getting ourselves in a test
configuration for that but yeah that's
the thing we're gonna have to figure out
and I'm not sure exactly what that
should look like so we'll have to take a
look at that hope you see you back here
next week for that until then everyone
have fun programming and I will see you
on the Internet take it easy everybody